Speaker 17: Hello everyone.
My name is Alexander Pivar.
I am machine learning engineer at Miata,
and today we are gonna talk about why
good models fail in the production and
how to build a system that don't fail.
So imagine a situation you
train a model and your model
achieved 95% accuracy in the lab.
So now you deploy it with a confidence,
but six months later it's performance
barely better than a random guessing.
And you think what happened?
And unfortunately, that scenario
is not a rare exception.
And industry report that 87%
of data science project never
make it to the production.
And those that do, many
of them fail silently.
So today we are gonna talk about the
core reason, core failure modes and
deep dive into the why model fail.
We'll talk about the monitoring
framework, how to build our instrumental
panel, what exactly we want to monitor.
The remediation playbook, how to
fix what's broken, the best model
training scenarios and the principles
of the production machine learning.
It's a best practice for success.
And we'll move beyond the theoretical
and dive into the practical challenges
of production machine learning.
So talking about the core failure
modes, we will cover data drift concept
drift label, drift feature pipeline
degradation, and train source queue and
feedback loops, and PS amplification.
And now let's go to
the first failure mode.
Data drift.
So imagine you train a self-driving
car and you do it exclusively on the
sunny and clear days, and now you
want to deploy it in a city famous
for its rainy and foggy weather.
And suddenly the performance
of your car drop.
It's because that the images that camera,
cars, camera received is different
from what was used in a training data.
This is a data drift in a nutshell.
The real world example
is Zillow buying failure.
So in 2020 first Zillow, automated home
buying division, Zillow offers collapsed.
Leading to the staggering was $1 billion
loss in layoff of 25% of its workforce.
And of course, the multiple
factors were in play.
But the main failure was
because of the pricing model.
It failed to the adapt to the
unprecedented market volatility
and shifting by performance of the.
Post pandemic era.
So what the data drift exactly.
So data drift occurs when the distribution
of the input data in production.
It's different from the
distribution of the training data.
So that's.
Tracking this distribution.
It's a good detection method and
the first detection method it's
a population stability index.
It's measures a change in the distribution
of a single variable, and it's
calculated by the bin in the data and
comparing the percentage of observation
in each bin between the two samples.
It's perfect for a tracking of the key
features and its performance over time.
The next one is a Coog Agoro
S Mironov test or Key S test.
It's a non-parametric test that
compares the cumulative distribution
functions over two samples.
And the best way to use it, it's
for a numerical features as the
last one is yen Shannon tests.
It's measures the similarity between
two probability distributions at it's
useful for compare the distributions
of the two categorical features.
Let's talk about the resolution.
And the first one, it's continuous
monitoring and retraining.
So that's the most
fundamental line of defense.
By implementing the automated pipeline
that can continuously monitors the
data drift, we can integrate it into
the, our machine learning pipeline.
And as soon as the data drift detector
alert any problems with our features,
we can initiate the modular training.
The next one is adaptive learning.
For some model, it's possible to
use an online learning techniques
and update the model parameters
when the new data arrived.
And the last one is the main adaptation.
It's a more advanced technique that
attempt to adapt the model training
on the source data distribution
to a different target data
distribution without relabeling.
Now let's talk about the constant lift.
Let's go back to our self driving
car example and it's known fact
that the red octagon signal with a
letter stop mean that car must break.
But what if tomorrow society will decide
to change it, for example, and prepare
to the prepare of stop meaning or just
speed up to clear the intersection.
In that case input feature has
not changed, but the relationship
between input changes input features
and target variable has changed.
This is an example of the tive
talking about the real life the
frog detection models there in
a constant battle with a tive.
So imagine that you train a model
to predict the fraud transactions.
And for example, now you model
learned that transaction from the
specific countries at a specific time.
It's likely a high risk and
but fraudster, they can adapt.
They might start using the VPN pretending
that they're from the low risk countries,
or they just can see their attack times.
So that's a really aggressive
example of the concept drift.
The concept drift, it's usually more
challenging to detect since we don't only
need to look at the input data, but we
also need to track the model performance.
It's offline and online metrics like
accuracy of fund score over time.
And that actually would be the
perfect first detection methods.
Performance monitoring.
We want to monitor the main
performance metrics of our model,
like accuracy, precision F1 score.
And on a labeled validation set.
And as soon as we will see any
sustainable drop, it will be
the signal of the concept drift.
The next one is adaptive window.
It's an algorithm that maintains
a sliding window of a recent data,
so it automatically, that window
automatically grow or shrink the window
size when the statistical property
of the data within the window change.
Signal in the drift.
And the last one is
drift detection methods.
It's when we want to monitor the model
error rate, and as soon as that model
error rate exceeds a certain threshold,
it's a signal of the concept drift.
Now let's talk about
the resolution strategy.
And the first one is online learning.
So we can use the models that
can update its parameters
incrementally when new data arrives.
For example, algorithms like
stochastic gradient, distance,
and naturally suited for this, or
we can use some sample methods.
And sample methods is when each model it's
trained on a different window of the data.
And assemble can give a higher weights
to the recent data, and, for example,
phasing out an older and outdated concept.
And the last one is trigger
based retrain on label data.
This is a most common industry practice.
It's when we, when monitoring
tools, detecting any problems any
significant drops in our model, we
will initiate the model retraining.
Perfect.
Now let's move on to the label drift.
And so imagine that you are working
on a model that predict that.
User will add an item, will click the
add item to the shopping cart button.
And usually probability of
that event is around the 5%.
But now the Blake Friday comes and
the input feature still the same.
And user user intended also the same.
They still want to buy something, but now
the probability that the user will click
add to the cart bottom is around the 20%.
So this is where the proportion
of the model output changed.
And this is an example of the label drift.
Talking about the real life, it's
let's think about the economic
recession and loan defaults model.
For example, model builds to predict the
loan defaults and model training trains
in a stable period of economic can set
the default rates as, for example, 2%.
But let's imagine that unexpected
recession hit and unemployment
skyrocket, and suddenly the actual
default rates jumps to the 10%.
Models still celebrate on the
2% rate, but now it's completely
underestimated the risk across the
board, and it can potentially lead
to the massive financial loss.
This is a label drift in a nutshell.
So talking about the detection, it's
more more similar to the data drift.
Because label drift can be detected by
the monitoring of the distribution of
the target variables itself, so again,
we need to look only on the specific
targets specific targets values.
And the first method, it's monitoring
monitors the class distribution.
It's a most straightforward way.
We will track the proportion of
each class in our label data.
Over time, a significant change in
any amount of object of specific class
might be signal of a label drift.
The next detection method
is a he square test.
It's a statistical test that can
be used to determine if there is
significant association between
two categorical variables.
And it also can be to compare
the distribution of labels in a
reference window in comparison
with the current window.
And the last one is track prediction
distribution, for example.
We can check the proportion of
the amount of the positive class.
For example, if model used to predict
the 5% of positive outcomes, and now it
predict around the 15%, it's could be
noisy, but still indicator of the label
drift, talking about the resolution.
So the first one is recalibration.
It's the.
Model output can often be adjusted post
hoc for the new class distribution.
For example, by using the techniques like
plate scaling or isotonic regression,
it can be used to recalibrate the model
probability scores to better marginality.
The next one is performance weighting.
So during the training we can
assign the, so during the training,
we can have, we can see the.
Difference in the distribution
of the class labels, for example
minority and majority of the objects
of the targets of the classes.
And we can use the weights to adjust,
for example, the higher weights to
the minority and lower weights to
the majority to balance our data.
And the last one is
cost sensitive learning.
When we train our model we can
use a specific learning algorithm
which can finalize the more costly
errors for model more heavily.
This can make the model more robust
to change in a class distribution.
Good.
Now let's talk about the failure
mode for feature pipeline
degradation and train source queue.
So imagine that you're a
chef working on the price.
And so now p recip is ready and it's
flawless, and you send it to the
chain of the really busy restaurants.
And for example, one restaurant
is using different ingredients on
salted butter against the salted.
Another one has 20 degrees o of oven.
And in the third one, for example,
keen ingredients is simply missing.
The is type hasn't changed, but
the ingredients and the cooking
environment has been compromised.
This is an example of the feature pipeline
degradation, and in the reality the world.
The best example would be the
Google Diabetic Rec Party ai.
So once Google developed a state of
the art deep learning model that could
detect the diabetic retinopathy by
using the high quality pictures and
the model performance was on pair
with a real human ophthalmologist.
And as I said in the lab, they used a
high quality, perfectly captured images.
But in the reality when the model was
deployed in the clinic in Thailand, it's.
Performance dropped because the
nurses working in a busy poorly.
Lead conditions often capture
images in the very lower quality.
So lead to the model mis classifications.
This is again an example where the
environment has been compromised.
Lead to the Fisher Pipeline degradation.
So talking about the best
way to detect it, we need to
consider different issue types.
For example, the first one
is a data quality issue.
It's when the data itself is corrupted.
For example, some column can have
different data types or increased
amount of the new variables.
New variables can even be
unexpected for this column.
It's where the data validation framework,
like great expectation or DQ, can help us.
This tool allow us to define suit
of expectations for our data.
For example, expected amount
of new variables or expected
mean in the shorten threshold.
This check will run every
time when the new data arrive.
The second issue type is schema changes.
This is pretty common for big corporations
where multiple people involved into
a different part of machine learning
pipeline, for example, multiple
people responsible for the feature
lifecycle, model lifecycle, et cetera.
And this is where, for example,
the schema had been compromised.
For example column was renamed
removed, or the data type changed.
And it's where the schema
monitoring can help us.
And our pipeline will automatically
validate schema and prevent the
corrupted data lead reach the model.
And the last one is train source queue.
It's when, we can have a feature
value from a specific pipeline or
from the specific part of the code.
And this pipeline or part of
the code can use a different
packages, for example leading to
the different value of the feature.
So it's where we want to log inputs
and outputs of the training and of
the same data, but on the different
environment training and the production.
And if.
Training environment and
production environment, and with
the same model produce different
responses for the same data.
This is a signal of the
feature pipeline degradation.
So talking about the resolution,
the main resolution here would be.
The feature store, it's a gold
standard industry gold standard.
So the feature store is a centralized
system that manages the definition,
computation and solving of feature
for both training and environment.
And it's programmatically
eliminate the class of problems.
The next one is robust data validation.
It's, as I said, we can integrate the
data validation checks into the directly
into the machine learning pipeline.
Preventing the bio corrupt data will
reach the model and cause any harm.
And the next one is data contracts.
The data contracts.
It's when we want to establish the formal
agreement between the different team
working on a machine learning pipeline.
For example to have an agreement in a
schema changed and prepare the model
for the, any feature changes, let's say.
And the last one, it's a containerization.
It's ba basically packaging
our model and its dependencies
ensuring that the training and
production environment is the same.
Now let's talk about the last one.
It's feedback loops and b simplification.
So let's think about the popular
musing streaming music streaming
service, and its recommendation engine.
Recommendation algorithm.
Suggest you have few rock on.
And yeah, you like them.
And now in return, the algorithm
re recommend you a few more rock
song and you like them as well.
And now algorithm thinks that
you are diehard rock fan and it's
completely ignoring your potential
interest in jazz and classical music.
So the model created a reality by
amplification its initial bias.
The real world example is a
compass recidivism algorithm.
So the compass.
A correctional offender management
profiling for alternative sanctions.
It's a tool that had been used
by the United States Justice
System to predict the likelihoods
of a defendant re-offending.
And 2016 investigation revealed
that the algorithm was significantly
pierced against the black defendants
flagging them as a higher risk for
the future crimes at nearly twice.
Rate as a defendant
with a similar history.
Why defendants with a similar history.
The defendant flagged as a high risk
and received a longer sentence be denied
parole and faced with a heavier police.
And all of that lead to the higher
likelihood of the future arrest regarding
their individual individual actions.
So this is where, again,
the feedback got broken.
So talking about the detection, they
usually feedback loops occur when
the model output y from t let's say
timestamp influence the state of the
world that will be used as an input
for the model retraining XT plus one.
And yeah, so we can use a several
detection method to prevent it.
And the first one is
diversity and exposure metric.
For example, we can quantify
the variety of prediction in
the mo the model is making.
For example, for the recommendation
system, we can ensure that number
of unique items we can ensure
that there are specific, unique
items recommended over appear.
Or we can use an AB test a test like
for example, run a small percentage
of a user that use a non-personalized
version of our software and the
personalized model recommendation.
And if we can see that the behavioral
of the model driven group has changed.
So it can be a strong
feedback loop in a place.
And the last one is a casual inference
techniques so we can employ more advanced
statistical methods to try dis tangle.
The model's influence from
the user organic preferences.
It's, for example, techniques like
uplifting model can help estimate the
true persuasive effect in a production.
It's can be used when, for
example, we cannot use the A tests.
So talking about the resolution, the
first one is exploration strategy.
For example, we can extensionally
introduce some randomness
into our recommendation model.
So this will allow the model to collect
data on a wider range of possibilities.
For example, if we recommend the batch
of 10 elements, one or two elements
could be randomly randomly selected.
The next one is positional dbs.
N. So when we talk about the
recommendation system usually they
can return rank at least where
the higher elements usually has a
higher probability that the user
will click of them and or like them.
And the model can misrepresented
as a stronger preference.
So that's where we want to add some
positional, the BS and technique.
So tell the model about the position
of the item in a recommended list.
And the last one is failure,
fairness constraints.
It's during the model training we can
introduce a mathematical constraints
to ensure that the model prediction
satisfies a certain fairness criteria.
For example, if we work on a loan
approval model, we can just use
statistical statistical concepts,
statistical similarity across
different demographic groups.
Now we covered the main main problems
and we can think about the proper way
to set up the monitoring and yeah.
So deploying a model without the
monitoring, it's like flying on
a plane without an instruments.
We are simply blind to any changes.
And it's also can make the
debug in this a, a nightmare.
So the first thing that we
want to cover with additional
monitoring is model performance.
We want to track the business metrics
and the model performance metrics
online and offline model performance.
It's recall F1 score accuracy and as an
online, for example, CTR or revenue lift.
The next one, which we want
to cover is data health.
It's statistical integrity of the
data which we feed to our model.
This is our early warning system, and we
want to track the PSI K statistic, new
rates, data types Hema changes me and Max.
All of that type of
changes in our features.
The last one is system health.
So system health is an operational
performance of the whole infrastructure,
and it's not only perfect for
debugging, but it's also perfect
for understanding the bottlenecks
and plan our future optimization.
So we want to track the inference
latency for output error rates
C-P-O-G-P-U and memory utilization.
And yeah, you don't need to
implement anything from scratch.
There exists a lot of open source
tools that can provide this
functionality out of the box.
For example in open source tools like
evidentiary AI in NEML and IB detection
they provide framework for detecting
data drift concept drift, and the
performance model performance degradation.
There also exists a lot of commercial
platforms like yaps, Fiddler ai arise ai.
They not only offer you end-to-end
observability platforms, but also can
allow you to integrate your model into the
more broader machine learning ecosystem.
Now when, for example, we have a
proper detection and let's say that
our detection framework just signal
alerting, and so we need to understand.
What we want to do how we
want to retrain our model.
And there exist different strategies.
And the first one is
a time-based strategy.
It's basically the skittle base,
for example, when we want to
train, retrain our model on a
daily, weekly, or monthly basis.
And it's on the one hand it's simple
to implement and it's predictable,
but it's also highly inefficient and.
Waste of the resources because
not always we need to retrain our
model so we can think about the
performance based on that case.
For example, we can retrain our model
once key performance metrics drop.
It's directly tied to the business
variable, and it's a train only when
we need it, but unfortunately, it's a
reactive and not proactive approach.
So the model already been underperforming
and it's already produced some losses.
Okay.
In that case, we can think
about the drift based approach.
It's when we can we can retrain the
model once we can observe any drift
metrics, any drift feature drifts,
for example, by track and PSI or
key statistic for key features.
And this approach is proactive.
So we can trigger we can trigger a retrain
before the model performance drop, but
it's also can be noisy and not all that
drift lead to the performance degradation.
So instead we can use a hybrid approach,
and it's a recommended approach.
It's basically a combination
combination of multiple triggers
into more sophisticated policy.
It's a more robust and practical
approach, and it's balanced pros
and cons of the other methods.
But unfortunately, it's also more
complex to design and implement it.
It require a lot of adjusting
of the multiple thresholds.
Yeah, talking about the best
practicing for building our
machine learning pipeline.
The first one is designed
for drift from day one.
So don not treat your monitoring
and retraining as an afterthoughts.
The architecture for detection and
responding to drift should be designed
in parallel with the model itself.
The next one is maintain
training, serving parity.
So we need to use an, we need
to ensure that we are using the
identical code and libraries for
production and training environment.
The next one is grad or allowed, so that's
not a secret, that never deploy your
model directly to 100% of the traffic.
Just deploy it to the low
amount, for example, 5% traffic
and monitor its performance.
And once you ensure that the performance
of your model on payer or even
better than the production in that
case, you can roll out those 100%.
The next one is instrument
for a feedback model.
Performance can only be measured if
you have a ground truth and you need
to design your system to collect
the feedback for models prediction.
It's also helpful for the not
only for the understanding of the
model performance, but also for
future improvement of the model.
The next one, it's document everything.
It's when the future you will.
Thank you.
It's, we need to track everything.
Model cards, data lineage, decision
logs, everything that possible.
It's not only helpful for understanding
the problems with the pipeline and yeah.
Monitoring of the model, machine
learning pipelines without.
Proper login.
It's a real nightmare, but it's also
helpful for understanding of the
bottlenecks and future improvements.
Yeah, my final suggestion is, the
first one is stop thinking of the
machine learning as a project and
start, think about it as a product.
Different part of the machine learning
pipeline has has all its own lifecycle,
features, models even infrastructure.
The next one is an invest into the lops.
So we already talked a lot about why we
need to add additional monitor into our
models and testing the model performance.
And the last one is foster
a cross-functional car,
cross-functional culture.
It's data scientist, machine
learning engineers, software
engineers and product managers.
They all must work together to build
and maintain this complex system.
Yeah, that's all from my side.
Thanks a lot everyone.
Feel free to reach out to me on LinkedIn
in case if you will have any questions.