Hello everyone.
I'm Serena Raju, a senior software
development engineer at Amazon.
Today I will be talking about one of
the most critical and rapidly evolving
challenges in e-commerce fraud, and
more importantly, how machine learning
is transforming, how we combat it as
the digital economic grows soon as
the sophistication of suicide crime.
We'll explore how traditional
systems are feeling and why machine
learning is emerging as a more
resilient and scalable solution.
So the topic is harnessing machine
learning to combat e-commerce fraud.
By 2026, the global e-commerce is
projected to hit nearly $9 trillion.
The tremendous growth.
It comes with a risk.
Fraud is growing at more than
20% per year for businesses.
This means not only direct revenue
loss, but damage to customer
trust and brand reputation.
I want you to think about this.
What happens when a genuine customer's
card gets strongly flagged and declined?
They don't just lose patience,
they might never return.
How many of you have experienced a
false decline while shopping online?
Probably many
traditional rule system worked well.
In a simpler time, you would set through
like block all the transaction over
a thousand dollars from a new device.
But today.
The frauds are faster
and more coordinator.
These rules can't adapt the consequences
over 28%, false positive meaning
real customers are turned away.
And these false declines cost
over $3.6 billion every year
just from lost transaction.
So if Ruby Systems are updated,
what's the alternative?
Machine learning.
Machine learning has changed the game
and through static rules we now use
systems that can learn and evolve.
Let's take a closer look.
ML models can process nearly millions
transaction per second and analyze
thousands of features far beyond
what an analyst can do manually
with over 96% detection accuracy.
And an 81% drop in false positive.
The result speaks for themself.
Customers enjoy smoother
transaction and business stops
more fraud with less friction.
In supervised learning, we train
models on historical data where,
which, where we already know
which transaction were fraudulent.
The random forest algorithm are
great inter interpretability
and work well when we need to
explain decisions to regulate us.
Whereas the gradient boosting shines
with imbalance data like fraud
case, which are rare but critical.
The neural network can spot settle complex
pattern even humans can't articulate.
And all of them work in real
time under 7,200 milliseconds per
transaction, even when handling over
a hundred thousand conference session.
Think of this teaching a spam filter, but
only the stakes are high and
it's more real in terms of the
customers and the dollar amount.
So model selection depends on the specific
fraud patterns and the data volume
and the explainability requirements.
Depending on that, we can either use
one of them or the combination of these,
but what about new frauds
that we haven't seen before?
That's where the unsupervised
learning comes in.
These model don't need labeled examples.
They just look at the anomalies.
Some of them are like isolation
Forest works by separating
out individual behaviors.
Another one is Altman coder.
Try to reconstruct normal behaviors
and flag anything that doesn't fit.
Clustering fine groups.
Sorry.
Clustering algorithms, buying groups
of suspicious pattern like fraud rings,
these tool detects over 26% of the
novel fraud items, threats that would
have bypassed traditional filters.
So these unsupervised learnings are
critical component as these will identify
some of the unknown fraud patterns.
And allow us to detect before it happens.
Features are the signals.
Our model learned from raw data, like
transaction time or IP address is useful.
But when we combine them creatively,
we unlock powerful indicators.
Temporal features help us to detect
timing anomalies like buying.
500 gift cards in five seconds.
Network features really reveal links
between users, devices, and ips.
Behavior features like cursor movement
or timing speed can distinguish bots
from human with over 90% accuracy.
Great models needs great features,
and these must evolve constantly.
As the frauds adapt to these feature
engineering transforms raw transactions
into the rich and informative
signals that could dramatically
improve the model performance.
The most effective feature
often combine data across these
multiple domains, creating a
multidimensional risk indicator, and
that FoST cannot easily manipulate.
Ion.
Yeah.
Evaluation is essential as static
feature sets quickly become targets
for sophisticated fraud techniques.
Detecting fraud is one thing.
Doing it at scale is another.
Imagine Black Friday, millions
of transaction in minutes.
We need system that make fraud decisions.
In under one 50 milliseconds and support
million transaction per minute, and
for sure it needs to be up and running.
It should never go down.
That's why we use distributed fault
tolerant microservice based architectures
with the terabyte scale storage.
This infrastructure enables
us to stop fraud in real time.
Without slowing the customers.
So we need high performance processing.
We're using distributed architecture.
We'll use the optimized storage and
we'll have a resilient infrastructure,
the cloud-based infrastructure that
will enable us to make sure if there are
any failures, we have the other set of
infrastructure up and running for us.
Some businesses aren't ready to
go all in on ML, and that's okay.
Hybrid systems are a great bridge.
They combine event driven
rules with ML intelligence.
Think like a pilot using autopilot,
but still able to intervene.
Rules provide guardrails, and
ML finds their nuanced patterns.
These hybrid system can push
detection accuracy above 97%.
And because they are explainable,
they satisfy the regulatory needs.
So we'll have this adaptive learning.
We'll have these business rules or the
guardrail that's encode the business
expertise will have the integration layer.
That is where decision on these fusion.
And we'll have this feedback
mechanism where we can
continuously optimize the system.
Now coming to the manual reviews,
now not all cases can be automated.
That's where we need
some smart manual review.
Comes in picture ml, prioritize
which cases to review and
routes him to the right analyst.
It highlights suspicious signals and
learns from analyst decisions, feeding
those insight back into the model.
This human in the loop system cuts
review time by over 30% and improves
the decision accuracy by more than 40%.
It's a win-win for both
security team and the customers.
The smart.
Manual review systems have improved
the review efficiency as well,
thus reducing the decision time
by a lot from minutes to seconds.
The human machine collaboration creates a
powerful feedback loop that continuously
improves both automate systems and
the human system for the more complex
cases where the pure automation.
It cannot be handled reliably.
Let's talk some of the business values
that we see with the ML four prevention.
The companies that uses the
ML fraud preventions reports
a 23% drop and fraud ops cost.
Nearly 18% increase in approvals of good.
Transactions, over 30% fewer customer
complaints due to false declines.
So it's not just stopping fraud,
it's about driving revenue,
customer satisfaction, and loyalty.
What's next?
Explainable AI will make black
box model easier to audit.
The next generation of fraud models
will provide clear explanation
of decision that could meet their
regulatory requirements while
maintaining the detection performance.
Federated learning will help companies
collaborate on fighting fraud
without sharing the sensitive data.
These collaborated more
across the organization.
Sharing NONSENSITIVE data will enable
industry-wide PRI fraud protection.
While we do preserve the private privacy
and realtime adaption will let morally
wall instantly when fraud patterns change.
So the continuous learning system.
That updates within seconds
of new fraud pattern images
will close the adaption gap.
With the fraud leading platforms now
demonstrate model and updating under 30
seconds after detecting the normal attack.
The future of fraud detection is
master faster and more collaborative.
So we need to have these fraud prevention.
With more collaboration, adapt
their and explainable system.
Organization that invest in advanced
ML capabilities now have been better
positioned to come back to more
sophisticated frauds while maintaining
the frictionless customer experiences.
Thank you for listening to the topic.
I hope you enjoyed it.