Speaker 3: Hi everyone.
I am Adi Nam Dave.
I am a business intelligence engineer at
Amazon, and today I'm going to be talking
about this interesting topic called
machine learning as the intelligence
layer for adaptive self optimizing
systems throughout the talk, if anyone
has any questions, comments, or concerns.
Please feel free to reach out to
me on my LinkedIn and I will be
more than happy to respond and
discuss it further with you all.
So machine learning as the
intelligence layer for adaptive
self optimizing systems.
Introduction to adaptive systems.
Adaptive systems improve agility
in the modern industrial.
Operations industry, they strengthen
resilience, helping systems
respond to change and disruption.
Industrial automation is
shifting from static rule-based
models to now dynamic systems.
These systems are self-optimizing,
continuously learning
and improving over time.
Machine learning is the key enabler
behind this adaptability and optimization.
70% of unplanned downtime is
linked to inflexible automation.
The core machine learning techniques
that drive this adaptability are
number one, reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement Learning allows
systems to learn from dynamic
interactions, optimizing decisions
through trial and error to improve
performance in changing environments.
Number two, predictive modeling.
Predictive modeling utilizes
historical data to forecast future
trends, enabling organizations to
proactively optimize processes.
And make informed
decisions for efficiency.
Number three, anomaly detection.
Anomaly detection, identifies
irregular patterns in real time data,
facilitating immediate responses to
potential fault, thus maintaining
system integrity and reliability.
Manufacturing impact how machine
learning relu revolutionizes
modern manufacturing processes.
Number one, it optimizes manufacturing
workflows using data-driven insights.
Number two, it increases throughput
by improving process efficiency.
Number three, it reduces downtime
through predictive maintenance.
Number four, it enables real time data
analysis for faster decision making.
And lastly, it improves overall
performance, efficiency and productivity,
logistics, automation.
These adaptive systems revolutionizing
supply chain efficiency are
not only reliable, but it also.
Increases the independency
of these systems.
Autonomous vehicles optimize delivery
routes using real time data and ai.
It improves route planning, which reduces
fuel consumption and delivery time.
Smart load balancing ensures better
utilization of vehicle capacity.
Automation minimizes human
errors and operational delays.
Enhance efficiency, reduces
disruptions across the supply chain.
Energy operations, enhancing
efficiency and resilience in
energy management systems.
This uses predictive load management
to forecast energy demand accurately.
It optimizes energy distribution
based on predicted usage patterns.
It detects anomalies in real
time across grid systems.
It identifies potential defaults
or irregular behavior early.
It reduces operational
failures and unplanned outages.
It improves overall efficiency and
reliability of the energy operations,
self-healing automation,
manual anomaly detection.
Traditional systems rely on manual
anomaly detection, which causes
delays in identifying issues leading
to extended downtime and increased
operational costs for manufacturers
severely impacting productivity.
Also, real-time anomaly
detection On the other hand.
ML Powered systems enable real
time anomaly detection, which
allow for immediate identification
and resolution of issues.
SIG does significant, does significantly
reducing downtime and enhancing
operational efficiency through
autonomous corrective actions.
40% of predictive maintenance impact.
Reduces the the ML intelligent layer
reduces unexpected equipment fa
failures by identifying issues early on.
It minimizes unplanned downtime
and production disruptions.
It lowers maintenance costs by avoiding
reactive and emergency repairs.
It also improves operational efficiency
through better planning and scheduling.
It extends the lifespan of machinery
and equipment with timely intervention.
It enhances overall reliability
and asset performance.
Model interpretability challenges,
explainability matters, ensuring
model explainability builds trust
and compliance with stakeholders.
Fostering confidence in ML systems and
their decisions essential for successful
adoption in critical industries.
Number two, the importance
of explainable pipelines.
Implementing explainable ML pipelines
facilitates transparency, allowing
users to understand model predictions
and outcomes, thus, ultimately
improving user experience and
enabling better decision making.
Complexity balance.
Balancing complexity with
understandability is key here.
Overly complex models may hinder inter
interpretability, while simpler models
might not capture critical patterns,
necessitating thoughtful decision
necessa necessary, sorry, necessitating
thoughtful design to achieve both.
Hybrid ai, OT integration.
Separation of concerns clearly delineating
AI and operational technology layers
enhances system management, allowing
in allowing independent updates and
innovations without disrupting existing
operational processes and maintaining
stability across the organization.
Data flow management.
Effective data flow between AI and
operational layers ensures real
time responsiveness, facilitating
seamless communication, and enhancing
the adaptability of systems to
changing conditions and operational
demands, scalability benefits.
This architectural pattern promotes
scalability by enabling organizations
to expand system capabilities.
Incrementally does accommodating growth
and enhancing the overall resilience
of operations as technology evolves.
Explainable ML pipelines
standardized model validation.
Implementing standardized validation
processes ensures models are consistently
tested against benchmarks increasing.
Trust and compliance across organizational
stakeholders while minimizing errors
and enhancing overall efficiency.
Cross-functional teams, establishing
cross-functional teams fosters
collaboration between data scientists
and operational experts, ensuring that
insights are actionable and aligned with
business objectives, thus ultimately
driving better outcomes in ML deployments.
Continuous feedback.
Creating a system for continuous
feedback allows for real time performance
assessments, enabling quick adjustments
and iterative improvements to models,
which does enhance the reliability and
effectiveness in dynamic environments.
Designing robust ML enabled
automation architectures.
Number one, modularity and scalability.
Prioritizing modularity allows
system to adapt and evolve
without complete redesign.
Scalable architectures ensure
operational efficiency which can
grow alongside the businesses.
Changing needs and demands.
Continuous learning.
Implementing continuous learning processes
allows system to adapt to new data,
improving decision making over time.
This adaptability enhances
resilience and maintains operational
effectiveness in dynamic environment.
Lastly, aligned KPIs.
Selecting KPIs aligned with operational
goals ensures that the performance of ML
systems is measured effectively, driving
improvements that are directly linked
to business objectives and outcomes.
Selecting meaningful KPIs,
throughput improvements.
Enhancing throughput is vital for
operational efficiency as it measures
production rates and ensures timely
delivery of products, ultimately driving
higher revenue and customer satisfaction.
Downtime reduction.
Reducing downtime directly impacts
productivity by minimizing disruptions,
thus increasing system reliability
and lowering maintenance costs,
contributing to overall operational
effectiveness and profitability.
Energy efficiency.
Focusing on en energy efficiency helps
organizations reduce consumption and
costs while promoting sustainability,
fostering a positive corporate image and
compliance with environmental regulations.
These three sub items define the
importance of selecting meaningful KPIs.
Lastly, ML not only automates, but
continuously learns beyond static rules.
Un unlike traditional automation,
machine learning models adapt over
time rather than relying on fixed
hand coded rules, learning from data.
Okay.
These machine learning models continuously
improve by learning from new data, new
feedback loops, and real world outcomes.
Self-improving accuracy.
Predictions and decisions get better with
the system as a system is exposed to.
More examples and edge cases
adapts to change machine learning
response to evolving patterns.
User behavior.
Market trends, fraud tactics without
manual reprogramming, feedback driven
optimization, human reviews, corrections,
and outcomes are fed back into the
model to redefine future decisions.
Thank you very much.
I hope this talk was helpful.
Thank you very much for listening in.