Hello everyone, my name is, and
today I'm excited to share our
journey and insight on machine
learning and system modernization.
A critical topic for 2025 and beyond.
We are living in an era where technology
evolves faster than our nation can adopt.
Legacy system legacy that once served
us well, have now become barriers.
It.
If we modernize, but how fast,
how smartly we can do it.
Today, 60 to 80% of IT
budgets are consumed.
Just maintaining whole systems.
That leaves very little room
for innovation and even less
for competitive differentiation
is not.
Servers are moving to the cloud.
It's about rethinking the way business
operates, making system smarter, faster,
and most importantly, feature proof.
Without modernization, organizations
face air costs slower response
to the market changes and
frustrated customers and employers.
So legacy modernization is essential in
today's digital landscape organization.
Face technical, operational, and human
challenges while balancing system
reliability With modern capabilities,
including cloud AI and advanced analytics,
we shall explore the strategic approaches.
Performance considerations and
implementation methodologies
for successful moderation.
Focusing on based implementation,
stakeholder management, and technology
integration that maintains system
stability throughout the transformation.
Okay, let's talk about the
strategic overview and challenges.
Modernizing is tough.
There are three big challenges.
The first, the financial burden.
Big transformation requires
investment before you see returns.
Legacy system, 60 to 80% of IT
budget severely limiting resources
for digital innovation and
competitive growth initiatives.
Second, the.
Legacy process and organizational
culture resist transformation.
Three quarters of organizations identify
outdated infrastructure as the critical
roadblock, preventing deployment of
modern digital services and capabilities.
And the third balancing performance
and innovation Legacy systems, 99.9%.
Lack essential agility, effective
modernization strategies, maintain
operational stability while introducing
advanced technology capabilities.
So we must keep critical systems
stable while introducing newer,
riskier technologies like
AI and real time analytics.
It's like fixing an airplane.
Where while it's still flying.
Let's talk about the numbers.
Imagine slashing cash cost by up to
30%, improving system response by
60% and boosting market adapt by 35%.
That's the moderation.
Promising success is not technology alone.
Its.
Tangible business outcomes like
adaptability and customer satisfaction.
So do we measure success.
In modern, we use clear hard
metrics, 15 to 30% cost reduction.
Successful moderation project typically
achieve significant operational cost
savings, 40 to 60% faster System
responses, improvement in system response.
Time after successful modernization,
25 to 35% better adaptable
to market changes.
This will enhance ability to respond to
market changes and customer needs, and
aiming for 99.9% system availability.
Nearly perfect time.
So maintain throughout the transition
is successful transformation.
So these are not just big goals.
Their directly impact customer experience,
revenue, and long-term survival.
If we talk about the performance
architecture considerations for current
legacy and modern system, and we will
talk about the impact assessment.
So architectural discussion today
determine whether we through
tomorrow scalability, the silence.
And flexibility must be at
the heart of every edition.
Hybrid cloud, microservices and
ation are no longer buzzwords.
They are the building blocks
for a responsive enterprise.
If you look at the moderation
aspects, if we compare with
current legacy and modern system.
The transformation transition
processing the legacy system, it
is handling 1 million transaction
per day with 99.99% reliability.
And if you can, if you see that modern
system, 40 to 50% better resources,
utilization, that really the impact
is high positive impact on response
time, milliseconds response time.
But if you use the modern system, it's
gonna be 65% faster time to market,
significant improvement, operational
costs, baseline costs, and then it's
gonna reduce 40% in modernized system.
Major cost savings over here.
Let's talk about cloud migration patterns.
Moderation also demands rethinking
of technical foundations.
We prioritize scalability,
the silence, flexibility.
So scalability system that
can grow as business grows.
The silence system that recovers instantly
from failures, flexibility system ready
for ai, automation and feature tech.
So cloud migration plays a
massive role, but migration.
Is not just lift and shift, we carefully
choose between rehosting, replatforming,
and refactoring based on business needs.
Choosing the right migration pattern
ensures we are not just moving problem
to the cloud, we are solving them.
The six R approach provides a
structured framework for moving advocacy
applications to cloud environments.
Organisms carefully evaluate each
application against these patterns.
Considering factors such as business
criticality, technical dip, and
required performance levels,
the strangler big patterns has
emerged as a particularly effecti.
Replace legacy functionality while
maintaining system stability.
It studies showing successful
implementation, achieving a 30
to 40% reduction in risk compared
to the big Bang approaches.
If you see the user experience
and change management.
Technology alone does not drive success.
It's the people.
A shocking 70% of digital transformation
fail because of poor change
management, not poor technology.
To overcome this, we focus on
gradual interface improvements, 80.
Success rate when organization implement
incremental changes to user interfaces,
allowing for adoption and feedback
change champions.
So 80% of success rate when organization
like change champions compared to
just 30% success without dedicated
adoption leaders complete system or.
Only 35% success rate with all at one
system changes, creating significant
disruption and adoption challenges.
And the last one is dig digital adaptation
platforms, organizations implementing
comprehensive digital adaptation platforms
experience 50% user adoption rate.
45% reduction in support tickets.
If we don't manage that well, even
the best technology will be rejected.
Training and supporting strategies,
training should not be an afterthought.
It should be embedded into the
modernization journey from day one.
Documentation and interactive feedback
loops creates self-sufficient users
and drastically reduce support costs.
Comprehensive training, interactive
e-learning modules, and micro running
segments, and modern documentation like
videos, tutorials, and interactive guide.
Chain champions, network advocates
across departments and feedback
systems, real-time user input channels.
So organization implementing real-time
feedback system report, a 65% implement
in system usability and user satisfaction.
Modern documentation approaches
including video tutorials
and interactive guides, 75%.
Better knowledge retention
compared to traditional methods.
Okay.
Innovation, integration and technology.
So mission learning and are
becoming the heart of modernization.
We use AI to predict customer behavior.
Optimize operations
detect an in real time.
Meanwhile, the other microservices
architecture breakdown mono system
into smaller dependent parts, making
them more flexible and silent.
Also embarrass embracing
mobile first and self service.
Technologies empower customers
and employees reducing operational
cost and boosting satisfaction.
The AI mission learning organizations
implementing AI driven analytic
experience, 25 to 30% implement
indecision making accuracy, and three
by percent reduction in processing
time for complex transactions.
45% higher success rate with
the structured approach.
If you take it, mobile and self
services organization, prioritizing
mobile first approaches achieves 55%
higher user engagement rates, 45%
increase in service accessibility,
and 30% reduction in support costs.
So microservice architecture organization
adopts microservice, Experian, 33%
I improvement in system flexibility,
28% reduction in deployment type.
40%. Integration issues,
fewer integration issues,
migration and strategy and implementation.
Risk assessment, when is going to
be 65% fewer critical incidents
and phase implementation.
It's gonna be three x higher success
rate and integration patterns.
It'll reduce 50% reduction in
downtime and AI assisted testing.
75% more issues identified
redeployment itself.
While 94% of organizations acknowledge
the need for legacy system migration,
only 25%, 28% report successful
completion of their modernization project.
Organizations leveraging
large language model.
For code analysis and documentation
achieved 45% faster migration planning,
and 60% more accurate dependency mapping,
stakeholder management and value delivery.
So the comprehensive RO 80, tracking
the organizations implementing
value tracking framework.
2.5 times higher stakeholders buy-in,
and 40% better resource allocations
and realtime progress visualization
organizations utilizing realtime
progress visualization tools achieve
70% better alignment between technical
teams and business stakeholders.
So to the performance monitoring.
Organizations implementing comprehensive
performance monitoring framework identify
60 per 65% more optimization opportunities
and achieve 50% better business
outcomes and the long-term support.
Planning organizations with well-defined
support strategies achieve 45%
better system sustainability and
35% lower total cost of ownership.
Okay, so what are the takeaway,
key takeaways, and next steps?
Let's wrap up with the a few takeaway.
Few key takeaways.
Balance, stability with innovation.
Do not sacrifice one for the another,
so ensure continuous operation while
introducing advanced capabilities.
Through strategic planning and
methodological implementation phases,
prioritize people, not just technology.
So invest in change management,
such as in cloud solutions.
So we need to allocate 15 to 20% of
your moderation budget to comprehensive
training programs, technical support
and adoption acceleration in situs.
Measure success holistically, cost
savings, agility, adaptability,
and user satisfaction all matters.
So when we implement robust tracking
of both the technical performance
metric and the business outcome, to
demonstrate tangible ROI and sustain
executive stakeholder commitment.
The last one is adopt
face phased approach.
It should be a phase adopt phased
approach, not a big bang approach.
Transformation is a
marathon, not a sprint.
So execute migration through
strategic incremental steps with
well-defined success milestones to.
Threefold higher success rate compared
to all at once implementations.
So moderation is not just a tech project,
it's a business evaluation strategy.
Thank you all for your attention.
Mission learning and moderation
are not just futuristic trends.
They are the foundation of sustainability,
silent and innovative enterprises.
I look forward to discuss discussing
this more during the session.
Thank you.