Hello everyone, and welcome.
My name is Pascal Goyle and I'm
thrilled to be speaking at contu.
Today we are going to deep dive
into a topic that's crucial for any
organization looking to leverage
artificial intelligence effectively.
That is cloud native AI at
scale architectural patterns
for enterprise success.
In the next 20 minutes, we will explore
how adopting cloud native principles is
t just a trend, but a fundamental shift
that's revolutionizing AI deployment.
As a slide says, these architectures
deliver measurable performance
improvements, faster development cycles,
optimize resource use, and ultimately
a strong return on your AI investments.
We'll walk through the challenges,
the core native concepts, specific
architectural patterns, and the tangible
benefits you can expect, often backed by
industry observations and project results.
Let's start by contrasting
the old way with the new.
Many of us have experienced
traditional AI deployment.
It often involved manual steps, complex
handoffs between data science and
operation teams, and infrastructure that
wasn't purpose built for ML workloads.
This frequently led to the
deployment cycles measured in weeks,
sometimes even in months, plagued
by manual error prone processes.
Now compare that to the
cloud native approach.
By leveraging automation,
containerization, and infrastructure as
a code concepts will detailed shortly,
will dramatically shift deployment times
down to days, hours, or even minutes.
Rollouts become automated
and consistent reducing.
The IT worked on my machine syndrome.
The measurable results often cited in
industry reports and confirmed through
project experience speak for themselves.
Organizations adopting these patterns
typically see around 70% faster
time reproduction for the AI models.
Think about the competitive
advantage that speeds provide.
Furthermore, the automation and
consistency lead to what case
studies show can be staggering.
85% reduction in deployment failure.
This isn't just about speed,
it's about relay reliability and
trust in the deployment process.
A corner store of cloud native
approach is containerization
using technologies like daca.
Why is this so helpful for ai?
First, environment, consistency containers
build the code, bundle the code,
libraries and dependencies together.
This eliminates those frustrating
works on my machine issues and ensures
the environment is identical for a
deployment through two production.
This consistency alone based
on operational data can reduce
deployment failures significantly,
often by as much as 78%.
Second reduced serving latency.
We can build highly optimized
minimal container images
specifically for inference.
This focus cuts down on bloat and
performance benchmarks often show this can
decrease modern inference time by around
35%, leading to a much better and faster
user experience for your AI applications.
Third resource, your isolation.
Containers allow components to run
in isolation, preventing resource
contention when one process hogs
CPU, or memory needed by another.
This isolation also enables
precise independent scaling.
You can scale your inference
service without necessarily scaling
other parts of your application.
Finally, enhance security containers.
Provide isolated runtime environments.
By using minimal base images,
which significantly reduce the
potential attack surface, a widely
recognized security benefit, making
our AI deployments more secure.
Another foundational element is
infrastructure as code, which
is sometimes called as IAZ.
Instead of manually clicking buttons
in a cloud console, we define our
infrastructure servers, networks.
Databases and kuban
Kubernetes clusters in code.
The key is declarative configuration.
We use tools like Terraform or Lummi
to define the desired state of our
infrastructure and the tool configures
out how to achieve that result.
This is much more reliable and repeatable
than writing procedural skills.
Do this and do then that.
These configuration files are version
control, like application code, giving us
transparent change tracking, and ability
to easily roll back if issues arise.
Tools like Terraform also offer
seamless multi-cloud deployments
using a consist syntax.
The business outcome of IAC is
profound for AI infrastructure as
seen across many implementations.
A potential 90% reduction in configuration
drift across environments, ensuring dev,
staging and production look the same.
Often 65%.
Faster disaster recovery because we
can automatically reprovision the
entire infrastructure stack from code.
Experience often shows 42% lower
infrastructure costs through optimization,
eliminating manual provision, zombie
resources, and leveraging automation and
significantly reducing operational toil.
Sometimes 75% fewer manual
interventions needed for routine task.
So the question is, how do
these concepts come together?
In an architecture, a common
effective approach is a layered
architectural pattern, which promotes
decoupling and specialization.
At the top, we have application
layer, which promotes
decoupling and specialization.
At the top below that we, that
sits the ML framework layer.
This is where optimized framework
like TensorFlow or PyTorch, often with
custom accelerated runtimes designed for
high performance or specific hardware.
Then comes container orchestration.
This is typically Kubernetes
managing the lifecycle of our
contained rise application.
And the model.
It handles auto scaling based on load,
ensure high availability, and can
use specialized ML operators like Q
Flow operators, TF job for managing
training and inference workloads.
Finally, the last is the infrastructure
layers, which provides the raw
compute power like machine virtual
machines, bare metal servers.
Which are crucial for ai
sometimes like GPUs, TPU clusters
for accelerated computation.
The beauty of this decoupled
architecture is that each layer can
be scaled and optimized independently.
Project outcomes often demonstrate
benefits like 45%, lower maintenance
cost, 60% improved resource utilization
as each layer is right sized and
greatly enhance operational flexibility.
Within our cloud native AI architecture,
it's critical to recognize that model
training and model inference serving
have very different requirements.
We should design separate
environments for them.
The training environment needs
massive computation power, often
leveraging high powered GPU clusters.
It benefits from the batch
processing optimization.
Admin can use cost saving
strategies like spot instances,
which are interruptible vs.
At lower cost.
Since training jobs can often tolerate
restart, the infrastructure here
can be ephemeral, spun off for a
training run or to down afterwards.
The inference environment, on the
other hand, must be optimized for low
latency to serve predictions quickly.
It requires robust auto-scaling
capabilities to handle
fluctuating request volumes.
Users right size, compute resources
for efficiency, and absolutely needs
a high availability design to ensure
the service is always responsive.
This separation has a
direct business impact.
Frequently observed and optimized
cloud deployments, we often see
35% reduction cloud costs by using
the right resources for each job.
Example, spot for training model
deployment can be 50% faster.
As the inference environment
is streamlined and ready, we
can achieve 99.9% or higher.
Inference service uptime a common
SLA target enabled by HA design
and the system exhibits elasticity.
Scaling automatically
during demand spikes.
As AI models become more complex, numerous
managing the d complex and numerous,
managing the data features they rely
on becoming, becomes a major challenge.
This is where a feature store comes in.
A feature store is a centralized
repository for curated, documented, and
versioned features used in ML models.
It typically involves several components,
feature engineering, standardizing how
features are defined, validated and
transformed through shared pipelines.
Feature storage, maintaining
time, consistent version feature.
Data often with comprehensive
metadata tracking so you can know
exactly what data was used for.
Track training.
Training access, enable, enabling
reproducible model training by allowing
Retriable retrieval of features as
they were at specific points in time.
Point in time, correct.
Inference serving, delivering optimized
low latency feature vectors needed
by models for real-time protections.
Feature stores significantly
accelerate air development.
A benefit highlighted in many M lops case
studies by enabling feature reuse across
team, they eliminate duplicated effort.
They solve the notorious training
service skew problem, which features
used in training differ from production.
And reduce overall
deployment time by about 40%.
Organizations implementing feature
store are often report results like 35%
faster time to market for new models,
and a 60% improvement around operational
efficiency related to feature management.
We mentioned Kubernetes earlier.
Let's look at some specific
Kubernetes organization patterns
that are particularly valuable.
For AI ML workloads, the first one
is custom resource definitions,
sometimes called as CRDs.
Kubernetes allows us to define our
own custom types for ml. This means
resources like TF Job or Python job
that understand the specifics of running
distributed training jobs or custom
resources for managing model deployments.
This enables a declarative approach
to managing the ML lifecycle itself.
Operators, these automate complex
stateful operations, ML operators
can manage the entire lifecycle of
the ml machine learning, workflow,
provisioning resources, running
training, deploying models, monitoring,
codifying operational knowledge.
Third is the horizontal pod auto scaling.
This automatically scales the number
of pods, containers based on metrics
like CP utilization, request volume,
or even metrics like GPA utilization.
This ensures inference services
have the right amount of
resources in the real time.
Fourth is a service mesh integration.
Example is issue a service mesh
provides advanced capabilities
like fine-grain traffic routing.
Essential for carrying deployment,
candry deployments or AB testing models.
Mutual DLS for security and detailed
observability metrics, latency
error rates across services.
These patterns turn Kubernetes
into a powerful ML aware platform,
enhancing automation and control
AI particularly.
Particularly deep learning
heavily relies on specialized
hardware like GPUs and TPUs.
Effectively orchestrating these
expensive resources is critical
in a cloud native environment.
So the first is the GPU and TPU
management Kubernetes device plugin
allow fine-grained hardware allocation.
Advanced schedulers can enable
multi-tenant GPU sharing
with some implementation.
Showing utilization increase to
three X compared to the dedicated,
dedicating a whole GP to one
task performance optimizations.
Techniques like numa aware scheduling
according to performance tuning
guides can improve throughput by 40%.
Similarly, using mixed precision
inference often reduces latency by
60% with minimal accuracy loss as
documented in frameworks, best practices.
Cost optimization.
In integrating spot instances
for training workloads.
A common cloud saving strategy can
slash training costs by up to 70%.
Furthermore, automatic hardware
hibernation spinning down expensive
GPUs TPUs when idle project experience
shows that it can be saved around 45%
on idle costs, which is crucial given
how expensive these accelerators are.
Intelligent orchestration ensures
we get the maximum performance and
value from our hardware investments.
Bringing all of this together requires
robust automation, which leads us
to ML lops and CI ICD pipeline,
tailored for machine learning.
ML OPS applies DevOps
principles to the ML lifecycle.
CICD pipelines are the backbone
of ML ops continuous integration.
This isn't just about code anymore.
For ml, it involves automated model
testing, unit testing, integration tests,
data validation, model validation against
predefined metrics and quality gates.
It often integrates with code
model repositories via web hooks.
We need automated checks for unit
tests, model quality metrics, and even
security scanning for dependencies.
Continuous delivery focuses on automating
the preparation for deployment.
It includes packaging the model and core
code o often in two containers, generating
environment specific configurations like
Kubernetes, helm charts and versioning.
All artifacts produce continuous
deployment, automates the actual
rollout of the model to production.
We use progressive deployment
strategies like blue-green deployment,
switching traffic to a new version
or caning releases routing a
small percentage of traffic first.
Automated analysis for of performance
metrics and roll back capabilities are
crucial here for ensure to ensure safety.
These pipelines central to
ML lops maturity models.
Ensure.
Moving from code.
Commit to a validated deployed model
is fast, reliable, and repeatable.
Deployment is in the end of the story.
Models degrade over time due to changes
in their data patterns sometimes.
What has drift?
Automating?
Monitoring solutions are essential for
maintaining performance and production.
Cloud native monitoring tools
integrated with ML platform
provide critical capabilities.
First is the faster drift detection.
Advanced algorithms continuously
monitor input data and model
protections, detecting data drift
and model drift in near real time.
This allows for immediate corrective
action like retraining before
performance degrades significantly.
Reports suggests improvements of up
to 85% in detection speed compared
to manual checks system of time.
A fault tolerant monitoring architecture
potentially with predictive maintenance
alerts helps ensure continuous operation
even during infrastructure clips
contributing to a 99.95% or higher
system uptime that many platforms aim for
resource optimization.
Intelligent monitoring feeds back
into the resource allocation by
observing actual workload patterns.
Dynamic adjustment can significantly
reduce cloud expenditure.
Practical results often
show reduction around 40%.
ROI multiplier crucially, end-to-end
monitoring connects ML performance
metrics directly with business
key performance indicators.
This allows organizations to clearly
see the value of AI is delivering and
optimized models based on business impact.
Effectively acting as an ROI multiplier.
Some case studies indicate this can
potentially triple the return on
AI investments by ensuring models
stay relevant and performant.
So to wrap up, adopting cloud
native architectural patterns is
fundamental for achieving AI success
at scale with the enterprise.
We have seen how containerization.
Infrastructure as code layered
architecture, separating training
and inference feature stores,
Kubernetes orchestration, hardware
management, ML ops, pipelines, and
automated monitoring work together.
The key to takeaways are the tangible
benefits widely reported across
industry, dramatically accelerated
deployment cycles, improved resource
utilization and cost savings.
Enhance reliability and security and
ultimately a much stronger and more
measurable return on your AI investment.
Thank you very much for your
time and attention today.
I hope this overview of cloud
native AI patterns was valuable.
Please feel free to
correct me on LinkedIn.
If you have any questions, my
contacts are on the screen.
Thank you so much.