Hello everyone.
I'm Vij Bajo.
Today I'm going to talk about
something I deal with all the time,
how we can use machine learning to
make log analysis faster and easier.
If you have ever spent hours digging
through logs trying to figure out
what went wrong, this talk is for you.
I'll walk you through how ML can help
detect patterns spot tissue early, and
made debugging a lot less frustrating.
Let's talk about the reality we all face.
Traditional debugging is still
largely slow and reactive.
We wait for alerts, dig through logs, and
hope we can connect the dots fast enough.
On top of that, we are dealing
with sheer volume, millions of log
lines, most of which are noise.
It's like trying to find a
sentence in Australia dictionary.
This leads to one painful metric.
MTTR mean time to resolution.
It keeps rising, and with that comes
stress pager fatigue and delays
that ripple into customer impact.
What's missing?
Intelligence?
Something that can help us
make sense of the mess quickly.
Not just search faster, but think smarter.
Now let's flip the perspective.
What if instead of treating logs like
noise, we saw them as a gold mine.
Logs are packed with patterns,
repetitive behavior, known
error trails and hidden signals.
They're often hiding in plain
sight, just waiting to be uncovered.
More importantly, logs are real.
They reflect exactly what happened.
User activity, system
behavior failure traces.
There's no modeling guesswork.
It's raw, authentic telemetry.
And here's the thing, manual
analysis just can't keep up.
Humans are great at spotting
obvious behaviors, but ML can
uncover subtle correlations and
patterns that would otherwise be
invisible, especially at scale.
Even though logs are rich in value,
there are major hurdles that can
make analyzing them a real challenge.
First, the noise signal ratio is brutal.
Most locks are noise.
Finding something meaningful feels
like digging through sand for a needle.
Second, formal inconsistency.
Format, inconsistency.
Different teams, different systems.
Every log looks different.
Some are JSON, some are plain
text and some are semi-structured.
Passing becomes a nightmare.
Then there are temporal gaps.
Logs don't always line up neatly in time.
You miss cause effect, relationships and
important, closer or lost in between.
And finally, rare event detection.
The critical stuff, it often shows
up once quietly, not in a burst,
and those are the things that
ML can help us actually surface.
So how do we actually extract
meaningful patterns from messy log data?
Let's look at a few core ML
techniques that make this possible.
First one is clustering helps
us group similar log entries.
It's like letting the algorithm say,
Hey, these events looks related.
Embeddings convert law raw
data into a format that models
can actually understand.
Think of it like turning unstructured
text into numbers that carry meaning.
Third is dimensionality
reduction like PCA.
Help us remove the noise and focus
on the most important features.
The next is sequence model.
Sequence.
Models like L SDMs can
identify patterns across time.
This is the key for catching time-based
anomalies or repetitive behavior.
All of these sequences or
techniques work together to make
patterns, recognition, more stakes,
more scalable and intelligent.
So when it comes to finding
anomalies in logs, there are
a few main schools of thought.
Each with its own strengths.
First, we have statistical models.
These are great for known
patterns and baselines.
Things like zco analysis or moving
averages can quickly flex spikes or drops.
But for more complex, hidden issues, we
need machine learning models, techniques
like isolation, forest auto encoders,
and one class SBMs can detect patterns
that humans or simple rules just miss.
And in many production systems, the most
practical solution is a hybrid approach.
Combining rule-based filters
with ML bag verification.
With feedback loops, the
system gets smarter over time.
The key is to choose the right mix
based on scale, noise level, and
what kind of anomalies you're after.
Here is a high level look at how
everything fits together in a real world.
ML powered log analysis system.
It starts with log collection.
We gather logs from multiple sources,
services, apps, infrastructure layers.
The goal is to cast a wide net
so we don't miss any signal.
Then comes pre-processing.
This is a critical step.
We clean, normalize and structure the
raw logs into a machine readable format.
Think of this as a
translating chaos in a mess.
Sorry, into order.
After that, we feed into the ML
pipeline where models perform pattern
recognition and anomaly detection.
This is where all those technologies
we talked about earlier, kick in.
Finally, the insight engine
takes those signals and turns
it into something useful.
Alerts, probably dashboards,
visualizations, so team can,
teams can act, not just observe.
So this full pipeline ensures that we go
beyond just logging and actually deliver
operational intelligence in real time.
So let's see what all of
this looks like in practice.
A real world example, right?
Incorporating machine learning
into observability and incident
management isn't just theoretical,
it has tangible benefits.
Take the H Estonia's Health and
Welfare Information System Center,
for example, by implementing
Elastic's observability platform.
They streamline their incident
management processes, achieving
a 40% reduction in MTTR.
Similarly, a major e-commerce
platform reported a 40% decrease
in MTTR after deploying an AI
driven root cause analysis tool.
These cases underscored the substantial
impact ML can have on improving system
reliability and reducing downtime.
Even with all the power of m. L, debugging
is never a fully hands off process.
Machine learning can surface patterns.
But it lacks context.
It doesn't know if a spike is normal
for Black Friday or truly unusual.
That's where human come in.
Engineers play a vital role in
validating what the models find.
They help fine tune alerts,
provide a edge case context, and
correct the system when needed.
And over time this
becomes a feedback loop.
The system learns from human
responses and gets smarter.
The more you interact with it and
more, the more useful it becomes.
So this isn't just an AI tool, it's
a collaboration between machine
learning and human insight that
builds trust and reliability.
As much as I believe in the power
of ml, it's important to recognize
its limitations and build and
responsibly build responsibility.
To say first transparency is a challenge.
Many advanced models work like
black boxes, which can hurt trust.
Engineers need to know
why an alert is fired.
If we can't explain it,
then we don't trust it.
Second model maintenance ML
models aren't set and forget.
They drift over time as system behavior
changes without regular retraining, their
accuracy drops and that creates risk.
And the third, ethical concerns,
not all systems get equal.
Attention bias can creep in.
For example, if alerting prioritizes
revenue critical services and
ignores others, we need to
design with fairness in mind.
The takeaway here.
ML isn't magic.
It's a tool.
It works best when paid with human
responsibility and continue scale.
To wrap up, here are
the four key takeaways.
I hope you'll leave with
first, scale and speed.
ML brings scale.
We simply can't achieve normal.
It spots patterns faster across
more data with less noise.
Second root cause detection, pattern
recognition helps us debug smarter.
We get to the why faster,
not just the what.
That's where real time savings happen.
Third, reduce noise.
Smarter.
Anomaly detection means
fewer false rhythms.
It improves focus, less alert,
fat fatigue, more clarity, and
finally, incremental adoption.
You don't have to go all
in one day on day one.
Start small.
Prove value, build trust.
That's how we evolve debugging
one smarter layer at a time.
I truly believe ML is not just a trend
here, it's a path forward to building
calm, more intelligent systems.
So that's it from my side.
Thank you so much for
joining this session.
I really hope this gave you some
insights useful into how ML can help
streamline debugging and reduce noise.
If it did spark any ideas, questions, or
if you're working on similar challenges,
I would love to know what you think about
this and discuss this more on LinkedIn.
If you want to connect to me, please
feel free to connect me on LinkedIn.
Thank you guys.