Hello everyone.
Hope all you guys are well.
My name is Vahid from University of TD
and International Student Recruitment
services company based in the uk
and we recruit the students from all
over the world to study in the uk.
So if you want to study
in the uk, just join us.
Okay.
Let's go.
It's wonderful being with you today.
I'd like to start with something
we all know artificial intelligence
which is no longer the future.
It's already a big part of our
lives and it's not going anywhere.
Whether we like it or not AI is
changing how we live, how we work,
how we learn, even how we think.
And in education, this
change is happening fast.
Students all over the world are
using ai in their studies today.
All of us know.
And the question is, are
they using it properly?
Okay.
A global survey by the digital digital
Education Council in July, 2024, which
included more than 3,800 students
from 16 countries found that 86% of
the students use AI in their studies.
And more than half of them
do so on a Bay Weekly basis.
Most of the students say they use
AI to research for information
mainly to write assignments.
About 86% 60, sorry, 66% said they
used chat g Pity, showing just how
prevalent the use of this tool has been.
An additional report by Status
Star published in August, 2024.
Also included about two months
late after, after two months.
About previous survey also concluded
that 86% of college students
use AI tools for their studies.
These statistics are attempting
to inform us about something.
AI is already a big part of
education, but here the question,
are students using AI to learn or
are they using to replace learning?
That's the question, that's the concern.
Too many students with AI to do
the work for them to do assignments
instead of as a tool to help and
empower them to think and create.
This is where the concern begins.
Today I want to talk about this
concerns, but also the potential
of the other concerns as well.
Because when when used in the
right way, AI can enhance a
student, not replace universities.
Let's explore how
ai detectors AI detectors.
Maybe many, you, many
of you guys know or not.
Programs designed to establish
whether a written work was
produced or with the assistance
of artificial intelligence or not.
And these programs have been installed
by the majority of the schools, majority
of profit university professors.
These programs like ING,
GPT Zero Regionality.
And even Grammarly now are employed by the
majority to check essay and assignments.
Now, I'm not here to argue about whether
these detectors are always correct.
We know that they're not sick, honestly,
and we already know they have so many
problems and issues to detect the ai.
They frequently get it wrong.
And even human written
stuff gets called hunting.
But again they may get
wrong, but this is the truth.
Most professors don't
depend on detectors only
because they already know about
AI detectors problems or possible
problems on something like that.
And.
They con, they contrast the
students' recent writing with
what they've written before.
They check their references as sites
because AI programs such GGPT tend
to use fictional or Foster Francis.
Indeed.
A study recently conducted reported
that just 7% of chat g PT generated
references were accurate and verifiable.
They also search for suspicious
patterns excessively formal tone,
absence of personal voice or academic
terminology that does not fit the
students' normal styles that they know.
Even some teachers talk with the
students about how they write with them
to see if they actually wrote or wrote
it or just submitted what AI offered.
So what did the student do?
Another hack arrived after so
many problems, AI humanizer.
Okay, let's.
Talk.
What is ai humanize?
Ai humanizes are softwares that
makes material written by AI and
rewards, rewards it so it sounds more
human, and we can call it humanized.
Nice.
They attempt to fool AI detectors
by changing sentence sentence
structure tone and vocabulary
even, or rephrase, paraphrase.
And in the majority of cases they
have succeeded, to be honest.
They have succeeded and
they've imposed on the system.
But there is a real question.
Did they make a difference?
Professors still call it out.
They sense the disconnect in tone,
the lack of through thinking and that
this, the disparity between the voice
of this student and the end result.
And more importantly students,
don students themselves know when
they did not actually do the work,
let's something else.
Even if the assignments is not called
if if it wasn't written by the students.
Let's think about that.
That's not fair.
It's not fair.
There's no learning involved.
Universities have different
policies, actually different
policies, and let me show you.
Okay.
Students, universities
have different policies.
Some of them ban AI use entirely.
Others allow it, but.
Only if the students disclose it.
It's a controversial topic.
Some professors view AI use as a cheating
while other view it as a chance to learn.
I remember one educator suggested
recently, instead of putting
detection front and center, let's
change the way we design assignments.
Make them personal, reflective
or event event driven.
Let's make it harder
to outsource thinking.
And I think that's the answer.
I think that's the answer.
We shouldn't fear ai, but we
should fear a future where
students do not think anymore.
So now the question is, what is the
right approach to using AI in education?
How do we move from
replacement to empowerment?
Okay.
Let's discuss about that in next.
Let's pause a MO for a moment
and imagine a different world.
A word where students don't use AI
to escape learning, but to deepen it,
imagine students asking AI not to write
their assignment, but to show them how
to write, imagine, and AI that teaches
them the structure of a strong say.
That explain what makes an introduction,
compelling how to organize arguments
and how to critically analyze
a source, something like that.
Picture a student working on a
difficult assignments and instead
of handing it off to ai, they ask.
I don't know how to start.
Can you help me think it through?
And the AI respond.
Let's break it out.
Let's break it down together.
Here's what's unclear and
here's how we can fix it.
I like a trusted mentor, this AI gives
feedback, identifies weaknesses, and
guides the students step by step.
But never does the work for them.
I believe it's beautiful word, isn't it?
Imagine about this AI mentor, AI friend.
It's the world that real
educators carrying professors
and mentors already try to build.
They they read every line
of a student's assignments.
They offer feedback not just
on grammar, but on ideas.
They don't just grade they guide.
Now imagine an AI that
assures the mission.
This mission is, let's talk
one that, two different ais.
One of that refuses to
do the work for you.
Even if you ask another one says I
won't write this for you, but I learn,
teach you how to become someone who can,
this is no longer a tool control.
It's a friend.
A friend who has your back,
but also holds you accountable.
In this world, AI
doesn't replace learning.
It re reinforces it.
It pushes students to become independent
thinkers, strong writers, better
learners, and that's the shift we need.
From common and controlled AI to
collaborative, ethical, empowering ai
let's stop asking AI to do our work and
start asking to help us do it better.
Okay.
Okay, so where does that leave us?
If we truly want AI to argue education
and not detract from it, we must rethink
our relationship with this technology.
We need to move away from shortcuts.
Away from plagiarism, away from
mindsets of let AI do it for me.
Instead, let's help a student
see AI for what it should be.
Powerful learning, power learning partner,
powerful learning friend, learning mentor,
let's instruct students and encouraging
them, encourage them to use AI as a tool
for exploration, feedback, and grow all.
And
Yeah, to ask more more.
Informed questions to understand
their mistakes, to grow with with
each try not avoid the process.
For in for, in its sense, AI was never
meant to take the place of human learning.
It was designed to accelerate
human growth, right?
And educator education.
Real education isn't just about answers.
It's about a struggle, reflection, wonder.
It's learning to think not what to say.
And also, let's create
environments where students are
not punished for leveraging ai.
What to learn to leverage its
responsibly, ethically, and creatively.
Let's give them to.
Competencies.
The mindset.
Mindset and the confidence
to own their learning with
the support of tools like ai.
Because if we do, we not just
protecting the future of education,
we are taking it to a higher level.
Okay?
Yes.
This better word, we can make this
award and I think this word is possible.
Okay.
What is the best part?
We are building it.
We are developing a new AI
powered platform in the ed tech
education technology space.
One that's not here to replace
educators or right assignments is
here to empower students to become.
Better thinkers and better
writers on this platform.
Every students gets their own AI
friend, a personalized academic guide.
They can name they can
interact with and grow on site.
This is more than a chat bot.
This is like an AI mentor.
Instructed not only by code, but by
actual academic professionals who
understand the struggles students
face with writing assignment.
TE is essay and academic articles
in the, and that's the point in,
in, in the first phase, this AI
friend will answer questions the
students have about academic writing.
Read their work and provide helpful
feedback, help them learn what went
wrong and how to read correctly.
Offer guidance instead
of something like hacks.
And most importantly,
don't do the work for them.
This AI doesn't attempt to be omniscient.
Omniscient
if it doesn't.
Know a response.
It won't guess.
Instead, it flags it.
That a human academic admin okay,
can step it, teach the correct
answer to this AI friend and
teach the AI and this ai friend.
Learn it in time, this AI friend
will become better than the past.
It will become more intelligent and it'll
begin to customize the guidance based
on each student's university and in the
future, maybe even based on the specific
expectations of individual professors.
And imagine that's,
let's,
okay.
Imagine that.
A deeply knowledgeable, always
available ethical academic guide.
Who knows your background, your
challenges, your goals, and is there
to support you, not replacing you.
Yeah, we're not just building a tool.
We are building trust,
accountability and growth.
We are not just implementing
AI in education.
We are fortifying education with ai.
And if we do it correctly, we'll
create a generation of learners who
don't just know how to write, but know
to how, and much know how to think,
how to question, how to ask a
question, how to ask a question
correctly, and how to innovate.
Okay with AI as a facilitator.
Facilitator, not an aid with AI
as a facilitator, not an eight.
And this regional responsible empowering
AI in education isn't just theoretical.
It's something we've started working on.
We are building a platform.
Called estimate an academic support
system where the students are not just
user users of ai, but collaborators
in their own learning process.
The idea is a simple but powerful.
Every student is paired with AI companion
one they can name, talk, and grow with.
Not a tool to perform their work for
them, but a guide to help them learn to
do it for themselves in its initial phase,
asking addresses academic writing it
reads students drafts, offers constructive
feedbacks, detects weaknesses and offers.
So many suggestions always based
on peda geological principles and
never replacing the student's voice.
What is the difference between
anate with all of the other ais?
What makes Ased unique is the
manner in which it learns.
It's not merely trained, but on the
base data or something like that, or
search on the internet or learning
from the internet, but under human
supervision by specialists in higher
studies and scholarly writing.
If the AI hesitates on a question, it
doesn't provide a placeholder answer.
No, not like other ais.
It flags the issue.
And a human admin a step in not merely
to response correctly, V, but to teach
the AI how to respond in the future.
This creates creates a model
in which the system grows.
Over the time, ethically, rightly,
and in the line with real academic
expectations, that's the point.
That's the right thing that universities,
or colleges or schools wants, or
professor wants or lecturer wants.
The ultimate vision is even broader
estimate comes of age with the students.
It'll eventually be capable of recognizing
institutional context, understanding
how expectations can differ between
universities or even between specific
structures and beyond beyond the academy.
It'll support the students through
daily challenges, finding housing,
navigating administrative procedures.
Adjusting to life abroad.
The hope is not perfection.
It's continually growth and trust.
Estimate isn't being built to
be the solution to all things.
It's being built to be a responsible.
A responsible alley in a more complex
educational landscape, helping a
student not by doing the work for them,
but by accompanying upon accompanying
them this is one way we believe
AI can actually make a difference
in education, not by replacing the
work of students or teachers, but.
By amplifying what makes them human
this isn't just a tool for students.
We are building estimate with the
clear intention of working alongside
university, not around them.
Our goal is to create a system that
academics, institutions can trust.
A system that encourages responsible A IU.
Which the university like that with
the colleges like that, which the
schools like that with the professors
and academic staff likes that.
We believe that if we do it,
do this correctly, universities
won't just adopt this AI friend.
They'll embrace it because it's
in line with their purpose.
It honors the.
Standards and it makes their
students more resilient.
That's the future we are working toward
one where technology and academia
aren't at art, but in collaboration.
Yes, that's the point.
Thank you very much for your attention,
for your kind attention and hope to
sue all of you guys in estimate and.
Change the future of learning, future
of education in education technology.
Thank you very much.