Speaker 25: Hello everyone.
Before we get into machine
learning models or architecture,
I wanna start with a simple idea.
Third party risk management was
never designed for scale, speed,
or complexity we operate in today.
Most third party programs are
built for periodic reviews, static
questionnaires, and manual judgements.
But today, enterprises depend on
hundreds, sometimes thousands of
third parties operating across cloud
or APIs, global supply chains, and
regulated financial ecosystems.
And risk doesn't wait for annual reviews.
So today I want to show you how we have
been rearchitecting, TPRM as a machine
learning driven intelligent system.
Not just a compliance function.
This is not theoretical.
This is what we have actually being built,
tested, broken, and rebuilt at scale.
Let me start with a quick
introduction so you know where
these lessons are coming from.
My name is Saga Berry and I lead third
party risk management oversight at a
blockchain based stable point company.
We operate in the digital financial
ecosystem, and we are a FinTech and one of
the largest issuer of stablecoin globally.
The reason I mentioned that is
because we operate in a high risk,
fast changing environment where
regulatory expectations evolve quickly.
Vendors change constantly, and
risk signals shift in real time.
I've spent over a decade across.
Third party and enterprise
risk in many fortune hundreds.
Big four consulting, FinTech, thanks.
Across all of these environments,
one patent kept repeating, risk
teams were doing the right thing,
but the system itself wasn't designed
for speed, scale, or intelligence.
My work today sits at an
intersection of risk management,
machine learning, and automation.
Not to cut corners, but to
make risk management smarter,
faster, and more defensible.
So what you'll hear today isn't
a theory or a vendor pitch.
It's a playbook.
We used to reduce our
onboarding time dramatically.
While improving risk outcomes,
auditability and regulatory
confidence, I am sure many of you
have already experimenting with AI
or machine learning in your third
party risk management programs.
My goal here today is simple.
I want you to walk away
with two or three ideas.
You can actually take back
and apply to your program.
Or your platform or even
your product roadmap.
All right.
Before we talk about solutions,
I wanna level set on a problem
we have all dealing with.
Modern enterprises don't
just have vendors anymore.
They have an entire ecosystem, hundreds,
sometimes thousands of third parties.
Your cloud providers, SaaS platforms,
payment processors, data vendors,
open source dependencies, each one
expand your attack surface and more
importantly, your risk surface.
But most traditional programs were
designed for a very different world.
They assume risk changes slowly.
They assume reviews can
happen annually or quarterly.
They assume static questionnaires
and manual reviews are enough.
That assumption no longer holds risk
today moves at a speed of software,
not at the speed of audit cycles.
At the same time, regulatory expectations
are going in the opposite direction.
Not loser, but tighter.
More transparency.
More explainability, more
continuous oversight.
So we are stuck with a contradiction.
We are expected to move faster while
proving more using systems that ne
were never designed to scale this way.
And the contradiction shows up
very clearly in our traditional
risk management structure.
Moving on to next slide, the
traditional structural misalignment.
This slide is very uncomfortable
because it describes how
most of us have been trained.
Let's start with a calendar based
reviews, annual or quarterly assessment.
Assume risk politely awaits its turn, but
breaches, outages, financial distress.
They don't care about
your review calendars.
If something changes in month two.
You don't discover until month 12
if, and that's if you're lucky.
Your next is static questioners,
one size fit, all surveys, same
questions, same order, same depth,
regardless of vendor profile.
So low risk vendors buried in unnecessary
questions and high risk vendors often
don't get the depth they deserve.
Everyone is frustrated.
Your vendors, your business teams, and
your, of course your risk teams as well.
And finally over there is
manual evidence review.
Humans is reading hundreds
of unstructured documents.
Your policies, soc reports,
certifications, PDF after PF stacked.
They don't just create bottleneck,
it creates inconsistencies.
Imagine this two analysts can
read the same document and each
reach different conclusions, and
neither one is technically wrong.
So what we end up with
is not a people problem.
It's a structural misalignment between
how risk behaves today and how TPRM
systems were originally designed.
And that realization is what
forced us to rethink DPRM.
Not as a checklist or process,
but a intelligent system.
So the question becomes, if this
model doesn't scale, then what does?
So once you accept that the
traditional TPRM doesn't scale, the
real question becomes, what does
scalable model actually look like?
For us, the answer wasn't.
Add more people or buy bigger tools.
It was Rearchitecting, TPRM as a
machine learning driven system, and
at a higher level, this architecture
has four moving parts, which I've
listed over there on the slide.
First one is data inges.
So instead of relying only on what
vendor sense, we ingest data continuously
through policies attestations,
public disco closures, intel threat
intelligence, financial signals.
The goal is simple.
Do not wait for risk to be reported.
Observe it directly
when wherever possible.
Second is intelligent processing.
This is where machine learning and
NLP starts doing the heavy lifting,
extracting control evidence from
unstructured document, normalizing
it and making it comparable.
Humans are great at judgment.
They're not great at
reading some 300 policies.
Then we move into risk evaluation
instead of static scoring,
we evaluate risk dynamically.
Based on vendor risk profiles,
your criticality control maturity
and absorbed signals, and just as
important, every determination comes
with explainability and not just score.
And finally, you have
continuous monitoring.
This is where the biggest shift happens.
TPRM stops being episodic and starts
behaving like a living system.
The architecture runs
continuously, not annually.
One of the first bottlenecks we
attacked was manual evidence review.
Think about how much time TPRM team
spends reading PDFs or your SOC reports.
Kz.
This is where.
Natural language processing
changed everything for us.
We trained NLP models to extract
and normalize control evidences from
unstructured vendor artifacts instead
of asking Does this document look okay?
The model asks, does this
document demonstrate the control?
We actually care about it identifies
the control, extracts the relevant
text, maps it back to the requirements.
And this is critical.
Every extracted data point
maintains full traceability.
You can click from risk conclusion all
the way back to risk extract sentences
in this source document that matters,
not just for audit, but for trust.
The impact were immediate.
Thousands of documents processed
automatically, massive reduction
in manual workload, and far more
consistent outcomes across reviewers.
Humans didn't disappear from the process.
They moved up the value chain from
reading documents to validating judgments.
Once evidence extraction was
no longer the bottleneck.
We could tackle something
even bigger as a redundancy.
Once we solved the document review,
we ran into a different problem.
We were still asking vendors way too
many questions, and not because we
loved questionnaire, but because the
different frameworks kept asking the
same thing in a slightly different way.
So we turned to.
Semantic similarity models instead
of treating question as a text
string, we treated them as meaning.
If two question, meaning two questions
are asking for the same control,
the system knows it, even if the
wording is completely different.
That resulted in eliminating redundancies.
The model clusters overlapping questions
across frameworks, be it SOC or iso
internal policy or Regulatory requirement.
So instead of five nearly
identical questions, the vendor
sees one intelligent question.
That alone removed a lot of friction,
but we didn't just stop there.
The system adapts follow up questions
based on how the vendor answers.
If the control clearly exists
and is mature, we move on.
If something looks weak, can ambiguous,
that's where we dig deep depth where
it matters, and speed where it doesn't.
Finally, context aware routing instead
of dumping every question on a single
vendor contact, the model routes the
question to the right stakeholder.
Security to security SMEs, finance
to finance teams, response quality
went straight up back and forth.
Went straight down.
That is the moment the vendor stopped
saying, this feels painful, and started
saying, this actually makes sense.
Now, if you're relying on machine
learning this heavily, there's a
natural question that comes up.
Whenever I talk to ML in risk
management, someone inevitably will
ask, but what if the model is wrong?
That's the right question to ask.
We never trust a single model
to make a risk determination.
Instead, we use assembling models,
multiple independent models, evaluating
the same risk signal each model.
Looks at data slightly different.
And if they agree, confidence goes up.
If they disagree, the system
flags for cases automatically.
So every risk output comes
with a confidence score.
High confidence, the
workflow moves forward.
Low confidence, a human steps in.
We didn't remove human judgment, we
aimed it where it actually adds value.
This also solved a major governance
concern, single model bias, black box
decisions, regulatory explainability.
With multiple models, you can
explain why a conclusion was reached
and how confident we are in it.
So at this point, something
important has changed.
TPRM was no longer just fast.
It was smarter.
More consistent and more defensible,
and that set the stage for a bigger
shift of all moving from a periodic
review to a continuous intelligence.
Up until now, everything I've shown you
focused on making assessments better, but
the real breakthrough happened when we.
Stopped asking, how do
you improve reviews?
And started asking instead, why are
we still relying on reviews at all?
Traditional TPRM assumes
risks changes slowly.
So we check it periodically but
modern risk doesn't behave that way.
So we moved from periodic assessments
to an event driven monitoring.
Instead of waiting for 12 months to
rediscover risk system, continuously
ingest signals from multiple domains.
When something materially changes,
a vulnerability disclosure, a
breach notification, a financial
signal, an operational anomaly, the
system doesn't wait, it reacts, and
that is the important distinction.
We are not continuously reassessing
everything all the time.
That would just create a noise at a faster
speed, but we are listening for meaningful
events and only then triggering actions.
So TPRM stops being a calendar
driven process and starts behaving
like a monitoring capability.
The obvious next question is,
what exactly are we monitoring?
To make continuous monitoring work,
we need diverse, reliable data.
We group our inputs into five
primary signal categories.
First, threat intelligence,
real time feeds, vulnerability
databases, indicators of compromise.
This gives us early visibility into
emerging cyber risk, often before
vendor formally discloses them.
Second security advisories,
CVE disclosures, vendor
bulletins, patch announcements.
When something critical drops, we
know immediately and we can correlate
it to the effective vendors.
Third, financial indicators.
Credit ratings earning signals,
market stress indicators, because
financial distress often shows up
before a fan operational failure.
And fourth, public disclosures,
breach notifications, regulatory
finding enforcement actions.
These are high signal events.
And they deserve immediate attention.
And finally, the behavioral patterns
change in mental behavior, operational
anomalies shift in activity.
These are often subtle, but
incredibly powerful when you
see them early individually.
None of these signals tell you this
full story, but when you correlate
them across domains and over time.
You start seeing risk forming,
not just risk reported.
That's what allows us to move
from detection to prediction.
Up to this point, we have been
talking about detection, but the real
value of machine learning in TPRM
isn't just detecting risk faster.
It is detecting risk before
it fully materializes.
This is where predictive
risk detection comes in.
We have trained models on historic
incident data across cyber
events, your operational failures
and financial stress scenarios.
The goal wasn't to predict the
exact next breach, but the goal was
to identify patterns that tend to
slow up before anything goes wrong.
What we found was very interesting.
Major incidences are rarely random.
They usually pre proceed.
They're usually proceeded by subtle
signals such as missed patches,
delayed disclosures, changes in
operational behavior, financial stress.
Individually.
These signals look harmless, but
when you analyze them together over
time, patterns start to emerge.
That's where machine learning excels.
Connecting weak signals humans
would never correlate manually.
So in store, instead of reacting after
an incident, we can intervene early as
targeted questions trigger reassessments
or escalate controls before impact.
This is the difference between
managing risk and anticipating it.
Now, whenever you talk about prediction
and machine learning in regulated
environment, that's a very reasonable
concern that always comes up.
The question is, how do you explain
this to an auditor who a regulator,
or even your senior leadership 'cause
prediction without explainability?
It's just a guesswork, and that's not
acceptable in risk management, right?
So the first design principle we
enforced was transparent reasoning.
Every risk score comes with explanation
which factors contributed, how
strongly and why they mattered.
No.
Black boxes is second
audit trail preservation.
Every decision is traceable.
End to end from source data to model
output to final human judgment.
If someone asks, why did
we rate this vendor high?
You can show them precisely.
And finally, regulatory alignment.
This architecture was built with
regulatory expectation in mind.
That is strong spar,
defensibility, and consistency.
Machine learning didn't
weaken our governance model.
It strengthened it.
Okay.
At this point, TPRM stops being
viewed as a compliance obligation.
It starts being seen as a trusted
intelligence capability, and that
shift had very real business impact.
So let's talk about what all
of this actually delivered.
Not in theory, but in
practice First scale.
We can now assess continuous monitoring
thou, we can now assess and continuously
monitor thousands of vendors without
growing headcount at the same rate.
That's critical because vendor ecosystems
grow faster than risk teams ever will.
Second response velocity, what
used to take weeks or months?
We can now detect and
respond in NR in ours.
A time difference matters, especially
when you are dealing with cyber
operational financial risk.
Third is consistency.
Machine learning helped us standardize how
risk is evaluated, reducing review or to
reviewer variability that makes outcome
more predictable and far easier to defend.
And finally, strategic intelligence.
TPRM stopped being a back office function.
It became a source of insight for
leadership, highlighting concentration
risk, systemic exposure, and emerging
patterns across the ecosystem.
And that brings me to the most
important shift of all for TPRM.
When you s. Step back.
What machine learning really did
for us wasn't just automation.
It changed how TPRM is perceived
instead of being a compliance check,
the box TPRM became a core intelligent
capability inside a resilient digital
ecosystem, one that combines scale,
explainability, and adaptability.
Machine learning gave us the ability
to see risk earlier, respond faster,
explain decisions clearer and adapt
continuously as vendor and threat evolved.
That combination is
what regulators expect.
It's what leadership needs, and it's
what modern digital ecosystem requires.
This is what allows organizations to
move faster without losing control.
So let me leave you
with one final thought.
If there's one thing I hope you take
away from today, it's this machine
learning doesn't replace risk judgment.
It amplifies it.
You don't need to start.
With a perfect model or
a massive transformation.
Start small, automate evidence
extraction, reduce redundant questions.
Introduce signal driven
monitoring, but once risk teams
stops chasing questionnaires,
they start anticipating risk.
With that, I would like to conclude
thank you for your time and hope
you all have a wonderful day ahead.