Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42.
It's g great to be here today.
I'm Balaji.
I have 17 years of
experience in it industry.
I. A significant chunk of that
experience I have deeply, mainly
with Salesforce architect.
My focus has always been on
creating solutions that are not
just functional today, but can also
adapt and scale as needs evolve.
It's been a fascinating journey of
continuous learning and problem solving.
It's fun to be a Salesforce architect.
Welcome to the Talk.
I'll be presenting low-code,
no-code Salesforce presentation.
So let's get into the presentation.
So Salesforce is stepping towards
low code and it might go towards
no code in the future as well.
It is a small steps that's
it is taking right now.
So what it does is it's, it is
revolutionizing the software development
landscape by democratizing the creation
capabilities across organizations, right?
These innovative solutions enable
businesses to design, build, and deploy
applications up to 10 times faster
than traditional development methods
requiring minimal technical expertise.
Whoever even doesn't have a Java
code knowledge or anything like
that, still they would be able to do
the configurations and the changes.
So that is where the low code and no code
is coming into picture in Salesforce.
They're revolutionary using this one.
By removing code barriers, they empower
domain expert and business users
to directly participate in digital
transformation initiatives, accelerating
innovation and reducing the IT blockages.
So even business team would also be able
to do some kind of minimal changes without
intervening with the technical folks.
So that's how they're stepping towards.
So how that will impact
the business, right?
So there will be total valuation of 13.8
billion that we are looking at, and the
efficiency of development will be higher.
Like 70% of developer timelines
will be reduced, right?
And the maintenance efficiency,
lower ongoing support costs.
We will also get reduced.
80% of the cost will also get reduced
because if there is no code that
needed or low code that is needed,
then it can be done by the business.
Most of the cases, aura,
low level developer can also
handle all those things.
So it'll also increase decrease
the infrastructure presence.
So that infrastructure
will be decreased by 40%.
That, so that is where the business
impact will come into the picture, and
then how they would be democratizing
the app developments, right?
So there are three key areas.
One is the business agility, rapidly
respond to market demands with
applications built 10 x faster.
Then the traditional methods, broader
development base enable domain
experts and business users to create
solutions without coding expertise.
Simplified development, replace complex
programming with intuitive drag and
drop interface and visual workflows.
So these everything will enable the
business team to go ahead and work
on these requirements on their own
as flexible as possible to get there.
Rapid development cycle reduction.
So there is no need of a development
cycle as such as in when there is
a requirement, probably they can
go ahead, business can go ahead
and do their changes on their own.
So the changes that we will be looking
at are more kind of a drag and drop,
and then there is dynamic values that
are being changed on a high level.
So there is no in-depth
coding is dated as such.
When we talk about coding right
now, apex Code is something
that comes into the picture.
Java can also be embedded into this
Apex code to write a complex code.
Salesforce is taking steps towards
that and they are going to reduce the
complexity of this coding by introducing
these drag and drop functionalities.
So that's how the app development will be.
Development time will be reduced a lot.
User demographics, right?
So business professionals, 42% of platform
users, domain experts who leverage
platforms to create business specific
applications without coding expertise.
IT developers, 38% of platform
users, technical specialists.
Who use low-code platforms
to accelerate development and
reduce maintenance overhead.
Other roles, 8% of the platform
users, including project managers,
executives, and CI citizen
developers from various departments.
I. And then analysis is 12% of
the platform users, data focused
professionals who create reporting
solutions and automated workflows.
So this is the demographics, how it'll be
taking part within the current partition
of this, so let's go to the next slide.
Cloud-based solution, right?
So cloud deployments will be there, 68%
of low-code implementation, leverage
cloud infrastructure in 2023, enabling
rapid deployment and global accessibility.
Radios infrastructure cost
significant decrease in capital
expenditure as on premises hardware
requirements are minimized.
Enhanced tech security, PLA framework,
enterprise grade protection with
automated complaints, controls and
continuous vulnerability management,
dynamic scalability, seamless resource
adjustment based on demand, eliminating
capacity planning challenges.
So that is how the cloud-based
solutions would look like once
we have this low or no code.
And then what are the implementing
implementation challenges?
So the governance issues and security
concerns, scalability, limitations,
and integration complexity.
So these are the challenges
that are available right now.
So 67% of enterprises struggle with
establishing comprehensive oversight
and controlling proliferation of citizen
developed application across departments.
Security concerns.
64% of organizations face
significant challenges in maintaining
consistent security standards and
compliance protocol across their
low code application ecosystem.
Scalability limitations, enterprise
grade applications with complex business
logic and high volume data processing
requirements make share the technical
capabilities of certain local platforms.
Establishing seamless connections
with legacy enterprise systems often
requires specialized technical expertise
beyond the typical low-code skillset,
creating implementation bottlenecks.
So that is where the integration
complexity comes into the picture.
So what is the approach
that we have to follow?
So comprehensive assessment
and strategic planning, right?
Conduct through analysis of
organizational requirements, business
objectives, and potential high value
implementation scenarios, and then
platform evolution and selection.
Identify and select platforms
that optimally balance technical
capabilities, security requirements,
and user friendliness for your team.
Targeted pilot implementation.
Execute a focused proof of concept project
to validate benefits, identify challenges,
and build organizational momentum.
Enterprise wide adoption and governance
systematically expand implementation
across departments with robust
governance protocols to ensure
security, consistency and quality.
So this is how we have to take an
approach for this implementation,
how the future investment
trends would look like.
So once the ration.
Gets adapted to low-code, no-code
solutions, then they are going to see
a tremendous saving of economy or or
they are going to see a huge potential
growth where they would accelerate
the page of low-code, no-code.
So 2021, it was 58%.
Initial adapt adaption phase focused on
tactical departmental implementations
and the proof of concept projects.
2022 was 65% strategic expansion
across business units with
increased ROI validation and
across functional applications.
Now 2023 73% widespread
enterprise adoption with mature
integration frameworks and
established governance models.
2024 was projected as 82% anticipated
mainstream implementation becoming
standard practice across diverse
industries and market segments.
So how the business process
would get transformed?
Process identification, systematically
evaluate and prioritize business
workflows with highest automation
potential, and demonstrable rate.
Return on investment application design.
Harness powerful visual development
environments to create complex
process automations without requiring
traditional programming expertise.
Rapid development.
Dramatically reduce implementation
cycles by up to 70%, enabling
organizations to capture business
value significantly faster than
conventional development methods.
Performance analysis will help us
leverage comprehension analytics
dashboards to measure operational
improvements, identify optimization
opportunities, and continuously refine,
transform the business processes.
Security and governance framework.
Centralized oversight, security
protocols, development guidelines, right?
So establish a dedicated center of
excellence to strategically manage and
coordinate all the low code development
initiatives across the enterprise.
Comprehensive application, inventory
management, real-time usage,
analytics, and monitoring enforceable
quality assurance standards.
Now coming back to the security
protocols, implement enterprise grade
security measures to protect sensitive
data and ensure regulatory compliance
throughout the application life cycle.
Role-based access control
mechanism should be implemented.
End-to-end data encryption protocols.
Automated compliance verification
checks has to be there.
Development guidelines.
So these are the guidelines we
have to follow for the development.
Establish comprehensive policies,
empowering citizen developers
while maintaining our initial
standards and best practices.
Standardized design principles
and patterns has to be followed.
Structured testing and
validation procedures, mandatory
documentation and change management
requirements has to be followed.
So these are the frameworks that we have
to keep in mind when we are implementing
this low-code, no-code strategy.
So what will be the key takeaways?
So you have to evaluate your readiness,
conduct a comprehensive audit of your
current systems, team capabilities,
and the business processes to determine
integration, potential research platforms.
Evaluate low-code or no-code solutions
based on scalability, security features,
integration capabilities, and alignment
with your strategic objectives.
Start small.
Implement a strategy targeted
pilot project with clear success
metrics to avoid, to validate
benefits, gain stakeholder buy-in
and identify potential challenges.
Build capabilities.
Develop a comprehensive training program
for citizen developers while establishing
robot robust governance protocol
to ensure security and compliance.
Alright, thank you so much for tuning in.
Have a great day.
Thank you all.