Hello, comp 42.
It's an absolute pleasure to be here.
My name is Srin Ana, and I
lead engineering efforts in
Microsoft's finance organization.
Today I'm excited to share a real world
transformation story, a journey where
legacy systems met modern technology.
And where measurable business outcomes
were achieved by combining cloud and ai.
The problem we tackled wasn't unique.
Many enterprises face the same friction
with aging systems, disconnected data,
raising costs, and compliance complexity.
But how we solved with discipline,
collaboration, and right.
Technical levers is what
I want you to walk today.
We didn't just modernize, we
revolutionized financial systems,
delivering results like 20%.
25% perhaps reduction in operational
costs, 40% improvement in data accuracy,
50% acceleration in delivery cycles.
And we did this while supporting
global financial operations that
run on tight schedules and intense.
Regulatory scrutiny.
Let's get into that now.
When we started, our systems were
stitched together with patches, outdated
architectures, and fragile integrations.
We had decades old reporting
tools running on Reise servers.
Teams were constantly
firefighting, rather in awaiting.
The root of the issue was threefold.
Legacy systems, they lacked
modularity, had hard coded logic
and couldn't scale to new use cases.
Integration silos, multiple tools and data
warehouses were not talking to each other.
Finance team spent hours
reconciling numbers.
Scalability constraints.
Business needs grow fast.
Our systems couldn't
keep up with the pace.
The cost wasn't just technical.
It showed up in missed deadlines,
poor insights and anxiety.
During quarter closes, by spending
time reconciling the numbers from
one place to another, we knew
we had to rethink everything,
not just migrate, but reimagine.
Our first step was to simplify
the environment through
platform consolidation.
Think of this like cleaning
out a cluttered attic.
You find five different tools
doing similar things, disconnected
spreadsheets with conflicting formulas
and pipeline running on legacy jobs.
We took a four step approach audit.
We.
An inventory of every financial
application, reports and integration
mapped to a business value.
We identified the systems and underused
tools as well by leveraging telemetry.
Map.
We designed a unified architecture
with clear integration points,
reducing friction between upstream
and downstream systems, consolidate.
We eliminated redundant tools,
standard data pipelines, and
focused on reusable components by
consolidating the systems as well.
Validate this was the key.
Every feature reported or rebuilt
was tested with performance,
security, and compliance.
For example, we had three
different separate systems
generating headcount reports.
We merged them into one platform, reducing
the efforts by 60%, and ensuring everyone
was working with the same numbers.
This laid the groundwork for the
next phase, which is cloud migration.
Cloud is more than just an infrastructure.
It's about agility.
We leveraged Azure to build a resilient,
scalable financial data platform.
The results were tangible, 50% is faster.
Time to market forecasting
models that used to take months.
To deploy now go live in within
weeks 35% cost optimization.
We eliminated redundant storage, shut down
legacy VMs, virtual machines, and scaled
compute on demand, 99.9% availability.
This was critical.
Financial systems must be
always on, especially during
close and forecast cycles.
A quick anecdote, we had a year
and close deadline where reporting
environments used to take nearly 12
hours to prep After cloud migration, the
same setup was ready under 20 minutes.
That's the kind of a business
agility that drives the trust
and credibility across the teams.
The cloud gave us not just speed, but
reliability, security, and much more
which is more resilience as well.
With clean architecture and cloud
scale, we leaned into AI to bring
intelligence into our systems.
This wasn't just about fancy
models, it was about solving real
pain points for finance users.
We focused on three care key areas.
Predictive analytics.
We built forecasting models
with 85% accuracy using time
series and historical signals.
This helped finance leaders anticipate
OPEX trends, hiring spikes, and
vendor spending, automated processing
previously manual workflows.
Like invoice matching, report
scheduling, and cost reconciliation.
Were automated.
We cut manual efforts by 75%.
Anomaly detection.
We used realtime AI models to flag,
duplicate payments, cost spikes,
and misla classified expenses.
30% better persistent
over rule-based checks.
This made our financial systems more
intelligent, responsive, and secure.
Analysts could now focus on insights
instead of troubleshooting the data.
Let's talk about the hidden
superpower in our stack.
Metadata.
Our platform is metadata driven,
meaning every dataset, transformation,
and the business rule is described
and governed by the metadata.
This impacts in self-documenting systems.
New team members ramp up faster and
maintenance becomes much more predictable.
Dynamic data models, instead of
changing code, we change metadata.
That means faster adaptability.
To regulatory or business changes.
Governance metadata allows
full lineage tracking.
If someone changes a report logic,
we know exactly where it propagates.
We treated metadata not as an
afterthought, but as a design principle.
This paid off in compliance
audits, system reliability,
and long-term maintainability.
Let's look at what all this deliver in
real business terms, report generation.
Improved from 24 hours to three hours.
Data errors reduced from 12% to 3%.
Operational costs came down by 25%.
Time to insights changed
from 48 hours to 12 hours.
These are just not metrics.
They reflect fewer escalations, more
confidence leadership decisions,
and an engineering team that's
respected, not firefighting.
We even heard from our CFS office
that our modernization platform
was now considered the source of
truth for executive dashboards.
That's a huge order of
trust in engineering.
Technology is only one piece.
Success required execution discipline.
This comes with strategic planning,
every initiative tied to a business goal.
Agile development, sprints,
stakeholders, feedback with faster
iteration change management.
We trained users, provided shadowing,
and had hands-on labs as well.
Continuous improvement Every
release had built in feedback loops.
We also built strong cross team
partnerships between finance, SMEs,
subject matter expertise, data engineers,
security teams, and product managers.
No one worked in a vacuum.
This was the key to not just delivering
transformation, but sustaining as well.
As I mentioned initially,
this has been a journey.
All journeys comes with learnings as well.
Here are some of the biggest
lessons that we learned.
Things we would do it again, and
some we would do it differently.
Start small scale fast.
Don't boil the ocean, prove value
in one area, and then expand
cross-functional alignment.
Engineers alone can't
solve financial systems.
Ambit finance experts in the
development process as well to
expedite it, prioritize data quality.
You can have the best AI model in the
world, but garbage in and garbage out.
These insights help us to build a
system that works not just today,
but in future Ready as well.
To wrap up, I would like to
say modernizing financial
systems is no longer optional.
It's a mission critical.
If you are facing similar challenges,
I encourage you to start with what's
broken and quantify the business plan.
Sometimes you would be surprised what kind
of damage the existing legacy systems can
do to your time, to your data quality, and
to the credibility of the systems as well.
Don't skip governance.
It's the foundational of trust.
Invest in the right levers,
cloud for scale, AI for insights,
metadata flow for flexibility.
This journey isn't easy.
But the rewards are enormous,
faster insights, trusted data
and operational excellence.
Thank you so much for joining me.
I'm happy to take any
questions or chat afterward.
Let's build the systems that work for
the business, not the other way around.
Thank you very much.