Hello guys.
Thanks for joining me today.
This is Bandana Muah, and I have
more than 19 years of IT industry
experience on variety skills and roles.
Currently, I'm working as a senior
software engineering manager, and today
I'm going to talk about some of the key
challenges we have on value-based care.
Implementation in healthcare and how
solutions or basically cloud-based
solutions help overcome these challenges.
Okay.
Let's talk about what is a
value-based care program and.
How the cloud solutions
help overcome this?
Value-based care represents a fundamental
shift in healthcare delivery from volume
to value with payment based on patient
outcomes rather than service quantity.
This approach emphasizes
preventative care, effective chronic
disease management, coordinated
delivery, and patient engagement.
However, organizations face significant
implementation challenges that cloud
solutions can uniquely address.
This presentation explores how cloud
technologies provide the infrastructure,
scalability, and in Interability needed
to make value-based care successful in
today's complex healthcare landscape.
Let's talk about value-based
care fundamentals transitioning
from traditional fee for service.
That is more services equal to
more revenue, to the quality-based
reimbursement where providers earn
incentives for meeting benchmark,
reducing cost, and improving satisfaction.
This emphasizes preventive care
strategies, comprehensive chronic
disease management programs,
coordinated care across multiple
providers and active patient
participation in healthcare decisions.
Success requires tracking numerous quality
metrics, including clinical outcomes,
cost efficiency, patient experience
measures, and population health indicators
across diverse patient populations.
While the VBC model promises better
care at lower costs, implementing
it requires substantial changes to
workflows, technology, infrastructure,
and organizational culture.
Healthcare system must overcome
several significant challenges
to realize its full potential.
Now let's move on to understand
the data fragmentation challenges.
Patient information exists
in siloed systems across
multiple providers, including
electronic health records that
EHRs, laboratory systems, pharmacy
databases, billing platforms,
and specialty care records.
This fragmentation creates blind spots
in clinical decision making, impacts care
coordination, and makes comprehensive
quality reporting nearly impossible.
Cloud-based solutions helps create
unified data lakes that aggregates
information from D Dispar sources
into a single accessible repository.
Fire based APIs and HL seven integration
engines enable real time bidirectional
data sharing between previously
INCAP incompatible systems, creating
a comprehensive patient view data
normalization services, standardized
information from different sources, making
it usable for analytics and reporting.
By leveraging Cloud Solutions
healthcare organization can
eliminate data silos, creating a
holistic view of patient journey
that supports true value-based care.
Okay, now let's talk about how
cloud solutions help in streamlining
complex reporting requirements.
Automated extraction from
multiple sources into cloud.
Data lake is the best example
where every organization might
be seeing the benefits today
processing using the cloud solutions.
That is AI driven data normalization
and metric calculation.
Utilizing cloud for analytics.
That is real time dashboards.
Identify care gaps and opportunities.
And submissions of automated report
to the organizations such as CMS
or payer organizations, other and
other stakeholders, value-based care
programs, demand reporting on dozen
sub metrics such as STAR rating, a CO
performance, creating administrative
burden, cloud platforms like.
AWS Health Lake, Microsoft Azure for
Health and Google Cloud Healthcare
API automates these processes reducing
manual work, while improving accuracy
and timeliness With cloud-based
analytics, organization can identify
care gaps immediately rather than with
discovering them during the retro spec.
Two reviews, enabling proactive
interventions that improve
outcomes and performance metrics.
Now let's talk about how Cloud solutions
helps bridging care, coordination gaps,
unified access.
Basically, role-based platform
ensures team members sees the relevant
information while maintaining security
and compliance workflow integration.
Cloud systems embed care
pathways directly into clinical
workflows, guiding evidence-based
decisions at the point of care.
Intelligent alerts.
Automated notifications, alerts
team members about critical
changes to patient status, mission
appointments, or care plan deviations.
Coordinating care across
specialists, primary care hospitals,
and community service has.
Traditional Will difficult
without integration.
Integrated systems.
Cloud-based care management platforms
creates a unified environment where all
stakeholders can collaborate in real time.
When specialists, PCPs, nurses, and
social workers can simultaneously
access and update shared care plans,
communication errors decreases, and care
transition becomes seamless, leading
to better outcomes and reduced costs.
Now let's talk how Cloud solutions
helps in enhancing patient engagements.
Digital outreaches, such as automated
SMS, email and app notification
for appointments and screenings.
Two-way communications such as securing
messages with the care team members.
Remote monitoring by wearable
integration for continuous.
Healthcare tracking self-management
by patients where patient portals
for accessing records and care plans.
Patient engagement barriers
represent a significant challenge
to value-based care success.
Patient may struggle to follow
care plans, manage medications, or
attend appointments, particularly
when social determinant of health
creates additional obstacles.
Cloud solutions enable scalable,
personalized, patient communication
tools that meets patients where they are.
These platforms can be tailored to
patient preferences, literacy levels,
and languages, making healthcare more
accessible to diverse populations.
Now let's talk about powering
the risk stratification using ai.
Helps in data aggregation, comprehensive
patient profile from multiple sources.
Machine learning identifies patterns and
risk factors, helps in access actionable
insights delivered to care teams.
Providers in value-based arrangement
often struggles with risk adjustments
and managing diverse patient populations.
Traditional risk models may not
account for all variables, particularly
social determinants of health that
significantly impact outcomes.
Cloud infrastructure provides
the computational power
needed for sophisticated AI
driven risk stratification.
These models can identify risk,
can identify high risk patients
by analyzing vast data sets.
Including clinical data, claims
history, social factors, and even
behavioral patterns, enabling
truly proactive care management.
Now let's move on to the security and
compliance area where, how cloud solutions
help leading cloud providers offer hipaa.
Hit trust and SOC two compliance
frameworks out of the box.
Reducing the burden on healthcare
organizations to build compliant
infrastructure from scratch.
Comprehensive security measures
encryption at rest in data transition.
Granular access controls continuous
monitoring, advanced threat
detection systems that exceeds
most on-premises capabilities.
Auditability.
Automated logging and monitoring tools
track all data access and changes,
creating audit trails that simplify
regulatory reporting and quickly
identify potential security issues.
Healthcare organization face increasingly
complex regulatory requirements with
frequent changes to the CMS rules.
A-C-M-A-C-U models and payer contracts.
Cloud solutions help.
Navigate this complexity by providing
robust security frameworks and compliance
tools that adopt changing requirements.
Now let's talk about a cloud-based
solution, which I recently
implemented in my organization,
which is we named it as value-based
care data enable enablement engine.
Which uses AWS Cloud solutions
and has been providing tremendous
support and value to the Our Nation.
Some of them are listed here.
These solutions gives a unified view
across systems, helps with the data
to give the complete patient journey.
It helps in real time.
Metrics against contracts helps
in documenting or onboarding
the providers, delivering
the value and accuracy
in the reimbursements.
The data provided by
these solutions helps.
Proactive intervention
opportunities in care management.
This helps in better experience.
Through coordinated care, this solution
has been helping our nation save cost
of implementations or onboarding new
providers by 25% or more savings.
Contract Enable data extract engine
demonstrate how cloud solutions can
transform value-based care performance.
This system aggregates data from desperate
sources to create unified view of
contract performance against key metrics.
The cloud-based architecture allows for
seamless scaling as data volumes grow
while maintaining consistent performance
by automating data extraction nine.
Standardization.
The system has reduced reporting
time by 75% while improving accuracy
by 30% directly impacting financial
performance under value-based care.
Now let's move on to the best practices we
can follow while implementing value-based
care programs assessment and planning.
Evaluate current data systems.
Define specific VBC goals and
identify critical integration points.
Create a phase approach.
Prioritizing high impact use case
first, involve critical stakeholders
from the beginning to ensure solutions,
address real workforce needs.
Choose between a multi-cloud
hybrid or single vendor approaches
based on your organization's need.
Design data governance framework that
maintain compliance while enabling
analytics, implement identity
management solutions that support
appropriate access across organizations
integration and adoption Where.
Use fire based APIs to
standardize data exchange.
Develop comprehensive training
programs for all staff levels, create
feedback mechanism to continuously
improve the system based on real world
usage pattern and user suggestions.
Successful implementation
requires thoughtful planning
and strategic approach.
Organizations should start with clearly
defined outcomes and build incremental.
Incrementally focusing on
demonstrating value at each
phase, or rather than attempting
a complete transformation at once.
Now, let's talk about the feature of
cloud enabled value-based care solutions.
If you look at the screen, you see the
tremendous cost reduction in the IT
implementation, which is around 40%.
And 68% efficiency, increasing
efficiency in reporting 3.2
times return on investment,
24 by seven availability.
So let's deep dial a little more.
You
can see the sources of these.
Data or the facts on the
bottom of the each item.
So in the cost reduction, healthcare
organizations have seen an average
operational saving of 40% after
migrating to cloud platforms.
This is primarily due to the
reduced IT infrastructure,
lower physical data storage and
minimized server maintenance costs,
reporting efficiencies.
By automating reporting processes,
cloud platforms have helped
healthcare organizations reduce time
spent on quality reporting by 68%.
Real time data extraction analytics,
and integration with regulatory
frameworks such as and a CO
have streamlined this process.
Return on investment cloud adoption in
healthcare has led to an average of three.
Point two times the return of investment.
This is driven by operational
efficiency improvements, faster and
more accurate decisions making and
reduced administrative overhead.
Cloud solutions are available 24 by seven,
which helps access to critical healthcare
data enhancing care coordination.
Enabling timely inter interventions
and improving patient outcomes
through the real time monitoring.
I hope this session was helpful
and if you have any questions,
you can reach me on LinkedIn.
Thank you for
being here.