Speaker 31: Good afternoon everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
My name is Han Kasra and I'm a structural
engineer with over 10 years of experience
in the telecommunications tower industry.
Today, I want to share how we can
leverage data analytics to fundamentally
improve the way we approach
structural analysis of telecom towers.
This presentation will cover the
structural engineering fundamentals.
That underpin tower analysis and design,
and then show you where data-driven
methods can add tremendous value to
this traditionally manual process.
Whether you are from the tech
side or the infrastructure side,
my goal is to somewhat bridge two
more, bridge these two worlds and
show the opportunity ahead of us.
Load demands on towers is
increasing due to network
upgrade requirements such as 5G.
Equipment is getting larger and heavier
while the overall infrastructure is aging.
Many towers in the US were originally
designed in the 1980s and nineties
for much lighter anti antenna loads.
The average structural load on existing
towers has grown significantly with
each generation of wireless technology.
From two G to 5G, the Tower infrastructure
market continues to expand through
2030, driven by densification
and rural broadband initiatives.
Continuous uptime is no longer a luxury.
It is a critical requirement.
It tower supports public safety,
communications, emergency services,
and essential connectivity.
It becomes critical.
That structural analysis accurately
captures all tower components to
maintain continuous network uptime.
This is where data analytics
can play a transformative role.
Before we talk about analytics, it is
important to understand the engineering
standards foundation that governs
everything we do in tower structure.
Analysis.
The International Building Code or IBC
is the overarching legal code adopted by
most jurisdictions in the United States.
It serves as the umbrella under
which all understands operate.
N-C-T-I-A 2 2 2 is the primary
standards specifically developed
for Antia supporting structures.
It covers towers types, including
self-support towers, monopole, kite
towers, and any other infrastructure
supporting wireless equipments.
The current revision of
the code is revision.
IASC seven provides the foundational
and environmental loads including wind
speed maps, ice loading criteria, seismic
parameters, and their load combinations.
TIA 2 22 references A SCE seven
and adapts its provisions for
tower specific applications.
A ISC 360 governs the design of structural
steel members and connections since
the vast majority of telecom towers
are steel structures, this standard is
critical for member capacity checks.
A CI 3 1 8 covers reinforced concrete
design as an and is essential
for Tower Foundation design.
Including drill shafts, spread
fittings and MAT foundations.
These standards form an
integrated framework.
When we talk about automating or
applying analytics to structural
analysis, we must ensure full
compliance with this code hierarchy.
This slides covers the critical
load types that every tower
must be designed to resist.
Understanding these loads is
essential because they are the core
inputs to any structural model,
whether traditional or data driven.
Dead loads include the self weight of
the tower, steel platforms, ladders,
an antenna, mounts, and all mounted
equipment such as an antennas, radios,
junction boxes, and feed lines.
Accurate.
Dead load accounting is fundamental
and is an area where data analytics
can significantly reduce errors.
And equipment inventory wind
loads are typically the governing
load for most telecom towers.
We calculate velocity pressure based
on the basic wind speed from a SE seven
wind maps adjusted for exposure category,
topographic effects and height above,
crown the wind loads and an antennas
and appurtenances can exceed the wind
load on the tower Structural itself.
Ice load is critical in
some certain climates.
Tia 2, 2 2 specifies radial ice
thicknesses, maps and towers must
be analyzed for ice weight plus
concurrent reduced wind loads.
ICE can dramatically increase
the effective projected area
of members and an antennas.
Seismic loads are evaluated based
on site classification, map,
spectral acceleration, and the
response modification factors.
For the tower type, while wind
typically governs tower design,
seismic loads can control foundation
design in high seismic zones.
Thermal effects, while sometimes
overlooked, can introduce significant
stresses in constraint members, especially
in guide towers and long monopole sections
with large temperature differentials.
The key point for this audience is
that each of these load types generate
large volume of site specific data.
Structuring and analyzing this data
at scale is where machine learning
and analytics begins to add value.
Modern structural analysis software
such as STA Reset Tower and TNX has
significantly advanced our ability
to perform detailed finite element
analysis on tower structures.
These platforms automate the application
of hundreds of load combinations.
Excuse me, required by TI 2 22
and a SE seven and perform member
by member design checks against
a ISC 360 capacity equations.
This alone has dramatically
reduced analysis turnaround time
compared to hand calculations.
Documentation and reporting is arguably
the most important deliverable in an
in any structural engineering project.
The structure analysis report
along with seal drawings is
what gets submitted to the local
jurisdiction for a building permit.
Without a permit, no construction or
modification can proceed at the site.
Standardized reporting formats that meet
regulatory requirement are essential
to obtaining permits efficiently.
Tower operators in the US own anywhere
from hundreds to over 40,000 towers.
For operators at that scale.
Centralized data integration is critical,
accurate, and clean data can reduce the
time spent on each tower analysis cycle
and also accelerate troubleshooting for
maintenance related structural issues.
This is where we start to see the
conversions of traditional engineering
softwares with data platforms
when analysis results are strode.
In structural databases, rather than
isolated PDF reports, we unlock the
ability to perform portfolio wide,
trend analysis and predictive insights.
High quality data is the foundation
of any analytics or machine learning
initiative and structural engineering.
For telecom towers.
The key data inputs come from multiple
sources that must be integrated.
Structural data sets include material
properties such as steel grade
yield, strength, member dimensions,
including leg sizes, bracing patterns,
pole sizes, connection details,
foundation specifications, et cetera.
These are the building blocks
of any structural model.
Stress ratios or demand to
capacity ratios are the primary
output of structural analysis.
Tracking stress ratios across all members
and across multiple analysis runs provide
a rich data set for identifying trends.
Similarly, deflection data can include
historical displacement measurements,
service serviceability, limit checks,
and dynamic response characteristics,
such as natural frequency and
vortex setting susceptibility.
Inspection records capture
field conditions, that
model alone cannot predict.
Corrosion progression,
connection loosening, foundation
cracking, and any member damage.
When digitized and standardized
inspection data can become a powerful
input for predictive maintenance models.
Key message here is that each of these
data streams independently ha has value,
but when combined and structured, they
enable a level of insight that was
previously impossible in our industry.
This slide illustrates the ELU evaluation
from traditional structural analysis.
To where we want to go.
That is intelligence driven.
Infrastructure management.
Think of it as a maturity curve.
On the left, we start with
traditional structural analysis.
This is the code based, standard
driven approach that has been the
backbone of the industry for decades.
It works well, but is inherently
reactive and project specific.
The next step is digital modeling,
where we move from 2D drawings and
static reports to full 3D finite
element models that can be updated
and reanalyzed as condition change.
This is where I feel we are at today.
Data integration is the
critical middle step.
This is where we connect analysis
results, inspection records,
environmental data, and equipment
inventories into a unified data platform.
Without this step analysis,
analytics, and machine learning
have nothing to work with.
Analytics then allows us to query
these integrated data for trends,
which towers in our portfolio have
the highest stress ratios, which
reasons so accelerated corrosion.
Finally, predictive analysis.
This is where we want to be.
Predictive analysis can use machine
learning to move from descriptive
insights to forward-looking predictions.
Instead of asking what happened, we
can ask what is likely to happen and
when each stage builds on the one
before it, you cannot skip straight to
machine learning without first having
structured high quality engineering data.
This is a message I want to
emphasize to the tech community.
The engineering fundamentals
must come first.
Let us talk about the tangible business
impact of adopting a data centric
approach to structural engineering.
Extended surface life is perhaps
the most significant benefit.
Proactive monitoring and data driven
maintenance decisions can extend a
towers operational life well beyond its
original 25 to 30 year design expectation.
Given that a new tower bill can cost
several hundred thousand dollars.
Extending the life of existing
assets by even five to 10 years
represent enormous capital savings.
Reduced liability is
critical in our industry.
Comprehensive documentations and
consistent analysis protocols provide
strong defensibility in regulatory audits
and legal context when every analysis
decision is traceable and every inspection
finding recorded in a structured database.
The operator's risk exposure,
it's significantly reduced.
Proactive decision making is enabled
when analytics ready reported reaches
leadership teams instead of reactive
capital expenditure driven by emergencies
or permit deadlines, executives can
make informed capital allocation and
risk management decisions based on
portfolio-wide data, this business
outcome, these business outcomes.
Represent real revenue and
cost optimization opportunities
to wrap up the future of resilient
telecommunications infrastructure lies at
a cover convergence of four key elements.
Traditional engineering provides
the standards based analysis and
proven design methodologies that
ensure safety and code compliance.
This foundation is non-negotiable and must
remain at the core of everything we do.
Structured data transforms,
isolated analysis reports and
inspection findings into queryable
analyzable data sets that this is
the enabler that bridges traditional
engineering with modern technology.
Machine learning takes structured
data and builds predictive models
and intelligent monitoring systems
that can identify patterns.
Human would miss across thousands of
towers and millions of data points.
The end result is resilient networks,
safer infrastructure that supports the
critical communications our society
depends on, manage more efficiently and
with greater confidence than ever before.
One message I want to emphasize
in all this, the engineering
fundamentals must come first.
Thank you for your time today, and below
Arm is my email address and LinkedIn, URL.
If you want to reach me anytime,
please feel free to do that.
Again, thank you for your time today.
I greatly appreciate it.
Thank you.