Hello everyone.
This is Winker Karti man from SCO Texas.
I'm an SAP project manager
having 21 years of experience in
S-A-P-I-I handled multiple clients
belongs to multiple industry like
manufacturing, food, and period.
When I started my career in SAP
Abap, I started working with R
3.3, and then later my current
experiences goes with s Foura 2023.
In between this many years I worked with
several clients several team members
and from different countries like India
China, Japan Germany, and different
European and Asia Pacific countries.
I have experience working with the
manufacturing and food processing
companies as an SAP project manager.
I'm also like SAP certified Project
manager and PMP certified AWS
certified and SCRUM certified.
So this is my overall SAP experience.
Today I'm going to talk about the topic
of transforming business efficiency,
the role of AI in SAP and ERP system.
How this AI in SAP is
affecting the AI ERP systems.
So artificial intelligence is
fundamentally transforming SAP and
Enterprise Resource Planning Systems.
It's like creating un unprecedented
opportunities for business to
enhance operational efficiency,
improve decision making, and deliver.
Superior user experience, which
you can see on my screen, which I'm
talking about SAP AI and ERP systems.
This presentation explores how
AI integration is recognizing
enterprise systems through automation.
Ate your task evaluation of breakthrough
analytics and enhance user interfaces.
And we'll see how technologies are
reshaping and how business operates
and interact with their core systems.
This is the overall topic which I'm
going to talk today about role of
AI in SAP and ERP systems, how the
AI revolution is enterprise system.
Let's see different things like
market growth, cost reduction,
revenue growth, how market growth
is affecting the AI in ERP.
The global ERP market is projected
to reach 97.2 billion by 2024, with
78% of oration reporting at least 25%
improvement in operational efficiency
following strategic AI integration.
Means we can see that most of the EIP
markets right now trying to move to AI
revolution and also how it is affecting
the cost reduction companies implementing
AI and answer SAP solutions have
achieved an average of 32% reduction in
operational cost within the first year
with automation of routine process.
Eliminating up to 40% of manual
workload means we can clearly see that.
Manual workload is getting reduced
and AI is coming into the game.
That's what we can see, where we can see
the cost reduction, where companies are
ideally thinking about cost reduction
when it comes to the budget, and also
the revenue growth, how the orations
are making mature integration with
the RP system so that they can grow.
Revenue wise.
Also, we can see the revenue growth
are 2.3, higher revenue growth compared
to industry periods with 65% reporting
significant improvements in customer
satisfaction and retention rates.
Let's see, automation of
repetitive task invoice processing.
So invoice processing is one of the
most important thing where most of
the companies use manual processing.
Some person is going to use any
like software or something like
that and process the invoice.
But let's see how AI is helping
here, like AI systems demonstrate.
Demonstrated remarkable efficiency
gains with improved automated matching
accuracy and decreased processing cycle
times compared to traditional methods
means we can see that the automated
invoice processing is taken care by
AI so that the workload can be reduced
and manual processing can be reduced.
This is one of the revolution that
we can see and also we see the
systems demonstrate self-learning
capabilities with no error rates.
Sometimes manual.
We may see some errors.
Person made some errors while issuing
invoices, but this AI capabilities
will remove the error and it's
like error free invoice processing.
And the next one is order management.
Why AI is implementing order management.
Let's see.
Studies examining and manufacturing
enterprise documented significant
reductions in order processing
time, swallowing AI implementation.
Audit accuracy improved translating to
substantial annual savings through the
elimination of costs associated with
other corrections, returns, processing,
and customer service interventions.
And also we see that order management
is also saying that they are going to
eliminate errors and all those things,
and they're going to see that how
the cost is associated with the order
corrections, processing returns, and
all those things, compliance monitoring.
Compliance monitoring, ai, power
monitoring solutions are identified as
much higher percentage of compliance.
And they say okay, as reportable
incidents compared to conventional
rule-based systems, okay, AI
is taking care of compliance.
Now it is monitoring, it's following
the rules, and it's saying that, okay
incidents will be reported and error free.
This proactive identification
capability translated to remission
in compliance related to panel.
Decrease audit preparation time.
Okay.
Like in compliance, if the auditing is
not done properly, then you see some
fines and regular issues will be there.
But AI is saying that, okay, I'm
going to reduce all these things.
I'm going to decrease the ities
and the preparation time too.
This is how we can see how AI in ERP
systems and automation, which is like
the repetitive task, will be eliminated.
Let's see.
What we are going to talk about
predictive analytics and forecasting.
Okay.
The most important things in any business
is like demand forecasting, financial risk
enhancement, supply chain optimization.
Okay.
Let's see.
Demand forecasting A and S planning
solution documented significant
forecast accuracy improvements
compared to traditional time series
forecasting methods, decreasing cost
while improving product availability.
Also financial risk assessment.
AI and S transaction monitoring
identified a high percentage of
fraud led activities before payment
execution, representing a substantial
improvement over rule based detection
systems, supply chain optimization.
Predictive AI models reduce supply
chain dis disruptions by identifying
potential bottlenecks, supply risk, and
de demand before they impacted operations.
We are seeing that AI is taking
charge of predictive analytics and
forecasting, and we are seeing that
it is going to reduce the cost.
It is going to reduce the risk, and it
is going to reduce the fraud and it is
making supply chain process very easy.
Move to next slide, and as decision making
capabilities so improve decision quality,
better outcomes in dynamic environment.
Advanced anm, a detection, early
identification of issues, inventory
optimization, reduce access
while improving availability,
financial intelligence, better cash
forecasting and capital allocation.
So these four are very important
while taking any decision.
So AI is also evolving now to make sure
that it is enhanced decision making
capability, so that improved decision
quality, advance analytic detection,
inventory optimization, financial
intelligence for better cash forecast
forecasting and capital allocation.
All nations utilizing AI Argumented
SAP analytics experience to
improve decision quality and reduce
decision latency compared to the
conventional analysis approaches.
These improvements were particularly
pronounced in dynamic business
and environments where Rapid data
assimilation translated directly to,
compared to advantages we see there is
lots of improvement is going to happen
when SAP is now integrated with ERP.
Let's move the next slide.
Okay.
Now it is saying that how AI is
going to enhance the user experience.
Right now we are seeing lots of
apps are coming, but again, we'll
see like how AI announced the
user experience for ERP systems.
Conventional interfaces solution like
SAP Joel and SAP Co-pilot enables users
to complex workflow, more efficient
and traditional menu drive interfaces.
These natural languages capability
reduce the technical knowledge barrier.
Then historically limited, ERP adoption.
Means we can see like a layman who is
not into the SAP technologies, like
when we do SAP implementations, the
clients, some of the clients, they
don't have SAP experience, but still
using these particular interfaces, they
can also easily use SAP capabilities.
Let's see.
The intelligent assistance, a power
assistance transform navigation in
complex ERP and NEUR environment.
By providing context aware
guidance, they reduce errors
while accelerating processes.
Through proactive suggestions,
particularly complex areas
like financial consolidations.
In the ERP systems, it is helping,
intelligent assistant is helping reducing
the address, which we already discussed
in our previous slides, and saying
that, okay, I'll take care of everything
proactively and give the suggestions.
Complex areas and financial
consolidations will be taken care by ai.
Personalized experience.
AI en enabled adaptive interfaces.
Improve information processing.
Decision quality research demonstrate
that AI driven, ation optimized
interaction path, minimizing load
while maximizing inside delivery.
It is also taking care of interfaces
for the information processing
decision quality means we can see
going forward the improvement of the
quality, which is really enhance the
personalized experience of the users.
Let's go to the next one.
Generative AI integration.
Right now we see like generative AI is
all, all over, like LinkedIn, all over
industrial area, and people also getting
certified when you do a PM certification.
You also suggested by PMP team to do
generative ai, p and p. Why generative AI
integration is coming into the picture.
In a RP, let's see, the contents.
Automated content creation code
generation enhance chart boards.
Okay, let's see what is Automated
content creation significantly
reduce effort for producing
business communications and reports.
Beyond time saving these systems
improve information consistency
through standardized formatting and
integrating validation frameworks means.
In like instead of doing manual reports,
this one is to taking care of creation of
reports different type of reports, like
budget reports or like status reports or
anything which is related to the business.
And it is also standardizing the
formatting, so you don't need
to worry about the formatting.
Okay.
That is one thing.
Second thing for the
developers code generation.
Transform application development
within SAP environment means it
is going to generate the code.
Then we are seeing that okay, going
forward, SAP developers will be reduced
and this AI integration will be playing
a major role to generate the code.
We know, like people, we are seeing
so many code generator tools for
different technologies, not only
for SAP, for different T net,
the Java, et cetera, et cetera.
But again, when it comes to SAP
environment, it is saying that,
okay, intelligent tool accelerated
development workflows will be improved.
Code quality improved to the applications.
Consistent applications of architectural
patterns means like it is following
the standard SAP code technology.
Okay, and let's see what's next.
Enhance the chat bots Modern AI
power system resolve most user
inquiries without human intervention.
These systems maintain contextual
awareness across conservations and
effectively address complex inquiries that
previously require specialized support.
See, we are seeing the modern technology
is trying to make sure that it is giving
like conceptual awareness to the users
and also address the complex inquiries.
So it is always talking about reducing
the frauds, giving you, reducing the
complex issues and giving you the
what do you say, like the specialized
support and all those things.
Let's see, AI assisted information
interaction, so how AI is helping us
to get the interaction information.
So smart summarization enhance
analytics, natural language filtering.
Conceptual recommendations.
I'm not going deep into this all topics,
but based on the headlines, we can see
like how it is helping us reducing all
this transformation, lengthy reports
and accelerate complex workflows
and also enables conversation data
exploration delivers faster, comparing
to traditional SQL based query interfaces
and also it's a recommendation.
User needs intelligent,
surfacing relevant actions.
Connections and insight based on
current activities, historical patterns.
Ordination.
So most of the ordination now leveraging
ai, enhanced analytical respond 40% faster
to changing business conditions means if
you see, if you have an SAP experience,
there are bi analytical reports.
Okay?
Now this AI is helping us to
respond 40% faster, comparing to
the regular bi analytical reports.
So this is like a game changer.
So it means how your internet
is speed based on your internet.
Your computers are working similarly,
this SAP reports give you faster reports.
This will really improve the information
accessibility and also visualization.
These capabilities deliver exceptional
value in data intensive environments
where information, volume, and
complexity would otherwise over him.
Human continue capacity.
Let's see.
Business benefits from AI
intelligence, operational efficiency,
reduce, we discussed already.
It'll reduce manual processing and time
significantly in financial services.
Next one is financial management
improves cash forecasting, accuracy
in manufacturing inventory management,
decrease holding cost in retail operation.
Customer service, that is one
of the most important thing.
Enhance the sort accuracy across
distribution networks means if you take
example of my current project where
I'm working as a project manager for
Levi's, like they have so many orders
in the distribution centers, so this
will definitely help them to enhance
their distribution across the network.
And also compliances accelerate
regulatory issue detection,
healthcare decision making, minimize
response time, telecommunication.
Okay, AI is taking, it is minimizing
response time in telecommunication
supply chain lowers disruption
rate in manufacturing environments.
User experience, like we discussed
about the apps and all those things
is boost the performance and also
system adoption within professional
services means it says it's easy to use.
Let's move to next slide.
Future implications.
Okay, now using the S-A-S-A-P,
AI integration, ERP, what
are the future implications?
Let's see.
Autonomous operations 2026 to 2028.
Predict maintenance, 2025 to 2027.
Cross system intelligence, 2026 to 2029.
Self-optimizing supply chain.
20 25, 20 27.
Let's see.
And autonomous operations, meaningless
system, increasingly capable of
executing complex business process
with minimal oversight, extending
beyond simple transaction to
sophisticated decision process.
Next, we'll see the rapid advancement
as operational technology integrates
with the enterprise systems, reducing
downtime and maintenance costs
through more precise scheduling.
So it's, it is going to reduce
the downtime of the systems.
And also maintenance cost, which is most
important for most of the organizations.
Cross system intelligence,
transgendering traditional application
boundaries to deliver unified
insights across business functions.
Enhancing all national agility through
faster response to market changes,
self-optimizing supply chains.
A orchestrated spanning multiple
application, improving strategic
alignment and reducing supply chain
cost by 41%, which is like game changer.
We'll move to the next slide.
Conclusion,
a paring shift in enterprise
technology, operational transformation,
fundamentally redefining efficiency
across business functions.
Decision quality enhancements, which
we already discussed, the operational
transformation we discussed.
What is the decision making?
Quality enhancement enable more informed
strategic decision through data-driven
insights, user experience, revolution,
creating intelligent digital ecosystem
that adapt to changing requirements.
The integration of AI within SAP and
DIP system represents the shift to that
extent far beyond incremental improvement.
Companies that successfully leverage
these capabilities are positioned
to operate with greater efficiency.
Respond more effectively to
market changes and make more
informal strategic decisions.
Organization that embrace these
technological advancements are not merely
as IT implementations, but as strategic
capabilities will fundamentally reshape
their operational models and competitive
positioning in an increasing digital data.
Driven in future means.
We can see this AI within S-A-P-R-P
systems represents extended.
For beyond incremental improvements.
The improvements which we already
discussed about the operational
transformation, decision quality,
user experience reducing the errors,
processing the invoice faster and
also reducing the fraudulent things.
So orations like most of the nationals
adopt these technologies advancements
not only for IT implementations,
but also for other strategic
fundamental business operations.
Let's see.
That's it.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.
It's nice talking to you all.
Thank you.