Good morning everyone.
I'm truly honored to be here at
Conference for Thank you for giving me
this platform to discuss a topic that is
shaping not just our industries, but our
societies, and ultimately our futures.
My name is Vanil mpa, and I specialize in
cloud technologies and ethical AI design.
Today I invite you onto a journey where
the story of cloud AI is not just about
efficiency, gains and profitability,
but with a lot of responsibility,
ethics, and trust, because technology
at it best serves the humanity.
And it, at worst, it can
divide, oppress, and even harm.
Let's explore how we can ensure
it, it all services better.
The cloud AI revolution we are living
through a once in a generation.
Transformation organizations are
embracing up to a 40% operational
gains with with enhancing in the ai.
Even a lightweight integrations create at
least 25% of baseline efficiency, which is
see which we're seeing as an improvement.
And the cost structures
have changed forever.
Millions are saved through
predictive analytics, optimization,
and intelligent automation.
Let's talk about some real-time examples.
UPS saved 10 million gallons of
fuel annually through through ai.
Routing healthcare systems are
cutting ICU vision times by 30% with
using predictive staffing models.
Amazon, which we use every day, generates
about 35% of its revenue straight
through AI driven recommendation engine.
AI cloud is.
Cloud AI is no longer optional.
It's a foundation of modern and com
to advantage, but with the speed
of the innovation is breathtaking.
The speed of ethical
replication also lags behind.
So what's the real time
intelligence benefits?
Three primary superpowers are
unlocked through cloud ai, which
is preventing the failures.
Predictive AI detects vulnerabilities
before cast failures occur.
Example IBM Watson, which we heard
recently, it's detecting the factory
machines, breakdowns weeks in advance,
accelerating the ratios, real time data
empowers leaders to act immediately
shifting the strategies with the agility
that today's fast moving world demands.
Example, American Airlines adjust
its flight flight routes dynamically
to avoid weather interactions.
And we are talking about next personalized
experiences from Spotify suggesting
what would the next perfect song.
And also and the hospitals tailoring
the treatments to genetic profiles.
Personal personalization is
just about the convenience.
It's about loyalty, outcome, and lives.
But these benefits must deeper
emerging risk if unchecked.
So the ethical challenges which,
which are emerging right now.
Ethical concerns in AI have existed
since its very beginning, dating back
to early debates of over automated
editions which happened in 1960s.
Today, three themes dominate the
landscape, which is a privacy.
Everyone is scared of their own privacy.
Data is collected and at unprecedented
scale, yet transparency content
consent mechanism often lagged behind.
So algorithm bias, AI learns from
historical data and the historical
data is real with sorele biases, real
time examples, the compass system.
Used by us criminal screening
systematically gave black defendants
higher risk of sc of scorings and re
reoffending Amazon internal AI hiring
tool performed male candidates, a better
over woman until it's what it was.
Disman, the transparency black box
system make decisions that even
their creators often cannot explain.
Ai at its core, AI ethics is about
protecting dignity, the fairness and
the agency, so the trust, the, there
are a lot of rising concerns here, so
trust is the most valuable currency
in the ai if you lose it, and no, no
amount of technical can compensate.
Once the trust loss cannot be
rebuilt, and especially in this
era, what are the different key
trends which we're talking about?
Regulatory pressure is increasing.
Is increasing.
It might be in G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A-E-U-A Act.
Canadas EID proposal investors are
prioritizing environmental, social,
and government standards, meaning
ethical AI is just a compliance issue.
It's a capital market issue.
Consumers are becoming activism
driven, boycotting companies,
which are seeing analytical proof.
The research shows that companies rank
highly in ethical technology practice
saw that the stocks raised 14% than
their competitors doing the market.
At Tmin Turbulences ethical AI
isn't slowing you down it ins
it's insulating you via loyalty.
Let's talk about few case studies.
Let's start with the financial services.
Cancel the financial sector.
The major global bank realized its loan
application AI systematically penalized
applicants from a lower income zip codes.
This is ethically wrong.
So what's, what are the character
mechanisms they have taken deployed the,
they deployed the advanced bias detection
models, restructuring the data sets
to ensure the balance representation,
empowering a cross-functional human panel,
human review panel, the, and the outcomes.
They were amazing.
Approving rates were
harmonized across demographics.
Within a 22% variance and the
customer side and satisfaction
it's sky, it's skyrocketed by 18%.
And regulatory scrutiny, coff
and the brand are so ethical.
Correction just didn't
compromise profitability.
It's enhanced it.
And the next case study, which
we can talk about is healthcare.
Healthcare amplifies the the stakes.
The cloud AI now predicts
the cardiac error, how was in
advance, analyze the cardiac scans
faster than the human radiology.
And Tyler postop treatment plans
based on the predictive models.
And what are the safeguards in this?
This healthcare AI needs to have
end-to-end transcript encryption
role-based access controls, graphic
variance audits, because in healthcare
bias isn't just analytical, it's lethal.
And what is the future of ai?
The future will demand
even more maturity from us.
Autonomous ai, the systems
that independently adapt and
self-correct, but always with
the human governance boundaries.
Edge, ai, moving intelligence
to where the action happens.
It might be in phones, factories, vehicles
enhancing privacy and reducing latency.
And the next is decentralizing
infrastructure, distributor clouds,
ecosystem, which are tamper proof,
failure, resistance, and trust enhancing.
The question is not
will we have the system.
It is, will they deserve our trust?
Yes, they need to deserve trust.
Deeper future risks, newer threats, loom.
So there, there's, there, there's
something called synthetic data bias
training is on synthetic data data risks
and embedding and amplifying unseen bias.
So what's emotion there?
There are a lot of emotional AI risks.
AI systems detecting and
manipulating human emotions
raise alarming ethical dilemmas.
What's deep?
A deep fake profile as generative
models become better at pro producing
synthetic tests, images, and voice.
The challenge of dis distinction, real
versus fake is getting existential
AI will increasingly act first,
but must never act against us,
but which is happening right now.
So we need to balance this
innovation with ethics.
Balancing bold innovation with
rigorous ethics requires systemization.
It needs a proper framework for this.
It's innovating fearlessly,
evaluate impact, thoroughly
implement ethical safeguards,
and continuous monitor and adapt.
And next we need to talk about
ethical ethics by design principles,
privacy by default, bias detection
as part of standard qa expandability
mandatory for all the critical systems,
regular, independent, and external rx.
Ethical AI is just not a destination.
It's a dynamic journey.
So not a single team or a dependent
can can can shoulder this burden.
So trust through a ethical AI
requests executive leadership by, in
the highest level, cross-functional
product teams, which leverage the go
product governance, multidisciplinary
advisory councils, genuine community
and stakeholder involvement.
The best technical systems will
just will be built just for the
society, but for the society.
So we need to, let's talk
about some key takeaways here.
So performance performance
analytics can and must coexist.
Ethical governance AC accelerates
and hinders the innovation.
Collaboration, diversity and transparency
will define winners in the AI era.
The systems we designed today will,
outliers, let's ensure they carry
forward with the best best values.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time, your
dedication, and your vision.
Innovation without ethics is empty.
Innovation, grounded in ethics,
that's how we change the world.
Thank you everyone.