Hi my friends.
This is Santo, so I am here to talk about.
The advances in minimal invasive
diagnostic and treatment across medical
specialties such as Ute bronchoscopy
are using a flexible endoscope
with LED and HD camera on the tip.
These innovations enhance the
precision of diagnosis and treatment,
hence improving outcome which
is revolutionizing patient care.
In the past decade and a half,
there has been dramatic progress
on flexible endoscopy space.
The surgeon or pulmonologist can now see
heart to visualize regions of the human
anatomy, such as the lungs, with the
advent of small CC, d sensors that could
be placed in the tip of an endoscope.
And shining light at the tissue
through a fiber optic bundle.
Using an external light engine was
the state of art say 10 years ago.
But today we have there
is a HD revolution.
The camera sensors got better in terms
of resolution with CM OS technology,
enhanced photon or light responsibility
that surgeons can see the tissue,
identify and evaluate lesion or features
of interest with high confidence
with visual feedback
received from what they see.
We currently have small, powerful LEDs
that can give light output in the order
of five to 10 lumen at a wide cone
angle to eliminate the tissue to give
high quality imagery of human anatomy.
Today we have a 10 20 P HT
resolution imaging that offers
unprecedented clarity with.
One 70 degrees field of view that
enables wider view of anatomical
structure with very low latency.
60 FPS image that captures motion
such as beating pulse smoothly or can
visualize vasculature with great detail.
Today, the size of endoscopic
tip has gone down from.
10 to 15 outer diameter to about five
outer diameter leading to enhanced patient
comfort in minimally invasive procedures.
And there has been
breakthrough in illumination,
size, and capability of
illumination technology.
LED on tip.
The size of the LED on tip
has gone from two to three
diameter to about 0.57 diameter.
So the LED, the what?
The two to three lED.
The light output of the two to 3M
LED is same as 0.57, about less than
an M-M-L-E-D today, minimizing the
thermal impact on the surroundings
and the thermal management, sophisticated
heat dissipation mechanisms and
temperature regulation systems.
Are designed to safeguard
tissues from thermal exposure.
These LEDs are state of the art, can
deliver exceptionally visibility,
exceptional visibility in poor,
accessible, an chemical regions, and
light absorbing environments minutes.
So there are various imaging modalities
modalities RGB imaging by far the
most common imaging modality where the
standard full colorization visualization.
Providing comprehensive tissue assessment
with natural color reproduction for
accurate and automatical identification
during routine examinations.
Then we have near IR imaging
that's specifically used to reveal
subsurface vascular network networks
and structural abnormalities.
Clear pixel technology is used.
To in challenging light stared
environments to ensure diagnostic
accuracy, even in presence of bodily
fluids or visual obstruction, narrow
band imaging or optical filtering
technology that isolates specific
blue green wavelength to dramatically
enhance mucosal surface patterns.
And microvascular morphology for early
detection of pathological changes.
So the endoscope tip, barring the LED and
the camera, we have space for biopsy tools
that biopsy tools, injection devices,
irrigation systems, and energy delivery.
The biopsy tools can be used to.
Extraction of a lesion for analysis
injection devices like therapeutics,
administrative therapeutic agents directly
to the sites, their energy delivery.
So you want to abl a
kidney stone, et cetera.
With a laser.
So basically we can penetrate
a laser if you want to perform
lacing irrigation system.
So if you want to suck
out the bodily fluid
in a procedure, say oscopy, the extra
space in the shaft could be used
for these regions for these reasons.
The, the clinical applications
across specialties.
It's like gastroenterology, pulmonology,
urology, otolaryngology, that's the ENT.
You can see the diagnostic
improvements between standard
endoscopy and HD endoscopy.
And HD plus enhancement.
So from standard endoscopy to the HD
plus enhancement, we see about 15 to
20% rise in sensitivity and specificity.
So the accuracy improves
about 15 to 20%, which is big.
What are the benefits for the patient?
Benefit for the patient is shorter.
Hospital stays.
It is reduced from multiple
days to mere hours.
So if you can imagine if I have
to do a biopsy of a lung to see if
there is cancer or not, I need not.
So a patient may not
stay for multiple days.
A single day is enough.
Using a flexible bronchoscope, go to the
accurately, to the lesion, and then get
the, use the tools to conduct biopsy.
Less pain medication,
significantly decreases pain
medication requirements, minimizing
side effects and dependency concern,
faster return to activities, dramatic
reduction in recovery time as well.
Lower total cost, substantial
reduction in financial burden through
decreased facility fees, medical
expenses, fewer follow up visits.
What is the impact of the healthcare
impact on the healthcare institution?
Reduced procedure times.
30% decrease in average procedure
duration, allowing more efficient
utilization of specialized
resources, increased patient volume.
Significant 25% increase in daily
procedure per endoscopic suit, enhances
access to critical diagnostics,
improved patient experience.
It's 92% positive feedback, ratings,
reflecting, enhanced comfort and
reduced anxiety during the procedures
and superior financial return.
So the inventory cost of the equipment
for the hospital or the healthcare
institution can be recovered within
within 16 months, demonstrating
exceptional operational value.
Implementation considerations,
capital investment could be 50,000
to about quarter million to quarter
to half a million depending on
configuration, specialized training
for the staff to ensure proper
system utilization and maintenance.
Maintenance requirements, regular service
intervals and sterilization protocols,
external equipment lifespan integration
with EMR, digital archiving of images
and findings enhances documentation,
future directions.
AI assisted diagnostics.
Machine learning algorithms will enhance
lesion detection and classification.
Automated analysis may flag
abnormalities during procedures.
A robotic integration, remote
manipulation will increase precision.
Autonomous navigation systems
will access difficult anatomy.
Single use endoscopes disposable systems
will eliminate cross contamination risk.
Cost effectiveness will
improve mass production.
AR vr visualization enhanced
3D mapping will improve spatial
orientation, immersive interfaces
that will provide intuitive control.
Thank you.