Speaker 16: Hi everyone.
My name is Neha Hana and I'm an
identity Solution architect at Harvard.
In today's presentation, we will
be talking about identity access
management and privileged access
foundation for a C secure O
Enterprise machine learning platform.
Throughout this presentation, if you
have any questions regarding this
video, please feel free to ping me on
LinkedIn and I will be happy to assist.
So let's get started.
In today's session, the topics which
you'll be covering will be around
identity lifecycle management,
which talks about provisioning, de
provisioning, and rule synchronization
with an authoritative source.
Access governance practices, mostly
about certification campaign, the
role-based access and the compliance
alignment, privileged access management,
which is all about securing the admin
accounts and the service accounts
in a machine learning platform.
And in the end, an integrated IM
solution centralized governance with
platform like SailPoint Identity iq.
Let's talk about the IM challenges
that are being currently faced
in the modern enterprises.
As the organization grow, expand, and
scale their machine learning platform and
data intensive workloads, it has been seen
that the identity and access management
also becomes increasingly complex.
From time to time.
This has been seen that traditional
security approaches struggle to keep
pace with this rapidly expanding
user population and service accounts.
Growing regulatory environments in
healthcare and regulated industries,
complex data access patterns across our
machine learning pipeline and analytical
tools, elevated privileges needed for
automation and system administration.
Besides that, some of the other
challenges being faced are like
access for that is uncontrolled
permissions across multiple platforms.
Compliance risk, that is audit failures,
regulatory gaps, and privileged
exposure, which is like elevated
account with without proper controls
seen accessing them some resources or
system which they shouldn't be doing.
Now let's talk about identity
lifecycle management.
The foundation of access control,
identity lifecycle management ensures
that access rights remain accurate
and aligned with job responsibilities
throughout an employee's tenure.
Integration with authoritative
sources like HR system enables
automated provisioning.
When employees gets onboarded, that is
when they jog, join the organization.
Role changes during internal
transfers, timely deprovisioning.
That is when they leave the company,
the organization, and rehired.
If the employee decides to come
back and rejoin the company.
This approach minimizes
the manual intervention.
Reduces the security gaps from the
often accounts and ensures a consistent
enforcement of access policies across
all data platform, analytical tool,
and machine learning infrastructure.
Now let's dig a little bit deeper and
see how connecting IM to an authoritative
source can help in automating the
whole identity provisioning process.
Let's talk about some of the
identity lifecycle management events.
The first one being onboarding, which
is automatic account creation and role
assignment based on a person's job title
and department when they join a company.
Role changes, which is just the
access modification triggered by the
transfer, promotion, or responsibility
shift of an employee offboarding, the
immediate revocation of all access when
employment ends or the status changes.
And last but not the least, the rehire
scenario where, which talks about rehiring
an employee who previously have left the
organization then decided to come back,
which eventually resolves in reactivation
of their digital identity and access.
On the left hand side is a small
diagram showing how all this
automated identity provisioning can
be achieved once you connect an IM
system to an authoritative source.
Integration with HR system creates a
single source of truth for identity data,
enabling real time synchronization and
reduces the chances of manual errors.
Now let's move on to access governance and
certification, the regular access review.
Access certification campaigns
are a critical control or part for
identifying and removing any excessive
or outdated permission, which an
employer and individual hold in the
current job title or responsibility.
By requiring managers and data owners to
periodically review and validate access
rights, organizations can detect privilege
creep and the dormant accounts and maybe
remove them if they are no longer needed.
Ensure lease privileges, privileged
principles are maintained, meet the
audit requirements and regulatory
requirements from time to time, and
also reduce the insider threat risk.
So in short, certifications are important.
Now let's talk about
role-based access model or RAC.
I'm pretty sure that we might
have heard about role-based
access control in our day-to-day.
Work life, but let's dig a little
bit deeper and try to understand
what exactly our back is.
RA simplifies the permission management
by linking access rights to job roles
instead of specific individuals.
This structure enhances organizational
consistency, cuts down on admin task
and strengthens compliance to career.
Auditable access rate.
Below is an example of how.
Different persons performing different
roles in the organization can be assigned
or are back, can be constructed out of it.
For example, a data scientist who, which
who accesses, who assesses the machine
learning platform, models the training
environment and approve datasets.
The level of access required for a data
scientist will differ from a business
analyst whose day-to-day task is to
do some running, some analytical tools
and curating some reporting dashboards.
So maybe a read-only access
will suffice for them.
Let's talk about infrastructure
team, which perform more admin
access or admin level task to support
system with login and monitoring.
So an admin level access will be
helpful for them to perform these tasks.
So this is how.
A role-based access control or an
RA model can help you in assigning
correct permission by just assessing
the right or the job responsibilities
on individual hold in an organization.
Now let's move on to
privileged access management.
Protecting your most critical accounts.
Proficient accounts represents
the highest security risk in
any enterprise environments.
Admin accounts, service account,
supporting machine learning platforms and
pipelines and application credentials,
often hold elevated privilege permissions
that can expose sensitive models, data and
infrastructure if compromised or misused.
Privilege management provides specialized
control to secure these accounts through
credential vaulting, automated rotation,
session monitoring, and just in time.
Access, which is nothing but the
short time access with town time bound
elevation, and automatic revocation.
In this slide, we are going to
talk the core cam pam capabilities
for machine learning platform.
The credential vaulting storing
of privileged secrets in encrypted
worlds, eliminating hardcoded
credentials and reducing the exposure.
Password rotation automatically.
Change privilege credential on a
schedule basis to limit the window
of opportunity for the attackers.
Session.
Brokering proxy privilege sessions
without actually relieving or
revealing your credentials.
Enabling account playability and forensic
review activity, monitoring record and
analyze privileged sessions to detect NLS
behavior and support compliance audits.
Now why is PAM or privileged access
management matters for a machine learning?
Let's try to understand this
machine learning environment.
Introduced unique privileged access
challenges from time to time.
Service accounts run
automated training jobs.
CICD pipelines, deploy models
to production and data engineers
manage infrastructure, supporting
petabytes of information.
Each of these accounts require
elevated permissions creating
potential attack for the vectors.
Palm controls ensure that these accounts
are properly managed, monitored,
and protected against any misuse.
On the left hand side, you can see some
of the points like model protection, which
is preventing the unauthorized access to
proprietary algorithms and training data.
The pipeline security, which is about
securing your automated workflows
and data pro transformation processes
and data set governance control, who
can modify or export the sensitive
training and validation data sets.
So in all this is why PAM is important or
privileged access management and important
when it comes to machine learning.
Now integrating IAM and PAM solution.
The most effective identity governance
program integrate, inter integrate.
Im governance with Pam Execution
layer to provide a unified visibility
policy enforcement, and auditability
across human and non-human identity.
In short, it provides you a single
governance view where you can manage
all identities under one platform,
unified certification, which is
about including your privileged
accounts and access reviews.
That is you can all, you can get your
service accounts, a admin, accounts
certified, and make sure the access which
they hold is correct from time to time
and consistent policy, which is applying
the same security standards everywhere.
Meeting of the regulatory requirements,
compliance and regulated industries,
healthcare and other industries regulated
industries have, or they face strict
requirements around data access,
audit rails, and identity governance.
The reason being these healthcare
industries hold tons of
P-H-I-N-P-I-I data, strict security
enforcement becomes important.
Designed, IEM and Pam programs directly
support compliance by providing
detailed audit logs, showing who can
access what data and what time regular
at tasks attestation that access.
Access rights are appropriate
and necessary, which is nothing
but just validating that whatever
the access currently you hold
are the correct, appropriate, and
do you really need that access.
Automated controls that enforce
separation of duties and lease
privileges, documentation of security
control for regulatory examination.
These capabilities help organization to
demonstrate compliance with HIPAA sox,
GTPN, and other regulatory frameworks.
So in the end, if we have to
sum up the all, we can see that
lifecycle management is essential.
Integration with HR system ensures
accurate provisioning, de provisioning
aligned with job responsibilities.
Governance reduces the risk, regular
access certification, and role-based
models help identify excessive
permission and compliance gap.
Pam protects your critical
assets credential, vaulting
rotation, and monitoring.
Secure privilege, account
supporting ma, machine learning
platform, and data pipelines.
Integration delivers value.
When Im and Pam platforms are
unified, they provide a centralized
governance and consistent security
controls throughout the enterprise.
Thank you all for attending this
session at Con 42 Machine Learning 2026.
I hope these insights help you
build stronger identity governance
foundation for your enterprise
machine learning platform.
Thank you.