Speaker 37: Hi, my name is Cha Calwell.
I'm a product manager and co-presenting
here with me on this particular topic
is Smoothie Chand, who is a principal
engineer and we both work at Adobe today.
At this hour, we are gonna dive into
the evolution of a really key piece of
marketing tech called Center Optimization.
So let's get going.
You know, for many years we as marketers
are totally obsessed with one question,
and that question is, what is the
absolute best time to send a message?
Why is this important?
It's important because marketers
and brands think that there is a
high probability of you opening a
particular message or a notification
at this so-called past time.
But what if I told you that this is not
enough, or this might not be entirely the
right question to ask in today's scenario.
Why?
Because we are in a digital era
where there is so much of noise
and that is ever growing and those
important digital signals are just
getting lost in this whole noise.
So today we are going to dig
into and see how this best time.
Has to turn itself into a decision making
system that can change the game and
you as marketer or brands, how you can
evolve and talk to your bus customers
in a better and a more efficient way.
So for that, we really have to move
out of the shoes of marketer and think.
As a consumer or a customer and understand
the reality and what is that reality?
And the reality is basically there is
a never ending flood of digital noise.
How do we swim through this?
And think about it every single.
We as customers or consumers, our
phones, our inboxes are buzzing
with notifications, emails,
text messages, you name it.
It's basically a digital battlefield
that companies brands have created
and every single brand is fighting
for that tiny slice of attention.
And what if I told you that?
This is not enough.
And this particular statement out
here, you know, tells all about that.
And it might sound a little weird, but
this is the fact we have to all face it.
We have amazing tools.
Every product, every customer have built
these tools that tell you, Hey, this is
the perfect time to hit the send button.
And they have nailed it to the
minute, and yet we see customers or
consumers like us are just tuning out.
And this tuning out is
not happening today.
It's happening over a period
of time, if you have noticed.
So what is really happening and
what are these consequences?
Well, the consequences are
pretty clear, honestly.
As you can see here, right?
We are in a digital era.
We have so much that we have to face in
terms of digital noise, engagement rates.
Things like clicks and
opens have flatlined.
Why?
Because there is a wall that we have
created between all of those digital
noise that we only tend to open.
Those important messages that we
feel appropriate, and only then the
clicks and the opens would go up.
Why is it flatlining?
Because of the digital noise and
all of those personalizations.
As marketers, as brands we put in those
messages feel very mechanical and robotic.
Why?
Because we are not even opening those
messages for the most of the time.
So all of those personalizations that has
been implemented, that has been gaining
so much of prominence over the years,
all of that is going down the drain.
Why?
Because in the first place, we
are missing the real human touch.
So we got a focus.
On the Who, because typically the focus,
all this while has been on the when and
we really forgot about the who and the who
being the CUS customer or the consumer.
So how did we get here in the first place?
Let's kind of settle back, rewind for
a minute and look at the tool that was
supposed to solve all of this for us.
And for a while it really was
a complete game changer, right?
We wanted those messages at the time
when I am free, when I am sipping my
coffee, but it has not been working.
So let's see.
The tool that was supposed to solve
all of these problems for us was sent
time optimization, or STO for shot,
and the idea behind it was very simple.
The plan was to use machine learning
technology to scan all of our
customer past behavior to predict
the exact moment that we're most
likely to open our next message, and
the process here was very simple.
We would analyze all the engagements,
which is typically the open and the click.
You would train a model and feed
this particular data so that it can
spot patterns in your data and can
spit out a personalized best time
for every single person on your list.
The whole goal was here.
Very much laser focused on one thing, and
that one thing was the absolute best time
or the highest probability time of a open.
And look, let's be fair, this
worked wonders back in the days and
honestly, even today, some of the
marketing tech has not evolved and
we are following the same old trend.
But hey, it worked wonders.
Marketing was mostly just about batching
blast email campaigns, weekly newsletters.
Well, in these scenarios, STO gave
marketers a massive, massive advantage.
But as we all know, the world is changing.
The world has changed.
There is so much digital noise, and
the world looks very different now.
And this is where it all started
breaking and AI is probably the
solution, but if you look back at
the ML that predicted, the send time
optimization sounds so very limited.
So the biggest.
The massive advantage that we got from ML
suddenly started showing its weakness, and
this quote absolutely nails the problem.
High probability does
not equal high wisdom.
Let's take an example.
Let's say my ML or the
prediction model tells me that.
10:30 AM is the most probable time
when I as a customer, sipping my
coffee would be opening my email.
But imagine there's so many other emails,
notifications coming in at the same time.
So as a brand.
Am I fighting with other brands?
Of course you are.
Am I fighting with my own other campaigns?
Yes, of course.
In that particular context,
sending a message do you
think is a wise thing to do?
Mull upon it, you will know what it does.
Let me give you a small example here.
This whole predictive model
is kind of a one trick point.
It's really good at just one trick, but it
does not answer the bigger, more important
questions that are very pertinent
in today's agent era of marketing.
Questions like, should we even send
this message in the first place?
Or, Hey, has this person
already heard from us?
Multiple times during the day.
Does this message even make sense for
where the customer is in their journey?
All that crucial context is just gone.
Or the prediction model is not
accounting for all of that.
That is where AI comes in the picture.
That is where decisioning
has to happen and.
That is the game changer because why?
There's so many scenarios.
The context is lost,
the world has changed.
Marketing in this modern era isn't just
about simple linear campaigns anymore.
It's a messy, a real time
cross channel conversation.
And if you're only focused on timing.
You are not having a conversation,
you are just shouting into
the void that we have created.
And that brings us to
this massive evolution.
We are moving beyond the simple
question of when to a deeper, much
more prominent, much more smarter
question, and that big shift from.
Prediction to true AI decisioning is here.
If companies and brands do not adopt
it, they are just creating or adding
to that particular digitalize.
Okay, now this slide.
It is everything and it sums it all On
one hand, we have got the old school
STO, it just asks what time is the best.
It's looking at one signal to optimize.
One metrics like open rate, but
on the other hand we have AI based
decisioning and it's asking a totally
different, but a very smart question.
What is the best action from.
Best time.
The best action is the evolution,
and the best action to take right
now is to send or to postpone
or to cancel in the first place.
It's using multiple signals.
It is creating of context.
It is becoming more probabilistic.
From deterministic when there
is probability or when there is,
there is decisioning, and when
there is decisioning, there is ai.
And AI we all know does a better
job than the humans or the ml,
and is using this multiple signals
to make a decision that optimizes
the entire customer relationship.
Don't you think this is a game changer
and we are entering into a different
ball together, ball game altogether?
I hope you all acknowledge that today.
So what are these signals?
As I said, it is looking at, of
course, your best prediction for the.
Best time.
Yes, that is a key ingredient,
no doubt, but it's just one
voice at a very crowded table.
The AI is also considering things
like where the customer is in the
journey, how many messages we have
sent to a particular customer.
In a given day or in a given
week, what are our business rules?
Are there quite ours?
Are there fatigue rules?
It weighs in on all of these factors
and it makes a decision, or it is
giving us as marketers a choice.
And that is where human
come into the picture.
Human as a service in ai.
This is what exactly it means,
and we have a choice to make.
Alright, let's see this in action because
this is where it gets really cool when
I've got one customer say one message.
Let's look at how each system would
handle this exactly in the same scenario.
First up, the classic prediction model,
it crunches the numbers from the past.
You know it.
And it says, Hey, probably 10, 10:30
AM that's the time with the highest
probability of an open send it.
It's as simple as it is.
It's data-driven and well
completely blind about the
context, but it still recommends.
But now what?
What the AI decisioning engine
Engine does, it gives that.
Of course the 10:30 AM prediction, as I
said, it is also a key in gradient, but
it is also considering many other factors.
So what are those factors?
We just talked about it.
Are there messages that were already sent?
Are there F rules?
Are there quiet times?
So the AI's decision, it says in
this particular scenario, hold.
Don't send a message, and that right
there is where AI starts to feel
like less of a machine and more
like a human with a lot of wisdom.
Does it resonate with you?
Yes.
As a consumer, of course.
And that one decision.
The decision to not send a message is
an absolute game changer, as I said.
And that is the fundamental shift away
from chasing short-term metrics towards
building long-term customer trust.
That is where the whole business
impact us, and this particular business
impact is not just getting you the
engagement that you are wanting for.
But for brands, it lasts because
you're not burning out your audiences.
You get lower turn rates because you
stop annoying people into unsubscribing.
And most importantly, you build real
trust by showing your customers that
you respect their time and their inbox.
And this is definitely a competitive
edge that no open rate can ever buy.
I, and so when you zoom out, you can
really see the clear evolutionary path.
We started with a very
clunky manual thing.
Then we got smarter with ML based
prediction, and now the smartest
brands are moving into the future,
which is AI based decisioning.
This isn't just about better tech,
it's the evolution of marketing itself
from just blasting messages to inte
intelligently orchestrating conversations.
So I wanna leave you
with this final thought.
For so long, we have been completely
obsessed with finding the perfect time,
but this shift forces us to ask a better
question and more important question,
are we creating the right movement?
Because as we have just seen, the best
time to send is totally meaningless
if it's the wrong movement to engage.
And with that said, I don't
want to create any more noise.
I would turn the mic to my colleague
who the, to dive into the technical
details and the nuances on the
technical side of this whole journey.
Thank you.
From my side.
Speaker 38: Thanks ti.
Hello everyone.
I am Ti Pathy, principal
engineer at Adobe.
Let me show you how this
actually works in practice.
I will walk through a live demo,
then explain the architecture.
Let me start with the core problem.
Traditional ML system output predictions
like the user has 73% engagement.
Likelihood or campaign
has 0.82 relevant score.
That's a probability.
It tells you what might
happen, but here is the issue.
A perfect prediction can
still make the wrong decision.
What if the user is fatigued?
What if they already received
three messages today?
How do we solve this problem?
What you are seeing here is the
AI stationing layer at the center.
The system does not just predict, it
decides it considers multiple ML signals.
Business constraints like message
limits, users, state across campaigns
and a real name context then produces an
action like either send, differ or skip.
With reasoning, I will run through
five scenarios that show how the
systems make trade off between
business goals and user experiences.
For this demo, we'll be using email
as the channel to keep it simple.
But the ING framework works identical for
push notifications, SM Sapp messaging.
Basically, it's channel agnostic.
Let's see this in action.
Five scenarios showing how
AI agent balances business
goals with user experiences.
Let's dive right in.
So fresh user, user, one fresh user
scenario that we're talking about.
User one, flash sale and
high engagement score.
Low fatigue or zero fatigue.
So our agent made addition to send the
campaign, and the key factors in this
station are the high engagement score,
low fatigue and higher urgency override.
Let's look at another scenario.
Same campaign, higher engagement row.
Higher, higher engagement
score, but fatigue is very high.
So look at the fatigue score
zero 0.80, and our agent made
agent to defer this campaign.
Here is a classic example of
prediction, or a perfect prediction
is not equal to the right duration.
Traditional systems are, are just a
prediction systems, a predictional
prediction system only, prediction
only system would definitely have
sent this or send this message.
AI agent is smart enough to make
aion and give you the reasoning.
The fatigue score is 0.80
is a key factor here.
As it indicates that the user might
be overwhelmed with messages, even
though engagement and urgency scores
are are favorable, protecting the
user experience is a priority.
This is the classic example
of how our agent works.
Let's go dive into the third
scenario where user three
we're sending a newsletter.
Low urgency, fresh user.
Ation made is to send, and
the high engagement score and
low fatigue levels, overweigh.
The channel preference.
The user is preferring a channel email
channel of high, but it overlays.
And then we, the station was made
by our agent to just sign it.
Let's look at the food scenario, which
is a product update where the urgency
is high channel preferences are there.
You see the newsletter one to compare this
product update the channel preference, and
it actually sends how to send the respect
respected contact email or channel.
That preferred channel.
The preferred channel is true for email.
So we're still sending while the user
is within the daily message, remain.
The high engagement and low 50 across.
Scores indicate that sending
this message now would provide
the best user experience.
That's the reasoning.
Let's look at the final scenario.
Here we have our user too, the
fatigue user, returning back again.
And we are gonna send the
product update to him.
So our trying to send the product update.
His fatigue score is still high
and the agent actually persisted.
The per state persisted the state.
Across campaigns.
The fatigue score is high, the key
factor, and standing during a high
fatigue score period, risks annoying.
The user and the nation is made to differ.
So look at the final statistics
where we see 60% were sand and 40%
were deferred out of this, right?
The system isn't maximizing sand, it's
basically optimizing for relationships.
So what, what we are, what
we are talking about here is.
This is what, when, when, what
we mean by agent ai, right?
So it's not only just the scores,
it's also preserving or balancing how
audation is made how AI decides this.
How does we do this station flow?
Let's look at that.
How did we build this?
This is three layer architecture where the
first layer is the ML prediction layer,
where you can see here, it uses the four
models, producing scores with confidence.
The second layer is the
AI stationing layer.
The agent that you just saw.
Consumes those signals and
reasons over constraints.
And finally, the state manager,
which tracks finally the state
manager, which tracks user
histories and enforceable limits.
So three layers, three jobs,
predict, decide, and protect.
The, the, the three key takeaways here.
The first one, ML output signals
AI makes Ation a perfect score can
still be leading to a wrong action.
The second takeaway, isation
layer is a first class system.
It's not just business rules.
It's an intelligent agent that
reasons over multiple signals
and constraints that we get from
the output of the ML prediction.
The third takeaway here is scale
requires engineering in production.
This runs millions of agents per day
with sub a hundred millisecond latency.
It's a distributed system.
It's a distributed system problem.
State management across competing
campaigns, realtime orchestration,
production, good reliability are required.
So one challenge we solved
is the state convention.
Multiple campaigns, campaigns were
competing for the same user as we
saw in the demo at the same time.
Addition layer arbitrates in real
time tracks how many messages the
user, each user received today enforce
limits and prevents over messaging.
So to wrap it up, we shifted from when
should we send to, should we send at all
that required a new architecture layer.
That reasons not just simply predict,
this is agent AI in production.
The demo code is on GitHub
and the link is here.
Happy to connect on LinkedIn.
Thank you for attending our session.
Thanks.
Bye.