Hi everyone.
Welcome to my talk on a powered
integration testing, transforming
enterprise Reliability
through adaptive automation.
As modern organizations increasingly
rely on seamless integration between
diverse applications and systems,
conventional testing methods struggle
with maintenance burdens, limited test
coverage, and inefficient execution.
AI driven test automation is
emerging as a game changing
solution to these challenges.
This presentation explores how artificial
intelligence introduces intelligence
and adaptability throughout the
testing lifecycle, from test design to
execution and analysis, transforming
how we verify enterprise integrations
and delivering significant improvements
in efficiency, quality, and cost.
Before I move further,
let me introduce myself.
I'm Shiva Yamani, currently working as
quality engineering manager with Infosys.
I have close to 18 years of work
experience in software industry
with focus and expertise on software
development and quality engineering.
During my tenure, I have worked
with multiple leading healthcare,
banking, insurance and retail
organizations across US uk.
Providing testing and
automation solutions.
Before we deep dive into AI powered
testing approaches and solutions.
First, let's understand what
software testing is and what
challenges organizations are facing
in today's world using traditional
test and automation practices.
Software testing is a critical phase in
software development lifecycle, ensuring
that products meet necessary functional.
Performance and quality
benchmarks before release.
Despite advancements in automation,
traditional methods of generating
and validating test cases still face
significant challenges, including
prolonged timelines, human error,
incomplete test coverage, and
high cost of manual intervention.
These limitations often lead
to delayed product launches and
unidentified defects that compromise.
Software quality and user satisfaction.
In this slide, I'll outline some of the
key challenges organizations are facing
today to start with growing complexity.
Modern enterprise ecosystems create
a complex web of connections that
traditional testing methods based
on static scripts and predefined
scenarios struggle to maintain.
The second key challenge
is maintenance burden.
Test maintenance accounts for
approximately 30% of total testing
effort, creating a significant drag on
testing efficiency as systems evolve.
And the third challenge is limited
coverage, where traditional
approaches typically achieve
only 40 to 60% test coverage.
Missing critical integration scenarios
as interactions between systems create
exponentially more test scenarios.
In this slide, we can notice how
organizations are rapidly moving
from usage of traditional testing
methods to a power testing solutions.
The global A enabled testing market
is experiencing explosive growth
projected to expand from 1.65 billion
UD in 2023 to 10.29 billion UHD by
2030, exhibiting a CAG of close to 30%.
This substantial growth reflects
organization's recognition
of a's ability to overcome
traditional testing limitations.
North America currently dominates
with 38.2% market share, followed by
Europe at 29.7 percentage, reflecting
the mature technology sectors in
these regions that typically deal
with complex integration challenges.
Now, since we talked about.
Challenges using traditional testing
methods and how organizations are moving
towards usage of a powered testing.
I will take you through the solutions
which can address these challenges
using a powered testing approaches.
First, a powered test solution
is intelligent test case
generation, which uses.
A, to automatically create comprehensive
test cases for software enhancing
efficiency, coverage and accuracy.
Compared to traditional methods, AI
can analyze code requirements and user
stories to identify potential weakness
and generate test scenarios that
cover various use cases and scenarios.
This approach helps reduce manual
effort, improve test quality, and
ensures more reliable software.
Some of the key aspects of
intelligent test case generation
are automated test design.
A algorithms analyze application,
data flow and architecture to
identify critical parts without human
intervention, creating comprehensive
test scenarios that would be difficult
or impossible to design manually.
The second key aspect
is improved coverage.
A driven approaches
typically identify 40 to 60%.
More edge cases compared to manual test
design, significantly improving overall
test coverage and risk detection.
And the third key aspect is usage
of natural language processing.
NLP based approaches transform how
test cases are created from business
requirements, enabling non-technical
stakeholders to contribute more
effectively through the I interfaces.
The next, a power testing solution is
usage of self-healing testing frameworks.
A self-healing test framework is a
type of test automation framework
that can automatically identify and
fix issues that arise during test
execution due to changes in the
applications, UI or underlying code.
This is achieved by using
a driven algorithms to
dynamically update test scripts.
Ensuring uninterrupted execution and
reducing the need for manual intervention.
Some of the key aspects of self-healing
test frameworks are detecting changes
where automatically identify modifications
in the application interface, data
structures, and business logics.
Another self-healing test framework is
to analyze the impact, which determines
how change affect existing test scripts.
And execution path.
And the third capability is adaptive
tests, which automatically update
test scripts to accommodate changes
without manual intervention.
Self-healing frameworks dramatically
reduce maintenance requirements,
which typically account for 70% of
the total cost of test automation
in traditional environments.
Research shows that these
frameworks can reduce maintenance
requirements by up to 60%.
With visual, A technologies
particularly effective for maintaining
UI tests across changing interfaces.
The next a power testing solution is usage
of autonomous execution and monitoring
techniques, which refers to systems
that can operate and manage themselves,
performing tasks and responding to issues
without constant human intervention.
This includes self-diagnosis, remediation.
And even re-planning based on a
real-time data and predefined rules.
Essentially, it's the ability of a system
to autonomously manage its own operations
and ensure its continued performance.
Some of the key aspects of autonomous
test execution and monitoring
techniques are smart scheduling,
which determine optimal test execution
order based on dependencies and risks.
The second aspect is intelligent
paralyzation, which distributes
test across available infrastructure
to ma minimize execution time.
And the third aspect is predictive
monitoring, which identifies subtile
patterns in system behavior that
might indicate potential issues.
Intelligent test case orchestration
can reduce overall testing time
by 30 to 50% while maintaining
or improving test coverage.
Machine learning algorithms can identify
subtile patterns in system behavior that
might indicate potential issues before
they manifest as failures, reducing
production incidents by up to 45%.
Next, a power testing solution is usage
of advanced AI powered anomaly detection
and root cause analysis techniques,
which leverage machine learning
algorithms to identify unusual patterns.
And deviations from normal
behavior in large data sets.
This helps to pinpoint the underlying
cause of problems enabling foster
and more accurate troubleshooting.
Some of the key aspects of advanced
anomaly detection and root cause
analysis are detecting anomalies
which identifies unexpected
behaviors across integrated systems.
Recommend solutions which suggest.
Specific fixes based on
historical data, unknown patterns.
The third aspect is analyzing the
patterns which correlate data across
multiple dimensions to find relationships.
And the fourth important aspect
is diagnosing root causes, which
pinpoints underlying issues
spanning multiple systems.
AI driven root cause analysis can
reduce debugging time by 40 to 60%.
Compared to manual approaches,
visual AI can detect functional and
visual anomalies with 99.9% accuracy,
significantly outperforming traditional
accession based testing approaches.
Next AI power testing solution
is usage of coverage optimization
and gap analysis techniques.
Coverage optimization and gap
analysis using AI involves using
artificial intelligence to identify
and address discrepancies between
what is currently being covered and
what should be covered, whether in
areas like software testing, content
marketing, or skills within a workforce.
AI helps by analyzing data, identifying
patterns, and suggesting corrective
actions to bridge those gaps.
Some of the key aspects of.
Coverage optimization and gap analysis
techniques are risk-based prioritization.
Focus at testing on high risk areas
first, then gap identification,
discover, untested or under tested parts.
And the third aspect is coverage
optimization, which maximize
coverage with minimal test cases.
A driven coverage analysis typically
identifies 30 to 40% more coverage gaps
compared to manual analysis methods.
Machine learning approaches can
analyze both code structure and
runtime behavior to identify
untested or under tested paths.
Enabling more comprehensive test coverage.
Visual A approaches can achieve 98%
test coverage with 99.9% accuracy while.
Requiring 80% fewer test cases
compared to traditional basic
testing approaches, focusing on
actual user facing functionality
rather than implementation details.
In this slide, we'll talk about real
world impact and benefits that can
be achieved through implementation
of a power testing solutions.
Using a power testing techniques,
40 to 60% of maintenance
reduction can be achieved.
Which will decrease in
test maintenance efforts.
Also, this will help with foster
deployment cycles by 30 to 50%.
In addition, 25 to 45% of better
detection defect detection can be
achieved overall, allowing organizations
with 35 to 55% cost savings.
In this slide, we could see how
industries or domains starting from.
Banking and finance, healthcare,
manufacturing, and retail have
started implementing a powered
testing methodologies to overcome
industry specific challenges.
Different industries are adopting
a driven testing at various rates.
With banking and financial sector leading
adoption with a significant market
share of 22.1% in the global A enabled
testing market in 2022, likely due to
the high regulated nature of financial
services and the critical importance of
maintaining reliable system integrations.
The future of AI driven testing
promises a more proactive.
Efficient and intelligent approach
to ensuring software quality AI will
automate tasks, improve test case
generation, enhance self killing
capabilities, and even predict
potential defects before they occur.
This will lead to foster testing
cycles, increase the collaboration and
ultimately higher quality software.
Some of the key aspects are.
Creation of digital twins, where virtual
replicas of physical systems are moving
beyond product development into quality
engineering, enabling organizations to
test integrated systems in environments
that closely mirror production without
the associated risks Adoption of
explainable A where emerging capabilities.
With AI technologies or addressing
transparency limitations by providing
insights into AI station making
process, thereby enabling testing
systems to communicate the rational
behind test case selection, defect
predictions, and root cause analysis.
Third one is through implementation
of natural language interfaces,
where 62% of quality leaders believe.
Natural language interfaces will
significantly impact testing practices
within the next two years by enabling
non-technical stakeholders to
directly contribute to test definition
without specialized in knowledge.
And the last key point is
usage of federative learning.
Where, which enhances collaborative
a approaches enable organizations
to share testing insights and.
Model improvements without exposing
sensitive data, particularly valuable
for integration testing across
supply chains and partner ecosystems.
Conclusion, we could notice that
organizations are leaning towards
aid driven testing solutions, which
will enable them to have competitive
advantage in foster turnaround
to markets with enhanced quality.
Some of the key points are.
Measurable business impact.
AI driven testing delivers substantial
benefits across multiple dimensions,
including reduced maintenance burden,
accelerated delivery cycles, improved
defect detection, fewer production
issues, and lower overall testing costs.
The second aspect is it's
an essential capability as.
Enterprises continue to expand
their integration ecosystems.
Yay.
Driven trusting will transition
from a competitive advantage to an
essential capability for maintaining
quality and reliability in increasing
complex digital environments.
The third key aspect is
competitive advantage.
Organizations that embrace these advanced
testing approaches will be better potent.
To deliver seamless integration
experiences while accelerating innovation
and maintaining their competitive
edge in the digital market space.
Thank you.
Hope This presentation gave an overview
of challenges in traditional test and
automation methods on the solutions to
overcome these challenges by implementing
a powered testing methodologies.
Thank you again for the opportunity.