Speaker 4: Hello, my name is Alex Kin.
I've been working in information
technology over 20 years, across wide
range of projects from engineering
roles to executive leadership.
Currently I am a CEO
of deep teach startup.
And today I want to talk about
next generation of AI agents.
What can we see behind current hype?
And where is current frontier?
Okay, let's get to presentation
Next Generation AI agents.
Quite ambitious topic, but my goal is
to bring to attention something from
scientific and research frontier and
show you it as a quite deep rabbit hole.
And if you like some you could have
a lot of fun building some knowledge
around it and possibly some basic
solution solutions or something.
So in this presentation, we will go
over some consideration of current
situation with AI agents in terms of.
Hyper facing, but how it's connected to
reality, trying to see connections to
next generation agents for building on
first principles and active inference as
a theory, as a framework which is based
on physics, biology, and our sciences.
How it is possible to build single legends
and then some kind of nested systems and
how it is possible to see it as a stepping
stone for participation in technological
evolution gain, starting from first
principles and physics, maths, and so on.
Yeah.
As for current situation, last year
was definitely a year of the agent in
terms of new developments and hype.
What was raised around even through.
Few months of this year, we see a
lot of new projects and some crazy
ones and see even shortage in Mac
Minis, which is used to launch for
log agent solutions for people.
And developers and builders.
But all of 'em still based on LLM
approaches generative AI approaches.
We promise Autonom, autonomous
and multi and team work working
on complex tasks and, use cases
that we are showing currently.
Foil, massive excitement.
Excitement, but actually
we're still waiting for some
real solution, which will.
Be in our everyday life following
that market booming and for,
again, for last year, it's already
around $8 billion and fast growth
expected to 50 billions by 2030.
Driving by enterprise automation demands
and working in with industry and so on.
But getting to some relative check.
Such agents still fail in novel scenarios.
We still data very data and
compute hungry and we still ate.
And we know how it goes when you
get to some something complex.
And more and more complexity,
getting more and more downfalls
of approach in terms of project.
How currently started just
through this year, up to 70%.
So them have risks to stop working because
of unexpected costs scaling complex
complexity and other related risks.
And it shows together a huge gap between
that hype and actually through autonomy,
through agency and while promising.
Most agents still like, adaptability
still like working with Istic motivation
and with GI that certain opportunities
for building next generation solutions.
And for this presentation, I show
information specifically about active
inference as an example of such first
principle framework and let's get there.
Yeah, some basics about active inference
from that first principle consideration.
It's as a theory.
It's based and routed in free energy
principle and theory, which is developed
by Carl Tristan most ci neuro scientist.
And it's pos that adaptive systems
have some interesting capability to
minimize surprise or prediction error
to will survive in entropy world.
And you build it with unification
on biology and physics.
And application to
artificial intelligence.
The core idea of approach that agents
reduce variational free energy or bound
surprise as some metrics intrinsic
metrics which shows how different model
of the world of the agent and actually
the world and through perception.
And updating internal world models of the
agent and through actions when changing
for world around is also possible.
So that action piece is very
important, not just inference and
updating the models about updating
actual world around according to one.
Yeah, and it brings specific
action perception loop.
And actually action and perception
could be considered a same
phenomenon in this approach.
And for sensing the data agent
can infer some hiding causes.
And update its beliefs on it,
and then act to refine models
or environment accordingly.
And learning from outcomes creating
continuous adaptation for himself.
So expected free energy is
also the metric which includes
consideration for epistemic value.
To explore exploration to reduce
uncertainty for the agent and
getting pragmatic values based
on given generative models.
So exploitation phase to achieve
some preferred states of the agent.
And why it's matter for building of
artificial inte, inte intelligence agents.
Its can provide interesting motivation
for the agent and build it very efficient
way unlike our current approaches and it's
enables draw autonomy in for changing and
uncertain environments for such agents.
And they can evolve through the time built
on first principles from active inference.
Yeah.
So free energy principles defines
that all adaptive systems minimize
free energy rational free energy.
Or surprise and it's physical, like a
physical principle for adaptive systems.
Active influence is a theory
or a framework, build it on it.
And is defines that agents actively
samples the world around to refine
where generative models and for we unify
processes of perception, actions, and
learning to be adaptive in an environment
through agent loop, which defining.
Some different states for agent and
environment in some informational symmetry
and loop of the agent on influence
states predicts outcomes of its actions
selections, policies for specific actions
everything based on calculation for
minimization of expected free energy.
And if building on that, we can
define agents and next generation
agents like autonomous entities
with a core of hierarchical active
inference over generative models,
which adaptive in the world.
And if we are ready to build on
that, we can get actually to enable
them through agency and build on
adaptation of such approaches and
build on interesting motivation of such
first principle agents in a new way.
As for such agents, active inference
agents, advantages very adaptive.
They actually solved dilemma of
exploration exploitation and have
it in some dual mode of handling
uncertainty through epistemic
for engine to reduce, yeah.
And by that outperform current approaches
and get into option and capability
to work with novel scenarios without
massive training for the models.
As for interesting motivations way
build it on that biology principles
it's possible to get to, goal
seeking and curious behavior which
emerge from such first principles.
And it's different from current only
reward and reinforcement approaches.
Such engines could be work,
could work very efficient and
by what, be very scalable.
And from scalability, it's also
possible to build a hierarchies of
generative models for, of such agents.
And we need quite low data and quite
load compute for learning which is
again, contrast one from current
approaches and important thing about
explainability of such agent's behavior.
And when governance software.
Behavior.
Through that approach, it's possible to
have it inspectable about where beliefs
of agents, about policies we're choosing.
So it's reduced in risk risks
compared to current black box models
is not understandable effects.
So active inference is a multi-scale
approach, and we can consider
building starting built in from single
agents to for scaling to multi-agent
environments and on the same principles.
And even on single scale
For agent, it will be.
Able to be real time adaptive and be able
to operate in uncertain environments.
With changes with novelty, and that's
important, for example, for robotics when
body control in changing environment still
quite huge problem and solving on that
scale, working together such agents can
share, the models of the world, keeping
their own boundaries as a mark of blankets
and building some nested structure with
belief propagation from message pacing
and working on expected free energy.
Minimization for whole
team of agent and emerge.
Orchestration from that
collective behavior through
common world model without central
controllers is also possible.
Achievement at some moment.
Yeah.
Active inference can be considered
in a context of technological
evolution and like accelerating of
technological evolution because self
evolving agents can drive innovation.
We can work and enable.
Complex, intelligent by mirroring
biological and physical evolution
mechanisms into digital world, we
can work through collective faster or
discoveries working with hypothesis
in the same manner of epistemic or
actions as biological agents are.
And this is refining model models
and working as researchers and create
some new ways of problem solving.
It is possible to build silent enterprise
system based on them because you could
have have a traceability of on what's
happening and that orchestrated structure
of multi-engine environment and workflows.
Which are capable to adapt in real time.
And using the same principle on
different scales through different
parts of automation robotics
parts and supply chains and our
activities of organizations.
And it's builds bridge to
systemic transformation.
And getting from isolated tasks for
ecosystem wide consideration and finding
some new business model, novel business
model by such agents, even possible social
structures and at some moment getting
to solve real global scale challenges.
Getting closer to the end and just
showing, yeah, that perspective
that behind the current hype it
is needed to trying to figure
out where is the next frontier.
And getting for whole AI movement gets
into first principles, approaches,
implementation, and here specifically for.
Active inference for agents.
I believe it's implementation of it could
really embrace through agency for such
agents because of defining next generation
through first principles for agents which
minimize that free energy or surprise
and, able to be adaptive and be able to be
efficient and be able to solve problems of
current LLM approach, LM based approach.
Limitations.
Yeah, it is good to have in mind about
what active inference providing solution
for exploration exploitation, dilemma.
And it's leverage to create agents which
work with uncertainty by that microbiome
be able to operate in real world and
in dynamic change in environments.
And such agent can work in hierarchical,
nested structure and arrange some
multi-agent emergent behavior.
And working as a single agent or teams
but with the same generative world models.
And doing the same in terms of
minimization of predictions and surprise
about the world and actions in that world.
And finally get to, need to get to some
specific actions in that rabbit hole
direction and trying to build next steps
and technological evolution we need.
To start experimenting with the
new tools which are available.
Some project are already and start
in place, and some startups getting
financing and first robots work
on active inference frameworks.
Let me to provide you
information about resources to
get into Rabbit Hole and yeah.
First is a textbook from
par Puzzle and Freestone.
It's available in for free
on MIT resource by the link.
And you can start from there.
Next textbook, which will be
available soon on fundamentals
of Active Inference for finally
for engineers as, which is good.
Some libraries on Julia on Python
with examples of basic agents working
on active inference principles,
which you can start play with.
And link to Active Influence Institute,
where you can get much more information
about information sources, some activities
on collective education and so on.
So if you interested in such approach,
go through links, start getting
information, start possibly building.
And if you.
Possibly have some questions.
You can reach me out through with QR
to LinkedIn and thank you for your
attention and hopefully we'll see some
new approaches and a new projects who are
building on something real from Frontier.