Hey, good day to everyone.
My name is Salam.
I'm part of Core I-T-S-L-L-C.
Today I wanna talk about the
transforming legacy banking
system through machine learning.
Today I want to share with you a real
world story, not very, not concept,
but the actual journey of how we took.
A legacy banking system and
transformed it into the digital first
mission learning driven platform.
So this transformation wasn't just
about the upgrade, it was about
rethinking processes, reimagining
customer experiences, and
building an agile resilient, and.
So over 18 months, we
revolutionized our operations
moving cloud native architecture
and adopting an API first design.
Every change we made was measured
by one simple question, does this
make experience better for our
customers and easier for our teams?
Today, I will walk you through the
challenges we face, the architecture
we build, that dramatic results we
achieved, and most importantly, the
key lessons we learned that could help
anyone tackling similar transformations.
Let's see our transformation
overview here.
So our journey unfolded through
four carefully orchestrated phases.
First one is the planning, so where we
assess our legacy systems and identify
the key modernization priorities.
The second one is migration.
So this was about careful.
12.5 million customers counts
ensuring that with minimal disruption.
And the third one, actually this we knew
that our, any slip up would impact trust.
And in banking we know
that trust is everything.
So the third one is the implementation.
Here we.
Cloud native architecture and
API first principles unlocking
agility and scalability.
So finally is optimization.
So the transformation did
not stop once we went live,
so we committed to a cycle of
continuous improvement, fine tuning
processes, measuring outcomes.
And iterating for.
So each phase we built on the previous
one leading us to a stable, scalable,
and customer focused platform.
So let's see.
The legacy challenge is here.
So
let's our starting point.
So our legacy systems had a serious
issues performance, bottlenecks
made transactions sluggish.
A 3.2 second delay might not
sound huge, but to a customer use
instant app, it felt painful, slow.
So we had limited
integration capabilities.
Every system was its own line.
So without unified customer view,
we could not deliver personalized
service or anticipate needs.
So security was another major problem.
Outdated protocols expose us to
compliance risk that regulators would.
Finally, maintenance crisis
maintenance pause for skyrocketing.
So we needed specialized support
just to keep lights on with
no room for our innovation.
So these challenges weren't
just technical, they directly
impacted customer first.
He employ more and our.
Comp two position in the market.
So let's see, the next slide, the
technical architecture transformation.
So to follow the about discussed
challenges in the last slide.
So we did not just batch the
old system, we reimagine.
Let's see.
The first one, we adopted a
microservices architecture.
So instead of used monolithic
applications, we built small
independent services that could be
developed and deployed separately.
So next we move on to
the cloud infrastructure.
Scaling resources up or down
dynamically, depending on the
load, without over provisioning.
And next hour is our API first design
created, standardized, reusable
interfaces that made integration with both
internal and external systems, seamless.
And we everything with.
Assuming nothing inside or outside
was worthy until proven otherwise.
So this combination give us
the flexibility, resilience,
callability, and top-notch security.
So let's move on to the next slide,
is the performance improvements.
So let's see the results here.
So the transaction processing speed.
Drop by 75 percentage from 3.2
seconds to the just 0.8 seconds.
So our platforms processing
capability, capacity, surge by that
300 percentage easily by handling
over 2.3 million transactions day.
So through the migration.
And beyond.
We achieved 99.999 percentage uptime.
So thinking about that virtually,
there was no downtime at all
during the complete platform.
So our system downtime across
18 months was just 0.01%.
It came from deliverable deliber rate
design, constant monitoring, and a culture
of continuous testing and improvement.
So it showed our customers they could
trust the new system, and it gave
our teams confidence to keep the
innovating customer experience impact.
So now you can imagine customers
notice the difference immediately.
So our customer satisfaction score
here it's climbed from 52 percentage
after modernization our net.
It's an indicator how likely
customers are to recommend us.
This was Rose, rose dramatically
from 28 to the 52 percentage.
So our mobile app ratings
also improved here.
This is an from average
3.4 stars to the 0.7 stars.
We like this new experience
with this statistic, so even
better customer retention here.
So the ultimate proof of
satisfaction jumped from the 76
percentage to the 92 percentage.
So in banking where switching
costs or high, but competition.
So that's a use gain.
So the.
They were the reflection of how much
value we had unlocked for our customers.
So let's move on to the next slide.
Accelerated customer onboarding.
So one area where transformation
made a massive difference
was customer onboarding.
So before modernization.
Opening a new account took 48 hours, so
multiple branch visits, manual document
verification, overnight batch cycles.
So as part of our intermediate
improvements, we introduced
the partial automation and the
digital document upload, cutting
the process to about four hours.
But the real game change came
with a full modernization.
Today a customer can open a new account
within 15 minutes, a fully digital
biometric verification, AI driven in
KY ctr, in intent account provisioning.
This streamline process lead to a
70 27 percentage increase in new
account openings providing that.
Frictionle experiences
drive real business world.
So in the in business growth.
So let's see, the next slide,
enhance regulatory compliance.
So let's see.
The compliance has always been
critical in financial services.
We all know.
When regulators are the only
are only getting its sector.
So let's see.
The before transformation and the opta
transformation, what was the changes here?
So before modernization, we relied on
manual compliance check and reactive
monitoring our compliance rate over.
Around 97.5 percentage, which
sounds okay, but until you
realize it means the real risk.
Slipping through audit preparations
took year, two weeks consuming,
tons of internal resources and, but
whereas a post transformation, it
took it's it here, compliance is.
So we have continuous monitoring
and real time altering.
Our compliance rate shoot
up 99.99 percentage.
And audit preparation now
takes only just three days.
And more importantly, our teams can
spend more time in strengthening
the operations instead of,
scrambling to checkbox as well.
So let's see the, our next slide.
Migration success metric.
The migration itself was a huge
endeavor and a huge success.
We moved to 1.5 million customer
customer accounts to a new system
without a single data loss.
We read the redesign and optimize.
8 43 critical banking processes to run
on the cloud native infrastructure.
So testing was in a comprehensive
year, 1.2 million automated test
cases covering 98.7 percentage of the
platform and deployments that used
to take 72 percentage no, 72 hours.
Full weekend of downtime.
Now just take just 25 minutes with
the continuous in, with continuous
integrations and continuous deployments.
So this wasn't just a technology
upgrade, it was a fundamental
change in how we operated, tested
and delivered banking services.
So let's move on to the next
slide employee adoption strategy.
So node transformation succeeds
without the people behind it.
So our employee adoption strategy
focus first on the awareness.
Make sure everyone understood that.
Why behind this chain.
So we launched the communication
campaigns to explain not just what was
changing, but how it could, would make
employees work easier and more rewarding.
Training programs.
We gave teams to an experience with.
Dedicated support teams were
available to troubleshoot issues
during the LA transformation,
the early transition stage.
And crucially, we kept optimizing
the platform based on the employee
feedback, not just the technical scale.
So as a result, we achieved the
89 percentage of stock adoption
within just three months.
Yeah, using forever
transformation of this scale.
So let's see the next slide
the cost optimization results.
So financially the transformation
more than justified itself.
So infrastructure cost fell
down by 42 percentage thanks to
the cloud optimization and the
maintenance expenses are dropped by.
58 percentage.
Because of the automation and the simpler
architectures, we slashed a third party
licensing cost by 37 percentage by
consolidating vendors and using open
source solutions wherever is possible.
And the development time for new
features decrease 58 percentage
letting us innovation to.
Letting us innovation faster and
supporting ticket fell down by 72
percentage showing that better systems
lead to the fewer problems overall.
The operations expenses dropped by
the 35 percentage, so that free up
investment for future innovation.
And what is improvement?
See.
Then the next slide is
integration strategy.
So here, integration was a
major pillar for our success.
So we built an API Gateway, gateway
layer that unified access to all
services, all and new in a standardized.
Now either service mesh, manage the
service to service communication
securely inside the cloud native.
And our data integration layer ensure
consistent access to legacy and the modern
systems like, and our security framework.
Across the board.
So this approach let us modernize
gradually without forcing an
overnight cutover, reducing
risk, preserving continuity, and
giving the teams time to adopt.
So let's see the risk mitigation
techniques we can discuss here.
What are the risks we are seeing?
We knew the transformation at.
And we address them around.
So we ran parallel systems with
synchronized data to ensure
no service interruptions.
So Canary deployment allowed
us to test new features with
small percentage of profit.
First, ensuring the confidence
before people rollout.
So the rollback capabilities mean.
That if anything went wrong, we
could revert changes in, instantly
without impacting the customers.
So the realtime monitoring, monitoring
across performance, security,
and system health enabled past
dimension and resolution of issues.
And the cross functional teams
bringing together a technical business
and compliance experts to ensure
a 360 degree view of every risk.
So let's move on to the next slide.
The key takeaways and the next step.
First, a comprehensive strategy,
aligning technical, organizational,
and customer goal is essential
for any successful transformation.
So second the critical to balance
innovation with stability.
So evaluation, not
evaluation in ecosystems.
So here the.
Each one prioritize the change
management just as much as technology
upgrades, because adoption and
drivers drives the real results.
Now the fourth one is
abra API first design.
It's your gateway to future ecosystems
and open banking innovations.
So our journey shows that legacy
systems can be modernized successfully
at scale without losing capability.
Now we are pushing forward into AI
driven personalization, deeper open
banking integrations and ER analytics.
So this all about Thank you.
All for your time and attention today.
I hope our story showed that with
the right strategy and execution,
even more complex legacy systems
can be transformed successfully.
So modernization isn't just about
the technology, it's about empowering
and improving customer experiences.
We are excited to explore ai,
open banking and new innovations
built on our modern platform.
So I had love to connect and discuss
how these ideas could apply to
your own transformation journey.
Thank you once again for your time and
if you have any questions or would.
Alum us@gmail.com.
I would like to repeat again,
S-R-I-N-I-V-A-S-A-L-L-A-M-U s@gmail.com.
I look forward to hearing from you all.
Thank you, and you have a great day.
Bye.