Hello everyone.
Welcome to conference 42,
machine Learning 2025.
My name is Baba PRIs ela and I
work as a staff technical program
manager at Walmart, where I
primarily lead infrastructure,
engineering and DevOps teams.
So today I am honored to
speak to you regarding.
Architecting intelligent platforms,
how machine learning is reshaping
modern enterprise infrastructure.
How machine learning is transforming
cloud platforms into intelligent systems
that deliver measurable business value.
So let's jump in.
So let's talk about evaluation
evolution of cloud architecture.
Let's start with how cloud
infrastructure has evolved.
Initially, we had traditional
infrastructure, manual provisioning,
fixed capacity, and reactive management.
Then came cloud migration, which offered.
Elasticity, scalability and automation,
but the real leap forward is the
machine learning integration.
This brought us
intelligent infrastructure.
Systems that predict,
optimize and self-heal.
Self-healing is a big thing in the
contemporary business because all
the enterprise technologies, all
the enterprise companies or the
businesses today, they are looking
for the systems which can self-heal.
So today, as I said, we are
entering the era of intelligent
platforms, infrastructure.
That continuously optimizes
itself delivering resilience
and efficiency by design
the new cloud architect.
Now this transformation demands
a new breed of architect.
So today's cloud leaders must blend.
Strategic machine learning integration,
aligning machine learning with business
goals, so aligning machine learning
capabilities with core business
objectives and the value creation,
advanced machine learning engineering.
So we have to ensure that designing
and implementing sophisticated
machine learning models.
Optimized for cloud environment
infrastructure mastery.
That's very important.
Leveraging deep cloud architecture
expertise as the essential foundation.
So modern cloud architectures
must develop a sophisticated
understanding of machine learning.
Alongside traditional infrastructure
expertise to create a very functional
and very true intelligent platforms
that deliver measurable business value.
Let's get onto the next slide now,
machine learning frameworks for cloud.
Now let's look at the building blocks.
There are four key frameworks powering
this transformation, TensorFlow on cloud.
TensorFlow.
It dynamically scales complex
machine learning workloads across
distributed cloud infrastructure,
which enables enterprise grade
model training and deployment.
I. Cube flow where Kubernetes is one
of the trending things in the market.
So cube flow, which orchestrates end
to end machine learning workflows
on Kubernetes, streamlining model
development training, and serving
in containerized environment,
machine learning ops platforms.
So this is very critical because it
automates the entire machine learning
lifecycle from development to production,
ensuring reproducibility, governance,
and continuous model monitoring.
And the final one is the Cloud ML
services, which delivers production
ready APIs for vision, language,
and predictive analytics tasks.
Accelerating time to market without
extensive machine learning expertise.
So as I said today, accelerating
acceleration, innovation, and
ready to move already to use APIs.
That's the vision, that's the
language, and that's the production.
So together.
They may democratize machine learning,
making it scalable and manageable
within cloud native environments.
Let's get onto to the next slide.
Governance for success Now,
but innovation without governance
invites chaos, as you all know.
So a miss.
A successful machine learning
platform demands standards
for architectural consistency.
So it defines standards.
We need to ensure that we are establishing
comprehensive guidelines and architectural
principles for machine learning
implementations across the enterprise.
Iterate and improve.
No leverage.
The outcome data to continuously
refine machine learning, implementation
strategies, and governance frameworks
ensure conce compliance is very important
because implementing robust monitoring
systems to verify adhering to security
protocols, regulatory requirements, and
ethical AI standards is very important.
Measure outcome.
So there should be metrics out of it.
So deploy comprehensive metrics to
quantify business value and written
on investment of machine learning
initiatives against strategic objectives.
Let's go to the next slide.
Now let me bring this to life
with a healthcare use case.
So what are the challenges a provider
faced a 30% readmission rate and
only 65% diagnostic accuracy.
Now, what will be the
solution for this now?
Cloud-based machine learning
algorithms, which are integrated
with existing EHR systems.
That enables real time clinical decision
support and predictive analytics.
How should the implementation
and what will be the results now
deploying machine learning models?
Analyzing patient vitals, lab results,
medication data, and social determinants
of health to predict deterioration,
risks and recommend interventions.
It also helps in implementing
cloud-based machine learning, as
I said, which are integrated with
EHRs that flags the risks early.
You know the results.
Readmissions dropped 47%.
Accuracy jumped to 92%, and
the most importantly, savings
exceeded 3 million annually.
That's the power of machine
learning applied strategically.
Let's go to the next slide now.
Machine learning value creation.
This is not theory.
This is measurable.
42% improvement in operational efficiency.
So when you enhance resource
utilization across cloud
infrastructure, that's the value.
That's the improvement we have shown.
67% is true resolution Now.
When accelerated anomaly detection and
automated remediation is in place, we will
be able to resolve the issues much prior.
So that's the number, that's the
percentage which we are seeing.
67% faster issue resolution, 31%
reduction in cloud costs in the
contemporary market where the businesses.
And the enterprises are looking
for optimization to save money.
Optimized cloud spending through
intelligent resource allocation is helping
to reduce costs, and most importantly, 3.5
x faster innovation cycles now accelerated
time to market for business critical.
Capabilities.
So these numbers are real world
outcomes from enterprises investing
in intelligent infrastructure.
Now human machine collaboration.
Let's talk about, let's dive into
the types of machine learning now.
Supervised learning, which
powers anomaly detection and
predictive resource planning.
So engineers.
They provide labeled data, enabling
models to learn from established
patterns and expert knowledge,
real-time infrastructure, anomaly
detection, intelligent cloud
resource optimization, predictive
capacity planning, and forecasting.
They are the benefits
of supervised learning.
Now, unsupervised learning
also helps us a lot.
It helps us to discover hidden
patterns for performance optimization.
It the systems autonomously discover
hidden patterns within cloud
telemetry without explicit guidance.
That is wonderful.
Uncovering non-obvious system
correlations and performance clustering
for targeted improvements and workload
segmentation for optimization.
The last one, which is really
crucial, the reinforcement learning.
It gives us self-healing systems
and dynamic security responses.
It saves lot of resources,
algorithms, which iteratively improve
operational decisions by balancing
exploration with exploitation,
dynamic infrastructure, auto-scaling.
Self-optimizing network configurations,
adaptive security response.
These are the vital things
of reinforcement learning.
This is the future.
Humans guiding machines and
machines learning from operations.
Let's get onto the next slide now.
What should be the organizational
readiness for this?
Success hinges not just on tick,
but on the organization's readiness.
What do you say?
Awareness on machine learning's potential
now by cultivating organizational
understanding of machine learning
capabilities and strategic opportunities
for business transformation.
So we need to ensure that we create
this kind of awareness for machine
learning's, potential skill development.
Through upskilling and hiring.
So investing in talent acquisition
and upskilling existing staff to
build robust internal machine learning
cap competencies or infrastructure
preparation with scalable infrastructure.
What can be done?
No.
We need to understand what is
the existing infrastructure
we have establishing scalable.
Technical foundations with appropriate
data, architecture, processing
capabilities and integration points, and.
One should have clear implementation
plans that aligns with the business.
So executing strategic machine learning
powered initiatives with clear business
outcomes measurement framework and
continuous improvement circle cycles.
It by which by doing all these
things, we can ensure that the.
Organizational readiness is met, and
we are on the way to adopt intelligent
learning and artificial intelligence.
Now, let's get onto the next slide.
For every new thing,
there will be challenges.
There will be implementation challenges,
and let's be honest, it's not easy.
So there will be key challenges.
Key challenges would be the data quality.
Meaning like garbage in, garbage out.
Poor data integrity severely undermines
modal performance established.
We need to ensure that we are establishing
comprehensive data governance frameworks
and advanced pre-processing workflows
to ensure reliable inputs for machine
learning systems integration complexity.
Legacy systems, they create friction.
So entrenched legacy infrastructure
creates significant integration barriers.
So make sure we deploy modern
APIs and robust microservices
architecture, which can seamlessly
connect machine learning capabilities
with existing enterprise systems.
Skill shortages, no machine
learning talent is cars.
So ensure that critical machine
learning talent remains in
high demand at short supply.
So develop targeted upskilling
programs and implement strategic
recruitment initiatives to secure
essential expertise across data
science and engineering domains.
As I said, critical machine learning
talent remains in high demand.
But we have a short supply, so make sure
that we are developing targeted people
with upskilling programs and ensure
to implement strategic recruitment
initiatives change resistance.
Cultural inertia can slow
progress, as you all know.
So organizational inertia, frequently
derails machine learning adoption efforts.
Ensure that we are crafting
comprehensive transition strategies,
highlighting tangible business outcomes
and establish executive champions
to drive cultural transformation.
So each of these must be
tackled head on with governance,
communication, and training.
Let's get onto the next slide.
What should be the steps?
How can we achieve this?
What, where do we start?
How do we assess the current state?
What's ready, what's not?
We need to ensure we are evaluating
infrastructure readiness and
machine learning potential.
Identify high value use cases.
Then develop a strategic roadmap.
Don't just do ml. Define
where it delivers value.
Meaning we need to create a roadmap
with prioritized initiatives.
Establish governance framework,
which is going to help us to
develop a strategic roadmap.
Start small with high value pilots.
Now for us to grow big, we need to
start small then, so then scale up
fast using repeatable frameworks.
Begin with targeted pilots, document
learning and expand successful patterns.
Make sure that.
We are documenting our success, our
failure, our learnings that will help us
to have successful patterns going forward.
Now with this I wrap my session.
Machine learning is not just enhancing
cloud infrastructure, it's reinventing it.
As cloud leaders, our role is
not just to adopt technology,
but to engineer intelligence.
Into the core of our platforms.
Thank you for your time today.
I hope everybody liked my session.
Thanks a lot.