Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42
Machine Learning Conference.
I am Ga Mohan.
Today I'm gonna talk about bringing AI
to the edge, how ML machine learning
models are covering the future of iot.
So that's my topic.
So let's get started.
So the first thing I wanna talk
about is what is h AI mean?
Because in iot, usually the machine
learning models are deployed in
the cloud rather than in the edge.
And but with Edge ai, what happens is it's
a little bit different because you have
the capability to deploy models locally
on the edge device and reduce the latency.
So usually what happens is if you see here
in the Edge device, in the H AI scenario,
so the devices are connected to a local.
Pre-trained model and which can do some
inferencing, and that pre-processing
is done in the edge itself.
And then any result that is there, it
goes directly to the user interface.
But in the case of the usual scenario,
the cloud scenario, what happens?
It goes one level step first,
the it goes into the cloud, to
the do to do the inferencing.
And once the inferencing results are
out, then the user gets notified.
But in the case of Edge ai, you are
reducing multiple levels of hopping here.
So everything is done at the edge itself,
and this helps in real time tracking.
For example, if you wanna do traffic light
control system, or if you wanna understand
if your appliances are broken, all these
informations can be immediately available.
And you can track also the real
time status of your devices.
So this also actually solves
the privacy issues being once
you send the data to the cloud.
So it can be geo geographically
moved from one location to another.
So you can avoid that by keeping the
model inferencing very close to the
source where it is getting generated.
So that is all about H ai.
So now let's see about, now
let's see about what it means to.
Actually seen in an actual scenario.
So for example, the first
one is a surveillance camera.
So I was talking about if you want to
create create inferencing in the place
where the cameras are located, for example
you want to track any anomaly in the
outputs so you can keep influencing models
right close to the source where the data
is generated, which is in the case of.
So you can detect if any anomalies
happening in the same way.
You can do that in the manufacturing
robot, so you can real time track without
sending these images to the cloud.
And then there is a smart speaker
in your home, which recognizes your
voice locally instead of sending the,
sending your voice and your prompt
to the cloud for further processing.
So instead, you keep everything
in the source for faster response
and also for privacy concerns.
So these are some of the
examples that you can see today.
And the next one is about why
edge is better than cloud.
So now we are moving the
AI inferencing to the edge.
So is it how better it is?
So you can see that in the
cloud, the inferencing happens
in the cloud, in the edge.
It happens in the.
Device itself.
So what happens?
What is a big advantage of this?
So the first advantage is latency, as
we have seen, because you are getting
the real time response as the data is
generated, and then the inferencing is
done, and also it reduces the bandwidth.
So bandwidth being so you are not
sending a lot of data to the cloud.
So there's minimal data that is
being up that is being processed
as as well as sent to the cloud.
Now comes security, which
we already touched upon.
So you are reducing the number of
hops that happens for the data.
So in this case, in this scenario, what
happens is you are creating a much more
secure solution because you're, you are
not moving the data around most often.
And also it's very reliable
because it operates with even
no internet connectivity as well
as limited internet connection.
That way you can create
reliable solutions.
And the last but not least
advantage of that is the energy.
So because you are not spending that much
compute com compute in the cloud, you're
basically reducing the energy as well.
So this is some difference between
Edge AI and then the cloud ai.
So the biggest change in the paradigm
shift for IOT today is 75% of the data
today as we speak for this year, is
actually processed at the edge, which
is revolutionizing the AI powered iot.
This is changing the way we approach the
iot solutions because you are doing a
lot more than what you can a lot more at
the edge than you were able to do before.
But doing this actually ha poses its
own challenges in the background.
So the first challenge is limited
computing resources because.
Now you're limited to, now you're
doing more than what you used to do.
So you have usually these devices used to
be resource constrained devices, right?
So now you have low processing power
compared to those powerful GPUs and
TPUs that are running in the cloud.
And then you also have limited
memory and power, memory and
storage for the AI models to use.
Because there are so much going on, right?
And the devices are already resource
constrained and the power supply.
So mostly these devices
are battery operated.
So because of that, there is a
constraint in the power as well.
And you cannot run actually complex
models like a full fledged resident
one 50 and stuff like that, because.
You don't have that much resources
in the case of compute, storage
processing power, et cetera.
And also the module deployment and update
becomes a challenge because it's very hard
to push all these updates to the we might
have 10,000 devices in the edge, right?
So it's very hard to go and,
update each and every device for
a new model when it is available.
And also you have the risk of
not matching the version that you
are actually, you actually need.
This also I mean we have already seen
that it actually helps with security, but
also it also possesses another security
in the other side of the spectrum.
So the security issues being
the devices are actually mostly
open to the public network.
So you you are prone to malware
attacks, and also you need
a secure boot in the device.
And also you need to use lightweight
standard protocols, which which
provides security from the start.
So other than that it becomes a huge
prone to threats and attacks even though
it is secure in its way that you're
not doing in the cloud, but there is of
course security risk in the edge itself.
So there are other challenges.
Let's go into the second
part of the challenge.
The second part of the challenge being.
Connectivity issues.
So connectivity issues, as I said
before these devices are usually
deployed in remote services.
Sometimes they don't have any internet in
them, so it is very hard to sync to the
cloud even after getting some inferencing
data and then you wanna store it in the
cloud or, use it for later purposes.
For deploying the cloud for using
the cloud for post-processing.
So it's very, it's
becomes a hard challenge.
And the next challenge is model
optimization and compression.
So you have to ensure that
you are creating a model which
is suitable for the edge.
So it has to be lightweight.
So the accuracy might be compromised
because you're not gonna get the full
blown result of the model because it's
very tailored to the scenario at the edge.
And in the case of observability,
it's very hard to do because.
You have to monitor
performance and failures.
You can do only simple logs and tools.
You cannot do complex telemetry data
like open Telemetry, Yeager, and
all that stuff because it's just not
possible with the resources in hand.
And there's also diversity problem,
Harvard diversity problems.
So there are so many devices.
So many different vendors are there.
So everyone has their own OS protocols.
So it becomes a challenge to
aggravate those devices and ensure
that you're able to run those models
everywhere in a uniform fashion.
So these are one of the
challenges that we have.
Now let's go into the nitty
gritty details of best practices.
So even though we have some
challenges, but there is a way
that we can actually make it better
by using some of these practices.
So there are four practices
that I'm gonna cover today.
So the first is deploying
ML models at scale.
How we can do that so that we have 10,000
devices and the devices keep increasing.
How do we make sure that the models
are getting deployed to every device?
And the second one is
updating models on the edge.
How do you do it?
If there is a new version of the
model that is available how we
can ensure that you are following
the best practice for that.
And also you use model compression
techniques, which will reduce the
model size and then ensure that it
is used for the scenario in hand.
And also last but not the
least, using AI pipelines.
The cloud is not in the not completely
out of the picture, but you can
still use them for your other
purposes, which will get into it.
So the first practice, which
I wanna cover, is like how to
deploy models at this edge.
Since we have so many devices,
thousands and thousand devices,
it becomes very critical to ensure
that you have model portability.
So you wanna ensure that you're
using a runtime in the device, which
is portable for all the models.
For example, use formats like Onyx
or TensorFlow Light that works across
different hardware because we wanna ensure
that why if it is working in one hardware
and if it's a different vendor in a
different hardware, it should work, right?
Because then there is a
model incompatibility.
So that's why you should use
a model that is portable.
And also you should also use hardware
abstractions like target accelerators
Nvidia Jetson or in Intel Vid or Arm
NPUs because these devices are designed
in a way to use unified run times.
And you can use these unified runtime
to deploy any model of your choice,
which is targeted specifically for H ai.
And the last best practice to deploy
models at scale is containerization.
So once you package all the dependencies
in a container, you can use Docker to
run it so that you have a consistent
execution across different platforms
so that in that way you have a
steady way to deploy these models.
So you package the models inside
the containers as well so that you
ha you, you're expecting something
in the same consistent result in
every device that you're deploying.
So this is one of the best practices
to follow first when you're deploying
so many devices for I iot H Solutions.
So the next solutions for
updating the models, for example.
If you have a new model that is
coming up after you have pre-trained
them with the data, that historic
data that you have, now you need to
understand how to update them, right?
Because frequent updates are
required required in order
to improve the efficiency.
As well as, if there is any vulnerability,
you wanna ensure that is also taken care.
So you need to adapt to an environment
that is constantly shifting.
So in order to do that, some of the
best practices to do is over the
air updates with version control.
So that is basically sell sending to
multiple multiple devices over the
air, which means over the internet.
And then there is another
practice called AB testing.
So you first test with one model and
deploy them and see how it works,
and then you roll out the rest of
them for the rest of the devices.
And there is also another scenario
you can use, which is digital twin.
So digital twin is basically, you
mimic the same physical device
to a digital environment and see
that if you put the new model into
the digital twin, what happens?
And if everything is the
everything is going fine, then
you can go ahead and update that.
So this one is about how
to update the models.
So the third practice is how to use models
that uses the compression techniques.
So since Edge AI is going to use
a different model than the usual
model that we use, so we need to
understand what kind of compression
techniques that goes to the model.
So the first one is the quantization.
So quantization you can think
of if you have a cloud, a beefy
system, you would use a 34 bit
machine or a 64 bit machine, right?
So now you are no longer in such a luxury
en environment, you're in a very small,
constrained devices like a raspberry pie.
So now you have to run
the model in there, right?
So you need to compress your
model to eight bit in teacher
so that it's smaller size and it
can also do faster inferencing.
And also another technique
that you can do is pruning.
So what you do is you remove
the insignificant fats or
the neurons from the model.
So this way what happens is it speeds
up the computation as well as gives
you inferencing the cells very quickly.
And then the next, the third one
is like knowledge distillation.
So basically it's a concept of dialing
down the model to a student model so
that it does the basic operations.
Correctly.
And then you try to learn to make the
teacher model, which is the larger model.
So in this way you get also higher
efficiency with good accuracy as well.
So these are some of the techniques
that are deployed in order to support
the model for the edge AI scenario.
So the last but not the
least practice is the.
Cloud managed AI pipelines so you're
not taking cloud entirely out of the
picture because rather you would try to
augment both cloud and edge together.
So rather than running the, managing
the life cycles of all these systems
manually, you can do it using
cloud based ML operations, which
are machine learning operations.
So these pipelines can actually
train and retrain on the cloud
and then update the dataset.
What I mean by that is like you're
doing behind the scene work, which is
doing all the training and, making the
model better so that you can, you don't
have to pre-train them anymore, right?
So the CICD pipelines are
there to automate the testing
as well as the deployment.
And also you can do telemetry
collection from edge to continuously
improve the models because.
Some basic telemetry is still okay
because you would need that to understand
what's going on in the edge device
and then use that information to train
your model better and then use it for
the, different version, which is much
better than the previous version.
These are some of the examples.
Azure, ml AWS SageMaker always,
they have their own solutions.
For AI pipelines so that you can integrate
and continuously deploy AI solutions
in for the real world application.
So now let's see some of the actual
real world application where it
is actually using some of the
principles we just talked about.
So first is the deploying example.
So Walmart actually uses, for deploying
models at scale, how what they did is
basically they deployed thousands of
cameras with AI models in their retail
stores to monitor inventory levels.
Also understand where each order, each
item is placed, and also custom behavior.
There is any theft or if there is
any anomalies that is happening.
So how they used it is they used compact
edge servers like Nvidia Jetson and also
they used computer vision models in which
is optimized just for edge scenario.
And they use tens.
Tens is it is a simpler
version of the user 10 flow.
So now we have the result.
So result is basically you have
reduced stockouts and you have
optimized the restocking schedules.
You understand how to improve the
efficiency, operational efficiency
across different locations.
So this is for deploying at scale
for, the first best practice.
So now let's go into the second
best practice, which is updating the
versions over the ensuring that you're
versioning it, and you are delivering
the right model to the right devices.
So Tesla actually did the
over the air updates model.
Model updates.
So what they did is they
routinely push AI updates.
For example, the autopilot vision
and the driving behavior models,
they go to the cars globally.
So how they did it was they
used the secure OTA pipelines to
validate and deploy the module
with rollback capabilities.
So they have ensured that for each model
that they are incrementing, they made
the minor major or minor improvements.
Without the customers going to
the store and making an update.
So they basically, they did it over
the air, which means that the customer
received the models just over the internet
and then it is much easier to deploy and
reduces the time and efficiency of the
customer as well as the service centers.
So this was, this is a very good
example of real time scenario
of Tesla cars getting updated.
So the last, oh no, the la
the model compression, right?
So Google actually did the model
compression for their mobile
net on their Android devices.
So what they did was they did the
mobile net family, which is basically
just targeted for a lightweight
mobile inferencing scenario.
So you can do image classification in
with the compute power that you have
for the mobile or object detection.
So how they did it, basically they
used quantitation as well as pruning
techniques, which we talked about to
reduce the model size and also use the
that to retain the accuracy in which they
wanna detect or image or object detection.
So the result was real time.
You were able to get AI
features in your phone instantly
without the use of internet.
So you can just even in Europe plane,
you can do all the image detection
and object detection pretty easily.
So this is an example.
Very good example for model compression.
So let's go to the last example, which
is the cloud managed AI pipeline.
So Siemen actually predicted
they did predicted.
Maintenance in the factories.
So Simons, what they did was they
deployed the AI across factory flows.
So whenever the machines were down, or
before even getting to that state, they
were able to predict it and they used
Azure iot as well as ML pipelines to
train models in the cloud and also deploy
the different versions that are needed.
By this way, they reduce the downtime
because what happens is whenever
the the machines go on maintenance
mode, it takes forever to come back
up and it creates a lot of downtime,
cost inconvenience to the customer.
So it, they reduced all that and
the machine downtime was reduced
to 30%, which is pretty nice.
So now they're also using the cloud
to continuously retain models.
For all the edge collected
for the edge scenarios.
So they were able to collect the
telemetry from the edge and use that
in the cloud and use the pipelines to
make this seamless so that they use
both the edge in the cloud scenario.
So this way they were able to reduce
the maintenance as well as make sure
that they are getting real time updates
of their devices using the AI models.
So these are some of the best practices
and we saw some real time use cases.
So that's pretty much what I had and the
how AI is actually re revolutionizing
iot in the edge space is amazing.
And hopefully this gave you some
insights into the into the background
of IOT and its solution and what
is being followed right now.
Thank you so much.