Hello everyone and thank
you for tuning into Con 42.
I'm sat and I'm today excited to walk
you through how predictive analytics
and machine learning are not just
enhancing but fundamentally reshaping
the way we approach population health.
In the next few minutes, we
will look at how data, when used
intelligently and ethically can drive
not only better healthcare outcomes.
But also more equitable
and cost effective systems.
We will cover the challenges we
face, the methods we are using,
and the impact we are already
seeing in real world population.
The population health challenge.
Let's begin by addressing
the core challenge.
Across the healthcare ecosystem,
around 60% of our organization
struggle to identify and proactively
manage high risk populations.
This is not due to the lack of will.
It's often due to the data silos,
outdated infrastructure, and
limited access to integrated tools.
Product two Care enabled by the
right analytics has been shown
to reduce hospitalizations.
By 25% and improve preventive
care enhanced by 30%.
We are talking about a real
shift from episode care to
continuous personalized support.
And these insights come from diverse
healthcare studies conduct across
35 states, leveraging data from the
C-D-C-C-M-S and institution like
Mayo Clinic and Kaiser Permanente.
The 360 degree patient view.
To make predictive care effective,
we must start with a complete
360 degree view of each patient.
We do this by integration, three key
types of data, clinical records from EHRs,
utilization and cost data from claims and
social determinants of health, or SDOH.
By combining these, we gain not just a
medical snapshot, but an understanding
of the context behind a patient's
health, their environment, income,
education, even housing stability.
With advanced ETL pipelines, secure
API Gateways and HL seven FHI
compliance, we ensure this data
is both producted and accurate.
Validated over 99.7% of accuracy.
The result, A foundation we can trust
for making life impacting decisions,
risk stratification models.
Next, we apply risk stratification using
supervised machine learning models.
Train on over 8.5 million patient records.
We evaluate over 3000 variables,
including lab results, medication
adherence, utilization patterns.
And even socioeconomic inputs.
We use algorithms like random forest
and gradient boosting, which have
outperformed traditional logical
regressions, delivering 87 to 92%
prediction accuracy in anticipating
hospitalization within a six month window.
This lets us bucket patients into four
tires, high risk, rising risk, low risk.
And healthy each time received a
tailored intervention plan from
intensive care management to
wellness and education initiatives.
This personalization at scale is what
moves the needle in population health.
Predict predictive analytics.
The results speak volumes in studies
Over 30,000 patients compare it to
predictive models, to traditional core.
Readmission dropped by 20%.
Er, we see visits decreased by 30%.
Overall health cost reduced by 20%.
Perhaps more importantly, patient
engagement increased by 40% with
higher appointment attendance and
better follow through of care plans.
All of this was achieved using
statistically significant
method of EAB testing and.
Prosperity score matching, ensuring the
outcomes were in just al. Predictive
analytics isn't just about risk scores,
it's about outcome, impact, and equity.
Geo special healthcare analytics, one
of the most powerful and sometimes
overlooked tools in our arsenal.
Geo hospital analytics.
Using GIS technology, we map disease
prevalence, resource usage, and care
access across gaps entire regions.
With this insight, we have helped
organizations identify healthcare deserts,
designing mobile outreach programs, and
even optimize where to place new clinics.
For example, you by using catchment
area modeling and ISOP prone maps.
We improved facility placement efficiency
by over 40%, reducing both patient
travel time and operational strain.
This brings precision to
population health, right
care, right place, right time,
machine learning applications.
Let's not drive deeper into how machine
learning fits into this equation.
We aggregate vast data sets from EHRs.
Labs pharmacy records to
socioeconomic indicators.
Our models range from decision
trace to deep neural networks,
the undercover patterns that would
take years to identify manually.
For instance, one model flags patients
at risk of readmission based on subtle
combinations of medication refill
patterns and prior claims data with What's
key here is not just prediction, but.
Inter interpretability, we ensure
clinics can understand why a
model made a recommendation.
Fostering trust and adoption
case study, chronic disease management.
A example comes from a regional
health system serving 150,000 people,
mostly between the ages of 45 and 75.
With the high diabetics burden,
they implemented our predictive
platform focused on hba one C trends,
medication adherence, and social data.
Over 18 months of diabetic
admissions dropped by 42%, thus
saved 3.2 million annually.
Even more powerful was the feedback loop.
Real-time patients outcome
were fed back into the system.
To continuously adjust care plans.
It's not just a dashboard,
it's living a learning system
addressing healthcare disparities.
A core value of this work is health
equity using SDOH and claims data.
We identify undeserved population
based on a zip code, ethnicity,
income, and access of access to care.
We partner with LO local organizations
to design culturally sensitive outreach
programs like mobile screening vans
and translated education materials.
We also monitor equity KPIs to track the
long term success of these interventions.
Analytics isn't just for efficiency,
it's for about fairness and inclusion
implementation roadmap.
Implementing predictive analytics
isn't a plugin and plug and play task.
It requires structured roadmap,
data integration connection, EHR
claims and SDOH sources, securely
and consistency analytics, depart,
develop, deployment, test and refine
predictive models, train staff on
BI dashboards, workflow integration.
Embed insights into real world
clinical processes without
disruption, continuous improvement.
Use a op plan, do study, act, look
to recalibrate models and expand.
Reach.
Change management is key.
We work closely with stakeholders to
ensure clinicals are supported not over.
Key takeaways.
Let's recap the core insights from today.
Integrated data creates
a complete patient view.
Predictive analytics shifts care
from reactive to proactive hospital
analytics, add geographic precision.
Machine learning powers smarter,
faster decision and equity
must remain front and center.
We are not just building models, we
are building better healthcare future.
Thank you for so much
time on in joining me.
It's an existing exciting time
to be in healthcare technology.
With the right tools and frameworks, we
can transform not just systems, but lives.
Let's continue building healthcare system.
That are intelligent,
inclusive, and truly impactful.
Thank you very much.
Thanks for joining me at Con 42.
Have a good day.