Hi everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
It's truly an honor to speak on
Conference 42, machine Learning 2025.
I'm D Patel, a seasoned data
engineer specializing in healthcare
data compliance and analytics.
Let's begin with a simple caution.
What if we could predict a heart
attack, not minutes before,
but a days before it occurs?
Thanks to the breakout in AI and data
engineering, that's no longer just a.
Healthcare is shifting from a reactive
model to a predictive one where we prevent
illness before it even occur Today.
I'll walk you through this
transformation, the technical journey
behind it, the real world example,
and how predictive healthcare is
changing the future of medicine.
So let's dive in.
All right, so from data to diagnosis,
engineering, ai, power predictive
healthcare system, we are at a pivotal
moment in the evolution of healthcare.
One where artificial intelligence
combined with robust data engineering,
is enabling us to move from reactive
care to a predictive system.
This technology allow us to anticipate.
Patients need in real time, significantly
improving early detection, enabling
timely intervention, and ultimately
enhancing clinical outcomes.
In this session, I will walk you
through how this system are designed,
the challenges and the measurable
impact they are already making
across the healthcare setting.
Alright.
So let's begin with the healthcare
transformation training.
It helps to take a step back and
look at how far the field has come.
Because the healthcare has been
undergoing a significant transformation
over the past few decades.
This transformation can be broken
down into three major phases,
traditional healthcare, digital
transformation, and AI integration.
Let's begin with the first phase,
traditional transformation.
This was the era most
of us are familiar with.
Healthcare was reactive by design.
You waited until you had a symptom,
maybe a chest pain, fever, shortness of
breath, and then you went to a doctor.
Diagnosis were based on symptom
patient memory or physical exam
or basis of a test lab test.
At this stage, very little was
systematically recorded or reused.
It was mostly paper-based
and the information rarely
left the physician office.
The role of data was minimal.
It showed only an immediate visit and a
long-term trend of across patient insight.
Lastly, invisible then comes the
transformation, digital transformation.
This really gained a momentum in 2000.
Accelerated by eruption of electronic
healthcare record, which is EHR.
Suddenly we started capturing
everything, vital sign, lab results,
medications, diagnosis, progress
notes, and all in a digital format.
But here's the catch.
While we were collecting all this
data, most of our of it went unused
beyond billing or record keeping.
We had a digital infrastructure,
but we are weren't yet unlocking
the true value hidden in the data.
That brings us to a third and
the current phase AI integration.
This is where things get exciting.
We now leverage AI and machine
learning to analyze massive amount
of health data in a real time instead
of waiting for a symptom to appear.
This model can predict risk
sometimes days or even weeks in air.
Advance hospital around the world are
now using predictive model to flag
patient at risk of cardio event hospital
remissions and more even consumers like.
Consumer devices like Apple Watch are
entering in the picture, capturing users,
heart rhythms, changing, change in the
mobility or, and feeding that data into
a health system for further monitoring.
So to summarize this journey, we have
more from and reactive care where
we responded to an illness after the
talker to a data reach where we capture
more information than ever before.
And now to a predictive care
where we can use this information
proactively to protect patient
health before it compromise.
This is the foundation of predictive
healthcare, and it's only possible
because how we evolve through
these three clinical phases.
In the next few slides, we will dive
deeper into how this is actually
implemented from the data pipeline
to AI model and real world impact.
It's having.
All right.
First, let's look at the
early detection success.
Let's explore what predictive healthcare
really means in practice, because
this is where we begin to see the
power of artificial intelligence comes
alive in a real clinical setting.
AI model with a vast and diverse
healthcare data sets are now
capable of identifying disease risk.
Long before symptoms surface, allowing
the healthcare professional to take
action proactively rather than reactively.
So there are few outcomes that
you can find on Marketplace First.
Research shows 70% improvement in
early cardiovascular risk detection.
This means.
We are identifying high risk
patients significantly, early,
often, while they are still feeling
comfortably, completely fine.
For instance, patient at risk
for heart failure or a stroke can
now be flagged during a routine
checkup or even when a traditional
diagnosis won't raise an alert.
Second, on average, the predictive
system provides about a week
or more advanced warning.
Before a symptoms actually appear,
imagine what can be done with that
time scheduling specialist visit, order
ordering additional test adjusting
medication, or for a cardiac patient,
few days could be a difference between a
manageable condition to an ER admission.
Third, the early intervention based on
this insight has resulted in one third
reduction of emergency room visits.
That's not just a
statistics, that's fever.
Patient in crisis, less strain in
emergency department, and better
resource allocation in hospital.
It's powerful demonstration of AI
driven, one insight translate into a
real world efficiency and better care.
This is what predictive
healthcare looks like.
It's about equipping doctors with timely,
actionable insight, transforming data
into an early warning, and fundamentally
changing the tragedies of the patient.
Patient's Health Journey
Data integration Architects.
As we move towards predictive healthcare,
one crisis critical truth stands out
without a strong data integration
architect, none of this works.
Predictive AI in healthcare does
not begin with an algorithm.
It begins with data,
specifically data that's timely,
accurate, and comprehensive.
First, we look at the source integration.
This involves bringing together
data from various system.
EHR.
Electronic Health Record
contains diagnosis, medications,
vitals, clinical notes.
Variable devices like Apple Watch
or Fitbit contributes continuous
monitoring data such as heart rate,
sleep patterns, even blood oxygen levels.
Genetic testing brings insight
into a long-term risk of a patient.
And a clinical system such as lab
information systems or image archives
brings the picture as a format data.
So pulling this data in
only one is only a step one.
The next major phase
is data harmonization.
Healthcare data comes in
widely different format.
One hospital might use milligram
per decimal while the other
use melo mile per liter.
Even diagnosis score vary from ICD to
snow harmonization, standardized this,
align units, terminologies, formats, and
even a, and ensure the consistencies.
Once harmonized, the data is.
Is ready for the AI processing model
are timed, trained on this high
quality, unified data to learn pattern,
generate predictive health, such as
who might develop sepsis, who likely
to be readmitted, or whose condition
is trending towards an acute ation.
The final and the perhaps most important
stage is a clinical insight delivery.
It's not enough to generate a prediction.
We must emel them into a clinical
workflow, whether it's through
an alert in EHR Visual dashboard
or mobile app, inside must be
accessible, actionable, and timely.
The takeaway here is simple.
Prediction is the is only possible
when we integrate data effectively,
and that's only possible when with
a robust data engineering architect
isn't just an infrastructure, it's
a foundation of a better healthcare
core.
Technical challenges.
Now that we have seen how data flow into
a predictive system, let's talk about what
can go wrong and what makes healthcare
data engineering uniquely challenging.
Building AI for healthcare isn't as simple
as collecting data and train a model.
We face four core technical
challenges that must be addressed
before we even begin modeling first.
Security and privacy.
Healthcare data is among the most
sensitive information we can collect.
Patient trust us with detail about
their body, their mental health, their
genetics, sometimes even their lifestyle.
We have a legal and ethical
responsibility to protect the data.
HIPA compliance isn't an optional,
and yet, AI system requires a
broad access to data to work well.
The challenge is enabling access while
maintaining rigorous privacy control,
audit will and encryption standards.
The technique like de-identification,
data masking or federated learning
are a part of the solution.
Allow us to train model without
even exposing the raw patient data.
Second interoperability
healthcare system are fragmented.
One hospital use epic.
Other use corner labs use different codes.
Peer use ICD 10 codes and devices
help proprietary format as well.
Without standardization, it's
nearly impossible to combine
data for these sources.
That's where interoperability standard,
like actual seven or fire comes in.
Third is latency.
Predictions aren't useful
if they are out too late.
In a clinical setting, especially
in emergency care or ICU, we
need a real time processing.
For instance, if a model detect
a sign of sepsis, but it takes 20
minutes to send that alert to a
nurse, that delay could cost a life.
The architect must therefore support a
low latency interference with a model
running close to the data source,
maybe in the EHR itself or at the edge.
The fourth is data quality.
Even with a perfect infrastructure,
poor data quality can derail everything.
A single miscoded allergy, or incorrect
medication dose, or outdated me diagnosis
can lead to an incorrect correction
or worse unsafe recommendation.
These issues aren't theoretical.
They happen even every day, and
that's why the next part of this
talk focus specifically on building
a rigorous data quality framework.
One that enables safe,
reliable AI in healthcare
data quality framework.
Let's now turn our focus on data quality.
Which is often underestimated, yet
it's arguably the most critical piece
of predictive healthcare person.
AI models are only as good
as data they train on.
In healthcare.
Bad data does not just
result, improve a prediction.
It can literally put life at risk.
That could be a multiple steps.
Data quality framework to ensure data
used in predictive system is clean,
standardized, and clinically meaningful.
The first step is cleansing.
We correct typos, fix unit errors
or remote duplicate records.
Common in fast phase clinical setting.
For example, temperature has
one oh three.zero Fahrenheit
if missing a decimal could.
Seems like 1,030 Faite
second normalization.
Healthcare data comes in varied
units, terminology, and format.
One lab might use glucose in
a milligram per decimal, other
use in milligram per liter.
One physician might use heart
failure, another might use
CHS, cardiac health failure.
Also standardization, need terminology
mapping, unit conversion, and
consistent DATETIME formatting.
Third integration.
This involves record lineage
matching a patient lab resolved with
their EHR, no medication records
and even variable device data to
build a unified profile that way.
Predictions are based on a complete
context, not fragmented data points.
Fourth validation.
Even after clean cleaning and integrating
a clinical review, statistic checks or
a logic based verification is needed.
For example, if a male patient is
listed as pregnant or a medication
is prescribed outside a safe dose
range, those are caught through an
automatic check or an expert review.
Simply put, better data equals
to a better and safe ai.
Okay,
next is AI model Architect.
Now let's sift from a data
preparation to how we design and
build an AI model in healthcare.
This is where data science meets a
domain knowledge and where the thoughtful
architect can make or break and initiate.
There are three major components in
EA architecture, feature engineering,
model selection, and training pipeline.
So let's first take a look
at feature engineering.
Healthcare data is noisy, irregular,
and deeply contextual feature
that extract trend over time.
Suggest changing of blood pressure
or a lab value rather than
relying on a single measurement.
Also normalizing patient demographic
and clinical context, for instance.
Resetting resting ha.
Heart rate of 90 means something
very different to a 20-year-old LIC
versus a 70-year-old cardiac patient.
Second model selections.
There could be a different choice
of a model that can be used.
Assemble method for complex structured
data like EHR, deep learning models
for radiology and image pro imaging.
Pro imaging data.
Based on network, where we need to the
model uncertainty, especially in case
where data is incomplete or ambiguous,
no single algorithm is perfect.
The best result often comes from combining
them, optimizing for an accuracy.
Third, training, a pipeline
in healthcare AI model must be
continuously trained and updated.
Auto ML techniques used to tune parameter
efficiently of federated learning.
When multiple institutes wants to collect
on model training without sharing raw
data, it's important to ensure a version
control properly so that a clinical audit,
trial and regulatory review can be done.
The goal of this entire architect
is deliver accurate, actionable,
continuous ipro, improving prediction.
All without compromising
clinical safety and privacy,
explainability innovation.
Now let's talk about a critical and
more often overlooked, an aspect
of AI explainability, no matter how
accurate the model is, it is, if
a clinician does not understand or
trust its output, it won't be used.
This can be addressed through four
key explainability techniques.
X feature at first is feature attributes.
Feature attributes shows which data
points influence model decision.
For example, if an EF flag, sepsis
risk, it might highlight rising white
blood cell count, or a recent fever as
a top contributor visualization system.
Second is visualization system.
Convert complex probability
model into an interac.
Dashboard using color coded alerts,
trendlines and confidence bar.
The third is contextual explanation.
It ties prediction back to the
established medical knowledge offering.
Clinical the why behind an alert,
not just what for this confidence
metrics, communication communi,
which communicate uncertainty.
A prediction with 95% confidence carries
more weight than the one with 60%.
It helps clinicals gauge how
much trust to place in the ai.
Ensure transparency builds trust,
and trust drives the eruption.
A
let's bring all together
with a real world example.
Let's look at a case study
from the marketplace.
Cardiac care transformation
at a regional hospital.
Original hospital integrates AI model
directly into an EHR system, focusing
on health risk, cardiac patient,
and the staff training, helping
clinician understand how the how to
interpret a I one alert and incorporate
them into their daily workflow.
Okay.
Within months, the research
shows miserable re results about
one third reduction in cardiac
related hospital remission.
Patients were flagged, almost flagged
with a risk almost a week or more
earlier for the potential complication.
Hospital reported over millions in
annual saving in a patient care.
This is the power of AI and this
properly integrated, not just
predictive, but transformative.
Let's look at the economic
impact beyond clinical outcome.
Predictive healthcare delivers
significant economic value.
Hospitalization is expensive.
Emergency care is expensive,
but early intervention that's
efficient and scalable.
Hence healthcare system implementing
ai, data engineering solution
achieves substantial cost reduction.
That's because the risk can be
captured away in a advance, and a
medication can be applied to a patient.
This isn't just about a
better medicine, it's about
sustainable healthcare economic.
Let's look at the implementation roadmap.
So how we actually implement a
predictive healthcare in a real world.
Let's look at the steps
that needs to be followed.
First assessment phase.
Evaluate your current data maturity
and a clinical pain points.
Second, understand the
infrastructure development.
Needed to build an AI application.
Build pipelines to inject
clean or harmonize data.
Third, AI model implementation.
Understand how to train AI model test,
validate model for a key use case.
Fourth, clinical integration,
Amber predictions into a clinical
workflow and train staff.
Fifth, continuous improvement.
Monitor, model performance,
and retain as necessary.
Now, let's look at the future
of predictive healthcare.
Finally, where is predictive
healthcare going first?
Personalized, predictive model.
By integrating gen data, we will move
from a population level inside to
an individualized risk assessment.
UBI case monitoring, continuous
input from a smartwatch, blood
pressure heart rate monitoring.
Even a smart toilet will feed predictive
information to a AM model 24 7.
The third is system wise integration.
AI will operate not in silos, but
across entire hospital networks.
Optimizing care delivery at scale.
AI acumen, Acumenta clinicians,
much like pilots rely on autopilot.
Clinician will use AI as
testosterone partner in the care.
In short, predictive healthcare is
not just evolving, it's accelerating.
Thank you.