Hey everyone.
I hope y'all are having a
wonderful conference at con
42 Machine Learning 2025.
My name is Asif Mabu, and today
I'd like to talk to you about a
topic which has kept me awake quite
a few times at night, especially
when designing new applications.
And that is the decision to choose between
which architecture is right for the
application that I'm currently building.
Whether to go with microservices or
to go with monoliths, the decision
between this monolithic or microservices
architecture is a really critical one
because whatever you decide with, you
get stuck with it for a long time.
And changing the architecture at a later
time is not always a straightforward one.
This decision early on is what shapes
the future of your application.
In this presentation we'll we'll explore
how each approach impacts key factors like
scalability, performance, the efficiency
to help you make the optimal choice.
This slide illustrates the
contrast between between the two.
Monolith is a single unified
structure versus microservices are
distributed modular components.
And understanding the trade-offs
between these two architectural
types is what is going to be crucial
for your application and selecting
that right fit is really important.
So what is this software architecture
dilemma, and why is it so critical?
It's because once you decide on an
architecture and you move forward with
that architecture, it becomes really
difficult to switch lanes at a later time.
It's not as easy as just replacing
a function or replacing a piece
of code within your application.
It's it's something much bigger
than that, and more often than not,
it'll be a rebuild from scratch if
you want to change the architecture
of your of your application.
So the software architecture
Choice is a critical foundation
decision that will impact the entire
development process going forward.
It and the right architecture can
enable scalability and business agility
as your product and company grows.
However, this architecture, it also
affects your long-term maintenance
costs and your technical debt.
So it's really important that
you choose wisely and ultimately
your architectural decision.
It needs to support your strategic
goals and the market responsiveness
for the business to succeed.
So now that we've heard the two
terms that we are discussing over
here, let's like break that down
and see what each of them means.
So what is a monolithic architecture?
A monolithic architecture refers to
a single unified application where
all of your components everything
lives within one code base.
Components in a monolith are
tightly coupled, which means that
they are directly interacting
with shared memory and resources.
The entire monolithic application
is deployed as a single unit.
Now this architectural approach
has of course some advantages,
otherwise it wouldn't really be used.
Simplicity of development,
simplicity of deployment.
However as your application grows
it becomes more complex to scale
this kind of an architecture.
And then in comparison, we have
the microservices architecture.
In this architecture, your approach
when you're building your applications
is to build them as a collection of
small but independent services, right?
Each service is focused on a specific
business function or capability,
and the communicate with each
other through well-defined APIs.
This allows for decentralized
data model where each service
maintains its own database.
Thereby reducing dependencies between
services the whole independent and modular
nature of microservices makes it easier
to develop, deploy, and scale individual
components as your application grows.
Now this architectural style, it
promotes flexibility, scalability, and
resilience of your software systems.
Think of microservices, architecture as
service oriented architecture done right.
So let's summarize that, what are the
core differences between your monolith
versus microservices architecture?
The key differences between
these two architectural
styles are what on the slide.
On the left, we have the characteristics
of the monolithic approach.
Centralized code base, unified deployment,
shared database direct function
calls, and a single technology stack.
In contrast, we have the microservices
architecture on the right.
It is basically distributed with
independent service deployment separate
databases per service, API or network
communication and the ability to use
different technologies for each service.
These fundamental differences
in architecture have.
Significant implications on your
application, scalability, its flexibility
and long-term maintainability.
And we'll explore all of that
in in the presentation further.
So let's look at some of the
pros and cons of of the two
different architectural styles.
So the pros of monolith
simplicity and speed.
Direct function calls between your
components that eliminates network
overhead which in turn makes
your communication really fast.
Debugging is simpler.
Since you can trace execution
flow through a single code base.
Initial development is quicker with less
infrastructure complexity to set it up.
And using a single technology stack
means a simpler tool chain with fewer
tools for developers to learn and manage.
Now some of the cons of this like we spoke
about, it limits your flexibility, right?
So they often have tight coupling
between your components, which, in
turn like I said, limits flexibility
and makes it difficult to make changes
without impacting the entire system.
Scaling a monolith can be
really challenging as I've seen
multiple times in my career.
Because you have to scale the entire
application, even if a small part
of your application is what is
experiencing the bottleneck, you'll
have to scale the entire application
to, to scale that particular component.
And as a monolith application
grows over time, the code base
can become increasingly complex
increasingly unwieldy, and
therefore it makes maintainability
a challenge as your code base grows.
Now for the pros and cons of the
microservices architecture pros
scalability, agility, right?
Microservices.
It allows us to scale individual
services independently rather than
scaling the entire application.
So this gives us much more control
over what our infrastructure needs are
and what the costs are going to be.
Each mi microservice can be deployed
independently, and it does not
affect the rest of the application
as long as your contracts between
those services remains the same.
So this enables us to release new
features and updates much more
quickly and much more frequently.
With microservices, we have the
flexibility to choose the best programming
language, the best frameworks, and the
best tools for each individual services.
You want to do something
in Python do that.
You want another portion
written in rust or go for it.
You want something in do net you're
free to use that, best tools for the
job is what microservices enables.
So this allows us to
optimize for performance.
It optimizes the developer's
productivity and also other
specific needs of the application.
Microservices also enables a high degree
of team autonomy, so different teams
can work independently on different
services without having to coordinate
extensively between each other, right?
As you saw with monolith architectures,
that is a channel challenge
with that architectural style.
It's not all hunky dory when it
comes to microservices either.
There's cons on that too.
Mostly around complexity and overhead.
It can introduce a lot of complexity
in managing the the coordination
between your different services.
Running more services means, you need
more infrastructure your operational
costs to maintain those services.
Then increases debugging issues because,
now that you have multiple services, it
requires more sophisticated tools and by,
it can be a little bit more challenging.
Network calls between your services
and the latency between those causes
your communication overheads, right?
So this is an interesting visualization
and shows you a visual comparison between
the two architectural styles, right?
So as you can see on the left, that
represents the monolithic architecture.
So it's basically a single large weight.
And on the right you have the
microservices architecture where you are.
You've got smaller distributed weights.
This basically says that when you are
scaling a monolithic architecture,
your entire application must scale.
Whereas with microservices, you
can scale individual services.
Right now, monoliths have
lower resource efficiency.
As you have to scale everything together.
Whereas microservices allow for
more targeted scaling, so your
resource efficiency is higher.
Scaling a monolith is
a much simpler process.
But microservices requires
more coordination.
Monoliths have limited elasticity,
whereas microservices are highly elastic
and scale up or down much more easily.
Right
now let's look at some of the
performance of the architecture.
Internal function calls within a
monolith typically takes around
one millisecond to complete because
it is within the same memory space
within the same shared resources.
Calling an API between
microservices usually takes 50
to a hundred milliseconds, right?
Microservice to microservice communication
adds about five to 10 times the
processing overhead compared to a monolith
because of, serialization network cost.
The performance latency differences
between a monolith and microservices
architecture are significant, and it
is important to to understand because
these latency differences can have a big
impact on the overall user experience
and your systems responsiveness.
So careful design and optimization are
required to mitigate these performance
impacts when mo moving forward with
the microservices architecture.
This slide basically highlights
the differences in failure modes
between your monolithic architectures
and microservices architecture.
On the left we see that a single
critical bug in a monolith can bring
down the entire application because,
it's one, one single unit, right?
Anything happens within
one component of it.
It affects the entire
application, just like.
When you're scaling the application,
you have to scale it completely.
A bug affects it completely, right
on the right we see a microservices
architecture, and in there service
failures remain isolated and the
system can degrade gracefully.
It shows that how microservices.
Enables resilience patterns like
almost like circuit breakers and
fallback mechanisms to handle failures.
The key point is that microservices
provide more fault tolerance
and reliability compared
to a monolithic approach.
Now, of course building an
application is one thing.
After the application is completed,
there are maintenance and update
scenarios that need to be considered.
Of course they are very important
when choosing between monolithic
or microservices architecture.
With the monolith, changes to the
shared code base requires modifying the
entire application, which then needs
to be completely tested, and then the
entire application gets redeployed.
In contrast, microservices allow
you to update specific services
independently, and this minimizes the
scope of your testing and deployment.
For development, a monolith
requires modifying the shared code
base while microservices lets you
update just the affected service.
Testing is also more efficient.
With microservices, you only need
to test the updated service and
all of its integration points
rather than the entire application.
Deployment is simpler
too with microservices.
You can deploy just the updated service
rather than the entire application.
Now smaller teams work well with
the monolithic architecture,
whereas microservices are more for
accommodation of multiple teams.
Monoliths require less coordination
between the teams, whereas microservices
involves more cross planning.
Monoliths have a lower initial
complexity while microservices require
more distributed systems knowledge.
Monoliths allow for faster delivery
initially, but microservices
enables long-term feature delivery
in a in a more quicker pace.
Now here's a comparison between the
cost and resource considerations between
monolith and microservices architecture.
The bar chart shows the relative cost
for for the different categories.
Including initial development,
infrastructure, maintenance, scaling
anti onboarding for initial development.
Microservices have a higher cost
compared to a monolith infrastructure
costs are also higher for microservices.
Maintenance costs are lower
for microservices, obviously.
Scaling costs are significantly
lower for microservices.
Team onboarding costs are
higher for microservices.
And overall the trade offs
between the two approaches.
Is what you need to consider carefully
because that determines the scale of
your application and that determines
the future of your application.
So based on the needs and
constraints of your project you
need to look at these trade offs.
Really so where does the
monolith architecture make sense?
Small, simple applications
with limited functionality.
You don't need to really go into
the overhead and the complexity of
microservices architecture go for
the simplicity of of monoliths and
the ease of maintenance that this
architectural style provides is best
suited for smaller applications.
Like I said, the overhead and complexity
of microservices architecture is not
worth the investment for these type of
applications, for early stage startups,
speed to market is more important than
your perfect software architecture.
So focusing on validating the
business idea should take priority
over optimizing the infrastructure.
Teams with limited resources, such as
tight budgets or smaller head counts,
can minimize infrastructure cost.
By going with the monolithic
architecture approach smaller
teams can also more effectively
maintain that entire code base.
Rather than the distributed code base of
a microservices architecture microservices
are a very powerful architectural style
that can be highly beneficial for certain
types of organizations and applications.
They're particularly well suited for large
enterprises with multiple development
teams high traffic web apps that need to.
Scale depending on consumer needs have
complex business domains with distinct
bounded contexts and organizations that
require rapid independent releases.
The distributed nature of microservices
allows teams to work autonomously
deploy features to production quickly.
Without impacting other
parts of the system.
Think Amazon, right?
I. Microservices can also enable
scalability as individual resources
can be scaled independently to
handle increased traffic or load,
Christmas shopping at Amazon.
However, microservices also
introduce additional complexity
in areas like service discovery
interservice communication, and
overall system observability, right?
These trade offs need to
be, carefully considered.
And the key is to evaluate whether the
benefits of microservices outweighs
the added complexity for your specific
use cases and organizational needs.
So Netflix started as a single
monolithic Java application and then,
they had a major database corruption,
which led to a multi-day outage.
And that kind of highlighted to
them the need for a more scalable
and resilient architecture.
So gradually they decomposed the monolith
into cloud-based microservices, and it
now runs over 700 microservices that
handle over 2 billion API requests daily.
The microservices based architecture
provides greater scalability,
reliability, and flexibility.
Compared to the original model.
With,
so this slide provides a
framework for deciding between
a monolithic or microservices
architecture for your application.
So there's four key factors
that you need to consider when
you're making this decision.
First, assess the complexity
of your application.
Simple apps tend to work better with a
monolithic app approach, whereas complex
domains often benefit from Microsoft.
Next evaluate your scale requirements.
So high volume or variable workloads
can be better handled with the
targeted scaling of microservices.
Also think about your team structure.
Large distributed teams, they'll
often work more effectively with
the ownership boundaries that
is provided by by microservices.
And finally, map out your
growth trajectory for the
next three to five years.
This can help determine which
architecture will best support your
company as your application evolves.
And considering these factors carefully is
what will enable you to make an informed
decision about the right architectural
approach for your specific needs.
In conclusion, I'd say there's no
one size fits all solution when it
comes to application architecture.
The right approach depends on your
specific business context and goals.
And rather than being dogmatic,
it's important to be pragmatic
and flexible when it comes to
your architectural decisions.
Hybrid approach that starts with a modular
monolith and strategically extracts
microservices that can be effective an
effective way to balance your immediate
needs with long-term scalability.
And ultimately, the focus should be
on choosing the architecture that best
supports your business objectives.
And not what is the
norm or fad of the day.
This requires balancing short-term
requirements with your long-term
maintainability and growth.
With this I come to a
end of my presentation.
Hope this proved useful to you and hope
you have a good rest of the conference.
Thank you.