Hello everyone.
I'm Sona.
I have working as a data solution
lead and a data scientist, so I would
like to discuss about a meets ml. How
the transforming financial decisions
by using neural network to what is
the financial decision intelligent
as it is used for risk assessment.
For example, credit scoring and fraud
detection and investment strategies.
Some algorithms are trend
tradings, et cetera.
And we can forecast market trends
and operational decisions, how
the loan approvals can be given.
So by incorporating this A ML
with the neural network, so it
fast the decisions and pattern
recognitions can be also happen.
And ha it handles noisy
and incomplete data.
And accurate predictions
in the real times.
So we will go into deeper the topic
how we have been implemented, and
what can be the chances of results.
About myself.
So as I mentioned, I have been working
as a data scientist and mostly in
the banking and finance two minds.
Whereas I had gone through multiple use
cases and the solutions given and which
is going very well, and live the projects
also has been happen with the solutions.
What proposed?
What is the role of a neural network?
This neural network is it's a human brain.
It's this inspired with the neurons.
It thinks as like a human brain.
These are the capabilities.
It can handle huge data sets, and it
captures non-linear relationships also.
And definitely it's a real time
how the human brain can think about
realtime processing the same thing.
And there are some types
of neural networks.
There's RN.
It's mostly, it's for time
series predictions and CNNs are
basically, it's for the chart
patterns and the transfer models.
It's both sequential and complex data
relationship and it handles internally
when we incorporated with these decisions.
So it'll take a neural network
into the considerations when
we choose an option for it.
And I would like to talk.
Talk about some of the transformations
the banking domain, how we, how
it has been getting used of this.
For example, this aid
driven risk assessment.
So how this past processing
the data and how it has been
banks and financial companies.
Uua, aI to scan through
huge amounts of data, right?
So it's internally how the data is
instantly the spots they can identify
how the customers can be defaulted.
So these kind of risk assessment can
be detectable and anomaly detection.
That is something which we can
easily identify what is the false I.
Alarms.
And though it is showing as a good,
but there might be internal is some
algorithms which will trigger yeah, the
positive positivity of anomaly detections.
So investment strategies also AI
can trend and learn from the past
rates and consistently improve the
strategies like, trial and error.
It is nothing.
But this helps investors and financial
firms make better decisions about
the data and when they invest money
sometimes even pitching human traders.
Executive intelligence is
strategic decision cycles.
This helps company leaders make
smarter decisions fast and faster.
This AI can predict trends, market
changes and customer behaviors.
And so executive don't need to
wait till weeks for analysis.
They can act with the real
time data and for intelligence.
So these are the major transformations
we can consider in the bank.
And the risk assessment engines.
So if we go for this pyramid, so if I go
for the real data time processing, this
is considered structured and unstructured
structured can be defined is a better way
since it is A-T-P-M-S and very structured.
So those can be handled, but the
unstructured and semi-structured
data is quite challenging.
We, with the standalone
systems, it's hard to do this.
With this cloud and AI solutions it
goes with the smooth processing and AI
created transfer learnings is something,
whatever the knowledge it is take
what if, what it learned from the one
area and it applies to another area.
If, for example somewhere the products
happened and it mentioned this kind of
scenarios is happening, so you may get a.
Chances of this default, so that kind of
previous it have a repository in that and
it'll come into the f in other location.
It happened the same type of scenario.
It mentioned that, okay, if this
is leading to your situation also.
So this kind of guided transfer
learnings also can be happened and
advanced prediction capabilities.
If you go for the system doesn't
just detect what's happening, then
now it predicts the later dates,
how it can be happen, and what is
the solutions for it, these extra
futures it predicts and give it help.
So in summary, this handles any kind of.
And it's learned from different
domains, not only from single bank
domain, but it consider all the domains
and this predict future problems
and keep improving over the time.
It's not a one time results and there
are some components in a ML risk.
So dynamic risk scoring is
something we can update risk
profiles that adapt some threats.
For example, this means that the AI
systems keep updating a person's or
company risk level as new data comes in.
So it, doesn't just use the
whole credit scores or reports.
It constantly check new patterns.
And it applies.
So for example, if a customer
who suddenly starts spending a
lot of more money and few payment
might be flagged as a higher risk.
So that brings to the situation and
scenario simulations is this where
the system imagine many what if the
situations to see how bad things
could happen, and it tells banks to
plan and advance more safety measure.
So the AI simulated stock market
crash, for example, are rising interest
rates are major economic slowdown.
F then checks the bank's
investment would perform each case.
I'll pick the bank plan and smarter
strategies also and explainable outputs.
Sir, this is not something,
the black box, it happens.
It's giving the results.
No, it takes explain the
detailed information.
For example, if the customer
is denied for a low, then it
mention why it has been denied.
This income is low.
Or it's too many recent credit inquiries
are late payment for the past six months.
All these kind of situations, it
explain so that it's a justification.
And if I take one of the examples, this
is the anomaly detection framework.
So what here I can mention that
there are behavioral biometrics.
So behavioral biometrics is something
AI watch how people interact with
other they devices and confirm.
So if it is accessing if you are usually,
ask the question or type quickly, but
somewhere you just became very slow
or else some, sometimes you are making
urgency of something so it identify
this behaviorals and if some, someone.
You are intense.
Something hit the phone shake and when
you are talking, so these kind of also
its aspect and transactional stress is
something as looking for the pattern.
How usually.
Spending the behavior.
We can say that if you usually show
up in your city at one local store,
suddenly you started spending high
amount and uneven times and all.
So then it identifies and triggers
that, okay this is something is
unusual and cross channel activities.
So it's a tracking behavioral.
Come across the behavior states, same
across phone, apps, website, and devices.
If you log from multiple devices
from one geographical location,
for example, us from different
locations, different states at a time.
So then it suspects why
this has been happening.
So something is efficient
and network analysis.
Also, it can be done, it finds
the multiple accounts are
making a similar purchase.
Transferring money to the same group.
This might be a fraud ring.
If two unrelated customers suddenly
send money back and forth multiple
times, it might be many hundred, right?
So these kind of things it's identified
basically in anomaly detections.
It's catch pro early stage
and reduce false alert.
And protect users without
slowing down the transactions.
AI announced investment
strategies is the sum thing.
It's a real reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning.
That's the optimal solutions.
That strategies, it keeps learning.
It's keep learning and explain
very well for us, which is the
better solutions and where it can
be, go for it in a better plan.
And it learns from the previous models.
It's keep learning and it's a mature.
That time and NLP sentiment
analysis, it's a text processing,
how you type in the text.
And is there any common type of words
or this, which is giving sensing for
something else, pro or something.
So just it'll give a sense of from this,
your text, whatever you are typing.
So personalized pro.
Portfolios truly that in whatever
the investment recommendations are
aligned, this any tolerances are
there, or any financial objects
behind this model portfolio.
This reinforce investment
strategies and this algorithm that
continuously learn from the market
condition and transactions outcome.
So by combining all this machine
learning with the human achievements
and these all deliver the sophisticated
strategies and continuously available,
only the investment investors are
net worth individuals and which is
they can get benefit out of this
and performance during market, is
something from the past three years, the
performance has drastically increased.
Now every of the financial companies
moving from traditional approach
to the strategies because instead
of spending a lot of time for
this analysis, data fetching and
individual vendors dealing all these.
Making them for long time processing
and the, they have to wait for
the results for long time too.
So now whoever is opting this one, 32%
is increased from the three years to
expecting more in the upcoming years.
And past performance is
something that's a response.
Time is market shift is a is
a fast because every banking
transactions are everything.
So they wanted to make a
decision very quick and at the
same time it has to be updated.
So that response and eventually the
client retentions will be good because
if they are satisfied with the service
and it's leading to their solutions, then
definitely the retentions will be high.
So that is what the 65
to 70% aspect research.
Execute this intelligent platforms
is give a predictive analytics
if forecast, what is the business
outcome and how it can be happened.
So it predicts and give the solutions
and scenario planning is something.
That you can plan for whether this
kind of scenario it fits, and how this
modeling which future can be used for
this to execute into the real time and
decision support is something, what
are the strategies which you can take?
Place a fit.
And every use case is different.
And it with respect to the
financial domains and that use
cases, they need to go for it.
And they can take decisions And
performance tracking is something that
they will have a measurable outcomes.
It's, we can see it rapid performance
implement by excluding this process
and this predictive analysis.
Analytics also giving a better decision
in the organization levels if you
wanted to implement this framework.
So first we need to identify the
use case, whether it belongs to our
organization or our financial, or
especially the use case which we
are planning because every problem
statement will not fit into the A ML.
So first we need to under
understand what is the purpose of.
To move this a ML and your network.
So why it has been Because
that we need to identify first.
Then after that, the in
infrastructure preparation.
So whether you wanted to go for cloud, if
cloud what, what else is a Google cloud?
And AWS says you, which platform you
wanted to choose it, that you can decide.
And most of the things.
The A ML all these services are matched
with the cloud platform, so we need
not to go first separately, so they,
we will have one bundle and deployment
strategies also very quick with us.
And pilot deployment as take samples to
and flow, you can develop with some sample
set of data and you can see the results.
If you satisfied with the small case
use cases, then that pilot project can
be deployed and monitored for some.
Time.
It is not something just we have
deployed and cannot go for it.
I just will monitor it and observe whether
the patents are tallying and the expected
outcomes are reaching out and scaled.
Implementation.
You can go for once it is the
pilots across successful and you can
follow the governance and monitoring
and treating affected approaches.
And then the, we can implement
the approaches in the best way.
So the most effective deployments
is is a dual focus on technology and
people and organization adoption.
The skill management development is also
required, and we need to have a clear
communication of bandwidth or what exactly
we are going to get of this technologies.
I would like to call out some
key takeaways from this session.
Say, hybrid is a superior.
Definitely.
We cannot just simply go
with the one one adoption.
We can combine AA and ML techniques
and neural networks in between.
Then underlying one single approach
just to, we develop one kind of model
so that will not give better results.
And even we cannot depend on one.
One application and you can have it.
Start with good data good data in the
sense we will, we have more noisy data
and identify what are the quality of
data and what are the parameters can be
used to take the decisions and whether
it is it passing the governance policies,
for example, this SSN and all we cannot
use directly the masking policies and
all will be in place and then we can
go for it and invest meant for this.
Data infrastructure before we are
passing the inputs to the model.
And Human Plus mission partnership
is an important definitely one.
Mission cannot implement and directly
go for all the decisions all the time.
The women intervention is required.
We need to pass it judgment so that
it'll learn it from there and give the
solutions and measure continuously.
It's not something just
implemented and done so.
No, it's just you need
to go for all the time.
How the regularly it's a ized
feeding and regular patterns.
Also, we need to feed it.
And complexity scenarios also
will have to measure continuously.
So this financial institution
successfully implemented this
combinations, and they got an advantage
of this operational efficiency
and risk management capabilities.
To begin with this a ML journey.
Understand the requirement as
capability assessments and high
value use cases, and create a roadmap
and infrastructure and go for it.
Success.
Thank you for giving this opportunity.
Yeah, we, I would like to mention if
any of your use cases or solutions is to
be addressed, feel free to contact me.
Thank you.