Hi everyone, and thanks
for joining us today.
I'm excited to talk about a powerful
safety in machine learning operations,
and one that's making a real impact across
the industry as wireless architecture.
Over the next few minutes, I will
show you how this modern approach to
infrastructure is not just a buzzword,
it's delivering serious results.
Organizations are stressing
operational cost while doubling
the speed at which they'll deploy
the machine learning models.
We'll work you through the core
principles of wireless AI share
findings from or cost industry research
and give you the practical framework
that has been like proven in real
order, real world implementation.
So you can take these ideas and apply
them right away in your organizations.
Before we dive in.
Let's have a quick intro.
I'm KU and I have spent past few years
working at intersections of ai, cloud
architecture, enterprise transformations,
machine learning, et cetera.
You can find my contact details
and LinkedIn here on the slide.
So I am always open to connecting and
answering the questions and continuing
the conversations after the sessions.
So feel free to reach out to me.
Let's look at the real impact.
Serverless machine learning is
having organizations ing serverless
architecture are seeing a huge improvement
starting with a 65% reduction in
infrastructure management over it.
That means less time spent on maintenance
and more time focused on innovations.
On average, they're also seeing
like a 40% in cost savings compared
to traditional deployment methods.
But perhaps most exciting models,
deployments has jumped three and put times
annually, and teams are able to iterate
and see models faster than ever before.
And it is not just a,
backend improvements.
Users engagement is up to 28% since
in products that have implemented
serverless AI and showing a get link
between the architecture and end user
impact what this tells us is simple
serverless doesn't just make these,
make the things more efficient.
It unlocks scales and speed
strategic focus for data teams.
These slides really highlights one
of the most dramatic benefits of
going serverless deployment speed.
Traditionally deploying a machine
learning models could take around two to
three weeks with the team stacks in the
cycles of provisioning infrastructure.
And configuring the environments and
setting up the manual, scaling with
a serverless transitions, those steps
has rings to about three to five days.
And team focus on the things like
the configuring the API gateway,
containerizing functions and
integrating with the cloud provider.
But the real magic happens once
you, you are really serverless and
deployments are dropped to just
two to four hours on an average.
So everything is automated.
There's no infrastructure to manage
and scaling happens in Stanley.
So this kind of speeds
is not just nice to have.
It's a really competitive age and in
industry where rapid iterations and AI
driven features define the market leaders.
So the ability to see models in hours
instead of weeks is a game changer.
These slides focus on the financial side.
This bar chart breaks down exactly
where server list machine learning
earn its repetitions for cost savings.
On average, organizations are seeing
like a 40% reductions in cost compared
to traditional machine learning
deployments, and it's not just a one area.
The savings came from poor
key fronts like infrastructure
maintenance scalings, and DevOps.
With serverless, you would not need to
verbal poisoning Hardware maintenance
is minimum and scaling is automatic,
and DevOps efforts are dropped like
dramatically, and by using the tool.
What really stand out here
is the paper use model.
So it's a perfect fit for the
machine learning where the workloads
often spikes around training or
deployment, but remain ideal.
In between serverless ensures that you
are only paying for what you use, which
means no wasted spend during during the
downtime and full powers when you need it.
Great.
And these slides really showcases
like one of the core strengths of
serverless for machine learning.
One of the most powerful features of the
serverless machine learning is elastic
scaling, and the pyramids is break down.
Break it down.
I. And the top, you have
the peak performance.
Serverless systems can automatically
handle thousands of concurrent
predictions request without skipping
a bit and be of that like a dynamic
scalings and the ability to instantly
adjust to realtime traffic changes.
So there is no mini manual
tunings or the planning needed.
Then we have the predictive capacity, some
systems, even the village machine learning
themselves to anticipate usage pattern
and allocate resources ahead of demand.
Finally, it's all sits on a cloud.
Foundations distributed across the
multiple availability zones for
resilience and the performance.
What that means, like in practice,
it's simple and organizations no longer
have to over poison infrastructure
just in case of a traffic spike.
And during real world like 10 time
traffic search serverless machine
learning systems maintained stable
and low latency responses and
delivering consistent consistent AI
performance when it matters most.
These slides connect the technical
improvements to real business outcomes.
Now let's talk about the
operational efficiencies.
Because serverless is not just about
the savings times or money, it's also
about doing more with the same team.
Organizations are moved to the serverless.
Were able to deploy 3.4
times more models annually.
That's a massive leap in, in output and
it changed how fast team can respond
to new opportunity and challenges.
So looking at the pie chart here,
deploying velocity improved by 72%,
giving team the ability to seep
updates and improvements faster.
Model diversity increased to build
in support for multiple frameworks
like a Inflow, py Tots, and others.
The continuous deployment has become the
norm with the automated CI I CT pipelines,
reducing the friction from experimentation
and through the protections.
And then finally, more rapid.
It since unlocked the new innovation
potentials leading to smarter and more
adaptive PI features, and it's pay
off organizations saw like a 28% boost
in user engagement after implementing
these serverless powered AI features.
And that's a direct line from
architecture to business impact.
This is a great slide actually
for grounding the strategy
in a real world architecture.
So here we are looking at a layered
architectural pattern that emerged
as a best practice for serverless
machine learning deployments.
Starting with the data ions layer,
everything is the event driven from the
streaming data to automatic features
extraction and optimized storage.
These NCOs raw data is immediately
usable for the machine learning.
Next, the model training layers use
really uses like a thermal compute
meaning compute resource spin up, like
only when it need and, we can get on
demand, GPU, access and hyper parameter
during functions and ability to scale
scale out the distributed training jobs
without managing the infrastructure.
Then we move to the in finance layer.
So where we train models are
containerized and start behind
the behind an API gateway.
We can have automatic scaling in
points and model problem worsening
and testing, casting for high
frequency queries, all fully managed.
Finally, the monitoring layer
and the ties it all together with
performance in ES and model drifting
detections and even automated
returning triggers so your models stay
accurate and relevant over the time.
Structure allows teams to scale and
optimize each part of the machine learning
lifecycles independently, while still
benefiting from the flexibility and
the simplicity of serverless computing.
This slide ties everything
together by showing the real
world impacts across the sector.
Let's wrap up.
The core content by looking at how
these serverless machine learning
strategies are being applied across
the different industries, each with
their own unique challenges and goals.
So in financial services, like
serverless, machine learning is a power
is powering like a four detection system
that reduce pulse positive by 34%.
Even as transactions
volumes increase five times.
These models runs in real time and
continuously adapting to new for better,
no time, downtime, and no batch deal.
So in healthcare, serverless functions
are being used for medical imaging
imaging analysis, what used to take days.
Can now be done in a minute.
So these systems scales automatically
to meet the patient's volume and
the remain remain hipaa compliant,
which is like health insurance.
Portability and accountability Act
compliant even with the massive data
sets and distributed processing.
And in a rural companies are using like
a serverless machine learning to deliver
hyper hyper-personalized recommendations.
And these have been like a 23%
boost in average order values.
Thanks to the model that updates
continuously in real time.
This also supports season
seasonal forecastings and
the inventory optimization.
So the key takeaway here is while the
underling server serverless principles
are the same, implementing the
strategies must align with the industry
specific needs whether it is compliant.
And the speed and the customer experience.
These slides focus on how
to refine the performance.
So performance optimizations is a
key of getting like the most out
of serverless machine learning,
especially as the workload skills.
So let's dive into some technicals
some techniques that have been
proven to make the big difference
and faster the model compresses.
So by using this technique like
quantization pounding and knowledge
distillations, so you can reduce
like the model size up to 60 to 80%.
This helps you to fit your models within
the serverless deployment constant
without sacrificing the performance.
Then we have the cold start mitigation.
So serverless environments often faced
like latency users where when functions
have to warm up and to solve this you can
implement the warm pooling strategies and
preload carbon models and manage functions
concurrency to minimize these impacts.
Memory optimizations is another big win.
Right sizing, memory allocations
based on the model needs to ensure
that you are not over poisoning
or underutilizing resources.
So pr that with adaptive batch, adaptive
batching to maximize throughputs.
And you have what a lean
and efficient setup.
Finally casting strategy by using
like a multilevel casting at the API
gateway functions and the database
layer, he would reduce redundant
computations and is spliting up the
inference times and the lowering loads.
So now what the, is like companies
use using these strategies reported
as 65% improvement in response type
and additional 25% cost deductions
beyond the initial serverless savings.
The base results comes when you
combine several of this techniques
and tailored to the specific models
and usage pattern in your environment.
These slides provide a
step by step roadmap.
So our deliveries would be clear
and structures and successful server
list lesson learning adoption doesn't
mean starting from the scratch.
So the key smooth migrations is
integrating serverless capabilities with
your existing machine learning workflows.
And it can be done in three main phases.
The faster is the assessment phase.
This is where you evaluate your current
machine learning workloads to identify
the candidates for serverless migrations.
Focus on models with variable
inference pattern or those that
require the frequent updates.
So you will want to perform like cos
benefit analysis to determine the best
workloads for migrations taking into
the account usage pattern and scaling
needs and any technical constant.
Once you have assessed and it's the
time to start the pilot implementation.
So begin by migrating the non-critical
models to minimize the risk.
During this phase, you will refactor
the model for the serverless deployments
and establish the performance baseline
and implement the CICD pipelines
for the automated deployment.
Key task here is to include like
the containerizing, your models
and configuring like cloud services
and setting up the monitoring
to track the performance.
The scale and optimize
phase comes after the pilot.
Once you have seen the success
with the initial model, expand
to additional workloads.
This phase is all about like fine tuning,
optimizing the performance, and creating
the inter internal based practices as
you move like higher value models into
the product sense and document everything
to yeah, across the team and ensure
those smooth transit smooth transitions.
And our research source like that
following this phased approach,
reduce like migrations risk and
after it's time to value in fact 87%
of pilot project made into the full
production within just three months.
To wrap it up, let's go over the
key takeaway and the next steps.
So first, when we are starting like your
our server list machine learning journey
focus on the interference workload with
the variable traffic pattern, these
are often like the best candidates to
see immediate 20 feed, such as improved
cost efficiency and the scalability.
Next make your the implementation focus
specific to your models, prioritizing,
like the optimizations techniques
that align with the characteristics
of the, of your workloads, whether
it's model compressions cold
start mitigations, or the casting.
Lastly for the long-term success,
develop a comprehensive serverless
machine learning roadmap.
This will guide your migrations and NCO.
The serverless principles are open into
your long-term, long-term AI strategy.
In summary, serverless architecture
are is levelizing like how
organizations deploy and skills ai.
It can, it can reduce the cost by
40%, and organizations are deploying
3.4 times more models annually.
The elastic scaling handles the
unpredictable traffic and empowers
data science teams to focus on what
they do based on the innovations.
So to get started, identify a few high
impact interv interference workload from
a small cross-functional team, and develop
proof of concept using the architectural
pattern we have discussed today.
And measure your result against the
established baseline and use those
inside to build your comprehensive
serverless machine learning roadmap.
Thank you all for your time and
at today, and I hope you found the
insights on several latest machine
learning valuable and that you are
excited to explore how this approach
can transform your organizations.
If you have any questions
or you would like to discuss
further, feel free to reach out.
To me after the presentation.
I am happy to connect and my
LinkedIn details are already in
the very beginning of the slides
so you can, and thanks again.
I look forward to hearing you about
your serverless journeys, and thank you.