Hi everyone.
I'm aka from the Trust King, and I do
have 14 years of experience in the data
ing tools such as Informatica exercise.
Data stage and Matillion, and also having
experience in the reporting tools such
as SSRS Cognos and also having vast
experience in the backend databases such
as Sequence Server, ours, snowflake.
And I am exit to talk to you today
about how ing the multiple data
integration tools can be a game changer
in your data engineering career.
The data ecosystem is evolving rapidly.
Demand is shipping from the tools
specialist to the S integrators.
Let me share a quick personal observation.
Like when I started a career, I
slowly focused on the informatic.
It served me well, but I soon realized
like job roles demands broader efficiency
across the multiple platforms, especially
in the hybrid and the cloud environment.
So let me.
Move to slide.
So the ch let me explain
about the changing landscape
of the data integration.
Year by year, the data complexities
growing the, it's demand for the more
data sources like APIs, streaming
internet, other things on premises on
a hybrid, cloud hybrid and also for
the diverse consumers like BI tools,
my pipelines, and business apps.
And nowadays, like traditional
tools no longer fit in all needs.
So the employees started moving
to the multi tool strategies for
flexibility on the scalable team.
Let me provide an example where a
retail company may use Informatica
for the bulk data warehousing.
And AP fee for I got streaming
and telling for the cleansing
and for the data governance.
Let me move to the next slide.
Why multiple skills made means like
if the professional skill with the
multiple tools they can demand up
to 42% has salaries and add advance
like 3 5, 3 0.5 faster in the career.
Growth and the benefits of a multi tool
skills, like a better job mobile team and
increase the leadership opportunities and
probably solve edge and cloud readiness.
Let me move on to the n slide
where we have a market analysis.
So if you look this chart these are
the tools like which has like a high
demand, informatica and Apache and
AWS Q, Microsoft, a D, F these are
the major major do dominated tools.
So coming to the next slide
we have three key platforms.
One is Informatica, it is the
in the healthcare industry.
So it is these are the key
features like AI power solutions
and deep health integrations
and the enterprise scalability.
And then coming to the tail
end it is enterprise grade with
the broad connectivity options.
Like it has unique features like
the unified platform on the.
Robust governance and
the cloud native options.
And like when coming to the Apache
initially it's one of the fortune finer
data first with the visual programming.
So where we have the key features
as like a drag and drop interface.
Real time processing and
provision and seeing tracking.
And also, apart from these, like
we do have AWS glue and the, and
data factory where it has like
serverless cloud native supports
transformation via spark pipelines.
And coming to the glue, so glue
good for the metadata catalog
and the schema discovery.
Let me move on to the next slide.
So by using these tools, these are the
critical capabilities where like we can,
automate like the workflows up to 5%
and 68% for the data quality management,
and 42% for the advanced processes.
Let me move on to the next slide.
This are the real time case studies.
One of the example is the FinTech success.
If you see here, the challenge
for the FinTech is where they have
a complex language systems with
200 data sourcing data sources.
So this are causing like
increasing the cost.
So for this challenge, like
the better solution is adopting
like a multiple integration.
So by using either the, on the
talent orchestrations, so the better.
So by using this approach the best
result is they can say $2.8 million
amount and also stiff first and first
crossing and coming to the second example.
Where they allocate transformation like
by using the Informatica tool for client
processing, it's taking around like 48
hours for the data processing with them.
And also they are getting the frequent
errors like so to work on this, like
they implemented like different approach
the real the real time integrations.
So they improved, like validation,
reducing errors by 75%.
Nearly the real time
process with 98.8 accuracy.
Let me move on to the, on next
slide, like the next slide that
talks about learning the framework.
So first of all, like we need to
be, have a foundation building.
And in the foundation building,
like we have like a. The key
features, like a complete option,
certifications and better to have
multiple products, practices, and then.
You need to have have expansion phase,
like you add a second platform and
identify the similar pattern and
solve the same problems differently.
And also have like integration mastery
so command to strategy drive to
develop a project like by using one
or more tools, so the, coming to the
next slide it's a skill development
roadmap where we have a learning
practice and applying and sharing.
So when coming to the learning you
need to have a strategic course and
documentation and you need to have a
practice, hands on the practice, hands
on the project implementation, and also
apply like when doing the practice,
apply, the reward implementation at work,
and also whatever, can share like with
the community community, and also can
participate can participate on mentoring.
So coming to the next slide so the
way of the tool masteries the career
investment so structural learning tool
like four to 60 was of the targeted goals.
So we do one 20 hours of building
up so realtime solutions.
And professional returns are
like you can measurably carry
advancement within 60 to 12 hours.
And coming to the final impact, right?
You have a 15 to 25 platform.
So it's going to be like immediate
based composition increase and
performance bonus ification.
So coming to the next slide, like we
have an action plan, like where we have
the self-assessment and set platform
goals and create a learning schedule
and build across platform project, so
when coming to the self-assessment,
like you need to be current tool
frequency where we are on that.
And also coming to the platform goals.
Choose the complement rules based
on the current market demand.
And also you should have to spend at
least five to 10 hours with you to
new platform skills and demonstrate
the master tools integrated solutions.
This solves about the multi tool skills.
So if you have any questions
you can drop me an email.
Thanks for the, for providing
this opportunity to.