Hi everybody.
I'm Anta Kamath.
I'm a senior software engineer at
Microsoft and have spent the last several
years designing and building high scale
distributed systems, especially in
the notification and messaging domain.
I'm thrilled to talk to you today
about combining machine learning
with high performance architecture
to delivers of notifications in real
time efficiently and intelligently.
So let's bring of what is our
notification landscape today, and
let's talk a little bit about it.
It's basically, we are talking about
billions of notifications daily
here, and these are delivered across
apps, browsers, iot, and variables.
Users expect something like a one
millisecond response latency, even
during peak load think Black Friday,
or a large scale breaking news era.
Systems must operate with fine lines
of availability across regions.
To support this, we must decouple
services, ensure low latency paths
using memory-based message buses, and
handle failovers without state loss.
Let's put our problem landscape to be like
speed, scale, and precision at this point.
Briefly touching up on what are the
m service architecture benefits here?
We build notification systems as
a polyguard Microsoft AR m service
architecture broken into components like
event receiver, for example, a Kafka
consumer or HTTP trigger message router
and forter channel adapters, which could
be a push notification email or SMS.
Think of it as triggers or adapters
and analytics and feedback pipelines.
Key architectural choices have known to
be using Kubernetes for orchestration
with horizontal port autoscaling
based on message queue lens at any
point using GRPC or product of APIs.
For service to service communication,
basically primarily due to compact
payloads and cannery rollouts.
Using something like agile
DevOps to ensure zero downtime
deployments, each component scales
independently in this case, and
stateless is the key for all of us.
Our systems are basically fully event
driven and designed around cqrs.
It's primarily known to be command query
response, segregation, and event sourcing.
Enrichment layer adds personalization
by pulling user preferences,
location and history from Redis
backed graph and makes it available.
At runtime or at near runtime scenarios.
Smart delivery involves using ML
models to rank the likelihood of
engagement, for example, at a given
point, what is the user being more
responsible to, whether it's a push
notification or an email or it's visits.
An SMS And our ML models basically
help us rank these in the a certain
order priority based on previous data.
Selecting optimal delivery windows.
We'll talk about the optimal
windows in a bit coming soon in
the late in the presentation.
Feedback loops are being captured
for every event given process.
What is the scale of opens,
clicks, dismissals, uninstall.
We could store all this data that we get
all the plethora of data in something
like Azure Data Explorer, A big query.
And this can be further used to train
reinforcement learning agents and.
It comes back into the system as
feedback loops and can be helped
to train the system holistically.
A brief comparison of different message
brokers, which are being used in the
different notification systems today.
Let's talk about Kafka first.
Primary use cases to ingest high
volume events and it's best for
durability and uses compression
to reduce the throughput costs.
So it's pretty much well known for that.
The second option that we.
Discuss here as RabbitMQ.
It's known for complex routing
and acknowledgement systems,
and it has a strong delivery
guarantees with dead letter queues.
Also ready streams known for ephemeral
messages and low latency and great
for send in for forget pushes.
It's like you don't really
care what the response is.
It's more like it's a fire and forget
scenario, and you just let it go and
let the system takes its own course.
One lesson known one is ser, which
is known primarily as a use case for
geo application and backlog handling.
And it's built in on tiered storage and
partitioning often combined scenarios or
Kafka for ingestion and ready streams for
real time delivery so we can make the best
known use of both of both of the systems.
Next we will touch upon
system resilience strategies.
We use multiple layers of resiliency
in this point, and that's like
primary one is self-healing.
Readiness and liveliness probes are a.
Good for restarting pods alert fatigue
radio use with LY based alerting is like
Grafana or AI model combined can help
us alert and figure out when our system
has cer certain spikes or certain tips
and can basically help without any human
intervention to take quicker action
and self-healing of the entire system.
Circuit breakers implemented via poly
or high stakes like wrappers, defines
timeouts, retries, and fallback handlers.
Another one coming to it as redundancy.
It's basically active deployments
using geo distributed clusters.
We could use something
like Azure or AWS here.
S testing.
We run periodic chaos tests using tools
like Gremlin to simulate broker outages
or CP starvation, and that basically
helps us making our system more resilient.
It's basically, it's
not optional at scale.
Your system has to be reliable and it's
not like an option for us at this point.
You.
It.
Each of these strategies could be
used individually or in combination
of each other to help make the
system more reliable as a whole,
coming to one of the primary
topics of this, of this talk.
And that's what, like how is
machine learning integration?
It's makes it more intelligent
and advanced in terms of delivery,
and that goes beyond the basic
delivery of notifications.
So let's focus on the part where
the system shifts from being
just an infrastructure layer to
becoming a truly intelligent layer.
And this is where machine learning
inter integration transforms the game.
Most traditional systems are
rule-based targeting, send message
X to Y users after Z Minutes, right?
It works until it doesn't.
Rules break at scale.
And this accounts for user
behavior, preference and context.
So this is where ML steps in and
learning from past behaviors, predicting
future preferences, and delivering
real time personalized engagement.
So let's start by talking about
smart filtering and which is more
like classifying a value, right?
What's our primary problem here?
And that's not every
message is meaningful.
Users are constantly bombarded.
How do we filter what to send?
What is our solution?
Use binary classification models.
For example, XG Boost or light,
G-P-M-G-B-M trained on engagement levels.
Open, clicked, dismissed, or ignored.
Input features could include
something like message type.
Is it a promo?
Is it an alert?
Is it a transactional message?
What's the context of the user?
Is it a device os.
Region, historical responsiveness
and time of day and channel.
Basically, does the user historically
respond on the phone during
evenings and more on the say
your system or a desktop during?
That's a channel which allows for the
delivery of the notification during
daytime, and all this is captured
in data and are very important input
features to your machine learning models.
What's your output?
A relevant score per message.
Per user pair, right?
So only messages above, above a
certain threshold make it to delivery.
And that's one of the brief explanations
of what smart filtering could possibly be.
This basically helps to reduce low.
Low I, low importance message noise
low value noise, and helps reduce the
notification fatigue for the user.
The second one where machine learning
is instrumental is targeted content
and its personalization at scale.
Problem.
Let's talk about briefly what the
problem is here, and it's like
generic messages don't convert,
but user content which caters to
a specific user, like handcrafted
content is really impossible to.
Make it for every user.
So how do we make targeted content, right?
So we try to use something which
is like energy, just natural
language generation models.
It's basically either template
based or fine tuned Transformers.
Examples could be TFI or distill GPT.
Let's take an example of an
e-commerce platform here.
You left this in your card.
Have you seen that recently coming to you?
Pretty often, yeah.
Still thinking about Nike Air.
They're almost gone.
What this does is, one, it reminds you
of you left something and you moved on.
You moved on for any reason, but
it basically adds a personalization
tone that it look it things about
what you left in the cart and are
you still thinking about that?
And the almost gone part tells
you that there is an urgency.
This deal is going to be gone
in the next three hours, right?
Is it really gonna be gone?
We don't know, but we are trying
to personalize the content for you.
The notification seems to be more
targeted and that basically helps you add.
Add that targeted audience
to the notification.
Personalization input could
be purchase history, favorite
categories, recent session
behavior and social proof triggers.
For example, what's its ubiquitous,
what's trending near you?
Where do you live, and what's
the local sales going on?
What's the market like in that region?
And these are basically
social proof triggers.
So this is known to engage or
boost engagement by 20 to 50%
in production environments.
Oh, the next one where machine learning
comes into picture as continuous
impro improvement or feedback loops.
User behaviors keep on evolving
and one time model training
leads to stale productions.
What is current today mean
will already be stale tomorrow.
And users and trust as well as, the market
is evolving that fast, that you really
cannot have stale notification data.
So basically we can implement in
the scenario is what it's called,
a closed loop learning system, and
every user interaction, whether it's
a click, ignore, mute, dismiss, is
logged and used as labeled data.
Daily batch jobs run, which retrain
the model and update the weights or the
scores on of each of the feature values.
New models are deployed using
shadow mode, for example, AB
test versus current production.
A scenario to avoid any regression
for on already learned data.
Some of the well-known tooling, which
is used is ML Flow or Azure ML pipelines
for experiment tracking and deployment
feature stores like Feast to manage real
time and historical data consistency.
Then we next move on to multi object
optimization, which involves timing,
channel, and volume beyond just content.
We use the ML pipeline
to optimize when to send.
Using time series predictions
with using something like maybe
profit or where to send, right?
Like we spoke about channels briefly
before as is the push notification
more ac more accurate at the given
point, or is it an SMS or an email?
We have different channels which
are available at our disposal.
And how often do sing, for example.
If you see that a user is continuously
dismissing a particular notification,
then we have to ensure that the user
gets that notification at a much
lower frequency than what is currently
available, and that is something which
is widely known as adaptive throttling.
In some systems, we try to combine
these multi-arm banded frameworks.
Each arm is a content timing channel
combination, and we optimize basically
for accumulative reward, which is user
engagement in our case, while we try
to increase the weights and scores and
determine and explore new strategies.
This approach ensures responsiveness and
adaptability in the fast changing world.
We also start using models like Onyx
and low latency environments or via
like tfs, running our cloud interface
inferences for determining the different
models which serve and what is more
ac accurate based on our adaptive
l continuously learning models.
We use feature gating systems basically
to roll, make rollout safe and ensure
no doubt, like the learning models or
incon incorrect label data does not
cause our models or outputs To fail
always, we need to maintain something
which is called as explainability,
especially in the regulated industries.
Whether it's Lyme can explain health
model decisions and precision is very
important from our learning experiments.
In short, ML doesn't just
make notifications part, it
makes them personal, context
aware and self-improving.
It's the difference between an
ignored ping and a message that
genuinely delights your user.
Moving on to adaptive rate, limiting
traditional rate limiting uses,
fixed thresholds, and it's more like.
We need to go adaptive at this point
and analyze the user data, time of
day, location, historical response.
Windows predict the likelihood of a
user, basically responding to a category,
whether it's a promo system alert or, and
make it more personalized on a weekend.
Maybe a user is more, aligned
towards answering a promo than a
working day in the morning hours.
But this is what data tells us.
This is what our learning
models continuously tell us.
Throttle using priority cues and leaky
bucket or in, in combination of ML
predictor logic rate limits aren't static
and they adapt to per user over time.
This definitely reduces churn and
notification fatigue for the user.
We have known pretty widely
in even our day-to-day lives.
That timing is everything, and that's what
brings us to predictive delivery, timing.
One of the most overlooked aspects of
notifications is when they are delivered.
We intend to focus so much on the
content, on targeting that we.
Generally forget even the most
relevant message when it ends up
on the user's channel or device.
It just gets ignored.
And this is where timing isn't
just delivery optimization, it's
the engagement multiplier for us.
Let me walk you through how we
analyze, predict, and optimize
delivery, basically based on their
data and machine learning combined.
Let's start with something which is known
as let's call it step one, and that's
known as behavioral pattern mining.
We start by ingesting here,
historical engagement logs.
Open times, click times,
mute, unsubscribe events.
And each of this is stacked
with timestamp, user id, device
notification, category and channel.
Using time series clustering
algorithms like K means with dynamic
time wrapping, warping, sorry.
Dynamic time warping DTW or DB scan.
We identify user cohorts with similar
notification engagement rhythms.
We often find patterns like
office workers engage at lunch,
which is like 12 to 1:00 PM.
Students respond post classes
after six to 9:00 PM is the primary
window, and parents engage late
at night, say 9:00 PM to 11:00 PM.
These temporal fingerprints form the
foundation of personalized scheduling.
The next thing we move on to
is the predictive modeling
of what we have captured.
So far.
We have grouped our user cohorts and
we have, we can now have the ability to
train time aware ML models to forecast
the open probability model choice could
be something like gradient boosting
or temporal neural networks like lstm.
What are the primary
input features for us?
Local time of day of week,
users, device status.
For example, screen time, app
usage, and recent engagement trends.
The model outputs a heat map of
likelihood scores for engagement
per hour in the next 24 to 48 hours.
Which brings us to our, now we
have spoken about predictions
and we know what data is there.
It brings us to our next important step,
and which is intelligence scheduling
instead of a fixed delivery window, our
notification service towards the next
best delivery time in the metadata for
each message uses a lightweight scheduler.
It just could be a background
worker or a crown job to NQ
messages into red streams or Kafka.
At the right moment and supports a
snooze fallback if the user hasn't
interacted for say X hours, retry
the second best predicted time.
This allows us to delay non-urgent
messages, prioritize system critical
alerts in real time, and our clustering
of messages around high churn hours.
Now.
We have done the tasks of delivering the
actual notification the right time, but
how do we really know that it worked?
And that's where our la, our last step
of impact measurement comes into picture.
So we compared productive
versus random delivery windows.
And one thing we have realized that
open rates have improved by almost
a. To 35% engagement rose by 45%,
and general uninstall and mute
rates dropped by a whooping 18%.
And this wasn't a one time experiment
as we saw the metrics were.
Gathered over several weeks with
different user segments, and we've
seen this consistently in different
experiments over the industry.
We can really track performance using
real time dashboards, Grafana or influx tv
daily reports, slides by time buckets and
user demographics and longitudinal studies
to verify sustainable sustained impact.
What are the key considerations
for us at this time?
All scheduled messages are item potent
and stored with time to leverage
TTLs to prevent outdated delivery.
Predictive timing works best when
combined with adaptive rate limiting and.
We need to be aware be
aware of notification storm.
Use a distributed scheduler
jitter to prevent spikes.
You don't wanna deliver all
the notifications to a user at
the same time, and it could be
through independent scenarios.
So we need to be really
careful about that.
To add jitters to suddenly increase
a notification fatigue for the user.
So to sum up, great
content needs great timing.
Predictive delivery ensures your message
lands, not just where it matters.
But when it matters most, it
turns your system from reactive to
proactive, and that's a game changer,
which is known in this industry.
Moving on to multi-level caching
strategies and notification system.
One thing that you should think
when you think of caching and
that speed our caching strategy
is generally like in memory.
Something like Redis, it's stored
session and personalization data
and available for quick access.
For example, less than a millisecond.
The second one is more
like a distributed cache.
You could use something like age or
Redis with clustering, and this can be
used for throttling counters or template
data, predictive fetching, and these
are the ML model, preloads most likely
templates and images before usage.
And the last one where we.
Speak about is the persistent
blob storage for cold and archival
storage, and it's used for audit
trails and retries kind of stuff.
We benchmark the cash hit ratio after
every release targeting 90% or greater
than 90% hit rates for hot paths.
And those are very, the hot parts
are primary important factor here.
Let's briefly talk about a case
study based on a e-commerce platform.
And this is let's talk about
it as a real success story.
Client basically had, say, a
68 person cart abandonment.
And the previous solution used
batch based fixed schedule emails.
Open rates was like 4%.
See, every night at 10:00 PM you get an
email about what you left in your cart.
Do you really care about it?
Mostly people won't.
What's our solution is like real
time eventing for cart abandonment.
We just spoke about that
example where you get, Hey, are
you still interested in this?
This is gonna be gone soon.
And that's real time eventing
ML model predicted intent.
To purchase within one to three hours
and messages had personalized spec
subject lines and discount triggers
based on past purchase history.
You bought this previously.
Are you still interested in this?
You bought a mattress, you still
want a mattress cover, right?
It really.
Triggers you and you feel like you
need that stuff when you don't know
how much you really need it at the
given point, but the message still
ends up as a notification for you.
What's the impact that we saw?
A 42% increase in recovery, 28%
fewer messages sent and 37% higher
click through rates and section
second reaction rates isn't Those
numbers sound really promising.
Now let's talk about an implementation
roadmap or our playbook for
building something similar.
One is the Microservice Foundation.
Break your system into core
services, ingestion, formatting,
delivery, and analytics.
Use scalable brokers and
content based deployments.
Have an intelligent layer.
Start with engagement prediction
models, add adaptive rate limiting,
and dynamic channel ranking over it.
Lastly, introduced natural language
graph for content personalization.
And one primary important thing that
we talk about in machine learning
systems is continuous optimization.
Use AB tests to evaluate
every model change.
Build automated retraining pipelines using
airflow ML flow and Azure ML pipelines.
Track long-term LTVs as lifetime value
and not just CDRs, and this is a very
good recipe or just a high level playbook
for you to implement an notification
system which integrates with basically
all the important parameters or
important gotchas of ML integration.
Thank you so much for your time
and building scalable, intelligent
notification system as a marriage
of real time infrastructure and ML
intelligence is challenging, but
incredibly rewarding, and especially
when users experience your craft.
I'd love to hear from you and
what challenges you're facing with
engagement or delivery systems.
You can find me on LinkedIn
or just let me know whatever
questions you have regarding dread.
So thank you so much for your time.