This is the agenda.
We'll go into artificial intelligence
introduction, AI revolution and
unstructured data, the tech stack for
ai, chat bots, and the future of ai.
So there are a lot of artificial
intelligence definitions out there,
but this is one of my favorites.
It says that artificial intelligence
is the ability of a machine to
perform tasks commonly associated with
intelligent beings, which means that
something that a human could do now, a
machine can do because you have given
it that ability to dig in and find
the right answers that it needs to.
This slide is very interesting.
It shows that artificial intelligence
isn't something new, right?
It started when IPM developed this
computer and, it fought against
Gary Sparrow in 1997 against him
for this chess game, and this
computer played moves, which were
so amazing and never seen by any.
Anyone or never played by
anyone, and that's why Gary
kis Farro couldn't defeat it.
Then there were games which were developed
and these games had its own way of
learning and fine tuning itself to be
able to win all the points and and get
whatever it wants to win the whole game.
There were, social media and
Netflix and all had recommendations
based on what you're watching,
it was gonna recommend you.
Okay?
This is what you can watch next.
This is good for you.
This content is something
you like or not like.
That's like artificial intelligence has
been around us for a while and then came
chat, GPD and it just took everyone away.
Within five days, like you can
see the graph over here, there are
these different applications and is
showing like within how many days
did it hit that 1 million user mark?
And you can see chart.
GPT did it within five
Ds, which is insane.
When it did that, before that Instagram
did it in 2.5 months, the 1 million mark.
And then also there was thread
which came in and within one hour
it was hitting 1 million users.
And within two hours I
think it did hit 2 million.
But today we are not interested in
threads is definitely an entrusting
applications for people who have used it.
But chat, GPT has its own different.
Use case, which is not just a social
media tool like all these others,
most of it you can see are more for
social media, entertainment purposes.
But Cha g PD is very
much used by everyone.
It be a researcher, may be someone
who's working in a corporate job
to make a jobs or lives easier.
You are going to use this application.
Next, we'll deep dig deeper into AI
revolution and unstructured data.
Why did this whole AI
revolution come into picture?
Because 90% of your data is unstructured,
which means it is in the format of text,
images, audio, video, and you want to
make sense out of this data because.
Data is important.
Any data you give someone, there is a way
to make analysis, predict future, and come
up with some better solution that can.
That you cannot, where if you don't
have that data, you can't analyze it.
So tradi traditional database struggle to
process this unstructured data, and that's
where generative AI comes into picture.
It goes in, finds the whole scenario or
what is happening in your data, gives you
the result and extracts value for you.
What is generative ai?
Generative AI is AI models that
generate text images or insights.
The examples are GBD four LAMA Cloud.
Why is it powerful?
Because it's humanlike.
The responses and summarizations
are amazing that you.
Even if a human had to dig into
so much like unstructured data and
bring it, it's was gonna be harder.
So someone who can do this for you without
any man, manual intervention is amazing.
Understanding your unstructured data.
There is a lot of unstructured
data out there and all these
things that you see on the screen.
Videos, images audio texts fall under it.
The types are also varied,
like email, chat logs clinical
notes, pathologic reports.
All of them fall down structured data.
And if you wanna make sense of it you can.
So why is it hard to process?
No predefined schema or structured.
That is why it is hard, because
if there was a proper table and
you had like your columns into it,
you could write a simple select.
S statement or write like a procedure
and do the whole data science or
python analysis on it and predict
the, what the data was bringing you.
But with this, it becomes difficult
because there is no structure.
How Gen AI processes it is.
It has the natural language
processing for text understanding.
It has summarization and
document classification.
It has con conversational AI for
chatbots feature, and then it
has rag and vectors and chalk.
So what this whole side means, it, the
gen AI has those specific capabilities.
Like it has those necessary functions
which can summarize your whole
essays, big, long paragraphs and
pages of essays into something small.
It has, that conversational ability.
So if you ask it a question and ask
it a counter question on the first
question, it remembers the first
question and gives you the answer or
the context of the answer accordingly.
There is rag.
Rag is a very amazing feature wherein
your data, unstructured data is
divided into chunks and it is given
that specific, unique identifier for
it to be able to identify later on.
So overall, all these things make
reduce the administrative burden,
enhance data driven decision making
for you, and that's how generative
AI processes your unstructured data.
The role of gen AI is twofold.
The traditional one was very predefined,
no learning and limited, whereas
AI power chat bot is context aware.
It is very much self-improving via,
data and highly conversational.
The tech stack.
This is my short and suite, I would
say like architecture diagram that you
can see wherein your whole flow of the.
Chat bot experience, you can see
over your, so the first thing,
it starts with a question.
This question gets the embedding.
Embedding is a specific, unique
identifier for your question based
on what question you're asking.
This embedding is then going and
searching in your vector data.
And this vector data, again,
is stored into embedding.
So like I was mentioning,
your data, the rag.
Chunks your whatever files and all
you have into specific embeddings
and stores it into vector database.
And whenever a match is found
between this embedding and this em
embedding, that relevant chunk is
returned and there is some engineering
done to make it look beautiful
and then returned to the end user.
So that's the tech stack.
You need a large language model.
You need an embedding database.
There's some vector search functions
you need to apply to be able to search.
And then the framework, which
is more of the UI piece.
You can do it a stream
data app or something.
So you can combine the both
UI and the backend to it.
Here is an example of a chat
bot that I built myself.
So what.
I did was I had this whole a whole stage
wherein I had different PDFs in it.
One of them was my resume and I
wanted to ask question on my resume.
So that's what I did.
And the chunk, I did the function for
that I created like a whole vector
database, stored my chunks into it.
And also called my, for call this
function to get the relevant chunk,
then did a getcha history function.
Summarize questions with history
was used to remember the context
of the previous questions.
Complete function and prompt function
was used to make the answer more better.
So these are the couple of function
and the whole script and the UI
piece of it for the chat bot.
So building chatbot step by step.
Definitely.
We saw the whole flow and how chatbot
can we build, but there is a little
bit of pre-processing and fine
tuning piece to it as well, right?
Like you cannot just build it.
And that's about it.
The pre-processing comes
with data ingestion.
So you definitely have to collect like
all types of data from different sources,
bring it in a proper stage, location, do
some data processing and transformation
on it because, so there is definitely
gonna be some special characters which
are gonna throw your s Python script away.
So make sure you remove those
special characters and then
build a model on top of it.
For that bot model.
You'll need like an LLM rack.
There'll be some fine tuning and
testing you'll have to do because
once you've built it, the first.
Three to six months is training
period, and there are questions being
asked by different users, is still
trying to understand what is the
question and context and trying to
make sense out of your data for you.
And then finally you'll deploy and
monitor and give it to like the
specific end users that you want to.
The case studies for industry
applications are unlimited.
There is no limit where you
can use chat bots, right?
From customer support patient q and
a, contract analysis, policy bots.
There, there are like finance bots
available to, for fraud detection and all.
So any industry, if you have
those unstructured data and you
want to make sense out of it.
It is possible with your chat bot.
Next steps to adopt chat gen ai.
I would say if you are trying to build
an application, definitely start with.
Start slow.
Start with the crawl phase wherein you
are bringing all your applications data,
you are storing it in a stage, trying
to do the cleansing on it, running
some scripts to do the chunking and
vectoring of your database and all that.
So that's like the first
crawl phase for you.
Then comes the walk phase wherein
you're building the whole decision
engine and you are deciding, okay,
if, what are the key parameters which
you would want to track or which the
users are gonna ask questions on.
How are you gonna understand okay,
if this is answered, it is a good.
Answer versus if this is answer
is the wrong, bad answer.
Those decision engines is the next phase.
And then finally, you are gonna deploy
it and put it out there for everyone
to use and see how the changes happen.
I. Also there are a lot of features
wherein the user can give feedback.
There are like plus thumbs up and
thumbs down features that you see
in different chat bots out there.
You can incorporate those so that
your model understand, okay, this was
a negative answer, and next time it,
it makes sure what are the positive
answers and brings you answers based
on that, rather than giving you the
negative ones or the wrong ones.
The future of AI Chat Botts we are
definitely in the tip of AI chat
Botts, and there is so much more.
There are multimodal chat botts, which
is voice and text related chatbots.
Combined, there is autonomous AI agents.
So here you can see there
was we trip booking.
I asked.
The GPT four, it went in the high camp
website, brought in the best deal for
me based on what dates I'd given it, and
then told me this is like the best deal.
It has 95% rating.
Would you like to book it?
And if I say book it, it's gonna
go ahead and book it for me.
So that's what an agent take.
AI would do it.
Will you just.
Have to type your questions
in your chat words.
This is gonna go in the specific
website, bring the answer for
you, and you are good to go.
Then there are AI powered workflows.
So a lot of manual processes
are going to be replaced by ai.
So right from your data engineering step
ingestion or the whole like data cloud
framework, building the whole, a raw gold
and silver layer, the scripts will do it
for you without any manual intervention.
So those those like startup ideas
are out there already and people
are working on it and building it.
And then there is gonna be a lot of
AI governance and safety measures
that are gonna be built out there.
So even like companies who are very
unsure about the usage of AI can securely.
Use AI under the whole governance
and framework and stuff.
Next is we'll see what will the future be.
So I'm gonna leave you guys with
this final slide, which is showing
two different perspectives.
One is a human from the wall e
movie which had nothing to do and
grow weaker and weaker over time.
Versus on the other hand,
there is this whole new phase
of discovery that we did with.
The AI revolution and we built amazing
products and amazing solutions.
So it's in our hands.
Are we gonna be this side or that side?
And I feel like use AI and chat bots
to your best use so that you can
do something which has not yet been
discovered and discover amazing things.
Thank you.