Hello everyone.
My name is Tta Eshi and I'm a lead
product manager or a principal
product manager at Palo Alto Networks.
I have over 12 years of experience
working in the tech industry, and
for the last seven and a half years
I have worked as a product manager
mainly in the cybersecurity space.
My area of expertise include AI security,
container security, and runtime security
to protect organizations applications
running on public cloud and private cloud.
Today I'm here to talk about how to
implement AI security so that enterprise
can innovate and introduce AI applications
in their environment confidently.
So let's get started with,
let's start with AI adoption.
As many of you might already
know, AI is consistently gaining
traction in the industry today.
According to the recent PWC report,
over around 86% of the executives
are expecting that AI will become
the mainstream technology in 2025.
Out of these 86% of the companies.
60% of the organizations are planning
to integrate AI technology into mission
critical infrastructure, and this was
what makes AI security really important.
Because with introduction of AI security
into the mission critical infrastructure,
the exposure or the risk related to
AI security increases exponentially.
L. Before we talk about the security
aspect, let's talk about why AI is
gaining so much of traction in the
industry in the last couple of years.
The first main reason is
enhance decision making.
AI can analyze large sets of
data, identify the pattern and
insight that might be difficult
for the human being to identify.
Okay.
Based on that data, it can
come up with a recommendation.
It can provide the forecast,
allowing organizations to make
business critical decisions.
Secondly, it can automate the
repetitive task and it allows employees
to focus on more innovative work.
On top of that, AI can
optimize the workflows.
It can reduce the human error, and
overall it improves the efficiency,
thus allowing organization to reduce
the cost and roll out the application
into their environment very quickly.
The third reason for AI adoption growth
is it opens up new business opportunities.
AI can help companies develop new
products and offers to their customers.
AI can analyze the market trends and allow
organizations to reach to new markets
or new geographical regions as well.
Lastly, improved customer experience.
So recently I attended the cybersecurity
conference called RSA in San Francisco.
And I, as I was talking to a lot of
customers and trying to understand
what different players in the
industry are doing, I saw that lot
of customers or lot of organizations
have already started to roll out AI
chat bots and virtual assistance for
their customers because this allows
organizations to provide 24 7 customer
support on top of that organizations.
Use AI to personalize the marketing
campaigns offer recommendation based
on the customer preferences and data.
On top of that, AI can potentially
identify the problems early on before
it impacts the customer, thus improving
the customer experience overall.
And these are the reasons why AI adoption
is improving significantly in the
industry in the last couple of years.
Now that we know why AI adoption is
growing in the market, let's talk
about some of the security threads
that are introduced because of ai.
First of all is the data vulnerability.
All the organizations use training
data to train their AI models.
Bad actors can take advantage
of this, and they can poison the
training data, which will impact
the integrity of the AI system.
Second reason is the privacy concern.
Imagine the situation where AI chatbots
is exposing the SSN number of the
customers, or it is providing critical
health information, the people who don't
have the right access or privileges.
So privacy concerns are going
to increase with adoption of ai.
Third reason is the AI generated threats.
Bad actor can take advantage
of sophisticated defects.
They can create the misinformation
campaign and they can create the
sophisticated cyber attacks at scale,
which might be difficult to detect.
The other aspect that companies need to
consider is the reg regulatory compliance.
Because compliance needs are different
for different geographical regions
as well as different industry.
For example, finance industry
cares about FIPs compliance.
Healthcare industry cares
about HIPAA compliance.
So organizations that are rolling out AI
application needs to be aware of potential
penalties that might impact them if they
are not following the right guidelines.
Let's talk about even more
advanced security threats that
are introduced because of ai.
AI has started to create the
realistic impersonations that will
bypass the traditional security,
and they are specifically targeting
executives with this impersonation.
On top of that, they are creating deeply
personalized attacks at scale that they
couldn't do it without the AI technology.
They are personalizing
the email campaigns.
Those to gain the entry into the
organization, and once they are inside the
organization, they try to move this attack
laterally to the rest of the organization.
Next is model poisoning.
Just like they can poison the
data, the bad actors might try to
poison the model as well, that way.
The integrity of the model might
be impacted, and it might start
giving the outputs, which are
not the right or not recommended
for the customers or end users.
Three versus real attacks because bad
actors can provide different inputs to the
AI models to see what kind of information
that AI model is revealing now.
Basically a, based on this, bad
actors can reverse engineer on what
are some of the vulnerabilities of
the models, and then they can use
that against the organization to gain
access to the sensitive information,
which otherwise they won't have access
to because of all these reasons.
Security of AI application is
becoming really critical because
that is the only way that will allow
organizations to roll out AI applications
confidently, either to their internal
customers or to the end customers.
Let's talk about what would be the
implications if AI applications
are not secured properly.
First of all, there will
be a huge financial impact.
If there is a data breach, then there
will be a huge financial loss for the
organization, and the recovery cost
would be significantly higher than
the investment that they can make
in protecting the AI applications.
Secondly, there might be a huge
impact on the reputation if customer
sensitive data leaves the organization
and comes in the hands of bad actors.
Or there might be a ransomware
attack, then there's a impact on the
re reputation of the organization.
This impacts customer retention
and hence the revenue of the
organization in the long run.
Lastly, there are legal consequences
if regulations are not followed
properly because of all these reasons.
Organizations need to invest in AI
security now so that they can confidently
roll out AI applications to their end
customers and internal users confidently.
Stop.
Now that we know AI security is really
important to ensure AI adoption across
the industries, let's understand
the key aspects of AI security.
We will start with
secure model deployment.
First of all, the model should
be protected all the time.
It should be protected
against E DDoS attack.
On top of that, the data transfer that
is happening between application and the
model should be secured all the time.
On top of that model should be
protected against prompt injection
attack as well as we need to, or the
organization need to ensure that.
There is no data leakage to ensure
organization's sensitive data
is not leaving the organization.
The next important aspect of
the AI security is the data
security and privacy control.
The data which is resting in
the database or in the files
should be encrypted all the time.
So that even if the bad actors are able
to somehow get access to the database or
the fire system, they still won't be able
to use that data for the bad purposes.
On top of that, there should be a
rule-based access scroll in place
that will ensure that users who have
the right privileges, they are the
only ones who are able to access the
application or a access the database.
That way, the attack surface is minimized
significantly and the chances of data
breach reduces significantly as well.
On top of that, one of the commonly
used architecture in the industry
is zero trust architecture,
which essentially means trust.
No one authenticate everyone back
in, back around 15 to 20 years back.
When cloud was not a big factor, the
architectures or the systems were
designed in such a way that all the
connections or all the requests that were
coming from within the organization's
infrastructure were considered valid.
But any connection or any requests that
are coming from outside the organization,
infrastructure were considered invalid.
Now that AI adoption on the cloud
adoption has grown significantly
and data resides in the data center,
but in the public cloud as well.
This architecture that was used 15 to 20
years ago, that is no longer applicable.
So with zero trust architecture, any
connection request is authenticated
to make sure it is coming from the
valid user or valid application.
And many times users, it is recommended
that multi-factor authentication is place
is in place so that even if bad actors
get access to let's say email or the
text messages of the user, there are with
multi-factor authentication, the chances
of the breach reduced significantly.
On top of that, any system or
any user who needs to access
any database or any system.
They should be given the least
privileges that they will need to
in order to do their job, in order
to ensure that even if a part of the
infrastructure is in, in infected,
because of the malware, micro segmentation
policies are really important.
These policies ensure that
threats are not moving laterally
to the rest of the organization.
So that even if part of the infrastructure
or some of the applications are
inspect infected by malware or
CVE, the same malware won't infect
rest of the infrastructure as well.
The other thing on top of
micro segmentation, which is
important to consider, is the
runtime security protection.
So many of you might have heard about log
four J vulnerability that was detected
in a software back in December, 2021.
Even though it existed in the software
for seven plus years, so the organizations
that are deploying all the right
security policies, they and they are
patching their applications from time
to time against the vulnerabilities.
They are still vulnerable to
unpacked and unknown vulnerabilities.
And that is why runtime security
protection where we are continuously
mon monitoring the traffic and
detecting any anomalies or threats.
It is important to have that all the time.
On top of that, it is good to have the
monitoring tool so that in it can inspect
any anomaly that might be vulnerable.
To ensure your or organization's sensitive
data stays within the organization.
Next, let's talk about
building the AI system.
So many times in the organization what
happens is while they are designing the
architecture or the system architecture,
security is not considered upfront.
It is an afterthought many times,
but that shouldn't be the case while
designing the architecture itself.
Software engineers and security architects
need to make sure the system and the
architecture is secure by default.
On top of that, once the architecture
is in place and development is in
progress, it is still important to
do continuous assessment to ensure
the system is secure all the time.
Monitoring tools will help
the organization to check any
anomalies or unauthorized access.
So the system is secure by the, on top of
that, it is important to have the recovery
planning and the backup available for
your system and important information
so that even if you are attacked, once
you recover from the attack, you can
quickly recover from your backup data.
You can restore your website and the
database and the system so that the
disruption to the end users is minimal.
Next, let's talk about
securing AI lifecycle.
As I mentioned in the previous slide,
security starts from day one when
you, when the organizations are
starting to build the architecture
or infrastructure for the product.
So it is important to have
comprehensive security requirements
while building the new system.
On top of that, it is important to
decide how the data that is saved
will be openly while developing the
models or developing any applications.
It is important to have the secure coding
standards so that as in when the system
is getting built, it is secure by design,
rigorous access control on who can access
what should be implemented from day one.
As in when the system is getting built,
it is important to do thorough pen
testing and the stress testing to ensure
your system doesn't break when attackers
are attacking from all the directions.
Additionally, regular vulnerability
assessments and attack simulations,
how to take place on the
system to identify any cvs and.
Fix them as soon as they are detected
so that the bad actors cannot take
advantage of that vulnerability to
steal organization's sensitive data.
Finally, as I mentioned in
the previous slide as well,
continuously monitoring your system
for anomaly is really important.
For example, let's say if you,
if the organization has all
their offices in United States.
All of a sudden, let's say an application
or a user who might be sitting in Asia or
Africa tries to access the applications
or data, which is located in United
States, they shouldn't be able to detect
those as in when such vulnerabilities
or such anomalies are detected on time,
that is when security can improve.
Continuously and ensure that your
AI applications or any applications
for that master are completely
secure and organization data is
safe, and then it is not going
into the hands of the bad actors.
Next, let's talk about the regulatory
landscape over the years, different
industry located either in United
States or outside United States.
They have come up with their
own compliance requirements.
For example, HIPAA is a very
commonly used compliance framework
for medical professionals.
FIPs is very commonly used by the finance
industry, and then there are other
regulatory standards like Fedra as well.
On top of that, GDPR is very
commonly used in the EU region.
GDPR enforces comprehensive
data protection requirements
for all their systems.
It requires explicit consent, it requires
data minimalization, and on top of that,
organizations have to provide the right
explanation for the automated decisions.
Now with the,
with AI adoption increasing day by day.
EU is proposing a new AI act which will
provide all the regulations on how to use
the AI applications, categorize the AI
application by the risk level, top the
prohibited practices, and then provide
the transparency obligation so that the
data that is used to train the AI models
or the data that is used to make systems
better, they are used in the right way.
Similarly, all the other compliance that
I mentioned, hipaa, fs, FedRAMP, they are
taking into consideration the fact that
AI adoption is increasing, so they are
changing the regulation so that it works
well with the AI applications that will be
rolled out in now or in the near future.
Uchen.
Before I end this presentation,
I also want to take in into the
consideration the ethical consideration,
first of all, is the fairness.
When we are training the AI model, we
need to implement the rigorous security
measures to prevent the bias against any
specific any specific diverse population.
It has to ensure demographically
balanced traffic dataset.
Second important thing to
consider is the transparency.
The AI has to balance the rubbish
security with maintaining the system.
On top of that, there should be
detailed documentation on all the
security controls, and they should be
updated from the, from time to ensure
the architecture and the system is
secure against new vulnerabilities.
On top of that, it is important to
establish the explicit data usage
policies, and it should be ac accessible
by all the important stakeholders.
Third important aspect to
consider is the privacy respect.
So individual rights and autonomy
should always be considered
while training the AI models.
Then on top of that, AI models need
to apply data minimization principle
to reduce the vulnerability surfaces,
and all the systems should be
patched for cvs from time to time.
Finally, no system is perfect.
So in order to ensure AI is
doing the right thing, human
oversight is absolutely important.
So just in case if AI is doing
something wrong, human should be
able to override that mechanism
that, or steps that AI is performing.
On top of that, there should be a
structured human process review.
So that all the critical
decisions are reviewed to make
sure AI is behaving correctly.
And if AI is not performing up to
the mark, humans should be able
to override them all the time.
So finally, let's talk about the
key takeaways of this presentation.
As I mentioned before AI adoption
is increasing rapidly in order to
ensure organizations are able to.
Successfully deploy AI
applications in their environment.
Security is very critical, so
security should be taken into the
consideration from day one, so
it should be security by design.
On top of that, customers or organization
should develop microsegmentation
policies, r back policies.
They should protect their AI
applications, models, data.
And they should continuously evolve
their security practices to ensure AI
applications are secure and none of their
sensitive data leaves the organization.
Like on top of that, they also need
to comply with the regular compliance
frameworks such as hipaa, GDPR, FIPs, and
any other frameworks that are applicable
for that particular organization.
And ethical considerations
are really important.
While training the models and
human oversight should be taken
into the consideration and should
be treated as a top priority to
ensure AI is not doing something
that it is not supposed to do hope.
This presentation provided you
all the insights that you needed
to ensure how organizations can
secure their AI applications.
So that they can confidently roll
out AI applications either for their
employees and for the end customers
in order to improve their operational
efficiency, reduce the cost, increase
the customer satisfaction, and
increase their revenue and position
in the market in the long run.
Thank you so much for your time.
I really appreciate it, and
if you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me.
Thanks a lot and have a nice day.