Hi everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42
Machine Learning Conference.
I'm Shania Psar, a senior product
manager at Cisco Systems, and I'm really
excited to be here with all of you.
Today.
I'll be talking about the convergence
of networking and security, a topic
that's more relevant than ever as
AI and ML continue to evolve, so
do the threats that they introduce.
Addressing these challenges requires a
unified approach, bringing networking
and security together to build resilient
and intelligent infrastructures.
In today's digital landscape,
networking and security can
no longer be different silos.
By converging these domains, we
create intelligent, automated, and
self defending infrastructures.
The integration is not only enhancing
protection against increasingly
sophisticated threats, but it's also
enabling enterprises to move faster,
innovate more efficiently, and respond
dynamically to changing business needs.
Ultimately, this convergence is key
to achieving resilient operations
and sustainable competitive advantage
in an ever evolving digital world.
So let's dive right into it
now.
Traditionally, networking and
security teams operate in isolation,
creating fragmented systems
that often left organizations
vulnerable and slow to respond.
Security policies were inconsistent.
Incidents took longer
to detect resolution.
And this led to higher business risk.
Today we are moving towards a converged
approach, uniting these two critical
functions into one cohesive framework
by integrating security directly
into your network infrastructure.
The organization is achieving unified
visibility, faster detection, automated
responses, and this is significantly
improving that ability and resilience
across these evolving threats.
Now, I wanted to give some,
examples of what kind of
business impacts are possible.
By integrating networking
and security together.
So for example, right?
You can see a reduction in your breach
related costs by an average of 15%, and
that directly reduces financial risk.
Additionally, integrating these two
can accelerate threat containment.
It can also lead to.
An improvement in managing security
incidents resulting in faster
resolutions and streamlined operations.
So it is definitely securing your
business and also empowering it.
It's reducing your risk
and improving your agility.
I wanna talk about a few key technologies.
We've seen evolve over the years.
Let's talk about four
key technologies here.
First, let's start with software defined
networking, where your dynamically routing
traffic based on realtime security needs,
ensuring performance and protection.
Secure Access Service Edge,
SSE, which is my favorite topic.
Unify secure security and networking
at the edge, enabling consistent policy
enforcement wherever users connect.
Zero trust architecture enforces
identity verification for every single
user and device, reducing lateral risk.
And finally, AI powered security, which
brings intelligent threat detection to
the forefront using machine learning to
spot anomalies and automate responses.
This is enabling proactive
defense at scale.
Together, these pillars are
making convergence possible, and
they're making it transformative.
Let's talk about the
market growth a little bit.
The SDN market is projected to grow from
10.5 billion in 2023 to 15.8 billion.
The SSE market is also exploding.
It's almost tripling in size from about a
billion to 2.4 billion in just five years.
Together these trends are fueling
demand for converge solutions, unlocking
massive new market opportunities
at the intersection of agility,
scalability, and cyber resilience.
So what all have to be done as part
of this organizational transformation?
So true convergence is not just about
technologies, as you might know, it
demands organizational transformation.
It starts at the foundation with
consolidated infrastructure where
hardware and software are unified to
create a co cohesive digital environment.
On top of that, you have integrated
tool sets that bridge networking
and security workflows and reduce
silos to enable efficiency.
Next you have collaborative teams
bringing together cross-functional
stakeholders with shared
accountability and success metrics.
And at the very top is where strategic
alignment ensures that business and
security goals are synchronized, making
cybersecurity not just a function,
but a driver of enterprise growth.
This pyramid is showing you how
organizational transformation happens.
And it's very impact driven
from what we've seen so far.
The promise of networking and security
convergence is clear, and we also
looked at how this can be achieved, but.
Obviously it's easier
said than done, isn't it?
Execution is not without,
its without its hurdles.
Firstly, there's a skills gap.
This is literally the
biggest concern out there.
This is basically a lack of professionals
who understand both domains deeply
enough to lead the integration efforts.
Then there is organizational res
resistance where siloed teams
cling to traditional roles and
processes, making cross-functional
collaboration very difficult.
There's legacy infrastructure with which
further complicates things, and there's
outdated systems that aren't designed
to support converged architectures.
And finally, we've all heard it
budget constraints that often
delay progress and there are.
Just other costs that compete with
priorities, even in the long term.
The even if the ROI is compelling,
it's really hard to get that budget.
So addressing all of these
challenges is one of, one of the
great ways where you can make sure
that your execution can happen.
Now let's talk about a little bit
about the cloud integration strategy.
A successful cloud integration
strategy starts with visibility
comprehensively assessing your cloud
footprint to understand the services
data flows and their security needs.
Then it's critical to establish
multi-layer security parameters
that consistently enforce
access policies across hybrid
and multi-cloud environments.
Organizations must also deploy
converged control systems that unify
network and security management
into a single coherent framework.
And finally, ongoing success depends
on continuous performance monitoring.
Using analytics to proactively
optimize both security posture
and network efficiency.
This cycle ensures resiliency, agility,
and control in any cloud environment.
A successful implementation of
converged networking and security
begins with assessment and planning.
Analyzing your current infrastructure,
identifying vulnerabilities, aligning
integration goals with business outcomes.
From there, team and technology
alignment is critical.
Breaking down those silos, implementing
unified platforms, training
cross-functional teams with the
right skillsets, and then finally,
implementation and optimization.
Deploy solutions in phases
to minimize disruption.
Use analytics to measure
impact and establish continuous
feedback loops for refinement.
This roadmap ensures that transformation
is both strategic and sustainable.
I wanted to give you a few examples
of organizations in specific verticals
that have actually achieved this.
For example, in the financial services
sector, a Fortune 500 bank was able
to cut security incidents by 35% while
also improving their transaction speeds.
And this was all due to their
integrated software defined networking.
In healthcare, there was a major hospital
that reduced breach containment from
over 48 hours to just under 60 minutes.
And this was by deploying SASE
across its network and securing
their sensitive patient data.
And the final example here is
in manufacturing where a global
leader protected their critical OT
systems and achieved 99.8% uptime
by applying zero trust principles
across their infrastructures.
So these are not just
theoretical examples, right?
They are actually delivering measurable
impact across all the industries.
To build a resilient digital
future organization's mistake,
a strategic and phased approach.
Start by assessing your readiness,
understand your integration
maturity, and identify initiatives
with clear business impact.
It's like they say start
small, but think big, right?
So pilot targeted projects that
deliver value quickly while laying the
foundation for scalable transformation.
Foster collaboration across your
networking and security teams by
unifying goals, breaking down silos, and
finally embrace continuous evolution.
Adapt to emerging threats and technologies
through regular strategic reviews.
It's not just a one time project, it's
a living process that drives lasting
agility, security, and innovation.
Thank you all so much for
being here and listening to me.
I definitely enjoyed being
here and talking to you all.
See you next time.
Thank you so much.
I.