Speaker 12: Hello everyone.
Thank you so much for joining conference.
My name is Lev Federov and today
I will tell you how to make
recommendations explainable.
My presentation will be very practical
and it'll consist of two parts.
In the first part, I will guide you
through the re existing recommendation
system pipeline, and in the second
part I will tell you which changes were
implemented to make recommendations
explainable for both users and developers.
To be on the same context let's understand
what recommendation systems are when you
watch the YouTube video during a launch
break or when you are listening to Spotify
music in the background while you are
coding, or where you're scroll when you're
scrolling at wis. In the tube you are
actually using a recommended services and
usually for this services, their homepage
will be recommendation feed, and that feed
will be highly personal and unique for
each user based on the user's interests.
And when I said that we would like to
be able to explain recommendations,
what did it actually mean?
So from user perspective I meant that
we would like to show the reason why
particular card appeared in their feed.
In this example, we have a video
about 10 tips for better productivity.
And it was recommended because
user in the past liked the
video about effective planning.
And what is actually motivation
for adding these explanations
and changing the system?
So we faced couple of problems.
First problem is user reports.
We have questionnaires in our service
and users start, sending that as
they see some relevant contents
that they're not interested in.
And the second problem, as the developers
with the current architecture, we had a
lack of traceability tools to understand
which interaction in the past all led
to particular recommendation for a user.
So let's go through the
recommendations pipeline.
In our system, we have a user and
when they open our surveys, we
associate user profile with them.
After that out of 100 million items
on candidate selection stage, we
select just couple of thousands
that will be relevant for users.
After that we compute features for each
candidate and pass the ranking formula.
So after that, we will have on the top
the most relevant items for this user.
And we are gonna apply some
business logic and receive just 20
items and return them to the user.
Recommendations feed.
Our recommendation system use
content-based filtering and
collaborating, filtering approaches.
And I'll not dive into details
how this approach works.
But the main fact that you should
know that after applying this approach
is we get embeddings as associated
with both users and publications.
And regarding embedding, it's some
vector in end dimensional space, or it
can be represented as a flowed array.
And you can see cat is being equal
to some flowed array in this example.
And regarding the embedding, since
the space for similar publications,
embedding will be close enough.
As you can see for Cat one and CAT two
and for different publications embeddings
in the space will be far away as you see
for cats and politics or cats and cars.
And when I say close, I mean
that their angle will tend to
zero and cassan will tend to.
So let let's go to the
first stage user profile.
Let's say we got our
embedding for example, this
collaborating filtering approach.
And our expectation is that this embedding
will be close to all the interest.
All the publications that
user is interested in.
But in the reality it's not the true
and we can have some other publications
and it's hard to interpret or explain
why this happened and also it.
This embedding With this embedding,
it's hard to explain in as a feed
of why certain publication was shown
this downsides and another approach.
For content based models we can use a K
means algorithm when we clusterize our po.
We select clusters with user interests.
We find the OID of this cluster.
And after that user profile is
represented with not only one
embedding, but with the multiple ones.
But in the reality, it's also not a
good approach because some clusters.
Can overlap with each other and user
and Centro for this cluster will
be in completely different cluster
that user is not interested in.
Or after finding the Centro it's closer
to C sharp and c plus that user don't
like while he liked J and Python.
So I'm gonna address these issues in
the second part of my presentation, and
let's move on to the candidate selection.
As I mentioned this stage is responsible
for quickly selecting k or thousands
of publications out of a hundred
of millions in our content base.
And for that we use methods that
is called KNNK, nearest Neighbors.
It can help us to return K nearest
neighbors to a given embedding.
And in this example, we
have an elephant embedding.
And when we select four nearest neighbors,
we got animals because they're embedding
as the closest one to the elephants.
And as an implementation, we use HNSW.
You can read if you're interested
about this structure in Eric in the
links that I attached to the slide.
But basically we gonna put in this.
Index all publications that we have
in our content base as an input.
We will pass the user profile and amount
of items that we would like to select.
And as an output, we will get K items
that we requested ations in our case,
and it'll be done very effectively.
The issue with this can and indices,
we, first of all when we ask
nearest neighbors, it doesn't mean
that they're really close to the
original embeddings that we passed.
So in, you can see that we got some
items with low design and they're
probably about different topics.
And also another disadvantage
of this index that.
We know our publications, that they're
similar, but we doesn't know anything
about their quality or their popularity.
And this issue I'm gonna address in the
second part of presentation as well.
So now we have our candidates
and for each candidates we go.
Compute some features.
These features can be as simple as amount
of likes or if the publication is a video
duration of this video or a bit more
complex as a sign between embeddings.
For collaborative filtering models
and content models, and we're
gonna pass it to ranking formula.
And ranking formula will predict
the score, the relevance for user.
So now we can sort all the
candidates by this score.
And in the top we are gonna get the
most relevant publications for the user.
And last part, business logic.
It's actually quite interesting that
after applying ranking formula, we
can get publications from one only
after in the top, or we can get
only publications about one topic.
So to avoid this situations, we gonna
reward the top in that way that it has
multiple outs and it has multiple topics.
So it's being diverse.
And let's talk about approach
that we implemented to make
recommendations explainable.
I highlighted in the green box user
profile and candidate selection.
These are the stages that
we would like to change.
Regarding user profile, if you remember
we used embeddings and the issue
that we can't easily interpret them.
But what if instead of embedding, we
store publication Id that user positively
interacted with so we wouldn't have any
approximations and user profile will
consist of the list of publication id.
Then in this case we need to rework
our candidate selection and, we
implemented the following structure.
So you can think of it as a simple
map, wherein keys, you will have
positives or publications and
keys are associated with values.
And each value contains a list of
candidates that is relevant, that
are relevant to the original key.
So let's talk about relevancy.
How we gonna, keep our list relevant.
So at the beginning, let's assume
that we have all the publications in
the list and we would like to filter
non similar publications to the key.
So to do we can annotate
pairs of publications as
relevant and irrelevant first.
And, for doing so, we use some
crowdsourcing platform and send some tasks
with these annotations so assessors can
mark our publication, similar or not.
And once we get this data
set, f for version zero.
We can define a assigned
threshold for content-based
model based on the sanitation.
After everything above this
threshold will be relevant and.
This will solve our problem.
But we can have some errors or mistakes.
And instead of that, let's train
some relevance formula that we'll be
using as a features multiple cosign
for multiple content-based models.
And it'll predict if, publications
are relevant to each other or not.
So now we have only relevant
publications in the list.
But what about order?
Can we order then somehow
how that the most attractive
publications are in the top?
And yes, we can for that.
We have another stage that
we called attractiveness.
For first version, we can
use a conditional CTR.
And conditional CTR is CTR of publication
A, given that the user had a positive
interaction with publication B. So
you can think that publication B is a
key of our index and publication A is
one of many publications in the list.
So with that, we can have a CTR for
all the candidates inside of the list
and we can order them by this value.
So we can have the most
attractive one in the top.
The issue here, again, the same.
We rely only just on one metric
while we can rely on much more.
So instead of that, let's use
attractiveness formula that will
be predicting positive interaction.
This publication a, given that the
user had a positive interaction
with publication B, it's very
similar to ranking formula.
And as a features, we can pass
their information met information
about publication in the key,
and we can pass met information
about the publication in the list.
And also we can pass conditional
CTR as another feature.
So now our recommendation pipeline will
looks like that we have a positive that
is associated with some candidates.
And let's say some candidates were
promoted and then they became a
publication in the feed of the user.
So how are we going.
Play now, why this
publication is being shown?
If we go back to positive, we know
that it is publication id and we
have some meta information about it.
We have a title, we have an author.
So we can say that you liked some title
or you interacted with author, and that's
why you see this publication in your feed.
And let's talk about one more issue
with our system over the time.
User user positives list will, growing
up and growing up, and obviously
we would like to limit this list
and select just the best items.
One of the approaches
determinational point process.
And this algorithm works.
As following, we select K points and we
try to satisfy both of the conditions.
We prefer to select
points with high weights.
And we would like to keep
diversity in the selected set.
And as a wait you can think of
for example, a rate between how
long user watched video and what
was the duration of the video.
We can increase the weight in case a
user liked this video or they share it
with their friends or they comment it.
So I just showed a simple example
when we have six positives and we
would like to select just three.
So on the right part, we
selected, this positive that meets
their original two conditions.
And also you can think
about positives as a three.
So each positive leads us to another
positive or leads us to nothing.
And if they leads us to nothing, then
probably we would like to eliminate
this positives from the user.
For doing so in the history event, now we
have positive id, publication ID and event
id like show click and anything like that.
So we can compute starts for
each positive, like CTR, like
dislikes, rate, watch time, and
we can train one more formula.
For ranking positives.
So we have the most impactful
positives in the top of the list,
and we can remove bad positives as
I showed in the previous example.
And we also can pass the statistics
to recommender ranking formula
to make our recommendation system
better and improve and improve it.
And now about candidate selection,
we can use some bandits ideology.
But let's firstly think of we have
three positives for some user.
So what we want to do.
We want to select 300 candidates
out of three positives.
Instead of equally sharing and
selecting 100 candidates, let's
use the CTR for the positives that
we know from the previous stage.
And we see that positive one has the
most impactful CTR, so that's why we.
Proportion in the proportion.
We proportionally shared the quota
and we selected 150 candidates from
it, and we selected 60 candidates from
positive three as a less impactful one.
There's a conclusion.
So we made our system transparent.
So our recommendations pipeline is very
explainable now, and we can show the
recommendation, explanation to the user.
We also addressed couple of
issues in, in previous pipeline.
So we managed to get feed relevance
increase and least but not last.
Developers can trace the backend, improve
system and investigate if user complaints
about the relevant cards in their feed.
And thank you so much for,
listening my presentation.
I hope you enjoyed.
If you have any questions, you
can contact me and link it in.
My link it in is attached
to the conference page.
Thank you.