Hi.
Hello everyone.
This is Anil Kumar.
I'm here to talk about 5G Infrastructure
Automation, and let me give you
a little bit intro about myself.
So I studied at Harrisburg
University, worked at Verizon, and
I'm currently working at United
Airlines as a DevOps engineer.
Now when you hear of 5G most people
immediately think a faster Netflix
or smoother Zoom calls and maybe one
or two dropped calls less, right?
So it's all about 5G.
So I will let explain
something more about 5G today.
But what if we had told you we used 5G?
Not to binge watch more tv, but to help
cities think we automated the traffic.
Include emergency response, even
made energy usage, more sustainable.
We gave cities a digital nervous system,
and today I'm walking you through, not in
theory, but real world deployed solution.
You'll see how edge computing small cells,
automation, and gold, good old DevOps made
cities faster, smarter, cleaner, right?
So let's dive in The first section
of it it's a smart city problem.
Let's go back to the straight point.
The mass cities are now well complicated,
but their systems are way behind.
Like when you compare, traffic
lights are like set on 2005 timers
with the grid locks and all.
All right, so like power grids
always on whether you need it or not.
Emergency services like often routing
through traffic with no dynamic data,
like when an ambulance is trying to go.
So they just follow the GPS and
go and follow through the routes.
Which they gave one funny example,
in one city the traffic sys light
system couldn't be updated remotely.
We had to send someone out.
But with the USB stick there, and
that's not outdated, that's prehistoric.
It wasn't just inefficient, it was
dangerous, wasteful and expensive.
Need a manpower.
We need a real time data driven
cities that where 5G and DevOps,
that's where DevOps came in and
we come up with some strategy.
Here.
The DevOps revolution, right?
So when I talk about the DevOps
revolution, so where DevOps meets
infrastructure, usually when you hear
right DevOps, you think deploying
microservices, managing CICD, et cetera.
But we use the DevOps to deploy networks.
Every router switch and edge
was defined as a code, like
an infrastructure as a code.
We had terraform plants
that spun up 5G clusters.
We did it in AWS hand charts configured
edge services, pipelines, auto tested
latency, bandwidth, even failures.
Instead of saying, let's send a guy with
the LA ladder, we set, let's push to
pro, we reduced deployment time by 85%.
You know what I'm trying to say is that,
so instead of sending a person with a
USD stick with, along with a ladder.
So what we just did was
let's push it to the prod.
Whatever the automation we did, we
reduced the deployment time by 85% and
created a rollback options that didn't
exist in the real traditional networking.
So here comes our next slide, which is
like a building the low latency network.
So it's about a latency breakdown.
I'm talking here to
make smart cities smart.
They need to respond instantly.
We need a sub 10 milliseconds latency.
That meant small cells on the light
poles building business buses, basically
anywhere with power and wifi and fiber
back haul, connecting everything,
edge nodes, doing local processing.
No more round trips to
a cloud 2000 miles away.
This enabled right live video
analytics, real time alerts.
And autonomous drone patterns.
We are talking Miss milliseconds here.
That's less than a blink.
Imagine a camera, spots a fire
and instantly rewrote the traffic
with a dispatching alerts.
No waiting, no bottlenecks instantly
rero the ambulances to a different
route so that you can save lives.
So it's like interesting
thing we built here.
So next go, I'll go to the section four,
which is a IOT mess like iot ecosystem.
What I taught, what we presented, so
it's like we have connected like network.
We layered in devices, lots of them.
So like 10,000 connected
endpoints per square mile.
Smart meters, pollution sensors, cameras,
emergency buttons, EV chargers, so all
talking, adapting, learning autonomously.
We didn't just install gadgets, but we
created a nervous system for the city.
One time our sensors picked up
an air quality spike and rerouted
a school buses away from it.
So that isn't a mesmerizing.
So no humans involved in there.
Like just the systems have been taken
care and they, the system just knew it.
So it has picked an air quality
in the air and spike and rerouted
the traffic along the distances.
So here comes our next slide.
It's a smart traffic management which
we call it as a smart traffic and power.
So I will talk a little bit
about the smart traffic here.
With AI powered video analysis, our system
adjusted traffic lights in a real time.
So I told you right, so it, the
traffic got rerouted in the previous
lights, so it's like a lights
adapted to the condition, not timers.
Like what we talk about
previous lives, green waves
reduced stop and start driving.
Emergency corridors were dynamically
open for the ambulances and fire trucks.
We reduced the commute times by
25% and cut idle time in half.
That's gas saved time saved
and air cleaned up, right?
So now on to the power.
We used a smart grids IOT meters
that automatically balanced energy,
a solar output high charged.
The EV stations demand low at night
power street lights using stored
batteries, neighborhood surge shift
load instantly, and this led to a
35% reduction in the city using it
and 28% drop in the carbon output.
And it was just efficient
and it was sustainable.
So that's where my smart traffic
and power management came in.
And let's do the next slide,
which is how we rolled it out
into the real time traffic here.
The, this wasn't just a one day
magic or something like that.
It was structured and in a
phases like, assessment phase
and automation work pilot zone.
Parallel rollout and all.
So assessment phase is every duck
pole and antione was mapped in the
assessment phase in the initial phase.
Then afterwards it's an
automation framework.
There, there comes our picture like,
building A-C-I-C-D pipelines with the
A bill for infrastructure and all this
comes into the automation framework.
And next phase we went to the pilot zone.
We started in dense downtown
zones, like where we have a a heavy
traffic and also to test it out.
So we did that in a,
as a pilot zone phase.
And after that parallel roll rollout
using IAC and kops, we scaled citywide.
So we treated infrastructure.
Like software, like a clean,
modular, testable, each
deployment validated itself.
And yeah, as I mentioned, this
all conducted in a phases, so that
helped a lot for us to move forward.
So here comes the, a real impact,
like a measurable impact, what we
have achieved using this one, right?
I'll tell you the numbers, right?
So it's all about 23%
lower commute times 42%.
Of a faster emergency response and 35%
of our energy savings have been showed up
and 64% bump in a resident satisfaction.
These are like an app approximate values.
What we collected so far from
the c, from the automation.
This wasn't just a dashboards
and data I was talking here, it
was a people living better lives.
Like when it comes to the commuter,
whatever the automation we did using the
5G one CT manager said, we used to respond
to the problems, now we prevent them.
That there isn't that amazing.
Yep.
So that's what we achieved
with the automation.
And next to the scaling
to the global cities.
What we talk here about is a
scalable architecture and open
standards and knowledge transfer.
So we didn't want to be a onetime
success year, so we opened or we,
so we open source the blueprint
model which is a modular playbooks.
Vendor, neutral tech and a
training program for cities.
So now as I spoke, we are working with
the 15 plus cities globally, scaling
up with the AI driven automation
and adding privacy fast designs.
So Citizen Trust is built in, this is the
future and that, and it's, and repeatable,
so scalable architecture, what.
We, when we talk about is that our
frameworks seamlessly adapts to
metropolitan areas of any scale
implementation can be faced.
Yeah.
So this is, as I told, this is the future
and it's unrepeatable when it comes to the
the path forward of what it is, expanding
the partnerships and, enhance the privacy
framework and advanced AI integration.
So this all comes under the
forward thinking, like a path
forward, what I'm talking and
he, it's just, it is a wrap up.
To wrap up everything.
So 5G isn't just a speed, it's
about a smart infrastructure,
and DevOps isn't just for a code,
it's also for automating cities.
Just as an example, as I mentioned, we
are not just solving traffic pro jams.
We are building a future where
cities think, adopt, and care for
their people in the real time.
And thanks so much for
listening my speech.
I'm happy to take your
questions and yep, that's all.
And you guys have a good day.