Hello everyone.
I'm Prakesh Vanga.
Overall, 13 years of exchange experience
specializing in AWS cloud engineer
and identity access management.
Currently serving as an A WS
data engineer, designing and
implementing scalable and secure data
pipelines, leveraging AWS services.
Over the years, I had the opportunity
to work across complex enterprise.
Environments helping organization
not only migrate to the cloud, but
also optimize how they manage data
securely, efficiently and intelligently.
Today I'm truly excited to speak to
you about a topic that close to both my
technical experience and future vision.
A driven integration
revolutionizing data management in.
Multicloud enterprise environments.
In today's session, I would walk with
how a power integration frameworks
can transform enterprise operation
by eliminating the complexity
of working across multiple cloud
platforms like AWS Azure GCP,
improving visibility performance, and.
Security and delivering measurable ROI,
while ensuring organizations stay fully
compliant with evolving regular standards.
Whether you are in financial service,
healthcare, our technology, the strategies
and techniques will explode today,
our designed to help you motorize your
data infrastructure, reduce operational
overhead, and gain a complete edge.
In a rapidly evolving digital world.
Let's get started.
So the slide, multi-cloud
reality, the integration
challenge, let's start with the.
Reality we face today, most
enterprises don't operate in a
single cloud environment anymore.
They're using AWS for scalability,
Azure for enterprise integration and
GCP for AI services simultaneously.
But with this flexibility
comes complexity, we end
corner four main challenges.
First one is of fragmented data.
And enterprise has moved to the
cloud, many adaptive multi-cloud
strategies leveraging AWS for
scalability, Azure for enterprise
integration, and GC GCP for a services.
While these hybrid approaches
provide flexibility, it also data
ecosystems it's not helping much more.
So what happened in practice is customer.
Records might be stored in AWS
S3, for example, applications log
logs are log and index in Azure.
Monitor and analytic data takes
results in Google Cloud BigQuery.
These environments don't
talk to each other natively.
Each uses different
formats, different APIs.
And next one, security vulnerability.
Each cloud has different
policies and protocols.
This inconsistency introduces gaps
between technology and also, let us
tell one example, let us know address
one of the most pressing issues in
any multi-cloud architecture, security
vulnerability caused by inconsistent
policy enforcement across cloud providers.
While each cloud being AWS Microsoft
Azure or Google Cloud platform, GCP
offers strong native secure controls.
They are fundamentally different in
design, configuration, and operation.
This lack of standardization
introduces significantly risk when
organizations attempts to unify
them under when one architecture,
what causes these vulnerabilities?
Different security models.
Each cloud product has own IAM
identity access management, AWS use
IM roles and policies and Azure users.
Role-based access control.
GCP relies on IAM bindings and
roles tied to resources hierarchies.
These models are not.
Interoperable and even small
misconfigurations like or permission
roles or inconsistent MFA policies
can become entry point for attackers.
Operational inefficient integration
is often manual error, resources
heavy and time consuming.
Let's now examine a critical
barrier to enterprise agility and
perform in multi-cloud environments.
Operational efficiency
caused by manual integration.
While the term may sound procedural,
it impacts in strategic affecting
productivity, scalability,
and business continuity.
So what is the manual integration?
Manual integration refers
to the non-automatic human
driven process of connecting
services, transferring data, and.
Aligning workflow between
cloud platform like AWS Azure
and GCP compliance complexity.
So for example, meeting HIPA
Health Insurance Portability and
Accountability Act are SOX Compliance
in a multi-cloud setup requires deep
expertise and constant monitoring.
Having discussion, the operational
security and data challenging
in multi-cloud ecosystem, let's
now turn to a domain that is
equally critical compliance.
But when your data and workloads
are spread across AWS Azure and
Google Cloud compliance becomes
exponentially more complex.
So why complex compliance is
so challenging in multi-cloud?
One is different regions, different rules.
Each cloud provides source
data in multiple regions.
By default, if you don't configure
storage correctly, your data might land
in incorrect path where Stryker rules
apply and you may not even know it.
For example, I will take A-H-I-P-A Health
Insurance Portability and Accountability
Act mandates end-to-end encryption.
And stick to access control for
healthcare data, one misconfiguration
can lead to regular breach and
several financial penalties.
And in consistent audit trail.
Each cloud logs and tracks
eventually differently.
AWS VS Cloud trial.
Azure has monitor and log analytics.
GCP has cloud audit logs.
Without integration, these logs
become disjoint, making it extremely
difficult to perform infra audits.
Responses to incidents are pro
compliance during external assessments,
evolving regulations, so regulator
requirements changes frequently,
keeping up with updates across
multiple compliance while aligning with
multiple cloud provided configurations
required constant manual efforts and.
Specialized knowledge.
This is not just a legal risk,
it's a operational drain.
We'll go to next slide.
AI transformation automation
integration, AI transform
automat, automated data mapping.
Let's now talk about how AI transforms
integration, starting with one of
the most powerful feature automated
data mapping in a multi-cloud setup.
Data exists in many formats,
structures, and locations spread across
platforms like AWS, Azure and GCP.
Traditionally, connecting this data
requires manual mapping, understanding
source and target fields, writing
transformational logic, ensuring
data types and format align.
This process is time consuming,
prone to human error and needs.
Constant updates whenever schema changes.
So what does a do differently?
So with automated data mapping,
we use advanced machine learning
algorithm that can scan and understand
data sets, even if they come from
completely different systems.
Automatically detects
relationship between fields.
For example, it can recognize
that customer ID in AWS.
It matches to Azure customer number.
If it don't match us, it'll cause
the issue generally accurate.
Mapping logic without requiring manual
intervention, the results are impressive
by using AI For this task, we are, we
have seen 85% reduction in manual data
mapping efforts, significantly improved
accuracy, especially in large scale.
Thousands of fields schemas.
So fashion integration, timelines
and fewer errors in production
and intelligent data routing.
So next, let's how transform that
where data moves across multi-cloud
environments with a concept
called intel and data routing.
In traditional systems, data
flow are typically static.
Once you define.
A route from one cloud service to another.
It remains fixed regardless
of change in network traffic
latency system performance.
But in dynamic multi-cloud environments
like AWS Azure and GCP network
conditions can change every second.
And a fixed road can easily become a slow
or overloaded path, reducing performance.
So what is intelligent data routing?
So with a power routing, the system is no
longer pass you our active learning and
optimizing in real time here what it is.
Analyzing network traffic conditions
continuously, such as bandwidth
availability, latency, and server
loads, chooses the fastest, most
efficient path for data to travel
every time as a request is made.
Instant.
If something changes like traffic spike
system, slow down this enterprise that
your data reaches its destination faster,
avoids bottleneck, and maintain consistent
performance across all cloud platform.
In real world, we see significant
reduce reduction in latency, improve
throughput, far high volume data
applications, and much better system
availability, especially during.
Peak traffic and next
governance enforcement.
The final piece of a driven
integration I would like to
highlight is governance enforcement.
A major leap forward is managing
complaints across multi-cloud BroadB beds.
Now, let's be honest, governance and
complaints are often seen as complex,
time consuming and constantly changing.
Every organization must follow industry
regulations like G-D-P-R-H-I-P-A,
or SOCs, depending on your sector.
But when you're working across
multiple cloud platforms, AWS, Azure,
GCP, keeping policies consistent,
become extremely difficult.
Each platform has different tools,
different permission structures,
different upgrade cycles.
So manually mounting is not
only slow, it is also risky.
So what does AI do for governance?
This is where AI powered policies,
engines make a huge difference.
These engines are self-learning, meaning
they monitor evolving regulations and
automatically apply the latest rule.
They enforce compliance consistently
across all cloud platform, no
matter how complex your setup is.
Companies that reduces the compliance
monitoring workload by up to 70% real
time visibility across cloud ecosystem.
So issue detection, early problem
identification with the ai.
Now let's talk about one of the
most powerful outcome of a driven
integration, early problem detection
in complex multi-cloud environments.
Issue can arise at any time.
A failed data transfer, a
slowdown in response time, or
even silent security misalignment.
So traditionally, these problems
are only discovered after they
cause visible damage like an outage.
CSLA or compliance were violations.
So A helps a change the game
by acting as 24 by seven
intelligent monitoring systems.
So here what it does, it constantly
scans logs, data flow, and system
behavior across all cloud platform.
It uses patterns, recognization and
detection to spot irregularities
often before humans can notice them.
It can even predict potential failures
by learning from past system behavior.
This proactive led to a 94% improvement
in early issues detection, so resolution
time, faster, troubleshooting with
the ai, following on early detection.
Let's talk about what happened next.
Resolving the issue with traditional
systems, even when a problem is
detected, finding the root cause
can take hours or even days.
Teams must manually check logs, trace
dependencies across cloud services,
and coordinate between multiple
platforms like AWS, Azure and GCP.
This is slow, frustrating, and costly
how a speeds are troubleshooting with
a driven monitoring and diagnostics,
the story is very different.
A helps reduce troubleshooting
time by seven six percentage.
Automate root cause analysis.
AI quickly pinpoints the source
of problem, whether it is
misconfigured permissions, a failing
service or drop network package.
Correlated log insights.
It analyzes logs across all cloud
simultaneously identifying patterns
and depending this in seconds,
small recommendations based on the
historical data, AI can suggest the
most effective resolution reducing.
Guesswork and back and forth
and operational efficiency,
pushing it team productivity.
With the ai, let's now look at one.
One of the most exciting outcomes
of AI driven integration is 3.5 x
increase in operational efficiency.
That means IT teams are getting more
than three times the work, the with
resources and less manual effort.
In a traditional setup, your
IT team is constantly switching
between cloud dashboard, writing
scripts, troubleshooting error,
managing integrations, and trying
to make sense of skater data.
It's not just exhausting, it's
inefficient, so a boost efficiency.
With a power unified monitoring
platforms, your team no longer have to
chase problems across systems in shape.
The benefit form single.
Pan of glass visibil
across AWS Azure and GCP.
Maybe you can use single dashboard.
No more jumping between dashboards.
Everything is integrated into
one intelligent interface,
automatic alert systems in place.
And hey, doesn't just tell that
you there something is wrong in,
tell what, where and how to fix it.
And going Next slide.
Implementation framework,
the assessment phase.
Let's now talk about how we begin
implementing AI driven integration
across a multi-cloud environments.
The first and most important steps in
the assessment phase, this is very,
we lay the foundation for success by
thoroughly understanding the current
environment, aligning it with the
business goals and identifying.
Where AI can make the biggest impact.
So the step one, current state analysis,
the first thing we do is map out
your existing cloud infrastructure.
We identify which service are
running AWS, Azure and GCP
based on the cloud technology.
Where there are performance gaps, T
process are security vulnerabilities.
This queues as clear
picture of the baseline.
What's working, what not,
and where we can improve.
Think of it as performing a health checks,
whatever, multi-cloud architecture and
step two, business requirement mapping.
So next we align the technic technical
side with the business goals.
What outcomes are you trying to achieve?
Is it faster taxes?
Lower costs, or strong compliance?
When then define clear key
performance indicators and return on
investments metrics to measure the
success of integration initiatives.
This ensures that the solution is not
just technical sound, but business driven.
And step three, finally, we look at how
data flows across your cloud platform.
How much data are you moving,
how fast that is needs to travel.
How complex are the transformation?
This help us identifying high impact
integrations, opportunities, places
where a can boost speed, reduce error,
and improve efficiency the most.
It also helps prioritize what we integrate
first for maximum business values.
So I'm going to next slide.
Strategic platform selection.
Choose the right
foundation for integration.
Once we complete the assessment
phase, the next key step is
implementing AI driven integration
is choosing the right platform.
This is what we call
strategic platform selections.
Not all platforms are created equal, and
the wrong choice can lead to login, poor
performance, and endless customization.
So we focus on four critical
factors that defines.
Further ready integration platform.
So the first one is interoperability.
First, we look at multi-cloud or
your integration platform must
work seamless with different cloud
APIs, various data formats, and
multiple communication protocols.
This means you should be able to
connect AWS Azures, GCP, and even
on print systems without writing
C code for each connection.
Think of it like a universal translator
that allows all of our cloud services
to talk to each other smoothly
and instantly has a capabilities.
We want a platform that comes with
built in machine learning tool for
predictive integration, like sporting
potential failures before they happen.
Pat recognized across data sets and.
Autonomous optimization of workflow.
So the system keeps
improving itself over time.
This isn't just about automation,
it's about in automation, and next
will go scalability, then comes
scalability as your business grows.
So the volume of data, the number of
users, and the complexity of your cloud
services, your integration platform must
handle this growth without slowing down.
For business a requirement,
a full architecture.
It should adapt dynamically
as your environmental evolves.
Think like choosing a bridge that
not only handled today traffic,
but is ready for tomorrow.
Rush showers and next vendor independence.
Finally, we took for vendor independence.
Your integration solutions should have
flexible architecture that doesn't tie.
You one cloud to other cloud, which
ensure portability of our cloud.
Easier migrations, our expansions, and
better dealing with the cloud vendors.
We'll go with next slide.
Performance optimization techniques,
making multi-cloud ran smarter and posture
once the right integration platform is
in place, the next step is performing
optimization, making the next step.
Multi-cloud environments not
only works, but work faster,
efficiently and intelligently.
AI plays a major role here.
We uses a combination of small
technologies to boost systems performance
by 40 to 60%, and I would like to work
through the four key techniques we use.
The first one is predictive
resources allocation.
The first technique is predictive.
Resources allocation.
So in this technique, a constantly
analyzes system phase and forecast
upcoming demand, whether it's a
storage, compute, or bandwidth based
on automatic, a automatically scales
resources up or down in real time.
This means you avoid performance
button, like during peak traffic,
and you also save cost during.
Quite period, but not overing.
Next is data filtering.
Instead of trans transferring
and processing all data, it
determines what relevant and
filter out unnecessary information
before it moves between systems.
This reduces network traffic storage
we and data processing loads.
Think if going through your
inbox and only keeping the
important emails automatically.
And next one is then we
integrated edge computing.
This means the data is processed
close to its source at the edge of
the network, rather than sending
everything back to the cloud.
Benefits like faster response
times reduces latency and
improve performance for real time
applications like retail transactions.
And finally, we use adapt to compressions.
A Dan Kelly compress data based on the
content network conditions, based on the
network conditions and priority level.
This ensure faster transfer, especially
across regions or providers, and
helps optimize bandwidth usage.
We get faster performance with less
traffic without compromising our data.
Going to next slide.
Case study, financial
services transformation.
Let's look at the real world example.
With a power integration in place,
the transformation was dramatic.
Integration time dropped by 87.
Percentage when took weeks, now
took just days or even ours,
thanks to automated data mapping.
And in routing data reduces
by 86 percentage A identified.
And corrected inconsistent in real
time leading to clean and more reliable
data complaints cost fell sharply.
Self-learning policies, engines
ensure that all systems stayed
aligned with the regulations.
Reducing manual effort and audit
related stress system uptime improved
significantly with prior to monitoring
and intelligent troubleshooting
out has become rare and recover.
Was much faster.
I will go with next slide.
Emerging technologies,
reshaping integration.
As we look to the future, it's
clear that a driven integration
is just the beginning.
A new view of emerging technologies
is reshaping how we manage data
systems and security across the cloud,
and it happened faster than ever.
Let me briefly walk you.
Four powerful technologies
that are revolutionary, the
next generation of integration.
The first one is autonomous operations.
First, we have autonomous operations,
what we often call self-healing system.
Imagine a system that detects an error
and it's won, identify the root cause,
and fixes the issue automatically
without waiting for human interventions.
These systems uses AI to monitor
operational in real time.
Learn from past instance
and adapt continuously.
It's like having an IT team
that never sleeps, never makes
mistakes and resolution problems
before users even notice.
And next one.
Second, we have edge computing,
a powerful approach where data
is processed at near their source
instead of central cloud system.
This is especially
useful for smart retail.
Real-time monitoring in healthcare
are manufacturing next year is
blockchain security in multi-cloud
and hybrid environments.
Trust and editable are critical.
Blockchain provides
immutable audit trials.
Records that can be changed are
added across cloud providers.
This creators cross-platform trust for
transactions and access better compliance
tracking and stronger productions.
Again, data.
Data time bring manipulating.
It brings transparency and
integration to data workflow
no matter where the data lies.
And finally, we have cognitive
integration, a concept that
brings natural language
understanding to cloud operations.
Imagine your voice comments are plain
English into managed cloud services.
For example, show me all fail
integrations five this morning, or.
Secure all healthcare data
with GDPR level encryption.
This makes cloud management more
accessible and user-friendly, even
for non-technical stakeholders.
Go to next slide.
Implementation roadmap.
A phase path of a driven integration.
Now that we explored the status
strategy, technologies and
benefits of a. Power integration.
The next big question is how
do we put it all into actions?
We follow a structure phase roadmap
that ensure that transitions to a driven
integration is smooth, measurable,
and aligned with business priorities.
Let me break down each phase
of implementation roadmap.
So the phase one discovery,
four to six weeks.
In this first phase we took
time to fully understand.
The current environment, we access
our existing cloud infrastructure
review integration points, identify
pain points, security gaps and
inefficiencies, and define clear
business and technical requirements.
This phase gives us foundation for
small decision making and phase
two foundation eight to 10 weeks.
So once we define the need, we
move to foundation phase here.
We deploy the core integration platform,
connect your primary systems, whether
AWS Azure, GCP, or on-prem, and
establish basic data flow and monitoring.
This step is all about getting
the system, talking to each
other in stable, scalable way.
And phase three, a enhancement
six to eight weeks.
Now we bring into real.
Power AI automation.
In this phase, we implement automated data
mapping, enabling indi data routing, set
up self-learning policies, enforcement
and configure ready to monitoring.
This is where we start seeing
significant performance gains and
reduce error and foster operations.
Your system becomes
more and more proactive.
And I final up phase
four, optimizing ongoing.
And finally, we, the journey doesn't stop.
With the implementation, we move
into a continuous optimizing phase
where we monitor performance metrics,
analyze system behavior, and fine
tune integration platform for
even better results forward time.
This ensure the system grow
with our business adopts to
change and keeps improving.
Going to next slide, key takeaways.
So transforming your
multi-cloud strategy with ai.
As we come to close off the session,
let's take a moment to recap the takeaway,
the core message that can help transform
your multi-cloud strategy using ai.
These are just technical points.
They are strategic shifts that can
help your business move faster,
smarter, and more content in the cloud
integration complexity.
First takeaway is simple but powerful.
A dramatically simplifies
integration throughout automated
data mapping and indulgent routing.
You can reduce manual
effort by hway percentage.
Unified visibility drives performance.
Performance.
Visibility is performance with the
a. Power monitoring is in place.
You can detect 94% of issues
before they have an impact.
And strategy Platform selection prevents
lockin by focusing on interoperability, AI
capabilities, and vendor independencies.
You'll prevent vendor lockin and set your
business up for long run flexibility.
It ensures that your cloud strategy is not
just effective, but also future reference
and measurable R way across industries.
And finally.
The real business results we see
in organizations in financial
services, healthcare and retail
achieve 40 to 60% efficiency gains
through aid driven integration.
This is in theory, it's happening now
across industries and across the world.
And next slide.
Thank you all for your time and today
it's been a honor to share insights how AI
is transforming multi-cloud integration.
Not just as a technology upgrade,
but as strategic enabled for
performance, compliance and innovation.
I hope this session has
helped you seen what possible.
And we bring intel and automat and
visibility into complex cloud environment.
Thank you.
Thank you all for your time.