Hello everyone.
Welcome and thank you for
joining today's session.
My name is Rahul Amte and I work as a
cloud architect with expertise in AI
infrastructure, DevOps, and security.
Today we are going to explore
how AI and machine learning
revolutionizing cloud automation.
Transforming how we manage and
operate cloud infrastructure.
This isn't just about automation.
It's about intelligent automation
that anticipates, adapts
and optimizes in real time.
Basically, cloud computing, as we all
know, has become the backbone of modern
IT infrastructure, but as environments
become larger and more complex, manual
management is no longer feasible.
That's where AI and ML
come into the picture.
They offer intelligent automation
solutions that not only reduce human
innovation, but also improve efficiency
and decision making across the board.
With that said, we also look at
like, why do we need automation?
What is the need for automation?
Cloud operations often involve
repetitive time and tasks such as
provisioning, scaling, and monitoring.
As organizations adopt multi-cloud or
hybrid cloud strategies, the operational
burden is increasing significantly.
So what can we do and how AI
can handle this and help us?
AI can handle this complexity with
ease, reduce human error, and enable
continuous service availability.
With that side, let's look at what
is AI powered cloud automation?
AI powered cloud automation refers to the
use of artificial intelligence and machine
learning algorithms to manage, optimize,
and troubleshoot cloud infrastructure
like traditional rule based automation.
We have currently, which of course
was not in the traditional world, but
in the current cloud world, AI learns
from historical and real time data.
To make predictive and adapt
decisions automatically as you speak.
We have some cool machine learning based
security tools already doing the real time
data, predictive and adaptive decisions.
But just imagine spreading
this into the infrastructure.
It's definitely going to be
a powered cloud automation.
Let's look at the core
capabilities of AI in cloud ops.
Let's talk about what AI can
actually do in the cloud.
It detects anize like certain
traffic surges or failures.
Predicts future needs, as a resource,
needs optimizes resource placement,
and triggers automated responses.
These intelligent futures can
create a self-managing, self-healing
environment with minimum manual effort.
Isn't it?
Cool?
Let's look at some use cases now.
Predictive resource scaling is one of
the use case I wanna talk about today.
With predictive scaling.
AI monitors the historical usage
patterns to forecast upcoming demands.
For example during an e-commerce flash
sale, like a, like during Thanksgiving
or Christmas, AI can predict traffic
spikes and scale up resources in advance.
I. This ensures performance while
minimizing over provisioning and cost.
Cost is one of the important factors.
At the same time, making sure that
consumer has no issues while there
is traffic surges, especially
during the holiday season.
So AI is definitely, a
helping factor there.
And the other use case is, as I
was mentioning, cost optimization.
Cloud costs can spiral quickly.
AI helps by analyzing resource usage and
suggesting optimizations like right sizing
instances, shutting down ideal resources
or switching to reserved instances.
It's proactive, not reactive, and helps
maintain financial efficiency across
cloud deployments as it underlines.
It's proactive.
What we do today for cost
optimization is reactive.
We have to set up things, we'll have to
make a decision, we'll have to execute
to make it work, but AI can definitely
help us with the proactive nature and
help us in cost optimization, which
has been a major issue in most of the
organizations in this couple of years
because of the spinning of infrastructure
left and right in the last decade.
We look at other use case
where AI can help us.
Downtime is expensive.
AI can significantly reduce
mean time to repair, which is
by detecting failures, correct?
Correct.
Correlating locks and metrics,
and automatically applying
fixes or rerouting traffic.
For example, if a note fails, a
can trigger a script to restart
the service of provision.
New instance.
In the world of incident management
and self feeling, AI can act as
the remediation as a service.
In the current setup we have in the
current world of infrastructure,
we have incident response.
We have monitoring as service.
We have alerting a service.
Just imagine incidents response as an
automatic service would be awesome.
That is what AI is going to do for us.
What are some key tools and platforms?
Let's look at some providers.
Each major cloud provider is
investing heavily in AI power tools.
As we already know, AWS offers DevOps,
guru and CloudWatch and MLA detection.
Azure has AI integrated with
the monitoring and monitor
and advisor, as in GCP.
Also provides auto ML
and cloud operations.
There are also some third party
apart from these three major
cloud providers native services.
The third party platforms like Dynatrace
and Splunk using AIOps are actually
used for the advanced automation
in the cloud infrastructure world.
But there are other tools, a lot
of companies investing in ai.
So there are a lot of other third
party tools as well, which are really
helpful, but we can only choose few.
Next let's look at benefits
of AI driven cloud automation.
The benefits are multifold,
as you already know.
You get higher uptime through
proactive management, cost savings
through intelligent resource
allocation and enhance security
through annually detection.
It also frees up DevOps teams to focus on
innovation rather than the fight fighting.
Innovation as in making things better
and faster than actually trying to
fix things, troubleshoot things.
AI is one of our team members.
Of course, every.
Future comes with some challenges
and some considerations.
Let's look at some here.
However, as I said, there
are challenges to consider.
AI systems are only as good as
the data they are trained on.
Poor data quality can lead
to incorrect decisions.
Integration with legacy systems can be
complex, and there's always the concern
of blindly trusting automated decisions.
So especially in the
regulatory industries.
We'll have to be very careful
because some decisions made based
on the data, poor data quality
can lead to some big problems.
So definitely the quality of the data of
the training being given for the models
that's considered by AI is very important.
With that said, I would like to
conclude by talking about the future
outlook of AI in cloud automation.
From what I said altogether, to sum it
up, AI and ML are pushing the boundaries
of what's possible in cloud operations.
Today, we are moving towards future
of autonomous cloud management, where
AI handles provisioning, optimization,
and even security in real time.
This evolution is not just
inevitable, it's already underway.
It's going to get better and amazing.
Once again, thank you for the opportunity.
I really enjoyed it and
really appreciate your time.
Thank you.