Speaker 27: Hello everyone.
Today we will be talking about
system level experimentation.
I will be mainly discussing pricing
in food tech, but basically we will be
looking at some general ideas that can
be applied in many different areas of
food tech or in many different other.
Business applications as well.
So let's start first of all let's discuss
what is the task that we're trying to
solve and what is the actually goal
that is tried to achieve by pricing.
In food tech and what
does pricing mean at all?
So here we are talking
about delivery pricing.
That's the amount that users pay for
their orders to be delivered from
restaurant by couriers on some platform.
You probably know some platform,
you probably used some of them.
And, what are the goals that are
usually aimed at by different
pricing methodologies by
different optimization algorithms.
There are two, two types of goals.
They can be broadly split into
two different groups, like
short term and long term end.
Short term goals usually involve
total revenue optimization, which is
more or less local problem to solve.
While long term goals usually involve
such things as users', lifetime value
optimization and these are a bit complex.
In terms of modeling and in terms of
the way how this thing that is called
LTV or lifetime value can be estimated.
Thus it is a bit more
complex to optimized as well.
And it's a bit different area.
Usually it involves some more
like strategic decisions or
business development teams.
So today we'll be talking about mainly
the problem of short term revenue
optimization and what are the trade offs
that we have, so basically they are.
Again, if we consider only short
term revenue, they are quite trivial.
So if you increase delivery fee
too much, so if you charge too
much from users for delivery then
you have revenue growth per order.
But the number of orders declines.
Because because yeah it's obvious.
So if you, if your delivery fee decreases,
you have the opposite effect, which
means that basically if you imagine
that your delivery fee is too low or
too high, then you have non-optimal.
Settings that lead to negative
impact on your revenues, meaning that
somewhere in between there is sweet
spot where your revenue is optimal.
Meaning that it's the maximum that
it can be for the given environment.
This is the trade off that
we will be mainly discussing.
And one of the core concepts that
usually are looked at in that context
is elasticity, demand elasticity
which describes how much your.
Number of orders or con conversion from
from a user opening a session, a new
session into a user making an order
changes if you change your delivery fee.
So that relationship is as I already
mentioned, obviously, monotonically
decreasing, which which means that
the higher delivery fee you have the
lower is the number of orders that
are going to be made on your platform.
But locally, if you consider only small
changes, it can be usually approximated
quite well with, some linear function.
And yeah, obviously for large for
large changes in delivery fee, that
probably doesn't work very well.
And you will have probably some
non-linear, some convex dependency.
But for very small changes,
you can basically have.
Assume that what you are, what
you really need is just a single
number that describes the first
derivative of that dependency of your
demand on the average delivery fee.
So how can that be estimated?
There are two main ways that
we will be discussing now.
One is AB testing.
The other is switchback testing.
And there are some other ways some
parametric ways to, to estimate that, the
dependency, using some assumptions about
the model that describes your demand.
But today we will be just discussing.
Experiments way of doing this.
So what are the tests that
that I just mentioned, and
what is the main difference?
What is ab versus switchback?
AB is a very simple setup based
on simple user randomization.
You basically.
Split all users that you have
into two groups for one group.
You say that you don't change
anything for other group.
You increase your average
delivery fee in some way.
Actually, that's very important
question how you change your delivery
fee because that also obviously.
Affects the orders and
user behavior in general.
But for now, let's assume that you have
some change of delivery fee in average.
And for simplicity, you just
increase all order all orders
delivery price by the same amount,
which is equal to that average.
What is the main disadvantage of AB
testing in that setup is that users
are in reality, not independent.
So AB tests, pricing, AB tests
can work well if if users are,
independent from each other, meaning
that decisions of one users do not
affect the system for the other users.
But this is not the case because the
food tech is actually a quite complex
three side marketplace, which has also
restaurants which also has couriers.
And quite often the main
bottleneck is the supply side.
Not not the demand for
the growth of business.
And if you increase for some group
of users price, then obviously that
leads to less orders from that group.
Meaning that you have additional courier
capacity, excess courier capacity.
That is freed because of that
change for half of your users, which
means that it's actually easier
to find the co for other users.
And that means that you
actually unintentionally
improve experience for them.
You unintentionally, actually depends
on your pricing algorithm, but maybe
you even additionally decrease the
price for them based on the fact that
you take into account, for example,
how far the nearest courier is from the
restaurant from which a user is trying
to order which is not what we want.
We want a fair experiment, which
doesn't, take into account any additional
effects that really estimates the
impact only of the price change and
not anything else that comes together.
And for that case on the right
hand side of that slide in foot
Tech switchback experiments are.
Quite quite common.
So what is a switchback experiment?
Instead of splitting all users
into two groups you basically split
your timeline of the experiment.
You use two pricing algorithms alternately
and within each period of time.
You price all orders
using the same algorithms.
So either you increase price for all
orders or you don't don't do anything.
So in this example, I basically try
to highlight how that can look like.
You can split you, let's
say that your experiment.
Lasts for two days and you split your
48 hours of the experiment into 12
blocks each one four hours length.
And within each of them you basically
have either one or another setting.
What is the main question here
is obviously how to choose
a window size appropriately.
And here is the trade off between either
two noisy results or the opposite.
Some.
Effects that are obtained only because
of some like local seasonality within
that overall experiment time span.
So if that window size is too large
then you basically may end up with the.
Unreliable results that are
not related to your change.
If it is too small, then basically you
just will have too unstable and results
that are not related again, to your change
because your system didn't really react.
So how to solve actually
the first problem.
Sometimes what is done is.
To avoid that like local seasonality
within within a day, which is like
for example due to lunchtime or
something else you can flip the mode
for example during night when you have
an overall very low number of orders.
You can basically in that way switch
the order in which algorithms are
applied between one day and another.
And it is usually recommended to
conduct switch back, ex switch back
experiments for at least two weeks
so that each day can happen under.
Each day of week, can happen
under both modes with like
flipping somewhere in between.
How to evaluate results of a test, of an
AB test that is a like simple statistical
problem that ha has been solved.
A lot of times with many different
classical, statistical tests.
So you basically assume that under the new
hypothesis that there is no difference.
Then you build some statistic, then
you say, okay, is my new, if my new
hypothesis is true, then my statistics
should have some given distribution.
And if the.
Sample value that is computed based on my
actual experiment results is too large.
Then probably my new hypothesis is not
true, meaning that I have some non-trivial
impact from the change that I did.
And some some examples are on the site.
So some examples are to sample t-test
improve a little improvement over
it that allows to avoid assumption
about variance equality between two
different groups is a Welch test.
Also there is one weakness test,
permutation test, but they all
are doing approximately the same
thing that I just described.
And each one of them can be
applied to many different
characteristics of orders.
For example you can.
Test how the average order
size changes, how the revenues
or profits per order change.
You can test how the conversion
of users into order changes the
probability of a session to end up with
an order and and many other things.
And overall that will allow you to.
Have an understanding of how
the total revenue will change
if you roll out your change.
You roll out your price increase
or decrease or any other maybe
less trivial change of the pricing
algorithm for the whole user base.
So with switchback tests, it's a bit
more complex and results evaluation is
a problem that is known as the change
point problem in time series analysis.
So basically you need to.
Find to identify the times when the
distribution of of the orders or sessions
or any other objects that you link to
the final order that is being made.
Change in time and to to make a step back.
So in, in general switchback testing
allows you to pick up more than just the
change in averages compared to AB tests.
It allows you to, discover changes
in variance and changes in frequency
of the stochastic process as well.
Which is a better description of
the behavior that you may found
also, you may find also important.
And in that concrete case I have here a
small comment that even though we know
when the change is assumed to happen.
Because we know what are the windows
that we use in the switchback experiment.
First of all we don't know whether
that experiment is affecting the
metrics that, that we're interested in.
We don't know the size of the jump
it, if it will be statistically
significant, and we will discuss
how to estimate the threshold.
Which to consider to be
like the lower bound of a
statistically significant change.
And yeah, that's that's
basically the common framework
of of the change point problem.
So how to solve it switch
back, tests usually.
And the, the common approach to solving
them the change point problem in
switchback tests is based basically
on maintaining some window of
observations to compute some average.
And this average can be
either computed as a simple.
Moving average, meaning that
it's like just the simple regular
arithmetic average of the observations
within the sliding window.
Or you can also incorporate some
model like exponentially weighted
moving average or garch model to
also con compute that mean value.
And yeah, that's that's the approach.
So basically the main question, as I
already mentioned, is how to choose
that threshold for the decision about a
change point being discovered to be made.
And that threshold can be computed
with the following algorithm.
So you just choose some, recent
period of stable regime, meaning
that this is a period when you
did not make any interventions.
You did not change pricing.
You split it into windows.
It is recommended to split it
into windows of the same size.
You compute average per each window.
Also it is recommended to compute
it in the same way as you are going.
To compute it within the sliding
window that you are going to maintain.
And then you just compute pairwise
absolute differences between the
windows of that stable regime period
to basically have an estimation
of empirical distribution of those
differences if there are no interventions.
Then the approach is to choose
a quantile of that empirical
distribution as a threshold.
Usually it's like either a 0.95
quantile so that it's relatively
high to avoid some false alerts.
And the after you chose that threshold,
basically the change points that you
will discover based on your time series
of the incoming orders, for example.
Can be validated by against the
experiment periods, meaning that
you can just check whether the
regime changes that you find much.
The moments when the experiment
was flipping the pricing
algorithm that is used.
And the impact estimation, if you use
that algorithm, is also quite simple
and it's just the difference that
turned out to exceed that threshold.
And at the same time what is important
is that you can maintain like a
monitoring system over multiple
different characteristics of orders.
Which can also track absence of
any negative impacts produced
by your intervention produced
by your like experiment.
That's that's it.
That's basically everything
I wanted to tell.
Just to, to sum it up.
AB experiments do not work well in complex
systems because of interdependencies.
A better way to conduct
them is switchback testing.
And one of the, common views on
results estimation after you conducted
a test is a view from the change
point statistical time series problem
perspective, which basically allows you
to estimate the impact to validate your.
Experiment to estimate any
unexpected negative impacts as well.
And that's it.
Thanks thanks everyone.
I.