Hi, welcome.
Today I'm here to present.
Our Yay is Transforming enterprise
Data Pipelines with performance
efficiency, up to 70 to 85%.
AI innovation, the data
engineering workflow.
In the context of context today world
motivational intelligence is having
a major impact on enterprise data
pipelines and the data engineering
transformations are happening across the
entire data lifecycle from processing.
Myself, I'm with 15 years of experience
in data engineering with a focus on
cloud technologies and automation.
I consistently pioneered innovative
solutions so that bridge technology gaps
and deliver measurable business impact.
Also implementation of data
solutions that changed how
large scale data.
So back to the topic of the
enterprise data pipelines.
Yeah, it can detect the data patterns and
automate the connections between different
systems such as cloud, on-prem, APIs, et
cetera, drastically reducing the manual.
And also it's
clean.
Ations and we can implement the
faster and smarter a within enhanced
data governance and security.
So thereby giving the result in
the real world measurement top two
85% gain in terms of efficiency.
What is the data challenge
we have currently, right?
On a daily basis we are generating
2.5 country of data with this
amount of data under the different
challenges in handling the large volume
efficiency gain.
Human intervention.
We'll discuss more on this topic.
So the, if we delve into what kind of
challenges we're facing in terms of data.
So the first one is, the data silo and
fragmentation it is often spread across
multiple systems, making it difficult
to create a unified view, integrate and
process efficiently across the different
data sets because why It's a problem.
Data engineers spend huge amounts
of time just locating, extracting,
and normalizing the data.
The second, I would like to
highlight the data quality, right?
Most of the times it seems to be poor.
So the organizations struggled with
the missing or incomplete data,
such as the duplicates, inconsistent
formatting and also the sche.
Impacts
the
data
decisions.
We cannot make it more efficient, right?
In terms of business.
And also the complex orchestration
in terms of the transformation when
we do ETL or e LT jobs across the
dependencies, schedules, and environments.
Coordination most of times seems to
be tricky, so failures can cascade.
And the next one would be
the performance bottlenecks.
As data volume grow pipelines
need to scale horizontally.
Many legacy systems.
Most of the times it's poorly optimized.
The pipelines can't keep up.
And the last one could be, data
governance and compliance, right?
Keeping up with the data
policies such as GDPR, hipaa.
CCPA is hard.
So the challenges include tracking
the lineage, the hardback, world based
access control, and the classification
of the data in terms of sensitiveness.
So these are the different
challenges, right?
We facing.
Under solution how can we find it like in
this slide automated feature engineering.
So what is about, how it can
address the data challenge?
So this is an AI driven, game changer
in the data science and machine learning
pipeline because it uses machine
learning, heuristics and domain knowledge
to automatically generate, select,
and optimize the features from raw
data without much traditional way of.
Future engineering, what it's all about,
it's a process of transforming the
raw data into the meaningful inputs.
When I say inputs, it's more of a
features for a machine learning model.
Traditionally, this is manual time
consuming and highly dependent on
the expertise knowledge of domain.
So now comes.
Yay driven automated feature engineering
flips that by using algorithms to
analyze data types and its relationships,
generating the new features such as
ratios, time aggregates, encodings,
rank, and select the best
features, continuously optimize
features for model performance.
It's often powered by the famous
tools like feature tools by alter
maker autopilot, Google Auto, DataRobot,
to name few, and one of the key
techniques being employed in this
engineering in a more automated way.
The number one is a
deep feature synthesize.
DFS automatically builds the
features from relational dataset.
And the next is recursive transformation
creates the layered and higher level
features, embedding and encoding,
which is a technique used to
convert categorical or textual data.
Vector what the algorithm
can be used in the selection
using a correlation method,
mutual information or values
to drop low value features.
Moving on to the next
slide, which talks about.
Data cleansing, right?
How it can be employed in an intelligent
way compared to the traditional methods,
which will give us the improvements in
terms of detecting the, in the data.
And also we can implement the correction
of data in a more automated fashion
and how to recognize the patterns.
So it's a data cleansing,
intelligent data.
Cleaning is more of is a use of ai,
machine learning and advanced automation.
To clean, validate and enrich
or enhance the data are more
precisely and efficiently
compared to traditional methods.
Relying on static rules or manual
review, intelligent cleansing
adapts to the patterns, context, and
domain specific logic to ensure high
quality usable data for the different
purposes, such as analytics reporting
on obviously the machine learning.
So now comes the question when we say the
data cleansing, what makes it intelligent?
Traditional data cleansing involves
manual scripts of pixel logic, like
removing the duplicates, filling
in null values, and standardizing
format to name few on the other.
And intelligent data cleansing
uses a that learn and adapt.
We came across in the data cleansing, most
predominant one is the missing values.
So out intelligence can help right
predicts the missing values using the
ML models, such K or regression models.
And the next one would
be outlier detection.
Using statistical or yay models to flag
the anomalies, not just thresholds,
then the data normalization comes in.
Or can we intelligently cleanse
the data with respect to them
data, an normalization by
learning the patterns, right?
Intake to dates,
addresses, et cetera, and.
And the entity resolution using fuzzy
matching or the NLP to merge duplicates
such as you can say IBM COP versus
International Business machines.
And data enrichment plays
an important role, right?
Attributes by putting from external
sources like business databases
or geolocation we and improve the
reaching the data in an efficient way.
So what would be the next step?
When we successfully cleanse the data?
It's gonna be an interesting
topic for all us, right?
The entire, how we integrate, right?
Using the.
So it is a practice of combining machine
learning systems with DevOps principles
to streamline the lifecycle, right
development, deployment, monitoring,
and governance of models in production.
It off as a glue between data science
and engineering, turning experimental
models into a robust, scalable, and
continuously improving business systems.
So what?
It integrates the lifecycle.
We'll see Ops connects multiple workflows
such as data ingestion, versioning,
model training, and experimentation.
And validation.
And the next one would be the deployment.
CA CDL model monitoring performance, drift
retraining, and the feedback loops.
So these are all the, some workflows
where we can integrate, right?
The would be CD pipelines
for machine learning.
Yeah.
What is the purpose of it?
It can automate model testing,
validation, and deployments,
and the second component would be
model registry, so that can tracks,
versions, metadata, and lineage
of the different trained models.
And the third component would be
feature store, which can be a central
for consistent reusable features across
multiple trainings and inference.
Automated retraining triggers
based on data drift or model decay
monitoring tools and can be used for
checking the currency latency drift.
These are the different components of the
integration of a machine learnings model.
Moving on to predictive
quality monitoring.
Monitor which is critical.
Business.
So statistical modeling and sensor
data to detect patterns forecast
the deviations and identify quality
risks before they lead to defects or
failure in product or the process.
So what would be some of.
We can see reduced defects
can be one of the benefit.
So we can catch the issues
before final product is made.
A lower cost of quality.
We can prevent the scrap rework on
warranty claims and the real time
decision making, which is really
helpful to fix the issues in process
rather than postproduction and also.
Which in turn will maximize the
output while keeping the I standards.
And if there is a issue even in
production, the benefit would be having
a predictive monitoring would be the
root cause insights that we can identify
key variables affecting the quality and
thereby improve upon it in production
regulatory compliance, which is.
Organization whether it's a
retail, manufacturing, finance, or
healthcare, the is sensitive, right?
So father, it'll have an impact
Mentioning the consistent quality
for audits and certifications,
having a monitoring method, which is.
We can say as an example, right?
The predicting health or medical
condition, sepsis in real time.
Yeah, hospital users and EA model
trained on vitals plus labs data.
For example, we can say all rate WBC
count ate levels, so system predicts
sepsis, risk others before the
symptoms actually show in the body.
Since alerts to the car teams, they can do
or provide early antibiotics and fluids,
which in turn can reduce the
mortality rate by 20 to 30%.
That's cool, huh?
Moving on to data enrichment.
How can we drive.
So it uses intelligent algorithms
right to analyze existing data, detect
patterns undocumented with additional
attributes, either from external
sources, derived insights or automated
predictions to increase its quality and.
We can quickly see the different
types of data enrichment, right?
So first is raw data from the
legacy systems unstructured content
areed from the disparate enterprise
sources, and and enhance the insights
which can deliver 56% greater.
So these are the different types, right?
The one popular one would be the
texture enrichment using the natural
language processing, NLP, what it does
basically extract the such structured
data from unstructured text, right?
So the example would be pulling
the job titles and skills.
And image or video enrichment,
that is one of the typical type.
What the AI is doing is uses the
computer vision to label a classify
the media, and the best example would
be tagging the product photos with
the categories, colors, and objects.
And the next one would be geospatial.
We can it, it basically what it
does is adding the location based
data from GPS or address fields.
The typical example would be
attach weather, region risk,
or store proximity data.
So this is how yeah, is powering right.
So it's a smart system that
manages the history and the
evolution of digital artifacts.
We can say such as code data, models,
documents, everything requires
the version controlling, right?
But how can we attribute
using yay to automate?
Detect changes, suggest actions
and optimize collaborations across
multiple teams and pipelines.
So what are the few benefits of
having a intelligent version control?
So smaller collaboration, faster
conflict resolution, and to
detect the semantic conflicts.
And suggest the resolutions
intelligently also improves auditability.
Better traceability automatically
logs the model data and code lineage
vital for the regulated industries
such as finance and healthcare.
Also, this.
Version controlling in an intelligent way
improves the models in data management,
like how changes in data sets can be
tracked quickly and efficiently, or
the features impact the model accuracy
and also effectively supports the
rollback to known good configuration
if any issue occurs reproducibility.
The full experiment, tracking
and rerunning the pipelines with
the exact inputs and parameters,
and also with all these benefits, right?
It can save the time.
And also automation in an efficient way
like intelligent merging, auto, tagging
our versions, change summaries, et cetera.
So what are the different
popular tools available now in
enabling the intelligent version?
Control would be DVC for
the data on thel versioning.
YAML flow.
Is there GitHub copilot is the
AI systems Smart Code versioning.
Yep.
This is all about version control
and we can see about, case studies, right?
Which are implementing these mechanisms.
So yeah, one of the financial services
company that they have booster analyzed
the data analyst, the productivity by
37%, enabling the deeper market insights.
So by tailoring the intelligence
automatically delivered to
each team member based on their
specific role and also the
historical pattern of interactions.
And one of the healthcare provider
automated successfully could say 73% of
critical classifications while maintaining
the strict compliance standards.
And also they can see that one intelligent
classification and masking technologies
help them to complete the sensitive
data on the protection of patient
information and PHI and one of the.
These algorithms and mission
language process, the I value
market data to be presented 2.8
times faster, creating significant
advantage over the competitors.
So this time sensitive, revenue
driven insights deliver the ahead
of their competitors in the industry
directly impacting their results.
Quarterly they can see.
So these industry leaders in the
different segmentation I've seen
their data operations through
the strategic implementation of
these different AI techniques.
We talked about there are transformative
results included dramatically.
Acceleration.
And also reduce the operational costs.
And particularly for the finance and
healthcare businesses or industry,
they could see an enhanced compliance
regulatory across them industry.
So this conversational yay
assistant in a day to day life.
Everyone we'll be coming
across with the AI assistant.
It's a virtual agent powered by yay.
That interacts with the users like
us using the natural language.
Basically text our voice, which automates.
And provides informations and enables a
self service across the digital channels.
It mimics human conversation patterns
and often supports multi conversations,
context retention and personalization.
Yeah.
And one, are the core technologies
involved in these agents used as a.
Which basically understands
the user intent and entities
natural language generation.
The NLG crafts, meaningful
human-like responses.
Dial management manages a flow of
conversation and machine learning.
Lms, for example, the good
example would be GPT covers
adaptability and reasoning, right?
Speech to text to speech.
Converts a spoken input
output for wise assistance.
The APIs and the integrations
are quite popular.
Connects with the backend
systems, so CRMs and databases.
So this is about a assistant.
How can we interact with them efficiently?
Yeah.
With that it concludes this presentation.
Thank you all for joining this session.
Yeah.
Before we wind off lemme conclude.
With the data engineering how
it transforms, it's not just
about adapting new tools.
It's about modernizing the
workflows, I embracing the
automation and aligning with.
Business goals, right?
To create a scalable, agile,
and intelligent data foundation.
So I can provide the quick roadmap
style to transform these data
engineering practices effectively.
So adopt the modern data stack used
in ingestion, storage processing.
Load, transform, integrate
thel for intelligent workflows.
So which will help for any business
in auto detecting schema drift.
Predict pipeline failures, enrich
data intelligently, implement data
observability, create data pipelines
like production system, monitor the
freshness, accuracy, volume, lineage,
and alert for anomalies or downturn.
Use tools like they're quite popular.
Monte load data band and big
test and version, everything,
which is a critical one, right?
Data testing, data versioning,
and model tracking.
And wherever the automation use possible
can be effectively implemented using
the data ingestion, pipelines, even
data quality checks.
So the goal is to reduce a manual ops and
increase pipeline reliability, and finally
try to foster your DevOps culture, treat
data as a product, not as a byproduct.
Yeah.
With this this session concludes.