Speaker 5: Hello everyone and
thank you for joining this session.
My name is Anci DeMelo and I
work for Ford Motor Company.
My main focus is on taking machine
learning from lab into reliable
production system at Enterprise Scale.
Today I want to talk about a
journey Many of you are on.
Moving from experimentation to
enterprise by building scalable,
observable ML ops systems on GCP.
Over the past few years, we
have all seen the same pattern.
Teams can train impressive models
and notebooks or in isolated POC.
But when it comes time to run
those models reliably in production
24 by seven under real business
constraint, things get much harder.
The promise of ML driven
insights often collide with harsh
operational realities in this talk.
I will walk through the key production ml,
challenges that block enterprise value,
a practical end-to-end ML ops framework
on Google Cloud, how we use managed
CCP services like verex, ai, data flow,
cloud run cloud monitoring, and BigQuery.
Deployment patterns, observability
foundation and governance practices
that make ML systems reliable at scale.
My goal is that you leave
with a mental blueprint.
You can adapt in your organization,
whether you are just starting with
ML ops or trying to standardize
around a more robust pattern.
The production ML challenge.
Let's start with the reality.
Many of us live in.
Production ML is hard.
On this slide, I am highlighting
the core problem moving machine
learning from experimentation into
reliable, large scale production
remains one of the most critical
challenges organization face today.
We can build a great model, but
the infrastructure is complex.
Tooling is fragmented.
Models degrade silently.
Governance requirements
keep getting stricter.
I like to think of it this way.
In the lab, the model
is a star in production.
The system is a star.
You are no longer optimizing just
for the model accuracy, but for
availability, latency, cause.
Auditability and the ability
to evolve safely over time.
If we do not address this
operational realities, the
business will not feel sustained.
And the value for the ML initiatives,
no matter how good your offline
matrix look, will not be sufficed.
So let's break down the main barriers.
Core barriers.
On this slide, four core barriers that
repeatedly show up when enterprise try
to operationalize machine learning.
First, infrastructure complexity.
We are managing distributed system,
orchestrating workflows and maintaining
compute resources across development.
And production environments, it is easy to
end up with bespoke clusters, handcrafted
pipelines, and snowflake deployments
that are fragile and hard to debug.
Second fragmented tooling.
Many teams are stitching together
different tools for training, deployment,
monitoring, and governance, often with
every weak integration between them.
The result is duplicated work,
inconsistent practices and system
that are difficult to observe.
End to end.
Third, model degradation data, drift
concept drift, and feature queue silently.
Ero, model performance over time.
You might ship a model that looks
greatly initially, but six months
later, your input distribution labels
and your user behavior has shifted
and your business KPI start to suffer.
Finally, governance requirements.
Most enterprise must meet compliance
mandates, ensure auditability and
implement human oversight while
still maintaining enough operational
velocity to ship improvements.
Regulations around privacy, fairness,
and safety are only increasing,
and our ML system must be able to
prove what they did when and why.
The framework I will present is
designed specifically to address these
four barriers in a cohesive way, a
production grade ML ops framework on GCP.
Now, let's look at the
high level framework.
This talks cohesive
end-to-end system built on.
GCP platform and addresses
this challenges heads on.
The central idea here is instead of
building everything from scratch,
we compose managed services into our
integrated architecture that gives
us scalability, observability, and
governance out of the box at a high level.
The framework covers data ingestion
and the feature pipelines, model
training and experiment management.
Deployment patterns for batch,
real time and streaming workloads.
Production observability for
both models and infrastructure.
CICD, driven model deployment, governance,
compliance, and human oversight.
Each piece is designed to work with
others so we can standardize patterns
and reduce one-off bespoke solutions.
In the next few slides, I will walk
through the GCP service stack and
how it supports this framework,
GCP managed Service stack.
Here you see the core GCP services
we use as building blocks TEX ai.
This is our unified ML platform for
training, deploying, and managing models.
It gives us built-in experiment
tracking and pipeline orchestration,
so data scientists can focus on model
logic rather than plumbing data flow.
This is a managed service for
stream and batch processing.
We use it for real time
feature computation and for
orchestrating data pipelines.
Which is critical when you, your models
depend on fresh, consistent features.
Cloud run, this is serverless compute
for containerized model serving with
automatic scaling and pay per use pricing.
It lets us deploy inference services
that scale up under load and scale down.
When I did without managing servers
cloud monitoring ring, this is our
observability platform for matrix
logs, traces, and custom model
health indicators across the system.
It is a backbone for our
dashboard and alerts BigQuery.
This is our serverless data warehouse
used for feature engineering.
Model training data and prediction
logging at petabyte scale.
It is also where we do a lot
of offline analysis of model
performance and the drift.
By standardizing on this service
stack, we can give teams a clear,
opinionated path, you know where
to put data, where to train, where
to deploy, and where to monitor.
This is the clarity.
That reduces the friction and
the acceleration, adoption,
deployment patterns, architectural
trade off, selecting the right approach.
Different workload demand,
different deployment strategies.
And this slide illustrates the
key patterns and their trade-off.
Real time inference priorities.
Subsecond latency for immediate
decision making, fraud detection,
recommendation, personalized pricing.
Here we care deeply about
latency, percentiles
availability, and auto scaling.
Behavior Batch processing
optimizes throughout.
For the offline scoring, nightly,
nightly risk scores, weekly
churn prediction, monthly flow
forecasting latency is less critical.
But efficiency and reliability
at high volume matter a lot.
Streaming patterns set in between
balancing real-time responsiveness
with continuous analysis.
For example, continuously
updating risk scores at events.
As events arrive, your choice depends
on business constraints such as latency
requirements, prediction, volume, cost
tolerance, and operational complexity.
Each pattern uses GCP services
slightly differently, but because
we keep the same stack, we can
reuse governance, observability, and
deployment practices across all of them.
Let me make this more concrete
with a real automotive example,
a vehicle oil change prognostics.
Traditionally, we change engine
oil based on our mileage or time.
Like every 5,000 miles or six months.
That rule is simple, but it ignores how
the vehicle is actually used in reality.
Stop and go city.
Driving frequent short trips or towing
a trailer can degrade oil much faster.
Then high highway cruising.
With an ML driven prognostic system,
we stream telemetry from the vehicle.
Engine temperature profiles, RPM
patterns, trip duration, load
condition, driving environment, and
historical maintenance outcomes.
A model learns to predict the
remaining useful life of the oil for
each specific vehicle, rather than
applying one size fits all rule.
On Google Cloud that looks like this.
Data flow, ingest and aggregate
streaming sensor data.
BigQuery stores historical
trips and maintenance records.
Vertex AI trains models to
predict optimal oil change.
Window and Google Cloud
run host the real time.
Inference service that responds
when a driver starts a trip.
Cloud monitoring tracks both system
health and model outputs, so we can
see, for example, how many vehicles
are being flagged as change oil
soon, and how this correlates with
actual shop visits and engine health.
This is a great illustration of
why deployment patterns matter.
We are streaming.
Data source, realtime recommendation
to the driver and batch retraining jobs
that periodically refresh the model
as new maintenance outcomes arrive
Production observability foundation.
Now I want to zoom into
observability, which is absolutely
critical for production without
comprehensive observability.
Production machine learning
systems operate in darkness.
You might see business KPI degrading
and not know if the cause is
data drift, a bug in the feature
generation or infrastructure
issue, or change in user behavior.
A robust observability strategy
combines model level telemetry and
infrastructure level telemetry.
On the model side, we monitor things like
input distribution, output distribution,
and performance against ground truth when
labels arrive on the infrastructure side.
We monitor uptime, error rates, latency,
percentiles, and auto-scaling behavior.
The goal is complete visibility into
system health and performance, so we
can detect degradation early and respond
quickly, ideally before customers notice.
In the next two slide, I will
separate this two layers.
Model monitoring and infrastructure
telemetry model monitoring.
Detecting model degradation.
On this slide, we look at model
monitoring techniques we rely on in
production first, data drift detection.
We run statistical test comparing incoming
feature distribution against a training
baseline to identify population shifts
if the distribution of the key feature.
Shift significantly.
We know our model may be operating
out of regime in trained, and it was
trained on second feature skew analysis.
We monitor discrepancies between
training and serving feature values.
This helps catch pipeline inconsistencies
such as transformation that that was
applied offline but not online, or a bug
introduced in the new feature pipeline.
Third prediction, drift tracking.
We detect shifts in model output
distribution that may signal changing
behavior patterns or model stateness.
For example, if a classifies rate
suddenly changes or regresses output
range, compresses or explodes, that
is a signal worth investigating.
Finally, performance
degradation monitoring.
When label become available, we track
matrix like accuracy, precision recall,
and business KPIs against ground truth.
This closes the loop and connects
model behavior to actual outcome.
All of this signal feed into dashboard
and alerts so the team can respond
systematically rather than relying
on ad HO checks or user complaints.
If we go back to vehicle oil
change, prognostics example, model
monitoring becomes very tangible.
We monitor data drift by watching how the
distribution of driving patterns changes
over seasons and or between the region.
We track prediction drift by looking
at the proportion of vehicles
flagged for early oil change.
If that certainly spikes in one
fleet, it might signal a data
issue or model that has gone still.
When vehicles come in for services, we
compare the predicted remaining oil life
with actual inspection results and feed
that label data back into our performance
dashboard and retraining pipelines.
This kind of feedback loop is what
keeps a production prognostic system
trustworthy over time instead of
slowly degrading into a more expensive
version of fixed mileage route.
Infrastructure, elementary and
system health model monitoring
is only half the story.
The other half is infrastructure
level, observability surfaces,
operational issues that degrade user
experience regardless of model quality.
Using cloud monitoring, we watch matrix
such as target availability, uptime,
error rates, and service health across all
inference endpoints, latency thresholds,
response times to ensure we meet SLAs
for real-time workloads, auto-scaling
efficiency, scaling behavior resources,
utilization, and cost optimization.
Opportunities.
For example, a spike in P 95 latency
might indicate cold start network issues
or contention in shared dependency.
By looking at both model and
infrastructure telemetry,
we can quickly distinguish.
Model is wrong.
From system is slow and route
incidents to the right owners.
We saw the value of this setup clearly
in oil life, prognostics incident.
Our operational dashboard suddenly
showed that in one region the share
of vehicles flagged for change of
oil soon had almost doubled while
infrastructure metrics stayed healthy.
The daily evaluation pipeline with
joins prediction with service outcomes
confirmed the model had become
overly conservative there without
improving engine health results.
Drift plots revealed that driving
patterns had changed due to many
new short urban trips that were
underrepresented in the training data.
We raised an incident, retrained the
model on the new data and rolled it
out via our CICD pipeline watching
the dashboard as early change.
Recommendation dropped back to normal
levels while outcome stayed stable.
CICD Driven model deployment.
Next, let's talk about how we ship
models to production safely and
reputably production machine learning
requires the same rigor as software
engineering, versioning, and automated
testing, progressive rollouts and
quick rollout back capabilities.
A mature CICD pipeline ensures every
model deployment is reproducible,
auditable, and reversible.
The deployment pipeline
architecture on this slide shows
a progressive rollout strategy.
A typical flow looks like this,
training validation model, fit checks,
and cross validation to ensure the
candidate model is competitive.
Automated testing, unit test,
integration test, and performance test
on the model and the serving code.
Canary deployment, releasing a small
slice of traffic, often around 5%,
and intensive monitoring, progressive
low rollouts, expanding to five first,
then 25, then 50, and then a hundred of
traffic if health checks remain green.
Monitoring and rollback,
if we detect degradation.
Automated rules.
Or on-call engineers trigger a
fast rollback to previous version.
This progressive deployment strategy
minimizes risk for exposing new models
to increasing traffic volume while
continuously monitoring performance.
It allows team to move quickly
without gambling the entire
user experience on each release.
Governance, retraining
and human oversight.
Finally, we have
governance and compliance.
Which often make or break ML
initiatives in regulated environments.
Automated retraining pipelines keep
models fresh as data distribution evolve.
However, regulated environments
require human inner loop approval
gates to satisfy compliance mandates
and manage operational risk.
In the framework shown here, we
see scheduled retraining triggers.
An automated validation against
holdout dataset for low risk
updates that pass all checks.
We can auto approve and deploy
through our CI I CD pipeline.
For high risk changes, same
models impacting credit decision
or safety critical systems.
We route approvals to domain expert who
review performance fairness matrix and the
documentation before promoting the model
Governance controls, auditability
versioning, and rollback model versioning.
Immutable artifacts with semantic
versions linked to training, data code
and hyper parameters to reproducibility.
Governance controls, auditability
versioning, and rollback
governance controls support.
This processes model versioning.
Immutable artifacts for semantic version
linked to training, data code and
hyper parameters for reproducibility.
Audit logging, comprehensive
logs, capturing who deployed,
which model, when with what
approval, and what the outcome was.
Instant rollback, one click rollback to
previous model version with automated
traffic shifting and health verification.
Policy and enforcement automated checks to
ensure models meet fairness, privacy, and
security requirements before deployment.
This control ensure we cannot only
operate at scale, but also answer
tough questions for regulators,
auditors, and internal stakeholders.
Let me close by zooming back out.
This framework provides a comprehensive
battle tested approach to building
reliable, maintainable, and observable
machine learning system on Google Cloud.
By combining managed services with robust
observability governance and deployment
practices, organization can finally
bridge the gap between experimental
ML and reliable enterprise production.
If you are starting on this journey,
my suggestion is do not try to
be perfect at everything at once.
Pick one or two high value use cases,
standardize on a small ated service stack,
and invest early in observability and CICD
as those patents prove successful, scale
them out across more teams and domains.
Thank you so much for your time and
attention today, and thanks for the
conference for giving me this chance.