Hi my name is AK K with overall 18
years of IT experience specialized
in data engineering background.
And I most of the time work with data.
I would like to thank comp
42 Machine Learning 2025.
But giving me this opportunity
to speak in this conference.
So without much delay, let's
dive into AI unhinged fraud
detection in financial services.
This presentation explores the
implementation of an AI driven
fraud detection system at a
leading financial institution.
The solution integrates
diverse data sources.
Applies sophisticated machine learning
algorithms and also enables real-time
transaction analysis through a
comprehensive cloud-based architecture.
This transformation from traditional
rule-based detection to a adaptive
multi-layered framework, significantly
improved fraud prevention while
also enhancing customer experience.
Let's talk about the evolution
of financial fraud and also the
challenges that are being faced.
During evolution there
are four main challenges.
The first being high false fossil rates,
the second one being siloed data systems.
Third one being significant
detection delays.
And the last one being
customer experience impact.
These inefficiencies resulted in
annual fraud losses exceeding 25
million, and also deteriorating
customer satisfaction metrics.
According to research organizations
with siloed data systems, miss critical
connection patterns that could identify
27.4% of complex fraud scenarios,
Industry fraud landscape.
So there were around four areas where
you could see in this slide there
are four various areas where we have
focused for gathering some of the
metrics financial services, retail and
e-commerce, healthcare and government.
According to the Association of Certified
Fraud Examiners is EFE two in 2022
report to the nations organizations.
Lose an estimated 5% of revenue to fraud
each year, which translates to global
losses of approximately 4.7 trillion.
Financial services remain the most
targeted sector with the median
loss per case, reaching 1.5 million
and cases lasting an average
of 12 months before detection.
So you could see some of
the metrics that have been
highlighted across various areas.
Like annual fraud losses the median
loss per case, and what is the
average detection time, the areas
being financial services, retail and
e-commerce, healthcare and government,
Technical architecture, cloud
page, realtime analytics.
If you see here in this slide.
Around 1 67 0.3 milliseconds.
Average crossing time has been done
for the real time station engine.
And there were around 237
behavioral indicators analyzed
in machine learning pipeline.
And finally in the data integration
framework, there were around 17
disparate systems that were unified.
The solution leveraged cloud
infrastructure with 99.99% availability.
S. Elastic computing resources that could
scale from 5,230 to 25,004 70 transactions
per second during peak periods.
The A CFE report notes that organizations
implementing cloud-based analytics
solutions with real time monitoring.
Different fraud schemes and an
average of 33.2% faster than those
using on-premise legacy systems,
resulting in 47.8 lower media losses.
The data integration framework, there
were three main layers in this framework.
The first one is data
standardization layer.
The second one is Apache Kafka
Kafka Streaming, and the last
one being Data Lake Architecture.
The data integration framework unified
disparate systems including core
banking, credit card processing,
digital banking channels, and
customer relationship management.
This consolidation eliminated data
silos that previously concealed
critical fraud indicators.
Within the data standardization
layer we processed around 7,000 8 34
transactions per second with ETL pipelines
normalizing 14 different data formats
using 2 83 transformation rules and
maintaining 99.99 percentage accuracy
With the Apache Capish streaming we
deployed across 32 broker nodes with
42.7 millisecond average latency.
Managing 47 topic partitions
with 3.8 GB per second throughput
and 99.9% delivery guarantee.
Within the data lake architecture
we ingested close to 17.3 terabytes
daily while maintaining query response
times under 1.2 seconds for 98.7
percentage of analytical workloads
with 37 months of historical data.
The next slide talks about
machine learning pipeline.
There were four core areas the
first one being feature engineering.
The second one is a continuous retraining.
A third one we have ensemble modeling.
And last one being the annually detection.
So the ML pipeline represented the
analytical core of the fraud detection
system, leveraging advanced techniques
to identify suspicious patterns
across massive transaction volumes.
The ensemble modeling approach
combined supervised learning algorithms
with unsupervised techniques for
comprehensive detection capabilities.
There were around 2 37
behavioral indicators across
transaction characteristics.
User behaviors, device attributes,
and network patterns within
the continuous retraining.
We had got a feedback loops from
270 3004 29, confirmed fraud cases
monthly with updates every eight
hours in the ensemble model, in the
ensemble modeling around six supervised
learning algorithms with many times.
Boost showing superior performance
around 94.7% precision.
And lastly, in the anomaly detection,
the multi layer approach, identifying
sat statistical outliers across
1 47 dimensions simultaneously,
This slide highlights about
the real time decision engine
the real time decision engine.
Sorry.
Transformed analytical insights into
actionable fraud prevention through a
high performance architecture capable
of millisecond level decisions.
This performance level enabled realtime
intervention before funds left the
institution in 94.7% of fraudulent
attempts compared to just 2.3
percentage with the previous systems,
Implementation results and.
The system demonstrated
remarkable implements across
key performance indicators.
Customer satisfaction scores improved
by 22.3 points on a hundred point
scale with the percentage of customers
reporting transaction friction
declining from 28.32 7.1 percentage.
Net promoter score recovered from
33 to 58, significantly exceeding
the ministry average of 45.
The, there were some of the
numbers that you could see here
some of the key performance index,
like the fraud detection rate.
It was increased from 65.3 percentage
exceeding industry average of 86.7
percentage, and the fall positive rate
decreased from to 3.7 percentage better
than industry average of 18.2 percentage.
And the detection time is close to
3.2 seconds, which reduced from 27.4
hours, enabling intervention before
funds left in 94.3 percentage of cases.
And finally, the annual fraud
retention by 19.7 million.
That represents a 78.8 percentage
improvement with 4 7 4 37
percentage ROA in the first year.
Implementation challenges.
We have three main, three major areas
where we face some of the challenges.
The first being data quality issues.
Legacy infrastructure comprised
27 distinct systems with 14
different data formats 23 timestamp
conventions, and nine incompatible
transaction classification schemes.
Required 2 83 normalization rules
and 1 42 data quality checks to
achieve 99.9 percentage data accuracy.
And the other one is
the latency management.
Balancing processing time
with detection accuracy.
Required sophisticated parallel processing
across 1, 2 6 nodes, performing,
profiling identified 23 critical
bottleneck, reducing evaluation from four.
Milliseconds to 1 73 0.4 milliseconds
while also maintaining accuracy.
Model explainability regulatory
requirements across 17 jurisdictions
demanded clear justifications
for transaction declines.
Custom explainability framework
generated human readable explanations
with 97.3 percentage accuracy in
reflecting underlying model logic.
This slide highlights some of
the key technical innovations.
We have adaptive feature engineering.
We also have federated learning.
And the other one is grab
based network analysis.
In the adaptive feature engineering
we continuously generated new
features based on evolving
transaction patterns, evaluating.
70,000 4 23 potential indicators monthly.
And also identifying 37.2 significant
new features automatically
integrated into de detection modules.
Federated learning, enable
collaborative learning across
seven participating institutions.
Increasing fraud.
Example database from
two 70 3004 nine to 1.47.
While also maintaining strict data privacy
through secure multi-party computation.
Lastly, we have a graph based
network analysis within the
key technical innovations.
We have marked relationships between
four 7.2 million nodes connected by 83.7
million edges identifying 34 previously
undetected fraud rings involving one three
accounts and 12.3 million in attempted.
Fraudulent transactions,
Future directions.
There are four core areas
for the future directions.
The first one being behavioral
biometrics integration of typing
patterns, device handling and
interactions patterns to achieve 94.3
percentage accuracy in distribution.
Legitimate users from IM posters.
Also expected to detect 92.7
percentage of account takeover
attempts with just 0.37 false postures.
The second core area is
voice pattern analysis.
Natural language processing to
analyze 73 voice characteristics
for detecting social engineering
attempts in customer service channels
with 87.3 percentage identification
rate of social engineering attempts.
The third one being cross
channel correlation.
Enhanced detection of fraud patterns
spanning multiple channels by analyzing
transaction sequences across an
average of 3.7 different channels per
customer, identifying 42.7 percentage
more sophisticated fraud attempt.
And lastly, we have quantum
resistant crypto implementation
of NISG standardized algorithms,
including crystals, cyber, and.
Lithium to protect against
future quantum computing threats
to current encryption methods.
With this we have come to, and and for the
presentation this is what I have for a and
h fraud detection in financial services.
I would like to thank once again
the comp 42 machine learning.
Giving me this opportunity to connect
with you all and hope to see you
and talk you again in the future.
Thank you all.