Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42.
My name is, I'm a senior DevOps
consultant with over 15 years
of experience in IT industry.
My areas of expertise include
CICD automation, infrastructure
as code cloud native solutions,
and more recently governance and
security within DevOps workflows.
What I'm especially passionate about is
helping teams build pipelines that are
not just fast and automated, but also
secure and compliant from the start.
Today security can no longer be something
we bolt on at the end of development.
It's no longer enough to have a
manual reviews, static checklist,
or gates that delay delivery.
As of infrastructure, applications
and operations move faster,
powered by automation and cloud
native technologies and DevOps.
Security must move just as fast.
This is where security as code comes in.
Security as code means.
We input security principle and
control directly into the code
pipelines and infrastructure we deploy.
It's about automating trust.
It's about trading security, not as
an obstacle, but as an integrated,
continuous, and a measurable part of
the way we build and run technology.
Trey, I'm going to walk you through
why security of code is essential,
how we transform risk management
into proactive discipline, and how
organization that embrace it, not only
safer, they are faster, more resilient,
and better prepared for the future.
Today's rapidly evolving software
landscapes, security can no
longer be an afterthought.
Security as a code is revolutionizing
how we approach software security
by embedding it directly into
the continuous integration and
continuous deployment pipelines.
Instead of treating security as
a post development task, security
as a code automates checks.
For the security within every
phase of the development lifecycle,
ensuring vulnerabilities are
detected and addressed in real time.
This integration not only ensures
consistence, scalable security
practices across all stages of our
development, but only accelerate.
Involve innovation by eliminating
traditional security bottlenecks with
security as a code, teams can focus on
building features while maintaining a
robust security posture, all without
slowing down the deployment process.
The true power of security as a code
lies in its ability to offer a real time
visibility into a system security posture.
Enabling teams to proactively address
risk before they escalate by scaling
security alongside applications.
Security as a code ensures that
growing system can remain secure and
resilient In the world where speed
and agility are paramount, secure as
a code is in just a best practice.
It's essential enabler of fast,
secure, and efficient after delivery.
As we move forward, integrating
security into our deployment pipelines
is in just a choice, is the future
of a secure software delivery.
So what is the challenges that we have?
The challenges is the
speed versus security.
In today's fast-paced software
development, world speed is crucial.
Businesses demand quicker delivery
cycles to stay competitive, and teams
are under constant pressure to release
software faster than ever before.
However.
This agency often comes
at a cost security.
Traditional security approaches typically
implemented as an afterthought, and
at the end of development process
create significant bottleneck that
disrupts the flow of development and
slow down the release cycles was still.
Relying on manual and inconsistent
security practices can lead
to serious vulnerabilities
slipping through the cracks and
reaching production environments.
This compromises both the speed of
development and the safety of the product.
The challenge then is finding a
balance between the rapid delivery
and a robust security, ensuring that
innovation does not come at an expense
of safeguarding against the risk.
What is the impact of the security
of the code Organization that
successfully integrates security of a
code into their development Practices
are seeing remarkable results.
In fact, studies show that significant
percentage of organization that
mature dev six ops programs have
automated security frameworks directly
embedded into their CI ICD pipelines.
This not only enhances the security,
but also leads to a faster remediation
of critical vulnerabilities compared
to the traditional security approaches.
Security as a code drastically reduces
the time it takes to address an issue.
Enabling teams to fix vulnerabilities
before they escalate into the
bigger problems beyond quicker
remediation, security as a code
significantly improves the overall
security posture of an enterprise.
Those with a mature security support
practices report far fewer security
incidents and enhance compliances
outcomes, reducing risk across the board.
Additionally, by integrating the security
seamlessly into the development process,
organizations can accelerate delivery with
their compromising the security standards.
Team are able to deploy more frequently,
keeping up the demand for a rapid release
while maintaining a high level of safety.
So what's the theoretical foundation
of security of code as the heart
of security as a code lies a
foundation built on automation.
I. Consistency and an early integration.
One of the core principle of security
as a code is ous feedback, automated
security scans that provide developers
with the immediate actionable insights.
This approach ensures that security
is continuously monitored and
vulnerabilities are caught before
they can even become issues.
Additionally, security controls
are treated as a first class
artifacts, meaning they are codified.
Version control and subject to
peer review and rigorous testing.
Just like any other piece of code,
a key tenant of security as a code
is a shift left principle, which
most security integration earlier
in the development life cycle.
By addressing security from the
beginning, organizations can
avoid costly and time consuming
remediation later in the process.
Another foundational
element is immutability.
Security controls are defined
once and deployed consistency
across all environments, ensuring
a uniform security posture.
This is similar to the principle of
infrastructure code where automated
version control methodologies are
applied to a security allowing for a
greater consistency and reliability.
Researchers show that organization
embracing the immutable
security controls experience 94.
Percentage fewer security misconfiguration
across environments and reduce
compliances verification efforts
by as much just 78 percentage.
This data underscores how security
as a code can significantly
improve security posture while
reducing optional complexity.
What is the economics
of a shiftless security?
Let's talk about that.
The financial impact of
integrating security early in the
development process is undeniable.
Research reveals that vulnerabilities
directed during the design
phase cost an average of just
approximately $25 to remediate.
In contrast, this.
Costs skyrockets is over $5,000 during
the testing, and over approximately
$15,000 during the implementation and
a staggering cost of dollars 75,000
approximately during the production.
This creates a dramatic 3000.
Dollars fold 3000 times fold
differences in the remediation
costs between the earliest and
the latest stages of detection.
This tax contrast illustrates why
adopting shift left security and
burdening the security controls early.
The development lifecycle
makes not only technical sense,
but also a financial sense.
By identifying and addressing the
security issues during the design phase,
organizations can avoid escalating
costs, reduce the risk of breaches, and
ultimately save significant resources.
This financial case reinforce the
importance of prioritizing security
for our outset, making it a critical
component of a cost effective.
Efficient development strategy.
So let's talk about the implementation
in the Jenkins pipeline.
Implementing a security as a code
in the Jenkin pipelines involves
several key integrations that
helps automate and enforce security
throughout the development lifecycle.
First, security scanning integration
plays a crucial role by integrating
static application security.
Software COMPOSTION analysis,
dynamic application security
testing, and container scanning
stages into your Jenkins pipeline.
Using a declarative syntax,
security scans are automatically
triggered with every build.
Ensuring vulnerabilities
are identify early and next.
The policy as a code implementation
allows the teams to define
security vulnerabilities in
the declarative languages.
These policies verify configuration
and enforce compliances
automatically ensuring.
Security standards are consistently
applied across all the environments.
The secret management is also critical
By implementing a secure credential
storage and a retrieval mechanism, teams
can prevent exposure of a sensitive
information, ensuring that credentials are
security handled throughout the pipeline.
Finally, compliance verification is
integrated by defining compliance's
rules as a code, which are then
validated during the pipeline execution.
This ensures that every artifact passing
through the pipeline is compliant
with the necessary regulatory and
the security standards, offering a
realtime feedback to the developers
and mitigating the compliances risk.
So what's the security scanning benefits?
The security scanning benefits.
Integrating security scanning
tools into the Jenkins pipeline
can dramatically enhance an
organization's security posture.
Research shows that organizations
leveraging these tools identify
vulnerabilities 17 times faster than
those relying on a periodic manual.
Security reviews.
This period is crucial, especially
as a gap between the vulnerability,
discovery, and the active exploitation
continues to shrink in today's
rapidly evolving threat landscape.
By incorporating automated scans,
vulnerabilities can be detected
and remediated much easier.
By much earlier, significantly
reducing the risk of breaches.
The comprehensive coverage
is another major benefit.
By utilizing a combination of a
scanning approaches, our organization
gains robust protection against
a wide range of threat vectors.
Static application security
testing to identify.
An average of 26 potential vulnerabilities
per thousand lines of code, offering
a deep insight into the code quality
and the security f flos software.
COMPOSTION analysis scanners
focus at evaluating third party
dependencies, which make up around
80% of modern application code.
Ensuring that known vulnerabilities
in these components are
flagged before they cause harm.
Lastly, the container scanning
has proven to be highly effective
in preventing 60% of the security
incidents that stem from deploying uns
scanned or insecure container images.
This comprehensive approach ensures
that security is embedded throughout
the development pipeline, providing
defense against a wide variety of risk.
So what's the organizational
transformation on this?
The shift of a security as a code
doesn't just impact the technology.
It drives the organizational
transformation as well.
One of the most significant changes
is the breakdown of silos between
security and the development teams.
Study shows that 78 percentage or 79
percentage of organization reports
significantly improved collaborations
between these team resulting in a faster
delivery of a secure applications.
This collaboration is essential for
ensuring that security is integrated
seamlessly into every stage of the
development cycle, reducing the friction
and the accelerating time to the market.
Another critical shift is in
the security role evaluation.
I'm sorry.
So evolution security professionals are
transitioning from being gatekeepers to
enablers as an automation and a security
scanning take over manual reviews.
Security teams spend around 62%
less time on the manual task and
are able to focus 48% of most
strategic architecture planning.
This allows them to focus on a
proactive security measures, aligning
securities with the business goals.
In tandem, developers are gaining
ownership of the security with the
right tooling and training developers
are now solving 77 percentage of
security issues on their own without
needing to involve a security team.
This shift of culture empowers developers
to take responsibility for security
early in the development cycle.
Finally, organizations are seeing improved
metrics with over 75% of reduction.
In the meantime to remediate the
vulnerabilities, significantly
shrinking the windows of exposure
to the potential threats.
So what are the challenges on
the implementation on these?
While security as a code offer
numerous benefit, its implementation
is not without challenges.
Technical complexity is one of
the most significant hurdles.
Research shows that 78% of organization
face substantial technical obstacles.
In their DevSecOps journey.
With the complexity of tool integration
being the primary challenge, a key issue
is that only 36% of security tools offer
robust API capabilities, sustainable or
suitable for the C seamless integration
into the CICD pipelines, making it
a difficult to automate security
checks effectively and consistently.
Another critical challenge in the skill
gap, a striking 82% of organizations site.
Talent shortages as a major obstacle.
Effective security as a code
implementation requires an
expectance in the development,
security, and the automation.
A skillset that is often difficult to
find in the traditional roles without the
right talent organization struggles to
implement and maintain the security as a
code practices effectively for companies
in the highly regulated industries.
Government requirements present.
Another big challenge.
67% of these organizations
reports extend the timelines for
security as a code implementation.
During to compliance concerns, auditors
unfamiliar with the audit date or
automated security controls often
face difficulties in understanding
and validating these controls, which
can slow down the adoption process.
Lastly, cultural resistance is common.
71% of security professionally,
initially worried about that
automation will diminish their role.
While 68% of developer resist
adding extra pipeline steps,
fearing that it may slow down the
delivery, overcoming these cultural
barriers is crucial for a successful
implementation of so security as a code.
So let's talk about the adaption journey.
The journey of a security of a code
unfolds in several distinct phases,
each with its own set of challenges and
opportunities during the resistance phase.
The first 90 days team often questions the
business value of security as a code raise
concern about the technical complexity
and the fear that will be slowing down the
delivery cycles by up to 23 percentage.
In fact, 84% of organization
reports facing initial pushback.
This phase is crucial for addressing
concerns, demonstrating the value of
security as a code, and aligning the
stakeholders in an experimented phase
About 92, 180 days, teams begin to
implement the targeted pilots integrating
two to three baseline security tools.
These early efforts often result
in 41 percentage of detection, rate
of vulnerabilities with minimal
disruption and existing pipeline.
This stage is focused on testing,
learning, and refining the security
process before broader implementation
by the acceleration phase.
180 to 1 365 days.
Security as a core option expands
significantly with 65% of development
teams implementing compressive and
comprehensive security control, including
the S-A-S-D-D-A-S-D, and SCA tools.
This results in a 57% of reduction in
the critical vulnerability, showcasing
the power of security as a code in a
significantly improving security while
maintaining the development velocity.
Finally, in the optimization phase,
that is beyond the 365 days mark team
focus on streamlining the process
and reducing the inefficiency.
False positives drop by 60 percentage.
The organization established a matrix
dive and governance that shows a 79% of
improvement in overall security posture.
High performing organization
accelerate their journey
through three key strategies.
First, by established in the dedicated
center of excellence, which is
71% of successful organization.
Implement the second one by
investing in the robust developer
security training averaging around
32 hours annually per developer.
And the third by creating an incentive
programs that reward secure coding
practices with measurable results.
So what's the future of security as a code
Looking ahead, security as a code is PO
to evolve beyond its current practices.
Driving even greater security
automation under RES today, security
has a code implementation focus
on foundational practices like a
basic scanning integration, policy
enforcement, and the security
management within the CICD pipelines.
These foundational practices ensure
that security is embedded early and
continuously throughout the development
lifecycle, providing essential safeguard
of the applications as we move forward.
The evolution of a security code will
introduce more advanced practices such
as a security Charles engineering,
and a continuous verification in this
generation, security controls will undergo
a regular testing through SI simulated
attack within the pipeline, allowing
teams to assess and effectiveness of
the security measures in the real time.
This dynamic, proactive
approach will ensure.
Security is continuously validated and
reinforced as a part of development
cycle, not just the point of a deployment.
Looking even further into the
future, AI driven security automation
will transform and landscape.
Emerging technologies will enable
predictive vulnerability detection,
offering an early warnings before
the vulnerabilities even emerge
as well, and automated remediation
suggestions that allows the team to
quickly address potential risk content.
Context of our security policies will be
enforced across the entire development
lifecycle, ensuring that security measures
evolve dramatically, drastically, and
dynamically with the changing needs of
a application and the threat landscape.
As deployment environments grow increasing
complex and the threat landscape evolves,
the automation consistency and the
scalability offered by the security
as a code will become indispensable.
For organizations, this capability will
enable teams to maintain both security
and the agility, ensuring that software
delivery remains fast, reliable, and
safe, ever-changing digital world.
That should be all for now.
Thank you.