Hi everyone.
Greetings for the day.
Welcome to Con 42, machine Learning 2025.
Thanks for taking out the time
and joining me in this session.
I am Neha Hacker, an associate
solutions architect with AWS,
and I'm based out of London.
I predominantly work with financial
services and FinTech customers
within the UK to help them design and
optimize their architectures on AWS.
Today I'm here to talk about how
you can transform your customer
interactions into actionable insights
in near real time, whether it's
phone calls or chat conversations.
This solution helps you understand what
your customers are saying, how they are
feeling, and what topics matter the most.
Let's walk through a typical
day at a bank's call center.
It's 9:00 AM the morning starts
with an unexpected surgeon calls.
Is it a system issue, a new
policy causing confusion?
Without new real time
analytics, no one knows.
It is now 11:00 AM Multiple
customers are raising concerns.
Agents sense a pattern, but there's
no way to confirm or quantify the
trend and valuable time is lost.
It is now 2:00 PM The quality
team is manually reviewing
yesterday's interactions.
Critical customer feedback
from this morning won't be
analyzed until next evening.
It is now 4:00 PM management
reviews, daily metrics, showing
declining performance, but lacks
the insights to understand root
causes or take preventative action.
The result a day filled with
reactive decision making, missed
improvement opportunities.
Frustrated customers and agents
and lost business intelligence.
Now let's examine what happens when
you can't analyze your customer
interactions Every day, thousands
of customer interactions occur,
but most of this valuable feedback
remains unanalyzed and unutilized.
This creates significant delays
in identifying emerging issues,
allowing problems to multiply
before we can address them.
The result unnecessary costs from
handling preventable repeat calls,
each representing a customer issue
that could have been resolved earlier
without analysis of this conversations.
We miss crucial insights that could help
prevent future issues and improve service.
This isn't just about missing data,
it's about every frustrated customer,
every missed opportunity, and every
preventable problem that slips through
the cracks because we are flying blind.
So let's look at how this solution
can help solve this problem.
It creates complete visibility.
Remember those thousands of unanalyzed
conversations, our solution ensures
every interaction is captured.
And analyzed automatically.
No more blind spots, no
more missed insights.
It gives near real time intelligence.
Instead of waiting days to identify
issues, you'll know immediately what's
happening in your customer conversations.
Think of it as giving your team
superhuman listening abilities.
It does intelligent analysis.
Gone are the days of manual reviews.
Our AI engine automatically understands
what customers are talking about and how
they are feeling across every interaction.
From audio calls and chat support,
it provides predictive action.
This isn't just about faster analysis,
it's about getting ahead of issues.
You'll spot trends as they emerge,
not after they have become problems.
Transform from reactive to
proactive service, and it also
helps generate strategic insights.
Finally, all of this intelligence
feeds in, feeds directly
into your decision making.
Every customer conversation
becomes a source of strategic
insight for your business.
This isn't just an analytics tool, it's
a complete transformation in how you
understand and serve your customers.
In banking where every customer
interaction matters, this level of insight
creates a genuine competitive advantage.
Now, let's walk through how our solution
transforms customer conversations
into actionable intelligence.
It starts with capturing every
customer interaction, whether it's
voice calls from your contact center.
Or chat conversations
with your service team.
Every customer touchpoint is automatically
collected and securely stored.
This ensures we don't miss any
valuable customer feedback.
Next, our processing engine goes to work.
Voice calls are automatically
converted to text while chat
messages are extracted and stored.
This happens in near real time,
creating a unified format for
all customer interactions.
Think of it as translating every
customer conversation into a
language or analytics can understand.
This is where the intelligence happens.
Our AI engine analyzes every conversation.
What are the customers talking about?
How are they feeling?
What patterns are emerging?
This gives us deep insights into customer
needs and concerns as they happen.
Finally, we transform this
intelligence into action.
Through interactive dashboards
and reports your team scan spot
trends, instantly identify issues
early, make data-driven decisions.
The beauty of this
solution is its simplicity.
It's completely automated.
Running 24 by seven, taking every customer
interaction into business intelligence.
No manual processing, no sampling, no
delays, just continuous near real time
insights from every customer conversation.
Think of it as giving your organization
a super human, the ability to listen
to, understand, and act on every
customer interaction simultaneously.
Now, let's build this
architecture using AWS.
We begin with two types of customer
interactions, voice calls store
does, audio files, and Amazon S3 chat
conversations from your support team.
For voice calls, we have
built an automated pipeline.
When a new audio file lands in
S3, it triggers a Lambda function.
This transcribed Lambda function
calls Amazon transcribe.
The resulting transcript
is sowed in an S3 bucket.
Next, we handle both the
transcribed calls and chat logs.
Another S3 activates our
sentiment Lambda function.
This function leverages Amazon comprehend,
which goes beyond basic text analysis.
Comprehend understands banking context
automatically identifies key topics like
loan applications or account issues.
It detects customer sentiment
throughout the conversation, helping
you spot satisfaction trends.
It helps recognize patterns and
customer inquiries, helping you identify
emerging issues before they escalate.
The structured analysis is
then stored for further use.
Finally, we make all of these actionable
insights actionable and accessible.
Amazon QuickSight transforms this wealth
of data into interactive dashboards
that your teams can actually use.
It offers machine learning powered anomaly
detection to automatically flag unusual
patterns and customer interactions.
Business users can ask questions
in natural language, no technical
skills needed for deeper analysis,
we can use Athena to run SQL queries
directly on the data in the S3 bucket.
What's powerful about this
architecture is it is automatic
and then it is near real time.
From the moment a call lands
or a chat closes, the analysis
begins within minutes.
The insights are available
in your dashboards.
There's no manual processing,
no delays, and no sampling.
Every interaction is analyzed.
This solution gives you a
complete, near real time view
of your customer interactions.
You're not just handling
customer service anymore.
You're turning every customer conversation
into valuable business intelligence.
Imagine identifying trends and
issues before they become problems,
understanding customer sentiment
across thousands of interactions and
making data-driven decisions based
on actual customer conversations.
Now let's look at a quick live demo.
So I have created this
solution on AWS console.
You can also create it using
infrastructure as code.
So this is how AWS console looks like.
You'll be able to select the
region where you want to deploy
your workloads or your solutions.
So I have used London region here.
And here you'll be able to see
my recently visited AWS services.
You will also be able to navigate
to this by clicking on the links
here, or you'll be able to search a
service here and go to the service.
Or if you click these buttons, you'll be
able to navigate to AWS services as well.
So now let's look at S3.
So I have created an S3
bucket within the bucket.
I have created these
folders for audio files.
This is where I'm gonna upload
the audio file of a chat of a
conversation along with its metadata.
So I will just upload an audio file.
Here along with its metadata, JSON
file, and this is gonna upload in a
fraction of seconds as you can see.
Once this is done this event
triggers a lambda function.
Lambda function will now call Amazon
Transcribe, which is a transcription
service to convert speech to text.
So here, if you see there's a
transcription job in progress,
but in the interest of time, I'm
gonna show you how it looks like
once the transcription is done.
So here you'll be able to see
the employee details, customer
details, and the transcript.
This information will be
stored in another folder of S3
bucket called extracted files.
Once this is stored here in this
folder again, a lambda is triggered,
which calls Amazon comprehend
sentiment analysis and topic modeling.
So if you see, you'll be able to see
that topic modeling job is in progress.
So again, in the interest of
time, I'm gonna show you how this,
how the final output looks like.
So it looks like this here.
So you have employee Id name,
customer ID name, and account type.
You have the transcript.
And we have done a sentiment analysis
on this transcript using comprehend.
So it is negative sentiment.
Comprehend also gives you a score
such as here it is saying it is
99.5% sure that this conversation
has a negative sentiment to it.
And for topic modeling, again,
I have selected 10 topics to be
picked up by Amazon comprehend.
So you'll be able to see all of those
here and the related terms to each topic.
And if you scroll down, you'll
see the metadata of this file.
So all of this is against stored into
another bucket of S3 call combined.
So you have all of this here.
Now I am feeding all of this
data into Amazon QuickSight
to create visualizations.
So this, these visualizations could be
created based on your requirement but
for this demo, I have created few sample
visuals like the one on the screen.
The first one is distribution
of customer sentiment.
So we have gotten 61 customer
conversations, either through chat
messages or through audio calls.
So I'm showing the sentiment
across these conversations here.
Here you'll be able to see the sentiment
distribution across across the account
type, such as which account type has a
negative sentiment associated to it, or
a positive sentiment associated to it.
And topic analysis dashboards.
I'm gonna show the dominant
topic in customer conversations.
So if you have.
Topics such as account services for
which the customers are calling you
often, such as how do I open an account,
how do I close an account, et cetera.
You'll be able to look at these
dashboards to maybe create an FAQs
document so customers can help
themselves rather than calling the
agents at the banking call center.
This way you are reducing the
calls that can be that can
be self-served by customers.
And here in customer service performance,
I have created a visual which
shows the performance of an agent.
So if an agent has a con consistent
negative sentiment while talking
to customers, you'll be able to
put them on a training program.
So you're making the customer,
sub customer experience positive.
Some other features of QuickSight
are you'll be able to connect to
QuickSight from all of these data
sources listed on my screen here and,
you'll be able to create executive
summaries and data stories of these
dashboards, such as executive summary.
I'm gonna click here.
So this is how you can do it.
And for data stories you'll be
able to create or select visual.
So I'm gonna write, create Me
data story for negative sentiment.
Then I'm gonna add visuals.
I'm going to select
these two click on build.
So it's gonna build me a data story based
on the visuals that I have selected.
It takes a couple of minutes to run, okay?
So here you'll be able to change
the format styles of the story
based on your requirement.
And here it gives you a good introduction.
A story for each visual, and at
the end it also gives you things
like these and also a conclusion.
So I think it's good for the people who
are reporting to the leadership at the end
of a quarter or at the end of the month.
It's quite handy for them.
Now, let me explain why
our architecture's, modern
design makes it so powerful.
It.
Our solution is completely event driven,
which means when a new call recording
occurs or arrives in an S3 bucket,
it automatically triggers analysis.
When chat conversations end,
they immediately get processed.
No scheduling, no batching, no delays.
Think of it as having an incredibly
efficient assembly line that
starts working the moment.
New information arrives.
And being serverless transforms
how we deliver the solution.
There's no infrastructure for
you to manage or maintain.
The system automatically
scales with your volume.
Whether you're processing hundred
or thousands of conversations, you
only pay for actual processing time.
No idle resources.
And this architecture
delivers three key advantages.
Speed analysis starts instantly
when conversations end efficiency.
Resources are used only when
needed Cost effectiveness.
You only pay for what you process.
And what does it mean
to you as a business?
There's no capacity planning needed, no
infrastructure management, no upfront
cost, automatically scaling during busy
periods, and cost optimizations built in.
Built in these modern approaches ensure
you're always ready to handle customer
interactions, whether it's a quiet Sunday
morning or your busiest hour on a Monday.
And security is fundamental
to this architecture.
Let me show you how we protect
your customer data at every level.
Data protection.
Everything starts with
comprehensive data protection.
All customer data is stored in S3 and
which is automatically encrypted at rest.
Every transmission between
services is encrypted.
We use A-W-S-K-M-S for secure key
management give you, giving you complete
control over your encryption keys.
Access control.
We implement certain access controls.
Each component operates
with specific IAM roles.
Lambda functions have
precisely defined permissions.
No service has more access
than it absolutely needs.
Think of it as each component
having its own security badge.
With every specific access, right?
Compliance features for
banking compliance, transcribe
automatically identifies and can
redirect sensitive information.
Every action is logged in
CloudTrail for audit purposes.
We maintain continuous
compliance monitoring.
This ensures you know exactly what's
happening with your data at all times
and coming to infrastructure security.
At the infrastructure level,
services run in your VPC network
access is tightly controlled.
Continuous security monitoring alerts
you to any unusual activity, and
the beauty of this design is that
security isn't an afterthought.
It's built into every
component and interaction.
You get enterprise grade security
automatically helping you maintain
compliance while protecting your
customer's sensitive information.
Now let's wrap up what
we have covered today.
You have seen how this solution
automatically analyzes every customer
interaction, delivers near real
time insights for calls and chats.
Securely scales with your
needs, turns customer feedback
into actionable intelligence.
And in the demo, you have seen how this
works in practice from conversation
to insight in minutes, not taste.
And this isn't just about better
analytics, it is also about
understanding your customers better,
solving problems before they escalate,
making informed decisions based on.
Real data staying ahead in
competitive banking environment.
The question isn't whether you need
these insights, it's how quickly you
want to start benefiting from them.
Thanks for staying with me till here.
I would love to connect with
you, so please feel free to
connect with me on LinkedIn.
Thanks so much.
Bye.