Hi everyone.
Hope everyone is fine.
My name is Hari Esh Babo gdi, having
totally yourself experience in
enterprise workflow architecture with
a strong focus on AI powered process
optimization and robotic automation.
Currently I serve as architect where
I design, develop, and support the
intelligent workforce systems that
seamlessly integrate real time
decision making, artificial in
intelligence and end-to-end automation.
My work is centered around solving
the complex business problems and
enhancing the operational efficiency.
Throughout my career, I had the
privilege of collaborating with
several pioneering organizations.
Across the telecom, finance and
insurance sectors driving innovation
and digital transformation at scale.
So today I'm going to present
how multimodal AI is transforming
a patient centered healthcare.
Our multimodal AI framework is redefining
the landscape of modern healthcare by
inly, orchestrating, and integrating.
Wide spectrum of patient data
sources, including health, healthcare
records, variable devices, genomic
data, and patient reported outcomes.
By synthesizing these adverse
impact in real time, we empowering
with deep actionable insight.
That support precise, timely,
and personalized care decisions.
At the same time, our system elevates
administrative and cognitive burdens
on healthcare providers by automating
protein analysis and surfacing the
most relevant clinical information.
Ultimately, enhancing the outcomes while
optimizing the operational efficiency.
Multimodal approach.
So electronic healthcare records,
robust electric electronic health
records serve as the backbone of modern
healthcare analytics by consolidating
the comprehensive medical histories,
clinical nodes, and diagnostic
information, electronic healthcare
records provides the essential foundation
for advanced AI driven interpretation.
Clinical decision support systems.
And the second one is
patient reported outcomes.
Direct structured input from patient
captured subject to experiences such
as pain levels or emotional wellbeing.
Data that traditional clinical
metrics often overlook.
These insights empower clinicals to design
truly personalized care pathways based
on what matters most to the patients.
And the third one, as part of the
multimodal approach is genomic profiles.
So detailed genetic profiling enables
the application of precision medicine.
By identifying individual genetic
variations and biomarkers.
So clinicals can select highly targeted
therapies, improve treatment efficiency
and reduce adverse reactions, transform
the standard of care for complex diseases.
And the fourth one, as part
of the multimodal approach
is wearable sensor data.
So real time data from wearable devices
allows for continuous psychological
monitoring, including heart rate, sleep
patterns, physical activity, and more.
This ongoing stream of data fills
the gaps between the clinical
visits offering a dynamic view of
health trends and supporting early
strategies reduce your clinical burden.
So it reduces the 42% of
the documentation time.
So this will reduce the administrative
documentation workload, and it
saved like 3.5 hours, whatever this
hours saved these additional hours.
Clinical, the S can spend
with patients weekly.
The third one is 89% of the provider
satisfaction where clinicians
reporting improve work-life balance.
So enhance your patient engagement.
So there are four things we
will cover as part of the
enhance your patient engagement.
The first one is increase
participation and impressive.
87% of the patients are now actually
involved in their own healthcare, engaging
more deeply in treatment planning,
following Daily Health, opines and using
digital tools to track the wellness.
This behavioral shift is fostering
better health outcomes and stronger
adherence to the care plans satisfaction.
So patient experience
scores have a surge by 42%.
A clear indicator demographics including
age gaps, socioeconomic levels, and
clinical conditions, conforming the in
universal effectiveness of personalized
AI support supported interventions.
And the third one is better communication.
So healthcare professionals are now.
68% more time to the
tailored care conversations.
Moving beyond the generic advice
to meaningful and patient specific
discussions, these enables more informed
decisions and stronger provider patient.
And the fourth one is
stronger relationship.
93% of the patients report elevated
trust in their healthcare providers.
When AI driven insights are openly shared
and clearly explained, transparency
and personalization are providing
essential in building long-term, trusted
partnerships between the patients.
Under care teams,
as part of our AI framework, there
are uncovering hidden correlations.
First one is their own genomic analysis.
AI examines genetic variance
across patient populations, and
the second one is the pattern
detection, so system identifies.
To traditional analysis method.
And the third one is
treatment optimization.
Medications match to the generic
profiles for maximum efficiency, and
the fourth one is outcome improvement.
Reduce adverse events and
enhance treatment responses.
This is the early prediction
of the patient ation.
So how our AI framework is
predicting the patient's ation.
Our advanced AI protection system
identifies critical determination
signals up to 48 hours before
the conventional monitoring
issues providing a crucial time.
Advantage for the clinical intervention
by analyzing sub psychological pattern
changes across multiple parameters
Simultaneously, the system issues
detection rates of 65 to 96% compared to
the traditional monitoring, 10 to 65%,
dramatically improving patient outcomes.
In times since two scenarios,
optimized oncology care, so it
improves the quality of life.
Our advanced data driven approach leads
to the significant enhancements in
patient wellbeing by delivering precisely
calibrated treatments that align with
each clinical history genetic backup.
Lifestyle and ongoing health data.
By minimizing adverse effects and
maximizing therapeutic efficiency.
Patients experience better day-to-day
functionality, reduce the symptom
burden, and a greater sense of
control over their health journey.
Reduce the hospitalizations.
By predictive analytics,
continuous monitoring, and
timely clinical interventions.
Our AI driven care model significantly
lowers the risk of emergency
admissions by identifying the early
warning signs and addressing the
health issues before the xray.
We enable proactive care management
that minimizes the complications,
reduces the unnecessary hospital visits.
And enhances the overall healthcare
efficiency, ultimately improving
the both patient outcomes
and the cost effectiveness.
And the third one is
optimize treatment pathway.
So leveraging the power of artificial
intelligence, our system generated
tailored treatment protocols
that are dynamically aligned with
each patient's clinical profile.
Genetic makers, lifestyle
factors and realtime health data.
This physician driven approach ensures
that care plans are evidence-based, adapt
to and highly individualized, leading
to the foster recovery, fewer side
effects and improved treatment adherence.
The communication.
So how our AI framework is.
Bridging the communication gaps between
the specialist primary care and the
patients in terms of the specialist
access to the consistent, comprehensive
patient data across all touch points and
the primary care enhancing visibility
into the specialist recommendations
and treatment ISTs AI system that
translates complex medical data.
Into clear, actionable recommendations.
And the fourth one is the patient's
better understanding of the complex
medical decisions and treatment plans
from React two to React two care.
So how our AI framework is
using a reactive to proactive care.
The shift from reactive to proactive
care in healthcare is being
accelerated by artificial inte
intelligence and how these diseases
are ED prevented and how unmanaged.
So predictive analytics and early risk
identification, AI excels at analyzing
vast amount of patient data, including
healthcare records, imaging, genetics.
And real time biometric inputs.
For example, AI can detect sub progress
in the vital signs or behavior such
as a small but consistent changes in
respiration or sleep quality that may
indicate the nearly onset of conditions
like sepsis or hyper protection.
The personalized risk profiles and
targeted interventions, AI enables
the creation of personalized risk
profiles by integrating data from
various sources, including genetics,
lifestyle and environmental factors,
and management, and improved outcomes.
So studies have shown that.
The proactive care management targeting
AI identified at risk patients can
lead to the significant reductions
in preventable hospital admissions.
For instance, one intervention at OLA
Health resulted in 27% drop in potentially
preventable hospital admissions among
high risk patients identified by ai.
And realtime monitoring
and dynamic care plans.
Wearable and remote monitoring
devices feed continuous data into
the AI systems enabling realtime
assessment of the patient health.
AI can trigger alerts exist.
Care plans are prompt outreach
when detect deviation from
expected patterns such as missing.
Missing medications are reduced
refill activity, ensuring
timely support and intervention.
And the last one is operational
efficiency and provider cost.
It also automates the risk screening,
trash and documentation, freeing up
clinicals to focus on high value tasks
and the real world impact and.
Our comprehensive five year study
across 27 healthcare systems
reveals transformative improvements.
34% increase in clinical efficiency,
41% reduction in adverse events,
and 23% enhancement in patient
reported satisfaction scores
across diverse populations.
The future of the patient-centered care.
So personalized medicine means
treatment tailored to individual generic
profile preferences and circumstances.
The second one is continuous adoption
AI systems that learn and evolve
with each patient's health journey.
And third one is empower participation.
So patients as active partners
in healthcare decisions through
AI enhanced information.
And the fourth one is
healthcare transformation.
A new paradigm optimizing both
clinical outcomes and human experience.
Thank you.