Greetings to 100 presenter today in
today's software world, data mapping
and transformation plays a critical
role to illustrate this, imagine
two servers, one can understand w
English and the other W Spanish.
For them to communicate successfully,
there need to be a mechanism or
system in place that can translate the
data from one language to the other,
ensuring that each server can understand
process and respond appropriately.
Now, imagine if this mechanism was
cognitive functioning like a digital
human brain, such a system would not.
Just translate.
It would understand contest, intent,
and adapt dynamically, much like
a person would, a conversation.
This concept can be extended to
support human with disabilities, such
as those with hearing impairments
where the system could convert
speech into text in real time.
Individuals with.
Visual impairments where visual data could
be transformed into audio descriptions.
People with colorblindness where
colors can be translated into
patterns, labels, or other sensory
cue, a cognitive system, enhance this.
Even further by learning users
preferences, recognizing patterns, and
delivering information in a personalized,
accessible, and meaningful way.
Just like the servers that overcome
language barriers, through smart
transformation, cognitive systems can
bridge the accessibility gap, making
technology more inclusive for everyone.
In today's presentation, I'm going
to discuss about beyond barrier AI
powered cognitive support system
reshaping digital accessibility,
revealing how artificial intelligence
is transforming digital accessibility
through sum smart adaptive technologies
that work across multiple modalities.
By the way, I am Esna.
I work as a software engineer at MSR
Cosmos, serving multiple clients across
the United States with specialization
in various domains such as tax,
health insurance, and payroll.
Now, let me step into my presentation.
The accessibility imperative growing
demand organizations are rapidly
integrating digital accessibility as a
core requirement in their development
life cycles rather than an after talk.
More innovations required while
screen readers and keyboard
navigation have matured.
Cognitive accessibility tools
remain underdeveloped and
insufficient for diverse user needs.
Universal benefits.
Implementing accessible design principles
creates clear interactions, simplified
navigation and usability that benefits
every user regardless of ability.
Voice interaction, breakthrough natural
language processing, transformative
communication support, enabling users
with cognitive disability to navigate
digital interface through IQ two.
Voice commands improved outcomes.
Significant increase in successful
task completion rates while reducing
dependency on external learning
assistance and support adaptive
learning, sophisticated AI system.
Continuously refined performance
by analyzing interaction patterns
during real world usage, creating
personalized accessibility
experience, exceptional accuracy.
Purpose built voice reorganization
technology calibrated specifically
for diverse cognitive needs,
including speech variation and
alternative communication pattern
color optimization systems.
Reduced vis fat.
Clinical studies confirm a 47%
decrease in eye strain during
extended screen usage, particularly
beneficial for users who requires
prolonged digital engagement, rapid
personalization, sophisticated algorithms.
Build comprehensive user profiles within
two to three interactive sessions.
Continuously refining settings
has usage pattern evolve.
CNN based processing, advance
convolutional neural networks
analysis and adapt to individual
color perception patterns with
unprecedented accuracy and efficiency.
Enhance accessibility.
Revolutionary color mapping technique.
Deliver transformative
experience for users.
With opia and other color
vision deficiencies.
Adaptive layout technologies,
responsive interfaces, dynamic layout,
intelligently adapt based on individual
cognitive patterns, learning preferences
and interaction history to create
personalized experience, navigation
efficiency interface navigation
time reduced by up to 47% for users.
With cognitive differences dynamically
improving digital accessibility and
engagement, task completion, successful
task completion rates increased by 68%
across all cognitive ability levels,
eliminating traditional digital barriers.
Through intelligent design support
reduction interface related
support, tickets decreased by 73%.
Freeing resource, while empowering
user with greater independence
and digital confidence.
Educational impact content retention.
Educational applications, leveraging
AI powered cognitive support systems
demonstrate remarkable improvement
in information retention rates.
Students with cognitive
disabilities exhibits the 32%
increase in recall proficiencies
during assessment evaluation.
Engagement levels.
Adaptive content intelligently calibrated
to individual learning profile.
Significantly boost students'
engagement metrics, interactive
sessions, so increased the duration
while simultaneously reducing
frustration indicators across diverse
cognitive processing patterns.
Independent learning.
The technology substantially
reduce dependency on direct
instructure intervention.
Self-directed educational exploration
becomes increasingly accessible,
empowering learners across the entire
cognitive ability spectrum to progress
at personalized optimal rates.
Implementation metrics.
Task completion, about 42% substantial
increase in successful task completion
rates for users with cognitive
disabilities, enabling greater digital
independence support production.
68% dramatic decrease in
accessibility related support tickets.
Freeing resource while enhancing overall
user experience, user satisfaction,
it tripled positive feedback
metrics across diverse user groups
demonstrating significant improvement
on overall accessibility experience.
The unified approach to accessibility,
inclusive digital environments, creating
technology that empower user across all
cognitive and physical ability, spectrum
enhanced user interaction, seamlessly
intuitive experience that adapt to
individual cognitive processing pattern.
Reduced support, diff dependencies,
self-optimizing system that significantly
decrease reliance on external assistance,
AI driven personalization, machine
learning algorithms that continuously
evolve to match individual user needs.
Case study.
Healthcare portal the challenge.
A major regional healthcare
system struggled with low
patient portal adoption rates.
Users with cognitive disability
encountered frustrating navigating
navigation barriers and overwhelming
information density, preventing
essential healthcare management.
Yay, implementation.
The solution, integrated advanced
voice interaction contacts ava
adaptive layout and personalized
color optimization systems.
The AI continuously learned
from individual user patterns
to simplify interfaces and
prioritize relevant information.
This is portal engagement, serves 89%
among users with cognitive disabilities
support request plummeted by 64% while
medication adherence improved by 27
person through enhanced information,
accessibility and comprehension.
Implementation roadmap
assessment.
Contact comprehensive analysis of
existing accessibility barriers
and diverse user requirements.
Pinpoint strategic opportunity for
AI enhancement with maximum impact.
Technology selection, identify and
prioritize solution, specifically
tailored to cognitive accessibility needs,
strategic incorporate voice interaction,
color optimization, and adaptive layout
technologies, integration and testing.
Implement solution with continuous
involvement from user with varying
cognitive abilities, leveraging
real world feedback to refine
and optimize functionality.
Deployment and evolution rollout solutions
with robust performance monitoring
frameworks, enabling AI system to
continuously learn and adapt based on
authentic user interaction patterns.
Creating truly inclusive digital
experience access, diverse need.
Conduct comprehensive research
to identify specific cognitive
and accessibility requirements.
Implement smart solutions, integrate
yay powered adaptive technologies that
respond to individual user pattern.
Transform accessibility, deliver barrier,
free digital experience that empowers
users across all ability spectrums.