Speaker 11: Good morning.
Good afternoon, everyone.
Topic of ml, power machine learning
Power, iot, internet of Things
from warehouse data to production
intelligence in real time elevator pitch.
So first of all, lemme introduce myself.
I'm Dineh Ger working for Honeywell
Inte, and I work as a senior IT
manager in the supply chain management.
So I'm a digital supply chain IT man.
So let's go back to
the start on the topic.
So my class is better panicky,
so I'm hoping it'll work fine.
So real challenge comes up is that
today most industries does have,
the data is lot more collected.
But what now since data is there
installed in most of the ERP
systems, most of the machine learning
system, most of the databases.
What next?
Beyond data collections,
what's the real challenge?
So modern warehouses generate
multiple terabytes or gigabytes
of the operational data.
And basically every transaction when you
do it, it requires like load of data.
So every assume that if you do inventory
transactions, so it stores like at least
four or five record in the database.
And that means all those records
doesn't mean anything unless we really,
somebody needs to analyze it and figure
out what really needs to be happening.
Now, that's why I just state our
statement is raw data doesn't
equal actionable intelligence.
Road data doesn't mean anything unless
we somebody make a mean out of it.
So we are right now looking at a lot
more doing in the machine learnings.
A lot of studies are doing
in AI last three, four years.
There is a lot of AI and machine learnings
are coming up, but if you really think
about, say most of this AI and ML projects
are really still not live in the industry
because they are just still theoretical.
Most of them are still not really
far away from the industry.
So if you see about, say some of
the examples like we do have noisy
sensors, equipments is failing,
evolving the conditions, all the
stuffs are really the examples of
the sum of these like data failures
or accuracy failures in operations.
And I'm just going to talk about it.
How do we really think about it in
terms of the ML and how do the AI
and ML can help out in the line?
Okay.
Next one is why traditional machine
learning approaches fails in production?
That's a good question.
So traditional machine learnings generally
fails in the production we needs to be.
There are generally three reasons.
One is the data quality issues as
data has, there's a lot of data
in the system survey, but still we
do not have the data what we need.
And methodologies are today.
They're still getting out away
from the exact methodology, but
still they are still far away.
Second one is integration challenges.
So everyone know who's working in the
industry knows about integrations.
So integration are the
hard of the industries.
So assume there, say for any
data we capture from the.
The shop floor, your, like any
devices, any sensors, everything
requires indication to the databases.
Now you can argue about say,
Hey, why do we need a databases?
We're still in the world
of the study databases.
All the data is still
level lying behind there.
And of course there's a third
point is performance degradations.
So after, say over time there is
too much data, too much scenarios,
and humans are getting a lot more
intelligence, that means those data
performance is degrading over on time.
So let's go a little bit deeper
on the data quality issues.
So data quality issues
means sensors failed out.
Data is drifting.
I recently wrote an article on the
inventory drifting, so I'm assuming
that it's very similar route.
Say if you're talking about, say
I do have, the shop floor does
have the 10 pieces and I actually
may have the eight pieces.
So data is actually drifting from the
equipment ing network is a big things.
Of course environment interference, right?
So somewhere say, or most of
these computers or sensors
sometimes just fail out.
I've seen our industries where we do have
the robotics and things like robots are
trying to record all the transactions
and in certain, like some kind of
like heat wave comes up and then all
those one transaction per period out.
Integration challenges if you, most
of them are aware of say, APIs.
Everything is trying to be in,
there's a, this a world of APIs.
Rest APIs are a lot more common.
So how do we really, how will we
connect the two systems with the APIs?
And most product will claim that hey,
they a P, they're rest a P compatible.
But in reality, most cases, like
rest APIs are not really compatible.
Latency.
Big gaps is we are moving into
the cloud and that means if you're
talking about the everything is
moving in cloud, not on-prem, they
will be, they intend to be latency.
Internet is really speaking,
moving speeds, but still we will
have the latency match between the
components, synchronization issues.
It is similar to integration, I will say.
Of course handling.
Now on the third topic of the perform, if
you talk about the scenario moving so many
and of course things I say and productions
like human behavior, as system behavior,
quickly moving.
Topic is talking about the, from
the raw internet or things data,
raw IOT data to the ML features.
So if you talk about say, how do we really
get into the machine learning features
where we can really use the production.
So if you see on those one, right
there are like, say four techniques
that are mentioned out here, but
honestly, there could be like,
could be way more than that.
So I will really think about say
like simple examples on the first
technique is say the rolling windows.
Rolling windows means if you
talk about the lead times in the
industry, which is still static.
So I will say that, hey, why not drive
instead of making a static lead test, why
not making a lot more rolling windows?
And of course we need to be tracking
or tracking our say time times.
Since the event tracking, so recently
wrote an article on the time based
lead times, to be honest or time-based
cycle counting or physically, mentally,
that means what will happened there is
that hey, I started my counting of the
parts and since the last time I counted
parts was the current counting there.
And if I'm doing a adjustment in
systems, can I take a like a. Detect
both the events and say, find out,
hey, I can do an hour detection.
Hey, normally I do a 10 pieces
of manufacturing or backlash.
Can I do it like eight pieces?
This time I only did, I
did the only one piece.
So something really happened.
Either the demand drop so badly
or supply English too badly.
So that's where the hour detection
really help out in the machine learnings.
Time series importations.
Basically, this is more of say
standard of forecasting methodology.
I would normally call us, so even
most of the ML models are really
getting on the time series as well.
So it's pretty helpful, but still
I think it needs to be really.
Use very carefully.
It may be useful in defining all
the missing data so that in terms
of say I do have, the demand is
missing for the period number three,
how can I still find the demand for
that one without doing out, without
asking, or without guessing it out.
Even still, I've seen industry, a
lot of planners still guess the data.
Then of course, edge computings, which
means of course we need to increase our.
Power and so that we do have, the
latency is pretty low, and then
we can see the real time data.
And of course that's a pre, pre
really story of pre production,
handling the messiness, missing
data and sensor failures.
Of course, every day we see out a
data is missed out in the industry.
When I see water every month where my
support team comes up and they tell
me that, Hey, we do have the 10,000
transactions failed, and they say, why?
They say, one of my interface fail
out, or one of the census fail on
the production line, which then teams
record the data properly and then we,
it comes up like, Hey, what shall we do?
Spreadsheets on these production floors,
they are still, the network is really
messy, so it is going to be happening out.
So there are three techniques
which normally will be helpful.
I'm still not very confident there.
It is still, we are still there, but we
will be at point of time we'll be there.
One is time series awareness invitation.
Second is Multisensor fusion,
and third is metadata.
Features time series Awareness means
if there is a data missed out, least
we can make it somewhat guess and
somewhat real, more informed decisions.
We can at least do her some context.
Of course instead of the one sensor,
can we do it multiple sensors or can we
do that requires a lot of cost as well.
So that means the cost will increase.
And then of course metadata features.
So metta features will tell out, say with
signals, are there, or in terms of the
metadatas, how do we really find out?
Say this transaction does have
the four kinds of metadata.
Can we really break down?
Can we really do an informed decision?
So that will actually analyze, help us
analyze the patterns of the signals, as
well as equipment health issues as well.
Let's move the next one.
Next one is machine learning operator
ops, architecture for production.
So this is pretty interesting there.
So we need to be really looking
at revamping the productions.
So basically we need to be creating the
systems that will actually work at scale.
Current bio machine learning
algorithms are pretty theoretical.
They're still evolving, but they are not
at a scale that production can be using.
Now we, I will say at least
five few years behind it.
So in this case, if you say there are
three technologies, we are talking about
containerization and model serving.
And second one is model
versioning and deployment.
And third one is continuous monitoring.
So let's think about what each means
containerization and model serving means.
Have you heard all the microservices?
So microservices
architecture is pretty small.
It's pretty lean architecture.
That means we are also using
our NoSQL kind of concepts.
NoSQL means.
Databases are pretty lean.
They do not store these steady things.
They're like say pretty much storing only
the metadatas, and that means what happens
there is production doesn't need out.
Like a big core, big APIs.
And also in that cases latency becomes
really reduced because we can do the
similar research using the one of
the AI or vector DB methodology where
you can simple example is how instead
of doing the static matches, why not
use the cosign similarly distances.
So in that case, you can do
the fast latency and you can
do the high serviceability.
It may not be exact.
But if you think about life, say once,
at the end of the day, it may most of the
production data, even as long as it is
80, 90% accurate, it'll be good enough.
Since even in the today's production
one, we're seeing so much loss,
we hardly get like 50, 60%.
But even if this, apply this, and if
we gives my 80%, 90%, 95%, so it's
most like the microservice architecture
and where the dbs normally are not
looking for exact matches since
exact matches, means you'll have the.
High latency.
And of course, poison of traffics
will always try to be, plot the
graphs and you can just run the,
like a traditional methodology.
The quality in production is used
as scatter ploting, for example.
Or say fish one diagrams.
People can like, quality can
do it all those diagrams still.
And they can look at it
like, Hey, where's the scale?
Where's the really, the anoma out there?
And they can actually do it.
So then we call the containerization.
Even the most databases currently are
coming up as like they're containerized
databases for the sake of so that we
can be really sustainable as well as
the architecture is pretty smooth.
And of course there's a second
method as we talk about the
model versioning and deployment.
I will say this one is more of say
not for the production, but it's
again, the technologies are going in.
So that means we are looking for say a
lot more like metadata data tracking.
We do have the lot more versions, like
instead of having the single version,
we can have like multiple versions.
And so that if it needed out, say
if you something went wrong, we can
always go back, like a sensor field
on the floor can be really really bad.
Go back to the old version real quick.
Like version would be like as fast
as like a couple of minutes back.
So what that means that you don't,
you're not dependent on say something
about parallel the production.
You don't need to rebuild a pil it.
All you just do is just simply go
back and redeploy the old versions.
Which may be like as, as good as a
couple of minutes ago because as we
are talking about containerization, if
you say that latency is pretty low and
you say Microsoft service architecture,
that means database is pretty lean.
So reimbursing a rollback
becomes really fast.
Of course continuous monitoring.
That means as I'm just a big, not
a big fan of drifting, so I always
talk about, I say inventory drifting,
always talking about injections
are drifting sources are drifting.
So how do we really monitor it every day?
And that's where AI development, right?
Hey, can we manage the trips?
Can we find out the
different kind of others?
Can we do the automation trailers?
Can we do the say business tracking?
Say I do have this spreadsheet or
something came out on the floor.
Can I use that one?
So that will truly help
out all this stuff.
This is is ML ops architecture for
production is again, a suggestion.
It may not really, we are
still not there, so it will be,
it will take some more time.
So deployment strategies
that reduce the risk.
So there are, like, say, I
would say there are three or
four different types of there.
We should be doing shadow mode.
We should be doing candidate
deployment, AB testing, full rollouts.
Again, if you talk about say shadow modes
means you can just do the predictions
alongside the existing system with
no operational impact to the compare.
Current practices.
Basically you run the, run your
predictions that, hey this existing system
and this new systems, i'll just say, run
the current system in the side, and then
I'll just deploy the am new system on the
side and then say, can I just try to see
run parallel and see can I make it closer?
Can I do the can management
instead of doing the full one?
That means we do a small production,
small percentage, like a agile kind
of methodology where you do this in
chunks rather than doing the full.
And of course we can compare out the run
still the parallel for AB testing while
doing the testing run, still run the, both
the transaction, the system parallel, but
the test mode and let's try to be compare.
Both these systems, and of course
there are the waterfall, traditional
water methodology, full rollouts.
Instead of doing everything,
we just monitor everything.
Last one is pretty risky, but I will
say that generally I was, I would
be really a big supporter of the
shadow methodology or shadow model.
Can deployment a testing is still written.
I will say it's there but may
not be as much as possible.
Detection and retraining.
So once we define all the new methodology
is our what doesn't really end here.
So all these more models will be
really going to be degrading, right?
They will be running
out for time and time.
They'll more scenarios will come up.
Humans becomes intelligent, systems
become intelligence, and then
data will start acting again.
So if you've seen outline the industry
from the last 20 years and I'm
seeing our, every new tools comes
up and say, oh, this is the best.
And after a couple of
years, oh, it's not working.
So we always, it doesn't
mean that tool has changed.
It means that new scenarios has
been error and people have been
detected, people have been intelligent
and that's where is come up.
So that's why it's really
important that hey.
We have models keeps on getting
retrained and it keeps on.
That's a kind of another one.
Really edge versus cloud distributor
machine learning architecture.
So if you talk about the as inferences,
can we do the time critical operations
like the A ZV navigation, realtime
routing, and quality and avoidance.
Again, this is say ultra, this
architecture will be really going on the
very ultralow latency with, because of
the lightweight architecture and, but it
will be, of course, as soon as you go on
the very low latency and light lightweight
architecture, that means you will be
sacrificing the speed or in the accuracy,
sorry, speed will be extremely fast, but
it'll be really sacrificing the accuracy.
Compared with Cloud Inference, which
will be a lot more exact, but it
will be really speed will be, sorry.
Accuracy will be really not
be compromised, but speed
will be really compromised.
Cloud inference is more of say
current study databases, but as
will be a lot more like animal diet.
So I will be really say that it has to
be chosen between one or the other one.
If you talk about like a medical industry,
like I will choose the cloud one.
But if you're like say talking about like
production one for something really making
our, like I do have, my industry makes
a convey bats, so we may be going out in
the, and of course there's a third one is
like you can do a hybrid of both of them.
So you can say, okay, some something I
will do in the time critical operation
I'll do in the edge and which are like,
say really quality kind of operations need
and maybe using all the cloud inferences.
So most of them I just out
again, this is a curator.
We are still really researching
out how to, we really use this one
more and more production machine
learning application in action.
So well, that's like the three
different actions we talk about.
This is very interesting topic.
Predictive maintenance, demand
forecasting, inventory, organization,
intelligent beginner, R. So I'm
just really excited about talking
about these three things you
asked me about demand forecasting,
inventory opener, optimization
has been there in the industry.
It's not new.
If somebody tell me that a AI is new
in this work, no, this is not new.
All these algorithms already exist
in forecasting and organization
for like almost more than 10 years.
Intelligent picking and routings.
That's again, our industry is
really working really hard.
So my industry, for example, is a
export in the picking and routings.
So we do have say, palletizer.
What that does is it automatically
points the routes and automatically
find out most efficient routes.
So what that means that we, and we
optimize our conveyors repair factories.
So all you do is you on the
door dock door, you just put the
parts and route into the current
lane and current operations.
Now, predictive maintenance
is the one which is really
getting more, more popular.
And that means all these parameters
and sensors are still doing
in manuals in the industry.
But they are getting out a lot more.
That's where the AI is really helping out.
As machine learning models are really
helping out and those are actually
monitoring the parameters, giving us
the signals, and then we'll say, okay,
do we need to adjust this parameters?
Now, steroids is not doing the automation,
but this is again, ai, I would say
the doing animal detection and just
taking the decisions really fast.
Next one is responsible ai.
So AI is really growing really
fast, so we as a human being,
needs to be really responsible.
Basically we needs to be fair, we
need to be making design such a
model that they can be explainable
and we need to build trust.
So a lot of models, formulas
are really extremely complex.
They are still not easy for the simple
human behaviors to be understanding of.
So that's where say we need to
be reducing all the, so all the
models should be really fair.
So that you put up say they shouldn't be.
I'll say equally.
It's like a human behavior
even applies in the model.
In the model school model.
Explanatory.
Again.
I set out they needs to
be really simple still.
Current models, what we do have it, they
operation teams or for the operation
team, it's really difficult to understand.
I was just like working on
like a safety staff home.
And when I developed my formula, it
was really complex and then finally I
just tried to explain operation team.
I was struggled out.
So what I ended up doing is simplify
the formula in such a way that any
Excel even completed easily so that
operation could understand as soon as
I did the same formula Rewr in the such
a methodology breaking down formulas,
even though it is five steps or patients
could understand it really well.
So that's where all
these models are still.
Really how large needs to make
sure that, how do we really openly
understand it, like the work on the
planning industry planning methodology,
planning engine are still difficult to
understand, but again, it's going there.
And of course, regress validation.
That means we need to be
really testing really well.
We needs to be doing a lot more
shadow, a lot more AB testing, a
lot more canary deployments instead
of doing the full deployment.
Pull deployments means you'll be either
the recipe of failure that's going on
the, that's why I say that, like in
terms of the IT product management,
we talk about say waterfall metal
almost getting over a lot more as well.
A lot more people say, Hey, I need D one.
I want to see this.
They don't really care.
Say what will be the system down the
line, but they want to see day one.
Day one every day.
Now, as I say about the edge deployment
means you do have the ultra low model.
Basically.
It's a lot more.
Speed is really fast.
Agency really, actually,
our LA agency is pretty low.
So three things on that.
One, we do should be
doing the quantitation.
We do should be looking at the parameters.
We should be looking at the knowledge
distillation so that anyone can really
those whatever we do, the whatever models
we use it or so their families are really
accurate and blockchain can understand it.
So all these one are basically really
good in terms of theory as well
as in terms of the practical even.
We start doing all the As development
only for critical operations.
It makes our life so much
easier, and of course the, it'll
be lot more faster decisions
in trends reshaping, warehouse.
That's exciting as well.
So if you see about say first
one is auto machine learning and
automatic feature engineering.
That means all the operation
teams are really looking for
the rapid deployment cycles.
They don't care about say, gone are
the days where the system where the
businesses say that, hey you do have 12
months, 18 months for deployment now, like
two months, three months, weeks, even.
Some cases you're asking for days.
Multimodal learning and sensor fusions.
Instead of the having the one model,
can we use the multiple models together?
Can we compare the data
and which model is better?
Can we have the multiple type
of sensor sensors instead of the
having the one type of sensor?
Can we have the like R sensors and
IOT sensors or environ sensors?
So that we can compare our say
different kind of the models
together, and then we can have the
better operational restraining.
And then of course we can
have the another detection.
And so then we apply our
time series to find the data.
5G enabled real time intelligence.
So 5G is really another
one shaping the world.
Like anything.
So now we don't need our like, say.
A lot more wifi, internet stuff that
everywhere there is a 5G available.
And that means you don't need
to be doing all the vast,
massive networking investments.
So we can use our, the
latency becomes really low.
And then of course the network slicing.
And for the machine learning
workloads enables automation,
anonymous vehicle coordination.
That means your databases a lot
more getting outta the autonomous.
So that means if not talking
about milliseconds, we are
talking about sub milliseconds or
really go even further than that.
So this isn't, are really getting
faster with this one as well,
because data is getting real times.
So it's not like we are talking
about data like a few hours ago.
Batch processing, all the
stuffs are not really there.
Sustainable and machine
learning and green computing.
Of course, we need to make
sure that whatever we do in our
models, they are energy efficien.
All the carbon awareness shield are there.
Hardwares are really optimized.
And that's where say we are talking
about the edge computing is really
shaping the world where you do
the models are pretty lightweight.
That means we don't need out
lot of commend, lot of resources
out and then we sure that light
lot more like workload manager.
So assuming that, say, just take out
the example, one of the biggest company
that I was really looking at it, the
e-commerce program was having service
and 20,000 service means who does that?
So what are the means that they do have
20,000 servers, but all the really lot
of them are the backup servers to make
sure that everything is optimized.
But all those 20,000 were really low
low capacity, low, pretty much in
terms of the schedules and everything.
They are really optimized.
Excuse me.
Lessons from the field.
What separates winner
from the field project?
So field product means if you're
talking about again, or same or say
full deployment, we should be definitely
avoiding out, do it in this lesson Pieces.
We should be doing the we, instead
of doing our report deployment,
do Azure methodology, which
means incremental deployments.
We should be doing a lot more
cross-functional integration.
That means we should be looking
at the lot more teams together.
So instead of doing one team, doing
all the only work, all the teams
needs should be working together,
finding out with what works best.
And then of course, the upfront
we need to do the machine
learning operation, investment.
Otherwise, what will happen
that if you don't need machine
learning operation, investment.
You you'll be this
before failure basically.
Main idea on that one is the
production, engineering, testing,
everything can be automated.
Otherwise, what will happen there is that
you taking the people out of the floor
and then trying to redo something and then
people will be not be able to testing out.
Pattern should be awarding out.
Big banks, boss, big banks for
deployment should be over out.
We shouldn't be doing the silo teams.
We shouldn't be not doing all
the algorithms we shouldn't be.
We should be away from the
without any monitoring.
Monitoring is must.
I would say reactive
approach to the issues.
I will be not a big fan of reactive, but
I would say reactive as well as proactive,
both of them, and may proactive as well.
Far
from insights to be implementations.
So if you talk about IC still,
production machine learning is not
same as academic and machine learnings.
Academic is a lot more theoretical.
Production is a lot more practical.
Production doesn't need
a lot more big formulas.
They're really looking at the symbol
where the people can understand it.
Start small scales, more smart, basically.
Same repeating or the methodology.
Should be at people, process, technology,
all feeling should be prepared together.
And of course, architecture matters.
It's a normal no brainer.
Next steps, if you talk about it, assess.
Assess your current methods, current
machine learning, maturity level, and.
So pilot is really, they
always go with 80 20 rule.
So 80 20 rule means high value
use case should be pilot first.
They're investing in machine learning
operation, infrastructure early,
and of course cross-functional teams
are a lot more people are doing it.
And deployment strategies should be
really made with the so safety gate.
So that's the takeaways from,
and thank you so much everyone.
That's all my side today and bye.