Hello everyone.
My name is Alex.
I'm head of Ops and DevOps at Z Coder.
I also double l de and in general, what I
like to call they have asked me anything.
It's a startup, so you
have to wear many hats.
Today I will be talking with you about
AI coding agents how you can code
them, how you can use them, how you
can leverage them to make your everyday
life easier and be more productive Now.
Recently you might have come
across headlines like this where
in this case, mark Zuckerberg said,
mentioned in his interview that
AI will soon replace developers.
And in this particular case, he even
went as far as saying that mid-level
engineers will be replaced pretty soon.
Now there are two main sort of sources.
For those headlines.
First of all, of course, new models.
New AI or LLM models are
coming up being released.
For example here the recent release
from Google of Gemini 2.5 Pro,
and they of course show that new
they are new model beats all the
previous models on the benchmarks
which is always the case, right?
Now for us for coordin agents in
particular, we are mostly interested
in the three code related benchmarks,
which I highlighted here in red.
Now the problem with benchmarks is
while it is good to see that models
are becoming better on them it's a good
way to compare models with each other.
It's all those benchmarks are not always.
Transferable one-to-one to the real world.
What I mean by that is for example, if
we look at either gl the main idea behind
this data set is that the LLM or AI is
presented with a list of tasks and it
essentially needs to create a function.
It create needs to create a class or
method that would fulfill that task.
So essentially it's one or
single file modification.
However reality of software
development is not that simple, right?
So usually you need to modify at
least multiple files inside the
repository, or sometimes you might
even need to modify files across
multiple repositories at the same time.
So basically, even though there are
improvements in the quality of AI of LLM.
They're not always transferable
one-to-one on in the real life world.
So you might not see as big
of an improvement as you
would see on the benchmarks.
So that's one source of those headlines.
And the second one is AI
agents, which is the main topic
of the day of today's stock.
So basically, we'll, we will
first cover what is AI agent.
Then we'll go through a live
coding session where we'll see
how we can, how you can create the
coding agent on your own right.
And you will see how they can
also interact with each other
for multi agent collaboration.
And then briefly talk about what is
next for the developers, what all those.
New improvements, what all
those new changes mean for the
future of software development.
So yeah, basically by the end of the talk,
we will potentially build an ai, which
might probably replace you or maybe not.
We'll see.
So first things first let's
define what is AI agent.
Now, AI agent can be defined as a software
that performs tasks on behalf of a user.
And you might say here that
any software performs tasks
on behalf of the user, right?
Especially if we're talking about
current generation of coding systems.
And they essentially perform tasks
of code generation on your behalf.
They perform tasks of documentation
generation on your behalf.
And, you can just essentially tap, tap
tab get a thousand slice of code in a
couple minutes, and then spend some time
on the bag in that the bag in that code.
Now the main difference between AI
agents and classic software is that AI
agents follow multiple design patterns
which you can see here on the side.
So first of all they have
what's called tool use.
So they can basically, can have
access to the tools, to the
list of tools at a disposal.
And those tools could
be pretty much anything.
It could be doing the web search, it
could be accessing some local file system.
It could be accessing
restful APIs and so on.
So basically any tool LLM can
use to gather information to
perform actions and so on.
It can use it.
Then of course, AI agents
can also do some planning.
So they don't just blindly perform
the task, perform code generation.
They can first come up with a plan on how
to tackle these specific task at hand.
And they then will follow that plan.
They can also reflect on their own
work, on their own planning step
on their, output or they can also
reflect on work of other agents.
And this is where we come to
this fourth design pattern, which
is multi-agent collaboration.
So basically you can have multiple agents
working together towards the same goal.
And those could be either working
together as in colleagues where they
for example, one agent, performs half
of the task, and then the other agent
performs the second half of the task.
Or they can also critique each other.
So for example, you could have one
agent, which critiques the work of the
second agent, and then the second agent
iterates on this critique and so on.
But basically yeah, those patterns are
what differentiates AI agents from the
typical or from the classical software.
And you can think about AI agents like
a, I guess a Roomba vacuum cleaner.
The software itself on the vacuum cleaner
is an AI agent, however, to perform.
To perform the task of
clean the house, right?
It needs also multi some
things on top of that.
So just software is not enough.
The vacuum cleaners, they also have
tools, so that could be brushes that
could be wheels to move around and so on.
They can also do playing and for
some reason charge GPT thinks that
robot vacuum cleaners are moving
this weirdly shaped pattern.
But it is AI being a AI, there is no
steel yet multi agent collaboration unless
you count these for the vacuum cleaners.
But maybe in the future they will be
able to also talk with each other.
They will be able to talk with the
other home appliances and so on.
Yeah, basically now.
Why is this important?
To answer that question, let's first
talk about what we as developers spend
our time on during the work hours.
And I will give you a few
seconds to think about this.
Spoiler alert, it's not drinking
coffee in reality, and this study was
done actually 10 years ago, however,
I don't think much has changed.
Since then now in reality 70% of the
time developers spend on understanding
that could be understanding
the code base, understanding
the requirements understanding.
Tasks and so on.
So basically most of the time developers
are not spending on writing the code.
They are spending on understanding.
Now if we juxtapose this with the
adjunct design patterns, which we
just discussed, we will see that,
for example, for the tool use.
We of course, have editing.
We need to use tools to edit the code.
We need to use tools when we are outside
of ID and on Googling something and so on.
And of course for UI interactions,
we also need to use tools.
Then of course for planning we need
to understand the task at hand.
We need to understand the requirements.
Because otherwise it's hard to
do planning of the work, right?
There is also reflection.
Of course, we can, we don't just blindly.
Follow the requirements.
Don't just blindly follow the task.
I hope we also can think about
different ways, solve the task.
We can think about different
ways to tackle the problem.
And so on.
And of course we don't
usually work in a vacuum.
We have colleagues with whom we can
work together, we can collaborate.
And this is where basically
multi collaboration comes in.
And of course, for that follow that
you'll need to have a good understanding.
You probably also need to
navigate the code base.
You need to spend something
outside of ID in Slack or whatever.
But basically all of the design print
principles can be directly juxtaposed
with what developers do in their free,
or, sorry, not free, but of course
what they do in their work time.
Now, with that let me switch the sides
and let's finally do some coding.
All of the code, which I will
be showing today, is available
on this, repository over here.
I done Q code or the link below.
And the way I structure the coding session
is I will go through several stages and
hopefully not those stages but basically
I will go through several stages.
We'll start with a simple
baseline where we won't have
any agenda egen patterns at all.
And then we will slowly build on top of,
on top of the previous stages to come to
the final step of multi-agent multi-agent
system, which will work together to,
to fulfill the task on our behalf.
So let me switch here to the to
the Jupiter notebook I have here.
Let's see.
Alright,
so let's start with our baseline, right?
And if you used AI in any capacity,
if you used any LLM, like open AI or
cloudy you probably have experienced
something similar to what we will
see right now in the baseline.
But basically, and again, if you are not
familiar with Python it's not a problem.
All of the code is pretty simple.
Pretty simple to it.
And, pretty sim pretty easy to understand.
Now, over here on this baseline basically
what I do is I will be using the most
recent model from Open ai, namely GT 4.1.
And basically over here, I'm just
defining the code to query the model so
that this function will send the input
from us, from user to the LLM and we
will get the response from GPT-4 0.1.
Now, the problem with the L LMS
is that they are leaving the,
somewhere in the cloud and they
don't have access to real life world.
What I mean by that is for example,
they can't give us the response time for
Google or for any website for that matter.
So it does try to be helpful, and
I think it probably will, yeah.
Does give us some command to run to GI to
get the answer, unfortunately on its own.
The LLM in this case, GPT-4
0.1, isn't able to help.
The same goes with the access
to local local machine.
This case in that it doesn't
have access to my local computer.
Again, it does try to help
me with providing some batch
commands to, to list the packages.
Unfortunately even for those simple
tasks, it can't really help me.
And, we are especially, we are going
to some more sophisticated tasks that
require, access to local to local machine.
For example, Iranian dock image.
The LLM would fail here and
wouldn't be very helpful.
And the same goes within
new and updated knowledge.
Now, in this case the GPT-4 0.1
has a more UpToDate knowledge.
If you try the same query with the
older model, like T four O, for example,
it wouldn't know anything at all
about Python three 14 in this case.
Because the knowledge cut off for
the model was, I think in June, 2024.
It does have some knowledge
about Python three 14.
And it does provide some
links for us as well.
However still the knowledge
is not up to date, right?
It is 2025, my 2025 right now.
And basically the gap between them.
Alumni knowledge and real life world
is essentially one year now and a
lot has has happened since then.
So yeah, basically, even though it does
try to be helpful by giving us command,
by giving us answers, but based on its
knowledge, it's not really that helpful in
real life world, in real life situations.
Now let's see how we can improve on
that by introducing the tool use.
To the LLM.
So let's let me switch for that
for the basic to the basic agent.
Agent over here.
Alright, so I'm again using
the same model GT 4.1 for that.
And what we will be using on top of
that is what is called react framework.
React stands for reasonable effect
and basically we will be instructing
LLM to go through the loop of
multiple stages, namely, thought,
action, post observation, and answer.
In the third step, the LLM would need
to think about what action it needs
to perform to get the answer or to
get the information to give us answer.
Then it needs to decide on
the action itself basically.
As a response to our request, it
will need to send the actual action.
It wants to perform with some,
along with some inputs potentially.
Then there is a post step where basically
the action should run on behalf of LLM.
Then during the observation
step, the output from the action
will be sent to LLM and then.
Based on this observation and the initial
input from the user the LLM hopefully
will come up with a, with an answer.
Or if that information is not
enough, it'll go to the second loop,
to the third loop and so on until
it gets asked the answer or until
it runs out of low penetrations.
And this can pretty easily
be implemented through this.
System prompt over here, and basically
I'm instructing a LLM to do, to follow
the same the, to follow the loop of react
framework, which I just described, right?
So you run in a loop of thought
action post observation.
I use thought, I use action.
And then we also provide a
few actions available for
LLM to use or to choose from.
In this case, those would be Ping.
So basically that would
perform the ping command.
On behalf of LLM, we have bh
which would allow LLM to use any,
to execute any batch commands.
And we will have web search
pretty basic web search which will
allow LLM to well do web search.
We also have some example session over
here for LLM to use as a reference.
So for example here, the question
from the user could be how many
islands make up Madera Ali Madera.
So it's a sort of nice, nice
small Easter egg for that.
And then the thought from LLM
should hopefully be that it needs
to do a web search for the madada.
Then it would need to perform to, to
reply with an action namely web search,
and then the input for that action.
In this case that could be just Madeira.
Then during the post, the
actual web search will happen.
And then based on the web search.
Based on the observation from
that web search the LLM should
hopefully come up with an answer.
In this case that would be four islands.
We are using the same code to query
the LLM, we'll just directly send
the input from from us, from the
user, along with the pro, with the
system prompt we've seen above.
And then let's also define
our three actions, three
commands to perform actions.
Name the ping bash and web search.
Let's test them out.
And ping for google.com.
Resource 200 milliseconds.
I do indeed have Python, three point
12.6 installed locally and for the web
search for Python three 14 it gave us
a lot of information from the website.
So this seems to be working fine now,
let's compile this in the dictionary
just to make it more easily accessible.
And then the main implementation of
react framework happens basically in
these, and these function over here
where we are going through the react loop
we start with the sending the, is the
query of the digital query to the model.
Then based on the output from the
model, we check if there is any action
that model decided to perform, which
will be, signified by these actions.
Semicolon prefix of the string.
And if there is an action
we get the list of actions.
We perform that action and give the
result of running that action to the
LLM to hopefully give us the answer.
And then of course, if it's, if
that information is not enough,
we will go to the second loop.
To the third loop, and so on.
Now let's try pretty much the same,
the same prompts, the same questions
we had before in the baseline, but
now with these basic agent behavior.
So let's first try to get the response
time for Google, in this case it, the A
lamp decided to perform Action Ping for
google.com which is a correct action.
It got the answer from the action,
and then as an answer to our
initial question, it gave us.
The rounded number of milliseconds or
seconds for the pink the same should
work with the Python packages, right?
So we decided to perform the action
batch with the input of P list
which gave the alarm a bunch of
packages I have installed locally.
And then based on that the answer
from LLM was, I guess sort of summary
of, of those Python packages which
have installed locally showing a
presentative sample apparently.
All right.
And this, let's see what will happen
with the, our Python three 14 question.
So the action that Ellan decided
to perform is a web search,
which makes sense, right?
It's pretty much the actual question
of ours was new by three 14.
It got to the.
Logical website from python.org with a
bunch of information and somewhere below.
Let me scroll all the way down, somewhere
below it should give us the answer based
on the observation from that action.
Namely over here.
It, it summarized some new features
changes in Python three 14, a few
PEPs, a few new features some changes.
So basically with just a
single system prompt like this.
We already are able to significantly
extend the capabilities of LLM beyond
it just being a sort of knowledge base.
We else, it, it now has access to web,
it now has access to our local machine.
It now has access to
batch commands, right?
So basically it already
can be much more helpful.
For us was in everyday life and
in our coding coding journey.
But of course it wouldn't
be very convenient to.
Modify this prompt every time
we need to add new action.
And there could be a lot of different
actions depending on what tool
you want LLM to be able to use.
Like for example, if you
think about Git right?
The Git itself has a bunch of
different commands like Git commit,
Git checkout, Git branch, and so on.
So you would potentially
need to define each.
Single git command as a set
protection, and that probably
would take quite a long time.
Now, ho fortunately for us, there are ways
to abstract all these tool definitions
from us, from the end user, and one
of those, one of these ways is MCP.
So let me go back to the
slides real quick over here.
Let's see.
So MCP stands for Model Context
Protocol, and it was introduced
pretty recently and the end of
November last year two four by Tropic.
So essentially MCP is a protocol based on
JSON RPC, which, which aims to facilitate.
The tool use and the development of
those tools, it consists of two main
counterparts, MCP server and MCP host,
and MCP client, and now MCP client could
be our LLM, it could be some id, it
could be any AI enabled tool, basically.
And then MCP server performs
essentially two main functions.
First, it, of course, interacts
with the, with the actual tool
performs the actual actions, right?
So it could access some local sources.
It could be MCP server for the file
system, so it could manipulate files,
for example, it could also be MCP
server that performs some a p requests.
So it could be MCP server, which provides
tools to access Jira, for example.
Or it could be tools to access.
Flight radar, right?
So basically any anything that can
be coded to be accessed through
code can be converted to MCP server.
And then through MCP Protocol,
the LLM can get the list of tools,
can get any names, different
descriptions, and how to use them.
And then again, through MCP protocol,
it would send essentially the request
to perform the action to the MCP
server, and then it would get the
response, from NCP server with the
result of running that ac that action
or the result of running that tool.
And it is pretty straightforward to
run to create your own NCP servers.
Let me switch back to our notebook
over here, and let's go now to
the agent with MCP directory.
So first, let's see how we can
implement our own MCP server.
And you can do that in multiple languages.
I think currently there are
SDKs of Python, JavaScript, Java
and Lin, if I'm not mistaken.
But essentially, of course, I'm sure
that more languages will follow, but
basically over here we have the two
MCP two or MCP server defined in Python
and Tropic provided a nice, fast MCP
class or from the MCP framework, which
basically requires us to essentially
just do essentially the server itself.
And then through this, the curator, we
can convert any function into an MCP tool.
So in this case, that would be a
bar tool which will perform any
we will execute any batch command.
For us, and of course you,
ideally, you don't want to
execute blindly any b command.
But for the sake of the, for the
presentation we we will allow that.
But basically those three lines is the
only thing, things that you would need
this in Python to create a bar Oh, sorry.
To create an MCP server for yourself.
And as I said, anything that
you can code can essentially
be converted to MCP server.
Now, along with that, we also would
require a sort of description of how
to call that server, that MCP server.
And over here I have a. Small JSON
file, which defines the MCP servers.
In this case, the only MCP server
is called B and it is run as
python command, right with the
arcs of just name of the file.
'cause it's essentially by Python script.
So that's the only two things that
needs that it needs to be executed.
But we'll see later different ways.
Beyond just Python script that
you can execute MCP servers as.
So let's now see how we can use
those MCP servers along with LLM.
So for that first of all,
we will switch to tropic.
In this case it would be
cloud D 3.7, I believe.
Yep, it's cloud D 3.7.
The reason for this switch.
Is initially tropic tropics Cloud
was more was better at using tools.
However, now you might have heard
that even OpenAI adopted the MCP
protocol from the arrivals, basically.
So the recent models are also
pretty good with following, with
using tools defined as MCP servers.
But still here we'll be
using, tropics called 3.7.
Now, what we essentially need to use the
CP tools is we will need an MCB client.
And in this case the main functions
or methods of this class is, first
of all, we need of course to connect
to servers to get the list of tools
available for us to use no for LLM to use.
These function is essentially
responsible for that.
So we just connect to each server in
the loop, in the server config, and then
get a list of tools from that server.
And then we also need to of course,
send the request to LLM and then act
accordingly to the response from LLM.
So basically we attach the list of tools.
I got from MCP servers in the format
of tool name, tool description, and
tool input schema, along with our, user
input message, and those things are
sent directly to CLA 3.7 in this case.
And then the clo, the LLM, decides
if it wants to just respond as
a plain text or if it wants to
perform an action or a tool use.
And this is how we basically
differentiate between.
Between those as part of the response
that would be a content type.
It could be either text or a tool use
in, and in the case of tool use, we will
see what kind of tool it wants to use.
So that will basically tool name and then
what kind of input arguments, it needs to
be we need to pass to that to that tool.
Then we will perform that
actual tool call over here.
And then we'll send the result of that
tool call back to LLM, and then hopefully
we will get an answer to our question.
And then here I have a small,
a nice small chat loop.
Where basically we will send the we
will send the query into the into
the text field, and then proceed with
this chat until we type the qui word.
So let's start with our, just
with our bar tool over here.
We got connected to the, to
our server which was run as
Python Bar tool, fast speed pi.
We have one single tool called Barge.
And let's ask LLM to do something.
Let's say list all files and
let's see what will come up with.
So in this case, he decided to call
the B command, the Bash two with
a comment with a. With the comment
LS dash la, which makes sense.
It got the list of files and
basically summarized them all.
Good.
Now let's see how we can extend these
two multiple servers to multiple tools.
And for that we will use
the full J confi over here.
Which basically defines four MCP servers.
First of all, we have a file system,
MCP server, which is essentially
an NPM package which runs with
few inputs, see few arguments.
We also have a web search realized
through Brave web search, and
that is run as docker image.
So here we have some
end file for the tokens.
We also have a fe, a web server, which
would allow LLM to fetch any URL from the
web, is implemented as Python package.
And then of course we have our
Bash MCP server, which we just
defined couple seconds ago.
So you can see, cP servers
can come in all flavors and
languages and ways to run them.
Now, let's see let's not give those
servers to our LLM and let's ask
to perform some actions, right?
First of all, let's see
what's new in Python.
Three 14.
So let's see if it'll need to perform
a web search to give us the answer.
All right, so it decided to call
the web search tool with the
following query, Python three 14
new features through release notes.
The unlike OpenAI GT 4.1, it didn't just
copy the questions from us and then based
on the response from the web search tool,
it gave us the summary of new features.
Let's also try to ask cla to create a file
called Hello the text with the content.
Hello world.
Alright.
Let's see.
So hopefully it'll be able to
access our local file system.
So in this case, we decided
to use the tool right file
with the following arguments.
And let's actually see, yeah,
we just got the new file.
We on our local file system called as
Requested, hello to 60 with the content.
Hello World.
Great.
So essentially with just a few lines
of code of basically the JSON config
of MCP servers, we, again extended
the capabilities of LLM beyond just
being able to answer questions based
on its on what is seen in the tearing
data, it is now also able to perform.
A lot of different actions and those MCP
server can come in different flavors.
And there are actually a lot
of different sources where you
can find M CCP servers online.
There are MCP registries, which
contains hundreds of different M
CCP servers for tools like, for
example, Grafana JIRA and so on.
So basically you can, give a lamb
access to any tools you use in your
everyday every everyday working life.
And basically, as we will see later, ask
it to, for example, solve the ticket.
Now let's let me quickly jump back
to the slides for a few more seconds.
All right, so we've seen MCP.
Now let's see how we can make agents
work with each other because of course,
before, before that, we, all the tools
we had, oh, LLM had at this disposal
were essentially just a software, right?
There was just API calls, it was just
file system manipulations and so on.
However, you can imagine those
tools being agents on their own.
And then one agent could potentially
call another agent to delegate a task
to ask it, to ask a subordinate agent
to perform some small subtask and so on.
And in our case, we will be building
a system which contains four
agents and it will be hierarchical.
Hierarchical system where, we'll,
where we will have supervisor,
agent which you can think about
as product manager, for example.
And this agent will be able to call
three other agents subordinate agents.
And those would be frontend
developer virtual frontend developer.
Virtual backend developer
and virtual DevOps engineer.
And they also would be able to
interact with us with the client to
ask for any clarification if needed.
But generally all of the
manipulation of the all of the.
Interactions between those
subordinate agents should happen
through a supervisor agent.
There is no direct connection from
one subordinate agent to another.
However, of course, you can also implement
this where where in the system potentially
all agents would be able to talk with
each other directly, not through the
supervisor agent, it would really depend
on what you want the system to work to do.
Now let me switch back again
to our Jupyter Notebook.
Alright,
and let's go to the final notebook
of the day, which is multi-agent.
Notebook.
Now here I will be adding one more
level of abstraction and memory,
link chain and glowing graph.
And the reason for that is of
course you can implement all of
the agent, all of the cross agent
collaborate interactions on your own.
It is essentially.
Just the structured inputs and
outputs and then some state
manipulations on top of that.
Why spend time on that when you
can use the frameworks which
do that for you basically.
So again, we will use the
same quality 3.7 here and.
Give it three, or, sorry, four four tools.
Pretty much the same tools
which we've seen before.
Shell tool for the batch
commands, we will, it'll also
have access to brave search.
Again, as we've seen before.
It'll also have access to
file file system manipulation.
And there is also one more new
tool which I called Human, which
basically would allow LLM to
ask back questions to the human.
And then we at the are
discussed on the site.
We will, we'll create four agents.
First, we'll create agent supervisor,
which will have access to three team
members, namely frontend developer,
backend developer and ops engineer, and
the system run the split straightforward.
We are telling the agent that it is
a supervisor overseeing the following
three workers, and it basically
needs to decide who's who is the
next agent responsible to, for, to
perform the task or to act next.
And then once the supervisor agent
is happy with the result, it should
respond with a keyword finish.
Basically, we will give access to
all the tools, all the available
tools to these agents as well.
However in real life potentially you
probably would want agents to have access
to different lists of tools, right?
For example, you might have DevOps
engineer, virtual DevOps engineer.
Being able to access tools like Ana or
Promeus or Datadog or whatever, right?
But at the same time, you don't want,
probably, you probably don't need front,
end agent to be able to access that.
But on the other hand, it
needs to have access to other
tools like Figma, for example.
So the only things we basically need
to create our supervisor agent is
this piece of code over here where we
define what what sort of nodes or what
sort of hand off notes are available
for these supervisor nodes to call.
And those are again, our team members.
And then of course, end
node to finish the tasks.
With that, let's also define our
three agents, namely front end agent
backend agent, and DevOps agent.
As you can see here, we are using
pretty much the same React framework.
As we've seen before, and again, we
are passing all the tools, all of
the available tools to those agents,
and the prompts are pretty simple.
Although in real life world, of
course, you probably would want
to be more creative or be more
specific with those prompts.
But in our case, we are just defining the
frontend agent as a frontend developer.
And this agent can also ask.
Help ask for help from backend
developer or DevOps engineer.
And it can also ask for
clarifications from the human client.
The same goes with a
backend backend agent.
It can help, can ask for
help from front end or DevOps
engineer, and it can also ask for
clarifications from the human client.
And the same goes with a DevOps agent.
It can also.
Call, ask help for front end
or backend developers and ask
for clarifications from human.
All of those agents or nodes in
the terms of land graph are defined
in a pretty three forward manner
through these comment over here.
And that's pretty much all we need to do.
To define those agents.
Now, with that, let's also build a graph
and let's also visualize that graph.
So indeed, as we've seen before, we
have the supervisor note or supervisor
agent which can talk directly with our
front end backend and DevOps engineers.
But subordinate agents
can talk to each other.
They only can talk through supervisor.
Over here I have just a small
help helper, now helper function
to color the output as we see.
That's what we'll see in a few seconds,
so I won't go over that piece of code.
And then the task for the, for
our multi-agent system would be to
create a website for the conference.
It needs to have three pages.
Namely intro intro page page
for people to submit it.
There, the docs and page
with the submitted docs.
I want the front end in React.
I want a backend test, API
and the submissions should be
stored in Postgres database.
And also, it's always as have
Docker and Docker compose.
So I also ask for that.
And then we also mention that they can ask
the human client for any clarifications.
This part over here is basically
all what is needed to initiate the
execution of our multi-agent system.
So I actually started and see
what will come up with first.
Indeed we went into supervisor,
which decided to call the front
frontend developer the frontend
developer itself decided to check
what kind of tools it has installed.
On the system.
I got the answer and then it went ahead
to check the versions the version.
Alright, it decided to create
a conference website directory.
So here.
So we already should be able to
see some changes reflected locally.
Indeed.
We have a few directors already.
We have the package on, so
probably it is, yeah, it is doing.
N-P-N-P-X command, which will potentially
take some time because, the n payment
style usually takes a few minutes.
We, yeah, we can see the non models
appearing for us with a bunch of packages.
All right, let's okay, let's go back
and we already starting to see some of
the code popping up over here, right?
Some CSS, some TypeScript code.
Let me.
Scroll scroll down here.
So it did install some packages and it
started to implement the code over here.
So it started with the Python.
Alright.
Yeah.
Basically it'll proceed to implement
the website for us on our behalf.
Now let me switch back
again to the slides.
All right.
But it is always nice to, fiddle
around with the code with the
agents, with the L lms and see
what you can build on your own.
Of course you don't always have time and
still you probably would want to be able
to use, those agents be able to have those
agents help you with your everyday tasks.
And of course there is a way for you
to have them help you with your coding.
Coding tasks, basically.
With that, let me briefly introduce
briefly talk about what we do at Z Coder.
Z Coder basically is just a plugin
for V Code of Brains, and this
plugin brings you brings the
agents to you, to your id natively.
You don't need to switch to any other id
outside of what you are already using.
And let me briefly show showcase.
Our agent basically solving the Jira task.
Let me switch to this code over here.
Alright,
so our agent, our z coder is already
natively integrated in the J So we
have this encoder test over here.
So basically we can tag
any ticket from the j.
I think that's the
wrong the wrong account.
Alright,
base.
Let's see.
Alright, so let's ask our
agent to solve this ticket.
Solve it create a branch called 42.
Check out and commit changes.
All right.
So the ticket itself basically
requires the agent to implement
changes across multiple languages
across the whole repository.
So what the, what our agent will
do first that we'll try to analyze.
The code base, it'll try
to understand the project.
So it will check some Python files.
It decided to also check
across different languages.
So this repository specifically contains
three languages Python, go in TypeScript.
So it went ahead to check some go
implementation of the repository.
Yeah, so it will, it can take
some time depending on the
task which we have at hand.
So it also create already a branch for us.
Thanks to MCP support, of course, you
can attach any MCP servers in this case.
I have Git, MCP, which basically allows
the agent to, to perform any git commands
locally on your machine, and we already
see some changes being implemented
in our repository, first and Python.
Okay?
Okay.
We already have modified, I
believe, two files over here.
Then agent decided to switch, to go
implementation of the repository.
All right, so yeah, we also need
to introduce this name space
thingy in the go go implementation
server as well as in Python.
Alright.
Then we also, of course as instructed the
GI a and Git and this small the sort of
nice feature I have here is I instructed
the agent through instructions to always
slack me when it is done with the task.
So let's go back to our chat.
And yeah, basically after the combination
of agen patterns and MCB servers, it
was able to basically pull the JIRA
JIRA ticket and then essentially do all
the all the tasks surrounding the, the
typical software development steps, right?
So it creates, the branch created
a commit for us and so on.
So basically in a matter of minute, it
was able to fix fix the ticket for us.
Alright.
Let's switch back to the
slides one more time.
Okay.
So yeah, and if you are wondering this
is how those messages from sun Coder
would look like in Slack, for example.
And, every time I get those messages,
it feels this meme and of course, I can
instruct Theod to not message you, but
your PM or whoever you wanted to message
and not necessarily in Slack or, you
can, through MCP, you can connect to
pretty much any messaging app whatsoever.
And well, of course, these sort of
improvements or what you've seen now.
Probably made you think if it's time
to switch switch the profession, right?
Is still a good time to
be a software developer?
And of course there are essentially
two main sides to that question to,
what's coming for the developers.
Of course, you can think
about, ai replication and.
There is also some, variability as to if
you see it as a negative or a positive
thing because for example, maybe you
always wanted to be a goose farmer.
And then once you are replaced by
ai, you finally would be able to
chase that long lasting dream of
whatever you whatever your heart
wants you, what wants you to be.
Now of course.
At least for now, AI is not able
to train itself without the data.
So there is at least one
job that is safe for now.
Namely writing the code for AI to
train on because, still it requires a
bunch of data for training, for model
improvements, however jokes site even
with those, all of those improvements
from, on the AI side, on the gen side
with things like white coding, you still
hopefully need to they still need to
have a good knowledge of what's going on.
Especially we're talking about some
mission critical systems especially
about putting things into production.
You still want to be able to un to be
able to understand what's going on.
You need to still need to be able to.
Read the code or know, debug the code.
So what we at Zone Coder and me personally
see as a sort of upcoming future for
the software development is that we as
developers would become more as a managers
of virtual virtual agents, virtual
junior developers, if you will, and.
We as humans would be more for
reviewers, more managers as that
rather than writing the code ourselves.
So basically we would be able
to offload any mundane tasks.
For example writing documentation,
writing new in tests, and so on to our
army of virtual virtual developers.
We as as people would be able to
focus on more creative or more high
level tasks, more architecturals
architectural tasks and so on.
So yeah, hopefully the future, no longer
doesn't look as as dark as it did before.
But of course, AI moves fast.
So we'll see what will
happen a few years with that.
A couple cure codes for you to use.
On the right is my contact details.
If you want to connect on LinkedIn,
if you want to follow up with any
questions, feel free to message me.
Feel free to send the connect request.
And on the left you can see the cure
code for our website for encoder ai,
where you can basically sign up for free
and try as, try the agents in your id.
Already they end with that.
Thank you for your attention.