My name is Al. We are going to
talk about the designing and a
centralized person data repository.
I have around 20 of experience in database
technology and currently working with a
healthcare company as a data architect.
So we are going to talk about
that, how to design a centralized
percent data repository.
Nowadays a large healthcare organization,
the percent data is scattered across
multiple systems, electronic health
records, lab reports, pharmacy
reports, and insurance claims.
Our task is how to design and
implement a centralized data repository
that would consolidate all percent
information into a single, secure
and easily accessible platform.
For that.
This is what the, today's topic
is designing a centralized.
Percent data repository.
Nowadays, the all healthcare
has a lot of data and we have
to see how to maintain it.
Healthcare, cognition worldwide are
experiencing a challenge in managing
and exchanging percent data across
various system and institutions.
The advantage of healthcare technologies
introduce new complexity data management.
With modern healthcare facility
generating an average of 6 65 terabyte
or percent data annually through
various source, including diagnostic
imaging, technical documentation,
and real time monitoring devices.
The system architecture, when we
talk, we are going to talk about
here basically Microsoft Architecture
Cloud approach, and cost efficiency.
When we talk about Microsoft architecture.
Microservice architecture is
evolved significantly to address
the growing complexity of
modern data management analysis.
Analysis of public health institution
has shown that implementing a
microservices based architecture with
distributed storage capabilities can
improve system performance by up to 45%
compared to traditional mono approaches.
A comprehensive study of public hospitals
revealed that organization adopting
cloud native architecture experience a
38% reductions in operational cost and
52% improvement in data accessibility.
The economic impact of
improved healthcare.
Interability has been substantial
healthcare cognition that have
been successfully implemented.
Comprehensive interability solutions
have observed an address cost saving of
$3.7 million annually to reduce duplicate
testing, improved resource allocation,
and enhance operational efficiency.
When we talk about the cloud native
approach or the cost efficiency health
cognition, adopting our cloud native
architecture have experienced a 38%
reductions in operational cost and a 52%
improvement in percent data as across
department, our specializing cloud based.
Archival system reduced storage cost
by 60, 60% while maintaining a rapid
retrieval times under 200 millisecond
for frequent excess percent revy data.
The core component is the data
storage and integration data
source layer and integration layer.
Once we talk about the data storage layer
basically represents the cornerstone
of healthcare and pharmacy system
requiring careful concentration of data
type access patterns and complaints.
Requirement research conducted across
multiple public hospital demonstrate that
post SQL implementation for structural
clinical data achieved 99.99% uptime.
While managing an average of 7800000.0%
records, the study reveals that facilities
utilizing MongoDB for unstructured
data can also improve the time the
cloud-based system reduce the storage
cost by 63% while maintaining several
retrieval times under 200 millisecond.
That is what going on because
it's a used amount of data.
If you talk about, or the same thing,
if you talk about the integration
layer, FHIR, gateway implementation,
reduce integration complexity by 56%
and improve data consistency by 71%.
Integration layer is basically.
Serve as a critical middleware
component, facilitating seamless
data exchange between this D
disparate healthcare systems.
Research.
Analyzing F-H-I-R-A-P-I Gateways
implementations across public
hospital indicate that externalized
API approaches reduced in complexity
by 56% and data consistency by 71%.
The HL seven masses processor component
demonstrate the capability to handle
850,000 clinical masses daily with
a 99.95% successful processing rate.
ETL pipeline implementations in
public health environment have
shown remarkable efficiency in data
transformation and loading process.
According to recent studies, modern
EL system can process up to three
50 GB of clinical data per hour.
While maintaining data quality scores
above 95%, the realtime event bus
architecture has proven particularly
effective in managing clinical workflows,
processing an average of 12,000
events per second with latency and a
hundred milliseconds enabling realtime
clinical decision support system.
The security layer, if we think about.
Security comprehensive IM system
reduced unauthorized access attempt
by 97% while processing an average of
500,000 authentication requests daily.
R Bs combined with A BAC has sown
to reduce security incident by 82%.
RBS means role-based access control, and
a BS means attribute based access control.
Analysis of public hospital implementation
revealed that comprehensive IM
systems reduce unauthorized access,
attend by 97%, while processing an
average of 500,000 authentication
requests daily encryption service.
Utilizing industry standard protocols
have demonstrated for robust protections
for sensitive health information.
Research indicate that modern encryption
implementation in healthcare settings
can secure up to 35 terabyte of
percent data daily while maintaining
processing over at below 3%.
Once we talk about how to design
data model for healthcare system,
designing data model of healthcare
system, we can talk about percent centric
schema, FHI compliant structure, flexible.
Storage approaches and
versioning and audit control.
PE centric schema.
Modern healthcare information
system requires sophisticated data
modeling approach to handle the
increasing complexity of PE data.
The research analyzing healthcare
data architecture has demonstrate
the implementation of higher schemas.
With optimizing index strategic
can reduce query response time
by 35% while maintaining data
integrity across the system.
A study of healthcare facilities
revealed that properly structured
percent centric schema can handle
up to 2,500 concurrent ES per second
while maintaining response time.
100 millisecond data duplication strategy.
We talk about term matching
approach, and we talk about istic
matching approach, deterministic
matching and probabilistic matching.
Deterministic matching like
combining identifier matching and
probabilistic is basically we talk
about machine learning based approach.
Healthcare automation face significant
challenge in maintaining accurate percent.
Identify across multiple system research
indicate in deterministic matching
algorithm has shown that combining
traditional identifier matching.
With advanced correlation techniques
can achieve equal rate up to 97.8%.
In identifying duplicated course,
the study of 15 healthcare institutions
demonstrate that implementing
multifactor determinating matching
reduce false positive rate to 0.03%
while processing approximately
600,000 records comparison per hour.
The effectiveness of deterministic
matching significant improve when
incorporating temporal data analysis.
What exactly?
Temporary data analysis.
Analyzing historical pattern
alongside by accuracy of 24%.
Once we talk about PROTIC matching
implementation, that advanced
processing matching techniques
have immersed as a component in
modern healthcare data management.
Analysis of machine learning based
systems has demonstrated accuracy
improvement of up to 28% compared to
traditional deterministic methods.
Particularly when dealing with
incomplete or inconsistent data.
The research across multiple healthcare
networks has shown that sophisticated
probability algorithm can achieve
a match rate of 92.4%, even with
particularly complete demographic data.
Once we talk.
Once we talk about to how to
F-H-I-R-A-P-I layer implementation,
this is basically, you can see
the numbers, 42% of integration
simplification, 31% data accuracy, 89%
security enhancement, 850 K daily API
request how it manage a lot of data.
The implementation of FHI based.
Solutions has demonstrated significant
impact on healthcare data action
Efficiency analysis of healthcare
organization has shown that F-H-I-R-R
for implementation can reduce data
integration complexity by up to 42%
while improving data accuracy by 31%.
Compared to the legacy systems,
the adoption office SMART on FHIR
authorization framework has ized
secure healthcare data access.
Studies indicate that implementing
comprehensive FHIR based security protocol
reduce unauthorized access by 89% while
processing authentication request with
an average latency of 180 milliseconds.
Data accuracy daily a I request
and security enhancement.
You can see the numbers, how it
match when talk about real time
simulation architecture, we talk about.
Change data capture that is also
called as a CDC event publication Data
Synchronization and Conflict Resolutions.
CDC.
The implementation of change data
capture mechanism in healthcare
environment has so remarkable improvement
in data consistency maintenance.
The research demonstrate that modern
CDC systems can effectively process
approximate 500 changes per second
during peak operational hours,
with average end to end latency
remaining under 150 millisecond.
Healthcare facilities implementing
CDC architecture have reported
a 57% reduction in data ation
errors, and a 43% improvement
in the real time recoverability.
Event publication system integrate
with masses Q had demonstrated
robust performance improvement,
conflict resolution mechanism.
Modern healthcare data system requires
sophisticated conflict, re resolution
strategy to maintain data integrity
across distributed environment.
Our research indicates that implementing
a version based vector based solution
mechanism can successfully handle up to
seven 50 concurrent updates per second,
while maintaining data consistency
across distributed healthcare network
event publications.
And data ation is also two major part,
talking about real time synchronization
architecture, how we behave.
Data protections, measures,
encryption, implementations.
They all are a part of this.
Our whole architecture, security and
compliance in healthcare system, data
protection, encryption, implementation,
access control system, and audit.
Implementation.
If we talk about data production
first, when talk about data production
measures, the security landscape
in healthcare information system
has evolved significantly with the
increasing digitization of percent calls.
Analysis of healthcare security
incident has revealed that approximately
63% of data breaches occur due
to unauthorized access, while 27%
reserve form system vulnerabilities.
Research indicate that
healthcare organizations.
Implementing comprehensive security
framework experience a 71% reduction in
successful breach attempt with modern
encryption strategy, sewing particular
effectiveness in protecting sensitive
present data encryption implementation.
Implementation we can
say we are implementing.
A S 2 56 Encryption for data address
had demonstrated 99.9% success rate
implementing unauthorized data access.
With performance overhead, everything
only 3.2% compared to encrypted system.
Unencrypted system, sorry.
So health ation must maintain robust
in encrypts mechanism to protect
percent data throughout lifecycle.
Studies of healthcare facilities
implementing standard encryption
protocol source, that modern system
can process up to 500,000 encrypted
transactions daily while maintaining
response time under 150 millisecond.
We are implementing ass 2 56.
Research across multiple healthcare
institution has shown that TLS 1.3
implementation for data in transit
can effectively secure network
communication while adding only 38
millisecond of parallel latency.
Implementing feed label encryption
report the ability to product sensitive
data element with 99.99% reliability
while maintain database query
performance within 94% of the Israel
measurement access control system,
modern health environment request,
sophisticated access control mechanism
to ensure appropriate data access.
Rule-based access control system
successfully manage an average of
15,000 unique rule across distributed
network with authorized and decision
process under 85 milliseconds.
The integration of attribute based access
control has shown it 76% improvement
in access season compared to the
traditional R BSC only implementation.
Emergency access procedures
have become increasingly crucial
in healthcare environment.
Research demonstrate that properly
implemented break glass procedure can
provide emergency access to critical PE
data within 30 seconds while maintaining.
Maintaining global robust security
protocol, audit tail implementation.
Comprehensive audit tail forms a clinical
component of healthcare security fracture.
The studies indicate that
healthcare system generate
between 4.2 and 5.8 million.
Tamper evident logging mechanism
ensure complete traceability of
all data access and modification.
Organizations implementing blockchain
based audit trail report a hundred
percent success rate in maintaining
audit log integrity across more
than 1.8 billion logged EV events
over a typical six months period.
Once we talk about.
The performance optimization in
healthcare systems, it is again,
go with the query performance.
Advanced indexing, casting
systems and horizontal scanning
query optimizing strategy.
The optimization of query performance
in healthcare require EHR system
has become increasingly crucial.
L Health cognition manage
growing data volumes.
Research, analyze query pattern in
large scale ER implementing has shown
optimized database engines can reduce
an average query response time by 64%
while supporting concurrent access
from multiple clinic applications.
A system process up to 15,000
clinical queries per second.
While maintaining average response
time on 150 millisecond, we should
advance indexing implementation.
Very important part.
It reduced the query execution time
by 74% for complex database joins.
Implementation of a s indexing approach
has demonstrated significant impact.
Analysis shows that data health
database utilizing composite index
for frequently accessed clinical data
path, reduce query execution times by
average 21% for complex wines evolving.
And clinical observation.
Health ation reports that implementing
partial indexes for filtered query result
in 38% reduction in storage requirements.
Text search optimization has emerged
as a critical requirement for managing
unstructured clinical documentation.
The response time from 1.8
second to 3 24 milliseconds.
Healthcare facility.
Utilizing optimizing task ing
strategy report the ability to
process up to 750,000 clinical
notices daily while maintaining
consistent sub second response time.
The casting system architecture
modern EHR system requires
sophisticated casting mechanism.
450,000 requests per second.
Wide latency under five milliseconds.
Casting consistency management
through write through policies
has shown particular effectiveness
in health environment.
The research demonstrated that EHR
system implementing a write through
casing, maintain 99.95% data consistency
while processing an average of
8,000 write operation per second.
The scalability strategy is basically
horizontal skeleton and load management.
Once we talk about horizontal scanning.
Scanning implement has
demonstrate significant
improvement in system capability.
Research indicate that percent ID based
sing enables ER system to effectively
manage data up to 2.5 million active
percent while maintaining query
response time under 200 milliseconds.
Auto scanning mechanism based on clinical
workflow patterns have proven particularly
effective in healthcare environment.
Once we talk about implement
consideration for healthcare system cloud
infrastructure for healthcare systems.
If you see here, we can see
infrastructure, cost deployment
time, the socialization, compute,
cost reduction, storage ion, and
security incident improvement.
Monitoring and operations is one very
important part that how healthcare
matters is database monitoring,
alerting system, and compliance.
Compliance monitoring will help
healthcare health matters.
Implementation effective monitoring
system plays a crucial role in
maintaining healthcare system liability.
The compressing application performance
monitoring reduced mean time to
detection by 62% compared to the
traditional monitoring approaches.
Healthcare recognition.
Implementing detailed
performance monitoring capture
approximately 6.2 million.
Metrices daily database monitoring
has become increasingly sophisticated.
In healthcare environment is a source that
organization implementing comprehensive
database monitoring, identify potential
performance issues and average of 32.
Minutes before user impact with 91%
accuracy, problem identification,
alerting system confirmation.
The modern health environment requires
robust alerting mechanism to maintain
system reliability analysis indicate
that organization implementing a
multilevel alert system reduce mean time
to resolution by 58% while maintaining
a false positive rates below 3%.
The study shows that properly
configured alerting system successfully
identify 95% of critical issues
within 45 second occurrence.
The implementation of compliance
monitoring alert has become
re for maintaining adherence.
Once we talk about the final
words, if I want to say here.
Today as a conclusion, the implementation
of centralized data repository represents
a complex but essential undertaking
for modern health coordination.
The success of system relies
on the careful integration of
multiple components, from robust
data governance policies to
comprehensive security measures and
continuous monitoring protocols.
By adopting a centralized framework
like FHIR and implementing sophisticated
security controls organization can
create systems that effectively balance
data accessibility with irregularity
comprehensive, the ongoing evolution
of healthcare technology, necessities,
commitment to continuous improvement, the
regular security assessment and strong
partnership with healthcare providers.
Implementation of the system
ultimately leads to improved patient
care outcomes, enhance operational
efficiency and better healthcare
service delivery through seamless
data exchange and access capabilities.
Thank you so much.