Hey.
Hi everybody.
Welcome to conference 42,
machine Learning 2025.
My name is V Kushner and I work
as a senior software engineer at
Walmart, where a primary work.
In infrastructure engineering today, I am
honored to speak on a transformative shift
that's occurring in cloud ecosystems.
That is the journey from reactive
to predictive with AI driven API
resiliency in cloud ecosystems.
Imagine a world where your
APIs don't just react.
To failures, but predict and prevent them.
Thus, the power of AI driven resilience.
APIs are critical business assets.
Any downtime can lead to lost
revenue, diminished customer
trust, and operational chaos.
Okay.
Moving from reactive to proactive
stance is no longer just beneficial.
It's essential,
the API management landscape in today's
microservices architecture driven world.
The following statistics highlight
the immense scale at which these
architectures are being adopted.
By 2032, the API Management
market is projected to reach a
staggering 27.3 billion US dollars,
highlighting how crucial APIs
have become to business success.
Companies that integrate AI into
their API Management strategies
experience substantial gains,
which includes 34.7% fewer errors.
28.5 percentage faster response times,
and that's clearly AI is becoming
an indispensable partner in ensuring
API performance and reliability.
Moving on.
Next, we have three main
pillars of API, resilience.
To transition effectively from a
reactive to a predictive approach.
The three pillars of API resilience
are critical, intelligent optimization,
which is nothing but dynamically
managing performance using ai, where
advanced AI algorithms that dynamically
tune performance, balance the
traffic loads and allocate resources
based on real time demand patterns.
The preemptive security.
Security plays an important role in
microservices, proactively detecting
threats before the A escalate rather
than reacting after an incident.
This involves advanced threat
intelligence that uncovers potential
vulnerabilities early and integrating
behavior analysis with context
error authentication mechanisms.
And autonomous healing autonom
automatically predicting, detecting
and fixing before they even escalate.
So the intelligence systems that
continuously monitor predict potential
failure points and automatically
implement corrective measures
before service disruption occurs.
And now we have intelligent
optimization in action.
How does it happen?
Imagine an API gateway that can
dynamically scale to process
3,500 requests per second.
That is 3,500 requests.
35 TPS achieving a 67 percentage
increase in throughput with
the no drop in performance.
And that's the key point, and
that's such a huge reduction in
processing, time of request, and
handling large loads of requests.
User experience is the most essential part
of a successful journey for any product.
We need to have AI deep learning
algorithms balance load intelligently
achieving 25% lower latency during
high traffic scenarios, ensuring
consistent, usual per experience,
the reinforcement learning based caching.
Predicts frequently assessed content,
reducing the database load by an
impressive 35% that can be devoted towards
CDNs or any cash enabled in the workflow.
And let's move ahead and check the
What's preemptive security framework is?
Traditional security models wait
for an attack to happen so that
there needs to be prevented.
With AI driven preventive security,
the narrative changes drastically.
Continuous monitoring, real
time monitoring analysis.
1 million security events per second.
So guys, just imagine 1 million
security events, and that's a
lot enabling instantaneous threat
identification, a powered contextual
authentication cuts, unauthorized
access attempts by up to 73% through
behavioral and environmental analysis.
Predictive threat detection improves
incident recognition, speed by
58%, dramatically reducing the
likelihood of a successful attacks,
and then comes the self
feeling architecture.
We just don't anticipate problems in here.
We fix them proactively.
We have baseline models.
Which analyze 50 K events per second.
Learning what normal looks like when we
say normal is the ideal system behavior.
So the early warning system detects 30
minutes before the conventional tools.
Autonomous recovery capabilities can
deploy solutions in milliseconds,
ensuring minimal D time and
seamless user experiences.
And again, I want to emphasize on this.
Point, user experience is very important
for any company success, and these
are the downtime reduction results.
Traditional ai enhanced predictive
versus autonomous, and this graph.
It clearly proves a point that you
know how moving to autonomous helps
us in reducing the down downtime
in any system or any applications.
So what is autonomous incident resolution?
Advanced algorithms autonomously
detect and resolve incidents that
humans might overlook, and that's
always a possibility with machines.
They own overlook, and that's why we
train the systems with the historical
data to help understand the system.
AI based incident detection rapidly
identifies subtle, anonymous, advanced
algorithms identify subtle, an anatomy
patterns invisible to human operators,
instant root cause analysis across
distributed systems, instant maps, and.
Analyzes complex system dependencies
across distributed environments.
Automated resolutions successfully handle
70% of the critical incidents, slashing
the meantime to resolution by 85%.
And that's the most important criteria
or the statistics that the operational
Excellency team is proud of when it's low.
So in AI world it's all
about continuous learning.
So what happens in this
continuous learning.
There is a point for our systems
to have more data points, help
understand the system even better.
So the AI systems continuously learn
and improve, creating a robust,
ever evolving defense mechanism.
Historical in incident analysis
provides actionable insights.
Systematically mine the past insights
to extract actionable intelligence
and optimization patterns.
This always helps in bettering operational
efficiency and system reliability.
Predictive models are refined,
constantly achieving 12 to 15% in a
quarterly improvement basis whenever
the incident response effectiveness.
Okay.
Enhance the predictive models with
real world data so that they create
more precise response Frameworks.
Train the system with previous
incidents so that the incidents are
fine tuned over the period, which
aids to smooth system running.
Continuous knowledge expansion
enhances long-term API Resilience.
Making your cloud ecosystem
smarter, more resilient over time.
Continuously enha enrich the incident
databases and solution repositories to
strengthen future response capabilities.
It's all about the learning and how
do we apply on the future instance.
That's all the AI is all about to train.
And how do we implement What
is the implementation roadmap?
So adopting to predictive a PR resilience
requires a structured approach.
It cannot happen overnight.
So the most important phase is
the assessment and the planning.
So we have to evaluate the
existing infrastructure and
identify the weaknesses.
Conduct comprehensive API
infrastructure analysis.
Identify the critical resilience,
vulnerabilities, and capability gaps.
Establish clear quantifiable objectives
with stakeholder agreement alignments.
And then comes the pilot deployment as a
responsible engineer using microservices.
In today's world, we have to deploy
them on a cannery deployment techniques,
like there are various techniques,
but this is one of the most used
techniques for any deployment.
So deploy AI solutions to
non-critical a PS first.
To refine the modules and then launch
AI powered monitoring solutions on
these selected non-critical APIs.
Established performance baselines
and detection thresholds, validate
the prediction accuracy against
these real world incidents.
And once these are done, we'll
move on to the full integration.
So when I say full integration,
we gradually expand the AI driven
resilience across all APIs.
Ensuring seamless integration
with existing tool happens,
expand the implementation across
production environment seamlessly.
Connect with existing monitoring
and management systems.
Develop and execute targeted technical
team training programs, and always
make sure to have a backup plans ready
just in case if anything needs to be
corrected or needs to be put back.
In these unforeseen circumstances,
so continuous optimization, enhanced
prediction modules using real
operational data and measure the return
on investment in downtime reduction,
and also in the improved reliability
on the system progressively expand
autonomous response capabilities.
So by now, we should be able to define
the next steps in our organization.
And how do we practically
begin this journey towards
this predictive API resilience?
Assess your current resilience
maturity, understand your baseline,
identify the critical APIs, evaluate
your API ecosystems resilience level.
Identify critical services
requiring the highest availability.
And always start small scale
fast, and that's the mantra.
Always remember that even thousand miles
of journey starts with a single step.
Incrementally integrate predictive
capabilities, starting with
analytics and expanding step by step.
Begin with monitoring and analytics.
Add predictive capabilities, incrementally
measure improvements systematically.
So build cross-functional teams.
So combine expertise from API
developers, machine learning specialists
and site reliability engineers
to maximize the effectiveness.
So when everybody, the when we get
a people from all different parts
of the world, they have different
experiences though that help us.
Bring more knowledge to the team.
So foster continuous knowledge sharing
to the team to learn and grow as a team.
So that's all.
And to conclude the shift from
reactive troubleshooting to
proactive and predictive management
is not only transformative, but
essential for sustained success.
Leveraging AI driven API Resilience
will future proof your organized
operations significantly enhancing
reliability, security, and inefficiency.
Thank you all for your attention and I
hope everybody enjoyed the session today.
Thanks a lot.