Speaker 20: Hi.
Hello everyone.
This is Puja.
I am excited to be presenting at the
conference 42 Machine Learning of 2026.
What a great way to start a year.
Talking about the IT of the IT
industry and the IT of all technology
that is machine learning and all the
cool advancements and developments
we are seeing in the industry here.
So let's dive into it.
Let me share my screen and, yeah.
Okay.
So I will go into the slideshow mode.
Yeah, let's talk a little bit about me
first before we get into the fun stuff.
I am Puja Ranjan.
I am an engineering
manager in Oracle America.
I work in the Silicon Valley.
I work specifically for Oracle Cloud.
Oracle Cloud has a lot of and recently
Oracle Cloud was the winner in the
second winner in the category of
highly fast growing cloud companies
according to Gartner ratings.
We are doing a lot of cool cutting
edge feature development for cloud.
And the push in the last couple
of years has been totally towards
building more AI centric tools
that will simplify enterprise
use cases and business use cases.
So yeah, I've been in this space
for about over a decade now.
I started as an software engineer.
I worked on several SaaS
platforms and projects.
I worked on one of one
of Zoom's competitors.
Actually, zoom is our online meeting.
A solution that most of you are aware
of, there is another product called
GoToMeeting, and I was the person who
was the, who started as an at 11 engineer
and then went to the lead engineer
level there on building it deploying
it, hosting it, and shipping it, and
constantly collecting customer feedback.
And then, keeping on optimizing that
product over Oracle, like for the far
past four years, I, again, I started as an
engineer on this team as a lead engineer.
Then I shipped out some AI
ML solutions for the cloud.
My target audience has been data science,
data scientists, so I build machine
learning related tools that they could
use in their day-to-day lives too.
Make the entire ML engineering
pipeline simple for them and to
leverage the security and reliability
and availability of the cloud to to
keep, to make their lives easier.
Over the past three years, I have
been leading a team of engineers.
It's a mix of software engineers and
machine learning engineers, and we try
to again, come up with the coolest tools
that we can ship out to data scientists
so they can easily extract, if they
have fragmented data sets, they can
move all the data set on the cloud.
So for migration purposes, for data
labeling purposes, for to organize
the data, especially unstructured
data to search through the data,
all the tools that Oracle Cloud
provides and other providers also
other competitive cloud providers do.
At the same time we have we help
them, like models are a very big
part of ML engineering, right?
Building models, all the tools that they
need to have, like smart models smart
model building and all the contact packs
that they need, all the environments they
need to set up do provide tools for that.
After that we also do, some more.
ML tools, two one STEM models already.
We provide ML tools.
I overlook those divisions where we
deploy those models to our large scale
heavy duty bare metal instances where.
There is very little hypervisor between
you and your workload, or we have them
deploy to GPUs that are shipped by
standard manufacturers like Nvidia.
So deploying those models,
training them, retraining their
models storing the results, doing
performing analytics on them.
And so the, these workflows basically
are a part of my day-to-day life.
So yeah, let's go to.
Why what we are doing right now in the
Silicon Valley is important for, the
machine learning evolution altogether.
So machine learning obviously is
is having, especially now AI are
large language models integrating
them, using them as drive that a lot
of large scale cloud organizations
and also smaller startups, smaller
AI startups are totally going for.
I, the trend that I see in the
Silicon Valley is, hey, let's
solve the more business use
cases we solve, the better it is.
For example a simple one is it support.
So in the past organizations and
my current organization anybody
having a problem with setting up
a policy or having an access issue
while logging in or accessing some
specific tools or information.
I had to go through, obviously, the
wedding, and there was rules around
who can get access and whatnot, but
then troubleshooting was an issue.
So then you had to wait for a person to
unblock you or come and help you out.
Sometimes the person had to be on
site to help you, that could add some
more delay and some more frustrations
to you trying to get your job done,
but having these logistical issues.
But now with all these AI ML models
and innovation that bit has been.
I would say 70% automated, because
most of these articles on how to
troubleshoot and how to go deeper when
something is wrong are all written, but
they're fragmented in so many places
across the organization's databases.
And then sometimes some of this
information is also just public
information that's available
on some of Google's websites.
So I, we have now in
the AI space deployed.
Models that are smart it support
assistants and the past three
tickets that I had to file because
of some missing access or permissions
were resolved by just talking
to the bot in my organization.
The bot could point me
towards the right documents.
Walk me through the steps.
It could exactly pinpoint which permission
or which user group was I not a part of.
And and I also asked it, Hey,
but I was a part of this.
I didn't know I was thrown out.
So then it put together a plan on
how to, it'll automatically set
up a reminder for me to renew my
permissions every time they expire.
Yeah, these level this is just an example
of how we are now integrating models
into our space of software development,
machine learning, engineering, the
whole technology bracket basically.
And that is helping us ship.
Focus on the real problems of machine
of data scientists and ML engineers
rather than spending our time on the
logistics part of everything that we
need to do to have access to our systems.
Yeah, and just this example, if you look
at the entire flow end-to-end pipeline,
be it machine learning engineering
pipeline, or a software development
engineering pipeline that's ML enabled,
all these pipelines are very heavily.
Inspired now and are benefiting
from having machine learning
integrated into several aspects and
several phases of their projects.
Why is all this important?
Because if you look at the revenue
and the business that SAS systems
that cloud systems generate for the
Silicon Valley, it's over 350,000.
Three 50 billion plus revenue annually.
And like just three to four top
players of the Silicon Valley are
able to bring this revenue together.
And not only does it create this huge.
Industry with huge revenue.
It is also providing a lot of governance
and regulation in terms of how smaller
businesses or enterprise customers, or
even a small or a personal entrepreneur.
If I want to have a small shop on
eBay or Etsy to sell a few of my
things I would be able to do that
in a secure and a reliable way by
creating an account with one of them.
So it's empowering.
People to have to go and build
and focus on their, again, on
their actual business use case.
Just worry about how will I sell this?
And not worry about, oh,
how will I host this?
Will my web website be up all the time?
Will I be under some
sort of security threat?
Or will my customer's data be lost?
So all these problems can be outsourced
to the cloud to a SAS organization.
And.
You as an individual or as a
business owner can only focus
on your business use cases.
How do I get my customers
to buy my things?
How do I boost that?
Or what are the problems?
Why are these products not selling?
Or why are, why is this the most
highly returned thing in my catalog?
So you can focus on that and you can
use ML engineering for that as well.
But the whole logistics
and deployment part of it.
That helps you maintain
an online presence.
All of that has been shipped
out and that empowers you to
to have more smaller businesses
and in turn then generating more
opportunities, more revenue, and so on.
So now that if you think of like
a customer or a person who wants
to use I will, I can actually give
a data scientist example because
that sounds more machine learning.
So if you talk about a data scientist who
wants to maybe has fragmented data sets
and now wants to put everything together
and extract meaningful patterns from it,
see and, get the most out of the data
that they have what can they do about it?
As step one, right?
If they come to a cloud or
if they come, go to any cloud
organization and request for certain
services like how do you start?
The first thing is like
feature definition.
So you might have a lot of data, but what
are you expecting to get out of the data?
There are two things.
What are you expecting versus what
the data is already giving you?
So for you to hey, I expect this data
to tell me the number of consumers
or the months in which the sale of.
Certain products go up, and now
I have this retail data that's
billions and billions of terabytes.
In these stages what you do is that
you use AI defined models, like
organizations will offer you a support.
An option to choose okay, do you want
us to tell you the latest and the
greatest of what the industry wants?
You may or may not have that data,
but there exists large language
models now that organizations
will offer you for nominal fee.
And these models strain on the latest
marketing trends that are collected.
And there are several sources.
We're not gonna go into the sources of how
marketing data is collected in this for
the purposes to keep the scope limited.
But assuming that there exists marketing
data from several sources they do exist.
A whole bunch of models that will help
you train that will help you pull out
advertisement specific information to
help you what is the next big feature.
That your customer wants.
So as a data scientist who wants to
get most out of data that is sales
related our AI ML models integrated into
our system will give you an insight.
They will run they will train
on billions and billions of
sales data sets, excuse me.
And they will tell you what is the
next cool thing the customer wants.
A recent example in our times has
been, some customers requested
auto code, like a code assist, code
assistance integration into their
development environments where the
code assist could explain code to them.
It could interpret the code for them,
it could auto generate some unit tests.
So all these things, that's a feature
request that even the customer
did not know that they wanted.
But when AI recommended these things
to them they were very happy to cus oh
wow, I could do something like that.
After that comes in the part where maybe
the data scientist is not very heavily
involved, but it could move towards the
the software development engineering
part of it where machine learning
engineers actually come into play.
They look at architectural
design and UML compliance.
If you have a feature request how
will your provider provide it to you?
They could either have that
feature available and it's just
about doing the legalities and.
Sales part of it where you come on board.
But the other bit is if the feature
is missing, we will go back.
The cloud provider will go back and
build it for the data scientist.
This stage is so every cloud
provider again follows very
strict networking patterns.
Architecture two a, two B, two C,
three C are some common examples that
can be Googled in networking patterns.
And then there are compliance tools
that make sure that every time you
make a feature request sometimes it's
called release management related tools.
And what these tools do is every
time you generate a new design
for a new feature they run over,
they run some compliance checks.
They run security checks to ensure that
you're not creating a breach or a leak.
They run some regression, they set
some platform acceptance standards in
related to and with regards to testing.
And they also make sure that
the new architecture that
you're introducing, the changes.
Are you introducing API changes.
Are you introducing UI changes?
Are you introducing like an
infrastructure as a level kind of
change, which is like a terraform change?
If you're doing all these, then there are
other regulatory standards to ensure that
your changes do not break or regress.
Anything that the organization
is already offering.
Once the architecture has been
laid out, that's when secure
development and testing comes in.
There's a huge bunch of software
engineers who will build code, will
build they might use code assistant
technologies again to comp, interpret,
comprehend to refactor that code, to
test the performance of that code.
Once that is done they will
once they open a pull request,
as we call it, a pull request.
There will be several tests run on it.
Although it's, it does require
some level of manual approval,
it's not touchless totally.
We do want developers to look at other
developers code and ensure that, Hey,
this change looks good to me as a
developer before we let AI and ML take
over and run compliance checks on it.
Once that happens, it's usually
merging and then putting it out there.
The deployment pipeline is totally is
totally orchestrated to be touchless.
So once you build and test in a certain
testing environment, you will roll it out
to like you will have a terraform level
infrastructure as a service tool that
will help you roll out your changes into
a more production-like environment first
and then into an environment and the.
In the live environment where
and usually you deploy it into a
smaller scale region where there are
lesser there are lesser customers.
Again, you have that insight from
the data that you collect and then
you deploy it to all your popular
regions with minimal impact to.
Existing performance of your system.
And then along with this,
there will be some compliance
verification standards, et cetera.
And so there are SOCs
as vpa data governance.
So there are certain e every
country basically has some
regulatory standards around data.
It implies not only to accessibility
and security, these compliances also
apply to, ease of use in simple terms.
So for example, VPA compliance says
that everybody, your websites have
to be accessible to anybody who's
reading a use, who is using a screen
reader or like an interpreter device.
Because they could have some hearing or
listening or speech related disabilities.
So your, the data, your website
should be very accessible to people
like these SOX compliance ensure that
everything that you promise a customer
or a data scientist you have set.
Acceptance, minimum acceptance standards.
And unless those standards are met,
you cannot call that criteria done.
Of course there are more legal legal and
sales later terms that come, but these are
at the core software engineering level.
These policies are established
for a software engineer to
manage the expectations and
the requirements of a product.
So once a data scientist has requested
a feature that maybe was not there, but
they wanted to use it on the cloud, and
the software engineering teams and ML
teams have built it and deployed it.
There be some level of continuous
monitoring and automation, and
that also requires a lot of
tools and ML specific tools.
We talk about them ML more.
So yeah.
What have, introducing these
tools and letting smaller
businesses, data scientists what
has this done to the industry?
What it has primarily done is that
it has it has empowered them, as I
mentioned in the past, but how do you
continuously monitor something like that?
So to continuously monitor and monitor
something like that companies typically
sign an SLA service level agreements.
And these service level agreements,
again, they come at the legal.
Aspect and sales aspect first, where
there'll be terms, you will sign
clauses with the companies, but for
continuous monitoring a company usually
promises like 99.99% times availability
that the service is gonna be up.
If you host your website on our
cloud, excuse me, your website
will be up and running for.
All of the year, except for
maybe two or three hours of
downtime, which is unpredictable,
could happen, could not happen.
But that's the max.
Your website will go down
and are reliable, secure.
Hardware, data centers, and
all the software we write over
it is gonna ensure that your
website is always up and running.
So these benchmarks also there
are other benchmarks around
sustainability and clean.
A few of them apply to companies
internally who are the cloud providers,
and some apply to the people, the
customer who's walking in as well.
And to maintain these compliance
and standards and reliability.
Excuse me.
A lot of requests okay, now when you
send a request okay, now I'm a data
scientist, I'm sending in a new request.
I am sending a request to maybe
create or launch a notebook or
Jupyter lab notebook, which could
be, which is actually just a vs.
Code editor equivalent
for a software engineer.
Now you launch a notebook because
you want to build a model inside it.
So the request that I send it should
be fulfilled under 500 millisecond.
If that's not happening, then that's
something that I put as a service
level agreement to my cloud provider.
And the cloud provider then runs
tools, automation tools to ensure that
there are constant monitoring alarms.
There are health check alarms that run to
ensure that this requirement is being met.
And the minute we don't, even
in the ML world now, we are
not even waiting for a breach.
We don't wait for the threshold to cross
500 milliseconds before you alarm and let.
Teams know that something is not right.
You start alarming at 300 milliseconds.
You expect your system to respond
within 200 to two 50 milliseconds.
And then if it's crossing
300, you start alarming.
You start creating tickets and
you start, and ML engineering not
only creates the alarm, but also
starts analyzing some possible ways.
Is there a hardware issue?
Is that, is there a scheduling issue?
Is there a round robin?
Did one of these data centers come down?
What happened?
Or is there too much overload and
is this a noisy neighbors problem?
Tenancy level issue, so
everything ML can help you.
ML is helping us at this point of
time optimize how do we look at
these problems and eventually provide
like great quality service to any
customer who is using the cloud.
Yeah, I did touch upon these regulatory
frameworks a little bit in the past.
So let's skip these for now.
Yeah.
Now in this pipeline of continuously
providing help and doing these things,
I spoke about Terraform bamboo and ci.
So now with.
Specifically talking about the CI ICD
stack and how it once a developer or a
machine engineer has built a cool feature
for his customer base, how is that gonna
land up in these production realms?
And what role does AI play here?
So although there are these automation
tools like GitLab, CI ICD, and even these
tools, these are third party tools and
even these tools are now integrating.
ML Insights through large language
models to understand what other
compliance gates are necessary.
So there are different tools
like clever that will analyze
the code coverage percentage.
You want to ensure that the best quality
code rolls out to your production regions.
So for that, you're gonna use you
will have an integrated use of these
tools and the ai and the algorithm
the large language or the small
language model that's optimizing your
prs your code that's coming in that
will run all these compliance tools.
It'll ensure that your
code coverage is optimal.
If it drops below a certain percentage,
you're not allowed to merge that code.
You have to add, you have to generate
your unit tests, you have to generate
aggression tests, or you have to, it'll
run security tests to make sure that
it'll lie all those standards instead of
Strat static security run time where it it
bombards your, like cross two, like it'll
simulate basically cross side scripting.
In a way it will simulate
denial of service attacks.
So these tools now can auto do
these on all your prs and all
your code that you're merging in.
And then it'll merge
into the master system.
It'll produce a build.
It'll produce a build,
which is like an artifact.
And that artifact has to be
deployed through Terraform into
all these several data centers.
Yeah, at every stage, ML is gonna
keep doing compliance automation
regression test to ensure
that your delivery is perfect.
Yeah.
And obviously the, coming back to the
resource optimization part of it, yes.
Hardware optimization is a very major
deal for cloud providing companies
because sustainability matters.
Your carbon footprint matters.
We know that data scientists
and data engineer.
Who manage like these huge data centers.
They know that like the usage
of electricity and water to
cool these data centers down.
And all of this has a very
huge environmental impact.
So you can pay for it and
you can afford to pay for it.
But then we are, we also have
responsibility towards the planet.
How are we utilizing ML in this space?
Machine learning optimizations now
most organizations like cloud engineer,
engineering orgs, especially huge orgs
that all orgs that, that manufacture
hardware or use hardware at a large scale.
They do have several.
Machine learning tools like something
it could be called something like a
cloud guard where these tools constantly
keep monitoring the usage of every
server instance that is brought up.
And if over a period of time if it
senses that, hey, your utilizations
always lower, then it will cut down on.
It'll automatically resize your
instances to a smaller size.
It'll run all load and performance
tests to ensure that the quality of
services, not impli, is not degraded,
but you end up having some savings
on how much CPU or GPU bandwidth or
memory that you're using there, you
will start saving on that and that
will have a good environmental impact.
Yeah.
So I spoke about these policies in
detail and how are we building and
monitoring at every stage of deployments.
And yeah.
In summary, I would like to say
that, this is just the beginning for
most ML and AI integration systems,
and it's a promising future ahead.
We have a lot of business and data,
sciencey based use cases that are
benefiting and will continue to
benefit in the future because of the
integration of large language models
and prompts and the data that we've
collected over decades and decades.
And the growth the growth and, the
growth of and explosion of AI for not
only, like smaller level use cases,
but even very high level use cases
like, or completely replacing search
algorithms with, large language models.
These things are in progress and these
things will continue to grow over time
and it's a very exciting future ahead.
So thank you for joining me on this
talk and I hope to see you guys in
person in the, in the in-person meet.
Thank you everyone.