I'm ach.
I'm happy to be here in Con
40 to Machine Learning 2025.
I'm a senior software engineer.
I have spent several years in building
a high performance microservices.
I'm here to talk about how to
build a high performance scalable
data pipeline for financial domain
in.
Today's volatile financial market
where millisecond can means
million in lost opportunities.
Traditional financial data
processing platform is failing to
meet the increasing large volume
of data processing in short time.
This architecture explains how to build
an high performance scalable data pipeline
for the financial institution to handle
millions of transaction in short period
of time with exceptional performance.
The challenges of modern financial data
processing be categorized into volume
constraint, latency requirement, and
data heterogeneity, volume constraint,
legacy system struggle to handle
thousands of transaction in a
second during normal processing
time, often it completely failing.
During market volatility, even when
volumes can increase by order of
magnitude latency requirements.
Modern trading platform operate
in microsecond environment where
even millisecond delays can
result in significant monetary
losses and missed opportunities.
For question adjustment data
heterogeneity financial institution
must integrate data from.
Multiple formats like Swift Jsl file
and in different delivery channels
like FTP, MQ channels, Kafka topic,
and many more, which creates complexity
that compounds performance challenges.
Let me explain this architecture
of this data pipeline.
This, let's start with
the canonical schema.
Normalization is the very first beginning.
Stage where data represent in
standardized format to enable
the seamless data integration
with cross platform capabilities.
Layer is.
Collects and the process data extremely
quickly while having backup mechanism
that automatically switches operation.
If the primary system fails, which have
the retry capabilities in the enrichment
framework, raw financial data will be
enhanced with additional information like
security details, account details, and fx,
and any conversion, and the calculation
will be done as part of this section.
Storage layer.
So once this enrichment is done,
the data will be flattened.
That will be stored into our Oracle
database with unique indexing and
the parting for each data sets in
the analytical consumption layer.
We are using the advanced realtime
visualization to generate dashboards
using the predictive analytics
with faster performance queries.
Let we deeply explain about the canonical
schema normalization in the input
format, multiple trading platform,
delivering data in proprietary formats
with inconsistent field structure,
different time zones, daytime format.
So this transformation engine is capable
of dynamically mapping the field based
on the predefined schema structure.
Which eliminates this input, format,
issues, and validation layer.
The schema validation is enforced to
prevent from the incompatible data
type and other formatting issue and
the configurable exception handling.
Ensure a data integrity through
the throughout the pipeline,
standardized output, uniformly
structured transaction with consistent
identifiers and the normalized
field enabling seamless downstream
processing regardless of data origin.
As part of the enrichment framework,
the perfor, our enrichment framework
in corporates, multiple reference
data to enrich the raw transaction
into complete data endpoints.
This help to spend less time
to analyze multiple platform
for different data points.
Strategic data storage.
We have, we are using the Oracle
database for the better performance.
As part of the strategic data storage.
We are first analyze while
onboarding the data set.
We will.
Analyze the query patents and data
volumes will be for, to analyze that
load of the data and partnering will be
done for all the required dataset with.
Advanced time series optimization.
Custom design indexes and optimized
query plans are used to better results.
Our database architecture have
dramatically reduced complex query
response time and production environments.
This strategy was engineered to
optimally distribute load across
multiple node for max availability.
This achieving?
Yes, 78% reduction in average
query latency for a mys
critical financial operation.
So mission critical financial operation,
auto-scaling mechanism.
I. Our auto schooling mechanism
that maintain consistent performance
during market volatility automatically
adjusting resource van tra transaction
volumes spikes during peak periods.
Our predictive scaling algorithm
analyze historical patterns and current
market conditions to proactively
provision resources before demand
materialize, maintaining latency SLAs
even during extreme volume events.
The performance benchmark.
Our performance benchmark showcases
the architecture throughput capability
capabilities with substantial capacity
to handle market driven search.
When record.
These metrics were validated under
simulated market volatility conditions
matching historical flash crash
scenario, ensuring robust during extreme
events our architecture is able to.
Process 300 k transaction per
minute in the normal scenario.
But in the, during the burst, it able
to process four 50 K messages between
the within eight to 10 millisecond
response time.
The availability is 99.99
percentage with this architecture.
Our implementation case studies results
as categorized into three sections
like transaction processing capacity,
system availability, cost efficiency.
Our implementation achieved the four
50 percentage increase in transaction
processing capacity, enabling the system
to handle significant higher volume
without performance and degradation.
This eliminated previously common
processing backlogs during market events.
The system reliability, unplanned
downtime was virtually eliminated
with a reduction from approximately
few hours to under three minutes.
Component.
Component failures now resolve
quickly compared to the lengthy
outages and legacy system.
With operational recovery, time
improves from hours to minutes.
Cost efficiency, pre-transaction
infrastructure costs were reduced
by 68% through more efficient
resource utilization and the
elimination of T processing.
Complete pipeline lifecycle through
accusation to the conception.
So when the publisher is publishing
that data into the data bus are
raw, consumer is able to.
Lesson messages from the database.
For each dataset, we have the separate
MQ channels to listen the messages.
The ingestion layer is able to
quickly read the messages from the
database and it publish into the,
our internal processing layers.
There we have the enrichment layer, which
transforms the raw data into the complete
data set by invoking the reference
data and enrich all the data endpoints.
And once this is.
Enriched.
We are using the Oracle database, which is
Oracle database where that data is
stored in flattened format and also
it able to perform like thousands
of records and a second without
compromising any performance and.
We have, and then we have
the analytical layer.
We are creating the dashboard
using the predictive analytic with
the past of performance query.
So we will not see any
lag in the dashboards and
and key takeaways and next
steps from this architecture.
The.
This presented architecture
has demonstrated the ability
to process hundreds of thousand
financial transactions per second
with sub millisecond latency.
Providing that properly designed system
can meet the demands of modern financial
market implementation consideration.
When it comes to the
implementation consideration.
Organization should begin with the.
Comprehensive audit of current data flows.
Identify the most critical
performance bench bottleneck and
implement the architecture using an
incremental approach that delivers
measurable improvement at each stage.
Architectural balance success depends on
balancing multiple competing priorities
like latency versus throughput,
complexity versus maintainability, and
specialized optimization versus flex.
Flexibility, a adoption to change
requirements future direction.
Our research continue to.
Continues into integrating machine
learning for predictive scaling
and anomaly detection, exploring
graph database technologies for
relationship modeling and implementing
zero downtime upgrade paths.
Thank you for visiting this presentation.
I hope this presentation helped to
build a high performance, scalable get
up pipeline for the financial domain.
Thank you.