Speaker 24: Hi, my name's Rohan Mitra.
I'm a product manager at
Phonepay, a Walmart company.
Today I am here to talk about
how the 10 page PRD is dead.
But by coding your way into
production is a recipe for kiosk.
Today we are defining the modern
AI spec, a decision engine designed
to turn on technical ambiguity
into high performing AI products.
Good morning everyone.
It's great to be here.
Let's dive right in.
So let's start with the big question
that's been all over our feeds lately
is the humble, but my TPRD dead, you've
probably seen the debates kicked off
by Ditas like mother guru at Google.
He tweeted recently that they're moving
from writing first culture to a building.
First one.
He made a great point really writing
used to be a proxy for clear thinking
when development cycles belong.
But now when you can white code
a prototype in the same time it
takes to write a doc by write.
And honestly, at some
level we can all feel this.
She hold 40 page VRD that sits unread
in a folder after that first email.
And at best, a handoff call.
That's probably a thing of the
past, but this new build first
world has its own set of problems.
It can be chaotic.
It's easy to fall into the feature
factory trap, build things fast,
but not building the right things or
building things that we can't measure.
And what you can't measure, can't succeed.
I am someone who identifies as a
vibe coder myself, and hence, I also
know firsthand that having the right
documentation and specs for both human
as well as agentic coding is more
important today than ever before.
So if the old PD is too slow
and vibe coding alone is too
risky, what's the answer?
I believe it's a new kind of
document, and it's not a manuscript,
it's a decision making tool.
It's something I call the modern AI spec.
So while the PRD dying, it's
because we've seen all seen ex doc
examples of documents like these.
This got out bo, what I call
the wide space spec, is to
look at the first example.
The problem statement has been defined
as the returns are a big problem.
Goal is to improve customer's
experience with returns.
These aren't decisions, they're wishes.
Returns are a big
problem for our business.
How big improve customer experience
By how much compared to what
Baseline decreased refund rates.
Are there any guardrails around?
It Doesn't look like it.
Let's look at the other example
on which is probably even better.
The AI behavior spec is
generate helpful replies.
Generate helpful replies.
What does that even mean?
What's helpful for one may not be
helpful for another and my personal
favorite, start small, then run.
There's a masterclass in saying nothing.
These documents are full of
words, but they're of decisions.
The ambiguity is the single
biggest source of wasted sprints
and confused data science teams.
The antidote isn't no document.
It's a document that forces clarity,
and that's what we are here to build.
So this is the framework.
This is our modern AI spec.
It's adapted from the best practices
at teams, from companies like mop,
ai, meta, and Google, as well as
what I use every day at my work.
It moves us away from generic requirements
and focuses on the five specific things
that actually make or break AI projects.
Number one, opportunity framing.
Why are we even doing
this in the first place?
Number two, behavior contract.
What does good actually look like?
Number three, evaluation.
How do we prove it works
before even before we ship?
Number four, boundaries and scope.
What are the trade-offs we are accepting?
What are some non goals that
are out of scope for this?
And number five, risks and recovery.
What are the risks?
What is our contingency plan?
What is our code switch?
We're going to deep dive and demo all of
these in a moment, but I want to zoom in
on the two pillars that are completely
unique to AI products, the behavior
contract, and their evaluation plan.
So let's look at the second pillar.
Number two, the behavior contract.
In traditional software, you write logic.
If user clicks button open model.
In ai, you can't really write logic.
You have to describe a personality.
If you just write, generate
helpful replies, you have failed.
Your engineer doesn't
know what that means.
He doesn't know what to prompt to the ai.
The behavior contract
solves this with examples.
Look at this real example
from a smart reply spec.
Good?
Yes.
Sending by 4:00 PM brief
and actionable bad.
I will send you the things you asked for.
It sounds robotic, probably
vague and reject any mention
of confidential project names.
This isn't just documentation.
This is you, the product manager, defining
the soul of the product so that the
engineer can tune the model to match it.
Next is the big.
Next is the evaluation plan.
This is the part that usually gets kept
in white coding, and it's one of the
biggest reasons that products fail in ai.
It works on my laptop, means nothing.
You need a rigorous way to
graduate, a feature from an
idea to production in what?
I make it more, less
probabilistic and more objective.
Deterministic.
We call this the evaluation ladder.
Step one, offline.
Before we show a single user, we test
against a golden set, 500 perfect examples
that we align and agree on human review.
Then we look at the output.
Does it feel right?
Is it hallucinating?
We sort of eyeball it.
Step three is online guardrails.
When we go live, we set guardrails.
For example.
It doesn't matter how
fast the rep applies, are.
If the block message rate goes up
by even 0.3%, we kill the feature.
And this is really what the difference
is between a prototype and a product.
A prototype has vibes, a
product has a passing bar.
Alright, enough talk.
Let's put this into practice.
Instead of talking about it, let's do it.
Remember that smart reply
spec that we laughed at?
Let's.
The one where the goal was
to just improve engagement.
We are going to rescue that project.
We are going to rewrite that spec right
now, using our five pillar framework.
We open a new doc.
Smart replies, but better respect.
All right, so let's fix that broken
smart reply spec that we saw earlier.
I'm going to start with a
blank five pillar template.
The first step was opportunity framing.
So here we clearly call out the
user problem first PM response
times average, whatever, eight.
Point three minutes creating,
lemme just get this communication.
Communication friction.
Alright, so what are we saying?
What will happen if we do this?
If we solve this problem?
Hypothesis.
If we offer three context,
sorry, aware suggestions.
P 50 reply times drop by.
Greater than or equal to 10%.
So 10% see the difference.
Now we have a baseline and a
target that we can aim for.
Next is the behavior.
Behavior contract.
This is where we kill the
ambiguity first, the numbers.
Proxy metric, smart reply.
Adoption
rates greater than or equal
to 25% guardrail metric.
These are based, these are hygiene.
There's nothing new.
But we are explicitly saying we want
adoption, but not at the care cost of.
Let's define what that cost is.
Point three, percentage
points versus control.
So we are saying that we want adoption,
but not at the cost of annoying users to
the point that they actually block people.
Another example then this
is crucial, a good response.
Yes.
Sending it by 4:00 PM for a Pacific time.
Actionable, specific.
Let's do a bad response next.
Bad response.
That's a bad response.
It's something that's
technically correct but useless.
I will send you the things
you asked for is robotic and
vague and frankly unnecessary.
You can just send things and
reject something that's forbidden.
Any response.
Mentioning confidential projects or PII.
Now let's make the V plan,
as I like to call it.
What's a V zero?
How do we be scrappy?
Do we need a massive LLM for V zero?
Probably not.
V zero hard code.
The top.
10 most common replies,
stuff like, thank you.
Thanks.
Got it.
You get the drift as buttons test
if people even click buttons.
We can build this day's V zero in
a day without even touching A GPU.
Finally, no, sorry, not finally.
Second.
From last, boundaries trade offs.
Accepted V will accept plus
300 millisecond latency to
generate better suggestions.
So we are telling engineering
right now it's okay to be slightly
slower if the quality is higher.
That's a leadership decision,
that's a strategic decision.
And then finally, risks,
or rather a risk avoidance.
Let's call it kill switch.
Feature toggle in admin panel.
No.
And accessible to On Call Engineers.
If the model starts hallucinating
inserts, we call it in five seconds.
And there you have it with, in about five
minutes, we've turned helpful replies into
a specific, measurable safe product plan.
This document is now a decision
engine with an opportunity framed.
A behavior contract signed,
sealed, and delivered a V plan.
Boundaries and risk avoidance.
Look at what we just created.
We took that generic and goalless document
from slide two and we turned it into this.
We have a proxy metric that
defines success, a guardrail that
protects the user experience.
We have an explicit trade off on latency,
and most importantly, we have a clear
trade behavior contract that tells
engineering exactly what helpful means.
This document is no longer a
masterclass in saying nothing.
It is a decision log.
It is a shield against wasted work.
This is how you lead.
Let's bring it all home.
We've covered a lot, but
it all comes down to this.
The modern AI spec isn't
just another template.
It's actually a single most powerful
tool for leadership in the AI era.
First, it's how you navigate the politics.
You, when a stakeholder uses
first principles as a rhetorical
tool, you don't have to argue.
Use the spec to make
the tradeoffs explicit.
Second, it's how you clarify the kiosk.
Pipe coding is fun, but
it can be unfocused.
This spec is the insurance policy
that gives your billion team the
alignment to build with confidence.
And finally, it's how
you build your skills.
The framework is the job.
It's how you practice scrappiness,
clear communication and low ego.
This is how you stop just being
a manager of features and being a
leader of a high performing AI team.
Thank you very much.
My goal today was to give you a practical
framework that doesn't just help you
write better docs, but to navigate the
complex realities of our jobs and build
the essential skills for this new AI era.
Please feel free to connect
with me on LinkedIn.
Thank you very much.