Hey, good evening everyone.
It is an absolute honor to stand
before you at Com 42 Mission
Learning 2025 conference.
My name is thi I'm leading
engineer from Credit Union.
Today we embark into the fraud of
financial security, a place where.
Artificial intelligence and mission
learning and risk management matches
to redefine our digital economy.
Imagine in our modern financial
ecosystem as a vast network of
countless transactions harming every
second in this vibrant landscape.
Trust is the foundation of every
interaction, and even the smallest
irregularity can spark a major
risk before risk management.
Coming through records, spotting
errors and reacting only
after incident had occurred.
That method, although one sufficient now
falls short against the sophisticated
methods of modern frauders.
Today, AI acts as a tireless guardian that
learns continuously from realtime data by
predicting unusual behavior long before
it evolves into a full blown threat.
With advanced neural networking and
machine learning, AI not only detects
anomalous patterns, but also stops them in
the tracks picture and intelligent systems
that monitors thousands of transactions
simultaneously with each transaction.
It.
Compared current behavior with
historical pattern learning what normally
happens and flagging any D deviations.
This proactive approach means that
potential threats or neutralize
it before any harm is done.
It's like having a vigilant security
team that never sleeps, always adapting
to new challenges and ensuring the.
Today will reveal how AI reshapes
risk management from increasing
detections accuracy to reduce false
alarms and up responses to threat.
I'll share real time examples
by illustrating how financial
institutes are saving millions
simply by being mu up ahead of.
As we dive in, think of AI not as
a cold mission, but as a dedicated
partner that supports you every
time you make a digital transaction.
Coming to next slide, oh.
AI power fraud detection.
Fraud detection in today's financial
world is no longer a reactive process.
It is a dynamic AI power strategy
that works around the clock.
Traditional systems rely on pixel tools
on historical data, but the static
models often fall short when facing
rapidly evolving fraudulent techniques.
Today, air fraud detection
elevates our defense.
By continuously learning from vast amount
of data, uncovering hidden patterns, once
responding to threats with unprecedented
speed and accuracy, imagine a system
that increased detection accuracy by 87%.
This means that rather than relying on
simplistic rules that might miss signs of.
Understands the complex
behaviors behind transactions.
By analyzing hundreds of
variables in real time.
AI identifies even the slightest
deviation from normal patterns.
For example, if your customer
who normally make small purchases
should initiate multiple high
value transaction, the AI system
instantly for further investigations.
Is only part of the story.
One of the biggest challenge in fraud
detection is the issue of false positive.
When a system triggers too many
alert, legitimate transactions
can be unnecessarily.
Customers and clogging
up financial channels.
AI addresses this by reducing
false positive by 63% by ensuring
that only through suspicious
activities are escalated.
These kind of this refined approach saves
valuable time and resources enabling
institutions to focus on real threats
without causing in to genuine customers.
Another remarkable benefit is accelerated
response time, which is up to 95%
faster than traditional systems.
In today's digital age, every millisecond
counts when an anomaly is detected.
The AI Systems act immediately by haling
a transaction before it completes.
If it deems two.
This near instantaneous reactions is
vital for preventing fraud as delays
can allow activities to succeed.
Coming to next slide pattern,
recognization breakthrough.
In this fight against fraud,
pattern recognition is the
secret weapon that sets a part.
Fraud detection often hinges on
the ability to see the unseen.
A web of SubT patterns
that humans might miss.
AI is breakthrough in pattern recognition.
Enormous dataset.
Identify normal behavioral trends and
pinpoint anomalies that signs fraud
before any visible damage occurs.
Let's begin with process
of data collection.
In today's faults, financial data use
sourced from different channels like bank
transactions, payment gateways, mobile
apps, and even social media interactions.
These AI systems aggregate this diverse
data stream to build a comprehensive
picture of financial behavior.
Every transaction service has a puzzle
piece contributing to an overall
pattern that defines what is normal.
Once this massive collection
of data is like harmonized.
It is analyzed using advanced
neural networking techniques.
These networks learn from historical
transactions, establishing
baseline patterns for individuals
and collective behavior.
Furthermore, AI leverages
anomaly detection algorithms
that flags activities even when.
When viewed in isolation, considered
multiple low value transactions
spread across different accounts.
Each transaction individually might
not seem suspicious, but together
they form a pattern that suggest
coordinated fraudulent activities.
Transaction systems might overlook
such kind of behavior, but AI
pattern recognizes brings this
hidden connections to light.
Coming to next slide, real time financial
transactions, monitoring and interactions.
Imagine a system that never sleeps, addit
Sentinel, that monitors every financial
transaction as it happens, scrutinizing
hundreds of risk factors in microseconds.
That is the promise of real transaction.
Access both the vigilant and
watchman under pro and scepter in
today's high speed distal economy.
Timing is everything ideally
of even f fraction of a second
can turn a minor anomaly.
Full-blown security breach.
Realtime financial transactions
monitors begins the moment
a transaction is initiated.
Data flow instantly through intelligent
algorithms that compare each new
transaction against millions of historical
records, checking for any deactive,
any deviations from expected behavior.
These systems evaluate details
like transaction amount.
The time, the geographical location,
and even the user's typical behavior.
When any unusual activity is detected,
perhaps a SHA done change in spinning
pattern or a new device used for access,
the system is immediately locked.
This instantaneous detection
allows the AI not only to flag the
as suspicious, but also to take.
For instance, when the system recognizes
a potential threat, it can auto inter
by using the transaction or routing
it for additional verifications.
The response is nearly instantaneous,
up to 95% faster than traditional
methods reducing the window
in which fraud can occur.
Coming to next slide.
This is the slide where we discuss
about transforming loan collections.
Loan collection has traditional
libin, challenging lab in process,
manual follow ups and standardized
reminders of and field sort of
addressing the unique circumstances of.
Revolutionizing loan collections
by transforming it for a rigid
one size fits all approach into a
personalized data-driven strategy
that improves recovery rates and
strengthens customer relationships.
At the heart of this transformation
is the ability of AI to analyze
and historical data points by evaluating.
Borrowing history, payment
behavior, seasonal spending,
and even extra economic factors.
AI can predict each borrower's likelihood
of repayment with remarkable procession.
Imagine in receiving personalized
outreach that does more than just
remind you about your next payment.
It speaks to your individual
financial situations offering.
Flexible solutions that suits your needs.
For financial institutions,
the benefits are very immense.
AI driven strategies have boosted recovery
rates significantly in many cases.
Personal roles, personal loans,
received recovery has seen
improvements up to 27% points.
In the business loans, traditionally
the most difficult to recover
have jumped from 41 to 76%.
These improvements are not just
numbers that represent real
challenges for borrowers and lenders.
When each interaction is tailored to the
individual collections become less about.
Confrontation and more about
clear empathy communication.
Consider the concept of
personalizing timing.
AI systems, analyze patterns to detect
undetermined, many borrowers most
to communications in the month.
When.
Later when a regular payment cycle is
able to begin by finding the optimal
moment, the system can send a friendly
and timely reminder that resonates
and results in positive responses
rather than a generic message that
might be ignored or cause frustrations
is also building relationship.
Borrow.
Understood.
They're most likely to engage with
the institution and work toward
resolving their financial challenges.
The system can suggest alternative payment
plans by offering counts on managing
finances and adopted approach as a
situation change in real time, continuous
feedback from these interactive.
Helps define the AI models by
ensuring that each subsequent
intervention is even more effective.
Coming to next slide payment
processing revolution in our
rapid evolving digital error.
Payment processing is undergoing
a dramatic transformation.
In the time are increasingly
unable to meet today's demands
for speed accuracy on security.
Enter the payment processing revolution
propel by a, which is rapidly redefining
how every transaction is executed,
conventional payments systems.
Being the backbone of
financial transactions.
However, these systems can
be inefficient and slow.
The rely on manual interventions
for exceptions, process transactions
in batches, and often like the
ability required in today's
high speed digital economy.
In contrast, AI enhance systems
offer a fluid adoptive approach
by payment processing the
dramatically improved performance.
Imagine every payment being processed
as if it'll on fast track once
your transaction is initiated.
AI systems immediately This.
Using a set of adapt multifactor
authentication checks, and
comparing current details with
historical data and patterns.
This means that transaction no longer
follow a singular predetermined route.
Instead, they are intellectually routed
through the network, along the path
that maximizes both speed and security,
in instance, where problem arises.
These systems can automatically
resolve issues by self-managing
exceptions that would have previously
required manual interventions.
The result is like transactions
are crossed almost instantaneously
with minimal risk of errors
or delays for businesses.
This translates to improved
customer satisfaction.
Free payment process for
financial institutions.
The reduction in processing times
means lower operational cost
and enhanced overall efficiency.
Every second.
Saving in processing helps build
more dynamic contrast once financial
ecosystem alongside speed and efficiency.
The revolutions in payment processing
also introduces a new level of.
Coming to next slide,
ethical AI framework.
Coming to ethical AI framework as
we integrate AI into every fact of
financial security, tackling issues
of fairness, transparency, privacy,
and accountability is paramount.
Our ethical AI framework.
Is the bedrock upon which
responsible innovations is built.
It ensures that while we leverage
sophisticated technology,
we remain steadfast in our
commitment to human values.
Fairness in AI means that every decision
made by our systems is free from our.
Audited to prevent discrimination
across any demographic.
By designing systems that adopt and learn
without reinforcing historical data.
We build trust not only within
institutions, but also with our customers.
Transparency is equally crucial.
Every action.
An AI system must be explainable
when transaction is flagged, or
a loan application is deviated.
The reason is clearly documented.
This transparency benefits regulatory
and instills confidence among.
Customers.
Privacy is another
pillar of our framework.
Financial data is highly sensitive, and
our approach guarantees that personal
information is never exposed to anyone.
High level encryption on Strat
an normalization protocols
ensure that data is used only to.
Accountability is
maintained through a robust
governance structure.
Regular review and designated
oversight committees and comprehensive
audit trials all contribute to a
system where every decision is.
Trackable and all stakeholders
are responsible for
maintaining ethical standards.
In our session today, we'll
explore how an ethical AI framework
is an obstacle to innovation.
It is the guide focus that ensures
technology serves humanity.
I will share example of institutions
adopting standard showing that.
Effective governance can coexist with
rapid technological advancements.
When people see that decisions are made
transparently, unfairly, the trust grows.
Trust is the currency of the digital
economy under our ethical framework.
Guarantees that AI works for all of us.
Just on responsible manner.
Coming to next slide, which
is regulatory navigation.
In this slide, navigating the regulatory
landscape in today's financial
voltage request, both foresight and
adaptability with evolving legislations
and diverse regulations across.
Financial institutions must be enough
to compel with new requirements
while continuing to innovate.
A is proving to be an invaluable asset
in this regard by offering tools that.
Not only ensure compliance, but also
enhance transparency and risk management.
Modern AI systems can continuously
scan changes in regulatory standards
across regions and sectors.
They flag potential contradictions
and compliance gaps in real time.
Imagine a system that updates itself
with every new regulation published.
Immediately adjust its risk assessment
models, ensuring all operations
remain within legal boundaries.
This realtime monitoring is not only
proactive, but also incredibly efficient
by reducing the risk of non-compliance,
which could otherwise lead to costly
ities and reputational damages.
Another significant benefit is.
Every decision made by ai, whether it
involves flagging, suspicious transaction
or processing loans is recorded with clear
documentation of reasoning behind it.
The documentation is invaluable
during regulatory reviews as it
shows a clear path of decision
making that regulators can follow.
Transparent documentation,
builds trust with.
Demonstrates a commitment to
responsible ethical financial practices.
Coming to next slide,
implementation strategy assessment.
Pilot program.
Scalable development and
continuous evolution are like
the four strategies we follow as
aspect of implementing artificial
intelligence in financial industries.
Implementing AI driven risk management is
yet transformational journey that requires
careful planning, testing, and scaling.
The process begins with assessment of.
During the pilot program, the focus
is on gathering data and refining the
algorithms through real world feedback.
The system is closely monitored by
enabling adjustments in the real time
to maximize efficiency and accuracy.
Coming to.
Oh, sorry.
There are two more strategies that need
to be discussed as part of this slide.
That is skill development
and continuous evolution.
We'll also examine strategies
for maintaining continuous
evolution without within.
Your AI system.
This means establishing feedback
loops that regularly incorporate
new data, updating the models and
ensuring the system remains robust
in the face of evolving threats.
The journey does not stop it.
The initial rollout.
Ongoing monitorings and regular audits and
interactive improvements ensure that AI.
Effective and secure.
Lastly, our decision will
include practical examples from
institutions that have successfully
implemented AI driven strategies.
These courses, studies highlights
the challenges they encountered.
The benefits realized and
the best practice serve.
Coming to next, last slide.
In conclusion today we have journey
to the transformation to role of
artificial intelligence and machine
learning and financial risk management.
We begin at Financial Frontiers
exploring how AI redefine security by
predicting and preventing threats before.
Current security landscape learned how
AI powered fraud detection and pattern
recognization on real time monitoring
creates proactive defenses and witnessed
how these technologies transform process
from payments to loan collections.
We have also seen that responsible
innovations is built upon.
That emphasizes fairness, transparency,
privacy and accountability.
Navigating the complex regulatory,
implementing AI solutions and
continuously evolving these systems
is not just a technical challenge,
but also cultural journey.
Together, these breakthrough
makes our financial systems.
And thank you everyone.