Hello everyone.
Welcome to conference 42.
I hope y'all have a great time.
I'm Sheika Ana, a dynamic Salesforce
professional with over seven years of
experience in delivering innovative CRM
solutions across various industries.
As a leading consultant in
Salesforce ecosystem, I have a deep
understanding of the platform and
the trend that's shaping its future.
My experience working with the Salesforce
customers and partners has given me
a unique insight and evolving the
landscape and the opportunity that lie.
Ah.
I am passionate about Salesforce
ecosystem because it represents
the powerful digital transformation
and innovation and business growth.
The ecosystem constantly evolving with
the new technologies, industry specific
solutions and partner specialized.
Emerging all the time by
sharing my perspective on
the future of this ecosystem.
I hope help the Salesforce partners
and the customers alike navigate the
changing landscape and identifying
the most promising areas of
the investments and the growth.
My goal is to provide the comprehensive
overview of the key trends that we, that
will define the ecosystem Salesforce
ecosystem better, so that you can
better position your organization for
success as a representative voice of
Salesforce community, I believe I'm
uniquely qualified to lead discussion.
I spent years studying the platform and
collaborating with the industry leaders.
And staying at the forefront
of the latest developments.
I'm excited to share my knowledge
and insight with you today.
And ultimately my aim is to
empower you with the information
and the strategic guidance you
need to drive into the Salesforce
ecosystem, like by understanding
where the platform is headed.
You'll be better equipped to make
the information informed dec sorry,
informed decisions and capitalize on
emerging opportunities and deliver
unparalleled value to your customers.
Having said this, let's dive into the
let's dive into the Salesforce ecosystem.
Which is a powerful success
through a platform partnership.
Like Salesforce has a long
recognition power of ecosystems in
diving innovative, delivering the
comprehensive solutions to its customers.
At this time, we will explore
the key Innovatives of the key
innovatives and strategic Salesforce
has implemented to foster the Drive
One network, which focus on the.
Focus on the app exchange
and Trailhead platform
Trailhead platform.
Okay, going to the next slide.
The major wins of the current ecosystem
is multi success and strategic
partnership and connected platform.
One.
What is multis success?
Salesforce ecosystem is designed to
foster the success of its partners and
the customers in a multi beneficiary way.
Like partners gain the access to the
larger customer base and comprehensive
resource and trusted bands, and
enabling their grow through that
Salesforce related business and customer
benefits with the wide array of.
Prebuilt solutions, deep integrations
and expert implementation and support
services from Salesforce Partners.
This is like a win-win approach
alliance, and the interest of all the
ecosystems participants, ecosystem
participants driving collectively
growth and prosperity, and other one
is, as I said, strategic partnership.
Salesforce ecosystem is built on
a strategic partnership with a
diverse range of players, including
ISV consulting firms, technology
providers, and developers.
And these partnerships enable
the Salesforce to expand the
platform capabilities and
address evolving customer needs.
And other one is like leverage the
expertise and the domain knowledge
of its partners and offers.
A comprehensive suits of solutions
and caters the various industries and
the use cases by fostering fostering
these strategic partnerships.
Salesforce can ahead, can stay ahead
of the curve, respond to the market
changes, and deliver the great values
to the customers and connecting.
Coming to the connected platforms
like Salesforce ecosystem, underpinned
by highly connected platforms that
seamlessly integrate the partner
solutions and service the app exchange.
Salesforce online marketplace
serves as a central hub of all.
Of this connected ecosystems like Hello
partners to showcase, showcase their
offerings and reach a wider customer base.
And other one is leverage the
Salesforce APIs and development tools
to build tightly integrated solutions.
And one more point is collaborate with
the other ecosystem members to create
a comprehensive end-to-end solutions.
And this connected platform
approaches Salesforce customer
customers to access the diverse
range of Preintegrated solutions and.
Streamlining the technologies,
adoptions and driving driving
greater business values.
Now let's go a little bit more
into the app exchange numbers.
As I said, app Exchange is a
world leading enterprise cloud
marketplace, like providing providing
the Salesforce customers with.
Access of a vast ecosystem, like
a prebuilt apps solutions and
the consultants, the numbers
behind this powerful platform was
like truly impressive and large.
As per me and the app exchange
boost over, as I said, like 8,000.
8,000 apps and the solutions
spanning a wide range of business
functionalities and industries.
And this extensive catalog allows
the Sales force customers to quickly
find and deploy the tools they
need to enhance their sales force.
And the app the apps and the solutions
available in the app exchange
has been installed like over.
90, 90 million times and test and
estimated the value that properly
among the Salesforce customer and
the massive adoption rate of high
highlights the app exchange ability
to deliver the business impact.
And an impressive of 80% of Fortune
500 countries has leveraged the app
exchange to extend their capabilities
for their Salesforce instance.
And this demonstrates the platform
widespread appear appeal and
the critical role play in its
enterprise solution landscape.
And AppExchange reaches the exchange,
the global, with the apps and the
solutions available in sales for
customers in over one 50 countries.
And the global footprint ensures
the business around the world.
Can access the tool and they need
they need to drive the Salesforce
Power Digital Transformation.
Since the app action has generated
like over 6.2 billion in revenue
for its partner ecosystem,
it, it's starring the figures.
Sorry, this starring the figures,
underscores the commercial success and.
Viability of the platform of the both
Salesforce customers and app developers.
This number span like compiling pictures
of AppExchange scale, impact, and
the importance with the Salesforce
ecosystem by providing a market.
Place of a pre-built solutions.
The app exchange empowers the
customers to quickly extend the
capability to the platform and drive
greater value for their investments.
As a Salesforce ecosystem
continuously evolve.
The app exchange is process to
play and even more integral role
enabling the business and unlock
the new level of innovations
and productives and competitive.
Competitive advantages.
Let's go into the next slide and
the enterprise app marketplace.
The app exchange has a transformative
impact on the Salesforce customers,
empowering them to enhance.
The Salesforce experience and
drive greater business value.
Here are some key ways that AppExchange
can benefit the Salesforce customer.
One is ac accelerate the time to value,
which means like the app exchange
provides a pre-built and ready.
To install apps and the solutions
that can quickly deploy to the address
specific business needs, and these
dramatically reduces the time of the
results and the require required to
implement a new functionality and the
help the customer realize, rely, realize
the value of the Salesforce first.
And other one is like increase the
productivity by integrating the
best in the cla best in class third
party apps where the Salesforce
instance instances the customer can
automate the workflow, streamline
the processes, and empower the team.
To work more efficiently.
This boosts in the productive translates
to improve optional performance
and better business outcomes.
And other one is like
best industry solutions.
What does that mean?
The app exchange offers a wide range of
industry specific solutions, allowing
customers to find apps that are perfectly
aligned with their unique business.
Requirements.
And this level of specification
helps the customers to overcome
the industry specific challenges
and gain a competitive edge.
And other one, I would say user
adoption, like enhanced user adoption.
Many app exchange.
App exchange apps are design.
To give the best user experience, make
it easier for the employees to adopt
the utilization of the sales force.
This improves the user
experience and drives the higher
engagement and ensure that.
The customer maximum
value out of Salesforce.
Salesforce investment.
And other point is reduce
the cost of ownership.
By leveraging the prebuilt apps from
the app exchange, customer can avoid the
time and the cost associated to build the
custom solution or custom development,
and this allows them to reduce overall
technology, spending time and focus more
resources on strategic innovates and
other one is like continuous innovation.
The app exchange is continuously evolving
with the new apps and the solutions
being added regularly, and the and
this ensures that customers always
have the latest innovations and allows
them to stay ahead of the curve and add
up the change of the business needs.
And like ultimately, the app exchange has
become the best tool for the Salesforce
customers, empowering them to extend.
The capabilities of the platform
and drives greater value and stay
competitive in their respective markets.
And.
And as as the Salesforce ecosystem
continues to growth, and Im and the
impact of the app exchange on customer
success will become more pronounced.
That's more about the app exchange.
Let's talk a little bit more
about the Salesforce trailhead.
Salesforce Trailhead it's, say
Trailhead is a Salesforce innovative
learning platform that empowers
individuals to develop in demand
of a Salesforce skills and.
Advance their careers, like Salesforce is
a but of a size of content, which with fun
and engaging learning experience make it.
Doing that, like making it
powerful tool for both Salesforce
users and broader ecosystem.
One is like interactive learning path,
meaning like Trailhead offers a wide range
of learning path, covering everything.
From the Salesforce administration,
development, and industry specific and
role-based skills, each learning path
is structured as a series of interactive
modules, allows learners to progress
through the content at their own
place and earn badges upon completion.
And other one is like hands-on challenges.
Trailhead incorporates hands-on
challenges and the projects enable.
Learners to apply their knowledge
and the skills in particular
particular and the real world content.
These challenges provides a safe
sandbox environment for learners
to experiment, problem solve,
and their Salesforce expertise.
And the other one is rewards Salesforce.
Oh, sorry.
Trailhead leverages the elements
such as points badges and leadership
boards, like to which to create a
fun engaging learning experience.
As learn as progress through the platform.
They earn the recognition and
their achievements and fostering
a sense of accomplishment and
motive to continue learning.
And other one is like personalized
learning, which we can talk
about trailhead trailheads.
Learning parts are like the
individual role experience and the
career goals ensures a personalized,
relevant learning journey.
Like a platform recommended engine
suggestions, relevant content.
And the next steps are based on
the progress and the interest
and the impact of a trailhead is.
One skill development for the Salesforce
users Trailhead empowers the Salesforce
user from administrator developers to
continuously expand their knowledge and
the skills, ensuring they can max maximize
the platform capabilities by providing
the structure and engaging the learning
experience and Trailhead helps the users
become more productive, efficient, and
valuable within their organization.
And.
Next point is like talent pipeline
of a Salesforce ecosystem.
Salesforce has become circular talent
pipeline talent pipeline of the borders
and enabling the individuals to en to
acquire the de demand of a Salesforce
Skills become job ready and many
Salesforce partners and the customers
leverage the trailhead to upskill.
The workforce and build a strong talent
pool of support, their interactive.
And the other one is the
Salesforce expertise.
Trailhead freeze up the accessible
of a natural Salesforce learnings
making it available to the wide
range of individuals regardless of
their background or prior experience.
And Salesforce expertise.
They help expand the pool.
Of the qualified Salesforce professionals
and supporting the platform growth and the
adoption and Trailhead is a transformative
learning platform that empowers the
individuals to develop the Salesforce
skills and their career and collaborative
success of broader Salesforce ecosystem.
And by combining the interactive
content and hands-on challenge, the
Trailhead has become a powerful tool.
For driving skills driving skills
of development, talent acquisition,
and the Salesforce expertise.
That's more about Trailhead.
Let's go into the Trailhead numbers.
Trailhead has built like, as I said,
like a large and a global community, and
Trailhead offers an expansive expertly
crafted curriculums spanning the entire
Salesforce ecosystem Beyond providing the
learnings with over I think 1200 hours
of 1200 hours of educational content.
And Salesforce have collectively
earned impressive 35 million badges
reflecting their dedication to
continuously running the professional
development, and Trailhead has
enabled remarkable professional.
Achievement with 73% of trail
based reporting, significant career
growth and progression, and these
impressive statistics highlights the
transformative impact of a Trailhead.
And the scale of 15 million Strong
user community demonstrates the
widespread adoption and into
enthusiasm of the Trailhead,
innovative approaches to the learn and.
The breadth and the depth of 1200
hours of Kirkland underscores the
Trailhead commitment to provide the
comprehensive and role specific education
to the entire Salesforce ecosystem.
And as I said before, the
35 million badges earned.
At the proof of the platform, ability
to recognize and validate the skills
achievements of its dedicated learnings,
and like the 73% career growth,
strategic of the Trailhead power to
empower the individuals regardless
of the background, prior experiences,
and collectively, these Trailhead
numbers highlights the highlights,
the showcase, how the platform has.
Revel is traditional learning developments
and access to the cutting edge of the
skills and fostering a vibrant community.
Lifelong learning.
Innovatives that's more
about trail a Trailhead.
And let's jump into trailblazer community.
Trailblazer Community it's a group
of global user group, like trail
based community supported by.
Driving local user groups access more
than 90 countries around the world.
And this group provides a platform
of participants to exchange
specialized knowledge, share
innovative strategies, and foster
the, sorry, foster the expertise.
Expertise and community events is one
thing which we can talk about the.
Trailblazer community offers a diverse
range of I missive experience from
the focus of the local workshops
to expensive global conferences.
This even creates a valuable opportunity
for learning network and strategic
connections among the community members.
And other thing is like online forums in
addition of a local and global events.
Trailblazer community maintains the
vibrant online collaboration spaces.
These are like round the clock.
Forums enable participants to solve
the complex challenge alongside
industry point thought of the leaders
and fellow trial basis and other
ones like recognition programs.
Like the Trailblazer community has
established and all aligned achievements
in the framework that spotlights the
extraordinary community builders and
technology innovators and transformational
leaders who shape the future of the
Salesforce ecosystem and the trailblazer
community traditional professional
networks by passionate innovatives
across the industries and broad us.
Th this dynamic echo system fosters
breakthrough, the collaborates that
accelerate the digital transformation
and amplify the individual success
stories and collectively address
the entire Salesforce landscape.
And some key highlights
about the Salesforce sorry.
A trail based community is global
reach, meaning like the user group
of a span of over 90 countries
continuing the trailblazer.
Worldwide and facility.
That exchange of the regional expertise
and diverse experience, meaning the
community, even range from local workshops
to large scale global conferences,
scattering to the various learning
preferences and the network needs.
And other one is like
vibrant collaboration.
The online forums enable.
As I said, round the clock, problem
solving and knowledge sharing among
the trail bridge industry leaders
and subject matter expert and other
one is like all light recognition.
The recognition program shines the
spot on the community of the most
extraordinary contributors, inspiring
the others, and evaluate the ecosystem.
Ecosystem by fostering these supportive
and dynamic communities, and trailhead
empowers the trail, bridges to
develop the essential skills, solve
the complex challenges, and drive
their transformative challenges with
their organizations and the border
shape of the Salesforce landscape.
Let's go a little bit into
the Salesforce partner types.
So Salesforce partner types.
The Salesforce ecosystem is supported
by diverse area of the partner types.
Each playing a virtual multi
role in delivering the innovative
solutions and diving the platform.
Growth consulting, pla partners,
consulting partners are the
professional services firms
that expertise in implementing.
The customized Salesforce
solutions for clients.
They provide expert guidance,
project management, and
technical expertise to ensure the
successful Salesforce deployments.
I. They leverage like a deep industry
knowledge to solve the complex
challenges and they optimize the business
processes to the maximum platform.
For example one of the company I worked
for and Accenture, Deloitte Cap, and
we have some other I. And other one
is like independent software vendors.
Independent software vendors are the
software companies that build and
sell the applications that extend the
functionality of the Salesforce platform.
These partners develop like industry
ex industry specific or special ed
solutions that integrate seamlessly
with the Salesforce they create.
The enterprise Ready Solutions addressing
the specific like business use cases.
And they are distributed among
different like apexes marketplaces
for example, I can say like Slack,
Tableau, or Doc DocuSign or Conga.
And third one is technology partners.
Technology partners provide the
complimentary product services.
And the integrated, that
enhanced Salesforce ecosystem.
This includes hardware, software, and
the platform providers that extend their
capabilities of a Salesforce platform.
Like they deploy the Seamless API
connections with the enterprise systems
and they expand the platform capabilities
through the complementary technologies,
like example, like AWS, Google, Microsoft.
This all.
And the fourth one is system integrators
like, execute complex implementation
to the client needs and design the
scalable architecture aligned with
the business objective and drive the
comprehensive digital information.
And the fourth one is like
manage service providers.
Like managed service providers are
the organizations that offers ongoing
Salesforce administration support
manage the services to the customers
and they maintain the system, which
has been built on Salesforce and
like they help the organization to
optimize their Salesforce investments
by handling day-to-day maintenance,
user support and strategic Salesforce
Innovatives like for example, I can say.
SMO and De Ranch on Demand.
These are the companies.
And fifth one is like App
Exchange Partners, which you
are already familiar with.
App Exchange Partners and the
solution providers that have built
and published their application on the
Salesforce app exchange marketplace.
This partners offers the wide range of
prebuilt Salesforce native applications
and integrates like for example, zoom.
Is one of the app exchange.
And the other one is
like Trailhead Partners.
Trailhead Partners are the are the
organizations that collaborate with
the Salesforce to create the custom
learning content pathway and the
resources on the Trailhead path.
These partners help the upskill,
like enabling the Salesforce users
and more knowledge and capable trail
trailblazer communities like for example.
Accenture and Deloitte are part of those.
Andra Head.
Acade is one of them.
And this diversity ecosystem of the
Salesforce partners works together to
deliver the comprehensive solutions
and drive the innovations innovations
and empower the organizations to unlock
full potential sense work platform
that's more about it and going next to
the innovation through collaboration.
So let's, dive, dive deeper into this
how innovation innovation through
the collaboration in the Salesforce
ecosystem manifest through the stages
and identify the market needs and
like developing a solution, thoughts
and delivering the integrity One,
like identifying the market needs.
Salesforce and its partners ecosystem,
partner ecosystem work closely
to understand evolving needs of
their customers and broader market.
And by collaborating, the partners
can leverage their diverse diverse
industry experts and customer insights
and the Salesforce platform knowledge
that identifies emerging trends and
the pain points and the opportunities.
This collaborative approach helps
ecosystem to stay ahead and the curve
and develop the solution that address
the most pressing challenges faced on
the Salesforce customers and other 1.2
is like developing the solution together.
Once the market needs are identified,
like Salesforce and IT partners engage
in co-creation and co-development.
To bring the innovation
solution to the life.
This involves leveraging the
specified skills and expertise
of a different partner type.
Such as as I said, like in independent
software vendors like developing a
new Salesforce native application and
consulting partners design, designing
the custom integrations and business
processes and like technology partners
built a complementary solutions
that extend the Salesforce platform.
Like by work, by working together, these
partners combine their unique capabilities
and share the best practices and create
the comprehensive in integrated solutions
that addresses the identify market needs.
And the third one is like delivering
the integrated experiences.
What does that means?
The collaborative approach.
Extended like extends to deliver
of the solutions where Salesforce
and IT partner works together to
ensure like a seamless and integrated
customer experience, like consulting
partners leverage their implementation
expertise to integrate the various.
Salesforce and the partners
develop the solutions and create
a streamline experience for the
customers and technology partners.
Ensures the solution integrates smoothly
with the Salesforce platform, enabling
like UN Finded user experience and data
flow across the ecosystem and this.
A level of integration and collaboration
allows the customer to benefit from
the full capabilities of the Salesforce
e system without having managing
a multiple displays of a system.
Vendors, for example, of innovative
through the collaboration like the
Salesforce, the development of a
Salesforce industry cloud, such
as Financial Service Cloud, health
Cloud, which were created through
the collaboration of a Salesforce.
Industry experts and consulting partners.
The integration of a sales force
with ERP systems, such as SAP
Oracle, enabled by the technology
partners and consulting firms, and
the creation of AI powered solutions.
With Salesforce partners leverage
the platform Einstein AI capabilities
to deliver the intelligence and per
intelligent and personalized experience,
like by fostering the collaborative
ecosystem and Salesforce and IT
partners are able to continually
continuously innovate the address.
And address the evolving market
needs and deliver the integrated
solutions that drive the business
transformations for the customers.
And let's go to the next slide, which
says about the partner success story.
Partner success story.
So let's dive into the compiling the
partner success story that showcases
the power of innovation through the
collaboration into the Salesforce
ecosystem across the different
industries, financial services.
Salesforce Partners velocity and
develop the Financial Service Cloud
solution enables the banks, insurance
companies, and wealth management
firms to deliver more personalized
content customer experience, like by
collaborating with the Salesforce.
Was able to leverage the platform
core capabilities like integrating
industry specific functionality
such as policy management, a claim
processing and portfolio management.
The result of comprehensive Salesforce
native solution that helped them.
Financial service organizations
team line operates and improves
the customer engagement and
drive the digital transformation.
Transformation and one of the w city of
the clients leading the insurance company
was able to reduce their policy processing
time by 50%, increase the customer
satisfaction by 20% after implementing
the Velocity City solution on Salesforce.
Other one is like healthcare.
Salesforce partners, Accenture worked with
a major healthcare provided to implement
Salesforce Health Cloud and develop
a custom patient engagement platform.
Like by collaborating with the
healthcare providers internal teams,
Accenture was able to deeply understand
the organization, unique needs
and pain points and their design.
Best solutions.
The solution integrates the Salesforce
Health Cloud, which provides existing
system and enable the 360 degree view
of a patient data and streamline care
coordination across the organization.
As a result of the healthcare
providers was able to improve the
patient satisfaction and enhance
the care team collaborates and.
Drive better health
outcomes of their patients.
And when it comes to retail success
stories, Salesforce partnered
with the Deloitte, worked on
a global retail chain to the.
Transform the customer experience
using Salesforce platform.
Deloitte leveraged its deep retail
industry expertise and Salesforce
implementation capabilities to
develop the comprehensive solution
that integrated the retail e-commerce
and in-store and back office system.
Like by collaborating with the retail
team, Deloitte was able to create a
seamless omnichannel experience enabling.
The customers to engage with the brand,
across multiple touch points, and enjoy
the personalized shopping journey and the
solution helped the retail increase sales
by 25% and improve the customer royalty.
And enhance the optional efficiency
across their global options.
And these success stories highlights
the power of the Salesforce ecosystem
where Salesforce ecosystem, where the
partners with the specialized industry
knowledge and technical expertise and
the deep understanding of the customer
needs, collaborates the deliver
delivery, innovatives and transformation.
And.
Let's that's more about
the success stories.
Let's go into the future
of a Salesforce ecosystem.
Future of the Salesforce ecosystem.
Air integrations, the continuous
integrations and expansion of a
Salesforce air capabilities known
as andin, will significantly drive
the innovations in ecosystem.
Partners will leverage the Einstein
machine learning machine learning nature.
Language processing and deliver
even more intelligent, personalized
solution for the customer.
This could include advanced
chat, chat bots and intelligent
process automations and analytics.
Predictive a predictive analytics that
drives better decisions make across
the various industry as a becomes
more deeply embedded into Salesforce.
Core platform, the partner solutions,
it was enable a new level automations,
insights to the customer engagement.
And other one is like industry
cloud expansion is the next thing.
And Salesforce industry specific
cloud solutions such as financial
service, cloud and Health Cloud has
been major Success will be continued
to the expand and partners will.
Play a critical, crucial role in
developing the industry specific
features and and Salesforce introduced
a new industry cloud, such as recently
announced manufacturing and partners
will have an opportunity to develop
a deep domain expertise becomes go
expertise in their respective industries.
That's more about the industry
clouds and and the other one is
like cross cloud integration.
As a Salesforce continues cross cloud
cross cloud Salesforce continue to expand
its portfolio to the cloud solutions.
And the ability to streamline integrate
across these clouds will become the
increasingly important and partners
will play a crucial role developing
these integrations and solutions to
enable Salesforce customer to connect
the data and process and the workflow
across the multiple clouds, such as.
Sales cloud, service cloud and
marketing cloud, these cross clouds
integrate will allow more un finded
holistic view of a customer enabling
more per personalized, effective and.
Effective engagement and innovative
partners will leverage technologies like
API, middlewares and custom development
to create these cross cloud integrations.
Unlock a new level of efficiency
and business value of Salesforce.
And other one is like by embarra.
Embracing these key trends, AI integrates
the industrial cloud expansion.
Cross cloud integration, Salesforce
partners will be proposing to
drive the future evolution of
the Salesforce ecosystem and
transformative to their customers.
And the Salesforce ecosystem is posted
to continue post to continue the growth
and innovation and the partners who
can leverage these emerging trends will
be equipped to success in the dynamic.
And exciting landscape as we come close
to this insightful conference on the
future of the Salesforce ecosystem.
I would like to extend my heartful
gratitude to all of you and all
of you and active participants and
engaged, and thank you everyone.
That's all.
I want to talk about the
Salesforce and, thank you and yeah.