Hi everyone.
It's great to be here.
I am Georgina Fu, a machine learning
engineer at gco, where I focus
on building real time AI systems
for video and speech analysis.
Today I want to walk you through a
project that's really important for
everyone in our team, how we are using
AI to detect and intercept harmful
content online, especially things like.
Child sexual abuse material,
and other high risk abuses.
This isn't just a technical show
and tell, I'll take you through the
challenges, the architecture and what
it takes to make this work reliably
at scale, across different regions
and real customer and environments.
So why does this matter?
Let's see, first why we are
even trying to give this type of
solution to the, to our customers.
We are living in a era where people upload
everything from personal vlogs and live
streams to gaming education and more.
A platform like YouTube gets over
500 hours of video per minute,
and that's this one platform.
But within that sea of content,
even a single instance of abuse
material is devastating legally,
reputationally, and morally.
And it's not just in big tech.
We work with smaller platforms too.
Niche streaming sites, educational
platforms, even creators using tools
such as Use Screen or W to host content.
They don't have armies of moderators
who are able to keep up with this
extreme rate of video uploading.
So we ask how can we detect
dangerous content early,
automatically, and responsibly
before it reaches the audience?
Let's be honest, this is not really easy.
There are four big challenges we
identified quickly and we had to overcome.
First, we have class imbalance.
Harmful content is extremely rare.
If you train a model naively, it'll
learn to say everything is fine
and to still be 99.999% accurate.
That's obviously useless.
Class imbalance must be taken
into account during system design,
model training and monitoring.
Second video data is huge.
A 10 minute video in a high definition for
math might be 500 megabytes or even more.
Scanning thousands of videos means dealing
with terabytes of data often in real time.
Smart triggering is critical.
It can help to significantly reduce
the amount of requests the system.
Third, we have privacy.
We can't just dump our user content
into a central server, scan it all.
We are bound by GDPR and more importantly,
by ethics users expect platforms and
infrastructure providers to respect
boundaries, to avoid scanning,
storing, or analyzing their private
content unnecessarily or invasively.
And finally, adversaries evolve.
We have seen harmful content hidden
behind innocent looking cat memes,
obscured by translucent overlays,
distorted with TikTok style filters,
or even encoding into the audio track
using state iconography techniques.
It's wild and it is intentional.
These are not accidents.
There are attempts to bypass any
type of detection system, so our
models can just rely on surface
patterns or static features.
They need to generalize across
manipulations, formats and behaviors.
We haven't explicitly trained them for.
So let's zoom now into our architectures
because this is where everything
we have talked about becomes real.
When we set out to design the system, our
goal wasn't just to build good models,
it was to build the moderation pipeline
that is modular, scalable, and resilient.
Something that could plug into different
environments, serve different types
of customers, and grow over time.
So here's the full pipeline we use.
It all starts with a trigger, and this
is how we design, decide what to scan.
This can be random sampling,
useful for stored content.
It can be met database triggers,
so for example, a spike in uploads
from one account or file with
a suspicious name, similar to
hashes that are available online.
And it can also be custom,
some type of customer signal.
So some customers can take videos
for post publish moderation, and
we'll ingest these events too.
This trigger phase is very important
because we don't want to scan everything.
We prioritize scanning intelligently,
which will save a lot of cost
and will preserve privacy.
Then we have the orchestration layer.
Once the content is selected,
it enter our task engine.
We use seller here, which is a
distributed task queue system, which will
allow us to run tasks, synchronously,
prioritize jobs based on urgency.
We try failed steps and
load balance across.
Multiple worker nodes.
So for, as an example, if a live stream
segment needs scanning in five seconds,
it, this task will jump ahead of a batch
job processing multiple stored content.
We also chart jobs by modality.
So we have vision, audio, and sequence
models that can scale independently.
And then we have pre-processing layer.
Before inference, we
need to prep our media.
So this will include splitting
video into short segments of a few
seconds, extracting and normalizing
audio resizing or re encoding
our model for compatibility.
And data duping content we have
already scanned before this step is
essential to ensure inference runs
consistently and across formats.
Some of our customers upload 4K while
others will use some other cent code deck.
And this layer will standardize every
input so it is ready for the next step.
So right after that, we
have the inference layer.
This is where multi multimodal ai.
We have multiple models running
in parallel, so we have frame
based image classifiers.
We have whisper style speech transcription
and keyword spotting, lightweight temporal
models such as their user, three Ds.
And each of these models will return
its own confidence score and tag.
For example, we have a video that
is marked as high probability
of not safer work content.
And then there is a keyword like
grooming found in the audio.
And then the last model attack the
output as violent motion sequence.
The inference is run in containers
that can scale horizontally
and will log model versions for
traceability and adaptability.
So then we have the post-processing layer
where it will take all the signals that I
described before, and we'll try to combine
them either by normalizing confidence
scores and applying some aggregation
logic or just applying some other
classifier on top of the previous models.
So here we'll attach some
text and optionally enrich
with additional metadata.
For example, the video title, the
language of speech, and so on.
This logic evolves with feedback.
For example, we recently added a rule that
time creates the not safer works scores.
If the video is clearly
educational, like anatomy, lectures.
Then we have the decision layer.
This is where we make the
final moderation decision.
This might mean flagging the content
for manual review, auto blocking if the
score is high enough, sending an alert
to the customer or just locking the
result silently if it is borderline.
We also store a decision trace.
So what the model outputs contributed
to the flag when it happened and why.
And this entire stack is loosely coupled.
So it this means that we are able to
scale or replace some individual component
without breaking the whole system.
So this pipeline is the core
of our moderation engine.
It is designed not to just analyze
content, but to do it in a way that
is scalable, auditable, and adapt,
adaptable to real world use cases.
Let's give a little bit more information
about the models as I, me, I mentioned
we don't rely on a single AI model,
but we use a mo multi-model ensemble.
So for video frames, we use CNNs.
They're similar to what powers
not safer work filters, but fine
tuned on stricter data sets.
So think this step as detecting nudity
or graphic violence in individual frames.
Then we have audio models.
We transcribe with a
whisper based pipeline.
And then we check the transcription
for keywords, for example.
We have a video where code can transcribe
a phrase like this is our little secret,
and this will be will flag will cause
relevant tag in the output of this model.
For temporal analysis, we use
lightweight JRU or 3D CNN models
to detect patterns over time.
This is critical for spot actions
like slapping or some other type
of violence, or generally content
that will unfold slowly, sub
across five or 10 seconds of video.
So all the signals are passed, as
we discussed in a decision layer.
This layer will fuse the output
of all the models and either using
score logic or some meta classifier.
It'll try to make sure
that nothing is missed.
So even if one model misses something
this layer will combine everything to make
sure that the accuracy is much better than
the accuracy of the individual models.
So now let's move from what we built to
how it can actually be used in the wide.
This system can be integrated
with a variety of platforms,
each with different needs.
For video platforms, moderation
happens at upload time.
Think of it like a pre-flight check.
So before the video goes live, it
gets scanned to ensure it's safe, live
streaming services, use it in real time.
The content is processed in short
chunks, about five seconds at a time,
and then we can flag problematic content
midstream while it is still happening.
And for hosting providers, the system
can scan stored content passively.
For example, it might sample and review
10% of a library of a video library
every hour with no disruption to users.
For example, a customer can ask to
help them scan a backlog of 10,000
old videos they have inherited.
During a platform migration, the
system will flag just a tiny percent
of them, and then even that small
percentage may contain a handful of
series violations that will be that
otherwise would be legal and reputational
risk if they had gone unnoticed.
So everything plugs in via
simple APIs or webhooks.
No deep integration required.
And this way, even link teams can add
Indus industrial grade moderation without
building, building it from scratch.
Now I know that some may wonder after all
this discussion so far that since we're
scanning video uploads, analyzing live
streams and scanning whole collections
of video, how do we make sure that we
are not just building some surveillance?
Infrastructure.
And this is a fair point when you're
dealing with sensitive content, trust
is not just technical, it is ethical.
So let show you what we have done
to build privacy first, responsible
moderation into the system from the start.
So first of all, we never
start our persist user content.
Unless it is absolutely necessary.
Once a video audio is scanned or stored
the original media is dis discarded.
We only keep the metadata we need,
like tax scores or timestamps,
and only when a flag is raised.
Then we rely on randomized sampling,
as I mentioned, or event based figures.
That means we're not just
scanning everything all the time.
Instead, we design our pipeline to mimic
how a human trust and safety team would
triage so it would target high risk
content while still preserving fairness
and unpredictability in their work.
Third, our system is compliance.
Aware by design, we respect regional
data laws like GDPR and others, meaning
we never scan without consent and don't
retain content outside allowed timeframes.
And we deploy different lodging
depending on jurisdiction.
For example, we avoid certain types of
scanning countries with stricter laws.
Around personal data.
Finally, we regularly audit our
models for bias and fairness.
We uncovered early on that some of
our models was di disproportionately
flagging windows with darker lighting
or skin tones, and that wasn't
acceptable from the beginning.
So we retrain the models with more balance
data sets and that it bias detection
hooks into our validation process.
In short, we are trying to build a
system, not just to be technically
strong, but also ethically responsible.
Now looking ahead while we have
built a strong foundation, we
know that the real power of this
system lies in how we scale it.
Our goal is to make AI powered
moderation feel native to the
internet infrastructure, not the
bolt on service, but the core part
of how content flows across the web.
So here is what we are working on.
First, we're exploring an edge based
moderation, meaning our detection models
run directly on CDN Edge nodes, close to
where content is uploaded or streamed.
That reduces latency sales
bandwidth and keeps data local.
We are also building region
aware moderation, pipelines.
Vary widely around the world.
What's acceptable in one country
might be illegal in another.
So we're designing a system that
can dynamically adjust thresholds
or swap jurisdiction specific model
variants depending on the geography
of the user or the customer.
Another priority is
lightweight deployment.
We are optimizing our models to run
under 200 megabytes so they can live
comfortably on edge servers without
taking up a valuable compute in practice.
This means that we strip down
dependencies, simplify architectures
and compressing inference graphs
as much as possible without
sacrificing accuracy, of course.
And finally, we're developing a set of.
Customer facing tools.
We have APIs and dashboards that allow
our customers to review moderation
events, customize their thresholds,
and receive real time alerts.
Imagine a streaming platform getting
notified within seconds if using
content appears mid broadcast, and
being able to act on it instantly.
All of this is in active
development and early stage rollout.
So when we talk about the future of
trust and safety online, we don't
just imagine it sitting in the cloud.
We see distributed, embedded at the
edge, tuned for local context, and
accessible to platforms of all sizes.
So let me wrap up here with some
lessons we have learned along the way.
First orchestration is key.
Our models are great, but without
task use retries monitoring, it
would all break down under load.
Then class imbalance isn't just
about lik it affects how our
customers perceive our system.
False positives erode trust,
so product taking is essential.
Then infrastructure really matters.
We have hardbacks where a queue failed
silently and nothing can count for hours.
Logging and fall, ba fallback
logic is really important
and can save such systems.
And finally, trust isn't
earned by being perfect.
It's earned by being transparent.
So logs, scores, explanations, any co
context we can offer to our customers
help them with building trust.
So if you are building an ai model
for safety try to think beyond
the model and think the whole
system and the product in scope.
Thank you everyone for giving the
opportunity to talk about this system.
It's we are still early in this
journey, but I truly believe that
AI moderation is becoming not
just practical, but essential, and
whether you're building platforms.
Delivering content or just care
about the safer internet, this is
something that we need to really
focus in building altogether.
So thanks.
Thank you.
Thanks a lot for your time, and
I would love to chat if you are
working on anything in this space.