Hey everyone.
I'm Manpo and I'm delighted to be here
today to discuss advancing financial
fraud detection with the graph databases.
Before we dive into the topic,
I would like to share a brief
introduction about my background.
I hold Master's degree in
information technology and bring
over 16 years of experience
across various technology domains.
My career started in database
management and I have since expanded
my expertise to include cloud
architecture and motor technologies.
Currently, I'm working as a lead cloud
data need at a prominent financial
institution where I focus on driving
platform modernization initiatives
with ai, power financial services.
Welcome to our exploration of
graph database applications
in financial fraud detection.
This presentation examine how graph
based approaches are revolutionizing
the identification and prevention
of sophisticated fraud schemes.
Over the next few minutes, we will
dive into the following key areas.
There are any capabilities in
modeling complex relationships.
We will explore why graph databases
are particularly well suited.
To present the indicate connection between
entities in the financial or advanced
algorithms travel for fraud detection.
We'll discuss specific algorithms
that leverage the graph structures
to identify suspicious patterns,
the integration of these databases.
With the mission learning, we will examine
how graph databases can be combined
with the mission learning techniques.
To create even more fourfold fraud
detection systems and practical
implementation of strategies for
financial institutions, we'll
consider the challenges and best
practices for deploying graph database
solutions in real financial setting.
Let's begin by understanding
graph databases.
Now, unlike traditional relational
databases that you might be
familiar with, graph databases are
structured around relationships.
This is the fundamental
shift in how we think about
organizing and querying the data.
Instead of tables, which organized
data into row and columns, graph
databases, users, notes, and edges
notes represents the core entity
in our data in a financial context.
This could be like accounts,
either it could be a checking
account or savings account.
Customers.
Transactions, merchants
and devices, IP addresses.
This relationship centric structure
mirrors the complicated interconnections
inherent in financial ecosystems.
Think about it in the real world,
financial entities are not isolated.
They're interconnected in complex ways.
A customer may have multiple accounts,
an account may be involved in many
transactions, and a device might be used
to access several different accounts.
Graph databases allow us to model
these complex relationships directly.
This is a crucial difference
from relational databases.
While relational databases can
represent relationships, then often
struggles with complex queries that
involved in tracing deep connections.
These queries typically requires
multiple giants, which can be
competitionally expensive and slow.
Especially with large data sets,
craft databases server excel at
addressing these relationships.
They're designed from the ground
up to efficiently navigate
and can interconnected data.
This makes them exceptionally powerful for
uncovering sophisticated fraud patterns.
Frauds often exploit these
complex relationships.
To hide their activities.
For example, they might use a
network of shell companies to
launder money, or they might create
fake identities to obtain loans.
These type of schemes create intricate
web of connections that are difficult
to detect the traditional relational
databases in the financial world.
Accounts, customers, transactions,
and devices become richly connected.
Notes.
This preserves the complex network
topology of today's financial systems.
By capturing these connections, we
gain a much more complete and accurate
picture of financial landscape.
These representations enables
investigators to efficiently follow money
trails, identify suspicious patterns, and
gain a holistic view of financial network.
This level of insight is simply.
Not possible when data is scattered across
multiple tables in relational database.
With graph databases, investigators can
quickly and easily trace the flow of
funds, identify anomalies, and uncover
hidden relationships that would remain
effective, invisible when analyzed using
conventional tabular data structures.
Building on our understanding of graph
databases, let's now explore in more
detail the power of relationship analysis.
One of the key strengths of graph
databases, licensing, their ability
to uncover hidden database connections
between seemingly unrelated entities.
This capability is particularly crucial in
the context of financial fraud detection.
Frauds rarely operate in isolation.
They typically engage in complex
schemes that involves multiple
individuals, accounts and transactions.
Graph databases allows to move
beyond a purely transactional
way of financial activity.
And instead, RRP network centric approach
by representing financial entities
as notes and their relationships as
its, we can create a comprehensive
map of financial landscape.
By recognizing these patterns,
investigators can quickly identify.
Potentially fraud activity and prioritize
their investigations accordingly.
Disability to quickly and accurately
identify suspicious patterns
is a significant advantage in a
fight against financial fraud,
where a time is of innocence.
Now let's dive into advanced graph
algorithms that make graph databases
so affect to in flood detection.
These algorithms go beyond simple
data retrieval and leverage the
structure of graph to uncover
hidden patterns and anomalies.
Community detection.
This family of algorithms focuses
on identifying clusters are group of
nodes that are densely connected within
themself, but separately connected
to nodes in their part of the graph.
In a financial network, a community
could represent a group of accounts that
are frequently interacting with each
other, potentially indicating a fraud
ring or a money laundering operation.
For example, imagine a scenario where
several accounts are rapidly transforming
funds among themselves, but they have very
few transactions with external accounts.
This pattern could suggest a.
Close network of colliding actors,
community detection algorithms
can automatically identify such
clusters, allowing investigators to
quickly focus their attention on the
most suspicious area of the graph.
There are several different
algorithms for community detection.
With each, with these sworn strengths
and weaknesses, centrality measures.
These algorithms help us identifying
the most important nodes in the
network in the context of fraud.
Detection important can have
different meanings depending on the
type of fraud we are looking for.
Between a centrality, for
instance, measures the number of
times a node lies on the shortes
path between two other nodes.
Nodes are with high between a centrality
access breaches in the network, connecting
different communities or groups.
In a money laundering scheme, a money
mule who facilitates the transfer of
funds between different actors would
likely to have between a centrality.
Degree Centrality, on the other
hand, simply measures the number
of connections a node has.
A node with the high degree might be
account that is involved in a large
number of transactions, which could
indicate either the list made high
volume business or a hub of fraud,
land activity path finding algorithms.
These algorithms are used to find route
or connections between nodes in the graph.
They're particularly useful for
tracing the flow of funds or assets
in the complex financial transactions.
Graph.
Databases don't just throw data.
They also enable powerful feature
engineering techniques to significantly
enhance machine lending models.
Think of feature engineering as art of
extracting most useful information from
your data to feed into your AI and graphs,
provide some incredibly rich information.
Let's break down the key types of
features we can derive from graph
data, extracting network metrics.
This is where we calculate
various properties of nodes.
Within the network, it's like
understanding the role or importance
of each entity in the graph, for
example, degree simply counts
how many connections a node has.
A high degree accounts might be
involved in many transactions,
which could be normal or
suspicious, depends on the context.
Page rank famously used by Google.
Gives the score for each node based
on the number and importance of its
incoming connections In a financial
network, an account receives funds
from many other high value accounts.
Might be a central hub.
We can look at pipelines.
How many steps does it take for funds
to move from account A to account B?
Short paths might
indicate direct transfers.
While long, convoluted paths could
suggest layering in money laundering, we
can track the frequency of specific path
patterns, our funds repeatedly throwing.
Through the same sequence of
accounts, this could reveal a
structured money laundering process.
And crucially, we can analyze
the timing of fund flows,
creating community features.
This leverages the community detection
algorithms we discussed earlier.
We can determine the community size.
Is an account part of
large or small group.
Large community might be
money laundering networks.
While small isolated accounts
could be shell companies, we
can measure community density.
How tightly connected is the group?
This are impressive.
There's substantial improvements in
fraud detection, accuracy, in some
cases, up to 35% of improvement
where the graph based features are
added to the conventional models.
This is huge forward in our ability
to detect and prevent financial crime.
Financial institutions operate
on the scale that hard to grasp.
For most of us, they process literally
billions of transactions every single day.
Think about critical transactions,
money transfers, and stock rates.
It's massive, constant flow of data.
This presidency, huge challenge.
For any database system and
graph databases are no exception.
To efficiently use graph databases
in this environment, we need
solutions that can truly scale.
Scaling in this context isn't
just storing the lot of data.
It's about doing it efficiently and being
able to query the data incredibly quickly.
Here are some of the
key techniques involved.
Query optimization.
This is where we make sure that
our queries, our requests for
information from the database are
executing as efficiently as possible.
Advancing index is crucial.
Think of an index in your book.
It helps you quickly find
the information you need.
Graph databases use sophisticated
indexing techniques to locate specific
nodes and relationships without
having to scan the entire database.
Caching is another important strategy.
Frequently accessing data is stored in
memory for ultrafast retrievals, so if
you are repeatedly querying the same
accounts are transactions, the system
can provide the results almost instantly.
Partitioning strategies,
when your graph sets.
Too big to fit in a single
mission, you need to spread
it across multiple computers.
This is called partitioning.
Sharding is common technique where we
divide the graph into smaller pieces,
our shards and store each chart on a
different server, the distribute workload,
and increase both storage capacity and
process power distributed processing.
To further speed up the query execution,
we can perform graph competitions in
parallel across distributed systems.
Instead of the mission working on the
query, multiple missions work on different
parts of it simultaneously significantly
reducing the overall processing time.
On storage optimization.
Finally, we need to use efficient data
structures to store the graph data itself.
Graph databases imply specializes
storage formats that are optimized
for traveling relationships.
This is very difficult from how
traditional relational databases
store data and it's that allow.
Graph databases to perform complex
relationships queries so quickly.
The good news is that leading vendors in
graph database space, often enterprise
grade solutions ally designed to
handle these massive workloads, these
systems can cap off touring trillions
of edges, representing the connections
between entities while still providing
millisecond level query response times.
These response is crucial for
real time fraud detection.
Streaming analytics for
real time detection.
This involves analyzing data
as it's generated to identify
suspicious activity immediately.
Batch processing for
deeper network analysis.
This involves processing large
amount of volumes, historical data to
uncover complex fraud patterns that
might not be apparent in real time.
By combining these techniques, financial
institutions can build robust and scalable
fraud detection systems that can keep
pace with the ever increasing volume
and complex of financial transactions.
Now let's shift gears and discuss
graph neural networks, RGNS.
If graph databases are foundations,
gns are arguably the most cutting
edge, a technique built on top
of them for fraud detection.
This is where things get really exact.
Traditional Michel learning
algorithms typically operate on
data and tables, row and columns.
To use them with graph data, we often have
to do a lot of manual feature engineering.
And as we discussed earlier,
calculating network metrics,
part based features and so on.
This can be time consuming and
require a lot of expertise.
GNS on the other hand, are
designed directly to process
the draft structures itself.
They can automatically learn
meaningful representations from complex
financial networks without us having
to hand in any of these features.
Think of an A, seeing the network
in the same way we do, understanding
the relationships and connections.
A core concept of GNN is
message passing neural networks.
Imagine each node in the
graph as a little messenger.
It receives information from its
neighbors, combines it with its own
information, and then pass on it.
This process repeats with information
flowing through the network, allowing
the GN Ns to learn the context
of each within the neighborhood.
What does this enable us to do?
Gen are particularly powerful for node
classifications and graph classifications.
Comes to note classifications
predicting whether a specific
account our customer is fraudulent.
Graph classifications predicting
whether an anti-trans work is fraudulent
and the results are compelling.
Recent research demonstrate that GNS
can achieve significantly higher fraud
detection rates up to 20% higher than the
traditional machine learning approaches.
This is essentially true for
detecting sophisticated fraud schemes
that involve complex coordination
between multiple entities.
Furthermore, financial institutions that
are implementing GN N based detection
systems are reporting significant
benefits reductions in false positives.
This mean fear estimate transactions
are incorrectly flagged as suspicious,
saving time on resources for fraud,
unleash improved detection for
previously unidentified fraud patterns.
GNS can uncover connections and
anomalies that are traditional systems
miss helping to stay ahead of evolving.
Fraud tactics.
In essence, GNS represents the shift
in how we approach fraud detection.
They move us from manually extracting
features to automatically learn
from the rich relational information
within the financial network.
Another real important technique in
this space is called graph embeds.
Now, this might sound a bit technical,
but the core idea is quite interesting.
Essentially, the graph embeds are a way
to translate the complex structure of
network into a format that traditional
machine learning languages, algorithms.
Can understand, think of as it's creating
fingerprints for each node that capture
its essential characteristics and
relationships instead of representing
a customer or an account as just
a set of individual attributes.
Graph embeds create dense
vector representations.
These vectors are like list of numbers
that encode the North's position
and roll within oral the network.
Why this is useful because it
allows us to cover the power
filtration, mission learning.
Things like clustering classification
and anomaly detection while still
taking into account the rich
relational information contains.
In the graph, there are several
different techniques that creates graph
membranes each with its sworn stance.
Here are a few key ones not to weak.
This method uses random works to
explore the neighborhood of each node.
Capturing both.
Its local connections and its broader
structural role in the network.
It's good to identify nodes that are
similar in terms of the network context.
Graph auto encoders.
These are neural networks that
lend to compress the graph
structures into lower dimensional
representation and then reconstructed.
They're effective at capturing the
overall structure of the graph.
Transi.
This technique is particular useful for
knowledge graphs where the relationship
between entities have specific meaning.
Transi preserves these relationships
in the embedding space.
Graph stage.
This is an index lending approach,
meaning it can generate embeddings
for nodes it hasn't seen before.
This is very valuable in dynamic
financial networks where new nodes and
transactions are constantly being added.
So to recap, by converting graph data
into vector representations, analyst can.
Apply familiar mission learning techniques
to identify suspicious patterns.
For example, you could use clustering
to group accounts with similar
transaction behaviors or classifications
to predict the likelihood of
fraud for a given transaction.
And there are significant
practical benefits.
Leading financial institutions report
substantial speed improvements, often
40 to 60% of faster model training times
when using embed based approaches compared
to directly processing the graph data.
This efficiency gain is the crucial
in a fast phase environment where
timely fraud detection is essential.
A real world example of how this
technology was used to uncover a
sophisticated money laundering operation.
It all started with initial detection.
Ment systems might have missed it, but
graph algorithms were able to identify
suspicious transaction patterns.
They involved accounts that on the
surface seemed to be unrelated.
However, the graph database revealed.
Connections in their transaction
behavior flagged them as potential
involved in money laundering.
They span across the financial
ecosystems making them even harder to
detect with the traditional methods.
The graph databases shows that these
accounts are connected by over 200
individual transactions, carefully
structured and designed to obscure
the flow of money and make it
difficult to trace graph databases.
Shows these accounts were connected
by over 200 individual transactions.
Carefully structured and designed
to obscure the flaw of money
and make it difficult to trace.
This is where graph database
accessibility to visualize and analyze
relationships became crucial pattern
analysis of this network expose
classic money laundering techniques.
Most notably layering.
Layering is a process where money is
moved through multiple accounts and
transactions to distance it from its.
Illicit source.
The graph database clearly showed the
funds moving rapidly through a series
of accounts, often in complex sequences,
making it incredibly difficult to follow
the money trail using traditional methods.
The temporal analysis capabilities of
graph database, its ability to analyze
the times of transactions were essentially
in revealing this layering activity.
So what was the investigation outcome?
In short, a major success, the craft
databases enable investigators.
To piece together the
entire Money LAU operation.
This led to the recovery of $4.7
million in IC funds, a significant
win for law enforcement and the
financial institutions involved.
But the impact went beyond
just recovering the money.
The investigation also led to
identification of previously
unknown criminal network.
By mapping the relationship between
account and individuals, the graph
database provide crucial intelligence that
helped to disman the entire operation.
This case study.
Demonstrates the power of graph databases
In uncovering complex financial crime,
it highlights their ability to see the
connections that traditional systems
miss, to visualize the complex networks
and to analyze transactional patterns
in the way they lead to successful
investigations and significant recoveries.
So to wrap up the practical side of
things, let's recap the key implementation
challenges and recommendation strategies
for financial organizations considering
graph databases for fraud detection.
First, we have the data integration
challenge as we discussed.
Financial data is often
scattered across various systems.
You have got customer data here,
transaction data there, account data
somewhere else, getting all this
data into Unified Graph database.
The solution to this is to
implement specialized ETL pipelines.
ETL stands for Extract,
transformation and Load.
These pipelines are designed to pull
data from these disparate systems,
transform it into consistent format
and load it into the graph database.
But it's not just about moving
the data, it's all about.
The entity resolution.
This is a crucial process of identifying
and merging records that are referred
to the same real world entities.
For example, making sure that John Smith
and j Smith are recognized as same person.
This ensure the accuracy and
completeness of the graph.
Coming to the performance optimization
challenge, graph databases,
especially in the financial sector,
can grow to enamor sizes containing
billions of notes and edges.
Ensuring that queries on these massive
graphs are executed in real time is
crucial for effective fraud detection.
You can't wait house for a result when
you need to stop a fraud transaction Now.
The solution here is to
employ hybrid architectures.
The SA involves a combination of in-memory
process keeping the most frequently
access data in the computer's main memory
for very fast retrieval, distributed
storage, spreading the graph data across
multiple missions to handle the sheer
volume on to allow the parallel process.
Financial data is highly sensitive,
and we have strict regulations
like GDPR and CCPA to add high two.
We need to able to analyze the data.
To detect fraud, but we also
need to protect customer privacy.
The solution to this involving
implementing granular access controls,
defining very specific permissions for
who we access, what data within the graph.
The solution to this involves
implementing granular access controls,
defining very specific permissions for
who can access what data within the
graph, data anonymization techniques,
masking or removing personally
identifiable information where
possible while still preventing the
structure of the data for analysis.
To effectively address the challenges and
successfully implement graph databases.
Here are some key recommendations
for financial organizations.
Begin by identifying specific
use cases where graph
approaches often the most value.
Don't try to implement graph
databases everywhere at once.
Focus on areas where they have
to be biggest impact, such as
money laundering, detection.
Synthetic identity fraud are
complex transaction fraud schemes.
Starting with a clear focus will
help you to define your requirements
and measures your success, and
start with pilot implementations.
Begin with smaller projects to test
the technology, learn best practices,
and build internal expertise.
It is crucial to invest not only the
necessary technical infrastructure, but
also in comprehensive analyst training.
Your third analyst need to
learn how to effectively query
and interpret the graph data.
The third one, ISPE Center of Excellence.
This can be dedicated team at a
cross-functional group responsible
for establishing best practices,
sharing knowledge, and providing
support for graph databases,
initiatives across the organization.
It is also essential to
establish robust governance.
Frameworks to ensure data
quality, security, and compliance.
Very importantly, integrated graph
solutions with existing systems.
Graph databases are not
intended to replace all your
existing fraud detection tools.
Instead, they should be integrated
to complement or enhance your
current capabilities, creating
a more comprehensive and
layer defense against fraud.
Let's wrap up by looking ahead
and summarizing both the feature
trends in graph based fraud
detection and my key recommendations
for financial organizations.
The feature of graph based fraud
detection is being shaped by several key
trends in time processing capabilities.
The ability to detect and respond
to fraud activity as it happens.
Is becoming increasingly crucial.
This means moving beyond batch
processing of historical data to
streaming analytics that can analyze
transactions in milliseconds.
Feature systems will leverage
advantages in-memory computing,
distributed processing, and a to provide
instantaneous fraud alerts and prevention.
Federated learning across institutions.
This is very promising area that
addresses the challenge of data privacy.
Federal learning allows multiple financial
institutions to collaboratively train
fraud detection models without actually
sharing their sense to customer data.
Instead, models are trained
locally at each institution and
only model updates are shared.
Preserving privacy while improving
the overall effectiveness to
fraud detection, improving
explainability of complex models.
A fraud detection system become more
sophisticated, often employing complex
AI techniques like graph neural networks.
It's essential that these models
can explain their decisions.
Detecting sophisticated fraud
schemes that involve multiple
coordinated transactions and accounts.
Focusing on these high impact
areas will maximize the on.
Investment and demonstration
the value of graph technology.
With pilot implementations, do attempt
your large scale enterprise wide
deployments from outset Instead, begin
with a smaller, well-defined pilot project
to test the technology and learn the best
practices and build internal expertise.
This approach allows adjustments
and minimizes the risk.
Crucially, invest in infrastructure
and analyst training.
Graph databases require
specialized infrastructure.
For fraud, analyst need to be trained
on how they effectively query,
visualize, and interpret the graph data.
By following these recommendations,
financial organizations can successfully
adopt graph databases and position
themselves to effectively combat on
evolving threat of financial fraud.