Hello all.
This is Nagi.
I have 17 years of experience in
enterprise integration architecture.
Currently, I am working in Career
plus SMX as principal consultant.
Today we are going to discuss
about bridging legacy and modern
architectural patterns for
Oracle Server Suite integration.
This presentation explores comprehensive
frameworks for integrating Oracle server
suit with Spring Boot microservices.
In cloud environments, we'll examine
architectural patterns, security
considerations, and implementation
strategies for seamless integration
between traditional enterprise
service plus implementations
and cloud native microservices.
Through systematic analysis of
service, mediation patterns, data
synchronization approaches, and develop
practices, we will establish best
practices for organizations undertaking
digital transformation initiatives,
successful integration requests.
Multifaceted approach, encompassing a
PA, management, security architecture,
and performance optimization strategies.
Background and challenges.
Evolution of cloud adoption.
Cloud adoption has fundamentally
transformed enterprise IT landscapes.
Shifting from traditional monolithic
architectures to distributed scalable
solutions, organizations are increasingly
adopting cloud native pattern to
design change tolerant software
systems that adopt to dynamic business
requirements, integration challenges.
Despite cloud advantages,
organizations face.
Significant integration challenges when
modernizing the enterprise architectures.
The complexity of integrating traditional
systems with modern cloud services
creates substantial technical and
operational huddles research objectives.
This research identifies
implementation fairness.
Facilitating seamless integration between
Oracle Server, suite, and Spring Boot
microservices in cloud environments.
Establishing best practices for
service orchestration, EAPA, management
and security implementation cloud.
Need to architecture
transform me to principles.
Cloud need to architecture fundamentally
transform how applications are
built, deployed under managed, in
distributed environments, emphasizing
contain radiation orchestration in
the service me patterns, key benefits.
Improved scalability, faster
deployment cycles, and enhance system
resilience or primary advantages of
cloud need approaches, particularly
in secs requiring high availability
implementation challenges, organizations.
Must overcome complexity in service
discovery, network latency, understate
management when adopting cloud.
Need to architectures
for enterprise systems.
Oracle Server suit, and Spring Boot.
Oracle, a comprehensive integration
platform bridging traditional
enterprise systems with modern cloud
services, featuring enterprise service,
bus business process management,
and business activity monitoring
capabilities, integration capabilities.
Supports various messaging patterns,
protocol transformations and service
orchestration scenarios, facilitating
hybrid deployments, models that
maintain existing investments while
ing to cloud native architecture.
Spring good microservices,
simplifies development of standalone.
Production grade applications through
comprehensive frameworks and tools
supporting service discovery, circuit
breaking under distributed configuration
management service mediation framework
service routing, intelligent content
based routing with dynamic protocol
transformation capabilities.
Load balancing advanced request
distribution, ensuring optimal performance
and resource utilization, error handling,
comprehensive resilience mechanisms,
including configurable, retrain
policies, adaptive circuit breakers,
and persistent dead letter queues.
Oracle service person.
Enterprise integration backbone,
orchestrating complex service
interactions and transformations.
A sophisticated service mediation
framework constitute the critical
foundation of any robust enterprise
integration architecture, Oracle
service, both implementation
functions as the enterprise central.
Our system intelligently orchestrating
service interactions, managing
complex transformations, and ensuring
seamless communication across
disparate systems throughout the
organizations technology landscape.
EPA Management Under Data
Synchronization, Oracle, EPA, gateway.
Centralizes service governance through
comprehensive portioning strategies
that preserve backward compatibility
while facilitating controlled
system evaluation and innovation.
Rate.
Limiting and throttling
implement sophisticated traffic
management algorithms to shield.
Backend services from traffic
suggests and ensure equitable resource
distribution across enterprise consumers.
Monitoring and analytics delivers
actionable intelligence through
real-time dashboards that visualize
EPA, consumption patterns, latency
metrics, and potential security
anomalies for Pro two intervention.
RIP Ence Orchestrate data synchronization
across distributed systems using advanced
cash sheet topologies, optimistic
locking mechanisms and configurable
consistency models that balance
performance with the data integrity,
security architecture, authentication,
comprehensive WS security implementation.
With CML token profiles X 5 0 9
certificate validation and OAuth two
org integration for federated identity
management and across service boundaries.
Authorization, dynamic goal-based
access control framework with attribute
based policy evaluation, hierarchal
permission structures, and centralized.
Policy administration enforce consistently
across all integration and points data
production, enterprise grade encryption,
glazing a ES 2 5 6 standards for data
address under TLS one three for transport
security supported by the hardware
security module, infrastructure for
cryptographic key lifecycle management.
Identity propagation seamless
identity contest transmission through
Oracle Security Token Service with
identity mapping capabilities.
Correlation ID and the comprehensive
audit logging for end to
traceability across the service mesh.
Develop integration successful.
Develop integration demands is
sophisticated continuous integration
framework that seamlessly unifies
Oracle, Oracle server suite artifacts.
It is greenbook microservices.
Our build automation implements
processes across the heterogeneous
integration landscape.
While comprehensive based automation
frameworks strategically incorporate
unit testing, integration validation,
and end to end scenario verification to
ensure enterprise grade reliability and
performance performance optimization.
Multi-level caching strategic
implementation of multi-level caching.
Optimizes data travel across system
boundaries, employing intelligent
invalidation strategies and data locality
principles to balance consistency
requirements with throughput demands.
Scalability patterns.
Advanced horizontal scaling implementation
incorporates dynamic workload distribution
with intelligent data partitioning
statuses completed by ed vertical.
Scaling for resource intensive
components to maximize cost efficiency.
Resource management,
orchestrated resource allocation.
Leverages containerization technologies
with fine tuned CPU memory quotas
and predictive auto-scaling
algorithms, ensuring optimal resource
utilization during peak workloads
while minimizing operational cost
implementation results.
Performance metrics demonstrate
the effectiveness of differing.
Integration patterns, even driven
architectures, shows the best of
performance with the lowest response
times and highest throughput.
While service bus integration provides
the most comprehensive features set
despite slightly higher latency, these
results validate the implementation
strategies and provide organizations with
concrete data for selecting appropriate.
Integration patterns based on the
specific requirements and constraints.
Conclusion Feature DI
Directions key contributions.
This research established a
robust frameworks for integrating
or server suite with the Spring
Book microservices providing.
Organizations is a clear roadmap
for modernizing their integration
architectures while maintaining
system reliability and performance
implementation considerations.
Effective integration requests careful
consideration of multiple factors,
including service orchestration, data
synchronization, and security mechanisms.
It develop practices.
Playing a crucial role in streamlining
deployment and management.
Future research.
Emerging areas for exploration include
service mesh architecture, advanced
security frameworks, and innovative
approaches for managing hybrid cloud
deployments as organizations continue
their digital transformations journeys.
Thank you.
I hope you all enjoyed this session.
Thank you very much.