Hello, friends.
Welcome to the session Conference
42 Beyond Algorithms, and today's
session is Building Trust in AI
Enhanced Public Sector Systems.
This session is about revolutionizing
government operations through
ethical AI integration.
So let's get started.
Myself, I'm the presenter, Sanjiv
pga, and I have 21 years of experience
working in it sector across all domains.
I have currently I'm working for Amazon,
but prior to that I have worked in
different domains, higher education
for a huge part of my career and other
domains such as retail and supply chain.
And yeah I have done more than 12.
A full lifecycle implementation
of ERP systems and currently
working on AI systems.
So let's get started on the topic,
the AI revolution in public sector.
What we have seen over the years is
that after the introduction of chat,
GPT and ai, artificial intelligence.
Artificial intelligence existed
for many years, but with the
introduction of chat, GPD Open
ai, things have changed around us.
Things like how we do our day-to-day work
has changed a lot and how it has been
revolution revolutionizing the public
sector is what we are going to see here.
Now, we have seen 60% reduction in pre
previously incidents through enhanced
advanced protective frameworks.
And automated compliance monitoring,
which has been a major pain point.
Previously, we have also seen 75%
administrative overhead elimination,
streamlining workflows, workflows
with intelligent process automation.
We have also seen 82% enhanced
service accuracy, delivering precise.
Citizen Services.
Three critical pillars of the AI in public
sector is AI integration in public sector
is the first one is comprehensive data
privacy, which is of utmost important.
We know data is the new gold, and the
data privacy is of utmost importance.
So comprehensive data privacy is
one of the, key benefits of having
the AI integration in public sector.
This helps in adaptive
protection framework that
evolve with emerging threats.
Second is ethical algorithm, all
algorithmic fairness, which is
robust bias detection and mitigation
protocols across all demographics.
The third one is system interability.
Which is nothing but fully
transparent decision processes
with accessible explanations.
Let's move on to the next slide now.
Privacy protection framework.
In previous pre protection framework, the
three main components are comprehensive
data audit, which is systematic
in inventory and classification of
all sensitive information sources.
And repositories.
The next is granular access control,
which is multifactor authentication,
like single sign-on and using mul
multiple factors, authentication
through phone or through text messages.
Then role-based permissions with
traction logging and verification.
And the third one is advance.
De-identification, which is
automated personal identifiable
information removal with cryptographic
safeguards and compliance.
Now let's look into each one of these
algorithmic fairness implementation.
This is all about defining the
fairness metrics, establishing
comprehensive standards tailored
to each demographic group.
With quantifiable equity measures.
The next is measure outcomes.
In Measure outcomes.
What we look into is we conduct
rigorous data analysis across all
populations segments to identify
disparate impacts and effectiveness.
The third is stakeholder feedback.
Where we look into integrating
diverse community perspectives
to validate real world equity
outcomes and guide improvements.
Now based on the feedback,
we also adjust the models.
We, so this is a ongoing circle, how
we make sure that the algorithm is
fairly implemented, which the last one
is adjust model based on the feedback.
So implement precise algorithm
refinements based on famous findings
to eliminate detected biases.
Moving on to the next one.
Now interpretability mechanisms,
technical transparency, comprehensive
system architecture, documentation.
With accessible code repositories
and detailed process workflows is
critical to interpretability of
the system of the AI interface.
The second is decision explanation.
Citizen friendly explanations
that translate complex algorithmic
decisions into understandable
rationales with contextual examples.
The third one is human oversight.
Robust review channels with
guaranteed human intervention
options and clear appeal processes
for all automated decisions.
Next.
Looking at public sector
specific requirements.
Now these are the three main pillars
of the public sector requirements
when it comes to AI integration.
The first one is enhanced
security, 40% higher resource
allocation and higher resource
allocation for critical protection.
Hardened infrastructure against
sophisticated cyber threats,
data sovereignty, compliance
across multiple jurisdictions.
The next is frequent bias assessment,
mandatory quarterly audits with
documented remediation, multidisciplinary
stakeholder review panels with citizen
representation, transparent publication
of assessment, findings and actions.
The third one is regulatory compliance,
which is harmonized alignment across
federal, state, and local requirements.
The third is second.
Next is comprehensive audit trails
for automated decisions, and the
last one is structured reporting to
overall committees and legislators
and all other stakeholders.
Now we have done some case studies and
here are the outcomes of the case study
of the AI integration in public sector.
Now what we have seen is that the
processing time is much less with the
AI integration compared to the usual
legacy in-house without AI integration.
Next is error rates.
The error rate is also significantly less.
The third is public trust score.
The public trust score, we see much higher
than a regular compared to AI processes.
And the fourth one, which is the
biggest factor, is the service capacity.
Now having an AI integrated public
sector of businesses, we have seen the
service capacity increase exponentially.
Now implementation roadmap.
The different steps of implementing the
AI interface is in the public sector,
specifically is assessment, ethics,
audit of current systems to understand
how the current system works, what
are the challenges stakeholder need,
analysis, technical readiness, evaluation.
These are the three
assessments that we need to do.
The next is framework design.
In Framework design, the first step
is customize the ethical principles.
Next is create governance structure,
and the third is define success metrics.
The next is implementation steps.
The implementation steps
are in a iterative fashion.
It's phase technology integration,
staff capability building and
public communication campaign.
So these are the steps
for info implementation.
Other implementation roadmap,
success factors, there are
four suc prime success factors.
The first is inclusive development.
Engage diverse stakeholders from
day one that is critical to the
success of the implementation.
Next is.
Capability building continuous staff
ethics training program to make sure that
they are able to support the application
and support the business processes
or the system once it is implemented.
Third is transparent communication.
Clear public explanation of AI usage
and if there are any challenges there,
address those challenges early, earlier
in earlier stages of implementation.
The last one would be adaptive
governance, which is regular
review and refinement cycles.
This makes stay aligned
with the customer needs.
So adaptive governance is key
to sustain development and
success of the implementation.
Now, key takeaways.
Ethical drive drives performance
organizations with strong
ethical frameworks achieve
superior technical outcomes.
Next is trust is measurable.
Public confidence metrics directly
correlate with transparency mechanisms, so
trust is definitely a measurable metric.
So over here, unique public requirements,
government AI demands specialized
security and fairness protocols.
And the fourth is continuous evolution.
Making sure that regular maintenance
and regular improvements are
done to stay in stay in base
with the developments happening.
Moving to the next slide,
and that was the last slide.
So thank you so much
for joining the session.
I hope you have a wonderful day.
Thank you.