Hello everyone.
My name is Sergey, and today I'd like to
talk about modern approach to search and
recommendation systems and highlight some
of the scaling challenges and how they
can be addressed based on my hands-on
experience over the years, I have led
work on video search, personalized video
recommendations, and product search at
companies like Yandex and Microsoft.
This presentation is fairly short,
so I'll focus only on the most
fundamental problems and solutions.
Each of these topics deserves
a separate deep dive.
If you have questions, feel
free to reach out to me.
This talk covers the core ideas
behind machine learning, powered
search and recommendation systems
from why they matter and how
they are built, rank and scaled.
We'll look at key models, system design
practices, and recent trends shaping
the future of recommender technologies.
Search and recommendation system are
essential for helping user navigate
huge catalogs of content or products.
They reduce information overload
and improve the user experience
by surfacing and relevant items.
They also drive key business metrics,
more clicks, purchases, and return visits,
and help optimize for long-term value
using tech techniques like reinforcement
learning and the impact is clear.
30% of YouTube views, 35 of Amazon
purchases, and 80% of Netflix watches
all come from recommendations.
These systems are not just useful.
They are critical to
modern digital platforms.
When evaluating search and
recommendation systems, we often
look at two types of goals.
Short term and long term.
Short term target are based
on immediate user actions.
Things like clicks, time, or purchases.
These are easy to track and give us
quick feedback, but if you focus only on
them, we risk our fitting to short-term
interests and ignoring real user value.
Long-term targets are about
user satisfaction over time.
They are harder to measure, but they
better reflect user value, true value,
such as retention, subscription,
continuation, or content diversity.
These metrics encourage exploration
and help build loyal users.
In short-term metrics are helpful,
but long-term metrics are what
really drives sustainable success.
Let's take a look at big picture.
This is a high level architecture of
a typical machine learning powered
search and recommendation system.
At the top, we have the server layer,
which is the heart of real time response.
It includes entity generation, which Rie
a manageable set of potentially relevant
items, future feature generation, which
builds feature season, user query, and
item data and models and business rules
where ranking models, score candidates,
and business logic handles diversity,
exploration and cold start cases.
These are the blocks we'll focus on
for the rest of the presentation.
Any degeneration and ranking.
Now, let's zoom out for a second and
look at the full loop and at the input we
have user data, que items and real time
events coming through a data procession.
That's how con, that's how context
and behavior enter the system.
Equally important is the
login infrastructure.
Everything users do,
clicks, scrolls, dwell.
Time is locked and sent
into offline pipelines.
Why is that important?
Because we rely on this data for
training, evaluation, and experimentation.
If you log incorrectly, we will
train on biased and broken labels,
which directly hear systems quality.
In the training pipeline, we
apply labeling strategies, some
manual, some assisted by LLMs
and train our models season full.
The training or active learning or online
updates at the bottom, we measure success.
That includes both offline metrics,
like how, and this and d, g, and online
metrics like CTR, time spent and revenue.
The top the loop.
Is closed by using these metrics to
guide further model improvements.
So again, in this talk, we'll
go deeper into the Kennedy
generation and ranking layers.
But keep in mind the rest of this
architecture is equally critical to
building a successful system to make
recommendations at scale, we use a
multi-stage retrieval and Rankin funnel.
The idea is simple.
We start with millions or even billions
of items and progressively narrow
them down to just the top 50 or so
that we actually show to the user.
Let's walk through each stage.
We begin with user profile
and query understanding.
This gives us context.
What has the user done in the past?
What are they looking for right now?
Then we move into candidate generation.
This stage focuses on high recall.
We want to gather as many
relevant items as possible.
The goal here is to cast a wide
net and collect around 10 K items.
We also factor in things like
diversity, freshness, and popularity.
Next is pre ranking.
At this point, we filter down from
10 K to roughly one K items using
lightweight models, often gradient boosted
decision trees or fast neural networks.
We are still optimizing for a
call and diversity here, but the
computation needs to be fast.
In L two and L three layers,
we do the heavy lifting.
These stages use complex models like
deep neural networks or transformers to
evaluate each of those one key candidates
in depth and select the top 50 or so.
The key metrics here is NDCG, which
reflects ranking, quality and relevance.
Finally.
Ranking stage where we applied business
rules, for example, to increase
category diversity or boost new items
to ensure legal and policy compliance.
What is powerful about this funnel is that
it balance performance and efficiency.
We use simple models early for
speed and heavy models later for
accuracy, so the system stays fast.
Stays fast, but delivers
high quality results.
Once we understood the query end
user profile, the first step in the
pipeline is candidate generation.
The goal here is to select a small,
manageable set of that, typically
thousands of items from a catalog
that may contain million or even
billions or sometime trillions.
Items.
These steps needs to be fast.
Provide higher goal
and maintain diversity.
There are several approach
to do so efficiently.
First, we have NN or approximate
nearest neighbor search, which finds
the closest items in embedded space.
Popular libraries include phase from meta
and scan from Google with fast algorithms
like HNSV, which is the most popular.
A N relies on good embeds, which we can
get from collaborative filtering like
a LS Alterna three squares, which is
fast, but struggles with call starts and
content based models such as two tower
architectures based on DSM or bird.
Another method is random book,
which discovers related items
by walking through a graph.
It's good for diversity
and Goldstar problems.
Though a bit outdated in modern
systems, in search-based systems,
we often use ANOR Index, which
maps query terms to documents.
This scales extremely well to trillions
of items thanks to techniques like term
charting and BM 25 based stren and q.
Finally, don't underestimate heuristics.
Simple based filters like
popularity, recency, or user
subscriptions are still widely used,
especially when latency matters.
The takeaway is there is no
one size fit all solution.
Most production system combine multiple
methods and N Heuristics and angle index
to balance performance coverage and.
Once we generated a list of
candidates items, the next step
is to rank them to decide what to
show and what other in what order.
The goal of ranking is to sort the
candidates by relevance and other
objectives like diversity or conversion.
Conversion potential.
There are two broad, two broad types of
optimization goals, short term metrics
like D-C-G-M-R-R, or precision at key.
These are widely used in industry
and are based on offline judgements
and historical user behavior.
And long-term metrics, which are
still an active research area.
This includes approach like
reinforcement planning and sequence
models that aim to optimize for
lifetime value or sustain engagement.
Engagement.
Let's look at the main approach
used gradient boosting decision.
Tree models such as Boost or Lead
GBM are very popular in production.
They're fast and Deb breathable and
work well on structured features.
They are often used as
the final ran layout.
On the other hand, deep neural networks
like DSM built and other transform
based models can model more complex
interactions and are commonly used in
upstream stages like NN, or as feature
generations for gradient boosting.
Of course ranking isn't easy.
It comes with several
challenges and biases.
Biases such as label and position biases
come from implicit feedback like clicks.
The coldstar problem when we lack
history for new user are, or items
the classic trade between relevance
and diversity and another trade off
exploration versus exploitation.
Do we show what's already working or
do we help users discover new things?
And adaptability is also a concern.
Gradient boosting is easier to explain.
While deep neural networks often
behave like black boxes, privacy
is becoming more important.
Many teams are exploring federated
learning to train models without
centralizing sensitive data.
And finally, latency.
Deep models can heavy, can be heavy.
So we need techniques like distillation
or caching to keep the system responsive.
In practice, teams often combine
these methods using neural networks
for representation and gradient
boosting for final scoring to
get the best of both worlds.
This slide shows a typical
architecture used for ranking in
modern recommendation systems.
We start on the left with input features.
These include user features
like demographic or behavior
signals, item features like.
Price, popularity or category
interaction features.
For example, how often the user has
interacted with similar items and
textile signals like time of the day
or device type, and often a score
from a lightweight to tower neural
network that helps preamp items.
These features are then passed to a set
of gradient boosted decision three models.
One model estimates
probability of relevance.
Another model can predict the
probability that the user will
click if the item is shown.
And the third estimates
the conversion rate.
If the user clicks, this course
can be combined into a final
ranking score dependent on business
goals like engagement or revenue
in more advanced appliance.
We may also use a multitask deploy deep
neural network shown here at the bottom.
This DNN is trained to predict the
same targets, relevant clicks and
conversions, but it can model more
complex relationship and input.
Finally, once we have LEAs,
we apply the ranking logic.
This includes promotion diversity
towards showing too much of the same
content, introducing exploration
to test new or less known items and
applying business rules, for example,
to boost sponsor content or ensure
policy compliance in production.
This architecture is often hybrid.
The DNN might be used offline or upstream.
Gradient boosting remains the final
model for online serving due to
its speed and interpretability.
Let's now compare two of the most
common approach to ranking gradient
booster decision trees and deep
neural networks, starting with
gradient boosting on the left.
These models are widely used
in production, especially
for the final ranking stage.
They work very well on structured
data and easy to interpret and
support fast training and AB testing.
They also grade for small and medium data
sets and have low latency, making them
ideal for high throughput environments.
But Gradient Boost also
has its limitations.
It struggles to model complex and direct
and doesn't handle sequences of multimodel
they also don't scale as effectively as
large data set compared to neural models.
Now moving to deep neural networks on the
right side, these are seeing increased
adoption in both research and industrial.
DN Ns can capture both explicit
and implicit feature interactions.
Handling billings for high cardinality
features and enable end-to-end training
on sequences like user history, they
also support multitasking and transfer
learning and scale better with more data.
However, deep networks also bring
their own set of challenges.
They are cap, potentially expensive.
Harder to debug and less interpretable.
They can suffer from issues
like bias, fairness, and even
hallucinations, and they tend to
be sensitive to noise or small, ch
small chain, small changes in input.
Because of these trade-offs,
many real world systems adopt
a hybrid approach using neural
network upstream for candidate
generation or feature extraction.
Gradient boost for final ranking to
balance performance and efficiency
when building large scale neural
networks for recommendations.
Performance is important, but
scalability and efficiency are critical.
This slide outlines some of the key
design principles that help us get both.
First, we have late fusion
and BN color architectures.
Instead of scoring user item pairs
in real time with a single tower,
we split them into a user tower,
which answered online and item tower,
which we pre-com compute offline.
This can lead to over 110 speed
up while preserving more than 80%
of total profit in some systems.
Next.
Is contrastive learning.
This trains the model to
distinguish between positive
and hard negative examples using
the losses like in or scent.
The goal is to produce a
billion that are compatible
with fast dot product retrieval.
In some cases, the teams report up to 100%
profit uplift in retrieval performance.
A common challenge at scale
is embedding size, so we apply
compression techniques like hashing,
quantization, or distillation to
keep memory and latency in check.
Another critical aspect is bias
correction, including popularity bias,
proposition bias and feedback loops.
One trick here is to add a context
of wear tower during training,
but drop it at inference time.
We also apply hard
negative mining to main.
To make training more meaningful
instead of using random negatives
with sample negatives that are
hard for the model to distinguish.
This makes the learning
signal much stronger.
Then there is multis signal learning.
Our models often consume inputs from
multiple modalities, text, images,
table or data, and from different
domains like search queries,
watch history, or card activity.
Finally, sequential model is crucial.
We use transformer based on coders
to capture the temporal aspects
of user behavior in recent events.
First, to predict what comes next.
These principles together make it possible
to run deep learning, massive scale
in production, recommendation systems,
results, sacrifice, and speed or quality.
Let's now talk about why scaling and
LU Commander system is much harder
than scaling and LMS or vision models.
On the left side, we see
that LMS and computer vision
models scale extremely well.
They take in long sequences like texts
or pixels, benefit from dance labels
and strong supervision and have powerful
pre tasks like next token prediction.
They use deep transformer architectures
and are often latency tolerant.
We don't mind waiting a few second for
a response In these domains, scaling
almost always improves quality and
scaling laws are well established.
Now contrast that with
recomme command system.
On the right we deal with
massive embedding tables.
Billions of user and item IDs.
Our models are often animal
to layer perceptrons, and they
must respond in milliseconds.
So we are under heavy latency constraints.
Our data is based on short,
sparse behavior sequences,
just few clicks or skips.
Feedback is implicit and we
don't have a universal self
supervised training task like lms.
Do.
Also no clear scaling law exists here.
As we grow models, we quickly run into
bias, noise, and diminishing returns.
The key takeaways is in the box at the
bottom, a Recomme Commander system.
Heat, unique scaling limits, including
latency, implicit feedback, massive
embeddings, and the main specific biases.
These can just be solved by
making models deeper or wider.
We need the main specific innovations.
Let's wrap up with some of the
most important trends in neural
networks recommended systems today.
First, we are seeing a strong
shift from traditional ingredient
boost models to deep learning,
what we call neural ran companies.
Like YouTube meta Alibaba use
models in production to power
personalized recommendations at scale.
Multi-stage pipelines with bean quarter
for fast retrieval and deep models for
final scoring are now fairly standard
while not new, they remain a reliable way
to balance quality and latency at scale.
We are also seeing LMS being used in
novel ways, not just for generating text.
But to interpret embedding spaces and
even answer queries based on vector alone.
In terms of architectural transformer
innovations like high performer or high
performer from DeepMind are pushing the
envelope for recommendation specific
models when it comes to scaling.
Several papers have shown that scaling
laws applied recommendation in bearings
and sequence models just like they do
in NLP Meta 2024, research on trillion
Parameters, transducers, and the VU One
project aimed to define scaling law,
specific to recommendations, another
growing trend in sequence modeling.
We are moving beyond simple.
Next item, prediction and modeling.
Richer multi-model, time
aware user behavior.
The area of graph neural networks models
are being used to better capture user item
relationship, especially in the long tail.
These use inductive and transductive
approach depending on whether the
graph structure is fixed or dynamic.
Finally.
Reinforcement learning
continues to gain traction.
It's used to optimize long-term
goals like retention or LTV.
Reinforcement learning also helps with
exploration, which is key to avoidant
feedback loops and filter bubbles.
Overall, these trends show that
recommendation system are evolving rapidly
with a growing focus on scalability,
long-term value, and deep user modeling.
That bring us to the
end of the presentation.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I've covered the fundamentals of
machine learning, powered search and
recommendation systems, explore key
architectural components, looked at
challenges in scaling and discussed
emerging trends in this space.
I hope this gave you a useful
foundation and maybe even sparked
ideas you'd like to explore further.
If you have any questions or want
to continue the conversation,
I'd be happy to chat.
Thanks again.