Hi, my name is Nikita and I'm from Jos.
I work as a head of design and as a
product designer and as a communication
and graphic designer as well.
Jos is a remit now, pay later
financial service and application.
So today I want to talk with you
about AI tool, which can help a
lot in early stage of each company.
When you are doing a design.
So let's start.
When I left my last company and
joined a startup, I realized very
quickly I was the only designer
and I had to manage everything.
Pitch decks, marketing creatives,
user flows, even sometimes
backend logic discussions.
And of course user
interface for application.
So all at once.
It was overwhelming and I realized
that this can be done in traditional
way anymore, and I needed to
rethink how design could scale.
And in 2024, I knew that working
harder wasn't the solution,
but working smarter was.
So I started exploring how
AI could help me speed up.
Creative production, maintain
quality, and also free my time for
more strategic design thinking.
And this presentation is a story
of how the journey unfolded and
what lessons you can apply to.
In early 2024, me Journey had yet
to develop a web-based interface.
In other words, generating images
required users to interact through
Discord chat, which felt stiff
link, especially for workflows that
required a more creative touch.
A web-based me journey did exist,
but it was in a closed be phase,
meaning that very few users were
able to access it having come
across plenty of other platforms.
I settled on Dream Studio, which
operated on stable diffusion, Excel 1.0.
This was primarily due to wanting
control over the graphical user
interface and clean design.
The Dream Studio had come to offer.
Not only did the platform provide
flexibility, but it also had a very fun
and intuitive way of allowing user to
experiment with prompts and tweak outputs.
But it came with limits, of
course, even with negative pros.
Getting realistic images, say a
Pakistani woman without a head
covering was extremely difficult.
It felt rigid, stereotypical,
and lack depth.
Despite limitations, stable diffusion
was good enough to generate the first
assets, images for our early pitch
decks, like an example or concept
like our first limited payment cards.
However, the generated output.
Often had obvious flows, so
like broken head, hand anatomy,
awkward details, and we had to do
significant retouching on that.
It was a start, but it wasn't
scalable for a growing company.
Even so stable diffusion
was extremely useful.
During the early days of our startup,
it helped me create a working model
of our first limited edition card.
So this prototyping step was
pivotal in our product design.
That added imaginative freedom in
the beginning, helped us formulate
a brand and launched a vision.
And then came great advancement
mid journey version 6.1.
This release was a watershed moment,
not only in regard to features, but
also the entire user experience.
Mid journey migrated from a discard
only interface to a fully functional
web application for the first time.
Now, the tools seem to be designed for
creator rather than mere developers
or early adopters, tech people.
And the most striking chance in version
6.1 was a level of customization,
aesthetic preferences, visual steadiness,
and creative directions could now be
controlled with much greater accuracy.
After all, the aim was not just to
produce random, stunning images, user
strove to attain their vision seamlessly
and reliably with each refined step.
Most importantly, it felt like
transitioning from riding a prototype to
feeling the thrill of driving a complete
vehicle, as the image underwent a dramatic
quality transformation, boasting clear
lines, more delicate nuances, lighting,
and better grasp of complex prompts.
At this stage, AI stopped feeling like a
proof of concept, a project or a whimsical
tool For site activities, for concept art,
visual storytelling, and rapid iteration
AI could now be relied on commenting.
Its presents as a critical partner
in creative production pipeline.
So in short, mid journey introduced
two powerful new concept.
First is personalization.
So it means rating 50 images during
onboarding, thought the model might taste.
And the second one is aesthetic tuning.
It's a sterilization, weirdness, variety.
Fine tuned how creative or
unusual results would be.
This allowed me to shape not just outputs,
but the entire feel of the brand's.
Visual majority is
superior in numerous ways.
When looking at issues such as the
quality of the image generated.
Majority, often outperformed other tools
in creating beautiful images, both from
technical and anesthetic perspective.
It generates detailed compositions
complete with anatomy,
sophisticated idea clusters.
Hues that are vibrant, as well
as balanced and lower levels of
artifacts and visual inconsistency.
It's efficient, especially with
higher tier plans in fast, dependable
performance, which helps create
creative, repetitive seamlessly
and effectively with majority.
I managed to achieve several
remarkable images in my initial trials.
UR revealed itself to
be a helpful partner.
When creating stories and drafting
ideas for campaigns revealing its
full beauty in not merely providing
strong composition, but rather
individualized, tailored AI generated
images built around focused narratives.
I can finally state that
it clicked for a reason.
Majority provided effortless flexibility
and thought after narrative advancements.
I remember one image that was
particularly eye catching.
The atmosphere and tone alongside
the composition matched perfectly
with what I had visualized.
That was the idea starting place for me,
a sandbox and try and different props
become an attempt to see how far the
prompts can take the visual narratives.
So the visuals created weren't
limited to internal trials.
They were integrated into live campaigns.
One of the initial images
created was incorporated into
performance ad creative on meta.
As expected, the ad performed quite well.
The image captured the attention
of users fairly quickly in fields
leading to a significant increase
in click-through rate when compared
against our standard creatives.
This confirmed that AI generated
visual visuals do have the
potential for enhancing engagement
in paid media campaigns.
The early success of this achievement
encouraged us to focus on developing a
broader strategy that incorporate deeper
exploration of generative content.
Just a head up, no matter which neural
image generator you use, whether it's mid
Jordan stable effusion, or anything else.
You'll always need to retouch the results.
AI generated visuals often have small
flows like weird, hands, awkward,
shes, or inconsistent textures
that need a human touch to fix.
And here's the thing, speed matters.
You and your marketing team are usually
working against the clock, so instead of
firing up heavy tools like Photoshop, the
fastest and most efficient way to polish
up images is to do it directly in Figma.
It's lightweight, collaborative,
and way faster for quick adjustment.
Perfect for when you are prepping
content for campaigns or social
posts or product mockups.
After all, it's not about spending
hours perfecting a single image.
The real value comes from quickly
iterating on ideas and moving
on to the next creative concept
that can make a real impact.
Here's what a fast research workflow
in Figma look like, for example.
So maybe the most perplexing
thing about Mid Journey was
grappling with its tendency to
misinterpret intricate directives.
While I appreciate the tools purpose
of artists concepts, once you try to
impose on any specific conditions.
Things fall apart.
You might have a particular
mental image, say an object.
Its relations to other elements in the
environment, texture or style, and even
an overarching artistic aesthetics.
Majority often works sideways,
meaning you at War Vision, an AI
train to get in to build something
that resembles your vision.
At one point I even juggling wondering
you know what, it might be just easier
to hire a photographer and go looking
for a cricket balls and spend all
the time begging me journey to make
a specific image in my imagination.
It doesn't lack power, the
tool, but rather arbitrary.
Novelty takes charge of structured
creativity, but then suddenly click
and after 120 variants, here it is.
The third in a row it's still not
perfect, but it's good to go for
small tasks such as using it as
an illustration for the pitch deck
again, or within an app proma section.
So one of the features I find
really useful in my journey
is the use of references.
Essentially created image collections
that act like visual modifiers.
Each references is assigned a unique
code like S Ref 6, 8, 0, et cetera, and
you can even create your own custom one.
It's a bit like a Pinterest,
but with superpowers.
Think of it in a way, like instead of
browsing folders full of images and
manual drawing inspiration, you can
feed an entire reference folder into Mid
Journey as context and let it generate
new images based on that visual DNA.
It's a creative shortcut and
a way to inject coherence or
intentional style into your outputs.
When I was working on my project, I
had a pretty clear mental image of my
target audience, but finding the right
visual tone, that sweet spot, blending
fashion, realism, wind touch, charm,
and hint of surrealism wasn't easy.
I dove into the explore tap and image
journey and comped through frequent,
frequently updated references.
It felt a bit like a treasure
hand, but eventually I found
the visual style that clicked.
So it looks like this outcome.
Okay, so now let's talk
about open AI and Sora.
So open AI and, yeah.
And by the way, this is all made
through Midjourney, and this is all.
Is ready to go mockup we
used in our previous and end
current ad campaign in meta.
So let's talk about SOA and charge pt. So
open AI on the heels of launching Sora.
Its new streamlined image generator
announced on March 25, the update
of its image generator features.
With GPT for all, so is
now fully incorporated into
the charge GPT experience.
This release was not only a remarkable
achievement on the technological
front, it's also indicated a nuances,
changes of in our branding and creative
focus, we have shifted to paying
more attention to representation,
seeking to populate our visuals and
communications with people from as
many different background as possible.
So unlikely, most tools.
Lead and with countless menus, toggles
and sliders is free from clutter while
everything else is left to what it
would essentially call a human versus
AI collaborative visioning process.
User gets the opportunity to set
basic parameters such as image
dimensions, expected outcome,
numbers, and even references.
It's not about fine tuning controls,
it's about vision, feeling, and
the descriptions that the company
is request the absence of clut.
Makes the interface clean, enhancing
focus, and creating a feeling.
Unlike most modern interfaces of
storytelling rather than technical
configuration here's how the main page
looks like, for example, together with an
explore section where the most ed pros and
images done by other users are displayed.
And let's see, some first experiment
with soa when I first got access to soa.
I was curious, but still cautious.
I had seen impressive results online,
but I wanted to see how well it would
respond to my own creative directions.
So I took some of my favorite mid
journey style prompts and adapted them
for Sora to see how it handled cinematic
language, mood, and details and result
genuinely blew me away for the first time.
The AI seemed to truly get what I was
imagining without endless tweaking.
Or rear rewind prongs.
Skin tones were quie, nuanced and natural.
Photo angles felt intentional as it showed
by professional expressions were subtlely.
Human emotive and believable
backgrounds weren't just feelers.
They were crisp, coherent and detailed.
It wasn't just impressive.
It felt like a creative.
Breakthrough.
Finally, I had a tool that could translate
my mental image onto something visually
tangible, with almost uncanny, precise.
So every tool has its downsides
in my attempt with complex scenes
having multiple people interact
with one another and display motion.
Sora had some difficulties.
Achieving this control took several
iteration, meticulous prompting, and
most of all time that said, once control
Sora produced, Polish marketing, created
assets with little to no ending editing.
So like this neuro Sora also has some.
Nifty features, for instance,
enhancing image resolution.
It's amazing how quickly you can transform
an image to meet higher quality standards,
making it even more versatile for
creative professionals who need polished
visuals on the fly, and then you can
finally get a nice result for product and
marketing purposes, like on this shots.
Oh, when speaking of Sora, I discovered
something really interesting.
It has the capability to remove
the background from images and
it outputs a transparent PNG
file with an Alpha channel.
This feature is beneficial when planning
to add graphics built, compositional
images, or for layering elements as one
can for work freely without a background.
If you prefer Figma, then.
Their recent update has a
builtin background remover, so
you are still covered to do.
You can do everything on the platform
without switching tabs or logged out, and
it makes the whole process effortless.
So a few available lessons
from this journey to start.
Remembering the evolution
of AI model is critical.
Understanding how quickly they
are changing can be overwhelming.
All that needs to be
addressing is remaining agile.
In this context, once mindset should
evolve far faster than technology.
This means that one should be open to
learn and adjust with frameworks and
capabilities that make emerge later.
Moving on, AI tools are not systems
that oblate designers jobs, rather,
they are an empowerment tool.
The argument comes down to whether or
not you will utilize the tool, or in
essence, the manner in which you are as
a designer will be able to utilize it.
Mechanism can assist one.
However, the ability to use
them proficiently separates
an expert and a doubler.
Finally, getting to attach to
one tool or platform can reduce
productivity drastically.
To reframe all your available
option is in the toolkit can be
unhelpful if your creativity is Stu.
Equally creative intuition is
where your value lies and is more
important than any gadgets or tool.
That said, once mind as a tool never
goes out of style, creative empathy
and a vision available assets,
which unlock endless possibility.
So thank you.
I hope you really enjoyed by this speech.
Thank you.