Hello everyone.
My name is Achin Var.
I'm a senior software engineer
passionate about building secure
and scalable distributed system.
It's truly an honor to be here at Con 42
and sharing my insight into how we can
architect and secure healthcare system
that go far beyond regulatory compliances.
Today, I will walk you through
guidelines and best practices that can
help design a system which not only
secure sensitive patient data, but
also significantly improve operational
resilience, efficiency, and patient trust.
So the topic name is how to Architect or
Architecting Secure Distributed Healthcare
System which focuses on providing a.
Blueprint for building systems that
not only meet regulatory requirements
like hipaa, but also enhances realtime
security operational availability and
patient satisfaction while securing
or preparing for the future stability.
This is a slide which, sets the
foundation for what modern secular
healthcare system should aim to achieve.
It is about more than about
just protecting patient data.
It is about ensuring systems that
should be responsive, proactive, and
resilient in order to maintain the
highest standard for the patient care.
So in that, the first point I want to
highlight is advanced security framework.
So it is recommended to establish
an advanced security framework
that can reduce unauthorized access
incidents up to around 90 point 99.89%
multilayered, and the system should
have multi-layered authentication
protocols should be employed to
validate access request thoroughly.
So all these numbers I'm going to
talk are are retrieved from the
papers, which are already published my
studies and existing implementation.
The second point I have here is
that critical data accessibility.
So in emergency healthcare scenarios
designing the system to enable sub two
seconds data travel can be lifesaving.
Critical patient data must
be made instantly available
while preserving its integrity.
The third point I want to highlight
is protect proactive threat
analysis, which is very important
while designing subsystem.
In the current age, we can incorporate,
AI, air powered monitoring system
that can significantly enhance anomaly
detection by approximately 94.7%.
And proactive analysis of such system
helps identify potential threats before
they escalate or into actual breaches,
which are very important to take care of.
And the fourth point on is, accelerated
incident resolution, the systems
should have a setup, which, should
be able to handle the incident
resolutions as, as quick as possible.
It is impossible.
It is important to architect security
posture that should aim to reduce
incident detection and response time.
From lengthy periods like 1 67
minutes which is this number is taken
from the existing research paper
and to down, as in as 12.3 minutes.
Ensuring threats are neutralized quickly.
Going down to the next slide.
System architecture, how we should
aim to design these systems.
So this slide discusses the critical
architecture component needed for
secure, scalable healthcare system by
layering distributed data management,
microservices advanced security
and efficient user interfaces.
So first point there is on
how we should design a data
layer in the distributed world.
We should architect the data layer to
orchestrate the encrypted patient data,
potentially managing volumes at large
as in exa heights with validation rates
of 99.997% to ensure the accuracy and
protection for both system and patient.
The second is how the microservice
system or the core of it should be.
It is advisable to build microservice
based core, capital of handling
millions of concurrent API requests
and targeting numbers like, in millions
while ensuring zero downtime through
the inclusion failure mechanism.
And the third is how we should,
the system should design its
security middleware integrate.
We should the system should integrate
real time behavioral in the middleware
to neutralize, the 99% of potential
threats and before they penetrate
deeper into the healthcare systems.
And the third, or of the four
point on architecture is that user
interface layer, which is very
important to have a system resilient.
So the system should design the user
interface to compliance while delivering
the sub two seconds response time,
especially for healthcare operations.
Going on to the next slides sorry.
So these slides explains about
how the high availability and
safe swift accessibility are
non-negotiable in healthcare system.
As explained before, it's.
The patient life is on stake.
So it is very important to
have these systems in place.
So this slide defines how ambiguous
but achievable targets to ensure
the system reliability under stress.
So first point is about
system up up times.
The system.
We should design the system architecture
to achieve finance availability,
ensuring uninterrupted access to
healthcare service around the clock.
And the second on this is
that data accessibility.
The systems should ensure that,
accessibility target is, again, close to
five nines, but enabling the clinicians
and healthcare staff to re try information
quickly, reliably, whenever needed.
Or 24 7.
And more on the third point on EP,
I request this as explained in the
system architecture, we should have
infrastructure which is optimized
to handle, millions of API requests
while maintaining sub to second
response times, which is, important
to guarantee operational efficiency.
Moving on to next slide.
While designing this system, how
we can have a audit mechanism.
So this slide maintains,
explains about auditing system.
Such healthcare system should be,
should have some sort of audit
trails to meet the compliance
standard and ensure traceability.
So it outlines how there are multiple
ways, but this slide explains how
blockchain inspired methods can adapt.
To achieve the tamper for auditing.
So the first point on auditing
is that event recording.
So a system should secure every
interaction with the system.
And within the crypto Go Seal
transaction blocks so that it's not
leaked or it's not accessible to
to people who doesn't have access.
And this is to prevent any trampling
or unauthorized alteration.
A chain validation.
So the system should imply distributed
consensus mechanism capital of post
processing around millions of events
to validate authentic authenticity
of every transaction, which is again,
very important to have this in place.
And along with that, the third point we
should consider that anomaly detection.
The system should build a mechanism
that identifies and isolate unauthorized
modification within milliseconds.
And this is to safeguard the
system integrity proactively.
And the fourth point is that like about,
history of imp impactability, so the,
we should preserve a tamper proof.
Chronological audit trail that not only
supports the regulatory compliance,
but also strength strengthens the trust
in system data handling and practices.
So all these four points are very high
level points and very but very important
to have our audit system in place.
Going on to our next slide.
As threat evolves so
much healthcare system.
And what does this mean?
Is that the mechanism which were
there in place 10 years ago or 20
years ago are not relevant now.
So we should evolve with how
the threats are evolving.
So this slides highlights how
productive security models using
AI and machine learning can detect.
Neutralize threats before they can
damage in the healthcare system.
So the first is that processing
power which is in current AI
world, which is very important.
So it is essential to architect system
capital of analyzing millions of
security events per second, utilizing
custom design, machine learning
acceleration hardware enables.
Rapid intelligent decision making systems.
Which are, one of the key to have
a predictive security models.
And the second on this is that
which is extension of smart
models, is that edge computing.
So we should leverage a strategic
edge computing nodes distributed
across all healthcare facilities.
And this should be real time processing,
closer to, source and that will help
it make sure that we are drastically
shorten the detection times and
response actions and while doing those.
So it is very important to have
accuracy metric, which makes sure
that the detections are moderated,
rightly the system should have models
if we are designing that way, which
should target close to 99% of threat
detection, accuracy which in this
high stake healthcare environment.
And while doing that we should, reduce the
false rate to a remarkable, close to none
or maybe 0.03% which is which outperform
the other industry average of 2.3%.
And the fourth point is very important
on the slide is early detection.
So build the system that can
identify potential breaches
which is based on the history.
We should and also this goes
hand in hand with audit trail.
Within a minutes and we should deploy
sophisticated counter measures within 200
milliseconds to neutralize the threat.
Going on to the next slide.
So when we do or analyze or
implement a system, it is very
important to analyze how this
will impact the patient confident.
So security investment aren't just
technical or just to satisfy the
compliance that directly impact
the patient trust and confidence.
So this slide basically highlights
how security secure architecture
influence the patient's satisfaction
and their privacy prescription.
First on data trust.
So healthcare providers should aim
to, have patient trust and privacy
satisfaction a significant uplift or
demonstrate a tangible proof of impact.
So this the first point is here we can
see that the before implementation and
after implementation the data trust and
the second bar here, it also explains how.
With this system implementation a
privacy satisfaction has been increased.
Which is again, very important in
while architecting such system.
And on the same line a security
confidence comes into picture.
And it based on the studies it's
it has been found out that if we
have all the systems in place,
as explained briefly about.
The security confidence
also gets increases.
Going on to the next slide,
we discussed a lot of points and how to
architect design what things to consider,
what we how we should incorporate AI
models, but ultimately it is also very
important to, consider the financial
impact of such technical implementation.
Implementing strong security not
only protects the patient, but also
delivers clear financial returns.
So this slide explains how security
investment translate into saving
efficiency and risk mitigation.
So the first point on that is that
annual cost evidence avoidance.
By preventing breaches and regulatory
penalties, healthcare organization can
save approximately 3.2 million annually
through proactive security frameworks.
So this number is again it could be on
north of a hundred million or, 1 million,
but ultimately it, it boost ups or avoids
the annual cost and boosts up the revenue.
And compliance efficiency.
So automating regulatory reporting and
enhancing security controls can lead
to, 97.8 reduction, percent reduction
in reportable compliance incidents, and
it reduces the audit and penetration
of preparation of workloads by 86%.
And the third is operational saving.
Through AI pod workflow automation
organization can boost the efficiency
of their security operations team
by, more than 50%, but resources,
if we have the systems in place,
discuss about the 70% 74%, security
operat operations can be, lifted up.
Yeah.
So to, or to summarize on operational
saving from a couple of hours, two minutes
that is the goal of the systems would be
going on to the next slide
implementation strategy.
Successfully deployment of secure system
requires a strategic phased approach.
It has to be very well thought out.
So this slides provides a
blueprint to follow when when
implementing Secure Healthcare
System and how we can architect it.
First, infrastructure assessment.
So we should start with a
comp comprehensive evaluation
of existing systems.
To uncover criticalities and operational
gaps, we should look at how, what
is the current rate of API request
we get and that will and how if
the load varies based on the season
system or season or any particular
part of the or month of the year.
So that all will help in infrastructure
assessment and designing.
Or choosing an infrastructure
and architectural blueprint.
So we should the system should develop a
customized security implementation plant
tailored to each healthcare facilities
or, systems unique environment, ensuring,
scalability if in case there is a need of,
and the.
Third is phase deployment.
So implementing security
components strategically in phases.
It ensures zero disruption and to
essentially the patient care services.
And also the phase deployment.
Make sure that along with the audit
trail, we find out the weakness
and strongness of our system.
So the pha, our deployment
in different layers.
We can analyze system pretty early and
fix it and continuous optimization.
Designing system that dynamically
evolve by integrating real time threat
intelligence and adaptive learnings.
It's basically ensures that defenses
that are, stay ahead of emerging
threats, which is very important.
Going on to next start a slide,
future selling capabilities.
As I mentioned the healthcare system
must be prepared for future, must be
prepared prepared for future scalability.
So this slide describes how to architect
or design a system that can withstand
tomorrow's challenges, scalability
issues including evolution quantum
computing threads, and massive data
growth, which is very much possible.
So advance.
First point on that is
I advance integration.
So architect security system that itself
evolve without human intervention.
Intervention by integrating AI models
is a gold standard, and that way
we can make sure that we are, going
hand in hand or one step ahead even
before the threats are generated.
The second is that point is that quantum
resistant encryption, so future proof
security by adopting cryptographic
protocols designed to withstand
attacks from quantum computing and
ensuring long term resilience issues.
And the third is that
expanded data capacity.
So as explained about during our
infrastructure slide we should
plan to infra have, infrastructure,
capital of managing petabyte of data.
So this number 45, 45 0.7 petabytes
is the number got from the recent.
He one of the biggest healthcare system
that receives that much data and yeah.
So going on to the next slide which
is a key takeaways to conclude these
slides, enforce reinforces the holistic
approach that is needed to architect
secure a scalable healthcare system
that are not only compliant, but truly
resilient intelligent and future ready.
The first point is that security
beyond compliance, so build security
architecture that exceeds minimum
regulatory requirements while
driving operational efficiencies.
The second is predictive protection.
There are multiple ways, but with
today's ai driven world we can
include or adopt AI driven security
models that proactively detects
the threats and ensuring protection
well before system would react And.
Th third point is that proven results.
So we should focus on achieving measurable
outcomes such as into finance, or close
to finance and future ready architecture.
So design system that accommo accommodates
considers growing data demands
evolving threats and new technology
all the way through 2027 and beyond.
Thank you.