As organizations globally embrace
digital transformation, implementing
a human capital management system
has become very essential for
maintaining competitive advantage.
Statistics say that almost 93% of
companies are planning to overall their
HR systems within the next three years.
My name ista sat, and I am an
implementation director with a
DP Technology Services, and I've
been in the HR transformation
space for close to 15 years.
Today in this presentation, I'm gonna
offer a comprehensive framework for
successfully deploying global he CM
systems, focusing on integrating.
Both machine learnings and AI driven
technologies, the buzzwords in
the industry on how organizations
can choose to optimize their
HR operations while balancing
standardizations with local needs.
Let us look at some imperatives before
we really jump into the who, why, what
of Global had seen transformations?
The modern HR ecosystem in organizations
requires sophisticated systems that
operate seamlessly across countries.
Now, when I say global organizations,
I'm talking about organi companies
in multiple countries that are
presented in multiple countries where.
There are systems that are extremely
fragmented and outdated HR technologies,
and they face a very critical
competitive disadvantage in the
market in attracting, developing, and
retaining talent in their space by
implementing a global HCM solution.
Organizations can establish standardized
processes across their countries, across
their locals, while also maintaining
that regional flexibility and creating
that equilibrium between consistency as
well as adaptability that will help them
make, get their workforce management
processes into and in an excellent space
that can drive good business outcomes.
Like I said earlier, 93% of companies
are upgrading out of which 42% are
really looking at efficiency gain in
their HR operational processes, and
almost 82% of them are moving into
cloud-based solutions, and they will see
the why behind it In a few slides here.
Before we get into the start, let's
look at the, why do companies want
to do global HR transformation?
And some of this is to really
require to build a compelling
business use case at the outset.
While there are many reasons that do that.
Sitting really at the top of the
pyramid is a strategic value that
comes out of HR transformations.
These transformations not just, elevate HR
as a business partner, but they also add
to the financial impact through reduced
administrative cost productivity gains.
There is also operational efficiency
when you implement processes
such as streamlined workflows,
reducing redundancies in your
global operations, et cetera.
And finally, at the base
of the pyramid is where it.
Powerfully unlocks data-driven
insights for proactive talent
management across the organization.
And hence, keeping all of this in mind,
securing your executive sponsorship
demands that you articulate these value
proposition so that it's not just a simple
cost reduction technique, but it also
impacts the organization tremendously.
Effective business cases quantify how
global systems drive these tangible
outcomes in terms of workforce
planning, enhancing your leadership
decision making capabilities, and
also fundamentally transforming the
employee experiences that such at
various point of the employee lifecycle.
Successful implementations also require
methodical stakeholder analysis and
engagement across your organizations.
It could be in finance, it could be in
IT operations, even within regional HR
leadership, these strategic allies become
very powerful advocates who can articulate
the system's, cross-functional benefits,
and help overcome resistance to change.
Now talking about so many people how
does the cross-functional collaboration
framework and how does this need to
work in a global HR transformation?
Fundamentally, there should be
stakeholder engagement, which means
identifying and mobilizing who are
going to be the key partners in your
transformation process, and identifying
a government governance structure.
Clearly establishing who our decision, who
are sitting in decision making power and
who are in operational power and what are
the protocols in the way they communicate.
Also, developing a responsibility matrix
in terms of who's responsible for actions.
Who's actionable, who needs to be
communicated versus who needs to
be informed And having a continuous
alignment to revisit some of these
governance and collaboration framework
is of atmos importance when going
through HR transformation exercises.
Leading organizations also deploy
purposefully built digital collaboration
platforms for doing these implementations
where there is real time knowledge
sharing, real time documentation, sharing
systematic issue resolution through
the course of your implementation.
And also a comprehensive decision
documentation process that is
dispersed geographically ultimately
driving accountability for not the
headquartered locations, but also.
All the other localized countries that
are a part of the implementation in
the transformation journey itself.
AI plays a big role when it comes to
HR transformation as a process because
AI has a very powerful risk mitigation
strategies that can be utilized.
Some of these include
predictive risk identification.
They can analyze implementation
patterns across similar
organizations so that it be able to.
Forecast issues before they emerge, right?
Real time monitoring.
There are algorithms, machine learning
algorithms that can continuously
look at system interactions to
just detect any sort of anomalies
and, indicate, hey, these are areas
where problems may be occurring.
And then finally, data quality is an
area where AI plays a very powerful
role where there can be automated
data validation tools to ensure your
information is, the information integrity
is maintained during your data migration
efforts in a transformation process.
Some of these AI powered risk management,
it represents a paradigm shift from
being reactive in your implementations
to being extremely proactive.
And this really helps and
boosts program governance.
At the outset set, we're
gonna take a tangential shift
from the why and into what.
Organization, global organizations are
moving towards in the HR transformation
space, like I traded earlier, almost
82% of organizations in the world are
now moving into the cloud-based space.
And why is that shift, right?
Why are organizations
choosing cloud-based?
Instead of on-premise, which has
been the preferred solution of the
nineties and the early two thousands,
because the SaaS based deployment, the
subscription based eliminates the access
for on-premise infrastructure, right?
Companies don't have to maintain
in-house teams to support the
infrastructure, have expenses on servers.
To host the data of these
large organizations.
S scalability becomes an in, a very
obvious answer because there is
instantaneous resource allocation
that flexes with your growth and
demand, especially after a pandemic
world where organizations are ups are.
Growing and retrenching
in, in waves and crest.
As the economy boosts and economy
falls, scalability becomes very
powerful and hence, cloud-based
systems are a preferred choice.
The infrastructure management
vendor maintain environment.
There are seamless updates
to SaaS-based architecture.
You don't have to have
the system down while.
Opting for these cloud-based systems
is also ensure zero downtime.
And finally, cloud-based systems offer
a very powerful security framework.
Almost all these cloud-based solutions
such as Workday, SAP, Oracle Cloud
Fusion, they give a very extremely
robust security frameworks for global
organizations that's going to help them
with end-to-end encryption and granular
access controls that suffice locally.
Forward-thinking organizations are really
implementing these hybrid cloud strategies
that secure highly sensitive personal
data in private clouds, while also
simultaneously leveraging public cloud
infrastructure for enhancing processing.
So there is a sort of hybrid cloud that
large organizations are preferring so
that they have, that is something that is.
That seems like promised,
but they're private cloud.
So the data and the security
is very well maintained.
This balanced approach also creates
a good equilibrium for these really
large organizations between an ironclad
security protocol and robust performance
metrics throughout your HCM ecosystems.
Also, let's talk a little bit about
data governance and regional compliance
as an imperative because when it comes
to global HCM implementations data
governance framework has become paramount.
Effective global IM implementations
require sophisticated frameworks that.
Comply with regional requirements.
Organizations must build systems that
respect local privacy regulations while
enabling consolidated workforce analytics.
Hence also the cloud-based system
becomes an imperative because data
governance and regional compliance
is much more easier to administer
in a cloud-based infrastructure.
Advanced implementations include data
ity solutions that maintain information
within the geographical boundaries
where they need to be housed, required
by law, while also providing that
accu, access for global functions.
I. In addition to data governance,
framework, machine learning capabilities
for these, HCM cloud-based platforms
are also one of the other preferred
area where clients are navigating
or, attracted towards advanced
machine learning capabilities.
E elevate our head CM systems performance
from just being traditional data
repositories into strategic advisors.
These AI powered systems,
ous predictive analysis.
There is intelligence behind the
scenes that gives them in valuable
information of how their workforce
is uti, of how their workforce is
performing, where are their areas of.
Focus for HR as a strategic function
market leading organizations, or
also implementing talent analytics
that achieve higher retention rate.
There are performance improvements in
in the workforce, and there are also
higher in employee engagement scores
that are being reported with the use
of these cloud-based technologies.
This transformation really in.
F enables HR functions to pivot
from time consuming reactive
interventions to high impact, proactive
strategies that, directly influences
their business outcomes itself.
So we spoke about the why
and the what are they doing?
Now let's move a little bit into how are
global HR transformations really done?
The fundamental core of how Global HR
transformations are successful is through
excellent change management practices.
And that comes at.
Three layers, right?
The first one is really
awareness building.
And basically before going into
a transformation, you need to
build that awareness across
your organizations of why this
transformation is gonna happen, right?
And from there, you're going to move
into a capability development where you
are equipping all the stakeholders of
your transformation process with the
skills as well as the knowledge that
is required for this transformation.
And finally, the adoption
support where you are.
Consciously embedding practices through
continuous reinforcement mechanisms.
Basically it could be,
standard operating procedures.
It could be job aids where you are
aiding adoption of the HR product
itself plays a very key role.
Industry leading organization often use
sophisticated persona based journeys.
They're tailored to unique concerns
globally, locally that are influencing.
They influence patterns for stakeholder
segments, right from C-Suite to
frontline managers to in, into
individual contributors or employees.
At the bottom.
The precision approach ensures that.
Capability building initiatives and
communication strategies deliver
maximum re relevance and also the
impact organizations across levels.
Moving over into balancing global,
standardized globally global
standardizations with local flexibility.
We spoke about how change
management is extremely important.
From there, I think what is important
in for implementing global HR
transformations is how you maintain.
Global standardization
with local flexibility.
There are fundamental global HR
processes that needs to be designed,
and then the regional adaptations
that are tailored elements that
address local compliant needs.
That comes into picture.
Now, world class implementations master
the art of maintaining that equilibrium
of what is a global standard process,
which is what is a localized process
for enhancing operational efficiency
and also for strategic customization in.
In the market itself, industry
leaders implement outcome focused.
Governance frameworks that
prioritize standardized results
rather than rigid processes.
Empowering regional teams with controlled
autonomy to execute within that.
Parameters that also make sure data
integrity, reporting consistency
and strategic alignment is
there across the enterprise.
Finally, we are gonna wrap up the whole
thing about how an HR transformation
really happens and what are like
the next steps of adopting there.
Typically, all transformations happen
through an assessment and strategy
phase where there is conduct, where
there is comprehensive current state
analysis, where there is articulation of
future state vision and there are also.
Developing business use cases of
ROI metrics, this is basically
sets the foundation of the
whole transformation process.
From there, we will navigate into
design and configuration where there
are global processes discussed with
local variations, where there are data
governance protocols, data migrations.
And integration frameworks are discussed
of how the HR system or HCM system
is going to integrate with the rest,
and then documenting some of these
dis decisions and, validating some
of these in your environments itself.
And from there, we really move into
the implementation and adoption through
deploying through strategic regional waves
with, whether we are going to go big.
Bank in all countries at once
or whether we are going to have
regional waves or are we going to
targeted deploy certain specific
user journeys in specific countries.
So the adoption and implementation is
different for different clients and
it can be done in a variety of ways.
And finally, optimization and innovation
is not just implementation, right?
Once.
Organizations go live with your HR
solutions, harnessing predictive
analysis and machine learning
there as well to identify any
sort of enhancement opportunities.
Establishing dedicated COEs that
continuously expand the system
capabilities that can con, that can
churn out measurable business outcomes.
Transformation extends not just with
initial deployment, like I said,
but they must institutionalize these
improvement mechanisms so that they
can fully leverage system capabilities.
This not just requires dedicated
expertise, it also requires executive
sponsorship and a very strong culture that
embraces technology innovation as a very
strategic advantage to the organization.
I'm hoping all of these, why, what and
how of how global HR transformation
works and can be adopted to the best
helped you in learning a little bit of
how ai, as well as ML contributes in in,
in many ways as how HCM implementations
are transforming the world.
Thank you very much for listening to me.