Good morning and good afternoon everyone.
I'm truly excited to be here with you
today as part of Con F 42 conference.
My name is Rag and I bring over a
decade of a specialized experience
in data warehousing, business
intelligence, and advanced analytics.
Primarily focused on the banking
and financial services sectors.
Currently working at one of the leading
financial organizations in the industry.
I lead AI driven analytics initiatives
that directly support making.
Regulatory complaints and
operational performance enhancement.
My team works at the intersection
of the data science and business
strategy, translating complex
information into actionable insights.
Today we are going to explore how
advanced AI techniques, particularly
privacy aware approaches like federated
learning and differential privacy are
fundamentally reshaping the predictive
analytics landscape in finance.
This transformation isn't just
about implementing smarter
algorithms or faster computing.
It's about building systems we
can genuinely trust with our
most sensitive information.
Moving on to the slide number two,
AI and ml transforming
financial Predictive analytics.
Covering smarter decisions in
risk, fraud, and client strategy.
What used to take weeks of manual
analysis can now happen in real
time, creating opportunities for
more responsive customer experiences.
As models, advance data privacy and
complaints have become non-negotiable
in finance, trust currency and
regulations like GDPR and DPDP are
changing how we work with the data.
Customer expectations are also evolving.
People want personalization, but
not at the expense of privacy.
Today's roadmap focuses on
responsible AI that delivers better
predictions alongside governance,
transparency, and business value.
This approach represents a
new co advantage in financial
services, the ability to innovate
without compromising trust.
Moving on to the slide number three.
Analytics in finance has evolved
from basic reporting to predictive
and prescriptive models.
Now we are entering the era of
responsible AI building systems that
privacy respects meet co complex
demands and deliver powerful insights.
Our models can't be
black back boxes anymore.
Regulations like GDPR and
India DPDP Act require us to be
intentional about data usage.
Creating both challenges and
opportunities for financial institutions.
Companies that adapt quickly
gain advantages in both customer
trust and operational efficiency.
This evolution isn't just
about technology, right?
It's about fundamentally rethinking
how we derive value from data
while respecting boundaries.
The techniques we will discuss represent
practical solutions to this challenge.
The next slide here talks about this is
where the things get truly exciting from
both technical and business perspective.
Federated learning represents an
advanced form of machine learning,
which fundamentally changes how
we approach model training, right?
Federated learning lets us train models
across multiple data sources without
data living it's original location.
The model travels to the
data, not vice versa.
This means sensitive constrain
customer information stays secure
in its original environment.
When we add differential privacy,
we can protect individual identities
even in aggregator results.
This provides mathematical guarantees
about privacy preservation,
not just procedural safeguards.
Secure multi-party computation
allows different departments
or institutions to collaborate
without revealing underlying data.
This isn't just good data science,
it's responsible engineering
for regulated environments.
For example, different banks could
build collaborative fraud detection
systems without sharing their actual
customer transactions Together,
these techniques form a powerful
toolkit that addresses both technical
and compliance requirements.
Next slide.
In banking, these techniques
enable better credit risk modeling
across global branches and
more effective fraud detection.
While mentioning compliance ability to
learn from diverse data sources without
centralizing them, creates models that
are both more accurate and more compliant.
We have seen fraud detection accuracy
improve by double digits, using federated
approaches that learn patterns across
multiple different payment channels.
While staying within co complex
boundaries, these improvements
directly impact the bottom line
through reduced losses, excuse me,
for a ML and transactional monitoring,
excuse me.
These approaches reduce false positives
without compromise, compromising
security or customer privacy.
I'm so sorry.
This means.
Legitimate transactions plot for
review, meaning flag for review,
improving both operational efficiency
and customer experience without
sacrificing regulatory complaints.
The key insight here is that privacy,
preservation and moral performance
are a necessary trade-offs.
They can be complimentary
with the right approach.
Excuse me.
Wealth management
involves deeply personal.
Financial data that reveals not just
assets, but life goals and tolerances.
Using federated learning, we can train
models across client segments without
centralizing sensitive information.
This enables personalized
portfolio recommendations while
maintaining strict data separation.
The insights flow to advisors and clients,
but sensitive details stay protected.
For example, market segment trends
can inform personalized advice without
exposing individual client portfolios.
These applications aren't theoretical.
They're being implemented today by
forward thinking institutions that
allow wealth managers to provide more.
Consistent advice across
different advisors.
Were preserving the human relationship
that makes wealth management valuable.
The result is enhanced service delivery
that maintains a confidentiality.
Clients expect on regulations.
Demand the next slide here.
Insurance deals with sensitive, structured
and unstructured data, spanning health
information, property details, and
behavior patterns, predictive pricing
and fraud detection benefit from ai,
but only when privacy is preserved.
Our privacy preserving models
have reduced false claim
approvals and optimum optimized.
Premiums while aligning with
regulatory guidelines like solvency.
Two, this dual benefit business
improvement and complaints make these
approaches particularly valuable.
These approaches don't
replace traditional models.
They enhance them by incorporating
diverse data signals without increasing
complex risk per stance, we can
now assess risk across placeholders
segments without exposing individual
ries, enabling more precise pricing
with appropriate confidentiality.
Insurance represents an excellent
test case for responsible AI because
the business fundamentally depends
on data analysis, yet operates
under strict privacy constraints.
Next slide.
Deployment presents significant
hurdles, inconsistent data quality,
organizational silos, legacy systems
as strict complex requirements.
Each organization will face its own
unique combination of these challenges.
Addressing these challenges
require combinations.
Between you, to say like combination and
coordination between data scientists.
Compliance officers, IT teams,
and business stakeholders.
Without this cross-functional
collaboration, even technically, sound
solutions may fail to deliver a value.
Successful implementations begin with
clear governance frameworks before
any code is written, establishing
proper guardrails for innovation.
This framework should define roles,
responsibilities, and escalation
path prevent questions arise.
The organization seeing
the most success are those.
That approach, responsible AI as a
business transformation initiative,
not just a technical project.
Next slide here.
Before we talk about a specific AI
toolkit available today, I want to briefly
reference a research paper, which I
co-authored with my colleagues, which was
recently accepted for publication by IEE.
In this work, we developed an
AI driven scheduling framework
that uses long short-term memory
networks to workload prediction
and isolation forest algorithms.
For anomaly detection in cloud ETL
environments, this is particularly
relevant for a big data processing
in banking and financial systems
where efficiency directly impacts
both costs and a customer experience.
We extensively tested this framework
across major cloud platforms like
AWS Azure and Google Cloud using real
workload traces and current pricing data.
The results were very compelling,
meaning we achieved up to 40% reduction
in cloud infrastructure cost with
significantly improved responsiveness and.
Intelligent auto-scaling behavior
that adapted to changing conditions.
This research matters to our
discussion today because it forms
a foundation for scalable privacy
aware data processing pipelines.
In fact, our next research phase is
actively exploring how the same system
can be extended using a federated
learning approaches to support
compliance heavy financial workloads.
So we are not just discussing
theoretical concepts here.
We are building a proven technology
that already working in real enterprise
environments and evolving toward
even stronger privacy protections
and operational efficiency.
Next slide.
Number 10.
The ecosystem around responsible
AI is maturing rapidly.
Enterprise Ready Tools Now make
privacy aware AI deployment
feasible in production environments,
not just research labs, right?
Measure cloud providers support
federated learning capabilities paid
with confidential computing environments
for comprehensive data protection.
These manage services reduce
the implementation burden while
maintaining strong security guarantees.
Open source differential privacy
libraries from Google IBM and Open
Mind gives teams flexibility in
implementing privacy protections.
These tools have.
Active communications and regular
updates make them wearable
options for protection use.
What used to be r and d concepts
are now deployment already.
Techniques with enterprise support and
growing communities of practice, this
maturity means financial institutions
can implement these approaches with
confidence in their sustainability.
Next slide.
You're wondering where to begin.
Start small, but think strategically.
Pilot a federated use case
where privacy matters.
Fraud detection is an excellent
candidate given its sensitivity
and high business impact.
Build a cross-functional team spanning
analytics, legal and IT capabilities.
This diverse key of prospective helps.
Navigate technical, regulatory,
and operational complexities
from the beginning.
Define success metrics upfront, not just
model accuracy, but regulatory alignment,
risk reduction, and business value.
These broader metrics help demonstrate
the full impact of responsible AI
approaches culture, establishing a
center of excellence that can document
learnings and establish best practices.
Remember, it's about building
a momentum responsibly, not
achieving perfection immediately.
Each successful implementation
creates institutional knowledge
that makes the next one easier.
Next slide here to wrap
this conversation up.
The future of AI in finance is
exciting because it'll demand trust
and transparency like never before.
Explainability, secure collaborations,
real time competence checks.
These are not nice to haves anymore.
They're becoming requirements.
And my last slide for today, if
you take one thing away today
from this topic, it's this.
Privacy is just a roadblock to ai.
It's a foundation for its
success in financial services.
Thank you so much for your attention.
Feel free to contact me over
LinkedIn and thanks again for
giving me this opportunity, conf 42.
Thank you.
Bye now.