Speaker 33: Welcome to Con 42
Machine Learning Conference 2026.
My name is Sumit Call and I'm a
staff software engineer at PHI.
And topic for my today's talk is
LLM, agent for site reliability
production, safe architectures
for AI Powered Incident Response.
So when we think about.
LLM agent or site liability or
production or incident response we
start thinking about data, right?
So the modern incident response
is overwhelming in many ways.
We have too many alerts, we have
too much data, we have too little
time to respond to those, right?
And the key question we have
to ask is, how can LLM help SRE
without putting production at risk?
And if you look at the very
theme of it, we do not fail
incidents because we lack data.
We fail because humans cannot
process it all under pressure.
So this talk is about using a lenss to
reduce that load in a safe manner, right?
And if you think from a problem
statement perspective also, so incident
response is becoming harder and not
easier despite better tooling, right?
So if you look at the core idea, LLM
agents can help reason faster, but
only if they're designed in a safe way.
And a production safe environment is
very important because when we talk
about incident responses, we're always
dealing in a production environment.
And this is not about demos or co-pilots
that can take risky actions, but do things
in a much more safer and trusted way.
So with that, we're going to
get started for our Con 42
Machine Learning Conference.
And this talk will basically talk about
how we'll use a L LMS in a real incident
response without breaking trust or system.
So the escalating Incident
response challenge, let's talk
about that, what exactly it is.
So if I had to describe
modern SRE reality.
We have thousands of alerts per day
across increasingly complex system.
So if I were to give you example
of our organization we have
somewhere around 4 million messages
per day coming for one endpoint.
We have more than 200
endpoints like these.
And if you can, just for the
example, it can easily go o over.
10 million requests per day,
sometimes few hours, right?
So it's a very high volume of alerts
per day across very complex systems.
So it's very important to call out
the alert fatigue and the shift from a
proactive to the reactive operations.
When humans are overloaded
because of that.
And I think if you look at the core
reason for that, those humans are not
overload because they are ineffective,
but because the system complexity
exceeds the human cognitive limits, and
if we have to tie this together, high
alert volume, complex systems, time
pressure results in poor outcomes, right?
And the key problem still stays.
In terms of, it's not lack of data.
We all have enough data.
It's too much data under time pressure.
So that's why we are going to
talk about why LMS matter for SRE.
So why LMS matter for SRE?
So let's walk through what we see
on the left hand side of the slide.
We have observability data, we have an LLM
processing, we have an actionable insight.
And then there is SRE decision, right?
And if you look in the right
hand side, we're talk, we're
talking about pattern recognition.
So we all know we connect various
different signals across logs, metrics,
traces, no matter whether you come
from Open Elementary, whether you have
Datadog implementation, whether you
have New Relic, Grafana, Prometheus.
Any kind of logging system, metrics
system, or trace system, right?
So we already identified that we have
enough tools in our ecosystem, and we have
enough data which gets adjusted into this.
So pattern recognition is more about LL.
M would connect these weak signals
across your logs, across your
metrics, across your traces,
and then we'll do the synthesis.
Around it.
And then census is mostly
talking about compressing massive
telemetry into something human
can act on, synthesizing the data.
And then we have reasoning, which
LM models are great at, right?
Which is generating plausible hypothesis
instead of staring at dashboards.
And when we talk about.
Any SRE workflow or any incident response
workflow, anytime in a symptom comes or
a production system is down, we come out
with these different hypothesis theories,
and then based on the data, looking
at the dashboard, looking at different
traces, we kind of start connecting.
There is a huge amount of
data and we time filter it.
So there's a lot of time lost around
that reasoning, around that hypothesis.
And then we come to the conclusion
so then we can utilize lns.
On those places where we lose majority
of the data, because when the production
system goes down, time is what matters
the most to bring the service back.
And the element here is elements
can assist in thinking, but
they don't replace the judgment.
We still, after the pattern recognition,
after synthesis and reasoning.
Everything is presented in front
of you, and then we have the final
judgment based on what has been
already pre-compiled for you.
Okay.
So the clear message here is
LM would reduce the cognitive
load, not human responsibility.
So that's what the LLM for SRE is.
And then we're going to also talk about
how critical challenge and the production
safety problem exists with this.
And then how do we solve those?
So the critical challenge, the
production safety problem, right?
One would ask if elements are so useful,
why aren't they everywhere in production?
SRE, right?
There are definitely some risks
and we'll walk through those risks.
One, health nation, right?
Confident but wrong suggestions.
We have.
Privileged escalations, right?
Tools, which means tools that
can mutate a production state.
And we have a trust erosion, right?
Once a engineer stop trusting the
system, adoption dies down, right?
And think from these perspective,
these risks are operational.
These are not theoretical risks.
These are actual production.
Operation risk, right?
So if you think from a production
safety problem or this critical
challenge perspective, the
biggest blocker is not accuracy.
It's not the model accuracy.
Hey, whether the model can
predict 99% of the pattern or
synthesis, or it can reason, it's
the safety and the trust, right?
So the LLM where they excel, why we would
say that they do not exist everywhere,
which is basically safety and trust.
Where accuracy is not the problem,
but the safety in the draft.
Now, with that, we're going to also
talk about what would the production
tested architecture would look like.
So let's talk about the
production tested architecture.
So if we had to explain the end
pipeline, this goes more like we'll
do data ingestion, we will build the
context, we will do the l and m analysis.
Human would review it, and then
decision logging can happen.
And one point I would like to emphasize
here is there is a separation of concerns.
So if you look at this pipeline, the
core theme is the AI would analyze.
And proposes the solution.
Human decides and act and key thing
to highlight would be nothing executes
automatically in the production system.
And if you have to.
Correlate this to how it aligns with the
SRE principles, which talks about change
control, auditability and postmortems.
So the key takeaway from this slide is
AI suggestions are inputs, not commands.
Now let's talk about the
foundation of multi-source data
ingestion and why we need it.
So if you look at a single
source of data, right?
In incidents or think from any incident
response perspective, a single source,
we don't look at single source.
We look at logs, we look at traces, we
look at dashboards, we look at n number
of things because we understand the
single source of data is insufficient.
When it comes to incidents.
And if we have to build a very
comprehensive context for an LLM
to analyze, to give us patterns,
synthesize, and reason, we need to
give the vast variety of data, which
means a different context, right?
So traces for a request
flow and latency, right?
Metrics for health
signals, logs for detailed.
Even context, we have to also be to
correlate what kind of deployments
were happening in our systems.
We have our SLOs, SLAs, and error
budgets to frame the impact, right?
And as, as it is as is, as it is very
well known, LLM is only as good as the
context or the data it received, so
the key theme I would want you to take
away from this is a better context in
the incident response, would beat a
bigger model any single day because
with a bigger, with a better context.
Your reasoning, your pattern
recognition, your synthesis, everything
would get met in quality and quality
methods rather than the accuracy
here or the bigger model here.
So the multi-source data ation
is the core element when it
comes to the better context.
So now let's talk about LLM generated
insights and what insights can we expect.
From lms, right?
So at the code level there are
three outcome types, situational
summaries, root cause hypothesis,
and suggested mitigation.
And when we talk about
situational summaries.
It's shared understanding
across responders.
So whenever there is an incident, you
would understand there's an on-call team.
There are multiple team members,
some are application teams, some are
infrastructure teams or SRE teams.
Some are from data side,
data engineering side.
Some are AI teams and product
and so on and so forth.
So everyone has an insight
and context of what the.
What the root cause of the issue can be.
And situation summaries would
basically share the understanding
across different responders.
So it, it, the, based on the situation,
those summaries can be generated.
It can also come up with a root
cause hypothesis, which is a ranked.
Explain explainable guesses.
But not facts.
And then we have suggested
mitigation, which is a runbook
style, human reviewable step.
If this happens next time, these are the
number of steps I would want you to take.
And the core piece here, which we
need to understand is mitigations
are never auto executed.
The core idea is.
To reduce the meantime to understanding,
which is M-T-T-U-I would like to call it
as we have MT TR, which is for response,
but idea here is to reduce the time, which
is meantime, to meantime to understanding.
So the goal would be.
To get faster clarity, not
autonomous radiation in this case.
So these are the LLM generated insight,
which we can definitely tap into.
So now let's talk about what is safety
first guard rail design principle, right?
So there's a difference between an
experiment and a production system.
So we just wanted to make sure
our production system are.
Safe, secure and guarded in that way.
So three core components, data hygiene.
You have privilege, boundaries,
and verification gates, right?
When it talks to, when we talk about
data hygiene, it's around, we have a
clean, bounded and compliant input.
When we talk about privileged boundaries,
it's least privileged by default.
And when we talk about verification
gates, specifically saying,
validate before you trust anything.
And guardrails.
If you think from a mental
mapping perspective.
These are architecturals,
these are not prompt tricks.
Or I will try to do another
prompt and then see what happens.
So these are architectural,
not prompt tricks.
So I think the core principle
is the safety must be designed
in rather than the afterthought.
So that's why the data hygiene, the
privilege ies, and verification becomes
very important in, in this world.
Now let's talk about data
hygiene and context control.
So we all know, we all operate in
a in a world where we have a lot of
VII data, some of those examples.
Our email addresses, phone numbers,
authentication keys, customer identifier.
So when it comes to data hygiene, we want
to make sure we have an automated PIA
reduction before data reaches the model.
And there are some of these listed on the
slide like I just mentioned, these are
sensitive types, which you want to red.
And when we talk about being a context
window to the model so that you don't give
it extreme amount of very broader context,
but you give it a very narrow context like
focus on last two arts because most of
the incidents happen in, and you're mostly
proactive working on something which
happened in last one or two hours, right?
Prioritize.
Allow metrics and recent deploys, right?
So something recently was deployed and
that triggered, which we have also seen
in many of our organizations where.
Recent deploy had triggered a code change
and that had triggered an incident.
So look for those patterns, right?
And then there can be many
more context you can set.
But these are a few examples of
some key metrics, some recent last
timeframes and some recent deploys.
You can add, right?
So if you look at the flow, the
raw data flows in a reduction and
filtering happens, and then we
have a re refined context, then you
have a way to analyze it, right?
And the key message here is less
cleaner data produces better reasoning
than dumping everything in, right?
We can dump everything in,
but that would also means our
results would not be as great.
So as we make our data hygiene
and context control narrower.
We will see better reasoning, better
results, and better actions and better
decisions for the human to act on.
So let's talk about the privileged
boundaries and tools integration.
So we have couple of components
here, which is read only defaults
allow list tools and audit trail.
So when we say donate
default, it's basically.
We always start with read only default
read only defaults, which means this
prevents an accidental production impact
because if you have a reads, not an
execute or elevated privileges, there is
no way the models or a limbs or agents can
perform actions on the production side.
So only approved tools.
When we say allowed list tools, only
approved tools with explicit scope
are added, and then every tool.
Is logged and verifiable, which is
an audit trail, has to be added.
And if you look from an architecture's
PERS perspective or auditability
perspective, it all ties together
with compliance, with security review
and incident retrospective, right?
And the core key message is
if an action isn't auditable.
It does not belong in, in production.
So that's how we set our
privileged boundaries and tool
integration in production.
So let's talk about verification.
How do we verify through
verification gates and validation?
So there are three core components
shadow execution, counterfactual
validation, and decision letter, right?
Shadow execution would be test
any recommendation through LLMs.
Isolation or in an isolated environment
where it can be executed independently
without any production impact.
We would also do a
counterfactual validation.
Ask yourself a question, would
this have helped last time?
Or if a similar problem
has happened before?
Would the suggestion sound
in the direction of which we,
what we did last time, right?
So counterfactual or counter
questioning those validation.
And then also make a decision ledger,
which is your immutable logs of
AI suggesting and suggestions and
human responses enable audits and
future model deployments, right?
That would enable some of the
model improvements for us.
Then also feed that to, into your learning
system and continuance improvement
systems in the organization, which would
then make your model better and better.
Like what was our runbook?
What was a decision?
So that way you're not only getting
help from LL but also giving it
more data to continuously improve.
The these verification gates and
validation would start building trust into
these systems because the core component
of trust is evidence versus promises.
So this will help us to
gather all of those evidences.
Now our core idea here is how do we
shift from a reactive to proactive usage?
A couple of patterns is first
line responders or first line
response, cross service correlation
and e evidence assembly, right?
So when we say fast line response,
it's most mostly around low
threshold alerts, filtering noise.
Escalating only when the genuine
issue to human responder.
So escalate only.
So core theme of first line response
would be noise reduction, right?
Because we understood from the problem
statement itself the noise or the too many
alert is basically overwhelming human.
So make LLM as a first line responder
for the noise induction, right?
We also start building cross
service correlation like.
Early detection of
systematic issue, right?
So if everyone service is going down
and then there's a dependent service,
it means that dependent service
is at a risk of a systematic issue
and early detection along those.
So that would start trickling down to
your dependencies, your upstreams, your
downstreams, and so on and so forth.
And then also build an
evidence assembly, right?
So pre-compiled evidence, which is ready.
Before a formal incident
declaration, it would basically
accelerate your incident response.
It is to prebuilt your incident context.
And core focus to test all
of these proactive deployment
patterns would be to target very
low risk, high return use cases.
And the win of these proactive
deployment patterns would be.
If we can know an incident before
an incident is declared, that's
the safest win which can come.
So if the, if we can get to the.
Point where now we know that
incidence is about to happen.
That's the goal of a proactive
deployment pattern for us.
So that would be a very proactive and
very u amazing utilization of LLM in the
context of proactive deployment pattern.
So now I wanted to I wanted to leave
you with practical pilot blueprint.
How do we implement this right?
As we all know in, in a software or
infrastructure system, always start small,
but you don't use cases, noncritical
services, which can be tested without
high impact on the production systems.
That would be your very first step, right?
Then you start measuring
trust, not just accuracy.
So do not just go by understanding
of, hey, there was a 90%
accuracy or 95% accuracy.
But start measuring trust in terms of
would I start trusting the system to make
these decision in an auto autonomous way?
And then also you have an, you
should have an iterative guardrail
tuning based on the real behavior.
So there has to be guardrail protection
based on how your system is responding.
So that not only your suggestions
are getting improvement, but your
guardrail around protecting your
system is also getting along with that.
And then you your kind of gradual
expansion would happen and scale
would come for these systems
as the confidence grows, right?
So as in the SRE world or in
the reliability world says.
Your production AI maturity would
grow the same way that reality re
reliability grows incrementally.
So that's the core way of hybrid
would start implementing start small,
measure the trust, not accuracy.
It rate over the guardrail so
that your guardrail can scale with
your system and expand your scope
to scale even to a bigger scale.
Also.
So as we start closing I would wanted
to leave you with some key takeaways,
which are four pillars of our talk today,
which is AI augments human cognition.
Guardrails would define the core
success of your system, and then trust
is always built through transparency.
And or another way of saying transfer
transparency can build trust and
proactive use delivers early value.
Early value.
So as we start building these systems,
as we talked about the proactive
use of building a system, which can.
Identify an incident even
before an incident is declared,
is a huge success for you.
So this is a the core problem
is this is a problem as much
as it is an ML problem, right?
So we all know a reliable AI
systems follow the same principle
as a reliable infrastructure.
So these four pillars would define the
key takeaways of my talk, which was.
Make sure your AI augments
human, you put your guardrails
in, you have a transparency.
And then transparency would
build that trust or you can call
it trust through transparency.
And then proactive uses use, delivers
the early value of an incident as well.
So I wanted to thank
everyone for listening in.
And I'm more than happy.
In my discussions around real world
constraints and failures, right?
I would love if you have any questions
on implementation in your organization
or across across our field whether
you're in from whichever industry.
Not just the theory, but the
implementation detail around this.
Feel free to reach out to you.
I would love to help on these
implementations because I was looking
at some of the latest products
which are coming up including.
Datadog Pops and other, which are
some of the wrappers around it.
I think there are huge
tooling, which is available.
There are multiple agents you
can build through Lang Chain
and other technology as well.
We can help us to build these systems
agents along this way as well.
And I have built out, I shared
my LinkedIn linked here as well.
Feel free to reach out to me for
any follow up conversation, and as I
said, this is just a starting point.
The real work happens in production.
So that's the key pieces,
which I'm looking forward to.
With that, I would love to
congratulate everyone in the Con
42 machine learning conference for
2026 for attending for the talk.
And I would love to have more discussions
with the other panelists around
some of the topics and some of the
exciting talks which are happening.
So I look forward for.
Many more collaborations with
everyone and the panelist and
from the audience as well.
With that, thank you.
That was my talk in Con 42
Machine Learning Conference 2026.
Have a wonderful rest of the day.
Bye
bye.