Hello everyone.
This is koala.
I'm a senior DevOps
engineer working for Rotter.
So today my topic is the
synergistic impact of AI in DevOps.
So today I'm excited to talk
about something that is, shaping
the future of engineering.
The convergence of a and DevOps.
As many of DevOps has transformed.
How we release software enabling
fast iterations, automation, and
also a culture of collaboration.
But what happens when we inject AI
into this already powerful lifecycle?
We get intelligent automation that
adapts, predicts and loans from data.
We move from reactive
processes to predictive.
And also perspective ones.
The shift means, fewer outages,
more stability systems,
and, faster feedback loops.
It's not just about writing code
and, shipping fast and fast anymore.
It's about shifting shipping.
Smart.
Let's take about talk about a key
takeaways from this project like our
which I'm presenting like a adds like
a predictive intelligence to automation
and also like a DevOps plus ai, which is
autonomous and adaptive delivery cycles.
It enables smarter decisions
across the software lifecycle.
Transforms feedback loops into
learning systems, turns raw data
into actionable operational insights.
So let's talk about the ai
assisted development tools.
AI is now sitting next
to developers in the IDs.
Tools like GitHub copilot, Amazon
Code Whisperer, and TAM nine are
revolutionizing how we build software.
Let's talk about like how this what these
tools do and how they're very useful.
They, auto complete full functions and
boiler plate logic and also suggest
variable names logic improvements
and also fixing them generates unit
tests and documentation on the fly.
And also their adapt to.
They adapt the code base and also
like a developer style over time.
So with ai developers move faster learn
quicker, and also produce a cleaner code.
No more searching stack workflow
for Synex help these tools act extra
experienced mentors helping engineers
write a better code and also reduce
bugs from day two, from day one.
And also it the impacts like by
using these tools are like, 30 to
50% faster development, speed lower
onboarding friction for new development
to developers higher consistency
and reduce the technical depth.
So let's talk about GitHub co-pilot
which is a AI coding assistant.
GitHub Copilot deserves a special mention
because it's not just auto complete.
It's contextual code
project prediction at scale.
Copilot learns from millions of
open source projects and adapts
to your project in real time.
If you want to talk about why
Copel stands out, it understands,
context, functions and dependencies,
and also can build entire block
of logic from a common prompt.
And also it suggests like a test and
its edge cases and, writes talk strings.
Imagine let's imagine writing a function.
To process a CSV data co-pilot, not only
reach the header, but suggest like how
to handle errors and, misleading fields.
That's next level productivity.
As eruption grows, teams are saving hours
per week and also increasing our test
coverage without trying and additional
benefits are like, it enhances paid
programming acts as a live documentation.
And also boost our creativity
and experiment experimentation.
Let's talk about a for
tive pipeline management.
So we all know CAC, right?
Until pipelines fail mysteriously a
helps us like, prevent them, it is very
interesting, like by analyzing build
histories and also commit metadatas.
And also job patterns air flags
issues before they happen.
A, in pipeline animals, like a prediction
of, flaky test and also like unstable
branches, smart reordering of job
execution for performance, and also
like detection of regressions before
matching to Maine dynamic resource
location to reduce cost and waste.
So while time, these intelligent
adjustments make pipelines
faster and far more reliable,
developers get faster feedback.
Least the reli teams get
cleaner artifacts and also like
businesses get better uptime.
Let's talk about the real time world
scenarios, like where it is really
valuable up to 40% faster pipelines
and also 20% fewer fail bills.
Like you can have confidence
scoring for every commit.
So let's talk about a Sigma solve which
is a predictive pipeline management.
Let's explore like a real time example.
Sigma solve this platform adds an a
layer on top of your CACD workflow.
What Sigma solve does, is it
analyzes, commits test coverages
and file vol volatility.
And also scores each build from zero
to a hundred for deployment readiness.
And also flags deployment that
resemble patched high risk pattern
suggests like a rerouting high
risk builds to staging r qa.
Sigma solve turns your pipeline
into a risk aware engine.
It also learns from your
team's behavior and address.
Its threshold.
As your code base evolve
developers trust it.
Managers use it to improve velocity.
Let's talk about a team outcomes.
It'll be used for fewer rollbacks and
more confidence in fast shipping and
also a better collaboration between
development and the operations.
So let's talk about a,
in a DevOp security.
Security is often the
bottleneck in fast delivery.
A helps, close the gap between speed
and safety security challenges.
A, what a s are like, secrets
hard coded in your pool request.
Ly permissive IAM policies
infrastructure drift from Terraform
to AWS and also behavior anomalies
in service to service calls with
a, you can scan for patterns across
millions of logs, not just signatures.
A learns from breaches.
Across the globe and once you, before
you make the same mistake, it clusters
alerts and reduces false positives
and recommends remedy remediations.
Bonus features are like NLP modules
that automate summarize incident
reports risk scoring by repository
environment GI hooks that enforce,
like a security posture early.
Let's talk about a DevOps metrics
improvement with a doesn't
just help, it shows results.
Teams using AI in the DevOps
pipeline have seen massive
implements in their core metrics.
Let's talk about some of the measurable
implements deployment frequencies
which are increased by twice.
Lead time for cha changes 50%
reduction hours from hours to minutes.
Like change failure
rate is reduced by 30%.
A helps, teams correlate incidents.
To metrics.
If a test fails, often a flags it.
If a release causes spikes in
latency, AA connects it to the commit.
Instead of reacting to the dashboards,
you respond to insights as observability
to action automated RCA like a root cause
analysis, and also like a smart alerting
that ties, logs to specific deploys.
And also it suggests to roll back,
scale up or like a change Confis.
So let's talk about a financial
services a applications in finance
every second matters, right?
And also does every transaction a
helps institutions secure systems
ensure uptime and maintain compliance
use cases in finance are like,
predicting night batch job delays.
Detecting out of patent a PA usage
flagging unauthorized config changes auto
generating audit trail from CACD metadata.
With ai finance teams can operate
fast without sacrificing security.
It's like having a compliance assistant
monitoring your pipelines compliance
meets velocity transplant traceability.
Prior to governance and also like a
built-in risk analysis on deployments.
So let's talk about e-commerce.
AI DevOps applications.
E-commerce is a battlefield of,
milliseconds, customers don't wait.
A ensures the backend scales just as fa
fast as user demands key enhancements
with ai r like, like eight four.
It is used to forecasting traffic
spikes for pre-cal cashy preloading
based on user trends and also
detecting slow queries in the real time
rerouting users during edge outage.
And also let's imagine like
deploying a new card service, like
10 minute before a flash sale.
AA monitors latency and the ab bots like,
a rollout if users, conversations drop.
And also bus let's talk
about the business outcomes.
It is used to, give zero down time
during events like a Black Friday.
Better user experience
and more conversations.
And also faster resolution of slow paths.
And the last talk about human
AI collaboration in DevOps.
AI won't replace, like a DevOps
engineers like, it'll make them
temps more efficient and effective.
A automates like a test
generation alert, prioritization,
documentation, and the summaries.
Humans still handle them by like
designing resilient architectures,
navigation, navigating trade offs,
and also like business logic crisis
management and communication.
Together, they create a more scalable.
Efficient and human centered
development culture.
AI is your partner, like
not your replacement.
Let's talk about the future
prospects for AI in DevOps.
We are just casting started.
Like the feature of a DevOps includes
conversational DevOps what's my current
release statuses and also like auto.
Generating run books and dashboards.
S that understand your observability
platforms and also autonomous pipelines
that self tune based on like a cost load.
As LMS improves we will build like
a system that don't just react.
They all sell off and also by
2025 we have we already saw like
a lot of aa involvement happening.
Looking ahead I think we use like
more sophisticated a models like
where that understand more and
generate better code across like
multiple programming languages.
Yeah.
So thank you guys.
Hope this p pity helps for you like to
understand how AI is reshaping DevOps.
Not by replacing what we
built, but by enhancing it.
Let's use this momentum to build
smarter, more reliable and more
human centered know, like systems.
So the future of DevOps is intelligent
and, we will be building for it.
Thank you.