Hello everyone.
Welcome to my session
on today's presentation.
I'm gonna be talking about API
architecture, and the goal of this
presentation is to show you how API
driven integration architecture,
help pharmaceutical operations.
My name is ard.
I have a nine years of experience
leading enterprise integration
initiative, currently working as
a principal integration engineer.
At Moderna.
I work into life science,
pharmaceuticals, manufacturing,
and supply chain industries.
Before we deep dive into the technical
architecture, let's first understand
how mRNA vaccines are getting developed.
It all starts by identifying
the virus and decoding.
Its RNA.
Think of it as a long instruction
manual made up of four letters, A, CGT.
It is adenine, uracil, ging, n cytosine.
Once they identify the virus sequence.
The next step is the mRNA design scientist
creates mRNA instruction that teach our
body, which can fight through the virus
so that we get immunized after that
vaccine goes into the clinical trial.
This clinical trial vaccine get tested
with diver population and once the
vaccine is proven and safe and effective,
they start manufacturing production
scales up quickly and agencies like FDA
checks everything before approving it.
And the last and important steps
is supply chain and distributions.
Special cold storage and transportation
systems are required to deliver
vaccines safely to hospital
clinics and around the world.
So this is just a high level overview,
but in general, vaccine development
goes through many phases across the
enterprise, and it is very important for
pharmaceutical industry to stay connected
across enterprise, to track the progress
and move forward into the process.
So now let's take a look at the
digital transformation journey we had
gone through to support the vaccine
development and the distribution.
The problem is pharmaceutical industries
uses so many different software and tool
across their different department to
perform their job because there is no one
software available, which does everything.
Also pharmaceutical industries
has a old systems manual processes
and lots of disconnected data.
They slow down everything to fix it.
We develop API integration with over
300 and integration to connect 110
plus systems across the enterprise,
internally and externally.
By developing those API, it helped us
broke down silos and build a connected
digital setup across the enterprise.
This led us to acceleration
Information becomes available across
all the systems, reducing delays,
and helping team move faster.
Finally, we focus on the continuous
improvement using the real time data.
We keep adjusting, improving
how we work, staying flexible
and ready for future need.
This wasn't just a small upgrade,
it's completely changed how
operations work, making everything
faster and more connected.
So when it.
When it comes to the connecting
different system, there is no
one size fits all solution.
Different situation needs
different API pattern.
So first is rest, API, rest API is a
simple, secure way for such systems
to share information in real time.
Then we have a pub sub model.
Pops up is a event driven updates, send
information as soon as something happens.
This pattern generally helps in
a real time data integration,
especially manufacturing use cases.
The E and third one is E-T-L-E-T-L
is extract, transfer and load this.
Pattern of the integration
used for the batch processing.
Whenever the huge data load is
required and required to sync two
different systems, it generally goes
through ETL processes such as use
case like financial and clinical data.
Processing that requires ETL processes.
And finally, the hybrid approach, which
is API plus file based integration.
So this approach requires when, or we
use this this approach when the partner
can't fully use their API or they are
not capable of integrating with API.
We combine.
With the file transfer integration, which
is a very traditional way of doing Integra
integrations, each method help create
a strong and flexible digital system.
So how it help,
so integration layer is a enabler.
Think of it as a enabler of the
business and across the enterprise.
It goes through different.
Saxons and integration helps as a
enabler to perform all those actions.
API integration layer becomes
enabler into each of our vaccine
manufacturing and distribution journey.
Because of integration, we had unified
data connectivity across enterprise.
Connected data from research,
manufacturing supply chain so that
information can flow smoothly.
This helps collaborate with
teams, partners, and regulators.
It allowed them to work together
in real time, making better
decision and faster decision.
It allow automated audit and
easier to meet regulations.
And lastly, innovative
workflow automation.
With AI and smart processes, we boost
productivity and speed up innovations.
The integration layer isn't
just about the connection.
It's help.
It's about helping companies move faster,
adapt easier, and innovate better.
So now let's talk about the manufacturing
transformation we had gone through when
we implemented this API integration
architecture across the enterprise.
In previous and legacy setup,
manufacturing was manual
and it was disconnected.
Data entries between system were causing
lots of delays and it also having a
human errors because it was manually
entering into different system it was
difficult to track anything because
each systems are not integrated or
are not in a sync with each other.
So it is hard to scale
operation when demand grows.
So now with the digital manufacturing
excellence, how we imple after the
implementation of the API architecture,
now it is very, all the systems are fully
integrated and connected with each other.
It eliminate all the paper
based workflows as well in.
Event driven architecture also helps
us decision making and compliance build
right into the system, making audit
tracking and validation much easier.
This upgrade isn't just
about moving faster.
It is about building stronger, smarter,
and future proof manufacturing.
So whenever they can require to
scale, they can scale with this
architecture, or they can scale
down with this architecture.
Because we develop API integration
talk with each other systems.
So it reduce the human effort to to enter
any kind of data manually into systems.
Another use case we have seen where
we got a lot of boost using this
API architecture is clinical trial.
So think of it clinical trial
happen across the globe.
Other different horizons and CROs perform
generally this kind of clinical trial.
So it is very important to integrate with
the CROs systems on a real time basis.
Otherwise we don't get the data
on a real time and then it.
Cause lots of additional delays
with having this architecture
implementation with directly with CROs
externally and to our internal system.
It cut delays by 30 to 40%.
It also help.
Make decision faster so that
scientists can look at the data
of whatever the clinical trial
data comes from, the CROs system.
They can make the decision whether this
vaccine is working effectively, or what
are, what kind of doses required to
do, or what kind of diverse population
required to get into clinical trials.
So those kind of decision
they can make faster.
And it also help reduce 14 days
under four days and be because of
this all integration architecture.
It maintain the GXP compliance.
Together, this change make clinical
trial faster, cheaper, and safer.
Because all it's going is through
the same integration architecture.
So with all these patterns and
integration, we have seen very
huge work over saving because all
the manual process are gone First.
It was required to do manual data entry,
which was eliminated, and we have seen
90,000 hours a year cutting a year of
saving and it reduced error by 78%.
Then automated workflow with
24 smart automation, which we
save an extra 35 minute on every
protocol which get executed.
And this led to strategic relocation.
So with saving of 90,000 hours
of manual work hour, scientists
can now focus on the research and
new ideas instead of paperwork.
In the end, enhanced productivity
means researchers now spend 40% more
time doing important scientific work.
Saving our isn't just about being faster.
It's about letting people
focus on what really matters.
This API architecture we
develop on the cloud native.
Everything is AWS We scale
up using molecule cluster.
We set up all the molecule cluster
and EC2 instance to support
GXP and enterprise workload.
We use mod modular architecture
with reusable component building
API and template that speed up
deployment by file times faster.
And we made sure that even with the
all the securities founds found essence
are strong separating GXP and non GXP
and SOX related workflows separately
validating compliance with 21.
CFR part 11 and securing
everything through Okta 2.0.
Sorry, OO 2.0, Okta and
web application firewall.
So security we take consider
as a important part of
our architecture because.
To stay compliant.
And in the regulated industry, it is very
important to stay compliant and secure.
This setup helped us stay
fast, secure, and compliant as
we scale operation globally.
So with this final takeaways
are speed and efficiency.
API helpless.
Cut time to market by 60% and
reduce clinical trial by 38%.
Reduce clinical trials cycle by 38%.
Quality and safety.
Automated validation, improved accuracy
by 99% and cut compliance issues by 94%.
Patient-centric innovation, AI power
systems and automation feed up over 90,000
hours a year for research breakthrough.
And the next steps is build secure modular
cloud native systems to drive innovation
and transform pharmaceutical operations.
At the end of the day, it's not just about
better systems, it's about building a
faster, safer, and more patient centric.
Systems for the future of healthcare.
Thank you everyone for listening to
me, and if you have any questions
related to this architecture, API
pattern or anything, please feel free
to reach out to me on a LinkedIn.
You can find me by typing my name.
And, one second.
Thank you very much.
I looking forward to hear back from you.
Thank you.