Speaker 34: Hello everyone.
Thanks for being here.
My name is Sujit ti.
I'm a product manager at Oracle where I
work on supply qualification compliance,
and supplier risk intelligence.
Over the last few years, I found
myself focusing on one big shift.
Supplier risk isn't predictable anymore.
It doesn't wait for review cycles,
and it usually doesn't show up
first inside enterprise systems.
It starts outside like pandemics,
geopolitical tensions or sanctions,
and only later do those signals
make their way into API data.
This creates a fundamental
mismatch between how risk actually
emerges and how most enterprise
systems are designed to detect it.
So today's session is not about
experimenting with generative
AI or showcasing a chatbot.
What I want to talk about is how
AI can really be put to work within
the constraints of the organization.
What I'll present is a
pattern, not a product.
Specifically an explainable hybrid rag
LLM framework that shows how retrieval
reasoning and governance can be combined
to produce supply risk intelligence.
To understand why a new approach
is needed, we first need to look at
how supply risk is typically assist.
Today.
Most organizations still rely
on traditional risk models
built around scorecards,
thresholds, or periodic reviews.
These systems operate on structured
data pulled from ERP platforms.
Something like financial metrics,
delivery, performance, or audit results,
and they evaluate supplies in a fixed
cadence often, quarterly or annually.
From the systems perspective,
these models are designed for
environments that are relatively
slow moving, stable and predictable.
The problem is that modern suppliers
does not behave that way quarterly.
Our annual reviews are fundamentally
misaligned with how risk actually emerges.
Risk doesn't wait for review cycles.
It evolves continuously and is often
triggered by external events that
occur between reporting windows.
By the time a scheduled assessment
runs, the conditions that created the
risk may already have escalated into
an operational or compliance issue.
Another important limitation is
that ERP data is lagging by design.
Enterprise systems are
excellent system of record.
They capture what has already happened.
But they're not designed to capture
what is starting to happen in
the world outside the system.
Regulatory scrutiny, legal action,
geopolitical tensions, labor disputes, or
ESG violations almost always surface first
in the external unstructured sources.
This creates a dangerous blind spot.
You can have supplies that appear
green across all internal metrics, like
on-time delivery, clean audits, stable
financials, while at the same time the
supplier is under regulatory investigation
or facing enforcement action.
That has not yet translated
into ERP visible signal.
From the systems point, nothing is
wrong in reality, risk is already
forming, and this leads to the core
insight that the system of record
is never where risk first appears.
Traditional risk models assume
that structure internal data is
the earliest and most reliable
signal in modern supply chains.
That assumption no longer holds risk now
happens outside unpredictably, and often
before rule-based systems can catch it.
This mismatch between how risk forms
and how systems detected is the
fundamental limitation that the rest of
this framework is designed to address.
Alright, this slide gets to
the heart of the problem.
Why traditional supply risk
intelligence falls short, and it
comes down to three key things.
The first is static logic.
Most traditional risk systems rely
on rule-based logic, basically
predefined conditions that assume we
already know what risk looks like.
If a score drops, be below a
threshold, trigger an alert.
If a certification expires, raise a flag.
That works fine in stable in moments,
but supplier risk today isn't stable.
New risks keep emerging
from regulatory changes.
ESG pressures or market dynamics
that didn't even exist when
these rules were created.
Static rules just can't keep up
with the constant manual updates,
and by the time you update them,
the landscape has already shifted.
Again.
The second gap is limited sources.
Most additional risk systems lean
heavily on internal structured data like
supplier questionnaires, ERP records
audits, or past performance metrics.
That data is solid, but
it's not the full story.
Early warning signs usually surface
outside first in unstructured sources
long before they show up in your systems.
If your risk engine only looks
at structured data, it misses
where the risk actually starts.
The third problem is delayed detection.
Because the system depends on
threshold and scheduled evaluations,
they tend to catch risk only once.
It's already significant.
The risk rarely shows up all at once.
It creeps in through
weak signals over time.
By the time an alert fires
you are usually reacting and
not preventing taken together.
These three issues reinforce each other.
Static logic prevents adoption.
Limited sources hide early signals
and threshold base detection
ensures risk is discovered too late.
This is why traditional risk systems
consistently fail to detect risk
on time in dynamic supply chains.
So it's not that the traditional
systems fade, they're just, they're
just built for a world that's changed.
But today, closing this gap
requires a new way to gather,
understand, and explain the signals.
This slide introduces the solution
to the gap we just discussed.
The core idea here is an explainable
hybrid framework that combines
retrieval, augmented generation
with large language models to
produce supplier risk intelligence.
That's adaptive
evidence-based and enterprise.
What's important is that it's not
a single model doing everything.
It's a pipeline with clearly separated
responsibilities, which is why it works
in regulated high stakes environment.
At the top, you see the rag level system.
Think of this as a grounding layer.
Before the system starts reasoning it
first gathers solid evidence from internal
systems and external intelligence sources.
Things like performance history,
compliance data, regulatory
actions, news or ESG disclosures.
That RIE step sets the gut rails.
It defines what the system actually
knows when it makes an assessment.
Below that is the LLM reasoning layer.
So the LLM isn't here to speculate, it's
here to reason it looks at the evidence.
We retrieved connect signals
across different domains and
helps explain why your supplier's
risk profile could be shifting.
And the key point is.
It stays anchored to that evidence.
If the data isn't there, it
doesn't invent an answer.
The output of that reasoning step is
what you see in the third step, which
is the transplant risk narratives.
So instead of a single score or a
vague alert, you get a risk narrative.
It explains what evidence was used,
how the signals came together, and
where there is still uncertainty.
That makes it genuinely usable, not just
something that you read, but something
you can evaluate and stand behind.
And this is where governance comes in.
The goal here is to combine strong
retrieval and smart generative reasoning.
And governance isn't an afterthought.
It's big deal.
You can trace every
conclusion to evidence.
You can review our overall decisions,
and there's always an audit trail
behind what the system does.
If there's one thing to take away
from this slide, it is we are
not replacing systems and people,
we are organizing intelligence.
So risk detection becomes more adaptive,
explainable, and scalable, and that's
what actually makes AI usable in real
procurement and compliance workflows.
This slide zooms in on the data
integration layer because everything
downstream, like retrieval,
reasoning, explainability, depends
on getting this part right.
At the foundation of this architecture,
we bring structured ERP data
together with external intelligence.
Instead of treating them as separate
or competing inputs, the framework
is designed to combine both of them
into a single reasoning pipeline.
On the internal side, ERP data
gives us stability and context.
It tells us which suppliers matter how
they're performed historically, and where
the enterprise already has exposure.
It's governed, trusted, and essential.
But it's also inherently backward looking.
That's why the external intelligence
layer is just as important.
We start with geopolitical risk indicators
like regional instability, sanctions,
trade restrictions or policy shifts,
factors that can disrupt supply even when
a supplier appears operationally healthy.
Then financial stability signals.
Not just internal payment history,
but early indicators like credit,
stress, liquidity concerns, market
commentary or rating changes
that often show up externally.
First, you also integrate regulatory
compliance signals like enforcement
actions, warning letters,
litigations, or regulatory filings.
And finally, ESG performance data.
Environmental, social and
governance signals are increasingly
leading indicators for regulatory
pressure, reputational impact, and
long-term SU supplier viability.
Treating ESG as a primary input,
not an afterthought, is critical
for forward-looking intelligence.
Now this, just as in data aggregation,
these sources are normalized, enriched
with metadata like recency and source
credibility and structured so that the
retrieval layer can reason across domains.
The system can waste signals in context
instead of reacting to them in isolation.
The result is broader risk, visibility
beyond traditional boundaries.
Instead of just asking what do we
know internally about the supplier,
the system can ask what changes
are happening around the supplier
right now, and why does it matter?
And disintegrated view is what
enables early detection, crossin
reasoning, and explainable risk
in insights at enterprise scale.
This slide is really about why
relatable augmented generation improves
detection and not just how it works.
Traditionally, AI models usually
rely on what they learn during
training that works in stable
areas, but supply risk isn't stable.
Things seen all the time, new regulations,
geopolitical shifts, financial issues
often after the model has been trained.
So instead of asking the model to guess.
This approach starts by retrieving current
information from different sources.
It pulls in what's actually
happening right now and uses that
as the foundation for analysis.
The model then looks at that evidence,
connects signals across sources,
and explains what might be changing
in a supplier's risk profile.
And importantly, those explanations
include traceable sources so people can
see where the conclusions are coming from.
That's what makes this usable
in real enterprise settings.
Instead of a mysterious score or an
alert, you get an explanation what
evidence was used, how signals current,
and why the risk level changed.
So the key takeaway is every risk
assessment is grounded in real
evidence, not just model prediction.
And that shift from guessing to
evidence-based reasoning is what helps
organizations detect risk earlier, build
trusting AI and actually use it in real
procurement and compliance workflows.
So far, I've talked about why this
architecture matters and how it works.
The obvious next question is, does it
actually perform in the real world?
This slide shows the results from
evaluations across manufacturing
and technology networks comparing
traditional rule-based systems
with hybrid ose, LLM approach.
Let's start with detection position.
The top meter.
When risk shows up in new ways,
the hybrid approach does better
because it reasons over the current
evidence instead of fixed rules.
This helps catch a real risk
earlier while reducing false alarms.
Next is response time.
Traditional systems often depend
heavily on manual analysis, people
searching for documents, connecting
signals, and interpreting data
across systems with a hybrid model.
Retrieval is automated and evidence
is presented in the synthesized.
That speeds up assessment significantly
without sacrificing quality.
The third metric is risk coverage.
Rule-based systems usually cover only what
they were explicitly designed to monitor.
If a risk doesn't fit neatly
into a pre-defined category,
it often gets missed.
The hybrid approach gives a
much broader view of the risk.
Importantly, these improvements
aren't coming from cutting corners.
Faster response comes from better
retrieval and automation, not
from simplifying the analysis.
Every conclusion is still
evidence-based and explainable, which
is critical for enterprise trust.
So the key takeaway is it's not just
faster or more accurate in isolation.
Retrieval, augmentation, reasoning
changes how risk systems perform
overall higher position, quicker
response to emerging threats and
broader visibility at the same time.
And that's what helps supplier
risk management shift from
reactive monitoring to proactive
continuous intelligence at scale.
This slide shows how the framework detects
risk, the way it actually happens in
the real world, not as isolated events,
but as signals across different areas.
And the key point is none of those
signals are looked at in isolation.
Let's start with the financial distress.
Traditionally, systems usually catch
financial risk after payments are missed.
Credit ratings drop or
financial ratios weaker.
This framework looks earlier, things
like negative market commentary.
Subtle financial pressure or shifts
in credits, outlooks individually.
This may seem minor, but together
they can signal that as supply, as
financial health is starting to weaken.
Next is compliance exposure.
Compliance risk rarely shows
up as a single violation.
It usually starts with increased
scrutiny, investigations,
warning letters, policy changes.
By tracking these signals at cross
regulators and regions, the system can
surface compliance risk before it turns
into an enforcement action or weapon.
Uh, that early visibility can
make a big difference, especially
in regulated industries.
The third area is ESG risk.
Environmental issues, labor concerns,
governance problems are often
treated as secondary risks, but in
reality they often signal future
regulatory action, reputational
damage, or operational deception.
So this framework treats ESG signals
as core inputs, not afterthoughts.
What makes this approach different?
Isn't just detecting these signals
individually, it's connecting them
A small financial concern combined
with a compliance scrutiny and ESG
signals can indicate a supplier heading
towards trouble, even if no single
metric has crossed the threshold yet.
The hybrid approach can identify
multifactor risk earlier, giving teams
time to act, engage with suppliers at
just sourcing or increase monitoring
before the problems escalate.
So the main takeaway is simple.
Risk rarely shows up as one big event.
It builds quietly across multiple signals.
This slide highlights something
that's critical for using AI in
enterprise and regulatory moments.
Auditability.
In simple terms, it means
we can trace exactly how a
risk assessment was produced.
The important idea is that
every step leaves a record.
Nothing is hidden or temporary.
First is retrieval.
The system records which
documents were pulled.
Where they came from, when
they were retrieved and why.
Next is extraction relevant facts
and signals are pulled from those
documents, and each one can be
traced back to its original source.
Then comes synthesis.
The model connects signals across
areas like financial, regulatory,
geopolitical, and SGS to create
a structured risk narrative.
Finally, this review.
Humans don't just see a
final score or answer.
They can see the evidence, the
reasoning part, and the context, and
any human decisions like approvals,
overrides, and escalations also
become part of the audit trail.
This matters for
regulations and governance.
Provenance tracking gives a
complete change from source
documents to final risk conclusion.
That means you can explain not
just what decision was made,
but why it was made based on the
information available at that time.
This level of transparency is
essential for compliance audits
and post-incident reviews.
It helps organizations show due
diligence, justify decisions, and maintain
accountability when AI is involved.
So the key takeaway here is
auditability isn't an add-on here.
It's built into the
architecture at this point.
There's a question that always comes
up when AI enters risk and compliance.
How do we control it?
In this framework, governance
isn't something added later.
It's built into the design from the start.
This slide highlights three core controls.
That's part of the architecture itself.
First is bias mitigation.
Supplier risk decisions can affect
finances, operations, and reputations.
So bias isn't just theoretical,
it has a real impact here.
Biases monitored across the entire process
in the data retrieved in how signals are
weighted and in the outputs produced.
Second is interpretability.
The system doesn't produce
mysterious course or alerts.
Every assessment includes a clear
explanation showing what evidence was
used, how the conclusions was reached.
This helps procurement teams, analyst
auditors, and leaders understand not just
the result but the reasoning behind it.
Third is human oversight.
This isn't an autonomous
decision maker, it's a decision.
Support important.
Assessments go through
structured human review.
Experts can review the evidence question,
the reasoning, override recommendations
if needed, and record their decisions.
Thus, actions become part of the auditing,
and these three controls work together.
Bias can be checked because
reasoning is transparent.
So the key takeaway is simple
governance isn't an add-on here.
It's built into the architecture,
and that's what makes it possible
to use advanced air responsibly
in high stake suppliers decision.
This slide addresses a question.
Engineers often ask, doesn't all
this slow things down in this
framework actually does the opposite?
The biggest performance gain
comes from automated review.
The system continuously pulls in and
indexes both internal enterprise data
and external intelligence sources.
So when something new happens, a
regulatory filing or an enforcement
action, or even news about a
supplier, the system can ev
evaluate it almost immediately.
That's what reduces latency.
We are not simplifying the analysis.
We are removing manual bottlenecks.
Retrieval happens in parallel.
Reasoning stays focused on the relevant
evidence that helps maintain accuracy
while speeding up the response time.
Another key piece is
continuous monitoring.
This framework runs like a live
pipeline as new evidence appear.
Risk assessment update.
That means decisions are based on what's
happening now, not what was two weeks ago.
From scalability perspective,
this approach also works
across large supply networks.
Because data retrival and reasoning are
automated and separated, the system can
scale without needing a proportional
increase in human effort, people focus
on decisions, not data gathering.
So the main takeaway is speed and
accuracy don't have to compete.
It enables rigor and scale, which is
exactly what modern supply chains need.
So far, we are talking about
the architecture, retrieval,
reasoning, and governance.
This slide shows what those design
choices actually deliver in practice.
First, better precision because the
system reasons over real evidence.
Instead of fixed thresholds,
it's better at separating real
risk from background noise.
Second is the faster response.
Continuous monitoring and automated
retrieval means emerging risk
can be spotted much earlier.
Instead of finding problems during your
next review cycle, teams can engage
suppliers, access sourcing, or increase
monitoring before the issues escalate.
Third is broader coverage.
Traditional systems usually
focus on specific risk
categories they're built for.
This framework expands that view by
combining geopolitical, financial,
regulatory, and ESG signals into
one single reasoning pipeline.
Next is regulatory compliance.
Because every assessment is stack
traceable, evidence and captured
through provenance tracking.
Outputs are auditable by default.
Fifth is scalability.
Automated ingestion, retrieval and
reasoning allows the system to work across
thousands of suppliers without requiring
proportional increase in human effort.
People focus on decisions and oversight
and not collecting and sorting data.
And finally, explainable insights.
Instead of black box course, the system
explains how evidence was interpreted
and why conclusions were reached taken.
Together, they are in small improvements.
They represents a shift in how
supplier risk is managed from
periodic rule-based monitoring to
continuous explainable intelligence
that operates at enterprise scale.
This slide really brings
everything together.
What we have been talking about today
isn't just one model or one technique.
It's a system level approach to managing
supplier risk in a world that's constantly
changing by combining accurate data, air
reasoning, and strong governance control.
This framework makes supplier risk
management more explainable and
responsible by design, the first pillar
is integrating diverse data sources.
This doesn't start inside
enterprise systems.
It often starts outside.
By combining internal data and external
signal, the system gets earlier
visibility into emerging risks.
The second pillar is automated.
RIE automation keeps the system current.
Instead of waiting for manual
reviews or reporting cycles, new
information is pulled in continuously.
That helps organizations respond
to risk while it's still forming.
The third pillar is explainable insights.
Detecting risk isn't enough.
Team needs to understand
it and explainability turns
into actionable intelligence.
And the final pillar is human oversight.
This isn't about replacing people.
Humans remain accountable
for important decisions.
Put together these four elements
define what resilience looks
like in modern supply chains.
It's not just more
dashboards or faster alerts.
It's intelligence that adapts,
explains itself and earns trust.
And ultimately that's how AI
moves from experimentation into
something organizations can rely
on in real supply chain scenarios.
I will close by quickly summarizing
the main ideas I want you to
take away from this session.
First, hybrid drag, LLM frameworks
help overcome the limitations of
traditional rule-based risk systems.
Second, combining multiple data sources
is critical for early risk detection.
Third.
Governance and provenance
tracking aren't optional.
And finally, the results matter.
This isn't just a theoretical framework.
Evaluations across a real supply chain
show improvement in detection, position
response time, and risk coverage.
So the broader takeaway is this, the
future of supplier risk management
isn't about smartest standalone models.
It's about building systems that
retrieve reason, explain and operate
under strong governance altogether.
And that's what ultimately allows AI to
move from experimentation into trusted
real world operational intelligence.
What I hope this session showed
is that applying AI to suppliers
isn't just about adding intelligence
on top of existing systems.
It's really about rethinking
how intelligence is produced.
The hybrid framework I shared
is not a silver bullet.
But it's a solid pattern for moving
beyond the static rules-based,
continuous and explainable intelligence.
Thank you all for your time and attention.