Morning or afternoon everyone.
Today we are diving into a critical
and exciting area, HDD generative ai.
Specifically we'll be exploring how
to engineer low latency AI solutions
designed for resource constrained
environments as businesses increasingly
look for real-time AI capabilities, right
where the action happens at the edge.
Understanding how to optimize
these powerful generative
models becomes essential.
We look at systematic ways to
maintain performance while cutting
down on computational needs,
power consumption, and latency.
This opens up fascinating new
possibilities for intelligent
applications directly on edge devices.
Just a little bit about myself.
I'm Ian, principal software
engineer at SD Engineering.
I direct my work focuses on enhancing
global connectivity through advanced
IP satellite network infrastructure.
My experience in network engineering
and software development gives me a
practical perspective on challenges
and opportunities of deploying
complex systems like AI in diverse
environments, including the Edge.
You can find more details or
connect with me on LinkedIn.
So why is Edge AI challenging?
Let's look at edge computing Frontier.
Unlike the seemingly limitless
resources in the cloud, edge devices
operate under significant constraints.
First, limited computational resources.
Think processing power, memory
storage edge devices typically
have much less than cloud servers.
Second, connectivity challenges.
Edge solutions often need to work
reliably, even with spotty, slow,
or sometimes no internet connection.
Third, energy constraints.
Many edge devices run on batteries
or have strict power budgets limiting
how complex our AI models can be.
And finally, realtime requirements.
Many edge applications like autonomous
vehicles or industrial monitoring
demand, immediate low latency responses,
putting high performance demands.
On these constant devices.
Despite this the challenges, the
demand for Edge AI is booming.
Let's look at market trends.
We are seeing strong expansion.
The Edge AI accelerator market, the
specialized hardware is growing incredibly
fast, nearly 36 39% CHER, projected
to hit almost 7.7 billion by 2027.
This signals huge demand for on-device ai.
What's driving this key adoption
drivers are primarily the need for low
latency, over 78% of organization site.
This is crucial for realtime responses.
Then data privacy is another major factor.
Almost 65% of organizations cite
this as another major factor.
Pushing processing locally instead
of sending sensitive data to
the cloud is important for them.
And the industry adapting is adapting.
Model optimization techniques, which
we'll discuss heavily today, are
already used in 82% of deployments.
This shows a clear focus on making complex
AI run effectively on edge hardware,
edge AI market evolution.
Let's look ahead.
We are really at an inflection point.
Currently generative AI at the edge
is still limited by those resources,
resource constraints that were mentioned.
But over the next 12 months, we expect
increasing adoption of optimized edge
AI solutions within eight to 24 months.
The prediction is that most enterprise
need real time edge capabilities
will be act actively deploying them.
Beyond 2025 H, AI is likely to
become ubiquitous, supported by
specialized hardware acceleration.
This rabbit evolution is driven by
hardware advancements, better optimization
techniques like composition and pruning,
and the growing need for privacy.
Preserving local computation.
The shift away from cloud dependency
for realtime tasks is well underway.
Market trends.
Just to reiterate, the those key market
drives drivers because they underscore
the why behind the edge optimization.
The market growth is significant.
As mentioned, 39% of CAGR for accelerators
and 7.6 billion market cap soon.
The primary need for low latency, for
immediate responses and data privacy, both
favoring local on device processing and
crucially, the industry is already heavily
invested in model optimizations, which
is done in like almost 82% of deployments
to overcome hardware limitations.
This sets the stage for the
techniques we are going to
explore in the rest of the talk.
Acceleration solutions?
Software optimization is key
Hardware plays a vital role.
Specialized hardware acceleration
solution dramatically boost performance
and energy efficiency for the edge.
Yeah.
We have neural processing units, N ps,
which are dedicated AI accelerators.
Now common in modern systems on
chips they offer 10 to 15 times the
energy efficiency for a standard CPU
for typical neural network tasks.
Google offers HT ps. Purposely
built edge accelerators providing
significant processing power, like
up to four terra operations in small
low power around two watts package.
That's impressive.
Then mobile GPUs are also increasingly
optimized for AI leveraging their
parallel processing power, and the FPG
accelerators offer re comfortable hardware
adapted for specific AI models and often
very power efficient in production.
These accelerators are designed
specifically for the math
intensive operations common in
ai, like matrix, multiplication,
it, GPU's, overview.
This table gives a snapshot of the diverse
landscape of it, GPU and accelerators.
Don't worry about memorizing the details,
but notice how the key players like
Nvidia Jetson series like Nano Nx, A GX
RTX, ADA AMD rise, AI inter core Intel
score Ultra and PS and R gpu, Google
score, HT ps, Callcom, snapdragons and
pos, and specialists like H Cortex.
Important takeaway here is the
variation in ai performance,
memory, capacity, and bandwidth,
power consumption, and form factor.
Choosing the right hardware depends
heavily on specific application
needs regarding performance,
power, budget, and physical size.
This plays a critical role in the
process of developing these models.
Now let's look at the inference
performance specifically for
large language models, which are
notoriously resource intensive.
Again, this table is illustrative based on
available data, which can be fragmented.
Key things to note.
High-end desktop GPOs like RTX
4 0 9 0 or 3 0 9 0 achieve very
high throughput tokens per second.
Using optimized frameworks like
Nvidia sensors R-T-L-L-M significantly
outperforming less optimized
methods like Lama CCP on the same
hardware for it specific hardware
like Nvidia Jetson's Orient Series.
A MD Rise, AI and Intel Core ultra
running models like LAMA or SSL
seven B, often using ization like
integer four is becoming feasible,
especially with dedicated frameworks
like Tensor, R-T-L-L-M-O-N-N-X.
Runtime with V is ai.
Iex, LLM, open V. However, specific
standardized benchmarking numbers
for throughput and latency on these
edge platforms is still emerging
and depend heavily on software
maturity, on automation levels.
That's why we see, needed data in
the, in specific rows and columns.
The power consumption is drastically
lower for each devices compared to
desktop GPUs highlighting the efficiency
gains, but also performance trade-offs.
Beyond physical hardware.
Hardware is only part of equation
Software specifically, AI frameworks
and optimization engines is
crucial for actually running models
efficiently on the hardware key.
AI frameworks like TensorFlow
Light and PyTorch Mobile are
designed for edge deployment.
NVIDIA sensor RT and its LLM variant
are highly optimized for their GPOs.
Inference automation engines
like ONNX runtime and Intel.
So open wino.
Focus on optimizing models for efficient
execution across various hardware
vendors.
Also provide specific software
stacks like Nvidia, Jetpack,
A MD Rise, and AI software.
Intel's one API Tools and Qualcomm's AI
stack, which bundles drivers, libraries,
and tools for their respective hardware.
The right framework involves trade offs.
As this chart illustrates TensorFlow
light generally offers excellent
hardware support through its de
delegation system, allowing it to
leverage n ps and GPUs effectively,
or in an next runtime, often provide
slightly better raw execution, speed,
and great cross-platform portability.
Py Touch Mobile is often placed
for its developer experience and
see simpler deployment, making
it good for rapid prototyping.
TVM Apache TVM can achieve the
best performance through deep
compiler optimizations, but
also comes with significantly
higher deployment complexity.
So the choice depends on your priorities.
Broad hardware support.
ITF flight, raw speed and portability.
Linux runtime is the one to
explore ease of use by touch
mobile, our maximum performance
at the far cost of complexity, TVR
automation techniques.
Now let's get to the core software
automation techniques, especially
critical for large models like LLMs.
On the edge.
The most crucial technique and the
one we will spend significant time
on is ization, reducing the precision
of numbers used in the model.
Next is network pruning, removing
redundant pairs of the neural network.
Then.
There is a knowledge distillation
training a smaller student model
to mimic a larger teacher model.
Other methods include low rank
approximation or factorization
and various memory optimizations.
Today we'll focus primarily
on top three ization, pruning,
and knowledge distillation.
Start with ization.
The fundamental idea is to use fewer
bits to represent the model's weight
and activations they're using size and
often speeding up comp computation.
There are several approaches
post-training ization.
PTQ is the simplest.
We train our model normally, usually
in 32 bit floating point numbers,
and then convert it into lower
precision like eight bit in TJ.
A represented as in eight or even in four.
Afterwards.
It's easier, but might have
a moderate accuracy cost.
Next is ization.
Our training incorporates the effects
of ization during the training process.
The model learns to be
robust to lower precision.
It's more complex, but usually
preserves better accuracy.
Then dynamic range ization adjust
how contestation is applied
based on the actual values
encountered during inference.
Offering a balance between
accuracy and performance,
especially good at varying inputs.
Precis, precis, our ization.
This visual helps illustrate the concept.
Standard training uses FP 32.
Simply converts this F 32
words into eight or in four.
After training Q 80 simulates this conver
conversion during training, allowing the
model to adapt and advanced technique
is mixed to precision deployment.
Here, you don't have to ize
the entire model uniformly.
You can analyze which layers are most
sensitive to precision loss and keep
them at higher precision like FP 32 or
FP 16, while aggressively contacting
less sensitive layers to inte or integer.
Four.
This offers a fine grain trade off.
Ization is powerful.
Moving from floating point 32 to integer
eight can make models four times smaller
and inference three to four times faster.
Especially on hardware with inte support.
Inference is a stage where model
makes prediction on not seen data.
Let's talk about ization technique,
PTQ, diving deeper into it.
What is it?
Converting pre-trained FP 32 model
after training is complete pro.
It's similar it's simpler and faster.
To implement because we don't need
to modify the training pipeline.
No retraining is needed.
Cons, it generally leads to higher
accuracy loss compared to QA,
especially when going to a very
low precision like integer four.
It often requests calibration data set.
A small representative data
set used to determine the best
way to map the floating point.
32 ranges to integer
or integer four ranges.
For many models, PT Q2 in eight results
in less than 2% accuracy degradation,
which is often acceptable because h the
use cases are like not very generic,
like this very domain specific actually.
Why is ization particularly to integer
eight, so beneficial for hardware?
Let's look at the specs for
NVIDIA eight 10 GPU often found
in servers, but illustrating a
common principle in accelerators.
Notice the performance figure for
standard floating point 32 math.
It delivers 31.2 terra flops,
but look at the par integer eight
performance using its tensor course.
Two 50 Terra operations per second.
Potentially up to 500 tops
with sparsity features.
This massive increase in throughput
for integer eight operations compared
to floating point 32 is why position
is so effective and so critical.
Hardware accelerators often specifically
designed to perform low precision
integer math much faster, and more power
efficiently than a floating point math
ization technique.
What is it simulating the
effects of conversation during
the model training process?
It generally achieves better accuracy
preservation compared to PTQ,
especially at lower bid depths because
the model learns to compensate for
the precision laws during training.
It.
What are the cons?
It's more complex to implement
as you need to modify your.
The training code and pipeline,
it requires access to the original
training data and that MA massive
infrastructure training time is
longer two 80, often keep accuracy
degradation below 1.5% for integer
eight, potentially even better than PTQ
dynamic rate ation.
Adapting the ization parameters
like the scaling factor based on
the range of activation values
observed at runtime, rather than
using fixed parameters determined
offline, what are the pros offers?
A good balance between the simplicity
of PTQ and the accuracy of Q 80.
It adapts to characteristics of
the input data being processed.
It can also reduce.
Memory bandwidth needs as activation
ranges are determined on the floor.
What are the cons?
There can be a potential runtime
overhead associated with calculating
this ranges during inference process.
Because this runs on the edge, although
often minimal, unsupported hardware.
Next condensation technique
mixed to precision.
Using different numerical
precision levels for different
layers within the same model.
So what are the cons with this approach?
Provides a excellent way to
balance compression and accuracy.
We can keep critical sensitive
layers at higher precision.
Example, floating point 16 or floating
point 32, while izing other more robust.
Layers aggressively into
integer eight or integer four.
It requires careful analysis to
determine which layers are sensitive.
It also needs framework and hardware
support to handle computations
involving multiple different data
types within the same inference path.
Studies have shown potential
for significant compression.
Example, up to 30 70% with minimal
accuracy loss, like less than 1% using
mixed precision because when you you
convert some of the layers to inte,
it offers more model compression.
Also,
next to major m automation
technique is neural network pruning.
The core idea is that many large
neural networks are over parameterized.
They have redundant weights or
neurons that don't contribute
much to final output.
Crooning aims to identify and
remove these non-essential parts.
The process generally involves
identifying redundancy by analyzing
weights or activation patterns,
then removing these elements.
This can be structured pruning where
entire filters or neurons are remote.
Often better for hardware speedups
or unstructured pruning where
individual weights are remote
leading to sparks networks.
Techniques like the iterative magnitude
pruning gradually remove small weights
while re retraining the network.
To maintain accuracy sensitive allow
VT analysis is often ever helps
to evaluate how removing certain
parts impact overall performance.
Effective pruning can reduce models
significantly, sometimes 50 to 90%
with very minimal impact on accuracy,
creating leaner, faster networks.
So here's a overview
of the pruning process.
Step one, training initial network.
We start by training a potentially
over network until it converges
and performs step two, identify
and remove unimportant elements.
This is crucial step where you,
we apply the criteria like weight
magnitude activation, frequency,
impact on loss, to decide which parts
are unimportant and remove them.
This might involve setting weights
to zero, unstructured and removing
entire structures like filters,
which is a structured way.
Then step three, fine tune, prune network.
After removing elements, the
network's performance usually
drops, so we retain the smaller
prune network for a few cycles.
This allows the remaining weights
to adapt and often recovers most,
if not all of the lowest accuracy.
This cycle of prune and fine tune
can be repeated iteratively to reach
a desired level of pars and size.
Let's look at specific pruning types.
Magnitude based pruning is perhaps
the simplest and most common.
It operates at the granularity of either
individual weights, weight pruning,
which is unstructured or entire units,
neurons or filters, which are structured.
Pruning
For weight pruning we simply remove
weights with the lower absolute
values closest to zero, assuming they
contribute least for structured pruning.
We might remove entire filters
based on the sum or average
magnitude of their weights.
And the result, unstructured pruning
leads to sparse irregular weight
mattresses, structured pruning
results in smaller but still dense
mattresses, which are often easier
for standard hardware to accelerate.
What are the pros?
Simple concept, high compression
potential, especially unstructured.
Structured pruning often gives better
inference setups on standard hardware.
What are the cons?
Unstructured pruning often needs
specialized hardware or libraries for
speed up while structured pruning is
ser and might impact accuracy, more
pruning technique.
Importance based beyond just
magnitude important based pruning
uses more sophisticated metrices
to decide what to remove.
What is a mechanism?
Instead of just looking at the
weight values, it might consider
the effect on the loss function.
If the weight were remote, using
techniques like tailor expansion
or optimal brain damage, or other
algorithms are they analyzed
neural neuron activation.
Or analyze gradient
information during training.
Goal is to make a more informed,
sophisticated selection of which elements
are truly unimportant for the need for
function, potentially preserving accuracy
better than simple magnitude training
based pruning technique.
What's the mechanism we use here?
As we see in the process diagram, it
involves repeating the cycles of prune.
Fine tune.
We remove a small percentage of weights
or neurons, retain briefly, then
remove some more written and so on.
The goal is to reach the targets
parity or size gradually, rather
than removing everything at once.
This gradual approach generally
leads to better accuracy prevention
for a given level of parity
compared to one shot pruning.
What are the trade-offs it's most
time consuming due to multiple
pruning and retraining steps?
A fascinating related concept
is lottery ticket hypothesis.
It proposes that dense randomly
initiated networks contains spar
subnets called winning tickets.
That.
Trained in isolation from the
start, using their original initial
waste can achieve performance
comparable to full dense network
magnitude Pruning, especially
iterative pruning, is effectively
a method to find these winning
tickets within the large network.
What are the implication?
It suggests that the inherent
sparsity might be fundamental
property of trainable neural networks.
We don't necessarily need
the huge dense network.
We just need to find the right
sparse structure within it.
This provides theoretical backing
for why pruning can be so effective
without catastrophic accuracy
loss, which is important for the H
loss technique, knowledge distillation
for the h. Imagine we have a large,
complex, highly accurate teacher model.
It performs great, but it's
too slow or large for the edge.
We also have a much smaller student
model, which is lightweight enough
for the edge deployment, but might not
be as accurate on its own knowledge.
Stands for is a distillation
process, which works by training the.
Student model, not just on the
ground truth labels, but also to
mimic the output of teacher model.
Specifically, the student learns
from the teacher soft targets
the full potential distribution
across all classes that teacher
predicts even for incorrect classes.
This encodes richer information about how
the teacher model thinks and generalizes.
This allows the small student model to
benefit from the knowledge learned by
the much larger teacher, often achieving
significant better accuracy than if
it were trained only on hard levels.
So for knowledge, distillation based
technique based on the type input,
this is the most common type,
focusing on matching the output
layer of the student to the teacher.
Using those soft labels that were
mentioned, it captures the teacher's
final pre pre prediction reasoning.
Example show a significant parameter
reduction while retaining high
quality up to 95% of teacher.
This goes deeper trying to mass
the activations in intermediate
layers of the student and teacher.
The goal is to encourage the student
to develop similar internal feature
representations as that of the teacher.
We can also categorize distillation
by how the training happens.
This is the standard approach.
First, train the teacher model
completely, and then we can, we
use the frozen pre-trained teacher
model to train the student.
Then there is online,
offline, online distillation.
Here the teacher and student
models are trained simultaneously.
They learn together, potentially
influencing each other, which can
sometimes lead to better results than
the sequential offline train approach.
An interesting variant where a model
distills knowledge from itself.
Often deeper layers of network
act as a teacher for shallower
layers acting as a student.
This can improve the performance
of the single model without
needing a separate teacher used.
This is used when there is a very
large gap between teacher and
student size or model capabilities.
We're optimizing existing large models.
Another crucial strategy is
to use edge optimized model
architectures from the start.
The, these are neural network designs
created specifically for efficiency
on resource constraint devices.
Example includes mobile nets.
Famous for using depth device separable
convolution, which drastically reduces
computations like eight to nine times
compared to standard convolution.
Great for vision tasks, shuffle nets, use
channel shuffling and group convolution
further automations for low power devices.
And then squeeze net employs fire
modules to reduce parameter counts while
maintaining classification accuracy.
Then the Efficient Net uses a
compounding scaling method to
intelligently balance network with
depth and input resolution for excellent
efficiency and accuracy trade-offs.
Using this pre-built architectures
is often more effective than simply
thinking a standard large architecture
as they incorporate efficiency
principles directly into their design.
Let's look at a practical example, an
H Voice assistant using a combination
of the techniques, likely neural
network pruning, and eight bit ization.
A baseline model was optimized.
The results.
The optimized model achieved 98.2%
wake word accuracy with a very low
false activation rate under 0.5%.
It managed 87.3 command
recognition accuracy across
different noisy environments.
Crucially, the model size
for the entire system Wake.
Workplace command recognition was
reduced to just 76 mb, a 73% reduction
from baseline, and the response
latency was only 85 milliseconds.
End to end well within the
threshold for a real time fee.
Knowledge distillation from a
larger teacher model likely help
maintain the higher accuracy despite
the significant size reduction.
This demonstrates how these techniques
deliver tangible, real world benchmark
performance benefits on the edge.
Takeaway and implementation details
go What are the key table covers?
First, establish performance targets.
Be clear about the latency, accuracy,
power, size, budgets before the
start start of optimization.
Secondly, apply the
integrated optimization.
Don't just rely on just one technique.
Combine pruning, ization, distillation,
and potentially architectural choice.
For the best reserves, their effects
are often multi multiplicative.
Third test on target
hardware ator arent enough.
Benchmark and profile directly on
the edge devices we deploy onto
to find the real bottlenecks.
Fourth, iterate with real world data.
Edge environments can be unpredictable,
continuously collect data and refine the
models after the deployment successfully.
Deploying the generative AI at the edge
needs the systematic, iterative approach.
Considering the whole pipeline,
a quick word on benchmarking,
it's absolutely essential.
To know this, we need to
define metrics clearly.
Latency, throughput, accuracy, power,
create a standardized test environment,
simulating real deployment conditions,
measure performance comprehensively
across different hardware and workloads,
and critically use benchmark results to
further guide optimization iterations.
Systematic benchmarking validates
the automation efforts and ensure
the solutions perform reliably and
consistently in the real world.
This is important because if you have
seen, there are multiple choices to make.
So what choices need to be made and
which techniques, which combination
of techniques needs to be done?
We can be only determined if we have a
standard benchmarking, so we can run this
iteratively and find if the combination
actually reaches our benchmarks.
Then finally, the implementation roadmap.
What are the practical steps if we
have to do this First audit model
requirements, understand the Constance
and performance needs, and then prototype
optimization pipelines, test techniques
individually first to see their impact
and implement combined approach.
Integrate the chosen techniques,
pruning, ization, distillation
carefully, and deploy and monitor.
The observability aspect.
Realize the optimized model, but
but include telemetry to gather
real world data performance
data for continuous improvement.
Start with audit, build
systematically, validate thoroughly,
and monitor continuously.
That concludes our look into engineering,
low latency, generative AI for the edge.
By applying techniques like ization
pruning, knowledge distillation, and
choosing appropriate architectures
and hardware, we can overcome resource
constraints and unlock powerful AI
K capabilities directly on the edge.
Thank you for your time and
attention, and have a good day.