Good.
Good morning.
Good afternoon everyone.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Weber Vanel vra, and I'm
a senior technical account manager
working at Amazon Web Services.
I'm really excited to talk to you today
about a topic that's become increasingly
critical in a interconnected world.
Zero trust, security.
The title of my talk is Zero
Trust Security From Perimeter
Defense to Continuous Verification
in the Modern Enterprise.
For decades, our approach to
cybersecurity was largely based on a
model we often call the Castle and Moat.
We built strong parameters, our firewalls
and intrusion detection systems.
To keep the bad guys out.
Once you were inside of that parameter,
within the corporate network, there was
a significant amount of implicit trust.
We assumed that anything inside
was safe, but here's the reality.
The digital landscape has changed
dramatically with the rise of cloud
computing, mobile workforces, connecting
from anywhere on any device and
complex supply chain integrations.
Those traditional network boundaries
have essentially dissolved.
The moat has dried up, and the castle
walls have crumbled in many places.
This is why Zero Trust isn't
just a new buzzword or a product
you can buy off the shelf.
It's a fundamental paring shift in how
we think about security at its heart.
Zero trust eliminates that implicit trust.
It demands.
Continuous verification for
every interaction on the network,
regardless of where it originates.
Whether you are inside the traditional
network or outside, you have to prove
who you are and that you are authorized
to access a resource every single time.
Over the next few minutes, we'll explore
the evolution that brought us here, the
core principles of Zero Trust, why it's
so important right now, its key components
and where this approach is headed.
To understand where we are growing.
It helps to look at where we've been.
Security models don't just
appear out of nowhere.
They evolve in response to changes in
technology and the threat landscape.
Think back to the traditional model.
As I mentioned, this was
our castle and moat era.
We focused heavily on the parameter.
Our main defenses were at
the edge of the network.
Inside things were relatively
open based on that implicit trust.
This work to a degree, when
most of our valuable, we're
at the edge of that network.
And.
Also, it worked to a degree when most
of our valuable assets and users were
inside that well-defined boundary.
It created a clear sense of trusted
and untrusted zones, but then
came the digital transformation.
I. And this was a game changer.
Organizations embraced cloud
computing, moving applications and data
outside the traditional data center.
Our employees became mobile, working from
homes, coffee shops, airports, accessing
corporate resources from devices.
We didn't control the internet of
things, or IOT added countless new
devices connecting to our networks.
These changes shattered,
those clear we control,
and these changes shattered those
clear parameters and exposed
critical vulnerabilities because
our security still relied heavily
on those new porous boundaries
and that internal implicit trust.
This is what led to zero trust emergence.
Security professionals realized we
couldn't simply patch the old model.
We need a completely different philosophy.
The principle that
emerged was never trust.
Always verify.
This means we don't trust any user,
device, or connection inherently,
regardless of where they are
located or originate on the network.
Every single access attempt needs to be
authenticated and authorized continuously.
Moving forward, let's drill down
into that foundational principle.
Never trust, always verify.
It's simple in concept, but
profound in implication.
Built on a few key pillars.
Firstly, and perhaps most critically
is continuous verification.
This means that every time something, a
user, a device, an application, tries to
access a resource, we treat that request
as if it could be potentially hostile,
even if they were verified a minute ago.
We don't implicitly trust
them for the next very access.
This requires robust identification
verification mechanisms for all entities.
It's not just about logging in once.
It's about validating access
for each specific interaction.
Secondly, we have least privilege access.
This is about granting entities only the
absolute minimum permissions they need
to perform their legitimate function.
If a user only needs to read a
specific document, they shouldn't
have right access to other systems.
This limits the potential, the blast
radius if an account is compromised.
An attacker.
Gaining access to an account with
least privilege is far less damaging
than one with excessive privileges.
Thirdly, comprehensive monitoring.
In a zero trust model, you need
visibility into everything that's
happening across your network and
systems, all traffic, all access
attempts, all users and device behaviors.
This constant monitoring and analysis
is essential for detecting potential
threats, whether they originate from
outside or from inside the network.
Without this visibility, you cannot
effectively verify and respond.
In this slide, we will see why the shift
to zero trust not just a good idea,
but absolutely is essential right now.
The factors driving it are the
realities of our modern IT environments.
Cloud computing means that our
application and data are distributed.
They live in on-premise data centers in
one or more public clouds and corporate
networks, increasingly at the edge.
Securing this distributed landscape
with a single parameter is impossible.
The mobile workflows is here to stay.
People work from anywhere
using a variety of devices.
We can't rely on them being
inside a secure corporate network.
Access needs to be secured
regardless of location or device.
Supply chain integration, it means
our partners and vendors often need
access to our systems and data.
This creates complex interdependencies and
expands the network of who needs access.
Securing these connections based
on old trust models is risky.
All of these factors contribute to a
significantly expanded attack surface.
There are more ways for sophisticated
threat actors to gain unauthorized
access than ever before.
Zero Trust is designed to address
this expanded surface by focusing
security controls closer to the
resources being accessed, rather
than relying on a parameter that
no longer effectively exists.
Let's see.
It's worth briefly
touching on the history.
The concept of Zero Trust
wasn't born overnight.
It really began with a recognition
of parameter limitations.
Security professionals observed
that once attackers bypass the
traditional parameter defenses.
They could often move laterally
throughout the internal network with
very little resistance because of that
implicit trust that I talked earlier,
this was a major vulnerability.
Understood.
This recognition was often a direct
response to sophisticated attacks.
We saw attacks that successfully
breached the parameter and then
lingered undetected inside the networks.
For extended periods
causing significant damage.
This highlighted the failure of
relying solely on parameter security.
So the conceptual shift happened.
Instead of focusing on where the access
requests came from inside or outside,
the new thinking was to verify who and
what was making the request and what
they were trying to access, regardless
of their location, it was about verifying
everything before granting excess.
The birth of zero trust idea.
Let's revisit these core principles
because they are the foundation upon
which a zero trust architecture is built.
Firstly, authentication and
authorization for all traffic.
This is non-negotiable.
Every single connection,
every data request must be
authenticated and authorized.
Identity becomes the primary
security control point.
The new parameter, if you will.
Secondly, micro-segmentation.
This is a critical technique
to limit lateral movement.
Instead of having large flat networks,
we divide them into small isolator zones.
If one segment is compromised,
the attacker can't easily hop
to other parts of the network.
It drastically limits the potential
blast radius of an incident.
Thirdly, dynamic policy
enforcement security policies
in zero trust are not static.
They are continuously evaluated
based on a variety of risk factors.
During the session, is the
user's device compliant?
Is their location unusual
is their behavior.
Typical policies adapt based on
this ongoing assessment, not just
a one-time authentication event.
And finally, comprehensive
monitoring occur.
This principle underpins everything.
You need deep visibility into all
networks, activities, to enforce
policies effectively, detect threats,
and respond quickly to incidents.
I.
This next slide really
highlights the contrast between
the old way and the new way.
Look at the traditional security model.
Its primary focus was on
building that strong parameter.
Inside the networks we're really open.
This created those distinct, often overly
simplified, trusted, and untrusted zones.
A major drawback was that it
granted excessive privileges
once a user authenticated at the
parameter and was inside of it.
It also often resulted in security
controls being implemented inconsistently
across different parts of the
environment, and as resources migrated
between on premises and the cloud,
these parameter cloud-based control
created significant protection gaps.
Now, compared that to zero trust
architecture, the fundamental
starting point is assume a breach.
We operate as if a threat actor
could already be inside or could
compromise any connection attempt.
Because of this, we implement
consistent verification processes
for all access requests, regardless
of their source or location.
The focus now shifts from securing the
network segment to protecting the resource
itself, the data, the application.
Every single access is verified based
on multiple factors, user identity,
device posture, context, et cetera.
This approach ensures consistent security
enforcement across all environments,
whether it is on prem, in the cloud, or
accessing resources from a remote device.
Implementing Zero Trust requires
building a security architecture with
several key components working together.
First, you need robust
identity verification.
This is foundational.
You must be able to strongly
authenticate both user identities.
And device identities before
making any access decisions.
This goes beyond passwords and often
involves multifactor authentication,
behavioral biometrics, and verifying
the security posture of the device.
Next is microsegmentation.
We've talked about its importance.
This requires technologies that
allow you to create those granular
network divisions to isolate sensitive
resources within protected zones.
This prevents the lateral movement.
Then this security information management.
Unique systems like the CM platforms
that provide comprehensive visibility
by collecting and identifying potential
threats through behavioral analysis.
Finally, you need policy
enforcement points.
These are control mechanisms situated
throughout your architecture.
They could be security gateways,
proxy servers, next generation
firewalls, or host base agents that
evaluate every access request against
your defined security policies.
These decisions are based on all
the factors we've discussed, who the
user is, what device they're using.
Where they are, what resource
they're trying to access, and
the current risk assessment.
Moving ahead.
Let's spend a moment more on lease
privilege as it's a cornerstone.
It's not just about basic access rights.
It involves more dynamic approaches.
Just in time access means providing
elevated privileges only for the
specific task that requires it and
only for the duration of that task.
This significantly reduces
the window of the opportunity.
That an attacker has to misuse
the elevated permissions.
Attribute based controls allows
for dynamic access decisions based
on a wide range of contextual
factors beyond just the user's role.
Things like the device health,
location, time of delay, and the
sensitivity of the data being accessed.
Identity governance is the ongoing
process of reviewing and managing user
identities and their access rights.
Are the assigned
permissions still necessary?
Have any rules changed?
This helps ensure that the
principle of least privilege
is maintained over the time.
Ultimately, it all boils down to
ensuring that users and systems
only have the minimum necessary
permissions required to perform their
legitimate functions and nothing more.
Microsegmentation is a key zero
trust strategy to contain threats.
How do we achieve it?
By one approach is through
software defined networking.
Software defined networking.
SDN allows us to define
security policies centrally.
Independently of the underlying
physical network infrastructure.
This makes it easier to enforce consistent
controls across diverse environments,
whether it's in your data center
or across multiple cloud platforms.
Another powerful technique is
application layer segmentation.
Instead of restricting communications
based on network addresses like
IP addresses and ports, which can
be complex to manage in dynamic
environments, we restrict communication
based on the identity of the
software or application itself.
This provides a more robust
level of protection that remains
consistent, even if the underlying
network infrastructure changes.
Workload isolation takes this even
further establishing security boundaries
at a very granular level, such as
individual containers or processes.
This means that if one workload is
compromised, the potential damage is
confined to that specific workload,
minimizing the blast radius.
Crucially, implementing
effective microsegmentation
requires dependency mapping.
You need a comprehensive understanding
of how your applications and
services communicate with each other.
What are the dependencies?
What communication flows are
legitimate, and mapping these
dependencies is essential for defining
the correct segmentation policies.
Remember, zero trust is continuous.
It's not a one-time check.
This is where continuous monitoring
and adaptive authentication comes in.
It starts with baseline establishment.
You need to understand what normal
behavior looks like for your
users, devices and applications.
What are the typical access patterns?
What are the usual data flows?
Establishing these baselines is
key to identifying deviations.
Then comes real-time monitoring.
You need to continuously collect
and analyze telemetry data from
every layer, endpoints, networks,
applications, identity systems.
This real-time stream of
information is vital for spotting
suspicious activity as it happens.
Based on that monitoring, you
perform risk assessment during a risk
assessment or an access request, right?
You evaluate multiple signals,
the user's behavior, the device's
health, the location, the time,
the sensitivity of the resources.
You assign a risk score to that specific
access attempt, and this leads to adaptive
response based on the detected risk level.
Your system can then dynamically
adjust the authentication requirements.
If an access attempt is at low
risk, perhaps standard MFA or
multifactor authentication is.
Successes are sufficient.
If it's at high risk, say a user is
trying to access sensitive data from a
new location at an unusual R, the system
might require additional authentication
steps or even block access all
together and alert the security teams.
This dynamic response makes your
security posture much more resilient.
While Zero Trust encompasses users,
devices, and applications, the ultimate
goal is often protecting the data.
So a data-centric approach is vital
within the Zero trust framework.
It begins with data discovery.
You can't protect what
you don't know you have.
You need to identify regulated and
sensitive information across all the
storage repositories, databases, file
shares, cloud storage, et cetera.
Once discovered, you need classification.
Categorize your data based on its
sensitivity and any regulatory
requirements like g. D. Hipaa, et cetera.
This classification informs
the level of protection needed.
Then comes protection.
Apply appropriate controls
based on classification.
This includes encryption of
data at rest and in transit.
Robust access controls and data
loss prevention, DLP technologies
to prevent sensitive data from
leaving where the data is stored.
And finally, governance.
You need to monitor and control
information usage regardless of where that
data is stored or being accessed from.
This ensures compliance with policies
and regulations and helps prevent
unauthorized access or misuse.
Implementing zero Trust is a
journey, not a destination, and
it requires a strategic approach.
Start with an assessment.
Understand your current
environment thoroughly.
Document your existing architectures,
identify your most critical
assets and data flows, and review
your existing security controls.
This gives you a baseline.
Next is planning.
Define your target zero
trust architectures.
What will it look like?
Establish a conceptual framework that
aligns your zero trust implementation
with your organization's specific security
requirements and business objectives.
Prioritize based on risk.
Consider a phased implementation.
Trying to implement zero trust
everywhere at once can be overwhelming.
It's often best to begin with high
value or high risk environments, perhaps
applications handling sensitive data
or user groups with elevated privileges
gradually expand the implementation
to broader categories of resources.
As your capabilities mature
and you gain experience.
Finally focus on integration.
You likely have existing
security infrastructure.
The goal isn't necessary to
rip and replace everything.
Adapt your existing infrastructure
where possible through technologies like
security gateways, proxy architectures,
and enhancing your monitoring
capabilities to fit the zero trust model.
The field of cybersecurity is constantly
evolving and the new technologies are
enhancing zero trust capabilities.
A IML is playing a significant role,
particularly in behavioral analytics.
Machine learning algorithms can analyze
vast amounts of historical access
patterns and contextual data to build
dynamic risk scores for users and
entities, improving anomaly detection.
Cloud Native Security is
embedding zero trust principles
directly into cloud platforms.
Service providers are offering
integrated identity federation,
granular microsegmentation controls,
and API security mechanisms that align
perfectly with zero trust architectures.
DevSecOps practices are helping
to embed security earlier in the
application lifecycle rather than
trying to retrofit controls later.
By building security into development
processes, we can ensure that
applications are designed with zero
trust principles in mind from the start.
And finally, the development of
standards and maturity models.
Is helping organizations understand
what a mature zero trust implementation
looks like and providing frameworks
for measuring their progress
across various security domains.
Finally, so looking ahead,
what's the future of zero Trust?
It's clear that zero trust
architecture has emerged as a
transformative security model.
It fundamentally changes how we protect
our valuable assets by addressing
the inherent vulnerabilities of
traditional parameter based approaches.
By implementing those continuous
verification processes across all digital
interactions, organizations are building
far more resilient security frameworks.
These frameworks are capable of protecting
distributed resources effectively in
today's complex computing environments.
As implementation frameworks mature
and the integration with technologies
like artificial intelligence, cloud
security, and DevSecOps deepens zero trust
capabilities will continue to evolve.
This evolution will be crucial
to studying and staying ahead of
emerging threats and meeting the.
Ever changing operational
requirements of modern businesses?
As I mentioned earlier, zero Trust isn't
a destination you reach and then stop.
It's an ongoing strategy of philosophy
that will continue to adapt to the
dynamic nature of technology and threats.
It is the future of enterprise security.
Thank you again everyone for
your time and attention today.
I'm happy to take any
questions that you may have.
Feel free to let me know.
Thank you again and have
a great rest of your day.
Bye-bye.