Speaker 21: Hi, this is Ishma Mila,
particularly specialized in healthcare,
data security, machine learning,
integration and regulatory compliance
for electronic health record systems.
Today I'll be talking about how PHI
is exposed during machine learning
development and why development
environments are now one of the
biggest security risks in healthcare
as machine learning adoption grows.
Securing data across the entire
life cycles become critical,
not just in production, but
everywhere where the data touches.
Healthcare data breaches have increased
dramatically over the last few years.
What's especially concerning is that
nearly half of these breaches happen
outside of the production systems.
At the same time, healthcare organization
process hundreds of thousands of
patient records every day, which means
even a small vulnerability can expose
massive amounts of sensitive data.
When we think about PHI exposure, we
often focus on production systems, but
in reality, production data is copied
into multiple environments, development,
testing, training, validation, and UAT.
Each of these environments
contains sensitive patient data and
creates additional points of risk.
Most healthcare organizations maintain, at
least three to five copies of production
data across non-production workflows.
Each copy contains dozens of
PHI elements per patient record.
This data multiplication dramatically
increases the attack and makes
machine learning pipelines much
harder to secure consistently.
Data shows that development environments
are a primary target for attackers.
More than half of reported
healthcare breaches occur outside
of healthcare production systems
with an average of tens of thousands
of records exposed per incident.
These environments often lack
the same level of monitoring and
controls as that of the production.
So if you look at this slide, 51.3%
breaches occur in dev environments,
which is like more than half.
Using real patient data in
development and testing has
serious financial consequences.
Organizations that rely on real PHI
phase remediation costs that are
roughly three times higher than those
that are using the synthetic data.
These cost include
regulatory, penalities legal.
Operational disruption and a
long time reputational damage.
And you can see a pictorial
graph here in the slide.
Moving on talking about the
advanced data masking solutions.
Advanced data masking and
encryption significantly reduces
unauthorized access while still
preserving the testing accuracy.
Deterministic masking ensures
consistent results for validation and
model performance testing, allowing
teams to maintain productivity
without exposing real PHI.
So talking about the modern healthcare
PHI 0.0 security frameworks they
can integrate production across the
entire machine learning life cycle.
Organizations adopting these
approaches see dramatic reduction
in reductions in cyber attacks, data
exposure, and reportable complaints
events by embedding security into
every environment rather than.
Treating it as an afterthought.
Dev security operation shifts
security left by embedding it
directly into development workflows.
Security scanning happens during
code writing, testing, and
deployment rather than after release.
Teams.
Using this approach remediate
over 95% of vulnerabilities
during development, dramatically
reducing the risk of PHI exposure.
AI driven security monitoring
continuously analyzes activity across
machine learning pipelines to detect
anomaly anomalies in real time.
These systems significantly reduce
incident response times, allowing
security teams to contain threats
before large scale PHI exposure occurs.
This roadmap, whatever you see
here, the five step practical
implementation roadmap, often
outlines a, realistic path forward.
Start with synthetic data generation,
then implement encryption and access
controls, secure machine learning
training pipelines, integrate
dev security operation practices,
and finally automate compliance.
These steps can be adapted incrementally
without disrupting innovation.
Synthetic data generation strategy
plays a foundational role in secure
machine learning development.
It preserves patient privacy, maintains
the statistical properties needed for
accurate models, and reduces breach
remediation costs significantly.
This allows teams to innovate
safely and cost effectively.
Security must be built into every
stage of the machine learning pipeline.
From automated PHI detection at
ingestion to isolated and encrypted
training environments to secure
validation and control deployment.
Each phase includes continuous
monitoring and logging.
End-to-end production ensures PHI
Remo remains secure through the
entire machine learning lifecycle.
Automated controls access, logging
and compliance checks work together to
provide continuous assurance that data
remains protected as models evolve.
Development environments are
one of the highest risk areas
in healthcare security today.
Synthetic data significantly
reduces cost and exposure.
Modern security frameworks deliver
measurable results and dev security
operations integration is essential
for building secure compliant machine
learning systems in healthcare.
These are all the key
takeaways from my presentation.
Hope you all found this content
useful and informational.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity.