Hi everybody.
My name is Udi and I'll be talking about.
The rise of generative AI in
marketing which has given rise to
the term called vibe marketing.
So a quick intro about me.
I have over 16 years of experience in
marketing, MarTech, and also go to market.
So I'll be talking about the current
state of use of generative ai
where it's going to go, and what
challenges you're likely to face.
So with that we'll start
off with a presentation.
I think the first thing we need
to keep in mind is what does
the word vibe actually mean?
Because and honestly I don't really
like the term vibe because it tends to
give people the impression that you're
trying to match the vibe of your audience
and, that's what vibe marketing is.
That's I would say, 20% of what
the truth is, but actually.
The definition is much closer to
what the original definition of
Vibe was, which is Vibe Coding and
Andre Carti, which whom you would
know as one of the most prominent
figures in artificial intelligence.
I think he put it very
succinctly, is that.
If I'm building a project or a web
app, and it's not really coding, I just
see stuff, stay stuff, run stuff, and
copy paste stuff, and it mostly works.
What he's basically talking about
is prompting these large language
models to help you with the coding
and then putting down the code in
your wherever you wanna post it, and
then getting the output you need.
Vibe Marketing does share some of these
characteristics, but as you will see,
it's actually much more than that.
Just to give an example, so
here's my vibe coded project,
which I built over eight hours.
It's just a fun little website
where you can go and click on all
the places that you've been to.
The reason I'm putting it up here
is to show that how accessible
coding has become to people.
I do have a background in computer
science, but I haven't done any
programming for the last 15 years.
And despite that gap.
I was able to come in speak to
chat, GPT, cursor wa windsurfer, et
cetera, and get a working product
out in less than eight hours.
Now applying this to marketing, I think
what vibe marketing is and there's no
clear industry definition, obviously,
but what I think it is giving.
Everybody and not just marketers.
The ability to interact with these
chat these large language models,
whether it's chat, GPT or Gemini
or, whichever you want to take.
And then cutting down
the time to market from.
Right from campaign planning all
the way to execution, iteration
reporting, and then re-op optimization.
So in that aspect it helps you,
first of all these tools help
you to understand what the what
personalization levels you will need.
For individual cohorts.
And that's basically what the
vibe guidance is all about.
And, and then that basically allows
you to create hyper-personalization
so you can personalize content down
to the individual and not just groups.
The second thing is it helps
you to rapidly scale up.
Creating content, copies, images,
videos, rapidly, create post, start
the campaign, observe the results,
iterate, and then optimize based on that.
And also because you have a lot of social
media listening tools nowadays listening
tools were a little bit difficult to
use in the past because the systems that
used to take all the text, the kind of
feedback and review texts those were
not fast enough to help you react fast.
But of course, because of large language
models now you can literally throw.
All your reviews or comments from
your customers and then get the
necessary instructions to move to
the next step of your campaign.
So yeah, yes, vibe marketing does touch
upon the vibe aspect, but I think it's
a lot more than that as you can see.
I think before we move on to
what exactly is happening, I
think we need to understand that.
Marketing as a whole, or mar marketing
technology as a whole has gone
through a lot of evolution, starting
from moving to cloud-based services.
Whether it's using Google ads or Facebook,
et cetera the advent of mobile which
allowed you additional creative space,
additional formats, it's additional
targeting options to go after to the
increase of social media where your
PII data comes into the picture, where
you create that whole unified profile
about your social preferences to, to
help marketeers do better targeting.
And all of these gave rise to big data.
And that led to the advent
of artificial intelligence.
Now generative AI is only a type
of artificial intelligence, okay?
Because we generally
just talk about AI as ai.
And that is the only kind of.
Artificial sorry.
Machine learning is the only
kind of artificial intelligence
that we humans know of.
But where generative AI comes in is
basically it's a deep learning form of
artificial intelligence, which means
that it is able to process, I think
analogous to how the human brain, you
can do processing of multiple layers
of information to come to your output.
And that's basically.
An evolution from what marketeers
have been doing for the last 20 years.
For example, I used to head a
product called Adobe Media Optimizer
which was from 2014 to 2019.
And that was a very powerful
machine learning system, but
it was a predictive AI system.
There was no generative ai.
What generative AI helps you do is it
helps you to create, so whether it's
art new forms of creatives, and of
course, as we saw it uses deep learning
as its foundational form of delivery.
Again, the other thing we need to
understand is what exactly are these
data models that people keep talking
about, LLMs and models and et cetera.
But the easiest way to describe
that is it's, and it's a system
which takes in existing data.
Okay.
Like text image videos.
And it understands what those things are.
For example if you ask Chad GPD to create
an image of a cat, it looks at a database
of what cats look like, and based on your
prompt, it generates or it predictively
generates what should come next.
And that's basically what it throws.
So that's basically what data model is.
So you take data in, you prompt
it, and based on that you can get
the output that you're looking for.
So that's like a very ELI
five version of Gen ai.
And the reason I'm talking
about that is vibe marketing.
The whole term came from the fact
that generative AI became so much
access, so easily accessible,
not just to individuals, but
also to enterprises via APIs.
What why marketing now?
Because gen AI came, I think
it's been about two and a half
years since open AI can launched
the public version of chat GBT.
But what's happening now is, and this is
true in, in the industry of marketing,
that marketing does tend to react a
little bit slow to these technological
advances, not because that's the nature
of it, but because a lot of iteration
and testing usually has to be done
before taking an idea from a concept
to an enterprise ready platform.
Okay?
But what's happening now is like,
based on various studies and surveys,
you can see 67% of CMOs are pivoting.
They're pivoting towards
generative ai, but.
By doing that, they are
indirectly also getting into
the whole vibe marketing scene.
Second thing is people are
starting to notice that.
When you, in the past, you need to
have, you had to have 10 marketeers,
but now you can get that job done with
just one person and use a bunch of
these AI tools which replicate, and
in many ways, they do a better job
than most of the human counterparts.
And because of, and a second thing
is it's not just a number of people
who are involved, but it's also.
How much time it's taking for marketing
teams to go from conceptualization
to execution of the campaigns.
And then we also see that there
is a huge shift in consumers
also wanting vibe match.
Honestly, that just means
personalization to me.
But we are now able to personalize not
just at a need level, but also at a level.
For example, you could.
You could include you could make
your emails sound in a certain slang
or in a certain dialect, which was
impossible earlier because you had to
manually instruct the system to do that.
But now by putting checks and
balances in place, you are able to
do that by just sending out a prompt.
And most importantly, obviously
it's all about the money.
And that's where we can see that.
Companies using a lot in generative
AI are typically seeing a higher
return on ad spend which is
always the most important metric.
Key differences are just to lay it
out, speed, it's much faster to launch.
Any campaigns if you're
using generative ai.
Team sizes are smaller, more agile.
And you also have a little bit more
control because the coordination aspect of
working with multiple people disappears.
In this model you are also able to run
these campaigns at a much lower cost.
AI tools don't cause, don't cost like
enterprise sauce tools, they, they're
not like a million dollar purchase you
make, you usually pay on a monthly basis.
And if you don't like the tool, you
can always move to a different one.
Personalization wise in the past,
as I said, you could personalize
you, you can still personalize,
but now it's hyper-personalized.
It's very mood based.
Testing, it's it's again, faster
because, not because it, the, the testing
methodologies have changed, which are.
They're pretty much the same AB
testing multi-arm banded, et cetera.
But the speed at which you
can do it now is much faster.
Also you're able to focus more on the
emotional connection, which with the
customer, which is becoming a very
important factor, especially because
brand loyalty has dropped significantly
over the last couple of over, I would say
over the last couple of decades actually.
And finally, workflow.
If you know how to use the right
tools, if you have a little bit of
understanding of automation tools
like Zapier, or if you have a little
bit of skill in coding in Python,
or even like prompting chat, GPT or.
Any of these tools to give you the
right prompt, you're able to move
really fast and adopt really fast.
So those are the main differences
between traditional vibe marketing.
Now, the way vibe marketing moves,
and this is, and of course different
companies have different flows, but this
is my way of doing it now is and it's
not different from running a standard
marketing campaign, it's just that
the tools have changed to some extent.
So defining the vibe defining the
vibe is basically defining what a
creative direction that we are trying
to get for this particular campaign.
Take that, prompt it into AI in
natural language, and then the
AI starts to generate content.
Okay?
And right now most of this content
is primarily text-based, but
we are reaching a point where.
To a certain, at a certain limited
level, you are able to create images and
even videos which have customization.
Although in mainstream, I probably
seen only five or six video ads,
which were completely AI generated.
But that's also because it's really
expensive and it's not a great solution
for SMBs and startups right now.
But again, we'll get to that in a bit
to see where the where the remaining
remainder of the challenges are.
And then after that, testing and
launching again there's a bit of
manual work involved nowadays,
but I think in about five years
that's gonna be automated as well.
Then it's about analyzing and optimizing.
So bringing the data you can automate
that data, send it to something
like Google Data Studio, Tableau,
or you can just do your good old.
Excel analysis, it doesn't matter,
but what's important is taking that
data and then having a chat with these
LLM models, understanding where the
optimization opportunities are, and then
adapting your campaign based on the the
feedback that you are able to generate.
Okay.
These are just a few of the tools
that are available right now and the
best thing about these tools is that.
Whether you are a startup, scale
up SMB, or large enterprise, there
is something for you out there.
And I have been involved in the
entire spectrum of company sizes.
So for example, as a big enterprise,
I would just speak to somebody like
Salesforce, Adobe, or HubSpot use
their enterprise ready products.
Although they can be a bit inflexible
sometimes, but for majority of
these large size clients I think
those tools will be sufficient.
And of course you will use
those in combination with
some of the smaller tools.
If you're a smaller company.
You have these subscription based options
and I've seen tools which are as cheap
as $14 a month, and they do a decent job.
And I, and we and I'm saying decent
because as you will see in a bit
why the, why marketing hasn't
actually reached its full potential
when I do the demo in a bit.
But as you can see.
If you wanna start testing out,
there are plenty of options.
A lot of free options as well.
So I would say go and test as many
of these as you can see which fits
your company's requirements the
most, and then stick to those.
Some of the recent viral campaigns,
which have done vibe marketing.
They come from Coca-Cola.
Which which made this really interesting
campaign where they use Dali.
So Dali is the image generation model of
open AI to basically let fans generate
AI r inspired by the Koch branding.
It sounds really simple,
it caught on really well.
So they received over 120,000 submissions.
And over 7 million social impressions.
So I would say that as a pioneer
of using gen AI for advertising,
I think Coke's doing a great job.
But again, if you move to a more
performance based example, which
is Heinz catch up they did a
similar thing where they basically
used image generation models to
create visuals of ketchup bottles.
Sounds really.
Basic, but they did get a 40% higher
ROI on these AI generated video ads.
So I would say that was a big success.
Mango has been doing something like
that, so they've been using virtual
models for their summer collection.
A lot of people are a little bit
on the fence, but I think the
quality of these image images
generated are getting so good.
There'll be a point in the
future where it'll be, they'll be
indistinguishable from real people.
One of the most interesting ones
I've seen though, was this Virgin
Voyages, which basically featured
gen ai, which is, Jennifer Lopez,
but a deep fake versions of her.
So you can create.
Personalized video invitations
using Deepak versions of her.
And of course, it's a bit of a
novelty, but it really impressed
how Virgin was quick to doing that.
Of course, that gave them
tremendous amount of viral
engagements increasing in bookings.
So I think the investments that they made
in this definitely paid off for them.
All right.
With that, I wanna do a quick demo
to show you a very simple workflow
of what a vibe marketing kind
of methodology would look like.
Now, obviously, what I'll show
you is not an all encompassing.
Example, big comp.
This is probably more suitable for smaller
companies, SMBs, startups enterprise
companies will have some of these tools
built in house with the right guard list.
But anyway, let's move on to the demo.
So let me pull up.
So what we're trying to do is in
this case, is we let's assume we, we
are this company called Hoka, right?
You've probably seen shoes from Hoka.
So let's assume that we have
a new campaign coming up.
And we need to be able to create ad
copies and also add creatives, which which
basically, so typically what a digital,
an advertising or marketing person would
do at this point is they have to manually
write down these copies, manually create
these images to create variations, okay?
And that usually would take depending
on how big the camping is, that
could take two to three days.
But here's how fast you
can do it in chat, GBD.
All I have to do is, and this is
something, this is a best practice, I
would say create a separate thread with
Chad, GPD, where you give instructions for
a specific platform or a channel, like in
this case I'm looking at X as an example.
So what I'm telling Chad, GPD, is that.
I need to create we, we will use
this thread to create ad copies,
creatives for my company, Hoka, for
each camping I will share instructions,
guidelines, et cetera, et cetera, to
create the best ads possible, right?
So it got it.
And then here is the the
camping instructions that
I'm sharing with chat GPT.
To be honest, I have used
chat GPT to refine this.
I just put like the raw information
in and this is the refined output.
But what's important is obviously to put
the important campaign factors, like what
your target audience is, what the brand
guidelines are, what key phrases to use,
color palette, et cetera, et cetera.
So you, as a marketeer, you would
know typically this is what you get
a brief from the client or from your,
companies, internal departments.
But if you are in a startup trying to
do vibe marketing I would say this is
a really easy, simple way to make sure
that your advertise your ads and your
creative stay within your requirements.
Alright and while I'm asking it is
create three variations of the ad copy.
Then three different images.
And so it went to work.
It created this really impressive ad
copies with great call to actions with
all the right information in place.
And on top of that, it also
helped me create this this copy.
I think it looks great.
I would just take it and put it straight
up into an ad. Obviously there are
some minor things I need to look after.
For example, as you can see, the color's
not contrasting with the background.
And so then again, this is one of the
things I wanted to mention earlier, the
reality of why marketing is that you will
still need a bit of human intervention.
Okay?
So it's still gonna make your
work about five, six times faster.
But there are these, if you are spec,
especially if you're a big company
with very strict guidelines, you have
to ensure that these kind of issues
don't make it to the final version.
Okay?
And this so it went on
and on and it made, and.
It stopped generating because I
ran out of credits at this point.
However, as a, if you're, obviously,
if you're using a company account, then
you can connect directly with Dali's
AI and then get these images generated.
That's a really powerful
feature I would say.
Now, as far as I know, there are
no other third party solutions
which are able to generate.
Compelling ads like this at scale?
At least in, at least based on my
knowledge the alternative to this
is, for example, you can actually
go into Canva and I'm just gonna, I.
You can actually go into Canva and
then you can manually create those
different versions of the ad as well.
But again, that requires
a bit of manual work.
It does make your work a bit faster.
I'll give an example.
For example, let's say if you take
the image of of the shoe, right?
For example, let me
just bring it up again.
And there, there's a shoe and I want to
quickly put it on a background, right?
So all I have to do is
remove the background.
And there you go.
That was done by ai.
And then I can take a template from here.
Let me put something like adventure,
right?
So obviously not all of these are
gonna match what you're looking
out, looking for, but I'm sure
there'll be something out there.
And just for the sake of, for
example, we just put somewhere like
here, oh, that's actually a video.
Let me just gimme an example.
Gimme a second.
I'm just gonna try to
find something useful.
Oh, these are all videos for some reason.
Just one second.
I think you have to spend some
time finding the right background,
but once you do, of course you can
upload your own background as well.
But once you do that, it's very easy
to just put this on that and it,
it's not gonna be a perfect ad copy,
but if you're looking for speed over
perfection, then this is a great option.
And then obviously what you have to look
at is you still have to go in and and.
You still have to go and analyze.
You still have to upload those ad copies.
Now, there are tools out there there
are tools out there which help you,
which connect automatically to Facebook
and Google and, various ad platforms
systems via API, where you can directly
push the ad copies and the images.
The only caveat there is that.
Those systems don't have a generative
AI system to generate those copies.
So as you can see, there's already,
this is one of the other issues
of wire marketing is there, the
entire ecosystem is fragmented.
And because of which, you're not able
to automate it end to end, right?
So again, that's something else
that you just need to be aware of.
Apart from that, what you could
also look at is doing some of
these things on your own Now.
This is sentiment analysis,
which I was doing for a company.
And so basically what we, they basically
gave me a list of all the various
comments that were reviews, et cetera,
that were shared by the customers.
And what I did was I spoke to Chad,
GPD and said, Hey, you know what?
I need to analyze these.
I don't have a, I don't have a paid
version of a software, but I'm sure
there are free kind of libraries
and tools available on Python.
Let's use those.
And of course, it gave me the code.
All I had to do is put the data
in and then after a few iterations
and after a few to and fros.
I managed to get this, basically to
find out that the biggest problem that
the company was having is they were
ha people were having login issues.
So this helped us prioritize the features
that need to, needed to be fixed.
And the best part is this entire process
took me only about 20 minutes to do.
And it was completely free, right?
'cause all I had to do was run Python.
Now obviously, if you want to run this.
Another time you can create this as a
separate application and all you have to
do is upload the data in the right format.
So that's another way that Vibe marketing
can help you save not just a lot of time,
but a lot of money for your company.
And also it can basically create
these systems which are very specific
to your company's requirements.
Similarly, I did another analysis.
And this was for segmentation to
understand which area should we be
focusing on to increase the revenue.
And this was for a gaming company.
So basically we found that getting people
to a whale status, which is getting them
to spend a bit more like fractional ends
up getting them spending a lot more.
So we were like, okay, maybe
we should build features to
help them get to that point.
Also maybe, win rates, for
example, could we reduce the
difficulty levels of the game?
And again, the entire process
completely guided by chat, GPD.
All I had to do was put
the data that we had and.
It produce a response from me.
So that's another way in which I
think you can definitely save a lot
of time, money, and on resources
to get an output like this.
Okay.
So I think what we've seen so far
is that vibe marketing is fantastic.
It's going to change the world.
It's gonna change the world
in many ways in how people do
marketing go to market, the speed,
execution, time, money, et cetera.
But.
As you saw in the demo there,
there's a bit of an issue there.
Is the whole ecosystem is very fragmented.
Now, this full stack marketing roadmap,
as you can see in the top layer.
This is where the AI part
comes in, the vibe marketing.
Now, I'm not saying that the tools
which are below that category don't
have any artificial intelligence,
but their use of AI is very specific.
It goes quite deep and you can do
all the AI stuff you want at the
top, but you still have layers and
layers of integration to go through.
And at this point, of course you
can chat with chat g and find
out, what's the best way to do it.
But usually what I've found is that
someone, somebody with experience running
these various tools is a much faster
and more accurate bet because you don't
have to do that trial and error to get
to the output that you're looking for.
So I think that's the first problem.
The second and more serious problem is
that there is a huge data safety issue.
Now, of course, whether you're a small
company or a big company ensuring
that your in-house data, your ips,
et cetera, stay in-house, right?
It shouldn't get shared on the free
internet where anybody can access it.
It has happened, for example,
when chat GPD first came out.
I think there was a developer from
Samsung who wanted to get some ideas
about his code and he published the
entire code base of his product,
Samsung product on chat GPT.
And because, these LMS are a
bit of a black box, anyone could
access that code after that.
So those are issues.
To avoid that companies like this
framework is from my days at Salesforce.
Companies do, have different frameworks.
This one is called the
data security framework.
Now, this works really interestingly
because when we prompt something
like prompt, you prompt an LLM,
it goes into the framework.
What happens is there is that the
first step is there is a secure
data retrieval, which is to ensure
that only data, which has been
sanctioned or approved for sharing
with these lms, get approved, right?
So companies like, as you can see,
products of major enterprises like
Salesforce, they already have those
guard rates built in place and
that's why they charge, hundreds
and s of dollars for the products.
Second and very important is grounding.
Grounding is where the actual
personalization happens, right?
If you take an example
of Ticketmaster, right?
And for example, let's
say I like pop music.
My wife likes jazz.
I. You want to send future pop
music concert recommendations
to me, not my wife.
It's a very basic thing, but the
important thing is that there's data
being shared between you and a potential
third party, LLM, and there are ways
to prevent that data from leaking.
For example, you can do masking, you
can do encryption, pretty standard
procedures, but you need to make
sure that is happening at some level.
If you are interacting with an LLM.
With your company's private data.
And then comes the gateway feature,
which is, as the data is sent to
these lms, you have two options.
One you can work with.
You can work with one of these big
lms using APIs to make sure that
the the kind of right parsing of
data right output is coming out.
But you also have to make sure
contractually or by system design that.
The data which has been shared
with them is not stored.
It's removed.
I'll offer your session with them.
The other option, obviously is that
you can ho you know, have your own
locally hosted models, which may
not be a financially viable option
for smaller companies because they
tend to get really expensive as the
processing, capacity requirement goes up.
And then comes generation.
Generation is where the output is.
Seen.
Usually a strong data security framework
will have guardrails in place to make
sure that there are no hallucinations
or toxicity coming out of generation.
Now this process is, is best.
If it's done automatically, but it may
need some manual intervention as well.
And finally, you also need an audit
trail to, to understand that if something
goes wrong, you need to know at what
point of the process what did this
happen and who was operating with the
system at that time Only once all those.
All these different areas are looked
after, that's when you can send it
to your third party platforms like
marketing apps, APIs, data exchanges.
And I think this is a
part of the process that.
A lot of marketeers are
underestimating right now if you ask
me, especially smaller companies.
But if you don't take these
precautions now as you scale up,
become a larger company these
could come back to haunt you.
So just be careful about that.
So I think that's all the time I
have for now and thank you very much.
Obviously, if you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me.
My email is up there.
But once again, thanks very much
for coming to my presentation
and I hope to hear from you.
Thank you.