Speaker 36: Good afternoon everyone.
Thank you for joining my session.
I will be discussing how machine learning
can be applied to optimize performance
in high volume transaction systems.
So modern enterprise platforms, they
handle millions of concurrent requests.
Maintaining performance, stability,
and efficiency at a scale is
a major engineering challenge.
Machine learning enables system to
predict the demand a scale intelligently
and optimize performance proactively.
This is about myself.
My name is Vive Kuma.
I am a staff developer at Y Tech
Systems Group, which is now Maco.
I have over 16 years of experience
building scalable enterprise
platforms across insurance, finance,
and cloud native environments.
My focus has been on designing
microservice architecture capable of
handling a massive concurrency while
maintaining performance and reliability.
So in this session, I'll share how
machine learning can leverage system
telemetry to predict bottlenecks and.
Infrastructure automatically, when I
say about telemetry is nothing, but
you have your continuous data log about
your CP utilization, all the requests.
Will be used.
We'll take care of those in.
I will explain about
those in extra slides.
So when I talk about the
static rules versus machine
learning, so here is the thing.
Traditional performance optimization
relies on static rules such as a scaling.
When CPU crosses a threshold,
for example, it crosses 70%.
Then some event will be triggered,
and after that we take some
axles, but damage is already done.
Downtime.
Downtime is already there.
Latency is, their system becomes low.
So many problems.
However, these approaches
are reactive by the time.
Scaling happens.
Performance may already be degraded,
but modern distributed systems require
predictive and intelligent scaling
to maintain consistent performance.
Next slide.
So what we are going to learn
today, I will cover four key areas.
First is modern microservice architecture.
Second, how telemetry becomes your
training data for machine learning.
Techniques.
ML driven.
Third is ML driven optimization
strategies, and finally, some real
world implementation examples.
We'll discuss.
So now this is about the
Architecture Foundation.
Modern transaction platforms
uses microservices ed APIs,
Kafka event streaming.
This architecture enables SCA scalability.
But also introduces complexity
in performance optimization.
So nowadays, if you see almost many
projects are using the same design,
like you have spring microservices,
so microservices basically.
We use Spring Boot to implement
microservices, but microservices
is like a type of architecture
where you're moving from monolithic
to microservices monolithic.
You had one big application.
You are breaking those services
in a small pieces, and everyone
has their own database.
And they are communicating with
each other through API gateway.
So what happens here is
your, everything is fast.
You can scale easily.
One service is down, but
it'll not impact the others.
Opposite to monolithic, if something goes
wrong, all complete application down.
And for any deployment there, there
was a. Downtime, which is not there
with this spring boot microservices.
As I said, telemetry is nothing,
but you have your continuous
data CPA, users and all.
So those things are being used
to train your machine learning.
So as it I'll, we'll come to
the next slide where you will
see it, how machine learning you
establish and you give continuous
data, better work in predicting.
So the moment CPUs will high
will increase, it'll predict
it like it is going to crash.
So you can scale, you can add more CPU U
but in meantime, you have a log to verify
the reason and identify the reason, and
you can fix it without any downtime.
So that's what it is.
So telemetry, basically every
system generates telemetry, right?
Including CPS latency, threat
utilization, and request rates.
So machine learning uses this telemetry
to understand your system behavior and
it predicts your future performance.
Based on this.
These are nothing but your
machine learning features.
So important.
Machine learning features include
concurrency, level Q path, transaction
volume, and resource utilization.
These metrics help much ML models
predict system load and performance.
So forecasting load machine
learning enables system to predict.
Load spikes before they occur.
This allows proactive scaling
instead of reactive scaling.
So earlier reactive means something
happened and then you are scaling,
you're adding more CPUs, but now
the moment it spike goes, and as
you said about telemetry, right?
So every system generates telemetry
data, like ccp, utilization,
latency and everything.
So based on that data, ML already
predicts and it forecasts.
So you can avoid, downtime.
These are basically ml or
optimization strategies.
So ML enables intelligent autoscaling,
dynamic caching, and real time
configuration optimization.
So that way it helps you a lot.
Dynamic configuration means in real
time you can, change the tuning of the
connection for timeout values, BA size.
We can retry policies across services.
So machine learning continuously optimizes
parameters based on the current workload
characteristics and performance goals.
You see also, there's adapt,
adaptive auto scaling.
This is what, you can scale based
on the prediction, not after
reaction, not like event happen.
And then you have to scale it.
So these are like three pillars
of machine learning models.
Next slide is about the
performance comparison versus ML
based versus rule based systems.
So you can see the ML driven systems
improve latency, throughput, and
infrastructure efficiency significantly.
For example, you talk about.
73% fewer performance incidents
with proactive optimization.
If you think about efficiency,
28% lower infrastructure cost via
intelligent resolution allocation.
So when I say about you are saving
costs, so how so if high load, you
need more CPU, you need more resources.
But if there is a low request in
the nighttime or oxygen time so you
can, it automatically, it'll remove
those, you can save cost there.
So next slide.
Okay, next slide is all about ML models.
So ML models, different ML
models have different purpose.
Very common one is LSTM.
It predicts load patterns and anomaly
detection, identifies unusual behavior.
Anomaly itself says, something is there
and your behavior is suddenly different.
So this will detect like suddenly
your CPU license is very high.
LSTM says L sst M is long short term
memory and it basically uses your
telemetry and it can tell you the
number more specific things about it.
And a regression model regression
predicts resource requirement.
As I told about you, the telemetries
or telemetries, nothing but the
automatic collection and transmission
of system performance data such
as your CPU uses latency request
metrics of monitoring and analysis.
But here, if you say about
the lstm, so as I told lstm.
Is the LSM regulation is a machine
learning technique that uses long
certain memory neural network.
Continuous numeric values.
So based on your past
sequential or time series data.
So predicting example, predicting future
CP uses future latency request volume
based on historical system metrics.
So this is what LSTM is?
Yes.
So building effective loop.
So what how this loop works is, as I said,
you start with a small, then whatever
your result, whatever your telemetry
data is, you feed that in ML model and.
Using that data, it works better.
So this feedback loop allows
continuous optimization.
Telemetry feeds, ML models which generate
predictions and trigger a scaling axels.
So based on the prediction it, it can
predict, okay CPU users are going high.
So now.
It already predicted based
on the number of requests are
coming or something happening.
So you can easily make decision
about a scaling and you
can scale your application.
You can add more CPU rather than
something already happened, downtime
is already there, and then you are
trying to scale it because number
of users are more, if we talk about
deployment considerations for production.
So production is like obviously
a very critical environment.
So in production systems,
reliability is critical.
ML models must be monitored,
validated, and deployed carefully.
So here you see, deploying ML models
in critical transaction path requires
careful planning and risk mitigation
models must deliver predictions with
consistent latency and high availability.
So ready to optimize with
intelligence if you guys are ready.
So we can, I can give you the
a more real world example.
So machine learning is not
just for the data scientist.
Broader users are there.
So instrument your systems.
Really select models aligned
with your optimization goals.
Deploy with proper safeguards
and hydrate continuously.
As I told you, feed telemetry to the
model and it does the prediction better.
And based on the prediction,
you can do the scaling.
We discuss about, so
what do you understand?
So if I talk about the four things we
understood or we give the priority here is
basically purpose of this presentation is.
Convincing everybody how moving from
reactive to predictive approach is better.
So ml, this transforms performance
optimization from firefighting
to a strategic forecasting
and proactive intervention.
It means.
You, your prediction is better.
You can predict it and you can
scale based on your prediction,
not based on the reaction.
Telemetry is your foundation.
As I said, telemetry is nothing but
your continuous, gathering of your
all CPA users, latency, all this data.
You fit the ML model, and after
that, it predicts better actually.
So measurable business impact ML
enhanced system delivers superior
responsiveness, stability, and resource
efficiency compared to static rules.
So a start is small.
So basically telemetry will
feed and better prediction.
So begin with focused one cases,
establish feedback loops and
expand ML cap capabilities.
So now this is just for, better
understanding because many people
are aware of AWS and Azure.
So these cloud platforms, they already
use ML driven scaling AWS, predictive
water scaling forecasts demand, and
a scale infrastructure automatically.
Azure bernet service dynamically
scales containers based
on the workload telemetry.
These platforms demonstrate
real world ML optimization.
Architecture.
So little bit about this.
So this diagram I will, and
next slide I have a diagram.
So basically this diagram is there,
so it'll basically shows the complete
machine learning optimization pipeline.
So telemetry is collected, which
is your very first screenshot,
CloudWatch or whatever tool you use.
So telemetry is C collected and processed.
ML models generate predictions,
auto scaling system, just infra
structure, which is at the last, you
see the container spot and prior,
second last, if you see already
Kubernetes and all before that LSTM,
that is your machine learning there.
So there they'll predict future.
And based on that you can
scale your infrastructure.
So this is screen whatever I'm saying,
this creates a fully autonomous,
self-optimizing system capable of
maintaining performance at a scale.
So thank you everyone.
Here is my LinkedIn ID and my
Gmail ID as well, any question
we can again talk about it.
So far I can just conclude.
So the takeaway is performance
optimization is shifting from reactive
to productive machine only enables
intelligent scaling, improving
performance, stability, and efficiency.
So thank you for your time.
I would be happy to answer any question.
If you have any question,
you can email me and connect.