Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Machine Learning 2025.
My name is Bala.
Kris, thank you for joining me today.
We all know that AI is the future,
but the fact is AI is already here.
It is in the apps we use and the products
we buy and the companies we work for.
Let me tell you a big story.
There was a delivery
company with a big problem.
The packages were always late.
Customers were complaining
about the late deliveries.
Then they tried something different.
They used AI to help drivers
choose the best routes.
The system looked at traffic,
weather, and distances and
gave the real time suggestions.
After a few weeks, the
delivery times are improved and
customer satisfaction went up.
Is the power of ai.
It is simple, helpful, and effective.
Today, AI helps with so many tasks,
stopping frauds in the bank, helping
doctors find diseases faster, and
reading job resumes and suggesting
the best candidates and showing your
ads that match your interests, even
helping students learn better on online.
So what are we going to cover today?
I will show you how fast AI is
going and what kind of systems
companies are building examples
from real time industries like hr,
finance and manufacturing, and what
problems businesses face with ai.
And finally, where this is
all going next, let's begin.
Yeah.
Let's talk about the area
market is going fast.
A is just not a cool tool anymore.
It is becoming part of how
businesses run every day.
In 2019, the global as software
market was about $28 billion.
By 2027, it is expected
to reach $315 billion.
That is more than 10 times bigger.
In less than 10 years.
What is driving this growth?
Let's talk some of that scenarios.
Companies want faster decisions and they
want to save time and money, and they want
better experiences for their customers.
Let's take one example.
Okay.
Online store had thousands
of product reviews.
Customers were saying all kinds of
things, like some good and some bad.
The companies use IA to read
those reviews and understand.
What customer liked or did not.
Based on that they
improved their products.
This leads to fewer returns and happy
yet buyers and companies use it.
AI to remove the checkout lines in stores.
This is one of the, another example.
Cameras and sensors track what people
picked up and charged them automatically.
No cashiers, no lines, just
a code that is AI in action.
Let's now see how these companies
build such smart systems.
Let's go to the next slide.
This is intelligent
automation architecture.
AI does not work alone.
It needs a system behind it, just like a
car needs an engine, fuel and a driver.
Here is how it is.
Usually looks data ingestion.
This is where we collect the
information from different types of
sources like websites, sensors, forms,
or anything, processing a modules.
Use this data to find patterns or make
predict predictions and analytics.
We turn the results into charts,
scores, or LX integration.
We send these results to other systems
like an app or dashboards presentation.
People see the outcome like a warning,
a recommendation, or a report.
A bank, for example, might check every
transaction with an A fraud system.
If something looks strange,
the system flags it immediately
and alerts the analyst.
This is a smart system in action.
Fast, secure, and connected.
Let's look how.
This helps in HR and finance.
Next.
Now let's go to the next slide.
Hr, analyticals and Financial
Intelligence Systems.
We can call it as AI in HR and finance.
In human resources.
HR companies are afraid with regimes.
Reading them all take days.
Now ai, AI tools can scan
regimes and pick out the skills.
Match people to the
right job within minutes.
They also check for bias and
try to making hiring fair.
One company went from 30 days
hiring cycle to just eight days.
Witha support in finance, AI helps in
different factors, trade, market risk,
and sports, suspicious payments, and rate
long contracts and highlight the key tabs.
One bank is an AA model to
read the compliance documents.
It's used to take three weeks for a
team, but the AA is finishing just
two days with the high accuracy.
So whether it is about hiring the best
people or managing the money better,
AA is becoming a trusted assistance.
Now let's talk about the decision making.
What happens when AI helps us decide?
And now let's talk about the
decision support system evolution.
AI is becoming more than a helper.
It is becoming a decision partner.
This is called a decision
intelligence, and it's growing fast.
In 2022, the market was
about 11 billion by 2030.
It may reach up to 44 billion.
Let's say you work in a hospital,
NAA system can look at the symptoms,
test results, and medical history.
They then suggest possible
diagnosis or treatments.
Doctors still make the final call, but
they have the most support and information
which they extracted from the aa.
Or if you talk about in.
A might tell the managers which products
are running low and when to restock.
This decision happens in real time.
For example, a good decision system needs
rules like what are all the guidance we
have to follow and data like the history
or the live updates and the AM models to
analyze and the feedback from the humans.
A financial form use AI to
rebalance risky investments.
They combine news reports, market
signals, and the past behaviors.
This is reduced, the risk loses by 25%.
Let's move on and see how
these systems all connect using
the real time integrations.
Now let's talk about the next slide.
Integration patterns in modern AI systems.
Now that we have seen how AA helps
with decision making, let's talk
about how the systems are connected.
AA does not work by itself.
It takes to the, it talks to
the other systems and you chase
the data and responds to the
events happening in a real time.
This is where the integration comes in
to think of a smart home.
The light turns on when you walk in.
The thermostat adjusts when you leave.
All the individuals are
talking to each other.
A company works at the same way.
Here are some ways AI is integrated,
real time data streaming.
Tools like Kafka, or he even helps,
sends live data to the AI models.
This helps in fraud detection
or monitoring missions.
Even driven systems like their
response when something happens.
For example, when a user logs into the
system checks for a risk and triggers a
security scan and streaming analytics.
Instead of waiting for reports,
a HX data as it arrives.
This is used in stock trading,
weather alerts, and even food
delivery Timings, hi hybrid setups.
Some models runs in real time,
others updates overnight.
This keeps the systems
faster and accurate.
A quick example for this scenario,
a flight company checks the
engine data during the flights.
There is a strange, significant,
the AA alerts the ground team
before the plane even lands.
That is how powerful a
the realtime AI can be.
Before we go to the next slide,
let's explore F1 and usual
part of aa, which is chat bots.
We have seen them on websites now.
We will look at how they actually work.
Now let's talk about enterprise
chatbot architecture.
Chatbots have become our first line
of communication with many businesses.
When you ask a question on a
website and a bot replies, it is
more than just pre-written answers.
It is a whole system working together.
Let's see how it is built.
The user interface.
This is where you type your questions.
It could be a website, a
WhatsApp, or a even voice, and
it understands the languages.
NLU, we call it as NLU.
The AI reads your cushion and
figures out what you mean, and the
next one is the dialogue manager.
It keeps the conversations going and
remembers what you have said earlier.
The backend connections.
This is where it takes to the
company systems like checking your
balances or booking an appointment.
And the next one is security and tracking.
Everything is logged and kept safe.
Chatbots are used in different
industries like hr. Asking for
a leave are checking the salary
informations and it supports resetting
the passwords, opening the tickets.
In healthcare, booking the appointments
with the providers, sending the
remind reminders about your future
appointments and retail checking
orders are giving the recommendations.
Example, a quick example here.
A telecom company launched a
chart board in four languages.
It handles 68% of customer requests.
Without a human, it save a lot of time.
And reduce the pressure on the supporting
team and give users a faster experience.
Let's see what makes the systems hard to
manage and how businesses are solving it.
And now let's talk about the
technical challenges in enterprise.
Aa
a AI sounds amazing and it is, but it
also brings some serious challenges,
especially in big organizations.
Let's talk about some of the top issues
we are seeing with AA data privacy.
AA systems often use personal data.
It must be protected.
Rules like GDPR and HIPAA are very
strict about this and model rate.
Over time, the world changes multiple
last month may not work today.
AI needs to be adjusted for this one.
Scaling problems when 10 users
becomes 10,000 systems must be fast,
reliable, unstable, and bias in models.
The training data has bias.
AI may give unfair results.
We must test and monitor
carefully and human review.
Sometimes a should not
make the final call.
Human should step in for
complex absence to issues.
For example, a financial company
tested a new model for approving
the loans in shadow mode.
They decide it was giving the lowest
scores for the recent immigrants, and
they passed it and fix the issue and
launch it later with better rules.
And coming up, we talk
about the infrastructure.
How do we manage all the data
models and try in a smart way.
Now let's talk about the next slide.
AI fracture and resource management.
Behind every smart AA system,
there is a powerful setup.
AI needs data pipelines, model
training and deployment tools,
and people who monitors it all.
Let's look at the key
bots automated pipelines.
Example, tools like Airflow
and Q Flow help more data and
trying the models regularly.
CSCD for aa.
Just like software get updates,
AA models also need to update it.
The essentials, they
stay accurate and safe.
A, some AA runs on small devices
like phones, cameras, or even drones.
These models are smaller
and faster future stores.
This holds common data pieces that
model uses like location, age, or
last purchase, human in the loop.
In some cases, people check or adjust.
What I suggest, this helps
with training and trust.
A quick example for this scenario, a drone
company uses small models and the drone
itself to detect cracks in the pipelines.
It work without needing to
send the data to the cloud,
and it saves the cost and time.
Let's no talk about the future.
What is coming next in the
AA and why it is matters.
Now let's talk about the future
directions, RIML, and expandable a.
The two big things are
shaping the future of the aa.
One is Rml.
We call it as automation learning.
This is a AI that builds other ai.
It helps teams quickly test and pick the
best model, even if there are no experts
and expandable ai, we call it as XA.
This helps us understand
why a AI made a decision.
It is very important in banking,
healthcare, and loss examples.
A bank is not to create
a credit approval model.
Then it used explainability tool
like shop to show customers why
they were approved or denied.
It builds trust and reduce complaints.
This tool get together Auto ML and
expandable AI makes a faster to
build and easier to trust and know.
Let's wrap up it.
Let's bring all it together.
Now let's coming to the
conclusion, let's recap everything
we have talked about so far.
AI is changing how companies work
from decisions to automation,
and it is going fast and it is
being used in all industries.
Smart systems need good design,
integration and monitoring.
We must think about privacy.
Fairness and keeping humans
involved and the future easier.
A without IM, L and more
trust with expandability.
And one final thought.
A will not replace people,
but people will, who uses a
will replace those who don't.
And thank you all for your time.
It's Bill aa.
That is not only smart, but
also useful, fair and trusted.
So thank you all so much for
being part of this session.
AI is not just a technology.
It is a way to solve the real
problems, make better decisions and
support people in their everyday work.
As we move forward, it will say systems.
They are smart, yes, but also
simple, safe, and helpful.
If you would like to connect,
ask questions, and continue
this conversations, feel free to
reach out to me and my email ID
is contact bama@gmail.com and my
LinkedIn is available in this slide.
I'm always happy to share the ideas.
Helping projects are, just talk
more about this exciting journey.
Thank you and enjoy the rest
of the conference party.
Thank you.