Hi everyone.
Good morning, good evening,
and good afternoon.
My name is Raach Ma. I have around
20 years of IT experience providing
solutions to various business domains
like healthcare, manufacturing, retail.
All these years like I have
contributed to legacy application
modernization, digital transformation.
I would say that's my
core area of expertise.
So if.
Already working on legacy platforms and
you are in the process of modernizing it.
Then you are in the right place.
So in the next couple of minutes
we will talk about how a powered
solutions would help us in
transforming these legacy systems.
That's about my quick introduction.
If you have any questions after the
presentation, you can please feel free to
reach out to Arch in the neuro@gmail.com.
Yep.
Let's write a bit jump
into the presentation.
All right.
So like I mentioned many of us in
our career would've worked with many
legacy applications and systems,
and we all know so much business
value would've been tied so tightly.
With these legacy applications.
But what happens when the business
expects these legacy applications to
be meeting today's business needs?
One of us definitely would start
thinking about how I can modernize
these legacy applications, right?
And definitely we tend to
follow the proven and the useful
conventional approaches, but
sometimes these conventional or the
traditional approaches might not.
Might not be good enough to meet the
business expectations or might not give
you the desired in income desired result.
So then you will start
looking for the alternatives.
So this is where I talk about, a powered
solution, which is which I call it
as a cognitive retail modernization
framework which will help me like how
exactly I can transform these legacy
systems at the same time I can enhance
this customer engagement mechanisms.
So what would be the the approach that
I would want to come with through this
presentation is like it would be an
embedding of cognitive capabilities
with this, legacy systems where
where you will produce a intelligent
hybrid environment that is going
to combine with proven technology
with the advanced AI capabilities.
Okay, so before we, we go down further
into the details, I want to call out what
are the present challenges the industry
may face especially in the retail sector?
So I, based on the research,
what I could read from various
articles or my own survey.
And it's 70% of these legacy systems
like they are like more than 20 years
ago that they have the age as 20 years.
Some of these businesses are still
running on these legacy applications.
And I would also see that 70 to
80% of the IT budget is being
contributed towards its maintenance.
Having not having much preference to
the innovation, which is not at all a
good good thing, good sign, I would say.
And 22, I would say like just 20 to 25%.
Only 20 to 25% of the data is
being utilized for decision making.
I would say today data plays a so vital
role that you have to use as a main key
driver for any of your decision making.
So I would say these are the,
some of the challenges definitely
we should be addressing keeping.
Keeping in mind that conventional
approaches may or may not address
your current business need.
So I have to always call out
for options and alternatives.
Yeah.
We, for this challenge, what other
options I have to address and then
meet today's business expectations.
Okay.
So like I mentioned, we would definitely
try to follow some of the traditional
approaches the conventional way of
modernizing these legacy systems.
But before we go there, I want to call out
like what limitations that you may face
when you try to deploy these approaches.
The first one would be high
risk and uncertains definitely.
When you use these traditional
approaches, it is possible
that, you may carry heavy risk.
Because these applications are
mission critical applications.
Some of them might be, and you'll be
having so much business logic inside that.
And when you use this traditional
approach, you may not really take
the business advantage of that, and
that would definitely be a high risk.
And you might not be able to
see the desired outcome of it.
And the second thing I would
say it'll be a migration without
transformation, what I meant to say.
You are able to migrate it to the
new platform, but you'll still be
treating that as a. A modern legacy
system, meaning you are not able to
really achieve what exactly you, you
plan to achieve because though you
follow a traditional modernization
approach using a lift and shift or
rip and replace you might be able to.
Migrate it, but you wouldn't be able
to completely transform the existing
system, and you wouldn't be in a
position to achieve the desired outcome.
And the third one is a gradual
improvement without vision.
So though the traditional approach
still suggests that you can apply the
phased manner, but still you wouldn't
really be able to achieve the the
vision that you have planned for it.
What I meant to say, we are trying
to do it in incremental fashion,
but still somewhere in at some point
of time, you'll feel that it still
lacks some amount of integration to
give you the holistic picture of it.
So these are the limitations of the
traditional modernization approaches.
Now, having said that,
these are my limitations.
What options do I have?
Let me see.
All right.
So like I was talking about
though, one option is to use
this conventional approach of
modernizing these legacy systems.
What if I try to use this in the, in this
era of AI and ml AI powered, cognitive
retail modernization framework and
how exactly is going to help me out.
So what is this framework all about?
So what are the various
phases or the layers it has?
Let's see here.
So it is primarily would be comprised
of for four different layers.
Cognitive layer integration.
Predictive analytics implementation,
hyper-personalization engine
in diligent process automation.
Let us see each of these
layers in a detailed manner.
So what I meant by
cognitive layer integration.
Though you have so much data residing
on these systems, you should be
effective position to utilize this data.
For a better decision making.
So you should definitely deploy
some intelligent methods or
techniques for processing these data.
Like you can use APIs or even streams
or various approaches so you can use
them and you would, you should be
in a position to effectively utilize
unprocessed these data streams.
And predictive analytics implementation.
What I'm trying to say here so while
you started the processing of data, you
should also think about applying various
machine learning approaches through which
you can process and produce a results
that can drive you in a better way for,
predictive decision making which is
definitely, it is going to be an optimized
way for forecasting these patterns.
And then decision making.
So that would be the second layer.
And the third one is
hyper-personalization engine.
So you have processed the data and you
have applied some machine learning models
or the techniques on this process data.
What would be the outcome
of these two approaches?
Like you tend to arrive at a stage
where you can tailor, you can use
this process data and you can produce
certain tailored approaches, how you
can reach out to the customers and you
can engage them, you can convert them
you can make revenue out of them, right?
That is hyper personalization engine.
And the third one is
intelligent process automation.
So now we consider data, we
process it, and we have, we started
working on this process data.
We use this process data for
making better decisions tailored
approaches and process automation.
So you should see wherever there's a
refinement, there is a fine tune fine
tuning required for this process.
And based on this processed data you will
have a better control how intelligently
you can automate some of these processes.
You can apply these cognitive
capabilities, but not,
re-engineering the whole system.
Yeah.
So why I'm, in one thing I would say why
I am multiple times insisting on this.
Sometimes we go with this rip and
replace as a whole cell approach.
That might not be really
helping you sometimes.
So that's when you have to think about
what if I use these AI powered solutions?
On these retail systems and when
you try to impose this framework
what it demonstrates actually what
kind of potential it'll give you
in in, in the cases of increasing
the customer engagement rates.
And I would say based on this
survey, I would say like 40%.
I would say there is a, there
is an amount of increase in this
customer engagement and also in
the overall operation efficiency.
When you use this
cognitive retail approach.
Okay, now we have seen what are the
layers various layers involved in
this methodology in this framework.
Now we will see what are the various
phases, how exactly we can implement
this cognitive retail framework.
Phase one is like cognitive foundation.
Phase two, intelligent augmentation and
phase three is autonomous optimization.
So what exactly meant
by cognitive foundation.
Now like I mentioned in the previous
slide, you have so much data, critical
data, siding on these platforms.
You have to build efficient data
pipelines and even streams so that you
can definitely build a core infrastructure
that, that, I would say that's the basic.
The foundation phase where you
will you will establish this
co cognitive retail framework.
And phase three is very
intelligent augmentation.
So now you put the foundation, now
you have to integrate these prediction
capabilities into these operation
systems so that you can augment
the capacity or the the efficiency
of these intelligent systems.
And the third phase is
autonomous optimization.
As the name series you, by
implementing phase one and phase
two, you are always welcoming.
These systems like to be self capable,
self-managed or self optimize these
algorithms and these closed loop systems.
These three phases would really help.
Anyone to implement this cognitive
retail modernization framework.
That way we will see like a tremendous
difference between the traditional
approach and the the a powered approach.
And I would see definitely I have
to mention this, by using this
approach, there is a success rate near
2.5 times higher for this approach
where you'll still be falling that
incremental and the phased manner.
Approach.
Okay.
Yeah.
I, to make it in a better,
under better understanding, I
would wanna take a case study.
It is about a regional grocery chain,
which which like, which, just like
any other grocery chain would be
handling things like out of stock
issues over inventory, overstock.
Like in terms of how effective we
do the promotion strategies, and
once I implement this, what are the
responses how it is really affecting
the customer's shopping trends and how
I'm really, retaining those customers.
So I want to take this case today.
I want to talk about what if I implement
this AI powered approach, how exactly
is going to bring the benefits, sir?
So I want to call out certain numbers.
This particular grocery change,
which I'm talking about, it is like
having an old application, a legacy
application, which is of 15 years
old merchandising management system.
Now rather than doing this conventional
approach of rip and replace of the whole
wholesale approach what if I try to
deploy this cognitive retail modernization
approach, how exactly it is going to
bring the differences or the results.
So I would say based on the case study,
it has tremendously, it has showed
the substantial business outcomes
with especially the positive return
on investment within the eight months.
I would say the total implementation
cost was like approximately $3.2
million, representing around
0.4% of retail's annual revenue.
And it is compared to the estimated
12, $15 million, had it been like you
have used this conventional approach.
Now I have said that I have used this
AI powered approach instead of this
conventional approach, how exactly
it is going to impact the financial
factors of this grocery chain,
first year financial be benefits.
So it has proved that it is going to,
or it has already given approximately
$5.8 million financial benefits
with 181% written on investment.
That is the first
obvious financial impact.
And the second thing,
inventory management.
So approximately $3.5 million you
can save or you can see the savings
through reducing the carrying costs
decreas shrinkage and improved sales
for enhanced product availability
and marketing effectiveness.
So under this category, it is
approximately like $1.2 million.
By enhancing this marketing
strategies promotional efficiency,
all, all because of introducing
these cognitive capabilities.
Instead of using this traditional approach
of modernizing this legacy systems and
with respect to operational efficiency,
this approximately $1.1 million savings.
Especially improving the delivered
financial benefits through reduced
labor requirements for administrative
tasks and improved workforce ization.
So not only these financial results if
I want to compare with this traditional
approach, it is, I would say it's a
true continuous learning and adaptation.
This cognitive framework has introduced an
accumulated data, analytical experiences,
along with its predictive accuracy and
business impact increased over time.
Okay.
So that, that, I would say the general not
general, the specific financial category.
What are the general benefits if I use
this cognitive retail moderation approach?
One is reduced implementation risk.
If you rightly remember I have called
out this as one of the risks when you use
this traditional approach saying so much
these are mission critical systems, and
so much business value or business rules
would've been implemented in the system.
It is so possible that you might
not carry it over when you use this
traditional approach, but considering
this AI powered cognitive retail
modernization approach, you would, it,
you would like reduce this implementation
risk and foster time to value.
Of course.
So it is so possible when you
use this conventional approach.
It'll take some time.
It'll take large amount of time, cons
compared to these augmented approach.
So that way when you use these AI
powered frameworks, it is so possible
that you can start seeing the results.
You can bring in the change
in a much faster way.
And you can start responding to
the market demands and needs and
lower investment requirements.
When you use this traditional
moderation approach, it is possible
that there is some amount of skill gap.
There is some amount
of efficiency problems.
There is a possibility that it'll we
tend to see some unexpected surprises.
If I use this AI powered modernization
framework it is definitely you have
a great chances of lowering your
investment or the capital investment
on these requirements and then
preserved institutional knowledge.
Like I kept saying in all these legacy
systems you have so much business
logic rules have been encapsulated.
You.
At any cost.
I don't think business is at
the liberty of losing them.
So by using this augmentation
methodology, I'm not going to move
away from it completely, but still,
I'm going to modernize these systems
res, be able to respond to the
business current business needs.
So what I'm trying to say, you
are, I'm still able to retain
the business knowledge what has
been there in those old systems.
At the same time I'm able to
respond to the new business needs.
Having said the bene the benefits and the
financial impact, what sort of challenges
we may face when you start implementing
this retail modernization approach?
So data quality issues, like I said,
so data plays a very critical role.
If the data is not being properly
maintained, not refined enough, so
whatever the data you are going to
supply for this moderation approach,
it is possible that it may not give
you the expected outcome because the
data is not in a very refined format.
It is possible that it'll
give you undesired outcomes
and integration complexity.
You have to understand I'm trying
to modernize these legacy systems.
During this process.
It is possible that I may have to
face certain integration challenges
and complexities when I'm trying to
bridge this gap with these a platforms.
So you have to be careful enough
and you have to consider ahead
what sort of those challenges.
That way it, it'll be easy
for us in the roadmap.
To make the process much
smoother and skillset evaluation.
So this AI powered approach, though,
we start seeing the results of it,
I would still say it is it is like a
quite a rapidly evolving technology.
So you have to be in a position to choose
the right set of skills and talent to
be able to apply their strengths and
weaknesses while I work on this moderation
approach on the change management.
It's so you are doing, you're
doing a big leap from this legacy
modernization legacy systems, modernizing
them to, a cognitive frameworks.
It is going to definitely
be operational challenges.
You have to bring in certain change
management procedures for effectively
handling all these operational procedures.
Okay, technical debt.
So not only these these four factors.
The fifth factor is what it is
going to talk about having, we
have already mentioned about this
increased integration complexities.
The, these approaches are going
to accumulate this technical debt.
When it is implemented without appropriate
architecture, vision, and discipline.
So these are the five challenges that
we may face when you, when we try to
implement this framework modernizing
or enhancing these legacy systems.
So having said, those are my
challenges that we may face.
What exactly the considerations
that you have to keep in mind
during its implementation.
You have to establish a
clear architecture standards.
Absolutely.
I agree with that.
So you should always have a a
standard way to design a coherent
architectural framework that
ensures shortterm enhancements and
supporting the long-term system
health and implement data governance.
Who will not agree with me.
Like when you are trying to deal
with such critical data, which is
going to be playing a key role for
your business expansion, you have
to have some governance in place.
You have to develop some master data,
go master management capabilities, and
you have to have certain frameworks
in place for maintaining the data
quality and develop talent strategy.
Like I said, it's a quite evolving and
rapidly changing technology platform.
So you have to have a strategy like how
exactly you can make use of the present
trends and techniques, and you can assess
the talent and the skills of the people.
And you can, put them in the right way.
So you should also see do you have an
internet expertise or you have to invest
so heavily so that you have to hire some
new people while you want to achieve this.
No the fourth one is
prioritize change management.
So in the previous thing, we have
considered this also one of the,
one of the challenges we may face.
So you have to keep this as one of the
implementation consideration that you
have to have a comprehensive change
management process for effective
utilization of these new capabilities.
So I would want to conclude, it is
all about like how we effectively
you balance like both legacy systems,
knowledge that is still playing
a pivotal role at the same time.
The new features, the new
enhancement that you can leverage
from this AI powered approach.
I would want to call out the three
various areas where you can balance it in
a very you can do it in a very balanced
way, enhance the customer experience.
So these cognitive capabilities.
I'm pretty sure it will deliver
personalized interactions, that is gonna
increase engagement rates by up to 40%
while preserving the human touch that
defines exceptional retail experiences.
So that is one, one factor.
The second one is preserved
technology investment.
I would've already spent so
many so much money on retaining
this making so, so stable.
My platform so much operational experience
and this refined algorithms that I
would've been having on my systems.
You should you should go in a
very amicable way to protect these
valuable institutional knowledge at
the same time you leveraging these
advanced, the cognitive capabilities.
And compelling financial deals.
This would be the third area where
I would say you, you would be
able to still deliver substantial
operational improvements and
compelling financial returns with
significantly compressed timeframes.
Yep.
What I would want to finally
say is you have a legacy system.
With so much institutional allergy
knowledge residing on this platform,
you have to assess in a very thorough
manner, should I be placing what sort
of approach or strategy that I can use.
Should I be using a whole wholesale
approach of lift and shift or rip and
leap replace, these approaches are
proven ones, but still are in the a in
the age of AI and ml, you should really
take one step back and then see what
if I try to deploy these AI powered
approaches like what sorts of capabilities
that it is going to introduce?
Is it going to just modernize or
is it going to enhance further?
So you should always have
such sort of decision making.
And then see when I introduce
this kind of new frameworks.
Am I going to minimize the risk?
Am I going to maximize the value?
If that is the way, yes you, you have
all the possibilities of effectively
apply these trends in this digital age.
At the same time not losing this
institutional knowledge, which has been
proven for so many years and helpful,
being helpful for your businesses.
Yeah I'm done with my presentation.
Thank you so much.
If you have any questions, I would be.