Welcome to my session about dynamic
rebranding in data, scaling content
for co-branding experiences.
So myself, I'm Rakesh Conda, a
solution architect with 13 plus years
of experience in enterprise content
platforms, including large scale
a EM and a EM guide deployments.
Today's conversation is for any team out
there managing complex multi-platform
content challenges and looking for
a smarter, scalable way to deliver.
So the agenda for the meeting is we
are gonna talk about the business
challenge, challenges faced by
business out there and how one can
decide a EM Guides is a solution.
And what happens when you
implement the a EM guides, a EM
in action and the outcome of the
implementation, the impact and results.
We are gonna walk through
all the four scenarios today.
First let's talk about
the business challenge.
So modern businesses are
expected to deliver fast,
personalized, and helpful content.
Customers want answers now
in their preferred format and
on their preferred device.
At the same time, internal
teams are being asked to do more
with less, more audiences, more
platforms, but fewer resources.
The challenge becomes how do
you meet rising expectations
while staying efficient?
Businesses must serve direct customers,
partners, internet employees.
You have many different
stakeholders, many different kinds
of audience who need the content.
So delivering the right content
to the right audience at the
right time has become critical
for every business out there.
Play go to be website.
It's p chat bot, mobile apps,
product and even P commission.
Every channel has its own
rules for contain and multiply
multi parts and bands.
Few have a product that.
You have research ation needs, so without
structure, things fall on all around,
which are scalable in certain are not
suitable or, and even sustainable.
There is a love current across channels.
So now the CS landscape, the many
organizations, they have too many
because they acquire product.
Each product comes their own combination.
And the, their own documentation source,
you end up too many contain management
system cycle or depending on what are
if, how comes and has requirements and
in process already, not modular tribal
knowledge, like knowledge cater up
and needs right to have deliver
on channel in for partner and to
different, black from s earlier.
Main organizations, they
are still looking up.
Mix of old dead semesters and old
publishing processes, lack consistency.
And with any semester you can is click
platforms, whether you need update
the product activation, it becomes a.
Without realizing the bending
consistent skin and skin brings
a bit what needed is shift a
structured, centralized, and automated
contain data and a guide command.
So pending.
Are there any points?
Each part come with a
different requirements.
Parts need the documenting to
be deliver in and required to be
delivering, in or in ML format.
So with
rebranding or ing with each.
Buffet brings a referred
problem or a different way.
Deliver, rebrand, deliver documentation,
omnichannel Indian put to be deliver.
So best say brand require, it,
let's say have who telling practice.
And.
The tap or chat PT or the technology
resell it, but with different
name you can relate GPAI or
AI view in that, the part one.
Now, newer product
accumulation, U-I-G-P-E keeping.
Check 18 month, but when
all partners to be placed, part
terminology need to be placed and
sometimes like you partner require.
Than brand guide like our,
have a DT board on e electric
company that do re our product.
So each brand has a own brand.
So our ation change reason
installer change logs.
And there the acquisition also can,
current innovation needs to change
and offering may also change, right?
In a product, it may
have different of fear.
And when you sell the product,
have gu set of features.
So there is a gap and
document need reflection.
And all time perhaps is do not.
End the flat, the least parts in you
in, in Africa.
You may have it in, so like
the volume is score by lot.
So if you rethink about this content
challenge, and if you are trying to
solve for this as a team or multiple
teams try to gather and solve it, right?
What I would say is tackling this
challenge starts with alignment, right?
Stakeholders need to surface the real
issues, whether it's version control,
branding apps, or inefficient reuse.
Clarify goals across teams forecast
growth because if the content systems
aren't built to scale now they're,
they'll collapse later or very soon.
You may not even realize how soon that
is with the way things are changing now.
So also focus on operational efficiency,
agility, data-driven decision making,
that's the foundation for content
systems that grow with your business.
So the CMS sprawl is real.
If your organization has multiple
CMS platforms, multiple branding
updates or inconsistent publishing
processes you are not alone.
And this session is one of those steps
that you can take to solve for it.
So modern content demands, unified
governance, automation, and intelligent
re reuse a shift to a smart content
architecture and that's where you
begin your road to a EM guides.
Like I was saying, a modern system must
start with a single source of truth.
Not too many CMS systems, just one
source of truth centralized From
there, it should also support modular,
reusable content blocks, automated brand
controls, and multi-channel publishing.
This is exactly what data
plus a EM Guides delivers.
It's not just about writing, it's
about publishing intelligently.
You get a single content
management system.
An omnichannel distribution, your content
is consistent and the maintenance is
centralized to one source of truth.
So why a EM guides, when you
are shopping, like you look for
certain set of features, right?
When choosing a platform, you
have to look for four things.
One structure, two scalability.
Three omnichannel capability
and the ease of use.
And if you are trying to bring in new
producers, new content creators, the
learning curve should be like minimal.
It should not be too difficult for them
to, start using the system because.
You may start with one team, but
it may grow to multiple teams.
So a EM Guides provides all of that
with the added bonus of native data
support partner specific customization
and seamless delivery options.
It allows you to manage everything
from one place and deliver anywhere.
So the answer is very clear.
A EM guides it is because
it provides all the.
Answers for the challenges
that modern companies with
complex content challenges face.
So how it all works, with a EM Guides
your content lives in data topics.
Each one is reusable, modular, and
adaptable data valves on one side filter.
Content for different audiences.
Conditional attributes allow
you to control what appears for
which partner or which platform.
Key maps automate brand swaps.
It's one content set that dynamically
gets assembled and delivered.
So with a system like this, you
get modular content structure.
You can rebrand dynamically for any number
of partners because it's modular you.
You have topics that
gets assembled into maps.
You can reuse and reduce duplication.
Your content assembly is like a Lego.
Lego blocks you.
You take each modular.
Module topic and try to build, assemble,
and then, create that user guide
or that troubleshooting document.
And with this, you also get a
better version control because
it is built on top of a EM.
A EM comes with a very good
version management tool, and
the maintenance is streamlined.
Update updates are reflected
across all content.
It's reused content and the ecosystem
is all unified with a better
enhanced authoring and authoring
system and a great user experience.
So let's take like I was
saying let's take this example.
Where you have a product that,
that multiple partners sell, you
take this example of like at and t
selling your product with a name,
and then Vodafone selling the same
product with a different name.
And obviously there is a feature
gap at and t Mega a. List of
features and Vodafone may get
a different set of features.
There is a product gap, and as you your
product may also behave differently
based on platform for Android, you
may have certain set of features.
For an iOS, you may have a different set
of features, so you, your needs, the, your
needs for customizing the content grows
with all these factors coming into place.
So yeah, if you look at the dynamic
rebranding in practice, let's say
partner A wants Smart Meet as the
product name, and partner B wants
to call it Global Connect, right?
You use key maps.
Each partner gets their own key map
and you say Product name is Smart
Meat for partner a. And product
name is Global Connect for partner
B in their own respective key maps.
And that key maps take care of the
dynamic product name swapping and
let's say they want a different
logo, different UI screenshots,
even a different support contact.
It's all configurable
within your key maps.
No content duplication required.
The kind of smart branding logic.
This kind of smart kind, this kind of
smart branding logic scales effortlessly,
And omnichannel output with one source.
You, when you write documentation, you
keep your first customer or the first
product your main product in mind.
So one source, but
different outputs, right?
Structured content allows you to.
Output to HTML, output to PDF
output to js ON or let's say your
chat bots wanted in a different
format, you can deliver with ease.
Each format pulls the same content,
but tailored via presets, the output
presets for each of the channel needs.
I may have one output preset for
Vodafone, another output preset
for bt and another one for Telus,
depending on the partners, your.
Number of presets grow, but the
scale also grows and it's easy.
One click and your output is
generated for each of these partners.
You write once, manage centrally,
publish confidently to every touch point.
So how to use data valves, let's say
there are like, like I was saying they,
there are certain features only apply to.
In this case, Avaya right one of our
partners and there is certain features
that does not apply to Vodafone.
So you have a feature name, you call
it an attribute, and then you exclude,
you have a set of data, valve file data
valve file where you configure all your
includes and exclude by brand rules.
And in your output presets
you can link these data files.
So depending on which
output preset it is, it can.
Easily include and explore
that piece of content.
And therein you get the
control by feature, right?
You can deliver different outputs
for different partners with a
smart use of data valves, key
maps, and multiple output presets.
And in this example, if you look at
this I have a product overview for
each brand overview written in multiple
different ways for each of those partners.
And for each of these sections,
you can tell the first one applies
to partner X, Y, Z, and the second
one applies to a different partner.
And that audience attribute allows you
to pick and choose and assign a piece of
content to a specific set of audience.
That is how you use attributes.
For different partners and link it's
like tagging the content by audience.
So with a mix of all these you have
key maps to manage your dynamic product
labeling needs, tagging needs, and
then you have data vials to control.
Where each of this content goes and what
you show based on platform or audience
or partner, and you have output presets
to generate different kinds of outputs
PDFs, HTML or JSON, or eBooks, right?
So once you have a system like
this set up in a EM Guides,
the impact is gonna be amazing.
The results are gonna shock you.
What takes.
Months, may take few days to, get
the same output with and without.
So someone wisely said, content
isn't the king, it's the kingdom.
And with the way the digital
content is growing it's at of Atmos
importance today, now more than ever.
So let's say you go ahead with
this solution and it's time for
celebration like you have solved for
the challenges that you plan to solve.
And, all happy faces, happy stakeholders.
So benefits wise, if I go
into the benefits, right?
Organizations that implement this model,
they report faster time to market.
Lower error rates and smoother partner
Onboarding content is always up to date.
Branding stays consistent.
Teams spend less time fixing
and more time innovating.
The system scales without,
scaling the workload, like fewer
resources, more output put,
and things to remember.
If you're dealing with content silos,
inconsistent branding on multi-channel
pain, this approach is built for you.
Structured authoring
gives you flexibility.
Smart rules give you control,
and a EM guides give you the
tools to scale one source.
Many faces deliver fast at scale.
Oh, that's everything I want to cover.
If I have any questions we
shipped feel free, reach out.
I always thank you.