Hello everyone.
This is Ramin and thank
you for joining me today.
I have 20 years of ID experience
and have been working with
UKRI as head of Data Platform.
In my past experience, I've worked with
IBM, Southern and Scottish Energies,
Experian and Scottish Government, and the
kind of projects I have been involved in.
Cloud migrations, legacy transformations,
machine learning programs, and
business process automations.
Today we're gonna talk about the blueprint
for the cloud, while building a future
ready data strategy to establish a right
data foundation for any AI initiatives.
As we all know, all the industries
today wants to grow faster and in this
highly competitive market, staying
ahead is more critical than ever.
Keeping that in mind, everyone
is jumping towards cloud.
Business understands clearly that
it takes huge investment to expand
their own network by keeping
scalability and security on the top.
At the same time, we know that data has
sprouted across legacy system in numerous
formats, which is coming through different
sources in the different structures.
All together, there is
a pressure of security.
Compliance and AI adoption across
all the private and public sectors.
The cloud migration without a data
strategy is a risk, big or risk, and
it's a huge risk for your initial
investments and the future vision.
The cloud adoption is important and it
is accelerating to deliver faster ROI and
expanding access to the global partners.
Let's look at the risks of the cloud
migration when you don't have a clear
data strategies, and what are those risks?
Data silos and inconsistencies.
Security vulnerabilities, regularities
and compliance failures when you don't
meet the GDPR rules or any kind of
other medical related APA insurance
rules in compatible head performance
due to multi vendors, slower time
to values and delay in the ROIs.
Increased cost due to unknowns.
And no clear strategies from the starting
duplicate systems, even the duplicate data
with the different formats altogether.
Traveling through all of your pipelines,
which you are structuring during your
modernizations without structured data
strategies, risks always multiplies and
it doesn't helps you to meet your vision.
Without a clear data strategies and
vision, it is always impossible to
harness the full potential of AI insights.
At the same time, we can't ignore
the challenges that comes with
legacy technologies due to their
limited features, rising maintenance
cost every year, and lack of
flexibilities when it comes to
scaling or meeting modern security
needs to meet our everyday demands.
We should definitely maintain the
inventories of our legacy technologies
as part of our clear strategies and
have a very clear path to get rid of
these legacy processes technologies.
As per the roadmap during our migration
journey, what we just need to do is to
record every legacy process, which we
believe is need to be changed, but it has
an impact to our cloud migration journey.
It can be legacy technologies, ETLs,
it can be legacy integrations, which
doesn't have a robust monitorings,
which doesn't have a logging
facilities, which are not resilient.
There can be a different manual data
processes, which needs to be automated.
It can be inconsistent when
the specific data formats.
We may have a huge impacts due to
these legacy processes or technologies.
So let's record those impacts
as part of your inventories and
act on these impacts The moment.
You have the right time or as per your
roadmap, based on your defined journey,
based on the critical processes, what
you need to deliver, or what you need
to deploy in the time zone, or maybe
in early stages or in the later stages.
So let's explore how to build the
secure and scalable environment with
the right strategy in our mind for
this smooth cloud migration journey.
So let's start with the first
and the most crucial step.
Setting up a clear vision.
One that's future proof.
Grounded with the strong principles,
and guided by the well-defined goals.
Secured by design, having zero trust,
encryptions and auditable policies to
validate and verify all the informations.
Scalability with modular pipelines,
cloud native platforms, AI readiness
with a very high quality data.
Data, map data and having
a metadata in place.
The ultimate goal we wanna achieve is to
accelerate the cloud migration journeys
with a clear defined data strategies in
place, and having all the inventories
in the place eliminate inconsistencies
with all the clear strategies and
unlock innovations through these clear
insights and the data-driven analytics.
Let's look at the key pillar of right,
data strategies, data governance.
Let's face it, without strong
data governance, things get messy.
It's not just about the rules, it's
about building trust in our data and
making sure everyone is on the same page.
Metadata management is a
heartbeat for the data, which
tells the story behind the data.
We don't understand where our data
is coming from or how it's gonna use.
How can we make the smarter decisions
centralized metadata catalog?
Imagine having a single where
everyone can see what this data means
and what exactly it's coming from.
This is the power of
centralized metadata catalog.
Behaves like a Google engine for your
storage, data, qualities, and lineage.
Good decisions starts with a good data.
And to trust the data, we need to
know where it's coming from, how it's
changing, whether it's reliable or not.
We need to take a call.
That's why quality and lineage matters.
Column level, lineage and impact analysis.
Sometimes it's not enough, whether
that is coming from, we need to right.
This kind of details helps us
understand the ripple effect of any
change we make during our pipelines.
So many consistencies across the domains.
It's very simple to use the same
terminologies across the platforms.
It's easy and flexible for the
better collaborations, data
quality engines framework.
Rather than fixing data after the fact,
why don't we building build the checks
at the same time from the beginning
itself, which means start updating all
the pipelines from the beginning itself.
Securities and access controls
with great data access comes
the great responsibilities.
We need to make sure the right people have
the right access and the sensitive data.
Cease protectors protected,
always secured by design.
Isn't something we bolt on at the end.
It has to be part of our
design from the day one.
That mindset gives time, money,
and repetitions in the long
run integration framework.
Our system needs to talk to each other
smoothly every day, 24 into seven.
That's why flexible integration frames,
frameworks are the key to flow data
across the platform, tools and teams.
Without any frictions, AI and
analytics enablement from the day
one AI isn't related things anymore.
We need to think about enabling AI
and analytics right from the start.
That means setting the right
data foundation today to
unlock insights for tomorrow.
Let's look at the key principles while
building a secure data Foundations
zero trust architecture, we don't
automatically trust anything.
Everything gets checked.
Instead of just assuming that
things inside our networks are
safe, we need to check everything
from this user perspectives.
Devices and the connections point of
view, it is always safer and smarter
way to handle the security encryptions
at the rest and in transitions.
We keep data safe, whether
it is stored or being shared.
At any point of time it needs to be
encrypted, no matter where it is.
Identity and access management and
fine grain access controls, people
only get access to what they need.
Nothing more.
We manage access carefully.
Not everyone should see everything.
We have to give the right access to the
right persons for the right reasons.
All the times.
Automated compliance audits.
All the times, not once a year.
Instead of waiting for audit, we
must in checks, runs automatically.
So we compliant for all the.
Identify legacy inventories, depth
risks, and impacts all the time.
Monitoring and alert dashboards,
look at the problems at the early
stages and fix them fastest.
With the help of these dashboards and
alert systems, we can use dashboards to
keep an eye on the systems in the real
time and enable these alerts to call
out the variances in our shop Locals.
AI and analytics in the
monitoring these days.
All the Smart Clouds tools
helps us identifying unusual
behavior and fix it on the go.
With ai, we can detect anything like
strange data patterns or unusual behavior.
It helps us act for smart small
issues, funds into the big problems.
It is always important to have
the right data inventories for
your cloud migration journeys.
Inventories may have a different
components like the ETLs and
a p, a platform with different
integrations or different solutions.
There can be numerous manual
processes in the file formats.
Because of different sources altogether,
different data owners may have a
different excess dependencies based
on your different solutions, maybe
power apps or the front end journeys.
We always need to ensure we map
our inventories with the right
data lineage and the critical
parts with the critical systems.
Non in advance.
It's important to identify your
critical systems critical process
for the right operational support
readiness at the start of the journey.
Your data catalog and the
metadata is always needs to
aligned to your inventories.
For the right production readiness
systems, AI modeling opportunities has
to be identified in the early stages.
The clear data models and the
concise model is a key success
for the cloud migrations.
For clear strategies, we need
to define the governance and
ownership right from the beginning.
The data keywords and the data
owners rules helps us manage and
take care of the data all the time.
It keeps the data clean,
accurate, and reliable.
The data usage policies keeps
preventing, misusing the data and
keeps everyone aligned all the times.
Data sharing agreements in
those data shared safely and
only for the right reasons.
Within the data sharing agreements
within an internal system or the
third party systems, the business
Aries and the metadata tagging helps
everyone understand their data.
Integrities the regulatory alignments
like cprs helps us, follows the data
privacy and the protection laws,
and keeps us legally compliant.
The cloud offers, tools and
services through marketplace,
which scales automatically and
makes it easier for the businesses.
The serverless data pipelines like Lambda
Athena enables faster processing with
low cost, without worrying about the
infrastructure cost, and can be scaled.
On demand at any point of time.
The data lake architectures slows
all the data in the raw form.
Makes it easy to access, easy to store
and analyze without the hassle of any
predefined data structures in advance.
The even driven injections allows
real-time data to flow through different
integration as soon as any even triggers
the containerized workloads provide
porta consistent environments to run
and deploy your apps faster in no time.
These steps becomes critical
for our transformation.
Discovery and assessment is key critical
process to identify our inventory at
early stages with the right information.
Defining governance and security models
helps us defining the rules and standards.
Continue modernizing your ETLs and
APIs with the deployment pipelines.
Start migrating in the phases
by identifying your key critical
processes and operational readiness.
Start enabling AI from the day one
by introducing the data quality
frameworks in your pipelines.
In my recent experience, I've been part
of migration project where we had to shift
the legacy systems to the a w solution.
We followed the similar migration
path as we discussed in the
previous slide, and we could see
the outcome without any slippage.
We managed to shift all the legacy
APIs to the cloud, hosted A-W-S-A-P-I
gateways, and we could see.
APIs are working fine without any issues.
Within the right time.
We continu developing our ETLs
with the lamb and the functions
and continued feeding back to the
business for the reporting purpose.
At the same time, we continue replicating
our legacy reporting to the new Power
BI tools and continue deploying this
functionality to the business users.
All I can say, it is important to
have a very clear strategy for your
migrations to reach your goal in time.
I. To summarize, it's important to
have a clear strategy and migration
path for successful migration journey.
Investing more time at discovery stages,
accelerate the journey, think beyond
the tools and focus on the outcomes.
Clear strategies helps us link solid
foundations for AI initiatives.
Thank you for having me here.
If you have any follow up
questions, please reach out to me.
Thank you.