Speaker 30: Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 20 26.
This is Riva.
I have 19 plus years of
information technology experience.
Worked with companies like at and
t, Adobe Systems, hp, and presently
I'm working with SAP America.
Today's topic is.
To discuss on a high level, what are the
challenges and key factors that needs
to be given a deep thought while moving
ML systems from experimental labs to
production systems, and what are the
infrastructure challenges that needs
to be given a thought and considered
while planning phase with that quickly.
Go through the agenda.
Today's agenda would be to go on a high
level, what are all the key challenges?
We can talk more on challenges to help
us understand why this is important
and what are the key factors that
needs to be considered to overcome
the production use case challenges.
And we can also go over modernizing
infrastructure availability and why
it is needed to have more scalability,
resilience, reliability, also
observability and security compliance
requirements for the production
systems and available options that
needs to be looked in the market to
address some of those challenges.
And IBM Cloud Soft Layer Foundation,
it has a good backend infrastructure
which gives us a good performance
metrics and resilient as well.
So we can go, as an example, what
it gives us pillars of resilience.
What are those like?
High availability, security, and
performance as previously mentioned,
reliability, also scalability zone
deployments for high availability.
And we can also talk about people and
process as this is a must need for
production systems where teams will
be cross-functional teams will be.
Coordinating and using the systems for
use cases depending upon the use and what
are the deployment patterns and how cloud
native approach will help us to maintain,
simplify the deployment patterns to
version maintenance and reproducibility.
And for also the auditing.
This is a comprehensive
requirement, which will help.
And finally, we'll be
talking about key takeaways.
Let's start talking about the challenges,
what we have from mowing ML systems from.
Pro experimental labs to production
systems and the key things in a
experimental labs where the data will
be pure and we will be more focusing on
benchmarking the performance metrics,
use cases but in production systems,
there are a lot more challenges
because of the drift management.
Use case scenarios varies.
It's not always the same.
And the scalability requirements
and latency comes into play.
Performance metrics and
availability as well.
That is the reason why, these are
the things that needs to be given
a deep thought while planning.
A move of ML systems from experimental
labs to production systems.
These are the sum of the key comparisons.
What we have from legacy systems and
current production demands and what modern
platforms offers the modern platforms
is more towards cloud native approach.
And in the market we have many
cloud providers, which does that,
and cutting edge technologies and
with the integrations, all the
reliability aspects, security aspects,
and also the monitoring alerting.
Absorbability made easy with
the cutting edge cloud agnostic
or cloud native approaches.
Now let's see about IBM Cloud Soft Player.
So this gives high performance, bare
metal and virtual compute options.
Also, we have global availability
zones and IBM Cloud Soft Player network
backbone, optimized for larger dataset.
Data transfers, which is key aspect to
consider while moving to your production
systems to overcome any bottlenecks on
throughput, iops, or it could be latency.
So IBM provides some of these
cutting edge technology options.
Which will help
productizing the ML systems.
Now, the what are the pillars
of resilient ML infrastructure?
The key pillars would
be high availability.
High availability, as we
discussed before on a high level.
While planning and designing phase, we
will have to think about the use case
scenarios like multi-zone deployments,
which cloud provider provides us
a zone features, which has their
presence across multiple zones and
offering its customers to deploy across
multiple zones with minimal latency.
And those benchmarks needs to be
looked at depending upon the use case.
That way, we have clear understanding
on what will be our latency
patterns, performance metrics, iVOS,
and this is mainly also
for disaster recovery.
When we have multi-channel deployments,
we will, it is good that we will
have another zone available.
And disaster recovery.
What in case everything goes down, right?
So a different site
from backup strategies.
There are, many a gap solutions
or you call it immutable backups.
These are the things that
needs to be given a thought.
While considering a disaster recovery,
that will minimize our recovery times.
And we should also consider which
cloud provider provides this as an
option in terms of the time to recover
should be minimal, and that should
be, understood before designing
a disaster recovery planning.
And security by design.
Yeah, zero trust.
These are must in today's infrastructure,
as we are mostly leaning towards cloud
agnostic and cloud native and multi-cloud
adoptions being a top priorities for most
of the organizations, the observability.
And security compliance are key metrics
for any organization, and we will have to
look into a cloud providers who does that?
Like who provides default blocks for
DDoS attacks or for ransomware attacks.
Those has to be thoroughly.
We've gone through while designing
this security by design and who
are all the players in that area
and the design of the production systems.
High availability architecture is a
must of our seamless activities and
for ensuring the s. Oh, we call four
nines or finance, whatever the numbers
are to meet those SLA Benchmarkings.
High availability architecture.
Architecture plays a critical role.
And the apps, what kind of flow?
Balancing distributed traffic across
Jones we are, we will be using and
if it is a, stateless serving server
models without a local space state.
Which will help us minimize our fail lines
and the availability will be much more
higher and there should be a mechanism.
We should also have fault tolerance
detection and take a preventative
measures for failing over the systems to
available systems to solve the traffic.
And health recovery is also a must.
And in this model, we should cover
like what Monitoring, preventative
measures, thresholds, setting up a
triggers for failovers or next step,
the correctable action items to
recover and how do we fail back to.
These are the things that needs to
be considered for high availability
architecture to achieve a good
high level uptime of the systems.
And how do we sustain ML workloads?
These are the, some of the, model linings
for the real case production ML systems.
De depending upon the types of the
workloads, we have each presenting unique
challenge for robust system designs.
Again, this will be on sorry.
Again, this will be on
case to case design.
This has to be given and how do we
rate limits, for example, rate limits
for unpredictable traffic spikes.
That has to be clearly
defined and benchmarked.
That way it doesn't affect
the other users traffic.
If there is an unpredictable
traffic in one of the use case, it
should not impact the other case.
For that, real time serving rate limits,
all this will help come into your play.
It could be, or in the case of
DDoS attack as well, how do we
limit, how do we predict that?
How do we set alerts at what are
the limits that the traffic should
be, blocked from a particular
source in a use case scenarios.
So that is how we will be,
more looking into sustaining
models for production systems.
And this plays a vital role, zero
trust segmentation for ML systems.
As we discussed in my previous slide,
discussions, security plays a vital role.
And for this, it could be, customers
auditing purpose and the compliance
requirements has to be clearly
defined and well known in advance.
And the drift management should be
there to ensure annoyingly something
got changed on the infrastructure.
It could be rate limits, it could
be, allowed port listing, or it could
be allowed software versionings,
or the release versionings.
So for all that, we can also make use of.
Cloud native approach.
Most of the cloud public cloud providers
are providing this as a feature.
I think it's a paid feature depending
upon the use case scenario and
what kind of network design that
we choose for the ML systems.
That has to be, clearly given a thought.
What are the available
options and cloud providers?
Who provides these information and
available for usage, depending upon the
test case scenarios, sign benchmarkings
SLAs, these can be considered and mainly
this is to, data set production and
training environment registrations.
The QA there of the training of the
testing beds should be separate from the.
Quality checks.
And from the quality checks, the
producting system should be isolated,
where always the changes should
come from the lower environments
to the higher environments.
Post testing, thoroughly testing,
and post security declarance.
And there should be a model
serving security, which is like
endpoints protected by an A PA
authentication rate limiting as we.
Spoke in my previous slide, discussion
and network segmentation policies.
If we are choosing a NSC level at the
cloud, NSC rules or acls, these are all
the things that needs to be predefined.
And most of the cloud providers
pro provide this by default, as
when we are consuming their service
for zero trust segmentation.
And let's talk about the
framework alignment, right?
Operational controls.
This is required for ensuring there
should be an asset management.
To ensure, the versioning
and maintenance releases are,
appropriately managed and effectively.
And for this also, we have identity and
access management for model registries,
which is nothing but access management.
A privileged access management is
available with most of the cloud
providers, which will clearly
define the roles, rollbacks and
responsibilities, a different version
where we can limit the users, depending
upon the use case scenarios and the
pipe, excuse me, and the pipelines.
Usage.
So this will be, through this we can bring
in more observability at the user levels
on who needs to access the production
systems and what can be done by defining
the clear roll center rollbacks, using
the, these are, these can be integrated
from the cloud, or if we have our.
At the odds that in the past that
I work, they have their own forest
management, which is DNS or, user
management use of active directory.
And that can be, integrated with
cloud providers, privileged access
management roles by defining is,
account and only the people who
are part of those account will be.
He able to perform the defined
roles according to the role
defined and audit logging across
training and serving pipelines.
This is critical for any kind of
debugging or to know exactly what
happened in the environment or
while executing the pipelines.
What is the source?
What are the targets?
What happened?
And if there is a failure, where
did it go wrong for debugging?
This is going to help us and compliance
validation for regulated ML workloads.
And there should be a, a defined
model of frequently to know to
meet compliance requirements.
And this is also important to automate
security scanning of container images.
Whenever there is an image that we wanted
to deploy or make use of, it has to, or
there should be a model that it should
come to the come to the environment
with proper scanning meeting all the
security and compliance requirements
and the versioning requirements.
Then only it should be allowed
to the, repositories for the
use within the environment.
Specific environment from QA to
production, or it could be from,
testing environment to production
and performance.
Now let's talk about
the performance metrics.
And what are the available
tools that we need to consider?
There are public cloud, which will
offer these when we consume their
services, or we can have our own.
Every org has its own tools like
performance metrics that can
be measured for the resilience.
Right?
And models are up time, which provides us.
The up times of all the assets in the
production infrastructure, availability
and in interference endpoints, failover
recovery, if there are any, use case
scenarios in the production systems
and automate automated recovery
time from zone level failures.
And if there are any
security breaches, right?
Lateral movement incidents
and segmentation deployment.
And these are all must things to consider.
And a training throughput improvement
and distributor training performance,
all these things are must while for
a, measuring platform resiliency and
every organization will have its own.
Benchmarking and SLAs.
So it has to be planned accordingly.
While considering to
define performance metrics,
now let's talk about people and process.
So this is some of the.
Areas, right?
Where it requires more than technology
that demand cultural shift towards shared
responsibilities across organizational.
When security and available team ownership
extends beyond the infrastructure
teams to include data scientists, ML
engineers, ML ops practitioner, and
platform engineers organization create
systems where resilience is built in it.
Every stage from model development
to deployment and monitoring.
This distributed ownership model
ensures team collaborate on shared
outcomes rather than simply handing
of responsibilities that result.
ML systems that are robust,
secure, scalable by design,
not as an afterthought.
And this has to be, as we were talking
about, more on high availability,
performance, be benchmarking,
security, availability, scaling, right?
These are all, these
shouldn't be afterthought.
These should be considered during
the design and planning phase
because with the people and process
right now, the responsibilities
are shaped where engineering
teams deploy or test in the labs.
And roll out a solution.
And the operational teams
productize it, right?
Product teams productize it, and
the operational teams to ensure
availability, uptime, and scalability
of this particular product.
So all these teams are critical
and they have to go hand in hand
by having a clear understanding
and, on, end to end deployment
of these systems into production
where these key metrics are, met.
So this is the, cross-functional,
responsible model looks like.
And, you can go through the slide,
which will give you a clear, clear
understanding on how the cross-functional
responsibility should look like.
And depending upon the organizational
use, there could be a number of teams,
even more teams like change management.
Vendor management.
All this comes into play depending upon
the kind of cloud we chose, vendors
comes into play and we'll have to
closely work with vendors or the cloud
providers to ensure, their well level
of any situation or any support required
for any deployments or availability.
And there should be also a clear
visibility on vendor Cloud S
maintenance, which should not impact the
availability of a production ML system.
So by ensuring that it is highly
available, architecture is applied there.
Now let's talk about deployment patterns.
Cloud native and hybrid, depending on
these are depending upon the typically.
When we are moving from legacy to
cloud, we end up using hybrid or
depending upon the journal presence
of the cloud providers, we end up,
we might end up using multi-cloud.
So these are the things that we
need to, consider what model.
What adoption?
Is it a hybrid adoption or a
completely cloud native adoption
or, multi-cloud adoption?
What is required for
the use case scenarios?
Depending upon the use case scenarios?
This has to be given a thought
during the design and planning phase.
And again, this is also
not a afterthought.
This has to be given
a good thought before.
Even starting, or I would say
before, considering a locked
architectural design for ML systems
and let's go over these, some of the
areas where in, you know, which talks
about infrastructure foundation.
Matters and matter security.
This has to be early, as we
discussed before, design for failure.
How, what is our, recovery strategy,
high availability, and what are
the key components involved in it?
How do we define and
distribute responsibility?
This is between the teams and
there should be clear acy defined.
Between the teams on who is responsible
and who is accountable for what and
how the handholding should be that
should be, clearly defined operational
model and and last measure and iterate.
So establish a clear SL os
for availability performance.
And security, then continuously
improvement against them because from
time to time there will be difference and
there will be different hot fixes that
will be coming in that will different
findings where we will have to quickly
adopt depending upon the criticality.
Some would be, less vulnerable,
some would be highly vulnerable.
And some would be highly critical
where we will have to immediately
address those to make sure that
the data or the, the data is not
compromised or the environment is not
contaminated with these vulnerabilities.
So with all this, this will ensure that
building a robust, secure, scalable ML
systems, when we take all these metrics,
what we have gone through on a high level,
we'll ensure building a robust, secure
environment for production ML systems.
And these are the key take
takeaways from this session.
And thank you very much for giving
me an opportunity to present this
and patients listening to me.
And if you have any questions
or if you agree or do not
agree please do feel free to.
Drop me a message to my email
or I'm there in LinkedIn.
Yeah, feel free to, post your
questions, comments, and I'll be
glad to answer as many as possible.
Thank you.