Hi everyone.
Thanks for tuning into Con
42 Machine Learning 2025.
My name is Mohan.
I'm a data and AI expert with over
12 years of experience in this field.
Today I'm super excited to talk
about from insights to Impact, how
can companies revolutionize customer
experience using AI and data analytics.
So without any further
ado, let's get started.
Here is a quick agenda for today.
First, we'll start off with
understanding what is the current
state of customer experience.
Then we'll spend some time
understanding what are some of
the key challenges in current CX
strategies employed by companies.
Then we'll touch upon what is
the role of data and AI driven
strategies in customer experience.
Then we'll explore how companies can drive
customer experience transformation using
ai, and at the end, we'll conclude with.
How can companies prepare for
customer experience transformation
using artificial intelligence?
Before we dive into the specifics,
let's first understand why
transform customer experience.
If we think about it, we are living
in a world where customer expectations
have evolved dramatically over
time, and now they expect more
personalized experiences across.
All the touch points they have with
a given product or s service and
companies that deliver on this promise
of hyper personalized experience, they
tend to outperform its competitors,
both in terms of customer growth
as well as customer retention.
In addition to that, there is a
massive data opportunity as well.
In the last decade or so, companies.
Started to amass huge amounts of customer
data, but lot of companies struggle to
tap into this data to generate value
and better experience for its customers.
And now with recent advancements in AI
and machine learning companies have even
better ways to take advantage of this data
and ultimately deliver superior customer
experience to, to their customers.
Now let's understand what is the
current state of customer experience?
As I said in the earlier slide in the
last decade or so, there is this huge
data explosion wherein companies started
to collect huge amounts of data about
its customers, about be it, be there.
Product usage, their transactions,
their behaviors within the website
or app, or their engagement with
the social media channels or the
customer service interactions.
The problem is a lot of companies
struggle to turn this data into meaningful
insights that ultimately improve customer
experience and lead to improvements in
customer engagement and satisfaction.
There are a lot of reasons for that.
And few challenges that I have noticed
in my experience are oftentimes the
data is fragmented, meaning they live
in siloed systems, which limits the
ability to comp for companies to have
a single unified view of a customer.
Also, companies tend to employ more
reactive strategies than proactive.
In terms of figuring out customer issues
or anticipating customer needs because
of this pro like these disconnected
systems, data systems, it limits the
ability to, for companies to personalize
a customer experience and that ultimately
lead to dissatisfaction among customers.
Also, certain few companies are very
hesitant to adapt to new technologies.
And that causes serious damage in the
long run in for the, for those companies.
So if we were to take a more deeper
look into what are some of the key
challenges in currency CX strategies?
As I said in the previous slide,
the bigger challenge that I have
noticed is siloed data systems.
Yes, companies collect huge
amounts of data that can be used
to improve customer experience.
But because the data is not so connected
well and live in live in a siloed,
disconnected manner, it becomes very
difficult for companies to take advantage
of this data and translate this into
meaningful and actionable insights.
So what happens is because of this.
It leads to it leads to a, it leads
to a place where companies cannot
truly understand like what is the
360 degree view of a customer?
What are the transactions or
behaviors exhibited by customers?
And that limits their ability
to personalize their experience.
So the root of all ultimately it leads
to poor personalization, but the main
thing that companies needs to solve.
Is solving for these siloed systems
and integrating all this data in
a manner that generates meaningful
insights to improve customer experience.
And that is what now we
are going to explore.
So how can companies solve for these
challenges and drive improvements
to their customer experience?
This is where the data driven
CX strategy comes into play.
So the very first step that
companies needs to do is.
They need to start off with data
integration, meaning rather than having
siloed, disconnected systems, they
need to think about a, think about
integrating all this data, consolidating
all this data from different touch
points, different systems into one
single place so that they can have
the true, that true holistic, unified
view of a customer so that it leads to
better understanding of their customers.
And once the data is in data is integrated
and they have and they have access to
this data, then companies needs to think
about how to translate this data into
actionable and meaningful insights.
Because without any insights coming out
of data, it becomes really tricky and
challenging for companies to act on or
act on it and improve customer experience.
So the second step is.
How companies needs to understand
how to translate this data
into actionable insights.
So it involves, looking at what are the
different patterns or like different
behaviors exhibited by customers like
using this for more advanced predict
to analytics and all that stuff,
which we'll get into in later slides.
But they need to figure out a way to
translate this wealth of data into more
meaningful and actionable insights and.
Once they have a good understanding
in terms of their customer, the next
step is how can they incorporate AI
and machine learning to basically
automate the experience the customer
experience for its customers.
So this is where, adopting technologies
like ai, machine learning comes into
picture, which will lead to, not only
personalizing customer experience, but
improvements in engagement, improvements
in customer satisfaction, and.
The most important thing is this
has to be a continuous loop.
It's not like companies do it
once and just be done with it.
They have to continuously refine
this process, figure out if there
are any gaps or issues, and figure
out ways to solve for these things.
And that is only possible, like once
they start measuring what are the
outcomes from this, like from this
system, from this framework where data is
integrated, insights are being generated.
Machine learning, ai, ML
solutions are deployed.
And what are the outcomes of it?
What are like, what are the areas
where they're still falling short of
customer expectations and go there
and start to improve those process.
So I think employing this data driven
framework really helps companies to
not just personalize experiences,
but also do achieve much more things
rather than just personalization.
Now let's try to understand these
things in a more detailed manner.
So let's start off with data integration.
So when I say data integration,
what I mean by that is, as I said
earlier, companies collect data about
customers through various systems.
In my experience, I have seen
companies tracking behavioral data.
Like what?
Clicks or like what, I mean what
buttons or like what features
have been used by customers within
the website or within the app?
So they do capture this data
through systems like Adobe
Analytics or like Google Analytics.
They do track this information.
They also collect customer
feedback and sentiment data.
This is where they talk about,
reviews or support interactions
or social media mentions.
They also collect profile
data that is with.
It, they have information on
demographics of a customer, their
preferences, their segment, whatnot,
and they also collect like contextual
data, such as like location, device.
But overall, most importantly,
they track the transactional data.
That is very important because the
end of the day customers are coming to
your website or your app and ultimately
buying something from you, tracking
the transaction data is also important
because that tells you what are, like,
what do customers like, doing with your
website or with your app so that gives
you a lot of, lot more information.
So once we have all this data
collected, this data needs to be
integrated at a customer grain level.
Meaning for every customer
company like once integration is
completed for every customer's.
For every customer company should be able
to help understand, okay, like how many
transactions this customer had made in the
last 30 days or in the last 30, 60 days.
What are the frequently bought
products or services by this customer?
What do they do when they
come to a website or like when
they come, when they use app?
So by having this single unified
360 degree view of a customer, it
becomes very easy to truly understand.
Who what is that individual
customer do and like what their
preferences and needs are.
And that leads to better
outcomes, better experience for
customers at the end of the day.
So that the very first step is how do
they integrate all these data sources
together so that it gives the foundation
to do the next things in this framework.
So moving on to the
next one once a robust.
In data, like robust data
integration is completed.
The next step is extracting
actionable and meaningful insights.
Sort of it, and it's typically
a four step process where it
starts with data refinement.
Typically raw data, is will, may
not give you better insights.
So there needs to be sometimes
spent on cleaning that data,
structuring that data in a way that.
It can be used for insights generation.
So once the data refinement step is
completed, the next step is doing
some data analytics on top of that
to understand and do some pattern
recognition to see what do customers
love to do, like what sort of patterns
or behaviors they exhibit when it comes
to a specific product or a service.
And from there, the next
step is insight generation.
This is where all these raw
patterns are translated into.
Business relevant customer
specific insights.
And once these insights are
produced, the very important step is
actually acting on these insights.
Generating insights is one thing,
but acting on these insights
is where we actually see better
improvements to customer experience.
We see improvements to metrics like csat,
NPS, so I think acting on these insights.
Is far more important than
just producing insights.
So that insights to action
is a very important step that
companies needs to act on.
So once you have a robust data foundation
built, and once you have these insights
started to come in, like that's
when you start to see the benefits.
Of like improvements in your CX metrics
or benefits in terms of better retention
or like better engagement with products
and services that a company offers?
The next step in this
process is incorporating ai.
So using AI or machine learning
can be done in numerous ways.
I'm just highlighting few examples here.
Through ai, ml, companies can have.
More intelligent virtual assistants,
like nowadays, chatbots have become
a huge trend in terms of using
incorporating genea and everything to
build chatbots so that they can help
assist customers to solve their issues.
Rather than driving all these all
these customers to a customer service
center or a contact center these
chart boards can actually help to
solve a lot of problems upfront.
So that.
You can companies can reduce the
traffic or they reduce the cost to
in terms of customer service as well.
And then the other thing is personalized
recommendations as we discussed in the
earlier slides, companies, customers
want more personalized interactions,
more personalized experiences, and AI is
enabler of these personalized experiences.
Using ai ML companies can take advantage
of, the data that they have and understand
like what are the historical behaviors
that were exhibited by these customers.
And use that data to predict what
I mean what can be done for these
customers based on their past past
behaviors, past transactions, everything.
And then practice service alerts.
I mean by, by, by integrating ai.
Companies can try to predict, what could
be the potential issues or customer
issues that may arise in future so that
we are having the proactive strategy
to mitigate these issues rather
than being very reactive in nature.
And also, through an lp through machine
learning, through NLP companies can
actually take advantage of all the
feedback data that they have received
from customers and try to understand
what is the sentiment expressed.
By these customers?
Is it positive, is it negative?
And if it is negative, like what is the
best way to route that particular customer
to his appropriate agent or appropriate
our team so that it helps to resolve
those problems early on rather than
just leaving customers out in the dust.
At the end of the day, the whole
purpose of incorporating AI
into translating into like a.
Making improvements for customer
experience is we want to see
better outcomes because of this.
We want to see higher
customer satisfaction scores.
We want to see improved loyalty from
customers for brand, and we want
to see improved retention rates for
these customers because those will
really translate into meaningful
bottom improvements in bottom
line metrics for a given company.
So let's spend some time
understanding how can companies
drive CX transformation using ai.
If we were to think about it AI is
completely reshaping the way that that a
lot of con industries operate nowadays.
And see a customer experience is
also is also a no stranger to this
transformation by incorporating
AI into customer experience.
Companies can completely reshape the
customer interactions by blending advanced
technology with human-centric design.
These are like few examples as
in how companies can leverage
AI to drive CX transformation.
Like one is predictive
and cognitive experiences.
These AI systems can anticipate
customer needs before they
even before they even arise.
So by having systems in place that
can actually understand what customer
wants, the companies are being very
proactive in figuring out the needs
of the customer and deliver those
to customers beforehand itself.
So that will lead to better customer
experience as a whole for customers.
And then the second one is
omnichannel journey orchestration.
We talked about how personalization is
becoming very critical for customers,
and having this personal personalization
embedded into every aspect of a
customer journey is going to be a truly
game changer for a lot of companies.
So companies can take advantage
of integrating AI in that whole.
Customer journey lifecycle so that
delivers more superior and more
personalized experience for customers,
which will ultimately lead to better
enhancements in terms of customer
metrics, customer satisfaction
metrics or other CX metrics.
Last but not least is
augmented human service.
This is where I mean by having EA
systems in place, customer service
representatives or associates can have,
better insights about a customer for more
effective interaction with the customer.
Like by having systems in place that can
tell what meaning, like who that customer
is, what are their preferences and needs
and having these insights, making it
available to service representatives
can make it easy for them to deliver.
That, that superior experience to
these customers as part of their
interactions when they reach out to
a customer service representative.
So these are some of the ways in
which AI is going to reshape the
customer experience as a whole.
The end goal is, again, as I
discussed in the previous slide,
the end goal is the same like it is
to deliver that more personalized.
Experienced experiences to
customers so that will ultimately
improve all the metrics related to
customers, related to the company.
And if we were to understand like
what is the role of AI and ML and CX
transformation here, we are going much
more deeper into what are some of the
ways companies can actually employ AI
ML in their transformation journey.
Like predictive analytics
still is one good example.
This is where like machine learning
models can actually look at the data
that you have, that companies have about
customers and use the data to predict
or forecast customer behaviors so that
companies can proactively plan and
meet the evolving needs of customers.
And there is the, there is this
real time decision aspect also
now with AI powered systems.
They can actually process
data in real time.
Pro data related to customer
interactions in related real
time across different channels.
And that will lead to
personalized responses.
Personalized experiences ultimately drives
improvement in customer satisfaction.
And a IB is being employed heavily
when it comes to automation.
Or by auto, by using AI for automation.
A lot of rapid two tasks,
particularly in the context of
customer service, can be automated.
So that way it gives it frees up
the time for human agents and they
can focus on complex issues and
providing more empathetic support
and solving bigger problems or
like bigger issues for customers.
So automation is gonna play a
very key role in terms of driving
CX transformation in future.
And last, but not least,
is personalization.
This is the, this is a theme that
we've been touching from the beginning,
that personalization is very crucial
nowadays to elevate customer experience.
So by having more advanced AI platforms
and systems that can analyze customer data
to deeply understand what customer wants.
And delivering those personalized
experiences is a real game changer for the
company when it comes to differentiating,
like when it comes to differentiating
itself from its competitors.
Now let's spend some time to
understand how can companies prepare
for this transformation, because this
is not just a one night or a one.
Like one month thing.
It is a continuous process.
It takes time, it takes effort.
More importantly, it
means changing things.
Cha changing things or systems
that were done certain way.
So the very first thing that I
would, that I want to touch upon
is it requires mindset shift.
Which means like, it requires that culture
shift in within the company because.
Unless, until there is the true
change in culture, it becomes really
tricky for companies to adapt onto
like to get onto this journey.
So having that customer centric, data
driven mindset is really crucial for
companies to have the CX transformation.
Also, companies need to invest in
developing their employees to work
with these new tools, new AI tools,
new AI systems, because otherwise.
They'll be left behind and become it,
and it becomes really tricky for them
to take advantage of these tools.
Also, there needs to be a
strong data governance strategy.
There are teams at various companies
like for the, for the companies that
have done really well in this space.
They have strong data governance teams
that look at what, like what is the data
that they're collecting from customers?
What sort of data quality they're
maintaining and they have a very strong,
robust framework when it comes to
maintaining privacy of the data also.
So it is very important for
companies to have this strong
data governance frameworks in
place to take care of this data.
And ultimately companies
need to measure this, right?
You can't simply go on a. Go on and then
say, I'm gonna do CX transformation.
You need to quantitatively measure
like how, what is the success criteria
to say we achieved CX transformation.
So companies need to establish
certain KPAs and metrics to
measure this whole process.
It can be a. Taking a look at
customer experience metrics like
csat, NPS, effort score, whatnot.
Or it can be looking at
like revenue led metric.
Like what's the gross sales,
like what's the do sale volume?
Or like what look what is, what are the
bottom line metrics, top line metrics, how
are they trending after CX transformation,
prior to CX transformation?
So by having that robust
framework to measure this is
going to be really crucial.
For leaders to invest in this whole thing.
In addition to that as
I was saying, right?
In addition to that, it requires cultural
and organizational change because
that mindset, mind mindsets shift are
like the change is very important.
It is very important for
executors to really believe in
this data driven cx otherwise.
If there is no leadership support or
executive support, it becomes really
tricky and challenging for companies to
act on this like to execute on this thing.
Also, it's not a one team effort.
It is a cross-functional teams
collaboration where like teams from IT,
marketing, customer support or product.
They all need to come together and then
they all need to collectively think
about customer experience as an end goal.
And form teams accordingly, set set
objectives and strategies accordingly and
try to deliver on the CX transformation.
Last but not least is companies need
to empower the frontline employees.
I. Meaning they need to educate them,
give access to these customer insights
because they're the ones, at the end
of the day, they are the ones who
talk to a customer who interact with
customers face-to-face at times, if
it is a physical store or something.
So these frontline staff staff also need
to have access to these insights so that
they can serve customers in a better way.
Give that the, give them that sense
of, having a better experience when
they visit the store or when they
interact with this frontline staff.
So I think encouraging the frontline
staff to actually look into these
insights and figure out a way to have
an empathetic view towards the towards
these customers and like delivering
better experience at the end of the day
becomes really important for a company to
succeed in the CX transformation journey.
So that's why like it starts with that
cultural and organizational change.
And it needs to have that
strong support from leadership.
It needs to have that collaboration with
cross-functional teams and ultimately
everyone in the company should be
empowered to enhance customer experience.
So with that, I would like
to conclude the presentation.
I hope this presentation helps you
to gain some insights into how can
companies drive CX transformation.
What are the like what's the, what
are the frameworks they can employ to,
to get on this journey and ultimately
achieve the CX transformation journey?
I hope you enjoyed the talk
and it's a great pleasure to.
Speak at this con 40 to
machine learning 2025.
So thanks for the opportunity.