Hello everyone.
Welcome to my session.
My name is Samuel bfi and I am a
principle solutions architect with AWS.
On today's presentation, I'm gonna be
talking about Amazon Bedrock Agents,
and the goal of this presentation
is to show you how really we have
enter an agent ecosystem and we
have entered the Gentech era.
So actually, when we talked about
agents it can be confusing because
that terminology can be quite.
Overuse and for different companies
and can mean different things.
So let's just set the level of
understanding of what we're gonna be.
Ma you know what we mean here on this
presentation, when we talk about the
Gentech AI at the very high level,
eight AI agents are autonomous systems
that can reason, plan and complete
multi-step tasks on behalf of humans.
So how do they do that?
Agents will break down high level
objectives into executable tasks
That's also known as planning.
Once they have those tasks, they'll
try to accomplish those tasks
using tools and informations.
Information can be knowledge, for example,
from knowledge base that from your
specific proprietary enterprise data sets.
And those tools and knowledges are
gonna be made available to them,
and that's what we call actions.
More importantly, these systems are
actually capable of observing the
results and that updating the plan
in real time until the defined goal
set by the human is accomplished.
And that's what we mean by reasoning.
So I'll give you an example instead,
if you have an an example of trying
to check availability of a meeting
room, rather than just checking the
availability of the meeting room,
an AI agent can actually access your
calendar, check everyone's availability.
That should be on that specific meeting.
It can send, invite to
that specific meeting.
It can then monitor for responses
on that specific meeting.
And if some of the critical persons people
actually respond with a no, it can follow
up asking for potentially times that
would work for them and that do that work.
So be a multi-step and
driven autonomous solution.
So why is now the era for AI agents right?
Multiple research organizations in
the world last year and this year.
These two numbers I'm gonna show here
are actually from Garner from, trends
that they expect to see in the next
couple of years is starting this year.
So the first one is 33% of enterprise
software applications will include
some sort of a ent AI by 2028, which
is upfront less than 1% in 2024.
And then 15% of the day-to-day
work decisions will be made
autonomously through Agent AI by 2028.
So you can see, about three years, a
very significant chunk of the work is
expected to be handled by AI agents.
So it's very important that companies
start to realizing the prospect and
the opportunity that lie ahead, but.
There is a evolution of agents
that have happened in the
industry in the last year or so.
As large language models became
more and more intelligent and
more and more powerful, it has
unlocked different use cases.
So in the beginning, you'd have maybe
a simple assistant, would you be able
to ask basic queries and you get a
response and maybe it will be like.
Using a single tool use, maybe
you were gonna connect with your
rag system with your knowledge
base and you use that, right?
It would be a simple, a single step test.
Then, companies.
Using the power of these
large language models created
deterministic agents, right?
So it's a very street strict
procedure within AWS we call the,
or we call those more like flows.
So be a flow of steps that are
predetermined and you just have a router
asking After that, a lot of companies.
Like Amazon and AWS have enabled
organizations to create autonomous agents.
So you can actually have the planning
aspect that I meant before where it can
go and understanding the objective and
monitor for the outputs that the model
is putting into a multi-step tasks.
But there'll be a single agent in this
case, which is, it might be expanding
the two sets to multiple tools.
Maybe you have a calculator, maybe you
have a browser access, maybe you have.
Web search access, maybe have some
sort of proprietary API that you're
connecting and enabling that agent
to use, but it's just a single agent.
Right now, what has become more and
more popular and what we believe is the
future is this agent, virtual workers.
Rather than just having a single agent
that has the capability of running
the planning and multi-step tasks, now
you can have a combination of powerful
experience and expert agents on a
specific areas that will work together
to achieve a much higher level task.
So you can think about long
running systems that you actually
mimic human things rather
than just mimic human actions.
And it can be cross
organizational boundaries.
And the more you see on this slide that
you see on the right, the more autonomy in
business impact we will actually provide.
So with that said, how do we at AWS
offer services and capabilities for
our customers to innovate and really
jump into this agent tech award?
We have what we call the AWS
Generative AI stack, which is
divided by three different layers.
The first layer, which is the bottom
one, is the infrastructure that AWS
provides to build and train models.
So we have Amazon SageMaker, ai,
which is this huge ecosystem for,
cleaning data, training your model,
influencing your model, and you actually
be the whole managed infrastructure.
But on top of that, we also have our
own hardware or partners for GPU and.
AI acceleration like Nvidia, and we have
our own hardware called AWS Training and
NWS information that provides the best
price performance into the AWS Cloud.
The second level of our AWS generative.
AI stack is the ability for you
to use models and tools so you can
think about building blocks to build
your generative AI applications.
And that's our very popular
service, Amazon Bedrock.
And we're gonna be talking today
in the next couple of slides.
And the demo that I want to
show you is gonna be building
on top of Bedrock, but our.
Highest layer is more on the
application to boost productivity.
We have a suite of services
called Amazon Queue, and Amazon
Queue has different flavors.
In this slide, this is presenting two of
them, which is the Amazon Queue business,
which is this assistant that can actually
provide a chat interface, but also
automate a lot of tasks and connecting to
your very common applications like your.
Office 365, your Google Drive, your
Salesforce, your Zoom, and it can
put all that into a single pane of
class with a lot of the guardrails
and security that enterprise requires.
And on the other spectrum is Amazon
Queue developer that provides developers
the capability of using ai, powerful
AI models to boost their productivity
while developing applications.
So that is the AWS generative
AI stack that we offer at
AWS at the very high level.
What we are gonna talk today is about
Amazon Bedrock, very specifically
Amazon Bedrock agents, because
this presentation is for agents
itself, but Bedrock is a suite.
Of building blocks that allows you to
build very quickly and very with a lot
of the scale in mind and also security.
Your generative a application.
So you have a lot of tools here.
Tools could be your knowledge base,
which is the manage, retrieve,
augmented generation system.
You can have, data automation that you
can upload PDFs and you can extract
all those PDFs with the location.
You can fine tune your model.
You can do model distillation.
We are gonna talk about agents.
So agents will be a very important
part of this capability that is native.
But you also have developer experience.
You have prompt management.
You can create prompts.
You can create variables
within those prompts.
You can store them on AWS, you have
a whole suite of ID capabilities
for you to really experiment and
do POCs and test different ideas.
Through the id you have
prompt optimization.
That is pretty cool.
Functionality on Bedrock.
The core functionality on Bedrock
is really making models, AI models,
foundational models from Amazon and
other third party like Tropic AI 21
Cohere, mistro Yama, and many more.
Manage for you in a fully
serverless capability, right?
So you don't need to, you don't
need to spin any instance.
You don't need to pay for any GPU.
You just pay for the consumption
that you have, in input tokens.
Output tokens and you know that
is what you're gonna be paying.
You can also explore different models.
You can maybe train a model from another
outside bedrock, and you can import
the model to be hosted on bedrock.
You can use the bedrock marketplaces that
actually expand the capability of models.
Much further than just what is
available via serverless on demand
capability, there is a whole suite
of evaluation metrics, right?
Applications are very powerful.
AI applications are very powerful,
but they're really important
for you to run evaluations.
So a Amazon bedrock also provides you
with a suite of tooling and capabilities
to do programmatic evaluation.
A rag evaluation, human
in the loop evaluation.
And just recently we announced the
large language model as a judge.
So you can have another judge you can
have another large language model judging
the response from your AI application.
And then, you can collect those
metrics and have dashboards and,
improve as you see the those results.
And then of course, you can
have inference at scale.
You can have different.
Flexibility of options on
how you consume those models.
You can have optimized inference.
By prompt caching, you can have
intelligent prompt routing, so
depending on the question that you
are sending to bedrock, bedrock can
automatically redirect to the right model.
That will be the best suited to answer and
execute that specific task or question.
And it's global reach.
Amazon Bedrock's, global reach.
There are many regions on AWS
cloud that have bedrock enable,
and you can also have cross region
inference for a specific model.
So you can actually utilize the
capacity across different regions
with a single endpoint, and that
makes your life much easier, right?
At the very high level and very quickly.
That is what Bedrock is and bedrock just
becoming bigger and providing you more
flexibility and building blocks to build
your generative a applications with the
whole experience that you are, if you are
already using AWS, you are familiar with.
It's very important to mention
it's secure and responsible.
So you can use VPC private
link, you can use encryption.
No customer data to any model
provider including AWS or third
party are collected and store.
You can use guardrails, so you can
set different restrictions from what
your application might be able to
respond and the things you don't
want the application to respond.
There is a lot of
compliance regulation that.
Bedrock has passed and has the stamp.
But also there is a lot of open source
integration you can integrate to Lang Chan
Graph Lamb Index through ai and many more.
Open source integration
frameworks can tie into the vast
service, which is Amazon Bank.
But because we are talking
about agents AWS offers a broad
choice for deploying agents.
And here are just three
examples, but these.
Could be way bigger.
If you want to run agents that
are specialized, you can use the Q
agents on the Q4 business or even Q
developer and you can automate your
enterprise productivity and workflow.
We are not gonna talk about those
agents, and then on the right
side, you can do it yourself.
You can, for expert
developers potentially using.
Open source frameworks you can see,
build that on AWS, use our compute,
use bedrock models, use our serverless
capabilities like lambda step functions
and automate and create your application.
What we'll talk today from the remaining
of the session today is using Amazon
Bedrock agents, which are manage service
that has all the scaling and capability.
An orchestration that
will be foundational.
The foundational model will
power those agents, right?
So this is our fully managed solution
for building and deploy agents.
What sets actually Amazon Bedrock Agents
apart is the building foundational
models, powerful orchestration.
So the orchestration and the
flexibility on how you decide to
build those agents are something
that was taught from the ground up.
This means you are not
starting from scratch.
You're leveraging sophisticated AI
capabilities right out of the box that
AWS has made it available for you.
So if you don't have a large data
science team, or you're small startup
and you just want to start using
agents that have the capability of
orchestrating complex tasks at scale,
Amazon Bedrock Agents is a great fit.
So you can think about Amazon Bedrock
agents as like having a team of AI experts
working alongside your developers that
can handle complex orchestration, while
your team will actually focus on the
unique aspects of your business logic.
What this approach allows you to
do is to dramatically reduces the
time and expertise needed to get
production ready agents up and running.
And that is the important thing, is we
are not just talking about POCs anymore.
We want to go to production and actually
provide the value both the economic and
business value that our organizations
are expecting into this new era.
While the potential of agents are
exciting, we keep hearing from customers
that they face several challenges when
they try to build production ready agents.
Developer teams struggles
with complex technology stacks
and infrastructure setup.
This is a very fast pacing ecosystem
and new frameworks keeping merging.
Maybe they're open source, maybe
they are different partners, and that
it becomes such a huge ask for the
development team to keep adopting.
The other area that is challenging
is the operational complexity.
Managing multiple agents and orchestrating
complex workflows is challenging.
How do you scale those?
How do you actually provide
the right sets of tools?
How do you make sure entitlements
and data are not actually being
widely distributed when they should?
Another one is, you know that
I already mentioned a couple of
aspects is agent ops requirements.
What are the governance required
for you to manage those agents?
What are the security and compliance that
your business will require you to have?
And mostly important, which is one
thing that when a lot of companies
are doing POC with the agents, they
potentially fail to realize this.
What is the observability stack?
How do you trace each step that
this agent tech system is doing?
How do you log those and how do
you run evaluations to actually
improve the capability and the
performance of those agents?
Right and rapidly evolving technology
landscape makes it hard to stay
current while maintain production seed.
Systems.
So the important thing here with all
these challenges is Amazon Bedrock
agents, because it's a managed
service and AWS will take the heavy
lifting away from you so you can
focus on your business values and the
outputs that you are expecting to do.
You will make your life way easier.
You still need to put a lot of
work, but it'll be easier than
potentially building on your own.
So before we talked about
what different types of agents
does bedrock agents provide?
How does an agent existing looks?
So you might have a user input.
That user input might have an,
we will be talking to an agent
application and you expect a response.
But what happens behind the scenes
is much more complex than just this
flow that the user sees, right?
The agent components that your agent
application will potentially build, you're
gonna talk about the foundational models.
So different tasks might be
using different foundational
models from different partners.
Maybe you're gonna use some of the
tropic models, maybe you're gonna use
some of the Amazon Nova models, right?
But also now that you have
those foundational models, those
models, because they were not
trained within your proprietary.
Enterprise data needs access to your
knowledge base using vector databases.
So Amazon Bedrock also provides
a managed re solution, which
is known as knowledge base.
On top of that, enterprises, we will make,
wanna make sure that the responses that
are provided to potentially our external
users or internal users, depending on the
type of application you're building, have
some safeguards in terms of the response
and the outputs that you're trying to.
Respond that, and receive, and
Guard Rails allows you to do that.
You can create a lot of the
tooling within Bedrock as well.
You can connect with your own
APIs by building action groups
within the Bedrock agents.
You can have memory built in,
you don't need to ma manage
the memory of those agents.
You can have memory being managed
store and maintained by bedrock, and
you can just provide the ID and ask
conversations for specific users.
Keep growing.
You still can maintain the memory,
which is very important because
it's context from the users.
Requests, previous requests and responses.
You can connect to other agents,
but you can also have, deterministic
flows which are, more like.
Static steps that your agent
can take, but all that, right?
One of the things we see more and
more in production is you wanna
make sure that you have a continuous
evaluation framework, right?
So as your agents are potentially
being consumed in the ward, once
you go to production, you wanna
log the valuation of those.
Of those steps and you wanna make sure you
have test cases that you keep evaluating.
Once you make changes, you wanna make
sure you have metrics and grading prompts.
And you can use being used judges as
foundational models that I mentioned.
So you can log all that into analytical
database or a vector database.
And then the last step is you can
have this dashboard where, add
your experts on whatever agent.
Output or agent task is created.
What is your business value?
You can have those humans evaluation to
analyze what's working well, what's not
working well, and you can update and
optimize to make sure your agents are
actually getting better with time, right?
So users will provide feedback and agent
application get updated, and as they get
updated, they'll get way better, but.
Okay, let's talk about what
is Amazon Bedrock Agents?
So Amazon Bedrock Agents provides you
with a managed capability for actually
managing and running agents at scale.
So if we think about the different tasks
that you and your development team would
be required to run by creating agents,
you probably will know that you need
to provide some tool capabilities for.
Your agents, right?
Within Bedrock agents, you have
the ability to create tools
with action groups, which can
call potentially your own APIs.
You can integrate with knowledge basis,
you can actually have code interpreters,
so your agents can generate code.
They can run those codes in a sandbox
environment that Bedrock provides
to your agents, and the output of
that code can then be consumed for.
Potentially as a response to your user or
later on collaboration with other agents.
I already mentioned about memory.
But one interesting thing that
we're gonna do with them, which
today is this idea of multi-agent
collaboration for complex workflows.
It's important to say that the less
one before last item, the comprehensive
trace debug and observability is
very important and critical for bad.
Okay.
By default using these capabilities of
bedrock agent, you get comprehensive tra
trace and debugging logs and metrics that
you can look and analyze each stage and
each step that your agents are taking.
And, there is building word rails for
security and compliance control which
you know, will provide a peace of mind.
For you and your enterprise as you're
building new capabilities with ai.
So think about Amazon Bedrock agents
as a powerful foundational model that
becomes even stronger when combined
with the full suite of bedrock agent
capabilities, from knowledge base to
flows, to guard rails, all working
together to create a more capable,
secure, and reliable agent application.
I just wanna, I apologize, I just wanna.
Drill down a little bit more on the
new capability that we release late
in 2024, which is the Amazon Bedrock
agent's multi-agent collaboration.
One of the most powerful capabilities
is the moody agent collaboration.
Let me walk you through how this works.
First, you can easily assemble agents.
And connect e each of those
specific agents with their
own specific knowledge base.
You can give access to
specific tools specific APIs.
These agents on its own can plan, execute
and comple complex tests togethers.
Think of, multi-agent collaboration
as a team of specialists that
are working coordination.
For example, one agent might handle
data analysis while another manages
customer communication, right?
And they can all report into a
specific supervisor that is planning
and delegating different tasks
and aggregating the results for
these coordinator agents, right?
Amazon Bedrock have built intent
classification to help unify conversation
across agents, ensuring that is smooth.
Handoffs and consistent user
experience across agents are kept.
As your need grows, you can scale
those agent experience efficiently
because it has built team.
Observability that lets you monitor
how each agent are performing
and interacting with your user.
And of course, all of these runs
on Amazon, bedrock Guardrails,
and AWS enterprise security
and privacy control by default.
So to summarize a little bit
here, what Amazon Bedrock Agents
allows you to do is to provide the
Lego blocks, the building blocks.
For you to create a powerful agent AI
solution for your own organization.
I already talked about some of these
configurations, some of these features
I haven't mentioned session handling.
So you can have session, then
you can have memory management.
All of these are secure within
the Amazon Bedrock ecosystem.
So this becomes even stronger capability.
Because the point I mentioned before
that development teams can get very
overwhelming with this very fast
paced environment of agent tech
solutions with Amazon Bedrock agents.
You can expect more and more
capabilities are gonna be added in
the future that will follow the same
approach of managing that for you
while you focus on your business needs.
I'll give an example of something that
Amazon have been very invested and started
releasing some of these capabilities,
and hopefully you see more and more
coming the next few months and a year,
which is the model context protocol.
I. You probably have already
heard about MCP, which stands
for Modello Context Protocol.
MCP was created by Tropic.
It's an open source protocol that
is standardized the way models
share and understand context to
each other and connect to external
data sources such as tools, right?
M making your application context aware
of what tools are available for them.
Okay, currently Amazon bedrock
inline agent, which is a way for
you to create agents with code
inline already support MCP servers
because, you can build clients.
The agent.
Agent is an MCP client that
can connect to MCP servers.
So you can have your MCP servers as action
groups in Amazon Bedrock age, the same
way you do when you're building a single
agent, or when potentially building a
multi agent collaboration that allows you
to enable connecting agents to external
tools and data sources via MCP servers.
You'll support passing information between
models and tools in a multi step workflow.
You can expect more capabilities, not
only within the bedrock inline agent, are
gonna potentially become more and more
native to this offering on Amazon Bedrock.
Now, before I do my demo, what I
wanna pause here for a few seconds
is if you have found so far that
Amazon Bedrock agents is interesting
and you wanna know more, please.
Scandi secure code to potentially
go to our Bedrock agents page.
Or if you wanna run a workshop and
you're already an AWS customer, you
can request a customized workshop
where we, as part of the AWS team will,
potentially virtually host a workshop
for you, for agents, or potentially your
account team might fly or meet you in
your office with your team and actually
host these specific workshop where
you're gonna be able to create agents
and play around with Amazon Bedrock.
And of course, there are free courses
that you can do on your own pace.
Just to scan the last Cure code here now.
Before I I'll talk about my demo, but
I just wanna show a diagram of what,
how my demo works because what I'm
gonna show you on the demo is a web
UI that is abstracting all these very
powerful investment research and agent,
which is actually using behind the
scenes, the moody agent collaboration
capability of Amazon bedroom.
So I have created three different
agents that are collaborators from
my supervisor agent, which is called
Investment Research Assistant.
The goal of this assistant is to help,
analyst, investors to do research
about the specific investments, right?
About the investment work.
I first have one agent that is
specialized on analyzing you.
News, very specific agent is tasked with a
different set of tools available for you.
The first tool that is available is the
ability to call an API to do web search.
So if I ask about Amazon News Amazon Stock
News this agent will be invo and they'll
be actually calling web search APIs.
And retrieving information
about a specific requests.
In this case that I said Amazon News.
The other tool that this actually
model has, sorry, this agent
has, is the connection with
proprietary financial data.
In this case, for the demo is just
Amazon earning reports, 10 Qs and
10 Ks that have been uploaded and
prepared by bedrock data automation.
And what happened here, I have created
the Amazon bedroom knowledge base that
ingest in, embed, and creates vectors
into my open search serverless index.
And then my agent can actually query using
natural language to actually retrieve
a specific chunks or of specific asks
for example, Amazon earning reports.
So that is one agent.
The second agent is
quantitative analysis agent.
What this agent does, it has a action
group that has tools capability to
actually call a Yahoo Finance API.
So you can call different APIs
to check, different prices,
different stocks, different date
range, and that can be real time.
And you return to the
model to the age of top.
Now the last agent is the
smart summarized agent.
This agent is prompt and capable of
summarizing a specific set of informations
potentially to give the response
back to the main supervisor agent.
The cool thing here is I've provided
a specific guidance for each of those
agents on how they should behave.
But because Amazon Bedrock
multi-agent collaboration has a lot
of the orchestrating intelligence
using, years and decades of machine
learning experience of Amazon, a
lot of that intent classification
is handled automatically for me.
And everything that I'm gonna do here
is gonna I'm gonna show in the demo.
I'll ask a prompt here to do
something that can retrieve data and
give a complex investment analysis.
And you see that.
Each step will be traced, and
you'll be orchestrated by the
supervisor agent with, which is
this agent that you see here, right?
The investment research assistant.
And as needed, you actually call
this collaborator agents, right?
And each step will be able to see
the input and the output for those
agents until we finally, once it's
satisfied because the planning.
And reasoning.
Once it's satisfied with the answer
and the data that is collected, you
get the response back to the user.
So you can think, you can see that
this is just more than just a simple
agent, a simple chat bot, right?
Even though this is a natural language
conversation with the bot behind the
scenes, you're using the power of
connecting different data sources,
different actions that a foundational
model on its own has no capability.
And everything you're gonna see on this
demo, I send a single, after I've created
all these agents, either by A-P-I-S-D-K,
cloud formation, or the console, I
can just re, I can just send AVO agent
API, and I can use this capability.
And because this is all managed on
AWS, all the scaling, all the security,
all the logging, all the valuation is
taken care for me by Amazon Bedrock.
So this is really powerful.
So what you're gonna do now is we
are gonna jump into the, into the a
web browser and I'm gonna show you
the demo on how this agent works and
hopefully we're gonna get excited and
potentially start building some of
these capabilities on your own as well.
We'll see you in a moment.
Okay, welcome back.
Here is just a very simple ui.
Right behind the scenes I have already
created the agent, the multiagent
collaboration that I showed you.
So here is me as the user.
We are gonna send a prompt
through this very simple ui.
With investment research
assistant, which is a supervisor.
And then I'm gonna show you the
traces based on my question.
What type of the different agency
requests to collaborate with, how
does he actually get the data back?
How does he keep integrating?
Iterating until it gets to a
final stage where it satisfy and
actually returns the response.
So this is like a, it can take, a minute
or two, three minutes to actually get
some of this response back because
it's doing a lot of different steps.
It's taking a lot of different action.
Given the planning that the
supervisor agent that is part of a
Moody agent collaboration on Amazon
Bedrock is actually doing right.
So this is again, it's an
investment research system.
The question I'm gonna ask here is given
the recent Amazon 10 Q, sorry, 10 K,
what are the, some, what are some of
the growth opportunities highlighted?
Then I want you to search the news related
to those opportunities, and I want you to
list competitors for each of those areas.
Finally give me a stock price range
expected within the next 12 months, right?
I wanna learn the growth opportunities.
I wanna see what the market's saying
in terms of expected price range from
different sources and then search the
current stock price and how much has
fluctuated in the last 30 days, right?
So in order for me to do this as
part, as a human, or if as an analyst,
you take me quite a lot of time.
As I send this request behind the
scenes, it's actually invoking my agent.
So the first thing it does here
invokes the investment research
assistant, which is a supervisor.
And then we are gonna see
now multiple different steps.
So the first step is the orchestration.
I'm, and I'm gonna try to now go
through all them because it'll be a
lot, but I'm gonna show some of them.
So the first one is just, you
can expand here and you can see.
You are an investment research
assistant responsible for overseeing
and synthesizing, synthesizing financial
research for a specialized agent.
You're always to coordinate
the subagent to produce.
Anyway, it's a very prompt, fine tuned
prompt here for my supervisor agent, but
what it does here is the supervisor agent
will actually do the first reasoning.
And the Asian reason is saying
first what I need to do is get
growth opportunities from Amazon.
10 K. 10 K. Then I need to find
recent news about these opportunities.
I need to identify the competitors from
different from these opportunities I need.
I need to get analyst price targets,
and then I need to get the current
stock data and recent volatility.
What he has done is, okay, now that is
the plan that I need to take and I need
to take multiple steps to get the plan.
So in the step four, what I realize is
okay, I need to request the collaborator
agent, which is the financial use agent,
to go and retrieve some data, right?
So the first one is go fetch
from the knowledge base.
Then if needed, fetch
latest relevant news from.
From a given stock base.
So you would try to do the knowledge base.
My knowledge base in this example
only has Amazon on your reports, like
the 10 K that you're talking here.
So you can see here that the
financial year is okay, I'll
first search the knowledge base.
From growth opportunities.
So he has hand off the task from
the supervisor into the financial
news agent and to say okay, I'll
search the knowledge base for growth
opportunities matching in Amazon
recent 10 k and related information.
So he goes, queries the knowledge
base on Amazon Bedrock knowledge base.
He gets some of the chunks, right?
Using the vector database here
he then he orchestrates the
response back to my supervisor, so
orchestrates back my response to
the supervisor, but now it's okay.
I need to get more data.
So it's like you're saying, okay, let
me now get the recent news about Amazon
growth initiatives and competitors.
So he collected the information
and the growth opportunities that
are listed on 10 K, and now it's
actually going and getting the.
Growth Initiatives and
competitors from Neils, right?
So you can see here it's actually running.
It's now finally doing something
that is called the tool use, which is
using the action group functionality
on Amazon Bedrock, and is doing a
search query using an API saying
Amazon Growth Initiatives, AI Cloud.
Retail healthcare competitive strategy
plans because that's what probably
was listed on than 10 K, right?
It has returned that, returned some of
those specific news and now it's saying,
let me search specific for analyst price
targets and competitor information.
So you can see that it's taking it step
as that is thinking is step at us at each
step adds each step in order to obtain my
final request, which was multiple, tasks,
which prosecutions at the same time.
So now he's saying, okay get
the news about the price target
and competitor market share for
cloud retail, AI and healthcare.
So he has gotten into that and it's
based on the knowledge based information
in the news, I can now provide a
comprehensive update on Amazon's
growth opportunity related development.
So the financial news agent has now
done within itself, has now done
take multiple steps to finally.
Achieve the single goal that the
supervisor agent requested, right?
So you can see how this
becomes very complex.
Remember the multiagent
collaboration here?
The good analogy is have a team of
specialists working together, and
this is one of the specialists just
taking a lot of the actions, right?
So the final response from the final
news agents okay, key growth areas from
the CEO recent communication is ai.
Core focus is shopping
code, personal assistant.
The growth opportunities will be major
infrastructure, AI infuse Alexa, voice
assistant healthcare service expansion,
showing positive customer sentiment.
You can see some of the competitors here,
and then you can see the analyst coverage.
What are the, the price
target that it has?
Share that, that they have.
Decided to put each of different kind
of companies and research institutions.
So it goes back to the supervisor and be
like, okay, here's the data supervisor.
What do I need to do?
And the supervisor decides some
information here and we could reel down,
but I don't wanna take too much time
and says, okay, now we need to actually
get another collaborator here, the
quantitative analyst agent to go and see.
And you can see here, you'll
try to, if you go here, the.
Agent reasoning now for the quantitative
analyst agent to be like, I'll retrieve
Amazon stock data and analyze the
recent price movements and patterns.
So it goes and makes a stock data
lookup API, using the tool function
to use on the action group so it gets
the data right, and then it's okay,
analyze the current price range and
key pattern over the past month.
It gets all the data so it
gets from current stock.
A price for today, 30 days.
Price lines, volatility,
and the pre price.
11 trading partners.
So it talks about some of the resistance
and some more like the, terminology
fundamental understanding of stock itself.
It goes back to the agent, right?
And the agent says, okay, let me
synthesize this information to a
comprehensive analysis of Amazon
growth opportunities and Mark lookup.
And then finally, if you see here on step
43, so this multi-agent collaboration
has taken 43 different steps using
different agents, using different
tools, using different knowledge base.
To achieve the response.
So you can see that based on my prompt
says here is the detail analysis of Amazon
growth initiatives and market outlook.
So the create growth opportunities.
One is artificial intelligence scale,
1000 generative AI applications
in developments within Amazon.
These are the focus areas.
Here's the competitors.
Now it's cloud service,
current growth opportunity.
Current growth is 25 year over year
AI contribution, three to 5% now.
Expected to be 10% this year.
Year.
Remember the 10 Ks from 2024?
That's site 2025 is the expectation
now, infrastructure, metadata, center
expansion, some of the competitors.
Third growth opportunity is healthcare
Talks about Amazon Pharmacy.
One medical integration showing
positive customer adoption.
Then it goes to Project ky, which is the
satellite internet service for Amazon.
Then it talks about different
competitors and finally goes
into the current trading metrics.
What is the price?
What has been the 30 day range?
What is the support level?
What is the resistance level?
And here is the analyst projection.
So some of analyst projections are saying,
okay, like Wolf research saying it's
200 notable j JP Morgan saying it's two
10 and recent trading partner has been.
Higher lows since April 24th.
Five consecutive days of gain, harvest
rate trading was April four to nine.
So it seems the wide ranging analyst
targets 200 to $261, reflects
varying opinions of AI initiative,
distribution success, AI AWS growth,
sustainability, healthcare expansion
potential, a competitive ion impact.
So I know it was a lot and I was
getting more into the response.
But this is the answer for this
specific prompt that is sent.
And if you were just to prompt
a model without having these
tools, it'll be way, way hard.
Again, these only run for three minutes,
but how about if you have a very complex
task that involves, dozens of agents
and you'll be running for hours, right?
To do a very in-depth research.
You could do that during your use case.
And I just called a single API.
This was just a single
API call that I made.
And that API call had all the
infrastructure managed for me, all
the foundational models using the
power of the AWS generative AI stack.
So again, my name is Sam bfi.
If you work curious or wanna talk
to me, please reach out on LinkedIn.
Could just search by my name Sam bfi.
Hopefully this demo was useful.
Thank you so much for taking the time and
watching and I'll hope you see you soon.
Have a great one.
Great one everyone.
Bye bye.