Hello everyone.
I'm Satish Kumar Puram.
I work as a specialist leader
in Deloitte Consulting, LLP
based out of Atlanta office.
I do lot scale SAP implementation
across the globe, and I have been doing
this from last 22 years in my career.
And I've done multiple SAP
implementations for big clients.
From various industries, starting
from manufacturing, insurance,
retail all sorts of industries I
would say that I've touched upon.
As part of con 42 mission Learning
2025, I would like to present the
driving digital transformation in
insurance with SAP and and machine
learning and a leadership perspective.
Now in today's insurance landscape,
the convergence of SAP expertise and
machine learning technology is creating.
Unprecedented opportunities
for transformation.
This presentation explores how forward
thinking insurance companies are
leveraging these powerful tools to
overcome industry challenges and create
sustainable competitive advantages.
We'll examine practical applications
across claims management,
underwriting, and policy
administration while highlighting
the real world success stories.
That demonstrate measurable dis impact.
Now, if you come to the insurance
sector, the insurance landscape,
there are multiple challenges.
Now, the notable challenges that
I would say is your InsureTech
disruption, like new digital first
competitors are challenging traditional
insurance models with agile operations
and innovative product offers.
At the same way you have limitations
based on legacy system that is.
You have an outdated infrastructure
restricts innovations.
It creates data silos and increases
operational cost for established insurers.
Same way, cybersecurity
threats is a big concern.
Increasing sophistication of attacks
against sensitive policyholder
data demands robust security
solutions and proactive monitoring.
Same way changing customer expectations.
You have digital, having
customers demand personalized,
frictionless experience across.
All touch points and
immediate service resolution.
Now answer this problems
within the insurance landscape.
I think SAP has come up
with multiple solutions.
Now, SAP solutions, powering insurance
transformation has set a 61 percentage.
A process time in reducing all
processing time with SAP implementation,
as well as it has provide 30% of
efficiency gain by Im by improving in
operational efficiency across functions.
And there is approximately 40
percentage cost reduction in
operational cost through automation.
And at the same point
time, there is 3.5 x.
A written of investment within
24 months of deployment.
These impressive metrics
demonstrate why leading insurers
are investing in SAP solutions.
By leveraging these powerful platforms,
companies are achieving unprinted levels
of efficiency while simultaneously
improving customer satisfaction
and reducing operational costs.
Now.
How SAP is solving this problem, how core
SAP solutions for insurance is helping
solve the problems of insurance companies.
Now, SAP comes with SAPS four
hana, which brings in a real time
data processing and an analytics
foundation that supports intelligent
enterprise operations for insurance.
And there is a specific SAP insurance
analyzer tool that has been specifically
customized and designed for.
Insurance companies, which
specializes in risk analysis and
complaints management for insurance
specific regulatory requirements.
And there is a systematic data
maintenance sewer, which helps in
comprehensive data integration,
quality management, and governance
for insurance information lifecycle.
And in the same way there
is S-A-P-C-R-M module.
This is very specific to customers.
It is customer centric platform enabling
personalized policy holders, ex expertise
experiences and relationship management.
These integrated solutions create a
foundation for insurance companies
to build modern digital operations
by connecting previously so solid
functions, insurance gaining.
Complete view of their business
and can make data driven
decisions with confidence.
And with SAP implementation, even with
machine learning integration there
are certain practical applications
that comes up with the advantages.
The main advantages that we see
out of machine learning integration
is with claims processing
automation, as an example.
Now, machine learning algorithms
review claim documents.
Identify fraud indicators and automated
straightforward claims approval,
reducing processing time from days
two minutes while retaining accuracy.
At the same time, mission learning
comes up with dynamic underwriting which
helps in pre predictive models, analyze
customer data to generate personalized
risk profiles and premium calculations,
enabling more accurate pricing.
And expanded coverage options for
previously underserved segments.
Now, there is a AI driven
customer service as well.
The virtual assistance and
sentiment analysis tools enhance
customer interactions flow 24
by seven support which leads to
proactive issue identification,
and personalized recommendations
based on policy details and history.
This application
demonstrate how SAP system.
Enriched with mission
learning capabilities deliver
tangible business benefits.
The integration creates intelligent
workflows that continuously
improves through data analysis
and pattern recognization.
Now, system integration strategies
within SAP and mission learning that
would come as business value alignment.
This integration prioritized
by business impact.
API first architecture, standard
connections between systems, data
governance, frame framework, consistent
data quality across platforms.
Security by design protection embedded
through I, I've seen security by
design as one of an important component
in my experience where insurance
companies are very happy with now.
Successful integration requires a
strategic approach that balances technical
requirements with business objectives.
By establishing this foundational
elements, insurance companies can create
a flexible architecture that connects
legacy systems with modern SAP solutions.
While ensuring data integrity and
security, this pyramid approach
emphasizes starting with business
alignment and binding upward through
increasing technical layers, ensuring
that integration efforts deliver
maximum value while minimizing
disruption to ongoing operations.
One of the biggest challenges
that I've seen in my entire career
while implementing SAP, not only to
insurance, even it applies to other.
Industries is data migration.
Now with SAP with machine learning,
there is a data migration where we
are putting in this practice now.
One of those will, will cover them one
by one, data discovery and assessment,
comprehensive audit of existing
data sources, quality assessment and
mapping into target SAP structures to
identify transformation requirements.
Cleansing and enrichment.
Of course, cleansing plays an
important role with data migration.
So what we do as part of cleansing
and enrichment, systematic process to
address data quality issues, eliminate
redundancies, and enhance record with
additional attributes to maximize value.
Testing and validation.
Of course, very important.
Multiple test cycles with respective data
samples to verify transformation rules,
system performance and business process.
Integrating post migration
monitoring while once the
migration is done will not stop.
The monitoring will be continuously
monitoring the system, the
data that you're getting in.
So what we do as part of post
migration monitoring is to do an
ongoing evaluation of data accuracy.
System performance and business
processes effectiveness to identify
and address issues quickly.
Insurance companies handle massive
volumes of sensitive data across policies,
claims, and customer records following the
structured migration practices ensures.
This valuable information transfers
correctly to SAP platforms
while maintaining the regulatory
compliance and business continuity
now process automation framework.
What we do as part of this
process automation framework is
process discovery and analysis.
The first step is identify the
process, workflow, observation and
documentation, identification of
automation candidates written of
investment calculation for each process.
Stakeholder alignment on priorities.
Then the next step would be automation,
design and development process
redesign for optimization, RPA bot
programming and configuration ML
model training for decision points.
Of course, machine learning models
will be very effective here and
SAP system integration setup.
Once this is automation, design and
development is done naturally, we'll
go into the testing and deployment
mode wherein we do control testing.
In staging en environments, user
accept acceptance verification,
then phased implementation approach.
And then we do a performance
monitoring dashboard setup.
And after that, once deployment is done,
there is always a lookout for a continuous
improvement wherein we look into the
regular process performance reviews.
We do machine learning, model retaining
with new data, as well as automation
expansion to related processes, and then
technology updates and enhancements.
This comprehensive framework
guides insurers through the
automation journey from initial
identification of opportunities
through ongoing enhancements.
By following this structured
approach, companies can e effectively
transform manual insurance processes
into streamlined digital workflows.
As part of this process, there are
leadership challenges as well in
SAP implementations, and one of
the important challenge would be
cross-functional team management.
Successful SAP implementations require
alignment between IT specialists,
business units, and external consultants.
Leader must bridge technical and
business perspectives while managing
competing priorities and resource
constraints across departments.
That is one of a big
challenge that I would say.
And then the next one would be business
continuity during transition, maintaining
uninterrupted insurance operations.
During implementation is critical.
Leaders must develop comprehensive
transition strategies that minimize
disruption to customer service, claims
processing, and policy management
throughout the transformation.
Then the technical technical barrier
resolution, complex technical challenges
inevitably arise during implementation,
effective leaders established
robust problem solving frameworks.
Empower technical teams to
innovate solutions and maintain
progress momentum despite optical.
So I think all these three factors will
be very critical, and I work on all
these types of problems in my day-to-day
SAP implementations that I work with.
Now let's look into the case study
how SAP and machine learning is
helping out by taking an example
of Northeast Insurance growth.
Now if you see the graph itself indicates
there is a pre-implementation and
post-implementation claim processing time.
We see that before SAP the claim
processing time is very high.
After SAP, the claim
processing time is very low.
Same with policy insurance time.
Even the customer satisfaction,
how it has enhanced after SAP
and how it was less before SAP.
Then how the operating costs have changed,
how operating costs were high before
SAP, and how it has cut down the cost.
After SAP, so not insurance group, a
midsize regional insurer implemented
SAPS four HANA and integrated
machine learning capabilities
to transform their operations.
This, the company faced increasing
competition from digital first insurers.
And struggling with aging systems
that that limited innovation.
Their phase implementation approach,
prioritize claims processing and policy
administration with careful attention
to data migration and staff training.
They, the results were Ed
dramatically reduced processing
times significantly significantly.
They had a good amount
of cost savings and.
Remarkably improved customer
satisfaction scores that revised
a declining market share trend.
So key takeaways and next
steps with this strategy is.
Strategic planning Align SAP
implementation with business Global
goals, team development, build cross
function expertise and leadership.
Phased implementation.
Start with high impact areas for quick
wins and then continuous innovation.
Leverage machine learning
for ongoing implement.
SAP Solutions Learning
Offer insurance companies.
Powerful tools to overcome
industry challenges and
drive digital transformation.
The companies that will thrive are
those whose leaders view technology
as a strategic enabler rather than
just an operational necessity.
We recommend being with a comprehensive
assessment of your current system
and processes to identify the highest
impact opportunities, develop the
a phase implementation roadmap that
balances goals, most importantly,
invest in developing both the technical
and leadership capabilities needed
to drive successful transformation.
Thank you, and thank you
for this opportunity.
I.