Hi welcome to my presentation
called the Limits of Imagination,
an open source journey.
Basically, this is about like my open
source journey and projects in natural
language processing over the years.
Starting from 2018 till 2025.
Basically like seven years of work.
Of these projects are open source.
My name is Aroma Rodricks.
This is a little bit about me.
This is my bio.
I'm a Python enthusiast.
I've been coding since 2014.
It'll be a decade next year.
I'm a multi speaker, so I've spoken at
Picon, US Estonia, Lithuania, Hong Kong,
Sweden, Europe, Python, bio Hire, Picon,
South Africa, India, and also had a pro
project being present at first Asia.
I've been on the natural language
processing train since 2018.
I do fun experiments sometimes through
data python and language models because
I believe as do most multinational
companies now that the human condition is
encoded in language just as science and
math, and it's inevitable that one day we
will be able to use computers to help us
linguistically as they do mathematically.
I've been using this bio since 2019
and it has come true basically.
So these are like some of the stories
that I'm going to be sharing with you.
I'm going to be sharing
like 10 stories with you.
The first one is from Picon n India, 2018.
It's a tho conditions summarizer.
The second one is Picon
South Africa in 2019.
It's an NLP fake News detector.
The third one is Picon US 2024.
It's called Only BMOs in the building.
The first one is bike on NTR 2018.
Terms and conditions, summarize it.
So terms and conditions, everyone
knows terms and conditions
and it's all very clunky.
Not great to go through, but you
basically just have to do it.
I personally have not gone through a
lot of terms and conditions except like
a couple of like rental agreements.
And for this project specifically,
I think I went through a terms
and conditions document by PayPal.
If I remember right.
We are always drowning in
unreadable legal language across
emails, apps, and websites.
What I was trying to do is I was trying
to build an NLP pipeline to extract
obligations, permissions, and risks
from terms and conditions, documents.
Basically what I wanted to do.
Was when I was going through
like a document that was full of
terms and conditions, I wanted to
see the risks associated in that
terms and conditions document.
The risk had to be highlighted
in like red basically.
It would have empowered users
to skim legal agreements with
context and not confusion.
And if the line would be like a risk,
it would like basically be highlighted.
My problem with this particular project
was that there was no existing data asset.
And I had to hand annotate
a bunch of sentences as
obligation, permission, or risk.
So I built a label data set
from scratch using first
principles of contact structure.
The outcome was an NLP pipeline
to extract obligations, risks, and
user rights from legal documents
because there was no usable dataset.
I could only answer it,
I want to say around two.
Which was not a good amount to
set of train a good classifier.
But I created an SNLI style dataset
from scratch using first principles.
And what you could do today to improve
accuracy is basically to use some of
those sentences to one shot train, an
LLM, which is a large language model, or
you could use an LLM, which is a large
language model to create like synthetic
data of around 10,000 sentences to train
like a more powerful classifier basically.
This project basically came from
my work at Fidelity Investments.
We were working on a bunch of 4 0 1
accounts and what happened at that time
was there's supposed to be a lot of
rules that are supposed to be applied
on of all of the accounts later.
And what happens is you
have legal documents.
That are these rules and then you
have aqua map in like a language that
computers can understand, but there
is no mapping between these two.
So because I was working with
natural language at that time, I
was like, we could maybe create
our own rule processor of thought.
The second one is from back on US 2024.
It's called Only Bads in the Building.
I was spending a lot of time at home.
During this week called fix
hackler at work, where they just
let you do whatever you want.
And I had a couple of existential
questions that I wanted answers to.
For example, will forensic
portrait artists keep their jobs?
Can AI write my job block better than me?
Can I build a clueless
trial fashion match?
How do I under clean, non
duplicate synthetic data?
So basically what happened was I was
waiting at home for my H one B Visa and
I was not in contact with my colleagues.
They were like 12 hours away from
me, so I could not collaborate
with them for this week.
I went through an existential crisis.
I got into a little bit of stoicism,
looked up a lot of philosophy,
and that's why I had all of these
philosophical questions basically.
So who gets to keep their
jobs in this post AI world?
Will forensic portrait
makers keep their jobs?
Not so what happened was.
What happened was we were going through
a lot of large language models being
released in the world and everyone had
this exist existential crisis of whether
they were going to keep their jobs or not.
And because I'm also an artist on the
side, do I don't draw a lot of portraits.
I was like what's a good job to
get into if they do take away
my software engineering job?
And, I was like what is AI not good at?
What is AI not good at?
And the answers were
like, oh, maybe images.
But they have to be like
very specific images.
And when do you need very specific images?
So the answer that came to me was
forensic portrait makers, basically.
And what I did was I went onto Kaggle.
I found this data set of character
actors, what happens with character.
They are like very they're
very descriptive, right?
You're always introduced to a
character as, or he was like
a particularly looking man.
He had a certain kind of a nose very
bushy eyebrows, maybe like a spot on the
top of his lip, et cetera, et cetera.
So the first one is a picture of the
actor and all of the rest of those
pictures are from they're created by ai.
So it's a man with a curly
hair, dark eyes, small nose
and thin lips, wearing glasses.
And there is a couple of, like
other descriptors basically.
And this is basically what AI created.
I do think this is a particularly hard
example simply because the first one
if you see the structure of his like
upper lip, it's like a certain structure
that's like difficult to explain.
Unless you like gesture, put
like your fingers or something.
So the AI didn't get it right till,
I want to say the third picture.
Here's a couple of like other examples.
This wasn't a very good example either.
It didn't get it right and it also put on
a lot of like facial hair or something.
This is another example with a
blonde character with dark eyes
and a side smile and fringe.
His eyes are dark and small and his lips
are thin, his upper teeth are visible.
He is smiling and he seems excited.
None of them accurate
are the original actor.
So basically my conclusion was
that, oh, maybe forensic portrait
painters will keep their job.
And then what happened is I put in
this example I really this example
because this is the perfect example
of what how to say, a really nicely
descriptive character actor looks like.
And what happens because of this
specific sort of description
is AI almost gets it right.
You should see these examples,
especially the first generated image.
It's like very similar.
It's very similar to the
face of the actor itself.
These are from, I want
to say a bank creator.
These are from Dreamworks.
And
both of them did really well.
I want to say even the bottom left
over here looks like the Charact actor.
What did I do then?
I thought about what would I do
if they took away like my job?
What would I do?
So I have a couple of dream projects
that I would spend a lot of time
on, and one of my dream project
was to write my own travel blog.
But I had a lot of logistical issues.
Like for instance I took 300
pictures of a day out in China.
So what I wanted to do was I
wanted to make AI do it basically.
So I wrote so I wanted to write my
own, and basically what I try to
do is I just try to use a lot of AI
models to write my trial log for me.
I had a lot of photos that I
plugged into from my drive.
Used a caption and I would just
say did pretty well actually
some of the captions like what a
child would say about an image.
For instance, this one says My prompt
was on her day out in China, a.
And it's all very simplistic.
It's oh, I saw through a window.
It doesn't say a lot about the
image or anything descriptive,
but it was like, it was factual.
It was a caption.
The second image, it's on her
day out in Chen Aroma saw I saw
this beautiful floor on her.
Day out in Chen Aroma saw she spotted
a car driving down the street.
Now the issue with that is that if
you check out images on Instagram,
you'll see an image posted.
Like the one with the car and like all of
those like colorful buildings of sorts.
And it wouldn't look like, oh, she
spotted a car driving down the street.
It would be something like, oh, there
were like a lot of colorful buildings
lining the street that would, that is
what like an artist would say, or someone
who was using Instagram would say.
But AI basically decided to
concentrate on cost simply because
of like how it had been tried.
On aroma saw the plums of the frania
trees were it basically gave me
like the descriptors, but it didn't
do a really good job with adding
poetry until the captions basically.
I was like there's some work
to do, but it'll probably just
write my child off for me.
And then I just basically gave
up and watched a movie, and the
movie that I watched was Clueless.
And there's this scene where it
lets you like match dresses and
lets the dress be fit onto your
body so that you can see what you
look like on that Kevin side, and I.
That sounds absurd, but can AI do
it because we can't do it anymore.
So I went to Kaggle again, and I looked
up like a data set that had a lot of
images of tops, bottoms dresses, et
cetera, et cetera, and I plugged it into.
This collab notebook of thoughts.
And what I tried to do is I tried to
superimpose it on the photograph of a
model wearing completely, a completely
different dress of thoughts by finding
out the boundaries of the dress that they
were wearing, like the top or the bottom.
And I tried to repair it using AI.
And let's see what AI basically did.
So this is what the original
image sort looked like.
And if you look at repair images.
I would just say the third and the
fourth one look slightly normal.
Everything else looks off, but the third
and the fourth ones look slightly normal.
A long way to go, but we are
basically on the right path.
The third one is from South Africa
in 2019, which was a natural language
processing, fake news detector.
So the goal was to trace
who was being blamed.
Misinformation, not just flag.
What's fake.
The dataset was real WhatsApp forwards,
informal, noisy, multilingual.
My method was combined SciPi and
NLT care based event models with POS
tagging and dependency parsing with
a lot of like minimal training data
required basically, because these
were parsers, these were not trainers.
These were not classifiers.
The improvement is today.
LMS will offer richer context,
better understanding of blame
dynamics and scalable solutions.
So impact of fake news.
Buzzfeed, they were like 22 million
interactions on the top 50 fake stories.
This is from 2018 Knight Foundation.
10 million plus tweets from 700 K plus
accounts linked to fight conspiracy
news routers, which is in India.
52% get news from WhatsApp.
Rumor fuel violence had led to deaths.
This was around the time when
WhatsApp forwards would basically
get you Lynch back home in India.
So techniques for detection keyboard
extraction and verification.
So basically I used direct and
LCK for extracting key phrases.
I used a news api.
Google had a news API back then
to crosscheck real coverage
of keyword based claims.
I used reverse image search
for detecting Photoshop images.
There was a lot of content verification,
so I compared articles from spoof
sites versus mainstream media.
I used a lot of fact checking platforms
such as all news or hooks, layers.
And for textual cues, we use grammar
and spelling mistakes, overtly
positive or negative sentiment,
no sources or suspicious sources
and repetition of certain words.
Some other techniques that were
used, and this is way before we
had like really good classifiers
on sentences before bot basically.
So all of these things are normal
parcels, and they use NLTK from Stanford.
Syntactic patterns, POS tagging
statements to detect blame assignments,
price even casually active passive
voice patterning using NLTK entity
and emotion tracking tracking name
politicians, detecting associated
emotions that are fear, hatred, sympathy.
My basic goal over here was
to actually detect propaganda.
The reason I wanted to detect
propaganda was because sometimes the
news stories are like, oh, X happened.
And sometimes it's X happened because
of Y. So they're basically trying
to blame Y for whatever happened.
Whatever happened.
So there is, like in literature,
there is a thing called depart
model of blame, coded what and why.
In literature, like in languages,
they basically have a certain language
model to identify if the structural
features of that particular sentence
would actually lead to someone to blame.
So there were like positive words,
basically ordered, cause claims.
There was some sort of thresholding,
like the percentage of sentences that
showed propaganda structure in that text.
So this is an example of how
the parts are basically worked.
This is a sentence and we are
just putting in like a pattern.
Now these patterns at that time,
because this is a parcel, right?
So you would have to write
your own pattern based on your
understanding of language and
whatever is present in that text.
And after parsing it, you would
find out if it's followed the
path model of blame model or not.
So these are some of the other stories
that I'm going to share with you.
The one in Estonia in 2023 is called If
Your Friends Are Bullshitting, using,
the other ones are were presented
at Europe Biden in 2022 by in Hong
Kong in 2021 by on Sweden in 2021.
Which was of how weird conditions
to believe the news is polarized.
The other one was presented
at Bio Ohio in 2020.
It was analyzing bias in
children's educational materials.
The one in Picon, Estonia in
2023 is called If Your Friends
Are Bullshitting Using SNLI.
SNLI is one of my favorite data
sets specifically because of like
iner contradiction and neutral
sentiment analysis basically because
I think it models a lot of things.
That we need, we will need to
use in the future, basically.
For instance, even when we are giving
like an instruction to an LLM, you need to
make sure that it's, understands if it's
a contradiction, if it's an entitlement
or if it's like neutral in comparison to
like the instruction it was given before.
So the goal was to use natural language
processing to spot contradictions
in statements proving when your
friends are being inconsistent.
This project actually came from, it did
actually come from a lot of bullshit that
I heard from my friends, for instance
they were like, oh, we are like 15 minutes
away, and then they wouldn't show up
for the next 30 minutes or something.
That's where this
project really came from.
So it was a real life scenario.
The models that I used at that time
were to compare using both and GP
two embeddings, GPD two embeddings
for detecting contradiction.
My data set was to leverage
SNLI for building and
training contradiction models.
The impact was to improve L lamp
coherency, tackle, hallucinations, and
filter, fake or contradictory news.
So this is like some of the slides that
are presented in this presentation.
It's like sex.
Why is you hone your bullshit detector?
Edward we're like surrounded
by bullshit all the time.
It would be really nice to give someone
else the job to detect bullshit.
It's like thinking through
bullshit all the time.
There's a couple of articles that
go like how to direct bullshit
even on sites like LinkedIn.
So it is actually a real problem.
It's not just a personal problem.
It would also be I want to say
a professional problem or how
to measure someone's bullshit.
And it seems to be for someone on the
spectrum, for people on the spectrum.
So I guess like people on the
spectrum needs a bullshit detector
more than someone else needs it.
So there's three classifications
for bullshiting using SNLI.
The first one is ENT entailment.
The second one is contradiction,
and the third one is neutrality.
Now these things mean
exactly what they're saying.
So entailment means that there
is two sentences that basically
say almost the same thing.
They like support each other.
Contradiction is like when they contradict
each other and neutrality is like when
they don't know anything or they don't
have anything to do with each other.
For instance, Jim rides a bike
to school every morning, and the
second one is Jim can ride a bike.
I would say these are like lightly
entailed because they don't contradict
each other and they're not too
neutral with respect to each other.
They do actually have some source
of information with respect to both.
So this is an example from the
paper that was published using SNLI.
The premise is a dog jumping.
For a Frisbee in the snow.
The example one is an animal is outside in
the cold weather, playing with a plastic
toy, which is an entailment, an animal,
a dog is outside in the cold weather,
in the snow, playing with a plastic toy.
A plastic toy is a Frisbee,
so it's an entailment.
The example two is a cat washed his
face and whiskers with his front P.
Now the animal is a dog, so
clearly it's not a cat, and
they're like washing their face.
Whiskers with their front paw.
So it's like contradicting what is
being said in the first sentence,
which says clearly that it's a dog
jumping for a Frisbee in this no.
The third example is a pet is enjoying
a game of fetch with his owner.
This is not neutral because it could
I want to say in sale or it could be a
contradiction or it could be like not
related to the first sentence at all.
I want to say precisely if you wanted to
use by precise language, I would say the
actual sentence that would be a direct
contradiction of the premise is a dog is
like a dog and you'd have to name the dog.
A dog is eating a bone inside the house
and you would have to basically make
sure that it's the same dog that we are
speaking about as in the first sentence.
SNLI is a collection of 570 k,
human written English sentence
pairs, manually labeled for balanced
classifications with labels,
entailment, contradiction, and neutral.
We aim for it to serve both as a benchmark
for evaluating representational systems
for text, especially including those
induced by representation learning
methods, as well as resource for
developing NLP models of any kind.
This these are like examples from a line.
There's text judgments and hypothesis
and everything in the judgment column.
Everything in the judgment
column is basically the label.
So this was basically my pipeline.
What on the screen is basically the
pipeline that I use to find out if
my friends were bullshit using Sana.
That's a dataset.
We use a tokenize, we convert like all
of our sentences into tokens and we
put them in into a model and we get
like pre-trained everything sort of it.
And then we put it into
a new model for training.
Basically what we are doing
at like the second step.
We are trying to use whatever
information has already been
learned by a certain model.
For instance, in this case it's B or
GT two, and we are extracting a form
of that sentence that has all of that
information from like the contact
space of b or two, which is what?
Which is why what we get
out is a pre-trained ing.
There's a sentence, and the end product
is basically a pre-reading, which has
the semantic or like the meaningful
understanding of that particular sentence
in the context of everything that has been
learned by a model such as, but or GT two.
So I enter this new model.
We're basically putting in all of our
old training as well, so it gets to use
it's old training as well as gets to do
some sort of like new magic on top of it.
And the last one was the
inference box basically.
Some details about the birth model.
The birth model was proposed in bird
pre-training of deep bidirectional
transformers for language understanding
by Jacob Devlin Ming by Chime,
Canton Lee and Christina Anova.
It's a bidirectional transformer
pre-trained using a combination of
mass language modeling objective,
and the next sentence production
on a large corpus comprising the
turn to book corpus and Wikipedia.
The abstract from the
paper is the following.
We introduced a new language
representation model called Bird,
which stands for bi-directional encoder
representations from transformers.
Unlike recent language representation
models, bird is designed to pre-train
deep bi-directional representations from
unlabeled text by jointly conditioning on
both left and right context in all layers.
As a result, the pre-trade birth
model can be fine tuned with just
one additional output layer to create
the state-of-the-art models for a
wide range of tasks, such as question
answering and language efforts without
substantial tasks, specific architecture
modifications, but is conceptually
simple and am empirically powerful.
It obtains new state of the art results
on 11 natural language processing tasks,
including pushing the glue score to 80.5%.
This is all really old.
Yeah, we don't really need bird
today, but this is an old project.
I say it's a very old project.
It's just, I want to say two
years old or three years old.
But that's basically how massive
the jump has been from Bird
to what we do today using GPT.
So this is like from the open source
documentation associated with birth.
The open a IG BT model was
proposed in language models.
Our unsupervised multitask learners by
Radford, Jeffrey W River, Charles David
Luan, Dar Moai, and Elia Soki from OpenAI.
So this is a large transformer based
language model with 1.5 billion
parameters too, and it's trained on
a data set of 8 million web pages.
All right, so this is like a page from.
It's open source sort of documentation.
These are the two language
models that I use basically.
And this is a diagram for you to
understand what happens when we get
pre-trained evidence from a certain model.
So this is the sematic space.
This is like meaningful space.
What it basically means
is this certain word.
A certain distance from the
X axis, meaningful X axis.
We don't know what the meaningful x
axis means, but the model nodes and the
meaningful y axis and the meaningful C
axis, basically, and these are like all
of the distances between those two words.
And those are like the sematic
distances between those two words
that basically says the meaning of
this particular word is different
from this, the meaning of this
particular word by so and so distance.
These are basically what I did.
I just trains both and G two embed things.
This is another example of
it's two headlines from two
different editions of news.
The first one says, Bernie
Sanders scored victories for
years via legislative siders.
The second one says we
are legislative siders.
Bernie Sanders won
modest victories, right?
The first one makes it seem like
the victories were really grand.
And the second one makes it seem
like the victories were very modest.
So someone who's reading the
first edition would think that
it was like a great thing.
It would be praise the second edition.
It would make it seem like it was not
praise, it was not such a great thing.
So this would basically slightly
contradict each other, right?
So these are like some of the labels.
I do not remember.
I think label two is contradiction.
And you can see like how.
The scores are like higher for the
first and the last sentence and like
slightly lower for the second sentence.
Maybe it just feels like modest victories
and victories is not that that different.
Maybe it's if we basically
said that Bernie Sanders lost.
It would say that it's contradictory
on a large scale, but it does say that
it is contradictory though lightly.
So this is another project that I
presented at Europe by, in 2022 by, in
Hong Kong 2021 at by on Sweden in 2021.
It was to analyze sentiments and news
headlines to examine bias, comparing
it to public perception from surveys.
The initial approaches.
Basically fail to capture the complexity
of these sentiments and the bias
in headlines, the revised approach.
It leveraged advanced NLP
techniques to metro line sentiment
with real world reader biases.
The outcome was the failure led to deeper
understanding of contextual sentiments and
analysis and bias measurement essential
for interpreting media influence.
So my next project was at Bio Ohio 2020.
It was analyzing bias in
children's educational materials.
This was specifically gender
biased such as portraying female
characters predominantly as
mothers and housewives while male
characters was seen as breadwinners.
I use NFP techniques.
This was way before birth.
Or maybe both had just come out.
So I was using a lot of parser structures
and rudimentary NLP techniques.
Using mostly NLTK.
We can analyze representation bias by
tracking the frequency of gender terms.
I. Identify stereotypes through
objective associations and detect
victim blaming language and text.
For instance, in some countries,
the proportion of female characters
in mathematics textbooks was
found to be as low as 30%.
To combat these biases is crucial
to revise curriculum, to promote
gender equality, update textbooks to
be more inclusive, and use NLP tools
to continually monitor and correct
those biases in educational content.
So some of these
techniques are really easy.
It's just basically counting a lot of
pronouns, making sure your entities
are mapped really well to their
genders and counting how many people
of that particular gender are present.
And because of like rudimentary
techniques, you were able to
like PUS tag a lot of objectives.
So you could associate objectives
with the entities in that particular
sentence and be able to deduce like
the sentiment of that objective.
You would not need a lot of I want
to say high tech NLP techniques.
You would only need maybe a
dictionary and a score of sorts.
So my research focus was examining how
gender bias in children's educational
materials shapes, perceptions and roles.
For example.
Female characters predominantly
portrayed as housewives, while male
characters are shown as breadwinners.
My key findings were there was
a representation bias, so female
characters were underrepresented
and fields like mathematics.
So a lot of the people doing
the math used to be meant.
So like it would be Tom bought 12
watermelons and never like daisy bots.
12 What moment?
There was also steward of bias.
For instance a doctor was usually
male and a nurse was usually female.
There was also sort of cultural blame.
So a lot of like victim blaming
languages maybe using passive language
as opposed to active language.
Like she was raped instead
of someone raped her.
So we did a lot of like analysis
on techniques for bias detection.
Representation analyst is
using token frequency in text.
Stereotype evaluation using
objective and role association
using spacey and LTK, blame language
detection via path model of blame,
identifying casual and labeling bias.
The change that I came out from the
study was to revise the curriculum
to reflect gender equality and
to remove these stereotypes.
So some of the other stories that I'm
going to share with you are one of it
is from by Lithuania again in 2023.
It's about chatting with Chad about
everything and nothing at all.
It was when Charge g BT first came out and
most of my talk is basically based out of
my free time explorations with charge GBT.
It started out as like a fun experiment.
I used to even post on social media
about, oh, this is what I asked Chad,
and this is what it said back to me.
A lot of like jailbreaking
and all of that.
And I decided to make a
whole study out of it.
Basically, my next story is about
AI and software development.
So it's about experimenting with SVMs
and why SVMs are really important.
And my ninth story is about
choose for the visually impaired.
This was a project that was
presented at First Asia in 2016.
So Pi Lithuania 2023 chatting with Chad
Gpt about everything and nothing at all.
So it was like an overview of
Chad gps rise and the question of
whether it was through AGI I or not.
There was an explanation of the
training process for including
data usage and model architecture.
I subjected it to the WIT test because
at that point Jiri was like trained on a
lot of data that was present on Reddit.
So it was not very good with wit.
So I decided to test like what it
feels or like what it understands
through like various riddles.
And I also use like riddles from like
specific languages like Hindi or like
some other sort of like cultural nuanced
riddles to see how it would perform.
And like complex context and
nuance language basically.
It had at that point, it had issues
with verbal math problems and concept
concepts of understanding Venn diagrams.
So if you would give a kid a problem
statement to solve using a Venn diagram,
they would be able to solve it easily
if they were, I want to say in grade
eight, to charge GPD at that time.
Also sensory experience gaps.
So highlighting the model's, inability
to process real world sensory
experiences such as hearing an egg crack.
'cause it, it didn't know what
happened after you heard an egg
crack 'cause it didn't have the
sensors to sense any of those things.
Also metaphorical
language on relationships.
Oh, at that time in 2023, child jupi was
not really good at metaphorical language.
And comparing it to human performance.
Basically to answer the question
of whether charge GPD is a GI.
My answer to that today actually
is that in certain ways charge
g PT is better than humans.
So it is I want to say a GI plus,
and at some things it's not, so it's.
In those areas, it's not a GI.
So some of these questions that
I basically asked Chad GTI was,
when is a door no longer a door?
So the answer you gave me was
very logical, but because this is
a riddle, it's a riddle, right?
So it's like a door is no longer a
door when it no longer serves the
purpose of providing an entrance or
exit to a room or building, or when
it is unable to be open or closed.
Logical answer.
But then I write it that we were
solving griddles, so it had to be like
in a fun mood of thoughts, basically.
So I was like this is a riddle.
Answer it.
When is a door no longer a door?
And then it's grab the answer
from somewhere and it's like
training data or something.
It was like a door is no longer
a door when it's a jar, which is
basically what the answer was.
So it was like way witty.
The second question was, what
tastes better than it smells?
And BOUs, it had like previous context
of oh, we were in like riddle mode.
It knew that something that sounded
absurd, like that was a riddle.
And it told me back, this is a riddle.
The answer is tongue because it
ties food but doesn't have a smell.
What building has the most stories?
It detected that this was a riddle.
It said the answer is library
because it has very stories.
It was right.
It got a bunch of them rights after I
told it that we were like in riddle mode.
So maybe it had to access like
some sort of like training memory
that was associated with riddle and
like witty I want to say language
and I guess it got like some sort
of an answer, which is probably
I dunno, it could be right.
Does the stackers have
a bottom at the top?
I don't know.
But the real answer was
supposed to be legs.
And it did give an explanation that could
in some contexts be the right explanation.
So I did really well on creative tasks.
I asked it like a bunch of questions
again around sensory experiences as well.
It didn't have really good
answers for it at that time.
So my next presentation is
about experimenting with SVMs.
This was presented at AI and
Software Development Summit in 2024.
The reasons we like SVMs, I like SVMs
or like data scientists like SVMs.
It's called Support Vector Clustering.
It's a clustering technique using SPM
principles for unsupervised learning,
it maps data to high dimensional hill
butt space versus a kernel trick.
It finds minimum enclosing
sphere and then maps boundaries
back to the original sphere.
It uses gian kernel, which is
a non-linear transformation.
It has two key hyper parameters.
Q stands for kernel width
controls cluster granularity.
P, which is a soft machine
controls stall, and star outliers.
And it does not assume shape
or the number of clusters, it
basically adapts naturally.
So going over it is basically the size of
the circle inside, which you would want
your points to be placed to say that,
oh, this is the space that is similar.
Then all of the others.
And p is it's like this soft
margin between two peaks.
If there are two peaks, there
could be points that lie in both
of, like those circles of sorts.
So you want to make sure that
those between points lie in
like circle one or circle two,
either of those circles, right?
Which is a factor that we call p And these
are like the hyper parameters that are.
To get that data.
So SBMs basically handle non
convex, overlapping noisy data.
They have better accuracy than traditional
clustering on complex data sets.
For example Iris is like a very, I would
just say f dataset that data set like
data scientists like to talk about.
It's an elegant blend of theory.
And practical clustering part.
The reason I really like spms,
the reason I really like spms, and
this is like an example that I give
everyone, is that say you have a
line which is only an X axis, right?
And it has, I want to say on the screen
14, those have to be 14 dots.
So you can see that clearly, there's
seven green bolts and then there's
seven red bolts and you're able
to draw like a line in between.
And you're able to say that these are like
two different clusters of data basically.
But what happens if the data is mixed?
Like on the line on the third line?
Basically it's like mix of like
red and green balls, so you can't
really go in and draw a line.
The X to say that.
This is the separation
between these two clusters.
Now what happens is, and this is
basically the principle of svs, we
introduce a different dimension.
We introduce a different dimension,
but take all of our data into this
different dimension, basically a
y axis, and we separate it out.
For instance, if all of the red colored
balls go to the positive y-axis and
all of the green colored balls come
to the negative y axis, we can just
separate out the data by saying
that the separator is the X axis.
So this is basically what s VNS do.
And this was my presentation at AI and
Software Development Summits in 2024.
The next project I want to talk
about is the one that I presented
at First Asia in 2016, which was
choose for the visually impaired.
My purpose was to improve daily mobility
and confidence for the visual impact.
They were just shoes with
some basic ultrasound sensors.
And what they wanted to do was they wanted
to sense an obstruction either in front
of them, behind them, or at the sites.
It was supposed to improve
mobility for visually impaired.
So instead of using like an ultrasound
stick they would be able to get
feedback using those ultrasound centers.
The control unit was a. And it had a
Bluetooth module, which transmitted
sensor data into an Android device.
The Android app at that time was built
using MIT app, inventor and phone Gap.
So our vision was to like maybe move to
a MATLAB based prototype at that time,
because this was back in 2016 and, maybe
change like the feedback, because at the
time it was like really clunky and you
would get feedback only through like voice
into your Bluetooth headsets or something.
A more graceful approach would be
to give like someone haptic feedback
like in the clothes or something else.
My last jury is create your
own data that are presented at.
So when do you need your own data?
We are in the mood of like
magical LLM thinking available
to all of us at all times, right?
So what do we do with lms?
Generative models are useful for creating
synthetic data, even if they struggle
with factual accuracy and reliability.
Use case one is thought
lodge generator train.
A model to generate Thought
Lodge is focusing on internal
consistency rather than grounded two.
Use case travel image tagging, generate
image captions from personal photos
using LMS to create contextual and
creative tag for journaling or curation.
Synthetic data creation through lms.
Use LMS to bootstrap data sets
for tasks like totology generation
or image captioning without
relying on factual correctness.
I use techniques like distillation
and fine tuning to help adapt other
elements to specialized tasks by
reusing generated data and tailoring
models for specific use cases.
The takeaway was synthetic data
generation can unlock meaningful
creator workflows in areas where
factual accuracy is not a priority.
So some examples from like the
experiments that I performed the
original collab is like cocky is
hundred 10 examples of dot lodging.
And do not give a reason why, because
usually what happens when you're like
talking to something that was designed
to be a chat bot is they give you a lot
of reasons back as to why the sentence
that they have is a chart logic.
A bunch of these sentences are actually
not real ologies, but some of them are.
And the trick that I found out to like
verify if the sentences are actually
ologies, is to give them back to another
element to verify whether they are
actually but some of the good examples
I really like are the second one.
Water is wet.
That's a tar.
Fire is hot, that's a tar.
And general 10 examples of metaphors
and do not give reasons why.
Her voice was a CD that played hundred
p in my mind, and basically I gave
her the prompt to use the word cd.
That's straight up crazy, right?
Can you think of a lot of
metaphors using the word cd?
Her voice was a cd.
His angers was a C that scratched and
sced the surface of our relationship.
My job was a CD that's kept and glitched,
making it hardware enjoy the music.
So there, this is synthetic data.
It's really cool data.
I just want to say it's really cool data.
Thank you.
This was all for an example of caption
generation using images that was
something that I used in my travel.
Thank you so much.
The slides are of slides, carnival.
Have a good bye.