Hello everyone, and welcome.
My name is Gupta and I'm excited to be
speaking with you today at Con 42, we
are going to dive into a critical and
rapidly evolving area resource allocation
for AI workloads in cloud computing.
The rise of AI applications from deep
learning models to complex machine
learning pipelines has completely changed
the game for cloud resource management.
These aren't your
traditional applications.
They have unique demands, complexities,
and behaviors that require much
more sophisticated strategies for
allocating compute, memory, and
network resources effectively as we'll.
Explore AI workloads are
fundamentally different.
They exhibit significant resource
variability, often requiring
specialized hardware like GPUs.
Or TPOs.
Their performance is highly sensitive
to latency and throughput, and their
resource needs can change dramatically
depending upon the face of execution.
Think training versus inference.
These unique characteristics create
novel challenges that traditional cloud
management systems often struggle with.
This talk, we will examine the convergence
of AI and cloud infrastructure.
Looking critically, how can we effectively
manage resources in this new landscape?
So let's ask this question.
Why is this so important?
Look at the scale and impact.
The global AI infrastructure market
is projected to reach a staggering
2 99 $0.64 billion by 2026.
That's not just not, that's not
just growth, it's explosive growth.
Their annual growth rate at 35.6%
is significantly outpacing that
traditional IT sectors, CAGR since 2021.
This signifies a massive
shift in investment and focus
towards AI capabilities.
But it's not just about spending
more, it's about spending smarter.
Implementing AI driven resource
management itself feels significant.
Benefits.
Industry analysis show that these
intelligent systems can lead
to transformative improvements.
We are seeing potential for up to 40%
improvement in resource utilization,
meaning less wasted capacity through
techniques like ML powered allocation.
Simultaneously, organizations are
documenting 25 to 35% reduction
in operational cost, primarily
infrastructure expenditure, while
maintaining strict performance banks,
benchmark and service level agreements.
Status.
SLS, this dual optimization,
improving efficiency and reducing cost
represents a true paradigm shift in
cloud economics Driven by the very AI
technologies we are trying to support.
To allocate resources effectively,
we first need to understand
what the workload needs.
This is where workload profiling
and resource estimation comes in.
How much C-P-U-G-P-U memory and IO
will a specific AI task require,
and when we have several approaches.
First static analysis.
This involves looking into
the AI model's architecture.
Its hyper parameters and known
pattern before execution.
For established workloads,
this can predict computational
demands with reasonably high
precision, around 80 to 85%.
Second, historic pattern analysis.
Here we analyze past execution,
data telemetry to identify
temporal signal signatures.
Advanced time series modeling and
techniques like wave decomposition
help forecast future requirements
based on past behavior.
Third, online monitoring.
This is about real-time assessment.
We continuously sample critical system
matrix during the runtime itself.
Things like compute, saturations,
memory, bandwidth usage, and IO
throughput to understand the immediate
needs and dynamically adjust.
Last, but not the least.
Hybrid approaches.
Often the best strategies
combines these three methods.
We integrate complementary techniques
to enhance prediction accuracy.
However, it is important to note that
for completely new and unpredictable
workload patterns, accuracy can degrade
perhaps for the 60 to 65% range.
Getting this profile right is crucial.
As noted, significant workload
intelligence systems have led to the
infrastructure cost reductions of up to
35% and utilization improvements of 40%.
The accuracy of our profiling directly
impacts how efficiently and stably we
can operate these next AI workloads.
Okay, so once we have an estimate
of what the resources need, how do
we actually assign those resources
to the workloads waiting to run?
This is the job of the scheduler for ai.
We need intelligence
scheduling mechanisms.
First priority based.
Not all workloads are equal.
ML algorithms can analyze patterns
and history to anticipate needs
and inten intent and intelligently
preempt lower priority tasks to
ensure critical jobs get the resources
they need when they need them.
Second, fair share.
In multi-tenant environments,
we need fairness.
Sophisticated frameworks ensure equitable
resource distribution across different
users or groups while still aiming
for the overall system efficiency.
Deadline aware.
Many AI tasks, especially in production
pipelines have critical time constraints.
The scheduler uses predictive model that
factor in computational complexity, data
throughput, and dependency to ensure
tasks complete within their deadlines.
Optimization resource allocation
is fundamentally a complex,
multi-dimensional optimization problem.
Advanced approximation algorithms are
used to find computationally feasible
solutions that are close to the optimum.
Even if finding the perfect solution is
intractable, often an NP hard problem.
Despite these advancements, the
inherent computational complexity,
the NP heart nature of the optimal
multidimensional allocation means we
often rely on design heuristic approaches.
This aim to balance practical real
world performance with theoretical ality
guarantees it's a constant trade off.
Okay, so AI workloads are rarely static.
Their demands fluctuate.
Autoscaling is the key to
handle this dynamic efficiently.
A typical AI powered autoscaling
architecture involves several layers.
First monitoring layer,
this is the foundation.
It collects detailed telemetry
data across multiple dimensions.
Your CPU, your GPU Memory network
application specific matrix, providing
a rich granular view of the system,
state and resource utilization.
Sophisticated deep learning
models are often used to
analyze these complex patterns.
Second layer is your analysis engine.
This is the brain.
It implements pattern recognization
and decision models often leveraging
reinforcement learning algorithms.
It.
Continuously evaluates historic
performances and real time
systems state to decide when
and how to adjust resources.
Should we scale up,
scale down, or stay Put.
Third execution layer.
This layer translates the decision
made by your analysis engine into the
concrete actions for your infrastructure.
Provisioning new virtual machines,
adjusting container replicas,
modifying resource limits.
While these AI powered auto-scaling
systems showed remarkable capabilities
in control tests achieving prediction
accuracy of often around 95%,
they face significant challenge
in the real world production.
We confronted sorry.
When confronted with unexpected
traffic patterns, anonymous
behaviors or system events.
Prediction accuracy can
deteriorate significantly.
Sometimes it drops to as low as 72%.
This highlights the ongoing need
for robustness and better handling
for unseen for circumstances.
Autoscaling Achieves resource
elasticity, the ability to
adjust resources dynamically.
This is implemented primarily in two ways.
Vertical scaling and horizontal scaling.
Let's first talk about vertical scaling.
This means adjusting the resources
allocated to the existing instances.
Think adding more CPU or GPU or
memory to our running virtual machine.
Using GPU partitioning technologies
to allocate fraction of A GPU,
employing memory ballooning techniques
without super within hypervisors.
These limitations are often the
limitations here are often physical
hardware constraints, operating system
support and application compatibility.
Not all application can handle graceful
and resource changing underneath them.
Second is horizontal scaling.
This involves adding or
removing entire instances.
So remember, vertical scaling
means adjusting the resources
within the existing instances.
Horizontal scaling, we add or remove
the entire in instances common mechanism
of include auto scaling groups that can
manage a pool of identical instances,
replica controllers in orchestration
systems like Kubernetes, and load
balancing mechanisms to distribute
traffic across the available instances.
The main challenge here is
the coordination overhead.
As you scale up out to many instances,
managing them and ensuring that they
work together efficiently introduces
complexity and throughput gains can
diminish beyond a certain point.
These elasticity mechanisms are
absolutely critical for modern ai.
Especially generative AI workloads that
we have today, which can exhibit dramatic
peak andro in resource demands during
different processing or phasing slides.
Okay, so now let's talk about this.
Containers have become a standard way to
package and deploy applications, including
AI, workloads, orchestration platforms,
manage these containers at scale.
Kubernetes has largely emerged as the
prominent orchestration platform for ai.
It provides a robust framework
with several key components,
networking layer, storage, layer
data, plane and control plane.
Your networking layer facilitates seamless
communication between containers, often
using sophisticated overlay networks.
Your storage layer ensures data
persistence across container life cycles
crucial for stateful AI applications.
Often using dynamic volume plugins, data
plane, this is where the work happens.
Components like the ber culet on each
note coordinate with container run times
to execute the workload control plane.
The brains of the operation, the
API Server Intelligence Scheduler,
and Robb Robust controller managers
orchestrate the entire system.
Empirical studies consistently show
Kubernetes outperforming alternates
like Docker Swamp in large scale
deployments, managing thousands of
nodes and containers efficiently,
while maintaining high resource
utilization and workload throughput.
However, this comes at a cost.
Kubernetes introduces significant
architectural complexity
and operational challenges.
Organization needs specialized
expertise and comprehensive training.
It's a high barrier to entry compared
to Simpl solutions, but it ultimately
delivers the superior scalability
and flexibility needed for the
complex AI computing environments.
Underlying much of cloud computing and
resource allocation is virtualization,
abstracting the physical hardware.
Several techniques are vital for ai.
CPU virtualization techniques like
Intel VTX and A MDV provide hardware
assistance to reduce the overhead of
virtualizing the CPU, enabling near native
performance for compute intensive tasks,
memory virtualizations technique like
SLAT, second level address translation,
numa, non-uniform memory access.
Awareness in the hypervisor and
transparent pace sharing improves memory
efficiency and introduce across latency.
Critical for data
intensive AI applications.
Input output virtualization.
Getting data in and
out quickly is crucial.
Technologies like single route I
virtualization, para virtualization
drivers, and direct di direct
device assignment, bypass some of
the virtualizations over it for
network and storage operations.
Enhancing performance GPU virtualization.
Essential for many AI workloads
method range from AI remoting to
hardware assisted partitioning, and
time slicing mechanism that allow
multiple concurrent users or workloads
to share a single physical GPU.
It is important to add a caveat here.
While these advancements offer real
native while these advancements offer
near native performance under optimal
conditions, or for a specific workload
types, performance degradation can
still be significant, particularly for
applications that are highly IO intensive.
The virtualization layer, however,
thin still introduces some overhead.
Ultimately, a major driver
for sophisticated resource
allocation is cost optimization.
How can we run these expensive
AI workloads more economically?
Several strategies are the key here.
First, VM allocation policies
intelligently allocating
virtual machine resources.
Based on the actual need rather than over
promising can yield significant savings,
potentially 30% cost reduction workload
placement, strategically distributing
workloads across different availability
zones or even geographic regions.
Based on the resource availability
and pricing difference can achieve
a saving up to 25% resource right
sizing this wind bots precisely
matching the allocated resources.
CPU memory, GPU to the actual measured
workload requirement, avoiding any waste.
This can contribute another 20% reduction.
Commitment discounts.
Cloud providers offered substantial
discounts, offered 45% or more
for long-term commitments, like
reserved instances or saving plans
compared to on demand pricing.
Leveraging these for a
baseline workload is crucial.
Traditionally, traditional
cloud environments often
operate as a surprisingly low
efficiency, maybe 30 to 45%.
Implementing these optimized
allocation policies can dramatically
increase utilization rates,
pushing them towards 65 to 75%.
However, these figure often represent
idolized scenarios where organizations
can have complete flexibility.
Real world constraints can
limit the achievable sale.
Achievable savings.
Okay, so shifting resources dynamically
in multi-tenant environment introduces
unique security consideration.
Sharing isn't always caring when it
comes to sensitive data and workloads.
Key security aspects include.
Sorry.
Isolation mechanism.
Strong boundaries are
essential Hypervisor.
Security features and kernel level
isolation prevent unauthorized
access between different workloads
running on the same physical
hardware authorization systems.
Robot robust policy engines must govern
who or what can make resource allocation
decisions adhering to the principle of
least privilege, continuous validation.
Security isn't a one-time check.
We need continuous monitoring of
allocation decisions against the
security policy for defense in
depth site channel protection.
When multiple tenants share physical
resources, especially accelerators like
GPUs, there's a risk of information
leakage through subtle timing variations
or cache aspect cache access patterns.
Mitigation against these
attacks are crucial.
So container platforms like Kubernetes
also presents with their own security
challenges when used for AI hardening
measures such as restrictive port
security policies, network policies to
control traffic flow and runtime security
monitoring are necessary additions.
Security must be baked into an allocation
strategy, not bolted on afterwards.
Okay, so now if we have come to our
end of the presentation, let's talk
about where is this field heading.
Several exciting directions are emerging.
First, automated workload characterization
using AI itself, deep learning,
transfer, learning casual inference to
automatically fingerprint, workloads,
adapt quickly to new application types.
And pinpoint resource bottlenecks
without manual analysis, energy aware
allocation, implementing scheduling,
and scaling policies that are
conspicuous of power consumptions.
This includes dynamic voltage, frequency
scaling and consolidating workloads
based on thermal characteristics to
reduce the overall energy footprint.
Carbon aware computing, taking
energy awareness a step further by
scheduling workloads to align with
the availability of clean energy.
This involves integrating with grid
carbon intensity forecast, and renewable
energy production patterns to run
computation when it is the greenest.
In conclusion, integrating AI into
resource management creates a fascinating
meta recursive system, AI optimizing
the infrastructure needed to run ai.
This enables unprecedented automation
and efficiency, but also introduces
novel complexity and challenges.
As we have discussed, this
technical analysis that we have
done today highlights the critical
need for continued research.
We need to address Al, sorry.
We need to address algorithmic
limitations, improve the robustness
of these systems, especially when
facing the unexpected, undeveloped,
standardized benchmarking methodologies.
To objectively compare
different approaches.
The journey of efficiently
powering the AI revolution is
still very much under the way.
I hope this presentation helped
you in a way to understand it.
Thank you.