Hi, my name is Harry Prima.
Thanks for joining this session.
I'm here to talk about reshaping the
very foundation of retail artificial
intelligence for store assistance as a
senior data engineer and architect with
over 18 years of experience in this field.
I've seen how data algorithms and smart
systems are transforming businesses.
AI doesn't just support backend analytics.
It becomes a frontline tool for
engaging customers, optimizing
operations, and driving strategic
decision making decision.
Today's session is designed
to unpack this transformation.
I will guide you through how AI and
machine learning are integrated into
retail environments, both online and
in physical stores, and how these
technologies are helping businesses
to meet modern consumer expectations.
This is not, it's.
It is about using data and intelligence
to craft better, more efficient,
and more personal shopping journeys.
Whether you are a tech guy or a retail
executive, or simply curious to know
about how AI is impacting in retail
stores, this session will help you.
To walk away with some
valuable insights today.
Let's dive in and explore what the
future of smart retail really looks like.
Here is what we'll
cover over this session.
First, I'll give a quick
introduction to the state of AI in
retail to provide context to it.
Then we'll see some statistics about
growth and investment in the space.
We'll see some specific applications like
virtual try ons, cashier list checkouts,
and AI powered restocking systems.
Then we'll dive into future trends,
especially hyper-personalization, dynamic
pricing and digitalization of and stores.
From there, we'll go deep into
core applications of AI in.
Inventory management, chat bots,
recommendation systems, and more.
We'll learn about ML models and
tools empowering these applications.
Next, we'll break down the most
important frameworks and technologies.
TensorFlow, PyTorch, Azure, ai, and Maker.
Then we.
We'll also cover a real case study to make
things tangible and show how it benefits.
Let's begin with the big picture
is undergoing a profound transformation
and AI at the heart of it.
In just the past five years, we have seen
become far more digital and automated.
AI and retail is projected to
grow from 26.9 billion in 2023
to over 60 billion by 2030.
That's a compound annual
growth rate of 31 percentage.
This is not marginal.
It's exceptional growth.
Why?
Because AI addresses two core challenges
in retail efficiency and personal.
Customers expect more faster service.
Personalized offers, seamless experiences.
At the same time, businesses face
pressure to reduce operational cost and
make smarter decisions in real time.
AI is uniquely positioned to
solve both the challenges.
Think about your last shopping experience.
Did you get.
Did HR Port assisted you?
Was your checkout fast and personalized?
If so, there is a good chance AI
played a role behind the scenes.
Retailers are using AI for dynamic
inventory management, ensuring shelves
are stocked, not just based on past
data, but on predictive insights.
They using it.
Demand spikes based on weather or
local events, or even to create
hyper-personalized promotions
based on processing behavior.
As we continue, I'll show you how
different types of ai, national language
processing, computer vision, predictive
analytics, are coming together to
create intelligent, responsive and
customer first retail ecosystems.
Many still rely on manual processes, gut
failing or outdated systems, but the raise
of cloud AI platforms and pre-trained
models, even small businesses, can
implement chatbots, customer segmentation
models, or pricing optimization tools
with minimal cost and high returns.
The future of AI in retail is incredibly
exciting and can be summarized in three
key trends, hyper-personalization,
real-time dynamic pricing, and
AI optimized physical stores.
Let's start with hyper-personalization.
This goes beyond showing how you
products based on your browsing history.
It's about using data from multiple
touch points, social media, purchase
history, realtime location, even biometric
signals to create a tailored experience.
Imagine walking into your store where
screen welcomes you by name and offers
deals based on your preferences.
That's where we.
Second real time dynamic pricing.
A models can now adjust prices
based on current inventory,
competitive pricing, market demand,
and even better, or even data.
Airlines and hotels have
used this for years.
Now it's coming to retail.
For instance, a grocery store
can rise or lower the prices
based on protect expiration
timelines or foot traffic trends.
Maximizing profits while minimizing waste.
Third brick and motor
optimization four years.
Physical stores have lacked
behind e-commerce in innovation,
but that's changing fast.
We now have AI power systems for
tech prevention, footfall analytics,
and automated checkouts stores can
analyze in-store movement patterns
to improve shelf layouts, deploy
virtual mirrors, or use computer
vision to track them interactions and.
Takeaway here is that AI is no longer
just enhancing what we do in retail.
It's redefining how we do it.
It's creating new standard
where convenience, speed, and
personalization are no longer pers.
They are expectations.
Let's talk about how are
reshaping operations.
And perhaps most impactful
area is inventory management.
Traditional stock control is reactive
and manual, but with ai, stores
now predict buying trends weeks in
advance, algorithm analysis, past
sales, seasonal patterns, and even
events like holidays, weather forecast.
This predictive approach not
only awards stock orders, but
also minimizes overstock, which
saves money and reduces waste.
Next is demand forecasting by
leveraging machine learning models.
Often time series based retailers
can fine tune recruitment
schedules, for example, a.
Stock more raincoats in advance of we
season predicted by AI models trained
on historical and meteorological data.
Then we have personalized
product recommendations.
This is one of the most visible
AI applications to customers.
Think about streaming our
online video companies.
You see solutions tailored just for you.
Retailers are now doing the same, whether
it's suggesting a new skincare product
based on the previous purchase or bundling
offers according to buying behavior.
These algorithms drive both
customer satisfaction and
higher revenue per transaction.
One of.
Is chatbots and virtual assistance.
These are not the clunky
boards of early two thousands.
Today's AI assistance use NLP
to hold real conversations.
They assist with FAQs, offer style
suggestions, event process returns all 24
by seven and often in multiple languages.
Let's not forget AI enabled fraud
detection, loyalty, program optimization,
and customer sentiment analysis from
online reviews and social media feeds,
AI turns noise, internal knowledge.
What's most powerful here is.
These use cases are interconnected.
A chat bot can collect customer
intent data, which fits into demand
forecasting, which influences
inventory, restocking the result, a
synchronized ecosystem where data flows
intelligently between functions and
reducing silos and maximizing efficiency.
Now that we have seen what
AI can do, let's explore core
technologies making it possible.
First up is natural processing,
natural language processing, NLP.
This is the engine behind smart
chat bots and voice assistance.
NLP models, analyze customer
queries, understand intent, and
generate human-like responses.
Next is computer vision.
This is where AI analyzes visual data,
images, videos, realtime camera feeds.
In retail computer vision powers,
automated checkout systems, virtual try-on
apps, and even in-store thrift detection.
For example, cameras can detect
when an item is removed from
a shelf and not scanned it.
Checkout instantly
flagging potential loss.
Then comes predictive analytics.
This is where machine learning
meets business strategy.
Predictive models analyze past behavior.
We want to know which customer is
likely to churn or which product
category will spike next week.
Predictive analytics gives the edge.
Another underrated but crucial
technology is recommendation engines.
This systems blend collaborative filtering
with the behavioral data to generate
real time tailored product solutions.
They're constantly learning and
evolving as customer behavior shifts.
Each of these technologies is
supported by specific types of data.
NLP uses text and speech.
Computer vision requires image,
video inputs, and predictive
analytics works best with structured
sales and transaction data.
Together, these technologies from.
To make all these technologies accessible.
We have AI frameworks and platforms
that development deployment and scaling.
Let's begin by, its flexible.
For building deep learning models in
retail, it's often used for time series
demand forecasting, image based inventory
tracking, and recommendation engines.
Retailers use tensor flow to forecast
food traffic, or detect low stock
products through shelf imagin.
Next is PyTorch.
A framework allowed by researchers
and developers community for its
ease of use and dynamic computation.
PyTorch powers, NLP Drive
chatbots, dynamic pricing models
and sentiment analysis engines.
A small business can use PyTorch
to create a simple chatbot that
lands customer preferences over,
or monitors brand on social media.
Moving on Microsoft Azure ai.
This is a cloud-based suite of tools
that helps to deploy AI models at scale.
Azure supports things like fraud
detection through anomaly detection
models wise enabled shopping assistance,
and automated product tagging.
It's fantastic option for businesses
that wanna rapid deployment without
worrying about server infrastructure.
Then we have Amazon SageMaker,
a fully managed ML platform.
It's perfect for hyper-personalization,
supply chain optimization, and
even real-time search ranking on
e-commerce site retailers use SageMaker
to fine tune product discovery a
and detect patterns in customer.
Each of these tools support a wide
variety of data types from structured
tables and transactional logs to
image, video, audio, and text.
Choosing the right framework
depends on your goals.
Are you optimizing logistic?
Then go with TensorFlow or SageMaker.
Building an intelligent chatbot.
PyTorch and NLP are the best friends.
The key takeaway here is you
don't need to reinvent the wheel.
The tools are measured,
scalable, and readily available.
Let's explore the fuel
behind all this AI engines.
The data retail AI doesn't work
without large volumes of diverse
high quality data, and it.
It's about having the right kind of data.
Let's break it down by time.
First, we have time series data.
This is historical sales records,
foot traffic counts, seasonal trends,
and other metrics measured over time.
A models like LSTM or Arima variance
can forecast demand or identify supply
chain in efficiencies using this data.
Then we have transaction data that
records of individual purchases.
This includes SKUs, payment
methods, discounts, store
IDs, customer IDs, and more.
It's the backbone for pricing
strategies, inventory, movement, and
customer lifetime value analysis.
Text data is crucial for
understanding customers reviews.
Descriptions and social media posts all
contain valuable sentiment and intent.
NLP models pass this unstructured text
to extract keywords, classify emotions,
or generate response suggestions.
Another measure input is visual data.
Images and videos feeds.
Cameras are used in computer vision
models for tasks like object,
ization, theft detection, facial
analysis, and product categorization.
Audio data is becoming more common
as voice commerce rises, voice
assistance convert, voice to text
integrated and trigger backend systems.
And finally we have clickstream and
behavioral data, which captures how
users interact with apps or websites.
Every click, scroll, or
page record, uh, page exit is recorded.
This data is used to
improve search algorithms,
personalized product, and reduce
collectively.
These data enable.
AI to operate in a truly
only FA omnichannel fashion.
Bridging online and instore
experiences that matters most is the
data integration and quality, clean,
well level, and regularly updated
data sets, produced better models,
performance and deeper insights.
The right data foundation.
The most powerful AI tools are
not much useful and effective.
To make this real, let's look at a
practical case study that uses open source
retail data to drive business decisions.
I worked with the data set that
include store sales history,
customer demographics, and
product transaction details.
Using machine learning, especially
recreation models and clustering,
have identified actionable insights
that could improve both revenue and.
First, I segmented customers based
on demographics and BA behavior.
This allowed for the creation of
targeted marketing campaigns that
significantly increased conversion rates.
Second, the recreation analysis
revealed interesting trends.
For instance, certain product
categories performed in specific
seasons and geographic areas.
This information was used to fine tune
product placement and advertising timing.
Third, I observed inefficiencies
in inventory stocking.
Some stores constantly overstocked
items with low demand using predictive
models have recommended for optimal
stock levels based on forecasted demand,
which resulted in a 12% reduction in.
I also applied a sentiment
analysis to customer reviews.
This helped the business to prioritize
quality control in products that
receive frequent negative feedback
while amplifying visibility for
the products with strong reviews.
Lastly, I evaluated promotional impact
using flipped modeling by comparing
customer who.
Future promotion strategies, ensuring
that discounts were targeted where
they have produced the highest return.
All of these insights came
from analyzing, structured and
unstructured data through ai.
What's more powerful is that these
methods are scalable, whether you are
a national chain or a small retailer,
these same techniques can be applied
to any business using open tools.
Python and cloud services like Azure ml.
As I conclude, AI is no longer
optional In retail industry.
It's essential, whether it's through
smarter inventory control, highly
targeted marketing, marketing,
or seamless customer experiences.
AI delivers real value.
What's most exciting is that
we are still at the beginning.
Emerging technologies like reinforcement
learning, generative AI, and H AI are
just started to enter the retail world.
Imagine autonomous stores that
continuously optimize layout
based on live customer behavior or
generative models that create hyper
product descriptions on the fly.
We are also seeing more
emphasis on ethical ai, ensuring
fairness, transparency, and
accountability in AI systems.
This includes preventing a securing
personal data and maintaining customer
trust for developers and engineers.
Focus on interdisciplinary collaboration.
Partner with marketing largest
finance team to solve real business
problems using right tools.
AI in retail is here to
stay and it's evolving fast.
Whether you a small startup, a
global enterprise, embracing AI
means embracing, continuous, improve.
Here are the some
screenshots from my article.
You can find more details and findings
in my articles, which is published with
the title, artificial Intelligence for
Store Assistance Exploring the integration
of AI and ML in retail environments.
My journals, articles are available
on research and Google Scholar.
Thank you so much for.
Thank you.
One second.