Hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
In this video I'm gonna talk about
revolutionizing the data management the
role of AI optimized block storage in
the exponential enterprise data growth.
So traditionally, the block
storage systems have operated
with static configurations and
manual management approaches.
However the recent growth in
the data volume and velocity
has exposed the limitations in
these conventional approaches.
The artificial intelligence optimized
block storage represents a transf shift.
Leveraging the machine learning algorithms
and advanced analytics to create an
intelligent and self-optimizing systems
that can handle the exponential growth
of enterprise data, which is projected
to go up to once of unstructured
structured and block storage data by 2025.
Let's see more about the data
growth challenge that the IT
industry is currently facing.
So the modern storage infrastructure is
facing and very complex challenge as the
volumes expanded unprecedented rates.
So the enterprise data
centers are undergoing.
A big transformation both in scale and
complexity with the global data sphere.
Not merely growing, but exploring
exponentially creating an immediate
need for and adaptive solutions.
Three, three key sectors be it healthcare
industry and manufacturing industry With
iot generated telemetry and financial
institutions with transaction records
and compliance documentations are at
the top most forefront for this data.
Critical applications are stringent.
Their medic, their mission
critical applications are stringent
and regulatory requirement.
Their mission critical applications
and regulatory requirements, demand
storage solutions that go beyond
traditional approaches, caring for
intelligence driven architecture that
can anticipate growth patterns and
optimize the resources dynamically.
So this, the, one of the solutions for
this data growth challenges are artificial
intelligence driven, storage management,
evolution integrating artificial
intelligence into storage architectures.
I. Brings a fundamental shift in the
enterprise data management strategy.
The modern artificial intelligence
enhance the storage systems continuously
monitor, analyze and performance.
Analyze the performance metrics
so significantly reduces the time
required for management, operational,
and troubleshooting tasks.
Let's talk about how artificial
intelligence and its predictive analytics
framework bring us like, the extra
benefits the artificial intelligence
optimized block storage systems.
I. Employ sophisticated they
have a sophisticated predictive
analytics that revolutionize the
enterprise data management by analy.
By analyzing this predictive
analytics, what it does is
it analyzes the historical.
Usage patterns and workload
characteristics and
infrastructure telemetry.
These intelligent systems
generate actionable insights
in real time applications.
This predictive analytics capability
dramatically improves the storage
utilization rates from an industry
average of 48% to 72% while reducing
the procurement cost up to 35%.
Through precision capacity planning
and intelligence resource allocation,
intelligent data tiering architecture.
A driven storage systems implemented
sophisticated multi-tiered architectures
that automatically optimizes optimize data
placement based upon the access patterns
and also the performance requirements.
This intelligent approach to data tiering
has delivered substantial benefits.
In both cost efficiency and performance
with the organizations achieving storage
cost reduction between most of the
organization has achieved a cost reduction
between 19 to up to 30, 37 percentage.
This intelligent data tiering is
applied on a hybrid storage where the
storage system has 15 to have five to
15% of high performance storage disks.
Rest of them with a mix of standard sssts
and, high capacity storage drives and also
in archival storage with cheaper cost.
So what we, what this intelligent
data tiering does is it combines the
whole storage as a single package, and
then these intelligent all algorithms
will move the data between different
tiers based upon the usage and based
upon the performance requirements.
Performance optimization engine.
So the modern artificial intelligence
driven storage system employ a
sophisticated optimization engines
that continuously monitor and
adapt to changing the workloads.
These autonomous systems represent
a significant evolution in storage
management, simultaneously analyzing
and adjusting multiple configuration
parameters in the real time.
Let's see more about let's see.
What are the implementation challenges
implementation challenges in achieving
this AI driven storage solution?
Multi-layered MO in multi-layered
monitoring, combining the infrastructure
level metrics with application
performance data to create a holistic
view of the system behavior, enhancing
the accuracy of predictive models.
And optimization decisions and higher
in high resolution performance tracking,
capturing detailed metrics through agent
based and agentless collection methods.
Enabling precision correlation of
events across the technology stack of
early detection and potential issues.
Block level meta data collection.
Gathering a detailed operational data
includes the timestamps, operation
types performance metrics through
distributed collection mechanisms to
identify subtle patterns and anomalies
and multi-stage data processing.
Employing a local aggregation and
adaptive sampling techniques with
edge processing capabilities to
optimize a bandwidth utilization.
While preserving analytical capabilities.
Let's see more about implementing
strategies, using machine learning
techniques under supervised
learning particularly effective
in predictive failure analysis.
These models analyze patterns in
device health metrics to identify
potential hardware failures
before they impact operations.
The accuracy of these predictions
show continuous improvements.
As the models incorporate more
historical failure data and
refine their future selection.
Unsupervised learning excel set
identifying and adapting to evolving
workload patterns by analyzing iwo
characteristics, including request
size read and write ratios and
temporal patterns this capability
proves especially valuable.
In dynamic environments where new
applications are frequently deployed
with changing requirements, reinforcement
learning enables continuous optimization
of complex storage parameters by treating
storage management as decision process.
Evaluation, evaluating actions
based on their impact on
system performance metrics.
This approach has shown particular
success in environments with changing
workload characteristics, often
discovering optimization strategies
that surpasses traditional approaches.
Let's see how an enterprise environment
strategize in, integrate in, in, in
the machine learning integration.
So the storage virtualization layer
creates an abstract creating an
abstraction layer that gradually
introduces artificial inter
intelligence optimization capabilities
alongside existing storage systems,
allowing organizations to target
specific workloads for optimization.
While maintaining an existing
operations for less critical systems.
We can also have an API based integration.
Leveraging API Connections to coordinate
storage optimization with broader IT
automation frameworks, ensuring storage
optimization storage optimizations align
with overall operational objectives.
While enabling automated responses
to changing application requirements,
a phased approach, also a phased
approach which is like beginning with
monitoring an analytics functions before
enabling automated actions, allowing
organizations to validate model accuracy
and build operational confidence with
maintaining a clear fallback procedures.
Let's see how organizations benefit
economically and operat operationally.
A optimized block storage deployments
has brought in a remarkable advantage
in resource utilization and total cost
of ownership in enterprise environments.
Modern AI driven storage
systems excel at optimizing.
Capacity allocation through continuous
monitoring and analysis of usage patterns.
The operational benefits extend well
beyond cost reduction and encompassing
significant improvements in reliability
and performance consistency.
Advance in monitoring systems track
hundreds of performance metrics
simultaneously enabling early detection
of any potential issues before.
They impact a critical service.
I.
With the current trend seeing industry
seeing the challenges with the data
growth and data management the future
of the enterprise storage will be.
Should be based out of a transform, should
have a transformation transformative
approach like a optimize artificial
intelligence optimized storage.
With the fundamental shift in managing
the increasing complexity of enterprise
data environments, embedding intelligence
throughout the storage infrastructure.
With proactive operations where
organizations can shift from
reactive to proactive operational
models, significantly enhancing
resource utilization system
reliability, and staff productivity.
And this has to be like like a
virtuous cycle, a synergistic
relationship where storage system
systems support AI workloads.
While being enhanced through artificial
intelligence enabling organizations
to manage a growing data complexity
while improving business outcomes.
Thank you.
I hope everyone has enjoyed
this talk and thank you so much.