Hello everyone.
My name is Ravinder.
Today I'm going to discuss about the
driving sustainability environmental
benefits of our efficient power
molding in vehicle software.
So today I'm going to a little
bit about the, how the vehicles
are using the power in both
electrical and convention vehicles.
Hope you will enjoy the content.
Let's get started.
Start with me.
I'm a one of the top automotive
industry in General Motors as
an advanced entertainment system
engineer, Christian engineer.
I was working in past 12 years in
in the same automotive field but
the different different backgrounds
embedded software engineer and then
firmware engineer, and then integration
engineer, entertainment engineer.
Different roles.
But but all are in automotive industry.
Let's get into that details and
then, let's get into the poor
poor management system and yeah.
Sure.
First thing, let's talk
about the basic things.
In in vehicle means
there are so many issues.
Issues means electronics control unit.
So each electronic control unit
manages particular function.
So let's suppose body control model.
It operates like, it's to maintain the
lighting and then break and then, the.
And the the body related things
it controls those things.
And then there are couple of, there
are around like, 16 to 32 eecs
in the in particular car, depends
upon the vehicle manufacturer.
Each ECU is operating differently, like
one ECU is using less power one use one.
Like other EC needs a
constant requirement.
Power to operate it, the
operated or perform the actions.
In order to con, in order to reduce
the power and then we need to minimize
those power consumption each ECU.
And we will talk about more
into the coming slides.
But yeah, that is the basic thing.
And then the battery life cycle.
So inefficient power molding
power management leads to
a shorter battery life.
You like, when you charge the
vehicle, it it was like, two 80
miles, but in the next day without
driving your car, but your battery.
Got shorter to a two 70 next day because
of you don't know what happens, what with
the difference because of, there are so
many operations running on the background.
So these are the issues.
Consume the power and then
run the background things.
And then there is another
thing is different power state.
We are guy we are we are going to discuss
the, in the propulsion and then run
and sleep and then, different different
power modes we are going to talk about.
And then how the.
Different acs, electronic control
units are using when you are,
when the vehicle is in sleep.
So we will get into these details.
These are the basic things we'll
get more into depth into the things.
Yeah.
So how the power molding works.
So the first question is
how the power molding works.
So power molding means there are different
kinds of power mode so whether power is
using the battery when you are driving
that is power used by your regular usage
and then the vehicle is sleeping, sleep.
When you are parked in your garage
garage and then vehicle is no longer
using, but still using the power.
That's the problem with that with
the electronic control units.
So they are constantly require
power to operate internally.
So that's where the power molding has
any different kinds like, whether it's
operated in sleep mode, operated in a
run mode, operated in a propulsion mode.
Propulsion means when you are
driving that is the propulsion.
So there are a couple of things.
So environmental sensing and then real
time analysis and dynamic adjustment,
and then continuous optimization.
So these are the four steps
we need to we need to discuss.
First thing is environmental sensing.
Vehicle systems monitor usage patterns,
driver behavior, and then environmental
conditions based on that one.
The power mode got adjusted.
When you are like, drive the vehicle to.
To speed too accelerated, too a
accelerated too frequently or then
the power consumption gonna be high.
And then based on your driving behavior,
the power consumption got changed.
And then there is an real time analysis.
How your how your vehicle is operated
different power states each component
which each component using the
how much power in the real time.
When you got the data from the
vehicle and then you'll analyze.
That is the second step.
And then third step is dynamic adjustment.
Once you got the data, once you
driver behavior, and then you know,
environment, condition of the vehicle,
and then you got any real time data
of that power power power molding.
After that vehicle and then you can
adjust the ECU or ECU EU Power a CU,
power between the two different issues
are like, how much power using when
you, when the vehicle is slipped,
so you can adjust based on that one.
And then the fourth step
is continuous optimization.
Once you are done with that all
this real time analysis and dynamic
adjustment, then the last step is
how the how to reduce your power.
Maximize the efficiency.
So that is the fourth step.
You need to be we need
to be work on that one.
So let's talk about the
quantity, quantifiable benefits
of electrical vehicles.
So nowadays so many vehicles are
in vehicles are using the battery.
Battery power.
If some manufacturers are like, hey we are
like, 500 miles per full charge but that
doesn't mean like it's 400 miles drive.
See the drive drive straight
because of there are so many
functions running on the background.
Let's suppose HVAC.
The AC and the heat.
So when you are turning on the ac,
the battery gonna be, reduced to
five percentage, two percentage
based on your driving behavior.
So let's talk about the
quantifiable benefits.
So first thing is energy efficiency gain.
Overall consumption of the power.
How the power you have an a
hundred percent discharge then
energy efficiency gain means how
your power consumption is going.
With your behavior, driving behavior,
and then range extension increase the
driving range in when you are driving in
a highway or without breaks or with breaks
or you are a sudden increase the speed.
So that is also your your power
management guard adjusted.
And then third one is battery lifespan.
Like most of the manufacturer are
suggesting 80% is of charge because of,
if you charge a hundred percentage every
time, the battery gonna be depleted.
And then so the power molding
is you want to maximize maximum
extension of battery life.
That's the goal of this one.
And then and then the
driver gonna be enjoy.
And then long, long drivers.
So that's the basic thing to
of the power molding model.
So let's talk about the impact
on the convention vehicle.
So in the previous slide we were talking
about the electrical vehicles, and then
now we are talking about the convention
vehicles, how the conventional vehicles
are, independent of the battery.
So when you fill fill the gas and
then, you, you need to be care care
about the fuel consumption, and then
CT emissions, and then the component
lifespan and then maintenance intervals.
So these are the things you need to be
con consider on the convention vehicles.
In the fuel consumption reduce reduction
of two to four percentage and savings up
to one 10 kg of CO2 annual labor vehicle.
So with the power consumption,
because of, if you are using the,
too much of power molding power
molding means too much of power in the
vehicle, so you need to burn the gas.
Hi.
So that's, that is another thing.
And then environmental impact.
So what are the environmental benefits
when you when you are working on the power
molding model or like in a power molding?
Reduce the power molding, in the vehicle.
So the direct emission reduction, like
the first thing is you you reduce the
fuel consumption, that is the first thing.
And the more more efficient
operations in the vehicle.
And then extended component life
cycles you reduce the re reduce the
battery, you reduce the power and
then increase the battery lifespan.
And then the battery the battery
gonna be sufficient for your needs.
And then manufacturing footprint
fuel replacement parts needed
throughout the vehicle.
Life.
Because of, you are reducing
the less power of the vehicle.
And then vehicle is vehicle is more
sufficient and then efficiently run
pro your vehicle life and then resource
consumption, lower demand after raw
materials and in battery production.
So the you are ultimately you are
saving the battery and as well
as the battery raw materials.
So that is the another
benefit of this power moving.
So implementation.
In the previous slides we were talking
about the how the bad electrical EVs
EVs are doing, and then convention
vehicles are doing, and then now
talking about the implementation, how.
We are going to implement
this power molding with the
efficient power mold model.
So first thing is vehicle preparation.
So software updates are updates
installed across around five
or fleet test fleet vehicles.
So that is test fleet vehicles.
And then, eU from their upgrades.
So these are the different
power consumption.
Power consumption when you, when
the vehicle is sleep when there
is an O OT upgrade or the air
update from the manufacturer.
But you don't want to install
right away when you are driving,
but you but the vehicle needs.
That is a critical update.
You need to update it as soon as possible.
Then the only way is during
vehicle sleep vehicle sleep, the
automatically trigger that update,
and then it automatically updated.
And then the third one is, the
second one is up EC ware upgrades.
When the ECU needs a critical update
update for your functionality, for
your safety, or for the infotainment
changes or anything any major
changes the manufacturer send it or
their update to upgrade your ware.
That needs to be power as well,
like for when the vehicle is asleep.
And then the power management
protocol integration.
So that is the that is the another
one, the third one when the when
the power is consumption by the
vehicle, when the vehicle is in sleep.
So we need to monitor that one.
So that is another one.
And then so algorithm algorithm
optimization based on the fleet data.
And then driving pattern recognition
and environmental adoption.
So these are the implementation
of refinement of the per mode and
then the monitoring pre period.
How long you gonna be monitored this,
power mode let's suppose collect the
data for 12 months of data and then
check the data, how, which issues
are con, con consuming more power.
And then after that you get
the data and then you get the
regular checks and everything.
And then you need to verify the data.
The comprehensive performance analysis
and then energy conjunction patterns.
You get all the components and then you
will, you'll find out like, what need
to be improved, what is you consume?
The more power which way we
need to reduce that power that.
That, that is this case study.
The case study is completed.
Then the technical
implementation challenges.
So once you got the data and then
and then you have an everything
what you are supposed to do.
So first thing is system
integration complexity.
So in in the first slide we were
talking and we were talking.
Talking about so the vehicle means
there are so many number of eec each
ECU perform different operations.
So each ECU communicated with
the different EC as well.
And then so creating a unified power
mode model is very difficult because
of, one ECU consume less power.
Another ECU consume more power
because de depends upon their usage.
And then, and then cross function
cross platform compatibility.
How the, whether the EECS is need to be
interacted with outside of the world.
Let's suppose telecommunication model
needs to be interacted with career
servers and like an at t. And then
the each e issue has a different
suppliers are like, different mechanism.
So we need to coordinate that.
That is the first one.
And then safety critical system.
So some of the critical safety critical
system when the vehicle is theft, so
you need to be the the, that particular
issue need to be a awake during the
safety critical operations or when the
accident happens though, or when the
when the, when somebody o open the,
your drawer when you are not there.
So those kind of situations the
particular you needs to be very active
and then need to be triggered The.
Safety alarms.
And then as well as the, you need to
be A-S-O-I-S-O 2 6 2 6 2 functional
safety standard must be maintained.
So these are the functional main
maintain, you need to be maintained.
And then legacy.
Hardware constraints.
Older vehicle platforms may lack
of lack the necessary hardware to
support and advance power states.
And retrofit, retrofitting capabilities
and request careful hardware
software code design may increase
the initial implementation costs.
So these are the technical challenges.
So we were facing, standards
and industry collaboration.
So this is another thing.
So what so there are the
functional safety ISO requirement.
That is a 2 6 2 6 2.
Establish the safety requirements
for both electrical and convention
vehicles in the automobile, ensuring
the power moving transition to don't
compromise their critical function.
Just we were discussing like,
when the vehicle is theft or
when the vehicle is not located
like, somebody stole the vehicle.
You need to be you need
the particular issue.
You need to be active
every, each and every time.
When the vehicle is also slipped,
that is the 2 6 2 6 2 functional
safety requirement assist.
And then the, another
thing is partnership.
Standardizes the software architecture
for the ECU Port management.
When you designing the designing the ECU,
you need to be care about the, how the.
How the ECUs are functioning, and then
how the ECU power molding are designing.
That need to be discussed earlier.
And then you need to be enabling
the inter interability between the
different manufacturer and suppliers.
Manufacturing suppliers need to be
a partner partnership to understand
the understand the requirements of
that particular power molding and
then as well as the how this whether
you need to be compromised or not.
Based on the functions they
perform that particular issue.
And then the another one
is cybersecurity standard.
So cybersecurity is unauthorized control
of that vehicle or prevent unauthorized
usage of that vehicle or security concern.
So those are the things you need to be
aware you need to be active every time.
So those are the
cybersecurity requirements.
And then you need to be.
Every time must be on.
And then cross industry working groups,
collaborative efforts between the
automotives and semiconductor and software
industries to develop next next generation
for next generation management solution.
These are the these are the
one we need to be focused on.
So these are the different kind
of industry collaboration things.
We are working on that.
And then future
opportunities and directions.
So current power mode model discrete power
states based on the predefined conditions.
And then the next phase gonna
be a driven optimization.
A looking into that power
power management thing.
And then see that, okay, this this
is, you can consume more power.
Why, if it is, if this is necessary, yes.
If it is necessary, yes,
you can use that power.
If it is not necessary, then
stop that ECU to use the power
and then shut down that ECU.
This is the next level
of a driven optimization.
And then V two X vehicle
to other vehicle to charge.
Vehicle to vehicle.
So these are the vehicle to x integration,
poor management control with the
infrastructure and other vehicles.
So these are the next level, and
then distributed in intelligence.
So autonomous power decisions at
individual or component level whether
the the issue decide itself whether I
need to be wake up or sleep or like you
don't use the power is this necessary
operation to perform right now.
Yes or no, based on the decision,
it auto autonomously taking the
decision by the ECU and based on your
program, it automatically change the
change the power model condition.
So the.
The final take key
takeaways and next steps.
So the first thing is
significant environmental impact.
So when the power management is
properly properly organized or
properly maintained in the software
level, vehicle software level.
So you need to be environmental the.
The vehicle is environmentally benefited.
And then a power molding delivers
miserable emissions reductions
resource con conservation across both
electrical and conventional platform.
With the potential and exp exponential
impact when the applied rate scale you are
produce millions of vehicles each year.
But you need to be.
More careful carefully about the
power moving because of, each vehicle
consumption vehicle con power consumption
with impact, so many emissions.
So that is the first step.
And then a software
driven solution so that.
That's where we are working on that.
Unlike hardware based efficiency
improvements, power Moding leverages
a software innovation that can
be deployed rapidly across the
existing vehicle platforms through
updates and providing immediate
sustainable benefits like, whether the
particular software, particular VCs,
consumption more so why it is more
then you need to be we need to be no.
Software that capable whether
the it is necessary use, use that
particular particular operation.
Yes, if it is necessary,
then use that power.
Otherwise just stop it and then just
don't use the power and then are
like, low or more just too minimal.
Power using our, so that's
the software driven solution.
And then industry standardization.
And then the advanced standardized
approach to power management will
accelerate the adoption of and
maximum environmental benefits
across all the automotive industries.
Require, continue continuing the
collaboration between the manufacturer,
suppliers and then regulatory bodies.
So these are the steps.
We need to be gave take care otherwise.
If the too much power consumption by
the vehicle, then it's gonna be, it's
gonna be du depletion the battery.
And then there are so many disadvantages.
So that's why the power power
management is a key component
for the vehicle manufacturers.
Hope you are enjoy this presentation.
Thank you so much.
If you have any questions, reach out
to me over the email or are linking.
Thank you so much.
Bye.