Hello and welcome.
I will be talking to you about AI in
the fast lane, how we can use smart
traffic systems to unclog our cities.
This way we can use intelligent technology
to revolutionize urban transport.
First couple of things about me.
My name is Ara Del.
I have been working as an engineering
manager for the last seven years.
I have worked in various technical
roles for the last 13 years in the
automotive, FinTech and tech industries.
I have worked four years in automated
driving and I have an electrical computer
engineering degree a PhD in the field with
focus on multi objective optimization.
And I have a degree in education.
Throughout my career, I have
been mentoring and trying to grow
professionally, computer engineers.
And fun fact, before switching to the
industry, I was working as a teacher.
I was teaching for seven years.
But let's yeah, let's look into.
More detail and what we
will be discussing today.
First, I will touch a bit on
what the current challenges are
in traffic management systems.
Then I will discuss a bit how we can use
software agents and smart traffic systems.
Then I will touch briefly on
what the required infrastructure
would be to be able to implement.
So it's a system.
And finally, I will present what
the benefits can be of using
ai driven traffic management.
Let's get started then.
So what are the challenges?
I'm sure everyone has faced, if
not all of them, most of them,
and everyone is familiar with 'em.
First we do have an
increase in congestion.
Yeah, congestion is rising in urban areas.
We have cities being overpopulated,
population is growing, and this also
leads to the increase in vehicle
usages, and this leads to longer
commute times and congestion,
the infrastructure in our cities.
It is often inadequate.
This can happen either because it's
outdated and it hasn't been maintained
for some time, or because it was not
built to withstand all the pressure it
feels now with all the vehicles and all
the road users that increase in number.
I already mentioned that we have
a growing number of vehicles.
This doesn't happen with the
same rate in every country in the
world, or every city in the world.
But the trend is still increasing
and this poses significant challenges
to the traffic management systems.
This all this also generates the other
problem when we have traffic events.
Usually our reaction is delayed.
Our systems are too slow.
Usually some human needs to
detect something and some
human needs to intervene, and
that can take a lot of time.
So the result is lost time, lost
fuel, or other type of cost, and
most importantly, lost lives.
But what if.
We didn't have to have such
a traffic management system.
What if every car and traffic
light was an intelligent agent?
What if they could negotiate, adapt, and
optimize their behavior in real time?
That is the idea behind the
decentralized traffic intelligence.
Let's, I'll look into
it a little bit more.
How would we use software agents?
In a smart traffic system?
There would be mobile agents that
would correspond to the vehicles,
and then in the intersections
we would have stationary agents.
Each of them makes decisions
based on local context mostly.
However, if we feel that there's
a need for that, we can use
more centralized optimizations.
And more centralized policies so
that we can try to optimize for the
broader urban area not just locally.
And this is the, a more system
which stands for adaptive multi
objective, optimized routing agents,
optimize for time, distance, cost
emissions, or any other objective
that one might thing makes sense.
The agents bid for road segments based
on current values of these objectives.
And the routes evolve continuously
as the traffic changes.
So in more detail, a vehicle approaches
a decision point, like an intersection.
It requests a potential next step
from the nearby stationary agents.
Each stationary agent.
Calculates a bit a cost estimate for
using the road segments over route.
It proposes for the vehicle to
take based on the current data.
Then the vehicle evaluates all bids using
its weighted objective function and its
selects the lowest cost next step, which
is the best trade off among the priorities
we have selected to optimize by.
How is the bid negotiation happening?
So the vehicle agent sends the route
request to the nearby stationary
agents, plus the wage for each objective
to optimize the stationary agent.
Then accesses segment
data for each objective.
And depending on the data freshness
or staleness, it may calculate
or update expected values.
For the segments of the potential
routes for the different objectives
that we want to optimize by then the
stationary agent will normalize the
values for each of these segments.
It'll calculate the cost per segment
using the weighted objective function,
which in the case of three objectives that
are time, distance, and monetary cost.
The cost of the segment
would be the weight.
All the time, multiplied by the normalized
time, the weight of the distance
multiplied by the normalized distance
and the weight of the cost multiplied
by the normalized monetary cost.
So the stationary agent will
calculate the possible routes
and that the pico can take.
As mentioned, the cost of each route would
be the sum of the cost of each segments.
The stationary agent bid will be
the cost of the lowest route cost,
and this will be the route that it
would be recommending to the vehicle.
So the vehicle selects and follows the
initial segments of the lowest bid route.
Then the process continues with
re-planning as the vehicle moves.
The vehicle reevaluates the
options, every few steps.
Why this happens because
conditions can change.
Like we can have congestion
present that wasn't there before.
We can have an accident or some other type
of emergency can occur, so the stationary
agents at the next step or some steps
forward could potentially suggest better
alternatives based on the new conditions.
And this allows for real time
rerouting and self adaptation.
Let's see how the big generation
process would work for yeah,
three objectives monitored.
So we would require a route, we would
query the database for the network segment
data, we would get the segments for.
For the different routes
that we could take.
We would estimate the expected
traffic vehicle speed for these
segments of the road network.
And then we would be creating our
network graph using the distance,
time, and cost in this case where
we have these three objectives.
Yeah.
And the waves would be according
to the profile provided.
We can use some algorithm to figure
out which one of the potential
routes would be the optimal.
It would be Dextra or it could be some
other more sophisticated potentially.
And then we would see if a
route exists, then we would.
Calculate the bid and
send it to the vehicle.
If it doesn't exist, then we would
send some negative value and then the
vehicle would select the lowest positive
value that we could get as a bid.
And let's see what happens next.
So we said a route exists.
If it doesn't exist, we cannot
go to the place we wanted.
So there's nothing to do.
If route does exist, then we receive
a list of the next nodes that we
need to go through and then we
start our journey and we see is the
next road congested or is the list.
All the next nodes
complete after this one.
If not, then we move to the next
node and then we check if the next
node is our target node or not.
If it is a target node or it's our
destination, yay, everyone is happy.
If not, then we move to the next node
after that, and then we check again.
Is our node list complete?
Have we been through all of them,
or is there some type of emergency
or congestion in the next node?
If there is some emergency or
congestion or the list is not complete,
we initiate an auction again, and
then the process continues until
we finally reach our destination.
Here's a conceptual diagram
of how this would work.
You can see vehicle agents, you
can see different type of mobile
agents like the vehicles, emergency
vehicles, public transport, and so on.
And you also see the stationary agents.
We do collect real time traffic
data, and it can be that stationary
agents can also exchange data.
In case it will improve their
estimations for the values that they will
provide for the different objectives.
So what I did was tried to run
some simulations to see how
effective such a system would be.
So I used the net logo simulation
environment and I run lots of simulations.
A few hundreds with different
scenarios that included cases where
there was congestion, emergencies,
different type of vehicles and so on.
And this happened for some fixed distance.
And this is the results I got.
So for the same distance,
I compared three different.
Approaches.
One is this normal routing distance base.
You try to find the route with
a minimum distance and then
you execute that same thing.
You try to execute the route, you find
this time using multi objective routing so
you can optimize for different objectives.
But once you, decide on some route
initially, then you execute it to the end.
And then the third approach is the
amor approach where you do optimize
for different objectives, but you do
dynamic re-planning every sum nodes
or as discussed when there is some
type of change, like an emergency or
congestion that wasn't present before.
What we see is that.
The cost, monetary cost, when you have the
multi objective approaches, the dynamic
and non-dynamic re-planning is more
or less the same, but it is lower than
planning route based on distance only.
And then we have a shorter travel time,
using multi objective optimization than we
would have optimizing based on distance.
And we have even shorter duration
of the travel when we do the dynamic
re-planning with the amor system.
And we can finally see that there's
really a huge difference in how much.
Our trip duration would increase if we
suddenly get consistent in the traffic.
So there is some slight difference
between the distance based approach
and the multi objective approach, but a
more with dynamic or planning is really
shining there with less than 20% of the
increase compared to the other methods.
And that's all very nice.
What would we need to actually
realize this in our roads?
First, we would need V two
Xen enabled infrastructure.
For those that are not familiar with
V two X, it means vehicle to anything
and it allows vehicles to communicate
with each other with different traffic
elements like smart traffic lights.
Or smart traffic signs, which
can adapt what they display.
And even with mobile phones potentially
so the vehicle could communicate
with the pedestrian that comes behind
the building in the next block.
So you could really see and understand
how the environment around you is.
Besides the smart traffic lights and
the adaptive road signs, we would
also have the roadside units, which
would be the stationary agents.
So from the vehicle side.
Vehicles would obviously need to
be V two X capable and the vehicles
would be running the actual app.
The agents that they would use
in order to to their smart road
planning and communicate with
the rest of the infrastructure.
On the cloud and edge layer level
we would need local road terminals.
This would enable a fast computation
and assuming we want to have some
centralized overview of the traffic
and potentially use this to do a more
centralized planning, we would need
a city traffic management center.
What assumptions are we making?
So we're making the assumption that
the map of the environment is known.
So the vehicles do not do continuous,
an online localization and mapping.
They know the map of
their environment already.
The road segments may have
tolls or different charges.
We do have available historical traffic
data and we continuously collect as the
system is online, additional ones and
the vehicles know their global position.
Okay.
We talked about everything,
but what's the benefit?
What would we gain out of this?
We have seen a few things based on
the simulation results, and this
allows us to to estimate that this
would make it easier to optimize
traffic flow B two X enabled traffic.
Signs and lights also play a role
in this because you can change
the signal timings based on the
traffic and reduce the delays.
AI driven systems that analyze in
real time the traffic data play an
important role in enabling this.
This would also help
us reduce bottlenecks.
Both because we would try to optimize
traffic flow, but we would also
potentially redirect traffic and
through different routes that would
enable them to have a smoother
journey and less congestion.
And all of this would lead to sort
travel times which in our current urban,
our current environment in our urban
cities would make a big difference
for a lot of people that have to
travel for a significant amount of
time, spend some time on the road they
could spin it in something potentially
much more pleasant and productive.
Besides this, using the ai driven
traffic management system, we could
have improvements with respect to road
safety or how we prioritize our traffic.
For example, when we have real
time yeah, road closers something
happens, we can rear out our traffic.
Smart systems will enable us.
To do this in a faster way and
this will optimize traffic flow.
And this would also help reduce potential
accidents when there is a road blockage.
We could also manage traffic in a
priority based way so we can dynamically
prioritize different actors and like
public transferred or emergency services.
And in the case of an emergency,
we could even help ambulances
negotiate some green wave access.
So they get they get priority and they
can go fast where they need to be.
And finally, there are also environmental
benefits and reduced emissions.
We have a smoother traffic flow.
This leads to reduced congestion but also
we don't have this stop and go traffic
all the time as the traffic is smoother.
And this enables vehicles
to consume less energy.
Emit less CO2.
And this also improves the
air quality in our cities.
Thank you very much.
Please share also your thoughts,
your views, or how you envision
traffic management in the future.
Thank you.