Speaker 19: hi.
I am pa and today I'll talk about a
practical problem that many developers
face when orchestrating workflows.
It's time consuming flows that fail late.
Imagine a flow that takes 30 minutes or
two hours to complete, and you only learn
that it's going to fail after the fact.
It fails.
The question is then what if
we can predict that the flow is
going to fail after the first or
second minute of it's running?
And can we do something about it, like
a board reroute or warn the developer
ideally with a reason why the flow failed?
And this is what this talk is about using.
Early science and signals inside Perfect.
To predict risk before the
expensive work starts, very quickly.
Perfect is a workflow orchestrator,
as I said previously in
which you can define a flow.
It's a. Basic entity of prefect
and it consists of tasks.
Basically task is a unit of work and
the cool features of prefect are that
it's allowing to schedule task that
can implement retries caching of flows.
And you can see the execution of
flows in the UI and you can interact
in d ui with this flows expand.
Collapse.
You can also see the parameters, logs,
timings, and failures of the flows.
And the reason perfect matters for
this project is that it sits at
the perfect point of the system.
So right at the start of the flow.
Perfect.
Already knows a lot about
what's going to happen.
It knows the parameters, the
environment, and meta metadata.
And after the first task or second
task, we can cheaply compute the
quality fingerprints of data and
collect earlier runtime signals.
So instead of waiting for the expensive
stage to burn the compute, we can
generate the score of the risk.
It's going to fail early in the system.
And perfect has mechanisms that allow
us to take action on this score.
So to keep this to keep things
concrete, I'll define failure as
an SLA breach just for simplicity.
And we just going to explore this
particular definition of failure.
So the SLAs, when the runtime
exceeds certain threshold, and
that's a common operational pain.
And we want a prediction.
Of that event early in the
system, ideally on the runtime
sorry, on, on the submit time.
And if we can predict earlier, we can do
not just alerting, but we can do other
things like completely stop the run or
maybe, request a better machine that's
used these particular parameters, and we
can then distribute the compute better.
Or we can simply yeah, fail and tell
the developer what exactly went wrong.
And that allows us to develop
in much quicker cycles.
In this particular presentation, I'm
going to talk about a financial setting.
Specifically portfolio risk
computation and the flow.
Looks like this.
So we generate a metrics of returns.
The first step, then compute some
statistics, and after that there's a
heavy step that needs to be predicted
if it's going to fail or not.
It's a covar estimation
and some other simulations.
So we exploit the fact that
useful signals exist earlier.
At flow start, we already know.
Some of the data which are number of
assets number of days, simulations, and
other metrics like data quality measuring.
Also we know the version of the code,
which is going to impact how we use
these parameters in our calculations.
And after the first step is completed.
We can compute metrics for returns
and measure the time that it
took to calculate the first step.
So in the end, I have defined 11 fields
to form the feature vector and I don't
use anything after the heavy step.
So only this 11, then.
Right after the first task, we can run
inference to get the probability that our
runtime of heavy step will breach the SLA.
And we attach the score to the
run and we can lock the top
drivers for in interpretability.
So the top features that
contributed to this prediction.
And only after that we can proceed to the.
Now we run an actual perfect flow,
end-to-end, and the first task
generates correlated returns, injects
the missing values and outliers,
and computes chip statistics.
Then they have a task does
the real CPU work, and this is
where we can avoid wasting time.
And the parameters are not just
linearly contributing to the runtime.
So it's just the synthetic setup to
test how we can learn models to predict
more closely to what is in production.
While this is synthetic, but the
idea is to show how can this apply?
How can this be applied to perfect and to
actual production system, which involve
non-linear, non-linear workflow behavior.
When it comes to model choice cat Boost
is a natural pick for this task because
this is a classic Tableau risk modeling.
We have mixed numerical features plus.
Some categorical features such as code,
version and cat boost tends to be a strong
peak here because it involves minimal
pre-processing and it can learn non-linear
interactions between features naturally.
So I benchmark it against
a list of other models.
With the exact data and feature set.
So I use logistic regression random
forest xj, boost the histogram, gradient
boosting, and just to have a sanity check.
I also include a rule in which we just cut
this threshold on a particular feature.
And for.
Validation I use rock ho metric and for
interpret interpretation of predictions.
I use shop to explain why individual
columns contribute to the prediction and
how can we signal that to developers.
Basically.
I have done some testing of the system
and I have run the system 5,000 times to
get the data and I've created a dataset
in which the SLA you speak the way.
That we have balanced classes of
failures and success EV events.
And after training and testing on
the holdout set this is the leader
leaderboard that you can see.
So the cat boost is the best
model and it's course around
zero point 87 on rock oak.
And we see that other boosting models also
score quite, high risk sorry, high scores.
And also logistic regression is
also scoring above 80% on rock oak.
A risk score alone isn't enough in our
case because in practice we want to.
Tell developers why this particular
run is going to fail because.
If we know this information, we
can click quickly understand if
we're missing something in the
either input data or in the code.
So we can compute per run explanations.
In this example, the model predicted
about 95% risk score before the
heavy task with the shop and the.
Explanation of particular, features that
contributed to this score at listed here.
So in this case the returns had
more extreme spikes than normal.
And that make a variance
simulation less stable and also
a lot of values are missing.
Had to be filled during the first step,
which also contributed to instability.
And this explain, this explanation
can immediately suggest developers
actions as I talked previously.
Okay, so this is the UI of Perfect and
as in dashboard, it looks like that.
And it shows latest runs as you can see
now, we have 13,000 runs because I used to
train models and generate data for that.
And if we go to deployments, we can see
there are successful try two deployments.
One is for successful runs and one for.
Failures and the difference is between
only parameters that are provided to the
runs, but the underlying code is the same.
So we go to successful run, we can
trigger a new run like that, and if we go
inside, we should be able to monitor it.
And at the moment, it's
pending, so it'll start soon.
If we click into parameters, we can
see we have numerical parameters and
the categorical one, such as version.
We see that the model here is used.
The model we use here is a Cabos model,
and now we see that the run is completed.
We have the generation return step,
and then they heavy computation.
If we go to the logs, we can
see the run logs and the earlier
risk predicted is very low.
Doesn't pass the threshold.
That's why we didn't stop earlier.
So let's go into the second deployment
which is there is deployment.
And here we can look into the parameters
and see that there are different
and we also can trigger any run.
And see what, what will
happen in this case.
We have said here that it'll not fail.
On the model prediction by default.
So it should just tell us the probability
of breaching and it'll not stop.
It'll, as you can see,
continue the calculations here.
But, the, early risk prediction.
Prediction is very high.
It's above the threshold, so ideally
it should be stopped and we can see
the top drivers for our prediction.
Basically, we can use that for
interpretability and tell what
contributed to this prediction.
Yeah.
And that will run for
maybe minutes or two.
We can actually suspend
it, or let's cancel it.
And if we are going to set the
parameter to actually stop.
When the prediction is above threshold, we
can see that it's going to fail the run.
Let's see.
So we click into the new run.
Okay, so this is the run
that we have triggered.
And as you can see, it has failed.
And if we see the logs, we see
that earlier risk predicted.
Is high, it's about threshold.
We see the top drivers for that risk, and
we see that the model enabled prediction
breached because of this threshold.
That's why the run has failed.
So yeah, this is how it works.
So how do we actually take this from
a synthetic demo to a production flow?
That can actually change over time.
For that we need to take
into account that the code.
Can change and many regressions
are actually conditional.
The same inputs can be okay in the first
version of the code, and in the second
version of the code, they can fail.
So we need.
Information about the changes, and we
can get that either from Git commits
or from the Git itself, and we can use
the DAST and for reference, there are
such tools as conventional change log
or change distiller that looks into the
A ST. Also we need to roll out safely
start in shadow mode and roll out.
Only like features similar to
alerting, and only when it's safe
we can trigger the gating actuals.
Finally we need to monitor
the drift of the system.
We can log.
Predictions historically and the outcomes
that we took of these predictions.
And that gives us the loop to retrain
and calibrate these thresholds.
And we also should utilize the
sliding window for retraining
the model because we want to get
rid of our data to data points.
And in real world applications
that can actually also be used.
Cut and the pattern actually generalizes
beyond this synthetic financial example.
Actually any long running workflow
where failures are costly can
be used for example, ETL jobs.
Large batch scoring ML models training
or CI pipelines that fail after hours
and like scientific workflows that
need a lot of compute and CPU time.
And the action is broader
than just aborting.
Sometimes the best action is rerouting.
We can send the route that predicted
to fail on this particular machine
to a different worker pool.
We can reduce the workload and switch
to for example, good implementation
that we know it's gonna work.
And we can tell the engineers
what specific features
contributed to this dec decision.
Also SLA breaches is not just one
particular example of predictions.
Another very practical label
is retry success probability.
If a task fails should we
retry, will it succeed?
Or we are just likely to burn
some more compute if it won't
succeed, and we can predict the
probability of freeze dry success.
The main takeaway is that if you can
predict risk earlier, you can turn
perfect from just being a passive
orchestrator into an active control
loop so we can save compute on time
and make failures much easier to debug.
That's the main idea.
So yeah.
Thank you for your attention.