Speaker 10: Hello everyone.
My name is Kiran Ramana and I am
here today to share with you the
AI Readiness Blueprint, turning
ambiguity into opportunity.
As generative AI transitions from
conceptual exploration to enterprise
skill deployment, organizations
are facing critical challenges.
What we are seeing is the
most AI initiative failures.
Don't stem from technological
limitations, they stem from inadequate
organizational preparedness.
This framework that I will share with
you today transforms organizational
ambiguity into actionable opportunities
through sim, systematic assessment
and structured implementation.
So let's start with the problem.
The numbers are striking.
80% or more AI projects
fail to deliver value.
88% of AI pilots never reach production.
These are staggering failure rates,
but here is the core challenge.
Pilots pro.
The problem lies not in
technological capability.
We have amazing AI technology
today, but in organizational
preparedness, the fragmentation of
machine learning initiatives poses
a significant barrier to success.
What we see repeatedly is
isolated experiments that fail
to deliver, measured, measurable,
enterprise impact and scalability.
This comes down to three root causes.
First, fragmented data.
Disconnected data sources
prevent cohesive understanding.
Second, unclear ownership, lack
of defined responsibilities
causing delays and misalignment.
And third, the governance
inconsistent practices.
Jeopardizing model
reliability and quality.
Let's look at common failure patterns.
We see across organizations.
There are four patterns.
First, silo data.
Data ecosystems remain fragmented
and ungoverned across departments
preventing unified insights, the.
ML models lack comprehensive data
for accurate predictions leading
to biased or incomplete outputs.
Second misaligned teams across
functional cross-functional teams
operate with conflicting expectations
and unclear responsibilities.
This leads to style progress
due to confusion about who is
accountable for project success.
Third, lagging governance.
Risk management protocols simply can't
keep pace with rapid AI deployment
ambitions, limited oversight ize model,
real reliability, quality and compliance.
And fourth, it's pilot sprawl,
disconnected experiments, proliferate
without architectural coherence.
Our enterprise strategy, this results
in wastage, resources, technical
debts, and organizational AI fitting.
Here is the contrast.
Typical pilot programs include
siloed data, ad hoc processes,
and no path from pilot production.
A production ready organization has
a unified data platform, standard
standardized processes aligned with
business and scalable ML implementations.
So what's the root cause?
Organizations lack a framework.
Specifically, they lack four things.
First, structured readiness assessment.
No systematic way to
evaluate EA capabilities.
Second, stakeholder alignment,
business and tech teams work in silos.
Third optimizational parts, no clear
journey from pilot to production.
And fourth is governance
framework, missing accountability
and oversight structures.
This is the four steps.
The result.
Without a structured framework,
organizations face technical debt,
wasted resources, and ultimately
lost confident in AI initiatives.
What enterprises need is a comprehensive
readiness model, connecting
discovery through delivery with the
discipline governance at every stage.
So here is the solution,
the AI Readiness Blueprint.
This framework makes three
unique contribution first
collaborative workshops.
We transform assessment from a audit
activity into a collaborative code design
process, business leaders ML team, and.
Data owners work together to identify
constraints and define the roadmap,
the benefit, cross-functional
alignment from the outset.
Second stage gate governance.
We establish clear governance
checkpoints between maturity
stages, requiring demonstrated
competencies before progression.
There are structured review
gates at each milestone.
This s. Mature premature
scaling and technical debt.
Third pilot sprawl mitigation.
We codify readiness as measurable
progression across interdependent
dimensions to consolidate fragmented
efforts, we use a readiness
assessment, Canva for evaluation.
This takes you from chaos to
coherent enterprise capability.
Let me give you an
overview of the framework.
It has five foundation pillars
with governance as a spanning
concern across all the all of them.
The five pillars are data preparedness,
focusing on quality and lineage,
process, adaptability, focusing on
agile workflows, infrastructure,
scalability for scalable system.
Cultural enablement for ai,
literacy and governance and ethical
framework for ethics and compliance.
Now, governance spans all pillars as a
cross-cutting concern and organization
progress through five maturity
stages, foundational, developing,
defined, managed, and optimized.
We will see through all of these.
Let's dive into the first pillar.
Data preparedness.
Data infrastructure forms a bedrock
of successful AI implementation.
There are four key dimensions,
completeness, full coverage of
your data, landscape accuracy,
consistency of your information.
Lineage, clear prominence tracking and
accessibility, discovering interfaces.
Why does this matter?
A consolidated high quality
data foundation is essential
for successful ML initiatives.
Without robust data foundation, even the
most sophisticated algorithms can flatter.
Process adaptability.
The second pillar, this is
about identifying appropriate
workflows for AI augmentation.
What makes a process an ideal candidate?
Three characteristics, it's
repetitive decision point,
are amenable to automation.
It's measurable.
Outcomes enable performance
validations and it's traceable.
There are clear input
output relationships.
You also need a continuous
improvement culture.
Foster iterative refinement, where teams
improve processes based on feedback.
Leverage flexible frameworks to
pivot quickly, empower teams to
innovate without rigid constraints.
The key outcome here is that technology
investments target genuine operational
improvements, not just experimentation.
Third pillar infrastructure.
Scalability.
Your technical architecture must
support both current and future growth.
There are four infrastructure components.
Compute flexible resources for variable
workloads with elastic scaling.
Storage systems for sustainable
data volume with high
throughput integration patterns.
Connecting to enterprise system and
observability, monitor behavior latency
and resources with real-time insights.
Why does scalability matter?
It supports ML production environments.
Provides flexibility to adjust
resources dynamically and ensures
optimal performance at all time.
The key benefit is that it prevents
technical debt accumulation and
enables smooth dev to pro transitions.
So the fourth pillar is
governance and ethical frameworks.
Governance mechanisms must be embedded
throughout the deployment lifecycle.
There are four components, explainability,
clear model logic, and decision
traceability leads to stakeholder trust,
bias detection, fairness metrics, and
demographic parity protects against
discrimination, the compliance.
Regulatory mapping and documentation for
G-D-P-R-C-C-P and industry requirements.
All of them are taken care
and the risk assessment.
Review gates and impact analysis for
proactive failure identification.
You need formal policies for
model validation, data privacy,
and compliance verification.
The principle here is to balance
innovation velocity with risk
management, creating clear decision
pathway that maintain accountability
while enabling experimentation.
The fifth and final pillar,
cultural enablement technology
adoption depends on human capability
and organizational willingness.
There are four elements of
cultural transformation.
Yale literacy programs, building
knowledge across all organizational
roles, cross-functional champions,
embedded advocates, driving
adoption, shared ownership, model
accountability beyond technical teams,
and change management proactively
addressing resistance patterns.
Why does culture matter?
Cultivating AI literacy is essential for
fostering innovation and collaboration.
It empowers employees to
effectively utilize AI technologies.
The key insights is to treat AI adoption
as a change management initiative,
not just a technology deployment.
Now it's important to
understand what these pillars,
what these five pillars are.
Interdependent.
Advancement in one enables
progress in others.
The key relationships are data
enables process, which means
quality data enables automation.
Infrastructure supports data, which means
infrastructure, stores and processes.
Data governance spans all, which means
insight spans into all the pillars,
and culture enables all, which means
people enables every other pillar Here.
You can't automate without quality data.
You can't scale without infrastructure.
Governance spans all as
a crosscutting concern.
Culture underpins adoption
success across all dimensions.
Organizations evolve through five
distinct stages of AI readiness,
each with clear benchmarks.
Stage one, foundational ad
hoc experiments, limited
governance, isolated teams.
No coordination is needed here.
Stage two developing.
Pilot projects and basic governance,
initial standards, and limited sharing.
Stage three, it's defined clear protocols,
data strategy, coordination between
teams, and also having structured teams.
Stage four, managed stage gate controls
and performance metrics, scalable
deployments and cross-functional teams.
Stage five is optimized.
Continuous innovation, adoption,
governance, and strategic alignment
with organizational learning.
Think of it as building
foundations in stages one and two.
Standardizing processes in stage
three, scaling operations in stage
four, and achieving continuous
innovation in stage five.
Let me show you the
implementation roadmap.
Four.
Progressive phases guide
organizations from assessment to
scale with disciplined governance.
Phase one discovery, which has assessment
evaluate capabilities, identify
opportunity and conduct workshops.
Phase two is foundation build.
Data infrastructure, governance
frameworks and literacy programs.
Phase three is pilot.
It's experiment controlled
experiments, use case implementation,
and iterative refinement.
Phase four is scale, which is to deploy
enterprise deployment, comprehensive
monitoring, continuous improvements.
The timeline progresses through
assessment phase where you analyze
current ML capabilities and identify gaps.
Capability building where you develop
training programs to enhance team
skills, governance, formalization,
where you establish formal structures
for compliance and scaling readiness,
where you optimize infrastructure
and processes for production.
Note the stage gates between each phase.
These are critical governance checkpoints.
Let's talk about Stagegate governance.
Clear checkpoints ensure requisite
capabilities before advancement,
preventing premature scaling.
The benefits are threefold.
It prevents tech debt, balances risk and
speed, and provides measurable progress.
The gait assessment criteria
includes people readiness.
Skills and training.
Complete process transformation
has workflow, adapted technology.
Infrastructure means systems deployed
data quality, which is standards
are met, and governance maturity,
which means policies are enforced.
Now what if you are not
meeting the criteria?
There are recovery parts,
targeted capability building.
Extending timelines with
milestones, external partnership
are parallel track developments.
The key is that this isn't about failing.
It's about learning and building
capability Before you scale,
let's discuss collaborative
discovery workshops.
These transform assessment from audit to
co-design for effective AI deployment.
The workshop benefits are clear,
identify constraints, define roadmap,
enable collaboration, who participates
in these business sponsors provide
strategic objective and success criteria.
Enterprise architects provide
technical integration requirements.
Engineering leads assess
implementation feasibility.
Data owners provide data
availability and governance status.
What are the workshops
outputs for key deliverables?
A maturity scorecard, a prioritized
gap list, a 90 day, or based on your
organization, say monthly or biweekly.
Action plan a gate
criteria for progression.
Let me show you real world validations
for enterprise mapped against
five pillars and maturity stages.
First, JP Morgan Chase in financial
services, they are at stage five,
optimized across all five pillars.
They have data modernization,
over 600 use cases.
LLM sued for 200,000 employees
and KPI gated stage gate rollouts.
They prevented $1.5 billion in fraud and
reached 200,000 users in eight months.
The second one is
Simmons in manufacturing.
Simmons, Amber, to be
specific, stage five.
Optimized in four pillars.
Stage three, defined in governance.
They run a data mesh on Snowflake with
50 million data points per day, IT or ot.
Convergence and co-creative
learning with shop floor workers
desserts, 99.99% quality, and 14
times productive improvements.
Third Unilever in supply chain
and consumer packaged goods.
Stage five optimized in most pillars.
Stage four managed in infrastructure.
They have an eight petabyte platform
processing 240 terabytes per week.
Their five stage AI ethic
process mirrors stage gate.
They trained 23,000 employees.
They are running over 500 AI projects with
50% risk reduction and the fourth Mayo
Clinic in healthcare, stage four, managed
in data, process and infrastructure.
Stage five, optimized in
governance and culture.
They have a patient data
stewardship model, which has the
view board as gate stage gate.
Multi-layer governance.
Their principle is
enablement, not gatekeeping.
They are running over 250 EI projects with
the deepest governance in the industry.
All case studies data is sourced
from publicly available academic
publications which are cited here.
Let me summarize the key benefits.
These are transformative outcomes
from structured AI readiness
and discipline governance.
To successfully transition from
pilot to production organization
must emphasize discipline governance.
This ensures scalability, accountability,
and alignment with enterprise
objectives for maximum impact.
The six benefits are clarity, transform
ambiguity into actionable opportunity
with clear assessment criteria.
The readiness canvas provides structured
evaluation alignment, which bridges
the executive vision and technical
execution through collaborative workshops.
Cross-functional teams work together.
It is measurable, which means tracks
progress across in interdependent
dimensions with clear metrics using
five stage maturity, progressions,
governance, balance, innovation,
velocity with risk management through
stage gates with formal policies and co.
Scalable, which is prevent pilots sprawl
and enable enterprise wide deployment
go from fragmented pilots to production
and it's sustainable build foundations
for long-term AI transformation
and organizational learning.
Cultural enablement drives adoption.
How do you get started?
Your path to yay readiness begins
with cross-functional collaboration.
You will use three practical
artifacts, the readiness assessment
canvas, a maturity scorecard,
and a 90 day action plan.
Here are four steps.
Step one, assess current state.
Evaluate maturity across all five pillars.
Step two, convene stakeholders.
Bring together business
architecture and engineering teams.
Step three, conduct discovery workshop.
Identify gaps and
prioritize opportunities.
Step four, create 90 day
plan, or monthly or biweekly.
Plan.
Define milestones and success criteria.
Step five, establish governance.
Set stage gate criteria for progression,
and then you follow a continuous
cycle, assess, align, discover, plan,
govern, and execute, and also repeat.
Let me conclude.
The key to enterprise AI success lies
not in algorithmic sophistication.
But in organizational discipline,
there are four principle to remember.
One, evaluate honestly.
Number two, organize systematically,
and three, build methodically.
And four is to scale responsibly.
The key takeaways, the five pillars
are data, process, infrastructure,
governance, and culture.
Discipline governance ensures
scalability and accountability.
Cross-functional collaboration
is essential for AI deployment
and use readiness assessment
tools to identify improved areas.
The AI Readiness Blueprint provides
the framework Enterprises need to
convert fragmented pilot proliferation
into intelligent ecosystems.
Delivering sustained competitive
advantage through responsible,
manageable, and strategically
aligned intelligent automation.
Thank you.