Hello everyone.
My name is Ra Gen, having 10 plus years
of experience in enterprise system
market architecture with the focus
on a driven workflow optimization
and robotic process automation.
Currently, I serve as a senior
software engineer where I design
and delivers scalable intelligent
workflow system that seamlessly
integrate real time decision making.
Artificial inte and end-to-end automation.
My work is centered around solving
the complex business challenge and
enhancing the operational efficiency.
Over the course of my career, I have
been fortunate to work with the leading
organizations in the healthcare,
banking, and finance and insurance
industry, driving the innovation and
the digital transformation at scale.
Today I'm going to present how
revolutionizing legacy system
migration to cloud architecture.
So the AI power zero touch integration,
revolutionizing legacy system
migration to cloud architecture.
Welcome to the presentation on
the No approach to enterprise
legacy system migration through
zero touch AI driven middleware.
This.
Innovative solution autonomously
facilitate the integration of aging
enterprise infrastructure with
the modern cloud architecture.
Our approach leverage advanced mission
learning programs and algorithms,
natural language processing,
and the knowledge graphs Two.
Automatically discover, map, and
optimize the legacy work environments
through the manual intervention.
So let's understand the
legacy migration challenge.
Here are three legacy challenges
that we have identified.
Legacy system barrier, complex
integration, high cost and disruption.
Let's discuss legacy system barrier.
Despite the proven reliability
legacy system now significantly
impede the digital transformation
initiatives and diminish competitive.
Advantage in the today's rapidly
evolving business environment.
The second one, complex integration.
Integrating the legacy system with the
modern cloud architecture extend far
beyond the technical hurdle, encompassing
the critical organizational financial
and operational challenge that demand the
comprehensive solutions, high cost, and,
disruption organizations encounter high
migration costs, increasing technical
debate due to insufficient integration
strategies and considerable business
disruption during the transition, creating
significant obstacles to modernization.
So zero touch AI driven integration.
Define, here are four things.
Autonomous orchestration,
AI port analysis, automated
transformation, continuous validation.
Let's go one by one.
Autonomous orchestration.
Complete migration without
a human interaction.
AI port analysis, intelligence,
discovery, and map mapping.
Automated transformation, self-optimizing
conversion pattern, continuous
validation, self-healing, integration.
Mechanism, zero touch driven
integration leverages artificial
inte to autonomously orchestrate the
entire migration process from legacy
system to cloud native environment.
This approach builds upon zero touch
networking orchestration principles,
extending them to enterprise
architecture transformation.
So current state of.
Enterprise system migration,
traditional approach.
Current migration methods typically
follow one of three established
approaches, lift and shift, relocating
the application without modification,
re-platforming, making target modification
to leverage specific cloud capabilities.
Refactoring.
Substantial code restructuring
to fully adapt cloud native
principles, key limitations.
Manual integration
methods dominate despite
inherent limitations.
Reliance on rare specialist
with expertise in both the
legacy and target technologies.
N dependencies on often outdated
or absent documentation.
Significant potential are human
error during transition process,
sequential nature, limiting
paralyzation opportunities.
The pinpoints of current
migration process.
Here are the four pinpoints
that we have identified.
The one is reduction in the legacy
knowledge, incomplete system discovery
data quality issue testing complexity.
Let's discuss one by one reduction in
the legacy knowledge original system
architects and developers retired or.
Transition to other roles, taking the
crucial undocumented knowledge with them.
Creating the fundamental challenge
in understanding the system behavior.
Incomplete system discovery, dependencies
and integration often emerge only
during the migration causing the scope.
Expansion and timelines delay
as teams encounter unexpected.
Connection between the system, data
quality issues, data quality and
consistency problem often come up during
the migration needing a lot of cleaning
work that was not planned for initially.
Let's discuss test testing capabilities,
validation complexity increases.
Expansion.
Expansion only with system size
and integration scope, making
comprehensive testing nearly
impossible through manual means alone.
Critical framework for
aid driven integration.
Precision layer, intelligence layer,
orchestration layer, execution layer,
governance layer, optimization layer.
Let's discuss one by one.
So perception layer.
Monitors legacy system behavior
through non-invasive methods.
And the next one, intelligence
layer builds comprehensive
model of system functionality.
Orchestration layer
coordinate transformation
activities across components.
Next one, execution layer implements
migration tasks through centralized
and APIs governance layer.
Compliance with organizational
policy optimization layer
continuously refine the system
performance and resource allocation.
This multi-layered architecture
enables autonomously migration from
legacy system to cloud environment,
drawing inspiration from advance
in network automation and service.
Management, the Keya Touch
technologies, enabling integration.
There are five things
that we have identified.
Natural language processing and
symbol methods, machine learning,
knowledge graphs, computer revision.
Rest discussed one by one.
Natural language processing extracts
the domain knowledge from unstructured
documentation code component, and.
User manuals
and simple methods combines
multiple yay approaches to
enhance the migration robustness.
Machine learning identifies pattern
and system behavior without explicit
programming knowledge provides
semantic representation of system
components and relationship.
Computer revision.
Analyze elements to map the user
interaction in systems, lacking a
PA access, so pro to methodology
for autonomous migration.
Here are the four stages
that we have identified.
One is S system analysis, workflow
discovery, code, transformation,
continuous validation.
Let's discuss one by one system analysis.
Non-invasive collection approach.
Monitor legacy system without disruption,
creating a comprehensive inventory of
components, interaction and dependencies.
The next one, workflow discovery process.
Mining algorithms, analyze event
log to reconstruct actual business
process revealing shadow workflow, and.
Exception handling pattern.
Third one, core transformation.
Automated tools transform the legacy
code into modern programming languages
while preserving the functional
semantic and generating equivalent.
A PS the last one, continuous validation.
Digital.
Simulation enables verification of
migration plans before implementation
with automated testing comparison
response between the legacy and migrated
components implementation case status.
Let's go Each industry wise if you look at
the financial industry, legacy environment
is for many financial industry.
Mainframe COBOL application.
Target architecture,
microservice architecture.
Key challenges, transition,
integrity, regulatory compliance.
Let's look at the manufacturing industry.
The key challenge, legacy, environment
firm manufacturing industry is customized
on Prime ERP targeted architecture cloud.
Now.
Native ERP with iot.
Key challenges, complex
customization, real time requirements.
Let's look at the healthcare industry.
Departmental patient system,
target architecture, unified cloud
platform, key challenges, data
privacy, system fragmentation.
Let's look at the telecom.
Industry network management system
is the legacy environment, the
targeted architecture cloud, native
orchestration, key challenge, hardware
dependencies, legacy protocol.
These diverse case study demonstrate
that efficiency of touch, AI
driven migration approach across.
Different sectors with each
implementation showing significantly
improvements in migration,
timelines, resource utilization,
and post-migration performance.
Key challenges and feature
research directions.
So here are the tech
technical limitations, highly
customized legacy system with.
Property technologies often resist
standardized analysis approach.
System with hardware dependencies
are non-deterministic behavior.
Present sustainable migration challenge,
security and compliance legacy system
often implement security through.
Security rather than
modern principle regulatory
requirements impose strict
constructions on migration approach,
particularly regarding the data
residency and access control.
Human, a collaboration complex
scenarios often emerge that suppress
the current a capabilities requiring.
Effective human AI collaboration
model with balance the advantage
of automation with human experts
to achieve optimal results.
The conclusion and key takeaways,
70% of cost reduction compared to
traditional migration approach.
60% of time saving faster
implementation of cloud migration,
90% of risk reduction, lower business
disruption during transition.
The achi, a driven integration of
framework represents a significant.
Advancement in the legacy enterprise
system migration by autonomously
mapping the optimization and
migrating the legacy workflow
organization can overcome traditional
challenge of high cost technical
debate under business disruptions as
a digital transformation initiative
accelerator across the industries.
This framework often.
Organization, variable pathway
to modernize their legacy and
infrastructure while managing the risk
and maximizing the business value.
Thank you.