Hello everyone.
This is Roja Perman.
I'm currently working as director of
professional services in a population
health management organization.
I've been in the technology industry.
Since past 16 years playing various
roles in areas like business
intelligence, product management,
software delivery, and implementations.
Today I would like to focus on how
SMS based solution is revolutionizing
healthcare population management industry.
We will go through some gaps that
current population healthcare
management industry has, and how SMS
based solution is designed to bridge
these gaps through intelligent message
routing and even driven architecture.
This framework we will also learn
today how it enables healthcare
organizations to deliver personalized,
clinical relevant con communications
that improve the outcomes and
value-based care environments.
So let's deep dive.
The major gaps in healthcare
population management are.
Our treatment plan, adherence gaps.
This is where healthcare organizations
are struggling with low patient
compliance to prescribed care plans.
Targeted digital communications
have shown a significant boost in
adherence and reduction in missed
opportunities for appointments and
decrease in hospital readmissions.
Next is patient engagement challenges.
Traditional outreach methods often fail
to maintain consistent patient engagement.
Strategic digital communication approaches
have enabled higher satisfaction
scores and also engagement levels
leading to improved care continuity.
Sometimes the medication
compliance deficits are also
a major gaps in this industry.
Non-adherence to medication regimens
represents a critical gap in effective
population health management.
Structured digital check-ins and
personalized protocols have achieved
major improvement in medication compliance
among previously non-adherent patients.
And the last one is about the
social determinants barriers.
Healthcare systems often lack effective
mechanisms to address non-medical
factors affecting healthcare outcomes.
Digital outreach strategies have
shown a significant improvement
in connecting vulnerable patients
with essential community resources
for food, transportation, and
housing needs almost up to 35%.
There are critical gaps in population
health management today that we
just discussed, and how patients
struggle with complex treatment
protocols leading to poor outcomes
and increased hospitalizations.
The missed appointments, create
discontinuity of care and
prevent timely interventions.
So the SMS based solutions provide
a healthcare specific technical
infrastructure which addresses these
gaps through seamless EHR integrations.
This is HIPAA compliant system, and it
also utilizes HL seven fire interfaces
to enable automated care gap and
identification and clinical data exchange.
Ensuring that there is an alignment in a
member population and healthcare industry.
Let's try to understand why SMS
is an important framework for
healthcare population management.
I. Today, healthcare population
and healthcare organizations face
significant population health challenges,
including inconsistent treatment,
adherence, and high appointment,
no-show rates, which are preventable.
Hospital hospitable readmissions.
But the delay in care gap closure
is what is the biggest challenge?
Traditional outcome methods reach
only 38% of patients within 24
hours, creating critical delays
in time sensitive interventions.
Population health management faces some
other critical gaps like how we just
understood, which are communication
delays, fragmented care coordination,
inconsistent patient engagement, and
limited monitoring between visits.
An effective self SMS platform
will address these challenges
through specialized architecture.
Let's look at how this
architecture on a high level is.
The healthcare integration layer,
which is comprises of healthcare and
FI hhl seven and fire interfaces.
We and also qua and also provides
a quality reporting systems.
The next layer comes into a clinical
message processing engine, then
protected health information database,
and then healthcare compliance layer.
This SMS technology and framework also
helps in addressing chronic disease
management among the population health.
Population health management currently
is facing continuous monitoring gaps,
medication adherence, and timely
intervention for diabetes management.
If you take, for example, the system of
SMS technology implements, structured
pathways aligned with American diabetes
association guidelines, providing blood
glucose monitoring prompts and adherence.
Support to address these critical care
continuity gaps within the patients.
Let's look into some care
transition management opportunities.
The critical gaps in population
health management include inadequate
discharge support, missed follow up
appointments, medication errors, and
insufficient post discharge monitoring,
which is especially affecting
patients with limited health literacy.
MS technology is helps with discharge
instruction reinforcement by
sequencing the messages following
evidence-based transitional care models.
SMS can also be used to send out
follow-up appointment coordination,
which is like an automated reminders
with preparation instructions.
SMS can also be Inc utilized in medication
reconciliation support with structured
check-ins to verify understanding and
adherence of medications by the patients.
SMS can also be utilized in post discharge
monitoring, where symptoms assessment with
a alert threshold, sending out alerts of
what kind of sub symptoms that a patients
are encountering and what should be the
next steps can be monitored and sent out.
The alerts can be sent out with the SMS.
Thus, SMS can also be can play a major
role in preventative care and screening.
Let's understand some of the
popular ways and significant areas.
The significant gaps exist in population
healthcare and delivery, which is creating
opportunities for systematic improvement
through structural interventions.
One of the such areas is low
screening completion rates.
Traditional reminder systems
fail to account for individual
risk factors resulting in missed
cancer detection opportunities and
preventable late stage diagnosis.
Conventional immunization outreach methods
achieve inadequate populate co population
coverage, leaving vulnerable groups
suspectable to preventable diseases.
Lack of pre-visit preparation leads
to missed care opportunities with
providers struggling to address
multiple preventative needs
during time constraint encounters.
The systematic approach of
SMS-based solution addresses these
gaps to targeted interventions.
For example, risk stratified cancer
screening, structured immunization
management, and enhanced wellness
visit coordination In all of
such targeted intervention areas,
SMS can play a major role with.
How we can align the proactive outreach
with pre visit guidance and also,
which also increases the care gap.
Continuancy, let's look into some more
gaps in population health management
where SMS technology has addressed
challenges and and also in social
determinants of health effectively,
which has created opportunities
for technology driven solutions.
Today, major portion, almost up until
75% of healthcare organizations report
significant barriers in coordinating care
across multiple providers and community
resources, resulting in duplicate efforts
and missed intervention opportunities.
There are access disparities where
vulnerable populations face higher
barriers to accessing preventative
services with transportation limitations
and inflexible appointment systems,
which are disproportionately affecting
rural and low income communities.
Communication breakdowns, traditional
communication channels reach only up to.
62% of high risk patients today with
one way messaging, failing to provide
actionable insights into patient
circumstances between clinical encounters.
Clinical decisions are made with
incomplete information and where social
determinant factors are impacting
health outcomes remain undocumented
in a traditional EHR systems.
Addressing these gaps requires an
integrated technology approaches
and an SMS based technology and
framework is a right way to address
these key and gaps and has shown with
significant statistics and improvement.
Let's look at some more healthcare
gaps that SMS technology has addressed.
There are some strategic communication
approaches where the, these gaps have
been bridged and let's look at them.
Limited patient engagement.
Many patients, particularly those in
underserved communities, does remain
disconnected from their care team
between visits, resulting missed
opportunities for early intervention.
Having that patient or
a member in a rural.
Setting have a continuous
engagement with the patient cares.
The team via an SMS is at least
cost effective yet that which
can bridge these gap that we have
spoken about, the critical gaps.
Inconsistent care protocol adherence.
Without structured communication
systems, care teams actually struggling
to consistently apply evidence-based
protocols across diverse populations.
In accessing the access disparities for
the member population, SMS technology
has bridged major gaps in barriers for
underserved and rural populations with
limited healthcare access care continuity,
where the structured communication
pathways address fragmentation and
post discharge and chronic condition
management that has taken leap and bounds
of improvement and has bridge the gap.
Healthcare literacy tailored messaging
frameworks overcome educational
and language barriers that impact
health outcomes for implementation
of support and additional resources.
These patients can always contact
these care teams of how to improve
in their healthcare outcomes and
disparities using SMS technology.
Thank you.