Hello everyone.
Thanks for joining the session today.
I would like to talk about
predictive maintenance using
iot and machine learning.
Basically, it involves the sensors, the
realtime data collection the analytics
using machine learning, and it covers
a bit of future respects as well.
Okay, I have split the
agenda into these categories.
First, the types of maintenance
and what is predictive maintenance?
The sensors, the market, the
challenges and the future direction,
and also the machine learning part.
Yeah.
When you look at a, an industrial
equipment that's installed in a
factory or a manufacturing unit or
the one that is used, transformers
that are used for power supply.
There are multiple types of
maintenance that are available.
Typically the one that is done is
a breakdown maintenance, like where
after we see a failure, we react to
it and start the maintenance process.
Like we call the company that
maintains it and the spare
parts that are needed and so on.
So that is breakdown maintenance.
The other one is preventive maintenance.
It is like periodic maintenance that
we do, like an oil change for the car.
There's nothing that's broken down,
but still you, you just want to
ensure that it runs properly and
you do a preventive maintenance.
This is mostly done on a schedule,
like quarterly or annually
depending on the equipment.
And what we find is one a PC study,
they said they found that more
than 80% of failures are random.
So you can't cover them
in preventive maintenance.
And of course, if it breaks down,
you have to do breakdown maintenance.
Here comes the the power
of predictive maintenance.
Now we have IOT sensors, which simple like
a microphone or a proximity switch or a.
A simple vibration sensor, which
can basically monitor or gather the
the broad data like a sound or the
vibrations, and which can be intelligently
analyzed using ML algorithms.
And you can predict even before the
equipment goes into breakdown that it's
going fail and without any downtime, you
can do a prevent preventative maintenance.
That's, that is called us predictive
maintenance sensors have matured greatly.
They use less and less of power.
They have a more accuracy has
increased and you can measure
various parameters like sound.
The vibration, as I mentioned,
temperature, pressure, humidity,
and this is real time, right?
Like when the mission is running
or the equipment is running, you
collect the data and we are pushing
it into cloud or some data lake where
you can gather all the information.
And now with the advancements of
ai, we have sophisticated machine
learning algorithms, which can process
these detect anomalies and report
as perform predictive maintenance.
The key benefits of IOT based
maintenance are, of course, like we,
we predicted early before it happens.
And even though there is a downtime,
you can schedule it like in
non-business hours or something
that doesn't have much of an impact.
And to be relatively less.
And to add to that, in case the.
There is a predictive
maintenance part of it.
The technician who comes in comes
with the right part that is needed.
So there is no back and forth to
go for, go searching of the parts,
finding out what's gone wrong.
He comes and does a surgical maintenance,
so that reduces the downtime.
Of course, it saves a lot of cost about
25 to 30% and then since it's maintained
even before a breakdown happens.
The equipments lifespan increases greatly.
And finally, what our feedback is
gathered by the predictive maintenance
can be fed back into the design table
so that the next products that are
iterated by the company can incorporate
all the findings that they have in
real time into their next design,
which basically evolves their product.
PTC is a company.
We just got a, which is very good in
microphone monitor, acoustic monitoring.
Basically they can be deployed
anywhere and it can be retrofit or
it can be deployed on an existing
missionary without disrupting, making
a lot of changes around, around that.
You can just go and place it on a
relatively benign spot and you can
start gathering the information.
It's non-invasive and, it basically
continuously sense data, which
are compared by the ML algorithms.
I will see about it later.
Further broadly it's it's
first data collection.
Getting the operational equipment
footprint, basically the creating the
acoustic footprint of the equipment.
It's like a thermal map or a,
something like that to imagine.
And the data is collected
continuously, so it's real time.
And, it's multimodal, right?
Like it has got the sound profile, it's
got the vibration profile, it's got the
temperature profile, so it's multimodal
which can produce a very complex pattern.
Like you can combine all these to
find out precisely what's going on.
And what needs to be maintained.
And the data can be compared like,
say for example, a company which
is manufacturing the equipment.
They can compare it with previous failures
or previous maintenance that they have
done, and which can reduce the false
positives and enhancing the credibility
of the the preventative maintenance.
Yeah.
Now we have the sensors.
How do we integrate the machine learning?
When you see the diagram, it basically,
there is a data acquisition part and
there is a signal processing part.
And third is the the signal is set
to a machine learning model and.
We also have something called
as h computing integration to
reduce the network latency and
feedback for the model refinement.
When you see I. Again, it cal collects
all the data that is the first point.
And signal processing is, as an example,
it is converting an amplitude of a
frequency into a time series data,
basically converting the frequency,
converting it into frequency domain so
that the ML model can better analyze that.
So it can look at the
peaks where it is speaking.
But for just with, without the
amplitude they can look for
the frequency time series also.
Yeah.
And we can train the machine, learn
models with the different algorithms
like random forest, CNN, to predict
anomalies, and maintenance needs.
Yeah, edge computing is very
interesting because these sensors,
they collect a lot of data.
We can collect every second, and there
are some which collect in milliseconds,
and you can of course configure
them, but you can do a localized
signal processing instead of sending
the raw data directly through the
network and kind of overloading it.
So you can reduce you can just
process the signal here and
eliminate what is not needed and
transformations that are needed.
And you can reduce the, by
doing this, you can reduce the.
The number of data the amount of data
that we transfer over the network
and basically to reduce the latency.
So basically you can find out
what's going on pretty fast,
relatively, and model refinement.
They keep on increasing, it's possible
to keep on increasing the prediction
accuracy through adaptive learning
and supervised learning as well.
So this is how it works.
Basically, we collect the sensor,
we signal process it, and affect
the machine learning model.
And if needed, we use the most
of it will have an edge computing
integration to reduce the network load.
And finally, there is a supervised
component to improve the model security
because you start with something that is
a false pass, it keeps on maturing and the
data can be made available on a dashboard.
And there can also be alerts that can
be triggered on a mobile phone, like
for a service engineer as an example.
Yeah, it's got multiple application areas.
I think maybe you already sensed it.
It can be applied in manufacturing.
If there is a say a bottling plant or if
there is a emissions that are running.
So in manufacturing basically, and
energy, like where there are the
turbines running and you can measure
the transformers frequency, the data
image, to find out if it's going to fail.
Using the predictive analytics,
because we have the sophisticated
algorithms to even detect a very
minor anomaly which is real, not of
all positive, and you can act on it.
And logistics per fleet management?
Large trucks, 18 wheelers, they carry.
There are so you can monitor it pretty
much because by avoiding failures
in that and maintaining it with
predictions, ML based predictions, you
can avoid failures and can ensure that
the SUP supply chain is not impacted.
It has got other applications
also like automobile, like there
are, there is a, in cars, they're
used as a vascular health systems.
And oil and gas industry as we discussed,
it could be used in railways basically
where, because that's a public transport
or it could be a good stream which
carries goods like, so those things
before they, if they break, they cause
downtime and supply chain issues.
We can, it can be predictive,
it can be maintained in using
prediction and utilities.
Of course, electricity,
we already saw gas.
Anything that that comes to us
through internet can be monitored.
Yeah.
Compared to 2020, the market has
grown or projected to grow 400%.
So it was about $7 billion
in 2020 and it's going to go
more than $28 billion in 2026.
'cause there are a lot of
advantages to this approach.
Easy to sensors are easier,
non-invasive can easily implement it.
And integration with the
maturing of machine learning, the
prediction accuracy is pretty high.
So thereby you can,
you can avoid downtime.
So there is a lot of investment going on
and even new equipments that are, that
already come with prebuilt sensors, which
could be used for predictive monitoring.
Some of the studies aggregated show
that there is a 50% downtime reduction
because of predictive mainten.
And of course there's cost savings.
It's more than 30%, but.
Typically it's 30% around
30% and uptime, right?
The mission is available for
manufacturing, which basically caters
to the, or makes the company efficient
trustworthy to deliver on time.
It increases by 60%.
So what it means is if there were no
predictive maintenance, then they, there
would be a 60% reduction in efficiency.
So because of implementation
of the predictive maintenance
using iot, industrial iot, the
company profitable as well.
Yeah.
Some of the challenges to implement
this is typically these factories or
the whole systems have some mindset
of, traditional reactive maintenance.
So to, to change the mindset and
come to a concept of predictive
maintenance can be challenging
because my, my system is working fine.
Why should I certainly
do it before it happens?
So that is the mindset, but we have to
educate them to come up to the speed.
And there is a lot of skill gap.
In, in terms of people who monitor it in
case like the companies themselves decide
to monitor it centrally or so people
who understand iot technologies, data
analytics, and even acoustics, like in
case there is a relocation of a mission.
So there is a skill gap in
this, and the most important
is the cybersecurity concerns.
Like the IOTs devices are highly prone to
cybersecurity attacks because the, there
are no frequent updates, like unlike a
desktop or a. System that's maintained.
All these iot sensor are just a
fit and forget kind of things.
And so they always tend to get old
or not up to speed to the current.
There are no frequent updates to that.
And they make them vulnerable.
The certificates expire
or they become legacy.
Yeah.
And the data that comes out
of the system is massive.
Because these are all sensors
it is it's going to just bombard
the system with so much of data.
So it requires maybe a data
like solution and sometimes you
may not get the data as well.
So it needs that kind of an object
storage system, like an AWS S3,
which can handle large volumes
of data, creating a retrofitting
old industrial equipment sensors.
Could, because it's a old system, like
we may not have the profile it has
got its own implementation challenges.
Challenges.
So there's a lot of homework that needs
to be done to successfully integrate a
legacy system, which kind of very old to
to this predictive maintenance system.
The future looks bright, so you can have
a. Can have a technician come up with
the AR and virtual reality augmented
reality so he can, when he looks at
the machine, he can see, he can be
guided by the machine or by a person
who's an expert, different geography,
location, to precisely go the things
that he needs to do to fix the system.
And you can have virtual models
that's got a digital twins that's
coming up and yeah the models
currently they're supervised, right?
So when the models eventually mature more
and more, they'll start to learn itself
like teach itself or to become better.
And there are a lot of cloud
platforms that basically companies
which are generic and they offer
predictive maintenance for multiple.
So that's a evolving model that's coming
up which will basically an outsourcing
sort of the company themselves only it
or the manufacturer of the equipment.
It could be a third party cloud
platform that could take care
of it for different systems.
So to conclude the.
Predictive maintenance using iot
delivers unprecedented insights
and operational excellence.
And it's going to grow in the future.
And a lot of equipments, even some
that are at home will eventually
be having some kind of predictive
maintenance in the future.
And they deliver a actionable,
intelligent intelligent plan.
To call to action, to to resolve the
issues which will basically ensure
the overall reliability of most
of the systems, thereby increasing
the the quality of life, making
the company's profitable and so on.
Yeah, I have added some
references which would go through.
Hope you like it.
Yeah.
Thank you very much.