Hi everyone.
I'm Hil Kati, a software engineer
focused on AI cloud and FinTech.
Today I'll be walking you through how
AI powered digital twin technology can
transform the way we manage financial
risk and optimize assets across
industries, especially in high stake
environments like finance and operations.
Let's begin by understanding
the context behind the stock.
In today's fast evolving financial
landscape, organizations are
under constant pressure to
manage risk, performance, and
efficiency all in real time.
So traditional approaches that
rely on static models, periodic
reports, or siloed data are
increasingly insufficient day by day.
So this is where our digital twin
technology becomes a game changer
for us in the financial world.
A digital twin is a real.
Time.
Digital replica of financial
entity or a system.
It could represent a portfolio,
a payment network, risk model, or
even an end-to-end business process.
Unlike static dashboards, these twins are.
Dynamic con, continuously
updated and also simulate both
current and potential feature.
Also like the states using live I
would say like live data streams here.
So now when we integrate this
with artificial intelligence
and machine learning, we
unlock the ability to predict.
Financial anomalies and also risks
before they materialize and also simulate
complex market and also credit scenarios.
And another thing is to continuously
optimize asset management
and decision making at scale.
And now I would like to walk you through
a framework that combines digital twins,
real time financial data, and also a IP
work pre predictive models, including.
Random Forest classifier.
A powerful I would say like it's more I
was saying like powerful because it's more
based on a learning method for classifying
risk patterns and financial events.
And another one is L Esteem,
which stands for long short-term
memory networks, which is like a
type of recurrent neural network.
Particularly effective for
detecting patterns over time in
financial time series kind of data.
So this fusion of technologies
empowers financial institutions to
detect irregularities early and also
allocate resources more efficiently
and also move faster and make more
informed decisions on a timely basis.
So in essence, this is how we move from.
Data to decisions using AI and
digital twins to minimize risk
and also maximize the value.
And coming to the background, what we are
trying to do here is it's like a more of
a concept evolved and why it matters today
in regular finance is the most important.
So now getting there, digital twins
began in aerospace and manufacturing,
I would say as digital replicas of
physical assets that initially helped.
Simulate and monitor,
improve their behavior.
But over time, the concept has
evolved beyond the physical world.
Today we apply digital twin technology
to finance to create virtual real time
models of portfolios, customer segments,
credit flows, and operation pipelines.
These twins.
As living financial models
continuously update using transactional
behavior and also the market data.
So now when we pair this artificial
intelligence and machine learning model,
we unlock next level capabilities.
That is more of like forecasting or risk
exposure before even they cause harm.
And another thing is to detecting
deviations in real time.
Like it can be like fraud or
even the default risk even that
can happen within a twin of.
Your actual financial system
that you have created.
So this shift reflects a broader
trend, part of Industry 4.0 and FinTech
2.0, where traditional systems are
giving away to automated, adaptive
and intelligent infrastructures here.
So I'd say instead of reacting
after risks or inefficient appear,
organizations can use digital twins to
anticipate and also act ahead of time.
So now there, obviously for every
thing that we work on, there's always
like problems that we come across.
So looking at the problem statement
and objectives that we would like
to identify as part of this talk
are presented in the next slide.
So before we explore the full architecture
and the process that's being done
as part of this overall digital twin
technology, let's define the core
problem that we are trying to solve here.
So most financial systems today
still rely on after the fact
analysis, whether it's like risk
scoring, asset performance tracking,
or operational reporting as well.
So these systems often.
Operate in silos like there's always
like a blind spot and also delayed
reactions in critical moments.
So even where digital twin models
exist, they're usually static
fragmented, and also like it can be
domain specific most of the time.
The most often things that they lack
here are like real time adaptability
and also like seamless integration
with live financial data streams, and
also the intelligence to learn, evolve,
and optimize themselves over time.
And also when these financial
activities are interconnected.
So they form credit risk to
liquidity management and also asset
performance of regulatory complaints.
So to address this, our objective is to
build an AI power digital twin framework
that brings real time awareness across
financial systems and also a driven
insights through models like RFC and
LSTM that I have discussed earlier.
And the ability to simulate and respond to
scenarios proactively, whether it's fraud
detection, market shifts, or like asset
financing, everything can be more likely
processed with some good data collection
and how we pre-process the data.
So that is something we can
look into the next slide.
So coming to the data collection
and pre-processing, let me walk
you through how the data processing
or overall collection can help
data with our digital twin models.
I would say more of helping a
real time financial data streams.
So we begin by tapping into real
time financial data streams,
which include transactional data
from payments, loans, and trades.
Portfolio level metrics, like if
you say the portfolio level metrics,
there are a lot more risk involved
in that, like exposure risk scores
and also a lot of fluctuations.
So coming to the indicators where we
can identify this, like there are always
like liquidity indicators, both internal
which I can say like reserve ratios
and external like funding availability.
These are like some of the.
Financial data that we
need to collect as well.
And coming to the market data such as
volatility, interest rates, or economic
sentiment indexes pulled from a lot
of different APIs are also collected
and which is very critical for us.
So as part of the data cleaning process
or like pre-processing, the first
step is to conduct data cleaning.
Handle missing records and
also detect anomalies like
spike in transaction volume.
That may be a system error or like it
can be also resolving or formatting
mismatches in general, like it can
be like a lot more anomalies too.
So then we perform normalization and
feature scaling so that all inputs
are aligned in a compatible range.
Which is crucial for most machine learning
models like random forests or L SDMs
to learn accurately and efficiently.
So coming to the proposed framework.
This is like a proposed framework,
which are like step by step done in a
defined way to, to get the overall data
cleaning and also the pre-processing.
As we see, this slide shows that
end-to-end architecture of the AI power
digital twin framework tailored for.
Financial risk management
and a sub optimization.
Here we see how the
data collection happens.
So the data collection begins by
collecting real-time financial data.
So we, that happened from core
systems, like as mentioned, like
payments, loans, credit platforms,
and also the market feeds, interest
rates, volatility indexes, and also.
APIs and third party providers, which
can provide complaints, updates,
and also the sentiment signals.
So this serve as the foundation
for understanding life, financial
behavior, and risk exposures or
outliers that we can always look for.
After this, we do the data cleaning to
correct or exclude all the flawed records.
So this is where the cleanup happens.
And now, and the next step is to normalize
to this like align different scales,
crucial for training relatable models that
we were discussing in the previous slides.
So the next step is the
feature engineering.
This is where the extract of
predictive indicators happen.
So rolling averages or
transactional patterns or like
liquidity shifts over time.
Anomalies in portfolio drift or credit
realization and also like synthetic
risk flags based on loan three sh also
happen in the future engineering step.
And then we do the digital twin
model development here, a real
time enhanced digital replica of
a financial system that has like.
Portfolio manager, credit underwriting
flow or fraud detection pipeline.
These kind of pipelines are built here.
So this twin evolves continuously as new
data arrives and it gets integrated with
the financial telemetry instead of the
physical systems and also simulations
of cash flow and also like market
turbulence can also be monitored and.
As said, these ML models are trained
on historical plus streaming data.
So now when we see this random forest are
used for rule-based risk classification
and like LS, TM is used for time
series predictions, example market
response which happens over the time.
And also like we use SVM model for
separating risk tires at different
levels, and we use auto encoders for
anomaly detection without label data.
So as we see the asset management happens.
More like into this insights feed
directly into capital allocation,
liquidity balancing, or fraud handling
strategies in a more dynamic manner.
So when we come to the reinforcement
learning here, so finally, I. When
we are applying the reinforcement
learning to continually improve the
system, it learns from our outcomes to
adjust thresholds, reallocate capital,
or also optimize strategies based on
the rewards feedback that like cost
savings or risk mitigation success,
anything that gets back to the system.
So in short.
I would say like this framework
connects data to models and models, get
connected to the financial intelligence,
and which in turn measures a lot of
business value in terms of different
aspects as part of overall process.
How does methodology and
overall this framework worked?
So there, there are like some
results that we got popped up once.
We are, once we are processed through
that system, so now when we look at the
results, how it performs, like looking
at the bar chart, we are comparing
four machine learning models here.
The random forest classifier, long short
term memory and support vector machine.
And also like the auto encoder.
So each was tested on a financial
data set to predict risk signals such
as anomalies in transaction flow,
portfolio stress, and also credit
utilization drifts that keeps happening.
So coming to the accuracy here,
so RFC is leading with 95.
0.5% followed close by lstm, which
is a bit shorter than that, which is
vital for realtime decisioning here.
And coming to the precision RFC
and LSTM models, again take the
lead indicating their ability
to reduce the false positives.
So this is very critical in finance
systems to reduce the false positives,
like I would say, like for example,
flagging fraud or credit risk only when
it truly matters is really important.
So coming to the recall part of it,
so again here, RFC and LSTM also excel
with a lot more higher percentage
compared to the respective other models.
So here, high recall means fewer false
negatives even, which is that which
is also more important in financial
risk analysis, which is important
also for catching all genuine risk
signals to understand if it is
really a false positive or a false
negative in coming to the F1 score.
Fund score is also indication for a solid
balance between precision and recall.
So if you see this even here, RFC in
L-S-D-M-R at a higher level indicating
a really good balance, as I was saying.
So auto and coder and SVM performed
reasonably well, but are a be ru
variable in balanced trade offs
when we are trying to make some
trade offs between different models.
So coming to the.
Overall results, the precision recall
and accuracy that is all important,
that when we are looking at the pre-call
recall precision recall and accuracy,
let's now break down like how the
performance of each model across four
evaluation metrics, precision recall,
fund score, and accuracy are monitored.
So these metrics.
We're calculated based on each model's
ability to predict financial anomalies,
like unusual transaction patterns,
risk threshold breaches, or also early
signs of asset under performance.
So when I say like random
forest classifier, so this was
achieved by highest across.
All categories, accuracy, precision,
recall, and also F1 score.
When we are looking at the balance
between these two, it helps
detecting true risk events and
minimizing the false positives here.
So long short term memory, LSTM model,
like each performs very close to RFC and
also like especially strong in recall
making it effective for capturing.
Time-based financial patterns such as
liquidity depths, and also like credit
defaults over time when we are coming to
the next model support vector machine.
So slow, moderate performance accuracy
is like 90% lower recall, such as it's
likely to mess risk signals over time.
So still valuable.
For binary classifications like fraud
detection and also with clear patterns.
So when it comes to the auto
encoder, we, it also performs well
considering it's unsupervised with
the more precision value, but also
compared to the anomal as it detects.
So when we are coming to the
final decision that we want
to make both RFC and LSTM.
Stand out best performing models for
real time financial monitoring and
also like risk prediction offering the
accuracy and balance required for high
stakes decision making in finance.
So looking at these models, there are lot.
There's another thing that we
need to focus on discussing like
overall like cost benefit coming
to how these models performed.
So when we're trying to
discuss the cost benefit.
So I'd say like the initial cost
would be like a little initial cost.
To make this overall digital twin perform
better would be like little lesser.
So ideally, like it would help, like
overall downtime reduction, like
traditional setups can't adopt in real
time, so they offer 0% downtime reduction.
But in DT enabled models.
We improve system resilience and
prediction accuracy leading to a 25%
reduction in downtime, like I would say,
especially during high risk events like
liquidate shortages or fraud spikes,
and however, the return on investment.
So traditional systems
ideally don't yield.
I. A meaningful return on investment
in dynamic financial environment.
But the DT Powered Systems by Contracts
show a one 45% return on investment,
validating not only their operational
value, but also their financial
justification for their I would say like
more of a decision making situation.
Coming to the final touch point,
what I wanted to say is digital twins
require great investment upfront, but
they generate substantial recurring
value over time, both in financial
returns and also operational silence.
So to wrap up, the digital twin framework
clearly demonstrates how AI integrated
system with digital twins can elevate
financial systems by making them more
predictive response and also silent by
analyzing the approach we have achieved.
I would say like very much measurable
benefits, a 25% reduction in
unplanned operational downtime, an
18% decrease in overall maintenance
or overhead costs, and also like a 20%
improvement in asset utilization where.
That helps with the capital
efficiency, liquidity deployment, or
also risk-based resource allocation.
This is possible just that we are
not just monitoring system anymore.
We are modeling them
intelligently in real time.
So when I say the random forest and
long short term memory models, we
are able to generate high confidence
predictions and simulations.
These predictions directly support
strategic decisions from mitigation.
Also to portfolio rebalancing
or also liquidity allocation.
So as a result, I, we have seen like
one 45% return on investments, which
proves that it isn't just a technical
win, but also it's a financial one.
And also these intelligent systems
also enable real time visibility and
automated scenario planning, which helps
financial institutions take action a
bit early, avoiding crisis, and also
can definitely improve the performance.
However, as the challenges remain,
the scalability is still across large,
multi-layered financial systems, right?
And the real time synchronization,
especially when integrating diverse.
Data sources.
It gets a little difficult,
but it's still manageable.
System compatibility is also how
well the system is compatible
with the legacy infrastructure.
That is one thing to really consider
here as these are more of like a solvable
problems and they don't really point
to the need for continued innovation
in cross-functional collaboration
to unlock the full potential of AI
powered digital twins in finance.
The future of financial
Resa lies in more of moving.
From static reporting to living
learning systems and here the digital
twins powered by AI are really
the bridge that can get us there.
Thank you so much for the attention.
I'm all good and open to answer any
questions that you have here today.