Hello everyone.
This is Shruti.
Today we'll be covering into how AI
is transforming security architectures
and cloud-based CRM systems.
We'll be looking into real world
enterprise implementations across
multiple industries, and we'll
examine the practical intersection
of how machine learning capabilities
can help robust security frameworks
through detailed case studies.
From Starbucks, capital One,
Mayo Clinic, JP Morgan Chase,
we'll uncover both successes.
And critical failures that
provide valuable lessons
for our own implementations.
In today's agenda, we'll be covering about
the core concepts of machine learning,
and we'll be going through case study.
One by one, which is Starbucks, followed
by Capital One breach, and then how
in the healthcare machine learning
security is transforming the industry.
And last but not least, the JP
Morgan Chase multi-cloud machine
learning security and how the
security is orchestration, how the
security is orchestrating across.
Multiple platforms.
So our session will move from theoretical
foundations to practical implementation
strategies with each case study.
Building upon the lessons
of previous examples.
In the current security architecture,
the challenges that we often face
are manual threat detection, which is
sometimes awfully long and painful.
We take reactive security
posters, which is.
What we do after the security
incident happens, rather than
protecting it proactively, we
have stat static access controls,
which needs maintenance over time.
And have to adjust based on
the industry requirements.
We have limited visibility across
platforms where the security doesn't
really talk and it works in silos in
each platform with machine learning, we
have automated analy detection, which is
continuously learning from data patterns.
And it detects the anomalies
and flags to the system.
We have predictive threat
modeling, which predicts the
threats even before they occur.
By behavioral analysis, we have
adaptive access management, which
switches the accesses dynamically
based on the role of the accessor.
The platform security correlation
helps in orchestrating the
security across multiple platforms.
And this is what we'll see in
the multi-cloud architecture by
JP Morgan J. Machine learning
fundamentally transforms cloud
security by enabling systems to learn
automatically from the data patterns,
predict potential vulnerabilities,
and take defenses in real time.
This shift from reactive to proactive
security postures is particularly
crucial in customer relationship
management industry, where the
customer data sensitivity is often.
It's often accompanied with
complex access requirements.
Let's dive into machine learning
security architecture components.
There are four building blocks to it.
One is threat detection, where the
machine learning models identify
enamels behavioral patterns and
potential security breaches.
Second one is access intelligence,
adaptive authentication systems that
adjust the security requirements
based on the risk profiles.
Data protection, which automatically
classifies the data into highly
sensitive information and enforces
the encryption security orchestration,
which helps us in orchestrating
security across multiple systems.
It coordinates security response.
These core components form the
foundation of modern machine learning,
enhanced security architectures.
When properly implemented, they
create a very synergistic system
that continuously improves itself and
it adapt its defensive capabilities
through learning while maintaining
compliance with regulatory frameworks.
Now, let's take a look into Starbucks.
Starbucks has implemented Salesforce's
CRM security architecture.
What are the core concepts that Starbucks
implement in their security enhancement?
One is personalized experience, which has
advanced machine learning algorithms that
deliver tailored customer recommendations
while enforcing robust security protocols.
Second one is behavioral monitoring,
sophisticated pattern recognition.
We'll identify and flag enamel
analyst transactions in real time.
Third one is going to be data
classification, which is com
compartmentalization, where it
automatically categorizes the data
during data ingestion itself and
enforces granular access controls
and encrypts the data as well.
So this Starbucks has revolutionized
their security framework by embedding
advanced machine learning algorithms
within their Salesforce CRM
environment, creating a seamless fusion.
Of customer experiences and
also robust security measures.
This implementation demonstrates
how intelligent data processing can
significantly reduce any potential
attacks while maintaining performance
at global enterprise scale.
The breakthrough innovation
lies in their security first
approach to personalization,
where protection mechanisms are
woven into the customer engine.
This inter integration ensures
that data safeguards automatically
scale in proportion to customer
interactions establishing a new
paradigm for secure CRM implementation.
Let's take a look at
the technical details.
There are three main components
to the security architecture
that Starbucks have implemented.
Which is first one is Einstein's
Einstein Analytics integration, which
is a core feature of Salesforce.
This in this feature, there are
custom machine learning models for
correlating security events with
customer behavior patterns across
30,000 plus locations globally.
There's real time encryption pipeline
where automatic field level encryption
is enforced based on data categorization,
and this is being processed over 87
million plus customer records while
maintaining quick response time.
Adaptive permission framework, which
is again, the role-based access we talk
about, we talked about as one of the core
building components of machine learning
architecture, the context of our access
controls, adjust the employee data access
based on behavioral baselines that are
set up by the company and ly detection
across two 50,000 plus user accounts.
The technical implementation
leverages Salesforce shield with
some customer extensions, creating
a security fabric that doesn't
compromise the customer experience.
This approach determines that security
and functionality can be complementary
rather than competing priorities.
Let's move on to Capital
One, AWS breach analysis.
So the backstory of it in
short would be there is a mis
misconfigured web application
firewall inside AWS environment.
The attacker was able to use
SSRF vulnerability to access
the metadata service, which is
server site forgery request.
How was the attacker able to use it?
The attacker was able to gain access
to IAM credential access temporarily,
which has access permission.
And was successfully able to data
exfiltrate a hundred million plus
customer records without detection.
So this 2019 Capital One breach serves as
a critical case study in cloud security
failures analysis reveals that machine
learning could have prevented this.
Let's do dive into how it
could have been implemented.
The first component that
comes into picture for machine
learning is behavioral analysis.
So the machine learning would
detect abnormal IAM credential usage
patterns, misconfiguration scanning.
So whenever there is any insecure
configuration or invalid configuration
built machine learning can automatically
scan the system based on the
regulatory checks that we enforce,
and it automatically identifies any
insecure wire firewall settings, access
intelligence, role-based access control.
It evaluates the access based on
the context for resource request.
Right?
Modern Machine Learning security
solutions could have prevented the
speech through the about three,
which is continuous monitoring of
credential usage patterns, automatic
detection of configuration, drift,
and alerting the system that there is.
Of Misconfigured Firewall by applying
zero trust principles in role-based
access controls which is enhanced
with machine learning decision making.
The system would have required
additional verification for unusual
access patterns, which potentially
blocks the attack before data exposure.
Now let's dive into Mayo Clinic
Healthcare Machine Learning security.
The three main components that Mayo
Clinic uses in machine learning
security are data classification.
So there is machine learning powered
automatic data classification of
protected health information with 99.3%
accuracy across 23 million patient
records ensuring appropriate security
controls are applied contextually.
Advanced role-based access control
intelligence, the predictive analysis,
the predictive access patterns analysis
that identifies potential unauthorized
access attempt before they occur with
87% reduction in false positives compared
to traditional rule-based systems.
Automated compliance monitor, which
is scanning the system continuously
for HIPAA compliance verification,
using machine learning models,
trained on proper audit findings.
Maintaining compliance while processing
8.4 TB of daily healthcare data.
This implementation is in Microsoft Cloud
for healthcare, and this demonstrates
how machine learning transforms static
security controls into dynamic learning
systems that adapt to complex workflows of
healthcare industry without compromising.
The compliance requirements.
Let's dive into the Mayo Clinic's
machine learning security architecture.
The first one would be data
ingestion, which is categorizing the
data automatically while intaking.
Okay with classification and
encryption enforced unclassified data.
The second component would be machine
learning process, where all the
behavioral and access pattern analysis
and anomaly detection happens.
Third component is compliance
verification, which is scanning
the system continuously with our
automated regulatory checks and
validations that we put in place.
Fourth one would be contextual access,
which is switching the permissions
dynamically based on context or role of
whoever is trying to access the resources.
Mayo Clinic's architecture creates
a continuous learning system
that enhances protection while
streamlining clinical workflows.
Their machine learning models evolved
from 76% accuracy to over 98% through
operational feedback loops, demonstrating
how healthcare organizations can leverage
AI to improve security posture while
meeting specialized industry requirements.
Let's dive into our last use case.
JP Morgan Chase, multi-cloud
machine learning security.
So JP Morgan Chase has used different
clouds to for different security aspects.
They've used AWS for AWS security, which
has machine learning powered ly detection
engine for transaction processing and
database access, which is handling
over 5 trillion daily data points.
Second one would be GCP Google
Cloud Platform, which has AI model
training environment with specialized
container security and federated
learning across jurisdictions.
Third one is Microsoft Azure, which
takes care of customer facing services
with adaptive authentication and real
time threat intelligence integration.
This multi-cloud strategy represents
the cutting edge of machine learning
powered security orchestration.
Their implementation creates a
unified security fabric across
A-W-S-G-C-P and Azure while maintaining
consistent policy enforcement through
machine learning governance models.
This approach enables them to leverage
the strengths of each cloud provider
while maintaining a coherent security
posture that meets stringent requirements
of financial services regulation.
The advantage that they have seen
with this cross cloud machine learning
security architecture, which 99.7% fraud
detection, so the accuracy of machine
learning driven transaction system
processing over $7.4 trillion annually.
They have 5,000 plus security
models deployed using machine
learning algorithms across clouds
for specific security functions.
89% incident reduction, decrease
in security incidents following
machine learning implementation.
The average time for
any identified threats.
Is three minutes, which is very quick.
JP Morgan's approach demonstrates how
enterprises can create a coherent security
strategy across multi-cloud platforms.
Their central machine learning
orchestration platforms normalizes
security telemetry from different
providers, enabling comprehensive
threat detection regardless of
where the workloads are deployed.
For any implementation of
machine learning, enhanced
security, there are four.
Building blocks that we
will have to start with.
The first one is security assessment,
connecting a comprehensive evaluation
of existing security controls,
identifying gaps and opportunities
for machine learning enhancement.
We'll have to map the current data
flows to understand where machine
learning can provide the highest
security value if we plug it in.
Then we start with developing the
models, which is building and training
the machine learning models for
specific security functions like anomaly
detection, role-based access controls,
compliance monitoring, scanning the
system, establishing the baseline
for all of the behavioral profiles
and validation methodologies Also.
Come under Model Development
integration architecture.
Now comes designing the technical
architecture for integrating this
machine learning security components with
existing cloud infrastructure, ensuring
appropriate data access is given and
the processing capabilities are granted.
Last one would be governance framework,
where you'll be establishing an
oversight process for machine learning
security models, including guardrails,
performance monitoring, bias detection,
continuous improvement methodologies.
So this framework provides a
structured approach to implementing
machine learning within your security
architecture, focusing on high value
use cases while maintaining appropriate
governance and compliance awareness.
So what are the key takeaways
and next steps for us?
Machine learning fundamentally transforms
cloud security from static rules to
adaptive reactive to proactive intelligent
systems that continuously improve secure
successful implementations like Starbucks,
may clinic demonstrate that security
and functionality can be complimentary
rather than competing priorities.
As you begin your implementation
journey, focus on identifying high
value use cases where machine learning
can plug in and address specific
security challenges in your environment.
Start with well-defined problems.
Establish clear success metrics,
build towards a comprehensive
machine learning security framework
through iterative improvement.
Thank you.