Hi Al. Welcome everyone
to today's session.
My name is David Kumar, a and I
have 20 plus years of experience
in information technology industry.
I'm currently working as a senior lead
software engineer at Mini T Technologies,
where I lead software development
projects and mentor a team of software
to deliver a scalable and innovative.
Before joining Minis sot I worked
15 years at IBM and three years
with the Toyota Consulting Services.
Throughout my career, I have constantly
demonstrated strong problem solving
skills, a deep understanding of
software architecture, and passion for
leveraging technology to drive business.
Today discussing.
How the convergence of edge computing
machine learning and multi-cloud
strategies is reshaping the
technological landscape and significantly
enhancing enterprise on investment.
This powerful intersection of
technologies is enabling business
to process data closer to the
source, derive real time insights.
Through intelligent algorithms
and leverage the flexibility of
multi-cloud environments for optimized
performance and cost efficiency.
Together, these innovations are not
only driving operational agility
and scalability, but are also
unlocking new revenue streams,
improving customer experiences and.
Data recommendations Making
across the enterprise.
This session will highlight practical
examples and believer strategies you can
implement across the following areas,
the convergence of edge computing,
machine learning, business value
of edge machine learning, few case
studies, healthcare, point of care,
analytics, and manufacturing maintenance.
Workload placement at framework
implementation challenges and
solutions, edge optimize remodel
architectures, multi-cloud integration
strategies, implementation roadmap,
key takeaways, and next steps.
The convergence of edge
computing and machine learning.
That's taught by comparing traditional
centralized machine learning with imaging
paradigm of edge machine learning.
Centralized cloud processing
brings latency and bandwidth
concerns, edge computing processes.
Data closer to its sources on
the device are at the edge.
Edge.
Machine learning further enables
real time AI interference directly
on devices, multi-cloud support,
flexibility, distributing workload.
Intelligently across infrastructure,
business value of edge machine learning.
The benefits of Edge machine
learning are not just technical.
There are financial and operational.
We have seen up to 60%
maintenance cost reductions, 85%.
From 300 plus milliseconds
down to 14 milliseconds.
Most importantly, eight systems
remain functional even when
disconnected from the cloud
case studies.
We have a few case studies
we are going to discuss.
First case study.
I'm gonna discuss healthcare
analytics, healthcare.
Patient data overwhelmed their network.
By deploying machine learning
at the edge real time vital
processing become possible.
Lightweight models were used
onsite and federated learning.
Ensure model improved
without centralizing.
Since two data, this will lead to
detection of critical events and.
We have another case study on
manufacturing predictive maintenance.
In predictive in manufacturing.
Unplanned downtime is costly.
This manufacturing, this manufacture
reduces maintenance cost by 60% with edge
based anomaly detection models run on
local factory sensors, detecting issues.
Days before failure data from
edge loop back into the cloud
to refine models over time.
Optional workload placement framework.
Not all workload should be on the edge.
This framework helps evaluate
placement if your system does
not sub hundred milliseconds
response time edges the answer.
Think about beta gravity.
Process it where it generate.
Consider privacy complaints
and compute needs.
Often a hybrid model is ideal.
Lightweight models on the edge,
heavy training on the cloud,
implementation challenges and solutions.
Machine learning deployment
isn't without challenges.
We face
model update to logistic.
Security concerns solutions
include automation learning that
adapts to hardware containerized
deployment, and federated learning.
Use differential updates and
version control to manage
model evaluation efficiently.
Edge optimiz model architectures edge
devices need compact efficient models.
Techniques like quantization, proning,
reduced size without closing the accuracy.
Use architecture search
to find the right balance.
Federated learning that trying
models across devices while
preserving data privacy.
Multi-cloud integration strategies.
A robust edge machine learning strategy
requires a multi-cloud integration
is abstraction, leads to unify APAs
and a wide vendor locking orchestrate
workload dynamically based on the
realtime performance and costs
governance and devs pipelines ensure
smooth deployments from the edge to.
Implementation roadmap.
Implementation begins with assessment,
define goals, use cases and metrics,
build foundational tools and governance
as you scale, automate optimization and
create culture of continuous improvement.
This roadmap ensures consistent
consistency and sustainable.
Performance complaints, benefits.
It's the best approach as
a distributed architecture.
Address technical hurdles
with optimized models.
Robust governance.
Start with the high impact use case for
the value and scale confident confidently.
Thank you.
Thank you for your engagement today.
I have invited you.
Change in your organization.
Once again, thank you all.