Myself vi, I'm here to present how
we can leverage AI in financial
marketing, compliance, boosting
content creation and risk management.
The financial service industry is
witnessing a remarkable transformation.
Through artificial intelligence
integration, particularly in addressing
the complex demands of regulatory
compliances while maintaining
effective customer communications.
This presentation explores how AI driven
solutions are revolution revolutionizing
financial marketing compliances
through a deal personal approach.
That combines automated system with
human oversight, enhancing regulatory
compliance efficiency, improving content
quality, and streaming approval processes.
Year driven transformation in financial
services marketing according to.
2023 analysis financial institutions
use using AI powered compliance systems
have experienced a 64 per 7% reduction
in regulatory violation while achieving
a 42% increase in content production.
Velocity.
Organizations in implementing AI
driven compliance systems have.
Realized substantial cost saving
with an average reduction of 31% in
compliance related operational expenses
over 24 months.
As you can see, there's 78% of EI
adoption financial institu institutions
adopting implementation on planning of
AI solutions for regulatory compliances.
And 73.4% efficiency gain,
reduction in content.
Review, review time for that
from 32 hours to eight 8.5 hours
per complex marketing piece.
The reduction risk reduction
decreases its regulatory violation
related to marketing contains
the, how AI is impacting the content
quality and regulatory alignments.
This chart gives you a,
US a very comprehensive.
Outlook.
According to exit l analysis reveals that
financial institutions using AI powered
content review systems have achieved
an average accuracy rate of 93% in
identifying potential compliance issues.
Compared to 76% accuracy
rate of traditional manual
reviews, that is human reviews.
This improvement has led to a
58% reduction in revision cycles
and a 41% re decrease in time to
market for new marketing campaigns.
The financial marketing regulation.
The EFLs perspective.
According to EFL 20 23 24 annual report,
the company experienced a 34% increase in
regulatory compliances, activities related
to marketing, communication processing
over 8,750 marketing content places.
This marketing compliance team expanded
from 12 to 17 full-time professionals
representing 41.7% increase in
dedicated compliance personnel.
As you can see, they there was, there is
a almost 96.7% accuracy rate in 20 23, 24.
The compliance accuracy.
The risk prevention 392 potential
violations prevented 37%
reduction in manual review hours.
Streamlined review hours from
the, from 32 hours to 8.5
hours, eight and a half hours.
Significant cost saving, 83.4 million.
Is avoided penalties.
So
The financial institutions are
using the deal person approach
for in the AI implementation.
That is you have refine approver
and the ref refiner agents.
Initially, the initial contents
optimized with the 55% reduction
in review cycle and 91% accuracy
in identifying compliance issues.
The refiner rule is human oversight
achieving 89% compliance accuracy, and
41% reduction in the revision cycle.
According to McKenzie 2023,
state of AI report, financial
institutions implementing AI
enabled workflow has reported a 50.
3% in operational efficiency
with 71% of organization is
citing significant improvement
in their content review process.
The dual personal approach has
emerged as a particularly effective
implementation model with the
organization reporting an average
reduction of 37% in content processing
time, where yeah, there's a seamless
workflow between AI and human expertise.
Reducing the time to market by 47%.
The the dual personnel approach is
the two agents, one access an approver
another agent, accessor refiner.
What are the benefits of of AI in,
one is the natural language processing
93% of accuracy in identifying
compliance violation and with
false positive rate reduced to 3.7
compared to industry average of 12.8.
Intelligent version control.
67% reduction in document retrieval
time with 99.8% audit trial
accuracy, processing 834 documents
version monthly that has in that
has increased significantly.
System performance response time of 1.8
seconds for standard checks handling.
8,743 concurrent compliance
checks with the 99.9% system
availability according to koani.
2024 research organization implementing
AI powered regulatory technology has
achieved a reduction of 43% in compliance
processing time while improving accuracy
rate by 37.8% Compared to the traditional
manual systems, these systems can.
Process an average of 1,247 regulatory
requirements per hour, representing a
312% improvement over manual capabilities.
The.
With added the capabilities, the cost
effective analysis of I implementation.
You could see the financial institutions
utilizing AI driven compliance systems
reported an average reduction of 71 per
0.6% in regulatory penalties, and an 84%.
Decrease in compliance, reg
related operational incidents.
The comprehensive cost benefit analysis
reveals substantial financial advantages
across multiple operational dimensions.
There you can see the recovery
time, implementation costs re
recovered within 7.4 months.
The operational expense, 52.3%
reduction compared to a manual
process, the risk management improve.
It has improved its effectiveness by 63%.
The 71.6% of.
Penalties are reduced
through regulatory penalties.
The ROI 287% return of
investment over 18 months.
The human AI collaboration
in financial compliances.
According to Kanga research
organization, adopting hybrid human
AI systems have achieved operational
efficiency improvement of 57.3%, while
maintaining compliance accuracy rate
of 96.8% financial in institutions
implementing defined interaction.
Protocols between EI and the human
reviewer has reported a 63.8%
reduction in decision making time.
That is human.
Ex experts focus on complex compliances
scenarios, increased engagement by.
Hundred and 43%.
The AI processing handling 73.6% of
initial processing, reduced routine
task by 67%, approximately 67 to 68%.
Human reviewers maintain 98.7%
accuracy through final verification.
Outcome, 76% fewer regulatory
violations and 94% success in
identifying the potential issues,
the impact of AI in the financial
service content creation,
according to Han Research.
Financial institution implementing
AI driven content solutions have
achieved an average reduction of 42.7%
in content processing while improving
accuracy rate by 56.3%, organizations
reporting the reported processing
2.8 times more content volume.
With I Systems SU successfully handling
73 po percent of routine compliances.
That is the content development
reduced from 18.4 to 7.2 days.
The compliance accuracy improved
from 83%, 80, 82 0.3% to 90.
Approximately 95%
first time approvals increased
by 43 per percent customer
engagement enhanced by 37.7%.
The rec tech market
growth and future trends.
The adoption, the global expansion, the
market valuation projected to reach 13.18
billion by 2029, with implementation
rates increasing by 156% annually, 71.6%
of reduction in cross-border compliance.
Processing time with 88.4 improvement
in accuracy rate innovation.
Focus the 92% of financial
institution planning to increase
AI powered compliance investment by
an average of 27% over 24 months.
The rec tech business report
highlights significant market trends
in cross-border compliance solutions
with integrated humans, AI systems
showing particular strength in
managing multi judicial requirements.
Financial institutions using advanced
rec tech solutions achieve a return on
investment averaging 312% over 24 months.
The key takeaways and future outlooks
year integration has demonstrated a
significant improvement in efficiency
53% and accuracy of 40, 42% of accuracy
and 63 per 0.8% in risk management across
financial marketing compliance process.
The combination of AI automation
with human expertise provided by
optimal result with AI handling 73%
of initial processing while human
focus on com complex decision making.
The.
Organizations report average return
of 2 87 to 312% over 18 to 24
months timeframe with implementation
costs recovered within 7.4 months.
92% of in financial institutions
plan to increase AI investment by
27% over the next 24 months, driving
continued innovation and rec solutions.
Thank you.