Hello everyone.
My name is Neil Kumar Muso.
I work in AI data engineering.
Today I want to talk about something
really important in mission learning,
making sure our data is clean and correct.
We will look at these three useful tools
that help with this great expectations,
DQ and TensorFlow data valuation.
This slides talk about why data
quality matters in ml. Machine
learning needs good data to work well.
If the data is messy or wrong,
the model can make bad decisions.
Even small mistakes in data can
cause big problems, so we cannot
just focus on building the models.
We can also need to check our data.
The common data problems.
Here are some problems we often
see in data missing values.
Number saved as text and data
format changing over time.
High, very high or strange
values, duplicate rules.
This all can hurt.
Model's performance.
The data validation means checking
if the data is clean and correct.
Before we train a model.
It helps us finding a problem early.
We can also set up to do
these checks automatically.
Let's look at these free tools
that can help to check our data.
Great expectations, dq
TensorFlow, data validation.
Each tool is good for
different situations and teams.
Great expectation is a tool in Python.
You can write a sample rules for what
you, your data should looks like.
It works with Pandas, SQL, and Spark.
It also gives a clear
and nice look reports.
It works better for Python users, handling
small to medium size of data sets, but it.
It is not ideal for very
large or real time data.
DQ is built by Amazon
and runs on Apache Spark.
It's good for checking big data
and data that change a lot.
It can also track your
data quality over time.
It works best for AWS users,
big data or teams using Spark.
But it is not ideal for
small projects or beginners.
This is my favorite tool, which
is TensorFlow data validation.
TensorFlow data validation
is part of a TensorFlow.
It checks your data before training
a model, and it is good for dataset
and can find a problem automatically.
It works better for TensorFlow users,
but not for people using other ML tools.
This slides compare the tools.
Great expectation, easy to use.
Work well with Python.
DQ is best for big data or AWS Spark
setups, but TensorFlow validation is best
for TensorFlow or production pipelines.
So choosing the right tools, using a
great expectation for flexible rules that,
and also clear the reports using a D dq.
If your data is big or always changing,
this is the best tool to use, and
if you are using a tensor flow, then
you definitely have to definitely
use TensorFlow data validation.
This is perfectly fit when
you're using a TensorFlow.
Here are the key takeaways.
Let's remember.
The good data is just important.
As good model, bad data can
silently hurt your results.
We should use tools to
check data automatically.
Great expectations, DQ or TensorFlow, data
validation all helps in a different ways.
Here is a conclusion.
Good data equal to a better model.
Pick the tool that works better
for your team and your setup.
Make sure to check your
data early and often.
Thank you for this wonderful opportunity.
If you have any questions or
would you like to discuss these
tools more in detail, feel
free to connect me on LinkedIn.
Thank you again.
Have a nice day.