Hello everyone.
I'm Aaron Subramanian.
It's a pleasure to be here at Conti
two to talk about one of the most
urgent and timely topics in tech today.
Ethical data engineering as AI systems
increasingly influence our daily
lives, the decisions we make as data
engineers have deep societal impacts.
My talk today will explore how
we can design and operate data
systems that respect privacy,
eliminate bias, and uphold fairness.
We are going to explore real world
case studies and dive into practical
techniques with the goal of leaving
you with tools and insights you
can bring back to your teams.
And think about this as a blueprint
for ethical, scalable data systems
that actually work in practice.
We are living in an era.
Of exponential data growth by 2025, we
expect to hit 175 terabytes globally.
That's a fivefold increase since 2018.
But more data doesn't just mean better
insights, it also means greater risk.
Take for example, Facebook's
Cambridge Analytica scandal.
Millions of users personal data was
harvested and used to influence selections
That wasn't just a model failure.
It was a data engineering
failure, a breakdown in
governance, consent, and ethics.
As engineers, our
responsibilities are expanding.
It's no longer acceptable to
say I just build the pipeline.
We are also responsible for
understanding the societal
implications of the systems we create.
So nearly half of engineering teams
are working with generative AI
reporting privacy issues specifically.
That model can output sensitive
information or identifying information.
This isn't just a technical problem,
it's an ethical and legal one.
For instance, a chat bot trained
on internal company data once
leaked social security numbers.
When prompted cleverly, we can't rely on
black box models to do the right thing.
We must enforce privacy at the data level.
This is where the techniques
like differential privacy.
Federated learning and careful data.
Labeling comment
bias in AI is not limited to model design.
It can creep in at every stage of
the data pipeline, from collections
to pre-processing, to labeling.
Let me give you a powerful example.
The recruiting algorithm trained
on resumes ended up penalizing
applications that include the word
women's asin, women's just captain.
Why?
Because the training data reflected past
hiring PA patterns that favored men.
This shows how deeply bias
can bake, be baked into data.
We must actively design processes
that detect and correct such
issues before they each production.
Let's look at two main strategy strategies
for privacy preserving techniques.
One being like differential privacy,
which offers mathematical guarantees
by adding noise to outputs.
For example, apple collects usage
statistics from your phone using epsilon.
Values between two and four.
This adds enough noise to mask individual
data while preserving aggregated trends.
Meanwhile, Google's wrapper
systems uses values as low as 0.3
to protect search and usage data.
These are real world scalable systems.
On the other side, data anonymization
techniques like K anonymity,
ensures that any individual data is
indistinguishable from at K minus one.
Others.
Combining these approaches, anonymization
plus differential privacy, offers
much stronger privacy protections.
So now let's talk about how are we
gonna address algorithmic bias and
how do we fight it systematically?
First, treat fairness checks as an ongoing
process, one time audit, third work.
Second, apply intersectional analysis.
For example, if credit scoring
model might appear fair by gender
or race independently, but still
disadvantage black women due to the
intersection of race and gender.
Only 29% of the organizations
currently test for this third use
automated tools to flag imbalances.
In feature correlations and model
outputs in healthcare general fairness,
metrics missed clinical relevant
biases in 47% of applications.
Domain specific understanding is key.
Now let's look at a
case study of eCommerce.
Let's explore on this specific to
recommendation engine for which was
performing worse for female users.
On average, women received suggestions
that were 18% less aligned with
their preferences than men.
After digging in, they realized
the training data was skewed
towards male purchase behavior.
They correct this using stratified
sampling, fairness aware, feature
engineering, and model retraining.
The disparity was already reduced
significantly, and customer satisfaction
scores improved across the board.
This illustrates how we even
seemingly neutral systems like
recommendation engine scandal reflect,
reinforce bias if we are in careful
in.
Let's go through the
case study of healthcare.
Arguably the most sensitive
domain for data ethics.
Predictive analytics model designed
to forecast hospital readmissions was
underperforming for non-white patients.
The root cause.
Under representation in the training
data, the team redesigned their data
collection pipeline implemented targeted
outreach and stratified sampling.
Non-white representation
rose from 24.7% to 49%.
They then applied federated
learning to protect patients'
privacy across five institutions.
And used synthetic data generation
by gans to supplement rare subgroups.
These changes cut
performance disparity by 68%.
That's not just fair,
it's clinically better.
Now let's talk about ethical gates.
How do we implement them?
Ethics is in test separate.
Separate step.
It needs to be ba baked into
every stage of the pipeline.
Think of it as a four
gates collection gate.
Are we collecting data ethically?
With consent and appropriate
representation processing it or
our transformation introducing
bias output gate, are the outputs
privacy, safe and fair monitoring it?
Are we continuously evaluating
deployed systems for emerging risk?
This ethics by design model merits
privacy by design, and helps prevent
ethical failures beyond they occur.
Now documentation and transparency.
These are like two important things that
we need to talk about when related to
bridging the ethics and accountability.
When we log data lineage from original
source through transformations, we
create a transparent system, but we
must go beyond technical details.
What tradeoffs were made, what biases
were discovered, what limitations remain.
For example, if your dataset excludes
users under 18 due to constant rules,
note that's a limitation that could
affect general accessibility, tailor
documentation for your audience.
Technical teams want reproducibility.
Regulators want compliance.
End users want clarity,
and let's talk about.
Interdisciplinary collaboration.
Ethical systems are
built by diverse teams.
Engineers bring technical rigor, ethicist
translate principles to policies.
Domain experts provide contextual nuances.
For instance, in an education app,
collaboration with teachers revealed
that an A tutor was reinforcing
gender stereotypes in math problems.
This wouldn't have been
caught by engineers alone.
End users, especially from
vulnerable communities, must
also have a seat at the table.
They can flag issues other misses
because they live with the consequences.
And let's talk about how are we plan
to automate this whole ethical checks?
Because manual checks are not
scalable, we need an automated
system that accesses beneficiaries.
Does the system produce net
positive impact non maleficence?
Does it avoid harm, autonomy,
or users are in control?
Justice.
Are outcomes fair across groups?
Applicability?
Can we explain decisions?
Tools like IBMA, fairness 360, and
Microsoft's offer promising capabilities,
but they're not silver bullets.
We must ensure they are aligned with
real world values and validated in
production settings, not just test beats.
Now let's talk about regulations.
Regulations like GDPR.
HIPAA and UA Act are forcing companies
to treat ethics as a compliance issue.
But the best companies go further.
They embed governance by design,
build pipelines that are flexible
enough to adapt to future rules.
They maintain audit trails that
demonstrate what decisions were
made and why, and most importantly,
they foster a culture where ethics
is part of engineering, not an
afterthought imposed by legal teams.
To wrap up, ethical data engineering
is about more than avoiding risk.
It's about trust.
It's about designing systems that are
not just technically sound, but socially
responsible with privacy, preserving
tools, fairness frameworks, rigorous
documentation and interdisciplinary
collaboration, we can build data
infrastructure that ends and deserves
the trust of users and regulators alike.
Thank you for your time.
I look forward to your
questions and conversations.