Hello everyone.
My name is Naman Goel.
Today I want to talk about a profound
shift happening in artificial
intelligence, a move beyond simple text
generation towards what we call agent ai,
often powered by advanced language models.
For a while now, we have seen
AI primarily as reactive tools.
You give a prompt, you get
a text response, but the
horizon is expanding rapidly.
We are witnessing the rise of AI system
that don't just respond, but act.
They are both product active, autonomous
agents capable of understanding complex
goals, planning, interacting with
their environment, and solving problems
with minimal human intervention.
In this job, we will explore
this evolution how AI systems
are transforming from passive
responders to active problem solvers.
We will develop into technical foundations
enabling this change, examining
key operational frameworks, discuss
the crucial ethical considerations.
And look towards the exciting future
directions this research is taking.
This isn't about just better chat bots.
It's about redefining human AI
collaboration and opening entirely new
frontiers of AI research and application.
So how did we get here?
Let's chase the journey.
Initially we had text generators.
Think of early LMS like GBD
three in its initial form.
Powerful, yes, but fundamentally reactive.
They excel at generating human length
text based on specific prompts, but are
limited awareness of broader context
or the ability to act independently.
The next shift involved developing
deeper contextual understanding.
Models became better at grasping
nuances, implicit meaning with
the then request and maintaining
contextual, longer interaction.
This was crucial, but still largely
within the input output paradigm.
The real transformation is the
emergence of autonomous agency.
Modern systems, the agent ai, we are
discussing exhibit gold active behavior.
You give them an objective and they
can figure out the steps needed.
Often with minimal human guidance,
they transcend the limitations of
just generating text, speech, and
pass pattern, and this agency often
involves multi-system interaction.
Integration Agent tech AI isn't
confined into a single interface.
It can coordinate actions across
different platforms, tools, and APIs
to accomplish complex multi-step tasks.
This ability to interact with
external environments is a hallmark
of this new generation of ai.
This shift from reactive responses
to proactive goal-driven action
is the core of agent revolution.
What makes this Jump two agency possible?
Several key technical foundations
work together, which we can visualize
as layers, building from bottom up.
At the base, we have
hierarchical planning.
Instead of tackling a huge goal
at once, agent systems break it
down into manageable sub goals.
From high level strategic objectives to
specific actionable task, and finally
operational execution of individual task.
This structured approach sometimes uses
techniques like recursive refinement,
allows them to handle complexity and
maintain coherence over extended periods.
Research shows models using
hierarchical planning achieve
significantly higher success rates,
sometimes around 45% than flat plane
planning approaches on complex tasks.
Building on planning is long-term memory.
Traditional LMS are often limited
back their context window.
Agent AI needs persistence,
specialized memory structures like
episodic memory for specific events.
Semantic knowledge, basis for conceptual
understanding and working memory for
current context allows this agent to gain
information, learn from past interactions,
and build understanding over time.
Integrating explicit semantic
knowledge, for instance, has shown
accuracy improvements of up to 37%
on certain domain specific tasks.
Next, we have tool
interaction integration.
This is crucial for breaking free from
the limitations of internal knowledge.
Agent AI can leverage external
tools, APIs, and knowledge sources.
Performing web searches for real
time information, executing code for
calculations, analyzing documents,
or interacting with other software.
This capability extension dramatically
expands their functional range
implementations, using tools have
shown success rate nearly three times
of complex information gathering tasks
compared to models without multiplexis.
Finally at the top, these foundations
enabled decision autonomy.
The agent can independently evaluate
situations, selects actions based on
its goals and context, and decide how
and when it's to use its planning,
memory and tool capabilities.
It's this autonomy that truly
distinguish agent tech systems.
Okay, we have the foundations, but how
do we, these agents actually operate two
prominent frameworks, illustrate different
approaches, react and plan, and execute
the React framework, which stands for
reasoning and action combines these two
elements in the tight iterative cycles.
First formalized around late 2022.
It mirrors human cognition, observe
reason, chain of thought is often
used here, act and then observe the
result to inform the next cycle.
This continuous looks mix
react very effective in dynamic
environments where conditions change
frequently and adaptation is key.
It shows strong performance on task,
requiring information gathering,
and a multi hub reasoning like
benchmarks, hotpot, qa, and Web
Shop where React showed 31% higher
completion dates than some alternative.
It also shows for better error
recovery because feedback
is integrated immediately.
In contrast, the Plan and Execute
framework emphasizes a clear separation
between planning and execution.
Inspired by classical AI planning,
the agent first generates a
comprehensive, often data plan,
and then executes its methodically.
Making only minor
adjustments along the way.
Significant replanning only
happens if major obstacles arise.
This approach excels in more structured,
predictable environments where a
good upfront plan remains viable.
Study shows it can lead to more coherent
solutions while stakeholder ratings,
sometimes 24% higher on consistency
metrics in domains like urban planning.
It can be more efficient if
the environment is stable, as
it avoids overhead of constant
reasoning, so which is better?
The performance comparison
shows there's no single answer.
Specialized frameworks
excel in different contexts.
Tax complexity, environment dynamism, and
the need for adaptability varies various
currents, often the optimal approach.
We are also seeing normal hybrid
models emerging through that and
trying to get the best of both worlds.
Context sensitive framework selection
is crucial for building agent systems.
As these agents became more capable,
a critical question, psoriasis,
how much autonomy they should have.
We need a way to manage this responsibly.
The graduated framework
provides a structured approach.
It defines different levels of
agent's independence, human oversight.
At the lowest level, the agent
might suggest actions, but a
human was to approve every step.
Direct supervision monitor.
The agent approach operates more
independently, but requires human
verification at key points or
from certain types of actions.
Founded independence.
Here, the agent has freedom to act
within predefined safety parameters.
Constrained or rules oversight is less
direct, but the boundaries are clear.
And lastly, full otomy.
At the highest level, the agent
operates largely self-directed
with minimal human interventions,
perhaps only for setting initial
goals on handling major exceptions.
The key idea is context.
Sensity.
The pre level isn't fixed.
It should adapt based on the
task risk actions reversibility
the agent's confidence and
the sensitivity of the domain.
Research suggests these nuance.
Context sensitive boundaries can
significantly reduce unnecessary human
interventions by as much as 64% in
some studies, while maintaining safety,
balancing efficiency with control.
The agent paradigm doesn't
stop at single agents.
One of the most exciting frontiers is
multi-agent systems, where multiple
socialized agents collaborate to
tackle complex problems far beyond
the reach of any individual agent.
This enables collaborative
problem solving.
Think of a team of experts.
Frameworks like Meta GPT demonstrate this
by assigning specific roles like product
manager, architect, programmer within
a software development process, each
agent brings unique skills or knowledge.
Effective collaboration requires
internal dialogue mechanisms.
Agents need structured protocols to
communicate, share information, build
consensus, and resolve conflicts.
Experiments within frameworks like
Autogens show that structured direct
agent to agent communication can improve
task completion rates by around 37%
compared to centralized approaches.
Often these systems exhibit hierarchical
organization mimicing supervisor
worker relationships for efficient task
delegation and coordination, and fastly.
We can see emergent social dynamics,
complex group behaviors and problem
solving strategies can arrive from.
Relatively simple interaction rules
between the agents and sometimes leading
suppressive and innovative solutions.
Multi-agent systems hold immense potential
for tackling multifaceted challenges
in areas like scientific research,
complex system design, and mobile
leveraging collective intelligence.
Another major frontier is embodied agency
connecting the reasoning power of LLMs
to physical worlds through robotic.
This requires several key capabilities.
Environmental perception, agents needs
advanced sensor vision, sound touch
for real time situational awareness.
This involves processing multimodal
data and understanding context
aware scenes physical interaction.
Moving beyond just text
requires precise manipulation.
This includes adaptive force
control and sophisticated
object reasoning and handling.
Spatial navigations agent must
move autonomously through dynamic
environments using obstacles.
Avoidance and path optimization
algorithms, physical digital interaction,
creating seamless bridges between
the virtual and material rooms,
perhaps through realtime digital
twins or augmented reality interfaces.
Research here focuses on grounding
abstract reasoning in physical reality.
Frameworks like vision, language
action models integrate perception,
language, and motor skills.
System like S Spam, ERT one and RT
two are demonstrating impressive
progress, enabling robots to perform
complex manipulation tasks based on
natural language instructions with
success rates, sometimes comparable
to specialized algorithms, but
offering far greater flexibility.
Potential applications are vast
from healthcare, patient assistance
therapy to complex industrial tasks.
Manufacturing maintenance is
potentially hazardous environments
Embodied agency significantly expands
the practical impact of agent ai.
Traditional, more adults are often
chatting and training agent tech
system, especially those interacting
with the world need to adapt.
Continual learning focuses on
architecture that allow agents to
improve over through ongoing experience.
This involves several processes, often
working in a cycle experience acquisition,
gathering diverse data from interactions
with user and the environment.
Second, knowledge distillation,
extracting meaningful patterns,
principles, and generalizable
knowledge from these raw experiences.
Model adaptation, updating the agent's
internal models on neural architectures
to incorporate this new knowledge.
Catastrophic.
Forgetting prevention.
This is a critical challenge.
This involves ensuring that learning
new things does not erase previously
acquired knowledge or skills.
Technical life retrieval, augmented
generation or specialized memory helps.
Preserve critical information frameworks
like Camel and R-L-I-C-M-L illustrate
approaches where agents refine behavior
based on outcomes and feedback.
The goal is to create systems that become
more personalized, effective, and align
with user preferences over time without
constantly costing retraining cycles.
Experiments show agents using
interactive learning can achieve 24
to 38% higher success rates on complex
tasks after multiple interaction
cycles compared to static systems.
This makes AI development
more sustainable and adaptive.
Perhaps the most ambitious frontier
is meta learning or learning to learn.
This aims to create agents that can
adapt their own learning strategies
when facing new remains or challenges.
Keeping capabilities include few short
adaptations, allowing agents to master
normal tasks with minimal examples,
drastically reducing training data needs.
Dynamic architecture modification,
enabling systems to autonomous,
restructure their internal
processing based on the problem type.
Optimizing for unseen challenges.
Transferable skill acquisition
learning in one domain enhances
performance in related ones, creating
compounding returns on learning
hyper parameter, self-op optimization
models, tuning their own configuration
settings, automating previously
manual resource intensive processes.
Frameworks like Agent Verse and
I-E-L-H-E are exploring how agents
can select learning strategies
like switching between imitation
learning and reinforcement learning.
Or identifying transferable
knowledge components.
The promise here is unprecedented.
Adaptability, research indicates meta
learning agents might require 40 to
65% fewer examples to master new tasks
compared to fixed strategy learners.
This represents a significant step towards
more general, versatile and efficient ai.
While much of this is cutting edge
research, agent AI is already finding
practical applications across industries
in healthcare can integrate patient
history, research and imaging to a
diagnosis or coordinate complex care
plans across specialists in finance.
Portfolio optimization agents can
balance risk and goals independently
executing complex trading strategies
across markets In scientific research,
hypothesis suggesting can design
and conduct experiments, adapting
protocols based on emerging data,
potentially accelerating discovery.
These examples showcase the potential for
agent systems to handle complex multi-step
tasks, requiring reasoning planning
and tool use in real world scenarios.
With great capability
comes great responsibility.
The rise of utmost agents introduces
significant ethical consideration
that we must atla proactively.
We group these into key
areas, agency alignment.
How do we ensure agent
goals remain consistent with
human values and intentions?
We need mechanisms for value
drift prevention and purpose
validation, control mechanisms.
As agents become more.
How we maintain reliable oversight
and the ability to intervene.
This includes drill switches, defining
clear behavior boundaries, and designing
effective human AI interaction protocols.
The paper identifies control
risk at a critical category,
societal impact.
What are the effects of workforce
potential, job displacement and
issues of access and equity?
We need to consider displaced
worker transitions and ensure
equitable access to these powerful
technologies accountability frameworks.
Who is responsible when an
ATMOS agents makes some mistake?
We need clear frameworks.
Defining responsibility, including
decision audit trails and
stakeholder recourse mechanisms.
Yeah, so we are gonna highlight
key risk categories, misalignment,
uninvented, consequences,
deception, and in adequate control.
Addressing this require interdisciplinary
effort and em embedding ethical
considerations throughout the design,
development and deployment life
cycle, not just an afterthought.
Frameworks like values sensitive
design are crucial here.
This slide gives us snapshot of current
research focus on publication trends.
As you can see, there's immense activity
in developing novel agent architectures,
the core structures that enable agency.
Multi-agent systems are also
a major focus reflecting the
interest in collaborative ai.
We are also see significant research
and avoided AI connecting these agents
to physical world and in advanced
learning paradigms like meta learning.
Crucially, ethics and governance
is recognized as a vital research
area, though perhaps still
needing more adventure relative
to capability development overall.
This lacks clearly shows the
significant shift in AI research
towards Atmos agency moving far
beyond traditional LLM capabilities.
Looking ahead, where is Agent AI heading?
We anticipate collaborative agent
ecosystems, self-organizing communities
of specialized agents tackling complex
problems through coordinated division
of labor human agent co-evolution.
Deeper sym relationships will emerge where
humans and AI adapt together refining
knowledge, work, and collaboration.
Cognitive architecture convergence.
AI systems may increasingly
mirror aspects of human cognition,
potentially incorporating elements
like emotion, creativity, or intuition.
Alongside logic embedded ethical
frameworks, agents, stem cells might
develop more nuanced moral reason
capabilities enabling principal decision
making even in ambiguous situations.
In conclusion, the emergence of agentic
AI represents a fundamental expansion of
what artificial intelligence can be and do
by booming from reactive text generation
to proactive goal directive behavior,
these systems unlock new possibilities
for human AI collaboration, andous
problem solving across countless domains.
As hierarchical planning, memory, tool use
and learning continue to advance, these
agents will become increasingly capable.
However, this progress must be.
Guided by thoughtful evaluation,
robust safety mechanisms and
strong ethical frameworks to
ensure alignment with human values.
The transition from passive respondents
to active problem solving is just
not an incremental improvement.
It potentially is one of the
most tion developments in AI
evolution, fundamentally reshaping
how these systems participate and
contribute to human endeavors.
Thank you for attending the top.