Good morning and good afternoon to
those joining from around the world.
I'm Kian Kumar, a senior cloud architect,
architecture leader, focused on
enterprise scale digital transformation.
My work centers on building resilient,
scalable, and secure cloud infrastructure,
and increasingly, that includes
enabling safe and responsible adoption
of machine learning and ative ai.
I'm thrilled to be here at Conference
42, machine Learning 2025 to share
some of those learnings with you today.
Generative AI is accelerating
innovation at incredible pace.
The market is projected to
grow from 13.8 billion in 2023
to over 118 billion by 2032.
But risk growth comes with
new and complex challenges.
Security threats, privacy concerns,
and ethical risks that existing
cloud frameworks don't fully address.
In this session, I'll introduce a five
pillar framework designed specifically
for secur and generative AI workloads,
a model that balances innovation with
security and agility with accountability.
My goal is to help you scale
gen AI confidently and securely.
Especially enterprise environments
where risk and regulation
can be an afterthought.
Let's jump in.
Our framework is structured around file
code domains, infrastructure, security,
data protection, application security,
responsible AI and regulatory compliance.
These are not just checklists.
They are interdependent layers of a
security posture designed to protect
gene systems from external threats,
internal misuse, and reputational harm.
Each pillar corresponds to real world
challenges we have encountered in
field deployments from access control
breaches to unmonitored AI outputs.
Let's look at it one step at a time.
Infrastructure security.
Let's begin with identity and
access management as this is
the number one attack vector.
67% of organizations report
unauthorized AI access attempt,
so least privilege and multifactor
authentication are foundational.
During data transmission, all
model endpoints and inter component
APIs must be encrypted end to
end using TLS 1.3 or higher.
You can also use additionally, HSM based
key storage, which could help further
protection, use infrastructure as a code
commonly called as IAC in the industry
with embedded guardrails to prevent drift.
Automate security poster
assessments quarterly gene.
A infrastructure must be designed
with defense in depth and
not just security perimeter.
Next, let's talk about
data protection strategies.
As data is a fuel and the
vulnerability of gene ai.
Poor data governance can
leak intellectual property.
Ate privacy, or introduce bias.
Enterprises should classify training
and inference data by sensitivity.
Use data minimization to limit what
the model can access to protect
intellectual property, implement
watermarking, provenance tracking,
and legal frameworks for AI
generated outputs for personal data.
Lean into synthetic data and federated
learning and differential privacy.
Let's move on to application security.
Gene systems aren't traditional apps.
Input and output security
is an entirely new surface.
We are seeing prompt injection
tanks where users manipulate model
behavior via cleverly crafted inputs.
These require input, sanitization,
and context of validation.
Equally important is out output
scanning, real-time toxicity
detection, context filtering, and
safety classifiers are essential.
A study conducted by MIT technology
reveal 72% of gene a adopters
have already experienced at
least one unsafe output incident.
Let's move on to responsible AI.
Security is not just technical.
You all are aware it's ethical too.
Enterprise needs clear AI usage policies
and risk categorization for use cases.
Red teaming should become a routine
practice simulate adversary use cases
to expose weakness, combine automated
bias detection with human review.
Also critical prompt engineering.
Sorry, prompt security.
Threat modeling.
Understand attack vectors like
instructional leakage and defend with
boundary enforcement, prompt chaining,
control and input context filtering.
Let's move on to regulatory compliance.
Regulatory.
As regulation is moving fast.
The EU AI Act creates gene AI
in critical sectors as high risk
requiring explainability, risk
control, and human oversight.
In the US agencies like the
F-D-A-F-T-C and NIST offer segment
or sector specific guidance.
This makes multi
jurisdiction com compliance.
Complex.
Enterprise must develop
adaptable governance models.
Maintain audit trails for every
generative AI interaction, input output.
User identities and system responses
ensure they are stored in a
tamper evidence storage system.
So let's look at some practical
implementation strategies.
This framework is not just theoretical.
Here is how you can make it real.
Step one, like I mentioned
before, conduct a generative,
a specific security assessment.
The things that you need to be aware
in this assessment are map your
models, APIs, data sets and endpoints.
So these all should be part of
the assessment so that you'll
understand where the loopholes are.
Then develop policies with
cross-functional ownership.
As you are aware, business legal and
technical teams must collaborate.
Like I mentioned before, secure your APIs
with auth 2.0 and PKC, which protects
against token interception, especially in
the client side and mobile app scenarios
or 2.0 with PKC adds an extra layer
by requiring a dynamic verification,
which cannot be reused by the attackers.
Finally deploy rate limiting
and usage monitoring to identify
suspicious patterns and prevent abuse.
Now let's look at some
future considerations.
Looking ahead, the JI threat
landscape will evolve, expect
adversary prompts, data poisoning
and modeling evasion attacks.
Resilience depends on governance,
integration linking human
oversight policy, and automation
into one unique posture.
Enterprises that succeed here
won't just secure models.
They will build customer trust
and regulatory readiness as
strategic differentiators.
As generative AI matures, security
strategies must evolve to address
emerging threats and governance demands.
We are beginning to see sophisticated
risks like data poisoning, prompt
injection chaining, and model
inversion attacks that target the
behavior of the model themself.
So this requires moving beyond static
controls to adapt security approaches
such as real time prompt inspection.
Output monitoring and retraining
aware threat modeling.
At the same time, innovation in areas like
explainable gene ai privacy, preserving
machine learning, and secure synthetic
data generation will become essential.
Equally importance is the integration
of governance, aligning security with
legal, ethical and policy frameworks.
The enterprises that invest early
in both technical defenses and
responsible governance will be best
positioned to lead securely and
sustainably in the gene AI era.
Finally, thank you for your attention.
This framework is designed to
help enterprises embrace gen
AI securely and responsibly.
Thanks again for the opportunity
to speak for speaking here.