hello everyone.
I'm Kumar Madla.
Today I'm going to present what
are the advantages of auto ML
and how auto ML is transforming.
Predictive analytics with 60
to 80% of foster development.
I'm currently working as a senior data
scientist at PepsiCo, and I had ma I did
my masters in artificial intelligence
from University of EBA back in 20 at 13.
I had a total of 11 plus years
of experience working in data
science, machine learning,
and artificial intelligence.
And I have implemented projects in
multiple industries ranging from
retail, healthcare, manufacturing,
banking, and finance sectors.
So based on all my experience
and my expertise, I'm going
to present this today.
So my topic title is Democratizing
Enterprise ai, how Auto ML is Transforming
Predictive Analytics with 60 to
80% faster deployment Development.
Before understanding this Auto ml in
olden days we were using different
machine learning models and different
hyper parameter configurations, and it
is taking more time whenever you take any
problem and we have to, if you have to
develop a predictive analytics solution
being it classification, recreation
or clustering we have multiple machine
learning models and each algorithm has.
And number of hyper parameters.
And each hyper parameter
takes many different values.
Building multiple models and tuning
those hyper parameters, multiple hyper
parameters in the, coming up with
the best model takes a lot of time.
But with the advent of these.
Auto ML techniques there is a
paradigm shift in the way that
machine learning engineers or data
scientists are developing these
machine learning models for different
problems that they're working on.
So these are the advantages, main
advantages of auto ML techniques.
So this automobile techniques encompasses
and the tools that automate traditionally.
Manual expertise dependent processes
from data preprocessing and feature
engineering tool algorithm selection
and hyper parameter optimization.
And another advantage of using these
autos the bridge, the talent gap if you
how to build a different machine learning
models, if without having these auto
ml, you need to hire a machine learning
engineer or a data scientist to build.
These different models and
to come up with a solution.
But by using these auto techniques,
you can effectively bridge the
talent gap that has constrained many
organizations, analytical capabilities,
enabling business analyst and domain
experts to develop predictive models
without extensive program expertise.
So these are the evolving capabilities.
As I said early systems focused primarily
on AMIC selection and hyper parameter.
And the recent developments in the
ml focuses not only on algorithmic
selection and the hyper parameter
tuning, they also address the
entire machine learning pipeline,
including deployment and monitoring.
So these are the theoretical foundations
of, as we initially discussed in the
previous slide, these are the common.
Or basic foundations of auto.
So one is the, so this optimization
theory employs various strategies
to navigate where as they discussed
in the beginning of the session.
So these machine learning models have
different hyper parameter configurations
and each configuration, each hyper
parameter has multiple values.
So this is related to this
optimization in theory.
So what algorithm to use and
what hyper parameter tool.
Tune and what are the best values
for those hyper parameters comes
under this optimization theory
and the second foundation for
auto ML is the meta learning.
So this meta learning includes, I.
How to learn across data sets and modeling
tasks modeling tasks here, it can be
regression classification or clustering.
And how do we train multiple models
to come up with the best model to
use it in the real time and the comp.
The next third foundation for
this art M is the computational
efficiency, balancing exploration and
exploitation during the model training.
Comes under this computational a, c, and
C. So we should not focus only on the
exploration or only on the exploitation.
So we have to do a balance between
the exploration and exploitation while
training these machine learning models.
So these automal systems leverage these
foundations to efficiently identify
promising solutions while transferring
knowledge between the problems.
The employee techniques such as base
optimization, genetic algorithms, and
gradient based approaches to navigate
the complex space of possible model
configurations significantly, and also
the significantly improve the efficiency
and performance of traditional systems.
So this is how the auto ML
frameworks have been about.
So it initially started with auto
which was introduced in 2013.
So this auto.
Pioneered combined algorithmic selection
and hyper parameter optimization,
and it established the foundation
of subsequent auto ml frameworks.
This is the first in the auto ml
frameworks or auto ML techniques
which was introduced by automaker
and then it followed by autos, KN.
So this autos, KN not only involves
hyper parameter optimization
and algorithmic selection.
It also introduced the
transfer learning concept.
So what does it mean by transfer?
Learning is so the, any model or
algorithm that was trained on one task
can be used to retrain on another task.
Maybe we can take an example
of any deep planning models
or image recognition models.
So the models that were trained to.
Identify cats and dogs can be used to
retrain from last couple of layers to
identify other things other animals
like horses of, or any other animals.
So this comes under transfer learning and
nowadays there are more advanced auto ml.
Frameworks are coming up into the market.
They not only focus on hyper
parameter optimization and algorithmic
selection, they also focus on
data preprocessing and other data
preparation and other techniques.
Some of the notable players in this
end-to-end platforms are Google
Cloud, R ml, and H2O is driverless
a and they extend automation
across the entire ML lifecycle.
This is an extension
to the previous slide.
These are the prominent
auto ML framework analysis.
Now I'm comparing the differences between
Autor, IBM's Auto, aa, and Microsoft.
And I, as we discussed it in the
previous slide auto was introduced in
2013, and it focuses more mostly on
the algorithmic selection and hyper.
Tuning.
And the technique is called sequential
model based algorithmic configuration,
and it uses patient optimization to
navigate these complex set spaces.
And in 2023 KDD has awarded auto.
As a test time award in 2013.
20, sorry.
2023. IBM's next one is IBM's Auto A.
It extends traditional capabilities by
addressing the entire machine learning
lifecycle within enterprise context.
It also includes automated
data preparation, feature
engineering, model selection,
and high parameter optimization.
The main difference with respect to IBM's
Auto AAEs, it has a strong integration
with IBM's Watson Ecosystem and it
enterprise focused features like built in
fairness checks and explainability tools.
The third one.
In this comparison is a Microsoft's NNI.
It takes a specialized approach
focusing on neural network optimization
and automated deep learning.
It provides infrastructure and a
neural architecture search, hyper
parameter tuning and model compression
through a highly modular framework.
It also supports deep learning
frameworks such as tensor flow by, sorry.
It's such as the tensor flow.
By touch, et cetera.
It offers flexible deployment options
across diverse computing environments.
This is the framework comparison,
strengths and limitations.
These are the different strengths
and limitations of the three
frameworks that we have discussed.
Auto, IBM's Auto, a I, and Microsoft.
And I let us first start with the auto.
So the primary strength
of Otca is in pioneering.
Cash solution.
And it also integrates with
established ML toolkit and it
has a strong academic foundation.
And the key limitations with AKA is it
has a limited end-to-end automation.
It has less support for deep learning,
minimal enterprise integration features.
And the best enterprise use cases
for using auto is academic research.
For developing proof of concept projects,
and it'll be suitable for organizations
with existing WCA investments.
The next one is auto EI which is from IBM.
The primary sense of auto from
IBM is its end to end ML lifecycle
Automation, built in fairness and
explainability tools strong, and it
has a strong enterprise integration.
The key limitations, it can be
limitation for some of the users.
We will have a vendor lock in with
IBM, and it's a proprietary ecosystem.
It may be expensive for some clients, and
it is higher implementation complexity.
The complexity of implementing IBM's auto,
difficult and the best enterprise use case
for IBM's Auto AEs regulated industries
like finance and healthcare organizations
since existing IBM infrastructure
application requiring explainability.
The third one in this comparison
is and I from Microsoft.
The primary strength of NI is it's
deep learning specialization, multi
framework support, flexible deployment
options, and the key limitations.
It has a steep learning curve, less
focus on classical ML algorithms and
requires more technical expertise.
Best enterprise use cases are day planning
applications, optimizations with teams
with strong technical capabilities.
These are the enterprise
integration considerations.
So IT infrastructure integration
organizations must evaluate compatibility
with current data, current storage
solutions, processing frameworks, and
more and model deployment infrastructure.
A PA based integration approaches
have emerge as preferred.
Allowing auto ML systems to interact
with existing data pipelines
while minimizing disruption.
And these are the deployment options.
Cloud-based deployments offer
scalability, but may introduce
data movement challenges.
So when you have to implement a solution
in the cloud-based infrastructure,
you may have to move your data from
in-house systems to cloud-based systems,
which comes with some cost and time.
On-premises implementations provide
greater control, but require significant
computational resources and the
middle ground like hybrid approach.
Leveraging containerization
and orchestration technologies
present a promising middle ground
data governance requirements.
Robust mechanisms for data quality
assessment, version control.
Linear tracking and access
control are essential.
Auto assistance typically require
substantial volumes of training data.
Amplifying the importance of
governance frameworks that ensure
data accuracy and appropriate use.
Organizational adoption for
auto MR. Traditional boundaries
between engineering, data science
and ation analysis roles often
blur as auto ML democratizes.
Model development capabilities
and these auto ML establishes
cross-functional governance.
Successful implementations typically
establish cross-functional teams
responsible for model governance with
clearly defined hands of between automated
and human LED processes, implement
change management address potential.
Resistance from technical specialists
while encouraging responsible
adoption by business users through
targeted training and communication.
Create tiered approaches.
Many organizations implement tiered
approaches where straightforward
predictive tasks leverage auto ml, while
complex mission critical applications
maintain greater human oversight.
These are the enterprise benefits.
Of using auto, 60 to 80% of the
development time will be reduced by
using these auto ML techniques or
strategies, and there will be a return
on investment within 12 to 18 months
of adopting these auto ML strategies.
And there will be 30% reduction
in downtime when using these
optimal strategies or techniques.
Democratization of predict two analytics.
The first one is expanded access.
Auto ML enables business analysts,
domain experts, and non-specialists to
develop sophisticated predictive models
with less machine learning knowledge.
Breaking down silos allows those
closest to business problems to direct
end engine and solution development.
Citizen data science.
Many enterprises establish citizen
data scientist programs with auto
ML as the technological foundation.
Multiply the capabilities
effectively multiplies analytical
capabilities without proportional
increases in specialized hiring.
These are the implementation
challenges, interpretability concerns.
Automated approaches often generate
complex models resistant to
straightforward human understanding.
Data quality dependencies systems
remain foundationally, fundamentally
dependent on data quality, potentially
amplifying underlying issues,
domain specific requirements.
Generic solutions often struggle with
highly specialized domain problems
requiring industry specific approaches.
Technical debt, cremation, unmanaged
adoption can accelerate technical debt.
Through model proliferation
without adequate governance.
These are some of the strategies
to overcome those challenges.
Implement explainable a address data
quality, enable domain customization.
So the first one is
implement explainable ai.
So integrated explainable AI
techniques alongside auto ml establish
interpretability thresholds for
different application categories and.
Maintain simpler model adoption
for high transparency requirements.
Address data quality, implement
systematic data quality assessment
prior to auto ML deployment.
Automated data quality monitoring clear
processes for handling quality exceptions
and realistic expectation setting.
Establish data quality
thresholds that must be satisfied
before automated modeling.
Proceeds enable domain customization.
Develop customized autoAML frameworks
that incorporate domain knowledge via
specialized pre-processing pipelines,
custom algorithm implementations, domain
specific object, two functions and expert
guided constraints on model exploration.
These are the future directions.
For using auto explainable a integration,
next generation auto ML frameworks
are incorporating explainability by
design rather than as in afterthought.
This includes optimization objectives
that balance predictable performance
with interpretability metrics and
automatic generation of explanation
artifacts, edge computing applications,
auto resistance, specifically designed
to optimize models for edge development.
Considering resource constraints, power
limitations, and specialized hardware
accelerators, these systems automatically
balance model complexity against
inference speed and memory footprint.
Federated approaches converging with
auto ml to address data privacy and
sovereignty challenges, enabling
prediction model development
across decentralized data sources.
Without requiring data centralization,
regulatory aware, evolving regulatory
frameworks are driving innovation
in automated compliance verification
and documentation generation with
systems incorporating regulatory
awareness directly into optimization.
Objectives.
Enterprise implementation roadmap.
Assessment and planning.
Identify high value use cases, evaluate
data readiness, select appropriate
framework and define governance structure.
Success metrics include prioritize,
use case portfolio, and.
Established success criteria.
Common challenges include
unrealistic expectations and
insufficient data quality.
Assessment, initial implementation,
deploy optimal for targeted use cases,
established and monitoring and evaluation.
Train initial user cohort,
and document early learnings.
Success metrics include model performance
metrics and development time reduction.
Challenges include.
Technical integration issues and
resistance from data scientists, scaling
and optimization, expand use case
governance, enhance governance frameworks,
establish model arts practices, and
integrate with business processes.
Success metrics include enterprise
web model inventory, and the
business impact measurements.
Challenges include model
proliferation and technical data
accumulation and advance integration.
Incorporate emerging auto ML capabilities.
Integrate with.
Complementary AI systems develop
custom domain adoptions and establish
continuous improvement cycles.
Success metrics include hybrid,
a, system effectiveness and
competitive differentiation metrics.
Strategic recommendations For
enterprise adoption, we have to first
start with phased implementation
and then proceed balance to
governance model, strategic workforce
integration with use case boundaries.
Organizations should adopt
phased implementation.
Approaches that balance ambition with
paradigm initial deployment should
target well-defined use cases with clear
success criteria and model complexity.
Moderate complexity.
Effective governance structures typically
combine centralized oversight with
distributed execution capabilities.
Thank you.