Hi everyone.
Good morning and good afternoon.
So myself, was Ari.
Good lady.
I am currently working
as a tech lead with Roku.
A streaming company which everybody's
familiar, most of the people.
And today I'm gonna talk about how we do,
how to handle a data skew in a production
ML pipelines, and what are the challenges
that we have and uncover encounter,
and then how we mitigated those issues
technically and in a step by step process.
So I try to cover.
As much as I can in these
next 25 to 30 minutes.
And so let's get started.
As I mentioned Roku is a streaming
company and in the streaming
business, like we process a billions
of watch events and ad impressions
every single day and every play.
Pause or recommendation,
impression and ad.
Click feeds into spa pipelines, powering
like personalized models, embedded
generation, and also ad ranking systems.
So these are the different machine
learning pipelines we run to understand
the user's behavior while watching
these shows or any television programs.
On paper, like everything looks scalable,
distributed computing and partition
at the storage level, auto-scaling
clusters, but can solve any many problems.
But again, like in reality, what we
have observed is jobs that normally
runs in 40 minutes or less than an hour.
Surely it started taking
like nearly three hours.
Without any code change,
any infra changes.
We started seeing such a long running
jobs and when we investigated.
That why these jobs are taking a lot of
time and it's many it's a case with the
many other teams and whoever is using a
spark for their ETL compute and all that.
We saw extreme task duration variance.
That's because we en encountered
a silent performance bottleneck
that's called a data skew today.
I'm going to walk you through the skew
manifestation in the manifest in the real
ML pipelines and how systematically we
can medicate the, those kind of risks.
Let's jump in.
So the first question, why these
why everybody have a question in the
mind, like, why these ML models trying
slowly earlier they were running good.
So the ML pipelines are performance
bottleneck is like ML plugged by
the Ian Performance Killer that
turns these minutes into hours and
training jobs extend indefinitely
and model deployments get delayed.
And so in turn what we have seen is like
our cloud costs burn through the budgets.
So then who is the culprit here again,
when we investigate, we saw data skew.
So it's not just about the bad code,
it's about like uneven data distribution
or any spike in the events or watch
events that basically distribution
across these partitions silent.
Stab sabotaging your pipeline efficiency.
So when we click it, it, when we click
down into more technicality of this
problem, and we see in the spark a
stage when the spark has different
stages, the if you know about the spark
process and so a stage only completes
when the slowest task finishes.
In on the, in the retraining jobs, we have
observed that 95% of the task is completed
like quickly within seconds, minutes, but
one executor ran significantly longer.
And processing nearly more than
10 x of more shuffle data than any
other executor in, in that stage.
And shuffle spills has been
increased and garbage collection
pauses and CP utilization is a
hundred percent and cluster dropped
because of the other executors
who are cluster users is dropped.
And executors were idle.
And this is a significant effect of
a data skew problem, even though most
partitions finish quickly, but anti
job waits for one single partition.
So let's look at what is
this data skew in general?
So a data skew.
In a simple words, what I call it as
like the unbalanced workload problem.
So your executors taking uneven data to
process uneven partitions to process.
But what is the expectation in the ideal
world is like we want to distribute
this data evenly spread across all
the executors, all workers processing
similar data volumes and power processing
because the spark itself is a distributor
parallel power processing ETL engine, and
we want it's full processing at a full
efficiency and predictable completion
times given the scale of the data.
But in reality with the skew problem,
some executors process gigabytes
while the other handle megabytes,
the entire job waits for one.
Particular or like the slowest
executor and the job times like
take like very much longer.
And the downstream, it has an impact
of the downstream jobs and it gives the
entire the pipeline processing performance
and the sources, the resources is like
the, these executors, it idle until
the other worker completes his job.
So when you talk about like the more,
deep dive into what what has happening is
like a spark uses like hash partitioning
during these shuffle operations and data
is distributed based on these hash numb
partitions, but the real world behavior
follows the power law distribution.
That means.
For an example, as this is a streaming
company, one user have one user
watches like a little program, so the
other user watches a lot of programs
and clicks on and different things
while he is watching the program.
And for the use case, like one user
has two interactions, another user has.
Say 150 interactions.
And when we group this data based on
the user's behavior and then and the
heavy user dominates one partition,
that partition spills to dis and it
overall increases the shuffle read time,
and causes the prolonged task runtime.
And in this case, the parallelism breaks
because of the workload is uneven.
So how this is going to impact
the production pipelines is.
The impact of the production purpose.
I can categorize into
two different categories.
One is a technical performance impact.
The other one is the
bigger business impact.
So when I talk about the technical
performance impact is the future
engineering bottleneck, so you
slow down on a features engineering
just because your jobs are running
and you need to handle these.
Issues and extended model training
times, and we want this job to
be completed in 30 minutes, but
it is taking three to four hours.
It's a, it is a bigger problem there
and delayed experimental psych and model
freshness, most importantly, as in,
in case of the recommendation systems.
And we want to process the data
within fraction of seconds.
And the business impact that I can see
because of these technical difficulties
and technical performance issues is
a higher cloud infrastructure cost.
Just because, like you, your
resources is just idle and
you are wasting money on them.
And then slower time to market for models
and reduce the data science productivity.
Of course the ML model is running
longer than they used to and we need to
compromise on these SLAs and all that.
Score.
So basically sku when we talk about the
data skew, is it's not only increases
the shuffle read size and specific
task, it also have execut imbalances
and also a lot of technicality in terms
of like long garbage collection cycles.
Most importantly in
recommendation systems, as I
mentioned, as a business impact.
The delayed retraining reduces
personalized freshness, meaning, so
basically you want to recommend as in when
the user coming in and want you watching
a program and you want to recommend
him, like a similar kind of a content.
And then thus that freshness and
personalization is something it reduces.
And in the ad ranking systems, like
sometimes we have seen a 20% inefficiency
just because of this data skew problem.
When it when we talk about the
business impact for this issue is
like we can translate into millions
annually in a compute cost, just for
the scale of 20% inefficiency and.
So how, like when we categorize
these problems in the machine
learning pri pipelines how we
can classify these problems?
So one is there are different
pipelines, ML pipelines and
that we are running currently.
We have recommendation systems
and we have classification models
that we run, and also the computer
vision pipelines that we run.
So in, in general in recommendation
systems, a small number of
power users are a viral content.
For example, super Bowl last
week is a like so many people
watches and a lot of interactions
which can overload those specific
partitions in classification models.
Majority of those classes dominate
the data set, creating imbalance
and uneven executor workloads.
John.
Similarly, in the computer
vision SKUs shows up both up
in uneven class distribution,
variable image crossing times.
This leads to the
computational imbalance and.
The key takeaway with this is we
need to, the skew is not an accident.
It is a natural outcome of real
world events or data patterns that we
are seeing if not handled properly.
This is going to cost a lot of
millions of dollars for the companies.
And at the scale of billions and
billions of regards we process
for these recommendation systems
and these classification models.
So let's deep dive into what are
the, like different root causes this
could the data skew should have.
The first root cause I can think
of is the natural imbalance.
As I mentioned this could be
because of the bigger events like
Super Bowl and where we get a lot
of traffic into into the system.
And training data naturally reflects these
real world patterns where user behavior
follows the power law distribution.
So that means that the customers
can concentrate, concentrate
geographically and seasonal patterns
create temporal IM imbalance.
Like any event or formula One or Superbowl
any event can create that imbalance.
So the, in that case, the most ML
training data reflects these power
law distributions where a small
number of users, products, and regions
generate the majority of activity.
This create a skewed source data.
From the start, such as popular
products and like we have these
ads category and highly active
users dominating these data sets.
When the partition data on these hotkeys,
certain partitions become overloaded.
When, while others remain underutilized.
So the problem often like propagates
downstream into feature stores and
model training pipelines, amplifying
the performance bottlenecks.
So this is one of the biggest
problems that we have seen.
And the key takeaways that SKU is
not a system bug originates from
the, again it's from the real
world behavior patterns and must be
anticipated in these pipelines design.
So the other root cause that I can, that
I see most commonly for this data skew
problem is the joint keys and aggregation
of these data on these joint keys.
So basically like in this one the
join and aggregation operations,
during this feature engineering,
when we join user features.
With the behavioral data, certain
popular or highly active I user IDs can
dominate the data set, creating these
hard partitions and uneven workloads.
This is known as a joint key sku.
Similarly aggregation, a similarly
aggregation operations like group
by or reduced by key can suffer
when a small number of keys contain
disproportionately large volumes of
the data and temporary aggregation,
such as daily, weekly summaries that
we do and often amplify this effect
because of the activity levels.
Can vary significantly across time.
The key takeaway is that even the
raw data looks manageable, but joints
and aggregations can concentrate data
and in unexpected ways and create
serious performance bottleneck all
because of these data skew problem
if you are not handled rightly.
One another one that I can
see is a computational skew.
Which means the text vector in
case of these machine learning
models, text vectorization, future
engineering, embedding generation
is a deep learning vary in
computation cost based on the input
characteristics and model complexity.
So even so as we talk earlier, like even
though we feel the data is right and when
we actually join this data, we have seen.
Imbalances in terms of these
partitions and these joints
is taking longer, much longer.
So even in this case, like even the data
is even distributed across the partitions
and workload imbalances can still occur.
And NLP models handle variable length
documents and longer sequences require
significantly more compute time in future
engineering and complex transformations
on these high cardinality category
data create uneven processing loads.
So this is like one of the and we
have seen these very frequently, which
silently creates these performance
bottleneck in these distributed system.
So as we have seen so far, what is
the data skew and how, what are those
different root causes that we see the
way data skew can decide and hide?
So now we talk about more about how we can
basically like mitigate these problems,
data skew problems in a step by step.
The number one solution I can
think of is repartitioning.
So this is the concept like where
we, instead of we give the system to
distribute the data, we explicitly
redistribute the data across the
cluster by specifying the partition
count and the column as I given in the
code snippet in this one, based on the
user ID and given the repartitioning.
Count is like a hundred.
I want the system, I want
the spark to redistribute the
data across the executors.
These forces spark to rebalance the
workload through hash partitioning.
And this is mostly best for moderately
skewed data sets and multi-stage
ML pipelines and future engine
workflows, training data reprocessing.
So this is most importantly this is
one of the best technique that we
can use when we have a moderately.
Less queue data.
The key takeaways that Repartitioning
gives us the control over the data
distribution and the better workload
balance before expensive transformations
like joins and aggregations.
Let's move on to the next slide.
So the repartitioning,
so when and how to apply.
So the optimal setting for this
one is a partition count two
to three x total core count.
When it all depends on which, how
big is your cluster, how many codes
that you are working with, and the
partition size is ideally a hundred
to 200 mb is a, is our sweet spot in
terms of the partitioning size count
and balance parallelism with overhead.
So when we talk about the limitations
and inter introduces a shuffle operation,
so as you are redistributing the data.
Hash partitioning does not
change the key frequency.
Eff ineffective for the extreme.
Skew scenarios like when you have a large
data, large skew for one particular region
or something, then you need to think about
other techniques to redistribute the data.
So the performance gains, like more rate,
performance gain, and most effective
in future pipeline stages and all that.
So in our case, we absorb with
the redistribution repartitioning
strategy, and we have 30% implement
in our repro pre-processing stages.
However, repartitioning does
not change key frequency.
Extreme hard keys still remain
dominant, as I mentioned in the slide.
And optimal, partion size is
like a hundred to 200 mb Move on.
Moving on.
The second solution that we, that's
most recommended and most popular
is a key salting me meaning like
so you identify the hard key,
which is improper distribution.
You add us all to it, you
add a random number or.
Some number and spread those partitions.
So in, in that example I just added
like a random of some random number
into multiply by 10 with the user
ID and then redistributing the data.
So this gives so when certain keys such
as high AQ user IDs dominate the dataset,
repartitioning alone may not be enough.
Key salting works by adding a
small random value as I mentioned,
the key mentioned in the slide.
Effectively spliting the single
hot key into multiple smaller keys,
spreads the workload across multiple
partitions, breaks up hotspots.
So the key takeaways
that salting allows us.
Proactively distribute the extreme
skew when basic is, are responsible for
overwhelming data overwhelming the cluster
with the, a large partition of data and
one executor taking that entire load.
So what are the best scenarios
like when we can use like low salt?
So there are like two to four.
Keys like that.
And the and we need to do 34,
so resolve for extreme skew.
So when a single dominant value,
so as I mentioned, like there's a
dominant key, hot keys will be there.
And so what we do, we basically we
I append the random salt keys to
heavy user IDs before aggregation.
Large partition reduces from eight gig,
like in our case, like eight gig to
600 mb or training runtime reduced like
nearly 50% in some cases, and salting
requires an additional aggregation stage.
But s the workloads significantly.
And the last one here I
have is the broadcast joint.
This is also very significant
in terms of improving the.
Spark jobs, performance and skew.
When we have a skew data.
So it's always ideal to send the
small, smallest table into the memory.
So send the small table to all
executor to join and it increases
the joints per joint performance.
And also this eliminates the shuffle.
That is a big thing of your large dataset
entirely as mentioned in the code snippet
here, we just need to use the broadcast.
It it under spark will understand.
This is a small table.
This is the table that need to be
sent to memory for all the executors
and it'll broadcast the data.
So basically essentially what you
are, what we are trying to do is like
we try to avoid redistributing the
large data sets across the cluster.
This, drastically or drastically
reduce the network overhead.
Broadcast joints are affect you
in future engineering pipelines,
whereas large behavioral data is
joined with a relatively small
dimension or lookup data table.
The key takeaway is that in
this one in stuff moving.
Massive data across the cluster.
We move the smaller table once
and process the joint more eff
effectively and efficiently.
This way our model performance,
like the pipeline performance
is significantly improved.
So here are some guidelines
and best practices that we can
use, keep the broadcast table.
Under 10 mb there's a typical
limit, use a maximum of 20, 21% off.
Execute memory to avoid GC garbage
pressure during training and a significant
data size disparity between tables.
So that means like when you are
joining a hundred gig table with
a one g, one GB of data set.
So that's when the broadcast
will be very helpful and handy.
And then we can send these a small table
into memory for a more efficient join.
And performance impact.
It eliminates the, as I mentioned it,
eliminate a lot of network traffic
and network shuffle, and the scale
with the table size, difference
and critical for maintaining model
freshness in production systems.
So in this case this as I mentioned
before this is a shuffle of large data
sets and one enrichment stage drop.
Like in our case, like 90.
90 minutes to almost 10, close to 10
minutes ensures the broadcast join size
remains under 20, 25% executor memory
to prevent these gc warhead issue.
So overall, the key takeaway so
we understand what is the data
skew and how it is going to
impact our production ML skews.
What are the root causes and
what are those like medications
that we can do in terms of avoid
this data skew and handle it.
We can't avoid the data skew.
We can handle the data
skew in a right way.
And so basically like I, as I said use the
rep partitioning when the data SKU is like
moderate sku or if you have a larger sku.
In most of the cases we have
used mostly the salting.
In terms of skew data and broadcast
joints, which helped significantly
optimizes selective targeting specific
bottlenecks rather than rather than
over engineering the entire pipeline.
Finally.
So I would say when implemented
correctly these, these techniques
lead to faster model training.
So it saves a lot of cost and
time and also freshness of the,
keep the freshness of the data and
better resource utilization, lower
infrastructure costs and also it'll
help to do a quicker development cycles.
So with that we are also currently
working on how we can leverage
ai in terms of identifying.
These gaps in a pre hand.
And help us suggest like when there
is a data skew that's going to happen,
we want to scan through these data
sets and help suggest these are the
hotkey or these other, this is where
the data has being distributed heavily.
So then we so that, like with the
help of ai, we are experimenting
with models trying on historical
spark metrics to predict a data skew.
Risk before stage execution.
These models could recommend partition
counts, as I said, and salting factors
and broadcast strategies dynamically.
This this represents a shift towards self
optimizing distributed ml P ML pipelines.
That's where, that's what we are
planning to achieve with that.
Thank you everyone and
hope you like the content.
If you want me to really want to
connect on LinkedIn you can type good
lady, and I'm happy to talk more.
Thank you.