Speaker 28: Hi everyone.
I'm Simon Ach.
I'm a senior machine learning
engineer working on perception
systems for autonomous vehicles.
My work centers on taking models
from research ideas all the way
through real world deployment
in safety critical environments.
In this talk, I'll share how the
autonomous vehicle industry is
moving from fragmented perception
pipelines to unified end-to-end
models, and what we have learned
while scaling the systems in practice.
Before we dive in, here's a quick roadmap.
We'll start with the fragmentation
problem in traditional perception
stacks, and discuss why separate
models for each task create
inefficiencies and hidden failure modes.
Then we'll look at the unified
perception paradigm and how a single
integrated system can learn, share
representations across task consensus.
From there, I'll introduce Multisensor
Fusion transformers, which are
a key architectural enabler for
making this approach practical.
After that, I'll share some real world
deployment challenges and lessons
from production because scaling
perception outside the lab is where
most of the complexity really shows up.
And finally, we'll touch on foundation
models for autonomous driving, which I
see as the next frontier for making the
systems more scalable and data efficient.
By the end, you should have both the
technical intuition and the practical
perspective behind unified perception.
Let's start with the core problem.
Most traditional perception
systems are highly fragmented.
We typically train one model for
detection, another for segmentation,
and one more for depth, and
sometimes even separate models.
Each sensor, each of those modules
processes the same inputs independently,
which leads to duplicated computation,
high latency, and errors that
cascade from one stage to the next.
But beyond efficiency, the bigger issue
is that these models never develop
a cohesive understanding of the sea.
They're optimized locally
rather than globally.
So over time, the system becomes
complex, brittle, and harder to maintain.
The alternative approach
is unified perception.
Instead of isolated models, we train
a single end-to-end system that
jointly learns spatial semantic,
and temporal representations.
All sensors feed into SHA encoders
and lightweight task heads
branch out for specific outputs.
Because those features are shared,
improvements in one task naturally
benefit the others detection.
L segmentation informs depth,
and everything improves together.
So we reduce redundancy while
actually increasing accuracy.
The system becomes both
simpler, architecturally, and
stronger performance base.
One of the biggest enablers of
this shift has been transformers.
Self attention lets us model long
grade relationships across the
scene, which is critical in driving
where context really matters.
Cross model attention allows the
network to align camera appearance
with lidar geometry automatically
instead of relying on and design fusion
Rules and token based representations
make it easier to handle different
sensor resolutions and modalities.
Together these properties make
transformers a very natural fit
for unified end-to-end perception.
If we break the architecture down,
there are three main components.
First, a shared backbone
that extracts general purpose
features across all sensors.
Second cross model alignment networks
that project lidar and camera information
into a unified latent space, and
third temporal fusion modules that
aggregate information over time.
This temporal component is especially
important because a single frame
can be ambiguous, but motion across
frames reveals intent and continuity.
When we train these models, we also
train the 2D and 3D elements of
it jointly rather than separately.
Images gives us rich semantics like
texture and appearance, while point
clouds provide precise geometry and depth.
By combining both these modalities,
we get the best of each.
This leads to better 3D boxes,
more stable depth estimates,
and a unified representation.
The downstream modules like tracking
and planning can depend upon.
In practice this joint learning
significantly improves robustness.
One key lesson from real world
deployment is that sensors don't fail.
Uniformly.
Rain or darkness might degrade
cameras while fall, or sparse
returns can affect lidars, so
static fusion simply isn't enough.
Instead, we use adaptive attention
mechanisms and dynamically weight
each sensor based on reliability.
When one degrades, the system
automatically leans more on the others.
This gives us graceful degradation,
extra sudden failures, which
is critical in terms of safety.
As soon as we move outside control
settings, new challenges appear, weather
changes, geographic differences and
domain shifts, all impact performance.
And then there are long tail scenarios
like construction zones, emergency
vehicles, or unusual pedestrian behavior.
These rare events matter the
most for safety, and they show
up the least containing data.
So we rely heavily on targeted
data collection, balance sampling,
and continual learning strategies
to cover those edge cases.
There's also a big
engineering benefit here.
Traditional stacks acquire multiple
models, multiple inference passes,
and complex interfaces between them.
Whereas unified perception simplifies all
of that into a single forward pass that
reduces latency, makes debugging easier
and significantly streamlines deployment.
From an infrastructure standpoint,
this is a huge operational bit.
Another important trend is supervised
rather self supervised learning
Labeling, autonomous driving data at
scale is extremely expensive, so instead
we use techniques like contrastive
alignment, temporal consistency,
and cross sensor reconstruction to
learn directly from unlabel data.
This lets us scale training
to massive data sets without
proportional annotation costs.
Helps capture the long tail scenarios
that are the hardest to label manually.
Even with large scale training
data distribution shift is
unavoidable in autonomous driving.
Every new city looks different,
lighting changes, road layouts change,
and even driving behavior changes.
So models that work well in one
place can negate somewhere else.
To handle this, we use domain adaptation
techniques that allow the system
to adjust continuously, including
adversarial, future alignment, test
time adaptation, and rapid fine tuning.
The key idea is that perception isn't
something you train once and freeze.
It's something that keeps learning
and adapting as the vehicle
encounters the real world.
Now, let's come to the new and hot
topic in the industry right now.
Those are foundational models.
By pre-training on massive
driving data sets, we learn strong
general purpose representations
that transfer well across tasks.
Then we only need lightweight heads
for detection, tracking, or prediction.
What's especially exciting
is zero shot behavior.
These models often generalize to unseen
scenarios without explicitly training,
which is incredibly valuable when you
can't label every possible edge case.
So stepping back, what do we gain overall?
We get lower latency because
everything runs in a single pass.
Better accuracy through shared
learning and simpler deployment
with fewer moving parts.
It's rare to find an approach that
improves both performance and engineering
complexity at the same time, but
unified perception really does both.
Ultimately, all of this
ties back to safety.
Consistency and understanding
reduces error propagation.
Temporal reasoning improves
predictions of dynamic agents and
adaptive fusion maintains robustness.
When sensors degrade together, these
improvements translate directly
into fewer disengagements and more
reliable behavior in the real world.
So unified perception ist
just an architectural choice.
It has a measurable safety impact.
To summarize.
Unified architectures
streamlined perception.
Multisensor fusion is essential, and
foundation models combined with self
supervision will continue accelerating
progress as these systems mature
autonomous vehicles become safer, more
scalable and better acute to handle
the complexity, the real world driving.
Thank you for your time.
If you'd like to continue the
conversation, feel free to stand the Q
are code and connect with me on LinkedIn.