Hey.
Hi everyone.
I am Sandid Gini, a technical
program manager with over 17 years
of experience right now working in
Hitachi Digital Services here at Dallas.
In my previous organizations, I have
worked acro, I have worked in large
technology transformation banking
projects across multiple geographies.
Today I'm here to talk about LLM
Power Banking Organization coming
to, coming back to the slides.
The first slide, I'm excited to
sh share with you a groundbreaking
approach to one of the bank's
banking's most persistent challenges,
LLM Powered Banking Modernization.
Coming back to the next slide, when we
look at the banking industry today, we are
facing that, what I call legacy burden.
This pie chart tells us a stock story.
Legacy maintenance is consuming
up to 65% of IT budgets in
most financial institutions.
Think about that for a moment.
Two thirds of your technology
spend just keeping the lights on.
Most banking systems still run
on cobol, a language developer
before many of us were born.
It's reliable, but it's becoming
increasingly difficult to maintain.
The talent Pool of COBOL
developers is shrinking.
While demand for new digital services
exponentially grown, I've seen
this firsthand while working on
transformation projects across multiple
banks across multiple geographies.
One CIO told me we are spending so
much maintaining our legacy system
that we can't invest in our innovation,
our customer's demand coming to the
slide three, it's a modernization.
It's talking about the
modernization paradox.
So why not just modernize?
The statistics on this slide, we, what
they call the modernization paradox,
traditional transformation approaches.
Have an 85% failure rate projects that
exceed budget missed deadlines, or simply
fail to deliver and expected value.
The average duration stretches beyond
24 months, and I have personally
witness asked budget overturns of three
to five times the original speeds.
One project I consulted on began with
an 18 month timeline and ended up
taking over four years to complete.
The reality is that financial institutions
need a fundamentally new approach.
Of all methods, ofri rip and replace
man or manual code conversion simply
cannot scale to meet modern demands,
especially given the criticality of these
systems and zero tolerance for errors.
Coming back to the next
slide, a new paradigm.
This is where our new framework comes in.
We have doubled three trial
approach that SSEs the core
challenges of banking modernization.
At the foundation, we have
a human AI partnership.
This isn't about replacing human
expertise, it's about amplifying it.
Banking domain experts work alongside
AI to ensure that business rules and
regulatory requirements are preserved.
Amelia Tire focuses on
accelerated modernization.
By using LLMs, we can transform code
faster and more reliably than manual
approaches, drastically reducing
project timelines at the top.
We enable competitive advantage
through innovation capabilities.
That were previously locked behind
Legacy Constraints One Bank using
approach was able to reduce their future
deployment time from months to days.
Our framework maintains regulatory
compliance while transforming legacy
systems a critical requirement in the
highly regulated banking environment.
Coming at the slide five, the results
we're seen are truly transformative.
This circular diagram
highlights the key metrics.
From our earlier implementations,
we have achieved an 80% reduction in
human effort for code trans translation
Tasks that would take developers weeks
can now be completed in days testing.
Notification cycles are 60% faster.
As our approach allows for automated
equivalence testing between all the
new systems post implementation, we are
seeing 75% fewer regression defects.
This is crucial for maintaining the
stability that banking customers expect.
Perhaps most compelling
to execute is a 35%.
Lower total cost of ownership.
One regional bank I worked with projected
the savings of over $12 million or
five years through this approach.
These aren't the theoretical projections.
They are the results that early
adopters are already experiencing.
Coming back to the technical architecture,
this slide outlines the four stage
process that powers our approach.
First, legacy code ingestion.
Handles COBOL passing and domain mapping.
Next LLM translation applies banking
specialized model processing to the code.
Third verification ensures
background and behavior equivalence
through rigorous testing.
Finally, human review provides
expert validation refinement.
This framework successfully overcomes
key challenges while handling
banking specific complexities.
LLM coming back to the slides.
Next slide is LLM Innovation.
The technical innovations driving
this solution are threefold.
Extended context windows
allow models to process entire
banking module simultaneously.
Previous reserving relationship
between functions and
improving translation accuracy.
Financial domain, fine tuning, ensures
model understandings, accounting
principles, transaction processing
and regulatory requirements,
multi-language processing.
Our proficiency enables.
A seamless translation between cobol,
Java, Python, and other modern languages
while maintaining semantic equivalence.
Coming back to the next slide.
It's a human oversight system.
Despite power of ai, human
expertise, domains essential.
Our system incorporates role-based
reviews, where engineers, compliance
offices, and domain exploit validate
different aspects of the transformation.
Automated compliance flagging
identifies potential regulatory
issues for human review.
Performance verification
ensures equivalent behavior
through side by side runtime.
Finally, feedback loop integration
allows human corrections to
continuously improve the AI model.
Coming back to the next
slide, investment impact.
This power shot demonstrates
the compelling business case.
For this approach, we see dramatic
predictions and maintenance costs feature
time to market and technical debt index.
After implementation, these real
role metrics confirm that reduced
cost and acceleration innovation.
Creating lasting complete
competitive advantages for adopters.
Coming back to the next slide this
is the transaction system where
we wanted to show the case study.
A major bank transformed this code
transaction system processing 3 million
daily transactions from 10 million lines
of COBAL code, which is a 30-year-old.
The process followed our framework,
legacy assessment, preparation,
phase IT translation, and finally
successful migration to containerized
microservices with improved
performance and its scalability.
This case proves the varied viability
of our approach, even of for
the most complex infrastructure.
Coming back to the implementation
roadmap for our organization looking
to adopt this approach, we need to
provide a clear four phase roadmap.
Beginning with the
assessment of preparation.
The process moves to pilot
transformation of non-critical
modules, 10 to scale implementation
across larger systems and financially.
And finally, continuous
improvement through ongoing
refinement, this actionable path.
Forward minimizes risk while maximizing
the benefits of AI powered modernization.
Coming back to this next slide,
transform the banking future.
This is the closing slide that emphasizes
the three key benefits, reducing
technical gap by transforming legacy
systems from liability to advantage.
Accelerate innovation by delivering
new features in days instead of months.
Enhance compliance through
improved regulatory.
And automated checks.
This the time for AI powered modern
Magnetization is now offering a way to
transform legacy systems while preserving
business logic and minimizing the risk.
Any questions?
Thank you so much.