Hello everyone.
I'm Teta with about 15 years of
experience into integration and AI
and enterprise integration platforms.
So today we are exploring how machine
learning acts as a catalyst for
cloud native digital transformation
over the next several flights.
We will see how embedding ml into
microservices containers and serverless
architectures not only accelerates
innovation, but also drives operational
efficiencies that weren't possible before.
So
before diving into the topic, let's just
cover the evolution of cloud architecture.
Let's begin with cloud architecture.
We started with traditional monolithic
applications, static, tightly
coupled and hard to scale systems.
Then came lift and shift migrations
to the cloud where we gained
better sources utilization, but
little architectural change.
Cloud native approaches broke these
monolithics into microservices
in containers with orchestration
delivering resilience and flexibility.
So finally, by augmenting this model with
embedded ml, our systems continuously
learn and adapt unblocking predictive
and automated decision making.
In the next slide let's just look about
the distributed computing benefits.
Deploying ML in a cloud native environment
lets us leverage distributed computing
to its fullest, VHU around 10 to 20 times
faster training via paralyzed pipelines.
Elastic scaling automatically
matches resources to demand.
So a petabyte scale data
processing becomes routine and
we only pay for what we use.
So we would be optimizing costs.
So together these capabilities
enable us to tackle complex
problems at unprecedented scale.
Speed.
So now let's look about the
intelligent automation capabilities.
So ML driven cloud integration powers
intelligent automation across it
operations With predictive scaling systems
can anticipate spikes before they occur.
So self-op optimization tunes parameters
continuously based on performance data and
automated security detects and neutralizes
threats without manual intervention.
So organizing organizations leveraging
these features report around 45 to
60% of less downtime and 30 to 40%
of greater resource efficiency.
Now let's look at the cross cloud
mul machine learning deployment.
So in hybrid and multi-cloud world, we
need seamless ml across environments.
So centralized governance ensures
consistent model management, monitoring
and security policies everywhere.
Edge deployments push inference
closer to latency sensitive users.
Provider optimization lets us exploit
hardware accelerators or pricing
advantages and failover, recie
keep predictions services running
even when a region goes offline.
So this flexibility strategy
maximizes performance.
While guarding continuity.
Now in the next slide, we will be
looking at the implementation challenges.
In the implementation challenges in
today's integrating ML into a cloud
native systems is not without hurdles.
So models can drift as real world
data changes, demanding continuous
monitoring and retraining.
Deep Networks act as black boxes
making inter interpretability
and audit auditability difficult.
So ensuring high quality data across
distributed services remains a
perennial struggle and new security
risks advisor attacks, model poisoning.
Privacy leaks require robust defenses.
So overcoming these challenges
for structured processes
and specialized skillsets.
Now let's look at what are the
emerging solutions for this integrating
ML into cloud native systems.
So emerging, the ecosystem is
evolving rapidly, so ML ops platforms
automate the end-to-end lifecycle.
From data prep through deployment,
slashing deployment times by almost
80% and enforcing reproducibility.
So ex explainable AI frameworks
like SHAP and LIME, demystify
model behavior to build trust
and meet compliance requirements.
Federated learning lets us train on
decentralized data without ever moving it.
Preserving privacy and
cutting bandwidth costs.
These innovations make cloud
native ML far more accessible.
So now let's look about the
business impact metrics.
When we measure the outcomes,
the gains are striking.
Teams deploying ML powered cloud solutions
bring new features to market 65% faster.
So operational efficiency leaps forward.
So customer satisfaction and
employee productivity both ways.
And while revenue growth improvements may
appear modest in percentage terms, they
translate into significant absolute gains.
So leaders report around 20 to 30, 20
to 30% higher growth versus pace relying
on the conventional architecture.
So now let's look at, look, let's
look about the implementation
framework for this ml integration.
So
a proven roadmap ensures
these benefits materialize.
First, conduct a strategic
assessment to align ML initiatives
with business priorities Next.
Design your cloud native ML
architecture defining microservices,
data pipelines and governance.
Then run a focused POC or proof of concept
to validate assumptions and demonstrate
clear RYA, written on investment.
Finally, scaling successful patterns
enterprise wide building the
organizational confidence and operational
rigor you need for long-term success.
So what are the future trends
in this article in this area?
What's on the horizon?
Autonomous ML promises self designing
neural architectures that minimize
human effort in model creation.
AI specific hardware think AI optimize.
The processors in the cloud will deliver
order of magnitude performance boosts.
So mesh intelligence will embed,
distribute distributed ML throughout
and organization ecosystem, enabling
services to share insights seamlessly
and natural interfaces conversational
and multimodal will put ML capabilities
directly into the hands of business users.
Without running requiring
specialized technical skills.
So what are the key takeaways and
the action plan in this session?
So to wrap up four priorities
will set you up for success.
First, align each ML initiative with
clear business value and metrics.
Second ensure your platform is truly
cloud native containers microservices.
Infrastructure as code before you layer
on the ml. Third, invest in DataOps
and ML ops to automate the pipelines,
maintain model quality at scale.
And lastly, upskill your team
upskilling combining data science
cloud, cloud engineering, and domain
expertise in cross-functional squads.
So following this action plan, and you
will build adaptive intelligent systems.
That continuously drive business values.
And lastly, thank you everyone for your
time and detection and how I hope this
discussion has given you a clear view of
how ML and Cloud Native patterns coverage
to accelerate digital transformation.
I'm happy to take any questions or
dive deeper into any of these topics.
Thank you.