my name is Rahing Taku and I am working
as a lead software engineer in Salesforce.
I have I wanted to talk about this.
I, how can we scale the the service?
So I do want to talk about the, how
can we enhance the clouds, scalability
and fault always using the sharding.
So before I start, I will give
the little background about this.
So now, nowadays it's very
common practice to deploy the
service as microservices, right?
When we deploy microservices, there are.
Replic of the service which runs.
And it is mainly done because we want
to make sure if there is an issue with
one replica of the service, the other
is still continue to serve the profit.
So my idea is also on the same.
But but it extend the idea.
So instead of having just one instance
of the service, we can actually, the.
Services itself, we can have the
multiple instance of the services
and then each instance of the service
serves the some traffic, right?
And and and using this architecture,
we can actually improve the.
Improve on and actually have the
high availability for our service.
Yeah.
So I will go in deep down on the
different aspect of the aspect of it.
So first thing is that why
sharding matters, right?
So if we do not shard, right?
Then most of the then you have one
single point of failure, right?
Everything goes on to
the same place, right?
Which means that if there is anything
has to go wrong it'll impact all
the all the incoming traffic, right?
And since everything is coming onto
the single place, you cannot have an
intelligent load distribution, right?
And then it affect your
availability, right?
If everything is on one place,
everything has to go down.
It'll affect it'll reduce the
availability of the service.
In my proposed architecture.
So there are I'm introducing a
metadata service and so in my proposed
architecture there are different
instance of the service, right?
So not only one instance, but
different instance of the service.
And now since there are different
instance of the service the request
need to go to the one instance.
Always need to go to the same instance.
So because of that, we
need a metadata service.
The responsibility of the metadata
service is to make sure that for a given
request identified as the same request
using the IP address or the customer
credentials, it always goes onto the
same chart of the service, right?
So that's why we need
the metadata service.
So Met also can be used for, managing
more metadata about the whole, all
the services that participate in
this, and then it knows about the,
all the charts of the services.
And then at the end, then it'll
redirect the service through particular.
Okay, so before, before I go further
deep, I just want to focus one more time.
Like what are the benefits of it?
So since we have now multiple instance
of the service running, it'll improve
the availability of the service.
If one instance is down, it still,
there are, let's say we have five
instance of the service still,
there are four instance running, so
that means the avail availability
is down only by the 20%, right?
And it also helps to make
sure that all the request, the
which.
So for example, we have dive five,
different instance, and then each of
the fraction, like 20% of the customers.
And then if we have a local cache, then
it can serve the customer better, right?
So we have a small instance and
then we know the request from
the customer will always come to,
come on this particular instance.
So then it can so it'll be able to.
And third one is like the, it can
optimize the deployment, right?
So now if you can configure your pipeline
to do Thete deployment and whenever
you are releasing the change and not
release on all the five instance, but
release it on the first one, instance
first, and do all kind validation.
To go into production and then
it's not causing any regression.
Just wanna add more on the benefits.
Since we have multiple instance
of the service, we can actually
have the intelligent routing.
Okay.
If you want to scale up or scale
down one particular instance of the
service to serve a different purpose,
then you can actually scale it up.
And then while you keep the keep the
so for example, let's say you have
five instance of the service and then
one instance which serves the current.
The request for the, let's
say for the current day, okay.
And then the other FI for
instance, they serve the request
from the historic data, right?
So you can actually scale the current
service, which serve the current data.
To be more performant.
So yeah, this is just an example, but the
idea is that if you have different, then
you can actually ma manage them separately
and then you can have the intelligent
load distribution also done for isolation.
For example, let's say we have,
again, going with the same
example, we have five instance.
They are running in different
five availability zone.
Let's say there is an issue with
the vulner availability zone.
It does not impact the other
four instance, which are on the
different availability zone, right?
So you can actually isolate the fault.
You can minimize the blast radius.
Then also if we use it correctly,
we can actually use it for
the cost efficiency also.
Because if we had only one instance
where you have to keep scaling, scale
up that instance all the time in this
scenario, you can actually scale up
or scale down the different instance
at the different point of the time.
So it gives you the flexibility
of managing it better.
Okay.
Now I do want to talk about the,
a little about the implementation.
So we need way to dynamically
provision this instance, right?
So now since we have
more than one instance.
And it is possible for the number
of instance to grow or reduce in the
size, as in when we, as in, when the
the product grow or shrink, right?
So it is possible, it is very
important for us to have a service
which can provision the service
instance dynamically, right?
So it need to be configurable and.
And then there need to be the
configuration, which can be done
separately for the each instance, right?
And yep.
So going next, yeah, we also need to
have, maintain some kind of configuration
for all these instance, right?
Since these are the different
instance, we, I mean it's the same
service, but it's still different.
Instance, there may be some runtime
properties which are different
for the different instance.
And what we want to make sure is
that the are configurable, right?
So for that we need a
configuration service.
And for each instance we configure the
properties same or differently, depend
on the use case and then then used
when we deploy the service instance.
Okay.
So as I told before, like we
also need a metadata service.
The responsibility of the metadata service
is to make sure that we are able to route
the request to the same chart every time
which means that we need to have the
consistent routing, also, I just want
to touch upon the stateful migration.
So if your service is state,
which means that it has it, it to.
Then if you want to move the customer
from the one, if you want to move
the customer from the one instance to
another instance for any reason, right?
There can be multiple reasons.
For example, one of the instances, is
not able to serve any more traffic.
So you don't want you want to distribute
the traffic and move some of the traffic
to the the other instance, right?
Or maybe for some other reasoning.
For example, you have a logical
distribution of the customers,
but then for some reason you
decide to move the one customer.
So this like open to.
But the point is, for any reason,
at any point, if you decide to move
the change the chart for a customer.
If it's in a stateful service,
then we have to take care of the
state for the data migration also.
And we all know data
migration is not easy.
But but I think if it's done correctly,
we can actually have this also.
The point is that we have to consider
the stateful migration when we are to.
Okay, now I would like to talk
about some of the challenges.
One is the deeper complexity, right?
When we want to debug an issue, right?
The first thing we need to know
the routing of the shard happened
correctly then we need to know
which shard the customer belongs to.
And then and then for each search, since
there are different configuration, we
just want to make sure that so it's up
to the complexity for debugging, right?
Migration complexity.
I think this is one of the biggest
challenge the migration complex.
As I explained before, we
have different insights.
We if for any reason we
decide to change the,
we.
Moving the data in the live
production system is not easy.
That's why I recommend if we ever try
to do it consider the dual ingestion.
So you keep ingesting the
data into the old shard.
You keep start to ingest the data into
the new shard, then the data is in sync.
Then you move the customer
from the from the, and.
Being served from the new shot,
then you can think about cleanup
from the from the old chart.
And also I will suggest that if we
keep the retention based cleanup,
that will be nice in that sense.
You don't have to worry about
cleanup of the data, but like when
the data leads to the end of life.
Then third is infrastructure complexity.
So since now we have multiple instance
you need to have a service which
can spin up the spin up the new
instance and take care of it, right?
Yeah.
So this will add up the extra complexity.
The data consistency.
I think that the data consistency is
mainly when we actually moving the
customer from the one shot to another.
So we just want to make sure
that the data is consistent.
Network latency is also in the
same sense that when we are when
we are actually moving the customer
from one shot to another, we are
actually doing the deal, right?
And then that might add up to
the latency for the customer.
I do want to to support some of the
mitigation for the Herbo problem.
The first thing is that if we have
the robust monitoring so for any given
customer, if we know the, like which
chart the customer goes, and then all the
configurations that we can see for the.
And then having a proper dashboard
and alarms to monitor the, monitor,
the each each service instance, right?
This will help to reduce the the debugging
effort to and can be done very fast.
The second time second
is caching strategy.
The caching strategy will help a lot
during the in the metadata service
when we actually wanna, assign when
we want to decide the which chart the
customer should go, I think the caching
strategy will play an important role
because the aiding or removing the chart
is not a frequent operation, right?
So we can very well have a
cache which gets invalidated
whenever there is an a new.
Through cache in here.
And then this will help us.
So this will help us like doing the
routing it without adding up on the
much latency because we'll be doing it
from the cash the deal right system.
So the deal right system is very
important when we want to do the
when we want to move the customer
from the one shot to the another.
I think if.
Make sure that the customer do not see any
downtime during the during this process.
And then the customer even would
know if there was any change
on the back in the backend.
Yeah.
Yeah, so I just want to conclude
on this, the idea is to have the
multiple charts of the service.
And so that each short serve some of the
data or some of the customer, it helps you
increase the availability of the service,
also doing the better load management
and improve on the fault tolerance.
Yes.
So I think, yeah, that's it.
And, thank you very much.