Hello, Griffin.
I'm Navin Kumar Beru.
I'm truly honored to be here
at conference 42 ML 2025.
Today's talk is going to be about
Beyond Perimeters, implementing
Zero Trust at Enterprise Scale.
In this session, I want to go beyond
the hype and breakdown what Zero Trust
really means, why it is not just a
security password, but a fundamental
architectural shift that enterprises
need to survive and thrive in today's
cloud driven distributed world.
Zero Trust has become one of the
most important strategies for
modern enterprises, especially
those operating across multi-cloud
environments, different geographies,
and supporting remote workforces.
In this presentation, I will walk
you through key concepts, shared
data points, and highlight real world
implementation challenges and outcomes.
Thank you for spending time with me.
Let's get started.
Evolving digital landscape.
Let's begin by painting the
landscape we are operating in today.
76% of enterprises run multi-cloud
environments spanning across average
3.7 cloud providers, creating a
highly complex, interconnected system.
Despite investments and tenter
defense, 95% of reaches still result
from human error, phishing attacks,
misconfigurations accidental exposure.
Breach costs are in class now,
averaging around 4.8 million
10.7 increase from last year.
These trends show that traditional
perimeter based defenses are
no longer enough to effectively
protect modern enterprises.
We need a model that assumes breaches
will happen and focus minimizing impact
the business case for zero trust.
So why zero trust.
Because organizations that embrace
mature zero trust programs save around
1.4 million on an average for breach.
Adoption has skyrocketed 49%
of enterprise support progress
and zero trust initiatives up
from 21% just a few years ago.
This shift is practically driven by
remote work, which has expanded attack
services by 37%, adding, unmanaged
devices, unsecured networks, and external
access funds Beyond security, zero
trust offers business benefits like
greater rigidity, safer cloud adoption,
and stronger regulatory realignment.
I think it's an essential for business.
From perimeter to zero trust.
Zero trust requests a
fundamental mind shift.
Instead of assuming that everything
inside the network is trusted,
we follow three principles.
Continuous verification.
Every request is checked every time.
Identity based trust s are based
on identity, not on location.
No default trust.
Nothing is implicitly trusted.
Even inside the network, this shift
matters because 70% of today's
traffic moves from east West,
inside the perimeter, the Old
Castle and motor approach leaves
too many gaps open with zero trust.
The trust becomes something you
earn, not something you inherit.
Identity centric security identity is
the heart of zero trust in this model.
Identity becomes a new perimeter, whether
it's a person, device, or a workload.
According to Nest.
All resource authentications and
authorizations are dynamic and strictly
enforced before access is allowed.
But this is challenging.
92% of enterprises use multiple identity
systems, making it inconsistent and hard.
Implementing leading implementations
now adopt continuous authentications,
checking identity at multiple points
during a session, not just at the login.
This has resulted in 37% reduction
in identity based compromises
proving the power of strong
identity centered defenses.
In short, identity management becomes
the foundation for all security layers.
Micro segmentation is another key zero
trust complement rather than managing.
Network zones, you apply granular control.
At workload level, 76% of enterprises now
implement software defined segmentation,
which controls ease to best traffic.
By ensuring that only explicit
allowed services communicate,
you reduce the breach by 66%.
In segmented environments,
micro-segmentation effectively
limits lateral movement, turning what
could have been a system-wide breach
into a small contained incident.
It reinforces the principle of
least coverage at the network level.
Cutting off attack
pathways before the spread.
Contextual access policies, dynamic
access policies are central to zero trust.
They rely on combining
multiple factors such as user
identity and behavior patterns.
Device health assessed by 83% of
enterprises request context like
locational time data sensitivity.
Ensuring sensitive resources
get extra protection.
By layering this control organizations
create adaptive risk of access decisions.
The result, 37% of infiltrate
exfiltration incidents showing that
smart policies make a real impact.
This isn't just a static role
based access, but it's a applying
context over every decision.
Again, dynamic policy and enforcement
is central to zero trust implementation.
Witness defining a core tenant that
access to resources is determined by
dynamic policy, including the observable
state of client identity, application,
service, and requesting asset.
The result is that zero
trust, security effectiveness.
Increases in lot of areas, reduction
in exploitable attacks at first by
41% reduction in breach scope based of
microsegmentation by 66% reduction in data
filtration instance by 37%, and reducing
identity based compromise instance by 37%.
Current state of zero trust adoption.
Let's look where most
organizations are today.
Oh.
Only 8% have fully implemented zero
trust across their enterprises.
But for others, the pro
process is under the way.
NI 90, sorry, 49% are actively applying
zero trust and key areas, and 34%
are still planning their approach.
This highlights the implementation
gap between early pilots and
fully enterprise coverage.
Zero trust takes time.
It's not a plug and play solution.
It requires careful strategy,
phase rollout, and alignment
across various teams.
Federated identity management.
Managing identities across a large,
complex organization is one of the
hardest zero trust challenges, mainly
because identity, confidence gap.
Only 29% of the organizations are
already confident in their identity
security controls creating a significant
challenges for zero trust implementations.
Privileged IDENT Identity Management
is 57% of the organizations Report U
using privileged identity management
and solutions as a part of the Zero
Trust approach machine identity.
73% of the organizations report
managing more machine identities that
humans human identifies, creating an
expanded identity surface requiring
consistent security controls.
Large organizations must, I must
implement, it must implement
federated identity solutions
that provide seamless, yet secure
across distributed environments.
The identity confidence gap
creates significant challenge
as 89% of organizations have
experienced at least one identity
related breach in recent years.
End-to-end encryption, zero.
Trust demands persuasive
encryption, protecting data
no matter where it travels.
This includes encrypting data
transit data trust, securing a PA
communications, protecting EastWest
microservice traffic, and implementing
robust key management practices.
Zero trust requires encryption to
protect data throughout its life cycle,
emulating implicit trust in network
boundaries or transport mechanisms.
Research shows encryption is one
of the fourth most common controls
supporting zero trust initiatives.
This shift reduces reliance on network
boundaries and ensures that even
intercepted data remains producted.
It's about making sure that data
sensitive information is always secure,
and even on unru channels distributed
policy enforcement, zero trust requests.
Enforcing policies consistently
at multiple levels.
Network layer, the secure gateways with
secure gateways and next gen firewalls.
57% of organizations imple implement
secure gateways as a part of the zero
trust policy proving foundational
security through next generation
firewalls and secure access
through SAS E Solutions service.
Meh layer using MTLS
and fine game controls.
Finding control policy in a containerized
environment enables zero trust principles
to modern application architectures
with service to service communication.
Securing the MTLS communication between
each service application layer, applying
rules through a PA gateway degrees, that
all a PA access and others to zero trust
policies with comprehensive authentication
authorization for each request.
Policy enforcement must occur at
multiple layers within the technology
stack to implement zero trust principles
effectively at enterprise scale.
This architectural approach to
policy improvement returns a
critical success factor with 70%
of the organizations reporting
through difficulty and incorporating
consistent policy enforcement
during distributed environments.
Without uniform policy informants
gaps appear and attackers look
for those inconsistencies.
Effective policy enforcement
is not just about tools.
It's about ensuring alignment
across technology stack.
Comprehensive observability is
true backbone of a successful
zero trust implementation.
Without it, you are operating
blind and in today's fast moving
environment, there's a risk.
No op, no organization can afford.
To succeed, you need a visibility
across entire stack from
infrastructure to application,
from network to user behavior.
This means that you're not just collecting
raw data, but you're turning it into
meaningful insights that can drive action.
Key components include secure
event collection across all
the systems, cloud and on-prem,
comprehensive visibility enabling
both proactive threat identification
and effective incident response.
Behavioral analysis to establish baseline
studies and quick, quickly identify
unusual patterns, establish baseline
behaviors and identify deviations that
may indicate security threats of automated
responses that contain threats, the the
moment they're detected, enabling rapid
mitigation of potential threats before
they can cause significant damage.
Cons, consistent feedback loops
where real time data helps fine tune
policies and controls over time.
Leverage operational data towards
adjust security controls based
on environmental conditions.
Currently, 42% of the organization support
expanding their logging, monitoring, and
telemetry efforts as a part of the zero
trust journey, but achieving comprehensive
observability about more than just tools.
It's about designing the systems
that integrate visibility, nativity,
and not an after that a thought.
Remember, you cannot
secure what you cannot see.
Zero trust requires full situational
awareness across systems,
identities, devices, and networks.
The more you know about the
environment, the faster, the more
precise, precisely you can act.
When something goes wrong.
Ultimately, I've done zero trust, zero
trust from a static policy framework
into a living adaptive security posture.
Let's talk about service mis integration.
When we talk about S securing Cloud
native application service me, service
meshes like STO Linkerd or a WS app
mesh become central to zero trust.
They aren't just networking tools.
They're embedded deeply into
how microservice communicate
to communicate with each other.
Serviceness provide critical capabilities
including MTLS, mutual TLS, ensuring that
every service to service inter interaction
is authenticated and encrypted.
All service to service communication
Explicit access policies defining
exactly which services are
allowed to talk to each other.
Can make zero trust, easy to implement.
Services can only communicate with
explicit authorized endpoints.
Telemetry collection is another important
feature of zero miss integration,
gathering rich telemetry data on
communication patterns, errors, latency
is critical for telemetric collections.
Detailed metrics on communication patterns
reveals potential security anomalies.
Cryptographic workload identities.
This gives services unique
verifiable identities that are hard
topo cryptographic identities for
services that can easily be spoofed.
By integrating these features
directly into the application layer,
organizations can and for zero trust
at a granular service level, service
to service level communications.
This reduces the risk of lateral movement.
Even if one part of the system
is compromised, the other
parts stay minimal impact.
It also provides better visibility
on how applications behave, enabling
tighter controls and faster detection
of anomalies without the service mass.
Mass integration, zero trust efforts
and mic Microsoft microservice
and environments often fall short,
leaving gap for attackers that GA,
that possibly could be exploited.
Think of a service mesh as a connective
tissue that holds zero trust principles
and high dynamic cloud architectures.
It's not about improving security,
it's about building resilience,
scalability, and adaptability
into the heart of the system.
Service mesh like.
SST O like we talked about, linker.
DAWS mesh ate zero trust by providing
critical security capabilities for
containerized microservice environment.
Service mesh provide critical capabilities
for implementing zero trust and micro
microservice environment by creating
an architecture by securities embedded
within the application infrastructure.
Now let's talk about a p
security and zero trust.
APIs are front doors to
modern applications and
they're under concentrate.
A zero trust framework, API security must
be treated as a first class citizen and
first class priority, not an afterthought.
Securing API involves several key
practices deploying API gateway as a
centralized centralized enforcement points
for all incoming and outgoing, a PA calls.
This helps in centralized
enforcement points.
For applying security policies,
implementing authentication requirements
for all, a PA consumer, regardless
of their network origin, applying
rate limit, and anomaly detection
to prevent abuse, denial of service
attacks, or unexpected spikes.
Protecting against this abuse
is critical for zero trust.
Forcing schema validation to block
malformed and malicious payloads that
could exploit the backend system.
This prevents, this is critical in
preventing controls, ensuring that
all data passed through a PA others
to expected format, preventing common
attack techniques like injection attacks.
Zero trust for API
becomes, goes even further.
It means authenticating every API
consumer validating authorization
for every action and continuously
monitoring for suspicious behaviors.
A PA often connect to sensitive data,
financial transactions, or critical
operations, making them prime target
for attackers Without strong a PA
security, even most well-designed zero
trust architectures can be bypassed.
Additionally, as organizations and entries
open ecosystems working with partners,
vendors, and third parties, API Security
becomes a vital piece of maintaining
trust across extended supply chains.
Zero Trust can be applied to APIs to
ensure that every single request is
evaluated, verified, and ultimately,
your zero trust strategy is only
as strong as your weakest a PA.
Now, let's talk about how to
overcome implementation challenge.
We can't talk about zero trust
without addressing its challenges.
Adoption is really smooth
and organizations fail and
face real practical hurdles.
About 60% of security leaders point to
legacy system compatibility as one of the
biggest obstacles for zero trust policy.
Older systems weren't designed for
continuous verification or granular
access control and retrofitting them
can be expensive and time consuming.
These.
These are also challenges with
other tools like sprawl, skill gaps.
There are also challenges with
skill gaps, cultural resistance,
and also alignment across teams.
State of trust isn't just a security
project, it's a organizational
transformation that requires
buy-in from leadership, IP
operations, and business units.
Successful organizations approach zero
trust as a structured and stage journey.
They start by identifying high value
targets, applying zero trust policies.
Where they can and applying zero trust
principles where they can have biggest
impact, and then gradually expanding
the output help build momentum.
But strong, long-term success
requires sustained investment and
cross-functional collaboration.
The transformation of zero trust
architecture presents numerous
implementation challenges that
organizations must systematically address.
Approximately 60% of the security
professional site legacy systems as that
main concern by decoupling identity from
network location, implementing rigorous
authentication and authorization, and
maintaining continuous verification
organization can build resilient security
framework that adapt to realities
of modern distributed enterprises.
It's important to remember that
zero trust isn't a product you
buy your checkbox, you complete.
It's a shift in how organization
thinks about trust, access,
risk, and a mindset that puts
continuous verification at its core.
At the end, organizations are
that succeed of those that see
zero zero trust as a strategic
commitment, not as a tactical fix.
In closing, thank you all so
much for joining me today.
I hope the stock gave you a
clear understanding on how zero
trust cancer enterprise security
and give you a realistic sense
of what it takes to get there.
If you'd like to connect and share
insights or continue this conversation,
I would love to hear back from you.
Thank you again and enjoy the
rest of conference 42 ml 2025.