Hi everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42
Machine Learning Conference.
Hope you're having a good day.
My name is S Kati and I've actually
been working as a senior software
engineer at Meta for about a year now.
Before that I used to work at Google
for about four years and prior to that,
Walmart Labs and prior to that in a
startup for about another five years.
Basically, today we are actually going to
talk about something that I've actually
been working on for quite some time.
And I think it'll actually provide
you with great amounts of insights
on how to make your decision when it
comes to building analytics pipelines.
On that note, we are basically going
to do a deep dive into the fascinating
world of real time machine learning.
So we'll explore how to build analytics
pipelines that delivers insights in less
than a second with the enormous amount of
volumes volumes of data generated today
which is around 2.5 quintilian bytes
each day, which is not an normal amount.
It's quite enormous, right?
Traditional methods
simply aren't keeping up.
We'll unpack why speed matters,
look at the challenges involved, and
discuss how industries are gaining
major advantages from realtime ml.
Now let's actually talk about
the data explosion challenge.
First, let's understand the sheer scale
of the data problem we face every day.
Like literally as we said, we produce
about 2.5 quintillion bytes of data,
which is even hard to visualize.
So to put it into perspective, right?
If we were to stack blue, red
disks containing this data, they'd
reach all the way to the moon.
Again, like this is it's
even impossible to visualize.
Around 75% of the companies now rely
on machine learning applications
that need immediate responses.
So for these businesses,
waiting isn't an option.
I. Real-time analytics provides
insights 35 past percent faster and
boosts efficiency by almost 42%.
Imagine how crucial the speed is
for decision making during live
events, medical diagnostic, and
final financial transactions.
Of course, like you will see
many businesses, which still
do rely on batch processing.
We'll of course come to that what
batch processing is versus what
streaming pre stream processing is.
But the thing that I want you
to keep in perspective is.
Every business has its own
needs for some businesses.
It's very important for you to make sure
that you actually process real time data.
For example, financial transac
financial transactions, right?
Real time insights are
the ones which matter.
Like for example, let's say.
Basically if if a fraud is being
detected, which is let's say a fraud
occurred like, let's say two hours
ago, but you're detecting right now it
wouldn't make much of a sense again.
We'll put things into perspective as
and when we go through the slides,
but I just wanted to visualize how
businesses want to process data.
And of course, like it differs from
business to business now coming to
batch versus streaming processing.
So I would want to you, I want, I
would want you to take a moment to
realize what batch processing is
versus what stream processing is.
Batch processing usually is
typically takes hours or days.
Which is basically for
monthly or weekly reports.
For example, let's say you are running
an ad tech business and you would want
your business people to understand more
insights into how your ads are performing.
I. Over a day for the past week, for
the past month, so on and so forth,
you would rather want to stick with
your batch processing pipelines because
which run like, let's say every hour,
every day, so on and so forth, which
would definitely fit your needs.
That's totally fine.
You would not want to go for very
high-end like engineering heavy
stream processing pipelines.
But on the other note, think about
what I have been discussing just now.
Think about fraud detection.
What if your bank took hours to
identify suspicious activities?
It's not at all good.
So now coming to that, there
is an intermediate approach
called micro batching.
Which basically cuts the latency
to milliseconds, of course,
like basically, which is which
in my opinion is really good.
For example, micros Micro batching
has actually been serving like near
realtime needs for quite some time now.
But realtime streaming actually
goes a step further, like as in.
How do you cut down that latency
to under 10 milliseconds?
Like for example I agree there is,
there are instances where you would
want to go for micro batching, but you
would definitely want to understand
where your business fits, right?
So let's say you are actually in
your amazon amazon.com and you are
buying like a couple of things,
like for that matter, let's say
diapers for your kids or whatever.
Basically.
It takes a couple of minutes for you to
actually go from the homepage to the page
where the product is, to the add to cart
page, and then again the checkout page.
So now let's say that you are an engineer
at Amazon and you want to identify all
the people who are buying diapers, let's
say in the, who are buying diapers.
So you got an event into your
into Amazon saying that, Hey,
somebody bought diapers, right?
You would want to identify what what
items were they looking at prior to that?
So as in what is a really,
what is the path of the user
starting from the homepage,
which is really important, right?
Otherwise, where would
you want to put ads?
How would you want to categorize things
which are bought together usually?
So for such sort of things, you would
want to analyze the path of the user.
To do that, you really want to.
Use micro batching because then you
would want to, let's say check, okay,
this time the buying occurred, let's
actually go back a couple of windows,
which is a couple of milliseconds, a
couple of seconds or a couple of minutes
back to identify what really went on.
Such sort of things is where microb
batching is really like really used
and it actually is really good too.
But there are obviously some businesses
which definitely want to take it a
step further to real time streaming.
As I said, which cuts down the
latency to under 10 milliseconds.
Now, this near instant processing
is essential in scenarios like
let's say livestock trading,
realtime gaming, dynamic online
content, so on and so forth.
As you can see, many of the
FinTech startups have come up and
many the FinTech scenarios have.
Like literally exploded after the ai boom.
You can see livestock trading, right?
That's an excellent example where real
time streaming is much more important.
You would definitely want to get real time
data, as in how the stock is performing
or as in how the options are being
sold but so on and so forth to make an
informed decision about what to do next.
So that's where real time
streaming is what is required.
So I hope you might, you could have
actually at least, form the mental
picture of where batch micro batching
and stream processing sit in the
entire analytics pipeline scenario.
But of course, like in this particular
thing, we would definitely want to as part
of this talk, I would definitely want to
dig deep into streaming analytics per se.
But again, of course, like batch
I think is easily understood.
Micro batching is a little
harder to understand.
But yeah, feel free to stick with me
and I promise you'll get better insight.
So now starting with, let's
say financial services, right?
Oh, sorry.
I think I might have.
Yeah, my bad.
So now starting with financial
services, real time fraud
detection is much more important.
Of course, as and when as and when the
internet exploded and frankly, as, and
when the AI is currently taking over the
world, you can see many and many more
new type of frauds and scams popping up.
So it is much more important to
do real time fraud detection.
So as to make sure that they are,
the banking is secure, right?
So banks started adopting the real-time
fraud detection, which have reduced
their losses by almost about 27% for,
let's say, considering a mid-sized
bank that translates to around
15 million savings in each year,
which is not a normal amount again.
So traditional fraud detection
mechanisms analyze data.
After the event has occurred, like
as we were just discussing, which
is often too late because of course
the event has already occurred, the
transaction has already occurred, and
as such, it is now near impossible
to reverse that particular event.
But near, but the real time systems
that we are talking about actually
flag the unusual activities
as in when they're occurring.
So you can actually stop the
fraud activity before the event
completes, which is what we, which
is what is of utmost importance.
For example, let's say detecting multiple
purchases in distant locations, right?
I've had the situation where my credit
card, got hacked again, like I, I assume
many people might have actually gone
through the same scenario and like, why?
While I myself live in California, I. I've
actually had some business transaction
go off in, let's say, Tennessee, Florida
which again, like from from from tracking
my, let's say my recent transactions,
let's say, which occurred literally
one hour ago, happened in California,
but the next transaction, which is
currently occurring now is happening in
Tennessee, which is quite impossible.
So basically flagging that particular
transaction as fraud actually
would save me a lot of money.
Again, like these sort of
scenarios are what are important.
So now how do we like detecting
multiple purchases in, let's say,
distant location simultaneously?
Some, something traditional batch
methods would completely miss, right?
Let's say for example, if you are taking
a batch processing approach to this
particular problem, what would really
happen is okay in this particular hour
a transaction happened in California.
In the next particular hour a
transaction happened in Tennessee.
But of course, like you wouldn't,
you would not necessarily get the
entire picture, let's say, okay, for
on an hourly basis if we check it.
Of course, even batch process would
pick it up, but the transaction
might have already occurred.
Like the person who would've actually
hack my credit card might have
already made like thousands of dollars
of purchases, and I am the person
who is responsible to pay for it.
Which doesn't really make sense.
So basically such realtime fraud
detection mechanisms are much more
important and they are becoming
more important day by day.
So now coming to let's say another
particular use case, right?
Which is the e-commerce, for example,
as I was talking about like with
the advent of at least I myself use
Amazon and Walmart quite frequently.
So what I have actually
observed is the personalization.
For the customers in these e-commerce
businesses have actually gotten way
better than what they used to be.
For example, they have as I was
saying, e-commerce businesses
have actually seen major benefits.
Some real time personalization
can boost sales up to like by 18%.
So for example, picture
yourself doing this right.
As you are browsing, let's say our real
time analytics immediately updates product
recommendations based on your let's
say current session, inventory status,
pricing strategies, so on and so forth.
So this dynamic approach will definitely
increase the average order values by 12%.
For example, let's say as I was alluding
to my previous example, like I have
a kid and I of course, the thing that
usually pops up into my mind is buy
diapers, screams on, and so forth.
So if you were to take the example
of buying diapers themselves, right?
So of course like running on
that less sleep more for quite
some time now with a kid.
Basically you sometimes forget, or
sometimes you might not even realize what.
Is really needed for you
to purchase something.
So for example, let's say as I was
browsing diapers, if let the real
time personalization kicks in, like
the analytics pipelines kicks in and
they say that, Hey, I have seen that
you have been buying diapers now and
it's been some time since you bought,
let's say diaper cream or let's say
moisturizing lotion for your kit.
Why don't you actually
add that to the cart?
Or of course, like this is, I think not.
Prompting per se, but basically
people have also bought moisturizing
cream, so on and so forth.
That would actually trigger
something in my brain saying
that Hey, I forgot to buy this.
Let me actually add this.
So this sort of personalization
is something that I would love
in any new product, right?
Because it is important for the
tech to make our lives better.
So now along with that, let's say
realtime systems prevent customers
from facing out of stock items.
Like I've always had this happen, right?
Like where, let's say I have seen
that you add a couple of items in
Target, a target shopping cart, or
Walmart shopping cart for that matter.
By the time you are just about to check
out, or let's say you are about to get
it delivered, it just says out of stock.
Such sort of events are actually
problematic for the user experience
and handling such events in real
time is much more important.
I. Again, you see these are much more
important when they, when there are
like peak shopping like ho peak shopping
events like holidays or major sales.
Like for example, when I was
working at Walmart Thanksgiving
is a major season, right?
So you would want to buy
gifts for your loved ones.
Want to make sure your family's happy.
I've actually seen this happen
many times where there is a
particular sale which pops up.
Let's say you want to fi, you want to
buy an iPad for your family members.
Okay?
There is a suddenly, there's
suddenly a sale which popped
up in, let's say Walmart.
That 20% off of iPad.
It's not a normal, it's
not a normal sale, right?
So you.
Basically many people along with you are
actually flocking to walmart.com to buy
that particular thing, and as such, it
would definitely make much more sense
to update them real time on what is
actually going on with that sale event.
As in, are you a little too late?
Are you are, let's say they're like,
there are, how many of the iPads
are actually still left, so that
way you can provide customers with
way better shopping experience?
Now let's actually discuss a completely
different side of the coin, which
is manufacturing for that matter.
Factories right have actually dramatically
improved operations by shifting to
realtime predictive maintenance.
For example, machines are now equipped
with advanced sensors which can
stream continuously stream data.
Like what is the temperature,
what is a vibration?
What is the operating
speed of the machine?
So now real time machine learning models.
Analyze this data instantly, and
they can actually predict equipment
failures before they happen for ex like
I, you may ask the question, right?
Like, why is this important?
So manufacturing is not something
which you, which you regularly
see on a day-to-day basis.
So why is this really important?
So regular maintenance of, regular
maintenance of machines is important
so as to streamline the operations
and not expect any latency.
For example, let's say again an out of
the mind example, I'm just thinking out
loud, where let's say you have ordered
some toys and basically for delivery
and let's say that has gone back to the
manufacturing plant for manufacturing.
Again, this is a completely out of the
world scenario that I'm talking about.
But let's say that, okay, the tie
manufacturing has started, but somewhere
down the line the machines failed.
And that the tie, which is supposed to
be delivered for your kid's birthday, has
now been, the delivery date has now been
pushed back let's say four to five weeks.
That is not acceptable, right?
There is a particular reason why you
pick that tie, and there is a particular
timeline that you have in your mind.
But now that because of a manufacturing
delay, all of this happened.
So equipping machines with such data
where it can actually stream the data.
Like saying that Hey, my current, the
temperature of the machine is so and
let's say that like the pressure which
is going through and that number of ties
that has been processed are built until
now or so and so such sort of numbers
would help us quickly understand, hey.
We have seen that let's say previous
day we have seen that this machine
is processing so many ties or so
building so many toys per minute.
But now that has gone down drastically.
What is really going on, right?
So you are able to identify the issue
with the manufacturing or the machine
way before something really bad happens.
And as such, you are able to
fix it so that your operations
are way more streamlined.
As and when more and more.
Machines are more and
more automation kicks in.
This is much more important.
So now let's actually talk
about the technical challenges,
which are event time processing.
So for example, there are
again, implementing this real
time machine learning is not
without its own challenges.
For example, a significant hurdle
is event time processing, right?
Accurately handling data based
on when events actually happen.
But not when they are recorded,
like as in there real.
There is it's hard to visualize.
So let's take a moment to
understand what is going on.
So there is a slight delay on
when the event actually occurs and
when it is recorded, as in, let's
say you clicked on add to card
button inlet on let on amazon.com.
So that event is being sent to
the backend server for processing.
So the, let's say you click the add
to cart right now, but because of a
server delay or something, the backend
processing system actually received
that event a couple of minutes late.
So that does not necessarily
mean add to cart never happened.
It means that the add to cart
event is actually recorded late.
So that is the distinction, like as
in when the event occurred versus
when it was actually processed.
So around 15% of streaming data
arrives out of order because there are.
There are a lot of issues, right?
There are, these are all computers
where there events are being recorded.
So let's say there is a network
problem, there is a machine, which
machine which went down, so on and
so forth, which actually makes the
streaming data this is a very common
occurrence where they are out of order.
Which complicates accurate analytics.
Again, this is this is something that this
is a, which has been a bigger challenge.
So now to overcome this, right?
Basically methods like sliding
windows or watermarking has been
has been used to ensure data
accuracy, like as in let's take a
moment to understand what these are.
Sliding window is basically what you're
saying is, again, going back to the
e-commerce example, you saw that.
An add to cart event is
is, has come to you, okay?
Like you are a software engineer,
and as part of the data that
an add to cart event occur.
You see that, but weirdly enough,
let's say you, you don't see an event
where the user landed on the homepage.
That doesn't make sense.
As in how would you go to add to cart
before going to the homepage, right?
Like you go to the homepage, you browse
the product, you then add to cart.
So there are like three events,
but somehow because of some server
delay or whatever, add to cart
is the one which you got first.
So what you say is hey, I'll actually
wait for two minutes or one minute.
Where for the home homepage event
and the product page event, so let's
say that is called, that is where you
ensure how you ensure data accuracy.
Okay, now that, yeah, you have waited
two minutes, let's say you have gotten
homepage and the product page, you bundle
this together saying that, okay, like now
I have gotten the full data, and as such
I have, I can order those events properly.
Homepage occurred, first product
page occurred next, then the
add to cart page happened.
So you can see the user
path or the user behavior.
As it is needed.
And again, if you were to take another
example of stock market trading, precise
timing of transactions is critical
again, which is really important, right?
Like you cannot just say let's say
I want to buy a stock right now,
but suddenly for whatever reason, I.
Like the event got delayed and the
stock price rose, you cannot just tell
the customer that unfortunately, we
could not buy the stock right now.
And as such that incorrect ordering
can cost significant financial impact.
Such sort of events are
much more kept in mind.
And as such, of course, proper
methods have been devised, like
siding, windows, and watermarking.
Again, just to reiterate now, going
over, let's say we want to understand
the model drift in continuous systems,
which is basically, which is, this
is another one major challenge.
Like for example over time
data patterns naturally change.
So this causes the models to become
less accurate because they have been
trained on a particular set of data
on our particular data patterns, but
naturally the data pattern changed.
You usually have to update the
models very frequently, as in the
training has to occur very frequently.
So as to make sure that
the models actually keep up
with the data pattern trend.
So if you were to take real
Ty retail businesses right?
Customer shopping behaviors
change seasonally.
For example if you were to take any
clothing business of sort summer
clothes and winter clothes are
something which are very common, and
as such, the buying patterns of summer
clothes increases over summertime
decreases as the winter approaches.
So is the case with winter clothes
where it increases over the wintertime
and decreases as the spring approaches.
So now considering such
seasonal behaviors, right?
Basically, which influence the products,
what products they usually buy.
Real time systems should address this by
detecting changes in data distribution
and automatically retraining the model.
So that such retraining of models
is much more important to make sure
that you keep up with the data trend.
Again, as we were just discussing,
think of it as keeping the
system fresh and accurate.
Automatically adjusting to shifts
without manual intervention, right?
Like of course there will always
be some data changes, which humans
might not have actually let's say,
been thinking about, for example I've
actually seen a couple of things where I.
There are a couple of scenarios where,
there are a couple of scenarios where
the flowers buying actually increased
by quite a lot and but as in when some
of the, some other events occur, it did
quite decrease and so on and so forth.
Such sort of things are very.
Almost impossible to predict, right?
As a human, you cannot deal with
every single data pattern, but
basically you would want your models
to automatically take care of it.
Let's say.
Now taking, talking about the
architectural comparison, so choosing the
right streaming framework is critical.
For example, until now, we have
established why stream processing
is important, how we have overcome
the challenges, so on and so forth.
Now let's actually discuss about what
technologies are actually present.
And what frameworks essentially that's
the right word, but what streaming
frameworks are actually present and
what are the ever so slight differences
between them and what, how do you
compare them against each other?
I.
So for example Apache Kafka, right?
It can actually process about 2
million events per second with
around 10 milliseconds latency.
Apache Flink is actually even faster
reaching sub millisecond latency ideal
for financial markets or real time giving
cloud services like AWS Kinesys and Azure
event hubs provide simpler integration.
But to have slightly higher latency.
So now business often adapt hybrid
approaches basically to balance
performance, complexity, and convenience.
For instance, using Kafka for event
ingestion and flink for processing
might be ideal for complex environments.
Again, you might ask the question, why
not actually go for the best one, right?
So there are a lot of reasons.
So when it comes to big companies or when
it comes to your use case it depends on
what sort of thing you're looking for.
It's just not always ideal
to go for the best one.
Again it's not, I'm not trying to say.
Increasing the latency is what you want
to go for, but basically there are ever
so many things that you can, you have to
think about, keep in mind as in how many
teams are actually looking for this data?
What is the latency that is tolerated?
What is the latency that you
really want to shoot for?
So on and so forth.
Again, like some things are easy to
integrate, some things are very hard
to go for, go with, go to integrate,
and sometimes the learning curve is
way too much, so on and so forth.
There are a lot of decisions.
Our thought processes,
which go into selecting a
particular streaming framework.
But at least in the span of my
career, I've actually always
worked with the hybrid systems.
Again, like as I was just saying, Kafka
for event ingestion is something which
is very widely used because it actually.
Elev for seamless event ingestion
and flink for processing is
something very widely used as well.
Again, there is park streaming, there
is park structured streaming, so on
and so forth, which provides similar
functionalities, but it really depends on.
What functionalities
you are you looking for?
For for instance some frameworks
provide better watermarking, some
frameworks provide better latency.
So if, let's say you require better
watermarking, you go with the necessary
framework I'm just trying to throw
all the details at you so that you
can make an informed decision and you
can actually learn what, how to make a
proper, informed decision and choosing
a particular streaming framework.
Now implementation.
Let's talk about the
implementation, right?
So basically how does the implementation
work when you are trying to
implement a real-time architecture?
So first the data enters through high
speed brokers like Kafka, for example.
Kafka is used for so that, let's say
for server fails, and you somehow.
Don't process the event downstream.
You will you have enough time for you
to process and which hand Kafka like
handling millions of events per second.
Next processor like Flink manages complex
computations and realtime analysis.
Then a real-time feature store
quickly delivers essential data to
models, because that is important to
create features, so on and so forth.
And finally, optimized models.
Serving infrastructure produces
predictions and constantly
monitor system accuracy.
So this setup includes
automatic retraining.
Where accuracy drops, ensuring
consistent performance and reliability.
Now let's actually talk about the key
takeaways and next things, next steps.
So to wrap things up again,
implementing real-time machine learning
has clear substantial benefits.
I. Dramatically reducing fraud
for an for instance, significantly
improving sales in e-commerce,
minimizing downtime in manufacturing.
The keys to now keys to key to
success in is include is to choose
your architecture very carefully.
Continuously monitor performance
and automating model retraining.
Now I would say begin by
targeting your most impactful
latency sensitive applications.
From there incrementally build your
capabilities and be on lookout for
changes in your data environment.
Again, thank you so
much for your attention.
I hope you learned a great deal
about streaming data structure,
streaming frameworks, so on and so
forth, and how, where they are used,
and I'm really happy that you are.
Again, thanks for
attending the conference.
Hope you have a really good time.