Greetings everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, machine
Learning 2025 s. I'm Srin.
Was ami, director of Technology
Portfolio at SPL Consulting Inc. With
over 23 years of experience in it.
Specialist in enterprise cloud
architecture, multi-cloud
integrations, data management.
I also have specialization in
financial systems, Oracle Cloud,
ERP, and payment processing.
Do you know that over 67% of
multi-cloud integration projects
implementation overrun because of
the challenges in the data and the
complexities in the integrations?
So today's sessions, we will
cover mastering multi-cloud ERP
integration, your framework for data
normalization and synchronization.
So ERP implementations and the systems
evolved over the period of time.
From monolithic architecture to highly
distributed cloud native implementations.
So organizations are adapted to implement
multiple clouds based on the domain
specialization, rather than implementing
a single ERP or single cloud ERP.
So example, if you take financials,
Oracle Cloud, ERP is based in
the market, whereas Workday is
for the human capital management.
Salesforce for customer relationship
management and bully under
for supply chain optimization.
So if the enterprise want to use best
of the domain cloud ERP system, then
implementing these multi-cloud in the
enterprise ecosystem is inevitable.
So this strategic approach delivers a
superior domain specific functionality
for the enterprises and the business.
However, it also brings lot of challenges
and data models, inconsistent APIs
and varying issues across the board.
Let's us look at this
multi-cloud ERP ecosystem.
Oracle Cloud ERP, specialized in financial
domain is implemented by almost 41
percentage of the Fortune 500 companies.
Is, so it has various modules, example,
general ledger, account receivable,
account payables, fix address, and
it also has superior functionalities
of financial consolidations
and reporting functionalities.
Workday is a human capital
management specialized ERP, and it
has unified data architecture for.
The complete workforce operations
for any enterprises, it holds over 38
percentage of market share across the
enterprises with over 10,000 employees.
However, Workday is using so based
web services with the complex
external schemas for their data needs.
Salesforce is customer
relationship management.
ERP system, almost 56 percentage
of the multi-cloud ERP ecosystem
holds Salesforce for its CRM needs.
The Salesforce ecosystem uses even
driven architecture generating almost
two 12.4 million even notifications
daily in large scale implementations.
On the other hand.
Is specialized in supply chain
orchestration with over 28
percentage of market penetration
among global enterprises.
If you look at these, all these ERP
systems, they're superior in functionality
in their respective domain and almost
have a very good market share across
the Fortune 500 and other enterprises
with the large scale operations.
So the enterprise has adopted these
different ERP systems to support
their functionalities and their domain
needs, which gives the complexity.
The very first challenge,
which we are going to look at
multi-cloud ERP implementation is
schema heterogeneity challenges.
We looked at why enterprises.
Or adapting to implement multiple
cloud ERP to gain the superior
functionalities available in each domain.
However, the fundamental challenge in
multiple cloud ERP integration lies in
reconciling their divergent data models.
Each cloud ERP provider, they
designed their data model with
different architecture philosophies
to support and gain the.
Superior functionality in each of
the domain, though this gives very
good architecture and data model for
individual Cloud ERP, integrating
these data models across the cloud.
ERP is always complex
and provides challenges.
The substantial barrier.
Is to integrate or exchange
this data, which has different
schema, our properties.
If you look at it, the Oracle Cloud
ERP, which holds the financial
data, has complex chart of account
segments, lot of business rules.
However, these start off
accounts and business rules are
exchanged with other cloud ERP
to derive accounting information.
Similarly, the workday, which holds the
employee data, has 23 related objects
with over 200 plus attributes per record.
When this is exchanged with other
cloud ERP in the ecosystem, they
do not need all these attributes.
However, the exchange
substantially become complex.
To get any user related
information from Workday,
the blue yonder system, which holds the
product informations, there are a lot of
master repositories and syncing them with
other cloud ERP, bringing lot of latency.
The CRM, which holds the partner data,
it has a lot of fragmented attributes.
Which also brings the complexity
across the cloud ERPs.
So this schema heterogeneity
always provides some challenges
which needs to be solved.
Semantic mapping complexities beyond the
structural differences, which we saw the
semantic variations compound normalization
challenges in multi-cloud ERP ecosystem.
Even when the systems appear to
represent similar business concepts,
subtle differences in terminology,
hierarchies, and business rules create
significant integration obstacles.
Let us look at this example of how the
business partner represented across
multiple cloud ERP systems, the supplier
representation in Oracle, whereas.
In Oracle Cloud, ERP the financial
relationship payment terms and tax
information and accounting classification
of the suppliers are maintained where the
enterprise do business with any purchasing
relationship is called supplier.
However, the same supplier is
represented as account in Salesforce,
whereas the primary attributes
around these accounts are.
Related to relationship attributes,
how we communicate with them, what
is the cases with them, what is
their histories and what are the
opportunities we have with them?
It's completely different than
what it is being represented
in Oracle, the same supplier,
which is mentioned in Oracle now.
If you look at the blue
yonder, it's called vendor.
Whereas the primary focus or the
attributes for the blue yonder system is.
The logistic performance
metrics, delivery capabilities,
and supply chain reliability.
So the semantic reconciliation,
almost 43 percentage of development
effort is spent on this.
We have seen schema
heterogeneity challenges and
semantic mapping complexities.
However, organization have developed
several sophisticated technical
mechanisms to address these challenges.
How these challenges or approaches
vary in complexity and architectural
impact with the selection, typically
based on specific integration
requirements and technical constraints.
Also, based on the
organization's capabilities
there are.
Predominant options available for
us to handle these challenges.
The first and widely used option
across the enterprises are EDL.
So you extract the data from the source
cloud, ERP, transform it to the target,
and finally load the transform our map
data in, into the target cloud, ERP.
So this ETL option is
widely used and very simple.
In terms of the implementation,
however, most of the work are mapping
are being done in the transform layer.
The second option, which we
have is schema mapping engines.
So you have sophisticated engine
which take care of all your
heterogeneous schema, mappings, and.
Across different systems.
Cloud ERP systems, it reduces the
development effort because the engine
provides the mapping for various cloud
ERPs, which can be adapted by different
integrations and seamlessly will work.
The canonical data models are evolving
as a trend and standardization.
To normalize these complexities, whereas
each source ERP system, the cloud ERP
system, which is master in their data,
agree with other cloud ERP systems across
the enterprise to standardize the format
or the canonical data model and publish
them as a publisher subscriber model.
So that the consumer will have
standardized data and attributes
available in the form of the
canonical data model to them.
So this takes lot of
initial design complexity.
However, in the long run, it
reduces the overall, the mapping
or the implementations record by
the consumers in the latter part.
Latency inconsistency challenges in
the distributed multi-cloud ERP system.
Various data elements are shared across
ERP systems, thus bring a significant
timing challenges that can compromise
the business process Integrity.
If you look at it approximately around
68% of the organization's report.
Their business impact from
timing related data ies across
integrated cloud platforms.
These delays can occur
due to various reasons.
Example, there is a network latency
or large processing queues between one
cloud ERP to other cloud ERP, or there
are validation rules which the data
will not go through to the target cloud.
ERP.
Sometimes there are middleware
transformation overhead.
All of these causes two things.
One is either there is a latency,
sometimes there is a integrity challenges.
So if you look at it, transaction
propagation delays, there are
almost eight to 15 seconds is
for the standard transactions.
Up to few minutes for the
complex ones across the cloud.
ERP systems, the eventual
consistency models.
There are 47% of the data entries
operate under even true consistency.
The even best triggers are very complex.
It brings overhead to to
the cloud ERP data model.
High volume data streaming also
contributes to these latency
and consistency challenges
with latency under data
integrity challenges.
There needs a conflict
less solution strategy.
So in the multi-cloud ERP, there
are a lot of bidirectional data
flows between the cloud ERP systems.
First, we have to detect the conflict on
time and also need to provide you proper
resolutions to handle this integrity
and the data conflict resolution.
The research indicates that approximately.
Six to 8% records in the bidirectional
synchronization scenarios.
Experience these update conflicts.
This postage may increase up to 12 to 15%
if the data is getting modified frequently
across the multi cloud ERP systems.
So there are certain strategies available
for us to resolve this conflict.
The widely used.
Approach.
Our strategy is time-based.
Resolution.
What it means is always giving the
precedence to the most recent update.
If there is a conflict between
multiple updates, ignore the one
which we received earlier, go
with the latest or recent update.
So this is called time-based
time timestamp based approach.
The second one, which we have
is domain specific rules.
Say example, when there are conflict
error between the data element, the
domain specific rule or the data
element wins that conflict and it takes
the priority over the other element.
Say example, if accounting
financial system, Oracle Cloud,
ERP, is the master or the supplier.
If Blue Yonder is the master or.
The customer, if Salesforce is
the master, the domain specific
system takes the precedence over
the other systems and holds that
attribute are the data integrity.
So that is the domain specific
conflict resolution approach.
The next one is manual reconciliation.
Say example, you cannot use time-based,
or we cannot use domain specific rule.
However, it needs a manual intervention
to reconcile the data to understand
which takes precedents and apply it.
There is still a 15%
adoption to this strategy.
The last one, which is conflict free,
replicated data types is the industry
standard, which we want to go to.
It is 8% adoption.
The way it is implemented will avoid
the conflict and it'll be conflict free.
Replicated data type
framework for synchronization.
An effective synchronization
framework for the multi-cloud ERP
system must incorporate several
architectural components that
collectively address complex.
Requirements for data consistency and
re resilience organizations implementing
comprehensive frameworks experience
approximately 76% fewer data consistency
incidents compared to those relying
on point to point integrations.
If you look at this different
architecture or framework, the
Oracle has a B, C, C connector.
Which simplifies the extraction.
Thus, it reduces the
extraction complexity by 45%.
If you look at the sales force, which
has this change data capture, it reduces
almost 97% in the data volume compared to
full synchronization, the even streaming
backbone for bullion, which publishes
the data or stream the data into Kafka.
Also almost process 50,000 to
hundred K messages per second.
The smart batching strategies,
which improves almost one 20%
with the adaptive approaches.
Adapting your right framework and
strategy between the multiple cloud
ERP based on their capabilities.
Will improve the data synchronization
and reduce the data inconsistency
issues while we are doing data
normalization approaches and solution
for heterogeneous schema challenges and
semantic mapping complexities, and also
synchronization framework to address
data inconsistency and latency issues.
One should not overlook
the security issues.
The multi-cloud ERP system brings
in, compared to the single cloud
deployment are the on-premise
deployments, which are more protected.
The exchange of data between the
multi-cloud ERP system, especially the
sensitive data, brings more vulnerability.
So approximately 41 percentage of
security in more security incidents
related to the data exchange in
the multi-cloud ERP system compared
to the single cloud ERP systems.
So we need to have some
security consideration.
Those are like, say cross
platform authentication.
So how do we authenticate between multiple
cloud ERP systems, the widely used.
Authentication, make comment
2.0, which is almost 82%.
Enterprises adapted these kind of
approaches to secure their multiple
cloud ERP systems and its data.
However, there are 72% multi-cloud
ERP implementer encounter
regulatory related violations, okay.
During the initial deployment.
So automated compliance monitoring
reduces these kind of security incidents.
Almost by 63%.
The data, which is tranent because
there are a lot of data exchange
between the multi-cloud ERP system
should be encrypted so that tss
misconfigurations are outdated security.
Cheaper suits.
Those are contributing almost 28% of
these kind of integration incidents.
Okay, so the organizations which
are adopting layered encryption
approaches experience 52%
fewer data exposure incidents.
The last one, data drift detection.
So 24% of integration failures attributed
to undetected schema changes between
these multiple cloud ERP systems.
So organizations implying
automated drift detection.
Identify 83 percentage of potential
issues before it impacts the business.
The proposed implementation strategy
to address these multi-cloud
ERP data integration issues.
A faced approach to address these
normalization and synchronization
challenges provides the necessary
structure to manage the complexity
of multi-cloud ERP integration.
So organizations implying structured
approaches experience approximately 43%
higher success rate than the organizations
those attempting to concurrently
implementing these strategies.
If you look at the strategy.
The first step should be the
data profiling and mapping
comprehensive analysis on the data.
And its mapping is very much record.
They should be the initial
phase of the project.
It also should understand the
quality data, quality issues,
what should be addressed.
Once the data profiling and
mapping is done, then enterprise
should move on to make sure to
design the canonical model design.
So spending quality time in this phase
to understand the actual canonical
model, which will be used by multiple
cloud ERPs in the ecosystem will
benefit the enterprise in the long run.
Once the canonical model design
is done, now the enterprise should
carefully choose the integration
burden across the cloud ERP systems.
Choosing the right integration
burden will solve many of the data
latency and inconsistency issues.
Once organization completed this
phase, we should move on to.
Synchronization mechanism implementation.
Almost 63 percentage of projects
encounter significant technical obstacles.
During this phase.
Incremental deployment achieves
more frequent delivery milestones.
Then once all these phases
are achieved, the enterprise
continue to monitor and govern.
All these implementations and
synchronization processes and frameworks,
so the comprehensive monitoring
reduces almost 54 percentage of their
meantime rate to their resolution.
Effective implementations capture 25 to
40 distinct metrics per integration flow.
Data profiling and mapping constitute
the essential face-to-face in
multi-cloud ERP integration.
Providing a very comprehensive
analysis of the data structures,
relationships, and business rules
across the platforms these foundations
ensures the subsequent integration
design decisions are based on accurate
understanding of the data landscape.
So there are various profiling
tools available in the market which
automatically analyze the sample dataset.
To identify the patterns, relationships,
and quality characteristics that
influence the integration design.
Apart from doing this automated
schema analysis, we should also focus
on collaborative mapping, effective
profiling actions beyond simple structural
analysis to include semantic evaluation,
business role, and documentation,
and quality assessment in this phase.
Typically Bo involves both technical
specialist and also the domain business
domain expert who provide the crucial
context about the data quality assessment.
Also very key in this data
profiling and mapping phase.
The next implementation phase
is canonical model design phase.
The canonical model design represents
a strategic architectural decision
that significantly influence
long-term integration sustainability.
This phase focuses on the development
of intermediate data models that
bridge the platform specific schemas,
providing a consistent reference
point for all integration flows.
If you look at it, the
canonical model design phase.
Almost reduces 37 percentage of them
maintenance costs for the integrations
across the multiple cloud ERP systems.
In a typical large scale enterprise
multi-cloud ERP system implementation,
there will be around 1 22 3 50.
Different canonical definition
needs to be done for various data
elements which should be shared
across the multiple cloud ERP system.
However, considering these large scale
implementations and the effort needed to
implement this canonical model design,
there is almost a 25 to 30 percentage
of initial effort increase will be
experienced in this implementation phase.
The next and crucial phase in
the implementation approach is
integration pattern, selection phase.
Enterprise should carefully select the
integration pattern for the various data
elements, which is shared between the
multiple cloud ERP systems, based on that
timing constraints, when the data should
be available, whether it is real time or
batch based on the volume, whether it's
a low volume data exchange or the high
volume data exchange between the multiple
cloud ERP and what are the transformation
complexity associated with this.
Data elements, and also if there
is a data exchange failure between
the cloud ERP systems, what are the
recovery mechanism which is needed?
All these inputs will determine the
right integration pattern to be selected
by the enterprise for a particular data
element in a large scale enterprise,
multi-cloud ERP implementation,
typically there will be five to eight
distinct integration patterns used
for various data elements needs.
What are the future
directions and conclusions?
So the AI driven mapping tools which
are available now in the market, will
use machine learning approaches to
automate most complex mapping task and
reduce the implementation time, and
also improve the accuracy through patent
organization and suggestion capabilities.
Also industry is evolving the
standardized exchange format for
the data elements, which will reduce
all the custom transformations
and mapping, which is needed.
The last one is the advanced
conflict resolutions.
The Next Generation Conflict
Restoration Tools using the machine
learning capabilities will know the
context awareness, thus provide.
Yeah, better reconciliation
and concrete resolution.
Mechanism.
Key takeaways from this conference.
Note, multi-cloud ERP integration
requests, careful orchestration
of data, normalizations, semantic
mapping, and synchronous approaches.
We have seen a lot of challenges
which needs to be addressed
through these approaches, and
also the success depends on them.
Balancing specialized to
functionality with the cohesive
data flow across platforms.
The framework, or the implementation
approach we have outlined provides a
structured methodology for tackling these
complex challenges while maintaining
the security and performance in line.
So begin with the comprehensive
data profiling, develop robust
canonical models and select
appropriate integration patterns.
For each data flow scenario in
a multi-cloud ERP ecosystem.
Thanks everyone for spending time with
me to go through this conference note.