Hello everyone and thank
you for joining today.
Today I'll be presenting on
harnessing AI for autonomous threat
defense in multi-cloud security.
My name is Pip Kura.
I'm principal architect at Trace three.
Today we will explore how artificial
intelligence is transforming security
in multi-cloud environments, helping
us defend against increasingly
sophisticated cyber threats.
Let's begin by acknowledging
the reality we are facing today.
In cybersecurity, the threats
aren't what they used to be.
Legacy security frameworks, things
like basic firewalls, VPNs and
intuition detection systems.
These were designed for a old
where threats were simpler,
slower, and frankly easier to spot.
Today's threats are incredibly dynamic.
We are seeing polymorphic malware that
changes its code every time it executes.
We are facing advanced persistent
threats, attackers that sit quietly
inside networks for months learning,
adapting, avoiding detection.
And let's be clear, these not the
work of random hackers anymore.
It's highly organized, often state
sponsored, and increasingly automated.
Machine learning is now used by
attackers themselves to develop
smarter, faster exploits.
One of the biggest problems, isn't it?
The gap between.
When an exploit is created and
when it's launched, it's shrinking.
Organizations barely have time
to patch these vulnerabilities
before attack a strike.
The old models of detect,
done, respond are too slow.
We need a fundamentally new approach,
and that's where AI begins to shed.
And now let's talk about
the AI security advantage.
AI brings three, transform two
capabilities to cybersecurity, and it's
important to understand them individually.
For the first, let's talk
about real time analysis.
We all know AI can process
petabytes of security data such
as logs, network traffic, user
behaviors within milliseconds.
It's like giving your security
operations team a super human vision.
Patterns that would take a human analyst
days to recognize or surfaced instantly.
Second is autonomous response.
Historically, once an alert was
raised, humans had to analyze,
validate, escalate, and finally
act that takes hovers or longer.
In the meantime, the attacker is
moving, stealing, and damaging the.
Enterprise Now, AI flips This.
Systems now detect threats and
immediately act by isolating, infected
missions, shutting down dangerous
processes often without needing a
human to approve it First, third,
and perhaps more most exciting is
adapt to defense AI based systems or
self-learning every attack they see.
Every anomaly they process
makes them smarter.
They evolve alongside attackers.
Traditional signature based defenses,
a static AI based defenses are alive
and growing stronger every day.
When we talk about measurable improvements
using ai, we are talking about operational
realities, not theoretical pro promises.
Think about false positives.
In many organizations, security
teams are drowning in alerts.
90% of those alerts, they're just noise
by reducing false positives by 30%.
AI doesn't just make teams more efficient.
It helps them focus on the right
threads faster with less burnout.
Response times are cut by 50%.
Means incident that used to take six hours
to mitigate now takes under three minutes.
In cybersecurity, speed is everything.
Every second, an attacker remains
inside your network, increases damage
exponentially and a 40% faster.
Incident resolution rate reduces
not just the duration of attacks.
But also their downstream costs,
like regulatory fines, lost
customer trust and recovery efforts.
These numbers translate into real
business value, not just better
security, but stronger bottom lines.
Now let's talk about AI
powered behavioral tactics.
Traditional security often relies
on static rules, for example.
If X happens or Y happens, block it.
The problem is attacker knows the these
rules and they find ways around them.
But now let's see it.
The ai, it takes a different approach.
AI watches it and learns from it.
It knows what normal looks like,
not based on rigid definitions, but
based on continuous observation.
For instance, or for example, if a user
always logs in from Austin, between
9:00 AM to 5:00 PM and generally
there's a login from Singapore at
midnight that's flagged immediately.
Or for instance, if a database starts
sending unusually large amounts of sense
to data outside normal business hours,
AI detects that and crucially, it doesn't
just flag anomaly, it takes action.
It takes action by automatically
locking those suspicious accounts or
isolating those suspicious devices.
A prevents minor anomalies
from becoming major incidents.
Let's talk about zero
trust implementation.
I believe this as being has
become a buzzword, but it's
also a fundamental principle.
It's like never trust, always verify.
That's zero trust implementation, right?
So we can no longer assume that because a
device is inside our network, it is safe.
We must verify everything like
every user, every device, every
access request least privilege means
thinking critically about access.
Does this really, does this user really
need database segment privileges,
or can they just read reports?
And assuming breaches means building
layer defenses like microsegmentation.
Microsegmentation is nothing but
dividing the networks in enterprise into
smaller zones, which limits that blast
radius if an attacker breaks through.
Now with ai, it enhances
zero trust strategies by
monitoring trust continuously.
Not just at the moment of login,
but during the entire session.
Let's talk about AI
integration security platforms.
AI enhances existing security
platforms within multi-cloud.
Think about a typical SIM platform.
S sim means security, informa
information and event management.
Traditionally what it does is it
aggregates logs, normalizes data and
triggers alerts based on rule sets.
But when you add ai,
something powerful happens.
AI can correlate security events
across systems automatically.
For example, it might see a strange
authentication attempt in Azure active.
Which correlates with abnormal API calls
that is happening in AWS cloud, and
tie that to a such specious download
that happens in a GitHub report.
Certainly what looked
like isolated events.
Now tell the story of
a coordinated attack.
Similarly in so platforms, which is
security orchestration, automation and
response platforms, AI helps automate
this instance of handling these workflows.
Now for the Imagine This, a
phishing email is de detected.
AI automatically quarantine.
The email locks affected user
account flags, similar emails,
and notify security analysts.
All within seconds.
Time is the key.
And this all comes with no
manual ticket triage, no waiting
hours for investigation it.
This is fast orchestrated
with intelligent action.
And finally, AI enriches alerts
with contextual intelligence.
Instead of just saying anomaly predicted,
the alert might include more details.
For example, this credential matches
known tactics, techniques, and
procedures of the advanced threat groups.
For example, like a PT 29 and.
Qualifies them as medium
severity, or it would even take
immediate action as recommended.
This kind of context reduces guesswork for
analysts and accelerates time to action.
Now, let's talk about task platforms.
Cloud security as organizations
expand across AWS, Azure, GCP,
and multi-cloud environments,
and even in hybrid environments.
The complexity of managing security growth
exponentially, there is no longer a single
perimeter to defend your applications.
Data APIs and users are scattered, are
across dozens of services and providers.
Thankfully, these major cloud
platforms have begun integrating
AI into the security ecosystems.
In AWS services like Guardian
AI continuously scan cloud trail
logs for unusual API activity.
Imagine detecting an administrative
API call happening at 2:00 AM from a
country where you have no employees.
In Azure, the security center uses
mission learning to a assess these
vulnerabilities across compute,
storage and identity services.
Which predicts potential breach points
before attackers can exploit them in
Google Cloud Security Command Center
applies a two and more importantly,
to monitor containerized workloads.
Given the rise of Kubernetes and
microservices, protecting containers
which are dynamic and affirm is critical.
Now what all ties all
this together is that YAP.
AI operates at cloud speed analyzing
millions of data points across
platforms that would or own human teams.
When security is consistent, automated
and intelligent across clouds, it allows
organizations to innovate confidently
without sacrificing risk management.
Yes.
Let's bring this all to life
with real world examples.
Financial services are high value
target for attackers, as we all know,
especially with the rise of FinTech.
But now with FIN FinTech companies,
banks can now deploy ea not just for
fraud detection post-transaction,
but to prevent fraudulent
authentication before it even succeed.
For instance, one of the major
institution implemented AI powered
authentication, anomaly detection,
which prevented them over 4.3 million
in losses in just in a single quarter.
Think about the ripple effect,
not just money sale, but
brand and trust are preserved.
Similarly in healthcare faces different
but equally critical challenges.
Patient data is among the most
sensitive information in the world
protected by regulations like hipaa.
Hospitals now use AI to monitor network
traffic for ransomware behavior patterns.
The moment AI detects later movement
or encryption behaviors associated with
this ransomware, it isolates affected
endpoints automatically sometime
before the ransomware fully executes.
And in e-commerce companies
face relentless DDoS attacks,
especially during peak season, like
holidays or major holiday sales.
Using AI, they can analyze
real time traffic patterns to
distinct use legitimate customers
from board driven traffic.
This allows them to mitigate attacks
without disrupting real shoppers.
Maintaining revenue flow, and also most
importantly, the customer satisfaction.
So where are we headed?
What does the future of
cybersecurity looks like?
When AI takes center stitch, one major
shift is towards brick two Defense.
Rather than just reacting to threats
and that have already materialized,
future AI systems will anticipate attack
patterns based on early signals such
as subtle network behaviors, metadata
anomalies, or threat intelligence.
From around the globe, AI will model the
most likely paths an attacker would take
and proactively close the vulnerabilities
before exploitation happens.
We'll also see more
self-healing infrastructures.
Imagine systems that upon detecting
compromise, automatically roll back
to a secure snapshot or reconfigure
themselves to eliminate infection
vectors without even human intervention.
Finally, with growing compute,
quantum computing maturity,
traditional encryption algorithms
will be increasingly vulnerable.
Yay will be critical in managing
adaptive quantum resistant encryption
strategies, evolving defenses in real
time based on quantum threat levels.
It's not just about detecting and
responding anymore, it's about
preempt strengthening defenses
faster than advisories can adapt to.
To wrap up, let's review the key
takeaways from today's session.
First.
AI is not optional anymore.
The scale, speed, and sophistication
of modern threats require
defenses that are equally dynamic.
Second, the results are measurable.
Organizations that integrate AI seek
quantifiable improvements in reduced
false postures, faster detection, faster
response, and lower breach impact.
Third you to start your
journey strategically.
Begin with AI enhanced
monitoring and instant detection.
Build muzzle there.
Then gradually move forward towards
fully autonomous response capabilities,
and finally, invest in your people.
AI is not a magic box.
It's a force multiplier for
skilled security professionals.
Develop teams that can
work symbiotically with ai.
Analyzing complex situations, providing
ethical oversight and refining
AI models with domain expertise.
Together, AI and human intelligence
are the future of cybersecurity.
Thank you again for
spending time with me today.
I'm excited about the feature
and I hope you are too.
Thank you.