Speaker 22: Hello everyone.
I am Raje Za, and in this session we
are going to talk about orchestrating
agent state machines with RAF,
using a practical use case that is
automating clinical documentation.
Let me unpack the title in a grounded way.
So when people say agentic, it
can sound like the model is doing
independent reasoning, like a person
that's not framing that I use.
Here's agentic meaning in a more,
much more engineering friendly way.
We break a complex task into
specialized testable step.
Each step is implemented as a node
that transformed a shared state,
and we use a graph to decide what
happens next based on that state.
So the agency comes from a workflow
design, conditional routing, retries,
and quality checks rather than a
single prompt that we hope works.
Now the problem.
So clinic clinicians have doctor patient
conversations and those conversation
needs to become some clinical nodes.
One common format is soap.
Which stands for subjective
objective Assessment and Plan.
This is a classic structure for
documentation because it separates
what patient says, what we observe
and what we think is happening
and what we plan to do, right?
So the challenge is that the conversation
is messy and human, while the note must
be structured, accurate and reviewable.
So in this talk, we'll build a prototype
medical scribe agent with four agents.
The first one being the transcription,
which converts an audio to
text or accept text directly.
Then the information extraction,
which will convert the transcript
into a structured entities.
Then the summarization agent that
takes in the structured entities
and converts them into soap notes.
And then finally, we'll have a
con consistency checking agent
that compares the entities
versus a note and flag problems.
And we orca orchestrate all of these
with land graph, which let us build
state machines which is nothing.
But these the cumulative sum of
nodes plus edges, plus conditional
routing and optional loops.
So if you want to inspect the
implementation later, the GitHub
repo is shown on the slide.
And I'll reference key concepts and
pattern so you can map them to code.
Quick disclaimer before we go further,
this is an educational prototype.
In real clinical setting, you
need thorough validation, privacy
control, and clinician oversight.
Nothing here is medical advice and output
should not be used for real patient care
without proper governance and review.
Alright, let's talk about
what, why this matters now.
So clinical documentation is
one of the biggest productivity
bottlenecks in healthcare, and
it also contributes to burnout.
There are three stable truths
that motivate this work.
First time multiple studies have
found that physicians spend a large
amount of time on EHR and desk work
related to patient facing time.
Often reported around two hours of
desk time for every one hour of patient
time, even if the ex exact number varies
By setting the pattern is consistent.
Documentation consumes a
major share of clinician time.
Second burnout, right?
So burnout rates vary by survey and
year, but commonly hover around about
half of patient physicians reporting
at least one symptom of burnout.
Documentation burden is consistently cited
as the major driver because it extends
the workday fractures attention and reduce
time for meaningful patient interaction.
And the third is the system impact.
So the burnout correlates with turnover
and reduce clinical hours, which
impact patient access and continuity.
There are large economic
estimates tied to burnout, related
turnovers and reduced hours.
The key takeaway is documentation
is not just a inconvenience,
it's a system level issue.
So why not just use an LLM
and call it a day, right?
Because healthcare nodes are
high stake artifacts, you
can't optimize for speed alone.
Nodes must be accurate.
No hallucinated meds,
diagnosis, or vitals.
It should also be auditable.
We need to know what happened at each
steps, and it should also be correctable.
That is human must be
able to review and fix.
So this is where architecture
matters and one huge prompt approach
tends to produce something that
looks plausible, but it is hard to
inspect and hard to improve safely.
If it's wrong.
You often don't know where
we went wrong, right?
So did the transcription.
Miss here, did trans, does the,
did the extraction miss a symptom?
Did a summarization, omit a detail?
Did the model invent a medication?
So in this talk I'm going to
emphasize transparent stateful
orchestration, which will be each
agent has a narrow responsibility.
All inter intermediate artifacts are
preserved in a state, and a final
consistency check makes error visible.
So that's the mindset shift from
generate a node to build a workflow
that can be debugged and trusted.
To understand why we are using a
multi-agent state machines, it helps
to understand why clinical nodes
are uniquely challenging compared
to normal summarization, right?
A clinical encounter is not just a story,
it's a mixture of subjective, parent
narrative, patient narrative, objective
measurements, clinic chin interpretation,
and action item with safety implic.
Right, and the raw
conversation is very messy.
Patient patients can jump topics,
clinicians ask clarifying questions.
There are abbreviations and shorthands,
and the critical facts can appear
once and never to be repeated.
So on top of that, clinical language has
special structure that LMS can mishandle.
Basically a negation denies
chest pain versus chest pain.
There can also be temporality,
which is started last week,
which versus what is ongoing.
Then there can be some uncertainty.
For example, if the phrase is
like, possible viral URI versus
confirmed new pneumonia, right?
And there can also be issues with
context like family history of
diabetes versus patient has histories.
So if you compress everything into one
prompt, you are asking the model to
transcribe, interpret, extract, facts,
decide what's important, format as soap
and validate consistency all at once.
That tends to create brittle behavior.
And when it fails silently
by separating steps.
We assign each complexity
to the right place.
That is transcription, handles,
formatting, and clarity.
Extraction handles, fact and negations
summarization handles narrative structure
and clinical tone and consistency checking
catches, mismatches and omissions.
And because we keep intermediate artifacts
in state, we can audit and debug.
This is especially important in
healthcare because plausible but
wrong is worse than no output.
So we design for safe failures.
If we can't extract reliability, we stop.
That's the real motivation
behind the architecture
you'll see in the next slides.
So let's define exactly
what we are building, right?
So the input is either an
audio recording of a clinical
conversation or a text transcript
for easier iteration and testing.
Right, and the output
is a clean transcript.
Structured extracted entities in typed
J-S-O-N-A structured soap note, a
consistency report, plus per node logs.
And on the right here you see the
pipeline, the transcription followed by
extraction, followed by summarization,
and then comes consistency.
These are the two
foundational design choice.
There are basically the choice One
is specialized agents instead of one
mega agent, each node does one job.
So basically transcription
should not try to diagnose.
Extraction, should not try to.
Write prose and summarization
should not try to invent fact.
And finally, consistency checking
should not silently fix things
without reporting, right?
So this separation creates
an engineering advantage.
You can improve one node
without destabilizing the other.
For example, if we improve the
extraction prompt and schema description
without changing the summarization
or prompt or summarization,
prompt of formatting, right?
The second choice that we
have is a shared state.
So every node reads and
writes a single shared object.
That shared object is the
system's memory and audit trail.
So to make that concrete,
here's a tiny example.
So basically, if.
A doctor says what brings you in?
And the patient's re response is dry cough
for a week low fever for a few days ago.
And the doctor's again says,
any shortness of breath and
the patient's response with no.
So in a monolithic approach,
you get a soap note, right?
But you can't easily verify
whether the negation, no
shortness of breath is preserved.
The fever value is accurate, or the plan
that addresses the cuff in our approach.
You can inspect this.
The transcript, the extracted
symptom list, including shortness
of breath, denied the soap node
and the consistency report.
All of it is traceable.
This makes the system not only more
trustworthy, but also easier to evaluate.
And we can evaluate extraction
independently from summarization,
which is very critical.
At the end, we'll also cover
how to run a demo via Streamlet
and how to run evaluations.
I've also recorded a live video
of our running application.
And I will go over it in the,
in few of the upcoming slides.
So even if you don't know to run the code
and the architecture the architecture
should be directly reusable, right?
So let me move on to the next slide.
So now the question is why land graph.
If you have built LLM workflows, you've
likely built linear chains, right?
Step A, then step B, and then
step C chains work for simple
flows, but they become fragile.
As soon as you add branching logic,
retries, fallbacks and auditing,
clinical documentation is full of
real world failure modes, right?
Missing audios practic partial
transcripts extraction that fails.
Schema validation, summarization that
omits key facts, inconsistent notes
where vital in objective don't match.
Don't match extracted vitals
or plans that don't addresses
the chief complaint, right?
In a chain, you often end up with
if else, logic scattered everywhere.
Now, over time, it becomes hard to
reason about what happens in each case.
A state machine is a better mental
model and land graph gives us a first
ca first class abstraction of first
state machines, a shared object node
as state transformer transformers,
edges defining flows and conditional
edges to decide what happens next.
This gives us three engineering benefits.
The first one is explicit control flow.
That is routing becomes a clear function.
You can read it and understand
the system behavior.
Second is recover recoverability.
So if extraction fails any
validation, you can retry once.
If it still fails, stop safely.
And if transcription is missing,
we can exit early, right?
If the consistency check finds
issues, we route to a revised
step or flag for review.
The third important point
is traceability, right?
So because each node logs
actions to a shared state, you
can reconstruct what happened.
A practical point can be like in
healthcare, auditability right is
not nice to, is not a nice to have.
If you can't see the system, like what the
system did, you can't safely deploy it.
So line graph is very valuable, not
just because it's cool, but because it
lets us express a workflow that matches
reality with stateful, brandable, debug
able and measurable properties, right?
So next we'll look at the shared
state object that makes this possible.
And if you're new to graph here's a quick
vocabulary map for the rest of the talks.
So basically, a state is a single
python object, often pedantic
model or a type deck that represent
everything we know so far.
And in our case, it includes a
transcript, extracted encounter,
soap notes, log and error field.
Node.
A basically a node is a function that
takes a state and returns a state.
You can think it, think of it
like a step in a pipeline except
it's explicit, explicitly typed
and designed to be compostable.
And a good node has clear required
inputs, clear outputs, and
predictable failure behavior.
And edge is basically a transition
from one node to another.
And in a linear change, edges are
very implicit, but in graph edges
are explicit and very read readable.
There is something called conditional
edge, which is where a router function
decides where to go next, and the router
typically inspect states and returns
a label like, extract, summarize,
and something like that, right?
This is a mechanism that makes work
flow very robust because you can
encode safe failures and fall back.
Parts there is something also
called cycle, which is pretty
pretty convenient to know.
Like cycle is basically simply an edge
that route back to an earlier node.
Yeah, and, why does this matter
for an agent taking medical stripe?
Because you know the problems you face,
missing inputs, validation, failure,
revision needs are all naturally ex
expressed as state fields, routing
conditions and optional loop, right?
So instead of scattering control
flow across your code base, you
centralized it in a graph definition.
And that's the main reason, this
approach scales and it keeps the
workflow understandable as it grows.
Okay?
Now we have got land graph
vocabulary, so let's look at
what we have in store and why.
So everything revolves around a. A
object called Medical scribed Street.
The the state object holds input,
intermediate artifacts, outputs,
logs, and errors at a high level input
text is an optional text transcript.
Audio path is basically the path
to audio intermediate outputs.
Then we have transcript, which is
basically cleaned text of the transcript
encounter between patient and a doctor.
Then we have a clinical encounter.
We also have soap notes, consistency
report and cross cutting fields.
And then we have logs, which
is list of audit trails.
And then we have errors, which
is a string of errors, right?
So this single shared state
is what enables orchestration.
You may ask why, right?
Because every node becomes a pure
transformation, which is state in
and state out that pure function
property is incredibly valuable.
You can unit test each node.
You can replay runs, you can
diff states across versions, and
you can build a regression test.
On the right here you see an add
log helper that add structured
log retries with a timestamp.
In real system logging is where
reliability is one or lost
some example of log details.
Important are important and matters a
lot like, which model and prompt versions
were used, how long each node took, how
many extracted entities were produced.
Whether validation failed and how
many retries occurred, and whether a
revision loops were triggered or not.
So a key engineering rule is basically
node should not crash the workflow.
If a node fails, it should
set a state dot error, log the
failure and return the state.
So that should, how, that
is how it should behave.
And then the router can decide, whether
to stop retry or route to fallback.
This is what makes
failure very manageable.
They become part of a state machines
rather than random exception.
Let me spend a bit more time on
this shared state idea, because it's
easy to underestimate how much it
changes the engineering story, right?
So when you build an LLM app as a
chain of prompts, you often end up
with a bunch of implicit variables.
The transcript is somewhere in memory.
The extracted entities
are buried in Jason Blob.
The no text is in another string,
and the debug information lives
in a scattered log, right?
That makes it hard to answer
basic questions like, what
did the model see at step two?
What did it produce at step
two, did we validate the output?
Which prompt version ran.
So a shared typed state object turns
those question into simple inspection.
And now from a testing perspective,
state testing perspective
also state is a gift, right?
You can, you need test each
node with synthetic state input.
You can snapshot the output state
and compare it across version.
You can also build golden set
hand, handful of transcript and
expected intermediate artifacts.
So basically you can run
regression test when you update
prompts, models, or any schemas.
So here's a pattern that I can recommend
is basically you create a dictionary
of test cases with transcript input
the expected extracted entities, and
optionally a reference soap note.
You run a graph end to produce a
state compare basically the extracted
clinical encounter against gold using
entity level metrics and then soap
nodes against reference using rogues
or plus, or, consistency check.
So this gives you a very tight feedback
loop and you can change one component
and immediately see what broke.
Another benefit of shared
state is human review.
So in a clinical workflow, you really
want to auto chart without review.
Instead, you want to.
Present the transcript, extracting
entities and everything so a
clinician can verify and correct.
So the state makes this very
straightforward because those
artifacts already exist.
And finally, state, encourages
a clean separation of concerns.
Basically, agents do the work
and write results into a state.
Routers decide which flow based
on the state, and the UI reads the
state and renders the output, right?
And basically the, and in the
end, the evaluation reads the
states and compute the metrics.
So the state object becomes the
backbone that connects engineering,
ux, and evaluation in a coherent way.
Okay?
So with that foundation, we can move
into schemas and structured extraction.
So now we need structure, right?
So if you want reliability, don't
let model output unstructured text.
When you need data, we, so
we define pedantic models for
the entities we care about.
Here.
We care about symptoms, vital diagnosis,
medication test, follow up instructions,
and then we combine them into composite
model called clinical encounter.
This is the key clinical encounter becomes
a typed intermediate representation
and why it matters, you may ask.
So schema becomes a part
of your instruction.
When you request a structured
output, the model is guided
strongly on what to produce.
So validation catches errors, early
missing fields any malformed structure.
These become explicit error.
And downstream logic also
becomes simpler and safer.
Summarization can also reference encounter
symptoms, encounter vitals, et cetera.
And it doesn't have to infer
facts from raw transcript again.
And one more advantage, like evaluation
becomes feasible because entities
are very explicit and you can
compute entity level metrics, right?
So basically a practical notice like
schema design can encode clinical nuances.
For example, if you have to represent
negation explicitly, that is, for
example, denies shortness of breath,
include units of vitals and keep
like uncertain field optional to
avoid forcing any guesses, right?
So the field description
also matters a lot.
If you describe what belongs in
a field, you reduce ambiguity
and improve extraction quality.
So how do we implement each node?
So the system is reliable.
We, what we do is we use
a universal pat pattern.
First.
We log a start, then we validate input.
We call LLM structure.
We update state, then
we log success metadata.
Then we catch some
validation errors, if at all.
We catch some unexpected errors and
we always return a state, right?
So this pattern is boring,
but it is very powerful.
It ensures that every
node behaves consistently.
Errors are surface phased in the same
way, and the system is easy to trace.
There are two practical refinements.
So control retries for validations.
So if structured output fails,
validation retry once or twice with
stricter prompt stop, like after a
limit and surface the error, right?
The second thing is prompt
version metadata, right?
So we can store prompt version on
hash in logs and you can correlate
co or relate behavior changes.
So this node template becomes the
standard for adding future nodes
like retrieval, grounding, or coding.
It also keeps the workflow
very maintainable, right?
Moving on to different agents, right?
So transcription is a first agent.
It accepts either a audio
path or a pres supplied text.
And the main responsibility is
to produce transcript, normalize
speaker turns, clean conversations
and write state or transcript right?
And the key point here is transcription
should be deterministic and conservative.
We don't improve the transcript
in ways that change, meaning
also negations matter.
So clean phrasing matters.
If you lose denies terms like
denies, you can in word the meaning.
Also, transcription is
often the most expensive.
And the slowest step in production,
you'll often cache, transcript
or store them secure securely
and reuse them whenever possible.
So for the demo, the key is the interface.
Regardless of transcription
method, the output is a string
transcript instate, right?
Moving on to next slide.
The next agent is extraction.
So this is where we go
from narrative to data.
So the input is here is the transcript
that we extracted in the first agent.
The output is a validated
clinical encounter.
And we combine basically a clear
extraction specification with a structured
output validation, which is the pedantic
structure that we had defined before.
Extraction prompt principle would be like,
we prefer empty or unknown over guessing.
We do not invent diagnosis meds or vitals,
and we handle ations explicitly extract
exact numerical values when present.
Also, some of the schema principle
for this agent could be like, list
of re reputable entities optional
fields for often missing in form.
We include units of numerical
values and also consider
adding evidence fields later.
And moving on to some of the
implementation principle for
this agent could be like, we
should validate required input.
That is transcription should, must exist.
And then we call the LLM
with a response field.
And then we update the state
encounter, whatever was encountered.
Extracted.
We updated and then we log the
counts and timings on any failures.
And we set state errors
in case of any errors.
So what, why extraction
first helps, right?
It makes summarization much safer.
Summarization doesn't
have to repart raw script.
It reads a structured truth
structured truth object.
This also makes evaluation
and debugging very easier.
If you use if you see.
Wrong info.
In the final soak notes, you can
check whether it originated from
extraction or from summarization.
On this extraction step, I want
to go one level deeper because
this is where most medical scribe
prototype actually succeeds or fail.
So if you ask a model to extract
entities in free from j free from JSON,
you'll see common failure modes, right?
We can have missing keys, inconsistent
nesting values in wrong types, partial
output, and basically any helpful
additions that weren't in the transcript.
The fix is to treat extraction
like an API contract.
So how what we do is
basically we define a schema.
We ask for that schema, we validate
the output, and then we retry
or fail cleanly when validation.
So in this project, basically
pedantic plays two roles.
It describes the expected structure,
and it also validates actual output.
So the practical implementation
practic practically looks we build
a system from that says you are an
information extraction specialist.
Specialist.
We build a user prompt with the transcript
and explicit rules that call the model
and request structured output in a
way that maps to your pedantic model.
And also pars and validate
into a typed object.
So now what happens when,
validation fails, right?
This is where agent takes
state machines actually shines.
So if validation failure is not an
exception, you ignore, it becomes
basically a state you handle.
So a robust approach is
basically the first attempt.
We do normal extraction, prompt If
validation fails, retry once with stricter
prompt, for example, output must be valid.
JSON do not include commentary if
unknown use null or empty list.
So if it still fails, set state
dot error and then log failure
and then just stop, right?
Importantly that you should
always log the validation.
Basically you should always log whatever
validation at failed and the error.
Oh, like what the error category was
and whether, retry, succeeded or not.
That log becomes actually
gold when you debug.
And another thing extraction needs
is, clinical text is basically
negation handling, right?
So clinical language
contains many negation.
Something like denies chest
pain, no shortness of breath,
not taking any medication.
So if you treat negation ni in
naively right, you inward the meaning.
So there are two strategies here.
We encode negation
explicitly in in our schema.
Basically, symptom dot present
can be true or false, right?
And also instruct the model
explicitly like denies.
X means X is absent.
So e, even without a dedicated
negation field, you can preserve
this by representing denied
symptoms like separately.
Similarly you'll see temporal
qualifiers like for three days
started last week was at night.
So these are clinically relevant,
and adding them to schema
improves the node quality.
Now because the extraction
output is typed, you can also do
deterministic post-processing.
Which is normalized in units.
Standardized medication names, map
common synonyms like SOB, shortness
to shortness of breath and do do that
without, involving an LLM to every call.
Finally these structured extractions
sets you up for solid evaluations.
And you can compute
entity level precision.
Recall if one for each category, be
it symptoms, vital diagnosis meds,
and you can actually see exactly where
your system needs to work, right?
So this is architecturally, this
is why, architecturally I treat
extraction as core truth layer.
So if extraction is strong
summarization becomes much safer.
Okay.
Next week turn the structure note
into a clinician facing SOAP notes,
which is our summarization agent.
Summarization turns a structured
entity into clinician friendly note.
The input here is the clinical encounter
and the output is a Sno soap notes with
subjective objective assessment and plan.
Some of the safety principle is
some summarization should not
invent fact, it should format
and synthesize extracted facts.
The prompt constraint could be like
use only extracted information,
cl key clinical tone, cover chief
complaint, and also ensure that
the plan addresses symptoms.
Also include follow up if
present, something like that.
And some of the engineer engineering
choices is could be like te
basically temperature can be zero
for determinism output as a schema.
So the sections are also editable.
So because we output structured section
you can display them separately in the
UI and allow targeted edits if you want,
now let's talk about hallucination hall.
Hallucination risk because it's the
elephant in the room whenever we generate
medical text, in this architecture,
there are three deliberate choices
that reduce hall hallucinations.
Choice number one is summarize
from structured entities,
not from raw transcript.
The model is not trying to parse
messy conversations while also
generating a note so it reads A
structured clinical encounter.
Objects and formats is choice number two
is constrain the prompt with no new facts.
If information is missing, do not guess.
Do not add any medication diagnosis
or lab values if not provided.
Choice number three is
keep the temperature low.
So for documentation,
determinism is often a feature.
If a note changes materially
between runs, that's hard to govern.
And beyond these choices, here are
some, prompt patterns that can help.
Basically ask the model to mirror
structure, like put vitals under
objective, put diagnosis under assessment.
So these prevent content from
drifting across sections.
Also we can ask for coverage like, ensure
each symptoms in the encounter is either
addressed in assessment or planned those.
So these kind of prompts
pushes for completeness.
We can also ask for clinical
tone constraints, something like
use concise clinician tone and
avoid any conversational fillers.
So this makes notes very easier to review.
We can also ask for explicit uncertainty.
So if diagnosis is uncertain, state
is like differentiable and not
of fact this also very critical.
Another engineering trick is to
make summarization output itself
structured basically a soap notes
schema rather than a single text block.
This makes human review way easier.
A clinical clinician can just
scan objective section quickly,
and also highlight fields
that changed after revisions.
Finally, one practical workflow
approach is like after generating soap.
Notes you run a consistency
check and then display both
soap and the issue side by side.
So that turns the system into drafting
assessment with the critique and which is
like way much like safer than auto writer.
Yeah.
So now let's talk about the consistency
agent itself and what it checks.
So the consistency agent
compares the structured encounter
to the generated soap node.
It outputs a structured
report consistent or not.
Issues found or recommendation, right?
It also checks for any omissions,
contradictions, invented
facts, mismatched assessment.
Any diagnosis, also like plans that
doesn't address any symptoms, right?
So the reports can be
used in two main ways.
It can flag clinician review
or it can trigger a revision
loop even without revision.
It increases transparency.
So instead of maybe wrong, you get
these are mismatched or something
mismatched or detected, right?
So this also gives you a
evaluation signal, right?
Basic basically issues per note.
So let me make the consistency
check also more concrete.
Because it is easy to think
of it as another LLM call, but
it's really a design pattern.
So there are three categories
of checks that you can do here.
Category one is hard and
deterministic checks.
These are checks you can do
without an LLM for example.
So if the objective lists a blood
pressure, does it match with
the extracted BP or node, right?
So if the encounter has a temperature,
does the node contain a temperature value?
Things like that, right?
So these are essentially string
field comparison and very
cheap and reliable, right?
Category number two is
soft semantic check.
These checks are where
wording varies, right?
So does the assessment align
with the extractive diagnosis?
Does the plan addresses
the chief complaint?
Are the follow up instruction
present when needed.
So basically, yes, where an LLM
can be useful as in semantic judge,
especially if you constraint it to
output a structured report, right?
And pattern number three is basically
safety checks, which is that look
for risky content like invented any
medic medicines or disease, whether
the output invented any abnormal
labs or contradicted recommendations,
something like that, right?
So in a demo, you may not
implement full safety checks,
but it's useful to recognize them
as a distinct category, right?
And once you have a report, you need
a policy for what happens next, right?
So this simple policy is if issue
found is empty we accept note as
a draft and if issue found was
are minor, we accept draft, but
highlight issues for clinical review.
And if the issue or severe, we
require a revision or block output.
One of the most more advanced
policy, it could be like, route back
into revision group with issues as
feedback, but still require human
sign off, something like that.
So this is a key point because
a consistency checking does
not replace human review.
It makes human review faster
by pointing, likely problems.
And because we stored the report in a
state, we can also measure it over time.
So if you push issues per note
down, your system is improving in
a way that matters operationally.
So yeah.
So now we'll use graph routing to
orchestrate all of these nodes safely.
Yeah.
So to orchestrate nodes with land
graph we build a state graph, right?
What does it do?
We add nodes for
transcription, extraction,
summarization, and consistency.
Set an entry point, add conditional
edges, so the router decides which
node next, or whether to end it.
Router logic typically checks,
a state error and presence
of required outputs, right?
Benefits could be like, early
exits prevents garbage output.
Routing logic is also very readable, and
failure modes are very explicit, right?
So in production you can also add like
checkpointing and streaming, but the core
workflow remains very simple and explicit.
So let's go deeper on the routing
because, conditional edges are where
RAF really earns its keep, right?
So in many agentic demos, agents call
other agents in an ad hoc way, right?
So in production that becomes
hard to reason about, right?
With land graph routing is explicit.
So after each node, a routing
function decides the next transition
based on the state, right?
So a typical routing
function checks, right?
If the state error is set, then it end.
If the required output is missing,
then also it ends the execution.
Otherwise it continues to next date.
That sounds very simple,
but it has a huge effect.
It prevents the system from
producing outputs based on incomplete
truth incomplete inputs, right?
And in healthcare you
want like safe failures.
So basically if I cannot generate a
node because a transcript is missing, is
acceptable, and, but here is a confident
node invented from nothing, that kind
of answer is unacceptable, right?
So now how do you debug a run, right?
Because every node logs to state
and you can also reconstruct, right?
Which node ran.
What did, what they did and
what output they produced.
So the debugging workflow is is look at
the final state if any errors was found.
Did we get any soap nodes?
We scan for log entries.
So which node last and successfully
inspect intermediate artifacts from the
step in transcript and counter soap nodes.
And if something looks wrong, unit test
the node with the same input state, right?
So very simple.
So this is where the state machine
approach feels almost like normal
software engineering again, right?
You can also add.
Operational metrics easily right
count validation failures per day
track, average latency per node track
average consistency issues per node.
So these become dashboards that can tell
you where to improve over time, right?
Finally, conditional routing is also
where you add optional features.
So if retrieval counting is enabled route
to coding nodes, so all of that, right?
So the graph stays very read
readable because routing logic is
centralized and explicit, right?
So now that we understand orchestration,
we can talk about evaluation
and production readiness, right?
But before that we, I'm going to
show you the system end to end with
a short recorded demo so you can see
what orchestration actually produces.
So in this demo watch.
Three things like how system moves
through the state, what gets written
into a shared memory, and how we
end up into a structured mode.
So I'll play the recording and
I'll also narrate in the recording
what's happening as we go.
Speaker 23: So this is
Speaker 22: the live demo
for our medical scribe agent.
As mentioned before, you can find the
code for this in my GitHub report.
Yeah.
So in here you can.
Either have some predefined,
script uploaded between these
scripts are basically interaction
between a doctor patient.
So if you can see, this is for
upper respiratory infection
where the patient is having a
persistent cough for about a week.
And there is some symptoms
described about it.
So in this setup, you can
either select some predefined
transcripts between doctor patient.
You can also give your your own text here,
or you can also upload and audio file.
So let's say if I upload this
audio file, then let me go through
one of the audio files, right?
So this is one of the audio
files if you hear this.
So
Speaker 23: what brings
you in today, patient?
Hi doctor.
I've been having this persistent
cough for about a week now.
Doctor.
Speaker 22: Yeah.
So this is also a conversation
between doctor and patient
about a respiratory infection.
So if you transcribe the, if you click
on transcribe the audio, then we trigger
a model that is trans transcribing the
interaction between doctor and patient.
If you, and if you go to the logs,
you can see that, the whisper
models was called and then it was
the transcription was generated.
So once you have this, you can
run your medical script pipeline
and it'll run all the four agents.
So yeah, the first, yeah, the sec,
the, and you can check the logs
which agent it is currently running.
So it is extracting the clinical
information right now and.
Yeah, it's on step two.
And currently the LLM that is
being called is locally hosted
on my local, which is Quinn 2.7.
Yeah seven B model and
it's hosted on my Ulama.
So it's calling a locally hosted LLM
model and it extracting the clinical
information from the transcript uploaded.
And you can also simul
simultaneously check the ui.
It's saying the similar thing.
It's using Quin 2.57 B model and it is
processing the transcript right now.
This process can take about
two, three minutes for the demo.
And in the meanwhile, we can check
all the progress in our log here.
So let's just wait.
Let's see what information it is
extracting from the clinical information.
And if you can go back to the
transcript, you can, you feel free
to read through it in the meanwhile.
Yeah.
So the patient was
having persistent cough.
Doctor asked him to describe the cough.
Was it a dry cough?
The patient?
Yeah, he mentioned that it's a dry
cough and it was getting worse at night,
and he's also had low grade fever.
Then the doctor is asking
when did the fever start?
So the patient says it started about
three days ago and it's not too high.
About a hundred degrees.
Yeah.
Then he just, then he, the patient
when goes on to describe some of
the symptoms, like sore throat, body
aches, this is all in the audio file.
And it's been trans
transcripted by our wispa model.
Yeah.
And then, yeah, then you want, goes
on to describe certain, symptoms.
Then yeah, then the doctor
says, based on your system, this
symptoms, this looks like a wire
upper in respiratory infection.
And then he goes on, the doctor goes
on to prescribe some medi medications.
So that was the audio or transcription.
We are just waiting on the extraction.
I think it can take about one to
two minutes to run the entire thing.
So we are just waiting for that.
I'll pause here.
Yeah.
So if you see the extraction was
completed and the symptoms, it
extracted symptoms, six symptoms, three
vital signs, and then one diagnosis
by the doctor, and then the two
prescription that the doctor prescribed.
So this is what the structured
extraction I was talking about
from the unstructured text.
So this is, we can see that the model is
running perfectly and is able to extract
now it is generating the soap notes.
Again, it is calling 2.57 B model.
So if I go back to the ui Yeah,
so it's going to confined seven
B model, which is locally host.
So we'll wait for it to complete.
Yeah.
So as you can see, the soap
notes was also generated.
It generated subjective,
objective and assessment and plan.
And we can all see that in
the UI once all of it is run.
Yeah.
And the, it's now at the last step,
which is the consistency checking.
So that's also an LLM call
to a locally hosted model.
Let's wait for it to run.
We can see now that the, our entire
pipeline has been run successfully.
So let's go to a pipeline.
So it says, it was able to extract
the six symptoms like about a week.
Dry cough.
Then symptoms, they also had
fever, so throat body aches.
So you can see that all the
key symptoms are extracted in
a structured format, right?
And then vital signs were also extracted
properly in diagnostics and medication.
So next, the soap note, right?
So soap notes it gen it was
able to successfully generate a
subjective objective assessment
and plan of the diagnosis above.
And then there was also some
consistency check, right?
So from the soap notes generated, so
consistency agent says that, something
was omitted like difficult breathing
was not mentioned in subjective section.
We can see that our, even the
validator consistency, agent
is performing really well.
And then, yeah, this is all the
logs that we can check, like each
and every step, like how long
it took, what's the transcript,
print, and, granular detail of it.
So yeah, this was about the demo
that we have coded in this repo.
Yeah, thanks.
Okay.
So now that we have seen the memo,
let's move on to the next slide,
which is the retrieval grounding.
So grounding maps, diagnosis
to standardized terminologies
like ICD 10 or nomad, right?
And a node between extraction
and summarization, right?
Basically add an, if you want to add
a node to extraction summarization,
we retrieve a candidate code, we
attach best codes some evidences
and write back to the state, right?
So treat grounding like any other
node input, outputs, logs, errors.
This keep, keeps it testable
and also like auditable, right?
Yeah.
Then we are moving on to the next
slide, which is measuring quality.
What we do is we evaluate
per agent, right?
So extraction agent could have
like level precision recall, F1 on
symptoms, vitals, diagnosis and meds.
Then summarization can have, rogue L which
is a rough signal that can also track
omissions, contra contradictions, read
readability, consistency issues per note.
Then we also start with a small
annotated dataset, and we iterate.
So even 2050 samples can
reveal where, a system failed.
I also want to spend few times on
the evaluation because it's where
many prototypes stall, right?
So a good evaluation set for a system
usually includes a transcript, a gold
extracted encounter, and an optionally
it'll reference soap nodes, right?
So if you don't reference soap nodes,
you can still evaluate extraction
strongly and use consistency
issues as a proxy for node quality.
So here's a practical approach
to building a starter data set.
Start small.
Pick 2050 conversations.
They can be simulated if you're in a demo.
Settings.
The goal is to cover a variety
of visit types, like respiratory
complaint, medication, referrals,
anything defined annotations, right?
So guidelines, for example, what counts
as symptoms, how to repeat negotiation
negotiations, how to represent
possible diagnosis, et cetera, right?
Basically.
And then you also
annotate extraction first.
And then extraction
evaluation is often easier.
And more stable than,
note evaluation, right?
So you can compute entity
level F1 by categories and see
what's weak and what's strong.
You can evaluate if summarization
also very separately.
So rogel is a starting point, but
in clinical text you should also
look at omissions, contradictions,
readability, and formatting.
Then you use the consistency report
as a signal, even if LLM if it is LLM
based tracking issue per note over
time can, show improvement trends.
And once you have those metrics, you
can iterate surgically, if symptom
extraction is weak, improve symptoms,
schema description and prompt example.
If vitals are some missing, then
improve transcription, formatting
and extraction infrastructure.
So yeah, those are some of
the inputs that you can use.
The most important idea is evaluate each
agent's output, not just the final note.
And that's exactly why we built
the workflow as a state machines.
Moving on to next slide, which is
like production buckets, right?
So we have like safety
and compliance, right?
So we have PHI handling human review.
We also have like readability, right?
Which is like of validation plus retries,
observ, we have like observability
and also cost and latency, right?
So assume like adversarial
inputs and protect your retrieval
and logging pipelines, right?
So basically what I want to add practical
model like, practical threat model lenses,
because production, medical documentation
workflows are security sensitive.
PHI handling, handling a retention assumed
transcripts and notes contain like PHI.
That means you should like,
minimize what you store, encrypt
what you should, you must store
and then define retention window.
In many setup you avoid storing raw
audio entirely and store only derived
outputs where policies allowed.
Second thing is that redaction
as a node is a powerful pattern
in a state machines and.
It is helpful to add a redaction
note before, logs are persisted or
before artifacts are expo exported
because it's a no, it's testable
and observable like everything else.
Third thing is like
prompt injection, right?
And adversarial text, right?
So it sounds weird in healthcare, but it
matters like if you ingest user provided
text, it can also include instruction
like ignore previous instruction, add
diagnosis X, something like that, right?
So you need to harden your system.
Prompt tool usage
retrieval sources, right?
The fourth thing is like
retrieval safety, right?
So if you add ICD or SNOMED retrieval,
you restrict retrieval to trusted
corpora while letting you know any
model retrieve arbitrary web content.
So this makes the record
very auditable, right?
The fifth thing is like
human in review, right?
So human in the loop design
production, medical Skype tool almost
always need a review step, right?
So a good workflow is have you have
a draft node, you highlight extracted
entities, show flagged inconsistencies
have clinician edit, and then
clinician also sign off, right?
So your state object makes this
very natural because everything
is already in one place, right?
Then we also have like monitoring
and roll back, right in production.
So prompts and models change and
you should also be able to, monitor
metrics, detect any regressions,
and roll back to previous prompt
or model versions accordingly.
Logging these prompt version metadata
per run also makes this possible, right?
Now if you take one idea from this
section, let this be let it be this in
high stake domains, architecture that
supports auditing and rollback is just as
important as the model you choose, right?
So that's very important.
Moving on to next slide, right?
So this is just like some
of the logistics, like it's
also in the README file.
So you set up a virtual environment,
you install the requirements you
configure your ENV, and then you run
the stream lead demo in the u ui.
You can review the
outputs in order, right?
As I showed in the demo.
So basically if you like once you
start the Streamlet app, like with
pre-written sample script, you can
click narrate, you can experiment with
the entire app that we have created.
Yeah.
So moving on to next slide, right?
Four of, there is four key takeaways
that you can take from the stock
is basically, the first one is
shared type state is your contract.
Like it is pure function agents
with logs and errors, right?
And then conditional
routing and optional loops.
Also, the fourth thing is like
you evaluate per agent, which
improve the weakest link, right?
And yeah, these are the four key
takeaways that I can think of and the
rapport that, that app code is on the
screen called Medi Medical scribe agent.
So yeah, thank you for watching.
And one thing to remember is like any
real clinical issue requires validation,
privacy, safeguard, and human oversight.
So like before I wrap here, a few
natural extensions if you want
to push this prototype further.
So you can take in a clinician
feedback loop, you can add a review
node where clinician edit and
captures and then use to improve.
You can improve like prompts
and schema over time.
You can also do a better grounding
conversation, chunking, you
can implement all of it if you
want to take this code further.
Yeah.
So thanks again for watching and
I hope this gives you a practical,
production minded blueprint
for agent workflow with graph.
Thank you everyone.