Speaker 18: Hello everybody.
My name is Paulo Hallar.
I play role as a technical architect
in Cognizant Technology Solution.
Today I'm going to discuss about a topic
of transforming inventory forecasting
with Russian machine language.
So this is the topic.
So this is all about the predicted
demand, automatized actions.
So it is all about the data, machine
learning language and vision.
This topic complies of.
So how we'll transform the inventory
forecasting with based of the applying
machine learning language to predictive
model, supply model, and optimize the
process, transform the inventory process.
This is all level.
I'm going to discuss the next slides.
One by you one.
So there are three component,
like basic component, that machine
learning, the data itself on which the
machine learning is going to apply.
And based on the apply, the
output is the decision which
leads to the automated execution.
Now I'm going to the next slide.
So in today's story, what we'll tell
why inventory forecasting fails.
Inventory forecasting mean it is
declared for all organization, all
organization and all big companies
where they need to keep inventory in
different warehouse for different purpose.
They use that inventory.
Like for the tering, they use
the inventory in the kitchen
for nail polish upon system.
They use the chemicals store
in the as a inventory in the.
Warehouse and then use E to make that
particular nail polish kind of thing
and different kind of contrasting.
So these all things is needed.
So inventory forecasting plays a
major role in different industry.
So what today I'm going to
discuss and utilize, so how we can
optimize the inventory forecasting
using machine learning language.
So the second second point I'm going to
discuss about the reference architecture,
how data-driven ion has been taken by
using machine learning language, then
the production machine learning life
cycle, the business impact and key
takeaway from the optimization process.
Okay, in today's date, inventory
planning phase, a volatile environment
of the demand sensitivity, there are.
Different kind of barrier in the supply
chain process, which may cause a supply
chain process, destruction and disruption.
As a result, the manual spread driven
process we have to apply, and this
also lead to the delay, the decision
leading to stockout and excess
inventory and operational list.
This volatile demand and supply disruption
manual planning delays and different
kind of lack of, so this is happening
due to lack of predictive intelligence,
no foresight to adjust the changes this
gap we are trying to implement here.
So in this topic, we'll discuss
about the, how we can implement
the predictive intelligence to
optimize the inventory planning.
The next one is why forecasting fails.
As I told, different kind of
barriers, different kind of errors
and different kind of approval
process, different kind of rules
regulation, different kind of audit.
There are thousands number of
reason why the forecast got failed.
For an example, like
there is statics rules.
There is.
OID data.
There is no feedback loop.
There is lots of this.
I only mentioned three, as I told, there
is thousands of barrier and thousands of
blockage, which cause the forecast fail.
So using the machine learning intelligence
and intelligence decision, we are going
to try to overcome those barriers to
make the forecast accurate and perfect,
and optimize the inventory process.
In the next slide, I am trying to describe
the target architecture, how we'll build
the target architecture of the system, how
it'll mitigate the traditional inventory
management to make it more effective and
time less time consuming, and it became
the optimized in nature of, in terms of
cost, in terms of labor, in terms of.
Automation in terms of every
time it'll get optimized.
So there are, this is that basic
architecture of the system, like
data feature model, and decisions.
So the data came from the unified
data pipeline will harmonize the
data and make the result data
source as a unified data pipelines.
Then the.
It comes as a signal.
High value predictive signals in the
model Azure native VML model apply.
On top of that, then we are taking
the automated action flow based on the
result we get by applying the machine
learning language, machine learning
algorithm to those model on top of
the data, and then take, generate
the vision based on the output.
The next slide, I provided the
data ingestion layer, how the
data ingestion layer occurred.
If you see in that different kind of
normalization, harmonization data is
there, ERP, po os IOT, these are the
data sources which ingest the data.
Data in inventory process.
The inventory process in the oil house,
there is different kind of warehouse.
There is inbound.
Warehouse, there might
be outbound warehouse.
There are different kind of warehouse.
So in those warehouse, all
the data has been collected
from different kind of system.
All those warehouse do not
have the same kind of system.
Like one warehouse might have ERP system,
another warehouse might have IOT system.
So the data lake that all the
data come ingest inside there
and come to the data lake.
Which build on top of the Azure platform,
Azure Data Factory Pipeline comes
all the data, lake Gen two storage.
We store all the data, harmonize the data.
If you see the data quality and
government, this is all the data quality,
which is the data cleansing process.
Like you clean, you verifying the
email id, you are cleaning the address
space, you are cleaning, the other
catalog objects, this kind of thing.
Validation data, quality validation,
data cleansing, taking process.
Also data.
Governments also take process
live by schema validation.
Linear edge and catalog, which I was
telling earlier, and then provide the
secured access control to the secure
person, to the specified person who having
assigned the role to access the data.
The next one is the feature
engineering, which sessionize
the signal and optimize the disc.
Optimize the disk for, given the failure
and the inventory management short and
lack of data, lack of inventory to the
warehouse, it reduce the risk of that.
Also, it reduce the, maximum overall
capacity and overall what targeted,
which material has been ordered overly
that it also reduce the risk for that.
So this is all about.
That particular description of that
particular feature engineering,
which a major part of the.
Processes.
So in this slide I described all
the detailed feature of the feature
engineering, which defines to lack
feature, define sessional signal.
So these kind of things.
This is, I'm providing an example,
so like lack feature session signal.
Then in this feature will provide
promotion and weather signal.
This is a kind of example I provided her.
So this incorporated promotion
and the kind of thing.
And then we are getting
the accurate result.
My mission is to.
Provide all the detail by using an
example how what is feature engineering
and why we will use feature engineering.
In the next slide, I tried to describe the
model validation, complies of different
kind of steps along which, which is a
back testing, evaluate accuracy, metrics,
everybody using different kind of.
Procedure, like M-A-E-M-A-C
mean standard evaluation.
Then M-A-M-A-P-E, these are the different
kind of statistic method that used to
evaluate accurate metrics for that.
Back testing and different
kind of other testing.
Also identify bias and fairness.
There is different kind of, as I
tell, told blockage, different kind
of restriction, different kind of.
Approval process and other rules that
block those inventory then disturb the
supply chain process to get that inventory
into the warehouse in proper time.
So each identify all the basis biases and.
Try to identify and collect those
information to push to the next step.
Okay, so it has different kind of
object like ED, a, fairness indicator.
These are the different kind of
metrics, vising techniques, all
the other metrics are there.
So that use to collect the barriers
and try to push into the next
layer so that we can identify that.
Outliner and remove them, and then
we are try to address those bias
and all those, stoppage, blockage to
avoid the supply chain disruption.
I'm going to the next slide, which is
talking about the deployment and the
email ops, which is the CI CD four
ml of ops using the machine learning.
That is track and managing models,
register and version ML models.
These are the deployment of the.
Processes, which involve in the machine
learning implementation for them,
inventory management optimization.
After applying the machine learning
algorithm, like linear regression to a
particular model, to a, based on the input
data, then what we need to do, we need
to maintain the metadata for auditing.
Register the Han email for deployment.
Then manual model for the deployment.
Then monitor performance
sales, these all the things.
Talking about model registry and
monitoring alerts, talking about that.
Deployment process, a deployment
in the email of now the prediction
to on how we are predicting this.
This comes in picture when we
harmonize the data, normalize the
data, and apply machine learning
agreement to algorithm dam.
This is a learning phase.
This is a model generation phase.
This is a deployment development app.
Once the model is trained properly, then
we'll do the model registry and each.
Passes to the actual data.
So we are maintaining the
data, using the historical data
with that supervised learning.
Then after either model is automated
and tuned properly, then actually
it is provided as out input to that
particular model after deployment
and module registry, and then it'll
generate automatic data, output
data and related data from the model
application after deployment to get there.
Proper inventory, what need to be ordered?
Suppose do we need 30?
So the predict tool define that.
Okay, we need 28 or 29.
This is very close to the expected order.
It'll never order 10,
which might lead to a less.
Inventories that might disrupt the
business process or some of hel
inventory like 70 that also waste
of the inventory that will log.
So that way it'll, it supposed to order
very close to the target, like 30, 20, 29.
So that's how actually after
training, it'll not the actual data.
So that's how after taking the data,
it'll order the inventory from the
third party vendor or the suppliers.
That is how the inventory process occurs.
That is the business impact for that.
If you order proper amount of
inventory and kept in the warehouse,
it'll reduce stockouts, lower
inventory costs, faster division.
It'll improve efficiency and it'll
continue help to continue the business
process, which subsequently led to.
The revenue, need revenue of the
company, of the organization like this.
I provide a healthcare scenario.
Yeah, for an example where demand
forecasting for supplier capacity
planning, they do capacity planning
and proactive replenishment, so do
that, how they improve cap efficiency.
And then in the capacity planning,
if you see there are sub steps where
they used to implement, prepare
for the high demand, then allocate
resource efficiently, then find the
proactive replenishment what they do.
They maintain the educate
inventory and reduce this shortage.
These all the steps, they applied.
The one way there, the data layer.
After the data layer, harmonization
of the data prepar preparation
layer, they applied to the next step.
The data where the applied, the email
algorithms applied to get the actual.
Output by learning those model
one by one to get accuracy.
And finally, the model is registered to a
deployment environment where it connect to
the application and produced proper output
supply chain scenario where again, I am
promoting another scenario where logistic
optimization done disruption prediction,
risk cover planning has been done.
The main, basic objective.
Is to show you how different
kind of optimization applied in
different business case and different
industry and different domain.
Here in the logistic optimization,
they adapt this adapt routine advance.
This is a kind of business scenario.
So in the sub scenario, they
applied some machine learning
and algorithm and generate some.
Data by after deploying those models
and this data flows to the next
table, like optimized shipping costs.
These are one, substep is
dependent on another, and it'll
lead to different optimization.
Subsequently sought purchases.
Finally list to a total optimized
way, material optimization,
to say target optimization.
Leading to resilience.
If you see in that risk cover
plan, this is another main process
where the optimization has been
acquired using machine learning.
AP applied in that model for
the inventory optimization.
That what we can say in here like
this kind of optimization, using
machine learning and supervising,
we can minimize the risk of, waste
of the inventory as well as we can
also ensure that our business will
learn in proper way and proper time.
It'll not stop.
Due to the lack of the inventory
in our system, it'll also
optimize the supply chain process.
It'll remove all the disruption from
the main processes, subprocesses and
different kind of approval processes rule.
It'll take care of the rule automatically
where manual intervention is not required.
That's how you can be very sure that,
okay, your business is running very
successfully using this optimization
where it'll finally lead to the
revenue for the organization.
So this is all about my pre topic over
here, inventory management optimization
using machine learning language.
Thank you.
I.