Hello everyone.
My name is Alman ti and I am a senior
database administrator at Tech Axel.
Over the years, I have had the
opportunity to work with numerous
financial clients, helping them
streamline their database environments
to achieve optimal performance.
Today I am excited to.
Present on a topic that is crucial to
modern enterprise landscape leveraging
AI powered predictive analytics to
optimize enterprise database performance.
As many of enterprise databases are the
backbone of critical business operations.
However, they often face performance
bottlenecks that can significantly affect
business continuity and user experience.
These issues can lead to downtime,
slow query responses, and
ultimately lost opportunities.
In this presentation, I will introduce
an AI powered framework for predictive
analytics that is designed to tackle
these challenges by utilizing.
Historical pattern analysis and
reinforcement learning techniques.
This framework can predict performance
issues before they occur and provide
real time optimization recommendations.
One of the most powerful aspects
of this framework is its ability to
automate routine tasks such as query
indexing and performance monitoring.
This automation allows DBS to
focus on more strategic decisions.
While the AI system handles
RIP two optimization work.
Ultimately, the collaborative potential
between human expertise and artificial
intelligence is what sets this framework
apart by combining the sense of both.
We can maintain optimal database
performance in the face of increasingly
dynamic enterprise environments.
Let's dive into how this AI powered
solution can transform the way we approach
database performance optimization,
the challenge of enterprise
database performance.
Let's see about the
complexity of the database.
As enterprises continue to scale,
the complexity of their database
environments grows exponentially.
Enterprise databases are no
longer just a collection of tables
and rows in a single database.
Today's databases handle vast
amounts of data that span across
multiple systems and geographical
locations supporting a wide array of.
Business operations.
This includes everything from transaction
processing and data analytics to
customer relationship management
and enterprise resource planning.
The architecture has become more
distributed and multifaceted.
In many cases, organizations rely on
a combination of relational databases
like MySQL and Oracle alongside NoSQL
databases such as MongoDB or Cassandra.
To handle specific use cases.
Additionally, many enterprises are
transitioning to cloud-based solutions.
Integrating platforms like AWS
Azure and Google Cloud for better
scalability and efficiency.
However, this diverse ecosystem
introduces significant challenges
in managing performance.
The different types of databases,
relational, NoSQL, and cloud databases
have varying characteristics, including
different query optimizers, indexing
methods, and storage architectures.
This heterogene genetically makes
it difficult to apply uniform
performance management practices
across the entire environment.
Managing these multiple
layers of databases often.
With thousands or even millions of
transactions per second requires not
just expertise, but a more sophisticated
approach than traditional methods offer.
These systems must support concurrent
taxes by thousands of users,
handle high velocity transactions,
and ensure real time analytics.
All of this must occur while
maintaining high availability,
security, and scalability.
In addition to the technology
complexity, the business
demands are constantly shifting.
Enterprises are increasingly adopting.
Digital transformation strategies such
as e-commerce platforms, IOT systems, and
big data analytics, which generate new
types of data at an unprecedented rate.
This requires the database infrastructure
to not only scale in size, but also.
To adapt in real time to dynamic
workloads, the need for seamless
integration across these systems becomes
even more important, ensuring that data
flows efficiently across departments,
regions, and even cloud providers.
Therefore, managing these complex systems
requires more than just knowing how
to tune individual database systems.
It demands a holistic, agile approach
that can manage diverse technologies
across multiple layers, keeping
all systems running efficiently and
ensuring that performance bottlenecks
don't disrupt business operations.
Limitations of traditional approaches.
Now let's talk about how traditional
database performance management.
Approaches have struggled to keep
pace with this increasing complexity.
Historically, database administrators
have relied on manual reactive
methods to address performance issues.
Traditional performance
tuning was typically reactive.
Problems were identified
only after they had.
Already impacted the system.
This often meant dealing with performance
degradation, slow queries, or outages
only after the damage was already done.
For example, when query performance
begins to degrade, DBS might manually step
through a diagnostic process, checking
execution plans, running performance
tests, and tweaking settings in an
attempt to identify the root cause.
However.
This process can be time consuming
and error prone, especially when
working with complex systems
that span multiple environments.
What might have seemed like a minor issue
can escalate, impacting everything from
transaction processing to user experience.
The consequences of this reactive
approach are far reaching
downtime becomes inevitable.
Systems may go offline during
troubleshooting, especially
when significant changes are
made to configurations in an
attempt to resolve issues.
Productivity laws is common, particularly
when users experience slow database
response times or application downtime.
Affecting operations such as
order processing, customer
support, and inventory management.
Customer dissatisfaction can result
when critical systems such as e-commerce
platforms like Amazon experience delays
or outages during peak traffic periods.
In summary.
Traditional database performance
management approaches are ill-equipped
to handle the complexity and scale
of modern enterprise environments.
They can only respond to issues after
they have already impacted the business,
leaving organizations in a perpetual
state of crisis management rather than
proactive performance optimization,
traditional database management phases.
Several inherent limitations
that contribute to performance
issues and inefficiencies.
One of the most significant challenges
is related to configuration issues.
20 per 27% of service disruptions
are cost by misconfigurations,
and 16% of system downtime can be
attributed to errors in configuration.
These problems arise because
the DBS rely on static.
Predefined configurations that fail
for adapt to dynamic business needs.
Traditional database management
places a substantial burden on DBS.
On average, 25% of DBS time is
spent on performance tuning,
but what's concerning is that.
About 67% of that time is spent on
manual trial and error approaches.
This trial and error process is time
consuming, inefficient, and often leads
to suboptimal outcomes, especially as
database environments grow more complex.
Another major limitation
is static configuration.
In many enterprise environments, 87%
of database configuration parameters
remain unchanged, even though workloads
fluctuate due to business cycles,
seasonability and other factors.
This inflexibility means that databases
are either over provision leading to
unnecessary costs or under provision.
Resulting in performance
bottlenecks during peak periods.
Traditional approaches simply do
not account for the ever-changing
nature of enterprise operations,
leaving the system vulnerable to
inefficiencies and disruptions.
In summary, the traditional methods
of database management are react to
manual and rigid, which makes them ill
suited for today's rapidly evolving
and data intensive environments.
Now let's talk about a framework for
AI powered database optimization.
At the core of this AI powered
optimization system is a layered
architecture that is designed to
tackle the complexity of modern
enterprise database environments.
The framework is structured to
include distinct layers, software,
data collection, analysis, decision
making, and implementation by
creating abstraction layers.
This architecture ensures seamless
integration with diverse systems,
including relational databases, no
SQL systems and cloud platforms.
This modular design allows the
system to scale efficiently and adapt
to evolving business deals needs,
making it suitable for heterogeneous
environments and complex workloads.
Historical.
Let's talk about historical
pattern analysis.
The framework builds comprehensive
knowledge basis for historical
performance data, such as query
execution, statistics, resource
utilization metrics, and system logs.
This historical analysis allows the system
to recognize recurring patterns providing.
A solid foundation for
identifying potential performance
issues before they occur.
By leveraging this data, the framework
enables proactive optimization,
tailored to the database needs.
So reinforcement learning models at
the heart of the system is adapt to
intelligence driven by reinforcement
learning this model continuously
learn from past experiences and
refine the predictions as new data
comes in this self-improvement.
Ensures that as the system encounters new
patterns or shifts in workload, it becomes
increasingly accurate in its ability to
suggest effective optimizations over time.
The realtime recommendations
framework generates.
Actionable optimization suggestions
in real time, allowing database
administrators to implement
changes quickly and effectively.
These recommendations span areas such
as query indexing, memory distribution,
and resource allocation, ensuring
that performance is continually
optimized without requiring manual
trial and error adjustments.
In conclusion, the AI powered framework
provides a dynamic and flexible.
Solution for enterprise database
optimization using machine learning and
reinforcement learning to continuously
monitor, analyze, and optimize
database performance in real time.
So now let's say the performance
improvements for AI power techniques.
So this graph highlights the significant
performance improvements that AI
powered techniques specifically
reinforcement learning can bring
to the database optimization.
One of the most notable benefits
is query latency reduction, where
reinforcement learning approaches
can reduce latency by up to 70 to 80%
compared to traditional query optimizers.
This improvement happens
quickly with training.
Times as short as 10 to 30 minutes
for moderately complex database
schemas, making it highly efficient.
Additionally, index tuning
and complex query performance
benefit from AI techniques.
Traditional optimizers can typically
handle join order optimization for
queries involving 10 to 15 tables, but
AI models can manage up to 50 tables.
Far beyond the capabilities of
traditional methods, AI also excels
in resource utilization and anomaly
detection, proactively identifying
the issues that would otherwise go
unnoticed until they impact performance.
This highlights the powerful
potential of AI to improve database
performance across multiple
dimensions leading to more efficient,
scalable, and responsive systems.
Let's say the synergy of
human and AI collaboration.
So
we can highlight how AI and the
human expertise complement each
other in database optimization.
So let's talk about AI trends.
Ai, Excel set processing vast amounts
of performance data, identifying subtle.
Patterns and continuously
monitoring hundreds of metrics.
It automate tasks like index management
and resource optimization, and detects
anos up to 47 minutes before traditional
alerts, ensuring proactive intervention.
On the other side, humans bring strategic
decision making with business context,
handle complex value optimization
and plan for long-term scalability.
They ensure that optimizations align with
business requirements and manage risk
assessments for implementation together.
AI handles.
The heavy lifting of optimization,
while human expertise ensures that all
actions align with broader business
goals, creating a powerful collaboration
for sustained database performance,
so creating effective human AI
partnership, now we can emphasize
the collaborative model between AI
systems and database administrators,
where both contribute the sense
to optimize database performance.
So the AI gen identifies patterns and
optimization opportunities in performance
data proactively suggesting improvements.
On the other hand, DBS evaluated these
AI generated recommendations considering
the business context to ensure.
The changes align with
organizational goals.
The impact of the recommended
optimizations is measured against
predictions to verify effectiveness.
Once the changes are approved, they are
deployed with the necessary safeguards
to identify any negative impacts.
Organizations that adopt this AI augmented
approach experience a 34% increase
in strategic projects completed by
DBS alongside a 47% reduction in time
spent on routine maintenance tasks.
This partnership allows both AI and human
expertise to evolve together continuously
improving database management practices.
So now let's take one of the case
studies in e-commerce platform.
This presents a real time case
study of optimizing an e-commerce
platform during peak shopping periods.
Let's talk about the problem.
The platform faced significant
performance degradation during high
traffic periods with query latencies
increasing three to five times, and
critical workflows like checkout,
exceeding ten second response times.
Severely affecting user experience
and business operations.
The AI framework was deployed alongside
existing systems, analyzing three months
of historical data to establish baseline
performance and identify recurring bot
limits during high traffic periods.
So the analysis of the
system found that just.
0.03% of distinct queries were responsible
for over 70% of the database load
during peak periods, providing clear
targets for optimization, and the
result after six months, the platforms
saw a 40% reduction in resource
over provisioning, 28% decrease in
average query latency and successful.
Successfully my mitigated 17
potential bottlenecks before they
could impact customers resulting in
improved performance and a better user
experience during high demand periods.
So the e-commerce platform
performance improvement.
So overall we have seen.
The improvements in EE E-commerce
platform performance after implementing
the AI powered optimization framework,
40% of resource optimization, the AI
framework reduce over provisioning of
resources, ensuring efficient use of
infrastructure, while maintaining optimal
performance during demand spikes, such as
during sales events or holiday seasons.
And the 28%.
Savings in query latency by optimizing
the database, the system achieved
at 28% decrease in average query
response time during peak periods,
significantly improving the user
experience by reducing delays.
45% improvement in
critical queries critical.
Workflows like checkout
and payment processing.
So a 45% improvement in performance,
ensuring smoother transactions and a
better customer experience during high
traffic times 60, 62% of DBA time saved.
With Routine Maintenance Task,
automated DBS saved 45 hours
per week, allowing them to bring
overall productivity and efficiency
in the database management team.
These improvements demonstrate how
air driven optimization can lead to
both technical gains and operational
efficiencies for enterprises.
The technical implementation
details for this slide presents.
The multilayered architecture of
the AI powered database optimization
framework, which is designed to
manage database performance efficiency
across enterprise environments.
Now, let's talk about the implementation
layer at the top of the stack, the
implementation layer ensures, sorry.
At the bottom of the stack is the
implementation layer that ensures that
approved optimization recommendations are.
Deployed in a controlled manner
with necessary safeguards in
place for low risk optimizations.
Changes are applied automatically
while more complex changes are
reviewed and implemented with human
oversight, ensuring system stability.
And next comes the optimization engine.
The optimization engine generates targeted
improvement recommendations based on
insights gathered from the analysis.
It suggests precise actions such as index
tuning and resource allocation adjustments
to address performance bottlenecks, and
the analysis engine works by analyzing
the data collected in the first layer.
It identifies patterns in database
performance and predicts potential issues.
This analysis enables the system to
proactively address problems before they
affect performance data collection layer.
The foundation of this, the top
most layer is the data collection
layer, and this layer, which gathers
comprehensive telemetry from the database.
This includes.
Query execution, statistics, resource
usage, and system logs, ensuring that
the system has accurate up-to-date
data to make informed decisions.
This multi-layered approach allows
the system to efficiency, efficiently
optimized database performance, adapting
to diverse environments, while maintaining
seamless integration across components
for consistent performance improvement.
And the future directions of this AI
powered database optimization framework
is cross-platform optimization.
The framework aims to expand beyond
traditional single platform environments.
The goal is to optimize across
heterogeneous database systems.
For example, relational NoSQL
and cloud by developing unified.
Performance models.
The system will be able to identify
optimization opportunities that span
multiple technologies while allowing
seamless integration and performance
improvement across diverse platforms.
The explainable AI component is
to increase trust standard option.
The framework will
focus on explainable ai.
It'll.
Provide clear rationals for every
optimization recommendation.
Enabling database administrators to
understand not just what optimizations
are recommended, but also why they're
expecting to expect to improve
performance, ensuring transparency
and better decision making.
And the natural language interfaces,
the framework will incorporate
a natural language interface
allowing DBS to interact with the
system using conventional queries.
This makes the system more user
friendly, enabling administrators
to express performance concerns, set
optimization goals, and ask questions
in familiar non-technical language.
Eliminating the need for specialized
syntax workload specific learning models.
The future of the framework includes
developing specialized learning models
tailored to different types of workloads.
This includes optimizing for transaction
processing, analytical reporting,
and even iot data management.
By customizing optimizations for
specific workload types, the framework
will be able to deliver more targeted
and effective performance improvements.
These advancements will ensure that
the framework continues to evolve,
adapting to new technologies, and
providing even more powerful optimization
strategies for diverse enterprise needs.
And in conclusion, as database.
Environments continue
to grow in complexity.
The synergy between human expertise
and AI driven optimization will be
key to ensuring that enterprises
can maintain peak performance,
scalability, and elig agility,
ultimately driving business success
in an increasingly data driven world.
I look forward to any questions you may
have, and thank you for your time today.