Hello everyone.
Myself, Ji.
I have more than 14 years of
experience in CRM systems.
Today we are going to discuss about the
A power CM policy and how it is impacting
between the innovation and surveillance.
This presentation explains how a
driven CRM system transform community
policy while raising important
questions about the server lines and
similarities raise of a port policy.
There are three main key impacted areas,
widespread adoption, miserable impact,
community focus in widespread adoption.
A CRM system now manage millions
subsidies, interactions annually
across major metropol areas.
Miserable impact departments
report significance, improvement in
response, coordination and feedback
Collection and community focus.
Neutral C enable more targeted community
engagement and resource allocation.
Benefits of a driven system.
There are main benefits
of the A driven system.
Sentiment analysis, faster response,
performance tracking, sentiment
analysis, algorithm flag, community
detections with high accuracy,
allowing prevention accents.
This means it collects the data
from the different sources like
9 1 1 calls, case management,
citizen compliance, and retracts.
Ignore them.
Faster response.
Predictive alert systems have reduced
response time in high risk areas for
performance tracking officer engagement.
Screen courts correlated with
improved community satisfaction.
There are success cases, 24% response
time, average reduction in emergency
response times across implementation
departments, and 37% satisfaction
increase in the community satisfactory
scores where systems are transparent.
42% engagement, more citizen police
and positive interaction reported
in participating communities.
The shadow side of the algorithm bias
unfair targeting of certain communities.
Documented case shows greater algorithm
flagging in minority communities
despite similar incident rates.
The enforcement cycles are
systems that learn from historical
data, often perpetuate existing
bias in policy patterns, and
as well as limited warfare too.
Public trust concerns the data
collections, use policies and
surveillance spheres when it
comes to the data collections.
Citizens often unaware of how the personal
data is being gathered when citizens
don't understand how decisions are made.
The database collected and
how it is going to be used.
So in this case, the trash can be broken
down, uses policies, unclear boundaries
on how information affects polishing
decisions, subline fears, especially in
communities that have already exposed
reward policy, the lack of transparency
make it even harder to build trust
community, a transparency framework.
There are four core principles of
community transparency framework.
One is visibility documentation,
participation review visibility.
Public facing dashboard shows how
algorithm make recommendations,
the documentation, citizen
accessible engagement logs, track
all system guidance, interactions.
That means they should be able to
track their cases, how it was routed.
Who was resolved on what basis?
They resolved participation,
community involvement in system
design and implementation, like
hosting public workshops at town
halls, reviewing mandated third party
algorithm audit conductor quarterly.
Just like companies have independent
financial audit, a system that how affect
public should regularly fairness audits
the framework results in pilot cities.
Boston implementation Ocland
Pilot Denver Adoption.
Boston implementation Trust in
policy technology increased 40 some
percent after dashboard launches.
Citizen complaints about
technology misses dropped by 62%.
The Ocland Pilot community or site
committee review all algorithms changes
public trust metrics improve 31% first
year of the implementation, then adaption.
Quarterly town hall discussion, CM
Insights with distance due to this
engagement with the police portal
increased 83% after transparency measure
key framework conference, public
dashboards, technical documentation,
citizen review boards impact as these
are the four key components of framework.
So when it comes to public dashboard,
real time display of algorithm activity.
And impact accessible to the all
citizens technical documentation.
Simplified explanation of how
a systems make recommendation.
Citizen review board community members
participating in the quarterly algorithm
reviews, impact assessment, regular
evaluation of these system effects
and different demo group groups.
There are four ways of implementation
pathways assessment, adaption, community
engagement, continuous improvements.
When it come to the assessment, conduct
comprehensive audit of existing AI
systems and gather technical community
feedback on specific concepts.
Adaption when it comes to the adaption.
Implement technical modification to
enhance algorithm transparency and
establish clear accountability protocols.
Community engagement.
Create formal channels for
citizens Prep citizens.
Participants in the system review with the
documented feedback integration process.
Continuous implement, established
quarterly independent audit
and systematic implementation
of evidence based on defense.
There are proven stakeholders,
benefits, law enforcement,
community member, government
officials in the law enforcement.
Increasing community trust leads to
better information sharing and cooperation
officers report less stress from
community tensions, community members.
Greater understanding of how the
data is used, reduced, and it
reduces the fear of the serve lines.
Visible feedback loops show
input creates the real changes.
Government officials reduce the
tension between the police and
community measure communities.
Measurable improvement in public
satisfaction with governance,
technical recommendations, open source
components, data minimization, bias
testing, citizen control, so when it
come to the open source components.
Critical algorithms should be
open for the public review while
protecting security elements.
The data minimization collect only
necessary information with clear
retention and detention policies,
bias testing, regular testing,
edged diverse dataset to identify
that correct and algorithm biases.
Citizen control allow individual
to view and manage their data with
reasonable security constraints.
Balancing innovation rights.
A CM system offers powerful
tools for improving policy.
Their benefits must be balanced with
transparency and accountability.
The community algorithm transparency
framework provides a proven path forward.
Thank you everyone.