Hello everyone.
I'm Dineh Raja Sharan.
I'm honored to be here at Con 42 to
talk about the future of cybersecurity.
As someone deeply involved in
both academia and industry,
I've seen firsthand how the
cybersecurity landscape is evolving.
And how AI is not just a
tool, but a game changer.
Over the next 30 minutes, I will walk
you through the transformation from
reactive to predictive cybersecurity,
focusing on how AI is enabling
organizations to stay ahead of ever more
sophisticated cyber security threats.
Let's dive in.
To app appreciate the urgency
of this transformation.
Consider this, the global cost of
cyber crime is expected to reach
10.5 trillion annually by 2025.
That's up from $3 trillion
just a decade ago.
This explosion is driven by everything
from ransomware to phishing,
data theft nation state attacks.
The good news is we have tools
today that can help us fight back.
AI is one such tool.
MIT's a AI two platform,
for example, detects.
85% of attacks and a
financial firm using AI saw a
60% drop in false positives.
These are in incremental improvements.
They are breakthroughs.
So why isn't traditional
security enough anymore?
First, it's reactive.
It only kicks in once
damage is already done.
Second, the sheer volume of data
in modern networks overwhelmed
static rule-based systems.
Third, traditional systems depend on
known attack vectors or signatures.
That means if an attacker
creates a new tactic.
A zero day your defense is blank.
This is like using a map from the past
to navigate a rapidly shifting landscape.
AI allows us to move beyond
that limitation by learning from
patterns, not just pass emails.
AI changes the game by enabling real time.
Dynamic threat detection.
It starts with comprehensive
data collection.
Everything from firewall
logs to user behavior.
Then it pre-process the data cleaning
and structuring it from analysis.
Next AI models, the large language
models dive into the data.
Identifying subtle patterns or
anomalies that humans might miss.
Finally, the system provides
security teams with actionable
insights, sometimes even triggered
automated containment protocols.
The result is faster detection,
better prioritization, and
more efficient response.
And how do we go about this?
So there are three foundational
techniques at play here, anomaly
detection, pattern recognition,
and real-time threat intelligence.
Anomaly detection uses historical data.
To flag behaviors that
deviate from the norm.
Pattern recognition identifies
complex combinations of events
that may signal a threat,
and the real time threat
intelligence integrates internal
data with global threat feeds
to assess risk asset intervals.
And then they act together.
Together.
These techniques enable systems to evolve
and adapt just as quickly as attackers do.
And then let's.
Zoom into the three models, what we
discussed in the previous slides,
ly detection, pattern recognition,
real time threat intelligence.
Let's consider the example
of a supervised learning.
Supervised learning uses
labeled data sets like previous.
Phishing attacks leveraging the
previous phish phishing attacks.
You can predict similar future attacks.
On the other hand, unsupervised
models are more exploratory.
They cluster data, they find outliers.
They're perfect for spotting
new kinds of threats.
Then there's deep learning which
shines in high volume, high complexity
environments like cloud infrastructure.
These models, especially the the
nns and CNNs of the world, are
able to process logs, sensor data,
user actions in a nuanced way,
identifying threats no human code.
Normally detection is
not a one time setup.
First, it builds a baseline
of normal operations.
Who locks in when, what actions are taken.
Then in real time, it flags deviations.
For instance, if an employee
suddenly accesses an entire database
at 3:00 AM which is not a normal
pattern, the system notices.
More importantly, these AI systems evolve.
They adapt their baseline to
reflect changes in normal behavior,
minimizing false positives over time.
They get smash smarter, not just faster
click.
Let's look at three case
studies, for example.
Let's take a financial institute,
let's say a major bank integrated
AI for fraud detection, and saw not
only fewer false positives, but a 50%
increase in new fraud types detected.
An e-commerce chain uses AI
to mitigate DDoS attacks,
reducing impact by 91st, 95%.
In healthcare, AI identified subtle
patient records, access patterns
that flagged insider threats.
These stories show how AI not only
helps protect, but also optimizes
how teams operate, freeing them
to focus on critical tasks.
Speaking of the pattern recognition
from the previous slides pattern
recognition is where AI truly shines.
Attackers don't always follow the
same path, but they are often common
sequences like login anomalies
followed by privilege escalation.
AI mines historical logs to
find these attack fingerprints.
With the graph based analysis,
AI can even detect coordinated
campaigns across distributed systems.
This transforms how we investigate
threats from reactive foreign
six two proactive hunting,
the real time threat intelligence part.
AI also uses, I said, ears
across the network 24 7.
It correlates activities across endpoints
servers, cloud apps to spot risks early.
More importantly, it reacts in real time.
Some systems can isolate
infected machines.
Automatically.
But by precious time and by
sharing threat intelligence across
organizations, we are creating a
more resilient digital ecosystem.
Studies show organizations
using threat intelligence reduce
breach cost by over 2 million.
However it's not all rosy.
AI requires data.
Specifically it requires clean label data
which often could become a bottleneck.
Poor data leads to poor models,
and then there's a trust gap.
If a model flags a threat can be
explained why this black box nature
can be a compliance challenge also.
False positives still happen.
And then if frequent, and then if
frequent, they desensitize analysts,
a phenomenon known as alert fatigue,
lots of alerts lots of false positives.
Lastly, ethical concerns around
surveillance data usage must
be addressed thoughtfully.
The future though.
Looking ahead, if you see explainable
AI models that just justify their
decisions adversarial machine
learnings to defend against AI attacks,
federated learnings for privacy,
preserving analysis and analytics and
fully autonomous security systems.
So these.
Models, advances are not decades away.
They're already being tested in research
labs, in early stage developments.
Right now, there are several
startups that have been spinning
up with the same models.
So in summary,
AI isn't just the future of
cybersecurity, which is going to
happen like 10 10 years from now.
It is happening right now.
It's present.
But it's real value lies in collaboration
between humans and machines.
Between ethics and innovation.
If you build AI thoughtfully the result
will be stronger, smarter, and more
sustainable security systems that adapt
and scale without increasing without
increasing increasingly digital work.
Thank you.