Speaker 9: Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42
Mission Learning Conference.
I'm Ra Kati, and today I will
present a topic that answers a
very pertinent question within the
credit card industry and how we can
leverage one of the most trending
technologies to answer that effectively.
And the topic is maximizing credit card
profitability with mission learning
driven customer lifetime value.
Before we jump in, by way of introduction.
I'm the director for data analytics
at American Express, primarily
focusing on small business and
commercial credit card customers.
In my role, I leverage advanced analytics
and mission learning to design strategies
that drive incremental spend and lend
behaviors among customers while balancing
the customer value and experience that
we offer through the various products
and managing the business risk prudently.
In my career spanning over 15 years,
I have been with major financial
institutions like Capital One and discover
across various business units, driving
product strategies, risk and response
modeling to predict customer behaviors
and growing the business profitability
while balancing customer experience.
Today, I wish to share the knowledge and
insights that I have gained over the years
through my hands-on experience with you.
Now let's take a quick look at what's
to come First, we'll start with the
high level overview of the credit card
dynamics, along with the review of the
various challenges that are plaguing the
companies in the current environment.
We'll also introduce a concept
of customer lifetime value here.
Next, we can explore the role of
mission learning and how we can leverage
it to solve some of the challenges
that the companies are facing today.
Following this, we can review the
optimal processes to convert some
of these mission learning concepts
into optimal business solutions.
Next, we can review a few real world
applications to see what kind of a
business impact can these mission learning
solutions drive for the companies?
And then we can take it home
with a few key takeaways.
Now let's jump in.
We all know that credit card is
a very powerful tool and very
critical in our day-to-day lives.
We do not think twice before making
a purchase or a transaction with
without credit cards, but what actually
happens behind the scenes and what
happens from a company's perspective?
From a company's perspective, the
overall customer lifecycle can be broadly
divided into two distinctive phases.
The first one is acquisition.
Which ends at the point of approval
or decline of a particular customer.
And the second phase is the customer
management, which starts with the point
of approval of a particular customer
and goes all the way as long as the
customer stays with that company.
In the first phase of acquisition,
we have a lot of activities starting
with the marketing activity, which
targets a whole lot of customers.
With different marketing materials,
advertising the credit card product,
followed by the generous sign-on
bonuses that the companies give
out to attract customers when
they get approved for a card.
And then there is a whole lot of risk
strategies that evaluate whether a
customer is a good customer to be
approved by the company or a risky one.
And then there are some operational
processes which happen on the backend.
As a comp, as a customer
gets approved or declined.
As you can see in all these steps,
they are very cost intensive and they
require an upfront investment from the
company to acquire a particular customer.
This is typically called
the acquisition cost.
Then, when does a company make back money?
That is in the second phase
of customer management?
Once a customer starts using their card.
In making purchase transactions or
revolving by paying the interest
cash to the company on part of their
transaction volume, that is when the
company starts making back money.
In the second phase, the company
earns money, but also incurs some
losses in terms of some negative
behavior from the customers who do
not pay back the money that they owe
to the company, and they charge off.
So there is a potential for both making
money and losing money in the second
phase, but net, this is where the
customer lifetime value comes into effect.
The upfront investment or the cost that
they make during the acquisition phase
and the net money that they either
make or lose in the second phase is
what makes up the total customer value
over the lifetime of the customer
being a member with the company.
And next, let's see why this
customer lifetime value matters.
As you can see, the first use case
is in the acquisition economics.
This is a place where a cus a company
has to decide whether they need to
approve a customer or decline them.
The cost of approving a wrong
customer is that they probably
would result in like heavier losses.
Ultimately turning out to be
a net loss for the company
from a business perspective.
At the same time, the cost of losing
out a good customer is also pretty
heavy, that they would leave money on
the table for competition and they would
not be able to maximize the value that
they generate for the business and also
that they generate for the customer.
So as you can see, there's a very
fine balance that happens between
approving a customer and declining them.
And all this is pursuant to what value
do we attribute from a customer lifetime
value perspective to a particular segment
of customers or a particular customer,
and what decision we make at that point.
The second use case is in
the portfolio strategy.
Again, once a customer is approved by
a company, it doesn't mean that like
it's hunky and dory for everyone.
As you can see, as you can see from the
current environment, there are a lot of
changes that happen on a day-to-day basis.
Be it in the macro environment, or be
it in the co competitive actions, or be
it even in the customer's profile on how
they use their credit lines, not just with
this particular company, but with all the
other companies or like other forms of
loans that they take as things continue
to change on a very dynamic basis.
The company also has to make decisions
on a dynamic basis to make sure that
they're not overly exposed in the
case of eventful turns, or they are
not leaving money on the table by
not maximizing the customer's usage.
So again, here, as you can see, the
customer lifetime value comes into
play to make sure that the company
is making the right decision at the
right time to ensure that like they're
maximizing the value for all the players.
The third point is in the p and
l forecasting, where we quantify
the expected revenues that we can
generate from a customer versus the
potential losses that can come from
any negative behavior from the customer
perspective, and combining those two
to make an informed decision at various
points of the customer lifecycle,
and making sure that the decision
is in the right sense for both the
customer and also for the company.
Now, let's see, like where
mission learning comes into play.
Historically, customer lifetime value,
or even the individual values for each
decision, were not driven by mission
learning or by multivariate enhances.
Things were mostly two dimensional, and
the effect of one variable was typically.
Analyzed in isolation and that led to
very skewed decisions, very dependent on
a few variables, while the majority of the
other variables which could potentially
Im impact the decision were neglected.
Now, this is where the mission
learning becomes a game changer
in the decision making process.
Typically, the model.
Can analyze multivariate multiple
variables at the same time to come
up with a multivariate impact and
predict the outcome based on the
changes on simultaneous change in these
different variables at the same time.
So that's where instead of analyzing
like one particular variable in isolation
and then another variable in isolation,
the model helps combine the impact of
those two changes at the same time.
And predicting what could be the potential
outcome on the customer's behavior.
And these predictive models are very good
at taking in hundreds or thousands of
variables at the same time and deciding
on which are the top most variables and
which are the most impactful in terms
of predicting the customer behavior.
And then we can build a specific model.
To U utilize those variables.
So what are the main components within
the customer lifetime value modeling?
Can we use machine learning?
So the first one is the future spend
patterns as we were discussing.
Once a customer is approved.
The level to which they use the card is
one of the key components in deciding
on like when they, when the company
makes back money and breaks even on
that particular customer and the usage.
So as you can see, how much would
a customer potentially spend and
getting a good prediction on that will
determine how valuable the customer
is if in the at the point of approval.
For a customer who spends like heavy
amounts, that is where like we, the
company would make back a significant
amount of the overall purchase
volume in terms of the interchange
revenue, and that will help the
overall economics of the credit card.
The second outcome is
the revolving behavior.
Once you make a purchase transaction,
the customer can elect to pay back it
in full, which is typically called a
transacting behavior, or choose to evolve.
And pay an interest charge for
the flexibility to pay back the
purchase amount in installments.
So this is typically called a revolving
behavior or a revolver, and this
is where the company earns a higher
income based based on the interest
rate that they charge the customer.
So accurately predicting who would
who or like what kind of customers are
more likely to reward and like how much
of an amount that they would reward.
Would help in accurate planning of
like how much exposure should they
maintain, how much reserves in capital
should they maintain, and also what
are the potential revenue streams that
they can expect from these customers.
The third one is in terms
of the payment reliability.
Not everyone would have the same
efficiency to make back a payment.
And or the willingness to make a payment.
So this is where like using machine
learning to predict, like the willingness
of a customer to make a payment, their
ability to make a payment becomes
critical in understanding what kind
of a customer behavior can they expect
if you if a customer doesn't have the
willingness or the ability to pay, they
are more likely to be a risky customer
and display negative delinquent behavior.
Which turns out to be a loss for the
company versus a customer who has
got the means to pay back whatever
they're spending or chooses to spend
less than, like what they can pay
back are typically good behaviors.
That would encourage in the
company also meeting out good
treatments to the customer.
The fourth and the.
Other cost component that we can
predict using this machine learning
concepts is the default probability.
This is the probability of a
customer actually going bad in the
near future or in a slightly medium
term of say two to three years.
So this is where this is the part
that helps the company to plan for
any potential losses that can come
from these negative actions that
they give out to the customers.
In the spirit of not being too
conservative they have to be some
decisions made by the company where they
give out like preferential treatment
or like they approve customers.
Knowing like what is the potential risk?
So ultimately it boils down to the
risk reward for each customer segment.
So even there, even though there would
not be any customer segments where
there is like absolutely zero risk.
So there is an accessable level of
risk that the customer needs to decide
based on its internal tolerance levels.
It's appetite for taking on risk and like
the required ratio of return that they
can generate on the capital employed.
And then make an informed choice on the
relevant customer segments that they can
venture into versus like what customer
segments are absolutely out of reach
based on the absolute risk that they pose.
Now that we have looked at what outputs
can come from the machine learning models,
let's look at what actually goes into
determining these components or like
the outcomes that we just discussed.
Over here we see some of the primary
categories that we typically use.
The first one being on the
spending metrics which translate
into the spending volume.
How frequently they are spending,
are they using it like once a month
or are they using it like pretty
much like twice or twice a day?
What are the categories that the
customers are spending the money in?
Because there could be some categories.
Which are like the daily things
like spending at grocery store,
spending on gas, things like that
versus spending at a casino, which
is typically a riskier transaction.
The next is the payment behavior.
How many times is the
customer paying back?
Are they paying back in full or
are they making partial payments
and multiple payments a month?
And this could potentially imply.
How the customer's cash flow is and
what kind of a risk do they pose?
If the customers are making full payments,
like early on, then that is typically a
good behavior versus if someone's making
almost towards the end of the payment
due date, and if they're making multiple
payments in partial amounts through
different sources, that's probably an
impending cash flow issue that could
potentially arise from the customer.
Balance utilization is the
concept where it is more prominent
for the revolving customers.
What kind of balance
do the customers carry?
How much of a credit line are they using?
Are they using up all the credit
line, which is typically a risky
behavior versus if they are maintaining
the utilization in a good range,
which is typically below 30%.
Some of the external signals
that we can also feed in are
typically the income proxies.
Which are modeled income, and that
also feeds back into understanding like
what is the ability for the customer
to pay back some of their balances.
And some of the credit bureau attributes,
which talk about not just the credit
lines with the current company, but also
with the other external competitors and
also the other types of loans that the
customers can potentially have now that we
have seen like some of these categories.
We understand that like we have a lot
of data that we can use to model these
in birds, but that's not just enough.
So once we identify these different
categories or like the different variables
that we want to feed into the model,
which typically form the raw transactions,
then we need to aggregate all these and
enrich the data to make sure that it is
in a easy to digest form for the model.
Having a lot of missing
values or having a lot of.
Extreme values for a particular variable
could skew the model, and that is
what we need to avoid to ensure that
we get a good output from the model.
It is just like adage goes
garbage in, garbage out.
If you feed in like garbage random
data, we do not expect to get
a good output from the model.
Once we feed in this clean out data
to the model, it employs different
we employ different techniques,
which we review on the next slide.
We can identify different behavioral
patterns from these models and I, and
assign a cause effect relationship.
And use, use this linkage to identify
like what patterns within these
transactions or the patterns by the
customer would typically lead to the
different outcomes that we discussed.
Be in terms of in terms of the
probability of a default or their
willingness to pay, or like their
probability of carrying a balance and
how much balance would they carry.
So all these different parameters can be
predicted once a model, a senses, cost
of effect, linkage, and identifies these
patterns to predict the outcome behavior.
Now as we are discussing, there is this
intermediate component of what is that?
Machine learning approach that
we can use to help the model
assign these different linkages.
And here we have three different
approaches, which are primarily
used in most of the use cases.
And the first one is the
gradient boosting model.
The XG boost or the light GBM
are typically the widely adopted.
Methodologies within the
financial industry and they help
predict pretty much like all the
outcomes that we were discussing.
A couple of other models are are the
approaches, are the deep learning
methodology, which typically uses
neural networks and recurrent
networks and transformations to
predict sequence behaviors, and can
be used for dynamic predictions.
The third component.
The third most used approach is the
survival models which uses different
parameters to predict the time to event,
and is predominantly used for metrics
like attrition and retention models.
Now that we have reviewed the different
approaches that we can employ.
To generate predictive outcomes and the
way we can actually use the different
inputs and the different variables that
can be fed into it, how do we ensure
that like the model that is being
finalized or that is being used or would
potentially be used in the business use
cases be up to the market standards or be
satisfactory and not have any bias in it?
So the first thing that we need
to ensure is to make sure that we.
Use a temporal validation methodology,
which is to train the model on a
different time period and validate the
model using a different time period.
So if you have say, three years worth
of historical data that we can train
the model on instead of using all
the three years and then validating
the model again within a part of
those three years will likely lead
to overfitting bias instead of that.
We need to use probably two years for
training the model and then like we
validated the model on the remaining
one year to ensure that like the model
continues to perform equally well in
both the time periods and it is not over
fitting to fit only the training period.
And the next component
is a segment analysis.
What kind of, or what's the
composition of the input data?
Is very critical in deciding on
if the model output can be used
across different segments or not.
For example, let's take like the
transac and revolver behaviors, right?
So if you develop a model completely
depending on the transac population
itself, and feed that as a input,
the model designs itself to predict
the transac kind of a behavior,
and that's where the output also
would be in the similar way.
But if we continue to use that model or
start or use that model for predicting
the revolver behavior, that's where the
output though we might get some output, it
would be way off from the actual behavior.
So the way or the segments that we use
the model in is very critical and we
need to make sure that like the use
case, the business use case that we
are employing has a composition of the
customers, which is very similar to.
What the model development
sample looks like.
A couple of other columns that we need
to do is like whenever we roll out the
model, it is always a good practice to
have a test control a setup where we
test the model output and the decisions
based on the model output in the test
population, and then hold the control to.
Continue the decision making process
in the traditional approach way before
we confirm that the model is driving
incremental value and employ the
model output for a broader use case.
And the second one is a continuous
evaluation to determine the stability
of the model as we are discussing.
Change is only constant, so the
macro environment could change or the
potential customer behaviors can change.
So we need to continuously evaluate on
a regular basis, preferably quarterly,
to make sure that the model output
continues to perform in a stable
manner for the current population.
If we observe any deviations
over there, that is when like.
We need to refit the model based on an
updated sample to make sure that the more
recent model or the more recent customer
behaviors are being captured by the
model and the output is being accordingly
tailored to accommodate these updates.
One component that we need to
evaluate again is the stress
part, the stress testing part.
So in a normal environment
the model output continues to.
Be as easily applicable in
our decision making process.
But there are some scenarios,
especially in economic downturns, which
proudly impact the overall industry.
We need to evaluate by placing
an additional stress on the model
output to see what kind of a
decision it generally leads to.
And the general norm within the
industry has been to employ a
factor typically to estimate.
The additional stress that we need to
take on in times of like broader economic
stress and evaluate if we continue to be
profitable in those kind of scenarios.
And this stress test typically helps
determine like if the model can continue
to be used or if it practically wipes
out the entire population from being
targeted, then that is when like we
probably need a more stringent model
to account for these stressful times.
Now that we have seen like the entire
model development journey and the
application of how it can be leveraged and
like how we can validate it, let's review
a couple of the real world applications.
And as we were saying earlier, the real
world applications can come across like
the entire customer lifecycle because
they play a role in determining the
value of a customer that the company can.
Take on at different phases.
So the first uses that we will evaluate
is related to the acquisition phase.
So how can the mission learning
based customer lifetime value help
us determine whether we can how we
can optimize the acquisition outcome.
So depending on the customer
lifetime value, if you identify
a segment of customers who
typically tend to be high spenders.
Or who typically tend to be like
revolving on like significant amounts
of the purchases that they make, then
we can expect that gradually over a
period of time, the money that you
make from, or the revenue that we can
generate from the usage patterns of these
customers would be typically very high.
In order to attract these customers
and have them open a card with
us, we can potentially afford to
give them higher sign-on bonuses.
And target them in a more aggressive
fashion so that we can generate a
better response rate and also have
higher volume of customers coming in.
So that's where like the segment
targeting can benefit heavily based on
the accurate customer lifetime value.
For the credit card.
The same goes to the credit policy tuning.
So we know that like we probably
identify a group of customers that
we can identify that we can approve.
But should we always be satisfied
with just that segment of customers?
Can't we actually go beyond and test
for some of these borderline cases?
Because for all that we know, the
model predicts based on the behavior
based on the, based on what it has
learned from the historical behavior.
What if some of the assumptions
that we make for these borderline
customers are not validated?
And is there a merit in actually
approving these customers?
So instead of approving like a whole
lot of like unapproachable population,
we can identify like those borderline
cases and the marginal segments that we
can potentially ident approve and try
to learn their behaviors and validate
the assumptions that we are making.
This also becomes important in
targeting some of the segments or like
launching new products that we have
that we don't have any history on, and
we just use some proxy to understand
or to get a baseline as a mission.
And going into this policy tuning
based on this machine learning will
help us I optimize for those policy
gaps and the maximum identifying
those maximum boundaries that we
can approve the population into.
Okay.
Now let's evaluate another use case, which
is more in the customer management phase.
So once a customer starts spending
with us, we probably originate
them or acquire them with say
average line of say, $20,000.
But depending on the customer behavior,
that $20,000 may not be sufficient
because they continue to spend a
whole lot and like they are either
making like multiple payments within
the month to make sure that they open
up their line and continue to spend.
So in a way, like we are causing
a friction at that point.
And eventually, like if the customer gets
a higher line or a better experience with
any of our competitors, they would tend to
migrate away from using our card at that
point to avoid those kind of scenarios.
And if you are able to capture or use
this machine learning models to accurately
identify the true need of the customer.
Then we can give them a much higher line
than the initial line that we gave them
and continue to build on the engagement
that the customer is displaying.
The similar goes other way as well.
We started off a customer with say,
a $20,000 line and for some reason we
observe like negative behavior or like
a signs of negative behavior from the
customer in terms of them becoming
riskier in servicing their loans.
Or having transactions which probably
indicate that they are turning out
to be risky, like spending in risky
categories or not being able to make
their full payment over time or like
struggling to to make payments because
of return payments, things like that.
In that case, should we still like
open ourselves to that entire $20,000
line that we gave to the customer?
We do have the option of proactively
reducing the line to make sure that like
we do not expose the business to heavy
losses and restrict our loss potential in
by which we would be saving on the costs.
So in such a fashion, we can
dynamically manage our exposure.
To maximize the value that we
generate for the customer and also
the potential business value that we
get out from these customer behaviors.
In addition to these, we also
have like multiple retention
strategies or like the fee waivers
that we give out to the customers.
Any reward one-time reward categories or
what accelerators that we give out based
on the overall value that the customer has
generated till now and could potentially
generate based on their behavior.
And we can give a very good experience
or a rewarding experience to the customer
back and make sure that like we continue
to develop that engagement with them.
Now that we have seen a couple of
real world applications, let's see,
like how we can actually measure the
profitability or the measure, the
improvement that these machine learning.
Solutions are actually helping us generate
as we are discussing in the acquisition,
if you target the right customer and we
know that or we have a good, accurate
assessment of what kind of spend and
like the balances that they can carry or
that they use in the future, we would be
able to accelerate the breakeven period.
So as I was saying, like four
to six years is the average.
But if you can identify the group of
customers who actually spend a lot with
us or who actually revolve a lot with
us, we could potentially achieve that
break even in less than four years.
So those are the kind of customers
that we want to essentially target and
and spend more on getting those kind
of customers versus still sticking to
the traditional approaches and making
terms on having that average break
given period of four to six years.
Yeah, not just that say the balance is
written is where if you know for sure,
like what is the kind of losses that
we can expect from a set of customers
versus what is the potential benefit
we can make an appropriate risk reward
decision to make sure that we chase higher
returns with acceptable risk instead of
being very conservative and going for
lower returns to maintain the risk flow.
So using machine learning models, we
can have a better accu and accurate
assessment of what that risk reward
ratio would look like for a segment of
customers and optimize like a targeting
strategy and be very aggressive in
changing some group of customers versus
being conservative in moving out of
some pockets, which may seem like low
risk based on the traditional data,
but they could just be a ticking timer.
In the same way not just from the
business decisions perspective.
We can also use these assessments
that we get using the machine learning
models to have the right optimized
allocation of resources, be it in terms
of the human resources or like the
marketing budgets that we can have or
the operational budgets that we need
to have to service these customers.
We can focus on what would be the
optimal allocation and essentially
assign more resources to target high
customer lifetime value customers
versus having a equal approach or equal
allocation to all different segments.
Now that we have reviewed so much
information let's, let me wrap up and,
provide four main key takeaways that
we have from this discussion so far.
The first one and the core concept is the
customer lifetime value and how central
it is to the credit card profitability.
Starting from the upfront acquisition
cost, all the way through a dynamic
customer management phase, that having
an accurate assessment of the overall
customer lifetime value and constantly
adjusting it to the ever changing.
Factors is a key input into how, or what
kind of decisions we make and what kind of
treatments we give out to these customers.
And this is the most important concept of
optimizing the profitability so that we
can continue to have a dynamic allocation
of resources and make sure that.
We are, we maximize the value
for both the company and also
the customer at the same time.
The second one is how mission
learning can actually help us
unlock some of the predictions that
the traditional ma univa kind of
models or analysis wouldn't help us.
Behavioral modeling and using machine
learning concepts can help us.
Understand the impact of like
multiple variables and multiple
factors on the customer behavior.
And it provides us like multiple
viewers that we can leverage to impact
the customer actions and how we can
build a deeper engagement with them.
And as we have seen, the applications
of these machine learning solutions can
span across the entire customer lifecycle
starting from the time of acquisition and.
Going all the way through the
retention phase, the customer
management phase, and how they can
actually play together to inform the
overall profit and loss statement.
One word of caution, I would still like
to call out is the rigorous validation
as I was saying, building a model.
Is fine, but making sure that the business
case stays true and we are taking an
unbiased approach along with the rigorous
validation periodically to make sure
that the model is still relevant to the
current times is of utmost importance.
If you continue to operate on a model that
doesn't make any more sense based on the
customer behaviors or the changed external
environment, we would be making like
very wrong decisions for the business.
And that is a huge cost to the business
which we will realize very late and
would take a lot of impact to both the
brand and also the customer experience.
With that said, thanks a lot for
your engagement and I request you to
please reach out to me on LinkedIn
and I will be very happy to connect
with you and discuss more about.
The machine learning applications and the
overall credit card industry in general.
Have a good one.
Bye.