Hello and welcome to
Comfort to Machine Learning.
I'm Mi Flo and I'm excited to have
you here with me at my session today.
I have a very special story
from AWS Community Dark 2024.
It's elevating human
photography workflows with AWS.
So I'm not holding you, let's.
Go directly to the session, but
before we begin, Sierra's from Vienna,
and I would like to mention that
this is not just a technical story.
This is a story about our AWS
community, about the technical
knowledge, how technical creativity
brings something interesting that.
To let us resolve some magnificent things.
And here I would like to quote that
technology alone is not enough.
It's technology.
Married with the liberal arts, married
with the humanities that yields
the results that make our hering.
And this is actually the story that fully.
Complies with this quote and yeah.
And a quick introduction of myself.
I am Ra Kanka.
I am cloud architect at app.
I am AWS community builder.
I am AWS user group leader at Vien
and Leans, and I am together with
my colleagues via, are working
on AWS community in Vienna.
I'm a big it geek.
I love.
Everything which is related to te and
I'm holding master since communications
Bachelor's in business management.
And I'm working with AWS who focus
on AWS for the last five years.
And I'm a big photography fan.
And actually those things that we have
here that I'm IT gig, that I'm working
with a and that I'm a photography fan and
hobbyist, so they're all collided here.
This is why I have this story for you and,
so in this session, we will talk about
the challenge that, first of all, we will
take my, as I mentioned, passion for the
photography and that I wanted to make lots
of magnificent pictures for our community.
That we do a big job preparing
a community dark with our team.
And I wanted to make it memorable for us,
for our speakers, for us, for sponsors
that, for example, we could back.
After some years and say that
yeah, so it was the thing
and we have done it together.
And yeah.
Then this is why it's actually related to
the technical event that how a LS let me
achieve much more efficient workflow for
the photo processing that let us deliver.
The photos to our marketing team, to
the speakers, to everyone involved,
and to reduce the management and
all the processing overhead that
comes after the photo shoot.
And let's also talk about the
technical perspective and what
kind of results does it bring.
But before we go to the technical
details, so some words about myself, I,
raised surrounded with the photography.
I'm a big fan of the technical side.
I really like to research.
So all the technical things
like sensor manufacturing image
data processing, so everything.
And I also dealt with another photography.
And it's a big passion because it
combines creativity, technical expertise.
And it's also one field
where I can express myself.
So I have done photo shooting of different
events such as Formula one TM, factory
team and I also was photographing
different AWS related events, secluding
our community days, our user groups.
So I was photographing AWS Stars such
as Victoria, Ziman, Anton, Bianca.
So lots of other exciting
people in our community.
And of course I also part of different
exhibitions for the festivals.
And I have.
Photographed Playboy models I
have was winning competitions.
So it's a pretty long way that I'm doing,
besides my main professional activity
related to AWS and bringing this, all
this experience to a s community doc.
So I used to take over 8,000 pictures,
30 speakers, about 650 attendees,
and the main challenge here, so what
should I do with this amount of things.
And normally, so even we are talking about
the photo processing, it's a huge process
because it starts from the planning of
the photo shoot you are shooting, you can
I make some adjustment of the amount of
work you can do if you shoot properly.
And since I'm a technician, for me it was
the question, how can I make it more easy?
Easy.
And I, first of all, I started to
research what do we have on market
from the commercial solution.
And since the story was about the
summer of the last year, I was.
Surprised that there are not many
AI solutions powered, AI powered
solutions, and none of them, they was
capable to do what I wanted to do.
And since we are builders,
we love to build.
So that's why I was thinking, okay,
let's maybe try to do it on AWS and.
So the whole process and together with
our marketing team, thank you to Susanna.
Hans.
Linda, you are amazing.
So we planned what, where,
and how and when we would like
to have, so then my task as a
photographer was to to be in time.
And to put the thing, so to capture
it, that we could have an image.
So for example, me with the guys,
we have done all the pre-planning
together with a LinkedIn post,
with the text, with all the needed
surrounding materials such as photos.
So where and how.
And we were thinking so how to
use it properly to maximize the
coverage for our media presence.
Then of course, it, my part came because
I was actually performing a shooting.
I was using two Sony Alpha cameras
because amount is the best system on the
market and no one can keep up with it.
And those cameras, they
extremely reliable.
I will, the main camera was Sony
Alpha nine Mark three with a 7,200
G master lens, and the second camera
was Alpha seven four with a 24 70.
And, I was shooting with the two
cameras simultaneously to, to have
different perspectives, but also my task
was to use the technical advantages.
For example, like iPhone nine.
It's because of its global sensory doubt.
We were, I was not afraid of the
light flicker or some other things.
And I was able to use both cameras
in pretty aggressive setup.
For example, taking ER images, which is.
Absolutely possible with the
current Sony sensors and, yeah.
And also they have extremely
variable of the focus and they
actually saved lot of work.
But still all this actually all this
gap that gets introduced by the faulty
auto focus, especially on the DSLRs that
are not capable to do face tracking.
So it causes more and more in work.
And then we are going to the point
when AWS is capable to step in.
So in this project I was trying to re.
So to reproduce the process that I'm
doing myself, so how I'm sourcing the
pictures, all this cognitive process.
So how basically the mission was
intended to do what I would to do
and to my target was to use technical
opportunities by AWS to represent
my way of thinking and all the.
Photography process.
And of course also to automate
the processing to perform
the automatic corrections.
And here we have a full
conjunction of different a s
services to perform this task.
And yeah.
But before I go directly to the technical
solutions, so in all my previous session,
if you have ever attended mine inclusive
at, so I'm always thinking that when we
are building some something on the Italy.
We treat the data and architecture
that interchangeable between
humans, machines, and software.
So all of those are, must be
orchestrated together and, and when
I'm starting any kind of project
on AWS my goal is to achieve unity
between technology and human needs.
And here AWS acts as a connector
between technical systems, all the
software and human requirements, and
using its services we can build it.
And talking about the building
when I'm, I see some process, some
applications, something that runs on AWS.
I always try to imagine it in a sort
of the waterfall, and this is why we
actually have a waterfall image and the
current set of AWS services, it deeply
reminds me as Swiss Army knife because
you have lots of the services, but if you
master serverless, Lambdas Dyna db, if
you know how to do the step functions.
So if you do it in proper way with
the CICD cloud formation, it's
already your key to the success.
And of course with the junctions, like
for, I don't know, SQA, if you use SQS, if
you use I dunno, Kafka, whatever you like.
So you can build resilience, scalable
systems that just they data is
like a bottle of fall is incoming.
All this flow of the data gets protest and
you deliver your technical vision for your
businesses, for your pet project because.
This project, it's what?
It was not coming out
from the just abnormal.
I was thinking a lot.
So for example, how to
conjunction different things.
How can some step of my normal cognitive
process that I'm doing myself when I'm
processing pictures, what function,
which service can be in back, end of it?
And yeah.
And all this vision, it always
comes to the orchestrated a
s services working together.
And our target is as an engineer
to interconnect them in the way
to make a comprehensive solution.
And basically, yeah, as I mentioned,
it's, it didn't come up from the
empty place before I even had spoken
about it at Con City last year.
So I was doing numerous variations of
system integrations of data processing,
data collection from a, from our third
party services that we have in app attack.
And that how we can.
Transform all this data to make
it a even driven that we could
interconnect transparently for our
teams, for users, for the people
who are not like AWS proficient.
Just to normally use the system to get
the data they need to make a daily job
they need, and looking to this experience.
For example, how I was integrating our
CICD processes, security processes,
configuration item management, inventory
management, et cetera, image building.
So it already gave me
the backbone that was.
Lay down the foundation of
this photography project.
And actually idea of it came just
from a talk with my colleague
because he was working with AWS
recognition for some proof of concept.
And we were targeting to train them
to recognize Austrian celebrities.
I'm not aware myself of, unfortunately,
that's why it's even tricky for a os
recognition, but it was a use case.
And I was thinking, but then I
actually forgot about the fit because
we were doing lots of reparations.
It's not only about the photos
because I was also helping with
the sponsorship of community data.
I was helping with everyone.
And at some point I just started think,
okay, let's translate my A risks.
Experience to save up lots of time
for myself, for my family, for even
for the beers and the result of
translating my photography workflow.
Including the experience that I have had
with AWS services before is this, and I
would call it community Photo Factory.
So the most important was to
first of all to get the pictures.
Yeah.
That's why I delegated it
to myself with Sony cameras.
I really love them, as I mentioned
and we gather quality files
that with which we can work.
Then the next target was to
put them somehow to a OS.
And of course we are working
with S3 bucket events.
We are working with a event breach.
So we are having the events
that to preserve because we have
to have everything processed.
I put them in this Q Qs, of course,
with the debt ladder, qe, and
here then we are stepping in with
the two different step functions.
So the actual, the processing step
function that does the whole process.
And, of the processing of the incoming
files because it takes out the
metadata that we have into the file.
We are performing the pre-processing
based on our weights that are
used to calibrate AWS recognition.
In this case, we have a custom written
liberal lambda, which is actually
make us possible to work with the
Air W files that are incoming from
Sony Alpha cameras and to actually.
Lets us to extract the data and I
develop them into different things.
And we store metadata in
the various dynamics tables.
We process the pictures, we sort them
based on the timestamps information.
We recognize the speaker
or kind of medium.
The photo was taken and we sorted.
And also using the metadata
recognized by Libro.
We feed through the bedrock cloud
haiku, then we compare it with
the comparable photo samples.
Then we the select the editing
strategy, and then it gets
put into the following bucket.
So this is the scheme that does
the, all the steps of the process.
Starting from the click of the button,
it gets uploaded to AWS, we do the pro.
Pre-processing of the image,
we recognize what is happening.
We detect faces, we get out metadata, we
compare with our already known weights.
We process it and we have a picture
that for example colleagues of
mind, they could just come and take.
And then we can simply share
those folder with our speaker.
And you can also notice.
The second step step function, metadata,
and yeah, one of the evenings I was
wondering how can I approach it?
And thankfully I have already enough
archives, so I have lots of photos from
the past community days, from our OS
community stage, from our user groups.
And I took pictures of some of the
speakers, of course, of Linda and some and
whatever, just to perform some testings.
And interesting fact, Claude
is afraid of the glasses.
And for example, when you are
taking, selecting the pictures I
think it's very important to have
the person with the open eyes on it.
And this is the core thing.
The clot at the time, 3.5 it was failing
because I took some pictures of Linda.
Both with open and closed
eyes, I gave them to the court
the prompt that I would like.
So you are working for the
professional press agency and you
are picking the picture if it's
suitable for the publication.
And yeah, Claude was recognizing any
kind of I state at Linda, so basically
opened and I also went and they
collected other people in the glasses.
So Claude was failing and it was very
sad because I thought to make it in
some modern way that we are delegating
it to the AI model, but unfortunately.
It failed here.
And then I actually remember it
to, to the story with my colleague
that I have already mentioned.
And then I decided, okay, let's try
AWS recognition and AWS recognition.
And it actually gave me
basically just like this, I
don't know what to give to you.
I have this year so that all the
data that actually I would need,
all the metrics, all the weights.
That I could process that.
For example, as far as you can
see, we can have sharpness metrics.
We can have exposure metrics.
So we can have the different facial
parameters as you can see from the slide.
And here I. What I have done, I have
aggregated the data based on our previous
data sets for the photos I picked and
I didn't pick, and it allowed me to set
up the thresholds and such a thresholds.
I collected them in Dynamic DB and
they were referenced for the Lambda
in the main processing workflow.
That was the sizing.
If we are taking picture or we are not.
Okay, so we have first
piece of our puzzle.
The second one, thankfully.
I can win an award to linking the systems
which are not intended to be linked.
And I don't know.
I think some of those crazy Japanese
engineers in Sony, they didn't expect
that someone would try to throw the
files through the ft PS services in.
Directly to a OS because
this is a normal approach.
Since in APA we have a lot of photography
colleagues who are coming, they are taking
pictures of sport events, different other
live events, and normally, especially
at sports, pictures are getting
uploaded to FCP host and I thought,
okay, let's try to use this function.
And AWS is offering transfer
gateways that are actually, have
done the jobs absolutely perfectly.
But thankfully I'm community builder
and for it compensated my mistake.
And you have to be extremely careful
keeping the transfer family up and
running, because in my case, it took
over $220 just because I thought.
So it has bit more serverless
approach for the pricing, so
please be extremely careful.
But yes, it's possible to give the
transfer gateway, endpoint the sensing
of Sonic cameras and directly stream
your pictures to the S3 bucket.
And when you have already the data on
S3 bucket, then we are in business.
We can.
Go through that.
As I already mentioned, I was
collecting the metrics and let's
first of all start with the things.
So for example, how I
would like to work with it.
Training phase, it involved calibration
with the existing data sets.
First of all, I collected
pictures from meetups.
I passed them through the recognition,
I aggregated the data and for me it
was the most important to know if.
Eyes are open and the picture is sharp.
So those are two main things
that I would personally open and.
Come and see for the views.
Also for for me it was important to have
confidence in the face detection that
we have faces and because of the faces,
we were recognizing the biggest face
and the sharp face because sometimes
you have a few persons and we are trying
to get it or, and it can be potentially
a marker of the faulty outer focus.
And yeah, we can also estimate
the post that, for example, I
can automatically throw away.
Some, I don't know, crazy facial
ex expressions that no one
would post on LinkedIn and yeah.
And basically I was using detect face
CPI and detect label CPI and, and it was
in all dedicated S3 bucket of training
photos, and it was not intercepting.
And I was with the threshold analysis.
I was extracting facial
expressions and also raw metadata.
Raw metadata was the core here
that I could implement the
actual processing core here.
And wait.
And and, speaking about the parameters,
for me it was the most important to get
the sharpness eyes open, confidence, fa,
face detection, confidence parameters
that we were actually storing in the gb.
And then we are going, when we
already have the thresholds, we
can already so prewarm our system
to do what is it intended to do,
and in the production workflow.
Here, as I already mentioned, we have a
trigger, so we are coming then before each
individual picture, and it was extremely
valuable because in any case it was
processing for the processing workflow.
It does not matter what
actually this picture is.
It's already was built to work with
the A RW files that were incoming
from the Sonic Camera and, all this
process was completely orchestrated.
I was extremely happy with the results.
And we were extracting the
metadata as I already mentioned.
So we were performing analysis with
the recognition that we could get
the metrics and, we were collecting
the parameter thresholds, we were
detecting who is actually this person.
And we, it was automatically taking
decision if it's taken or rejected.
And that's why we have to
separate packets because yeah
it mes can still make a mistake.
So we were just to make
pre-approved and approved appro
an unapproved approach here.
And what is the most important?
It's actually discussed in written liberal
lambda, which is using the pyro library.
And here we just starting from the
camera, we are delivering presorted
completely good pictures to our team.
And talking about the
recognition API strategy.
So I was mainly using the detect
phases API, yeah, because I had to
get the scores, as you can see on the
screenshot, and I was also using the
detect labels for the analysis and to
reduced the price usage of recognition.
I was not using index faces.
Because we already have information
about what is present and I wanted
to work just specifically with one
phase and it was the most important.
And we were also using detect moderation,
labels as secondary filter and just
not to overcome the service and
to avoid any kind of API TRT link.
We also had some.
Dynamic calling so that we have
some jitter in calls that we are not
hitting any kind of service API limits.
And of course, we had the lamb
concurrency here and also what was
important, for example, sometimes when
I'm shooting, so I'm shooting series
of the pictures and sometimes you can
have almost similar pictures with a.
Pretty tight timestamps.
So I was sending such pictures
of a batch to the recognition.
So for example, because sometimes
you can have four pictures
and only one of it is sharp.
And to reduce this aggregation to
reduce number of API counts so yeah.
We have taken a out more efficiency
from AWS recognition and also I used AWS
Lambda Power Tools, which is an amazing
library that gives you lots of backbone
to boost your development, for example,
for ex extensive logging, error tracing.
So it's extremely useful.
And you must use AWS Lambda
Power Tools in your projects.
And yeah.
For example, here you can see an
example of some piece of Lambda
code I have, and, so in terms of
calibration of the sharpness data,
it was a logarithmic function.
So it was logarithmic scale.
So that goes 25 to 100 usually,
and we were targeting pictures
that usually hitting over 70%.
And yeah, we, I would say it was
even 80 for the speakers and 65
for the more general photos because
they are usually like, have more.
Fine grain details that are getting
lost and for me, it's also to reinforce
the like quality of open eyes.
So I have went through them, over 500
pictures that just to be confident
enough and I haven't done any additional
pre-training of the recognition
because it was already very like
reliable and I absolutely love it.
And also the Lambda was controlling.
So if we actually recognizing single
eye or both eyes and, but it was like
some of the third party, like second
priority metrics because mainly we,
I was getting normal metrics for both
open ice and also I was taking the
official expression analysis and actually
one of good ideas of development of
this project that we could count the.
Amount of happy, surprised,
cold, angry to get more like
statistical overview of the mood and
atmosphere on the conference part.
We will speak about it a bit later.
Yeah.
And post assessment is important
because we can already drawn out
some pictures that have some strange
positions of the hands, et cetera,
in combination with the wear face.
And it already saved lots of work here.
So we are getting properly
exposed pictures from the set.
We are having high confident eye detection
and here, and we are already cutting down.
A good piece of input that could be
potentially not useful in our project.
And one of the pillars of this projects
and I was thinking a lot what actually
could have been on this slide because
I was considering different options.
I. Starting from running some
E two instance, which had a GPU
with some kind of windows script
automation to perform editing.
Then I was considering running any
kind of commercial solution and, but
unfortunately only solutions with by topa.
Are capable to provide UCL access and
I haven't worked with the topos much,
that's why I abandoned this idea.
'cause I'm mostly use Luminar Neo and
the XO photo app in my processing.
So Luminar is amazing for portrayed
or studio sessions and the so is
great when you are processing huge
events like diesel or some, I dunno.
Yeah, when you don't
need to weak the faces.
And then I was thinking and I looked in
the direction of the open source things.
And yeah, we have a very good
known liberal library, which
is used for example, in dark
table in the road therapy.
And I thought, give it a try.
I. And the reason, actually, you could
ask me, Dima, why do you need to do it?
Because you can already have GPX from
the camera, and this is a thing when you
are working with the profiles, you have
a file which has 14 bits of information.
It means that in our situation when
most of the speakers are standing
behind the s with a tors, with the
bright or dark slides, and we, I
was trying not using the flash.
Because I didn't want to disturb
attendees, not to disturb
speakers, to keep everyone focused.
So basically, I was a ghost.
So that we keep our attendees to
focus on the technical topics, to
let them enjoy the conference and
not to disturb them with, all this.
So how is sometimes
called welding and Yeah.
When you are shooting GP you have
eight bit files and you cannot simply
recover the highlights or shadows.
You can, but just a bit.
And here, for example, when you're working
with the row, just by working with the.
Specific functions, you can recover
all the background that have e
equally equalized ex exposed picture.
So here, using the liberal library, I was
also considering if I would like to run
it on the ECS or run it like a Lambda.
But I also noticed that, if you lambda,
since we are receiving the picture and
so there is no, there is always a gap
between like supplying of the pictures.
Yeah.
There would be some idling time when
you are running the container and I
noticed that if I was running Lambda
with the capacity of memory of one and
half gigabytes, it was giving you much,
I was receiving much better performance.
Then a comparable container
running on the Fargate.
This is the first false response
time was within 10 seconds, and we
already had processed image on the.
On the storage and I'm
using AMA algorithm.
There are lots of algorithms
from the basic ones.
So ama, it's so the idea is that
it does an detection of the edges
that allows you to reduce more
and also some kind of steps.
On the edges, and this is the
most advanced algorithms which
are available like an open source.
And LiRo, actually this lamb
that works in two functions
based on the event it receives.
The first scenario is every
profile, TNGC two, nf, IRV,
rough, they have the miniature.
Which is extracted by photo viewing
software when you are coming to
the row, because sometimes it's
a very like performance demanding
operation performed in the mosaic.
That's why camera always includes a
small like preview miniature inside
of the file, which is taken by
the photo photo viewing software.
And I used to extract this picture,
actually like to perform pre-processing.
On the recognition and to already save
the time and cost of recognition, not to
waste it processing every single image
because this resolution, it was already
enough to perform the person examination.
Yeah.
And then we were taking the right one.
Then of course we could take the
bigger one and perform more precise.
Analysis of the quality.
So basically we were taking and working
with more progressive options here.
Yeah.
And also already mentioned, we have
already aggregated loss of metadata,
which, so basically I was telling,
okay, we have this picture based on
this recognition data plus metadata.
And I would process it like, like this.
And here we are pushing
metadata of the sample.
We are campaigning it with the weights.
It all goes to cloud.
CLO through the bedrock, and
it was suggesting the potential
scenario, and it was extremely
good because it was compensating
the highlights very precisely.
I was happy how it was adjusting
the wide balance and, also all my
profiles, they had extremely aggressive
highlight and shadow reconstruction.
I was achieving with this lambda, so the
quality and coloring and processing that
I was not able to achieve, for example, by
using the picture profile on the cameras.
But mainly because of the limitations
of the loss of the dynamic range on the
file that is caused by eight BT GP files.
And yeah.
This thing, it was it done most
of the job here because not only
selection takes lots of time.
The actual processing, it
actually can take even more.
And it's always mu it must be
consistent because sometimes you
can start processing one day.
Then I know you had something,
you are coming back on the next
day and then you're looking.
Oh my God, everything is green.
No.
So here it was also consistent.
It was very fast, very efficient,
and it's just a must have
and big win of this project.
And yeah, as I already mentioned, so
we were cutting the small batching
logic so that I was combining
the series, comparable pictures,
and to reduce the number of the.
Calls to the AWS bedrock and
I think all these miniatures,
they were around 1,200 pixels.
And also it was going
to the step functions.
They were concurrent and we were, I was
also dynamically adjusting the concurrency
based on the number of the events.
And it was very parallel.
Parallel.
And pictures were coming one
by one and they were not.
Interact, interacting between each other.
So this is a good technical part of it.
Looking here, the results.
First of all, I, it was extremely
memorable when such an amazing
people like Luke, like Jan, they
published all these pictures.
I. So they are LinkedIns and first
of all, it's good memory for them.
It's support of their
work that they are doing.
As a speakers, as a technicians, as
a part of AWS community, I got lots
of amazing feedback on the email and
it already give lots of powers for
me because physically it was very
exhausting to shoot such a big event.
And yeah, from the AWS community
side, we expanded the, so we enhanced.
Our impression and community experience.
So we could use these pictures to have
more community restaurants because we
can show to the people in the good way
with the cool photos, what are we doing?
And this is a good memory that, for
example, when I will be old and I
don't know all of us, one day we'll
be old unfortunately, and we could
back to it and see, hey, we were cool.
And for the speakers, it's
also the support of their.
Brands, brands development,
it's support of their employers.
And for me personally, it was a huge
win because I spent about I don't know,
I would say less than I. I would say
maybe 15, 20 hours to get it done,
to work very relaxed without any rush
or crunch, but it saved potentially
over 60 plus H hours of manual work.
But I believe even more because from
8,000 pictures, the whole processing,
it took out 4,200 candidates.
They were pre preferences.
We were just performed additional pre
selection based on our needs that we
have preplanned with our marketing
team and talking about the costs.
It's absolutely worth it because
I spent $20 on a s recognition.
I spent $30 on AWS Lambda orchestration.
They name a DB step
function transfer family.
So if counting the price only for the day
of the conference, and in total we spend
$50 and less than 1 cent per picture.
This is an amazing.
Values just because time and for
example, my health that my mind that
I'm using to process the pictures, it's
all probably would cost more than $50.
Definitely.
And such a big response.
How much.
Effort it saved and how it in allowed
us to develop the process also to have
a good reason to give a speech for you.
And it was absolutely worth it because
it done job even more than four
$50 and talking about the things.
So that I would like to reflect
the, to the Steve Jobs quote
that I have had in the beginning.
So that technology alone is not enough.
And and a s. I never speak about of
it, just like about the call provider.
It's a toolkit that provides and let us
solve the problems in the creative ways.
When you are equipped with those
tools, using our unique skills,
you can create unexpected value.
So I.
Guys, UCWS don't think just you are
running virtual machines, go beyond your
engineering division and make a real
projects like this one that might make
an impact on some, something significant.
For example, like on a s community.
And here we have achieved a good
foundation that can, in the future,
can be developed in automatic.
Collection generation and delivery
platform for any kind of event.
For example, for publishing, for
realtime events that, for example,
people, they are on the N, they can
sunk your code and come and see it.
But we have a technical backbone
and for me, the task would
be to have even more for it.
So to make a, not only at the point
when you can come and take it,
but to make it in the way that.
Pictures are coming to you.
So looking to the takeaways from all of
this story, first of all, the, so AWS
services, they are amazing and they can
be combined creativity beyond traditional
use case or for what they're intended
to do and combining with the things
that are intended to do something else.
But for some reason, they're
useful and we have it here.
For example, that FCP function
streams directly to S3 bucket
and let us work with the data.
And I have combined here recognition,
step function, Lambda S3 bedrock
in the way that actually they
were not like, designed for.
And it's just going knowledge and seeing
beyond the intended use of a LS service.
And they are all the services
there building blocks that can
solve any problem in any domain.
You just.
Come and solve it.
And I think it's not a regular case
when AWS services in that matter,
they're solving photography tasks
in the way like a human would
work with the same photo data set.
Yeah.
And this project also
shows wise is amazing.
And you can make you can delegate to.
Labor intensive tasks without
of any management overhead.
You're just coming and creating
the logics that brings economical,
strategical business value to you.
And all this orchestration, it turned
hours of manual work to the amazing thing.
And since we pay only for use, it's
also very economical, effective, and,
so yeah, if you have some projects with
such behavior, feel free to continue
with and it'll solve your tasks.
Yeah.
And the most important, all this
technical part, it allowed us to
develop human connections and make
us a good memory of the conference
that we have done altogether.
Yeah.
This is What about was it?
So thank you very much.
I'm always happy to discuss any, anything
technical, AWS, whatever you like.
Even formal one.
Please come to me or add
me on LinkedIn please.
I. So I'm open for any
kind of discussions.
Thank you very much.
I hope you enjoy conference.
You do.
I'm very thankful to, to the
mark for having all this idea,
pushing all this community.
And this is the second time this year and
I'm exciting to be here in support of you.
So please enjoy the conference.
I hope you like the session, and we will
see us any other time on the clouds.
Thank you.