Hi everyone.
Thanks for joining this conference,
42 Mission Learning Event 2025.
I'm excited today to share this
mission learning for the advanced
document management systems.
In this session we will see how we
can leverage this mission learning
for the advanced document management
system, revolutionizing the
efficiency, compiles and automation
in today's ATE business environment.
Organization face increasing
challenges in managing the.
Vast amounts of document data and
whether it's invoices, contract,
the insurance claims, or the
regulatory documents efficiently.
Extracting and analyzing this data
is very crucial for operational
efficiency and compliance.
And Microsoft Machine Learning offers
a powerful platform to address these
challenges by integrating AI and
machine learning technologies with the
document management systems, enabling
the automation and data driven insights,
and streamline the workflows across
the industries, including the life
sciences, the healthcare insurance,
and general purpose operations.
And my name is re I'm a Microsoft
certified professional, a technology
specialist, and also play like
a Microsoft 365 Cloud architect.
And I play a technical manager.
So for the various projects
which I work on through my 17
years of IT industry experience
coming to this, machine learning.
For the document management system,
we will see the various extraction
methodologies or the models and
how we can leverage this machine
learning for our document system
into the various industries.
When coming to this topic, automated data
extraction on the classification, we see
like how it reduce the manual effort, the
cost reduction, and the intelligent class.
Applications when it comes to the
manual effort, the Azure Machine
Learning automates the data extraction
from the various document types.
It's significantly reducing
the manual data entry and
the associated human errors.
When it comes to the cost reduction,
the company is using this AI
powered document processing.
See up to 30 to 50% reduction in
operational costs related to data entries,
operational costs related to data entry
task, and the intelligent classification.
Intelligent classification
is like a machine learning.
Azure Mission Learning classifies
model classifies and tag the documents
based on the content, categorization
them into the relevant groups of.
Relevant groups for efficient Val Azure AI
document AI document intelligence, which
is formally form, like form recognition.
It extracts all the.
Structure data such as the dates,
amount, the names, and the product
details, and the ID card details from
the various documents like the invoices,
contracts, and regulatory forms, and
streamlining the inform and streamlining
the information management process.
When it comes to the when it comes to
the search capabilities, when it comes
to the search capabilities that in
the document management system, such
capabilities plays a critical role
because, like for the business users way,
they search for the particular document
in the traditional approach, they use the
keyboard to search for the document and
where, how we are enhancing the security.
Like how about this, how to differentiate
between the general documents and the.
Sensitive document and for showing for
one department, the document should
not be shown and one for document for
one department it has to be shown like
the for HR document cannot be shown
to the employees and the employees.
Documents to business documents
cannot be shown to the customers.
So in this way, like how we enhance
this capital, this machine learning,
we will see how this machine learning
enhances the such capabilities when
it comes to the traditional approach,
semantic analysis and improved results
in the traditional approach is nothing
but the keyboard based methods often
fall with the short, ambiguous terms.
When it comes next to the semantic
analysis, Azure artificial
intelligence analyzes the context
and the intent behind the.
Queries improved results.
Improved results.
This results it re, it returns
the relevant documents even with
the in incomplete search tab.
Azure ai, Azure Artificial
Intelligence search.
Enhance enhances the document
tool by understanding the
meeting behind the search queries
rather than just the keyboards.
What this is particularly valuable for
the large document repositories where
the traditional search models often
fall in written more relevant results.
And coming to the, one of the key area
for the mission learning for document
management system is like automating
document workflows, how we can automate
the document workflows from the manual
approach to the traditional approach
to the advanced workflow systems.
When the whenever the business upload
the document, either into the Microsoft
SharePoint, there's a repository
or to the blog storage repository.
What, and when the document is uploaded,
what is artificial intelligence?
What it'll do, it'll analyze this.
The help of this machine
learning, Azure machine learning.
It analyzes, classifies and extracts
the key data of the document and
it transforms into the workflow
trigger at a workflow trigger.
Here the Microsoft uses the advanced
workflow systems like a Microsoft
Power Automate, and Azure Logical Apps
undo Azure function apps, which are
built on top of this Microsoft Cloud.
So the with workflow trigger system
indicates the notifications, updates or
the approval process parallel up towards
it has all three facilities to connect
with the external connectors, like a
business to business B2B integrations,
and to perform these automated
documents workflows and transforming
to the next completion status.
The process it process the completes
with a minimal human interventions.
We use something like here, Azure
Azure Logical Apps and Azure
functions enable the automation of
the document workflows significantly
reducing the manual intervention and
accelerating the decision making.
According to the recent, according
to the recent data, automating
the workflows can lead up to the
40% of the operational efficiency.
This is this, document workflow place,
automating the document workflows in
this IT industry for the various of the
domains like insurance, in insurance, the
life senses, health, pharma, and retail.
Like these are all the IT domain,
which are heavily dependent on
the document management system
and the enterprise content
management system and the metadata.
Is very crucial here.
And it also, the classifications and
between the sensitive data and the
non-sensitive data and the record
retentions, and these are all, that
plays a very critical role, even
with from one process when it, when
the workflow processing from one
department, the another department,
and this is how the Azure machine
learning helps helps the business.
Help the business users through this
document management system process.
And when it comes to this compliance and
security monitoring, this compliance and
security monitoring is one of, is also one
of the three key critical area for the.
Azure Machine learning, the document
management system, the compliance and
security monitoring, how we do this, like
document analysis compliance verification,
issue detection, and automated deduction.
Automated reduction is nothing
but a hiding or removal of the
certain certain information.
The document analysis, machine learning
models scan for regulatory compliance.
And compiles verification.
Final check again, the industry
regulations issue detection, system, flag
sensitive, and non-complaint information.
Automated reduction.
LNLP models.
Identify and redact P 11 three and
compile is a major concern for the your
IT industries, like the health industries
healthcare, finances and the life.
S Azure Mission Learning helps address
these challenges by analyzing the
documents for compiling the industry
regulations such as like hipaa.
Ft federal regulations requirements.
Research shows that automated
compliance monitoring, using artificial
intelligence can reduce the likelihood
of regulatory violations by up
to 70% of mitigating the risk of
costly data breaches and penalities.
When it comes to the industry specific
applications that when it comes to
industry specific applications, like the
insurance and the healthcare and the life.
S automated claims auto automates
the claims processing and the fraud
detection by analyzing the data,
patents and the historical claims.
By reducing by reducing the processing
time, by reducing the processing time,
and enhancing the customer satisfaction.
And when it comes to the
healthcare area, it processes.
It processes the patient, record
patient records information
while ensuring the HIP compiles,
improvising the care coordination,
improvising the care coordination, and
reducing the administrative burden.
The life sensors.
When it comes to the life sensors it
automates the quality management system
processing, ensuring the ensuring
the SOP based on audit reports com
compiling with the regulatory standards
while tracking the document revisions.
Azure Machine Learning provides a
tailored solutions for different
industries addressing their unique
document management challenges.
By evaluating the documents quickly
and efficiently, organizations
can also streamline the operations
while maintaining the compiles with
the industry specific regulations.
This is all about the industry specific
applications when it comes to the
data analytics and visualization.
It's not about always the how we how the
rate raw data in the document management
system, and it is helping the business.
It's also in the modern world of this
one, the data can be converted through the
data analytics and the visualization for
the base of easy understanding, the easy
calculation, and for the decision making.
When it comes to the interactive
interactive dashboards, the trend
analysis and compile tracking, and
when it comes to the interactive
dashboard, the custom power BI dashboards
visualizes extracted document data,
and it's enabling the stakeholders
to track the key metrics at a glance.
When it comes to the trend analysis,
the visual representation of a
document, processing the trends
helps the identifying of the patents.
And the opportunities
improvement, compliance tracking.
Compliance tracking is all about the
real time Visualization of compliance
metrics enables the proactive
management of regulatory requirements.
Azure's integration with the inter
Azure's integration with the tools
like the Power ba transforms the
extracted doctor in into the actionable
insights in quality management systems.
Users can visualize.
Audit findings like audit findings
we can say recertifications of the
systems under the risk assessment,
under the document status, whether it's
in like draft status, approved status
approval, pending up rejection status,
and enabling the informed, the decision
making based on that real time data.
Scalability and security.
In this scalability and security
measures, you will see how the
enterprise grade security happened,
the cloud native infrastructure, how
the native infrastructure is happening,
and how the role-based access controls
is helping under data encryption,
enterprise grade security, comprehensive
protection for the comprehensive
protection for sensitive documents.
It just like how we are
making the documents like the.
Once the document is once the document
is uploaded and it, when it passed,
the certain stages of the approval
passes, that the document has to
get log his state by making the read
through the record management of the.
Part of the document management system,
how the cloud native infrastructure,
not only always with the security
of these external tools and how the
infrastructure also backed by backed
by this system and how it is helping
this document management system.
It is through this back by the Azure
Kubernetes sub service you can also call
at is a Kubernetes as a K eight service.
And the role-based access
controls in the real world.
In the real world particularly in the
documents document management system.
The role-based access controls are very
very crucial between the departments,
between the users, from the, for
example, for the insurance documents.
It can be from the policies, the claims.
The re policies casualities department,
personal property, and various
kinds of various kinds of insurance
things between the department.
The document should not be
shown how we choose this.
It is achieved through the
rule-based access control.
It means adding granular permission
management, like a unique
permission to only see the document,
who are eligible to see the.
Document not the other not the
other business customers or the
customers or any department.
Data encryption.
Data encryption is crucial.
Like it's, it has to be
like end-to-end production.
End-to-end production.
It's not to be the, it's not to be
exposed to the third one, right?
So end-to-end production, but it's
like a one-to-one kind of thing.
And mission learning provides Azure
robust security features, ensuring.
That sensitive information
remains protected.
As the organizations scale their.
Scaled.
The operations assured machine learning
infrastructure ensures that mission
learning models can be deployed at
a deployed at a scale of the real
time in inference without compromis
without compromising the performance
or the security when it comes to this.
Implementation benefits.
We should also see that when, whenever
free or implementing a system, whenever
we are utilizing some, technology, the
models, the artificial intelligence,
whether it can be a cloud or enterprise
or talk, whatever the system, we need
to see whether it is a, whether that
the cost reduction is there or not.
Whether we are gaining the
efficiency gain is there or not.
Whether it is part of the.
Compiles is improving or not?
Here when it comes to the implementation
benefit, there is a 50% of cost reduction,
decrease in the operational cost
related to the document processing and
reducing the paper thing, reducing the
paper thing, reducing the manual thing,
reducing increasing the efficiency.
And it's like efficiency.
It's like a 40% of efficiency gain.
In improvement in improvement
in the operation, implement in
the operational efficiencies and
through this workflow automation.
So workflow automations plays a key role
in eliminating the manual process and
the manual approaches, and 70% of the
compiles improvement is not only about
the automation or the cost reduction.
It also improves the compiles improvement
by, in reducing the likelihood
of this regulatory violations.
Organizations implementing the machine
learning for the document management
see a significant measurable benefits.
These improvements translate to better
resourcing allocation, allowing the
teams to focus on strategy task instead
of manually administrating work while
maintaining a high compelling standard.
Coming to this coming to this roadmap.
Coming to this roadmap when
it comes to the Azure machine
learning models or methodology.
So we will see how the
RA roadmap will be there.
The one is like the
assessment and planning.
It'll, any implementation roadmap,
whether it's machine learning,
whether it's artificial intelligence,
or it's the cloud or the standard
waterfall or any process, any project
we start, it goes with the plan.
It's like assessment and planning
model development and training,
integration and deployment and
optimization under the expansion.
So when it comes to the first
one, the assessment and planning.
So what it does like in an assessment and
planning, we evaluate the current document
process, identify the pain points, and
define specific objective goals for
the mission learning implementation.
Determine which document types
and the number of the workflow,
the type of the workflows will
benefit from the automation.
It can be workflows when I mentioned
like the type of the workflow,
whether it's automated or it's a
diamond or it should based or it's
trigger based on other action.
Or it can be like a business B2B
workflows, or it can be like a customized
workflows or connecting workflows
triggered based on another workflow.
So this kind of the automation benefit
this kind of workflows which will
benefit for most of the automation
from the most, from the automation.
When it comes to the model
development and training.
So in this model development and training
this is the next sta this is next stage
to the assessment and the planning.
In this model development, we we
start with what we gather the, and
what we plan in the first to phase
of the assessment and planning.
In this model, we completely
concentrate on developing and
training Azure methodology models.
Specific to your document types
and the business requirements here.
So here we don't do, again analysis.
We will just do an improvement
in case of any assessment
according to the development.
But all the assessment will happen at
the fastest stage, and the planning
will happen at the fastest stage.
So in this development we just
train the Azure methodology model
specific to the document types
and the business requirement.
This includes the data extraction models.
And the classification systems and
the compiling verification tools.
And next comes to the, once the
development, once assessment
and the planning is completed,
and we once we complete the
development and training, then what?
Then it's like the integration
and we have to deploy some
where what we develop, right?
So the develop integration deployment,
integrate the Azure machine learning
solution with the existing document
management systems and the workflows
that has been developed in the.
Second stage of the model development
and training, deploy those models
to the production environments or
from the lower environments to the
upper environments with appropriate
monitoring and the security controls.
Once this deployment is completed,
we will go to the next process
of the step like optimization and
how we can expand this process.
Like that, what we have done from
the assessment and planning and
building the development and after the
integration and develop deployment.
So we have to see where we can expand this
kind of solutions into the other system.
Like continuously optimization.
What is an optimization?
It's like continuously improvise the
model accuracy and expand implementation
to additional document types and business
processes based on measured results.
Conclusion.
Conclusion and revolutionizing
the document management.
It is enhanced operational in
revolutionizing the document management.
Here in this section, you'll see how the
enhanced operational efficiency improved
compile, and we discuss and data driven
insights and superior customer experience.
The customer experience is the most
important thing for all the work
we have done through this mission.
Learning for the document
management system.
So for anything the customer experience
is the most top priority in the project.
So enhanced operational efficiency in the
significant improvements in the processing
time and the cost savings through the
AI powered automation improved compiles.
How the better the adherence to
regulatory requirements with the
automated monitoring and the verification
data driven insight, transformation
of a document data into actionable.
Business intelligence, superior
customer experience, the faster response
time, faster response times, and
more accurate information delivery.
So integrating we can achieve all
these things by integrating the machine
learning, integrating the machine learning
with with the document management system.
The document management
system which offers un.
Precedent opportunities to optimize the
document processing to ensure, compile
and improve data accessibility and
automated workflows in the real world.
Results in the real world.
Results speak for themselves
with the business, seeing a
significant improvements across
all the operational metrics.
And we'll coming to the final section
of this section, and we have seen how.
How the mission learning for the document
management is revolutionizing the
complexities and helping the business,
and helping the business
insurance, the life sensors.
And here we'll also see in the
real time how it is getting
benefited to the industries.
We will see we'll see.
We'll take an example for the
insurance life sensors and how the
AI and Microsoft for the document
management is helping because the
Share Pan Micro Microsoft Share Pan is
the leading software for the document
management system in the IT industry.
And we will see how the machine
learning impact on the real business.
So the insurance, the machine
learning significantly transforming
the insurance industry with the
integration of the yay and the pro.
Under the process of this
claims management has become
much faster and efficient.
The AA algorithms are now capable of
analyzing the historical claims data,
identifying the patents that can be
used to predict what we can predict
the fraud, or assess the risk levels.
In addition to this, the claims
processing time is reduced as yay.
Automate, such as the administrative work,
providing the faster claim resolutions.
Mission learning also improves the
customer satisfaction by automating
the responses and offering the
personalized recommendations
here in this life sciences.
When it comes to the life sciences,
when to the real business, in this
life sciences sector, the AI and the
mission learnings are used to automate
the quality management systems.
It's called the, in the life s
we mostly called it as the terms,
like the QMS, the IR information
research, and the QMS is like a
quality management systems and in the
commercial systems and the patient care.
And these are all the things which we use
during this life sensors like standard
operational procedures, which are called
the S four piece and the call pass.
Like a corrective actions and the
pre preventive actions, ensuring the
compiles and the regulatory standards
by tracking the document revisions,
auditing the reports, and ensuring that
standard operation, standard operating.
Procedures, SOPs are followed.
A artificial intelligence ensures
that all processing, all processes
meet the industry standards.
This this particularly important
in industries where the compiles
is critical, such as the FTA or
other regulatory authorities.
Additionally, the data analytics,
the data nalytics, powered
by this mission learning.
It helps the researchers.
It helps the researchers
are who are performing the.
CTM is like a clinical trials
management systems, and it makes them
more discoveries quickly improving
the overall research and development.
Yaya in share, yay in SharePoint
document management system.
In the case of the, in the case
of the Microsoft SharePoint.
Machine learning has improved the
document management systems by automating
the document classification and the
analysis using Azure Machine Learning.
The documents are categorized,
the documents are categorized.
Into the documents are carrying
into the relevant groups based on
their content, which improves the
efficiency of the document ritual.
Furthermore, the workflow
automation powered by a can
trigger the actions such as the
notifications, updates or scheduling
the documents for the migrations.
Archival, archival, this
reducing the manual effort.
Required for the compiles and
sensitive industries like the
healthcare or the insurance.
The A models scan for regulatory
compiling, ensuring that all documents
adhere to necessary industry standards.
And this is how, and this is how we
all discuss about the mission learning
for the document management systems.
We have covered what are the automated
solutions for the workflows we have
covered for the compliance and security.
We have covered the agent models.
We have covered about how the, it
is impacting the real business.
And we have covered about
the process flow of the.
Mission learning in the
document management systems.
And thank you very much.
Thank you very much.
And thank you very much for patience
for joining the live event of the
conference 42 mission learning event.
And thanks and thanks for the
CONFI 42 team, for providing me an
opportunity to showcase to showcase
and present the deep drive analysis.
And deep drive investigation things
through the mission learning for
the document management systems.
Hope you enjoyed this event.
And one second.
Thanks for joining this event.