Hi, I'm and welcome to my talk
on machine learning management.
I have over 13 years of experience in
finance, digital transformation, focused
on enterprise performance management
tools and expense optimization.
And today I want share some lessons
I've learned the way in my career
journey, and I hope this will be
useful for most of your listening.
In today's Asian world, we see many
organizations focused on optimizing
and reducing expense base as a way to
improve their profit margins and give
a better return to their shareholders.
However, we see many financial teams such
as F teams struggling with inaccurate and
inefficient processing of expense data.
They spend excessive time
with reconciliations.
While strategic decisions are
hindered by incomplete and
inaccurate expense forecasting,
some of these challenges can be addressed
by utilizing machine learning models
to transform how businesses manage,
analyze, and optimize their expenses.
I've used financial services as
a reference for many of my slides
here, but these concepts apply to
pretty much every industry out there.
So without further ado, let's just.
So to set a baseline, let's talk about
some problems with the traditional expense
forecasting methods where there is no
utilization of historical data trends and
patterns to refine your expense forecast.
So with those traditional methods, we
see about 27% of forecasting accuracy,
which means your expense forecast
deviate that much from your actions,
undermining your budget process.
We see about 42% classification.
So these are pure expense categories,
categorization, classification,
and it could lead to significant
misallocations of expenses across
departments and their performance.
And overall, this leads to high budget
volatility, meaning the way when you
start off your budget exercise and
variation in.
The budget exercise.
So as you can see, traditional
methods fall of expectations,
and we need a smarter approach.
So what is that smart approach?
Let's just get there.
Now.
This approach is basically categorized
into four different steps, and
it's a sequential process here.
Starting with organizing your raw
financial data, which includes your
expense data into structured taxonomies
and hierarchies, which make it an optimal
setup for machine learning analysis.
And once you have your data ready to
go, you can deploy any basic outta
the box machine learning model, or you
can build your own custom models to
analyze that data and identify some
hidden patterns, correlations, and an
anomalies with any complex expense.
And after your initial analysis,
you can generate some insights and
discoveries using some strategic business
intelligence tools like dashboards or
even simple analysis tools like Excel
to give you some insights that help
you make some strategic decisions which
drive measurable cost optimization
decision.
Input make it.
So let's just go deeper here.
And before we go into side of things,
I wanna upon a few definitions and
way we define expense and department
hierarchies in organization.
Forecasting with machine
learning works the best.
So my first slide here is
about cost and profit centers.
And this concept I know is not very new.
Every organization, every company
out there has a concept of cost
and profit centers, but I've seen a
simple missing in many organizations,
which I wanna highlight here.
So I'll start off with the basic
definition of cost centers.
As you think of these are the departments
or in terms of data, the fields where
you book your expenses, and these are
expenses that could be generated while
you produce your revenue, or it could
be overhead costs necessary for running
a business, which includes the pure
cost centers such as hr, IT facilities.
And any nonpersonal expenses such as
data fees or sub subscription fees.
So in short, cost centers are
where you book your expenses.
And moving on to the next definition
here, which is profit centers.
These as a name suggest strategic
business units where you.
Front trading or sales divisions or
product line divisions where you produce
or make a sale and generate revenue.
And that revenue is against
these profit center quote.
Now, the nuance I wanna highlight
is every profit center should and
must have a equivalent cost center
where you book your expenses against.
So that means every profit center
has a cost center, but then not every
cost center has a profit center.
So those pure cost like it,
they revenue need code for
assuming that is clear, let's get to
the next set of business definitions.
Business definitions.
So I wanna talk about the expense
hierarchal framework here, which divides
expenses into three different categories,
starting with direct expenses, which make
about 38% of any organization expenses.
These are costs that tied specific
to revenue activities with the,
with clear ownership of where
the revenues are coming from.
So these could be personal compensation
and benefit expenses related to
people and teams in profit centers.
Or it could be direct revenues
produced in revenue units such as
license costs or data, subscription
fees and things like that.
So in short, direct
expenses are booked to.
Gets allocated to
now.
The next bucket is allocated expenses.
This sounds a little bit like debt
expenses, but here I'm more focused
on the organization overhead costs,
which you can think of the technology
costs, the it costs the compliance,
legal risk teams cost, where these
are all essential for a success.
And these are peer cost centers like
we spoke about in the earlier slide.
And these could have some expenses,
which could be confused as
direct expenses because all these
functions have dedicated personal.
So all those expenses are direct
expenses in those cost centers.
But then at the end, all these expenses
get allocated to frontend profit
centers, which would then help you.
Expenses are
then waterfall method
flow expenses, where when department
allocate to another department,
it only works one way and.
So these overall expenses make
about 45% of any organization's
expenses, so roughly half.
And that's very standard.
And then the third bucket
here is the variable expenses.
So these, as the name suggest,
are variable and they scale up as
your organization or your company
scales up and these are produced as
and when you're producing revenue.
It could be any non overhead costs that
are directly a function of your revenues.
So these exceptions are a, these
expenses are a bit of an exception
because these are produced during
revenue generation process.
So these get booked
directly to profit centers.
So this is a slide deviation
from what we discussed earlier.
I would.
So now this is established.
Let's move on to the more technical
aspects of using machine learning models.
So the first step for building
any technological solution to,
to make your business better is
to have a strong data foundation.
Is to identify your required types.
So in this case, we're
talking about forecasting.
So we need have clearly defined
transaction metta we need
historical categorization
between, it real estate and so on.
Categor expenses have to.
We also need vendor information.
So these are third party vendors and
companies that we make payments to.
And once you identify those data
types, you need to prepare your
data to be able to be effectively
used in a machine learning model.
So that means you need to standardize
your transaction formats handle
missing values in your data.
This is, in other words, mastering
your categorization data.
And we also need to normalize your vendor
information in terms of formatting and
so that the machine can recognize it.
It's a vendor information
every time you input it.
And then once you have these steps
done, you need to build your data
structures around your transaction
records, which unique such as
primary keys and foreign keys.
And you.
Required for your organization.
So if it's a financial services
firm, you might need some
external data as reference data.
So that's an example there.
So any robust machine learning
implementation requires comprehensive
data span at least 12 to 18 months
before you can utilize that to do
your budget reporting forecast.
And as they all say.
How properly your data is structured
and how it, how your math data
is defined, and how your data is
clean and all, all well defined.
So with that, once we set up your
initial, your groundwork to set
up your initial data structures.
I wanna talk about a simple low
hanging fruit use case of utilizing
a quick machine learning model
to make your job better as a
financial analyst or an team member.
So one such use case is your, is
an automated class classification
using a machine learning model.
So this is simply helping you
automate the way you categor expenses.
And with those transactions, you clearly
define your categories of expenses, spoke
before between it, hr, your reimbursement,
your travel costs, and so on.
And then you engineer your
features around those expenses.
So this could be your transaction
amounts, your vendor timing patterns,
your payment methods, and also.
And using
another use case for.
So this anomaly detection here.
So these are simply identifying any
outliers or anomalies in your expenses.
So an example would be a spike
in it to a product line unit.
And this could be a allocation
or could be a misallocation.
So this model identifies that,
and for that work you, you need
to clearly define your features.
So that would include involve transforming
all your raw transac data into categories,
your master metadata defined, and then
for your model itself around how much your
expenses are deviating from expectations.
And you can also set up.
Routing with expenses and
have them reviewed by,
and
you could also give feedback
them or help them better
identify anomalies in the future.
So that means reducing your false
positives and making your machine work.
Machine learning model work better
with each cycle going forward.
So typically, anomaly detection system
employs multiple sophisticated approaches.
They could be as simple as any
unsupervised learning algorithms,
or you could also use statistical
techniques like which are applicable
for any distribution functions.
Further and deploy advanced
machine learning or deep learning
auto really complex patterns
with extensive financial data.
And as you could, as you can imagine,
each model should be customed your
organization size, complexity.
Model doesn't fit for
everybody is what the point is.
And with those models you could
also define dynamic threshold.
So the model incorporates any
seasonal patterns on both while
customizing sensitivity controls
to allow precise tuning by expense
category to minimize false positives.
So these are some really like high
level use cases, which could be
quickly achieved and established and
make a big difference to your day
to day expense management processes.
Now let's talk about a
bit more complex use case.
So this is the time series
forecasting up expenses, so where
you would forecast your expenses.
Where budgeting and forecasting into play.
So as mentioned, this complex
selection on timeframe,
so starting with the smaller
timeframes for about one to
three months, which is a quarter.
You could use models such as the Arima
model, which is the integrated moving
average model, which is more suitable
for stable expenses such as it costs,
which are more or less predictable
and for the not so stable expenses
that compliance costs, which are more
variable depending on the business.
Forecasting,
which again, would take into account
and those longer term, anything
over one year or longer, you
might have to use an ensemble of.
For each of these models focused
on individual timeframes, you
could use metrics such as the MAPP
for any accuracy measurement.
And these are powerful metrics to help you
identify if your model is working well.
And also to give it the right feedback to.
Defining it further as you go into your
process and use them for dayday use cases.
So again, I wanna highlight that for
all these work you need to have your
data those, you need to have your data
recognized and.
So with that I wanna also like
recap on the implementation roadmap.
So starting with the data assessment.
So this goes this back to
the step of organizing and
figuring out your data sources.
So your first step would
be to assessment to.
Think about buying a
machine learning model.
And once, once you have the step
next, the next step would be to
assemble and create a of engineers and
specialists and financial analysts.
And this step is really the most
important step, and that's where
many organizations fumble because
it's very quick and easy to.
But then having that team that uses that
to its fullest extent and generates value
the model,
and assuming you have your team set
up then the next step would be to.
Deploy, deployment needs to be approach.
Don't wanna build a complex machine, wanna
gains and some champions across.
So let's consider.
Of the simple models with automated
expense, categorization and detection,
and for those full time series
expense forecasting like we discuss
in the previous slide, I would
give it on two to three months,
assuming that models work well and.
Keep in mind is to have a team, a
process for continuous monitoring
and improvement of the models.
Because even if your models are
working very well, there's a need
to refine, recalibrate, customize
as your organization changes or
especially if it susceptible to any
as.
I wanna quickly touch upon the
technology stack options available
for implementing these machine
learning models in your organization.
So if you're a small to medium
size business, there are many
open source solutions available
in the market for data processing.
Data to visualize it in a way that
makes sense to the business audience.
And for deployment.
Like flak, Docker are small to
medium businesses, but if you're a
more bigger business, there are many
other enterprise solutions available.
And nowadays all the p and tools out there
come with inbuilt machine learning modules
that you can quickly deploy and get.
Factor that have to think about those
readily models even those clouds
and.
You think about your data
integration architecture.
So you build your data pipelines
for ETL from data sources.
You need to build a feature store
for training your ML model, and then
a model registry for deployment.
And also think about any a layers
that have to build to connect systems,
so of finance, build those systems.
Manufacturing, build a
keys and
your supply chain units
tools.
Make sure effectively, and
again, like I before monitoring.
So with that, I wanna close
I some case.
So from finance.
Achieved remarkable
improvements in classification.
So it reduced its class
misclassification rate from 30%, 6%.
And in that process, an annual savings
of million, just simply from better cost
visibility and optimization that follows.
They were able to achieve 76% reduction
in processing time from just utilizing
a huge manpower for categorizing
and reconciling your expenses.
So the machine model and freeing
up the time for a team to focus on.
This was all achieved within like an 18
month timeframe and three to five, and
the initial values, the low three months.
So I hope this inspires you and
this was for you to understand and.