Speaker 14: Hi everyone.
My name is MoMA Naja.
I work as a solutions architect at Amazon
Web Services, and today I wanted to
talk about how you can build generative
AI applications at AWS sustainably.
So I'm going to walk through.
Some of the design concentrations
and what are the techniques you can
adopt when you're building majority
applications so that you can reduce
your overall carbon emissions that
are emitted by your gene applications.
So I wanted to start the session
by showing you some study based on
the data available from Deloitte,
Gartner Goldman Sachs and few other
major companies around the world.
And you might be already familiar
or have heard of this energy spikes.
That are being spiked all, all across
the world due to this AI models, right?
And we know that the AI models are
getting bigger day after day or each
month, we see a new releases of LLM from
a leading companies all around the globe.
And so on the left hand side, what
is the model training size index.
And from 2014 all the way to
2024, what we have seen is.
It has increased more than 350,000 times,
and this is this spy coordinated in
the year 20 21, 20 22 when the chat GPT
started to make waves around the world.
And people started using more and
more AI and curious about how they
can integrate that into their own
organizations and applications.
And we've seen people building
and training these models with
the vast amounts of data, right?
And that takes a more, a huge amount
of energy from all across the world.
And on the right hand side, what you can
see is the total data center electricity
demand from 2022 to 20 20, 30, 20, 30.
And you can see that, that the.
It has been quite steady since 2022.
2020. And then from 2022 it has
started to spike all across the world.
And what we are expecting to see by 2030
is almost 800 tent hours of electricity
will be needed to power these data
centers powering the ai workloads.
And we also have certain studies by
Goldman Sachs research, which they
are forecasting that 60 percentage
of the increasing electricity
demands from data centers will need
to be met by burning fossil fuels.
And that's not something that we
encourage, or we none of us need want.
And because this could increase
the carbon emissions, the
global carbon emissions spike.
Approximately 2020 220 million tons.
And that's a huge amount.
And another article from World Economic
Forum says that the computational
power required for AI is doubling
approximately every hundred days.
And that, and these figures are
quite staggering and shocking and
with the pace the AI is evolving.
We need to be responsible when we
are developing or creating generative
workloads in our own organizations, right?
And we need to think about how
sustainably can we achieve this and
get this business use case right?
And that's the main agenda
for my session here.
What, and how AWS can help you with that.
So one of the things I wanted to touch
upon is how AWS can lower your carbon
footprint by up to 99 percentage, right?
And this is by migrating your workload,
which you may have on prem all the
it workloads that you have there.
And by shifting into a energy
efficient data center that
AWS has all around the world.
And Amazon had a. Climate p
pledge in 2019 to be a hundred
percentage renewable resources in
order to, power our data centers.
And we achieved this goal by 20
23, and we are quite proud of that.
And all of our data centers are
powered using this a hundred
percentage renewable resources.
And we also.
Integrate the efficiency at the
hardware layer, at the cooling the
water that is being recycled to cool.
These servers and the machines that
we have in the data centers, and
the carbon free energy that's being
produced and used by the data centers
and all the managed services that we
have at a W Ss or optimized workloads.
So when you're thinking about creating
or developing a generat, a application
when you create that inside or within
AWS by default, you achieve that
sustainability and you reduce your
carbon footprint by up to 99 percentage.
And that's a huge number.
And I also want to touch about
the managed services, right?
So when you have migrated to or
when you're, if you're planning
to create something with AWS, what
are, what we all recommend is start
with the managed services or the
serverless services that we have.
The reason is simply because we take
that undifferentiated heavy lifting
for you, whether it's maintaining
the hardware or the underlying
networks, or the security of the data
center, or the patching of the oil.
So you don't have to worry about
the underlying infrastructure.
You can't just focus on developing
your application, setting the right
configurations and the access policies.
Those kind of stuff where we focus.
On more of the basic the
heavy duty stuff for you.
And we do that with sustainability,
with cost efficiency and operational
efficiency and everything in mind, right?
So that's gonna help you to achieve that
sustaina sustainability in, in a longer.
And you may ha you may already have
started using some of the services that
you see on the screen, or might have,
already aware of the services such as EKS,
which is our elastic Kubernetes service,
which is for Kubernetes orchestration.
Amazon petroc is our fully managed
serverless service where you can
access 200 plus foundation models
with the use of a single API.
And Petro Core is a newer service where
you can build agent systems, multi-agent
tick orchestrations that you want
to implement at a enterprise, scale.
And SageMaker has been our, one of our
popular a ML service for people have
been utilizing to create train models
and deploy models at scale as well.
The takeaway is simple.
When you have the option, when your
organization policies allows, always go
for the managed and serverless services
to give you that that to remove that
undifferentiated heavy lifting and the
opera, operational, burners that you do
not want to, and we take that chunk from
you where you can focus on your more
important application related tasks.
And the next important factor
is model selection, right?
And we know that lots and lots of
models are coming up every month.
And so when, whenever you are
creating an application you start
with an particular model, but later
down the line you will see that the
same provider has an updated model.
So this is a frequent process, right?
At regular you will have to evaluate
your model and decide does that.
Does that meet your criteria, your
business use case, the latency
or the hallucination, or a bunch
of evaluation criteria that your
organization has and once only passes,
then you make that change internally.
So there are different criteria
that each individual company
takes into consideration, such
as multilingual capabilities.
Does it need to speak any other
language than, or, generate text in
any other language other than English?
Or does it needs to be a proprietary model
or an open source model, or which size the
number of parameters and co copper size.
Or does it need to be a generalist
model or do we need to make
it a Des Moines specific?
If you need to be held more
integrated with financial services
terms or healthcare domain,
do we need to fine tune it?
So this is some of the questions that
people ask when selecting the model.
And what we see is that you often don't
need the biggest and the most intelligent
LLM to power your applications.
For example, you might not need a
cloud Opus 4.6 4.6, which is the
latest one that they released recently.
But your business use case might
be achieved by using a cloud
HighQ for 4.5 instead, right?
So when you use a much lighter
model, that means you're.
First of all, you are not spending much.
It is a, much cheaper model.
At the same time, it doesn't need
that many resources to get that
inference, which in turn means it
doesn't require that much energy.
So when you're using a lighter
weight model, it, most of the time
it says you are consuming lesser
energy compared to a larger model.
So selecting a model, which
is at the lightweight.
Is an important factor.
And next one is about evaluations.
And we have the Amazon Petro evaluations
where you can evaluate your models and
also if you have knowledge basis and
you want to evaluate against a different
set of models and parameters such as
helpfulness, faithfulness, correctness,
all the way to harmfulness and refusal.
Those are some of the
parameters that we have.
And if you also have certain custom
evaluation metrics, you can also integrate
that into this to identify which model.
Is the best option for you.
And the other aspect is the moral
customization and adaptation.
So what we have seen is when we
are building ai, generative AI
applications, we often try to tweak
the prompts in order to achieve it.
A specific output that we want.
So at the bottom of the screen you
can see is the pro prompt engineering,
and this is the easiest and the
most energy efficient way to.
Get, customize and a model and some,
and we know that sometimes or, so for
specific use cases, it might always not
work the best way, and that's why we have
a bunch of other options as well, right?
Such as retrieval.
Augmented generation is where
you connect to your own.
Proprietary internal data and you
have a vector store so that when you
are generating the text it always
fetches the data from your internal
data to, to reduce the hallucination
and also gives you more accurate data
like a customer's data based on your.
Organization informations.
And then we have the fine tuning and
then we have the full fine tuning
as well as parameter efficient fine
tuning theft which is basically a way
to fully tune the model so that it is.
So we keep the, it is subset of,
labeled data sets and, we are
teaching the foundation, the LLM,
to to give a much better results.
That's something that we
are looking at, right?
So basically teaching,
teaching the foundation model
and the parameter revision.
Fine tuning is where you only tweaks
a subset of parameters, not the entire
parameters, but in full fine tuning you.
It does the full parameter customization.
So those are like some of the
options that you have there.
And lastly, we have the training from
scratch which only very small number
of customers globally does because it's
really expensive to train something
from scratch, and the amount of data
that's needed is also much greater and.
It also is the high yes, energy
consuming and the highest carbon
emitting in a process, right?
And this is something that nobody wants
to do, but only very few use cases will
lead to explore that approach as well.
And choosing the right
silicone is really important.
If you are going for a service where
you are training your model, your
own, and you are, you want to sell.
The right infrastructure,
the right virtual machine in
order to train the models.
And we give you a couple
of options there, right?
And that is training instances.
Train are custom.
Amazon built silicon chips,
which keeps you up to 25% more
energy efficient than comparable.
Easy to instances, right?
So there is no question that is
more sustainable and much better.
Performing as well.
And we have the Rainium two instances, the
next generation, which offers three times
more energy efficient than rainium one.
And I'm also happy to say that it's
not included in the slide, but we just
released in the last rain that we have
rainium three instances, which are
four times more energy efficient and
performing than the previous train too.
So it's just.
Getting better and better.
So whenever you are thinking about moral
training, we advise you to make use of
the silicon chips to get that better price
performance as well as sustainability
and reduction in the carbon emissions.
And if you also have inference
workloads, you and you.
There is also an option to use your non
GPU chips, and that's where GRAVITANT
comes into play and it again gives
you a much better price performance
when compared to it's Amazon.
Easy to alternatives and it also
takes up to 60 percentage less energy
compared to an a c two in as well.
So these are some of the hardware
options that give you, right?
And how you can reduce and make your
applications more sustain sustainable.
And next I wanted to talk about the
model deployment inference optimization.
So these are the different boxes that
you see here are some of the techniques
that you can use to reduce the overall
model size and optimize memory usage.
So when you're using, when you're
reducing your modal size or when you're
optimizing memory usage, you are only.
Using the most required amount
of resource and energy, right?
So it is very important that you you
consider these different techniques
when you build such a applications.
We have a model compilation, which
is optimizing models for hardware.
We have model compression, which is
reducing model size, very efficiently
and all the way to distillation.
And this is where we have a larger
model such as op cloud, Opus 4.6.
And we have a smaller model, like a
student model where it teaches all
its learnings to the underlying model.
And the idea is to.
Let the smaller model handle most
of the queries efficiently and
with, almost the same accuracy as,
or intelligence of the cloud opus.
So these are like some of the
techniques we can explore and
in order to achieve that similar
energy efficiency, but also without
sacrifice, sacrificing the accuracy.
Accuracy as well.
And lastly, I wanted to touch upon the
importance of observability, right?
And it is similar to everything
that we have been doing so
far in the IT world, right?
Whenever we are building something it's
important that we observe or we monitor
that we need to create the corresponding
dashboards with the right metrics,
with the right alarms to get notified.
And the same applies here.
And we have the native observability
toll called Amazon CloudWatch, which
can help you and monitor this bedro
metrics or if you have certain bedro
guardrails that you have configured.
So guardrails are a way to apply
responsible AI into your applications.
This would for example.
Identifying toxicity or, foul
language or harmful less.
So these are some of the factors
you can configure in the cart rails.
And you can basically
monitor that in a dashboard.
And which user and what is the input
and output that you're getting, right?
So it's really important that you
continuously at every stage, monitor that.
And if you're using.
More of a SageMaker.
Then we have to DecisionMaker profiler
and AWS neuron monitor to monitor
the training metrics and then memory
info, the GPU utilization, memory
utilization, and all that good stuff.
And lastly, we have the nvidia.
So you are using Nvidia processes
that you have, the system manager
interface that you can leverage as well.
So that's all I wanted to cover today.
It's just to give you a few options
and to think about how you can
build your application sustainably.
And we touched upon using, making use
of managed services or server services
like by truck and, the base model
selection is also really important to
use the lightweight models and evaluate
that and and if it meets your business
use case, you'd always go for that.
So you get low cost and, but also good
sustainability into your application.
So we have the model customization
techniques where we touched upon prompt
engineering, fine tuning and rack
approaches that you should consider.
And we also talked about the deployment
inference optimization, things like
model distillation, model compression,
and pruning those kind of stuff.
And silicon choice is
also really important.
So if you've been thinking
about training your own models.
Always recommended to use train
for training, which gives you much
better price, performance and also
the energy efficiency that you need.
And lastly, the continuous improvement is
really, so this is not like a one single
journey or ride you build and go away.
It's not that the case, you just
need to continuously monitor.
You will need to change the
underlying foundation model.
So it's always important to
monitor criteria applications.
Okay.
So that's all I wanted to cover today.
I hope this session has been useful
and what is a couple of links to
the AWS blocks where we talk about
how you can sustainably optimize the
Generat A workloads and also AI ML
workloads in general sustainability.
And you will also see this design
considerations and the things
that we just discussed in detail.
In those blocks.
So thank you so much for your time.
I hope this has been useful session
and have a good rest of the day.
Thank you.