Speaker 2: Hi everyone.
My name is AB Kumar, and today
I'll be presenting Beyond Surveys
realtime user Satisfaction
prediction with L LMS and Telemetry.
This model realtime net promoter
score prediction using a multi-model
AI aims to address one of the
most persistent challenges in
customer experience analytics.
The inability to capture timely and
unbiased user sentiment at scale.
Dynamic net promoter score model
leverages behavioral data, telemetry
signals and text analytics to
predict net promoter score in real
time with significantly higher
accuracy than traditional approaches.
Let's see, what is Net Promoter Score?
Net promoter, so or NPS is widely
recorded as the industry standard
me for measuring customer loyalty.
It is based on a simple caution.
How likely are you to take Windows
users respond on a zero to 10
scale, and their responses or
categorized into detect passes and
promoters despite its simplicity.
NPS remains one of the most influential
metrics in product organizations,
guiding strategy, customer satisfaction
initiatives, and growth forecasting.
Let's see how NPS is calculated.
As you see here, detectors are the one
who provided the rating of zero to six.
Out of 10 and passes seven to eight
and promoters nine to 10 and NPS
is calculated using the percentage
of promoters and detectors.
It is calculated by subtracting
the percentage of detectors from
the percentage of promoters NPS
changes from minus a hundred to a
hundred scales below zero indicate.
Poor customer sentiment While scales
between one and 30 are considered
good scales, between 31 and 70
shows a strong market portion of
the product, and anything above
70 is considered world class.
This framework has been
adopted globally due to its
simplicity, but I'll show later.
It also comes with
significant limitations.
Let's see how companies collect NPS today.
Currently NPS data is collected
mostly through email service
survey in app popups, SMS surveys
and more manual follow-ups.
These methods rely heavily
on active user participation.
They're slow disruptive to
the user experience, and often
provide tail information.
Sometimes collected days, or even weeks or
even months after the actual interaction.
While these tools have become
standard practice, they fail to
reflect real time user sentiment.
The next slide is we'll see
what the companies are facing.
Problem with the NPS.
There are four major challenges
common in traditional NPS collection.
First is the participation gap.
Response rates generally fall
between G one, between one and 5%,
which means majority of the users
remain silent, so less than 5%
of users respond to our service.
Second is the speed barrier.
Insights become available only
after a significant delay.
Third, the results suffer from
severe response bias because
only extremely positive.
Extremely native users tend to
answer service and it is reactive.
By the time a team receives the NPS score,
the opportunity to fix the issue has
already passed so we have the low response
rates, still data, vocal bias responses,
which results in large customers, no
visibility and slow response, which
in turn results in the millions.
In lost revenue for the companies.
This leads to us to an important question.
What if we could eliminate
service altogether?
What if we could calculate user
sentiment instantly without
requiring any form of user input?
What if we could reliably predict
net promoter score in real time?
This forms the foundation for our work
predictive multi-model NPS estimation.
Introducing DNPS Dynamic
Net Promoter Score.
Let's see, what is DNPS?
DNP predicts user sentiment
using its combination of tele
metadata, behavioral analytics.
Session patterns and machine learning.
The goal is to produce a reliable,
continuously updated sentiment
score for every user session without
requiring survey participation.
This approach allows organizations to
transition from reactive measurement
to proactive sentiment prediction.
As you see here, we have different layers
for the DNPS model, data ingestion, AI
prediction engine, and real time insights.
Let's see what each layer do.
So first one is the data collection layer
to achieve accurate predictions, DNP has
reli on three key categories of data.
First, behavioral interaction data,
which captures how users navigate
and interact with the system.
Second, telemetry and system signals which
provide insights into the performance
of the platform during each session.
Third.
User feedback and textual inputs,
which include explicit comments,
support messages, and survey responses.
This multi-model signals enable a more
holistic understanding of user sentiment.
Some of the examples of behavior
interaction data or click patterns
and navigation flows, session
duration, drill time event.
Error events and drop offs, future usage
sequences, tele and system signals, event
logs from backend services, performance
metrics device application, metadata,
user feedback and textual inputs in apps.
Survey comments and
chart agent task scripts.
So once the data is collected.
It provides to the next
layer data processing layer.
Data processing layer consists of
data cleaning, normalization, and
structuring, timestamp alignment, future
extraction, data storage, staging.
Our pipeline begins with data
cleaning to remove noise,
duplicates, and incomplete entries.
We then perform normalization and
structuring to convert raw session
data into consistent formats.
Timestamp alignment is critical.
Since events from multi sources
must be ordered accurately.
Next, we extract future key features,
including statistical metrics,
behavioral patterns, and text embeds.
Process data is stored in a staging
layer, which supports both offline
training and real-time predictions.
Let's go to the next layer.
Hybrid a modeling.
Our DNPS architecture uses hybrid
multi-model structured, designed
to handle structured metrics,
sequential behavior, and text data.
Each model type specializes in a
different modality and contributes unique
insights into the final prediction.
The fusion of these models ensures
higher predict accuracy than any
single model could achieve alone.
Additionally, this.
Structured supports explainability
enabling us to assess the
contributions of each input future.
See here all the models, calculate
and provide it to the fusion layer.
And fusion layer combines all the model
scores and provides the final NPS score.
Let's see.
Each model did in detail.
The hybrid model is composed of
three components, core components.
First, a structure, a structured
data model implemented using gradient
boost radiation trees such as XG
Boost or light GPM, which as in ca,
capturing non-linear patterns in
behavioral and teleme tele metrics.
Second, a temporal sequence model
implemented using LSTM or transformer
architectures, which learns.
User behavior, behavioral trends
across time that a text model using
but based emits, which captures
sentiment, semantics, and topical
relevance from user generated text
Together, this models provide a
multidimensional representation of user s.
Let's talk about the fusion layer.
Fusion layer combines outputs from all
three models into a single prediction.
Rather than treating each model equally,
it lands to weight each mo, each one,
depending on its predictive importance.
This selective vein ensures that the
most relevant signals, whether behavior
performance related or textual,
dominate the final NPS estimation.
The fusion player has explain
explainable a i two to ensure
transparency and interpretability.
We apply post hoc explainability
methods such as shop and online.
These methods allow us to analyze
how each future influences the
predicted NPS Explainability is
essential for trust and adoption.
Especially in operational
environments where business leaders
need to understand why your model
generates a particular prediction.
See here clarifies why
your prediction was made.
Use sharpen online, improves trust
and transparency, helps with debugging
and violation, supports compliance and
audit needs the excess increases ness by
showing how and why prediction was made.
Finally, it produces the fuck.
Final DN dynamic NPS score provides the
ES level of the prediction and shows
root cause factors affecting the score,
suggests actionable recommendations, and
delivers insights to business dashboards.
Let's talk about the prediction
results and model performance.
D-S-P-D-N-P-S model achieved an
accuracy of approximately 85.9%
outperforming all baseline.
Models evaluated the model,
produced a low mean absolute error
of around 1.21 and demonstrated
strong F1 scores across promoter,
passive and detected in categories.
Application study is performed
and shows that removing text data
reduces accuracy to around 55% while
removing behavioral and tele data
results in a drop to about 78%.
As you see in this chart, removing
each one like no text, no structured
text, only unstructured only drops the
accuracy of the percentage of the model.
Real time inference latency is
roughly 80 milliseconds, which
makes the system viable for live
dashboards and operational workflows,
explainability and insights,
and business value.
Explainability analysis reveals several
key drivers of NPS High back click.
Frequency strongly correlates
with negative sentiment.
Short session durations often
indicate dissatisfaction.
Higher intentional click activity tends
to correlate with promoter behavior.
This insights help product and
engineering teams identify root causes
such as UI friction system buffering.
Our negative feedback patterns
From a business perspective, DSPS
enables proactive patient making,
reduces reliance on service, and
produces the realtime sentiment
intelligence across customer journey.
Let's talk about the
limitations on future work.
Despite it, its advantages.
The DNPS approach has several limitations.
It requires access to large.
High quality data sets and performance may
degrade in cold start scenarios involving
new users model complexity introduces
operational overhead and text base signals
can introduce bias for future work.
We intend to explore more drivers data
sources, incorporate advanced transformer
architectures improve cold start handling
and enhance real time explainability.
This improvements will support
broader adoption and even
more reliable NPS predictions.
Thank you.
If you have any questions, please
reach out to me on LinkedIn.
Thank you.