So today I'm, I have come up with
an unique topic that will help you,
to optimize your test automation
and be successful in your endeavor.
So before going into the topic, I
would like to thank Con 42 for giving
me this opportunities to exchange
our ideas and for common benefit.
Okay, now the topic is about rethinking
test automation, a utility based,
modern approach to manage complexity.
Alright, so right now in
software engineering and mainly
with test automation, since
it is not a conventional.
Department or con, conventional
part of software engineering.
There's still, there is lot of
maturity needs to be achieved and
there is lot of failure rate in
this, especially in this area.
So this is where I'm going to
focus and walk you through how
we can rate maximum benefits.
Okay.
Before getting into the topic,
I would like to take you through
the evolution of test automation.
Early 2000.
2000, we have a, simple and tools
like, with the limited maintainability
and limited scope it helps to cover
application of four to five screens
and with it's like a simple, it
doesn't have any help, any integrations
or APIs or any new s right.
And 2010, we have come up with
the page object model, open source
software to test the application which.
Even though we are able to progress a
lot with the increase of software in
our life day-to-day life, the success
rates still stay at the same level
as in the original days and even the
present day with a lot of technological
shifts, advancements, we have advanced
systems like Selfing Scripts, ml,
visual Recognition Analysis, but still.
The success rate remains same.
Why?
Because these are still evolving and
there is lot of scope to evolve in this.
So the right approach, we take the
right place, we invest our money today
helps us to reap the maximum benefits
of these technological advances we
are going to see in the coming years.
Okay, so what are the
current day challenges?
So current day challenges
is the growing complexity.
Now we have seen the software is
there in every minute of our lives.
Every minute we live, we are using, we are
depending on some part of the software.
So that's how the complexity of it's
growing and it needs to be more integrated
and more there is no chance of failure
because it can result in huge loss
and huge customer dissatisfaction.
So that is the, significance of
software test automation where we
have, where it'll help us to test all
these bits and pieces of softwares and
make sure there is no overhead costs.
That is the failure of the co
software is going to create us
to avoid those failure costs.
We have to have it thorough testing, and
the test automation helps to achieve that.
The technology shift?
Yes.
The pace at which the technology
is changing is unforeseen.
Nobody has imagined to this level.
And this is just a starting point.
We are just still in the
first step and right.
So there is a lot more to go through.
Long way to go in this technology channel.
So given the, this scenario, what
are the common pitfall pitfalls?
Organizations are attempting to
automate more than 60% of test cases
with first year experience, 78% failure
rate teams managing over a thousand
test cases spend around four to five
hours weekly on maintenance, while
67% of automation product fails due to
improper test case selection, right?
So what this gives us.
This common pitfall is the coverage or the
results of automation is not as expected.
Like we are expecting a hundred
percent, but we are achieving only
seven 32%, where 78% is the failure.
Second thing, we are spend in huge
amount of time in maintaining the
software and why we fail, because
why we fail in achieving the coverage
or in achieving the maintenance
health of the software we developed.
Why?
Because we are failing in
automation, test selection.
We are failing in identifying
the right automation candidate.
So that is where that tech strategy
comes in, and we have to spend time on
this strategy to achieve the results.
Okay we have seen theoretically,
but practically what is it happening
in, on ground is we expect a
hundred percent pho rate, but we
are achieving 62% in the first run.
And as the age we have seen
the previous slide, right?
So we have to keep on
investing money on maintenance.
If we don't maintain it, this
62% will fall to 26% very soon.
And then the test coverage, we expect 80%.
We are achieving 54%.
There is a huge gap of 26%.
And mainly the CICD integration, we are
still in the native primitive standards.
We are still not there where we can see.
The, our target of achieving
a hundred percent success.
And same with the defect detection.
Why?
Because most of our tests failed
due to lack of maintenance.
There is still, majority of our scripts
doesn't get an opportunity to be
executed and do identify that defects.
So giving this background,
what do you see?
So we see that, right?
There is a huge investment we are putting
in, but for less result, less output.
So that is what we call it
as a white elephant syndrome.
So why do we call this?
Because it's test automation
is a kind of a black hole where
it drains all our resources.
Because we have to invest tons
in building the big elephant.
And it's not done by building an elephant.
I have to feed it every day.
So unless there is a proper approach
to use proper environment, eco
ecosystem to use this elephant, it
is going to eat all my resources.
Just imagine you are repeating,
you are petting elephant today.
What is the use?
No, but you have to spend
a lot to mainten it.
So similarly, the maintenance challenges
as we discussed, it's a huge maintenance.
Like even, any company in generally
small software project has to invest
in 2.5 fulltime engineers with
each engineer about hundred K 25.
Just in maintenance in
the resource cost, right?
And tools and then failures, and then
technology shifting, upgrades migrations.
These are all additional, right?
So how does the annual cost looks like
the breakup, as I told you right, the
tools and licenses they cost a huge,
actually if I member team or 10 member
team roughly, it would cost about one
20 k. And as you discussed, the huge
maintenance cost and the personal cost
as I told you, 2.5 full-time employees
and a direct and opportunity cost.
So these are direct end opportunity
costs or the failed initiative costs
directly impacting roughly around two.
For any decent size of the software
team with five to 10 testers, and while
opportunity costs reach to 300 k, the cost
per test case execution raises from two
to $3 to eight to $10 within two years.
With the raising with the raising
raising, the resource cost,
personal cost infrastructure tools.
All these costs are going to add
up and it's going to multiply
our costs in near future.
So I would say this is the high and
that we spend time on the proper
strategy and we invest on the tools
wisely so that we can be saved or we
can sustain in this global market.
Okay.
What is my proposed solution?
So my proposed solution is based.
In our model framework here the
core strategy comes into play in
identifying the testing candidate.
So the testing candidate should be in such
a way that it is to, it has to help the
manual testing speed up their most complex
jobs with the simplest script, right?
And less maintenance.
This is where the strategy comes up.
So when you implement this strategy.
The manual testing resources,
the manual testing personal
could be drastically reduced as
majority of the heavy weight load.
Is taken by these utilities.
So why I would say this utility,
I can say it as a normal test
automation framework test case
flow or something I can say, right?
Why I'm calling this as utilities.
So these utilities will have,
everything will have unique entry
and exit points, unique capabilities.
Like for example I have to test a
data a data set of 1 million records.
So manual testing, manual, it'll
take me five days, six days
with sampling technique, right?
But this utility technique,
we can implement.
Forget about the conventional
testing approach.
So we develop utilities.
You take any technology you bring in
a new technology that is completely
different to your technology stack.
For example, Python.
You validate that data set and give
a result in a standard format, right?
So these utilities will help us to
solve the main pain areas of the
software testing or the manual testers,
and these utilities will fit into
our overall enterprise framework of
keyword driven, and then our standard
logging and logging framework.
That way the output of this utility
will become in input further next
utility to carry on to carry upon.
So that's how we are decoupling
these complex pieces, calling them
as utilities, building in its own
ecosystem, its own technology stack.
And then integrating them with
our life framework, which includes
the enterprise level logging.
You got it.
So that's how we are going
to scope our test automation.
We, we are not going to, with attack the
whole hundred per a hundred percent of
test cases, testing testing landscape,
and pitfall unable to achieve it.
So here we are wise enough to
choose what is to, what is most
required to be automated, where it
is going to help us more for that.
We take the help of this universal
framework and universal login.
Okay.
So with this approach,
what did we achieve?
We achieved 85% of maintainability.
It's very easy.
We have reduced 85% in maintenance costs.
And then since these are utilities
we focused more on API based testing
rather than UI based testing because
the major pain or the major failures
happen at API are integration level.
And then we have implemented
separate tools for UI testing alone.
That way we have we, we know
the strategy, like where we are
going to cover what component.
That's how we are able to
achieve better reliability and
then the better reusability.
Yes, of course.
So if I develop a utility in my
team, I can definitely use it
anywhere else wherever it is needed.
And then faster execution.
Since this is not a conventional
testing, we are taking every approach
to test database EAPI or UA layer
separately, disintegration of UA layer.
Separately.
Our execution is very faster.
And main importantly, more importantly,
it is about the sanity testing.
We are able to san test the sanity
of any application within minutes.
Sorry.
So what are the benefits
of this utility approach?
As I told you, the, the improved
scope management, it's not
like I'm planning to cover.
And I'm able to achieve 25%, but here
I'm sc Descoping my the coverage and then
I'm trying to reach, achieve a hundred
percent of the redefined coverage.
So that way I know what I'm doing, what
I'm expecting, and how much money to put.
I'm not building resources to
automate everything a hundred percent.
Just putting resources to automate
my 25% and hundred percent of it.
And then the tool flexibility.
Yes.
And then faster implementation,
reduced maintenance.
Yes.
Overall with the technology
shifts, new tools coming in,
new technologies coming in.
Since my standard approach is fixed, my
platform is fixed, I just have to, migrate
from one technology to another technology.
But my strategy, my automation resources
are going to stay safe forever.
So as in long run, right?
In long run since the strategy is good,
somebody who knows the strategy, it's
just a matter of with the latest we
have the GitHub co-pilot or charge GBT.
It's very easy to migrate
from one to others.
And then the implementation strategy.
This is like more of generic,
established, clear objective.
To say, here, establish a clear strategy
on how much to automate, what to
automate, what component to automate.
Just forget about everything.
Focus on that component,
develop the utility, and then
we can integrate with others.
So build organizational support.
Yeah, do analysis and get
the stakeholder buying.
Implement gradually.
Measure and optimize.
So measuring success?
Yes.
Key performance indicators.
So define your key performance indicators
and track your written on investment.
So in my projects, wherever I have
implemented utilities, so they
are like independent utilities.
Most of the cases where we have
achieved return on investment, it's 300%
return investment in first few months.
And then, and there are some comp,
some utilities where we had to fit
into the enterprise architecture
for the continuity of the flow.
So this is like a top down or bottom
up approach the conventional testing
where we come with list of test cases
to be automated while automating it.
I develop utilities slowly
and then go on right.
But here it is like bottom up approach.
I, first, I know the utilities where
I can help to manual testing to
ease up their complexities charts
and later if time permits or if I
need, I can build on test cases by,
by integrating multiple utilities
so that way we know where we are
going to, how much we have to
invest, and then quality first.
Teams should always monitor the
automated execution results.
But still we have the standard logging
system and the logging pattern is
what integrates from one utility.
It very easy to track and.
Okay.
Thank you friends for
giving me this opportunity.
So hope you would have got some idea
on how these unconventional strategies
maverick thing thinking implementations
will help ease up our life.
In software testing space and
especially in software test automation.
So if you need any help or future
guidance or some case studies of my
previous works, I'm happy to share.
So please do reach out to me.
Thank you.
Bye.