Welcome everyone.
My name is Ush K and I am here ready
to present one of the most exciting and
transformative shift happening in modern
healthcare, the integration of artificial
intelligence into precision medicine.
As we all know, healthcare is
becoming increasingly complex.
We have dealing with
growing patient population.
Rising cost, clinical burnout,
and a massive influx of data
from electronic health records
to genomics and variable devices.
This is where AI steps in.
It gives us the tool to make sense of all
the data and use it to deliver better,
faster, and more personalized care.
Today, I will walk you
through the key domains.
Where AI is making a difference in
clinical decision making, administrative
efficiency, pharmaceutical safety,
diagnostics, research, and of course in
enabling vision of precision medicine,
I will also highlight some ethical
considerations and offer an implementation
roadmap for those of you who are
bringing AI into their organizations.
So let's begin by looking at
the promise AI holds across
the entire healthcare spectrum.
So here we are, the promise
of AI in healthcare.
Sorry for the technical difficulty.
So first of all, AI is
not a distant concept.
It is actively driving miserable
change across three core areas,
clinical impact, administrative
efficiency, and research advancement.
Let's start with a clinical impact.
One of the most critical challenges
clinicians face in this time
is spent on documentation, AI
assisted documentation tools.
Have helped reduce medication
errors by about 30%, which is a
huge improvement in patient safety.
Even more notably, these tools
are saving healthcare providers
around six hours a week.
That's valuable time that clinicians
can now spent with patients rather than
trying into electronic health records.
Next, administrative efficiency.
AI is streaming claim processing.
We are seeing turnaround time go
from several weeks to just few days.
More importantly, AI is helping
reducing the denial rates of the
claim by 25%, which means fewer claims
are rejected, fewer reimbursement
cycles, better financial health for
provider organizations and return
on investment is typically realized
within four to six months, making
these solutions not only effective.
But also financially sustainable.
Finally, research advancement in the world
of clinical research is speed is critical.
Machine learning algorithms are
accelerating the discovery of new
treatment options up to 200 times
compared to conventional research methods.
These systems can shift through
massive database, detect hidden
patterns, and even identify new s.
Paving the way for more effective
and personalized therapies.
Clinical documentation improvement.
So very important.
You can see the big numbers here, right?
37% error reduction, 4.2 hours time
saved from the clinical documentation
burden, 93% accuracy rate.
Here we are.
AI powered documentation systems are now
capable of achieving 93% accuracy rate.
That means they can organize clinical
nodes with very little human corrections.
This reduces the burden on the clinicians.
These systems can crosscheck medications,
highlight discrepancies, and even suggest
corrections based on clinical guidelines.
Time saving is another major benefit.
This doesn't just
improve job satisfaction.
It directly impacts the quality of
patient care by allowing doctors
and nurses to focus more on what
they do best caring for people.
Administrative workflow
here, we need to see that.
Starting with the clinical submission,
the claims, the AI system now pre
scan claims before they are submitted,
identifying coding errors, missing
documentation, and non-compliance issues.
This proactive review insurers that claims
are accurate and complete, dramatically
improving first pass resolution rates.
Second automated processing.
Machine learning algorithms can now handle
routine claims without human intervention.
This has led 65% reduction in staff
workload to, for claim departments freeing
up those resources for more complex tasks.
Denial prevention, AI system analyzes
historical data and flag claims
that are likely to be rejected.
They help administrators correct issues
before the claims even leave the door.
And what's the result of all of this?
It is faster processing time by 42%
and a 28% reduction in costly denials.
That means a smarter cash flow, fewer
disputes and better relationship
between payers and providers.
The next is AI in pharmacy applications.
AI's role in pharmacy is
equally transformative.
Let's look at how it's reshaping.
One second, let's look at
how it's reshaping medication
safety and personalization.
So we are first covering the
prescription verification.
AI Systems now performing initial reviews
of prescriptions with 99 by 2% accuracy.
That is significantly more reliable
than manual clerk Check work alone.
Next, interaction detection.
An area where AI really shines.
These systems can instantly scan
a patient's full medical record,
including prescriptions, lab results.
An allergy history to detect
harmful drug interaction.
This level of rapid accurate
detection simply isn't possible
with manual review alone.
AI also supports dosing optimization.
It takes into account a range of patient
specific factors such as age, weight,
renal functions, and even genetic
markers to suggest personalized dosing.
This minimizes side effects and
maximizes therapeutic impact.
Finally, outcome tracking is where
AI become a long-term partner.
These tools continuously monitor
how patients respond to medications
and alert clinicians in real
time for any adverse event.
This helps ensure early
intervention and improves.
Overall treatment outcomes.
Moving down to personalized medicine,
p Precis medicine is all about tailoring
care to each individual's unique genetics,
environmental, and lifestyle factors.
AI is accelerating this
vision in several key ways.
Let me move it a little bit here so
you can look at the presentation.
So the first second is bio discovery.
Traditional analytics often misses
SubT patterns in complex data, but
deep learning models can uncover new RS
that reveal disease pathways and help
identify novel therapeutic targets.
Time to treatment and
another area of improvement.
Clinician decision support system powered
by AI are helping reduce the time it
takes to get the right treatment in place.
35%. That means patient starts effective
therapy sooner, recover faster, and
spend less time in the hospital.
Lastly, AI enhances outcome predictions.
By analyzing a patient's full data
profile, labs, imaging history, and
even variable data, AI can forecast
how they will respond to treatment.
This enables clinicians to
adjust the care plan early,
increasing the chances of success.
This is where is a very interesting
thing I want to share with all of you.
It's diagnostic imaging breakthrough
through artificial intelligence.
AI system trained on large imaging data
sets, like CT scans, MRIs, x-rays are now
capable of identifying abnormalities with
high level of sensitivity and specificity.
This means that they can detect
both the presence of disease and
accurately rule it out in many cases.
Matching or even exceeding
the performance of experienced
clinician for certain conditions.
One key advantage of AI in
imaging is its consistency.
Unlike human observers, AI does
not suffer from fatigue, bias,
or variations in judgment.
It sees every scan with the same
level of detail and attention.
And with the right training, it can
spot subtile patterns that might
be missed during a manual review.
AI is also reducing the
radiologist workload by 28%.
That's not because it's replacing them.
It is because it is filtering
and prioritizing routine task.
For example, it can automatically
sort normal scans from those
requiring urgent attention.
Helping Radiologists focus their
time where it matters the most.
Another exciting application
is early detection.
AI is already being used in
identifying early signs of diseases
like breast cancer, lung nods,
and even neurological disorders.
Early diagnosis leads to
earlier intervention and often
have far better outcomes.
Ultimately, AI doesn't
replace radiologist.
It augments them acting as a second
set of eyes and helping them work
more efficiently and effectively.
Workforce adoption very important.
Why?
Because without this, all AI is
adjusted, accommodated, understood,
and applied by the workforce.
It'll not give its fruit to us.
One of the most important and sometimes
overlooked component of AI adoption in
healthcare is preparing the workforce.
We begin with AI literacy.
This means ensuring everyone in the
organization, from frontline clinicians
to IT staff, executives, they all
understand what AI is, how it works, and
how it applies to their specific roles.
Establishing a common vocabulary
and baseline knowledge is critical
for cross-functional collaboration.
Next role, specific training.
A one size fits all
approach Want to work here?
Clinicians, for instance, need to
understand how AI can support clinical
decision making and documentation.
Administrators may focus on claim
processing, operational analytics,
or scheduling optimization.
Technical staff need to understand
how to maintain, monitor,
and troubleshoot AI systems.
Then we move to hands-on implementation.
Theoretical knowledge
is only the beginning.
Simulated environments like AI powered
EHR system or virtual diagnostic
tools allow staff to get comfortable
using AI in low risk settings before
applying it to the real world scenarios.
And finally.
There must be a commitment
to continuous development.
AI tools and practices
are evolving rapidly.
A structured programs that includes
peer learning, regular updates,
workshops, and even certification
track help ensure that knowledge
stays current and still stays sharp.
When organization invest in
people alongside technology, the
results are a smoother adoption.
Higher trust in AI system and ultimately
better outcomes for our patients.
Next is ethical considerations
in AI implementation.
With all the benefit AI offers,
it is essential that we take a
thoughtful and ethical approach to
how it's implemented in healthcare.
First, we must address fairness and
equity algorithms are only as good
as the data they are trained on.
If the data lakes diversity or
if it reflects historical biases,
then the AI can unintentionally
spread those differences.
It's critical to ensure that AI
systems are tested and validated
across diverse population.
So that everyone receives high
quality care regardless of
race, gender, age, or geography.
Second, privacy protection
healthcare data is among the most
sensitive types of information.
Organizations must implement
strong enterprise grade security
protocols to safeguard patient data.
At the same time, we must find ways to
enable data sharing for AI training and
development in ways that respects privacy.
Then there is transparency.
Clinician needs to understand how AI
system arrives at their recommendations.
If an AI suggests a diagnosis or
flags a risk, there must be an.
Interpretable explanation
behind that output.
Transparency builds trust, which is
essential for adoption and also aligned
with the regulatory requirements.
And finally, we can't forget
about human whole oversight.
AI is a tool, not a replacement
of clinical judgment.
Doctor and nurses should always
be in the control of decision.
Using AI as an assistant,
not an authority.
In fact, some of the best performing
systems are those that blend AI
suggestions with human experience
makes the most informed choices.
Ethics must be embedded into design,
implementation, and monitoring of every
AI system we deploy in healthcare.
Now, let's talk about financial aspects.
Because at the end of the day,
AI adoption tools be sustainable.
It must deliver value here.
Yeah.
So one of the most promising sign
is that the healthcare institution
begins seeing a positive return on
investment within nine to 14 months.
That's relatively short timeframe,
especially for hospitals or healthcare
systems that are used for a long ROI.
The saving come from multiple areas.
For example, documentation cost drops
significantly by about 1.2 million
annually for a mid-size hospital.
This is due to automation and reduced
errors that would otherwise require
rework or lead to billing issues.
Medication related errors
are dropped by 42%.
These kind of errors can lead
to costly adverse events.
Legal actions for extended hospitality
preventing them is both a patient
safety and a financial imperative.
Another benefit is a staff productivity.
By automating routine task, clinical
teams can handle more patient and some
number of with the same number of staff.
In fact, institutions have 9.3%
increase in patient throughput,
meaning more patient treated.
Shorter wait time.
Improved care without
hiring additional personnel.
The key takeaway here is that AI, when
implemented strategically, is not just
a cost, it's an investment, and it pays
dividend in financial savings, quality
of care, and operational capacity.
Implementation roadmap
for healthcare leaders.
So now if you're wondering how
to get started with AI in your
organization, this roadmap outlines
a practical and phased approach is
step one is assessment and planning.
Look for high value opportunities
that align with your strategy is your
biggest pain point is documentation
or claim processing or diagnostics.
Identifying the right
starting point is crucial.
Next is stakeholder engagements.
Build clinical and administrative
champions at all level and how you do
that, get buy-in early and include end
user in the design and rollout process.
The more ans they are, the smoother,
easier implementation will be.
Then comes phased implementation approach.
Don't try to deploy all
AI everywhere at once.
Start with focused pilot in
one department or workflow.
Use those to refine your system, train
your teams, and work out any issues.
Once you are proven success on a smaller
scale, you can expand with confidence.
And finally measure and optimize.
Define clear metrics from the start,
like error rates, time savings,
return on investment metrics.
Track them continuously.
Use this data to improve the system.
Fine.
Tune the algorithm and ensure you
are delivering the result you expect.
Following this roadmap
does not just reduce risk.
It builds a foundation for sustainable,
scalable success with AI in healthcare.
I hope this talk has given you a
clear sense of both the opportunities
and the practical steps involved in
leveraging AI to transform healthcare.
Thank you.