Welcome everyone.
I'm Gagan pre sha.
As someone who helped transform
LinkedIn's messaging platform.
I've seen firsthand how communication
at scale reshapes everything
from relationships to revenue.
Today, we are going to explore how AI
is not replacing human communication,
but partnering with it to make messaging
smarter, faster, and more human.
Like the Hitchhikers Guide
reminds us don't panic Messaging
is changing, but that change is
something we can reshape responsibly.
When I led LinkedIn's messaging
revamp, we moved from a rigid InMail
inbox to a dynamic chat interface,
but that wasn't just the ui.
It required rethinking
how professionals engage.
We had to rebuild the backend for
speed, scale, and migrate 17 years
of messages with zero downtime.
And evolved norms around
tone and responsiveness.
The result was dramatic.
Conversations increased, users
reconnected more frequently.
This was the moment LinkedIn
messaging became a living, breathing
network, not, not a slow email proxy.
My messaging matters.
Let's zoom out.
Why does messaging matter so much today?
First, it's the backbone of modern work.
People use Slack teams, LinkedIn
chats, Facebook messaging
as their primary workspace.
Slack alone processes over 1.5
to 2 billion messages a week.
Second, it accelerates decision making.
What used to take hours by email can
now happen in minutes via messaging.
Third, it builds relationships,
mentorship, networking, deal making.
Often all of that starts with one message.
Professional messaging has come
a whole long way from the dear
sir. Dear Madam, email days.
We're in a world of back
and forth emoji LA chats.
This evolution isn't just about speed.
It's a cultural shift.
Messaging is now less formal, more human.
A casual, got five minutes.
Ping has replaced a long outstretched
outreach and persistent group chats.
That's today's virtual office where
ideas live, decisions get made and
alignment happens in real time.
Scaling messaging is more, more
than just about the servers.
It's about social complexity.
As the platform grows, we see new
problems, noise, spam, etiquette, drift.
So we invested in
features that scale trust.
Spam filters, rate limits,
message invitations.
Read receipts, do not disturb statuses.
Scaling communication
isn't just technical.
It's cultural shaping norms,
expectations, and invisible rules of
interaction, as well as responding to
the changes in these changing norms.
This is where the magic starts.
Today's messaging tools
are already including ai.
Think smart replies don't checks live
translation and message summaries.
We've already been playing with that
in all the tools that we all use.
But here's the nuance.
The best experiences are AI
assisted, not AI authored.
AI helps draft coach contextualize,
but it's still the human who
decides, personalize and connects.
That's the loop.
AI offers scale and speed.
Humans bring the nuance and meaning,
and that's where the power is.
As I look ahead for the next five years,
this is where I think messaging is headed.
AI message assistance
will become the norm.
They'll triage, they'll
draft and they'll schedule.
But you come in and
figure out what to send.
The boundaries are gonna drop real time
multilingual conversations with tone aware
translations are gonna become the norm.
It's gonna be the basic expectation
we have, uh, from our tools, the
language and country and location
barriers are gonna melt away.
Thirdly, I believe context of aware chat
platforms that pull up relevant docs.
Flag risks as well as contextualize
your conversation is again, going
to be a step by step increase in
expectations from all customers.
You know, one platform will bring
it in and then it'll be everywhere.
Lastly, we've just scratched the
surface on our mediums, right?
Right now it's all text chat, but as.
We, we move into this era of,
uh, AI spatial messaging with
gestures, voice, and even ar might
start showing up in a small way.
And lastly, but most cri critically
AI secured systems that ensure
authenticity are going to be where
most of the innovation is gonna happen.
People are assuming it's gonna end
up being ai, talking to ai, whereas
my belief is at the end it is a human
connection that's going to be amplified
with the tools that are evolving around
us, and it is the tools that will
ensure that we can have more authentic
conversation and dispense with all
the other formality that was needed
and years before the line between
email, chat and meetings will blur.
But AI will bring us together
and as humans, what else would we want?
Uh, as, as product leaders, as we think
about where we spend most of our time, I
would say the rules are still the same.
Keep it simple.
If it takes four clicks, it's too much.
You know, build for trust,
let users control or decide.
What do you do with their
data and their inbox?
Don't blindside them.
It's trust is very difficult to gain and
very easy to lose and use AI thoughtfully.
I know everybody who's talking
about AI talks about this, but it
it, here, the guidance is clear.
It should be used to enhance, not
replace the human voice, because
then what's about messaging?
Um.
L. We also need to think about
how to operate at scale planning
for billions of messages.
But protecting the experience is
a very fine balance to maintain.
And as product leaders, we need
to think about how we shape the
culture, the norms, as well as the
safeguards for safety in place,
uh, and.
Like all good product leaders, focus
on the outcomes, you know, optimize for
message quality, then count quantity.
Optimize for human connection
rather than message depth.
And, uh, make your messaging products
feel like a superpower, not just another
inbox because you know, God knows
if we need to learn another inbox.
Zero technique for new
AI enabled messages.
Lastly.
At the heart of messaging,
it's the human right.
All of this AI scaling transformation
still leads back to one thing
that is people tools must
strengthen trust and connection.
Empathy, nuance and authenticity
can't be automated even if we try.
So we follow a human in
loop philosophy, AI assists.
Never replaces because messaging
at its core is about relationships.
That's where I see the future heading.
And you know, like Douglas
Adams says, don't panic.
Uh, the Babelfish will let
you understand any a language.
And in today's world, AI is our babelfish,
translating, suggesting, reminding, but.
We are still the pilots.
AI can chart the course,
but we set the destination.
So here's my ask.
Build boldly.
Use AI to reduce friction, but keep the
human touch at the heart of your product.
And lastly, grab your towel.
Let's go build messaging
platforms worthy of the future.
Thank you.