Hello everyone.
My name is Vanka Krishna Ramesh, mark.
Today I would like to present
you with digital identity.
With ai.
AI powered digital identity solutions
are fundamentally reshaping how
verification occurs across financial,
healthcare, and government sectors.
These intelligence systems not
only strengthen security through
advanced biometric authentication.
But also eliminate friction
in user journey while enabling
personalized digital experience
that were previously impossible.
Example, how users are opening a bank
account online in two minutes with
facial and fingerprint verification,
digital identity, powering global
prosperity, the economic promise.
Potential economic value
unlocked by 2030 through global
digital identity implementation,
75% UN SDGs.
Percentage of substantial development
goals supported by digital identity
systems, 6.2 billion apps are projected
to use digital identity applications.
We are up from 1 billion in 2020.
Example.
India's other system saved 11
billion by reducing identity
fraud in welfare distribution.
Core AI technologies, facial
recognition, AI systems, map
distinctive facial features into
mathematical representations,
enabling secure identification with
sophisticated anti spoofing mechanisms.
Examples, airport eGates
fingerprint analysis.
Deep learning algorithms detect and
compare microscopic bridge patterns
and minute points achieving near
perfection verification accuracy.
Example, smartphone unlock.
Voice identification, sophisticated
neural network analyze or a hundred
al characteristics, including pitch,
tune and to create unique voice
signatures for authentication.
Example, banking via phone
assistant behavioral analytics.
ML algorithms continuously monitor
typing patterns, navigation habits, and
devise interaction styles to provide
seamless background authentication.
Example would be continuous
verification during app use.
We can take an example.
AI flagged a credit card fraud attempt by
spotting unusual geolocation and behavior.
This is possible by using AI technologies,
fraud prevention system.
Real time detection.
Advanced AI algorithms continuously
monitor transactions instantly
identifying and flagging suspicious
anomalies before fraud occur.
Pattern recognition, sophisticated machine
learning models analyze historical data
to identify complex fraud patterns,
invisible to traditional systems.
Multi-factor authentication.
Robust security frameworks integrate
biometric, behavioral and knowledge
based verification methods for
comprehensive protection, adaptive
security, self evolving protection
mechanisms automatically adjust to
emerging threats through continuous
learning and feedback loops.
Example, a FinTech app, allowing
password, let's log in and
instant transfer via face id.
Industry applications, financial
services, advanced biometric verification
enables secure account and frictionless
payments, reducing fraud rates by
90% while boosting customer trust,
streamlined customer onboarding,
completed in minutes instead of days.
OneTouch transaction approval, eliminating
password frustration healthcare.
Precise patient identification,
safeguards, medical recognition,
integrity prevents treatment,
errors and protections to health.
Information from unauthorized access,
HIPAA compliance, health data access with
multifactor security, automated insurance
verification, reducing administrative
burden, travel and border control.
AI powered contactless verification,
accelerate security process by 60%
while significantly enhancing threat
detection and passenger experience.
Average wait times reduced
from hours to minutes.
Advanced risk assessment capabilities
for proactive security, touchless face
scans at airport customs, reducing wait
times from two hours to 15 minutes.
User experience benefits
faster transactions.
AI powered verification slashes,
processing time from minutes to seconds,
eliminating unnecessary, waiting
and boosting customer satisfaction.
Cross platform compatibility.
The unified digital identity
functions effortlessly across
multiple services and platforms,
creating a cohesive ecosystem.
Experience
reduction, friction.
Seamless passwordless authentication
eliminates the frustration of
remembering complex credentials and the
hassles of constant resets, excuse me,
personalized experience, secured verified
identity, enabled tailored services and
recommendations while maintaining robust
user privacy controls and data protection.
Example, a user logs into their insurance,
banking and travel app with a single id.
Privacy challenges data minimization.
All systems must collect only
essential information for
verification or collection.
Not only increases privacy
vulnerabilities, but also
amplifies regulatory compliance
risks and erodes user trust.
Consent management users require
granular control or how their
identity data is shade and stored.
Implementing transparent
user-friendly consent mechanisms
is crucial for building trust and
maintaining regulatory compliance.
Surveillance concerns, biometric
identification systems, risk
enabling unwanted mass surveillance.
Robust ethical frameworks and technical
safeguards must be implemented to
prevent identification technologies
from facilitating privacy intrusions
or civil liberties violation.
Example, transparent consent prompt
before collecting voice data.
Inclusivity considerations,
universal access.
Ensure equitable identity verification
for all demographics regardless of age,
economic status, or technical proficiency.
Cultural adoption.
Designing systems that represent
cultural sensitivities around
biometrics personal data and identify
representation, access global communities,
accessibility features, implementing
diverse verification alternatives
for people with visual, auditory,
or our motor impairments to prevent
exclusion technology options.
Providing multiple identity
verification pathways for users
with limited connectivity.
Older devices are restricted
access to advanced technologies.
Example, using voice instead of face
fingerprint for visually impaired users.
We can take numerous examples for this.
We can consider all the multifactor
authentication options as part
of these technology options.
Regulatory landscape data protection
regulation, G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A and similar
frameworks establish strict requirements
for data minimization, user concern and
security measures in identity management
systems, digital identity frameworks,
EI DS in EU and DI A CC in Canada.
Provide comprehensive technical
standards and trust frameworks,
ensuring secure interoperable digital
identification across sectors.
Ethical AI guidelines,
emerging regulatory standard.
Emerging regulatory standards
addresses algorithmic bias,
decision transparency, and corporate
accountability in AI identity systems.
While prompting fairness and human
oversight, crossroad interoperability.
International collaboration
initiatives seek to harmonize
identity verification protocols.
Enabling secure cross border
transactions while respecting
al so and privacy requirements.
Example, G R's requirement for
explicit consent in biometric use
implementation roadmap.
Conduct comprehensive audit.
Of existing identity systems and
define specific business and technical
requirements, infrastructure.
Develop secure technical foundation
with encrypted data storage and
robust API integrations pilot program.
Deploy to sector user groups
with detailed feedback.
Collection to validate
performance and usability.
Scale deployment, expand implementation
across organizations with real time
monitoring and iterative enhancements.
Example, pilot project.
Pilot project for
digital ID in university.
Our local government service.
The future of digital identity,
the digital identity landscape is
evolving towards self-sovereign,
decentralized systems secured
by quantum resistant encryption.
These advanced frameworks will deliver
unparalleled protection against
emerging threats, while empowering
individuals with complete control
or their personal information.
The convergence of blockchain verification
and international standards will
enable seamless crossroad integrity
verification without compromising
fundamental privacy rights.
Example, decentralized ID on blockchain
with user control data wallets.
Are you ready to lead the
identity renovation revolution?
Assess your current identity
systems and consider AI integration.
I would like to give an example of
overall system where we can implement ai.
It could be a network security
or an application security.
Our data privacy, our
data security.
We can implement ai.
Let's take one, one example at each
instance, for example, network security.
If we implement AI in network security,
we can save a lot of our team's time
and effort in, in figuring out what
exactly the fraudulent activity are.
We can reduce the numerous false
positives and increase, increase
our team performance and try to.
Increase our effectiveness, the way
in which the team is performing.
The tasks are increase our productivity.
By implementing ai, like for example,
if we are collecting all the logs and
we are storing them in a system that we
are getting from sim, if we integrate
ai, it would be much easier for AI to
go and review the data and tag it along
with the most recent activity and figure
out whether any unwanted activity or
unauthorized activities are happening.
Which which a normal
network resource can do.
But that takes a lot of time.
But whereas AI can do it much faster
with less resources when coming to the
development, we can use AI to write more
code in less time and help to validate
our, test our systems proactively.
And for any.
Leaks in the code or any memory management
or any password leaks that are happening
through code, we can use AI to, to make
our code more secure and coming to the
data security we can implement AI to, to
figure out what exactly would be the best.
Applicable solution for our environment
and we can try to test multiple solutions
that AI provides and choose the best one
that suits our budget and the resource
that we have to manage that solution.
That's all.
Thank you.
I will, I would like to thank everyone who
is present here to watch my presentation.
Thank you.
Have a good day.