Hey everyone, my name is, and today
I'm gonna talk about a particular
section of US healthcare system where
the healthcare peers go out and do a
contract negotiation with the providers.
Providers be being the practitioners,
the hospitals the provider
groups, and how can we utilize.
AI to do those contract
negotiation better.
What's the current state, the current
challenge and what's gonna be the
future and what kind of solution
proposition that we're gonna talk
about in this particular talk.
So let's go ahead and get started.
As some of you know us
healthcare system is quite big.
It's a trillion dollar industry where.
Various entities are involved and
contract negotiations specifically that
carries out between these two entities.
One being the healthcare peers, another
being the the, these, all these providers.
It's quite manual and paper-based and it's
oftentimes creates a lot of confusion.
So that leads to a payment error.
Negotiation, delay administrative overhead
and oftentimes also creates the stain in
the provider relationship with the payer.
So AI can make this much better,
where instead of having a static
manual driven payment method, we
can do some sort of data driven, AI
model driven payment contract where
the system can be much more fair.
Accurate and efficient
in the whole process.
So let's deep dive into, in, into
the talk more and see why, where we
are, what is the current challenge.
As I already mentioned.
There are many challenges of today.
The number one, and most importantly,
is a manual process where we
have to spend a significant
time to do that, do to do that.
Contact reviews, and
there's a lot of to and fro.
With the providers where we have to
finalize the rate and then we need
to put that rates into the system.
So that's being one.
And as a subsequent, because of
those manual negotiation, and
oftentimes that gets to a human error.
There's a payment discrepancy, and because
of this payment discrepancy, the providers
are oftentimes are disa dissatisfied
because they don't get the payment on
time and and leads to like unhappiness.
And the most importantly from a healthcare
peers perspective, because you have
a department who goes out and do this
contract negotiation with the providers.
You have so many people involved
doing various contracts, be it
practitioners, be it hospitals.
Oftentimes hospital
contracts are quite complex.
So you need to, and there are so many
hospitals in a particular zip code,
in, not in a particular county where.
The insurance company has to
go out and do this contracting,
and then that's a department
overall overhaul and the burden.
But but if we continue to do that,
it would be a quite significant
challenge that, that currently
health healthcare system faces.
And with that, it also creates, as I
said some sort of stained relationship.
With the providers because this process
is not so smooth and it lacks that the
data-driven decision making that we are
talk, gonna talk about in the stock.
Now we know the challenge.
We know where we are.
Coming from now, let's talk about what
are the advantage that AI can solve.
The number one being is the predictive
analysis, meaning we can forecast
some sort of optimal rate while.
Doing the negotiation by utilizing
historical data market trends
and some sort of pattern.
So that helps to do a negotiation.
What would be the future rate?
Be it, say, office visit, be it a PCV
visit, or be it your specialist visit
for a particular specialty or whatnot.
And it also gives a real time adjustment.
Because it's a data driven dynamic we can
adjust to that contract more of a real
time than somebody has to go over manually
do that adjustment, put their correction
into the system, and then during the
claim processing, it'll pick it up.
But if we use some kind of a AI
driven solution, it'll be more
of a real time, faster, smooth,
efficient and that brings to the.
Third point is a error prevention
because we are doing everything
through some sort of a AI tool
driven approach data-driven approach.
It's more of a errorless system
than to have somebody or a group
of people to go over manually.
Review that, put it in the system.
So it makes it much more fairer system,
much more efficient system, and as a
result, the relationship between the
provider and the peer is much more better.
It makes the working environment also
smooth and providers a happy and that
makes also the peer also makes happy.
Now let's look at some of the
leading examples in terms of what
are the industry leaders are doing.
So here I have taken some of the
examples where, for example, there is
an, there's a company called Cognizant
who has many many softwares that
caters to the need of healthcare.
One being the networks modeler,
where we can utilize those modeling.
Methodology to predict the future price
so that during contract negotiation,
the providers can know what will
be the rate change, say for a given
year there's a particular rate.
And the future year, the next
year, there will be a rate change.
If we utilize the historical data
pattern, make some predictive modeling
and tell them this much, a percentage
will be increased for a given service.
It makes it much more fairer.
And there's another leading
Medicaid healthcare peers health
s they also often use AI driven
approaches where they found it.
It tends to lead a reduced time
while doing all this negotiation.
And then we have United Healthcare where.
It's one of the leading healthcare
system in the United States.
They reported like $110
billion for Q1 2025 revenue.
So you can guess how big it is They.
These companies are utilizing various
sort of AI driven methodology to
do the contract negotiation because
that helps the entire processes
faster and efficient and the smooth.
Now let's take a look at the framework,
like what kind of, optimization that
we can do with that data driven.
Now the most important thing
is it makes the process smooth.
Meaning I don't have to deal with all the
paper contracts, I don't have to deal with
going through each of these terminology.
I don't have to deal with going
through each of these contract rates,
historical data manually, rather.
It's more of a. Data driven
outcomes, and it can easily be
automated into the workflow system.
Meaning if there are multiple system,
one does the capitation, one does
the claim adjudication one does the
validation, one does the clinical edits,
all various system does its job in silos.
But if we utilize.
Some data driven approach where we
can integrate that into the workflow.
And during claim adjudication, every
diff every different parts of the engine
can talk to each other, and the entire
process can be very comprehensive.
And the claim processing
is gonna be very smooth.
Now let's look at the
business measures like.
What can we achieve by utilizing
these AI driven solutions?
Now, there are several case studies
where performed where they have studied
various aspect of utilizing AI in this
AI driven contract rate negotiation.
The major ones is how soon, how
fast we can lock in the contracts
do we save any dollar value,
and do we increase the fairness?
And satisfaction with the providers.
And the answer is yes too.
And there are some case studies
were performed where they have
found close to 42 percentage.
They were able to lock in the
contract and it was way more faster.
And that lead to a significant
dollar value save on a when
this particular case study were.
Perform on a lesser number of
contract, not on a large scale.
And this also helped with the
provider disputes because the new
art system is very fair and clean.
The disputes were very LA
and everybody was happy.
So it's definitely there was a miserable
business impact and it help the system
overall and makes the payer system to go
towards more this data-driven solution.
Now we talked about the challenges.
We talked about the various
entities that they are utilizing
these AI driven solutions.
We are talk, we talked about what
kind of outcome that we are expecting.
Now, if we have to implement, we as
in any healthcare payer system has
to implement this AI driven solution.
What are the stages?
What are the steps that they can do?
The first and the most important is like.
Assessing your current state, where
we are do we use a legacy system?
What kind of data that we have?
Can we transfer the data from one system
to another system so you identify the gap
and potentially make this quantify can we
quantify where and how can we implement?
And the second thing
will be define strategy.
We have to implement some sort
of a AI tool, which AI tool is
the best to solve that need.
And we also have to establish
some kind of a governance because
healthcare is all about governance,
where data is very important.
So we set up this governance, we set
up the criteria, we set up the right
tool, and then we phase out this.
Deployment in multiple phases.
Phase one being we piloted out
with a less number of contracts.
And see the results see the
improvement, quantify that.
And once that is being done, we can
integrate that solution into a large
scale with a large number of contract
and see how that's, that is doing.
And we some kind of a figure out, some
kind of an ROI and quantify the entire.
Results.
Now the next one is, okay.
What?
It's fine.
We can do that.
What is the best practice?
Of course, the best
practice is always gonna be.
Assessing your system.
Are you coming from a legacy system?
If you are coming from a legacy system,
can we exchange those data from a legacy
system to your newer AI driven system?
And if we do, what kind of
efforts that you need to do?
And once you implement, you also
have to train your staff who has to.
Utilize those tools, how to handle
it, how to run it, how to do
this do how to do run the entire
workflow into your existing system.
And then of course, as I said,
you also have to employ some
kind of an governance because US
healthcare system is quite regulated.
We have to follow various
regulations and the rules.
So we have to have some kind
of a governance and once.
All this done.
We make sure everything is
implemented correctly and fairly.
And then as a result, what
would, what is the outcome?
What is the ROI, what is the KPI?
And we can measure all sort of stuff.
Now the one that I have talked many
times because of this manual as of
today approach where it oftentimes
leads to a provider dissatisfaction.
But if we implement this newer AI driven
solution, it's more of a fair rate.
Settings where data-driven approach
creates this this contract with the
provider and it's trend, then the
relationship with the providers and when
the contract rates are set using more
of a transparent data-driven framework,
both parties are happy and it makes
the process itself is quite smooth.
So this definitely helped.
To the to this relationship
between the provider and the payer.
And it also helps to make
the payment system is more
transparent and predictable.
Meaning when we use any kind of AI
tool, use the historical data, run the
predictive model, model the future price,
and go with this negotiation and say,
this is gonna be the rate for, say.
Say a particular specialist
visit for in our office settings.
And if it is fair, it's all
predictable, transparent, and that
will also help the provider to
understand what they're gonna be paid.
And the entire process is very very
laid out, integrated in the workflow.
Everybody's happy.
Now the future innovation.
Now, when we are here, we also
have to look at, okay, fine, we can
utilize the ai, why, where the AI
stands as of today, where we are
going, and what kind of different
methodology that we can implement.
The first being is the natural
language processing, the NLP
most heavily used in the ai.
Wherever we implement where we can.
Take any data, extract it, and interpret
to the right contract language so we can
totally eliminate this manual review.
So that's probably one of the best use
case of AI that we can do in this context.
And another one is gonna be we can
utilize the blockchain based payment.
Some of the healthcare system already
started doing it more of a in-house closed
blockchain system where the payment to the
provider or some kind of a decision making
happens automatic with a smart contract.
Yeah.
And the third one is being the market.
Adaptive contracts, like oftentimes
healthcare system is keep changing,
regulation, keep changing.
There is CMS, there is state and
everybody makes their changes on time.
So if there is a change happens,
and because we utilize some sort
of a AI driven solution, we can.
Adapt to this market strategy on the
go and implement the solution much more
quicker so that claim processing can
happen on the up to date market data.
And the last, and most importantly,
is the value based optimization.
Because AI can align your payment based
on the value of certain predefined
task, the member can do or the
provider can do based on that, the
payment can be made and scheduled.
And the last but not the least, I wanted
to end this talk with this particular
closing remark is AI is here to stay.
It will shape and help many aspect of
our life, not necessarily the healthcare
system specifically in our talk that
involves related to the provider
contracting world between the peer.
And the providers.
It has many element, integr
and the complexity involved.
If we adapt today, we know in the
future we can utilize those tools
and make the system much more fairer.
Efficient and make everybody's happy.
So overall, it'll also help the
members who can go to the provider
and get the service provider is
happy to provide the service.
So overall, this is the future.
I can see AI is here and it's
gonna be implemented in this
particular section, I hope.
Everybody had a good time listening
to me and with this closing remark I
wanted to say, if you really wanted to
talk to me regarding this particular
topic, please ping me in LinkedIn.
I'm happy to assist and help you on that.
Thank you so much for listening
and tuning on this talk.