Hello everyone.
Today I'll be discussing how machine
learning is transforming the landscape
of high speed protocol testing.
We'll explore innovations in both hardware
and verification techniques and how
AI is driving new levels of efficiency
and accuracy in these critical areas.
Okay, so let's take a closer look
at the key challenges we face when
verifying modern high speed protocols.
As interface speeds increase in standards
evolve, our traditional methods of
verification are simply not keeping pace.
First time is a major constraint.
Verification timelines are
shrinking while the complexity of
protocols is growing exponentially.
Traditional methodologies re rely heavily
on manual test creation and execution,
which can't scale fast enough to meet
today's aggressive development cycles.
This results in longer debug cycles
and a high risk of missing critical
issues before tape out or release.
Next, we have coverage gaps
despite having large test suites.
Conventional approaches often miss
rare edge cases, especially at protocol
boundaries or during state transitions.
These are precisely the areas where
critical failures occur in the
field, and catching them late in
the cycle can be extremely costly.
The inability to guarantee full
state space coverage leaves a blind
spot in overall system quality.
Lastly, scaling is a growing problem.
Emerging standards like PCI Gen five,
gen six, USB four come with exponentially
more states configurations and timing
requirements than their predecessors.
Verifying, verifying them thoroughly
requires orders of magnitude.
More test vectors and existing tools
or methods can't build to handle
that kind of scale efficiently,
to effectively tackle the
challenges of protocol verification.
We have developed a Hy Hybrid
approach that combines the
strengths of formal methods, dynamic
simulation, and AI integration.
This layered strategy allows
us to maximize coverage,
accuracy, and efficiency in
validating high speed protocols.
First, we use formal verification
to mathematically prove the
correctness of the protocol behavior.
These techniques such as symbolic
execution and theorem proving
are exhaustive, meaning they can
explore all possible states and
transitions within a protocol.
All a key strength here is
for zero false negatives.
If the formal method.
If the formal model passes, we are
guaranteed that certain classes
of bugs simply don't exist.
This is especially critical for ensuring
absolute compliance with protocol
specs at the architectural level.
Formal methods alone don't capture
real world hardware behavior, which
is where dynamic simulation comes in.
Simulation continue.
Simulation provides hardware accurate
testing, letting us observe how the
implementation behaves under actual
traffic, variable timing conditions,
and diverse system configurations.
It's essential for catching edge cases
that depend on electrical noise, race
conditions, or timing violations.
Scenarios, formal methods
may ab, ab abstract anyway.
So the third layer of our approach
is AI integration, which acts
as a smart bridge between formal
and simulation environments.
Machine learning algorithms
analyze verification results and
dynamically adjust test priorities.
By using coverage data and prob
problematic fault models, AI helps
us focus on the areas most likely
to contain bugs significantly
improving verification efficiency.
This creates a feedback loop where
insights from simulation inform
formal analysis and vice versa,
continually refining the test process.
By combining the precision of
formal methods, the realism of
simulation, and the adaptability of
ai, our hardware approach delivers
a comprehensive, scalable solution
for high speed protocol verification.
This synergy allows us to achieve
faster time to coverage and higher
confidence in protocol compliance.
Now let's look at the performance
impact of integrating FPGA acceleration
into our verification framework.
These results de demonstrate how hardware
acceleration can dramatically improve the
speed and scalability of protocol testing.
First, we achieved.
85% reduction in overall verification time
compared to traditional CPU based methods.
This is a game changer, especially
for teams working under tight
time to market constraints.
FP Gs allow us to offload
computationally intensive tasks such as.
Packet parsing protocol, state
monitoring and real time error
detection directly into hardware.
This result is significantly faster,
results in significantly faster test
execution without compromising accuracy.
Next, we have reached two.
Operation Latencies, which
is a mega major breakthrough.
This ultra low latency enables real
time protocol analysis where the
system can react almost instantly
to protocol events or anomalies.
It's particularly valuable for
debugging time sensitive issues and
observing transient faults that might
be missed in slower environments.
Finally, our 12 x increase in
trans transaction throughput is
due to the inherent parallelism
in FPGA architectures.
Unlike CPUs, which process
sequentially, FPGS can execute multiple
verification tasks simultaneously,
making them ideal for handling high
speed, high volume data streams.
This allows us to ra.
Run far more test vectors in
less time, covering a broader
spectrum of protocol behavior.
These results clearly show that
FPGA acceleration isn't just an
optimization, it's an enabler for
next generation verification demands.
With faster execution, real
time responsiveness, and
massive increased throughput.
FPGAs unlock new possibilities
for scalable high
performance protocol testing.
So at the heart of our verification
framework is the AI driven
verification core, a powerful.
Engine that transforms how we
approach protocol validation.
It uses machine learning, not
just for automation, but for
intelligent decision making
throughout the verification process.
The core begins with
decision intelligence, where
problem prob problem models.
Problem models I use to predict high
risk, edge cases up to 94% of accuracy.
This allows us to eliminate
redundant test cases, focusing our
efforts where they matter most.
Instead of brute force testing, we
apply smart targeting, save both
time and computational resources.
Using deep learning algorithms, the system
continuously analyzes historical test data
to uncover su subtle protocol violations
that might escape traditional checks.
These could be timing anomalies,
rare sequence violations, or usage
patterns that deviate from spec
but aren't immediately obvious.
With this intelligence,
we can dynamically.
Prior prioritize test scenarios based
on likelihood of exposing hidden bugs.
The core continuously refines its
strategy, adapting to feedback from
ongoing simulations and formal analysis.
Finally, AI enables semantic
coverage analysis, mapping each
aspect of the protocol spec to
actual test scenarios or test cases.
This ensures a hundred percent
functional coverage, not just in
terms of code or state space, but
in how the system aligns with real
world protocol, behavior, and intent.
It also helps identify coverage
blind spots early, reducing the
risk of missed issues in production.
In summary, our AI driven
verification core delivers faster.
Smarter and more thorough testing by com.
Combining predictive analysis,
learning from experience, and actively
guiding the verification process.
It's a major step forward from static
rule-based verification toward a truly
adaptive, intelligent led methodology.
So this slide outlines how we've
implemented supervised learning to
enhance our verification workflow by
learning from historical verification
out outcomes we have built.
Models that predict and prioritize
the most impactful test ca test,
test vectors or test cases.
Again streamlining the entire process.
So we first start with a
large data set compiled from
historical verification results.
This includes both
passing and failing cases.
What sets our approach apart?
Is the expert driven classification
of past defects, which provides
meaningful context and labels
for the learning process.
This label data gives the model a
deep understanding of what constitutes
a meaningful protocol violation and
what patterns typically lead to them.
For each protocol, we use custom neural
network architectures tuned to unique.
Characteristics of that network,
such as timing parameters or timing
patterns like you call it, sequence
behavior or encoding anomalies.
We also apply advanced hyper parameter
tuning to optimize for both prediction
accuracy and model generalization,
ensuring that the model isn't just
memorizing past failures, but truly
learning how to anticipate new ones.
Once trained, these models are
deployed via lightweight inference
engines within the en, within
the verification environment.
They identify high yield test vectors,
those most likely to uncover bugs
with an impressive 97% precision.
And because this is a self-improving
system, it continuously.
Updates and refines its predictions with
every new round of verification data.
This creates a closed learning loop that
gets smarter and more efficient over time.
In summary, our supervised
learning implementation transforms
historical verification knowledge
into real time predictive power.
It's a strategic upgrade from
reactive testing to proactive,
intelligent verification, ensuring
we spend time where it matters most.
I.
So one of the most time consuming aspects
of protocol verification is generating
effective and comprehensive test cases.
A solution uses machine learning powered
test generation, which significantly out.
Outperforms traditional,
manual or rule-based methods.
Traditionally, test generation
relies on expert written scenarios
or constrained random techniques.
These methods can be slow,
redundant, and often mis edge
cases, especially in high complex
protocols with massive state spaces.
Our system uses machine learning
algorithms to learn from prior test
results and protocol specifications.
It automatically generates test cases
that are both relevant and high impact,
focusing on areas likely to reveal
hidden bugs or unverified behavior.
What sets our approach apart is that
it excels in both volume and precision.
We are able to generate far more test
vectors in a short time while maintaining
a high signal to noise ratio, meaning
fewer redundant or low value tests.
This leads to more efficient
simulations, faster coverage
closure, and a higher likelihood
of uncovering critical bugs early.
The system also adapts as as verification
progresses dynamically adjusting
its output based on gaps in coverage
and feedback from failed tests.
It's a li, it's a living learning
test generator that evolves with the
design and verification process itself.
In summary, our automated test generation
system delivers smarter, faster, and
more complex, a more complete coverage f
freeing engineering teams from repetitive
test development and allowing them to
focus on deeper analysis and debugging.
So this this slide breaks down the
custom neural network architecture we've
designed for protocol verification.
It's built from a ground up to
handle the unique demands of high
speed interface testing, combining
deep learning techniques with
protocol specific intelligence.
So the first part is the input layer.
The input layer is ca carefully crafted to
capture a rich and relevant feature set.
It includes protocol specific
PA parameters, such as encoding
schemes, error checking rules,
and RU and flow control.
We also feed in precise timing and
synchronization data, essential for
identifying timing related violations.
Another key input is the
vector of state transitions.
These represent the full
behavior model of the.
Of the protocol, allowing the network
to understand expected sequences.
Finally, we aggregate historical defect
patterns, giving the model context
from past issues and their signatures.
Next we look at the hidden layers.
In the hidden layers.
We leverage a mix of
deep learning techniques.
So we look at T cns, which is the
temporal conation networks that are
used for pattern recognition across
time series data, which is typical
in waveform and transaction streams.
Bidirectional LLS TMS allow the model
to understand protocol behavior in
both forward and backwards sequence
flows critical for protocols with.
Complex handshake or error recovery.
Multi-head attention.
MEChA mechanisms help the model focus
on specific parts of the sequence,
such as state transitions, where
violations are most likely to occur.
We also use fully connected layers
in high dimensions to allow the allow
for complex feature interactions and
decision making at a semantic level.
So lastly, the output layer.
This layer supports multi key verification
tasks, such as prioritizing test vector
generation with each test ranked by
a confidence scoreboard on predicted.
Impact and risk predictive coverage
mapping which highlights which parts
of the protocol spec are insufficiently
tested or missing altogether, real
time violation detection, where
the model can flag anomalies as
they occur during simulation.
And a statistical probability
distribution for likely defect types of
protocol failure categories, enabling
smarter debugging and reporting.
This architecture isn't just about
prediction, it's about driving.
Actionable intelligence into
the verification process.
It helps us test smarter, identify issues
earlier, and ultimately ensure high
protocol reliability and compliance.
Yeah, this is just a slide which
talks about specific results of
different protocols like PCIE five,
USP four, ddr, R five H, DM I 2.1.
The different protocols.
These are all the high speed.
Protocols that have, that
are being used in these days.
And, how we have been able to reduce the
time that is needed for like generating,
or basically testing, like generating, as
well as testing out all these different
cases as we have, as I have explained in
the previous slides it also gives you a
chart of how coverage, where, how much
of coverage we get out of our our the.
The neural network that I was talking
about, the algorithms that we've put
in place, so how it actually helps
with coverage and also bug detection.
With this, instead of going in for east
spins are generally so expensive, this
is very good for bug detection because
you keep running, you keep learning.
The system keeps learning and keeps
running those tests, which have
which have sourced bugs in the past.
So it's a good repetitive process of
finding out where the bugs really recite
and regressing the system further.
So in this slide, we focus on how
feature selection is handled by
our AI driven verification system.
Feature selection is critical for
ensuring we focus on the most impactful
protocol parameters, enabling more
efficient and effective testing.
First, we use advanced machine
learning algorithms to analyze
the protocol specifications.
The goal is to automatically identify
and extract the most critical
parameters that need to be verified.
These could include packet
types, state transitions, timing
sequences, or error conditions.
By intelligently focusing on these key
parameters, we reduce the amount of
irrelevant data being processed, ensuring
a more targeted verification approach.
The system then moves to correl
correlation detection, where it
uncovers complex relationships
between verification variables.
For example, it might find that certain
protocol violations only happen under
specific timing conditions, or when
specific combinations of inputs occur.
Recognizing these interdependencies allows
the system to generate tests that explore
edge cases, scenarios that are critical,
but often missed in conventional testing.
Once correlations are detected, the
system applies feature ranking to
prioritize verification parameters.
Each parameter is ranked based on its
impact on overall protocol coverage
and its potential to uncover defects.
This ensures that the most critical
parameters are tested first, improving
the efficiency and effectiveness
of the verification process.
Finally, the system is self-optimizing.
It continually refines its
feature selection strategy
as verification progresses.
With each test, itration, new insights are
incorporated, allowing the system to adapt
and evolve its approach based on real.
Real time findings.
This dynamic refinement allows, ensures
that the test coverage always remains
comprehensive and test resources are
directed where they're needed most.
In summary, feature selection intelligence
enhances our verification process by
ensuring that we focus on the most
critical parameters and edge cases.
This intelligent data driven
approach leads to smarter testing,
better coverage, and ultimately
more reliable protocol validation.
Okay.
Lastly this is in conclusion as we look
to the future, the role of AI and machine
learning in hardware verification will
only continue to grow, making the process
smarter, faster, and more adaptable.
Let's explore three key trends shaping the
next generation of hardware verification.
First, we are moving towards enhanced
ML integration, especially with
the use of reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning will allow
our verification systems to self
optimize over time learning.
Self optimize over time learning the
most efficient test strategies based
on feedback from each test cycle.
In addition, predictive models will
advance to a point where they can
anticipate potential design flaws before
a protocol can even be implemented,
reducing costly post design fixes.
Essentially this means we'll catch issues
earlier, saving both time and resources,
while improving design reliability.
Another exciting development is
cross protocol intelligence as
different protocol types evolve.
Like ethernet P-C-I-E-U-S-P, we will
see knowledge transfer between domains.
This means insights gained from.
Verifying one protocol can be
applied to another, accelerating
the entire verification process Over
time we'll start seeing universal
verification patterns emerge.
Simplifying the testing process across
diverse interface types and making
it easier to validate new protocols.
Finally, we are heading toward a
verification driven design paradigm.
AI Insights will no
longer be a afterthought.
Tale.
Actively guide hardware design from the
outset by shifting verification left.
In other words, moving it earlier in
the development timeline, designers will
have instant feedback on the robustness
and correctness of their designs.
This will not only help to
identify issues earlier.
But also drive more reliable,
optimized hardware from the very
beginning of the design process.
So in conclusion, the hardware.
The future of the hardware verification
is deeply intertwined with AI
and ml enhanced ML integration.
Cross-functional intelligence and a
verification driven design approach
will re revolutionize how we approach
hardware validation leading to faster,
smarter, and more reliable designs.
Thank you for your time.