Good morning or good afternoon everyone.
My name is Kuman and I bring with me
over 15 years of experience in robust
scalable enterprise applications.
I'm currently working as a
manager at Cognition Technology
Solutions US Core, where I lead
innovative technology solutions to
solve complex business problems.
Today I'm excited to be here
to present my conference on.
Transforming supply chain, smart
logistics and fleet management
through event driven microservices.
Today I'm going to walk you through how
we can transform supply chain operations
using event driven microservices, a
scalable, intelligent, and architecture
that's already delivering measurable
impact in logistics and fleet management.
We are going to move beyond buzzwords
and look at real world outcomes, lower
costs, faster operations, and smart
additions, all enabled by modern tools
like Kafka, Kubernetes, and Springboard.
The problem with traditional mic,
traditional logistic systems.
Let's start with the reality Logistics
operations are under intense preserve.
High delivery expectations, rising
fuel costs and complex urban routing.
At 60 to 80% of IT budgets in this sector
go toward maintaining legacy systems.
These monolithic systems are
slow to update, often taking four
to six hours of minor changes,
vulnerability, vulnerable to downtime.
Two to three hours per update cycle.
Poor at scaling performance drops
drastically beyond thousand users.
And on top of that, and on top of that,
data security concerns and
lack of digital readiness make,
transform make transformation.
Incredibly difficult
for this.
We have designed our
solution into microservices.
Why microservices even microservices.
Because microservices enabled
independent deployment fee.
Deployment of features can scale
dynamically based on demand.
And also our fault.
Fault, tolerant.
And resilient.
Although real time evil processing,
which is crucial for logistics, we
have built this using Spring Boot
for modular development, Kafka
for event streaming and Kubernetes
for auto scaling and resilience.
Event driven, a architecture,
high correlation accuracy, low
latency and disruption detection,
core use cases, fleet and logistic
modernizations among them.
One is real time GPS
tracking implementation.
Traditional GPS systems
are passive and often lag.
We implemented a hybrid active
passive tracking model that provides
five to 10 meter accuracy in cities
and 15 to 20 meters in rural areas.
Kafka processes up to 25,000 updates per
vehicle per hour with 95% transmission
success even in poor signal areas.
And coming to Edge, competing
for traffic management.
Our edge competing setup processes,
vehicle speed behavior, and violations on
the edge, not on the, not in the cloud.
That is 85 milliseconds.
Response for speed violations, one 20
milliseconds for complex vehicle behavior.
This reduces false alarms and.
Cuts bandwidth usage by up to 78%.
EEA route optimization.
We use historical data, realtime traffic,
and customer windows to dynamically
reroute delivery deliveries with a
result of 40% pasture road planning,
25% more deliveries per vehicle.
Up to 20% reduction in the vary costs.
What is the performance
and business impact?
Here is the results.
We are seeing 45% reduction in
vehicle breakdowns, 25% lower
in maintenance costs, 98.5%.
Fleet tracking accuracy drivers
improved to 35% better driving behavior.
30% fewer accidents and 20%
drop in insurance premiums.
All told for a fleet of a
hundred vehicles, this system
saved over three 50 K annually.
Just from fuel and maintenance
warehouse and urban logistic improvements.
Smart logic sticks isn't
just about vehicles.
It's about warehouses too.
We reduce picking times by 38% in
by 38% in using intelligent order.
Batching improved space utilization
by 42% through realtime inventory
management and in carbon delivery.
Last mile delivery cost dropped by 30%.
Carbon emissions reduced by 28%.
Thanks to intelligent road planning and
load consolidation, the scalability and
reliability and architecture benefits.
Let's talk about the infrastructure.
Our Kubernetes based architecture
allows horizonal scaling Autoscale spots
between three to 10 instances, maintains
70% CPU usage, cost optimization.
Ensurers, 99.95 uptime
even during updates.
We also use service shedding to prevent
cascading failures, active replication to
recover from outages in under 30 seconds.
That is what modern
resilience look like, right?
Even driven microservices
are not just a tech trend.
They are strategic advantage in the
digital supply chain by shifting
monolithic to modular systems.
From static to real time processing,
and from human guesses to a additions.
We are all reshaping the way
goods move through the world.
This transmission is not optional, it's
essential, and it's already happening.
Thank you so much.