Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, mission Learning 2025.
I am Vishnu
Today.
Today I'm discussing about quantum
computing encryption trends
in cybersecurity as quantum
computing advances traditional
encryption methods like RSA and
ECC facing unpredicted challenges.
This presentation.
Explore how the cybersecurity
landscape is evolving to address
quantum thread, focusing on quantum
safe encryption methods that
will protect our digital future.
We will examine vulnerabilities
in current systems, explore forced
quantum cryptography approaches.
And discuss how organizations are
preparing for all where quantum
computers would break encryption.
The quantum thread to
traditional encryption.
Yeah, traditional encryption.
Mainly we are using.
R, SA and ECC RSA and ECC.
Vulnerabilities like the current
encryption system depends on mathematical
challenges that classical computers
find unstoppable, but quantum computers
can potentially solve this relatively
easy mathematical foundation.
Yep.
Current traditional encryption, RSA.
Depends on computational difficulty
of factoring large prime products.
While ECC protection lays on the
complexity of solving discrete
algorithms within elliptical curves
source algorithm, this groundbreaking
quantum algorithm it breaks both RSA
and ECC encryption by solving their
underlining mathematical problems.
Exponentially faster than
any classical approach.
First, quantum cryptography.
PQC, it's aims to develop encryption
methods secure against both classical
and quantum computer attacks.
These approaches can implemented
on current systems, allowing
for smoother transactions as
quantum computing advances.
Yeah.
One of the method is code based
cryptography based on difficulties
of decoding general linear codes.
Yep.
Now it it uses error correcting codes
to create secure cryptographic systems.
It's based on difficulties of
decoding messages that have been
purposefully corruption with errors.
The security of the systems relates
relates on the hardness of the certain
coding theory problems like syndrome
decoding and learning parity with noise.
And next one, ASH based signatures.
It's leverages quantum assist
cryptographic ash functions.
It is a type of digital signature
scheme that utilizes as ash
functions as core component
offering forced quantum security.
These signatures are promising
alternative to traditional digital
signatures, which are vulnerable
to attacks from quantum computers.
Hash based signatures are designed to
be secure, even in presence of quantum
computers by relaying on hardness of
hash functions rather than mathematical
problems like in factorization.
Yeah.
One more method is lattice
based cryptography.
It relates on hard lattice
problems on quantum solving.
Lattice.
Basic cryptographic systems are a whole
class of systems based on hard questions
around spaces formed by commanding set
of vectors for to form new vectors.
All new vectors you can form by
this combination are called lattice.
A lattice is usually usually
introduced as a 2D or 3D vectors.
Because you can draw pictures
that can make some institu sense.
In practice, the number of variables
of vectors can be arbitrary,
and for a cryptography, they
are much greater than three.
Your quantum decision security
is a desire to withstand both
classical and quantum attacks.
Yeah, first quantum cryptography
advantages and challenges.
Some advantages are it's a
robust protection against
future quantum quantum threats.
Seamless integration with existing
classical computing infrastructure was
still cryptographic approaches tailored
to specific security requirements.
Yeah, it's a continuous innovation through
extension, economic and industry research.
Yeah.
Now you forced to quantum cryptography
will have some challenges significantly.
It's increases processing
power and memory requirements.
Expanded key sizes leading to potential
bandwidth and storage constraints.
Necessity for rigorous ongoing crypto
analysis to verify quantum resistance,
complex standardization process and
organizational adoption barriers
co comparing traditional versus
forced quantum approaches.
Yeah in security aspect.
Traditional cryptography mainly
depends on mathematical problems like
factoring and discrete aga algorithms.
First, quantum cryptography.
You say quantum resist problems.
Lattice problem coding theory,
quantum vulnerabilities.
Highly vulnerable to so algorithm,
solar algorithm can easily break
traditional mathematical problems.
First quantum cryptography, it's designed
to resist quantum attacks, efficiency.
Generally ENT on classical
computers first content may require
more computational resources.
Key sizes in traditional, relatively
small in first, quantum encryption
is often large, larger impacting
storage and transmission maturity.
Yet traditional RSA and ECCR
well-established extensively
studied forced quantum cryptography
near under undergoing active
research and standardization.
Quantum key distribution.
How we distribute quantum
keys from sender to receiver.
Let's how analysis a sender is the
receiver unless in course random binary
data into quantum states transmit these
photons to Bob, leveraging fundamental
quantum mechanical properties.
Measurement and safety.
Safety.
Bob measures incoming photons using
randomly selected measurement basis.
Both parties then compare their
basis choice choices or classical
channel returning only matching
measurement to family shared key
error de error detection and correction.
The parties analyze error rates to detect
potential error dropping, then employ
classical error correction protocols
and privacy amplification to distill
final, secure, cryptographic key.
Yeah, the system's key advantage
is that any interruption
attempt, attempted disturbs.
The quantum states making is immediately
detectable through increase error rate.
Quantum key implementation and challenges
current implementations or China 2000
kilometers based in Shanghai Quantum
Link, satellite based quantum key
distribution, demonstrate expanding range.
Integration with adjusting fiber
optic networks, technical limitations,
distant limitations due to
quantum state degradation.
Slower key generation rate
compared to classical methods.
Specialized hardware
requirement, increasing costs,
practical challenges.
Vulnerabilities to side channel
attacks and classical components.
Integration difficulties with
existing network infrastructure.
Scaling issues for widespread deployment,
needs standardization efforts.
Needs to launch first quantum cryptography
standardization process on 2016.
It is calling for algorithm proposal
from the global cryptographic
community from 2017 to 2022.
N did rigorous evaluation and public
cru scrutiny narrowed down to candidates
based on security performance and
implementation characteristics.
First selection, NIST announced first
set of selected algorithms on July, 2022.
Crystals kyber for encryption
crystals, d, lithium, falcon, and
S effects for digital signatures.
Yeah.
Crystal Skyr for encryption.
Crystal's de lithium s are
lattice base with Shan performance
and reasonable key sizes.
Parcon offers compact lattice base
signatures while Phoenix plus proves
con conservate ash based approach
with strong security assurance.
Yeah.
The strength of each key.
Adoption challenges in organization,
if you want organization will face
some challenges with the to adapt to,
to adopt first quantum encryption.
Crypto cryptography, legacy system.
Compatibility.
Yeah.
In integrating quantum resist
algorithms with existing infrastructure
without operational distribution.
Disturbs performance concerns,
addressing increases competitional
overhead and bandwidth
requirement from larger key sizes.
Transition.
Period.
Period risks managing hybrid
implementation that maintain security
during the migration from classical to
first quantum protocols, global education
and training, developing specialized
cryptographic expertise to ensure
correct implementation and management.
Organizations face challenges in
transmission forced quantum cryptography.
This evaluation requests balancing
immediate security requirement against
future quantum threats while navigating
complex technical limitations.
Operational constraints, knowledge gaps.
Success demands a coordinated global
approach to ensure interpretability
and comprehensive protection
across digital ecosystems.
Future proofing encryption systems.
Hybrid approaches.
Commanding, classical and forced
quantum algorithms provides immediate
enhanced security against both
traditional and quantum threats, while
enabling a smooth transition period.
This complete systems
offers fallback security.
If vulnerabilities are discovered
in the newer algorithms, security
principles future proof systems
must maintain or enhance.
Fundamental security principles
like confidentiality,
integrity, and availability.
Sta strategic implementation
organization should adopt forward
looking approach to address our rest New
decrypt letter thread While carefully
testing first quantum algorithms.
Before full deployment to avoid
introducing new vulnerabilities
or performance issues.
Yeah.
Thank you all.