Good morning, good afternoon,
good evening everyone.
I am Cypress, the Moala.
I'm working as a enterprise architect
IN Focus INC, and today I will walk you
through how GPU accelerated A I at hs.
Not only delivering up to 15 X
performance gains, but it is also
solving one of the biggest challenges
in enterprise computing today.
Balancing performance
with data sovereignty.
Imagine a wind turbine in remote field.
It's equipped with sensor
monitoring, vibration, temperature,
and blade speed in real time.
Now, imagine that turbine analyzing
all that data on onsite in
milliseconds predicting failure
before they happen without sending
a single bite to the cloud.
This is not a science fiction.
It's HAA in action powered by GPU
acceleration, and it's quietly
transforming industries as diverse as
manufacturing, healthcare, and logistics.
We will explore real benchmark
data, industry use cases and
practical implementation strategies.
By the end of this session, you
will have actionable insights into
deploying edge AI solutions in
your own enterprise infrastructure.
Coming to the next slide, the
shifting AI deployment paradigm.
Let's break this down
with the simple example.
Imagine a modern, smart factory.
In traditional model, hundreds of
missions generate sensor data, vibration
level motor temperature, production
rates, and all the raw data is sent
straight to the cloud for analysis.
But this creates a heavy button on the
network, increases latency and can even
become a security or compliance issue if
the data is in insensitive or regulated.
Now in the.
Emerging paradigm, we flip the process.
Each mission is a an HAI device, like
A GPU enabled industrial computer.
These device process, the sensor data on
site, they can detect anom, analyze flag,
maintenance issue, or adjust parameters
in real time, all within milliseconds.
Only high value insights or
summary data are sent to the cloud
for storage, audit, or long-term
learnings had in hybrid architecture.
Some models might still run in the cloud,
like large scale trend forecasting while
critical operations happen at the edge.
This combination gives the business
the best of the both worlds.
Instant decision making where
it is needed and strategic
insight powered by the cloud.
The result, faster response, lower cost,
and better control over sensitive data.
Coming to the next slide, GPU
acceleration, performance breakthrough.
GPU acceleration is driving
a paradigm shift in HAI.
Delivering unprecedented performance
gains and energy efficiency by enabling
parallel processing, GPUs unlock up
to 15 X faster performance compared
to traditional CPU only solutions.
This immense performance boost
is crucial for enterprise seeking
to process complex AI workloads
quickly and efficiently at the edge.
Key performance gains.
Let's talk about 15 X performance
gain, GPU acceleration dramatically
speed up to competitions, reducing
the time required for deep learning
models to generate a results.
For instance, tasks that typically
take a minute with CPUs can
now be completed in seconds.
Optimizing real time decision
making and redundancy latency.
Less than millisecond inference time.
GPU enabled production grade deep
learning models to achieve inference
time below 10 milliseconds, even
for sophisticated neural networks.
This means AI application at the edge,
like autonomous vehicles, industrial
automation, and real time image
recognition can respond instantly.
Without delay, making them
truly real time and responsive.
Let's talk about efficiency
benefit, 60% power reduction by
paying GPUs with energy efficient.
RM architectures companies can reduce
power consumption by up to 60% compared
to traditional server environments.
This is not only leads to
lower operational costs.
But also minimize the environmental
impact helping business
meet sustainability goals.
Coming to the next slide, real
world impact, real transformation,
operational cost reduction,
customer experience improvement,
low prevention and enhancement.
The real time industries expect
experiencing a digital transformation
driven by a G AI technologies that
are improving operational efficiency.
Enhancing customer experiences and
boosting security by processing data
directly at the edge on devices such
as cameras, sensors, and in-store
kiosk retailers are gaining a
real-time insights and achieving
significant business outcomes.
Let's talk about
operational cost reduction.
Operational cost reduction,
28% decreases in expenses.
A GAI enable retailers to optimize
inventory management by processing
real time data from in the store
sensors, tracking stock levels,
and automating replenishment.
Predict two maintenance systems,
analyze sensor data from equipment
to predict failure before they occur.
Preventing costly downtime.
As a result, overall operation expenses
are reduced by 28%, improving bottom
line profitability, customer experience
in improvement, 65% reduction in latency
by processing data locally at the edge.
Retailer can achieve faster
decisions making for personalized
recommendation and dynamic pricing.
While real time processing recommendation
engines are able to provide personalized
offers, targeted promotions, and product
suggestions, instantaneously this leads
to 65% reduction in latency, improving
customer satisfaction and boosting sales.
Coming to the last prevention enhancement,
real-time security monitoring.
A G AI powered video analytics
system provide real-time security
monitoring, analyzing camera feed for
suspicious activity with sub-second
identification of potential theft events.
Security teams can respond
instantly reducing shrinkage
and increasing store safely.
Coming to the next slide, manufacturing
excellence through Edge AI A G AI,
revaluation manufacturing by providing
real-time insights, enhance operational
visibility and predictive maintenance
by processing the data directly at
the source edge computing ensure
that manufacturers can react faster.
Optimize the production lines and
reduce downtime, leading to significant
cost saving and improved quality.
Let's talk about increased operational
visibility, predictive maintenance,
quality control, automation coming to
the increased operational visibility.
Real time monitoring of production line.
Using edge devices such as
sensors and cameras allow
manufacturers to gain continuous
visibility into their operations.
Instant data processing helps identify
bottlenecks, inefficiencies, and
equipment failures at the occur,
allowing for immediate corrective action.
Predictive maintenance, 44%
decrease in unplanned downtime.
A G AI power predictive
maintenance system.
Monitor the health of missionary in
real time analyzing sensor data for
early sign of wear or malfunction.
The proactive approach reduce unplanned
downtime by 43%, translating to
millions in saved production cost
by preventing equipment failure and
ensuring the continuous operations.
Quality control automation
sub millisecond.
Second defective detection with
the computer vision at the edge.
Manufacturing systems can analyze
products in real time deducting
defective with sub milliseconds latency.
Immediate corrective action can take
into address issue before product move
further down to the production line,
preventing costly waste and rework.
The quality control automation help
ensure product meet regress due to the
combination of high volume sensor data
and the need for real-time processing.
By implementing edge based
solutions, manufacturing can
achieve real time operational
insight that enhance visibility.
And decision making use predictive
maintenance to dramatically
reduce unplanned downtime and
optimize asset utilization.
These edges based systems drive
operational efficiency, cost
savings, and higher quality output
making edge AI critical component
in modern manufacturing excellence.
Coming to the next slide, telecom
enabling 5G application innovation.
The rollout of 5G Network is unlocking
new possibilities for telecom
providers and their customers with
application that require ultra low
latency and high performance computing.
Traditional cloud-based
infrastructures however, struggle to
meet these demanding requirements.
Due to inherent network latency.
Let's talk about legacy
infrastructure, age deployment,
next generation application.
Let's talk about L Leg
legacy infrastructure.
Five to between five to a
hundred millisecond milliseconds.
Application response times traditional
telecom systems, relay on cloud.
Dependent architectures where data
is set to centralize the cloud
servers for processing and analysis.
This setup introduces latency in
the range of between 50 to hundred
milliseconds, which is insufficient
for realtime rep responsiveness
required by advanced applications
like autonomous vehicles or industrial
automation coming to the edge deployment.
Moving process to cell sites and
aggregation points To address this
challenge, telecom providers are
deploying GPU accelerated compute
at cell sites and aggregation points
to closer to the network edge.
This edge deployment allows to be.
Process locally reducing the need for
long distance data transmission to
centralized data centers coming to the
next generation application, single
digit millisecond response times.
Edge computing enables real time
single digit millisecond response
times, which is essential for
next generation applications like.
Autonomous vehicle coordination, which
requires near instantaneous communication
between vehicles, infrastructure,
and the cloud industrial automation
where factory robots must operate
with minimal delay to maintain high
efficiency and safety automated reality.
Where.
Imperceptible processing delay
are crucial for providing seamless
immersive user experience.
The deployment of GPU accelerated edge
computing at the edge of network is
making it possible to meet the strike sign
latency requirement of 5G application.
Coming to the data sovety challenges.
As AI technologies continues to scale
globally, data Sovety has emerged
as one of the most significant
non-technical challenges, regulations
around data privacy and cross border
transfer data complexities that require
careful ion to ensure compliance and
mitigate risks coming to the cross
border data transfer restrictions.
Let's talk about this cross
border data transfer restrictions,
different jurisdictions.
How, where very varying rules
regarding how and where data can be
stored, processed, and transferred.
For example, the European Unions,
GDPR, mandates that personal data must
not to be transferred outside the US
unless certain conditions are met.
Creating hurdles of global AI
deployment strategies, the complexity
of these regulations across countries
can make it difficult for companies
to build consistent globally.
AI models that require large scale
cross border data exchange, GDPR,
and similar regulation frameworks,
regulations such as GDPR impose strength.
Requirements on how data is handled,
including the need to ensure data
is processed securely, has the
appropriate consent, and is stored
within specific geographical boundaries.
Non-compliance with these regulations
can result in hefty fines,
millions of dollars in penalties.
That pose serious financial and
reputational risks to organization using
centralized cloud-based data processing
architectures coming to the governance
consistency with the distribution of
edge computing across various locations.
Maintaining consistent governance
and security policies become
increasingly challenging.
Ensuring compliance at each edge,
node, or deployment point, which
could span several countries or
even continents, requires a robust
framework to enforce uniform policies
and maintaining data integrity data.
Ty challenges are increasingly
complex in a globalized world,
especially for AI driven solutions.
While Edge Computing offers a
potential solution by keeping data
within its jurisdiction of origin,
it introduces new challenges in
maintaining consistent governance
across distributed edge environments.
Developing a robust governance
model that balance data severity,
compliance, and security across all
edge node is critical for successful.
Scalable AI developments.
Coming to the next slide, severe
security in distributed edge, AI
edge deployment, grow and evolve.
Securing distributed system
become a top priority.
The expanded attack surface in
distributed environments calls for
rethink in traditional security
models, focusing on defense in depth.
Strategies and zero trust
approach to safeguard data and
workloads across edge nodes.
Let's talk about zero trust
architecture, quantum resistant
encryption, continuous vulnerability
scanning, secure AR hardware enclaves.
Coming to the zero trust architecture,
zero trust architecture, assume
that threats can exist both
inside and outside the network.
Requiring identity verification
for every system interaction.
Whether it's a user, device or service,
this never trust, always verify ensures
that only authenticated users and
systems can interact with since two
data and applications, minimize the
risk of unauthorized access coming
to the quantum resistant encryption.
With the rise of quantum computing
on the horizon, traditional
encryption methods may no longer be
sufficient to protect sensitive data.
To prepare for forced quantum threat
landscape, forward thinking, organizations
are already implementing quantum
resistance encryption protocols, which
are designed to secure data against the
future capabilities of quantum computers.
Coming to the continuous vulnerability,
scanning the dynamic nature of
distributed edge environments
necessary states continuous monitoring
and proactive security measure.
Automated vulnerability scanning helps
detect and remediate security flaws
in real time across all edge nos.
This continuous assessment ensure
that vulnerabilities are addressed
before they can be exploited.
Keeping secure posture up to
date and reducing response
times to potential threats.
Coming to the secure Hardware
enclaves offers isolated exception
environments designed especially for
running since two workloads securely.
These enclaves protect the critical data
by preventing unauthorized access or.
Tampering, even if surrounding system
is compromised, ensuring that high stake
operations like AI model training or
financial transactions remains secure.
Coming to the next slide at
autonomous edge infrastructure,
the operational complexities of managing
distributed edge infrastructure.
Especially in remote and geographical
environments are driving the
development of autonomous system.
These systems are designed to
optimize, heal, and defend the edge
infrastructure without human intervention,
ensuring continuous, efficient and
secure operations, self-optimizing,
dynamic workload balancing and
resource allocation, self-optimizing.
Platforms automatically adjust resource
allocation based on the demands of
incoming workloads, ensuring that
computational power is used efficiently.
This dynamic workloads balancing optimizes
performances while simultaneously
minimizing energy consumption,
making edge infrastructure both cost
effective and sustainable as workload.
These platforms can scale
resource up or down as needed
without manual intervention.
Coming to the self-healing, automatic
fault detection and recovery.
Self-healing capabilities are crucial
for ensuring the reliability of
distributed edge system where physical
access to hardware may be limited.
These systems can automatically detect
the hardware or software failures and
quickly initiate recovery procedures such
as a rerouting traffic or reconfiguration
nodes to maintain functionality.
This fall.
Detection and recovery reduces downtime
and help ensure high vis availability
in environments where immediate
hormone intervention is not feasible.
Let's talk about self defending.
Prior to threat mitigation without
human intervention, the most advanced
edge systems now incorporate self
defending mission mechanism to
address security threat in real time.
These systems continuously monitor for
anomaly and vulnerabilities within the
Edge network and can proactively take
action to mitigate potential threats.
Such as isolating compromise node
or blocking malicious traffic
without human involvement.
This prior to threat mitigation
ensures that edge environments
remain secure even when operating
in remote unmonitored locations.
Coming to the next slide,
implementation strategy framework.
Successful A G AI implementations required
a methodo methodical structure approach
that spans from the initial workload
assessment to continuous optimization.
It is comprehensive framework
that guides the deployment of
AI application at the edge.
Ensuring both efficiency and scalability.
Let's talk about work workload assessment,
infrastructure deployment, application
migration, continuous optimization.
Let's talk about workload assessment.
The first opinion, any IT deployment is
to thoroughly evaluate the application
characteristics to determine if the edge
is right environment for the workloads.
This includes accessing.
Latency requirements, data
volumes, processing needs.
This assessment help prioritize which
application will benefit the most of
the edge computing, ensuring optimal
performance and resource allocation.
Let's talk about
infrastructure deployment.
The next phase is the physical deployment
of edge infrastructure with a focus
on standardization and modularity.
80 noes should be implemented with the
GPU acceleration to handle the compute
intensive task of AI applications,
ensuring high performance at the edge.
The infrastructure should also emphasize
reliability and security, especially
in remote or distributed environments.
Standardized edge node allow for eraser.
Easier scaling and maintenance
across diverse deployment locations.
Improving consistency in management
and performance security protocol must
be implemented to safeguards, data and
operations across distributed edge notes.
Application migration.
Once the infrastructure is in
place, application needs to be
migrated to the edge environments.
This typically involves refactoring
existing application to make them
compatible with edge environments.
Containerization technologies are
used to package application into
portable containers, making them
easier to deploy, manage and scale
across distributed edge nodes.
Orchestration system help manage
containers across multiple edge nodes.
Ensuring that the application
operates consistently across
different environments.
The use of con containerization
and orchestration also enhances
flexibility and portability,
allowing applications to be moved
between different edge environment
with easy, continuous optimization.
Finally, after deployment, it is
essential to continuously monitor
performance metrics to ensure that
a GA AI system operates optimally.
The, this includes tracking metrics
like latency, data throughput, and
resource utilization based on the
insight organization can interactively
improve the edge deployment.
Adjusting configuration, scaling
resources, or refining application as
needed to address real world challenges.
The future of intelligent edge computing,
the governance of GPU accelerated
AI and edge computing is poised to
rephrase enterprise technology landscape
in profound ways as the next wave
of distributed compounding unfolds.
These technologies will seamlessly
integrate into every FT of
our physical infrastructure.
From smart buildings and
connected vehicles to industrial
systems and urban environments,
embedding intelligent everywhere.
In the coming years, edge computing
will become a core component
of many physical environments.
Buildings will become smarter, vehicles
will have autonomous capabilities.
And entire industry will leverage
real-time AI insights at the edge
to drive efficiency and innovation.
This ing of inte at the edge means
that enterprise will not only process
data closer to its source, but will
also see applications evolve into
self aware systems capable of making
real-time decisions without relaying
on centralized cloud infrastructure.
Leading the future with a GI.
Organizations that successfully implement
edge intelligence strategies today
are poisoning the cells as leaders
in future of distributed computing.
By adapting GPU Accelerated Edge AI
early on, they are setting themselves up
to take advantage of future innovations
in field like autonomous systems,
industrial automation, and smart cities.
However, this journey is not without
its challenge addressing the technical
security and operational huddles we
have discussed such as data sovereignty,
security at the edge and workload
optimization is crucial to ensure
a successful, scalable deployments
unlocking transformative potential.
The power of GPU Accelerated Edge AI
license, its ability to transform business
operations, enabling real time decisions,
making predictive analytics and enhanced
user experience, all while reducing
reliance on centralized cloud systems.
By overcoming these challenges,
organization can unlock the full
transformative potential of.
These technologies gaining a
competitive edge while maintaining
the control and sovereignty needed
in rapidly involving landscape.
And thank you.
Thank you for this opportunity.