Hi everyone.
I'm Nia Gio.
I'm a cloud application architect at
Amazon Web Services, and today I'm
here to talk about the topic machine
learning for advanced AI search.
So let's quickly get into the topic and
before I dive deep into the advanced
AI search, I wanna talk about, some
of the terms that we are going to
talk about through the presentation.
So let's get started.
So what is generative Artificial
intelligence also known as gen ai.
So it refers to a class of AI models.
And it's designed to create new content
such as text, images audio, video or code.
By learning patterns and
structures from existing data.
So unlike traditional AI systems that
analyze in or classify data, gene AI
can actually produce original outputs
and that mimics human creativity.
So that's why it's the buzz right now.
So these models often based on
deep learning architectures.
Are trained on vast data sets and
can generate responses if they can
complete tasks or they can even simulate
scenarios with remarkable realism.
So that's why gen AI is widely used
right now in applications ranging
from content creation or design
to personalized recommendations.
Coding assistance is a big one.
And also natural language interfacing.
And now that we understand on a high
level, the gene ai generate gene ai, let's
talk in, let's talk about gene ai how it
is found powered by foundation models.
As I said, gene AI is powered by
foundation models and throughout this
course we are gonna reference to them
as fms or foundation models, depending
on how we get through the content.
But they're also short formed
into fms with which are these
pre-trained mass on, which are.
These foundation models, they
are pre-trained on massive
amounts of unstructured data.
It could be text, images, audio, whatnot.
And these models contain a very large
number of parameters and it enables them
to learn complex patterns and concepts.
Because of the broad knowledge
and flexibility, foundation models
can be applied across a wide range
of tasks and enterprises even.
When I say enterprises like industries,
enterprises, organizations, whatever
you call it these organizations
can customize these models.
Also, they can use their own data to
fine tune these models for specific
domains and very specialized applications
that unlocks greater value for
these organizations and enterprises.
Really cool.
And we talk about
foundation models, right?
And the first thing comes to our
mind is what are the inputs and
outputs of foundation models?
Yeah.
So we, when we talk about a foundation
model, and also when we talk about
inputs inputs can be anything.
And they're typically unstructured
data sets like we talked about,
like text, images, audio, video.
It can be code.
It depends on the model type, in fact.
And these inputs are used during the
pre the pre-training phase to build the
general capabilities and during inference
as well when users provide prompts
or questions or content to process.
So these are, this is how the
inputs is defined and the outputs.
What are the outputs of foundation models?
So the outputs, they are typically
the newly generated content based on
the input, such as, it could be a text
or it could be a translated language.
It could be a generated image, it
could be a summarized document.
It could be answering a question
that you have asked, or if you it
could be a nap, it could predict the
next step in a sequence if you, if
that's how you phrase your input.
So the the important thing here is that
for the foundation model, the output
of the foundation model is that these
outputs are designed to be coherent,
contextually relevant, and often creative.
That reflects the models understanding,
the learn understanding of how
complex patterns, of how complex
patterns it can analyze and how
well it is responding to your input.
A quick recap on what an input is.
It's typically a raw or unstructured
data or prompts like text or
image or audio, et cetera.
And the output would be the
generated content based on the input.
It could also be text, image, audio
or any that answer to your question.
Based on the learned
knowledge that it has.
So now that we are covering the basics,
let's talk more into how we can customize
these foundation models as well.
So yeah, I was talking about that, right?
Like foundation model, you give a
prompt and the prompt can be anything.
And this is the example I'm
using here where it talks about
the prompt could be as simple as
explain what thermodynamics is.
To a middle school student, right?
And the foundation model, based on its
initial pre-training or whatnot, it is
supposed to be, it is going to use all
the data and generate a response, which
is our answer, which is the output.
And it'll explain in terms that a
middle school student can understand.
So that's how smart an answer should
be from the foundational model.
As I talked about, how do we
customize a foundation model?
So foundation models can be customized
to better suit a specific task, or
a company based on, we have several
approaches that we can do, and I'm gonna
talk about three main approaches at hand.
The first is the instruction
based fine tuning.
So instruction based fine tuning is
adjusting the model by training it in
on example prompts and also like desired
outputs like teaching it how to respond to
a specific instruction more effectively.
So that is the name suggests like
what it is going to do, right?
The instruction based fine tuning.
And the other one I have brought
here is the domain adaptation.
And this makes a lot of sense
for domain specific needs.
For example if you need to fine tune
the model, but domain specific data.
And when I say it could be like
the domain could be medical
or legal or financial content.
So the model.
We do this domain adaptation
so that it better understands
specialized vocabulary and context.
It can play a crucial part in,
when it has such use cases.
And the next one I have is
the information retrieval.
So this approach could be that.
We are enhancing the model by
integrating it with external
databases or search systems.
So what it does is it allows it
to fetch and incorporate UpToDate
information during responses.
And for this process you don't
have to retrain the model fully.
Like you could augment the data so
that your responses are accurate.
These are some of the customizations
that we could do to a foundation model.
And information retrieval is also
standing out prominently for a lot of
organizations because not everybody
could effort a lot of time in retraining
for specific use cases, but rather
this will help them augment the data
as they go and not, don't have to
deal with retraining the model fully.
So it works both ways.
And this addresses the situation
that we have at hand, right?
Like, why do we customize the
foundation model also, is that using
all these methods, depending on the
use case, these allow the organizations
to tailor foundation models for
relevance and higher accuracy and
effectiveness for their use cases.
So it works really well that way.
And now that we talked about a
different all things about gen AI
and the foundational models and the
inputs and outputs and customizations.
Let's also slowly get into our topic.
And here I'm bringing,
introducing the word vectors.
So in machine learning a vector is
simply an ordered list of numbers.
These numbers represent data
in a mathematical form that
algorithms can easily process.
Vectors each number in the vector could
be like a component or a dimension.
So they allow the machines to perform
calculations like similarity measurement,
clustering classification, and more
let's say you have a customer profile
and it is being represented in a vector
like, age, income, number of purchases.
They could all be grouped
together in a vector dimension.
And so the key point here that is, has
been highlighted here as well, is that
vectors are the ones that turn real
world data into a format, like a array
of numbers or floats to be precise.
That machine language.
Machine learning models can understand
and they can compare and they can
manipulate the data efficiently.
So that's that's a huge role
that vectors play when it comes
to the machine learning models.
So now that we talked about
vectors what is a vector embedding?
That's the next question
we have in our mind, right?
As we talked about some of the
terms, now putting them into context.
Vector embedding is machine
learning, especially is a way of
representing complex data like
words, images, products, or users.
Everything has different structure of
format of the data as numerical vectors.
That is a list of numbers like in a
continuous high dimensional space.
So each embedding captures
the meaning features or
relationships of the original data.
Like for example similar items.
Are placed together in the space while
different items are placed further apart.
Like for example, if you are
looking at the recommendation
systems two similar movies will have
emits located next to each other.
The key points that we have
to remember is that they are
learned from data using models.
They preserve important properties
like similarities, structure, and
they allow machines to perform
operations, like I mentioned like
similarity search or clustering or
classification in a very efficient way.
That's a huge role that vector
embedding plays in here.
And the next topic I have is vector store.
And I want to talk about Vector
store using a setup that I have
by like how the vectors, like how
the for whole flow looks like.
And here I have in the setup, I have some
raw data such as audio, images documents
and whatnot is first put into I'm using
Amazon Bedrock, the machine learning model
for emitting here and bedrock processes.
This data and then it generates
embeddings into our dance vector
representations that capture the essential
meaning and features of the input.
As you can see here, the representation
is how the vector embeddings look like.
So these dense vectors are then
stored in a vector database and
in this sample I'm using Amazon
open search as a vector database.
Which supports vector
search capabilities also.
Storing a embeddings en enables
efficient similarity search.
It also supports semantic retrieval
and recommendation systems so that
users can quickly find data points
that are meaningfully related
based on their vector proximity.
Yeah.
So now that we understand about foundation
models and vectors, vector stores,
vector embeddings, let's start into
look into some of the vector databases.
And I want to quickly
highlight Postgres sql here.
Before I go into that,
let me also talk about.
The Vector data stores because in
this topic I'm covering most of the
AWS services because that is what
I'm familiar, a lot, familiar with.
I wanna touch, because in the previous
example I picked up an example to show
Amazon Open Search, but that's not
the only data store that is available.
There are multiple others that are
available the director stores as well.
The first one here is the Amazon Kendra.
There are multiple, as I mentioned, there
are multiple vector data stores that are
available and they all work efficiently.
But depending on the use case
that we have, you could be
looking at one over the other.
For example, Amazon Kendra, it
is a intelligent search service
that now supports semantic
search using vector embeddings.
It helps find users, find
relevant information based
on meaning not just keywords.
So it's very powerful tool.
And you would be, this would be a
good fit for you if you're looking
for something low-code, no-code
solution and rapid deployment.
This is your go-to use case because it
supports a lot of ingestion data sources.
It has 40 plus connectors
and stuff like that.
So you do not want to deal with some
of the things like data chunking and
embeddings and mixing algorithm choices.
It does all of that for you.
So really powerful service to go with.
And the next one I have is the
Amazon Open search service that I
just used in a previous example.
This is an open source search
and analytics engine that
supports dense vector fields
and K nearest neighbor search.
It is useful for use cases like
recommendation systems, semantic
search engineer retrieval.
So really good as well.
And.
This will be a good use case for you
if you are already using Amazon open
search service and you wanna go with a
solution where you are you don't really
want a lot of deal with sql, like a no
SQL solution, and you also need like a
low latency algorithm and you want higher
search accuracy and stuff like that.
The other item that I have and more
focused on our use case for this
presentation today is a, is about the
Amazon RDS and also Amazon Aurora.
So this has the post se Postgre
SQL with the PG vector extension,
and I'm gonna talk about those
things also in the upcoming slides.
So this is a managed relational database
that supports that now supports the
vector storage and querying as well.
So this is great for applications needing
tight integration of structured data with
vector search, such as, and this also
helps with, personalized recommendations.
Gives you hybrid search
as I mentioned, right?
It could have that integration
between your vector search as well
as your structured data search.
And this will be a good use case
for you when you already have.
You prefer SQL and you are dealing
with RDS or Aurora Postgres sql and
you want to keep the application and
the AI ML data vectors in the same DB
for better governance and faster loans.
So this is the, I think, the biggest
advantage that you get with this
solution where you wanna keep them
together, the application and the AI
ML data and vectors in the same db.
So that's where this is coming from, and.
Now that we discuss some of the data
store vector data stores here I want to
dive deep into the poster SQL and the PG
vector and why and how they're beneficial
to what we are trying to achieve.
Yeah.
Also, one more thing is that offer
all of these services, right?
One of the advantages on using
them also is that they come with
all the builts and whistles like.
You have role based access controls, you
have authorization authentication, you
have these are fully managed services
with serverless options available.
So you don't have to work on managing
the infrastructure, setting these up,
but rather work on the actual meet.
And that's, that, that's one of
the big advantages coming out.
For this use case, as I mentioned,
we are going to be focusing on
Postgres SQL in Aurora or Amazon, RDS.
And the PG vector connected into it.
So let's dive into that.
So why Postgres sql, like, why I
have chosen this for this use case or
what I'm trying to talk about here?
Postgres sql it's becoming a popular
choice as a vector database because it
combines the reliability of traditional
relational database with new capabilities
to store and query vector embeds.
The.
If you ask me like, why, what are the
reasons that we might wanna go for
PostgreSQL, for a Vector database is, as I
mentioned, there is a PG vector extension.
It adds native support for
vector data types and similarity
search and the flexibility.
It lets to store both structured
data like a customer data like
product metadata alongside vectors
in one database that enables you.
Powerful, really powerful hybrid search.
Like you can get filters and similarity
and that is one of the examples towards
the end where I'm gonna show you with
the PostgreSQL, PG vector, how that
looks like, and also the scalability and
maturity that we are talking about here.
So PostgreSQL is battle tested.
It's highly scalable and.
Trusted already for mission
critical applications.
This is not something new
that has not been around.
It's been around for a while and
does a great job and cost effective.
Why am I saying cost effective?
Because typically, RDS might not sound
like it is cost effective, but the
thing is, it avoids the need for a
separate, specialized vector database.
For many use cases, it simplifies the
architecture and reduces the cost.
Be because you don't need that.
Another separate
specialized vector database.
It supports natively now.
So PostgreSQL with PG Vector, it can
give you a very powerful, unified
platform for building intelligent,
vector driven applications with very
familiar tools and minimal overhead.
So let's talk about a
little bit about PG Vector.
It is an open source
library for vector search.
A vector as a data type helps
in similarity search and it
has the senior SQL integration.
So I say these things, right?
So what are the key features
that I'm highlighting here
is also vector data type.
So it enables storing vectors.
It's as I mentioned it, you can think
of that as a list of a red area of
like numbers, especially floats.
Think of it as an area of float.
And it supports it as a native data type.
It provide, provides similarity search,
so supports finding vectors that are
closest to a given vector based on
metrics like cosign similarity and to
the EQU and in distance or inner product.
I, it can index for fast search.
It has seamless SQL integration.
So for all these advantages.
We can go this is a good good choice and
there are many use cases, as I mentioned,
the semantic search or recommendation
engines or personalized delivery,
content delivery, all of these will be
a very good use case for the PG vector.
So I want to discuss the Fiji
Vector example with using the query
in the nearest neighbor sample.
So let's talk about some of
the algorithms we have at hand.
So the first one.
So it has three common similarity
metrics, like it enables the nearest
neighbor searches in post SQL by using
three most common similarity metrics.
The first one is the Euclidean distance.
So it measures the straight line
distance between two vectors.
So typically it is very useful
when the physical closeness.
Or the raw differences really matter.
And this is how you show
that it's a Euclidean.
I will talk about this, the
thing, the hyphen that you're
seeing within the brackets.
We will see how that
plays into the picture.
In the next slide where I'm giving,
going to give you the actual sample.
And the next one the next metric
is the co-sign similarity.
Cosign similarity.
As you can see the picture, it
measures the angle between two
vectors, like it focuses on their
orientation rather than the magnitude.
For example, I think some of the most
common use case would be like in text
embeddings, where the direction of the
meaning matters more than magnitude.
And it also has, it is
depicted using a hash.
And the next one is.
The top product.
Also, I think I also use
inner product to define this.
So it calculates the product of two
vectors and then sums the result.
So this is often used when
embeddings are normalized.
And higher dot products
mean greater similarity.
If you are looking at some of the examples
for query patterns in a PG vector.
So it would be like finding a vector's
closest to a vector when using one of
these distances or similarity measures.
And that is a sample that I'm going to
show you right now and you can combine
similarity search with SQL filters.
Like product categories or user
segments or something like that.
So that is a sample that we
are going to look at right now.
So that is yep.
So I'm going to give an example
for query nearest neighbor.
And to do this, I'm going to create
a table called test Embeddings.
And it has two columns
product ID and embedding.
You see this embed column, it
is using a vector data type.
And this is possible because
I have the PG vector plugin.
So now the next thing I'm going to do
is I'm going to insert some data, like
I think 1, 2, 3, 4, 4, 4 data points.
So the first one for everything
I have product ID and embeddings.
The product ID is a big in
inte, and the embeddings is a
vector data type that I have.
So in each of them, this is a
sample test data that I'm inserting.
So the first item is one, and
then it's vector embedding.
Second is two, and then it is,
it's vector embedding and so on.
In real world, these embeddings that I
have, the 1, 2, 3, 2, 3, 4, the vector
embeddings that you're seeing, these will
come from your machine learning model.
Now, if you do the nearest neighbor search
what you would say could look like this.
Like you would do a select query
select product ID and embeddings where
embeddings is similar to this vector.
So you see that hyphen right there, right?
Bracket Hyen.
Bracket beside embeddings.
So that is what we saw in the previous
here, where you have shapes behind each
work, one for hyphen hash and equal to.
So here, which means that we are
using the similarity metric Euclidean
in my sample that I'm trying to use.
So it is using Euclidean metric.
And what we are trying to say is that
we are selecting the product ID and
and embeddings and we are seeing where
embeddings is similar to this vector.
This is the, like I said,
symbol, fake cian distance.
And from the stable test embeddings, and
we are saying that to order by embeddings.
So you can see how easily we were
able to integrate this vector data
type into our regular structured sql.
And how powerful it is and easy it is.
If you already have SQL knowledge,
then it's not big, a big learning curve
or maintenance curve for you either.
And I'm all and you, and when I run
this query, I'm getting this response.
And I'll get an answer like this.
I'm getting an answer like this,
and it has only two rows because
if you see my query, I said I'll
limit it to only two results.
So it is able to find that and give me
that data correctly, as you can see.
In summary, I can say PG Vector.
It helps you build a product.
Catch log similarity.
Search this way by allowing you
to store product embeddings.
Which you get from your foundation models.
These are the vector representations
of products directly into
your Postgres SQL database.
So you can generate embeddings
from product attributes like you
titles or descriptions, images
using your machine learning models.
And with PG Vector, you can efficiently
perform nearest neighbor searches
to find products that are most.
Similar based on semantic
meaning, not just keywords.
So through this we are able
to see that you have a lot
of key benefits here, right?
As I mentioned as a recap of what
we have been discussing so far.
Like with this approach,
you have unified storage.
You get to keep product metadata and
embeddings together in one database.
You are getting this
flexible similarity search.
As we just saw in this example we
were able to use utility distance.
And to find related ones and I'm
able to write hybrid queries.
I'm able to combine my traditional SQL
filtering here I with the filtering
with vector based similarity search.
So not and it is giving me
very highly relevant results.
And also, I didn't need any
separate vector database.
I was able to extend my
existing Postgres SQL setup.
In, in all together, like in
short this PG vector helps.
It enables fast and intelligent
and it is very scalable.
Similar search product search
by it's bringing powerful AI
vector search capabilities into
already familiar workflows.
I think I was able to explain,
the use case and also how to use
this advanced data search using
Post sql, PG Vector, a data store.
Hope you learn something new
through this presentation.
And yeah, thank you.
I hope you have you guys
have a good day now.
Thanks a lot.