Hey everyone.
Welcome to the session on evolution
of Natural Language Processing.
Here I would like to cover how we
have progressed over the years from
counting words to conversing with ai.
The ability to communicate
through language is one of the key
characteristics of humans for decades.
The dream of training machines with a
similar understanding has fueled the
field of natural language processing.
What began as rudimentary attempts
to analyze text has blossomed into a
sophisticated discipline, culminating
in generative AI and multimodal models
that capture our imagination today.
This journey marked by breakthroughs
and paradigm shifts is a testament to
human creativity and the relentless
pursuit of artificial intelligence
that truly understands us.
Before we begin, a quick
introduction about myself.
I'm the Director of IP Strategy
and Technology at United Lake.
I'm based in Austin, Texas.
In United States of America.
I lead the IP data science
team where we create innovative
solutions at the intersection of
intellectual property and technology.
One of the products that our team
has developed is Vantage for ip.
It is a patent intelligence platform
that processes hundreds of thousands of
patents using natural language processing.
It provides competitive
intelligence, evaluates patent
strength, and uncovers licensing
opportunities amongst other things.
Two of my key focus areas are developing
deep learning models to evaluate
patents and designing user-friendly
platforms to convey the results.
NLP being the hot field it is at the
moment can be attributed to the surge in
investment in this domain, and also the
improvement in computer hardware, thus
increasing the compute capabilities.
According to the 2023 AI index
report by the Stanford Institute of
Human-Centered ai, global AI private
investment was about 92 billion in 2022.
This amount was 18 times greater
than it was 10 years back in 2013.
The amount of computational power
used by significant AI machine
learning systems had increased
exponentially in the last half decade.
As pre-trained large language models
have gotten bigger and more capable
over the years, they have required
bigger and more elaborate training sets.
For example, when OpenAI released
its original G PT one model in 2018.
The model was trained on Book
Corpus, which is a collection of
about 7,000 unpublished books,
comprising about five GB of text.
GT two Launched next year in
2019, was trained on about 40
GB training set created based on
scrap links from Reddit users.
Next year, G PT three was released,
which was pre-trained on more than
500 GB of text from open sources,
including book Corpus, common
Crawl, Wikipedia, and Web Text Two.
While officially the training set
details are scanned for G PT four, which
launched in 2023, the training set has
been reported to be 13 trillion tokens,
which would be a few terabytes of data.
The early days of NLP were characterized
by statistical models, techniques like
bag of words, prevalent in the early,
late 20th and early 21st centuries
treated text as an unordered collection
of words, disregarding, grammar and
syntax, while simple to implement.
Bag of words, enabled basic tasks like
text classification and information
retrieval by analyzing word frequencies.
Term frequency in words, document
frequency built upon this by weighing
words based on their importance
within a document and across a corpus.
These models though limited in
their understanding of context
and relationship between words
laid the foundational statistical
groundwork for future advancements.
The limitations of pure statistical
approaches became increasingly apparent
when tackling more complex NLP tasks.
The inability of compute, the
inability to capture semantic
meaning and the sensitivity to
word order led to the development
of more sophisticated techniques.
Engram models represented a step
forward by considering sequences of N
consecutive words, thus incorporating
some contextual information.
Perplexity is a common metric
for evaluating language models.
It estimates how well a model can
predict the next word in a sequence.
Lower perplexity scores generally indicate
a better model, meaning the model is
more confident in its predictions.
Our perplexity score of 120 plus
for engram models highlights
the limitations of early models.
These models also suffered from the
curse of dimensionality as vocabulary
size increased leading to data
sparsity shoes, for example, with a
vocabulary of 10,000 unique words.
Each document will be represented
by a vector of 10,000 dimensions.
If we have only few, hundreds of few
thousand documents, each document
vector will mostly be zeros.
Trying to find similarities or train
a classifier on such spars, high
dimensional data can be very challenging.
With sparse data in a high dimensional
space, the data points or document
vectors become increasingly
far apart from each other.
This makes it difficult for distant
based algorithms to find meaningful
similarities between documents.
The concept of neighborhood
becomes less reliable.
Further storing and manipulating
these large spars vectors can consume
vast amounts of memory, potentially
exceeding the available resources.
The late 2000 and early 2010s witnessed
a paradigm shift towards machine
learning, particularly with the rise
of deep learning word embedding,
such as what to work and globe
revolutionize, how words were represented.
These techniques learned
dense, low dimensional vector
representations of words based on
their ence in large text corpora.
Crucially, these embeddings capture
semantic relationships, allowing models to
understand that king is similar to queen
in a way that simple statistical models
could not design for sequential data.
Recurrent neural networks are an ins.
Utilize a unique lube architecture
that allowed them to remember past
information, making them useful for
tasks like language modeling and
predictive text where context matters.
A significant limitation of RNN
is their struggle with long range
dependencies, primarily due to the
vanishing radiant problem, which
causes them to lose information from
earlier parts of longer sequences.
Long short-term memory or LSGM networks
were developed as an advanced RNN
architecture, specifically to overcome
the vanishing gradient problem.
Their introduction of memory cells
capable of retaining information for
extended durations and intelligent gating
mechanisms that control information
flow, enable them to effectively
learn long-term relationships.
The best per reported perplexity
score of RN models on pen tree
Bank dataset was around 73.4.
And few LSTM models have also achieved
perplexities in the forties, such as 44.9.
While LSGM offer a substantial improvement
over RNAs in handling long sequences, they
come with a higher computational cost.
Their complex skating mechanism
require more computational
resources and training time.
Moreover, their inherent
sequential processing still
hinders parallel computation and
can limit their effectiveness
with extremely long dependencies.
The transformer architecture introduced
in 2017 with the groundbreaking paper.
Attention is all you need
marked another significant leap.
By leveraging the attention mechanism,
transformers allowed the model to
weigh the importance of different
words in a sequence when processing
it regardless of their distance.
This overcame the limitation of RNs
and enabled parallel processing.
Leading to significantly improved
performance and scalability.
Blue, which stands for bilingual
evaluation UNDERST study.
It's a metric used to evaluate the
quality of machine translated text.
It measures how similar the machine
translated text is to a set of
high quality human translations.
Transformer architecture
achieved a blue score of 41.8 on
English to French translation.
Here is an example of the attention
mechanism following long distance
dependencies from the paper.
Different colors represent different
heads of the multi-head attention.
Attention shown only for the word making.
As we can see, many of the attention
heads attend to the distant
dependency of the word making.
Completing the phrase
Making more difficult.
Here is another example of two attention
heads involved in N four resolution.
On the left side, we see full attentions
for one of the heads, head five, and
on the right side we see isolated
attentions from just the word.
It's for attention.
Heads five and six.
While Head five relates, its to only the
word law Head six relates it to both the
words law and application fairly strongly,
but or bidirectional encoder
representations from transformers.
This architecture achieved 94.9%
accuracy on sentiment analysis,
benchmarks, surpassing previous
models by a significant margin.
Bert introduced several key innovations
that significantly advance the field
of natural language, understanding the.
Bidirectional training.
Unlike previous language models
that process texts, unidirectionally
either left to right or right to
left, bird is designed to learn
deep bidirectional representations.
This means it considered the context
of each word from both the word
that preceded and the words that
follow it simultaneously in all
layers of the transformer network.
This bidirectional understanding allows
Bert to grasp the meaning of words
based on their full context within a
sequence leading to a more nuanced and
accurate understanding of language.
For example, the.
Bert can better differentiate
the meaning of bank in river
bank versus financial bank
mask language modeling.
To enable bidirectional training,
Bert employs a novel pre-training
task called Mask Language modeling.
During pre-training a certain percentage,
typically 15 percents of the word in
the input sequence are randomly massed.
The model's objective is to predict
the original mass words based
on the context provided by the
unmasked words in the sentence.
This forces the model to understand the
meaning of each word by considering its
surrounding context from both directions.
This is crucial for learning deep
bidirectional representations.
Pre-training and fine tuning.
Bird established a powerful
pre-training and fine tuning pattern.
The model is first pre-trained on a
massive amount of unlabeled text data
using the mass language modeling task.
This allows the model to learn general
purpose language representations.
Then the pre-trained bird model
can be fine tuned on smaller tasks,
task specific labeled data sets
for various downstream NLP tasks.
Example, text classification question
answering named entity recognition, et
cetera, by adding a simple task specific
output layer, this approach significantly
reduced the need for large label dataset
for each specific task, and led to
substantial performance improvement
across a wide range of NLP application.
The GPT series developed by OpenAI
has shown a remarkable evolution in
its capabilities, primarily driven by
scaling, model size, and training data.
G PT one released in 2018
included 125 million parameters.
It demonstrated the effectiveness of
pre-training a transformer model for
language understanding and generation,
followed by task specific fine tuning.
GT two released in 2019
included 1.5 billion parameters.
It showed significant improvements in
text generation, quality coherence,
and the ability to perform various
downstream tasks with little to
no task specific fine tuning.
GPT-3 released next year in 2020
included 175 billion parameters.
It showed remarkable few short and
even zero short learning capabilities.
It could perform a wide range of NLP
tasks, including translation, question
answering, and code generation.
With a few examples or even natural
language instructions, it showed
improved coherence and context
understanding compared to its producers.
Superglue is a benchmark data set for
evaluating natural language understanding.
It focuses on tasks that require
deeper reasoning and understanding of
language, including tasks like question
answering, core reference resolution,
and natural language inference.
While GPT one had a super glue score of
45.2 GPT-3 had super glue score of 71.8.
This scaling trend in the GPT series has
been a major driving force behind the
advancements in generative AI and has
paved the way for even larger and more
capable models like GPT-4 and beyond.
The latest frontier in NLP is
the rise of multimodal models.
These models go beyond processing, just
text, and can understand and generate
content across different modalities,
such as images, audio, and video.
By jointly learning representations
from diverse data sources, multimodal
models can achieve a more holistic
understanding of the world and
enable exciting new applications.
Combining text and image data has
improved healthcare diagnostic accuracy.
In a recent study, multimodal models were
used to generate assessments based on
medical images and clinical observations.
Those were evaluated against
physician authored diagnosis.
In 80 plus person cases, the multimodal
assessments outperformed human
diagnosis, AI-driven diagnostics minimize
misdiagnosis, leading to fewer malpractice
claims and unnecessary treatment.
Automated data processing speeds
up disease detection, decreasing
patient wait times and hospital stays.
AI enabled hospitals report 30 to 40%
improvement in workflow efficiency,
allowing providers to treat more patients
without increasing staff workload.
Visual question answering or view
QA model, which understand images
and answer questions about them
have achieved 84.3% accuracy.
This has wide application in
education, accessibility tools, and
even in visual impairment community.
Video chat two achieved 51.1% MV
bench surprising the previous date
of the model by over 15% in accuracy.
This benchmark evaluates complex
temporal reasoning in videos.
L MSS or large multimodal models show
promise in generating accurate and
contextually relevant closed captions.
Their ability to understand the
video context can lead to better
handling of similar sounding
words, speaker identification
and overall caption quality.
Multimodal retrieval enhanced
by LMS aims to retrieve relevant
content, images, or videos based
on complex multifaceted curies,
including text and visual elements.
Large language models, while powerful
are computationally expensive and
memory intensive to make them more
practical for various applications
and deployments, researchers have
developed several efficiency techniques.
Here is an elaboration on
some of these techniques.
Model compression or pruning.
Pruning aims to reduce the number of
parameters in a model by identifying
and removing unimportant weights
or even entire neurons and layers.
This leads to reduced model size, faster
inference, and low memory footprint,
knowledge distillation.
Knowledge distillation involves
training a smaller, more efficient
student model to mimic the behavior
of larger, more complex teacher model.
The teacher model, having learned
from a vast amount of data, transfers
his knowledge to the student.
This leads to smaller model size.
The student model has significantly
fewer parameters, faster inference,
and improved performance.
The student can sometimes
generalize better.
Then if trained directly on the target
task, limited data as it benefits
from the teacher's broader knowledge.
Quantization reduces the precision of
the numerical representations used for
the models, weights and activations.
Instead of using floating point
numbers like 32 bit or 16 bit, the
model uses lower precision numbers
like eight bit or even four bit.
This leads to reduced model size, faster
inference, and lower power consumptions,
which is crucial for edge devices.
Sparse attention.
It is an efficiency technique, used
large language models to reduce
the computational cost of the self
attention mechanism, especially when
dealing with long input sequences.
The standard self attention
mechanism in transformers has a
quadratic time and memory complexity.
Sparse attentions aims to elevate this
quadratic complexity by only computing
attention scores for a subset of possible
query key pairs rather than all of them.
The selection of these pairs is based on
a specific pattern of learned criteria,
aiming to retain the most important
contextual information while significantly
reducing the number of computations.
Throughout this session, I have
mentioned various metrics or scores like
perplexity, blue glue, or super glue.
As the models have evolved,
the metrics have evolved too to
effectively compare different models.
Here are a few metrics which will be in
focus for comparing future and LP models.
Training efficiency and sustainability.
Energy consumption will
be a key metric to watch.
Studies have shown that training
large language models can have
significant carbon footprint.
Researchers at the University of
Massachusetts amhurst estimated that
training a single large language model
could emit around 300 tons of CO2
equivalent reasoning capabilities.
New benchmarks will emerge to assess a
model's ability to perform multi-step
casual reasoning, which involves
understanding how different actions
of or events cause specific outcomes.
Current evaluations often miss
these capabilities, which make
up a large portion of human
reasoning, ethical alignment.
Future metrics will evaluate models
on their ethical considerations.
Including fairness,
transparency, and safety.
This should lead to creating responsible
AI systems that align with human
values across diverse cultural context.
This brings us to the end of this session.
I would like to thank every
one of you for attending.
From the humble beginnings of the
counting words to sophisticated
capabilities of generative and
multimodal ai, the evolution of
NLP has been a remarkable journey.
Each stage built upon the limitations
of it producers driven by the desire
to create machines that can truly
understand and interact with humans.
As we continue to push the boundaries of
ai, the future of NLP promises even more
exciting developments bringing us closer.
And human interaction.
Thank you.