Speaker 8: Hello everyone and
welcome to Con 42 Machine Learning.
And today in this session, we are
gonna explore the role of machine
learning in modern payment ecosystems.
This is not a talk about any specific
algorithms or model architectures.
And so we are gonna take a deeper look
at how machine learning is gonna fit
as a system in the current payment
ecosystem and the prospectus of how
it fits, why it matters, and how it's
transforming the modern payment ecosystem.
My goal is gonna be very clear a
practical understanding of how machine
learning enhances payment systems.
Where regardless of whether you're
an engineer, you're a product owner
an architect, or simply interested in
knowing about the future payment systems.
Before we dive in let me introduce myself.
I'm Meyer.
I work in the financial industry.
With over 16 plus years of experience
in handling large scale payment systems
I spend more than a decade or more in
handling payment platforms and enterprise
architecture throughout this journey.
I'll I'll be sharing my experiences
on the practical adoption of
mission learning that we have
experience in production environment.
What brings me to this conversation is
not just about the theoretical knowledge,
but real world experience that's
connecting the payment challenges along.
The machine learning solutions I've seen
work and most importantly how machine
learning is truly adding a value to
the current payment solutions and how
it's just not a high, the focus of this
session is to where the gap between
real payment challenges and applied
machine learning, and we'll be examining
how machine learning solutions are fit
fit into the current payment systems.
And the prospective of looking beyond
mathematics and statistics that are
involved in machine learning algorithms
and how machine learning capabilities
integrate into a broader payment landscape
and deliver a tangible business value.
So what essentially are
we gonna cover today?
So here as the agenda that we are gonna
cover today we will be understanding
what is modern payment system.
Whereas modern payment ecosystem it's
inherent complexities then we are
gonna explore how machine learning
basically fits into the ecosystem, the
specific touch points across different
payment life cycles and where machine
learning makes a difference over there.
We'll also look at some of the real
world examples and the key areas like
merchant acquisition, transaction
processing operational decision makings.
These are not just hypothetical
situations or scenarios.
They're based on the actual
implementation that we have
seen in production environment.
Next, we'll discuss more on the
system level benefits of how machine
learning algorithm works in terms of
scalability, automation, and how low
level latency decision making side being
handled by machine learning algorithms.
The capabilities are to enable payment
platforms to operate at scale speed with
accuracy, and that's required by modern.
As payment systems.
Finally, we'll be looking ahead
in the future, like how machine
learning is evolving with
emerging payment technologies and
challenging customer expectations.
We'll also be touching on challenges
and considerations that come along
with machine learning algorithms in
terms of biases and how we are handling
in terms of the critical domain.
Expertise that mission learning brings.
Let's start by understanding what we
mean by the modern payment ecosystem.
When we talk about modern payment
ecosystem as of today, we're not
just talking about moving money
from one bank to another or 0.8 to
point B. We are dealing with much
more complex, interconnected systems
that span across multiple domains.
At a high level, we are going to have
much merchant acquisition, the process of
onboarding, underwriting new merchants.
And then we go ahead with the transaction
processing where payments and are
authorized and executed in real time.
And then it comes with the, with its
own challenges of fraud detection system
that needs to be continuously assessed
with its risk and preventing fraud
fraudulent activity on a day-to-day basis.
Settlement hand is the action movement
of the funds and reconciliation
across the payment network.
Analytical brings business
intelligence to all stakeholders
and operation ensures that platforms
run smoothly, efficiently, reliably.
And moreover, it it builds the customer
trust on using the payment system.
Each of these domains
have its own challenges.
They bring more and
more interconnectivity.
A decision made in fraud direction
affects authorization rates.
For example, if a bad decision
made by a fraud direction system.
May in her or cause a bad experience for
customers using the payment platform.
As well as the financial implications
for the financial institute.
Insights from Analyticals also inform
us more on the acquisition strategies.
Operational intelligence also
improves system reliability.
You are the key challenges
that we're seeing today.
The system must handle millions of
transaction in a very short, low latency,
like less than a hundred milliseconds.
High accuracy and continuous
adoption to evolving patterns.
Traditional rule-based approaches
simply cannot handle such complexities,
and that's where we see like machine
learning fits into this entire picture.
Now let's understand why
machine learning match.
Let's contrast the traditional approach
of machine learning enhanced approaches.
In traditional payment systems, we
relied heavily on rule-based systems.
With static threshold.
You would have rules like decline of
the transaction is over 5,000 for a
new card or flag review if the velocity
exceeds 10 transactions per hour.
These also created by domain
experts and updated periodically.
Manual reviews and
interventions are very common.
Humans would.
Look at flag transactions
and make up parole decisions.
Processing often happened in batches.
We would run reports at the end
of the day to support issues.
The systems were very reactive
to fraud patterns, meaning frauds
often had the window of opportunity
before rules were updated.
This was limited to personalization.
Every customer with similar
characteristics got treated the
same way and perhaps more important.
These systems are very
slow to adapt to changes.
Updating rules require committee
meetings, testings and deployment cycles
and a full round of loan assign testing
and and exhaustive testing before
moves to the production environment.
Now, on contrast to this, with machine
learning enhanced capabilities instead
of statics, we have more adapt, adaptable
models that learn from continuous data.
The models are, can process hundreds
and thousands of transactions.
With low latency finding patterns
that humans would never spot.
Decision making happens
automatically at scale.
Millions of decisions per day.
Each informed by the latest data
processing happens in real time streams.
There's no waiting for batch windows.
The system are predictive and
proactive identifying potential
issues as they occur, and
personalization becomes possible.
Each transaction is evaluat
in its own unique context.
Who's the user?
What is his history?
What's the norm for them?
And the system continuously
improves itself, learning from
every transaction outcome.
This is the fundamental shift
that machine learning enables in
current pay medical ecosystem.
That's moving from the Richard
manual processing and reactive
systems make it more adaptive and an
intelligent platform using machine.
Let's go with machine learning
across the different payment
cycles that we have on a basis.
Let's get more specific about how machine
learning fits in the payment lifecycle.
I want to see that machine learning isn't
just bolted on one part of the system.
It touches every stage
of the payment chain.
Now starting with the first stage
is known as acquisition phase.
Machine learning helps with the
risk scoring and KYC automation.
When a merchant applies to use payment
platform machine learning models can
instantly access the risk profiles,
verify their identity and make preliminary
decisions about approving and the
pricing information for the customer.
Now, going for the next stage
of the payment lifecycle
during the authorization phase.
The ML powers fraud direction at real
time and optimizes routing decisions.
Every transaction model.
A fraud risk decides whether the payment
network to be used and determines
whether to approve, decline, or step
up authentication In the pre-processing
phase machine learning provides more of an
anomaly detection and a load production.
It.
Spots, unusual patterns
in transaction flows.
Predict predicts more of a capacity
needs and helps in the system
performs settlement benefits from
machine learning through improved
reconciliation and cash flow forecasting.
Models can predict settlement times,
identify discrepancies early and
optimized liquidity management
and in operations machine learning
enables performance optimization
and intelligent alert alerting.
Systems can predict where
infrastructure issues might occur
and automatically adjust resources,
maintaining tools service quality.
Below the lifecycle stages.
We also have crosscutting machine learning
capabilities that enhances all the areas.
Patternation helps and identifying trends
and transaction data across millions of
events, risk assessment, as well as the
transaction risk in real time concerning
hundreds and several factors and.
Honestly, the predictive analytic
analytical future also has a kind
of a behavior and outcomes from
fraud likelihood to merchant success
rates and optimizes constantly
improving routing decisions, resource
allocation and system performance.
The key insight here is mission
learning creates an intelligent layer.
That runs through the entire
ecosystem, not just isolated
buckets or functionality.
Now let's move on to the first stage
of the payment ecosystem, which is
known as the merchant acquisition.
Now let's look at some concrete
application examples starting
with the merchant acquisition.
The challenge in traditional merchant
acquisition onboarding is significant.
The process is slow,
manual, and inconsistent.
Underwriters have to review
the application one by one.
Evaluating business documents, financial
statements, and the risk factors.
This can take up to days or weeks creating
frictions for merchants who want to start
accepting payments right away and quickly.
Decision quality vary based on
underwriter experiences and judgements.
They can be human biases, different
reviewers can have different perspective
and come up with different conclusions.
On the same type of similar application,
and the process doesn't scale.
You need to hire more and more
underwriters linear as the
application grows on the scale.
Now, how does mission learning factor?
Mission learning models can automatically
assess such merchant risk by analyzing
a comprehensive set of factors like the
business side, the category the financial
history of the merchant the credit scores,
ownership information transformation
pattern for the similar merchant.
And also some extra source of
data that we can get from online
reviews or from public records.
And these exhaustive testings or
exhaustive record collections cannot
be manually assessed by a human which
is going to be a cumbersome task for
them and might take days or weeks to
collect information across different
sources that are available online.
The models have to be trained on
thousands and on thousands of previous
applications, learning which factor
correlate with the merchant success.
And which indicates elevated risk.
This can make instant decisions
for straightforward cases.
Lower risk merchants get
approved immediately.
High risk merchants can get dec declined
with clear reasoning and optimization.
Interesting cases probably the edge
cases where human judgment truly
adds value, gets routed to the
experience underwriter with the model
assessment and key factors highlighted.
This means a human expert, a manual loop.
Spend their time where it matters
the most, not on the routine.
Evaluation.
This bus this impacts the
business substantially.
We typically see around 90
percentage of reduction in processing
time for standard application.
Manual reviews decreased by 75 percentage
as most of our handle automatically.
And perhaps the most important
is that almost 40 percentage of
implement and risk direction.
The model catches problematic
merchants at scale.
That might have slipped through
the manual review, but it's not
just about speed and accuracy.
Machine learning enables consistent
decision making at scale, creating better
user experience for merchants while
maintaining appropriate risk controls.
Now let's move on to the transaction
processing life stage of payment
systems where the demands are.
Even more extreme I would say payment
authorization happens in milliseconds,
and it has to happen in milliseconds
to have a better customer experience.
When someone fights a car, for example,
or clicks by now, the system has to make a
decision within a few milliseconds whether
to approve or decline the transaction
within those tiny vendor, you need to make
a distinguish a legitimate transaction
whether it's a fraud without adding
friction to the customer experience.
Static rules create dilemma
and if it's not governed or
doesn't go to the review cycle.
And if it's too strict, you
decline legitimate purchases
and frustrate the customer.
If it's too lenient, you let fraud
through the system and lose money.
Either way, you are making business
trade offs on incomplete information.
And most of these manual transactions
or manual rule rules are exposed.
Easy to understand and easy
to break for middleman.
The challenge in intensifies because
fraud patterns constantly evolve.
What worked last month
might not work this month.
Fraud says, test the system in
and out, find the weaknesses,
and try to exploit them as much
as we can, as much as they can.
By the time you update the rules, they
have moved on to the next tactics.
Machine learning transforms this equation.
Real time mission models score every
transaction based on hundreds of features.
They look at device brands, your location
of the customer velocity patterns.
Is this the 10th
transaction for this card?
In the last few hours they consider
merchant categories, historical
behaviors, or even the time of the
day when the transaction was made.
The model continuously
runs from his feedback.
When the transaction is approved and later
reported as a fraud, the information flows
back to improve the future predictions.
And that's where the deep
learning model comes into play
for fraud direction system.
When a legitimate transaction has
been declined the customer calls to
verify that and teaches the model
that it's legitimate transaction and
should not be a fraud transaction.
So it back propagates all the
rules and decision making back
to the machine learning layers,
hidden layers in learning model.
And that's when this creates this makes a
system more smarter over a period of time.
And we will see le lesser and
more enhanced user experience
through less friction.
The result is a set of key
machine learning capabilities
in real time processing.
Actually the fraud scoring as assesses
the risk and less than a hundred
milliseconds providing a probability
score rather than a binary decision.
For example, if a fraud has been detected
and it falls within the category of.
0.5 to 0.7.
There needs to be an enhanced a customer
validation for this transaction.
And if it's beyond 0.7, it's a clear,
legitimate fraud transaction that
has happened which has to be tagged.
Routing such intelligent decisions
optimizes approval rates by selecting
the best payment networks for
each of these transactions based
on the historical performance.
Anomaly detection, identification
unusual patterns are detected instantly.
Perhaps there are certain spikes
in the transaction for a particular
region or specific merchandising,
unusual card testing activity.
And dynamic threshold are just
rule based on the context.
What's normal for one merchant category
might be suspicious for other merchant.
All of this happens in real time
at scale with accuracy that exceeds
the rule-based systems that and
that is the power of machine
learning in transaction processing.
The third application the third
application area is the operational
decision making, which is often
less visible, but equally important.
Payment platforms generate massive
amounts of operational data system
metrics, performance indicators,
error rates, resource utilization.
The volume is overwhelming.
Human teams struggles to monitor
all of this at real time.
Spots emerging issues before they
impact the customer and make optimal
decisions about capacity and resource
Allocation approaches are very reactive.
You notice a problem after it affects
the customer and then scramble to fix it.
Are you over approaching the
resources to be safe wasting money
or having unutilized capacity?
Neither approach is optimal.
Machine learning enables the fundamental
enables of fundamental of different
models action of reacting to a problem.
Machine learning system predicts them.
The model learns from the normal pattern
of the system behavior and detects
anomalies that indicate potential issues.
They forecast traffic patterns based on
time of the day of the week, upcoming
events and the historical trends.
This enables proactive operation.
The system can scale up
capacity before a traffic spike.
It's, it can identify the performance
degradation before it causes outage.
It can optimize resources.
Allocates dynamically ensures
your capacity where you need
it without or provisioning.
That is.
System, let me give you a
specific operational use case.
Like for first the capacity
planning more machine learning
models forecast low patents and
trigger auto scaling decisions.
They optimize resource distribution
across infrastructure and also
ensure efficient utilization without
sacrificing the proper buffer.
The second is incident detection.
Anomaly detection algorithms,
spot issues in real time, and
generate intelligent alerts.
Like a root cause analysis model helps
teams to quickly identify what's wrong.
Some systems can even trigger automated
remediation process like resetting
fail services, rerouting traffic,
or even adjusting configurations.
And the third one is about performance
tuning machine learning models.
Continuously to monitor latency.
Identify bottlenecks in the transaction
processing and suggest any and suggest
or automatically implement configurations
that can optimize the throughput and
response time for any transactions that
rely on the machine learning algorithms.
The result in payment platform is just not
about running the system but it is about
continuously improving its own operations
with minimal human intervention.
This not only announces the
customer capabilities of
using the payment platform.
But also has less friction of
humans getting involved in the
process of maintaining the system.
Now let's step back and look at the
system level benefits that machine
learning brings to the pay medical
system, these transient individual
applications and transform how the
entire platform operates First.
The scalability.
A machine learning machine learning
algorithms enables payment system
to handle millions of transactions
without linear cost increases.
Think about for a moment like
traditional systems have to scale
linearly twice a volume requires twice
infrastructure and twice the stuff.
Now, machine learning over here
breaks this pattern models that
have handled increased volume
without degradation in quality.
They quickly add up to
traffic spikes automatically.
Adjusting to processing priorities
and business allocation.
This enables global expansion without
the proportional clean growth.
You don't have to like constantly
keep hiring people just because
your traffic is linearly expanding.
You can enter into new markets, support
new payment methods, and handle growing
transaction volumes without hiring
an army of analysts and operators.
Mission learning algorithms are quite
capable of performing analytics,
analytical skills at scale and
give more insights and forecast
for the transaction that are
happening within the payment system.
Now moving forward, the second
one would be automation.
This is perhaps the most,
most tangible benefit I see.
While using machine Eye, the machine
learning reduces manual intervention.
From 50 percentage of cases in traditional
systems to less than five percentage,
when you're using a machine learning
enhanced ecosystem, most decisions
like fraud checks risk assessments
routing choices happen automatically
with high accuracy and at scale.
This frees human experts to focus
more on complex edge cases where
judgment and creativity matters.
And this ensures this man in
the loop in the entire machine
learning models learning skills.
The payment analyst isn't just serving
hundreds of routine transactions
but they have been investigating
sophisticated thought drinks or making
strategic decisions about risk policies.
The platform operates 24 by seven.
You don't have someone just stepping
out because he needs to have dinner.
And this and the system is not
being monitored for a while.
So those kind of anomalies can be
avoided when you are using machine
learning at scale because it's
going to operate 24 by seven without
any without any human intercept.
And it still maintains a high quality
and appropriate risk controls.
Now the third one I would say is
more about low latency intelligence.
Machine learning enables
real time decision making
under a hundred milliseconds.
Even when processing complex feature
sets with hundreds of data points
the model maintains a high accuracy
throughput handling thousands of
transactions per second without
compromising on decision quality.
And that's the magic and power of
machine learning and payment systems.
This is critical in payment systems
when milliseconds really matter.
Because when you swipe a card at
a merchant location, you want the
transaction to happen quickly.
So every milliseconds of latency
will affect the customer experience
and the conversion rates.
Machine learning achieves this seamlessly.
And with sophisticated intelligence
and internet speed, these
three benefits the scalability,
automation, and low level latency.
Intelligence represents a
fundamental shift in what.
It's possible with payment platform.
They enable business models and
customer experiences that were
invisible with transaction approaches.
And let's move on to the
mission learning ecosystem view.
I'm gonna give you a conceptual
framework of thinking how machine
learning fits in the payment ecosystem.
The second diagram shows shows mission
learning, not as a feature or an
application, but as a foundational layer.
At the bottom we have the data layer that
includes all the raw data transaction
data, event streams, user behaviors,
system metrics and various other
data points in the payment platform.
The data is incredibly rich.
Every transaction, every authorization
decision, every fraud report
contributes to the learning process.
About all that sits is the machine
learning intelligence layer.
This is where the data becomes
more insight and insights
become more of an action.
The model processes incoming data
in real time, generates prediction
and scores, identify patterns and
anomalies and ans automated decisions.
This layer a central nervous
system for the payment ecosystem.
Now the application layer sits on top
of the machine learning intelligence.
This includes all the visible payment
functions like payment processing, fraud
detection, and analytical dashboards,
operational tools API interactions ui.
And each of these application
leverages the machine learning
layer for their intelligence needs.
But the intelligence itself is centralized
and shared across all these different
functional and operational areas.
Finally at the top of the business
layer we have the merchants,
the customers, the partners who
interact with the payment platform.
They experience the benefits of machine
learning algorithm through faster
onboarding, smoother transactions, and
better fraud protection and more of a
personalized service using association
relation, using in machine learning.
The key insight here is that
machine learning intelligence
layer connects everything.
It transforms raw data into more
of an actionable intelligence.
That powers all the applications about.
It enables the applications to be
faster, smarter, and more adaptive
than they could be independently.
That virtual view helps
explain why machine learning
is transformative in payments.
It's not just about improving
individual features, it's creating a
new foundation that elevates the entire.
System.
Now let's go with the
challenges and consideration.
Of course, machine learning, eruption
in payment is sent without challenges.
Let me be clear about the
considerations and potion pitfalls
because understanding this is crucial
for any successful implementation.
First, the data quality and availability.
Machine learning models are only as
good as the data they are trained on.
In payments you face
challenges like missing data.
Not every transaction has
a complete information.
Biased samples.
Their training data might not represent
all the customer segments equally.
The data quality issues like errors
or duplicates and inconsistencies that
could undermine the model performance,
secondly, I would say the model
explainability in financial services.
You can't just deploy a black box
model and hope for the best regulatory
requirements, demands transparency.
You need to explain why a
merchant was declined or why a
transaction was being flagged.
Business stakeholders need to
understand the trust and how
the model is making decisions.
They require balanced model
sophistications with the.
Inter operat ability.
Now, the third is the
real time constraints.
Payment decisions happen in
milliseconds, which puts several
limit limitations on the model cap.
Capabilities and complexities You can't
run and sample of deep learning networks.
If it just take, if it takes two
minutes of more than more than five
minutes in making the computation.
Models must be optimized for latency
without sacrificing accuracy.
This means that using simpler faster
models or implementing sophisticated
caching and pre computational strategies,
so that limits the machine learning
capabilities if you are using at real time
where the latency is the utmost priority
for having a better customer experience.
Now fourth is about continuous monitoring.
This is often underestimated.
And to be frank it's not once
you have de defined the model,
develop the model you push into the
production and your job is done.
It's and that does not stop over there.
Fraud patents evolve daily
customer behavior shifts.
And there are new and new
regulatory environments that change.
So concerning all these different
factors, a model that performs well
today might not be performing or degrade.
In the next quarter, you need to have a
robust monitoring to detect performance
degradation automate restraining pipelines
to keep the models current and have many
or robust alerting systems to flag when
human intervention is absolutely needed.
Now fifth comes with the
integrational complexities.
Payment platforms are complex, often
involving legacy systems that weren't
designed for machine learning algorithms.
You need to integrate machine learning
systems with the existing infrastructure
and you have to maintain its backward
compatibility, meaning and we meaning for
example, if a mission learning model does
not work for us, a particular service.
It has to be refactored and should
have a fallback mechanism to the
traditional rule-based models.
And that basically puts a lot
of constraint when we are often
involving legacy systems that
basically weren't designed to
use mission learning algorithms.
You might need to integrate machine
learning systems with the existing
infrastructure and maintain backup
compatibility meet compliance
requirements, and also ensure a
fail safe operational environment.
This integration is often more
challenging than I would say.
Then building the model, the.
Finally.
When we take a, when we talk about
risk management addressing payment
systems have real financial impacts.
A bug in a fraud model could cost
millions and only aggressive risk
models could decline legitimate
customers and harm the revenue.
This demand this demand robust fallbacks
human human oversights for edge cases.
And careful validation for
deployments, the stakes are high
and you need to balance innovation
with appropriate caution.
The challenges are real but they
are not uhum consumable successful
machine learning models adoption
is in payment system requests.
Thoughtful consultation of these
factors, not just our technical
expertise in mission learning.
What is the future of mission
learning and payments?
Looking ahead where does
machine learning in payments?
Heading to let me share some trends
that I believe will shape the next
generation of payment ecosystem.
First is the embedded financing.
We are seeing payment experiences across
embedded devices seamlessly that are
getting used on a day-to-day application.
Like ride sharing, food delivery,
social media, gaming and so
many different industries.
Machine learning is what
makes this possible.
Enabling instant underwriting,
real time fraud detection, and
personalized payment options.
Within the derivative context, the payment
becomes invisible if handled intelligently
behind the scenes moving on forward.
The second option is real
time personalization.
We are moving more just beyond beyond
fitting one size payment experiences
towards and moving towards more of a
dynamic offering pricing and experiences
tailored to an individual user mission.
Learning enables this by understanding
the customer preferences predicting what
offers they will value and optimize the
payment experiences for commission while
maintaining the appropriate risk controls.
And with the advent of more and more
usage of agent AI we are seeing the
machine learning algorithm plays a
vital role in shaping the agent ai
experience where the users have more of a
personalization and do a better shopping
experience using agent TK framework.
Like for example, he may just say go
ahead and do the purchase in TX store.
And get me get me a video game concept.
So the agent AI has to make a intelligent
decision given that banks can have
more of a pri private level credit
cards or dual cards and it has to pick
up the right credit card, which is
going to give them more reward points.
Then he purchases on a TJX store online.
And the agent AI has to make,
intelligent decisions using machine
learning algorithms to pick up
the right credit card and do
the purchases behind the scenes.
Now moving on the third will
be cross-border intelligence.
As commas becomes more global,
payment platforms need to be
more smarter routing transactions
across international networks.
Dynamic concurrency optimization.
And as well as automated
compliances with diverse regulatory
environments across the globe.
Mission learning helps to navigate these
complexities, making cross-border payments
faster, cheaper, and more reliable.
And one such example the banking
system that I'm working, we are
now started using stable coins as
part of the cryptocurrency world.
And we have infused into the emission
learning algorithms for for quicker.
Cheaper and more reliable way of
transferring money from one institute
to the other banking institute.
Now, the fourth point would
be alternative payments.
The payment landscape is
fragmented to be honest.
We have cryptocurrencies,
we have buy now, pay later.
We have digital wallets and new
methods we haven't imagined yet.
Like nfcs or push provisioning.
And there are different ways of payment
systems that are that are being proposed
as part of the imaging payment system
ecosystem Machine learning enables
payments platforms to up to these new
methods quickly with the right tools
assess the risk profiles, optimized
routing decisions, and provide a unified
experience across diverse payment.
Now the fifth one would be more
of an autonomous operation.
As we are moving towards self failing
systems that predict sand resolve issues
before they're impacting the customers.
Machine learning enables these
platforms to detect anomalies,
identify the root cause, implement the
fix automatically, and continuously
optimize their performance with
minimal human intervention.
These aren't.
Science fiction.
We are seeing early implementations
of all these capabilities as of today.
The future of payment is more
intelligence, more adaptive, and have a
more seamless experience that we have now.
And mission learning is the enabler.
The key message here is that mission
learning is not just for improvement
in payments, it's redefining what's
possible in the payment ecosystem.
It's enabling business models,
customer experiences, and operational
efficiencies that weren't visible before.
Now let's move on to the key takeaways.
To summarize the key
takeaways for the session.
First machine learning models
is the foundational layer
in modern payment ecosystem.
It's not just an add-on
feature going forward.
It's not something that you
bolt onto the existing system.
It is a new architecture
layer that transforms how a
entire ecosystem operates.
Second that will machine learning enhances
every stage of the payment lifecycle as
we are seeing right from the acquisition
to the settlement to the operations.
They're not part of just
the payment journey but.
Machine learning touches every aspect
of the entire payment lifecycle.
This comprehensive integration
is what makes it so powerful.
The third is the system benefits
that we have seen in terms of
scalability, automation, and low level
intelligence that are becoming that
are transforming the payment industry.
They aren't incremental improvements.
They represent the fundamental
shift in how payment platforms
can do and how they're operate.
Now, the fourth one would be the success
that requires a thoughtful consideration
of the data quality, explainability
integration, and the risk management.
Machine learning is powerful,
but it's not the magic one.
Successful implementation demands
attention to these practical challenges.
Finally, we have seen that machine
learning enables platforms to evolve
along with emerging technologies
and customer expectations.
It's not a destination,
but it's a journey.
Continuous learning, continuous implement,
continuous adaption to the changing
landscape makes the payment ecosystem
more reliable, more trustable and
seamless experience for the customer.
The payment industry is
undergoing a transformation and
machine learning is part of it.
Whether you're building a payment
system, using them, or making
decisions about them, understanding
machine learning roles in the
ecosystem is essential for navigating
the transformation successfully.
We move on to a quick demo
on, on the fraud ion system.
And here's a simple demo that
I have pro promised earlier.
So I have a docker that's
running on my local.
So I have Kafka that's running.
I've basically downloaded
from the public repository.
It's running locally on my system.
I have producer a stream
producer on my local and event
consumer that I have written.
It's a small Kafka program
that I have written.
So basically this is the.
Model creation code.
It's a simple code.
I'm synthesizing the data.
I'm not using any real time
data synthesizing the data.
So for a few of the data elements that I
have, if the amount is greater than 3000,
and just adding the score as plus 3.5.
And these are all like adding some
weight to the fraud transaction.
And over here I'm returning it as
one of the score more than 60% each.
So if the cumulative data, if it's
the amount is greater than 3000 device
trust score is less than four 40 if
it's an international transaction and
the fraud count is greater than two, so
they're all gonna add up to the score.
So the score is more than six percentage.
I'm going to as one or zero.
So this is how the model
gets trained and it.
Packages sent into the PKL file.
You will see over here the p
file over here and what basically
so this is a. Generator.
So I'm randomly generating data
on the fly like amount laying from
$10,000 to sorry from one to $5,000
on transaction areas, randomized.
All this data randomized.
I'm randomly selecting the location
and what I'm basically doing is I am
generat generating this transactions
and I'm sending it to a Kafka.
Topic.
So this is how I would send the data and
when I'm basically consuming the data
from the Kafka stream I look at the I
predict the transaction and basically I
use the model that I had built before.
You will see the model
has been loaded out here.
And these are the features
that are there as part of that.
And I'm using the model to
predict the transaction.
And if it is one basically if the
prediction is one, I'm saying like the
transaction is a fraud transaction as it
goes through without identify as fraud.
I go ahead, I stop the fraud.
Transmitter.
Basically it's just generating
the transactions and I will
be consuming those events.
So if you look at the
consumer side so yep.
If you look at the consumer side you'll
see that the data is getting consumed.
Not all the transactions
get track tracked as fraud.
It is a combination of data.
And I'll probably pause this.
So it is a combination of data.
So if you focus, if you look
at this particular transaction,
the amount is better than 3000.
The device code is less than.
And we, it's an international transaction,
so this gets tagged as a fraud and it
basically identifies as a fraud election.
And this gets propagated
into the downstream system.
Very simple program.
The thank you for your attention.
I hope this session has given a
tier understanding of our machine
learning fits into the current
payment ecosystem and why it matters
for the future of digital payments.
I'll be happy to take any questions.
Feel free to reach out
to me in the LinkedIn.
You are that I've given in the slide.
I will be more than happy
to answer any questions.
Anything like specific to application
implementation challenges, technical
details where you want to see which
kind of machine learning model can
fit your use case where you see
opportunities in your own context.
I'll be more than happy to understand
your use case of and see how
machine learning can fit seamlessly
into your operational model.
Thank you again and I will
look forward for any discussion
that you have at this point.
And thank you for con 42 for
giving me this opportunity to
speak in a wonderful audience.
Thank you all.
Thanks.