Speaker 32: good morning everyone.
I am Kumar Alala.
It's happy to be part of con 42
Machine Learning 2026 conference.
Today we are going to explore a critical
evolution in the world of cybersecurity.
The topic which I chose is a
machine learning driven complaints
engines for zero trust, security.
As we navigate the complex
landscape of 2026 and the sheer
volume of the data and the speed of
modern attacks have fundamentally
outpaced human managed security.
We are here to discuss a paradigm
shift which is transforming static
policy enforcement into an inclusion
adaptive security controls.
This isn't just an automation.
It is about building a defense
system that thinks, learns and
reacts autonomously at the same
velocity as the adversaries we face.
Before getting into the topic more I would
like to have a quick intro of myself.
Currently I'm working as a
client delivery director at heel.
America and do with this role we
are primarily providing ZT and a
frameworks and the aid driven compliance
solutions for multiple enterprises.
And also SMB customers few of them are
part of fortune five organizations.
The insights, which I'm sharing today are,
primarily coming from the challenges which
we faced while implementing our solutions
in high stakes environments where
static is synonymous with vulnerable.
Let's get into the topic itself.
The while we are trying to implement
these solutions primarily it's a gap of,
the compliance gap in zero Trust itself.
While many organizations have implemented
a Zero Trust network security protocols
and access they're still tethering this
modern architecture to a legacy mindset.
Currently many of these organizations are
rely on static manually defined policies.
Now that simply cannot keep the pace with
the rapid evolution of modern threats.
These traditional rule-based controls
struggle to adapt a new attack
patterns and fail to scale across
hybrid and multi-cloud environments
that define our businesses today.
Let's deep dive into why the
status quo is failing us.
Because many of the organizations have
defined their policy enhancements or
upgrades or updates is very periodical.
This traditional policy refresh
on fixed schedules often leaving
security gaps between update cycles.
While threats evolve continuously.
And the second thing what I found is
the manual configuration risk itself,
the human defined rules are primarily
it's pro to misconfigurations or
inconsistencies and simple errors that
create exploitable vulnerabilities.
The third one, which we've seen
is that scalability barriers.
As digital footprint is kept on expanding
maintaining thousands of individual
rules whether it's individuals or
whether it's for groups within the
organizations are fragmented systems are
becoming operationally unsustainable.
So these are the three key
pillars in terms of the issues
which we can categorize while
implementing these solutions.
Let's move on.
What exactly the solution which we
are looking currently our solution
is a transition to and a machine
learning driven compliance framework.
We are moving away from very
rigid rule-based logic and two
words and intelligent models.
So these models are capable of learning
adapting and enforcing complaints.
In real time directly with ZTNA ecosystem.
We are essentially replacing the
manual bottleneck with an intelligent
and a self garnering engine.
So if you see the architectural
overview so it's a closed loop design.
It functions across four
critical repeating stages.
One is the the first step
is the data ingestion.
This is the sensory layer gathering the
telemetry from across the enterprise.
And the second area is second
pillar is the model training where
the engine turns the raw data
into an actionable intelligence.
The third one is predictive
enforcement based on the data
which got through the ingestion
layer and the model training layer.
This is a a proactive layer
which makes an access decisions
based on the projected risk.
The fourth one is the automated feedback.
This primarily ensures the system
learns every outcome and create
a self-optimizing control layer.
So with these four layers where
we are currently looking at
predictive enforcement and automated
feedback we can ensure we we can
avoid the delays and then secure.
The organizations.
So if you see the source of powering
these decisions are primarily if
you see that the engine pulls the
data from three primary pillars.
One is endpoint telemetry which provides
the real time data on the device health
configuration states and the patch levels.
And the second is the user
behavioral analysis itself.
From which we can analyze and access
the pattern and authentication history
to generate the contextual risk
force, risk score for the individuals.
The third one is the cloud native
threat intel where we integrate
global threat feeds and industry
specific vulnerability intelligence.
Data to stay ahead of
emerging attack vectors.
While we are by synthesizing
these data points, we enable a
dynamic risk assessment model.
We no longer rely on snapshots in time.
The system evaluates risk-based
on current conditions.
If threat indicators change
access decisions are just.
On real time.
And furthermore, predictive analytics
allow us to identify potential
complaints violations before they
occur moving us from reactive defense
to a proactive posture management.
So while deploying these production
solution, these ML based solutions what
we found is, there is an achievement
of 40% faster incident response through
automated enforcements and also 98
percentage of reduction in critical policy
errors through ML generated controls.
And and there is an a 60% decrease in
manual effort allowing team to pivot
into the new strategic initiatives
rather spending on mundane daily tasks.
So the continuous learning feedback
loop this is primarily the brain
of the system is the self-improving
int intelligence itself.
Every enforcement decision
becomes a training data.
The system learns from both successful
interventions and false positives
continuously refining its accuracy.
This closed loop approach
ensures the framework evolves.
Alongside the environment
and emerging threats.
Next is the enterprise
considerations for this framework.
Likely to be succeed it must have
explainability and governance.
Enterprise adoption requires trust,
so we provide a clear decision,
rational and complete audit trails.
This ensures that even though even
though the engine is automated
it remains transparent and meets
all regulatory requirements the
security must be also be ethical.
The bias detection and mitigation should
be avoided because it ensures the access
decisions remain non-discriminatory.
A human oversight which is required
sometimes security teams, we should have
a supervisory control with the ability to
review and override the decisions privacy
and preserving the analytics, which
are primarily respecting user privacy.
Through anonymization and the purpose
Limited only to the data processing
deployment, flex flexibility.
What we have done is we
have designed this for SMEs.
We have considered as a lightweight
deployment with managed ML services for
rapid time to value for large enterprises.
Primarily we support hybrid
deployments and integration with
existing SIEM and so platforms.
As well.
The future of the z zero trust
compliance is in conclusion, what
I would like to say is machine
learning transforms complaints from.
A static checkpoint into an intelligent
self-learning control layer.
This represents the vital shift
from reactive policy enforcement to
proactive intelligence driven security.
Thank you thank you for your time.
My name is Kumar Ala, and it's been.
Privilege to share this vision at
conf 2042 machine learning 2026.
Thanks everyone.
Okay.