Hello everyone.
I'm I senior software engineer
manager in payments, and also
an independent AI searcher.
Over the past several years, I have
worked extensively in the financial
services domain, leading the design
modernization of cloud native system,
realtime transaction platform, and
AI driven risk management solutions.
Today I will share how generative
AI is reshaping financial services.
Transforming raw transactions into
personalized financial journeys
and intelligent decision making.
I will go to the, go to my first
slide, which is our agenda.
So we are going to introduce what
generative BI is and how it matters
and FinTech, and then we will
eventually follow the evalu evaluation
of gender financial services and ai.
And then generative AI in action,
like narrative personalization
risk, then we will address the
challenges and consideration.
And then we will move to how do we
overcome those kind of challenges?
And then what is the future?
How do we utilize it to show the
generic pi future in the finances
and then statistical case study
and then take hours and conclusion.
With that, I will start
with my first slide.
So finance is a data-driven industry,
so for decades, banks have collected
structured ledges and transactions,
but until now, those transactions
were treated as an isolated event.
Generative AI changes that it can
combine structured and unstructured
data, like spending history of strict
transaction and even voice data
into dynamic contextual insight.
For example, instead of just
recording that I spent $50 at
Starbucks generative AI can possibly
mention that it has, spending $50
at Starbucks has given 18% right to
rise to my expenditure, minimizing
certain percentage of my savings.
So basically it is a fundamental
shift from transaction to
financial storytelling.
So how the evaluation of
AI happened in finance.
So it's not new.
It has been there with the
finance industry from 1990, but
obviously at a different scale,
completely at a different scale.
So in 1990 to 2000 if you see the
fraud alert credit scoring, that these
are already part of the financial
industries and that is also some
kind of rule-based system integration
adding a lot of value to it.
It is very rigid, but it has a
lot of false positive outlook.
In 2010, machine learning improved
personalization and risk scoring
better, but still predictive.
In late 2010, deep learning
brought a realtime fraud
detection and LP power chatbot.
This is a serious style banking.
So in 2020, genetic ai, it's not just
detecting or predicting the fraud, or
it is also creating the new output,
like genetic rewards simulating risks,
producing personalized recommendations.
So in short, it is not only about
setting the problem, but also proposing
a solution of how do we minimize it.
So let's see.
What is generative AI in finance industry?
It's not just doesn't classify
your credit, it creates
the insight and actions.
Like I just quickly, you briefly
mentioned in my previous slide, it
can write personalized financial
reports directly from broadband data.
It can similar crisis in annual.
Somewhat of what if things, right?
So what if the employment is gets
a spike and interest rate double.
It can also propose a custom
loan and investment products
tuned to a customer profile.
This means finance shifts from what
happens to what should we do next.
Like I mentioned in my previous
slide, as it's not only predict
service, but also proposes a
solution of how do we handle that.
Moving on.
So transactions to narratives.
So what is narratives?
So narratives is as simple what
explanation of what just happened,
especially especially for the younger
generation who doesn't, who never tries
to look at the statement, but probably.
If you just tell them that your
expenditure has been increased or
this is how you save more, probably
that is something would be very easy
and quick to grab their attention.
So every customer leaves
behind a financial data trail
pending saving, investing.
So generative AI teaches
those into storage.
So instead of statistic or
static dashboard you are going
to get contextual narrative.
For example, the first slide or the second
slide I just mentioned that spending
$50 at Starbucks means that 18% higher
expenditure affecting my savings this
month, or based on my investment history,
I might miss out some of the tax saving.
So this is something is a storytelling
function, so it catches more people,
it catches attention, and also from the
layman user, like the consumers who are
actually using the finals but not into
the financial industry, it is very easy
to grab their attention and help them.
So personalization.
Traditional banking is one size fits all.
So they have the limited four, five
categories of the products, and we
just have to customize our need to make
sure which product fits with generative
ai, enable sales to conventional
assistant that answers plain language,
dynamic loan offers interested,
tailored to our realtime profiles.
Adaptive investment advice that
address when market shipped.
Our major European bank reported
that AI powered personalization
increased cross sell conversion by 35%.
So obviously for individual,
instead of using those five, six
predefined categories, it helps
to tailor loan and the percentage
and the usage for everything.
So for example, that we have a home
mortgage loan of 500 k generating
an EMI of 30 three K every month.
And that is supposed
to be paid in 20 years.
So what if you pay a thousand
dollars per month extra?
What if you pay a hundred k extra?
So what is the duration of the loan that
reduces to what is the EMI that reduces
to, those are the kind of personalization
that is very easy to opt in through this
generative ai and give an answer to the
tailored answer to the speak consumer.
Last, but last, but not the list.
Free scan fraud intelligence.
On the different side, fraud.
Fraud are using ai, right?
So there are so many fraudulent activity
that is trying to attack our system,
and they are all using ai opting for
the smartest way to hack a system.
So if we use the generative
ai, we can defense at the same
scale that we are being hacked
or at least trying to be hacked.
So generative AI helps to create
synthetic fraud patterns, to
train models that are more robust,
similar adversial attacks, like fake
transaction even before they happen.
It builds stress for
liquidity and credit crisis.
This moves banks from being reactive
to a proactive guardian, and we can
just think of it as a digital vaccine.
Instead of the time we are hacked,
how to try to get out of it, making
sure our system doesn't fail.
We are developing tests in, or
test suit in such a way that
we are actually isolating the.
One in a million kind of
possibilities and the age cases.
And we are actually and proactively
testing our system against those
kind of attacks, making our system
more prepared to handle those kind
of AI generated attacks, which are
more vulnerable than any other, any
of the previous that used to happen.
Yeah, but nothing is free of course,
obviously any big innovation comes with
a bigger responsibility and definitely
Generative BI is not free of that.
It definitely has some challenges
and consideration to address.
So bias, obviously there are people
who are financially privileged,
there are consumers who are not
that financially privileged.
So we definitely, while using the ai,
we must take into consideration that
it should not be the case that we are
implementing security in such a way that
those who are more financially stable are
getting to those security versus those
who are not that financially stable.
If.
Getting reprint from ING there.
So we just have to maintain a balance
and kind of implement in such a way that
cost should not be a bias at the consumer
level, making those kind of facilities
available to all level of consumer.
Privacy banking data is amongst
the most sensitive data.
And it has to go through so many laws.
It has G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A, so we
just need to make sure that we
comply with those kind of laws.
Otherwise miss you utilizing of those
kind of PIs can cause bank a lot of mail.
Explainability regulators won't accept
this bag box answer like modern LLS.
Most of the times we just keep
command and things get executed.
So we do have to deal with all
the regulations at the bank admin
level, and we need to make sure
that we have answers to any kind of
justification on any kind of output.
Security model sensor can be attacked,
obviously because that's a system.
There like we used to have in old
time R-D-B-M-S, we used to have
the SQL injection, so like that
we can have a prompt injection.
So we need to make our models
prepared for all this kind of setup.
So success is not about just the accuracy,
but it's also about trust and fairness.
So it is not an impossible to
overcome those kind of challenges,
but while designing our system, we
definitely have to make sure that we
take all of this into consideration.
So privacy preserving generative ai.
So obviously with that this is
also again, a part of the risk and
especially with the banking data.
There are lot of security issues.
There are a lot of privacy related issues.
So how do we do that?
We have to implement the federated
learning so we can have, we
can let the bank collaborate
without sharing the raw data.
So we can definitely think through
that direction to protect the privacy.
At the same time, use such a net.
B, we can use differential
privacy privacy that ensures
output can't expose individuals.
Explainable ai.
So this kind of the, in the previous
slide, this is one of the challenges
that we need explanation for the
regulatory and compliance things.
We cannot accept the black box answers.
So to do that, there is explainable
ai xai that helps regulators and users
understand the decision that this is
what happened, this is what is rejected,
why this has happened or rejected.
Without exposing the direct
rules, but also harm some user
understand format of the rules.
So when these are combined we
would definitely get systems that
are not only powerful, but also
ethical and reor regulatory ready.
So how do we use it in future
like autonomous finance?
Let's imagine where this
technology is heading.
We are on the path towards autonomous
finance, but many financial DI
decisions are optimized in real
time by intelligent systems.
So here are now three emerging directions
that our finance industry is heading to.
So multi-agent AI systems.
So instead of using a single model making
decisions, there are specialized agent
work together, farming and agent TKI.
This Azure system that has one agent
for risk, another for liquidity, another
for compliance, and they can negotiate
balance, trade off, self optimize.
For example, a risk agent might
signal an alert and liquidity
agent might automatically relocate
funds to mental stability.
So that is fully automated, right?
Without any kind of manual intervention.
So personal finance
copilot, so just as many as.
As many of us uses the GPS today for
any kind of navigation system, even
for searching a gas station, the
same way we can have an AI copilot
to for balancing our finances.
For example, the it can remind us
for the bill pay, it can remind
us of the credit card payment.
It can schedule the payment
for us in a more advanced way.
There is some account that
is running out of balance.
It can transfer funds between that
so it can actually start or manage
the finals in an autopilot mode.
From optimizing our monthly savings
to choosing the, choosing the
right tax advantage investment
to automatically adjusting the
portfolio to as the market shift.
And the third and the biggest one is
the large scale financial and simulation
regulators and central banks could
be AI driven simulations of entire
economics to credit systematic risk.
Imagine being able to stress test,
I release of a new currency, like
a digital dollar or a euro of
hundreds of scenario before launch.
So this is finance that is resilient
and in process, but again, success
depends on embedding fairness, privacy,
and transparency on every stage.
Moving on to bring this down
from vision to practice, let
me share a concrete case study.
Personalized wealth management
assistant, we piloted.
So we will have an input
process and output.
So from the input perspective, it we will,
it would be a system ingested customers,
real world data spending, pattern setting
behavior and investment preferences.
So what do we process in it?
It would be, it would
use the generative bi.
It'll create the customized report
projections and even what if scenarios.
For example, if we increase monthly
savings by 5% maybe we will reach our
retirement three years already again.
So what do we do?
What is our goal and what
do we do to achieve that?
Personalized proposals for
a solutions and output.
Generated tax optimization strategies.
For example that we should have there
was a tax investment scheme, like we
should have invested in four one K more.
We haven't.
So that kind of ended up with this
much of tax tax credit, which we could
have easily avoided by using this, and
we can probably plan that next year.
So what do we input, based on our
real time data, the process is the
what type analysis and output is.
What do we actually do to
avoid what we didn't the same.
So the results were remarkable.
The customer's engagement
increased by 40%.
The financial literacy score improved
significantly because the customer finally
understood the money in plain language,
which I say that from non-financial
consumers payments were, it is, it
was never more than just a number.
Just the numbers and some balance,
but they never used to understand
finance by looking at it statement
over last 30 days or 60 days.
It is probably just random numbers for
them, but with this generative AI and
simplified language and the storytelling,
like financial storytelling, that helps
the name and consumer to understand the
financial language and plan accordingly.
So this demonstrate that the generic
PPI isn't just password, it can
drive business KPI's, customer
satisfaction and regulatory alignment.
Moving on key takeaways.
So as we, there are four messages
that I would like to carry forward.
Generative AI is moving finance
from data to experience.
We are no longer limited
to raw transactions.
We are building personalized
financial journeys.
It enables both customer value and
institutional resilience on the front end.
The hyper-personalization
improves engagement.
On the backend, the synthetic fraud
scenarios and stress, strength, and
defenses responsible AI is non-negotiable.
Privacy, fairness and explainability are
the nice they're not just nice to have.
They're regulatory, ethical,
and strategic requirement.
The future is autonomous finals.
Multi-agent system, personal finance,
co-pilot global financial simulations
will transform not just the banks,
but also society, not also how
society interacts with the money.
If I had to summarize the winner, sub next
ticket in finance will be those who can
balance innovation with responsibility.
So with this note, I just would
like to conclude my presentation.
So generality, BI is not just transforming
finances, it is humanizing it, turning
core transaction into meaningful journey.
Thank you.