Hello everyone myself, Malika.
I am a software engineer working in
Barlay as a business inte developer
mainly focusing on building AI power
solutions that drive Smart Edition making.
So my tech stack is using tech
clicks, clicksense, Tableau,
sql data models and cloud-based
AI ML integration using Python.
So mainly focusing on turning complex
data into the actionable insights.
So I'm here to discuss on the ML ops
for the scalable BA and real time
analytics, like it's a comprehensive
guide to building, deploying, and
managing production grade machine
learning system and financial services.
So today agenda is, we are
focusing on five stages.
So one is first one, like here.
We'll start the fundamentals of
ML ops in financial services.
Then walk through the ML lifecycle
from injection to the deployment.
After that, we'll look at the monitoring
and governance and finally how all
of these currents with BI tools that
decision making make us use every day.
So we'll go through one by one.
Yeah.
Next one is the ML of maturity gap
in financial services, where you can
see the 83% of ML models in finance
never make it to the production.
That number should scare as well because
it means billions spent on talent
and platform without business value.
The reason of familiar complex
requirement that slow down the deployment
legacy system that resist integration
and the real time performance needs
that most pipeline can't handle.
The big insight here.
The bot link is in model development.
It's everything that happens after.
From building models to managing them.
The reason is clear, it's not
enough to develop a great algorithm.
Financial banks need framework
that automate auditor has integrate
models with legacy systems and
monitoring performance in real time.
This is where ML ops comes in.
Think of it as a bridge between model
development and business impact.
Automating the pipeline that handle
deployment, logging, and compliance check.
Whereas next stage would be the
versioning and monitoring tools
so that it makes sure every model
update is stress and if suddenly
risk reviews that used to take weeks.
It can happen in days or even hours.
The point is when you solve.
After problem, all the investment
in talent and technology.
Finally start paying off model, move
from prototype to production, and
business teams actually see the results.
That's how we close the gap
between building something
amazing and making it useful.
Yeah.
Next slide would be
the financial MI cycle.
So it has a multiple stages.
So each stage has its financial
twist coming to the first
stage of data injection.
So it is not just pulling the CSV files
you are streaming marketing data injecting
payment data, and even using the alternate
data sets for that, whereas coming to
the next stage, featuring engineering
which is a critical for risk signals,
things like violating windows credit
utilization ratios, or liquidity metrics.
And coming to the next stage model
training which needs versioning
and para parameter tracking, but
also regulatory documentation.
Every DEC decision needs to be expandable.
Coming to the next stage is deployment,
so model might be, must be ized,
deployed via continuous integration
or continuous deployment, and often
tested with the required frameworks.
And last stage is monitoring.
This is this includes a drift
performance metrics and compliance,
auditing and financial impact.
So each stage has unique demand in
finance, especially in the documentation.
And sable.
Coming to the next slide which is a tech
stack for ML ops, for the fine tech, so
we can, I can go with the breakdown for
the ML ops, like data engineering and
the management would be the first task.
Stage one, like data pipelines, like
tools like Apache Airflow and Apache
Spark Q Flow help build building the
automated data pipeline that handle
data extraction transformation,
and loading the ETL to ensure high
quality input Strat for the models.
And within the same area, data versioning
and tracking tools like DVC data
version control enable teams to track
data sets, change changes across the
experiment, and making it easier to
reproduce and debug modules and another.
Another thing is like data quality
monitoring, like ensuring data
quality through validation.
Tools like monitoring prop helps
detect issues such as missing values
or anomalies that could degrade
model performance, which comes
under the data quality monitoring.
Whereas like second the other other
module is model experimental and
versioning, which is nothing but
experiment tracking like ML flow and.
ML Flow are used to log model
hyper parameters, metrics, and
configuration, and allowing those
data scientists to systematically
compare experiment for comparison.
We so for the comparison we use
neptune.ai and within the same
area, the model versioning are
stored in registry like ML flow.
Model ing, which documents the
metadata training data training
data and performance metrics for eg
versioning and tracking the deployment.
And coming to the deployment.
So deployment with the CSCD pipeline,
like using automated module testing
and validating and ensuring that
all the models are thoroughly
evaluated before the deployment.
This streamline streamlines the
continuous integration and deployment
of the new models and the scalable
deployment, like continuation with
Docker and orchestration using.
Es enable, enable the flexible and
scalable model deployments, which
is nothing but adapting the resource
to the real time domain mind.
And using the Bento ml and Amazon
SAG Maker is a fully managed
cloud-based machine learning that
provides tools and services to
build, train, and apply ML models.
And next stage would be the
monitoring and maintenance like.
We are using evidently, AI for
drift detections and for the
metric collections as well.
Yeah.
Next slide would be featuring engineering
in financial data, whereas like some.
Financial ml require specialization,
feature engineering to capture temporal
pattern market and the risk factors
where coming to the temporal patterns in
finance, the timing of events is critical.
Generic features like average price don't
capture the market first, but you want
to feature that reflect how price and
volume evaluate over the time, right?
Let's say, example, let's smooth
out short term fluctuations
and high highlighting trends.
So short term versus long term and
make and signal movement to challenges.
So we coming to the market,
MicroStrategy future, this is nothing
but this bit spread the difference
between buying and selling the price.
Which comes within the same
area, like depth imbalance.
Transaction cost and sleep level.
Coming to the next slide CSCD for the
financial MI models, which is nothing
but continuous integration and continuous
deployment, whereas coming to the data
validation, every new data must be passed.
Quality and bias check.
Next stage would be data model training.
Training pipeline generates
the documentation and risk
reports automatically.
And next stage would be the testing
and staging that can read department,
reduce risk before full rollout re
regulatory gates, which is the next stage.
Like compliance reviews are
integrated in the pipeline.
So approval rt, manual bottlenecks.
CSCD isn't just a DevOps idea, it's a
governor frameworks in financial mi.
So next day next slide would be the
real time interface architecture.
This is where ML ops made systems
systems engineering, whereas low
latency use cases like fraud detection,
algo trading, instant credit scoring.
If you are too slow, either
fraud slips through, a legitimate
customer gets declined.
So come with tech stack tech stack
solutions like optimization model or
GPU acceleration and streaming platform
like Kafka something sometimes even
edge deployments, which takes a matter.
So the other thing is
like scalability pattern.
To handle market payments to wide variety,
you need auto-scaling clusters and a
load balancing and ation framework to
keep core services Stable in finance and
performance is not just nice to have,
it's must that it should deal with it.
And next would be the complaints
and governance for the FinTech.
Okay governance is the foundation like
model cards that compel with SR 11 by
17 and exp expandability report using
shape and line, so washing control
violation, artifacts for audit, you need
an immutable logs reportable environment,
and deploying deployment issues.
Security also matters like encrypting
a pipeline component and using a strict
role based contact access and scanning
container without these like you can't
have mls so you have a risk exposure here.
And monitoring financial ML in production.
There are a few steps to track
down in production for monitoring
the machine learning so that track
is nothing but track data and
prediction drift over the time.
Your model input data and its prediction
can shift leading to decreased accuracy.
So monitoring these trips helps
identifying when retraining is necessary.
Watch for the training service crew ensure
that the data used during training closely
matches the data and the production.
Significant decreases differences can
cause the model to perform poorly.
Like next would be the
monitoring data pipeline health.
Issues in data process can introduce
errors or delays affecting data model's
performance, keeping an eye on this
pipeline, ensure smooth operation.
The other would be evaluating model
performance continuously and which
is nothing but back testing and other
metrics to access how we model the
performing the real time conditions.
So this helps in making information
about updates or re retraining.
Finally the setup setup the alarm
implementing alert mechanism to quickly
detect and respond to any unexpected
changes in model behavior performance.
So by focusing on these areas
you can maintain the ability and
effectiveness of your mission
learning models and production.
Coming to the next slide,
like concept driven.
Drift management in financial model.
Drift management in financial model
is about detecting changes in data
and relationship that can degrade
model performance all the time.
So it involves monitoring, input,
features and model predictions.
Using metrics like PSA or kl ence
to flagships when drift is detected.
Models are recalibrated or retrained
on recent data to maintain accuracy.
So continuous monitoring and governance
ensure the model stays reliable in
dynamic market or credit environment.
So next slide would be, the integrating
ml with the BI tools in finance, like
integration approaches or like a PS
for the model prediction and endpoints
and embedded Python are for in dash com
dashboard computation and pre-computer
feature stores for the low latency access.
Custom visualization extensions
for the model insights.
To these capabilities that
suppose the BI platform is Tableau
or bi looker and ThoughtSpot.
Whereas there's process for that
integrating the ML with the BI
tools and finances pretty predicate
to analytics like ML algorithm
analysis, historical data to forecast.
Future trends such as sales or
customer's behavior and enabling the
proactive decision making and also
automated the insight, insights and
enhancing the forecasting and detection
and personalized recommendation.
So that would be the integrating
the BI tools with the mi.
Next would be the NLP Dr.
Driven Financial Analytics.
Which is nothing but ai.
Added it course like NLP technologies
built on the interaction of computer
science, artificial intelligence.
And so main core components
of NP systems are like.
Tokenization passing and machine learning.
Which is nothing but breakdown
text into the different
individual words or pa passes.
Allowing systems to analyze
smaller part of a sentence.
Such words are shorter basis is
nothing but a to tokenization.
And the next would be the passing.
That understanding the grammatical
structure helps system integrator
relationship between words.
And finally, the NLP model can
generate more accurately by using the
machine learning outputs, by training
with vast amount of text data, while
additionally data can enhance performance.
Model also need careful monitoring to
avoid the degradation over the time.
So machine learning uses an
algorithm to detect pattern.
Text enabling the NLP system to
identify and categorize data efficiency.
This approach allows models to
recognize recurring themes, sentiments,
and entities within the text data.
And key takeaways are like.
Start with the, when we design something,
like start with the architecture, like
designing machine, learning of pipeline
with the specific requirement in mind
from day one and integrate early, connect
the ML capabilities directly into the
existing BI tools where users already
trust that tool and make it governance.
And com compliance isn't an,
and afterthought, I built
it into your workflows.
Yeah, that's all.
Thank you.