Hello everyone.
My name is, I am a solutions
engineer at Symbiotic LLC.
I have just over six years of experience
in warehouse automation engineering,
where I design, implement large
scale automated distribution centers.
My work spans fortune hundred
retailers across grocery, healthcare
app, RL, and paid food sectors.
I help them transform supply chain
operations with robotics, ai.
And advance ML operation practices.
Today we'll be discussing why AI
system that look flawless in the lab
often fail in real world warehouses
or experiences, and most importantly,
how we can prevent those failures.
So let me begin with Paradox.
The autonomous mobile market, mobile
robot market is surging worldwide.
Warehouses are inventing investing
millions into AI systems that
are in the lab and deliver
success rates of above 90%.
But there is reality when these
systems enter real warehouses,
performances often collapses.
We have seen projects delayed for months,
millions wasted, and operations disrupted.
Why does this happen?
That's the story I will
share with you today.
So here is what I'll cover in next
20 minutes for devastating failure
patterns in ml in real world that
are not considered, that issues
were not considered in labs.
The blind spot in the ML operations
that caused them performance breakdowns,
game changing strategies for success.
My goal is my goal is to leave
you a practical playbook that
you can take back to your teams.
So first failure pattern is the
physical reality gap in the lab.
Robotic picking bot looks flawless
as you can see in the picture.
But what happens when the
system meets the real world?
Scenarios like transparent shrink wrap.
When the pallet is built completely by
robots and they wrapped with plastic.
Then second one is irregular shape
products, and third one is dust
interfering with vision sensors which are
built, or which are, which have placed
on the robots, the accuracy plunges,
sometimes from 95% down to early 60%,
and.
What are the blind spots do you think of?
I think blind spots are clear here.
First of all, if I was mentioning
about lab, that means training data.
That lab is considering lacked messy real
world cases or real world experiences.
I would say second one is validation
happen only in labs, not on life floors.
And when errors happen, no feedback
loop pushed back into retraining.
So teams optimized for
benchmarks instead of reality.
They set their benchmark and they aim high
in lab, but in reality it was different.
So the results was brittle systems
I, so second failure pattern I would
say is forecasting models predicted
demand perfectly until market
volatility hit volatility, hit.
Suddenly we had overstocking of wrong
SKUs, empty shelves during peak demand
and error rates, spiraling, unchecked.
And what other root cause do you think of?
So root cause first one is no robust
drift detection, outdated ground
truth, and no human in loop oversight.
That means human in the loop verification
points led to cascading errors.
When error cost, and fourth one is
no fallback plan when things went
wrong, there should be some plan B.
When we think of going system in wrong
direction, it's like driving blind.
The model keeps staring even
as it heads off the clip.
Third pattern is similar,
I would say to everyone.
Have you ever had a deployment
where warehouses ran seven to eight
middleware systems, and each one seemed
fine in isolation, but the moment
traffic spiked, the latency cascade
across them like falling dominoes?
The single schema mismatch
become single point of failure,
the entire deploy deployment.
Collapsed like house of cards
and the root cause issues.
The root cause issues are monitoring
was not shared across teams.
When we are monitoring any issues or we
are finding any, we are, if we are, we
have new findings, we should always share
across the teams and get their feedback.
Second one is testing only covered
components, not the full system,
and no graceful degradation plans.
There should be some plan B always
in term when we know there might
be some chances of failures.
And the last failure I would
think of is human factor.
You can design most advanced systems, but
if workers don't trust, they won't use it.
Think of this what happens when early
failures cause operators to bypass
the automation I have dealt with.
Operators with 20 years of experience,
they are doing things manually.
And when it comes, when the point comes of
automation implementation and using those,
the operators are hesitant to use the new
advanced systems due to fear of losing job
or they are not ready to use advancement.
They think they are more productive
the way they're doing the things.
That's exactly what
happened at one autonomous.
Parts distributor, they invested
approximate 7 million system and, but the
no work, but the workforce rejected it.
The entire system was abandoned
and they wasted $7 million.
So what are the game changing
strategies you think of here?
So I think first one is phase deployment.
Start with small control pilots
running shadow mode alongside existing
operations Scale progressively
when metrics are validated.
So I have been working closely
with one of the customer a
retailer biggest customer in USA.
They have implementing their
warehouse automation into.
Different phases.
For one of the FA Warehouse, they
have three to four phases and they
will work on only one phase at a time.
And alongside they will have
their existing operations running.
And this help that organization
drastically, which reduce
integration risk by nearly 40%
compared to Big Bang launches.
So obviously phase
deployment always helps.
This is the first strategy.
I would think of and I
would suggest definitely.
The second one is comprehensive
testing protocols.
We should have a comprehensive
testing protocols use advise
testing, stress test edge cases.
Always use the worst case
scenarios for your testing.
Use chaos engineering deliberately
break things and see how your system
approaches or deals with these things.
Augment training with
synthetic edge cases.
And test, test the whole
integrated system under peak load.
And one other thing is always this
system we should test in peak modes,
which is like when you have festivals
like Christmas, black Friday, sales.
So we should consider those peak times
and test your systems so that you get a
hundred percent results and you understand
where the failure might come from.
Those who adopted these methods
cut failures drastic dramatically.
Third strategy, I would
think of human AI approaches.
Hybrid human AI approach.
Define clear human in loop.
In the loop protocols, there should
be always some protocols to inter
intervene humans in the automation
and they should work side by side.
Feed human corrections
back into the training.
If there are any correction errors made
by human, we should always feed them
into training so that those errors are
not, have, will not happen in future.
And design AI to augment
humans, not to replace them.
The best outcomes I have,
the best outcomes I have
seen were not just accuracy.
Some warehouses achieved 99 plus
percent of inventory accuracy
and improved workforce morality.
So as I promised, there
will be a playbook.
So here's the playbook I would think of.
First, I would say it's validation.
Validate the in the new invention in
real world condition, not just in labs.
Always use worst case
scenarios and test your.
Operations, monitor
everything across all systems.
Integrate humans in the loop
and take their feedback and
use that data to retrain them.
Deploy incrementally, not all at once.
Plan for resilience, graceful
degradation, and fallback modes.
There should be always some plan
beef when it comes or when you
know that the system might fail,
For closing.
And the key takeaways I would think
of is the most successful warehouse
automation projects don't always
have most advanced algorithms.
They succeed because they follow
machine learning operation practices.
So remember, the Lab of Success
is not operational success.
Monitor everything and plan for it.
Plan for the drift test systems
holistically, not just in parts that.
Test them in parts as well
as a hundred percent with a
hundred percent implementation.
Never underestimate the human factor.
Always consider humans operators when
implementing a new warehouse automation,
because they're the one will be working.
Ask them questions.
Ask or take their feedback in the
loop and apply when you are designing
or when you're implementing things.
Also make sure or feel them, let them or
try to make them comfortable with the new
machineries or new system so that they
don't feel that they're losing their jobs
and phase deployments to manage risk.
Always deploy these new automation
in different phases, not whole
warehouse system in one go.
So that's all.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you for your.