Hello everyone, and thank
you for joining my session.
My name is Raju Shari.
I'm a senior cloud and ML lops
engineer with over 10 years of
experience building large scale
cloud and machine learning systems.
Currently at Freddie Mac, I'm
a senior cloud developer on the
enterprise data science platform.
Today I'm talking about scaling ML
mops with self service platforms.
Here's a roadmap for my talk today.
First.
We'll look at the evolution of ML
operations, like how organizations
move from satellite experiments to
enterprise grade production systems.
Second, I've introduced the cell service
platform architecture and it's key
components, integration patterns, and the
go governance models that supports it.
Third, we will discuss a measured impact
and implementation roadmap, including case
studies, metrics, actionable steps for
organizations that want to get started.
Finally, I will share future trends and
strategic positioning, things like auto
ml, serverless ml, and premise, which
will reshape how financial services
approach ML ops in the coming years.
So by the end of the session, you should
have a clear understanding of how cell
service platforms can drive efficiency,
governance, and innovation all at once.
Let's begin with MLS maturity shift.
In the financial industry,
human operations has gone
through a big transformation.
We started with solid experiments.
Teams build models in isolation, often
method without path to production.
Deployments are manual,
slow, error prone, and how to
reproduce later are inconsistent.
Water worked.
One laptop might fail in production.
The governance was aocc with the
little oversight of traceability.
Overall, rever disability was limited.
Making it hot to scale or meet
regulatory requirements over
time, this evolved into integrated
platforms that generalize the pool.
MLI cycle.
These platforms bring consistency,
automation, and governance
while assuring compliance.
This shift from acceleration
to integrated platforms.
Is it hot OPT task scaling ML mops
in banking and financial services?
Now that we've seen how ML operations
was involved, evolved, let's talk about
why self service platform matters.
You see there is 71 point percent
duction in the data preparation time
because platforms provide standardized
pipelines and reusable components.
A 40%, 40% duction in training
cost by optimizing compute.
So the workload run on their.
Instead of wasting resources like
GPU and CPU 8 38 30 8% improvement
in deployment success with indicated
CACD pipelines and enrollments.
But beyond the numbers,
platforms transform.
All financial institutions
manage ML risk and compliance.
They enable force innovation while
maintaining strict regulatory standards.
Now look at the code
platform architecture.
Strong architecture is the foundation
for organizational ml at scale.
It ensure the platform is
stable, secure, and compliant.
While supporting the MLI cycle
and meeting the regulatory needs,
the architecture has three layers.
The first one is
foundation infrastructure.
Its scalable.
CPUs and G Bs.
Resilient shortage and secure networking
organization must decide whether to
go cloud or on-premises or hybrid.
Here Kubernetes key role
in standardization while
strong data securities,
essentially related industries.
The second one is data and
feature engineer management.
Unified environment for data
envision, processing, validation,
versioning, and incentive feature.
Short the feature short, ensure
consistency and reasonability
while keeping everything auditable.
The third ml lifecycle management.
This covers fermentation,
draining, versioning, deployment,
and continuous monitoring.
It includes C, D pipelines,
registries, testing, and observability.
Ensuring models are high
performing and compliant.
So in short, provides the power data,
provides a foundation and lifecycle
ensures governance and control.
Now let's put the piece together
and work at the different
architecture in financial services.
A platform like this crucial,
it helps tax in complexity.
So data scientist can focus on
models, ensure provisioning,
compute, networking, or storage.
So at the same point, it's built by
compliance Andro the street controls,
generates audit trials or in an inch
and deployment and ensure separation
of duties between developers,
operators, and compliance teams.
So when regulator ask how this
model client, who approved it,
my data was used, when was it?
Is it updated?
The platform provides answer answers in
gently, so in stock, achi and operations
for ensuring security and compliance.
Now, let look the key components here.
There are four pillars.
First, content or situation
ban schedules, ML workforce,
customer resources behind jobs.
So they CanBan consistently
across environments.
Scalability and isolation
in multitenant setup.
The second here is distributed compute,
spa and DOS handle lodge scale data.
They provide parallel computing and
lineage tracking, so every transformation
can be traced, which regulators demand.
The third, the model registry and
artifact stored all time models have with
compliance metadata, who trained them when
data was used and when they were uploaded.
So prevent UN from going live and.
CRYPTOGRAPHICS checks ensure
models are not tampered with the
fourth CICD integration here.
Automated pipelines run test
security scans and approval
gates before deployment.
This enables post consistent
and complete releases.
Together these four pillars make
platforms scalable, secure, and auditable.
Let's talk about governance layer.
So up to this point, we
talked about infras compute.
Pipelines.
The final layer that ties
everything together is governance.
So without governance platforms,
these regulated industries
simply cannot succeed.
So it has three parts.
The first automated policy
enforcement, the platform enforces
access controls at runtime, respect,
model limits, and applies security.
Security consistently.
Even if a data scientist config
misconfigured something, the
platform prevent compliance issues.
Second, compliance documentation.
Model course lineage diagrams
and validation reports were
generated automatically.
Instead of manual documentation.
Evidence is corrected in real time
as part of third audit observability.
The platform capture, lack
logs, monitoring data and
explainability outputs.
If a regulator ask, why did
this model make a decision?
The platform provides
explainability immediately.
The takeaway.
The governments must be built in
front of the stock, not voted on.
Later
here, self service experience,
developer view, the goal is
freedom to innovate quickly, but
within the compliance boundaries.
This can be shared in two ways.
First, AB obsession with control.
Developers use curated
environments with pre-approved
packages, so they avoid setup.
The award setup delays, security risk.
So templates given consistency
across team for more, more flexible
team allows custom environments
without breaking guard guidelines.
Second, seen as that flow with one click.
Developers deploy models into staging
complaints, check and documentation,
and automatically integrated
packing and monitoring health
track performance issues between.
For developers, the platform
feed simple brand cost.
Behind the scenes it enforces
governance, compliance, and security.
Now we talk about building versus buying.
One of the most important question
here is it should we build the platform
ourself or by a commercial solution?
There are three options here.
First, in our development offers
full customization and integration
with legacy systems, but it usually
takes 12 to 18 months and the query
requires a team of specialized
engineers, second commercial platforms.
Faster time.
Faster time to value, usually three
to six months, and we include building
complaints, but you make force
vendor LOCKIN integration challenges.
Third, the hybrid approach.
Take a vendor code for speed, then
add even one governance integration.
These feature reach tion
in six to nine months.
For most financial organization, the
hybrid approach is the best balance of
speed, customization and complaints.
Let's talk about future of mops.
Strong foundations will sell highly
platforms, governance, automation, but the
architectures of the feature go further.
It involves HML most workload
closer to data sources.
It reduces ency improving privacy
and cutting cost for fraud detection
and trading makes a big difference.
Enterprise ml, it enables automated
model selection and tuning.
Its explainability built in so
business users can build models safely.
Serverless trainings, we shift to
event driven paper use models, making
process simpler and cost efficient
while keeping governance intact.
Privacy, preserving ml, its uses federated
learning and encryption to train across
silos without exposing sensitive data.
Today's architecture choices should
prepare us per this edge, native,
automated, and privacy first future.
We talk about engineer architecture.
Traditionally, ML and finance
has been cloud-based, centralized
training and inference.
It works, but introduce latency and
require more into data to be to the cloud.
The next step is hybrid training
in the cloud inference at the edge,
this registers latency for realtime
use cases while keeping scalability.
The ultimate stage is edge.
Need two ml training across distributed
devices with the Feder learning.
Running models directly on device,
discuss dis discuss latency by up to 40%.
And hand.
Hand has privacy.
Since data never lease its source.
The future will be hybrid and Azure.
A two.
Combining cloud scale
and edge responsiveness.
Let's talk about emerging trends.
Financial ML ops first enterprise
auto ML Automation with guard rails,
automatic model selection, hyper tuning.
But with explainability so
regulators can audit out outputs.
Second serverless PY is event driven
paper computation ml that emulates heavy
infrastructure while still enforcing
governance code privacy, preserving ml.
Its use ED learning and encryption to
PY models without exposing sensor data.
This enables collaboration with while
maintaining privacy together auto ML for
speed, serverless efficiency, privacy,
preserving ML for complaints, create
a blueprint of next generation ML ops.
Here are the four.
Here are key takeaways.
First, platforms are so essential.
Scaling M Financial services
without them is not illustrate.
Second, governance must be and build
from the start, not added later.
Third, start at the
minimum viable platform.
Focus on the first restriction
areas, then expand.
And fourth.
Plan, the feature's edition
will shape how Ready we are.
Edge Auto ML and privacy reserving
ml. Here's 90 Day Roadmap one.
All ML workflows and complaints.
Gap design requirements in
both technical AGGREGATORY
teams prototype the small team.
It's usually have to do three
points, deliver an MB, focus on high
friction areas and measure success
with KPAs like deployment time, donor
efficiency, and level of satisfaction.
So by calling these steps, organization
can move from foundation to enterprise
grade ML in a structured way.
And that's it.
I will bring this session to close.
Thank you so much for your time.