Hello everyone.
My name is bu.
As a DevSecOps and multi-cloud
architect, I have spent the last 19 years
helping companies architect secure and
optimize their cloud infrastructures.
I have had opportunity to lead
some incredible projects from
innovating gene based solutions
for AIOps to re-engineering high
performance payment systems.
The topic I'm here to discuss today is one
of the topic I'm deeply passionate about,
securing our, a pipelines from development
all the way to production as we.
Op operationalize machine learning.
We will creating we are creating
a new kind of battlefield.
The challenge is that our traditional
DevSecOps practices, which we have relayed
on for years simply fail to address the
novel threats that ML ops introduces.
We are facing an attack
surface that extend beyond
code to our data, our models.
And our entire infrastructure
today, we are going on a journey.
We'll start with the reality
that you have vulnerable ML
models, but we won't stay there.
We are going to move from a state
of vulnerability to position
of strength and creating what
I call unbreachable pipelines.
We will do this by looking at real proven
security frameworks, seeing a security in
action and leveraging battlefield tested
strategies used by Fortune 500 companies.
My goal is simple to show you
how to stop playing defense and
make your pipelines more robust.
So how will.
We get there.
Here are our agenda for today.
First we will define the problem
by looking at the expanding
ML apps attack surface.
Then we will introduce the solution,
adopting the zero trust mindset.
The core idea of never
trust, always verify.
Then we will get the practical
with the framework applying these
principles across ML lifecycle.
I will share the impact with the proven
results and real world case studies.
And finally I will leave you with
the, with your roadmap actionable
steps to get started on building
truly secure MOPS environment.
So let's start with the core problem.
Machine learning pipelines have created
a brand new security battlefield.
The traditional DevSecOps practices
we have relied on for years simply
failed to address these challenges.
Think of your ML ops pipelines.
Like this hose in a practic,
in perfect world clean.
One valuable data flows through
it, through, through it smoothly.
But in reality this pipelines
has multiple weak points.
An attacker can target your training data,
poisoning it stealing, seal it outright.
They can go after the model itself.
Tampering the tampering with its logic.
And stealing intellectual property,
they can compromise the underlying
infrastructure where your model
is trained, or they can attack the
interface endpoints where your model
makes live decisions leading to envision
attacks, data leakage, the attack
surface has expanded beyond just code.
And we, we need a new
strategy to defend it.
So let's zoom in on this.
Hidden threats.
While we still worry about traditional
code, vulnerables ML Labs brings
a new and dangerous class of high
risk threats to the forefront.
Let's look at three major
ML lab specific threats.
First data poisoning, which has a
staging sta staging 95 risk score.
Imagine an attacker stop subscale
feeds your fraud detection model.
Bad data, turning your fraud
detector into fraud enabler.
Next is model theft with
an 85 5% of risk score.
This is a direct attack on
your company, core business
asset, your proprietary models.
Finally, we have interface interference
attacks, carrying 90% risk score.
This is where an attacker manipulate
a live model to get desired outputs or
to extract confidential information.
It was trained on.
So how do we fight back?
The solution is a fundamental
shift in mindset called zero trust.
The core principle is simple but powerful.
Never trust, always verify.
It's a security model built
on maintaining strict access.
Access controls, not trusting
anyone by de default.
Even if they are already
inside your network.
What does this means for ML apps?
It means every single
action is scrutinized.
Every request to access data or
deploy a model must be authenticated
authorized and continuously verified.
And the benefits is not
just a theoretical adopting.
This approach has.
Shown a cause of 70 by 73%
reduction in security instruments.
This is not just about better security,
it's about building a more resilient and
trustworthy AI systems from ground up.
So it's important to understand
that applying zero trust
is not a. Single action.
It's a continuous practical
practice applied at every
stage of ML Labs pipelines.
We are going to break down the
implementation of zero trust into four
key stages of machine learning life cycle.
We'll start with the data and
preparation where we securely
gather and prepare our data.
Then we will move to model
training and validation.
Ensure we train our models with
a strict action access controls.
After that, we will cover
deployment and survey serving where we
deploy models into secure environments.
And then finally, we look at
monitoring and governance.
Where we continuously watch watch over our
models to keep them in secure production.
Let's start the start at
the foundation Data inion.
The goal here is to fortify your
data foundation in machine learning.
We all know the phrase, garbage in,
garbage out, but from a security
perspective, it's far worse.
It's the poisoning and poison
out, how do we apply zero trust?
Here we build a SEC data security pyramid.
At the base we'll use a strict identity
and access management to enforce
authentication for data sources.
Next, we enforce data encryption for
all data, both in transit addressed.
Under trust.
Finally, at the top we ensure
data, lineage and integrity.
We need to be able to track data
origins and transformations using
checksums to verify that the
data has not been tampered with
stage two model training and validation.
So now.
We move to stage two model training.
This is where your secret SaaS is
created, and our goal is to secure
this environment at all cost.
We do this in three key ways.
First, we created
fortified training zones.
Think of this as a isolated every
training job in a sandbox container.
To prevent unauthorized access.
We then server all, we serve all necessary
network access and scan every dependency.
Second, we enforce the
principles of least p release.
The A training script should only have
absolute minimum permissions if needed.
To function, read access to
necessary data and right access to
specific model artifact location.
And the third, we focus on
mold model artifact security.
Every model that is trained should
be digitally signed and versioned.
Those models are then stored in a
secure and audited model registry.
With its own strict access controls
stage three deployment and serving.
In stage three, we focus
on deployment and serving.
This is where the model meets
the real world, interfacing
with users and other systems.
So our goal is to hard
these live endpoints.
We start with the runtime protection model
should be deployed on hardened minimal
container images using network policies
to restrict all unnecessary traffic.
Then we secure the A
PA endpoint endpoints.
Every single interface request must
require authentication and authorization.
We also need to implement a
practical defense like rate limiting.
And input validation.
Finally, we need a secure
configuration management, things
like a PA key keys and database
credentials should never be hardcoded.
They must be stored in a managed,
in a dedicated secret manager like
HashiCorp Walt or a W Secret manager.
Monitoring and governance.
Our final stage is
monitoring and governance.
Here, our mindset has to shift.
Our goal is to assume breach and to be
continuously look looking for threats.
Security is not a static,
it's a living cycle.
It start with the continuous monitoring.
We need to log every request,
response, and access event
across entire pipeline analysis.
With that data, we perform
behavioral analysis.
We actu, we actively look for anomalies
like model performance drift, and data
skew, which can indicate a subtile attack.
When anomaly detected, we
trigger automated response.
Instead of waiting for a human,
we have automated workflows to
mitigate threats such as review,
taking access, alerting the security
team for further investigation.
So what is the ultimate
impact of all this work?
Adopting zero trust framework
does not, does more than
just, we just reduce the risk.
It's a fundamental build resiliency
by design, you shift your
entire secure security posture.
You move from reacting to threats
to a building, a pipeline, secure
pipeline that expects and ies them.
By verifying every action and enforcing
the principles of least privileged
access, you harden your systems
agonist, both external internal threats.
The result is a dramatically lowering of
your organization overall risk profile,
and leading to that proven 73% reduction
in breaches we talked about earlier.
So let's look at how
this works in real world.
Let first FinTech leader, so
they challenge was immense.
They need to be protected
and sensitive financial data,
proprietary fraud detection models by
implementing a zero trust strategy.
Their solution was.
To implement a strict IEM and sign
all model artifacts, the result they
eliminate, they eliminated all major
audit findings on data access controls
and reduce the time they team spent on
manual com compliance reporting by 40%.
Next consider a healthcare platform.
The challenge was complying
with hipaa while using a
patient data for a diagnostics.
Their solution was to deploy models
in isolated environments with their
token based a PA authentication.
The outcome was a huge success.
They achieved a HIPAA compliance, and
most importantly, secure sensitive
patient healthcare information.
So this might seem like a lot,
but you can begin with journey
today with four actionable steps.
This is your roadmap to zero
test ML Labs, the first assess
and baseline identify all.
Components in your ML pipeline
and map current access controls
to find high risk areas.
Second, implement a strong
identity, assign unique identity
to all users and services and
enforce multifactor authentication.
Third, enforce least privileged
access grant only minimal.
Permissions required for each task.
Use just in time access
where it is possible.
And fourth, monitor and respond.
Implement continuous logging and
anom anomaly detection to identify
and contain threats in real time.
The good news is.
You don't have to build all
the, all this from scratch.
There is a rich ecosystem of
security tools you can leverage
to implement this framework for
identity and access management.
You have tools like Okta, Azure
active Directory, HashiCorp Vault,
and AWS or GCP, secret Manager
for code and container security.
You can use scanners like sync.
Three V and dependent bot for networks
and runtime security services.
Service mesh O are linker can handle
encryption and policies where while
Falco can detect runtime threats.
And finally, for data model governance
tools like DVC can track data lineage.
While ML flow or clear ML
can provide secure model,
as you start on this path, there
are like, there are a few common
pitfalls I wanted to avoid first.
Don't ignore the human element.
If you create so much friction,
your data scientist will.
Build insecure shadow IT workflows.
The solution is to automate security
within the CACD pipeline and prove
secure by default project templates.
Second, the set.
The set, set and forget mentality.
Zero.
Trust is continuous process,
not a one time setup.
You must regularly logs,
rotate credentials, and perform
automated security drills.
Finally, remember to treat models
differently than regular code.
A signed container is good,
but it doesn't prevent a model
from being stolen and poisoned.
You need model specific controls
like digital signature for.
The artifact themself and actively
monitor for performance drift.
So as we wrap up, I wanted to leave
you with the core four takeaways,
which you can think of as the
MLF security pyramid at the base.
I understand that ML maps
attack surface is unique.
It extends beyond code to
data models, infrastructure
requiring a specialized approach.
The next layer is embracing
the zero trust mindset.
Never trust, always verify is the
guiding principle to effectively
secure modern AA systems.
Building on that, remember that securities
security is a life cycle, not checkbox.
You must apply zero trust controls
at every stage from data ingestion to
production monitoring, and finally, at
the top know the results are proven.
Adopting this framework is
a strategic investment that.
Secure and reduce the secure
and reduce security incidents.
So that brings to me
end of my presentation.
We have covered unique threats
facing ML lops and laid out a
comprehensive proven framework to
make your a pipelines unbreachable.
Thanks for your time.
I would like to be happy
to answer any questions.
You can reach out to me in
my LinkedIn or like my email.
Id.
Thank you guys.
Okay.