Hi everyone.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Nja.
Today I'll be sharing insights on how
we can successfully scale AI systems in
the financial industry, specifically,
how to handle high volume transactions.
While processing and while staying
compliant with strict regulations,
the talk will cover on operational
strategies, infrastructure
choices, and real world lessons.
We have learned from deploying
ML pipelines across the financial
services transactional ecosystem.
What is the challenges that we are looking
at when we look at financial institutions?
The challenges are unlike in
any other industry, right?
Fundamentally.
We are processing billions and billions
of transactions with less than a
millisecond of a second response times.
On top of that, every decision
must satisfy the regulations like
G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A of CRA, and then
you have to also maintain 99.99%
of time for critical systems.
While achieving the uptime latency is
another aspect of it as well, right?
You need to provide responses within a
fraction of a second while also making
sure that the right decisions are made
at the right time, the right level of
compliance checks and balances happen.
I'll give you an example, right?
When you're doing a credit card
authorization transaction, the
authorization has to happen in less than
like a fraction of a second because the
customer is still there in the session.
While the customer is still there
in the session, you are engaging
with the customer behind the scenes.
You need to make sure that KYC
is done, the KYB is done, the
sanction screening check is done.
So all these things have to
happen simultaneously in parallel.
And then final decision has
to be taken while ensuring the
business outcomes are met, right?
Because every.
Every drop that happens when the
checkout conversion doesn't happen,
that means it's a lost sale.
A lost sale means it's a lost in revenue.
So these are the factors that
needs to be considered when we
are looking at deploying machine
learning systems in financial space.
What are the three three
critical financial applications?
There are three core areas.
One is, as I alluded in the previous
example, it is real time fraud detection.
Then the credit assessment, then automated
financial management of it, the first,
again, I'll quickly touch base on this.
The first is real time fraud detection
models that can scan millions
of daily transactions to spot
suspicious activity milliseconds.
The credit assessments where
platforms needs to value the
credit worthiness while remaining
compliant and explainable, right?
Imagine a scenario where you are
applying for a personal loan or
you're applying for a credit card.
You would have seen this from
your real world examples, like
what the decision is in life.
Few seconds, but behind the scenes, the
whole aspect of assessment, prospecting,
underwriting, all these things need
to happen in a pretty quick time.
And lastly, it is the
financial management.
Everything from portfolio optimization
to old algorithmic trading to
personalize financial guidance.
These are mission critical so that
they rely on the strong ML operations
foundations and the associated pipelines.
Real time fraud detection
architecture is super important.
As you can see over here on this
slide what I'm presenting over
here is various channels, right?
You have the transaction
sources from where.
A transaction can originate.
You have point of sale channels, you have
online channels, you have mobile channels.
So all these channels have their own
respective streams, and those streams of
data have to be processed and published.
And that is where the next aspect of
pipelines and feature store come into the.
Where we outline what are the low
latency inference systems, what
are the decision engines, what are
their rules that they're applying?
And finally monitoring
and audit systems, right?
Ensure telemetry,
retaining, and compliance.
The key point here though, fraud
detection isn't just about a model.
It's about a pipeline that can
handle massive scale in seconds.
What are the challenges in
fraud detection in MLO Ops?
And this is another key.
Vector that needs to be considered.
And as you see on this slide goes
is the real time performance.
Achieving sub 10 millisecond latency
while processing over a hundred thousand
transactions per second during peak
periods is incredibly demanding.
Then the feature freshness, right?
Fraud stills evolve quickly.
The DDoS attacks that we
have seen over the last few.
Instances will actually peak, right?
And that.
That plays a critical role in ensuring
that our features stay in compliant
and with various fraud patterns.
The third is the rapid adaptation,
which is pro tactics emerge
constantly and our systems need
to recognize them immediately.
False positives, that's
the final behavior.
If we flag too many legitimate
transactions, we are losing the
risk of losing the customers.
So that's another thing that needs to
be kept in mind, and that is where the
balancing act has to be super efficient.
Otherwise, we run into the risk of
losing value of customers, which
in turn impact sales and revenue.
The next slide as you guys can see over
here, it speaks about what are the key
vectors in assessing a credit application
or assessing credit worthiness of an
individual using the ML ops framework.
As you can see the frameworks ensure
data orchestration that tracks the full
lineage of every data source model.
Governance provides version history,
approval, workflows, so we know which
model made which decision and validation
systems rigorously test for payments.
When it comes to lending, regulators
and customers need to know the
system is both accurate and fair.
That's.
On the credit assessment
side of the world.
And of course the final aspect is the
automated financial management systems.
This is, again, super important
because if you consider in any line
of business, whether it is payments
or lending or further matter, any
financial transaction, at the end of the
day, everything has to be inside the.
It's a zero sum principle, right?
The debits and credits have to
match, and you cannot have money
being created on the fly, right?
It cannot be created, nor
it cannot be destroyed.
Every record has to match, and that
can be achieved through streamlined.
Model deployment pipelines, monitoring
systems, integration workflows,
automated workflows where you can
actually achieve this through various
streaming technologies as well.
As and when a transaction happens,
you publish it to a Kafka topic.
Consumer subscribed to the topic.
Then you record the transactions
in your ledger system.
You use it for reconciliation, settlement
clearing, making sure that everything
is reconciled behind the scenes.
So it's super important to have
automated financial management systems.
Otherwise it becomes super
tricky to track the transactions.
And the next slide.
As you can see over here, it covers
the high level architecture for
deploying MOPS and financial services.
As you can see, the foundation
is a data infrastructure, right?
Governance, processing, storage
for structure and unstructured data
need to have a set of policies for
both structure and unstructured.
One set of policies for structure.
Another set of policies for unstructured
data on top of it sits the training
and validation pipeline which automates
the compliance checks, which automates
the testing procedures of the same
all of the various validation.
Pipelines, right?
And then the layer that is the
engineering and storage layer that
delivers both batch and real type
features, depending on where you need.
And then where finally we have
the model registry and deployment
systems for versioning, AB testing
and various rollouts, right?
You want to do controlled rollouts
control testing, where you actually
decide, oh, if I. Pull the lever of a
particular parameter in one direction.
How is it going to behave?
Or how the impact is going to be
on my core products and features.
Will it improve, take rate?
Will it improve conversion?
Will it improve?
Will it reduce the, fraud
rates or will it increase?
So there are, these are the various
vectors that you can control by virtue
of having versioning and AB testing.
And finally, at the very top is
the model serving, which is the
high performance APIs that powers
customer facing applications.
You need to have, as I alluded into
the, at the start in either of the use
cases where a customer is waiting on
the checkout screen, trying to process
a, or trying to purchase a product.
Or a customer waiting on the screen
where they're trying to apply for a loan.
These are very time
sensitive customer flows.
So the high performance API layer
on the top ensures that the right
level of information is abstracted.
They buy servicing the
clients in a timely manner.
The next slides talks about how do
we do model deployment strategies
in a containerized manner?
Containerization has been a game
changer in this space, right?
The Kubernetes size separate clusters
are there for training and inference.
GPU nodes for deep learning and auto
scale based on demand compliance,
critical models, you can in fact scale
horizontally and vertical by dedicating by
having dedicated nodes or isolated nodes.
Financial institutions also add
domain specific optimization,
hot standby replicas for zero
time geo distributor deployments.
So that's.
That's super, super critical in
terms of having real, like your
well-defined deployment strategies.
On the next slide, it's on about
real-time monitoring and alerting systems.
This is where all of the key technical
metrics would be like, what is
the latency, what is the triple,
what is your resource utilization?
Is it at the max resource
utilization main?
Main resource utilization?
So that you can dynamically at runtime
either increase the capacity or
reduce the capacities, and so you can
also actually track the error rates.
The key other thing is the
model performance, right?
Predicting what is the accuracy of it?
What are the drift in
terms of distribution?
How is that being used?
And of course.
Pertaining to that would be the business
KPIs in terms of what are the approval
rate, what are false positive, how
is it impacting the revenue, customer
experience, and all those things.
And lastly compliance
is a key aspect of it.
So ensuring that the end-to-end
transaction is thought through in terms of
observability and reliability standpoint.
And what are the various automated
validation frameworks you have?
You have data validation, you
have model training, performance
and fairness, explaining the
compliance side of the world.
Financial institutions have
to ensure that the validation
processes needs to be there.
Otherwise, how do you know the robustness
and the accuracy of a particular
model before you go ahead and deploy
that in production and thereby.
You don't want to have such a scenario
where you don't validate and deploy it
in production, and then all of a sudden
it can have negative impact across the
length and breadth of the spectrum.
And then the next slide is about, I
would want to speak about like the
model drift in high stakes environments.
Like what exactly is a model done?
You just cannot avoid, model drift, right?
It's unavoidable in a, especially
in a high stakes environment, right?
How do you detect dread drift
through statistical tests segment
based analysis and, whenever a
drift occurs, how do you respond?
You respond through shadow
deployment comparison.
You gradually ramp wrap the traffic,
ramp down the traffic, and then that
is where when in doubt you have a back
fall back approach of human in the loop
approval and then track the audit trail
to make sure that the performances
through transitions is seamless.
And then I would also want to
speak about implementing AB
testing for financial models.
That's, that is where e testing is
another area which is super critical.
Start with clear hypothesis type
to business metric test designs.
Ensure statistical rigor, ensure carefully
and control for adverse effects and
practice analyzed at the segment level.
And rollout is progressive
with continuous monitoring?
Yes.
Innovation is the key, but not at the cost
of, not protecting the customers, right?
Safe AB testing is super important.
So to wrap up, what are
my key takeaways, right?
Design for scale from day one, integrate
compliance throughout the pipeline,
automate everything, but ensure the
fallback mechanisms are there, where
human in the loop intervention is there.
And then investing in robust
monitoring and response systems.
That's pretty much it, and I
hope you, you were able to gather
some insights on my presentation.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity.
I.