Everyone.
My name is Barta.
I have around nine years of
experience in Salesforce cloud
technologies and AI driven solution.
I have worked with finance,
healthcare, and real estate industries.
Today we are going to talk about a
problem that resonates across industries.
Why so many promising machine learning
models never make it into production?
And how we lop peers practices
can help bridge that gap.
Think of this talk as a roadmap from
research to production ready systems
covering the challenges, orchestration,
infras monitoring, and ca cd.
Today's agenda, our journey
will move across five pillars.
The MOPS challenge, why so many
model get stuck in the lab?
Yml pipeline orchestration tools and
techniques to automate workflows.
Production infrastructure.
How to make Y ML systems
scalable and reliable.
Monitoring and observability.
Ensuring model continues to
deliver value after deployment.
CI cd for EML adapting.
DevOps best practices.
Machine learning.
By the end of this session, you
will have a complete picture of
what M-L-O-P-S maturity looks like
and our organizations can, the main
challenge, the M-L-O-P-S challenge,
let's start with the problem study.
Show that 20% of ML model server
ever make it to production.
That means four out of PRO five
projects never deliver value.
BM research.
Why does this happen?
Some key barriers include reproducibility,
gaps between research and engineering,
lack of standardized deployment process,
insufficient monitoring and maintenance
of framework and inadequate testing
methodologies for particularly ML systems.
Poor integration with enterprise systems.
I am sure you have seen brilliant
proof of concepts die in a lab
because of these exact issues.
The M-L-O-P-S evaluation
over the years, M-L-O-P-S has matured
in stages manually, ML process,
isolated notebooks, one of deployments.
No repeatability, and we have EML pipeline
automation, basic training automation,
but limited to production integration.
CACD for EML, bringing DevOps,
rigor, automated testing, structured
releases, and inconsistent deployment.
Full E-M-L-O-P-S maturity.
End-to-end.
Automation monitoring, drift detection,
retraining rollback strategies.
For organizations that reach
maturity, reduce deployment times by
80% and it'll sustain 95% accuracy
in the production environments.
This is not a just technical
gist transformation.
It's a cultural world.
This engineers and operation
teams collaborates seamlessly.
ML pipeline orchestration.
Now let's dive into orchestration.
Imagine the ML'S lifecycle
as a factory assembly.
If any step is manual or fragile,
the whole process slows down.
A fully automated MI pipeline should cover
data prep, cleaning, future engineering
validation, and model training in that
hypermarket tuning, tracking experiments.
Model evolution testing against
holdout data sets and validating
business KPIs, deployment, packaging,
and serving models consistent.
And the other one is monitoring
continuous watch for drift
error and performance issues.
Without this orchestration, every new
model is a reinvention of the wheel.
And yummy pipeline
orchestration components.
Different teams choose different
orchestration tools based on their eco
ecosystem, for example, or QB flow.
QB flow is the one thing it has,
uh, Kubernetes native platform.
Great.
If our org is already invested in
Kubernetes, it has strong model serving.
Pipeline Libraries.
EML Flow, it's it's lightweight,
experiment tracking model,
registry, and language specific.
Perfect for the experimentation
and for that particular heavy
teams and airflow, Apache airflow.
The general workflow engine, it is
not specific to ML specific, but
great for complex data, heavy process.
In practice, many organizations have mix
and match of these, uh, comparison tools.
For example, you might use ML
flow for experiment tracking while
deploying models, we have a QB flow.
When picking tools always ask, does this
fit our workflow, our skillset, and are we
forcing the team unnecessary complexity.
Production infra structure.
Even the best model fail without
the right infrastructure here, what
modern ML infrastructure look like.
Infrastructure has cored with terraform
are pmi, ensuring environments
are reproductive containerization.
With docker package dependencies
to eliminate, it works on
machine deployment automation.
Like CACD pipelines, pushing
code and model across dev test.
Broad scalability, Kubernetes,
auto scaling for spikes in
production, fast optimization,
dynamic scaling, and right size.
The main goal is to build infrastructure
that as a, as the model themselves.
Real time inference
architecture, many applicants.
Many applications, fraud detection
chart bots, recommendation engines
require real time predictions.
That means 50 to 20 millisecond latency.
Key design considerations.
Horizonal scaling Kubernetes clusters that
scale out with the demand load balance,
ensuring spread evenly with health checks
cashing, using Redis for frequent queries.
It'll reduce the compute
hardware acceleration kind
of GPUs, pus wherever needed.
One example, like a healthcare client,
a realtime insurance eligibility checks
the reduced wait times from minutes
to milliseconds because the model on
an optimized auto-scaling architecture
and real time inference architectures.
For example, our scaling load, balancing
caching layers, hardware acceleration.
These are the things
monitoring observability.
Deploying a model is not the end.
Beginning model.
Drift has changes.
Monitoring covers three layers.
Data drift.
Statistical checks, scale divergence
and population stability index.
For model performances accuracy, we
F1 A UC, and we have to continuously
track against those benchmarks.
Operational metrics, latency, thorough.
Put.
As well as resource
utilization is the main.
If you are not monitoring
your flying behind even that's
a dangerous in production.
We have to maintain that properly.
Model monitoring systems,
automated retraining deployments.
How do we respond for that?
How do we respond?
The drift is detected.
Automated retraining, common triggers,
performance drops below threshold.
Time-based schedules, weekly or
monthly retaining database triggers
significant distribution shift, and
we have to follow the distribution
and deployment strategies.
Deployments, new models will run silently.
In parallel canary releases roll out five
person of the traffic before scaling up
and AB testing, measuring the business
impact, we have to test it thoroughly.
And automated rollback.
If the new model under profits, if it is
not performing perfectly, we have to roll
back that, uh, functionality and we need
the deployment strategies to be in place.
These combinations ensures both
agility and safety particular
and.
Particularly automated retraining.
We spoke right based time
based database volume.
Those are the main key things.
And CACD for machine learning.
Finally, we have to
speak about CACD for EML.
DevOps, transform Software Engineering.
Ya Melo peers does the same for.
Ski testing MLCA CD Pipeline
data validation schema checks,
missing value detection model.
Model performance test.
Ion checks prevent black
sliding integration test.
We have to validate the entire
pipeline and load and performance
test ensuring the production
readiness based on the application.
Security and compliance test.
We have to follow GDPR,
hip, uh, PA production.
We have to, security is the main concern.
Without these all models, whatever
these will, if these are not there, we,
that particular models will be failing.
Production with them becomes
predictable, reputable, and it's there.
And.
In my specific strategy for testing,
we have different data validation, test
model, performance test integration,
test load, and performance test.
We have to verify the data for data
validation, and we have to check the
delivery scenario, model performance test.
We had to check whether
we met the model or not.
If not, we have to check that particular
and the integration test, validate the
entire pipeline and load performance test,
ensuring the production, the readiness,
security, compliance and everything.
And coming to the real challenge of this
is most of the ML models never, never
have the never reach the production.
MLO PS offers a way
far from orchestration.
Infrastructure monitoring and
C. A C. It means S is not just
about the models, but about the
system culture and collaboration.
If there is no one takeaway, read machine
learning as a product, not a project.
Product requires lifecycle
management, testing, monitoring,
and continuous improvement.
These are the key things for us.
Thank you for your time.
If you have any questions,
please reach out.
Thank.