Hi everyone.
Thanks for tuning in.
I am Manu Kumar Awa, and I work for
GoDaddy as a senior telecom engineer.
And today we are going to explore how to
scale conversational AI in production.
And this is specially for contact centers.
Now, when I say contact center, you
might think of, long hold times choppy
sounds, and then the, background music
and agents juggling multiple screens.
But actually the behind the screens AI is
quietly transforming these environments.
Sometimes you talk directly to it other
times, it helps an agent responds faster.
So this talk is all about how we
can make those AI system production
ready, reliable, and scalable.
So here's what we will cover.
First thing is the cha, the challenges
unique to the contact center.
Ai and ML ops framework are
tailored to conversational ai.
Some technical details like architecture,
CICD, pipeline and monitoring.
And finally how to measure the success.
And when I say measuring the success,
it's not just with the technical
KPIs but with business outcomes.
So as we go through, I will also share
some stories and particular examples.
So this doesn't feel like a theory,
but something you can imagine in
in action, with contact centers.
A good thing is we all actually experience
this on a day-to-day basis because every
company does have a contact center that,
once in a lifetime, obviously you have
to call them and have to experience it.
So let me start with a story.
So a few years ago, a telecom company,
tried launching a chatbot to handle
customer complaints on day one,
customer asked about a network outage.
The bot had no idea what was going on,
and kept replying with generic message.
Something like, Hey, have you tried your,
restarting your phone, router, or modem?
Messages, customers, obviously were
furious, based on this kind of response.
But why?
Because contact center AI is
unique, uniquely challenging.
So to say, we are take, we are talking
millions of conversations per day.
Unlike an agent who handles 30 calls,
a handles everything, and it's instant.
And second thing is human in the loop.
So basically it has to work
side by side with agents.
Think of it like a co-pilot, not
but not the actual replacement.
And the other thing is cost of errors.
A wrong answer is not just
about one unhappy customer.
It could training complaints
on Twitter or any other social
media platform within ours.
It's wildfire in social media nowadays.
And the next thing is diverse language.
So every industry has its own jargon.
Take it like healthcare, insurance,
retail, banking industry.
You can't rely on one generic model when
it comes to the contact center language.
So the real challenge isn't about
building ai, but it's building AI that
scales adapts and earns customer trust.
So this is where ML ops enter the picture.
So if you think of.
Theater production, the actors on the
stage, but the backstage crew, makes
sure the lights work, the sound is clear,
and they actually run the show on time.
That is how here the ML ops is.
So the ML ops is the
backstage crew for ai.
So basically tens features are
consistently engineered, training
pipelines run smoothly every time
deployments happening safely.
And monitoring.
Catches issues before customers actually
do so without ML Ops AI project end up,
as cool demos that has, that doesn't
actually survive the chaos of production.
So now the features, so think of
features as, what the model pays
attention to for conversational ai.
It's not just the text it's the context
which means, what's being said earlier in
the conversation and how they said it and
the timing, how quickly customer replies,
how often they contact the support, right?
And the third one is the language.
Which is basically sentiment intent
and domain specific keywords.
We manage all this
through a feature store.
If you think of cooking, it's
like a well organized pantry.
You don't want to discover midway
that you know you're running
out of salt or something else.
Similarly, your A model shouldn't
find that a feature is missing
or something that is outdated.
I have seen teams skip this
step and they end up with models
that work fine in lab, but they
actually fall apart in production.
Next comes training.
Training can't be a one time
experiment on someone's laptop.
It has to be robust
repeatable and automated.
Which basically means that, checking
data quality, garbage in, out generating
synthetic data for for rare but important
cases like fraud detection detecting bias.
Imagine a model that works well for
one language, but fails for another.
As an example, maybe it works well
for retail, but when it comes to the
healthcare industry, you have complicated
medicine names or or the formula
names that they have to pronounce.
And system should be able to recognize it.
And the next one is, tracking experiments.
So you know why one version
worked better than the another.
And finally, validation.
We don't just measure
accuracy, but we test how.
How the model, would affect actual
KPIs, like customer satisfaction
scores or resolution time.
Think of it like testing an airplane.
You don't just check if it can fly.
You actually, simulate the
turbulence, emergencies, and
worst case scenarios as well.
AB testing okay, now your model is ready.
Do you unleash it on
all customers at once?
No no way.
We are doing that.
So basically we start small.
So shadow testing, the model
runs silently in the background.
It makes predictions but actually
doesn't affect real customers.
Canary releases a tiny fraction
of traffic, goes to the new
model and then staged rollout.
So gradually increase exposure
as confidence bills and
always a rollback switch.
Ready?
I like to compare this to, teaching
someone to drive first they watch from
the passenger seat and then they drive in
a parking lot, then slowly onto the main
road and freeways, you don't actually
throw them straight onto a freeway, right?
So that is how this is.
And obviously monitoring deployment
isn't the finish line, right?
It's actually the starting point, but
we need to monitor at four levels.
The first one is technical
metrics speed and the error rates.
The next one is data quality,
which means our input's actually
drifting the model or not.
And the next one is performance, right?
Like accuracy, agent overrides, et cetera.
And finally, the business outcome.
Our customers happier,
our issues resolve faster.
So this is like having
multiple dashboards in a plane.
One for altitude, one for fuel,
and another for weather, and
something else you don't rely on.
Just, one metric.
So here's what the overall
architecture looks like.
We ingested data from calls and chats.
We run it through a feature store
on an, and, to enrich it, the model
service predictions in real time.
And then we log everything, feed
it into the monitoring tools and
agency suggestions directly in their
workspace while, they're having
the conversation with the customer.
So the key here is AI is invisible
to the customers when they,
when the experience is faster.
And the service is much smarter.
So scaling requirements
for the CICD, right?
So we treat models like software, so code,
configurations, and the features like gi.
We automate test files on each change.
Models are registered with metadata
deployments are containerized
and they rolled out gradually.
So basically this cuts deployment
time from weeks to hours.
It is a difference between mailing a
letter and sending a WhatsApp message.
That agility allows, business to
adapt in the actual real life.
But even the best pipelines can't stop.
One thing that is data drifting.
Picture this, it's a holiday.
Seasons.
Suddenly everyone is
asking, where's my package?
Or imagine a viral outage million
people calling about the same issue.
So over time, even language evolves.
A year ago.
No one was asking about charge GBT.
Now it's a common
customer, support question.
So if the model isn't updated,
it slowly becomes irrelevant.
That is why, drift detection is essential.
It's a statistical check embedding,
monitoring, and animal alerts.
So it's like having a
doctor check your vitals.
Small shifts can tell you, something
wrong, long before you actually collapse.
And when drift is detected, retraining
shouldn't require a massive manual effort.
It should be automated, so collect
new interactions, verified by the
agents trigger retraining jobs
automatically validate against all
and new scenarios roll out carefully
with monitoring these kind of method.
This closes the loop.
So this is, it's never static.
It act, it all, it
actually always learning.
Just like your agents are.
I think of it like fitness.
So if you don't exercise, your body
drifts, retraining keeps your AI in shape.
So let's wrap this up.
Some of the key features are the
foundation training pipelines.
Progress your rollout, which makes,
basically minimizes the risk.
Monitoring keeps us honest and retraining
ensures the system, keeps evolving.
And the golden rule here is
AI doesn't replace people.
It frees them, and it take
cares of the routine questions.
So agents can focus on empathy,
problem solving, and complex cases.
And when humans and AI work
together, contact center,
shifts from cost center to.
Value creations.
And I really thank you
for watching this session.
Scaling conversational AI is not just
about building models, it's about
putting the right MLO practices in
place so those models stay, reliable,
scalable, and value over time.
When done right.
AI doesn't replace human agents.
It empowers them and it takes
of the REIT tasks so people can
focus on actual empathy, judgment,
and complex problem solving.
I hope this gave you a practical ideas,
you can take back to your own work.
Thanks again for joining and
I will leave you with this.
The future of customer experience
isn't just human or ai.
It's human with ai.
Thank you everyone.