Is Moning from AWS, and first off,
I wanna thank conference 42 for
the opportunity to be here today.
In this talk, we are going to explore
how AI first platforms are reshaping
lops, moving from manual reactive
operations to autonomous self-healing,
and continuously improving systems.
By the end of this session, you'll
have a clear understanding of the
building blocks behind self wheeling
infrastructure, intelligent scaling,
and auto autonomous code modernization.
Let's take a step back and
look at how MOPS has evolved.
In the early days, it was very manual.
Engineers were literally on call
at 2:00 AM trying to put out fires.
Whenever pipeline broke.
It was stressful.
Reactive work then came automation.
It helped a lot.
Workflows were faster, errors
were reduced, but it still needed
constant human supervision.
Now we are inferring something new.
Autonomous m lops systems that
learn, adapt, and fix themselves.
No more.
2:00 AM wake up calls,
no more firefighting.
That's the real game changer.
So the question is how do we get there?
I like to break it down into three
pillars, which we'll explore next, the
three pillars of autonomous m lops.
First pillar is self-healing
infrastructure systems that can
detect issues and fix themselves.
The second is intelligent
scaling, anticipating demand,
and scaling proactively.
And the third is automated
code modernization systems that
consciously evolve through AI
driven refactoring and patching.
Think of this like a human immune system,
detect, respond, and adapt new threats.
Let's try deeper into the first page.
Self-healing infrastructure,
a self-healing system
that has four key points.
Monitoring that uses ml to spot
nominals diagnosis that pinpoints
root causes across logs and signals
resolution with automated playbooks
and a feedbacking that makes the
system smarter at every incident.
It's like an autopilot in airplanes.
It doesn't just alert the pilot, it
stabilizes the system immediately.
Real world use cases.
Observability driven AI that detects
certain deviations, cross service
intelligence that understand dependencies
and automated patch where systems
fixed vulnerabilities themselves.
These speak themselves for themselves.
NR reduced by 90% and up to 80%
of routine operations eliminated
once infrastructure heals itself.
The next step is scaling intelligent.
So how do we actually
implement self hearing systems?
It starts with observability driven AI
tools that don't just monitor, but
actively detect subtle deviations
before to become incidents.
Next, cross service intelligence
systems that understand dependencies
across services, not just with inbox.
That means failures are diagnosed
in context, not in isolation.
And finally, automated patching
infrastructure that can find and fix
vulnerabilities on its own without
waiting for human intervention.
The results are powerful and we
see recovery times reduced by
almost 60% and as much as 55% of
routine operation tasks linear.
Once your infrastructure can
heal itself, the natural step
is to make it scale intelligent.
Traditional auto-scaling is reactive.
It waits until demand
spikes before responding.
That's like s slamming on the brakes
after you've already run the red line.
It works, but it's late and inefficient.
With predictive resource management,
we flip the model using analytics
and machine learning system
forecast demand hours or even days.
This allows resources to be provisioned
proactively and just as importantly
scaled down when they're no longer needed.
The impact is clear, better
performance, lower costs and resources
aligned with business priorities,
not just technical triggers.
So how does predictive
scaling actually work?
It follows five steps.
Collect telemetry, not CPU or memory, but
also request patterns and business matrix.
Analyze with ML or AI time
series models, uncover S circles,
correlations, even seasonality.
Forecast the demand.
Produce predictions from the next
few minutes to several days out.
Plan resources turning forecast
into precise allocation strategies,
automation, or automate the execution
using infrastructure and scope and
feedback loops to scale in real time.
It's a closed loop system that
gets smarter with every itration.
Ensuring resources are always
aligned with the impact.
Now let's shift to the third
pillar, AI driven code evolution.
Think of your code base, not as
something static, but as a living system.
With AI code can now self
optimize, self-cure and self adapt.
This means automat refactoring
or performance proactive patching
before vulnerabilities are
exploited or continuous adoption
of emerging risk practices.
All without waiting for
manual intervention.
This is powered by large language models.
Advanced code analysis and
reinforcement learning.
Instead of developers constantly
chasing technical data, the system
reduce reduces on its own, allowing
teams to focus on innovation.
At AWS my team used to spend around
30% of the time in cleaning, migration
or migration detected itself.
So how do we actually modernize code?
There are three main approaches.
First, performance optimization.
AI detect bottlenecks, applies,
fixes, and even validates
improvements through AB testing.
Second, dependency management, autonomous
systems assess risk and libraries
flag issues and perform safe upgrades
without waiting for path cycles.
And third architecture revolution.
ML power tools recommended and
sometimes implement structural
improvements as systems grow.
The payoff is huge.
Like we have seen 90% fewer
vulnerabilities, 30 to 50% performance
gains, and a 30% dramatic reduction in
maintenance overhead for just my team.
So what's the real business impact of
auto autonomous lops organizations?
Adopting the systems has seen
operational overhead cut by 75%,
recovery times reduced by almost 90%.
Infrastructure costs lowered by now 35%.
These aren't small,
incremental games gains.
They their step function
improvements, unlocking efficiencies,
bilities, and agility all at once.
That's why autonomous lops isn't
just a technical evolution,
it's a business transformation.
The journey to AutonoMe
doesn't happen overnight.
It's phased progression
usually over 18 to 36 months.
Phase one is foundation get
observability in place and
standardized infrastructure as code.
Without good telemetry,
autonomic cannot work.
Phase two is augmentation layer
in AI powered monitoring, anomaly
detection, and early predictive
scaling, often with human percent.
Phase three is autonomy systems not
handling remediation and predictive
scaling with minimal intervention
plus early code optimization.
Phase four is evolution.
Self-improving systems that
adapt architecture through
reinforcement learning.
The key point is that each phase
delivers measurable value on its
own, so the benefits start well
before full autonomy is reached.
Now looking ahead, several trends will
push autonomous lops even further.
First, multi-agent systems.
Instead of one AI making decisions,
multiple agents collaborate to
manage infrastructure dynamic.
Second, explainable AI operations or
x AI ops, bringing transparency and
accountability to autonomous decisions.
Third cross-platform optimization.
AI that can seamlessly shift and
optimize workloads across hybrid
and multi-cloud environments.
Finally, continuous learning
infrastructure systems that don't just
learn from local incidents, but from
global patterns across industries.
The takeaway are self-healing,
intelligent scaling and code modernization
are only the be what's coming as
fully autonomous cloud ecosystems.
To wrap up, thank you all for joining
me on this journey into autonomous mops.
I hope the talks gives you the vision
of what's possible and a roadmap to
start your own journey towards Autonom.
I'd love to hear the conversation, so
please feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you.