Hello everyone.
My name is Fu Sadik.
I've been working as a solution
architect for security ai.
I have over 18 plus years of experience
in data security and privacy space, and
today I am here for a session on a driven
cybersecurity intelligent threat detection
and privacy in the post quantum era.
Today we'll be discussing about the
evolving cyber threat landscape, where
we'll be understanding the current threats
and the essential role of a ML for modern
defense and building a ML classification
for framework where we'll be architecting
multimodal detection system and realtime
time pipeline for emerging threats and
privacy, preserving ML techniques and
those, how we can leverage that in.
A ML Detections and implementation
and operational excellence.
We transitioning a ML solution proof
from proof of concepts to the production,
deployment and monitoring, and finally
preparing for post quantum error where
we'll be using the feature proofing of
A ML system again, is the challenges
of course, quantum cybersecurity.
Evolving cyber threat landscape.
So we all know that the signature
based systems currently are not
of capable or sophisticated to
the attacks that we have now.
We have all modern ways of doing attacks
or coming from different sources.
So there are apps employing increasingly
sophisticated EVA techniques.
There are zero day explosives targeting
previously unknown vulnerabilities.
Polymorphic wall bear and file less
wall bear and even in the supply
chain attacks compromised, trusted
software distributed channels.
And so all because of these advanced
attacks, the conventional security
tools struggle to keep up the pace
and they are failed by 38% detection
today with the sophisticated attacks.
And so there is a need for a,
an enhancement where we use
a ML. Cybersecurity to detect
these ahead of the time.
So what we do here is we will first do
the behavioral detection and then we do
the predictive capabilities and then adapt
to response and resource optimization.
In the behavioral detection, we use
A EML techniques, Excel to identify
anomaly anonymous users and system
behaviors and detect threats that
signature based tools or lack of.
Then predictive capital, it is
leveraging these threat intelligence.
MLL algorithms can proactively forecast
emerging threats before fully materialized
means we leverage the threat intelligence
and the M-L-A-M-L algorithms, how a
predictive analysis to do and then
predict it before it materialize.
And then the adaptive response ML systems
continuously learn from the new data.
And enabling them to adopt defense against
the attacks the vector autonomously.
So resource optimization will do
a power trade significantly reduce
by intellectual intelligently pre
threats based on comprehensively
scores and the contextual analysis.
And so where we know that how
to respond, and then based
on the priority and severity.
Use resources optimization
while responding in.
And these advanced ML classification
models drastically improve the
cybersecurity outcomes, and that enables
93% detection date from previously.
And same the signature
based tools that we have.
And here we'll be using multimodal
detection architecture where
we first gather the data.
We use supervised learning
and deep learning here.
And in the supervised learning, we
utilizes the label data sets of known
threats for classification, where we'll
be using random for as gradient boosting
and super support vector machines.
And so in unsupported unsupervised
learning, we, it identifies
anomalies by detecting deviation
from the normal patterns where
we'll be using isolation for us.
One class, SVP DB scan, clustering it.
And finally, the deep learning
where we employ neural networks
for complex pattern recognition.
Where we will be using LSTM
networks, transform models,
computational, conventional networks.
And these are the, an approach
combines diverse models to achieve
significant higher accuracy and reduce
false positives compared to the.
Individual model.
So if you compare what's happening in the,
compare it to the traditional way of data
classification to the a, a ML base, in
the traditional classification, we use a
regular expression or a metadata patterns.
But here as as a ML is evolving, we are
using all these AI techniques to more to
add more context and, context and content
to it so that we will be doing a more
accurate data classification where we'll
be seeing 80% of the accuracy without
any efforts and where we'll be, we are
minimizing the false positives at a
greater rate and then high increasing the
higher accuracy in the classification lab.
And then feature engineering for cyber
security ml where we'll be using.
Network traffic feature features and user
behavior feature and host specific feature
means in the network traffic features.
We will be studying the protocol deviation
anomalies and the deviation flow metadata
where deviation volumes will be featured,
and then temporal patterns and burst
and destination and tr and new location.
In the user behavioral feature,
we'll see we'll verifying that
authentication patterns and how the
users are authenticating and access
and distribution, at what time they're
trying to access and data access, and
the movement patterns and where, at
what time they're running some queries
or the command frequency profiles, C
profile set, and then host based feature.
We will process execution,
chain system call sequences,
resource utilization patterns.
And registry and file system changes.
So effectively effective feature
selection increases model
performance by 40% when reducing the
computational overhead and realtime
classification pipeline architecture.
So this is very important here.
The, from where it starts and
how we automate this process.
The first step is data tion.
We collect all the information
from sensors, logs and network
tabs, our database logs and all.
And then we feature extract as
we discuss in the real time.
We we real time pass it and vectorize
signals based on the data tion.
And then we do ML and where panel
supervisor and deep models will be used.
And then based on that,
we'll do the scoring.
You'll use aggregated models to, to to
add the risk scores and based on the
risk scores, you automate the responses,
you take your mitigation or update data.
And then the, where we can use the
privacy pre preserving ML techniques.
So because you are processing a huge
data as part of this, and there could
be some sensitive data about the
industry that you are working in.
That's where we use these techniques
to be in compliance and with the
regulations like GDPR, hiphop,
P-C-I-P-H-I regulations, CCPA regulations.
So we'll be using the here, the
federated level and differential
privacy and homo encryption in learning.
It transforms the data into
decentralized UIS with the local
data and eliminate the raw data
exchange means that data is not going.
Anywhere it's all local to
the model and we process it.
You, even with the sensitive data,
differential privacy is the same
thing as but where we'll be adding
some noise to the trying data to put
output of our mathematical privacy
guarantees preserving utility.
So in this case, we.
It's a, it is the same raw data, but we'll
be adding some noise to it so that it
mimic the data and then use that, use data
for ML processing it and homo homomorphic
encryption where it enables competition
on encrypted data without decryption
allowing a ML operations answers to
data while maintaining confidentiality.
Yeah, this is.
On the fly encryption it does, and
without decaling it so that AI ml can
use that data for their processing
and how we do the implementation.
So from previous two production, this is
a phase approach where the first voice
is the phase one is the foundation.
Phase two is the control deployment, and
phase three is the scale, the production.
So in the phase one, what we do is we
establish a robust data collection, as I
mentioned, from different sources like,
and then we do the labeling as part of
data classification and perform extension,
feature engineering and selection.
And we conduct initial model training
and validation and integrate this
with the existing soft tools.
And then in the control deployment,
we deploy models in shadow mode.
Again, as the existing systems
we measure performance rigorously
against as establish baselines.
We optimize threshold and minimize false
parties, false positives using techniques
and provide a comprehensive security
team training and collect the feedback.
And in phase two, it's a scale production.
We gradually transition from legacy
detection systems implement CACD pipeline
to continuously update the models.
Automate model retraining
and deployment cycles.
And finally integrate this with the
real time performance and visualization.
This as this is a phased approach, the
advantage is you reduce the risk while
enabling continuous validation and
improvement of ML systems and then the co
operationalize the excellence and monitor.
And as part of operationalization,
that for excellence.
We see the performance indicators
like you detect the latency and
average time to classify incoming
traffic and false positive rates.
Then attack coverage and percentage
of a known attack vector detected
zero day detection success rate
in identifying previously threats.
So this is a continuous improvement
process where you automate
these models to detections.
Take the human feedback and then the
intelligence integrated with that.
And then we do heavy testing
of model improvements.
And next one is preparing for
the post quantum cybersecurity.
So post quantum is the next
generation where how we were
leveraging the post quantum
cybersecurity into the set detection.
Where here we'll be using quantum
threat models, where the quantum
computing, particularly algorithms like
source processes a significant threat
to current public key cryptography,
including R-S-A-E-C-C and deal Mann.
And then the post quantum cryptography.
NIST has identified poster quantum
cryptography standards like crystal.
This is a key encapsulation.
The lithium digital signature
to protect ML models against
the future quantum threats.
So these are the prone the
cryptographic techniques that the
ML models are currently using.
And then the strategy ML system
preparedness where key strategies for ML
systems in the quantum transition involved
integrating crypto agility, adopt hybrid,
classic, and post quantum approaches and.
So proactively if we integrate
post quantum cyber security
into ML pipelines is critical.
Because from the coming five to six
years, the transition is projected.
Our nation must be now ensure
long term cyber security.
Our automation should be ready to adopt
to these post quantum cyber security
embedded into the a ML processor.
So key takeaways.
So we covered DIML, driven cybersecurity,
transformers privacy, first ML
deployment, and how with the phased
approach and shared implementation.
And and then finally,
proactive quantum readiness.
Thank you for your time.
I hope you enjoy session and thanks a lot.