PA Perva.
I'm a strategy leader in the finance
industry, and today I'll be talking
to you about scaling AI and finance.
With the focus on ML ops strategies,
which are behind the 70.86 billion
market transformation, we focus on how
production rate ML ops infrastructure
is enabling financial institutions
to deploy reliable, compliant, and
profitable AI and systems in the world.
Most regulated industry.
Let's quickly talk through the
financial revolution and the
detailed numbers behind it.
85% of the financial institutions
are deploying AI systems today,
transforming everything from risk
assessment to customer service.
78.6, a number I previously
mentioned is the market size.
Buy 2030 for this industry.
This is the projected value of
AI applications in financial
services representing massive
investment in infrastructure.
Thousand plus.
That's a big number, but those are the
credit variables that are processed
in real time by modern financial
ML systems for decision making, and
then millions of daily transactions
happen, and those are analyzed by
fraud detection AI with required
high accuracy and minimal latency.
Latency just meets the
time required to do those.
As you can see then financial institutions
aren't just experimenting with ai.
They're deploying at scale and then
driving a fundamental transformation
of the industry core operations.
For today's agenda, we will focus
on ML ops of financial industry.
There'll be three things that we'll cover.
One unique challenges in financial
ai, which are regulatory compliance.
Model explainability data security and
the real time processing requirements
that distinguish finance from the
other machine learning domains.
Second, we'll talk about the production
gate machine learning operations
architecture, which includes the
technical components required for
scalable, reliable AI systems in banking,
in short and FinTech environments.
And then lastly, we talked through
some actionable strategies, which
are practical frameworks and
approaches for transitioning from
prototype to production Powerhouse.
What are the unique challenges
of AI in financial industries?
There are four different
pieces that we should, we cover
one regulatory compliance.
All models must satisfy the regulatory
requirements, primarily F-C-R-A-E,
C-O-A-G-D-P-R, and the basal standards
while providing full audit trails.
Then there's explain explainability
requirements where customers and
regulators are entitled to understand
the decision factors that go behind
the ML models, including like adverse
action notices, how this comes into play.
Then there's market volatility models,
experience rapid trans performance
degradation during economic shifts.
And lastly, there's adversarial threats
where fraud detection systems often
face sophisticated attackers actively
working to circumvent these detection.
So how does financial ML ops
differ from the standard practices?
There's unique demands of the
financial service industry, which
requires specialized ML lops
capabilities that go far beyond
standard ML engineering practices.
The standard machine learning
operations includes a basic model
versioning, has simple AB testing,
has general purpose feature stores.
Has standard CI CD pipelines, and then
basic monitoring dashboards as well as
a general on purpose infrastructure.
We can be applicable across
different industries and places.
However, for financial ops, given
the challenges we've discussed
earlier, we need immutable audit
trails with regulatory metadata.
We need a champion challenger
with segment isolation.
We need time series optimized features,
stores with point in time correction.
We need compliance, integrated
deployment workflows.
We need segment level performance
monitoring with diff detection.
We need secure isolated infrastructure
with control access patterns.
As you can see, financial institutions
that attempt to implement AI with
it without sub specialized lops
infrastructure will face regulatory
challenges, model failures, and often
security vulnerable vulnerabilities
if they're using standard mops.
Let's then talk through what is
required for machine learning
operations architecture for the
financial services industry.
A robust financial MLS platform integrates
specialized components to address the
unique challenges of the industry while
enabling reliable, scalable AI operations.
Each component must be designed with
regulatory compliance, security,
and audibility as a foundation
requirement rather than afterthoughts.
What are the components?
A big chunk of that is
the data foundation.
You want your data to have three
different kind of qualities.
One, it should be a financial feature
stop where that, what that means
is a specialized four time data.
With point in time correctness, which
guarantees critical for accurate back
testing and regulatory compliance.
It needs to support thousands of
variables per customer version, feature
definitions with lineage, and then
batch and online serving capabilities.
You also need to make sure that you
have a secure data access layer,
which means you have role-based
controls with fine brain permissions
and comprehensive audit logging.
This should follow the data
minimization principles.
It needs to make sure the personal
information is handed via a tokenization
so no one has access to PII information.
You need to have access.
You need to ensure there's
encryption addressed and in transit.
And then lastly, there's
a data quality framework.
You wanna make sure the data is
automatically validated with strict
schema enforcement and anomaly direction.
You need to have statistical profile
monitoring data, drift detection,
integrity constraints, validation.
The second component of the ML
lops is the model development.
For that, you need regulatory compliant
experimentation, tracking frameworks
that capture all model development
activities with required regulatory
metadata, fair lending analysis,
integration, disparate impact assessment
model cards with regulatory context.
So then as previously mentioned, you
need to make sure there's explainability
toolkit where you have a pre-approved
method for generating customer and
regulatory facing information, which
relates to adverse action code generation,
shap and Lyme integration, as well as
counterfactual explanation systems.
There are four stages now to
the deployment and operations.
One is the validation gateway.
You ensure this pre-deployment
verification, which ensures that
the model meets performance,
fairness, and compliance standards.
Then within that, you have to make sure
you have the champion challenge analysis,
stress testing across market scenarios,
sensitivity analysis on key segments.
The second is compliance integrated
CI c. You wanna make sure you have
the deployment pipelines, have the
required approvals, documentation,
and the various validation steps.
You wanna ensure there is immutable
audit, trail of deployments.
Role-based deployment controls,
automated regulatory documentation.
Thirdly, you wanna make sure there
segment of their monitoring so you
ensure at a segment level there's
performance tracking, especially
for critical customer segments.
They're alert with alerting for
regulatory constraint concerns.
Within that, you need to have
granular performance dashboards, drift
detection by segment, and then outlier
analysis for high value transactions.
Lastly is the automated retraining.
You wanna make sure you have a
scheduled or trigger based retraining
with validation guard rates, so
that when there's like a market
volatility of our scheduling, like a
COVID-19 scenario, you get a trigger.
You also wanna make sure there's
validation, gated promotions, and
then training data set versioning
so that after every figure, your
training data sets get updated.
As you can see each stage, you need
to enforce compliance requirements,
and this has to be done while
enabling operational efficiency.
Lastly, for the implementation
strategy, you wanna make sure you
have a phased approach against.
There are four phases.
The phase one is the foundation.
Where you build core infrastructure,
which is focused on data quality,
governance, and basic model tracking.
Within that, you wanna make sure you have
imple, you implement feature stored with
regulatory compliance built in, establish
experiment tracking with required
documentation, create secure development
environments with appropriate control in
phase two, which is a production pipeline.
You will develop automated
workflows for work model training,
validation, and deployment.
Within that, you will have to build a
compliance integrated CI ICD pipeline,
implement validation gateways with
regulatory checks, create model
registry with approved workflows, and
then coming to the third part, which
is operational excellence, where you
wanna make sure not only is your model
compliant and ready to go, but it is
actually contributing to the firm.
You will establish comprehensive
monitoring and automated retraining,
deploy segment aware performance
monitoring, implement drift protection
and alerting, and then create automated
retraining pipelines of validation gates.
In the last is where you take a
model from not just being good,
but to being an industrial leader.
You focus on the advanced capabilities,
you add sophisticated features
for optimization and scaling.
Within that, you focus on the imp,
you will implement multi-arm banded
systems for model selection, deploy
shadow mode testing for new models,
and then create adaptive monitoring
thresholds by segment so that you can
constantly evolve and upgrade your model.
We've talked through some of this
previously, but I wanna highlight what
are the common pitfalls and how you can
avoid them as you enter the space of
ML ops for your financial institution.
Don't underestimate the
regulatory requirements.
Often the problem is that firms discover
compliance gaps late in the development,
which forces expensive rework.
The solution is to engage compliance teams
from day one and then build regulatory
requirements in technical specifications.
Secondly we've talked about this a
couple of times now, but there is a
concern about inadequate explainability.
The problem often arises when
the firms are unable to provide
required explanations for model
decisions in regulatory timeframes.
The solution, simple integrate
explainability methods during model
development and not as an afterthought.
So if you start thinking during
the model itself, how Q can explain
it up to regulators and customers.
Thirdly, which is the
insufficient segment.
Monitoring it basically means that if.
Your model's working well overall,
but you might be missing degradation
in critical customer segments.
Despite the overall good performance of
the model, the solution is to implement
granular monitoring across demographic,
behavioral, and product segments.
Lastly, it's the poor
handling of market volatility.
Sometimes models are made for steady
state markets, but off, but, and they
collapse during economic shifts like a
COVID-19 and lead to poor performances.
So the solution is to implement
stress testing across historical
scenarios and ensure that you have
responsive retraining triggers.
With that, let me.
Recall all the pieces that we've
talked about and summarize that into
the four major takeaways to build
production grade financial ML lops.
One, compliance is infrastructure.
Your compliance underpins everything, so
you wanna build regulatory requirements
directly into the ML lops components
rather than adding them later.
Second.
Segment level, everything.
While your model might look good overall,
you wanna make sure you're designing
all systems to operate at the segment
level for deployment, development, and
monitoring, and not as an afterthought.
Third, explainability by design.
You want to integrate explanation
systems from the beginning of the
development process so that when your
model is complete, you are able to
answer any questions related to that.
And then lastly, resilient architecture.
You wanna build systems that can
mean performance through market
volatility and data shifts.
These are the four underlying
pillars of how you would build
an ML model, ML lops model.
Anything else?
Thank you.