Hello everyone and thank
you for joining me today.
It's truly an honor to be here
at conference 42 ml Ops 2025.
Let's start this.
Start with my introduction.
This is NA ti and I'm currently working at
State Sheet Financial Corporation and I'm
bring with me over 19 years of experience
in FinTech technologies, specializing
in digital transformation, system
modernization and regulatory compliance.
So in this session, I'm excited
to share, insert some, how we can
architect responsible AI at scale,
particularly in a highly regulated
world of financial services.
So financial services is an industry
where innovation must always be
balanced with trust and compliance.
So the big question is how we bring
the cutting edge AI into this space.
Without compromising on
responsible responsibility.
So for our next 15, 20 minutes,
we will unpack that together.
So let's begin with some context.
The AI revolution in financial services.
We are in the middle of AI revolution
in finance, but by 2029, the global.
AI in FinTech revenue is
projected to exceed $61 billion.
That tells us AI is no
longer an experiment.
It's becoming the backbone of how
financial institutions operate.
So nowadays, the banks are investing
heavily in machine learning
pipelines, explainable models
and complaints, first workflows.
But here is the reality.
As air adoption accelerates,
regulators are watching more
closely than ever before.
So the challenge is not just
building high performing models,
it's building models that are
trustworthy, explainable, and auditable.
And this is where MLO Mops
becomes absolutely essential.
So let us jump into the agenda.
For today's stock, and here is
how I structure today's stock.
We will start with the fundamentals
of ML ops in FinTech and the unique
challenges the industry faces.
Then I will walk through some
high impact AI applications that
are transforming finance today.
From there.
We'll explore how financial institutions
are architecting complaint ML platforms.
And finally, I'll share best practices
that leading organizations are adapting.
By the end of this talk, you will
see why ML Ops is not optional in
financial services anymore, but it's the
backbone of scaling AI responsibility.
So ML ops as the backbone.
So when people hear the term ML ops,
they often think that basically think
about pipelines and our automation.
But in finance it's much bigger than that.
So automation ensures that every model
is reproducible with a clear audit trial.
Monitoring.
Monitoring keeps an eye on models
in real time, detecting drift
or anomalies before any cause.
Damage.
Governance adds, checks and balances,
ensuring approvals, documentation, and
complaints are part of the process.
And explainability.
This is critical in finance.
You can't deny someone a mortgage.
Flag a fraud case without
being able to explain why.
So without transparency, you risk
both the trust and regulatory ities.
So ML Ops is not just a technical
discipline, it's the A, it's a very
framework that makes responsible
AI possible in financial services.
So let us discuss the challenges
in financial services.
By using ai.
Of course, none of these comes easy.
On the technical side, we face
real time processing demands.
Fraud detection systems, for example,
can't be delayed even by a second.
Integration with the legacy systems
make this even harder, and all of
this happens while we are handling
some of the most sensitive personal
and financial data imaginable.
So on the regulatory side,
the bar is even higher.
So studies shows that nearly 60% of models
still exhibit by us regulatory requires
complete audit trials for every decision,
and they expect rigorous validation before
models go live for global institutions.
Complaint is not just one f. It's many
from GDPR in Europe to CCPA in California,
plus some sector specific banking laws.
So building in building AI in finance
is building an aircraft engine.
You need precision, safety and
accountability at every step.
So let us look at the high impact
applications despite these challenges.
Is already driving major impact.
Fraud detection is one
of the best examples.
Modern systems can analyze thousands of
attributes per transaction in milliseconds
flagging suspicious activity instantly.
So if you take MasterCard's example,
it uses AI to monitor billions of
transactions daily and reducing
false positives while meeting
global compliance requirements.
That's a great example of
responsible AI at scale.
Risk modeling and credit
scoring are also being reshaped.
JP Morgan Ha.
JP Morgan Chase has used advanced
ML to strengthen credit scoring
models and embed explainability
so that decisions are transparent.
This helps them extend credit more
fairly while staying regulatory ready.
Compliance is another
area where AI VA shines.
So HSBC, for example, has tested NLP
powered systems to pass regulatory
filings, improving accuracy and
reducing manual compliance workloads.
So that's a huge efficiency
gain in a high stake areas.
And finally, customer intelligence.
Productive AI can help financial
institutions offer proactive guidance,
even identifying elderly signals of
financial distress before they escalate.
Each of these examples
show the same pattern.
Success is not just about
model, it's about the ML lops
framework that supports the model.
So next we'll discuss
architecting for scale.
So how do we make as scalable
and sustainable in finance?
The answer lies in that picture.
From an infrastructure point
of view, secure and isolated
training environments are crucial.
Hybrid cloud and on-premise setups
allows flexibility while respecting
data residency requirements.
Containerization provides
security and portability.
And redundancy across regions.
Ensure systems don't fail
when they are most needed.
And operationally institutions are
building human in the loop of workflows
for I risk cases, running rigorous testing
before deploying models and planning
disaster recovery with fallback models
and automating compliance reporting.
This combination of robust infrastructure
and discipline operation is.
What enables financial institution
to innovate quickly while
remaining compliant and resilient?
And let's talk about legal guard rails,
but even the best architecture is
not enough without ethics, isn't it?
So we know the, we know that models can
be highly accurate and still unfair.
Leading algorithms, for example,
but lending algorithms, in fact.
I been slow shown to
unintentionally penalize 10 groups.
This is why institutions are
embedding ethical guardrails
into entire AI life cycle.
It starts with ethical data practices that
make sure data sets are representative.
It continues with the responsible modeling
where fairness constraints are applied.
Deployment is transparent with
documentation of how decisions are
made, and monitoring is not just for
accuracy, it's also for fairness.
So if you look at the results that
speaks for themselves, some institutions
have reduced bias by more than 70, 70%
without sacrificing the performance
after implementing this model.
So that's a real win for both
business and the society.
Now let us look at the data governance.
For compliant ai.
Data governance is the
foundation of compliant ai.
Think of data lineage like a supply chain.
You need to know exactly
where each dataset originated,
how it was transformed, and
how it flows into the model.
Without this visibility,
regulators won't sign off.
So privacy is equally essential.
Auto automated tools can detect
personally identifiable information,
anonymize it, and apply advanced
productions like differential privacy.
Data quality must be validated
continuously because bad data equals
bad outcomes, and access management
ensures that only the right people
touch sensitive data with every action
logged far from being a bottleneck.
Good data governance actually
accelerates innovation because
it's builds trust with regulators,
executives and customers alike.
So the validation and monitoring
bring rigor to the entire ML life
cycle before deployment models, under
undergoes test testing, statistical
checks, and compliance reviews.
The real test starts after deployment
when live data begins flowing.
And here the continuous
monitoring is also a key.
It detects drift anomalies or degradation.
Automated response can retrain models,
trigger alerts, or switch to fallback
models before problem escalates.
Complaints documentation.
Once a heavy manual process is
increasingly automated, that means
regulators can get full transparency
in minutes instead of weeks.
So one major retail bank saw model
related incidents draw by 64% after
implementing continuous validation.
That's the power of discipline.
ML ops.
Now let us look at the best practices.
So what does success look like?
Successful institutions design modular
platforms with the clear separation
of data model and serving layers.
So they use infrastructure as code
to make environments reproducible.
They maintain model, so
every version is trackable.
And when it comes to implementation,
they start with low risk use
cases like compliance automation.
Before actually moving to the
sensitive areas like lending, they
develop standardized reference
architectures, create center of
excellence for governance, and
involve compliance teams from day one.
This is exactly how institutions
like MasterCard, JP Morgan, and
HCPC have been able to innovative
responsibly while satisfying regulators.
So here the last is very clear.
Building compliance in from the start is
far easier than bolt bolting it later.
So now the key takeaways
from this session.
So we will wrap up here with
some key points to remember.
First, ML ops is non-negotiable
for financial services.
Without this, AI simply
is not scalable or safe.
Second one.
Ethical AI requires continuous
vance bias detection.
Fairness testing and explainability
must leave throughout the life cycle.
And the third one, innovation
and compliance can coist.
With the right platforms,
financial institutions can move
fast and still remain audit ready.
And finally, success
requires collaboration
across roles, which includes.
Data scientists, engineers,
compliance officers, and business
stakeholders must all work together.
So responsible AI is not just technical
goal, it's an organizational commitment.
So that brings us to closing this talk.
And thank you very much for
spending your time with me today.
I hope this session has shown
you why ML Ops is the backbone of
responsible AI in financial services.
And how institutions can invo innovate
while staying compliant and trustworthy.
If you would like to continue the
conversation or share your own
challenges, please feel free to connect
with me, and I would like to thank
everyone once again, and I wish you
success in building AI that's not
only powerful, but also responsible.