Hi, this is, I have a total
of 18 plus years of experience
in information technology.
Currently, I am working as a
principal software engineer
in Liberty Mutual Insurance.
Today I'm going to talk about how
ML driven Slack integration cut mean
time to resolution by 88.5 percentage
across 17 enterprise systems.
Now we are going to
talk about the problem.
Enterprise applications.
Processing millions of diary
transactions generated an overwhelming
volume of errors and alerts.
This led to critical issues being
buried in noise and severely
impacting our operations.
With manual monitoring across 17
production systems, supporting
over two 30,000 daily active users.
Our teams faced significant
challenges, which are mentioned below.
Slow average detection
times of 1 62 minutes.
A staggering 68.2 percentage of critical
issues discovered first by customers
after H'S incidents averaging a prolonged
1 31 minutes to detection SLA compliance
plummeting to a 62.3 percentage.
This slide, we are
talking about the agenda.
The challenge alert fat, you
understanding the presu issue of alert
fat you and its enterprise wide impact.
The ML solution architecture slide
is going to talk about designing a
robust middleware system for efficient
and low overhead exception capture.
The Intelligent Alert registration
le talk about leveraging EML for
context aware routing of critical
alerts to optimal channels.
The results and business impact slide
is going to talk about demonstrating
quantifiable improvements in mean
time to resolution, cost savings,
and developer productivity.
The implementation guides
is going to talk about.
Practical ML OPS patterns for
deploying your own intelligent
error monitoring system.
The challenge alert, fat fatigue,
you the hidden cost of scale.
Our 17 enterprise systems, were
generating two 30 K plus daily active
users, 3.7 million daily transactions.
12 k plus Diary error events,
eight 60 plus diary alerts.
On the right hand side, we have
represented the operational impact.
The meantime to resolution
is represented in minutes.
The customer reported
issues are represented.
The SLA compliance percentage is
represented on the right hand side.
Alert to action ratio.
This alert overload meant engineers
spent 23 percentage of their
time triaging alerts, diverting
crucial effort from building new
futures and resolving core issues.
Next, we are going to talk about
the ML solution architecture.
Middleware system capturing
exceptions with minimal overhead.
The key technical specifications,
99.7 percentage of exception capture
rate across all systems only.
3.2 milliseconds overhead per transaction.
Distributed tracing for
context preservation.
Event driven architecture with Kafka
backbone, containerized ML interference
endpoint, the ML classification models.
93.8 percentage of accuracy
in prioritizing errors by
business impact NEM approach.
Combining random forest for categorical
futures, LSTM first stack trace
analysis, gradient boosting for time
series patterns, continuous retraining
pipeline with human feedback.
The ML model Futures, what
makes an alert critical?
We have divided into four categories.
The exception characteristics is the
first category, the stack trace pattern
matching exception type classification.
Mrs. Semantic analysis
code path frequency.
The next category is business
context based on affected user
count estimation, transaction
financial value, business process
criticality, data integrity impact.
The temporal patterns is the
third category based on the
time of delayed correlation.
Error frequency trends.
Business hour waiting.
Seasonal pattern matching based
on the historical response.
Prior resolution times SLA.
Breach prediction,
historical escalation rate.
Developer response patterns.
Models are trained using 18 months
of historical incident data.
Encompassing 12,387 resolved
incidents with complete
resolution, workflows and outcomes.
This slide is going to talk about
intelligent alert registration,
the adapter, routing, getting
right alert to the right person.
Contextual evaluation is.
It means each alert is evaluated across
14 parameters, including severity, system
impact, time of day, and team workload.
The ML decision engine leverages ML
to determine the optimal notification
channel and urgency level based
on predicted business impact.
The channel selection routes alerts
to the most appropriate channel Slack,
direct messages, Microsoft teams, or
email based on context and urgency.
The alert delivery formats alerts with
actionable information and includes
severity, appropriate urgency signals.
The intelligent rate limiting our
ML powered rate limiting algorithms
effectively prevented alert storms
during major incidents achieving 68.2
percentage of reduction in overall alert.
Volume during incidents 99.8,
percentage detection rate of unique
issues maintained automated clustering
of related errors, predictive
suppression of cascading failures.
Now we are going to talk about
the results and business impact.
The transfer to results
across the enterprise.
On the left hand side, we have represented
the key performance improvements.
On the right hand side, we are going to
show that tangible business impact, 88.5%
of mean time to resolution reduction.
$2.3 million of annual savings, 23.5
percentage of developer productivity,
73.4 percentage of alert volume reduction.
The meantime to resolution is decreased
from 1 62 to just 18.6 minutes.
We are able to get $2.3 million of
annual savings is achieved through.
Reduced downtime and enhanced
operational efficiency.
23.5 percentage of developer
productivity is boosted by significantly
reducing time spent on alert triage.
73.4 Percentage of alert volume
reduction resulting from intelligent
clustering related issues.
Now we are going to talk about the key
takeaways and implementation guide.
On the left hand side, we have
represented the ML ops best practices.
Start small.
Scale gradually.
Begin with one high volume
system and expand as models.
Mature human in the loop feedback.
Create explicit feedback mechanisms for
continuous model improvement and accuracy.
Measure the business outcome.
Focus on mean time to resolution.
And cost savings, not just model accuracy.
Metrics build for transparency.
Ensure engineers understand why an alert
was triggered and how it was processed.
Your implementation journey is
represented on the right hand
side, secure data foundation.
Implement robust exception capturing
with minimal overhead and distributed
tracing across all enterprise systems.
Model training and validation.
Curate historical incident data
for training and continuously
validate ML classification models.
Registration integration.
Connect your ML engine to intelligent
routing and notification channels
like Slack teams and email iterate
to development, roll out the solution
incrementally gathering feedback and
refining the system with each iteration.
Thank you.