Hello everyone.
My name is Samis Joshi.
I'm working with Cognizant as a
senior, a technical architect on Duck
Creek Technology Cloud platforms.
I'll Today we're walking you through
how robust ML ops practices are
transforming insurance operations.
And then over the next few slides,
I'll show you how AI driven
strategies are delivering up to
65% efficiency gains and reducing.
Processing times by as much as
99% across insurance functions.
So let's dive in.
So here's our agenda for today.
First, we'll look at the broader
AI transformation in insurance.
Then we'll dive into ML Lops
architecture and examine specific
technical deep dives like modeling
computer vision and telematics.
Next we'll touch on compliance
and biases detect, followed by an
implementation roadmap and ROI analysis.
Finally, I'll summarize the key takeaways
and share the actionable next steps.
Let's start.
Insurance as an industry has
come a long way in AI adoption.
Before ML ops only about 18% of the
carriers are experimenting with AI.
Today, thanks to ML ops that
option has grown to 54%.
The results are tangible 65% higher
operational efficiency, and a 60%
improvement in underwriting accuracy.
This isn't just about automation guys.
It's about enabling cons, consistent
data driven decisions that scale.
Let's rewind and see why
transformation was needed.
Traditionally, policy applications
involve paperwork and manual data entry.
Underwriting was often subjective and
policy issuance took three to four days.
Claims assessments could stretch
for weeks, and risk evaluation
was limited to annual reviews.
The net effect was higher cost.
Long cycle times and inconsistent
customer experiences.
So now here comes into picture the ML ops.
So ML lops brings order and automation.
So here we are talking about continuous
integration and deployment pipelines
that cut the deployment cycles by 78%.
Feature store architectures,
architectures that reduce
feature engineering time by 67%.
And model registries that ensure
traceability and compliance.
This integrated architecture allows
insurers to respond quickly to
market and regulatory changes.
That's interesting.
Proceeding with transformative
transf transformative results
on the policy issuance.
So consider policy issuance.
So traditionally it
took three to four days.
With ML lops, it's down to just 15%.
Now with mops.
So that 99% re time reduction in time
while maintaining a 93.6% accuracy rate.
The key lies in the automated risk
assessments, document processing
and continuous monitoring that
ensures model remains accurate
even as risk profiles evolve.
Proceeding to next step comes
the catastrophe modeling.
That's a very important point in here.
Catastrophe modeling is critical for
insurers but traditional approaches relied
on static data and quarterly updates with
machine learning operations model in just
real time weather data, satellite image
imagery, and even assemble approaches that
mix physics and machine learning together.
The outcome.
It's a 31% boost in the flood
prediction accuracy, nearly 30%
better cyclonic forecast, and a 43%
improvement in claims readiness.
And that's a very good number.
If you pro, if you look
into the computer vision.
In case of the property and casualty
insurance let's start on this point.
In this case, if you see computer
vision has ref re redefined the property
inspections with drones running Edge,
deploy on the running on the edge deployed
models, insurers can capture pre-pro,
insurers can capture pre-process and
assess property damage in real time.
Accuracy has reached 89% and
inspections that once took days
are now completed in minute.
Importantly, champion
challenger frameworks.
Ensure models are continuously valued and
improved proceeding with the telematics.
This basically brings the real time
example where I'll tell you how
telematics is helping in assessing
the real time driver risk assessment.
Driver behavior is another area
that is being shaped by ai.
Telematics use uses OBD two.
Which is on onboard diagnostic
devices and smartphones to
capture over 300 driving features.
Kafka based streaming pipelines
processes, terabytes of data
daily and containerized inference.
Inference engines adjust seamlessly to
traffic loads compared to traditional
demographic based risk assessments.
Predictive power has improved by
83%, and that's again, a very good
number now proceeding to regulatory
compliance and bias distinction.
So no AI transformation is
complete without addressing
fairness and compliance.
So automated adversarial
testing detects nearly 80% of
potential bias before deployment.
Model validation pipelines,
automate documentation and
regulate regulatory reporting
cutting compliance cycles by 67%.
So techniques like lime, LIME,
local interpretable model, agnostic
explanations, and SHAP shapely
edit additive explanations.
These enhance explainability, which
is crucial in market regulated like
insurance now proceeding with the.
How the architecture looks like
the integrated data architecture.
So to achieve accurate models,
insurers must unify data.
So here eight to 12 data sources come
together, like customer data, property
details, IOTs, telematics, imports,
credit scores, even alternative signals
like satellite imaginary imagery.
So by integrating these sources.
Through automated feature
engineering predicting accuracy
improves by more than 36%.
Now, if we come to the key components
for the MLF implementation, ML LOPS
implementation there are four components
that make it make this possible.
Automated deployment
pipelines using GitHubs.
Monitoring frameworks for real time
drift detection experimentation platforms
for AB testing and centralized feature
stores with versioning Together, these
form a mature ML ops ecosystem that
balances speed, accuracy and compliance.
So now if we look into the
implementation roadmap, so
transformation doesn't happen overnight.
So phase one is building the foundation
registries, versioning, and pipelines
over three to four months it, it
takes to build all these things.
Now, phase two, operationalize.
Workflows, like automated
training and monitoring.
The typically, this typically
takes two to three months.
And then phase three, that adds
optimization, automated retraining,
AB testing, and compliance
automation over three to four months.
So within a, within less than a
year, insurancers, insurers can go
from POC to production, and that's a
very good timeframe to achieve this.
So next we'll proceed
with the ROI analysis.
The results speak for
themselves, which on my slide.
Before ML ops model deployment,
claims processing and process and
policy issuance times are much
higher after adoption carriers.
Certain big carriers saw improvements
within nine to 12 months, and
these aren't just marginal gains.
They are game changers that
reduce operational costs and
scale as new models come online.
Proceeding to the key takeaways.
First is ML lops is driving a 300%
growth in AI adoption across insurance.
Secondly, end-to-end automation
insurers accuracy above 93%
while enabling rapid iter.
Third, compliance and fairness
frameworks cut regulatory cycles by 67%.
For your next steps assess your current ML
maturity and pri prioritize high value use
cases, establish foundational components
like registries and feature tools,
and integrate compliance from day one.
Doing this as it was mentioned,
we can go from POC to production.
In within nine to 12 months.
Thank you guys.
Thank you for your time and attention.
I hope this session gave you a big picture
and technical depth on how ML Ops is
revolutionizing the insurance operations.
Thank you and good day.