Hello everyone and thank
you for joining my session.
My name is Krishna Uluru, and today
I'll be talking about how we built a
production ready ML ops pipeline for
telecommunications focusing on a neuro
network based over IP monitoring system.
This work demonstrates how AI driven
monitoring can transform carrier
grade wise over IP operations.
With both high accuracy and
automated deployment pipelines.
By the end of the session, I hope I will.
You will see how integrating ML ops
with telecom can make networks more
resilient, cost effective, and scalable
here did.
Here is what I will cover today.
First.
I will describe the challenges with
traditional telecom monitoring.
Then I will introduce our ML lops
architecture, followed by a closer look
at the neural network model we developed.
Next, I will walk through the deployment
strategy showing how we ensure
reliability and scalability in production.
Finally, I will share the
business results and the roadmap.
For ongoing improvements,
traditional monitoring has gaps.
So let's start with the current
state of white monitoring.
Traditional tools only provide
about 40% visibility into the
network, leaving blind spots where
critical issues can go Unnoticed.
They're also reactive.
It typically takes 15 to 30 minutes to
detect and respond to issues in telecom.
That delay can mean thousands of
drop calls and frustrated customers.
And finally, the statistical
models used for quality predictions
only reach around 65% accuracy.
This gap is exactly why we
need an AI driven approach.
Capable of understanding complex
patterns and operating in real time.
ML Lops Architecture Overview
our architecture brings together
real time data ingestion, feature
engineering, automated training,
deployment, and monitoring into a
single production ready pipeline.
We use Kafka for streaming
wise or IP events.
Cube flow for training, orchestration,
ml, flow for model registry and
monitoring through Prometheus and Grafana.
The key here is that all of these
components are tied together,
so models aren't just trained.
They are continuously deployed,
absorbed, and improved.
Let me highlight four
essential components.
First realtime data ingestion with
Kafka processes thousands of events per
second at sub 100 milliseconds latency.
Second, the automated training
pipeline orchestrated by cube flow,
which runs distributed GPU based
training with hyper parameter training.
Third deployment automation.
We use blue green deployment models
for zero downtime and instant
rollback if performance degrades.
And fourth comprehensive monitoring
where custom metrics and dashboards give
visibility into both deployment, both
model performance and system health.
Together these ensure a carrier grade
reproducible and resilient ML lifecycle.
Our neural network combines CNN layers to
extract features from packet sequences and
LSTM layers to recognize temporal patterns
across sessions, we added innovations
like custom emitting layer for protocol
specific features and attention mechanism
to focus on anomalies and hierarchical
feature extractor across timescales.
The result, 88% prediction accuracy
with a 23 point movement over
traditional statistical methods.
That's a major leap in how
accurately we can predict and
preempt call quality issues.
The model is only as good as its
features, so we built a fully
automated feature pipeline and the
edge high throughput collectors
capture sip, RTP, and QS metrics.
These are processed in real time
with Apache Beam handling over
10,000 events per second while
extracting 45 plus features.
We use recursive feature elimination
for automatic feature selection and
feast as a feature store to ensure
consistency across training and inference.
All of this is logged and monitored
to maintain data quality and lineage.
Training is orchestrated
through cube flow pipelines.
We use TensorFlow data valuation for
schema checks and drift detection.
Then run distributed
GPU training at scale.
Every experiment, parameters,
metrics, artifacts, is tracked in ML
flow, so results are reproducible.
Models are versioned and registered with
clear approval workflows so teams can
roll forward or backward confidently
in production system maintains 96%
anomaly detection accuracy while
handling thousands of concurrent
requests with 99.99% available.
We achieve this with containerized models.
Intensive flow serving orchestrated by
Kubernetes with horizontal auto-scaling.
Bluegreen deployments provide
zero downtime and edge inference
Nodes across regions deliver
responses in under 50 milliseconds.
This is a true carrier
grade ML deployment.
Comprehensive monitoring
system has been de developed.
Monitoring goes beyond just accuracy.
We track model performance metrics
like precision and recall data
quality metrics like feature rift
and missing values, system health
such as latency and throughput.
When drift is detected, retraining
is automatically triggered.
We also run.
AB tests in production and
use self-healing mechanisms
for infrastructure issues.
This makes the system
adaptive, not just reactive.
Trust is critical in telecom
operations, so we have built
explainability into the pipeline.
We use shop values for feature importance.
Counterfactual explanations to show how
outcomes could change and dashboards
that track feature attribution over time.
Automated model cards and audit logs
document every version and decision.
This means engineers can always
trace a prediction back to its root
cause, essential for both regulatory
compliance and operator trust.
What does all this mean in practice
with this system fault detection
time has dropped from 30 to 15 to 30
minutes, down to two to five minutes.
Network visibility is greatly improved.
Licensing costs are reduced through
open source tooling and uptime
has reached carrier grade levels.
Most importantly, customer satisfaction
improved because quality issues are
caught before they affect end users.
We rolled this out in phases.
Phase one, the foundation, the data
collection, feature engineering,
and an initial model, phase two.
Is automation CICD, pipelines,
testing registries and dashboards.
Phase three is scale distributed
training and geographic deployments.
Phase four, ongoing optimization,
ensembles tuning and knowledge transfer.
This phased approach allowed us
to deliver incremental value while
building towards the full vision.
To wrap up three points.
First, production ready ml
requires end-to-end thinking
from data to monitoring.
Second, automation drives reliability,
especially at telecom scale.
And third, explainability builds
trust, which is essential for
adoption in mission critical systems.
These principles.
Guided us in creating a system that's
not just research project, but a
reliable production grade ML ops system.
Thank you for your time.
I hope this session gave you
insight into how ML Ops can
revolutionize telecom monitoring.
Thank you.