Hi everyone.
My name is Brian Ish.
I'm an engineering lead at Ditto.
And I'll be talking today about
Sky Computing charting a new
course in AI cloud infrastructure.
First of all, apologies, this
will be my first time using OBS.
And so if there are some technical
glitches, I apologize for that.
But let's get started.
So my name is Brian.
As I said, I'm an engineering lead
at Ditto currently spent the last
seven or eight years as an SRE.
Doing production ber workloads at
super orbital raincoat and bayfair.
And I have two total decades of
experience going back to 2005.
I wanted to talk first about what
the cloud has meant to us and what
kinda the promises that it's made
over the course of its lifetime here.
We've been promised on demand,
scalability pay as you go, pricing
models near instant global reach.
They've achieved all of these things.
They've made, they've kept those promises.
I say they, it's a concept but
it's not without it's drawbacks.
So I wanted to draw
attention to some of them.
Vendor lockin.
We all know how difficult it can be to.
In practice, be cloud agnostic.
Data gravity is another concern and
I'll talk about that more later.
And we all know egress charges can be a
huge shock in your AWS bill, for instance.
How expensive hosting in the cloud
can be can be very eye-opening for a
lot of organizations out in the world.
I think this what, this is
what has led to a lot of.
Repatriation.
And what do I mean by that?
There's a quote from an article I read
that was 42% of organizations surveyed
in the United States are considering
or have already moved at least half
of their cloud-based workloads back
to on-premise infrastructures, a
phenomenon known as Cloud repatriation.
I thought that was very interesting
and I wanted to make a note of that
and say something about that and.
While I applaud what these
companies are doing from a pragmatic
viewpoint on their infrastructure
costs, it does beg a question.
Did these companies meticulously
plan their cloud usage from the start
with cop cost optimization in mind,
or are they really just reacting
to the unexpected high AWS bill
they got at the end of the month?
I think most evidence points to the
latter companies that are now repatriating
their infrastructure often failed to
implement basic cloud cost controls from
day one, like automatically shutting
down dev environments during off hours,
using spot instances for batch workloads
or implementing resource quotas.
So rather than fixing those
foundational issues, they've chosen
to abandon the cloud completely
and that's their decision.
But I think taking a step back to on-prem
might not truly be a step forward.
In the long run, if we remain in
the cloud though, how do we address
the fundamental challenges of vendor
lock-in data gravity and rising costs
in a transformative way, rather than
just applying incremental fixes?
And this is where I want to start talking
about the concept of sky computing.
So Sky Computing has been around since Ian
Stoica and Ian, and I apologize if I've.
Mispronounced your last name.
Since 2021 he published where when
he published his very notable paper.
And I very much encourage
everyone to go read it.
It's not a very long read.
I believe it's 20 or so pages.
And it really gets to the
heart of the problem and what
he believes the solution is.
And I think he's spot on.
I'll be talking more about it in, in
the future slides here, but, just as
a general overview, workloads flow
seamlessly between cloud providers.
Therefore they are free from
vendor lock-in and inefficiencies.
And you as the operator have much
better control over data governance.
And these are very big issues,
especially for enterprise.
So the three pillars that I've coined, and
these are my pillars that, these are not
official or written in Ian's paper at all.
But these are what I've dwid it down to.
And that is pillar one being abstraction.
At the heart, oh, sorry.
Moving ahead there too fast.
At the heart of Sky Computing lies
abstraction, which serves as the
glue that unifies the disparate
cloud platforms through compatibility
layer, leveraging tools like
Kubernetes Ray and standardized APIs.
Like S3 sky Computing hides the
complexities of individual clouds.
This means you won't need to worry about
whether your data sits in AWS S3 or Azure
Blob storage, the abstraction layer.
This one handles those details.
Deciding on the optimal storage base
storage base and cost and performance
based on cost and performance.
Sorry.
By providing a right once run
anywhere experience abstraction,
eliminates a vendor lock-in and
simplifies application deployment.
As more cloud platforms become supported,
the abstraction layer offers greater
flexibility, enabling smoother transitions
and substantial cost savings without
requiring you to change how you develop
or how you manage your workloads.
Even beyond the hyper cloud providers of
today, like A-W-S-G-C-P and Azure, you'll
see support for neo cloud providers like
Lambda Labs Core Weave or nes, providing
even greater operational flexibility.
Pillar two here I have is automation
and building on the foundations of
abstraction automation is the really the
next pillar driving sky computing forward.
InterCloud brokers embody this
pillar by serving as intelligent
decision makers who manage workload
placement, cost optimization, and
compliance across multiple clouds.
These brokers continuously analyze
factors like pricing, resource
availability, and regulatory
requirements using AI and realtime data.
They automatically route or adjust
workloads based on current conditions.
Ensuring your applications always
run in the most cost effective
and efficient environment.
This removes the manual overhead of
juggling multiple cloud providers,
reduces the chance of human error,
and lets you focus on higher level
tasks while the system optimizes
operations behind the scenes.
This is perhaps the largest pillar, by
the way and the hardest to get right.
Third and last pillar here I
wanna talk about is agility.
Agility is about creating responsive
and flexible cloud ecosystem where
data and workloads can move freely.
Reciprocal reciprocal peering
agreements are key to this agility
and you'll see me mention this a
couple of times in the presentation.
These agreements are collaborations
between cloud providers that allow
for free or low cost data transfers,
or discounted data transfers,
breaking down the barriers such
as egress fees and data gravity.
As these agreements take shape, often
organically driven by hyperscale
providers keen to support popular brokers
serving the automation layer workloads
can move seamlessly between clouds.
This dynamic environment empowers
businesses to adapt quickly to shifting
costs, regulatory changes or performance
performance requirements without
being locked into a single provider.
Crucially, this level of agility
opens up the cloud ecosystem in
ways never but seen before by
tearing down silos and encouraging
collaboration between providers.
Sky computing creates an interconnected
landscape where innovation thrives
smaller and more specialized.
Neo cloud providers, like Land
Lambda Labs, for instance, or run
pod they gain a seat at the table,
fostering competition and driving
breakthroughs and service offerings.
Enterprises can mix and match services
from various providers without fear.
Leveraging the best features from
each platform to suit their needs.
The result is an agile infrastructure
that can pivot on demand, offering both
resilience and the flexibility to innovate
and disrupt rather than just iterate.
This unprecedented openness not only
breaks the barriers of vendor lock-in, but
also sparks a whole new era of creativity
and efficiency across the entire cloud.
Indu, cloud industry, fundamentally
changing how businesses
harness cloud technology.
Sky Pilot here is the
inaugural broker framework.
And the third bullet point here, this
is encompassing the automation pillar
that I just spoke about before and
the central pillar it was developed
by uc, Berkeley Sky Computing Lab.
They're the creators of Spark and Ray.
It is also, by the way, the residency
of Ian Deca, author of that paper.
It is an open source InterCloud
broker framework implementing
Sky Computing principles.
They have over a million
downloads as of July, 2025.
They're on version zero point 10
including enterprise features.
They have a unified interface to 17
clouds plus Kubernetes plus on-prem.
And there are key capabilities here,
three to six times cost savings
through spot orchestration alone.
Four x faster provisioning.
You can get 200 GPUs in
less than 90 seconds.
9.6 x faster checkpointing
with Mount cached.
Zero code changes for
existing ML workloads.
And you have one yamo file and one
command to run Sky Launch Cloud.
Any.
Now what kind of impact does this have?
This is ML lops, after all.
What kind of impact does this have on
workload impacts or ML workloads rather?
And I wanna reference a couple
of case studies that were
written by these companies.
They're, and they're available on the
sky Compute, or, sorry, sky Pilot website
which I'll have a link to shortly.
But there are two case studies
that were of particular interest
that I wanted to bring up here.
A bridge.
There, they were a slum shop running
their AI infrastructure on s slm.
And I found this quote in their case
study from one of their research
scientists that I thought, I, I have
to include this in the presentation.
I thought that was pretty great.
And covalent as well.
They built a whole new AI stack and really
combating the scarcity in GPUs that I'm
sure everyone is aware of these days.
But you can go on Sky sky Pilot's website,
sky Pilot, I believe it's Sky pilot.co.
And this one I wanna go into more details
about the Abridge case study and bring
some things further into this presentation
that I thought were very interesting.
Sky Pilot delivered, and this, these
are their words, by the way, not mine.
Sky Pilot delivered the familiar
experience our researchers
wanted with the reliability.
Our production workloads required.
With interactive development, you can run
Sky Launch dash GPUs, H 100, colon four,
which provides immediate SSH access to A
GPU enabled shell without complex setup.
Just S Run Dash dashs equals GPU
colon four dash PT y Bash and
S slm, but it works seamlessly
across all of our infrastructure.
Jupyter Notebook hosting.
We can spin up Jupyter Notebooks
directly on GPU clusters, enabling
researchers to prototype with high-end
hardware that wasn't available locally.
Sky Pilots manage jobs, provide the same
convenience as SLMs job scheduler, but
works across all of our infrastructure.
Automatic restart on job failures,
strong isolation and reliable job
management for long running training jobs.
And model evals.
Quick model evaluation becomes simple.
We can deploy models as fast API
services in minutes for testing.
Unlike lm, which lacks native API
endpoint support, sky Pilot makes it
easy to expose models as services.
This is one of their examples
from their case study.
This is a Ya the entire YAMA file for
running distributed training on Sky Pilot.
Not complex at all.
Researchers can use pure PyTorch
and hugging face without wrappers
or additional abstraction layers.
Sky Pilot seamlessly sets up multiple
nodes, populates environment variables
with a cluster topology information
like number of nodes, GPUs, IP
addresses, and then kicks off the jobs.
It's a huge win since machine learning
engineers don't need to struggle with
scaffolding for distributor training,
and it works with any package manager.
So when it comes to AI and ML workloads,
different stages of a pipeline may
benefit from different cloud providers
Specialties and this is where sky
computing really becomes interesting.
With an InterCloud broker like Sky
Pilot, you can split your pipeline and
run model training on Google Cloud.
With TPU optimized instances for deep
learning then decide to run inference on
AWS with their in chips for lower latency
and your data pre-processing on Azure.
Why would you do this?
For one, speed and efficiency of the
machines that I say it I mentioned above.
Cost savings Azure oftentimes
is much cheaper than a AWS.
And regional data regulations.
Again, going back to your data
governance for compliance purposes,
this is huge for organizations.
So what's preventing sky computing
from becoming ubiquitous?
These are some of the challenges
that I foresee personally.
Standard standardization is a huge one.
Universal standards across all cloud
platforms is unlikely Due to competitive
interests and proprietary technologies,
progress can still be made by leveraging
existing widely adopted tools such
as Kubernetes, Ray and S3 APIs.
These standards don't cover every
scenario, but they provide a practical
bridge, allowing sky computing to
move forward without waiting for
complete industry-wide uniformity.
Another challenge is economic resistance.
Hyperscalers will resist reciprocal
peering agreements as sharing
data freely between platforms can
conflict with their business models.
While this resistance exists, smaller
cloud providers and innovative
startups have strong incentives to
embrace sky computing principles.
Their agility and the desire to
compete with larger players drive
them to support the ecosystem
gradually encouraging wider adoption
and putting pressure on the bigger
providers to reconsider their stance.
Infrastructure inertia
is a very big topic here.
There are significant investments.
Preexisting investments organizations
have already heavily invested in
existing cloud infrastructure.
Not just cost, but expertise,
tooling and processing or
processes leading to hesitation
and dramatic changes such as this.
There's resistance to
new paradigms, right?
That's gonna be the case
every time there's a new one.
Reluctance to adopt new paradigms
like sky computing due to
lack of widespread adoption.
Good enough status quo.
Current cloud deployments often function
adequately, even if they're not, cost
optimized or performance optimized.
And there is daunting overhead concerns
about retraining staff, updating
deployment pipelines and refactoring
applications for sky computing's
abstraction layer perceived risks,
apprehensions regarding reliability
and support when moving away
from established cloud providers.
Negative services.
Moving on to something like Run Pod or
Lambda Labs, that is not as proven as AWS.
Nothing is gonna be as proven as
AWS, but and so these factors create
substantial inertia, hindering
widespread sky sky computing adoption.
Finally, I wanna speak about the
challenge of legitimacy, and this is
maybe an understated one, but deserves
a mention here at the very least.
The concept of sky computing faces
challenges in establishing legitimacy,
partly due to a Wikipedia entry
with a warning banner, questioning
source reliability, and noting
a lack of academic citations.
This stems from an incident where a
commercial entity attempted to shape
the narrative around sky computing
through Wikipedia editing, leading
to their ban from the platform.
This incident highlights
a broader challenge.
Commercial entities sometimes
try to claim thought leadership.
For emerging technologies through
questionable means, inadvertently
damaging the credibility of
legitimate technological advances.
However, the fundamental value proposition
of Sky Computing providing a unified
interface across cloud providers
while optimizing cost, performance,
and compliance stands independent of
any single company's implementation.
So for final thoughts, I wanted to say
I genuinely believe that we're at a
turning point in cloud infrastructure.
I don't think sky computing
is just another buzzword here.
I think it's a practical
fix for real problems.
It brings together different cloud
services into one smooth system,
making life easier for businesses
and SREs who need reliable,
flexible, and efficient operations.
At the end of the day, this makes
a sizable dent and balance sheets.
That's what matters.
As more sky computing solutions
emerge, tech leaders worldwide will
continue to notice they'll see the
benefits and quickly move their
workloads to these smarter, more open
and more cost-effective cloud setups.
The future of the cloud is
here knocking at our door.
It's an exciting moment to rethink how we
build and manage systems that stand up to
real world demands, more resilient, more
adaptable, and ready for what's next.
Thank you very much.