Hello everyone, and thank
you for joining this session.
My name is Terrance Stan, Joseph Ra.
I specialize in enterprise data
architecture, cloud data engineering,
and AI driven business intelligence.
I bring close to 25 years of
experience in building data
systems for global organizations.
The title of today talk is Yaya
Driven Enterprise Intelligence.
Enabling real time decision making.
In ops, the topic is important
because businesses cannot
depend on slow reports anymore.
By the time traditional
insight reach leaders, the
opportunity may already be gone.
What organization need is real time
intelligence data that is processed
instantly analyzed with the ai.
And acted on right way.
The next 30 minutes, I will
walk you through four areas, how
enterprise intelligence has evolved.
The building blocks secured the role
of responsible ai, and finally, your
practical roadmap to make it real.
By the end, you will see how a and
ML lops together enable smarter,
faster, and more reliable decisions.
Here is the agenda for today's session.
We will start with evaluation
of enterprise intelligence.
I will explain how organization
move from retrospective reporting
to real time decision systems and
why these safety is necessary next.
We will explore the building
blocks of AI driven intelligence.
This includes distributed
processing, machine learning
models and automated workflows.
They form the core technology that
makes real time decision possibles.
After that, I will discuss
responsible, yay, a implementation
as yay A becomes more powerful.
It also raises ethical questions.
We need governance, transparency,
and trust to make sure these
systems are used responsibly.
Finally, we will cover a
practical amount of blueprint.
This includes architecture, integration
strategies, and an implementation
roadmap that organizations can follow.
My goal is not only to explain concepts.
But also to give you a practical
takeaways, by the end of this session,
you should have a clear picture
of how enterprise intelligence
can transform organizations.
I,
let's begin with the sif from
retrospective intelligence to real
time intelligence for many years.
Traditional business intelligence
only looked backward.
It was based on historical data
and shared through periodic
reports daily, weekly, or monthly.
The common issue was delayed.
By the time leaders received this report.
The situation had already changed.
Traditional BA answered the question,
what happened, but gave little
guidance on what should we do now?
Real time enterprise
intelligence changes this.
It takes continuous data steams
and process them as they arrive.
This allow organization to react
immediately, not hours or days later.
Yay.
A take this even further.
Predictive analytics highlight what
is likely to happen while prescriptive
analytics recommend the best Next action.
Some of these actions
can even be automated.
For example, fraud detection system
systems, it can block suspicious activity
in real time without human review.
The sift from descriptive reporting to
predictive and prescriptive intelligent
is the core difference between yesterday's
BI and today's AA driven systems.
Enterprise intelligence become
powerful when poor parts come together.
The first is CAM models.
These are algorithms that recognize
patents, predict outcomes,
and generate useful insights.
Without them, the data
stays raw and underused.
The second is Yamal Lab's practices.
This ensures model.
Don't just stay in research.
They are deployed, monitor,
and updated as needed.
YMO allows, makes AA relatable
and ready for business use.
The third is realtime processing.
Instead of waiting for overnight report,
data is processed as soon as it arrives.
This give business agility
and immediate responses.
The fourth is government.
Governance provides rules,
accountability and compliance.
It makes sure YAYA systems are
ethical, explainable, and trusted.
When all four intersect Y models, your
labs realtime processing and governance,
we get enterprise intelligent that is
fast, scalable, and trustworthy, missing
even one piece weakens the system.
Together, they create the
foundation for smarter, faster,
and more sustainable decisions.
Yay.
Driven, intelligent is built
on three main building blocks.
The first is distributor data processing.
Large amounts of data need to be
processed quickly and reliably.
Tools like a Kafa Spark Streaming
and road services make this possible.
They handle steams of information
at scale with very little delay.
The second is machine learning models.
This can be symbol.
Statistical models are advanced
deep planning net worth.
They find patterns, predict
outcomes, and recommend actions.
Models can focus, demand,
produce, customer churn, or
detect fraud in real time.
The third is automated decision workflows.
Once insights are generated,
they must be turned into actions.
Rule engines, region re enforcement
landing, and automation tools
help systems act on insights
without waiting for humans.
Especially for routine decisions.
When combined these three elements,
processing, modeling, and workflows turn
raw data into real time intelligence,
they are the foundation of enterprise
systems that can add, not just report
many organization.
Start their Yay journey with small pilots.
These pilots often sit in silos
managed by different teams
with the little coordination.
This leads to duplicate
efforts, inconsistent
practices, and wasted resources.
The next stage is integrated platforms.
Here, organization move away
from scattered pilots and
use shared infrastructure.
They standardize processes, connect
data pipelines, and encourage
collaboration across departments.
This reduces duplication
and increases efficiency.
The most advanced stages.
Enterprise intelligence at this level.
Yay.
A models, data and workflows
all operate together.
Insights from one area, such
as supply chain can directly
inform another area like finance.
Customer insights can influence product
decisions in the journey moves from
fragmented pilots to integrated platforms,
and finally to enterprise intelligence.
The real value comes at the
final stage when embedded into
everybody business process.
That's when organization unlock
the full power of intelligence.
Let me ask you this.
How often have you tried to get the data
and felt stuck with technical tools?
Most people don't want to write queries.
They just want answers.
This is where natural language
interfaces play a role.
They let people interact with systems
using normal conversation, for example.
Yeah, manager can ask, what
were our sales last week?
Under this, the system
can answer instantly.
Even with the chart.
These enterprises do more than qa.
They understand intent, recognized
domain terms and work across multiple
models like text chart or wise.
They act as the bridge
between humans and ai.
The benefit is democratization,
cell service, analytics, operational
health, workflow automation, all become
available to employees at every level.
Not just technical experts by lowering
barriers, natural language, inter
interfaces bring AI into daily work.
They make interface intelligence
easier to use, so that data driven
decision become part of everyone's job.
Now let us see how these
ideas work in real industries.
In financial services, Yaya
detects fraud in real time, often
stopping it before damage is done.
Algorithm trading reacts faster
than any human and banks personalize
services for each customer.
In healthcare, yay.
A helps doctor with clinical decisions.
It predict patient's risk resource use in
hospitals, and even support personalized
treatment plans in retail companies
use a, a for dynamic pricing, inventory
optimization and personalized shopping.
It also improves supply chain flexibility.
Helping stores stay stock even
during disruptions in manufacturing.
Predictive maintenance
prevents costly breakdowns.
Quality checks becomes automated, and
production is optimist for efficiency.
Each industry has unique needs,
but the foundation is same.
Real time data a model,
and automated workflows.
This source, the flexibility of enterprise
intelligence, no matter the field.
These tools help organization move faster,
serve customers better, and save cost.
Now let me ask, would
you trust your system?
That is fast because,
but unfair, probably not.
That's why responsible Yay is the
foundation of enterprise intelligence.
Businesses depend on trust, and trust
comes from doing yay the right way.
Governance is the first.
Clear rules and review processes.
Make sure someone is
accountable for every bottle.
Fairness means testing for bias
and ensuring decisions are balanced
across different groups of people.
Explainability allows leader to
understand why the system gave you a
certain output instead of treating it
like a black fox, complaints ensure we
follow laws like GDPR, industry rules
and privacy protections with those
responsible AI system risk failure
lawsuits or loss of reputations.
With IT organization gain trust
from customers, regulator,
and employees responsible.
Yay is not optional.
It is what makes enterprise
INT intelligence safe,
ethical, and sustainable.
One of the hardest challenging is
balancing performance with ethics.
Businesses always want more accuracy,
but sometimes the most accurate model is
not the fairest or easiest to explain.
The first step is to map trade
off, recognize where accuracy might
conflict with fairness and privacy.
The second step is multi
objective optimization.
Discerning models that optimize across
several goals, not just accuracy.
The third step is stakeholder input, legal
teams, ethics boards, and even end users
should have a say in what is acceptable.
Finally, we need continuous evaluation.
Our society changes.
What is fact today may
not be fact tomorrow.
The goal is not for perfection in one
area, but balance across all by making
this decision openly and documenting them.
Organization build DIA, systems
that are strong in performance,
but also ethical and trusted.
That balance is what sustains
enterprise intelligence over time.
Let's look at what the
architecture of enterprise
intelligence actually looks like.
It begins with cloud
native infrastructure.
Containerization makes sure
models run the same everywhere.
Kubernetes managers scaling and serverless
functions allow even driven processing.
And infrastructure as code
keeps everything reproducible.
The second layer is data architecture,
even streaming backbones, like
Oris carry data in real time.
Features, tools, keep models
supplied with fresh inputs, laco
patents, campaign structure, and
unstructured data in one system.
Data contracts ensure consistency.
And prevent errors together.
This creates a strong foundation
data flow continuously.
Models always have the latest
information and the infrastructure
grows as business needs expand.
Think of it like building not
just a single building, but
a whole city of intelligence.
Each part connect supports
others and scales together.
That is a kind of blueprint needed
for modern enterprise intelligence.
Now that vehicle seen the architecture,
let's talk about how machine learning
integrates into business systems.
First step is continuous integration.
Every time your model or
data pipeline changes.
It must be tested automatically
this quality and avoids
the prices in production.
The second step is continuous delivery
models move from development to
production in a repeatable process
with version control and validation.
Gates, this prevents error
when rolling out new updates.
The third feature is management.
Using feature flax are canary deployments.
Organization can test new
models on a similar scale before
rolling them out to everyone.
Finally, monitoring and
observation is essential.
We track not the system performance,
but also businesses outcome data
drift and model accuracy integration
ensures ideas don't stay in notebooks.
It turns experiments into working systems
that support real business decisions.
We thought integration
innovation starts with it.
AI becomes part of everyday operations.
I
should DAA make decision fully on its own.
The answer depends on the situation.
Okay.
Some cases work well
with full automations.
These are high volume row risk
decisions like filtering, spam
or flaking duplicate records.
Other cases need a human in the loop.
Yaya give recommendation, but
humans approve the final decisions.
This is common in medium risk areas like
loan approvals or medical test reviews.
Then yeah, there are Yaya
augmented decisions here.
Yaya provide insights, but
humans stay in control.
For example, your Dr. May use AA
to highlight areas in the scan, but
doctors still makes the final energies.
The key is matching automation with risk.
Low risk tasks can be automated.
Highest stakes tasks must involve people.
These balances give organization
both speed and accountability.
A e is powerful, but humans add
judgment Together, they create the
right mix of efficiency and trust.
I,
how do we bring everything together?
The answer is through a clear roadmap.
Step One Foundation between
three to six months.
In this stage, organization set up
ML ops, infrastructure, governance
frameworks, steaming capabilities,
and an initial catalog of models.
Step two, integration anywhere
between six to 12 months.
Here, models connect to real systems.
Low risk decision can be automated.
Monitoring is deployed and
retaining pipelines are built.
Step three expenses, 12 to 24 months
at this age organization adopt advanced
methods like reinforcement learning
or natural language interfaces.
Yay.
A capabilities expand across departments
and scale across the enterprise.
The key is not to rush.
Organizations succeed by starting
small, proving value in yearly use
cases, then expanding step by step.
Yeah.
Roadmap, provide direction, ensures steady
progress and builds trust in the system.
So how does this work
move the field forward?
First, we are building unified.
Cloud native YAML ops platforms.
Instead of scattered tools,
models and workflows run on
scalable and cloud systems that
connect across the enterprise.
Second, we enabled real time intelligence.
Instead of waiting for reports,
leaders get immediate insights
and prescriptive actions.
This level of responsiveness
was not possible in the past.
That we design, adoptive and resilient EA
systems, this system do not break easily.
When condition change, they
are self-optimizing, fault
tolerant, and reliable.
Finally, we embed ethical EA by
design, fairness, explainability and
complaints are built into the system
from the start together, these advances.
Change enterprise intelligence
from your reporting tool into your
real time trusted decision engine.
This is not just evaluation.
It is a step change that pushes
the entire field forward.
Let's look at the measurable research
organization have achieved with
AI driven enterprise intelligence.
First, forecasting accuracy.
BU by about 30 percentage.
This means companies predict, demand,
supply, or risk more effectively leading
to better planning and fewer surprises.
Second, reporting efficiency increased by
90 percentage reports that once took our
third days now generated almost instantly.
Leaders can access insights
quickly and make timely decisions.
That companies achieve total to 15
percentage revenue preservation by
predicting risk earlier and optimizing
operation, they avoided losses and capture
opportunities that might have been missed.
These numbers are not just statistics.
They represent real business outcomes,
better planning, faster decision,
and stronger financial performance.
They also prove that AI driven
intelligence is more than theory.
It delivers enterprise level
transformation in real environments
for Fortune 500 companies and beyond.
These impacts are clear evidence of value.
So what does it mean
for the wider industry?
It meets.
These models are not
just useful in one place.
They are shaping new standards.
These frameworks are now being
used as a reference architectures.
They are seated in case studies,
studied in professional forums, and
adapted by multiple organizations.
This will source their
reliability and broad relevance.
Many companies adopt the same approach.
It validates the model.
It proves that unifying Yay ops real time
data and governance works in practice.
This adoption also creates momentum as
more organizations follow these practices,
technology vendors and platform adopt
their tools to support them in the
innovation spreads becoming an industry
now rather than an isolated success.
This is a real power of this work.
It doesn't just transform one company.
It raises the bar for how
entire industry thinks about yay
driven enterprise intelligence.
I,
before we close, let us
review the key points.
First, yay.
Driven enterprise intelligence
transform decision making.
We move from backward looking
reports to real time predictive
and prescriptive systems.
Second, integration is essential.
The real value comes when organization
move beyond isolated pilots and adopt
unified frameworks across the enterprise.
That responsible, yay, responsible,
yay, is not just optional.
Ethics, governance and transparency
must build in from the beginning.
Test is the foundation for adoption.
Finally, ops maturity is the
enabler consistent practices for
model development deployment.
On monitoring 10 yaya from one time our
projects into sustainable capabilities.
This takeaway summarized the
journey from past focused PA
to integrated, responsible, and
scalable enterprise intelligence.
This is how organization can stay
competitive in a data driven world.
We have covered a lot today.
From the evaluation of enterprise
intelligence to the building blocks
responsible, yay the architecture, and
finally, the roadmap to make it all real.
Enterprise intelligence is
no longer about looking back.
It is about acting now and
preparing for what comes next.
Yay.
And LOP ops together allow
organization to make smarter.
Faster and more reliable decisions.
These are the decision that save
growth, reduce risk, and create
real competitive advantage.
Thank you all for your time and attention.
I hope you found this as useful.
Thank you.