Hello everyone.
My name is Tejasvi Nuthalapati and I work as a
lead software development engineer at
Amazon, and I'm super excited to be
here with you today presenting my topic.
So let's get started.
The title of my talk is
Human in the Loop, ML Ops
Production Patterns That Boost
Model Performance by 40% while
maintaining human Control.
Now it's now.
That's definitely a how a mouthful,
but I want to set the stage.
Clearly, the session is not
going to be abstract theory.
It is about real architectures,
measurable outcomes and patterns that
you can apply in your own environments.
My goal is simple to show you that
when we design ML LOP systems in a
way that balances automation with
human judgment, we cannot only
improve performance, but also build
systems that teams actually trust.
So if you've worked with machine
learning and production, you
know the pain of extremes.
On one side we have full automation.
Everything is left to the model and
the pipelines look clean and fast.
But underneath that Polish
drift starts creeping in.
Something like false
positives should show up.
Each case pile up and B long.
No one is really sure why the
system is making the decisions.
It is making trust evaporates.
So on the other side we have a, we
have like multiple manual bottlenecks.
Every decision requires a human check.
Accuracy might look good, but the
system becomes slow and expensive.
CU burn out on repetitive
work and throughput collapses.
You heard that right?
Both of these extremes fail us, and yet
too often organizations think the solution
is to just double down on whichever
extreme they have already chosen.
More automation or like more humans.
But the truth is, may
the path is sustainable.
So let me talk to you about the third.
This is a new concept.
Um, so instead, humans versus machines.
It is humans with machines.
That's the third way thinking of it as
designing systems where AI brings scale,
speed, and pattern recognition, and humans
bringing judgment, context and ethics.
Each is doing what they do best at
what they do, and the pipeline treats
both as first class participants.
Here's a story that
illustrates a simple point.
I was researching about a FinTech com, uh,
company, and, um, it was drowning in false
positives in their fraud detection system.
Transactions were consistently
being flagged and estimate.
Customers were furious.
Initially, they tried tuning
the models, but the improvements
were a bit teeny tiny.
What made the real difference
was embedding structured human
review into the pipeline.
Analysts weren't just fixing mistakes
on the site, their decision were
logged, versioned, and directly
tied to the retraining cycles.
So finally, what's the result?
It's the false positives dropped by 40%.
It essentially means there's an
uplift that that just didn't come
from some breakthrough algorithm.
It came from rearchitecting the
system so that humans and machines
were truly collaborative and
collaborating at the same time.
I'm going to talk to you about a
few patterns that have identified,
and let's go one after the other.
First one is the tiered autonomy.
This essentially enables this
collaboration that is something,
um, I call it as a tiered autonomy.
So let's go back to the
fraud detection example.
Low value, low risk transactions
where the model could have like
high, very high confidence.
Those could be auto approved.
Medium risk cases where the model
is a little bit uncertain should
be routed to a human analyst, which
can bring in context to the problem.
And high risk cases involving
large sums of money should be
escalated to full human review.
But with AI generated insights and
supporting data attached to speed
of decision making, from a technical
standpoint, this can be implemented
in multiple different waves.
So let's start with service
measures that, uh, handle routing.
Uh, CICD branching that responds to
confidence thresholds or even, uh,
Kubernetes operators that govern,
which requests require intervention.
But the technology is not
the heart of the pattern.
The heart of it is, um, essentially
designing autonomy as a spectrum in stuff.
A binary choice in one production
deployment, um, the tier autonomy
reduced analyst workload by 60%.
Analysts were no longer wasting time
on trivial cases and their expertise.
Which was essentially, um, must be
concentrated towards what matters the
most and the throughput increased.
Um, and finally the
customer trust also went up.
So the system as a whole
became much more reliable.
So I'm also talk, going to talk about
the pattern and the second pattern,
which is the observable ML model.
Which is essentially
absorbability in a fancy way.
So if you think about it, in
traditional software engineering,
we would never deploy a service
without logs, metrics and traces.
Yet with machine learning models, too
many organizations throw models into
production as opaque black boxes too bad.
So imagine a recommendation system
that suddenly starts suggesting
irrelevant or outdated products.
How would you see that?
Just imagine.
So without visibility
into confidence scores.
Feature drift or reasoning traces,
you won't realize there's a problem
until customers start complaining.
By then, trust has already eroded.
The solution is to bring absorbability
patterns or the principles into ML system.
That means structured decision logging.
And that also means, it means, uh,
building dashboards that show confidence
distributions, um, and also drift
indicators along with feature stability.
That means explanations that are layered
so that engineers, business stakeholders,
and even end users can understand
decisions at the level they need.
When models become
observable, two things happen.
First, operators can catch drift and
bias early before it becomes a crisis.
And second, trust grows stakeholders
who might otherwise rest a state
adoption, start to see the system
as something transparent and
manageable, but not as a black box.
This is a huge change in
perspective if you think about it.
The last and the most, much more important
one is the human in the loop pipeline.
So the, this is the one that I'm, um,
more interested in driving the point.
So right now, in many organizations, human
feedback is treated as an afterthought.
Yeah, a human spot's a mistake,
files a ticket, and maybe that
data makes it way back into
retraining month, many months later.
So that process is far too slow,
and by the time it completes the,
the system might have already
drifted far, far farther apart.
So instead, we should treat human
feedback as first class data.
Every human correction
should be logged, tied to the
specific model version that it.
Um, like it began and was in the pipeline,
that feedback should be automatically
incorporated into retraining, so
the system continuously learns.
Let's look at content
moderation as an example.
When a moderator flags post that model
misclassified, that feedback is not
just noted, it is captured, version,
and fed right back into the pipeline.
When you see this over time,
the model becomes sharper, more
aligned with real human judgment.
In one system, I observed this loop
raised the production F1 score from 0.72
to 0.84 in just a few three training
cycles, a 16% lift in measurable accuracy.
That improvement didn't just come from
new features or maybe new algorithms.
It just came from designing the pipeline
so that human judgment flowed directly
into the model's learning process.
And here's the few key points.
As models get stronger, human input,
bigger doesn't just become less valuable,
it becomes more valuable because
humans are the only ones who can guide
systems through the messy, ambiguous,
ethically sensitive cases that no
model, sorry, that no model will have
a fully master, which is what I said.
So the final one is
the scalable oversight.
Which deals with the reality of scale.
As systems grow, you cannot have humans
reviewing every single decision of yours.
That simply doesn't scale.
But if you reduce human oversight too
much, you expose yourself to risk.
The answer is adaptable.
Oversight, you guessed it.
Right?
Uh, so you stratify risk levels.
You, you use, you just use intelligent
sampling and you design escalation parts.
Take supply chain, um, anomaly
detection as an example.
Instead of reviewing every alert,
the team over sample low conference
cases and routed them to humans.
By doing so, they caught 90% of
novel anomalies, thinks the model
had never seen before, while cutting
overall human workload in half.
That's what scalable oversight looks.
Human attention grows, subline.
Subline yearly.
With system growth, you still have the
quality and the trust that human review
provides, but without overwhelming
your people, just what I said.
So how do you measure success
in human, in the loop systems?
You don't stop at model accuracy.
You just don't stop there.
You have to measure the system,
humans as well as machines together.
That means tracking the
reduction in false positives.
It also means measuring
time to drift detection.
It means calculating how quickly human
feedback makes its way into retraining.
It even means surveying operator
confidence because a system that humans
trust is one that they actually use
effectively across multiple organizations.
Um, also, uh, let me
forget, uh, not forget this.
So these patterns have consistently
driven around a 40% improvement
in effective performance.
Again, not because the model
themselves got radically better, but
because the system just not just.
It's the system.
The collaboration between
humans and machines were, was
architected more intelligently.
Let's look for.
Farther ahead.
The future of ML lops is not about
squeezing humans out of the loop.
It's just about amplifying them.
Machines will continue to handle
scale, speed and repetitive pattern
recognition, but humans will
continue to provide oversight,
creativity, and ethical grounding.
When we design systems with that balance,
we don't just get models that are a
few percentage points more accurate.
We get systems that
organizations actually trust.
We get pipelines that operators
can debug as well as improve.
And also let's not forget, and we get gen
AI that end users feel confident depending
on, so my closing thought is this, stop
thinking of humans and AI as substitutes.
Start thinking of them
as co-collaborators.
This is where the real 40% uplift
comes from, and that is how we build
the next generation of production
ml, lops systems, systems that are
powerful, scalable, and trustworthy.
Trustworthy.
Thank you.
I.