Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My name is, and today I will walk you
through the ML ops in healthcare, or
simply how we can scale AI models in
hospitals and clinics by using smart
automation and monitoring frameworks.
Before we dive in, I
have a quick question.
How many of you have seen an AI project
in healthcare that worked great in
testing, but struggle to go live?
I'm pretty sure a lot
of y'all have seen that.
Yes, that's exactly the gap
we are addressing today.
Let's move on to the next slide,
the healthcare ML ops challenge.
Healthcare organizations
are excited about ai.
It promises better diagnostics, faster
admin processes, and even cost savings.
But here is the reality.
68% of projects face IES production
failures reduce trust and
compliance slows everything down.
So let me ask you, what do you think
is harder building the AI model?
Or getting it safely into production.
Most of you would agree.
Deployment is where things get tough.
Let's move to slide three,
research backed lops Impact.
Now, here is the good news.
Research shows that structure
lops makes a huge difference.
Projects succeed.
73% more often, models stabilize
40% faster errors reduce, and
organizations save millions each year.
So if I could summarize, ML Ops isn't
just about better tech, it's about
better outcomes, faster and safer.
Let's move on to the next slide.
Healthcare specific ML lops challenges.
But healthcare is different
from other industries.
We face four unique hurdles.
First is regulation, meeting
FDAs and HIPAA standards.
Second is sensitive data.
Patient privacy is very critical.
Third is workflow fit.
Doctors cannot be slowed
down by clunky systems.
For is monitoring at
scale across hospitals.
Not just one system.
Now the question is, do any of
these resonate with challenges you
have seen in your own organization?
Something to think about.
Alright, let's move to the next slide.
Comprehensive framework.
To solve this, I use a four
phase framework model assessment,
infrastructure readiness, pipeline
automation, monitoring systems.
Think of it like building a hospital.
First, you can check the
quality of materials.
That is the model assessment.
Then you make sure that the
building is safe and compliant.
That is the infrastructure.
Next, you automate daily operations
like elevators and security.
That is the pipelines.
Finally, you keep everything
under 24 7 surveillance.
That is the monitor.
Let's move to the next slide, phase one.
That is the model assessment.
Healthcare models can't just be accurate.
We need to check, does it work
across different patient groups?
Is it fair and unbiased?
Can clinicians understand its decisions
and can we prove this to the regulators
when we follow this process accurate.
Rates go up by 64%.
So assessment is our foundation.
Moving to the phase two infrastructure
readiness, imagine trying to
run MRI scans on a laptop.
It just won't work.
Infrastructure readiness means making
sure we have the right compute and
security, ensuring HIPAA compliant flows.
Designing integrations with systems
like EHR, so doctors aren't disrupted,
and planning for scalability when
more hospitals adopt the model.
Doing this right reduces
disruptions by 68%.
Let's move to the next slide, the phase
three, which is automated pipelines.
This is where we save
time and avoid errors.
Pipelines take care of data,
pre-processing and de-identification.
Moderate training with version control.
Safe deployments, using cannery tests
and rollbacks automatic generation
of documents for regulators.
Here is a quick analogy.
It's like setting up an
assembly line in a factory.
Once built, it runs
smoothly and consistently.
Let's move to the next phase.
That is a phase four monitoring framework.
Now, here is the most critical part.
That is monitoring.
We track model accuracy in real time data
drift when patient data starts changing.
Alerts for clinicians.
If something looks wrong, this step
improves reliability by 47%, and most
importantly, keeps patients safe.
Let's move to the next slide.
Technical implementation
on ml Lops Architecture.
For those of you who like the tech site
here is the stack version Control with
Git, CICD, pipelines for approvals,
Dockers and Kubernetes for deployment,
Prometheus and Grafana for monitoring.
But remember, technology,
just the enabler.
The real goal is trust and
safety in clinical use.
Let's move to the 11 slide.
That is the implementation roadmap.
Rolling this out takes about a
year, but we break it into phases.
It starts with month one and
two where we assess and plan.
Month three and four, where
we build the foundation.
Month five to six, we
pilot with one model.
From month seven to 12, we
scale to more hospitals.
Question is, if you had to pick, would
you prefer a faster pilot or a more
cautious rollout across the system?
This is something which
we need to think about.
So let's move to the key takeaways.
So to wrap up our session today,
we have some key takeaways.
Structure lops is equal
to higher success rates.
Healthcare has unique challenges,
but they can be sought.
The four phase framework gives
us a practical path, and the
ROI is clear, safer, faster, and
more cost effective deployments.
The next step, starting by assessing
where your current MLO system starts.
Thank you so much for your
time and your engagement today.
I would love to hear your
thoughts about what is the biggest
deployment challenge you're facing.