Okay.
Hello everyone.
My name is Angen Das and I studied at
Indian Institute of Management and I'm
currently a technical leader at Meta.
So here I work in ads ranking
systems where we use big ML models
to find the right kind of ads.
That can be shown to users on
Facebook, Instagram, et cetera.
So today I'm here to talk about
lops at massive scale, how massive
trillion parameter large models, right?
And we'll see what are the
operational challenges that we
get while training this model.
These models, these really
large language models.
Okay let's dive right in.
In agenda, the first item, which
we have, is to how to deal with the
scale and what are the challenges
while dealing with this really large.
Machine learning models training
them, operationalizing them, serving
them, doing the inference, et cetera.
So we'll talk about that.
The second point we'll talk about
is that what are the infrastructure
components required to build
these kind of models, right?
And serve these kind of models.
The next is pipeline
orchestration automation.
We'll talk about different frameworks
and techniques for managing this
really long training cycles which can
be weeks or sometimes months, right?
Then we'll talk about the
monitoring and failure recovery.
These train, these models are getting
trained for a really long time or weeks.
And then what are the metrics that we
should be tracking because otherwise
we are just flying blind, right?
And also so we'll be tracking
how stable the models are when
the training is happening.
And if some error happens, the
loss should not be, catastrophic.
Okay.
The next is resource
optimization and cost management.
So we'll talk about different
strategies, how to utilize the
maximum of these hardwares so that
we can bring down the cost, right?
Okay.
So the first thing is the skill challenge.
The scale is very high.
And this is a really challenge
because we are talking about
trillion parameter models, right?
So the first challenge that we see
is, I think we already touched Job on,
is that really long training cycles.
Because of these extended
training cycles, it takes.
A really long time to actually find
out whether anything worked or not.
So you have data, you train and train
for weeks, and then you got a model.
Model is good or not.
You only find out after weeks, right?
Okay.
So next is numerous distributor,
GPU working in synchronized.
And parallel manner, right?
So you need a literally lot of GPUs.
So we are talking about thousands and
thousands of GPUs are required, and
these GPUs have to be synchronized.
Otherwise, you'll not be able
to get a model trained, right?
So that's a second challenge.
The third challenge is cost, because this.
Training is happening on a data center,
which have a lot of GPUs and GPUs.
Cost is massive power cost is massive.
And on top of that, people who
know technical expertise on
these things these people's cost
a lot to the companies, right?
So that is a substantial training cost.
So the second is massive
amount of training data, right?
So you have very big, cluster.
And then, you have a very big
model you want to train on,
but what is the data, right?
So we need really massive data
to be fed into this really
hungry, right data hungry models.
And so that is the next challenge.
And then, the last challenge is
considerable volumes of model checkpoints.
So you have really big trillion,
trillion parameter, large model.
Now, if you want to save a snapshot,
like you train for say, one hour
and you want to save a snapshot,
okay, what are my weights right
now that trained weights right now?
So you have to save the whole, whole
model and saving that basically means
that, you need that much memory.
So these are the biggest challenges of,
of training these big models, right?
Let's take look at, take a look
at financial realities, right?
So what are the financial
cost involved here?
We talked about.
That it takes a lot of time.
And then the weekly training
cost is super, super high, right?
That is first thing.
The second thing is cost per failed hour.
If it fails for some reason, right?
The training is happening and it fails.
Then then because of the.
Because of a failure.
Your cost is very high because
your GPUs are sitting idle.
You have already invested a lot of power
in running the GPUs and that is gone.
You might have to go back
to a last checkpoint.
Because so any kind of downtime.
Basically cost a lot, right?
Then there is potential waste, right?
So potential waste means
the data is not coming.
That's why your training is not
happening, or your power went
out or power's not enough, right?
So that is always chances of waste, right?
So we have to make sure that
we minimize the waste, right?
Yeah.
Third is the last one is
basically trading duration.
And since.
This training is going on for a really
long time, then, you have to have right
strategy to minimize cost here because
it's going to take a really long time
and really lot of money because of that.
Okay.
Okay, moving on.
Now let's take a look
at the second agenda.
Basically we have is what are the
infrastructure components required?
To build this and operationalize
these large language models.
The first is very obvious.
You need a distributed training
infrastructure because these
are really large models.
They cannot fit in one machine, and
you want a really big cluster to.
Basically load these models and
then train these models, right?
That is first, and then there
since they're distributed.
That's why you need a right very
high bandwidth connection between
GPUs, between clusters, so that
you can actually effectively train.
Otherwise, you'll lose
lot of time to only data.
And on top of that, additionally
you can have custom kernels.
Kernels are nothing but programs that
run on the single set of instructions
that run on multiple machines, right?
And that way it helps to
train the model efficiently.
But to harness the hardware power
you can have custom kernels.
And they can really harness the hardware
specific, acceleration capabilities
that are provided by these hardwares.
Okay.
So the next is data pipeline system.
You have your distributed training
infras already, but you also
need and those are data hungry.
That's why you need a data pipeline system
to feed data continuously into that.
So that's a data pipeline
system we're talking about.
Okay.
The third the third is
orchestration frameworks.
So you need, different kind of
frameworks, which are aware of the
GPU and which you can schedule right.
Kind of jobs and right
kind of hardware, right?
And orchestration is very important.
The last one is monitoring
and observability.
This company is very important.
So in monitoring and observability
we talk about what kind of
metrics that you want to track.
Okay.
And if those metrics are going,
haywire going up, down and you have
right kind of alerts are set up right?
So that what you have is, as the
training is progressing, you are know,
what's going on because without the
metrics, you are basically flying blind.
Okay.
So let's move on and take a deeper look
at distributed training frameworks.
We talk about four components
distributor training, component
distributor training frameworks, and
then we talk about data pipelines.
Then we talked about automation and
frameworks, and then monitoring, right?
So the first thing, we talk about
distributor training frameworks now.
We have, we are here, we are
showing two distributor frameworks.
One is Megatron by Nvidia.
The other is deep speed
by Microsoft, right?
So in Megatron we have tensor parallelism
for efficient layer distribution.
So any neural network has lot of layers.
So with tensor parallelism, we can
basically make it more efficient.
Then the next one is sequence parallelism.
What is sequence bism?
So let's understand what is sequence.
You send a set of send a prompt
some text to a large language
model that is a sequence, right?
So input sequence can be really
large and that has a very
big memory footprint, right?
And this is in for sequence,
we can chunk it out.
And assign a chunk to
A-G-P-U-A specific GPU, right?
So that way you can manage
that memory footprint, right?
So that is what a sequence parallelism is.
And then we can basically megaton
is optimized to Nvidia GPUs, right?
Since we have some GPU here, a 100 H
100, but it can be more different kind
of GPUs also similarly deep speed.
Have something called zero optimizer,
which kind of me optimizes memory.
You have pipeline parallelism or
for balance computation, you have
some offloading techniques for
CPU and VME memory extensions.
So these are different kind of techniques.
These distributed frameworks used
to make the training faster, right?
This modern, massive
scale parameter training.
Combines multiple parallelism
strategies simultaneously.
So you can have tensor parallelism,
you can pipeline parallelism,
you can data parallelism.
It's a sequence parallelism all working
together to together to basically
train the model more efficiently.
Okay.
So next let's talk about
the pipeline organization.
So we talk about distributed
components, distributed
architecture, distributed frameworks.
And then we talk about
pipeline organization, right?
So pipeline organization, we talk
about what that the first is, first
step is data preparation, right?
So without data you don't
have a model, right?
So you will prepare the data and then
feed that data to this data hungry
training clusters where we are training
the, training this models, right?
So in training, so the next
step is training orchestration.
You are doing this, orchestrating
this training on, various
big cheap U clusters, right?
And after that you have to have a
model and you have to evaluate the
model and see what is good or bad.
And if it's good, then you
have to register the model.
You have to, basically, you have to
save the model version it, register
it in a way that you know, you can
basically, you have thousands of versions
and you can find the right version.
Which version is working correctly,
it was good or bad, and all that.
So the good model checkpoint or snapshot,
basically will be store in model registry.
So all these components, all these
com pipeline orchestration is very
important to get this whole thing running
smoothly for a long duration of time.
Like we are talking about
weeks or sometimes months.
Okay.
Moving on.
The third is automated
recovery strategies.
What kind of so here we'll talk about
what kind of failures can happen and
what can we do if a failure happens,
so a failure detection, right?
So the first is failure detection.
So it'll be continuously
monitoring for harder failures
without gradient explosions.
Basically your training and you
have forward path and backward
path, and then you are computing
this gradient and a gradient spike.
So you have to basically notify for
that, and you also have to notify
about data corruption issues.
So that's very important.
The next point is checkpoint management.
We talked about, which we touched
upon it a little bit earlier that you
have, like your training is going on.
For two weeks.
It's not that you will see,
you will be having a output
only after two weeks, right?
You're getting an output after
every little training you do, and
basically keep track of what is the
checkpoint, what is the saving the
checkpoint as a training progresses.
It should have a right kind of
strategy that if something fails,
which checkpoint I should look at, and
how many checkpoints I can fall back.
Two.
The third one is, the next
one is resource reallocation.
Dynamic provisioning.
And cluster reconfiguration happens here.
Your resources allocated for
some training, but then you can
want to reallocate it, right?
So you can be, you should
be able to do that here.
Then the training re redemption.
So if something fails.
Which the training should
resume automatically.
It's not you have to manually
go and fix something.
It should be automatically doing.
So robust recovery automation is
very important and mission critical.
Okay.
Moving on.
What kind of monitoring are we doing?
We talked about metrics.
So what kind of metrics
are we tracking here?
So the first metric is system
metrics, and the next is training
metrics, because your system metric
is basically hardware metrics.
So G utilization, network
bandwidth disc io power.
So these are hardware.
Hardware and power, right?
So these are system metrics,
but you are training it.
So there are training
methods, training a model.
That's why they have a training metrics.
So you have loss, you have a
gradient, you have a learning rate
and a parameter, denomination,
parameters, how they're doing, right?
Evolution of parameters.
So these are the metrics.
And then for all the system metrics
and training metrics, you have
to have some kind of alerting.
So if something is not right
or not tending right, then you
have to have an alert system.
Anomaly detection algorithms can basically
notify folks whenever there is an anomaly.
And then you can have
predictive failure analysis.
You have the data, now you can do some.
Put analysts on that, then you
have to have, you have notify
multiple channels, right?
It's not like only a phone rings.
You have a phone, you have Slack,
you have IM messages, email, right?
Call, everything you can do, right?
And automated escalation policy.
If you, if somebody doesn't pick up the
phone and fix it, then, keep on escorting.
Okay.
So that is real time monitoring systems.
Let's move on to some
advanced monitoring systems.
And early warning systems, right?
So those are not early.
So these are earlier,
early rise systems, right?
The gradient explosion signals, so
we talked about this gradient, right?
So gradient is the way to
adjust the weights, right?
So you are turning the model.
Turning the model is nothing, but,
adjusting the weights of the parameters
and whenever the gradient becomes, shoots
up or shoots down, shoots up really high.
Then it will just mess
up the training, right?
The stability of the training
will go sideways and go south.
Monitoring for certain
spikes is super important.
Activation distribution ships, right?
So tracking layer output distribution
statistics for unexpected pattern changes.
So if you are basically tracking every
activation and there's like super high
change on that, then also it should
be basically, taking some action here.
Validation and trained ence.
So you have trained the model a lot and
then you have validated it that, okay, the
trained model is actually performing here.
Or not.
If the difference between train and
the test, train and validation is
really high, then something is wrong
and we need to be notified for that.
Similarly, learning data and loss
correlation, monitoring for unexpected
loss behavior during learning rate changes
that also needs to be tackled, right?
So early duration basically
enables intervention before
catastrophic failure happens, right?
So you have some ation happening
that if something is going on,
so you can intervene, right?
You can see a temporary
learning rate reduction.
You can do, you can say selective
gradient clipping adjustments.
The grad is going high, so
you can clip it a little bit.
You can do emergency checkpoint,
emergency check pointing.
Things are going bad.
So then that's why you can checkpoint
quickly emergency so that you can save
a good snapshot and a snapshot of the
weights, and then, train from there.
Or you can do some automatic hyper tuning.
So now let's talk about
computational efficient optimization.
So we're talking we
touched up on this, right?
So you can do hardware acceleration
and those kind of things.
But here we have some optimization
techniques we talk about.
So the first optimization technique
is mixed precision training.
Use using f floating point
16 bit instead of 32 bit.
You can basically reduce the memory
footprints and you can also increase
the throughput of the system.
Basically, number of bits is less so
computation is less and memory is less.
That, so the, so overall, the
throughput of the system improves.
So next is activation Checkpointing.
So activation checkpointing is
basically a mechanism to, to trade.
Memory for compute, when the
training is happening, you are
having, creating activations and
then saving those activations.
And in the backward pass you
can use it in the backward back
propagation, you can use it.
Instead of that, you are
basically computing it on the
fly during the back propagation.
So that is basically is
active reject pointing.
Okay.
The flash attention.
So these are, this is a special technique
which basically makes the attention.
Computation is really faster.
So that is flash attention.
And with a lower memory footprint,
they can be really helpful in speeding
up your machine learning model train.
Okay?
So with all this computational
efficiency optimizations you'll get
faster training cycles and lower costs.
Okay moving on to resource
optimization strategies.
So sometimes the resource so this
approach is basically dynamic
resource allocation strategy, right?
Your resource needs to change
without within the training.
Throughout the training, your
resource might change, right?
Resource requirement will change.
So initial phases you'll
need a really high memory.
When the middle phases, you'll
need more compute, less memory.
Or stable memory and final phases,
you might basically reduce passage.
So that's why in the final
pages know resource requirement
might be different, right?
So there are graphs which
basically show that you know
how things are changing, right?
Early phases here, then phase, then later,
then scaling down and refinement, right?
So in all these phases.
Different kind of resource
requirement is there.
So if we can, manage that,
that will improve overall cost
and the resource requirement.
Okay.
The next is model deploy permanent.
So you have the whole thing ready.
You have trained four weeks and you
have the, finally you have the model,
which can be used in production.
But to use a model in production,
you need to do a lot of things.
The first is serving these para big
models will require big memory, right?
So that means you need a substantial
GPUs to basically just serve request
to, for predictions on these models.
Next is inference latency.
Yeah, you have a model, but then
when the request comes in to
predict it, you have user's expert,
not super responsive responsible,
basically super fast responsive.
But if the inference latency is very high
because because you have less GPUs or
something like that, or your bandwidth
is not good, then it'll not work.
So for that, we have.
Inference, la inference we have to
be very careful about it, right?
So inference latency basically
increases or basically increases when
the sequence length increases, right?
When the number of inputs,
sequences is very large.
Then this attention layers that we have
in large, longer models or transformer
layers that we have, that competition
skill will basically increase a lot.
Throughput optimizations.
So you can do some batching strategies
and balance latency versus throughput.
So you can do some batching.
So basically increase it.
So key diploma strategies that we need to
make sure that first extensor parallelism
across multiple GPUs within a node.
So within a node, basically you have
multiple GPUs, and then you can do
Tencent pallets in there, right?
That is the first thing.
Second is quantization basically use.
Reduced memory footprint because you
are using lower precision, 14 point
numbers and quantizing and lower
precision lower precision, 14 point
numbers if you use, it'll be good.
And then KV cache optimization
for efficient context handling.
So you can use some caching there.
And then specialized high performance
hardware you can always use to, and the
speed of the performance of your systems.
Okay, so let's come do key takeaways here.
So for ML ops to work for you, you have to
have infrastructure first approach, right?
At a massive scale.
This ML Ops is not an afterthought.
It has to be critical foundation
that makes training possible.
So you have to invest
in distributor systems.
You have to invest in distributor
system expertise in terms of
people who know what they're doing.
Next is automate everything Manual.
Manual intervention during extended
training runs is impractical.
And build a comprehensive, you
can't just do that manually.
So you have to, comprehensive
automation, we talk about monitoring.
We, you have a recovery,
you have optimization.
Everything has to be automated.
So then multi-level monitoring.
So you have to have integrate hardware
level monitoring, like system level
monitoring and alerting is there.
Then for similarly, you have the training
level metrics and training level alerting.
So multi-level monitoring
and alerting has to be there.
Okay last but not the
least is cost, right?
So cost is a first class method.
At this scale, at basically a trillion
parameter, large language models, right
at that scale, ML ops efficiency directly
impacts substantial learning cost, right?
So you can reduce the running cost
very easily if you improve your mops.
So that's why you have to track
it, optimize it, report it, and
keep on improving it, right?
And this has to be a si a similar
goal as model performance.
So model you train is performing
better that you track, but I
would tracking the cost also.
Okay, so that's the key takeaway and
with that I would like to say thank
you very much and have a nice day.