Good morning, afternoon, evening,
everyone, and welcome to my session,
ML Ops at Scale Production Ready
AI Systems for HR Transformation
here at ML 42 ml OPS 2025.
My name is Ram PRIs Miana.
A little bit about my
background as we begin.
I have over 20 years of work experience
in the technology space working at top
companies such as NSF International,
Abu Dhabi Investment Authority, and.
Oracle.
I'm currently serving as an
Assistant director of HR Information
Systems at NSF International.
Throughout my career, I've been
instrumental in driving digital
transformation, AI and ML integration
and enterprise technology architecture.
My expertise spans HR technology
modernization cloud ERP
implementations and AI driven
automation across various industries.
These experiences have given me a deep
understanding of how innovative solutions
can enhance operational efficiency and
deliver tangible business outcomes.
Today I'll be sharing a little technical
blueprint for deploying generative AI in
HR Shade Services Center, focusing on not
just operational excellence, but trust,
compliance, and the ability to scale.
Let's dive in.
Here's what I'll be covering
in the next 30 minutes, right?
First, I'll introduce our ML ops
architecture and show you what it really
takes to run a reliable production
grade ML system supporting over 10
million HR transactions every month.
Then I'll cover how we approach
performance monitoring, including
drift reduction and custom HR metrics.
Keep in mind, this is critical for any
regulated hr, high volume HR operations.
Next, I'll walk you through our data
engineering strategies, including
building privacy, preserving,
and real-time feature pipelines.
After that, I'll break down our
scalable deployment patterns,
highlighting how we serve our 50,000
employees efficiently and securely
across multiple business entities.
And finally, I'll focus on our
operational excellence and governance
framework as to how we build audit
trails, how we reduce bias, and how we
can ensure compliance at every step.
Let's talk a little bit about
the HR AI Production Challenge.
HR Shared Service centers present
a unique set of challenges for AI
operations, and we must process sensitive
employee data that crosses national
and legal jurisdictions, workforce
size and needs fluctuate seasonally.
Mass hirings performance review
cycles and benefit open enrollments
can spike query volumes dramatically.
Models must deliver reliable,
consistent results across a
wide variety of HR query types.
On top of that, strict compliance
requirements in regulated
industries are negotiable.
Okay.
All of this has to operate
at massive scape, right?
Over 10 million monthly interactions.
Standard MOPS approaches just aren't
enough for these high stakes and
in an ever changing environment.
So we need a customized architecture and
continuous automation just to stay ahead.
Let's go to the next slide.
In this slide we'll talk a little bit
about the production ML ops architecture.
Our production environment is based
on containerized model deployment
orchestrated with Kubernetes.
This architecture gives us a
flexibility to optimize resource
use and tap into GPU acceleration
where needed for both training.
And in France we use an automated AB
testing and cannery deployment framework.
This allows us to roll out new
models safely and deploying to
a small segment of users first,
backed by statistical significance
testing, so we never compromise on
the employee experience scheduled.
Automated retraining pipelines
are at the core of our life cycle.
Keep in mind that these key part models
maintaining at least 92% accuracy
even as business requirements and data
distributions shift across a diverse range
of HR query types, and the next slide.
Next, let's talk about the ML
Ops pipeline workflow here.
Let's look at our ML ops pipeline designed
to ensure not just speed and accuracy.
But also the robust compliance.
We start with data ingestion,
streamlining the data from HR
systems, chat bot logs, and ticketing
workflows, and data validation is next.
Applying strict privacy and
schema checks right upfront.
We dedicate significant effort to
feature engineering, creating and
transforming model features that
truly reflect HR business logic.
Like capturing tenure
or internal mobility.
Next comes the model training.
It's tightly tracked and experiment
managed for reproducibility.
Every model goes through a
rigorous evaluation and approval
process, combining quantitative
metrics with stakeholder reviews.
It's a balance.
This end-to-end workflow ensures
we never sacrifice quality
or auditability for speed.
And the next slide, let's talk
a little bit about the model
performance and monitoring.
This is the key.
Monitoring sits at the heart for
problem ready production readiness.
We maintain real time dashboards
that give granular visibility into
every HR metric that matters, like
chat bot response accuracy, average
resolution time, or single satisfaction
rates, or robust drift detection
infrastructure spots, the changes.
In input data or model output,
very quickly recognizing the
degradation, 73% faster than before.
We track custom HR relevant metrics
and use automated alerting to guarantee
a 19 9.5 SLA for the business.
Staying proactive means catching
potential issues before the
impact of real employees.
We're not reactive.
So now let's talk about the
continuous feedback and improvement.
As we can see in the diagram, we operate
a continuous feedback and implement loop.
All user interactions, every
question, every chatbot
response and every satisfaction
rating are thoroughly tracked.
We analyze fail interactions and
patterns that flag friction or confusion.
These insights flow directly into
our supervised retraining cycles.
Ultimately resulting in 28%,
which is a big number boost
to overall model accuracy.
The lesson here is that HR AI
systems should never be static.
They should evolve as the workforce
and the business needs change.
In the next slide, we're gonna
talk a little bit about the
data engineering for HR ai.
HR data requires the highest
standards of privacy and data quality.
We cannot compromise on that.
We have fully automated pipelines
for PII, detection and tokenization.
These are built to comply with
global standards like GDPR and CCPA.
Data quality is protected by strict
schema enforcement and anomaly detection.
With our systems achieving a 99.2%
data accuracy rate to keep things fast,
we use real-time feature engineering
with streaming architecture, cutting
model inference latency by 65%.
That means no compromise between
privacy, compliance and user experience.
Now this is the key.
How do we implement it?
What is in store for each feature?
This is the key enabler, right in our
pipeline, which is our HR feature store.
This provides consistent
features for both training.
And real time inference with point in time
correctness to prevent leakage, especially
important for time series HR data.
It's supposed low latency, less than
10 milliseconds feature serving for
instant response in HR applications.
And everything is automatically versioned
and lineage tracked using Spark and Flink.
The result is twofold.
A 65% reduction in latency for
end users and a 40% savings on
computer infrastructure costs.
This is a great outcome.
Now, how can we scale this?
Let's talk about the
scalability plumbing strategies.
So how do we operate at scale?
Our multi-tenant, my, our, excuse
me, our multi-tenant architecture
isolates business units while sharing
secure reliable infrastructure,
which supporting over 50,000
employees with risk separation.
For model updates, we use BLUEGREEN
deployment, ensuring zero downtime and
instant rollback If something goes wrong,
our auto scaling infrastructure gracefully
absorbs traffic spikes up to 10 times.
During busy seasons, cost optimization
is built in leveraging spot instances
and dynamic right sizing to deliver a
40% cut in the infrastructure spend.
Let's understand the graph about
the seasonal scaling patterns.
This is some real data.
You'll see big spikes in query
volumes and infrastructure costs
corresponding to typical HR cycles.
For example, onboarding in January,
performance reviews in December,
benefits enrollment in the fall.
Our auto scaling setup dynamically adapts
to these cycles, so resources are always
available when needed, but we aren't
over-provisioned and wasteful in quite
periods, so we're saving some money there.
If you only remember one thing
here, keep in mind that you should
align your technology scaling with
your business and HR calendar.
This brings me to the operational
excellence in governance.
Operational excellence goes
hand in hand with governance.
We've implemented a comprehensive ML
ops governance framework tracking all AI
decisions with end-to-end audit trails
that enable rapid compliance responses.
Automated bias detection is built
in, and our approach has reduced
discriminatory outcomes by 89% while
maintaining high model accuracy.
We offer multi jurisdiction compliance
monitoring and model explainability
tools tailored to HR so that the
decisions impacting people's careers
can always be interpreted and justified.
Now talk about, let's talk about the bias
detection and mitigation on the critical
topic of fairness, which is our automated
frameworks for bias detection, mitigation,
and validation have been transmitted.
We check for bias, both in training data
and during ongoing model evaluation.
Constantly monitoring and revalidating
for each retraining cycle.
Thanks to this, we've reduced
discriminatory outcomes by 89%
while maintaining model performance.
Keep in mind that biases bias
is not something you solve once.
It's a continual responsibility for
hedge, for every HR data practitioner.
All right, so we reached the end
of our presentation, so let's
talk about the key takeaways and
we can have a q and a to close.
Let me summarize the key lessons.
Always use containerized deployments
and automated retraining to manage
diverse changing HR workloads.
Build HR specific metrics.
Talk to your leadership, understand
what's required, and also include drift
detection into your monitoring workflows.
The third one is bring, is
bringing privacy and data quality
to the core of your AI pipelines.
You're dealing with HR
data, so we have to vary.
Careful about it.
Always architect for scalability.
Use multi-tenant blue, green deployment,
auto scaling, and cost efficiency.
It's all about the numbers and about all.
Make comprehensive governance and bias
reduction a pillar of your operation.
We should always be running with
trust, fairness, and compliance.
This a non-negotiable.
So finally, thank you for
your attention and engagement.
I hope you find these blueprints
actionable for your own HR AI journeys.
Thank you so much.