Hello everyone.
Welcome to my session.
My name is Samuel bfi and I am a
principle Solutions architect with AWS.
I'm very excited to talk to
you today about Agent Core.
Agent Core is a new AWS offering, which
is a set of functionality and primitives
that allows you to build very quickly
and powerful production grade agent.
The name of my talk today is from POC
to Production Shipping Enterprise AI
Agents with Amazon Bedrock Agent Core.
Without further ado, let's get started.
When we talked about Agent Tech
ai, things have moved very quickly
in the last couple of ears.
But when Che Giti and, a smaller.
Previous large language models
were released back in 2022.
One of the very common things
that were being released was
generative AI assistance.
So chat bots that could maybe
respond to you, but do very little.
Moving that we have created in the
industry, a lot of generative AI agents.
So you can achieve a singular goal.
Maybe there is one or few tools
available for the agent, and you
could automate, specific workflows.
And what we are talking about now and the
future of agent AI is agent AI systems
that can operate fully autonomous, it can
have conversation across multiple agents.
And now rather than just automating
a specific workflow, it can mimic
the whole human logic and reasoning.
Of course, we is still human in
the loop for security verification
and hallucination and so forth.
The whole idea is to increase productivity
and business values for our customers.
A very interesting stats from 20
24, 30 3% of enterprise software's.
Applications will actually
include iGen AI by 2028, which
are up from less than 1% in 2024.
So you can see in four years one third
of applications will include the agenda,
and we can now already see this trend.
That has been very
quickly evolving in 2025.
These are also both researchers
based from and created by Gartner.
Another research was that 15% of the
day to day work decisions will be made
autonomous through Agen AI by 2020.
There are pros and cons to that, and
we're gonna talk about some of the
capabilities that can help you with that.
Here are some agent AI use cases
across different industries.
Each industry will be able to
apply agent and agent AI systems.
At the different levels of
utilization and productivity.
But let's say you are part of the
healthcare, you can do a lot of the
patient and member engagement automation
that before always require a lot of
humans in the end, in the backend.
Now you can automate and make
those humans way more productive
with automation of agents.
What is the AWS vision for agents?
The vision is to provide the best place
for you to build the most useful agents
for your specific vertical to solve the
best and most important use cases that
will help your customer improve, customer
expectation, potentially bringing down the
cost and few other benefits that agent.
Agent KI bring to the system and the
vision for AWS is for you to be able
to deploy those agents while empower
empowering different organizations within
your company to deploy those reliable
securable and scalable agents on AWS.
So that's the vision.
How do we do that?
First we focus on the fundamentals.
Four very important pillars
of the fundamentals are.
We wanna use the state of the art science.
So we have, Amazon has a big science
team and we put a lot of science
work on building Bedrock Agent car.
And you're gonna see that a lot of the
features built on Agent Car are very
common requested features when companies
are building agency in production.
Secondly, as very typical
AWS fashion, we wanna provide
best in class infrastructure.
For you to build and run those agents, and
we wanna manage that for you and make it
easy for you to manage and invoke agents.
Third is we wanna be the best place
for you to deploy a specialized agents.
And when I talk about specialized
agents and talking about your magic
sauce, what makes your business unique?
How can you move some of that
magic specialized knowledge
into a specialized agent?
And make your productivity boost.
And fourth, provide intuitive
experience so anyone can
build and use powerful agents.
So that is the fundamentals
that Agent Core was set to help.
Now, before we talked about Agent
Core, it's important for us to take
a step back and realize the broadest.
Set of services that AWS offers for
customers to build and deploy agents.
We have applications such as Q Dev,
KIRO, which are, set of applications
that help developers build code and
have agent capabilities so we can use.
Generative AI agents to help be your
co-program and help you actually
accelerate the productivity as developers,
but you also focus for business.
So you have Q Business and multiple
features that have generative AI
capabilities within AWS services.
Then you have some tools for
building AI agents such as Bedrock
Marketplace, bedrock agents.
Is STRs Nova Act, SDK, and many others.
We're gonna talk about some of
those as we move forward here.
The important thing to highlight is
Bedrock Agents has existed for almost
two years now, but Bedrock Agents is
actually different than Bedrock Agent car.
Bedrock agent is a more opinionated.
Way for you to deploy agents where Agent
Core is this new set of primitives that
brings a lot of flexibility and new
functionality for you to build on top of.
That's just one important aspect that you
should be aware when you look at AI stack.
We are not gonna talk about that
in depth, but we have a lot of
chip sets, our own chip sets.
We have nvi, the chip sets, we have md,
we have a service called SageMaker ai.
So if you wanna actually go and
build your own models, you apologize
you should be able to do that.
But you also have a lot of the
fundamentals of large language
models available for you on demand
with foundational models on bedrock.
So you can use.
And Tropic Cloud models.
You can use Nova Models, you can
use metal models and many other
models available in Bedrock.
And we are gonna mostly focus on the
rest of the presentation on Agent Call,
which is a set of primitives that allows
you to build production grade agents.
So what is Agent Core and
how does he actually work?
The whole idea is we kept here hearing
from customers in the last couple
of in the last year, a couple months
that they're building rf, agent POCs.
But the really challenge was from moving
from a POC that was running locally on
a development laptop from a specific
developer to actually making that widely
available within the ecosystem of the
company and also production writing.
And the challenge to get to production
are how do you manage performance?
How do you manage scalability?
How do you manage security?
And how do you have proper governance?
With all those four pillars, if you have
a way to create a solution that you can
deploy on top of, you are gonna get way
closer to your AI production agents.
So let's now go and talk about some.
Of the different primitives that Agent
Core have available for you to use.
So the first primitive is
called agent Core runtime.
Agent Core runtime.
You can think of as the compute
where your agents can run.
You can scale from zero agent
invocation now to as many as you want.
It gets involved with very low latency.
When you create a agent on agent
carbon time you have a way to
invoke those agents through APIs.
Those single agent invocations can
last for up to eight hours or less,
and you pay for as much as you
are consuming within those session
invocations is support different
payloads across different modalities.
So if you have an agent that
requires different modalities
like images, you can also provide.
But the idea is this serverless
agent compute environment
for YouTube run another.
One of the things I should have
mentioned before, and I can mention
later on, is the whole thing with
Agent Core is the ability for to
pick and choose different primitives.
One primitive is agent Core run time and.
Only the primitives you want.
So you are not buying into the whole
ecosystem if you don't want to.
You can bring bits and pieces of what
you care to actually build your agents.
And with agent carbon time, you
can actually deploy any agent using
pretty much any framework, either
some familiar open source frameworks.
Or actually build your own framework
as well with a very few lines of code.
You can get a runtime up and running,
and then you can invoke your agent
that is running on the cloud.
You also have security by default,
so we have true session isolation to
protect your customer data and integrates
very easily with identity provider.
We're gonna talk about agent core
identity, but by integrating there,
you can have a proper authorization
and authentication systems.
Using o or 2.0 that it can connect
to your agent carbon time in
order to invoke when you need to.
How does it work behind the scenes?
You build your agent.
Your agent can be using any framework
strengths, land graph lang, chain crew,
ai your own proprietary framework.
You can use any models.
It can be bedrock models, it can be
Gemini models, it can be open AI models.
It doesn't really matter.
Asian carbon time allows you to
pick and choose whatever model you
wanna use, and then you bring in
the Asian carbon time decorator.
You provide some observability
configuration if you wanna
use Agent Core observability.
And if you wanna do identity, you
also bring that behind the scenes.
The way it works, you
create a Docker file.
That Docker file gets a stored into a
registry, a ECR repository, and then you
create an agent within Agent carbon time.
And every time you have a user,
the user will invoke that.
Endpoint where you have your agent
deployed and behind the scenes we will
actually create a compute environment
for you with true session isolation.
Okay.
One important aspect to highlight
with Agent Core is Agent Carbon
time allows you to roast agents like
strands, graph agents, we, those are
using the HT P protocol, but agent
carbon time also have a different
capability, which is the ability
for you to host a remote MCP server.
Automatically for you.
So you can create exactly like here,
you'd create a Docker file, but
rather than using, Lang framework,
you'd be using maybe Fast MCP and you
deploy that on Agent Core run time.
And behind the scenes agent Core
run time supports the ability
to actually talk MCP protocol.
I don't have slides here, but that
is one of the capabilities as well.
Another important aspect of building agent
is the ability for you to create identity.
So once I have an agent, there are a
couple things I wanna do with the agent.
How can I enable agents to be
using and be involved properly?
Let's say I have an account into an
agent, and I wanna make sure that
only the specific groups within that
system are able to invoke that agent.
Let's say I have my application
built using third party tools such
as Google, Salesforce, or Slack, and
I wanna give access to my agent to
use that specific systems, right?
Agent Core identity does multiple things,
and I'll show you in the next slide.
But the whole idea of agent
core identities to minimize.
The amount of work that it takes for you
to secure both the inbound authentication.
So when you are calling an agent, and also
when the agent itself needs to call third
party tools like Google in order to grab
some data from maybe your Google drive
into the agent run specifically, right?
So it's trying to streamlining
your authentication flows.
What it allows you to do is to accelerate
AI agent development because there'll be
a lot of set of prebuilt primitives that
you can use from the agent core identity.
Like you can use your existing
identity systems such as Okta, Azure,
ad, Amazon Kognito, and any other
that are supporting OAuth 2.0 flow.
And the end goal here is to
lower custom development efforts.
Without needing to migrate users
for this specific credential
system or identity system.
So how does it actually work?
You have a user that user needs
to authenticate to a system you
can be using, either IM or OAuth.
Once you have the permission, you can
provide that permission to your agent.
The agent will verify that your permission
is valid and you have access to actually.
Invoke the agent.
Remember this agent, because
these pieces of Agent Core
can be consumed independently.
The agent itself can be hosted
on Agent Core one time, or it
can be hosted elsewhere, and you
still can use agent core identity.
That's what we call agent
inbound authentication.
Now, what is an outbound authentication
is now that your agent is running,
and let's say your agent needs
permissions to call an AWS resource.
Let's say your agent
is calling a database.
What Agent Core identity allows you
to do is you also have outbound.
Authentication.
So you can configure that.
Your agent should go and talk to it
identity to require and retrieve the IAM
permission to then call AWS resources.
But that can also be you can
see three different types of
out outbound authentication.
Another outbound authentication
could be an external resource,
either through an API key or
potentially through a full flow.
Two leg or three leg aut flow.
Let's say you wanna go and
you're gonna talk to Salesforce.
That will be an external resource.
And I'm gonna pause here because
I'm gonna talk in a moment
what Agent Core Gateway is.
But another way to do is to
integrate a outbound authentication
with your agent Core gateway.
So Agent Core identity
allows you to seamless.
Create solutions for your inbound
and outbound authentication
in production for the agents.
Now we hear from a lot of customers
that MCP has become so popular
and, but managing potentially
hundreds of MCP servers can be very.
Cumbersome.
So what Agent Core Gateway allows
you to do is to simplify two
development and integration.
So Agent Core Gateway way you can think
about is it's a MCP server managed
for you that you can very easily.
Expose different tools that the
MCP server will make available.
So you can turn existing APIs.
So if you have an open API swagger
is schema, you can provide that the
endpoints through that open API schema
to agent, core Gateway as a target
and automatically agent Core gateway
will lease that as an available tools.
You can also.
Create Lambda functions as targets for
agent core gateway, and those Lambda
functions will then behave as MCP
tools and you can access thousands of
tools through a standardized interface,
which is agent core gateway itself.
I'll show you how it works in a moment By
default, agent Core Gateway operates as
a remote MCP server and you are required
to provide authentication to that agent
core gateway, so only people that have
the proper authentication can call the MCP
server because they have an endpoint that
is available either through the internet
or through in the future, through your
VPC, and you'll be able to combine that.
And also one of the
capabilities that is pre cool.
It allows you to do intelligent
tool discovery, and I'll show
you in a moment how that works.
So you have an MCP client,
which is your agent or your IDE.
You going to create a gateway
within agent core gateway.
That gateway automatically
will behave as an MCP server.
The beauty is behind the scenes,
you can create different targets.
So one gateway can have multiple targets.
And one target can have multiple tools.
So one of the target type that is
supported right now is the API endpoint.
So you provide your open API
schema and whatever are the
endpoints that we have available.
Agent core will auto automatically
convert that into tools.
So as an agent or an MCP client, you can
very easily now consume your existing
APIs as tools into your agent system.
The other option is you can create a
Lambda target and you can build your
own code, which whatever programming
language the Lambda supports, and you
have a preference to build tools itself.
So you can write code and build more
complex tools through Lambda functions.
So that is how Agent Core
Gateway works at a high.
Now one of the amazing capabilities
of Agent Core Gateway is what we
call Symantec Search, which is a
very unique and cool feature that
Agent Core has by default because
this is just using the MCP protocol.
If you go and you do the list tools
request to your MCP server, which is the
agent core gateway, gateway behind the
scenes, and you have hundreds in this
case 360 tools, when you do list tools.
Into the agent core gateway, it
is gonna return all the 300 tools.
That is really not good practice.
And why It's not good practice.
I'm gonna talk about that in a moment.
One of the capabilities that Agent Core
Gateway allows you to do is to do a
semantic search on agent Core corrugate.
So Agent Corrugate, you created some
knowledge base of all the tools that
you have, and you can call an API
on agent Corrugate to say, Hey, my.
Agent now, once you create a social
media post, go and find the tools
that you have across these 360
tools that are able to do that.
In this case, it returns four
relevant tools and you provide
to the large language model.
Now, what are the benefits to do this?
First is Agent Corrugate will
automatically indexes the tools and
gives a serverless semantic search.
Think about a small rag
system for your tools.
But mostly important if you're doing
the search, it allows you to reduce
the context that you're passing for
every single agent's large language
model, which is going to improve
your accuracy, speed, and cost.
Because the more tools you provide,
the less accuracy you have.
The is lower it is and the more
costly it is because you are gonna
get charged by how much, how many
tokens you are providing as inputs.
And what allows you to
do allows you to improve.
The agent focus because it's only
focusing on the tools that are
given for that specific task.
So moving forward, another primitive
on Agent core is agent core memory.
So memory is a very important aspect
of agents, which allows you to save.
Maybe interactions that you have with
agent for future use that might be maybe
history, like raw history between user and
agent, or potentially some preferences.
What we call there is this
differentiation on agent core memory
of short term memory versus long term.
And they're gonna talk
about that in a moment.
But agent core memory is built
for enterprise by default.
So you have a completely data privacy
with dedicated storage for each customer.
You can create these specific
namespace that only specific
customers can have access.
You can bring your own encryption to each.
So if you have multiple customers and
you wanna encrypt the data differently
across customers, you can do that.
And you have deep customization.
If you wanna bring what we call
long-term memory, you can define
memory patterns based on your use
case, and you can extract the, you
can extract rules and customize those
rules that are being done asynchronous.
How does that work?
The first concept on engine core memory
is what we call short-term memory.
So you have your agent and you are
having conversation with your agent.
So user message and response
from the larger language
model and the specific state.
What you can do is you implement
a integration agent core memory,
that you're saving those messages
into the short term memory space.
You can store short term memory for up to
3,365 days and you can customize how long
the specific messages are gonna be stored.
Once you have short term memory, you can
then, of course, once a new invocation
of your agent is spun up, you can
retrieve the API for agent core memory
to retrieve maybe the last day or all
the memory that you have on short term
memory into your existing conversation.
That's one type of memory.
The other type of memory, which
is very powerful, is what we
call the long term memory.
So the raw messages are useful at some
point but actually what you want to.
Do in the long term is extract a
specific long-term memories, right?
And when you have a short term
memory, you can decide if you want
to also enable long-term memory.
And behind the scenes agent
core memory will asynchronous
automatically extract pieces of
memory should be saved on long term.
You can specify, so you can
do Symantec where you specify.
What type of memory you
wanna extract for long term.
You can provide user preferences.
So let's say I go on my agent and I
always say color blue behind the scenes
agent core memory will extract that
and I will be saved as a preference.
Or I can provide summary.
So let's say every day after the
agent does, its some type of work, it
goes and summarize the work has done
and saves long-term memory, then the
long-term memory can be retrieved.
And you can provide those
memories, long-term memories
as part of new invocations.
Because remember, large language
models don't remember memory by
defaulting from past interactions.
You are responsible in providing that.
And agent core memory
allows you to do that.
And you can see, okay, that's what I want.
So the next capability
is Agent core browser.
So is the ability for you to use
a automated serverless browser
infrastructure if your agent needs
to use, so let's say you wanna
build a agent and you want the
agent to literally use a browser.
Let's say you wanna buy a,
you wanna build an agent that
can buy items from amazon.com.
If the agent needs to use a browser,
and there are different tools that
support this capability of navigating.
A browser using a large language model.
I'm gonna show you some of the tools,
some of the models and open source
libraries that allows you to do that.
But you always need to have the
compute for your specific browser.
Agent Core Browser is a tool that is
available on Agent Core that allows
you to have very low latency browser.
It can scale from zero to hundreds of
concurrent session, which each session
is gonna create its own browser and not
share any data across the other sessions.
And also you can do proper
secure credential handling.
You can.
I also do live streaming
RL for monitoring.
So if you wanna show the user what your
agent is doing and clicking buttons,
you can do the live streaming URL
and embedding into our application
on how the browser is being used.
You can do session replace for debugging
and you can do very extensive logging
for all the browse commands that have
been done through CloudTrail if enabled.
Now, how does it work?
As a user, if you have an agent and
you say buy shoes on Amazon, you
need to have a large language model.
The large language model can be
Nova X, it can be Nova, it can be
Cloud, it can be many other things.
You create a tool, that tool is you
need to build or you can use open
source tools such as browser user
and few other Cap, a few other open
source libraries that are there.
But what the tool use will be, you'll
be explaining how to use the browser
into this specific large language model.
So you translate the tool, call into
instruction commands using playwright,
library or browser using library.
Once you translate then that execution
environment where you see headless
browser or hosted library server is
specifically where Agent Core will
be running, and you can run multiple
invocations for the sessions right there.
So very powerful because he allows you
to completely remove the necessity of
you managing the browser itself and
just give that, that, that specific.
Power to agent core browser, and you
can focus on the end goal of your agent
in this case navigating amazon.com.
Another tool that is made available as
part of Agent Core and you can pick and
choose if you want to use, is the ability
to red code as part of a code sandbox.
So models are really good at trying
to solve problems by generating code.
But you always need to have
some place to run the code.
You can execute this code securely using
agent card code interpreter because it
creates this isolated sandbox compute
environment that you can run code.
Check for the results.
Run code again.
Download the outputs.
It can process gigabytes of
scale data sets efficiently.
If you're using S3 integration and
without any a p limitation, it's very
easy to use because it has prebuilt
execution run times for JavaScript
types with Python, with Common Library
springs out, you can customize that
and the way it would work and the way
it would look is you have an agent.
And that agent has a large language
model and you give a tool selection to
create a sessional code interpreter.
So you create an agent that gives a
tool to execute code, and that code
would be execute on code interpreter.
You write some API integration with
age agent, core code interpreter.
That code interpreter
will have a file system.
And Michelle and the large language
model now can generate code,
run code on code interpreter.
The beauty of this is completely
isolated and secure by default.
So even if you have some hackers
trying to do charge, export some
vulnerability on your agent.
If they go on code interpreter,
there is no root access.
There is nothing they can do to share
any data across any other session
that code interpreter is doing.
And of course, you can explore the
telemetry with observability, which
you're gonna talk about in a moment now.
The last but not least, is
the ability for you to monitor
everything that is happening.
Agent Core Observability allows
you to provide a comprehensive
end-to-end visibility into your
agent orchestration system.
It allows you to accelerate the debugging
and audits by using the primitives that
you pick and then exposing the metrics
and logs into agent core observability.
The good thing here is if you are already
a CloudWatch user, you can use very
quickly prebuilt dashboards, traces
that Agent Core Observability brings.
But if you don't want to use CloudWatch
or you use some other type of monitoring
systems, what you can do is you can
export the logs as Open Telemetry.
Open Telemetry is.
A open standard that is commonly
used and accepted across
multiple observability systems.
And that with that open telemetry,
you can just expose that to
whatever monitoring system.
If, let's say you, in case you don't
wanna use CloudWatch, but if you
only use CloudWatch, you can see the
first image agent Car Permissibility
dashboards is built on CloudWatch.
And you can see the traces,
you can see every single call
that it was made to your model.
Every single tool that it was.
Use, and you can see the whole
tracing automatically being done.
So the way it works, you have agent core
observability that integrates with of
course, agents running on agent carbon
time memory, using agent core memory tools
for an agent car gateway, browser for
an agent, car browser code interpreter
for code interpreter, and whatever you
pick and choose, you can just integrate
into Agent Core observability and use
the benefits either on CloudWatch or
if you wanna expose logs into other.
Systems.
You can do that as well
as you can see here.
Now, we talked about the features.
This is the whole ecosystem
of agent core, right?
So it allows you to pick and choose either
the whole ecosystem of a specific features
like Agent core run time or agent car
gateway and build your agents with less.
Burden on the security, the
scalability, the monitoring the
reliability, the pay the cost as well.
Because everything you've
seen here is pay as you go.
Any scale from zero to as many
as you need it given er demand.
So this is the whole
ecosystem of Agent Core.
As of now, today's September 5th,
as I'm recording this session.
Agent Core is in preview hopefully
soon, BGA and you'll be able to build
production grade agents at on AWS
using whatever framework you want,
using whatever models you want.
And then some things that are coming
soon is of course HA are coming soon.
So agent to agent integration right now is
not supported as a protocol will be coming
soon for a specific I think runtime.
It will be an example
that will be supported.
HA, the frameworks, screw ai, line graph
length change, trend agents, and many.
But of course you have
the agent core capability.
The whole bedrock ecosystem is pretty big.
You have the ability to
access models on demand.
You have the ability to do optimization
and caching of those models.
You can create and fine tune your models.
You can bring guard rails.
You can create automatically manage
re databases With Bedrock knowledge
base, I highly recommend you look into
knowledge base if you have a retrieval
augmented generation re use case.
So Agent Core comes into very
good position to contribute to
the whole bedrock ecosystem.
And what I recommend to you, if
you are interested here, are a
couple cure codes that you can
pause the presentation and scam.
I really recommend you look at Agent
Core samples, you redirect you to
a GitHub repository where you're
gonna be able to actually see.
Multiple tutorials and use cases using
the different capabilities of Agent Core.
So if you're interested on Agent
Core Gateway, you can navigate to the
GitHub repository and you can see very
specifically how to implement the code.
You can see the code, you can see
the different use cases, you can
see the different tutorials, and of
course, our agent core documentation
and the agent core blog posts.
Without further ado, thank you so
much for watching for my presentation.
If I have any questions,
again, my name is Samuel bfi.
You can find me on LinkedIn at
just at Samuel bfi and you'll
be able to find me there.
You can connect if you have any
questions about the agent core and I'll
be available to answer any questions.
Thank you so much.
Enjoy com 42 ml ops and
I'll see you around.
Bye-bye.