Hello everyone.
Good morning or good evening,
depending on your location.
My name is MuTu and I have 23 years of
experience across data engineering, AI and
ML Cloud technologies, enterprise, BI data
science, and in the manufacturing sector.
It's pleasure to be here at Con
42 to share insight on the topic.
AI driven predictive
maintenance that transforming
the backbone of manufacturing.
For decades, factories have
relayed on two extremes.
First one is waiting until the
occupant fails and then fix it, which
is reactive maintenance or carrying
out scheduled preventive maintenance
that often wasting valuable resource.
But today we stand at pivotal moment.
With the power of AI data and connector
systems, we can move beyond reactive.
Fire factoring and embrace proactive
intelligence maintenance that
drives efficiency and resilience.
Let's get started.
Here is the agenda today.
First, critical inflection
point in the manufacturing.
Second, AI driven maintenance resolution.
Third, evolution of
maintenance strategies.
For the technological Archite
architecture, enabling transformation,
fifth advanced AI methodology
in industrial environments.
Six Real world stories.
Seven.
Why 60% of predictive
maintenance initiative fail?
Eight.
Implementation of blueprint for success.
Nine.
Emerging technology and the future trends.
10. Actionable roadmap for implementation.
11 key takeaway.
Let's start with industry
challenges, critical inflection
point in manufacturing.
Let's see why AI based
approach is essential.
Let's look at the problem and the
high cost of reactive maintenance.
Manufacturers today are under the
pressure and a traditional way of
maintaining equipment are simply too
costly to sustain reactive maintenance.
When equipment fails without warning,
the impact is massive up to three times.
Three to 10 times more expensive
than predictive maintenance.
The average loss during unplanned
downtime is up to $50,000 per hour.
This includes production loss,
labor inefficiency, and sometimes
even penalties for late shipments.
The market speaks for itself.
The AI in maintenance sector is
expected to grow from 4 billion
to nearly 16 billion by 2028.
These numbers highlights why
manufacturers cannot afford to
stay in reactive maintenance.
Moving on to next AI driven
maintenance solution.
Let's see what happens when
companies embrace AI for maintenance.
One first industry implementing.
AI maintenance have reported 50%
reduction in downtime, which is Hal the
mission, offline time compared to before.
Second, 32% decrease in overall
maintenance cost, which includes
parts, labor, and energy savings.
Third, perhaps the most impressive
is 385% return on investment.
These project don't just play themselves.
They multiply value delivered fourth, the
models provides provide eight to 12 days.
Advanced warning, which is
critical for planning downtime and
avoiding production disruptions.
This means organizations can
plan interventions, orders,
spare parts ahead of time, and
prevent crisis before they happen.
This represents shifting from reactive
maintenance to strategic ascent management
where decisions are data driven.
Next evolution of maintenance strategy.
Let's take a step back and look
at how maintenance has evolved.
First, reactive maintenance equipment
is fixed only after it breaks,
which is leading to emergency fix.
Also, it costs us unpredictable cost
and a major production disruption.
Second Preventive maintenance here.
Maintenance follows Fixed schedule, often
replacing pos too early or too late here.
Downtime is reduced, but inefficiency is
there, and also waste of resource also,
is there third Predictive maintenance.
It is a conditional based
maintenance and a service.
The equipment as needed basis.
This method minimize disruption
while keeping the cost under control.
Fourth, AI driven
predictive excellence here.
Machine learnings predicts
failure up to 88%.
Accuracy also provides eight
to 12 days advance warning and
continuous improve over time.
Here we are moving from rigid
schedule two dynamic and data
driven decisions, moving to the next
technological architectures,
enabling transformations.
What make this possible?
Let's talk about technology stack
Number one, IOT sensor network.
Industrial missions Accu equipped
with sensor with the capturing
real time data like temperature,
vibration, pressure, et cetera.
Each setup generates 1.5 to 2.3
terabyte of daily data, and also
enables continuous health monitoring.
Second edge computing.
Onsite processing cuts response
time by 75 to 80 per 85% and
it pre-filter sensor data.
It also supports instant alert
and rapid decision making for
critical equipment conditions.
Third cloud data platform.
It is a scalable infrastructure
stores historical data and powers.
Powers Advanced ML
training and deployment.
It enables predictive model and cross
facility performance benchmarking.
All together these layers gives
us both speed and intelligence.
Moving on to the next
advanced AI methodology.
First auto encoder
based anomaly deduction.
It learns normal equipment
pattern to spot deviations.
It also, it achieves 90% accuracy
with 31% fewer false alarms.
Second random forecast forest classifier.
It classifies and pinpoints
specific failure mode.
It also delivers 78 8% precision
in the predictive diagnostics.
Third recurrent neural network
IT analysis analyze time serious
sensor data over long period.
Also, it deducts degradation
pattern before it failures.
Fourth digital twin simulations.
It creates virtual replica
of physical equipment.
Also, it boost prediction accuracy by 67%.
Throw simulation insights.
Each technique has a role
depending on the context.
Next, let's see the real
world success stories.
Why 60% of predictive
maintenance initiative fails.
Of course, not every initiative succeeds.
In fact, about 60% of project fails.
Let's see why it fails.
One, data ingestion complexities.
Nearly 80% of deployment struggles
with the legacy machine, siloed IT
system, and inconsistent data quality.
Also, lack of sensor and
poor standardization.
Slow down, reliable predictive insights.
Second scope and budget management
project often exceed budget by.
30 to 40% due to
underestimated complexity.
Overly wide scope, weak proof of concept
validation leads to cost, overturn,
and delayed return on investment.
Third, organizational resistance.
Around 65% of technicians resistant,
resist, adopt adoption because fear
in the job loss or not trusting
AI recommendations in inefficient
training and weak change management
amplify resistance to new system.
Predictive maintenance is not
just a technology problem, it is
also about people and the process.
Moving to the next
implementation blueprint for success,
first, value, first approach.
We need to start with the most
critical equipment where the failure.
Cost is most and also focus on high
impact wins before wider rollout.
Second, strategic data integration build.
Yeah, unified data architecture
by linking maintenance, production
and quality system breakdown silos.
To enable seamless predict two insights.
Third, human center design.
It engage technicians early in the
process to shape tools and workflows.
It creates.
Natural interface that
builds trust and adoptions.
Fourth phase to scaling.
We need to scale step by step with the
return on investment validation at each
stage, and also prevent budget over time
while ensuring measurable business value.
When you follow this blueprint,
adoption improves significantly.
Emerging technology and the future trends.
Let's see what is next here.
First.
Explainable ai.
It uses transparent algorithm that
makes predictions human interpretable.
It builds trust among technicians
and also increase adoption by 47%.
Second system level monitor,
it goes beyond single component
to capture, cascading effect.
It enables entire insight across the
Interconnector production system.
Third, sustainability applications.
AI driven maintenance cuts unnecessarily
energy and resource U usage.
It lowers emission by 500 to 1500
metric tons per facility each year.
This is about building a
smart, sustainable factories
X number roadmap.
Here is the practical roadmap.
First is foundation.
It takes one to three months time
to build a foundation, access
equipment, criticality, set.
Baseline metrics and deploy
sensor on top assets.
Begin data collection and
integration to build the
foundation for predictive insights.
Second pilot implementations.
This process takes four
to six months of time.
Apply ML models to highest impact
equipment and then train the
maintenance team on the new workflows.
Track KPIs, validate re results,
and document early return on
investment to build the momentum.
Third expansion.
It takes seven to 12 months
of time scale deployment.
To the secondary assets and refine
models from the pilot learning.
Integrate with ERP production
planning and rollout.
Structured change management.
Fourth in the second year.
Work on the optimization.
Optimization and innovation.
Leverage advanced analytics under
digital twin for higher accuracy, develop
custom ml and establish a predictive
maintenance center of excellence.
Key takeaway to wrap up
here are the key takeaway.
One proven return on investment,
AI driven maintenance, cut, cut
down cost by 50%, and also lower
cost by 32%, and also delivers 385%
return on investment in three years.
Second, strategic implementations
success come from starting from high
impact equipment, unifying data system,
and engaging maintenance team early.
Third future proof operations.
The next step is moving from isolated
predictive tool to fully integrated
smart manufacturing ecosystem.
Thank you so much for your time.
I'm happy to take any questions.
Bye.
See you later.