Good morning everyone.
It's wonderful to be here
at conference 42 ML Labs.
My name is Shelia kgi and
I am Systems QA engineer.
With 18 plus years of experience
in the information technology and
software development industries
over the years, I have seen how
machine learning and automations have
transformed industries like healthcare.
The finance, manufacturing, but there
is one area that often goes unnoticed.
The place where we all live,
our residential communities.
Welcome to today's presentation on
revolutionizing the community living.
Through artificial intelligence, how AI
can transform the fragmented community
into connected, thriving ecosystems.
As someone with extensive experience
and technology integration and
living in community, I'll share my
challenges, the hidden costs, and most
importantly, how an AI driven solution
can empower the residents, the managers.
And the community as a whole.
And just to be clear, what I'm gonna
present today is part of my vision.
The goal is to spark the ideas about
what's possible, the challenges
of disconnected community living.
Um, let me start with
the familiar scenarios.
How many of us have missed the last day of
school registration because the reminder
was buried in the WhatsApp messages.
Or maybe we have wished our kids could
meet other children nearby instead of
spending hours in front of the screen, or
perhaps you have hired a service provider
only to regret the decision after hours
of searching and endless back and forth.
This is the reality of residential
community living today.
In fact, the studies shows that about
23% of the US population, that's 77
million people live in some of the
farm of the community association like
HOAs, condos and housing cooperatives.
And more than 80% of new homes sold in
2023 were part of these communities.
Yet the experience of living
in them is often fragmented.
Communication is scattered all over.
Service coordination is slow and
manual, and residents lack the
visibility into the resources that
could improve their daily lives.
In short, people are living side by
side, but not really living together.
So the what's the true?
Cost of the fragmentation
first, it's time drain.
In today's world, time is everything.
The importance of timing and the
feeling of constant pressure,
residents waste hours of navigating
multiple apps, threats and follow ups.
Secondly, it erodes the trust and
satisfaction when processors are.
Inefficient, the communication
becomes poor and residents began
to feel isolated and frustrated.
The next one is the valuable
community assets, clubhouses,
greenhouse, green space.
Even, uh, events remain underutilized
because people simply don't have.
Uh, don't have time to go there or don't
know how, what to use, how to use them.
And finally, the property managers are
struck in endless manual workflows,
preventing them from building the
proactive, the connected communities.
This combination quite eats away
an engagement, the satisfaction,
and yes, even the property value.
So I'm going to the next slide.
Introducing.
What the AI power single pane of
glass, this is where the AI can help.
Imagine a single unified
dashboard that consolidates all
essential residential services.
The information, the communication
into one simple view interface
that consolidates data and
management tools from various
systems and sources into single.
Centralized view and streamlines
the operation through
intelligent AI automation.
Now add the personalization AI that
knows you are a parent with a 7-year-old,
so it shows use school updates
only, like the kid activities, the
tutoring opportunities instead of 11.
Nice.
And behind the scene, the
automation reduces the overhead.
No more changes down.
The managers are shifting
through the clutters.
This is what all called AI powered.
I call the AI powered the single
pane of glass solution, a platform
that is resident first and manager
friendly and designated to make
the communities more connected.
So going to the next slide, how
these service providers can help the
education is one part of the life.
Let's start with education.
A bigger priority for families.
The platform aggregates school.
Reviews from multiple trusted sources and
gives parents a clear, comprehensive view.
It tailors the recommendation
to your child's age.
If you have elementary school,
you only see the content
relevant to ages five through 11.
It can also suggest extracurricular
opportunities from math
tutor the football coaches.
For high schooler, it can only
feed in about academic clubs,
such as debate, math, science,
coding, and leadership, depending
on the family needs and interests.
The beauty is that the system
learns over the time with families,
engage with certain recommendations.
The model continuously refines
results, creating the virtuous
cycles of optimization.
The education is one part of the life.
What about the daily services that keep
our homes running the platform Bills?
A trusted service provider ecosystem.
It connects you with the ai,
wetted, plumbers, electricians, or
handyman, complete with ratings.
The prices, the real time availability.
It automates the scheduling for
property and upkeep like lawn care,
snow removal, or pest control, and even
add smart, sensational recommendations.
It goes further.
Uh, recommending financial services like
mortgage refinancing or home insurance
options, as well as healthcare reference
with the fast appointment bookings.
It's not just convenience, it's a
peace of mind knowing you are making
a reliable cost effective choices.
So the advanced AI
capabilities, now let's, let's.
Uh, peek under the oath.
The platform leverages the
productive analytics to
anticipate the residents needs.
For instance, if families usually
request maintenance right after the
first of all, the system can prepare
resources in advance, natural language
processing powers, chat boards that
allow residents to interact naturally.
So no technical learning curve
needed, and the computer vision
helps with facility monitoring,
automatically generating maintenance
tickets when issues are detected.
All of this works together to
create a deeply personalized,
yet seamless experience.
Enhancing the community
engagement also comes with the.
Connectivity and the engagement.
Of course, the real power
of the community is people.
This platform enhances
connectivity and engagement.
It enables seamless facility
reservations, reducing booking conflicts.
It matches the rental opportunities
with the high success rate.
It even coordinates play dates for
families with children of similar
ages that are so built in support for
youth voluntary programs, encouraging
participation and giving young residents
way to contribute their community.
As a result, a virtuous cycle, a
stronger connection that lead to more
engagement and more engagement drives
the greater adoption on the platform.
Going to the next slide.
It's.
The real time housing market insights.
The another benefit is
the financial empowerment.
The platform is provides the
real time property valuations
insights that typically reserve
for real estate professionals.
It shows how the neighbor would
come, impro implements directly
impact your home's values.
It suggests the property upgrades
with the predictive ROI and also lets
you benchmark the comparable sales,
inform the data driven decisions, help
residents grow personal wealth, and also
pro promote the community stability.
So what, how the future
development roadmap looks like.
So where does this go from here?
Uh, in the near term we see enhancements
like product maintenance for shared
areas, more personalized services and
better social connectivity features.
Looking further ahead, the long term
vision includes the autonomous community.
Vehicle management imagined shared
self-driving shutters for residents.
Why not the system used to operate,
monitor, and maintain autonomous
vehicles for the community use?
It has a potential to provide a safer,
more efficient, and more equitable
transportation option for residents,
which in turn reduces the traffic.
And emissions.
So the, these are the lot of options
we can come up with these AI solutions.
The, the another option is integrational
engagement programs, connecting
toddlers, youth, the seniors in the
meaningful ways to build the mutually
beneficial relationships and as well
as the foster community, uh, cohesions,
the, and the cross community networks
that link different neighborhoods.
To solve the shared challenges
and the opportunities.
So AI is not static.
It continuously evolves, incorporates
new data and new technologies to keep
improving the residents experience.
So going to the next slide,
transforming communities together,
let's bring it back to impact AI
driven communities offer the enhanced
living experience with convenience
and quality or life at the forefront.
The success starts at the community
level By valuing the local expertise
and putting decisions, making power
in hands of the residents, and also
can make quicker and wiser decisions.
The property value growth.
As connected, engaged neighbor
root becomes more desirable.
Operational excellence.
This study is the cost
improving service quality.
The true community
transformation ensures that.
All these voices are heard and benefits
the change to reach every individual and
a sustainable future with smarter use
of resources for greener communities.
The real transformation happens
when residents feel empowered, when
local expertise are valued, and when
decision making power is shared.
So to wrap up.
The story of AI is residential communities
isn't about technology for its own sake.
It's about people.
It's about building the places
where neighbors are connected,
empowered resources are
visible, decisions are smarter.
The future of the community is living,
is unified, intelligent, and inclusive.
Uh, thank you for giving this opportunity
to share the vision with you all today.
Thank you.