Welcome and thanks everyone for tuning in.
I'm Anisha Kouri.
I'm a senior software developer.
I'm truly honored to be here at Confe 42.
In this talk, we'll explore how
low code and public code can
come together to simplify and
scale modern software delivery.
We are living in a world where digital
transformation is no longer optional.
Every organization, whether the public
or private, must deliver services faster,
more transparently, and at lower cost.
Citizens expect government
apps to work like Uber.
Employees are expecting internal tools.
To be as in Q2 as Slack executors are
expecting data insights in real time.
Traditional coding.
While it's powerful, flexible, and often
essential, it has become bottleneck.
Skilled developers are in a short supply.
According to IDC, there will be a shortage
of 4 million developers globally by 2026.
This stock is about more
than this technology.
It's about rethinking how
we design, build, and govern
software in 21st century.
These are the topics
I'll be covering today.
The challenges of traditional coding
and why the change is necessary.
What is low code really is beyond
the buzzword, the core principles
behind public code architectural
patterns that allow low code and
public code to work together.
Governance and engineering standards
that make these approaches reliable.
Integration in real practice with
real world examples, case studies
and scenarios across the government,
enterprise and healthcare.
The challenges and pitfalls
we must acknowledge.
Future directions, including aa assistant,
low code and digital government, a
conclusion that ties all together.
Traditional coding has given
us the digital world we live in
today, but the model is showing
its cracks under new demands speed.
Atypical enterprise application can take
six to 12 months to develop and release.
By then.
Business needs have often shifted.
Cost.
According to standardish Group Ks
report, over 50% of software projects
either fail out rate or delivered
late, and or budget talent demand
for developers outpaces supply.
On the business side, customers are
expecting updates weekly, not yearly.
Regulators are expecting
transparency and complaints.
Beg them both.
And executors expect a clear
written of investment from
every technology investment.
Low code addresses the speed and access
problem by letting the teams build faster.
Public code addresses the trust
and sustainability problem by
making the software transparent
and auditable together.
They're not just incremental improvements.
They represent a new paradigm
in software delivery.
What is low?
Low code is often misunderstood as just
drag and drop coding, but it's much more.
The key dimensions of low code
are visual development, drag and
drop workflows, UI builders and
configuration over code prebuilt
components connected for databases,
APAs authentication and notifications.
Rapid prototyping, the ability to
go from idea to functional, proof
of concept in days, collaboration,
empowering both developers and
business experts to contribute.
Gartner forecast that 2026.
Three quarters of all new
applications will be built using
low code or no code platforms.
A global bank use low code to
automate its compliance reporting.
What used to take 20 developers
six months was accomplished by a
hybrid team of five developers and
five analysts in just eight weeks.
What is public code?
Public code is about a software that
is built in open with accountability,
transparency, and usability.
At its core, the three principles
of public code are openness
code is shared publicly, often
under open source licenses.
Transparency architectures under
documentations are auditable, reusability.
Other organizations can adopt the
software instead of reinventing it.
Why does it matter in government?
It builds the citizen trust.
When a city launches a new
digital service, people can see
how it works in enterprises.
It prevents vendor locking and ensures
knowledge is not siloed in communities.
It foster collaboration
and collective innovation.
Public code is essentially the
open source move in adopted
for institution accountability
architectural patterns when low
code and public code converge.
Architecture is critical.
These are some of the patterns
that we, that can make it work.
Hybrid workflows, user facing layers
are designed in low code, while core
business logic is in public code.
Customer support.
Chatbots built in low code, but escalating
logic coded can be coded openly.
A p first design, every function exposed
as an a p ensures modularity and.
An example would be, instead of
typing, tying the forms directly to the
database forms can call reusable APAs.
Event driven pipelines systems react to
events with resilience and audit trails.
An example would be a region files
a request event triggers local
workload processes, unlocks a written
for transparency, CICD integration.
Three lower code artifacts as code
version, them test them and deploy them.
An example would be low
code workflow stored in Git.
Tested automatically in pipelines,
observability and governance metrics
logs, traces embedded for transparency,
governance and engineering standards.
Governance is waste.
Low code projects is a
success as spiral into chaos.
Without governance, you can risk shadow.
IT projects built without oversight.
Data leaks due to poor access
control compliance violations.
Some of the standards that we can enforce
for this two work are version control.
Every low code artifact is tracked
like a source code, automated testing,
data validations, integration test
security scans, security by design,
role-based access, integration,
encryption, and audit trails.
Reproducibility dev test and
production must be identical.
Forrester Research shows that
organizations with structured low-code
governance reports 50% fewer compliance
issues compared to those without.
Governance is not just an afterthought.
It's a foundation for
scale and sustainability.
Integration practice.
How do these really work in reality?
Data pipelines and automation,
low-code orchestrate, CTL flows, public
code, enforce transformations and
validation logic, DevOps integration.
Low-code apps automatically tested
and deployed through Jenkins.
GitHub Actions R Azure
DevOps Legacy Modernization.
Old COBOL are mainframe systems
wrapped in APAs workflow orchestrated
usually in low-code cross
team collaboration businesses.
Units create prototypes.
IT teams harden them for scale.
A large hospital automated its patient
admission process nurses designed
the workflow in a local platform.
It integrated with EHS
system using public code aps.
Result.
An average admission time dropped
by 30% on compliance audits
became simpler case studies.
Let's look at the sector
specific examples.
Government, Estonia, government, often
called most digital country in the
world, uses open standards and public
code to provide nearly all services.
Only pairing this with low code
interfaces, low rapid delivery of
oxygen fitting, facing port portals.
Enterprise it.
A retailer.
Use low code to prototype
store dashboards in four weeks.
While supply chain algorithms remained
public code for reuse across regions.
Healthcare a compliance workflow built
in low code documented as public code
helped a hospital demonstrate GDPR
compliance to audit us in the court time.
According to Deloitte, low code can
reduce development time by 50 to 90%,
while public reusability can save
governments up to 30% of it budgets.
Challenges and pitfalls
as the benefits there are.
Often challenges include scalability.
Some local platforms struggle under
millions of transactions per day.
Vendor lockin proprietary
tools can become cages.
Governance, drift without oversight.
Fusion developers create
unmonitored workflows.
Skill, balance.
Non-technical users need guardrails.
Engineers need freedom.
A global insurer adopted
low-code widely within a year.
They had 500 Fs, but
no central governance.
It spent months auditing
and consolidating them.
The point is, low-code plus public
could work best when they paid
with the discipline and foresight
where this is heading.
Citizens and engineer.
Citizens and engineers
collaborate and they join.
Design sessions shared accountability.
Open source, low code platforms
like bhi Base and jogi are reducing
lockin AI assisted development.
Generative AI suggest workforce detects
anomalies and autogenerate testing
cases, public sector acceleration.
Governments aligned with digital first
policies, making public code the norm.
Imagine a CT planner drags a
workflow for the permit process.
A instantly suggest compliance
checks, accessibility standards,
and data security improvement.
That is the near future.
To conclude low-code excels delivery
and impose teams across skill levels.
Public code, ensure transparency,
trust, and long-term sustainability.
Together the balance, speed,
governance, agility with compliance.
The future of software delivery is
not developers versus business users.
It is developers plus business
users working together with the
shared tools, shared governance
and shared responsibility.
Thanks for your time.