Hello everyone, and thank you for
joining my presentation on building
ML ops for autonomous mortgage.
I want to start by asking you to imagine
the scenario now you have found your
dream home, you made an offer, and now
you're waiting for mortgage approval.
In a traditional world, a mortgage
application goes through 40
some manual steps, and it takes
anywhere from 30 to 60 days.
And all the while workflows, either
manual or digital goes between people
and within different departments.
But imagine if that entire process
could happen in three days, and
also with better accuracy and
compliance than the old manual system.
And just introduce myself.
I am na.
And I have spent the last several
years building exactly these kind
of systems in the mortgage industry.
Today, I want to walk you all through how
MOPS principles can transform one of the
most paper heavy and regulation intensive
industry into something that can actually
work for customers in the 21st century.
And just to provide a sense of what's at
stake, the market industry process about.
$2 trillion in loans and
just in the US alone.
And this is an annual figure.
When you apply modern m lops to that
scale, with all the regulatory complexity
and legacy system challenges, you
get some of the, I mean, fascinating
technical problems to solve.
More importantly, you get the
opportunity to make real difference
in people's lives because, you know,
to be honest, buying a home shouldn't
feel like navigating a bureaucratic.
You know, maze from the 1980s
and just to give you a short you
know explanation about myself.
Now, to give you some context on where
I'm coming from, I've been working at the
intersection of AI and financial services,
and what I find most interesting is how
MOPS principles had to evolve, especially
when we applied them to really regulated
industries like mortgage learning.
Now that $8 million savings.
I mentioned in my PowerPoint
isn't just a number on a slide.
It actually represents thousands
of families who got approved
faster application approvals with
fewer errors and less frustration.
The generative AI chatbot we built now
handles about 60% of all customer service
inquiries, which means human agents
can now focus on the really complex
cases that need genuine expertise.
Now, why this do special?
And here's what.
It makes mortgage ML
lops more fascinating.
From a technical perspective, traditional
ML lops assume you can move fast and
break things in mortgage lending.
Breaking things means someone might
not get a home that they've always
dreamed about, or worse, you might
even violate fair lending practices
and face multimillion dollars in fines.
So we have to get creative on how
to apply these principles safely.
I'd like to start by going over the
industry challenges on adopting mops.
Let me start by giving a sense of
how, just how complex traditional
mortgage processing really is.
Like I mentioned previously,
there are 47 distinct steps from
initial application to closing.
And that's for a very
straightforward purchase loan.
There are other file forms of loan
types that can be even more complex
and have more distinct steps, and,
and I also want you to quickly walk
you through a real world scenario.
Now, someone applies for a
mortgage through an online
portal on Friday evening.
That application is going to sit in
a queue until Monday morning when
a human processor will pick it up.
Then they need to verify the
employment of the application.
Owner.
Which means calling HR departments
that might not respond until Tuesday.
They have to order an appraisal, which
gets scheduling for the following week.
Meanwhile, the credit
report needs manual review.
Bank statements get analyzed line
by line, and then there are dozens
of regulatory compliance checks.
Now, each step involves different
people, often different systems that
don't talk to each other, which is
typical in any industry, and there
are countless opportunities for
applications to get stuck in queues
and also to fall through the stack.
Here lies the technical opportunity.
From an MLS perspective, you are dealing
with incredibly diverse data types,
structured data from credit bureaus or
unstructured data from documents like tax
returns and bank statements, and real time
feeds from property valuation services.
Now, all of this has to integrate
with mainframe systems that
we were built when, you know,
probably in the 1970s or eighties.
But when you apply modern MOPS
principles correctly to this problem,
you can reduce the 30 to 60 day
processing timelines to just three
to five days while also improving
accuracy and regulatory compliance.
That is the transformation that we are
going to talk and explore here today.
Now I want to discuss the unique technical
challenges and regulatory hurdles.
You know, in building AI enabled
mops for mortgage industry scaling
is the first reality check.
When I talk about scaling in mortgage,
I'm talking about processing a hundred
thousand plus applications daily.
And this is especially during peak period
volumes like spring home buying season.
But it is not just about high volume.
It is high volume of incredibly
complex high stakes decisions.
Each application.
Might involve dozens of ML models working
together, like fraud detection, income
verification, property valuation, risk
assessment, and even compliance checking.
The second hurdle is the
regulatory complexity.
Now, here's something that makes
mortgage ML ops fundamentally different
from almost any other ML domain.
Explainability is not just to have a nice
feature, it is a legally required feature.
If we deny someone a loan, we have to be
able to provide specific, understandable
reasons that regulators can audit.
That means every model decision needs
to be traceable back through the entire
data pipeline with completely lineage.
There was a situation where I
remember one regulatory auditor when
an examiner asked about a specific
loan decision from 18 months ago.
In traditional systems, that would
mean days of detective work going
through log files and database records.
With the proper lops architecture, I
could pull up the complete decision
tree in seconds, which models were
involved, what data were used, which
business rules were fired, and even
the exact version that we're active at
that moment when the rule engine ran.
Now there's also the legacy integration
reality that we all know about.
Which is probably the most challenging
aspect of the mortgage mops.
We have a critical loan data living
in mainframe systems from the 1980s.
There is no TPIs, no JSN, no
microservices, just batch files
and data farm mats that literally
predate the worldwide web.
Now you end up building entire AI systems
whose primary job is to just translate
between the modern lops pipelines
and these legacy, you know, systems.
It is like building universal
translators for computer systems that
speak completely different languages.
Traditional MOPS principles had
to evolve significantly when we
applied them to mortgage processing.
Now let me walk you through how each
Korea core area had to be re remanage.
The first aspect is data governance.
Data governance in mortgage ai.
Goes way beyond typical ML governance.
Every piece of data that influences
a loan decision must be tracked
with completely nature, not just for
dworking, but also for legal compliance.
Now we need to know what data
was used, when it was collected,
how it pro processed who had
to access it, and how all these
contributed to the final decisions.
Now we developed something what
I call compliance first, feature
engineering, where every feature pipeline
automatically includes bias detection.
PII, anonymization and
audit trail generation.
The feature engineering code itself
generates documentation that complaints
officers can actually understand
and use in regulatory submissions.
Now, the second MO aspect is model
deployment practices and its evolution.
The model deployment looks
completely different to, we
cannot just optimize for accuracy.
We have to simultaneously optimize
for fairness, explainability,
and regulatory compliance.
The training pipelines include automated
fairness, validation across different
demographic groups, bias detection
and explainability report generation.
We develop something we call a regulatory
aware cross validation architecture where
our validation sets our specifically
constructed to test model performance
across different demographic groups.
Geographic regions and market conditions
to ensure we are not annoyingly
creating discriminatory outcomes.
The other aspect is deployment
becomes complex, especially
because mortgage applications can
take 30 to 60 days to process.
If we deploy a problematic model,
we might not discover the issues
until weeks later when loan starts
performing poorly in the real world.
That's why we developed extended
shadow mode testing where new run
models run in parallel with production
models for complete loan life cycles.
Even before we considered switching
the traffic to these new models
we are essentially running dual
processing pipelines to validate
behavior over long timeframes and
also for end-to-end applications.
I want to discuss next
on the key components.
And challenges in building AI
driven mortgage data pipelines.
I wanna start with
complexities in data injection.
Now let me paint a picture of
what data injection looks like.
In mortgage ai, you are dealing with
PDFs that might be scanned at weird
angles bank statement with hundreds of
different formats depending on the bank.
Now, pay stubs may come from different
companies that all format them very
differently, and this complexity.
That I'm talking about is just
on the document processing side.
Then you have real time data feeds
from credit bureaus, property valuation
services and employment verification
systems, each with their own API quirks
rate limits and vocational outages.
During PC periods, we might be making
about 50,000 to a hundred thousand
API calls per our personal systems,
and each service has different.
Reliability characteristics
and failure modes.
Now these are not even our
biggest challenges yet.
Our document processing pipeline
is probably one of the most
complex parts of the entire system.
We use a, an ensemble OCR model,
la think of it as a combination
of different OCR models because
no single OCR model can handle all
different document types effectively.
Then we have named identity recognition
models that are specifically
trained for financial documents.
They understand the difference between
gross income and net income, and they
can also identify debt obligations
versus assets, recognize different types
of employment documentations as well.
But this is where it
really gets interesting.
From an ML ops perspective, we have
to maintain separate discrete model
versions for different documents.
Pay stubs from 2020 may look
different from one in 2024.
And the models need to be able
to handle both types of documents
because people submit historical
documents as part of their
applications to, you know, especially
to prove their credit worthiness.
Then every single piece of data
flowing through these pipelines have
to be handled with extreme care.
Now again, we implemented what we
call Privacy by design pipelines
architecture, where PII gets
automatically identified and masked.
Sensitive data is encrypted, both
addressed and in transit, and every
access is logged for audit purposes.
The feature store becomes very critical
here, especially because it allows us
to pre-compute these features while
maintaining strict privacy boundaries.
The credit scoring model never
sees raw bank statements at all.
It only gets carefully engineered
financial behavior features
because it preserves privacy.
And also it enables
providing accurate decisions.
Now there's also the storage
reality that we all have to face.
We maintain multiple storage tires
optimized for different use cases,
hard storage for real-time decision
making with less than 50 millisecond
retrieval requirements, warm storage
for model training and experimentation.
And the last one is the cold
storage for long-term regulatory.
The challenge here is to maintain
consistency across all these tires and
also ensure that we are maintaining
performance requirements training
data for mortgage AI presence.
Some, like I said, unique
and fascinating challenges.
You need historical loan performance
data to understand what makes a good
loan, but you also need to account
for changing market conditions.
Evolving regulations and demographic
fairness requirements because these
change tend to change if not frequently.
Occasionally, the data itself tells
stories about economic cycles,
regulatory changes, and social evolution.
Now we generate synthetic data
strategically for such edge
cases and bias mitigation.
Now let's say for example.
We might not have enough historical data
for a certain demographic group or in
certain or specific geographic regions.
So we have to use generative models to
create realistic synthetic applications
that help ensure our models perform
fairly across all populations.
Now, this is not just
about filling data gaps.
Think of it as a proactively
testing model behavior in scenarios.
In which you haven't seen
how to handle them correctly.
Also, rather than building one massive
model that does everything end to end
you have to build specialized models for
different aspects of the loan decision.
Like, you know, one model for income
verification and one for fraud detection,
one for property valuation, and one for
compliance checking, et cetera, et cetera.
And you have so many different workflows
in an end-to-end you know, market
process, application processing.
Each model is optimized for its
specific task, and they communicate
through our event events, architecture.
This approach gives much better
explainability because we can
trace decisions back to specific
models and its particular features.
It also makes debugging and iterative
improvements much more manageable than
trying to tune one giant model and you
know, breaking things along the way.
Now, our validation process also goes
way beyond traditional ML validation.
We run business KPI simulations
before any model goes to production.
We simulate how the model would've
performed during historical market
ments, like the 2008 financial crash.
Or during the early pandemic period
of 2020, now we test fairness across
protected demographics with static
statistical significance testing.
One of our most important validation step
is what we call a regulatory compliance
simulation, where we run the model against
historical data and verify that its
decisions would not only have violated
any fair lending practices, but also
not create any discriminatory impact.
It
Now, deployment in mortgage industries
requires a much more conservative
and sophisticated approach than
any typical ML application.
We've developed something called
a three-phase deployment strategy
that minimizes risk while also
maintaining business continuity
and regulatory compliance.
Now the first step is shadow mode.
And shadow mode in this context isn't
just running models in parallel.
It's about running complete
loan processing workflows.
In parallel, newer models process
real applications, but their decision
is will not affect customers.
Human underwriters will will be there to
see both the production decision and the
shadow model decision, and they provide
detailed feedback on the quality and
reasoning of shadow model recommendations.
Now this gives us incredibly rich
validation data beyond any technical
accuracy metrics we can see.
Where the model's decisions would've
led to better busi business decision
outcomes, and also for faster processing
times and improved customer satisfaction.
The second aspect is canary
release sophistication.
Our canary releases are much more
sophistication than typical END tests.
We don't randomly assign
applications to different models.
We carefully select applications based on
this profile demographic characteristics.
Loan types and geographic regions so
that we can ensure we are testing across
all the different relevant scenarios.
We also monitor KPIs in real time
because canary releases in row if
loan approval rates are shifting
outside expected statistical bonds.
If processing times increase beyond
thresholds or if customer satisfaction
scores drop, we have an automated
system that can roll back these models
within minutes to previous versions.
Now the third aspect is
full deployment monitoring.
Even after full deployment, we maintain
comprehensive parallel monitoring systems.
Each model decision is logged
with complete context and we
track both technical metrics
and long-term business outcomes.
We can correlate model confidence scores
with actual loan performance, but this
has will happen over months or years.
And later to continuously
improve our systems and validate
the decision making quality.
Now CICD in mortgage industry is
significantly more complex than typical
software deployment because you are
not just deploying code, you're also
deploying decision making systems that
affect real people's financial lives
and, and they also need to comply with.
Regulatory federal you know, regulations.
Our model registry is like a combination
of docker hub and a compliance database.
Each model version includes not just
the trained weights and inference
code, but, but they also contain
comprehensive fairness testing results.
They also contain regulatory compliance
documents, performance benchmarks
across different market conditions
and detailed explanatory reports.
Before any model can be promoted to
production, it has to pass automated
tests for, for technical performance,
bias detection, regulatory compliance,
and business impact simulation.
We also maintain detailed metadata
about which models are approved for
which loan types and for geographic
regions and also for market conditions.
Now when it comes to comprehensive
testing, our test suits include
standard model test unit like.
Data processing logic and integration
test for model serving infrastructure.
However, they also include
mortgage specific tests that
don't exist in other domains.
We test model behavior during simulated
market stress scenarios, validate fair
lending compliance across demographic
groups, and also verify integration with
all the external service we depend on.
Now one of our most valuable test
is what we call the end-to-end
simulation loan simulation.
Where we run thousands of synthetic
loan applications through the complete
pipeline, and also validate that all
the models work together correctly,
and they also produce explainable
decisions, and we also make sure that
it meets regulatory requirements.
Now, we also use external configuration
management extensively because mortgage
regulations change frequently and
we need to adjust business rules
without redeploying all the models.
Our models will pull their decision
thresholds, feature weights, and
compliance rules, and business
logic from external configuration
systems and rule engines.
At runtime, this capability became very
crucial, especially during the pandemic
when lending criteria needed to change
almost weekly in response to economic
conditions and regulatory guidance.
The next slide is about orchestration and
workflow automation in mortgage envelopes.
Now, mortgage Workflow orchestration
is incredibly complex because you're
coordinating dozens of different
systems, also external services and human
reviewers across multiple workflows.
Now, these can take, like
I said, typically weeks to
complete, or even months.
Now, unlike typical ML pipelines
that might run for minutes or hovers.
These workflows have to maintain
a steady state and coordinate
activities over month long periods.
Now, managing state, especially across
long running workflows is very critical.
You have to use event sourcing
extensively so you can reconstruct
the complete history of any loan
application and at any point in time.
This is not just useful for debugging.
Now, it is also essential
for regulatory audits.
Where we might need to explain
every decision made many months
ago using data and models that
we see we have updated since
now.
We also use event driven architecture
extensively to manage this complexity
when a credit score gets updated
during the loan processing.
Now this event triggers cascading events
that cross risk models to recalculate not
just the pricing models to adjust interest
rates, but also compliance systems
to reverify regulatory requirements
all automatically, all in parallel,
and all with proper audit trails.
Now, the beauty of this approach
is that adding new models or
changing business logic does not
require modifying existing systems.
Everything communicates
thoroughly through well-defined.
Events now, which makes these systems
much more maintainable and adaptable.
Now we also integrate with dozens of
external services like credit bureaus,
property valuation services, employment
verification system title companies,
insurance providers, et cetera, et cetera.
Now each API has different a PA patterns,
and they all have different rate limits.
They all have different reliability
characteristics and failure models.
Now we build a comprehensive service mesh.
That handles circuit braking,
retries, fail hours, and back
pressure management automatically.
Now, during peak periods, we, we might
hit rate limits, especially with these
external services, so the orchestration
system should automatically cure request,
manage these back pressures and optimize
the order of operations to ensure
we don't lose the application state
or violate service liable agreement.
Now the final you know aspect here
is intelligent automation triggers.
Now, this is needed to maintain
a sophisticated automated trigger
for model returning now based on
performance, degradation, data, drift
detection, or significant changes
in market conditions, because these
triggers also include business logic.
We don't return models during the busiest
processing periods or right before
important regulatory reporting deadlines.
Especially when system stability
is crucial during these periods.
Legacy integration is probably the most
challenging and underestimated aspect of
market mops and integrating with legacy
systems that are literally older than
most people who are actually working
on training or building these models.
We have a very critical loan data
in mainframe systems from the 1980s.
Now these systems process batch files
once daily or you know depending
upon the frequency of how you
know, frequency, it is required.
Now these use data formats that vastly
predate json format by decades and have
zero modern a PA capabilities, but they
contain decades of loan performance
data that's essential for training
accuracy, AC risk models accurately.
Now we ended up building what we call
legacy translation agents, especially
specialized AI systems, whose entire job
is to speak to just mainframe systems.
Now they convert modern human streams
into archaic formats that mainframe
will understand and also translate
back the modern data structures.
That is, that, that is an output of
our ML models back to mainframes.
So they can both, both
work with each other.
Now legacy system often have
data quality issues that human
processors have over the years.
Learned to work around over decades
now, missing fields, inconsistent
you know, formatting, business logic
that's embedded in user interface
screens rather than databases.
Undocumented transformations
that happened years ago now.
Our ML systems had to learn to handle
all these different cooks automatically.
Development of the sophisticated
data quality pipelines can only
detect and often automatically
fix these issues is necessary.
When they can't fix problems
automatically, they route
applications to human reviewers with
very detailed explanation of what
exactly is needed and what is where
the attention is needed and why.
On the same note we cannot just
turn off legacy systems overnight.
They're running critical
business operations that
generate billions in revenue.
So parallel processing validation
where both legacy system and
new ML systems process, the same
application simultaneously should
be developed and put into practice.
Now we can compare outcomes, build
confidence gradually, and shift
processing from legacy to ml as she
process these systems work correctly.
This approach not only gives us incredible
insight into where the legacy systems
we are making suboptimal decisions,
but it also helps us understand the
business value of the ML transformation.
Now from an ML ops perspective,
legacy integration requires building
sophisticated data abstraction
layers, building modern APIs that
provide consistent interfaces
regardless of whether data is coming
from a cutting edge microservice.
Or a 40-year-old mainframe system.
Now, this abstraction allows the ML
models to focus on making good decisions
rather than dealing with all the
complexity of data source integrations.
Compliance isn't just a you know
in mortgage, it's not just going
to be an optional factor or
something that you can add later.
It is going to be the
foundational architecture that.
Everything that you
build is going to be on.
Every model decision has to be explainable
in terms that human, underwriters,
customers, and especially federal
regulators, can understand and validate.
Now, one has to build, sorry.
Now one has to build automated
ity generation directly into
every model in the pipeline.
Now, when a MA model makes a decision,
it automatically generates explanations.
That include which features were most
important and how those features were
calculated now, what data sources
were used in those calculations,
and also how the decision aligns
with the regulatory requirements.
Now, these explanations are not just
going to be for internal debugging,
like I previously mentioned.
They're used in actual
adverse action notices.
That get sent to loan applicants
when applications are denied.
Now these explanations have to
be accurate, understandable, and
especially legally compliant.
A continuous bias monitoring system should
also be running across all demographic
groups and protected characteristics.
These models are trained to optimize
for both accuracy and fairness
simultaneously using specialized loss
functions and constraint optimization.
If we detect bias emerging in certain
model decisions, now we can trace it
back to specific features, training,
data issues, and or model architecture
problems and fix them systematically.
Now, this is not only about being ethical,
even though it is obviously important.
It is also about avoiding a multimillion
dollar regulatory fines and also to
which is in, in turn, re required for
maintaining our license to operate
in this heavily regulated industries.
Also, the next aspect, security
and mortgage lops means protecting
some of the most sensitive
personal information that exists.
It may be income, it may be the
customer's income or their assets.
Or the credit history or the
employment details, so on and so forth.
Now, the practice of end-to-end
encryption, the zero trust networking
and principle of least privilege access
controls throughout the entire system.
Architecture needs to be used from dma.
Now, every model interaction is
logged for audit purposes, but the
logs themselves are encrypted and
also should be access controlled.
We can prove to regulators that we
track who accessed what data and when.
But we can also demonstrate that
sensitive information was never
exposed inappropriately and shared
only in situations where required and
to the right you know, stakeholders.
We also automated as much compliance
reporting as possible because
manual compliance processes don't
scale with volume of decisions
these systems are going to make.
Now our systems generate
regulatory reports automatically.
They track fair lending metrics in real
time or where or near real time, and
alert us immediately if any metrics
drift outside acceptable ranges defined
by our internal regulatory guidance.
Next I want to talk about how can
we implement efficient strategies
to meet the performance demands,
performance requirements in mortgage.
Industry are driven by both customer
expectations and business economics.
Customers expect instant prequalification
decisions when they're shopping for
homes, but comprehensive underwriting
needs to balance both speed and
accuracy because the financial
stakes and logistics are very high.
Now.
The use of model quantization
and pruning helps reduce latency
without sacrificing accuracy.
However, implementing intelligent
caching for frequently accessed
features and common application
patterns is very crucial.
Using predictive free predictive
prefetching where we anticipate what
data and features will be needed based on
the current application characteristics.
Now, during peak periods, like the
spring home buying season, which
I mentioned previously, we might
process three times the normal
volumes, our auto-scaling policies.
Monitor queue depth, processing time,
resource utilization, and also external
service response time to automatically
spin up additional capacity to scale
up or scale down as and when required.
Now we also optimize cost by
using different infrastructure
tiers strategically, like
real time decision models.
Run high performance instances
with guaranteed resources.
All the while batch processing models
use spot instances and preempt VMs.
We also use predict scaling based on
historical seasonal patterns to minimize
infrastructure waste, while also ensuring
performance during demand spikes.
Now we monitor everything from multiple
perspectives anywhere from model and
latency, percentiles, resource utilization
across the entire slack, external service
response times, queue, depths, and most
importantly, business KPIs like loan
approval rates, and customer satisfaction.
Okay, now our dashboards show technical
metrics alongside business impact metrics.
So now we can understand the
business consequences of any
performance issues immediately.
Mod k GI systems can fail in ways
that they don't show up immediately.
Like other traditional application
monitoring model degradation due to
very, very subtle market changes.
Might not become apparent until
weeks or sometimes even month later
when loan performance data comes in.
Now, a bias issue might only surface
when you analyze approval patterns
across demographic groups over time
now using statistical drift detection
to monitor input data distribution,
but you also need to monitor business
outcome changes continuously if loan
approval rates are suddenly shifting.
Or if you see average processing
times are increasing, or if you notice
that your customer satisfaction or
dissatisfaction rates are dropping, or
if you see the agent overrides rates
are spiking then you need to investigate
immediately, even though your technical
metrics are all looking normal.
Now, the incident response
includes automated technical
rollback capabilities, not just for
infrastructure issues, but also.
Involves human expertise
loops for business anomalies.
Now, when technical problems
occur, we have automated systems
that can restore service quickly.
But when business metric anomalies
occur, we have to immediately
bring in domain experts because
they are the ones who understand
mortgage markets and regulations,
and also customer behavior patterns.
Now every incident becomes a
structured learning opportunity.
You have to conduct thorough post-mortem.
That include both technical
root cause analysis and also
business impact assessments.
Now these learning will automatically
feed back into your monitoring systems
alert thresholds and also, and, and
should also eventually go into a
deployment procedures and, and also helps
in your model validation procedures.
Finally, I want to talk about.
Future directions and key
takeaways from today's discussion.
Now, LMS are already transforming
document processing in mortgage industry.
Instead of training dozens of specialized
models for each document type, now
using LMS that can understand and
extract relevant information from any
doc financial document with minimal
additional training is the next step.
This dramatically reduces the complexity
of document processing pipeline.
Now federated learning is becoming
an interesting concept in mortgage
industry because it could enable
collaboration between institutions
while maintaining strict data privacy.
Now, imagine training, you are training
a better fraud detection model using
insight from across the industry or
even your competitor now without any
of these institution sharing sensitive
data or sensitive customer data.
Now let me leave you with you know,
couple of essential lessons from building
mop systems, especially for mortgage
industry that apply broad and not just,
sorry, not just mortgage industry,
but to any broadly regulated industry.
Now, the first one is regulatory
compliance is sent a constraint that you
should always work around from the get go.
It should be an architectural requirement
that you design into every component.
Now, trying to add compliance later is.
Exponentially expensive.
And it, it is sometimes an expensive and
impossible ticket to, you know complete.
Now the second one is legacy
system in integration will always
be more complex than you expect.
So plan for it.
You allocate significant
budget time and resources.
Now, you also build abstraction layers
that can evolve as you gradually
modernize your legacy systems
into, into, you know legacy mode.
As you modernize your legacy systems.
The third aspect is, you know,
business outcome monitoring is just
as important as technical monitoring.
Your technical metrics can look
perfect, but your business outcomes
are quietly degrading in a ways that,
like I said, will not be apparent
until weeks or even months later.
And also change management and
stakeholder buy-in are absolutely crucial.
The most sophisticated ML system in
the world will fail if the people who
need to use it don't understand it
are trusted or see the value in it.
There has to be a mixture of both
top down and bottom up approach.
Now, when you're getting ML ops right in
the market industry, the transformation
is going to be dramatic and measurable.
Now, loan processing times
will drop from weeks to days.
Accuracy will improve significantly.
Your operational cost will decrease
substantially, and regulatory compliance
becomes automated and bulletproof.
And most importantly, the entire home
buying process will become something
customers actually enjoy rather
than enduring for weeks or months.
Now, the mortgage industry has been
essentially unchanging for decades, but
ML ops will give the, give us the tools
and techniques to transform it completely.
The.
Organizations that master this
transformation, especially the first
one, to master them will dominate
the next set of financial services.
The technology exists, the
techniques are proven, and the
business cases also company.
Now.
It is just a matter of execution.
Now, I also want to thank
you all for your time today.
I am excited to continue.
I am excited to continue to have
these conversations and also help
more organizations successfully
apply mops principles and transform
their industries successfully.
Now, let's align, adapt, and accelerate
for a breakthrough transformation.
Thank you.