Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My talk today is on ML Ops at scale.
Before we dive into ML ops let
me quickly introduce myself.
I've been in the data analytics
and machine learning space for
over 15 years, building large scale
platforms, predictive models, and
intelligent system across industries.
Over the years, I've seen data evolve
from simple dashboard to mission critical.
AI systems that influence
billions of decisions.
Every single day in my career, I have
led teams that designed end-to-end ML
pipelines, architected the petabyte scale
data warehouse, and deployed models,
powering finance, hr, and other use cases.
And more recently, my focus has expanded
to world of agent AI building autonomous
AI agents that don't just predict but
can act, collaborate, and make decision
with other systems across all of this.
One lesson that has stayed constant
is building a model is easy.
But operationalizing it at
scale is the real challenge.
That's why ML ops and and now ML ops
and agent DKI ops are so critical.
They ensure models are reliable,
auditable, and scalable turning
experimental prototypes into
real business solutions.
That's why I'm passionate about ML Ops.
This is the foundation that allows
enterprise to move from experimentation
to impact safely, reliably, and at scale.
Let me move on to the next slide.
I wanna make sure that
I give some disclaimer.
All the views and opinions shared in
this presentation are my own perspective.
They don't represent or reflect
the views of Amazon or AWS I'm
just sharing this purely out of
my passion for ML ops and ai.
All right.
I wanna start with a simple idea.
A model in a Jupyter Notebook
is an experiment, a model in
production, monitored and gone
at scale is a business solution.
Think about how critical this
is at companies like Amazon,
Netflix, or major banks.
Machine learning system drive billions
of decisions, recommendations fraud
detection, supply chain optimization
or even workforce planning.
If these model fail the business
feels it's very instantly.
Now we are also entering the
era of large language models.
They're powerful, but
they're also unpredictable.
ML ops is what keeps the system
reliable and trustworthy.
My goal today is to show how
automation CICD, monitoring and
governance ensure just that let's
talk a little bit on the challenges.
Traditional ML project often fail
because pipelines are brittle.
Maybe a column name changes in
the source data, and suddenly
the feature store breaks.
Deployments are often manual.
Someone copies of model file pushes
it into production and then sprays.
It works.
And then there is monitoring,
or rather the lack of it.
Many enterprise have models running
in production right now that haven't
been retrained in months or even years.
That's a big problem.
Let me give you an example, A credit
risk model at a financial firm that was
trained on pre 2020 data when COVID hit
consumer behavior, changed overnight,
job loss, losses loan defaults.
Government relief checks and so on.
But the model was sent, monitored,
and for months, it misclassified risk
leading to massive financial losses.
Now brings in LLM, or now
let's bring in the LLM.
They add even bigger risk cost explosion,
hallucination, or compliance gaps.
So if ML ops was important before in LLM
world it's absolutely mission critical.
All right.
Let's begin with what is ML ops?
ML Ops is about taking the best of dev
ops, continuous integration, continuous
delivery, infrastructure automation,
and applying it to machine learning.
But there's one more.
DevOp DevOps deals with code while ML
ops deals with code data and models.
Let's break it down.
Data pipelines feed
features into the model.
The model itself is trained,
validated, and washed.
Deployment must be automate automated
across environments and monitoring keeps
track of the model performance over time.
And now with large language models.
We need to extend this thinking
to what some call LLM Ops.
Where we manage not just training and
deployment, but also prompt pipelines,
retrieval, augmentation, and fine tuning.
The principles remains the same.
Automate, monitor and govern.
I wanna talk about ML ops in
the large language model era.
As we shift now into the
age of large language model.
Some people ask.
Do we still need ML labs?
And I think the answer is, and
in fact it's, this is a big yes.
If anything, we need it even more.
Why?
Because the complexity of operating
large language model is even higher
than classical machine learning.
Just like we manage feature
pipelines for machine learning
in large language, we need.
Are we now manage prompt
pipelines prompts evolve.
Chains of prompts need testing
and they must be version control.
Fine tuning and large language
model is very expensive.
Without automated evaluation
pipeline, you risk wasting millions
retraining models unnecessarily.
Monitoring also becomes bo broader.
We don't just watch accuracy or latency.
We track hallucination,
toxicity, bias and grounding.
For example, a large language
model chat bot in healthcare starts
producing producing advice, not
grounded in medical solutions.
We need guardrails to
catch that instantly.
Finally, governance.
With machine learning, we tracked.
Data sets and model versions
with LLM, we must also track data
compliance and human feedback loops.
ML ops gives us the foundation to
make lms reliable, responsible,
and scalable in enterprise context.
Without it large language model adoption
will stall because enterprise won't
trust them in mission critical use cases.
Let's move on to ML lops lifecycle.
The ML of lifecycle looks like
a loop not a straight line.
It begins with data ingesting in
pre-processing, validating data,
detecting schema changes, applying
feature engineering, and so on.
Then comes model training and fine tuning.
Often tracked in ML flow or SageMaker
with hyper parameters and metrics.
Next is validation.
This isn't just accuracy,
it's fairness, robustness, and
interpretability then comes deployment.
This could mean exposing an
API containerizing in model or
serving it via a feature store.
Finally monitoring and feedback
loop closes the entire cycle.
We monitor accuracy, drift, and latency.
If something falls out of the bound
retraining triggers automatically.
A real world example a retail store
recommendation models retrain daily
with new browsing and purchase data.
They're validated against test
sets, rolled out with shadow
deployments and monitored for
drift for large language models.
This lifecycle also includes prompt
chain testing, ground checks, and
human in the loop review to ensure
the output remains useful and safe.
All right.
Automation I think automation is the
first pillar without it, ma a machine
learning model becomes artisanal
slow and consistent and fragile.
Take a retail company
running pricing optimization.
If a data engineer has to manually rerun
the pre-processing scripts, every time
new sales data arrives, they'll never keep
up with the changing market condition.
By automating the pipelines with
airflow or QB flow retraining happens
daily and reproducibly for LLMs.
Automatic automation
is equally cr crucial.
As I've mentioned before, imagine a chat
bot trained on enterprise documentation.
Automation ensures that when new docs are
published the retrieval index is refreshed
prompts are validated and evaluation.
Test are triggered.
No one has to manually intervene.
Automation ensures that models are
not one off science experiments.
They le their living systems.
CICD for ML and large language models.
CICD bring agility and
discipline in machine learning.
We work in not just code,
but data sets and models.
Tools like DVC or ML
Flow make this possible.
Every new data set goes through
regression test, bias test,
and unit test for features.
Example let's say at Netflix, thousands of
models are deployed using CICD pipelines.
If one experiment fails, it can be rolled
back instantly for large language models.
CICD includes prompt worsening, so
you have a customer service chat bot.
Each new prompts template gets
tested against historical customer
interaction, shadow deployment let
you compare the new version against
the old before fully rolling it out.
And just like microservices,
rollback strategies are essential
because the cost of a bad model or
prompt in production can be huge.
Moving on to governance and
responsible ai governance is
all about trust and compliance.
Enterprise needs to answer
which model made this decision?
What data was it trained on?
Can we prove it wasn't biased?
And financials services regulators may
demand proof of why a loan was denied.
With ML ops governance, you
can show the dataset, the model
version, even the code used.
LLMs take it.
The, take this a little bit further.
We must track data where training or fine
tuning data came from red teaming results.
What failure modes were tested
and regulatory compliances
like GDPR or eu AI Act are very
explicit about AI transparency.
Responsible AI is not optional.
It's the price of doing business
with with ai model and LLM training.
So monitoring is where
the battle is won or lost.
For classical ml, we monitor accuracy,
latency, drift, and infrastructure cost.
For example, a fraud detection at
a bank looked great at launch, but
started missing new fraud patterns.
After six months, continuous monitoring
detected drift earlier early and
triggered retraining, saving millions.
LM introduced another.
Monitoring challenge the hallucination
rate the toxicity grounding our
answers tied back to real data sources.
Some enterprise now run red teaming
in production monitoring outputs for
unsafe responses, and automatically
flagging them for human review.
Without monitoring, large language
model can quickly become liabilities.
I wanna talk about, some of the best
practices in the large language model era.
So what works well use
infrastructure as a code.
So every environment is reproducible.
Adopt feature stores for ML and emerging
prompt stores for LLMs, automate
bias testing, fairness checks and
safety evaluation as part of CICD,
build cross-functional teams because.
Reliable AI requests, not just data
scientists, but engineers, compliance
offices, and business leaders.
Moving on to my final slide.
This is just my closing and
call to action to close.
Let me emphasize this.
ML OPS is not outdated.
It is evolving.
It is the foundation that allows
enterprise to scale both classical
and machine learning and modern
large language models responsibly.
Without automation, CICD, monitoring
and governance models will fall or
fail silently cost too much and expose
you to regulatory risk with them.
AI becomes reliable,
trustworthy, and scalable.
So whether you're deploying a
custom churn model or recommendation
engine, or a generative AI assistant,
remember ML ops is the bridge
between innovation and trust.
With that, I want to thank everyone for
taking the time to listen into my talk.
And thank you very much.