Hey all, thanks for being here.
My name is Jimmy Kaar and I'm a
senior manager at C-X-M-U-S-A.
Today I'll be talking about
building scalable ML ops
pipelines for enterprise systems.
This topic is critical because
most machine learning projects
don't fail due to poor models.
They fail when trying to
scale them in production.
I'll share how at C xm, we build
systems that can support millions
of daily transactions reliably.
The aim is to provide you with a mix of
theory and practical insights that you
can apply in your own organizations.
Here's our agenda.
We'll begin with the
challenges enterprise face.
In deploying ml, I'll show you
why traditional IT deployment
approaches, uh, break down when
applied to machine learning.
Next, we'll dive into the
architecture fundamentals.
These are the building blocks that
every production ready EML systems need.
Okay, then I'll explain the implementation
framework, a step-by-step way to
automate and streamline deployments.
After that, I'll share some real world
impact metrics from Sirius xm, so
you can see the measurable benefits.
Finally, closing with the strategic
roadmap so you know how to bring
these practices into your own
organization incrementally.
Now let's talk about the
enterprise ML challenge.
Many organizations still
rely on manual processes.
Deployments are done by hand.
Environments don't match between
development and production,
and teams work in silos.
As a result, the deployments can take
months, incidents occur frequently,
and compliance is difficult.
This isn't just a technical
issue, it's a business one.
When it takes 60 to 90 days to put a
model into production, you lose agility.
Competitors can trade faster with.
And will outperform you.
So the gap between data science,
experimentation, and production
requirements become a major obstacle.
Here we see the ML Ops
maturity journey at Level Zero.
Things are completely manual.
Deployments are ad hoc, and
monitoring is almost non-existent.
Level one introduces some
partial automation, maybe a few
scripts, or a basic CICD setup.
At level two, you can start
continuously delivering models
with pipelines and some monitoring.
Finally at level three,
everything is automated.
You have self-healing systems
and robust monitoring in place.
At Sirius xm, we went from level one
to level three in just 18 months.
That shift reduced deployment times from
weeks to ours while ensuring stability
for millions of daily transactions.
These are the four pillars
of ML Lops Architecture.
First automated model Val.
Validation ensures only high quality
compliant models get deployed.
Second, CICD pipelines, standardized
deployments, and make rollbacks easy.
Third, monitoring systems keep
track of model performance, data
drift and overall system health.
Finally, scalable infrastructure
such as Kubernetes allows us to
manage workloads dynamically.
Together.
These pillars are what make scaling to
hundreds of production models possible.
At Series xm, we built an automated
validation framework to ensure that only
production ready models make it live.
This framework ensures models on three
dimensions, statistical performance,
operational readiness, and compliance.
Statistical checks cover
accuracy, precision recall.
F1 score and business KPIs.
Operational readiness checks,
latency, scalability, and throughput
compliance ensures explainability bias
detection and regulatory alignment.
By putting these gates in place,
we reduce production issues by 94%.
That's a massive
improvement in reliability.
This diagram illustrates
our CICD pipeline.
It starts with version control, not
just for code, but also for data
sets, configurations and artifacts.
The build and test stage uses
containerization, performance
benchmarks, and security scanning.
Staging is where we do shadow
deployments and AB testing to ensure
the model behaves correctly under load.
Finally, in production, we
rely on candidate deployments,
automated rollbacks and audit logs.
The result we brought deployment times
down from 45 days to just four hours.
That's the power of automation
and a standardization.
Monitoring is essential because
models degrade over time.
We monitor across four dimensions.
Model performance, data quality.
System operations and business impact.
That means looking at accuracy and
KPIs, checking for data drift, watching
latency and error, and finally,
measuring revenue or conversion impact.
In the first year alone, our
monitoring system detected 28
critical drift incidents before
they could affect customers.
This kind of proactive monitoring helps
prevent costly business disruptions.
Enterprise ML workloads are
unpredictable, so infrastructure has
to be both powerful and flexible.
We use Kubernetes for container
orchestration and autoscaling Apache Spark
for distributed data processing and load
balanced interfer interference services.
For ancy security is equally important.
We enforce strict access controls,
encryption, and audit logging.
As a result, our system now
handles 3.5 million inference
requests daily with 99.99% uptime
and sub 50 millisecond latency.
That's production grade
infrastructure at scale.
Of course, technology alone,
alone doesn't solve everything.
Organizations fail face challenges
like mismatch skill sets.
Fragmented tools and
inconsistent success metrics.
Often engineers and data scientists
simply don't speak the same language.
The solution we found at CSXM was to unify
development environments, standardized
workflows, and create shared KPIs.
Cross-functional collaboration was key.
In fact, our VP of AI engineering
said the biggest win wasn't technical.
It was getting both sides
to speak the same language.
This chart compares metrics
before and after M lops.
Before deployments were slow,
expensive, and error prone.
After implementing M Lops, deployment
timelines dropped dramatically.
Incidents were fewer, iterations
became easier, and costs went down.
The takeaway is that ML Ops
isn't just about engineering.
It directly translates into
business efficiency and agility.
Here's the roadmap we recommend
for implementing ML ops.
Phase one is about laying the
foundation, standardized environments,
version control, and basic pipelines.
Phase two introduces automation with CI
c. D pipelines, validation dashboards,
model registry, and metadata tracking.
Phase three scales.
The system with Kubernetes orchestration
and advanced monitoring, along with
data drift detection systems and
establishing automated rollback mechanism.
Finally, phase four focuses on
optimization, implement advanced
features, stores self-healing
infrastructure, features, stores
restraining and governance.
The key is not to attempt a full
transformation overnight, but
to deliver increment values.
In phases.
Now let's look at common pitfalls
First, don't become tool obsessed.
Tools should serve workflows
not the other way around.
Second, don't underestimate
the cultural cha.
Change required.
If teams don't adapt, the
initiative will stall.
And third, don't over
complicate your first steps.
Start small, prove value, and then scale.
The most successful implementation,
start with a single high value
use case and expand from there.
To summarize, ML Lops provides
a real competitive edge.
Organizations that do this
well can deploy models 20 to 30
times faster than their peers.
The four pillars, validation, pipeline
monitoring, and infrastructure are your
foundation, but equally important is
bridging the cultural gap between teams.
Finally remember, start small,
focus on value and scale quickly.
Once you have proven success,
this approach will maximize both
technical and business outcomes
from your ML investments.
That brings us to the end of the session.
I hope you're walking away with
not just theoretical knowledge,
but also practical steps for
building scalable ML lops pipelines.
Thank you so much for your
time and attention and have
a great rest of your day.