Good morning and good afternoon.
Thank you Con 42 and the organizers for
providing me the amazing opportunity.
And let me start with a brief background
of the problem that you are going
to talk about and how to solve that.
So in the biomedical research field,
there are more than a million of.
Research papers are being published every
year, and if you take the citations of
those research papers it'll multifold
such tsunami of information is out there.
When a researcher comes to do a
research in that field, they first
look for doing the literature review.
That's the first step in any
literature any research process.
When they attempt to do that, they have
to go through these millions of records.
Probably they can do a quick search in
somewhere, but in spite of that, finding
the relevant literature is very difficult.
First of all, there may be
a good literature out there.
That may be hidden from
the researcher search.
That's also not good.
There may be processing issues like
if they take into these millions of
records into account it will take
forever to do that literature review.
So in sum up I would say the average,
the researchers spend like a total of
eight, more than 80 percentage of time
just for doing this literature review.
So this is the clear problem statement.
This slide we already discussed about
it, and our solution for this problem
is intelligent AI literature agents.
It contains four, four
subdomains, like domain adapted lms.
That's LLM is large language
model, advanced rag system.
It is.
Advanced retrieval augmented generation
system, precision, NER System.
N-E-S-N-E-R is nothing but entity
recognition for genes, proteins, and drug
directions, robust ML ops infrastructure.
Let's go through this agenda.
We'll first start, talk about talking
about the ML ops architecture.
And then we'll move on to
biomedical NLP Pipeline.
We'll also talk about vector database
scaling after that and following
followed by monitoring and observability.
And finally, we'll close with
the continuous experimentation
and deployment strategies,
a ML Ops architecture overview.
So when we talk about ML lops
everyone might have cared about this.
ML lops.
It's a machine learning how
to ma operate, operationalize
the machine learning pipeline.
So it's, ML ops is is a critical part.
Like just by developing the models,
we cannot achieve everything.
We have to implement it and
make it production ready.
ML ops is a crucial role in
any machine learning lifecycle.
So effective lops, if you consider
that, if you ask me to define an
effective lops architecture I would
say that few components are necessary.
The first one is
contentized microservices.
It's for modular scalability
and version versioning.
This model registry.
So models keep getting updated,
so we need to have it versioned in
the model registry, a synchronous
processing pipelines for efficient
batch citation updates because in
research company is very vibrant the
citation results and and citation
count, those things will vary every day.
So we need to get the latest information.
To give the correct picture of the
literature to the researcher, clear
separation of embedding generation
from retrieval services real time
inference, AI A PA layer, engineered
for subsecond responses and dedicated
evaluation enrollment to ensure
rigorous scientific validation.
So when we look at the biomedical
NLP pipeline there are a few
challenges with the domain adaption.
Because biomedical is something
which only few people who are really
into the bioTE, biotechnology and
bio biology and healthcare and those
people are interested in, and it has
lots of jargons and technical things.
And not all of them will work on
the can understand this biomedical,
vocabularies, even the language
and, the researchers out there.
So it processes it, it poses sorry.
It poses some challenges because the
biomedical language it's complex.
It's because it's highly specialized
vocabulary across sub-disciplines.
Entity relationship, recurring domain
expertise like gene protein interactions
that needs a domain expert to, give
good understanding to the researcher.
Contextual meaning that changes across
research areas need for continual
updates as a new discoveries emerge.
Traditional NLP five plants
failed in, in this domain without
specialized adaption techniques.
So as a machine learning engineer
or somebody who does the NLP on this
biomedical data, not everyone can do that.
They should have certain knowledge
about this domain and the languages
and certain level of understanding.
Model training and
deployment over workflow.
So model training, it starts with
data ingestion and cleaning and
doing the exploratory data analysis.
Those are typical steps
in any machine learning.
And once model is you do all those
things, you'll develop the model
and, you will have it checked with
the test set and validation set,
and you'll have a working model.
So imagine that it all happens
and data ingestion happens.
Okay?
And then you will go and training the
pipeline, you'll run the training,
the pipeline and evaluation framework.
So we need to have a specialized
metrics for biomedical accuracy
with the domain expert review.
And then we finally deploy the models.
Scaling vector databases for
30 plus million citations.
So the operational challenges is like
efficiently generating a biddings for
massive document car and balancing
recall against computational cost,
managing seamless index updates.
These are like issues with the
operational issues with the vector.
Vector embeddings.
And with our ML op solution to
encounter that is a synchronous
embedding generation pipelines with
batch processing, hierarchical indexing
strategies and then read replicas, which
staged updates, optimist query caching.
So these are the techniques to
encounter those shortfalls or
challenges like I would say.
Rag architecture and
production implementation.
There are lots of key components like
domain specific impacting models,
multi-stage retrieval, pipeline
citation, network enrichment,
and context window optimization.
And but with respect to performance
metrics we have to, evaluate the things
like evaluate any, the performance
against baseline, I would say to
make sure that the performance has
indeed has improved like subsequent
correl latency 90 percentage accu
accuracy in the entity recognition.
And citation relevance score
is coming up more than 85%.
As such, KPAs are really important
when evaluating performance.
It's not about just doing the things.
We also need to make sure that
we are doing the right thing
and getting the right expected
results within the stipulated time.
So the final one is, yeah, reduction
in the researcher literature searched.
Monitoring and observability framework.
So once we deploy the model, and
the data may change, it's evolving.
The model which work efficiently
while we implement it, first time
may not work over the period.
So we need to constantly monitor the
models and then do the fine tuning.
So model performance tracking,
scientific accuracy, validation,
and user interaction analysis.
They're really important and we have
to, once we are done with the work,
we cannot be, we cannot say that.
Yeah, it's all done and
we don't need to revisit.
We have to come up.
Come back again and we have to have a
certain metrics to evaluate every time
and make sure that if it's derailing
or maybe deviating from the desired
expected outcome, then we need to
intervene and fine tune the model.
Or maybe enhance the ecosystem
to, to produce the right output.
Real time monitoring dashboard.
Our custom monitoring solution provides
both ML engineers and scientific
stakeholders with visibility into model
drift detection, citation accuracy system
health and performance metrics, user
query patterns and success rates, resource
utilization and scaling triggers A and B
a RB testing, a performance comparison.
Continuous experimentation methodology.
We have implemented AB testing
framework that balance experimentation
with scientific reliability, so it
enables targeted HO cohort testing.
My research domain measures both
technical metrics and research
outcomes and provides statistical
confidence for biomedical application.
Supports multivariate testing
across model components.
If this approach has yielded 80 percentage
reduction in ture search time while
maintaining scientific rigor and results,
infrastructure, scaling patterns, so we
have to have a baseline infrastructure
it's core component size of our
average load with two times redundancy,
elastic scaling layers, autoscaling
inference endpoints based upon query
volume and scheduling, scheduled
scaling events predictive scaling for
known search patterns like especially
maybe sometime towards academic.
Term then if you observe that sorry.
If you observe that the demand
increases, we may have to plan for
the scaling in advance, specialized
to compute GPO allocation for embedded
embedding generation and inference.
Our infrastructure scales efficiently
across both batch processing needs
and real time query patterns.
So this is really important, while
making sure that we are not doing less
or more, we are doing the right thing.
Key lops learnings from biomedical ai.
So we have to, yeah, already
we saw that we have the, in
integrating domain expertise.
That's really important.
Without the involvement from domain
scientists, it's it's difficult
to do a right lops without the
domain experts help developing
scientific validation pipelines.
That's also another important, we cannot
just be sure that the performance has
increased just because the time to search.
Has come down.
We have to also measure based upon the
other scientific variables and KPIs
enabling continuous corpus updates.
This is really important.
Corpus is increasing, so we have to keep
up to date for the latest and greatest
information, prioritizing explainability.
Biomedical research application necess
creates significantly higher transparency
and inter, relatively interpretability
standards compared to consumer AI system.
And with that, I'm concluding.
And thank you for this
opportunity t thanks a lot.