Everyone.
I'm Lolita Lanka, currently working
as a senior, a PN developer at
US Food and Drug Administration.
Today I'll be talking about scaling
AI in education through ML ops.
Unlike enterprises, schools
face unique challenges such as
limited budgets, diverse, revised,
and educators who aren't Mr.
Engineers.
And that's why we need a different
approach, like low-code platforms,
privacy first design, and offline
ready architectures that make AI
practical and inclusive for classrooms.
Over the next few minutes, I will
walk you through the challenges,
strategies, and results we have seen
in bringing ML ops to education.
Welcome to today's session on
machine learning operation strategies
tailored for educational environments.
As AI and ML continue to evolve, it
is crucial for schools and educational
institutions to embrace these
technologies despite resource constraints.
In this presentation, we will explore
strategies that empower educational
stakeholders to effectively integrate
AI tools into their institutions.
We'll begin by examining the educational
ML ops landscape where we will discuss
the unique challenges faced by schools
such as limited resources and the current
gaps in technology infrastructure.
Next, we will explore low-code
platforms as enablers, showcasing how
these platforms can democratize AI
deployment, allowing non-technical
users to take part in the process.
This is an essential part of ensuring
that AI tools are accessible to everyone.
Not just those with deep
technical expertise.
Well then let dive into ML ops
Architecture for Education, where
we will discuss the balance between
rapid AI development and the need
for robust governance, security,
and compliance, which are often
crucial in educational settings.
We'll also highlight implementation
strategies, focusing on practical
approaches like containerization
and federated learning, which can
help schools implement AI solutions
effectively, even with limited resources.
Finally, we will provide key takeaways
and future directions outlining actionable
strategies that can directly apply to your
educational settings, helping you navigate
the complexities of AI deployment and
setting the stage for future innovations.
As educational institutions begin to
integrate artificial intelligence and
machine learning technologies into their
operations and curricula, they face a
unique set of challenges that are distinct
from those encountered in other sections.
These challenges are influenced
by various factors such as budget
constraints, infrastructure disparities,
and the need for specialized expertise.
Unlike enterprise level AI
implementations, schools and universities
must account for additional considerations
like governance, privacy, and the
diverse technological environments in
in which these systems will be deployed.
This slide outlines the key obstacles
educational institutions encounter when
adopting AI system and ML Ops practices.
Understanding these challenges is
the first step toward identifying
solutions that can make AI deployment
accessible, affect you, and sustainable
in schools and educational environments.
Let's discuss the challenges
one by one with some examples.
Infrastructure disparity.
The infrastructure available in
educational institutions varies
widely, especially between
urban and rural settings.
In urban environments, schools may
have access to high speed internet
and advanced computational resources.
However, schools in rural
or underprivileged areas may
struggle with limited internet
connectivity and outdated hardware.
Example in well connected cities, a
school can deploy machine learning tools
and cloud-based AI platforms seamlessly.
However, a rural school in a
remote location may face difficult
even accessing internet making
cloud-based AI solutions challenging.
Additionally, high performance
computing infrastructures required
for intensive machine learning tasks
might not be bio available, which would
limit the AI system's effectiveness.
The second is the
technical expertise gaps.
Most educators are not trained in
specialized fields such as DevOps
or machine learning engineering.
As a result, they may lack the
necessary technical skills to
implement, maintain, or even
troubleshoot AI solutions effectively.
This skills gap makes it difficult to
leverage AI systems without external
support or significant training.
Example, a school that introduces
an AI powered educational tool to
assist with grading and personalized
learning may find it difficult to
handle technical issues such as
training new machine learning models,
integrating the system with existing
platforms, or maintaining it over time.
For instance, an AI tool that helps
with automating lessons, plans or
grading may require constant updates and
maintenance, which requires technical
expertise that may educators do not have.
Third is strict governance and privacy.
Educational institutions must adhere to
strict governance frameworks, especially
when handling sensitive student data.
This includes ensuring compliance with
privacy laws such as Family educational
Rights and Privacy Act called third
part in the United States, which
protects the privacy of student records.
A systems in schools must comply with
these privacy standards to ensure that
they do not violate student rights.
Example, when planning an AI
power platform that analyzes
student performances, it's crucial
to ensure that no unauthorized
access to student record occurs.
And the data is used appropriately.
Any AI tool that process students'
data must have stringent access
controls and security measures in
place to provide reaches or misuse.
For example, a school should could use
a machine learning model to predict
student success, but the model must
ensure the data, like grades, behavior,
records, and other personal details remain
confidential and are securely stored.
Next is the resource constraints.
Many educational institutions operate
on limited budgets, which can restrict
their ability to invest in dedicated
infrastructure or specialized
personal for AI de deployments.
This makes it challenging to purchase
the high end server software or
professional development needed to
implement AI solutions effectively.
Example, a small school district
might struggle to fund cloud-based
machine learning services.
As a result, they may have to rely on
low cost or open source platforms, which
might not have the same functionality or
support as commercial systems for instead,
instruc using a commercial AI based tool
for personalized learning, a school may
have to use a simpler, free alternative
that lacks robust features or scalability.
Finally, heterogeneous device ecosystems.
In many educational settings, there is
a mix of different devices, laptops,
desktops, tablets, and smartphones
that students and teachers use.
These devices often have different
operating systems and performance
capabilities, making it difficult
to standardize AI system deployments
across the diverse device ecosystem.
Example, a machine learning platform
designed for students may not be
compatible with all devices in the school.
For example, a high-end AI-based
educational application might run
well on modern laptops, but perform
poorly or not at all on older
tablets or low spec computers.
Consider a scenario where a district
deploys an AI tool to monitor
student progress in real time.
The tool might work on newer Windows
laptops, but failed to perform as
expected on outdated Chromebooks or
tablets, limiting its effectiveness
across the entire student body.
These unique challenges faced by
educational institutions require a
tailored approach to ML ops, which
is significantly different from the
typical enterprise implementations
used in larger corporations.
Solutions that work in business often
cannot be directly applied to schools
without considering the specific needs
and constraints of the education sector.
Education focused ML ops strategies
should consider factors like limited
technical expertise, tight budgets,
diverse devices, and the importance
of strict privacy and governance.
For example, local platforms or
hybrid cloud solutions can offer
these more accessible, cost effective
parts for schools to integrate ai.
By understanding these challenges and
adjusting strategies accordingly, schools
can still unlock the potential of AI while
navigating these barriers effectively.
Having discussed the broader challenges
in deploying AI systems in educational
institutions such as infrastructure
disparities and limited expertise,
it is important to understand that
the nature of data in these settings
presents its own unique complexities.
Educational data does not behave like data
from techn typical business environments.
Instead, it exhibits distinct
patterns and constraints that impact
how machine learning models are
trained, monitored, and maintained.
In this slide, we will divide into
the data distribution challenges
specific to educational setting and
how they require specialized approaches
for effective AI implementation.
Seasonal behavior patterns.
Student interactions with
educational patterns.
Platforms follow the academic calendar,
meaning usage spikes and drops aligned.
Its semesters, holidays, and exam
periods, for example, during summer
breaks or holiday seasons, platform
activity significantly decreases
without accounting for this.
AI models might mistake these
predictable changes for a problem
with model accuracy, triggering false
alerts of model drift when the shift
is actually natural and expected.
Age-based distribution shifts as students
progress through different grade levels.
Their learning behaviors and
interaction patterns evolve.
For instance, a sixth graders engagement
style with digital content is quite
different from that of a 12th graders
preparing for college entrance exams.
AI system needs to distinguish
these natural ships from
genuine performance degradation.
Otherwise, a model trained on younger
students data might underperform or
flag errors when applied to older
students leading to unnecessary
training or inaccurate predictions.
Limited data volume.
Many smaller or rural schools
generate far less data than large
urban schools due to fewer students
or less frequent platform use.
Traditional AI monitoring techniques often
require large, statistically significant
data sets to detect meaningful changes.
In these cases, limited data volumes poses
a challenge, making it harder to identify
real issues like model drift, which
requires tailored methods that affect
work effectively with smaller data sets.
By accounting for these unique data
distribution challenges like seasonal
patterns, evolving student demographics
and data volume disparities, we can
develop monitoring systems that accurately
detect genuine AI performance issues while
minimizing false alarms and unnecessary
training re uh, retraining cycles.
This approach is crucial to building
robust adaptive AI systems tailored
for educational environments.
After understanding the unique challenges
and data distribution issues based
in educational ML ops, the question
arises, how can we overcome these
hurdles, especially when technical
expertise and resources are limited
in many educational institutions.
This is where low-code platforms come into
play offering a transformative solution.
These platforms are transforming
how AI is adopted in schools by
making the process more accessible,
scalable, and collaborative.
This is especially important because
many educational institute lack the
specialized ML engineering resources
that typical enterprises may have.
Let's explore how these platforms
drive democratization and
scalability in educational mops.
Empowering educators
without coding expertise.
According to 2022, survey by EdTech
Magazine, 60% of schools reported lacking
dedicated data scientists, orl engineers,
creating a major barrier to AI adoption.
How low-code helped these platforms
provide drag and drop interfaces and
pre-built AI components, enabling
educators to deploy AI models like
student risk scoring or adaptive learning
recommendations without writing code.
Example, new term and adapt to
learning platform enables teachers
to customize content recommendations
via in Q2, interfaces boosting
student engagement up to 24 5%.
In a pilot program, a school district
reported that 70% of teachers could
configure AI models independently
within two weeks of training.
In Q2, visual interfaces for
configuration and monitoring.
Real time MO modeling model monitoring
is essential for maintaining
accuracy and avoiding false
alarms, especially with seasonal or
demographic shift in student data.
How low-code helps platforms like
Microsoft Azure ML Studio offer dashboards
that let users at thresholds monitor
data drift and receive alerts visually.
Example, a school system using Azure
ML reduced false positive alerts by
40% by adjusting monitoring thresholds
via visual interface, allowing
counselors to focus on genuine cases.
Educators can tweak parameters
such as alert sensitivity in under
five minutes without IT support
automating complex ML workflows.
Traditional level ops pipelines require
manual handling of data ingestion, model
retraining, validation, and deployment,
often needing weeks of effort per update.
How low-code helps platforms like
Google Vertex AI automate retraining
and redeployment when new data arrives?
Ensuring models stay current
without manual intervention.
Example, a pilot with the Midwestern
school district saw retraining
times cut from two weeks to one
day using automated pipelines.
This automation led to a 30%
increase in model accuracy for
predicting student dropout risk.
As models incorporated the
latest sinister data promptly.
Built in governance and
compliance, why it matters.
Educational data is highly sensitive.
Compliance with laws like ferpa, which is
Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act
in the US or GDPR in Europe, is mandatory.
How low code helps platform enable
compliance mechanisms like data
anonymization, role-based access controls,
audit trails directly into the workflows.
Example, in a consortium of a hundred
plus students, a local platform, ensure
a hundred percent compliance with FERPA
by automatically masking students'
personal identification information.
During AI model training and
inferences, schools avoided costly
fines and reputational risks, saving
an estimated 500 K dollars annually
in complaints related overhead.
Reducing technical barriers and costs.
The average cost to hire a
full-time ML engineer in the US
exceeds one 20 K dollars per year.
A prohibitive expense for many schools.
How low code helps By minimizing
the need for specialized staff and
infrastructure schools can implement
AI projects at a fraction of the cost.
Example, a rural school district
within a budget under $1 million
implemented predict two analytics for
student retention using a low-code
platform for less than 15 K dollars
annually compared to a traditional bill
estimated at over one 50 K dollars.
This cost efficiency enabled them
to identify at risk students early,
improving retention rates by 12%
within one academic year, facilitating
collaboration between technical.
Teams Insights.
A 2023 report by the E-D-U-C-A-U-S-C
Center found that successful AI
deployments in education requires
strong collaboration between
educators and technical staff.
How low-code helps shared platforms
with visual tools allow teachers
and ML engineers to work in tandem.
Teachers provide domain knowledge
and context contextual feedback
while engineers handle model tuning.
Example at a major urban school
district, a low-code platform
reduced communication gaps, speeding
up AI project cycles by 15%.
Teachers could adjust model parameters
based on classroom observations,
leading to 20% higher accuracy in
personalized learning recommendations.
Local platforms are not just simplifying
the low technical side of ai.
They are fundamentally demo, demo,
democratizing it by making AI
accessible, governable and collaborative.
These platforms enable educational
institutions to leverage data-driven
insights effectively and ethically.
The result is a scalable.
Cost effecti and impactful AI ecosystem
that helps educators focus on what
matters most improving student outcomes.
Now that we have discussed how to design
scalable and modular ML ops architectures
for education, it's time to talk about
the most, one of the most non-negotiable
elements of deploying AI in schools,
which is the privacy in education.
Protecting student data isn't just.
Best practice.
It's a legal and ethical obligation
whether you are working in a public
school in the US under Family
Educational Rights and Privacy Act
called FERPA in Europe, under General
Data protection Regulation called GDPR,
or in countries like India under the
Digital Personal Data Protection Act.
D-P-D-P-A.
Your ML ops pipelines must be
designed with privacy at the core.
Data mining pipelines.
Let's begin with data minimization.
A core principle in privacy
law, the idea is very simple.
Only use what is essential.
For example, if you're training a model
to predict students dropout risk, you
might not need full names, addresses, or
even attendance logs from early years.
Many modern ML ops tools now
include pre-built data masking
and anonymization features.
For instance, a development deployment
in an Australian school district
showed that using a minimized data
reduce exposure risk by 40% with no
measurable drop in model accuracy.
Differential privacy implementation.
Differential privacy takes things
further by adding statistical noise
to the data to prevent re reverse
engineering of individual identities.
This is especially important in small
classroom data sets where there's a
higher chance of re-identification.
Google's educational AI lab ran a
pilot with differential privacy, was
applied to student writing analysis.
The result.
Model performance by only 3.5%,
but zero personal traces could be
reconstructed even by red team auditors.
This is must have for national
exams, learning diagnostics,
and performance dashboards.
Third is a federated
learning architectures.
Now let's revisit federated learning, but
from a privacy first perspective, rather
than sending a raw data to the cloud,
models are trained locally on school
servers or, or even teacher laptops.
Only the learn weights, not the data
are sent back to the central system.
A real world example comes from a
Canadian province where 42 schools
participated in a federated model to
identify learning delays post COVID.
This strategy preserved full
compliance with local privacy laws
while improving predictive accuracy
by 16% over a centrally 10 baseline.
On device inference prioritization on
device inference pushes the privacy
boundary even further here, students'
data doesn't even leave the device
at runtime models, run predictions
locally, for example, on a school
tablet or a server making it I for
behavioral models or assessments.
In Brazil, a school network used raspberry
pi clusters for local inference on
student attention monitoring tools.
This architecture allowed predictions
to stay entirely within the classroom,
ensuring 99% of the data locality
even in low bandwidth environments.
Conclusion why privacy first ML
lops is non negotiable in the
enterprise world, privacy features
are often add-ons on upgrades.
But in education, these are baseline
requirements, not optional layers as
we move forward, privacy preserving
techniques like these must be embedded
from the design phase of any ML
op workflows deployed in schools.
Not only does this protect
institutions legally, but it also
builds the trust that's essential
when students, parents and educators
rely on AI to shape academic futures.
Now that we have explored how to protect
privacy in ML ops pipelines, let's
address another critical challenge in
educational i ai, which is the bias.
Bias in educational AI doesn't.
Just affect accuracy.
It can amplify existing inequalities
from understanding the potential of
students from certain backgrounds to
misrepresenting learning challenges
due to language or age differences.
Unfair morals can do real harm.
So how do we catch and fix these
biases before they impact decisions?
Through the automated bias detection
mechanisms, which are now being
integrated directly into modern ML
O pipelines, this can be achieved.
Multidimensional fairness
metrics in education.
Fairness cannot be one dimensional.
Models must be evaluated across multiple
access, including social, economic
status, language proficiency, disability
status, and geographic location.
For instance, in a New York pilot
study, a dropout prediction model
showed 12 percentage performance
drop of students from English
as second language backgrounds.
By adding multidimensional fairness
checks, the school district corrected
this by adding language based
feature and retain the model age
appropriate evaluation frameworks.
Models must be developmentally aware, a
10 year olds learning patterns difference
dramatically from those of a 17-year-old.
Yet many AI tool use static benchmarks.
A good example in Finland bias
detection tools flag that reading
comprehension models built for older
students were misclassifying, anger,
anger learners as underperforming due
to natural vocabulary limitations after
adjusting for age appropriate metrics.
False negative rates drop by 22%.
Okay.
Next is the cultural context.
Awareness bias doesn't, does,
uh, just come from data.
It also comes from cultural misalignment.
For example, a model trained in a Western
education system might misinterpret
student silence as disengagement,
whereas in some eastern cultures, they
may reflect, respect or contemplation.
In India, a sentiment analysis based
feedback system had to be retained with
regional linguistic nuance dataset after
it misread passive positive student
responses as disengaged behavior.
Local collaboration is essential.
What works in Texas might not work in
Tokyo, CICD integration for bias testing.
Here where ML Ops becomes powerful
bias detection shouldn't be a
manual after, though it should
be part of your ci cd pipeline.
Every time a model is retained,
train, or pushed to protection,
a bias gate should check metrics
across all key demographics splits.
Microsoft's Fail, learn, and Google's
What if tool offer integrations for this?
Allowing real time flagging
when a model begins to diverge.
One university deployment saw violations
reduced by 48% within six months just by
implementing CI CD based fairness checks.
Final message.
If you want AI to be a force of
for equity in education, we must
hardcode fairness into the every
stage of the model lifecycle.
And thanks to low-code ML ops
platforms, these advanced tools, once
the domain of AI research labs can now
be used by teachers, administrators,
and education departments without
requiring heavy ML expertise.
We have discussed bias, privacy, and
democratization in ML ops, but how
do we actually structure ML ops to
support millions of students across
different schools, districts, or even
countries with drivers infrastructure?
This is where a distributed
ML ops architecture tailored
for education comes into play.
Unlike traditional centralized AI
pipelines, educational environments demand
a balance of governance, scalability,
local autonomy, and data privacy.
So let's explore how an adaptable
architecture works in this context.
This slide outlines a scalable and
privacy conscious ML lops architecture,
especially designed to meet the unique
needs of educational institutions.
We are moving from a monolithic
cloud only approach to a layered
distributed framework that accounts
for diverse connectivity levels,
privacy mandates, operational
flexibility and scalability needs.
Here is a layered architecture
breakdown, central training
infrastructure district or native.
This is a centralized brain for of
the architecture where AI models are
trained, tested, and governed at scale.
It acts as a central tower, enduring
consistency, compliancy, and reliability.
The core functions are aggregates.
An anonymized or synthetic student.
Data from schools handles training,
retraining and version controls.
Ensures complaints with loss like
used in US GDPR, from Europe,
PIP, they from Canada, et cetera.
Integrates bio detection, privacy,
preserving training and audit
logging here is a real world case.
The New York City Department of
Education runs centralized AI system to
analyze student progress and learning
gaps across 1.1 million students.
They use a custom ML ops platform
built on Azure and Databricks to
ensure privacy and consistency.
Second is the regional deployment
hubs, clusters, or province level.
These apps as distribution notes
that cache models locally and
support rapid low latency deployment
across geographically group schools.
Main core functions are pre-stage
updated models and assets, perform
local validation before full
deployment, and just model slightly
for regional content or curriculum
differences, and act as intermediate
repositories for edge deployment.
Benefits are like minimizes van traffic,
which is wide area network traffic,
enables differentiated rollout, simplifies
rollback in case of deployment issues.
Here is a real old case scenario In
India's thumb, Nado State, a government
backed EdTech system uses regional
data centers in Chennai and HOR to
serve over 30,000 government schools
across diverse connectivity landscapes.
Each hub handles localized distribution,
pushing updates to schools without
overlaying central servers.
Finally, the school level in inference
edge, ai, local devices, AI models
are executed on local devices.
Example, raspberry by tablets, school
servers, minimizing data transfer, and
improving privacy and responsiveness.
The core functions are performed
real time inference for things
like student engagement, adaptive
learning recommendations, real time
alert for learning difficulties,
retain raw student data locally.
And provide offline support, which is
crucial in local connectivity areas.
A real world case, uh, use case
for this category is in Rwanda.
Over 1200 rural schools use
Raspberry Pi powered local AI
models to assess literacy skills.
Results are processed offline and sync
weekly when internet is available.
This has reduced data
exfiltration risk by 85%.
This architecture reflects the future
of ML ops in education privacy.
First, locally adaptive, scalable,
and compliant designed for
connectivity constraint environments.
It empowers governments and schools
network to deploy fair, safe, and
effective AI at scale, even in
resource constraint or remote areas.
Let's now explore a crucial component
of ML ops in education, containerizing
models, serving specifically
designed for offline capability.
In many educational environments,
especially in rural district, low income
regions or even urban schools, with
aging infrastructure, reliable internet
access cannot be taken for granted.
This reality makes cloud T AI
solutions impractical or inconsistent.
So how do we overcome this?
The answer lies in containerization, a
modern software packaging strategy that
allows us to bundle AI models, runtime
environments, and dependence into a
self-contained unit that can run reliably
on premise even without internet access.
In educational ML ops, containerized
AI applications allow localized,
secure, and consistent delivery
of AI services directly on school
infrastructure, such as teacher laptops,
school servers, or student tablets.
Here on the key implementation
strategies, lightweight container images,
optimize it for educational hardware.
The first pillar is minimizing
the weight of containers.
Many schools still run on low spec
hardware, vehicle lightweight container
images, often under one 50 mp.
That can still deliver high
value a functions like grading,
tutoring, or content recommendation.
For example, a reading assessment
model was compressed using OS and
QUANTIZE to eight bit precision,
allowing it to run smoothly on a
raspberry PI four with two GB ran.
Progressive model loading.
Not all components of an AI
model needs to load at once.
With progressive loading, we can
prioritize loading critical model
components first, such as coding
or classification layers, and then
gradually load personalization
modules or visualizations if and
when resources are available.
Think of it like an AI that gets smarter
the longer it turns, but never blocks
learning even with minimal capability.
In intelligence synchronization
protocols, when connectivity does
return, we use synchronization
protocols that are smart and secure.
These protocols, buffer data,
locally encrypted and attempt
transition transmission only when
stable connectivity is detected.
This ensures no student data
is lost, even if the device
goes offline for days or weeks.
In Ghana's Eastern Pilot Project
schools with only four hours of internet
per week, still managed to sync over
93% of data logs using Delta updates
and RESUMABLE protocols like syc.
Local data caching with
privacy, preserving encryption.
We don't just cache
data, we do it securely.
Every interaction, score, or submission
is stored locally in encrypted form,
often using a ES 2 56 or lightweight
homomorphic encryption methods.
This protects sensitive educational
data even in shared classroom devices.
Graceful degradation pathways.
Finally, what happens if the AI model
fails to load fully due to power issues,
hardware crashes, or memory constraints?
We implement graceful degradation
where the system defaults to predefined
rules, cache outputs, or static learning
content, ensuring the students experience
is disrupted as little as possible.
A practical example, if you're writing
feedback model crashes, the system can
fall back to where Rubik based scoring
guide already embedded in the app.
To summarize containerized modeling,
serving is not just a DevOps convenience.
It's a strategic imperative for
ensuring that AI tools in education
are accessible, resilient, and
equitable, especially in connecting
connectivity constraint environments.
And as we scale AI in education,
this approach will be the backbone
for enabling consistency, privacy,
and functionality regardless of
a school's internet bandwidth.
Now that we have discussed deployment
and offline capabilities, let's focus
on a, on a critical lifestyle component
for any AI system in education.
Automated retraining, unlike
tactic software, AI model, lean
from learn from data, but they
also become outdated over time.
In education model, drift can be caused
by academic calendars, curriculum changes,
seasonal learning behaviors, or even
localized student progress PA patterns.
So how do we ensure our AI system remain
accurate, fair, and effective over time?
The answer lies in building automated
retraining pipelines, customized
for the operational and ethical
demands of educational environments.
The cyclical nature of retraining
pipelines as shown in the graphic.
The retraining process follows a
continuous loop that allows us to refresh
our models in a privacy preserving
context, sensitive and scalable way.
Let me walk you through
each phase of this pipeline.
The first phase is the
scheduled data collection.
It all starts with.
Schedule data collection at regular
intervals, say monthly or quarterly.
We aggregate anonymized model performance
logs from school infrastructure.
These logs include accuracy of
predictions, confidence levels,
engagement metrics, edge case flags.
Importantly, this process must be
compliant with data privacy laws
like FE, GDPR, or India's DPDP Act,
depending on where the schools are.
We use differential privacy or federated
integration techniques so that student
identifies never leave local devices.
Next comes distribution analysis where
we compare current data distribution
to those from previous cycles.
For instance, a model train in February
may begin underperforming in June due
to exam stress, summer learning loss,
or changes in students' engagement.
Drift Detection in education is
complex because you need to account for
seasonality and economic performance.
Separate natural learning
progression from true model drift,
detect regional disparities in
how AI is used or interpreted.
This is where education specific
drift detection frameworks become
essential, not just traditional
K tests or care divergence.
The next step in the.
Framework is the contextual retraining,
rather than retraining the entire
model, we use contextual retraining
approaches, which means we target only
on the underperforming components.
Example, feedback modules, prediction
heads focus on effective student segments.
Example, grade five, ESL,
learnings in roller clusters.
This saves compute, avoids over.
Fitting and ensure more
localized and equitable updates.
For example, in one district pilot,
only 11% of the models parameters
had to be updated to correct bias
against neuro divergent learners.
Multidimensional validation.
Once retrained, the module undergoes
multidimensional validation.
This testing isn't just about accuracy.
We look at fairness across gender,
linguistic background, disability
status, interpretability metrics.
Example, it's a model's
feedback, actionable
bias, or its using synthetic
counterfactual data.
A retrained model that performs well
only for urban students, but degrades
for rural schools is immediately
flagged in real world deployments.
Models that pass five plus geo, geo,
uh, demographic, uh, validations
were found to main gain up to 97%
Fairness, parity in public school
settings, graduated deployment.
Finally, we don't roll
out changes instantly.
We use grad, graduated deployment.
Start with pilot schools, monitor
outcomes for two, three weeks.
Get feedback from educators and
school admins, then roll out to
the broader district or region.
This prevents mass failure and
ensures human oversight at each step.
Why this matters in education,
unlike tech tech companies that can
retain models nightly with millions
of realtime users, school operates
on slower structural timelines.
You must respect the economic year.
Student stability and policy constraints.
These retaining pipelines balance
automation with caution, ensuring that
AI tool remains relevant and useful
updates don't introduce new bias.
The system evolves with
students not ahead of them.
In short, automated retraining
pipelines make educational AI systems
adaptive, safe, and sustainable.
They help us avoid model dk, uphold
ethical standards, and deliver consistent
personalized support to students,
whether in a major urban school or
a remote classroom in the mountains.
As we move from retraining pipelines,
let's now look at how large scale
collaboration across multiple schools
can be made, both powerful and privacy
respecting through federated learning.
Unlike traditional AI models that
rely on sending raw data to the cloud,
federated learning flips the script.
The model goes to the data instead
of the data going to the model.
What is Federated Learning in Education?
Federated Learning is a decentralized
machine learning approach where local
models are trained on individual
school devices and only model
updates, not student data, are
shared back to the central system.
This is especially, especially crucial
in education because schools are
spread across district with different
resources, bandwidths and IT policies.
Students data is highly
sensitive and centralizing.
It creates compliance risk in
rural and underserved regions.
Connectivity is sporadic,
but learning must continue.
Let's break down how it works in practice.
Local model training on school devices.
Each school trains its version on
model locally using only the student
data available within its premises.
We a smart tablet or a school
server or a classroom AI assistant.
For example, a middle school in
a tier three city can train a
reading comprehension model using
their own data on device, capturing
local essence, reading patterns
and curriculum specific nuances.
Encrypted parameter sharing one.
Local training completes.
Instead of sending raw data, each school
sends only encrypted model updates
to the district coordination server.
These updates could be gradient vectors,
weight, weight changes, performance
deltas all transmissions use end-to-end
encryption, such as TLS 1.3, and a S 2
56, and often pass through zero trust
architecture, ensuring the process
is tamper resistant and auditable.
Differential private receive
integration to award the risk of
reverse engineering student information
from gradients, which is possible.
In NA federated setups, we implement
differential privacy mechanisms.
This involves adding calibrated noise
to model updates so that no single
student contribution can be identified.
Even if a malicious actor access
the updates, they would learn
nothing individual or identifiable.
This satisfies legal mandates in
GDPR Article 25, which is Privacy by
Design, F-E-R-P-A, which is Student
Educational Records protection, and
India's D-P-D-P-A 2023, which is local
storage and processing of personal data.
Next is the adapt to AG
aggregation, strateg.
Once updates from all the schools
are received, the central server
does not average them equally.
Instead, we use adapt to aggregation,
which takes into account,
vary school sizes, demographic
diversities, update trustworthiness.
These strategies ensure fair
representation across districts.
Low-code in interface for simplicity.
To make federated learning accessible
to non-technical educators, we use
low-code platforms like automate
training, job triggers, visualize
model performance for per school,
provide compliance ready logs require
no advanced DevOps or ML expertise.
This is critical for scaling
federated learning in real world
school system, many of which lack
full-time data science staff.
To sum up, federated learning is
not just a technical innovation,
it's a governance breakthrough.
It allows us to honor privacy laws,
leverage local intelligence, and
enable district-wide learning,
progresses through collaborative
intelligence, not centralized control.
Up to this point, we have talked about
architectures, privacy deployment
strategies for AI in education.
But an equivalent important pillar of
ML Ops is monitoring, making sure our
models and systems continue to perform as
expected once they're in real world use.
Now in the most enterprise environments,
monitoring is somewhat easier because
the devices are relatively standardized.
Servers in data centers or companies
show laptops with similar configurations.
Education is very different.
Schools operate on on shoestring budgets,
often relying on a mix of newer devices,
older desktop, shared lab machines,
and even students' personal devices.
This creates what we call the
heterogeneous device ecosystem.
Why does that matter?
Because traditional one size fits
all, monitoring does not work here.
If we push enterprise grade monitoring
tools onto low end machines, they
will struggle just to keep up.
On the other hand, if we only apply
lightweight monitoring everywhere,
we lose the deep visibility needed
for high performance systems.
So the real challenging is finding
a balance, designing, monitoring
strategies that respect device diversity,
keep system relatable and remain
accessible to non-technical stakeholders
like teachers and administrators.
On this slide, I will walk you
through four key strategies that
make monitoring both practical and
inclusive in educational environments.
Resource aware metrics collection,
what it means, monitoring systems
adapt to the capability of each device.
And how it works.
High-end servers can collect
detailed metrics, while older
laptops may only track essentials
like uptime and memory usage.
Example, in a rural school with decade
old desktops, only basic health checks
run, so learning apps remains usable.
Meanwhile, an urban school with newer
hardware track advanced telemetry like GP
utilization for AI driven tutoring apps,
device specific performance baselines.
What it means, each device type
has its own normal performance
thresholds and how it works.
Instead of using one benchmark across
all devices, the system knows that a
Chromebook should not be expected to run
at the same speed as a lab workstation.
Example, a math learning app runs slower
on a low cost tablet, but that's expected.
The baseline is adjusted to
avoid constant false alarms.
At the same time.
If the same slowdown happens on
a powerful lab pc, the system
flag, it is a real issue.
Centralized monitoring
dashboards what it means.
Complex monitoring data is transformed
into simple visual insights through
low-code dashboards and how it works.
Teachers or administrators see
color-coded health indicators,
trend lives or alerts of roll logs.
And an example for this, a district admin
logs into a dashboard and sees school
is devices are healthy, but school based
hitting memory limits on older laptops.
This empowers them to act maybe
by shifting workloads or prior
prioritizing an upgrade without
needing deep technical expertise.
And finally, automated intervention works.
Flows.
What does this mean?
The system can respond automatically to
detect tissues, reducing downtime and
dependency on it staff and how it works.
Predefined rule, trigger actions like
rolling back a buggy model, reducing batch
sizes, or switching to offline cache data.
Example for this.
If a school's internet drops,
the AI app automatically switches
to offline inference mode.
Or if a new model starts slowing
down old machines, the system auto
automatically reverts to a previous
table version until it reviews it.
These four strategies, adaptive metrics,
tailored baselines, educator friendly
dashboards, and automated interventions
together ensure that monitoring isn't just
technically effective, but also practical.
In resource constraints schools,
the goal is resilience, keeping AI
systems running smoothly, even in S and
unpredictable classroom environments.
We have looked at architectures
and monitoring, but a key question
many institutions have is, how
do we actually get started?
Implementing ML ops in education
isn't a one step process.
It needs to be staged carefully
because schools have limited
resources wearing technical skills
and strict privacy requirements.
This roadmap breaks the journey
into four clear phases, foundation.
Scale and optimization.
Each phase builds on the last.
Ensuring institutions can start
small, prove value, and then
expand sustainably without
overwhelming their teams or budgets.
Phase one, the foundation, what it is,
setting up the initial low-code ml, lops
platform privacy frameworks and training.
This focuses on building a
secure foundation before scaling.
And in the example for this, a
districts in a low-code AI platform
that trains a small group of educators
and IT staff to manage deployments.
Privacy measures like differential
privacy and access controls are
ap, uh, are established upfront.
The phase second phase
is the pilot deployment.
What it is running small scale
pilots in selected schools with
different resource profiles.
This focuses on testing containerized,
model serving basic monitoring
and governance workflows.
And an example for this
is a rural school test.
Offline ready AI models to handle poor
internet via an urban school test.
Federated learning for scaling the
pilot reveals practical constraints like
certain devices needing lighter models.
The third is a scaled rollout.
What it is, expanding deployment
district-wide with localized adaptations.
This focuses on standardizing
governance, integrated federated learning
for collaboration across schools.
And example, once pilots succeed,
the district rolls out AI assisted
learning apps to all schools.
Models are turned differently
depending on bandwidth, but all share
updates through federated learning.
And the final stage is
the optimization phase.
This is the continuous improvement
through retraining and education
specific monitoring and focuses on
fine tuning, automated retraining
pipelines and dashboards.
Example, the system detects
that match models underperformed
for younger students.
A target retraining cycle is launched
and dashboards are updated to
highlight grade level performance
differences for administrators.
This phase roadmap ensures institutions
do not try to boil the ocean from day one.
Instead, delay a strong foundation,
test and control pilots expand in a
managed way, and then continuously
optimize This approach delivers immediate
wins while building toward long-term
scalable AI adoption in education.
Up until now, we have explored challenges,
architectures monitoring, and the roadmap
for rolling out ML lops in schools.
But at the end of the day, the most
important question people ask is,
does this really work in real world?
This slide captures the outcomes
we have seen when districts
adopted these approaches.
What's powerful here is that the
results span technical reliability,
cost efficiency, and human engagement.
In other words, it's not just about
keeping AI running, it's about
keeping teachers and students engaged
while saving schools money and
staying compliant and with privacy
regulations offline real reliability.
What does this mean?
AI tools continue functioning even during
internet disruptions and why it matters.
Many schools, especially rural
ones, face bandwidth issues.
An example, a literacy is assist app in
a rural district kept working seamlessly
during outages because of contain, uh,
containerized offline inference, ensuring
students didn't lose learning time.
Resource utilization, what it means?
Optimized edge deployment reduces
computing loads and costs.
And why does it matter?
Schools operate on tight
budgets with limited hardware.
An example, by using lightweight
containerized models, one district reduces
server costs and extended the usable
life of older laptops by two years.
The next one is a
non-technical engagement.
What does it mean?
Educators and administrators
actively participate in AI governance
through low-code tools and why it
matters without engaging educators.
AI remains a black box
and risk low adoption.
Example, teachers use a dashboard
to tweak content delivery thresholds
without calling it directly
improving classrooms engagement.
Implementation impact AI tools
scaled across multiple districts
serving millions of students.
Consistency, maintained model performance
in bandwidth constrained environments.
Teachers adjusted AI recommendations
without coding regulatory compliance.
Met privacy regulations across
regions using federated learning
and differential privacy.
Reduce the technical burden,
self-healing deployment architectures
maintain it interventions.
These results prove that when we
design ML lops for education with
low-code privacy, offline capability,
and inclusivity, it's not just theory.
It leads to a real world impact
keeping students learning, saving
schools money, empowering teachers,
and ensuring compliance at scale.
Now we have.
We have now walked through the
educational ML ops landscape,
the challenges schools face, the
architectures that can work, and even
real world results from implementations.
But I know that in a fast moving
conference setting like this, it's
easy to get lost in the detail.
So I want to step back and highlight
the three key takeaways that really
capture the essence of the entire talk.
These are the principles
that should guide everyone.
Anyone trying to scale AI
responsibly in education?
Think of them as a north star,
simple, practical, and non-negotiable.
If schools or districts follow these,
they won't just deploy a, they'll deploy
AI that's sustainable, equitable, and
trusted by educators and students alike.
Low-code empowers education.
One of the most important points
is that low-code platforms
break down technical barriers.
Instead of relying solely on
machine learning engineers, which
schools rarely have teachers and
administrations can participate directly
in AI deployment and governance.
This democratization makes adoption
much more feasible In education.
Example, a teacher adjusts
content delivery thresholds in
a dashboard, improving students'
engagement without any coding.
Privacy first by design In
education, privacy is not optional.
It's mandatory by integrating federated
learning, differential privacy
and data minimization, pipelines
From the very beginning, schools
can protect sensitive student data
while still leveraging AI insight.
Example, instead of sending raw student
data to the cloud, only encrypted model
updates are shared across schools.
And finally, offline Functionality is key.
Connectivity can be taken for
granted, especially in rural
or underserved districts.
Containerized serving with local
inference ensures AI tools keep
working even without reliable internet.
This isn't just a nice to have,
it's a critical requirement
for equity in education.
Example, a rural schools AI tutoring
system continues guiding students
during an internet outage, syncing
updates later when the network returns.
So to sum it up, AI and
education must be inclusive.
Privacy first and T local code EM empowers
educators to take part privacy, safeguard,
build trust, and offering capabilities,
ensure no student is left behind.
If we design with these principles, AI
can truly scale across education in a way
that is sustainable, far and impactful.
That brings me to the end of my talk.
I want to sincerely thank you all
for your time and attention today.
Educational ML Ops is not
just a technical challenge.
It's about making AI accessible,
equitable, and sustainable for teachers
and students who need it to the most.
My hope is that you leave here with
a few ideas on how local platforms,
privacy first design, and often
functionality can come together to
truly, truly democratize AI in education.
I would also like to thank conference
42 for creating this platform to
share ideas and all of you for
thoughtful discussion and innovations
you will take forward from here.
Thank you, and I would be
happy to take any questions.