Hey everyone, this is Dlip Kumar
and I'm thrilled to be here today.
I'm currently working as advanced
cloud engineering professional with
over 19 years of experience in the
information technology industry.
Over the past several years, I have
been deeply engaged in initiatives
that leverage artificial intelligence
and machine learning to solve critical
business challenges, and particularly
within the financial services domain.
My experience with Swift integration
onto Azure has provided unique insights
into how machine learning can enhance
fraud detection and risk management
In payment processing, I have actively
explored how to apply machine learning
models to improve security and efficiency
of financial transactions, optimized
resource allocation, and improve
predictive modeling for customer support.
Today we are here to explore how
we ensure these models can operate
effectively in the real time world.
I will demonstrate how ML Ops can
help scale the models for financial
systems and walk through the key
components of successful ML ops
strategy for financial institutions.
So we'll try to explore on
understanding the problems and
identify effective solutions that
is crucial for achieving success.
Ultimately, our goal is
to ensure success in that.
Financial industry so that fewer
individuals suffer from fraud.
We'll provide guidance on how to
implement the steps needed for AI models
to be reliable and capable of scaling
effectively with the financial sector.
Through this mops, principles can step
in, techniques, can help in creating
robust and highly effective ML pipelines.
Okay, so how the current state of
ml in financial services looks like.
So financial institutions have
increasingly realized that the machine
learning isn't just a passing trend,
it's truly changes the landscape, right?
So they are increasingly relying on ML
for the first application is a real world.
You, if you can consider that as a
realtime fraud detection, allowing us
to picture the potential prevention
of a fraudulent transaction.
So the models can catch the crime
instantly, avoid the loss for
all who are, who all involved.
So this will also contribute
to make an easier financial
system for every single one.
So additionally ML can make accurate
credit risk assessments and follow
specific financial regulations.
However lots of organizations
experiencing the complications
in implementing the above.
What are all the things that are there?
So usually we will not be able to
experience such kind of complications
when you try to follow the process or
the governance framework around it.
Putting models in place is often
done manually, like imagining a
team, taking a weeks to get set up,
putting systems in place, and also
installing code rather than focusing
on making their models better.
So the poor tracking of models
can cause them to shift over
time, losing their accuracy.
Governance gaps, create
complaints, problems for all
of those about things, right?
We will discuss how ML Ops has
solved all those issues, right?
So with that, so we can see how ML
Lops transformation opportunity is
going to be looking like for us, right?
So let's take a look at
what ML Ops really is.
So in short, mops are
machine learning operations.
We can say like it's the same
as how you call it as DevOps
development operations, right?
But for ML ops in, as it has a
foster deployment to speed up models.
So deployment of systems can occur
with just hours which has never
happened before due to the old method
old methodology of implementations.
So now lops can create an environmental
of enhancement, reliability,
therefore preventing of any issues.
So good collaboration with other
engineers is very important,
and lops can provide just that.
So in addition to the various
other great points the one thing
to highlight is the ML ops enhances
regularity, adherence, right?
So all of these things that ML Lops
provide can help create a strong
foundation for the AI models to develop.
So with these concepts and
more, an organization can scale
with agile management and be
set up for a very nice system.
So to help out all these kind of
implementation of ml. So with these
things like you can really achieve
what we are actually looking for.
So the core, core components of
financial ML lops think of these core
parts at the blueprint for building
a successful ML lops framework.
So they are the main building blocks that
connect to make a great and robust system.
So infrastructure automation
is the key point here.
These are the clouds to manage resources
and set up with infrastructure as a code.
So the whole system must
be defined as a code.
So ci cd pipeline automate the
process of building models.
Testing and deployment, all the actions
can be quickly done and automated.
Monitoring and alerting is the
place where everything is checked.
Always check if something is wrong or
not which is always a good thing, right?
Like whenever something is wrong,
like you immediately alert it.
So since that can cause if you handle
the alert well, it can significantly
avoid any issues to happen.
Governance framework makes sure
everything goes as per the plan.
In a regular regulatory
compliance point of view, right?
It's important to take
a note in governance.
So these are all the, these are
all for major for implementing
a financial ML strategy.
So infrastructure as a code
for ML neuro environment.
So it is extremely important to understand
how necessary infrastructure as a code
is in the financial sector, right?
So where regulations and safety and
security are very much important in
this financial institutions especially.
So if you, if there is no security,
there is so much of fraud to be
prone in those systems to be.
So that's why like you have.
We should really be focusing on isolated
development environment so that there are
no problems with current or new projects.
It's extremely important to test every
single step and also the complete
project you have to review thoroughly.
So there must be some sort of
production infrastructure so that
deployment is safe and secure.
So with the systems like
Terraform, it makes setting up
and running the systems easy.
You can also set your own security
in place with these systems.
So how CI ICD pipelines for
model deployment it's going
to be look like, right?
So the ci cd pipelines are like an
assembly line for artificial intelligence.
So this means every step can
move smoothly without breaking.
So CI I CD will help automate systems
with the steps like automated testing
and checking for a deployment.
And how the post
validations are happening.
Is there any pre-steps that needs to
be implemented before the deployment?
And all these things can come
into, continuous integration and
continuous deployment lifecycle.
So you can test as many as
areas using automated testing.
This makes it more accessible to detect
fraud and bad actors, especially, right?
So this way you can easily handle CIC.
When it comes to advanced monitoring
for financial ML models, so data
accuracy must be present for
the models will lose the edge.
So the way to solve this is
having a constant lance and
monitoring the data all the time.
So another thing is model metrics
needs to be tested constant,
constantly as well, right?
So this involves running through
different steps and setting
outcomes become the model.
So this constant cycle makes the
model accurate and ready to be
useful for the users to test it out.
So the last thing to do important
can start tracking to make sure
the data does not shift and change.
So this can be solved through
checking feature importance.
All of these helps improve
a model performance.
So how automated model model retaining
workflows that, we can imagine in this
particular scenario, like you have to
make sure the models don't lose relevance.
So keep in mind that the models
have to keep up with every change
that is out there to prevent this.
Automate models are there to help
out with every situation, key
components or drift detection to
see if the data changes, right?
So if the situation is a change in data.
Then next steps is to update
through the training pipeline.
After this is done, then everything is
done and the model should be ready for
you to use for a real world scenario.
Any example, all of this happens
through an automated components.
With all of this in mind, leading
firms can de, deploy models into just
hours versus it becoming take days
and deployment like so everything
comes down to a needing a quick
setup because all these settings
can be very difficult and slow.
So how ML governance and compliance can
be implemented for compliance models have
to go through the same rigorous steps.
The step.
The first step is to take when setting
up governance is the documentation you
need to document, model data, and steps
to make sure nothing bad will happen.
With all those in mind, you can follow
and automate systems when that occurs.
Compliance with government can
also occur in just more natural.
So cloud platform and implementation
patterns we can discuss, like to create a
model that cloud is very much, IM a factor
nowadays because everything is, cloud
version of data being a Azure platform or
Google cloud platform or AWS like whatnot.
Like you can consider any cloud, but
it lets you, create your own artificial
in inte platform and have what it
needs to be successful platforms
can do what they do best, right?
However, you must consider all
situations before making a choice.
All in all, it comes down to your
needs and situations to do customizing
systems to make them unique and
in sync with important great
artificial intelligence solutions.
So how real time inter like
scaling for financial systems.
So in the space of financial systems
like every second matters, as one
of the things that everyone expects
are 24 7 availability and zero
downtime for situations of fraud.
If one second there is a fraud
attack, there should be always
be severe, ready to deal with
these kind of issues immediately.
One of the strategies to do this is to
have servers that automatically adjust.
So that allows them to handle
any type of, volatility, right?
So you have to be ready
for any type situation.
AB testing frameworks
for model validation.
How you can do it before
every launch, right?
Like you always wanted
to test if it'll work.
The method you can implement
is using AB testing.
Ab, it makes sure that
each change goes smoothly.
You also need to make sure that they are
not destructive and that they are very
much safer to do and when it comes to
automated bias detection and mitigation
like in every system people come from
a different background, ages, and more.
You cannot discriminate
against anyone, right?
So it should be fair for in every AI
step that you are gonna implement.
So implement the right
process that we'll catch.
If AI is not what as expected,
so cross-functional ML ops team
structure, how it's going to be.
So for artificial intelligence
relative, you need to a solid
team in order to prevent this.
Everyone should work together.
So there should not be any team that,
that say we don't, we do not connect.
So we have to be very
very manageable at times.
Like with all the cross-functional ML
ops team structures, everything has to
connect seamlessly so everyone can work
their best and give the best results.
So key and next steps.
In summary, there is a lot a lot
that goes into the system, right?
As you all know, like you have to
monitor, automate, and be secure.
Everything has to work together.
But the highest chance of success, if you
are starting up, one of the main things
you should do is measure the situations.
To do this, you should measure
what is there, like what needs to
improvement, and then you are set to go.
These are all the main
components that we can consider.
This is what I can, I know I can
provide with my best experience.
So with all the information that I
have had by working with closely with,
many teams, many people in the past.
So it might be a useful session
for you folks, like hopefully it's
giving you good enough content.
Thank you all.