Hello everyone.
I'm Chita Eshi and I'm principal
Product Manager working on
the cybersecurity industry.
I have close to eight years of
experience working as a product manager,
mainly in the cybersecurity space.
In the last couple of years,
the importance of edge computing
has grown significantly.
With the increase in edge computing,
the security risk have also gone up.
So today I'm here to talk about
the importance of observability
to ensure edge devices are secure.
So let's get started.
Before talking about the security
challenges associated with edge
computing, let's talk about why edge
market size is increasing significantly.
First of all when all the applications
are running on the cloud, either
public cloud or private cloud.
The latency between the application
and the cloud is significantly higher.
However, if all those applications start
running on the edge, that reducing,
that reduces the network latency
significantly to mere millisecond.
As a result, applications that
need near real time response are
better suited for edge computing.
Second of all, operational efficiency.
Imagine a situation where your critical
applications are running in the public.
One, if the internet goes down, let's
take an example of a self-driving car.
Let's say self-driving car is running
in the remote location where there
is a limited internet connectivity.
What happens in that situation?
If there is a critical decisions that
need to be made by the self-driving
car, without the internet connectivity,
it won't be able to make the right
decision, and that is where the importance
of edge computing really matters.
With edge computing, even if the
internet connection is lost for the
timing, the application or the device
will continue to function as it is.
Ensuring the operation
resiliency as well as efficiency.
Last thing is the reduced bandwidth.
Imagine all the applications
running in the public cloud.
Then there will be a significant data
transfer between the application running
on the edge and rest of the database
running, or the rest of the applications
running on the cloud that will require
significant ban bandwidth consumption.
With edge computing, a lot of the data
processing happens locally, which results
in reduction in the bandwidth required.
Just now let's talk about
the US Edge computing market.
As of 2025, the US Edge computing
market is already over one $60 billion.
However, by 2034, it is expected to go.
As high as $1.5 trillion, which
is a growth of 25% year over
year, between 2025 and 2034.
Because of this high growth,
the importance of edge computing
as well as security associated
with the Edge computing devices
is increasing day by day.
Let's talk about the security challenges
associated with the Edge devices.
First of all, edge devices operate outside
the traditional network boundaries.
Today, most of the applications
are running on the public cloud.
However, there are some applications which
are still running on the private cloud.
Now, edge computing devices operate
outside this network boundary.
As a result, the traditional
monitoring tools that are monitoring.
Cloud applications as well as the
hybrid or on-prem applications,
they are oblivious to what is
happening on the edge devices.
Secondly, limited visibility.
The legacy monitoring system usually
lack the ability to detect edge specific
threats, compromises, or if there are
any unusual behavior in the edge devices.
Now because of that, attacker can take
advantage of this edge devices and
then they can treat edge devices as an
entry point to get inside the network.
Once they are inside the network edge
devices are obviously talking to rest
of the applications running on public
and private cloud as well, right?
Bad actors can take advantage of this
situation and once they are inside
the network, they can penetrate the
threats to the rest of the organization.
And that is why observability is so
important for all the applications
running on the edge because of these
threat challenges on the edge devices.
The threat landscape of the edge
devices has gone up significantly
in the last couple of years.
According to one of the recent studies,
45, 40 5% of the organizations have
experienced at least one significant
edge security incident in last one year.
Here are some of the ways that attackers
attack the edge device network.
First of all, the network
mentioned in the previous slide.
Lot of times edge devices
have limited CPU and memory.
As a result.
There is always a compromise between the
fast response and the security capability.
Now, lot of times because for edge
devices, speed is really important.
Lot of times network security teams or a
security team end up compromising on the
security capabilities of the Edge devices.
Now attacker can take advantage of
this situation to make edge device
as an entry point for their attack.
Attack.
Once the edge device is
infected, attacker will try to.
Move their threats or mal malware
laterally to the rest of the organization,
to the cloud devices or on-prem devices.
As a result, edge devices need
to be secured all the time.
The second is data breaches.
Many times the edge devices
are not properly secured.
There is a lack of observability on
the behavior of the edge devices.
And many times, many of these edge
devices have unencrypted data.
As a result, they become the easy
target for the bad actors, and
once bad actors have the access to
the edge devices, they can easily
exfiltrate the rest of the network has.
Finally, third thing is the DDoS attack.
The edge devices have limited capability.
To protect against attacks which
are sophisticated in nature.
With the beginning of AI era, botnets are
often designed to create the DDoS attacks.
Considering the edge devices have limited
capability to protect against such
attacks, on top of that edge devices are
not properly secured from time to time.
Edge devices are especially
vulnerable to DDoS attacks.
Because of this increased threat landscape
for the Edge devices, it is important
to continuously observe the edge devices
for their normal behavior so that we
can identify the difference between the
known normal behavior and the attack.
And on top of that, it is important to
secure the edge devices because they are
the extension of the existing network.
All the existing applications running
on public cloud and privately private.
Next, let's talk about the importance
of observability for your edge devices.
In order to identify the attack or
the malicious activity for the edge
devices, it is really important to
continuously monitor the edge devices
in real time in order to do that.
Re edge devices should be equipped with
smaller micro agents, which will be
able to detect the behavior of the edge
devices along with the CPU and memory
footprint of the applications based
on the subtle differences, indifferent
signals, along with CPU and memory
utilization, the observability tool.
Should be able to detect any suspicious
activity or unusual behavior.
For the Edge devices, this is
applicable not only for a single Edge
device, but this should be implemented
across all the Edge devices as well.
And with Observate observability
tool, you should be able to correlate
these signals, these metrics
across different edge devices.
So that you can identify
the attack in real time.
Once the attack or the unusual behavior
is identified, there should be a
automated process or automated defense
mechanism so that rather than waiting
for the manual intervention, the
observability tool or the security devices
should be able to take the necessary
corrective action within milliseconds.
So that Compromise device is
isolated, and that will ensure that
threats are not moving laterally
to the rest of the organization.
Now that we covered how to implement
observability tools and monitoring
tools for your edge devices in
your architecture, let's talk
about the impact of implementing
observability for your edge devices.
Here is the case study of the large.
Automotive manufacturing plant.
This particular customer
implemented edge security monitoring
for three straight months.
Within three months, they were able to
reduce the incident escalations by 78%.
Secondly, they were able
to identify 89% of the.
Unauthorized access attempts between the
edge system and the core infrastructure
that resided on public and private cloud.
Third advantage was they were able
to identify 80% of the critical
security anomaly within literally their
first hour of deploying the Observa
observability tool on their edge devices.
The end result was that after introducing
observability and monitoring tools
for their edge device, they were able
to reduce MTDD, which is mean time to
detection from 1 97 hours to only four
hours, which was a significant improvement
on on how they were implementing
edge security for their environment.
Before talking about how to implement
observability and monitoring for your
edge devices, let's talk about how to
secure edge devices because monitoring and
observability are just a starting point.
So here are some ways, first of
all, continuous authentication.
So all the devices and all the users
should be authenticated all the time.
The normal policy would be,
verify everything, trust nothing.
And this aligns with the zero
trust architecture as well.
The second most important thing to do is
provide the least privilege enforcement.
Basically, if an employee is requesting an
access to any particular resources, either
on the edge device or on the public cloud.
We should be providing minimum privileges
to that employee to get the work done.
More the privileges for that person, the
higher the chance that if the vulner,
if that particular user is compromised,
it'll in impact or infect the rest the
other parts of the infrastructure as well.
Third important thing to do is
implement the micro segmentation.
What microsegmentation is to divide the
network, either on the edge or on the
cloud, into different subsections so that
even if one of the devices either on the
edge or on the cloud are infected, it
won't, the threat won't spread to the rest
of the infrastructure easily so that you
can minimize the impact of the breach.
And third or the last important thing
is to implement the runtime protection.
Even after implementing all these
policies, there are chances that your
applications running are impacted by
unpatched and unknown vulnerability.
One example I would like to give
here is the log four J vulnerability.
Log four J.
Vulnerability was detected in
the software in December, 2021.
Even though it existed in a
software for seven plus years.
So even after implementing all the
right measures, it is possible that
you might be impacted by unpacked and
unknown vulnerabilities, and to protect
against those, you need to have the
runtime security protection in place.
So here are the steps you can
take to secure your edge devices.
Please note that monitoring is just
the first step You need to implement
these additional measures to ensure
your edge devices and the rest of
the infrastructure are secure from
the malware and the bad actors.
Before talking about how to implement
monitoring and observability
for your edge devices, let's
think about our overall goal.
In the large organization you would have.
The devices across devices
and applications across
all different environments.
Lot of the organizations today would
have applications running on cloud.
That includes AWS or Jaw, GCP, and some
of the other cloud providers as well.
They would also have some applications
running on premises system like Red
Hat, OpenShift, ESXI, and others.
On top of that, they will have
the Network, secu Network fabric.
From which all the data is being
transferred from one place to the other.
So all these things have
to be secured properly.
On top of that, there should be an
end-to-end visibility and monitoring
across all these different infrastructure,
including cloud, infrastructure,
on-prem, and network fabric.
Additionally.
Lot of the companies are starting
to have the edge devices on top
of that manufacturing plant.
Also have the IOT devices, which are
monitoring different parts of the plant.
And then they are providing
the critical data all the time.
So in order to get end-to-end visibility
across the entire environment, it is
really important that observability
across all these different tools
are integrated so that you can get.
Complete visibility into your infra
entire in infrastructure, irrespective
of whether your applications are running
on public cloud, private cloud, on
premises, on IOT devices, and so on.
And once you correlate this data from D
coming from different devices, then only
you will be able to have centralized
visibility, centralized monitoring,
and that will help you enhance your
security capability in the long run.
Finally, let's talk about how to
implement and introduce monitoring and
observability for your edge devices.
First of all, start with the assessment.
Identify all the edge devices and
critical vulnerabilities or point
of vulnerability that you think
that are part of your edge device.
Second point would be to
identify the most critical edge
device that you want to secure.
Once you have identified that, start
implementing the observability and
monitoring tools for a single edge device.
And over time, implement the
performance to see how you are able
to reduce your mean time to detection.
How are you able to ensure reduction
in lateral movements of threats as
well as other improvements once you
have seen significant improvement
in your mean time to detection.
Also called as MTTD.
You can integrate your edge monitoring
with the rest of the platform.
And the rest of the platform
could be running on the public
cloud, private cloud, anywhere.
That way you can get consolidated single
pane of monitoring and observability
across your entire environment.
Once you feel that you have integrated
your single or few of your edge
devices with the rest of the platform,
the next step and the final step
would be expand that to your entire
Edge network available anywhere.
This will be specifically
challenging for the organizations
that have edge devices worldwide.
So by integrating all the devices
worldwide with your entire in rest
of the infrastructure that includes
public cloud, private cloud, network,
fabric, IOT devices, you will be
able to get a centralized visibility.
And monitoring across your entire devices.
And that is the roadmap that we laid
out in the previous previous slide.
So once you have that visibility, you will
be able to completely visualize everything
that is going in your environment.
And over the long run, you will
be able to improve the security
posture of your edge devices, as
well as your entire infrastructure.
With that, I want to
thank you for your time.
Hope this session was helpful on how
monitoring and observability for your edge
devices, plays a critical role in securing
your edge infrastructure as well as your
entire organizations in infrastructure.
Thanks a lot and feel free to reach out to
me if you have any additional questions.
Thank you.