Good afternoon everyone.
My name is She Gupta, and I'm thrilled
to be here today to talk about a
truly transformative trend in the
world of artificial intelligence.
Serverless AI rise revolutionizing
ML deployment with scalability
and cost efficiency.
Over the next 25 to 30 minutes, we'll
explore how serverless computing is
not just an incremental improvement.
But a paradigm shift in how we
manage and deploy AI solutions.
We'll see how it is enabling organizations
to build and scale AI's application
faster, more efficiently, and often
more cost efficiently than ever before.
As you can see, serverless computing
has already made a significant
impact offering automatic scaling.
And paper use models without the headache
of managing underlying infrastructure.
The market itself valued at USD
17.2 billion this year is projected
to grow significantly hitting
A-C-H-E-R of 14.1% through 2030.
Okay.
This presentation will delve into how
serverless AI is streamlining deployment,
boosting resource utilization, and
ultimately accelerating innovation.
Let's begin.
So what exactly is serverless
AI architecture at its score?
It operates on an event driven model.
This means computing resources are
dynamically allocated only when needed
in response to specific triggers.
Think of it like a light switch.
The power is only on
when you flip the switch.
The key components as illustrated
here include even sources,
function, containers, supporting
services, and finally, resource
management for even sources.
These are the triggers I
mentioned, things like API request.
Changes in data or schedule task,
they initiate the process function.
Containers.
These are stateless environments where
your AI model code actually executes.
Stateless is crucial here.
Each function in vocation is
independent, which is what allows
for massive parallelization
and seamless automatic scaling.
Third, supporting services.
These are essential backend components.
Authentication data, storage
monitoring, all managed for you.
And finally, resource management.
The platform handles the
dynamic allocation of resources
based on the workload demands.
This architecture significantly reduces
the burden of infrastructure management.
In fact, organizations leveraging
this approach have reported up
to a 68% in the reduction in
infrastructure management overhead.
That's a huge win.
Freeing up teams to focus on building
great ai, not managing servers.
Now we understand the architecture.
Let's look at how serverless AI
solutions are typically implemented.
It generally follows a cyclical pattern
as you can see in the diagram model.
Encapsulation first developer
package, their machine learning models
within their stateless functions.
These functions are often triggered
via STTP request for inference points.
Or other events.
The beauty here is the minimal IV
infrastructure code, second deployment.
Next, this packaged function, which
was created in model encapsulation,
is pushed to a serverless platform
along with its trigger configuration.
Third execution.
When an event occurs, say an API call with
new data, the function runs performing
the AI task, like making a prediction.
Scaling and critically, the
platform automatically allocates
resource based on the demand.
If you see a sudden spike
in request, it scales up.
When demands drop, it scales down.
You only pay for what you use.
Modern serverless platforms are quite
versatile, supporting diverse simul
frameworks and model architectures.
We are seeing successful deployments of
complex deep learning models ranging from
75 MB up to 1.8 gb, all while maintaining
impressive performance, like an average
inference time of just 1 1 2 milliseconds.
Can you believe that?
Okay, so of course not all serverless
platforms are created equal.
Choosing the right one is critical
for AI deployments, especially when
considering performance, cost, and
specific functionalities like GPU support.
This slide presents a snapshot from
standardized benchmarking studies that
used identical deep learning models.
RESNET 50 birth base, and YOLO V
four across major cloud providers.
Let's talk about GCP Google Cloud
Functions, which is a product of GCP
standouts for an image classification
workloads demonstrating the lowest average
inference latency at 1 1 2 milliseconds,
and also the fastest cold start time.
Their GPU support is also
quite comprehensive for Amazon.
AWS Lambda follows with a strong
1 36 millisecond inference latency
and their Snap Start feature.
Significantly improved Cold start
time for Java functions with
good but limited GPU support.
Currently it's on T four.
Azure functions for Microsoft
offers the most consistent
cloud Cold Start performance and
container based GPU supports.
Last but not the least, A BM
Cloud functions while cap.
A capable platform currently shows
slower inference and cold start
times in these benchmarks and lacking
direct GP support for function.
Let's see, what's the key takeaway here?
It is the cold start, the initial delay.
When a function is invoked after a period
of inactivity, it is called a cold start.
This could be a significant
factor, especially for A
GPU accelerated functions.
Google Cloud functions, for
instance, showed 58.7% faster
initialization time for these.
So depending upon your specific AI
workloads, sensitivity to latency.
And the choice of
platform matters greatly.
Okay, so now let's talk about the
key advantages of serverless ai.
The benefit of adopting serverless
AI are compelling and transformative.
Let's look at some numbers here.
It has 64.8% deployment time production.
Imagine cutting your deployment
model cycles from an 85 hertz
down to approximately 29 hours.
This is a reality for many teams adopting
serverless, a massive improvement
compared to a traditional infrastructure.
79.3% resource utilization improvement.
Serverless ensures you are using
computing resources much more efficiently.
No more over provisioning services
servers that said ile, most of
the time, 38.4% cost reduction.
This directly translates to
average savings compared to
the traditional deployments.
As you are only paying for the
compute time, you actually consume.
99.95% deployment availability.
This high reliability is inherent in the
managed nature of the serverless platform.
So to conclude, as mentioned earlier,
automatic scaling capabilities are a
game changer for various AI workloads.
Platform can scale from handling 40
requests per second to over 4,200 requests
per second in just over three seconds,
all while maintaining the response
time of under 23, 2 35 milliseconds.
This agility is incredibly valuable.
Okay, so let's make this entire numbers
concrete with a real world example
from the financial services industry.
A leading global investment banking was
struggling with the scalability for their
traditional risk analysis infrastructure.
They had 38 dedicated high performance
servers, but they were operating at an
average utilization of only 31.7% A.
So it's a classic case of over
provisioning and inefficiency.
They decided to migrate to
a serverless AI solution.
The migration took about 4.5 months.
And it wasn't without challenges
adapting to complex workloads and
ensuring regulatory compliance
were key hurdles, but the post
implementation results were substantial.
68.2% reduction in infrastructure
cost a direct result of
optimized resource utilization.
Three one 5% increase in
the peak processing capacity
they could now handle over.
12,000 concurrent model execution.
During the peak reporting periods,
something unimaginable before 62.2%
improvement in the processing speed.
Average latency for a risk analysis
dropped from 8.2 seconds to 3.1
seconds, and crucially for finance
enhanced regulatory compliance
through comprehensive audit trails
and improved security protocols
inherent in the new system.
This case study clearly demonstrates the
tangible business benefits of serverless
AI in a demanding regulated environment.
Now, let's take a real life
case study for another critical
center, which is healthcare.
A healthcare technology provider
specializing in medical diagnostic
tool faced similar challenge their
traditional server based architecture
for a medical image processing required.
Significant upfront capital
investment, specialized personal, and
suffered from a long infrastructure
provisioning timelines, averaging
86 days to expand service.
They adopted a serverless AI solution
using container I achieve learning models.
The migration spanned over seven
months, over three phases with a
strong focus on security, strict access
controls, and comprehensive encryption.
The outcomes were impressive.
First operational improvements, a 73.5%
reduction in the operational overhead.
Their auto-scaling capabilities now
support variable workloads from 50 to
5,000 images and R without any manual
intervention deployment efficiency.
Their deployment cycle for a
new model updates plummeted
from 36 days to just 4.8 days.
This allowed them to rapidly
interior research advances
into their production system.
Financial impact, they achieved a 41.3%
reduction in total expenses despite a two
one 2% increase in the processing volume.
Imagine that.
Number furthermore, the granular
price pricing models of serverless
server allowed them to better
serve smaller healthcare providers.
Again, we are seeing serverless
AI delivering significant
improvement in efficiency speed.
Cost even while handling
increased demands.
Okay, so now let's talk about
innovation and rapid development
and how it helps there.
Beyond operational efficiencies, a
serverless paradigm fundamentally changes
how organizations approach innovation
and rapid prototyping in AI development
organizations leveraging serverless
architecture have on an average, reduced
their development cycle time by 57.8%.
High performance teams are even
seeing up to a 73.5 reduction in time
to market for the new AI features.
That's incredibly fast.
Rapid prototyping in particular, sees and
impressive games development teams can now
deploy and test a new AI model variance
in just 3.4 hours compared to nearly 23
hours in the traditional environment.
This agility, flu fuels increased
experimentation, reduced complexity,
improved collaboration, and
accelerated time to market.
You can see the numbers here
for increased experimentation.
Hydration speed can be increased by 2.9 x,
allowing for much faster validation of AI
models and hypothesis teams have reported
a 68.4% reduction in the implementation
complexity, which also leads to decrease
in your bug density by 52.3% and
few post-deployment issues improved.
Collaboration code reusability
improves significantly with teams
reporting a 53.2% improvement.
Average feature deployment time
dropped from 15 days to just
under five days with a high first
deployment success rate of nearly 79%.
So it is safe to say that
serverless empowers AI teams to
innovate faster and more freely.
Okay, so now let's talk about
technical challenges and limitations.
It's important to be balanced
despite all the advanced advantages
which we have discussed so far.
Serverless AI isn't what isn't without
its technical challenges and limitations.
Cold start latency.
This remains one of
the significant issues.
Complex deep learning models can
experience significant delays up to
6.2 seconds during initial initiation.
While platforms are improving,
it is a factor to consider.
Memory limitation.
There are constraints on the model
size and the complexity that can
be loaded into a function's memory.
Execution time limits functions typically
have a maximum execution duration limits
ranging from two 50 to eight 50 seconds.
This affects nearly 39% of
the complex AI processing task
that might be longer running.
Vendor lockin dependency on
provider specific features and
services can make it harder to
migrate between the cloud members.
Imagine you started with GCP
and then you wanted to shift to
Microsoft in the between determine.
Imagine the number of times the number
of ads you have to spend a resource
constraint while scaling is automatic.
The available compute options, your
CPU types, memory configurations for
individual functions might be more limited
compared to dedicated virtual machines.
Especially for a very
large or specialized model.
In fact, over 82% of the enterprise
AI deployments encounter at least
one resource related constraint.
These are real considerations
that organization needs to plan
for when adopting serverless ai.
Okay, now let's talk about security.
Security is of course, paramount
in any AI implementation.
So first less introduces its
own unique considerations
compared for to the traditional
architectures isolation mechanism.
Functional isolation is a primary defense
against the cross tenant vulnerabilities.
Container-based isolations
used by many platforms provides
effective security boundaries.
For a vast majority, nearly 95%
of the common attack vendors.
Access control, effective identity
and access management is fundamental.
Around 69% of organizations are
implementing fine-grain access
control at the functional level,
ensuring functions only have
permissions they absolutely need.
The use of short-lived credentials has
been particularly effective, reducing
credential misuse incidents by over 72%
data protection, end-to-end encryption
strategy for data addressed in transit.
And during processing are
crucial and well supported by
serverless platforms compliance.
Comprehensive logging and monitoring
capabilities are available, which
are essential for meeting regulatory
requirements and for auditability.
While the attack surface ships
with serverless robust security
practices and platform features
can effectively mitigate risks.
Okay, so now let's talk
about the future outlook.
Looking ahead, the serverless AI
landscape is set to evolve rapidly.
We are expecting significant
transformations in the serverless
platform with increased specialization and
optimization, especially for AI workloads.
One exciting concept is nano functions.
This represents a ship towards
even smaller execution units.
Capable of executing specific
components of a computational
graph rather than the entire model.
This could lead to more precision,
precise resource allocation, improved
parallelization and early results
already showing a potential 37.8%
reduction in the overall execution time.
Here's a potential timeline
of emerging trends.
Let's quickly go over 25 to 26.
We likely see standardized
function interfaces and deployment
specification emerge, which will
help reduce vendor lockin service.
Lockin concerns 26 to 27 expect an
ultra light weight container format
optimized for AI workloads 27 to 28.
Predictive scaling algorithms
could achieve a very high
frequency in workload forecasting.
28 to 30 platforms will very
likely incorporate more inbuilt
capabilities for responsible ai,
such as bias detection, fairness
evaluation, and explainability tools.
Therefore, the future of serverless
AI is bright and full of innovation.
Okay, so to recap, serverless AI
offers a powerful new way to deploy
and scale machine learning models.
Bringing significant benefits in
terms of cost, efficiency, speed,
scalability, and fostering innovations.
While challenges exist, the ongoing
advancements and a clear value proposition
make it an interesting, compelling choice
for organizations across industries.
Thank you very much for
your time and attention.
I'd be happy to answer any
questions you may have.
Thank you.