Hi good morning everyone.
I'm Gpro Oli from G two Solutions and it's
a pleasure to join you today at Con 42.
Let's talk about something most
financial organizations fear,
but clearly rarely see coming.
Systemic risk, hiding in plain sight.
Our topic, observing the invisible
cloud native observability for
real-time financial risk detection.
In the session, I'll walk you through
how we turn bankruptcy monitoring once
a slow reactive black box process into
a transparent cloud native pipeline
that delivers real-time insights.
Measurable, ROI and
audit ready compliance.
Risk reduction system architecture.
We be, we began by reimagining
our entire architecture.
We ingest data from multiple sources,
legal filings, credit scores,
transactional databases, and third party
feeds, but raw ingestion isn't enough.
We built a serverless ingestion
layer using cloud native event
driven functions that normalize and
processes the data as it arrives.
From there, Apache Spark takes over.
It performs complex entity resolution,
matching data names, identifiers,
and even patterns across the data
sets to generate a risk scores.
Apache Airflow orchestrates
this entire pipeline managing
dependencies and execution schedules.
What sets the system apart
is embedded observability.
Unified logging, distributed tracing,
and real-time metrics are foundational.
We monitor not just for failures, but for
risk, signal quality, pipeline health,
and regulatory thresholds in real time.
The visibility crisis.
Before this transformation, we faced
what I call a visibility crisis.
Legacy systems were siloed and manual.
When things broke, they did.
We couldn't trace the root cause.
Risk signals took hours
or days to surface.
Compliance teams spent
weeks teaching together.
Audit trail that were never met.
We reconstructed, and every blind spot
was opportunity for financial loss.
We weren't just lacking the observability.
We were operating in darkness.
That crisis forced a mindset.
Mindset shift.
Observability couldn't be a bolt-on.
It had to be built in
our observability approach.
So we built observability in from
day one, full stack inability from
ingestion to orchestration to alerting.
Distributed tracing using open
telemetry to track every transaction
from entry point to risk score.
Internet logging, not just technical
data, but logs and raised with businesses.
Context like case type, risk level, and
client integrated metrics like we tied
system KPIs like latency and throughput
to business outcomes like detection,
accuracy, and compliance Completeness.
This latest bridge engineering
and compliance, both now
speak a shared language,
observable serverless architecture.
Let's dig into architectural
observability layers, ingestion layer.
We capture quality metrics for
every document, format, issues
missing fields, delays in real time.
Follows part, workflows every
transformation is traced, enabling us
to monitor matching precision, detect
bottlenecks, and measure scoring contents,
airflow pipelines, each step logs,
validation status, error categories,
retry rates, and regulatory checkpoints.
This isn't just observability for
uptime, it's observability for trust.
Knowing the system works and.
Understanding why it works.
Next comes our trans
transformation results.
Here is what we achieved.
We reduced average processing
time by 78, percentage from two
hours, 40 minutes to 31 minutes.
Improved detection accuracy by 92%
risk alert now reach decision makers
in under 45 seconds and throughput.
Three 50% with 99.97 up 10.
These variant vanity metrics, each one
translate into less risk exposure, faster
interventions and lower compliance costs
with reduction through visibility.
One of our biggest wins.
Error reduction false
positive dropped by 87%.
False negatives, the most
dangerous ones fell by 94%.
Time orders and data mismatches
are now detected and resolved
in the early, early in the flow.
This has slashed wasted analyst hours
and prevented missed bankruptcies,
both, which directly protect our
clients and reduce operational burden.
Building observable components
we didn't get here by chance.
We established a unified logging strategy,
structured log echo service services, and
reached with client and risk metadata.
We deployed end-to-end
tracing with open telemetry.
Now every match and
transformation is traceable.
We implemented multidimensional metrics,
not just system health, but kps like
documentation, completeness and detection,
LA latency and match conference.
Now engineering and
complex compliance teams.
Sharehold shared dashboards, share
alerts, solve problems together.
Here comes the compliance transformation.
Client compliance has
senior radical shift.
The documentation completeness is 97%.
Audit prep time down by 71%.
Evidence is 89% faster.
Audits that took weeks now take hours.
Every risk signal has stressful path.
Every regulatory inquiry has
structured reliable evidence behind it.
This level of visibility
doesn't just reduce risk.
It builds credibility with
regulators and stakeholders alike.
Dashboard design principles,
dashboards are more than just charts.
You know that, right?
Executives get KPIs and financial impact.
Engineers get deep dives into
task failures and latencies.
Compliance team get
traceability and alert blocks.
We apply business context integration.
Every technical metric is paired
with your business indicator, and
we use historical correlation tools,
identifying patterns, emerging threats,
and opportunities for prevention.
Before issues reoccur
our implementation roadmap.
Our rollout followed a clear roadmap.
First, the telemetry gap assessment
mapping what was missing across
tech and business layers.
Second instrumentation, adding,
logging, tracing, and metrics across
serverless park and airflow dashboarding.
Designing role specific views
with stakeholder feedback.
Next enablement training teams,
creating playbooks and embedding
observability into our cultures.
Each step delivered immediate
value while building toward fully
observable ret resilient pipeline.
Key takeaways and looking ahead to wrap
up here are four principles we believe in.
Designed for business context metrics
should matter to your mission.
Built it in not on observability
should be part of your architecture.
Enable end-to-end visibility across
all layers from ingestion to alert,
quantify the value, so how it improves
risk detection and compliance speed.
Looking ahead, we are exploring AI
augmented observability, using machine
learning to detect hidden risk signals
and optimize compliance at scale.
Thank you for your time.
I'm happy to take your questions or
connect afterwards to discuss how
observability can reshape your financial
risk systems just like it did two hours.
Thank you so much.