Observability  without  identity  is
like  using  maps  without  landmarks.
No  matter  how  detailed  you  are,  you
can  never  get  to  where  you  are.
My  name  is  Cynthia  Akiotu,
a  cyber  security  analyst,  and
I'm  happy  here  today  to  be
here  today  presenting  this.
Intriguing  topic.
Access  is  the  new  bridge.
Why  observability  must
start  with  identity?
I  would  like  to  ask  this  question.
When  last  did  you  conduct  access
reviews  in  your  organization?
Or  how  often  do  you  conduct
access  reviews  in  your  organization?
Is  it  automated?
Is  it  manual?
Or  you  don't  even  conduct  actor?
I  would  like  to  tell  you  to
try  and  conduct  access  reviews
and  you  might  just  be  surprised
in  what  you  will  find  in  your
system  or  within  your  environment.
The
blind  spot  in  today's  observability.
Most  tools,  or  most  tools,
observability  tools  we  use  in
our  organizations  are  good  at
checking  logs,  metrics,  traces,
like  your  downtime  in  the  system,
or  the  spike,  there's  a  spike  in
your  system,  checking  the  system
health,  checking  the  server  health,
but  there's  a  missing  link.
Can  these  observability  tools  or
these  logs  also  show  who  did  what?
Was  this  downtime  as  a  result  of
the  activity  of  a  particular  user?
Was  the,  these  spikes  in  our  API,
was  there  as  a  result  of  elevated
permissions  or  misuse  privileged?
So,  this  is  the  blind  spots.
in  today's  observability,  most
observability  tools,  we  are  seeing
these  beautiful  logs,  these  metrics,
these  dashboards,  but  there's
no  identity  contest,  there's  no
synergy  between  the  traditional
observability  tools  and  our  identity
and  assets  management  tools.
And  this  creates  a  big
vacuum  in  organizations,  Those
days  we  invest  so  much  on  firewalls.
Permeter  security.
But  now,  identity  is  the  gateway
and  the  entry  to  our  resources.
This  brings  me  now  to  this.
Identity  is  the  new  perimeter.
Identity  is  the  real  attack  surface.
Identities  was  attributed  to
just  humans  or  human  users.
Now  we  have  managed  identities,
we  have  service  principles,
we  have  bots  in  our  system
acting  on  behalf  of  users.
With  the  complex  nature  of  our
technology  landscape  and  the  advent
of  artificial  intelligence,  we've  seen
lots  of  things,  heard  lots  of  things
like  AI,  Agents  working  in  our
systems,  bots  working  in  our  systems
and  all  these  now  have  identities.
Hackers  no  longer
put,  initiate  malwares.
They  are  logging  in  and  moving,
they  log  in  secretly  and  move
laterally  within  our  networks,  our
perimeters  without  getting  unnoticed.
About  80  percent  of  breaches
now  are  all  related  to  identity.
We  have  the  most  common
identity -related  breaches.
We  have  insider  threats.
As  they  always  say,  we  are
as  strong  as  our  weakest  link.
Insider  threats  are  employees,
vendors,  third  parties,
affiliated  to  organizations.
Who  may  innocently  or  even
maliciously  gain  access  to  our
sensitive  information  and  leak
it  out  or  use  this  information
in  our  organization  to  the
detriment  of  our  organizations.
Unauthorized  access.
We  have  audit  violation  and
privileged  misuse  of  rights.
This  is  the  most  powerful
one  where  an  admin  can
elevate  his  or  her  rights.
and  use  it  to  conduct  something
malicious  within  our  organization.
I'd  like  to  give  an  example  in
May  2023,  I  think  to  be  precise,
Tesla,  ex -employees  of  Tesla  leaked
or  divulged  sensitive  information
of  employees,  about  700  employees
in  the  organization  to  the  media.
This  personal  identifiable
information  include  names,  of
the  employees,  their  social
security  number,  payroll  data.
As  you  can  see,  these  are  employees
who  had  access  to  secret  and
confidential  information  and  then,
use  those  privileges  to  gain  access
into  the  sensitive  information
and  violated  the  company's  policy.
because  I  know  normally  as
an  employee,  when  you  join  an
organization  you  should  be  happy.
OK,  Ok,  now  we  are  going  to
see  how  to  make  sure  that  we
sign  some  agreements  or  non
-disclosure  agreements  and  all  that.
So  this  is  how  we  see  the
easiest  way  to  our  perimeter.
It's  our  identities.
I'll  now  like  for  us  to  see
the  visibility  gap  between  our
identity  and  assets,  management
tools  and  our  observability  tools.
I  like  to  put  this  quadrants  here.
This  quadrant  as  you  can
see  This  quadrant  as  you
can  see  We  have  the  identity
visibility  and  risk  awareness.
The  identity  visibility,
basically,  is  we  are  aware  of
the  identities  in  our  systems.
We  know  their  names.
We  know  the  credentials
of  these  identities.
Then  the  awareness  or
risk  awareness  is  we  can
easily  monitor  our  systems.
At  the  system  monitored,  can
we  monitor  our  activities
within  our  systems?
But  now  the  main,  what  this
quadrant  is  looking  at  is
the  likely  challenges  we  may
face  when  there  is  no  synergy
between  our  identity  and  access
management  and  observability  tools.
The  first  quadrant,  which  is  at
the  top,  the  green  one,  I  like
to  call  it  the  non -known,  but
I  call  it  the  visible  fortress.
Why  do  I  call  it
the  visible  fortress?
Because  the  identity  and
the  observability  tools
are  working  hand  in  hand.
We  know  what  users
are  in  our  systems.
We  know  what  they  are  doing.
We  know  the  resources
they  are  assessing.
We  can  track  their  activities.
That  is  the  known  known.
And  sometimes  some  people
call  it  the  safety  net.
But  also,  even  within  that  quadrant,
the  known  known,  there  is  the  risk.
of  overconfidence  yes  because
sometimes  you  feel  you  have  the
right  policies  in  place  we  have  on
boarded  our  systems  properly  we  have
different  signals  device  are  compliant
we  have  our  identities  all  in  place
we  have  good  life  cycle  policies  to
see  when  an  employee  is  is  in  the
organization  and  when  he  exits  the
organization  after  changing  different
roles  But  there's  also  an  issue  of
complaisance  where  an  organization
becomes  so  relaxed  and  then  forget
to  monitor  or  conduct  continuous
access  reviews  of  the  systems.
In  2022,  an  employee  in  Uber
got  compromised  as  a  result
of  MFA  fatigue,  multifactor
authentication  fatigue.
She  was  sent  this  login  approver
attempt  several,  until  she  clicked
that  link  and  that  exposed  Uber.
So,  the  identity  of
the  user  was  known.
The  systems  of  course  are  monitoring
activities,  but  at  that  point  it
will  be  difficult  because  the  issue
is  the  system  will  flag  this,  flag
the  identity  as  an  illegitimate  user.
Thank  you.
was  tracking  these  activities
without  knowing  that  the
system  has  been  breached.
Let's  go  to  the  right,  the
top  right  quadrant,  which
is  the  known  or  known.
I  like  to  call  it
identities  living  in  fog.
Imagine  handling  the  keys  to
someone  or  giving  the  keys  to
your,  of  giving  the  keys  to
your  company,  or  let's  just
say  you  have  a  small  office.
with  several  rooms.
You  give  the  keys  to  those
of  that  office  to  a  friend.
Immediately  you  give  that
key  to  your  friend,  you
don't  even  care  what  rooms
your  friend  goes  to  check.
You  don't  care  what  wardrobes
your  friend  is  checking,  what
files  in  your  company  or  your
house  your  friend  is  checking.
So  this  is  what  I  call
the  known  or  known.
The  identity  is  known,  but  you
are  not  tracking  or  monitoring
activities  in  your  system.
With  the  use  of  AI,  artificial
intelligence,  we  have  shadow  IT  now.
Employees  downloading  AI,  large
language  models,  let's  say  for
example,  chat  GPT  and  using
it  for  daily  tasks  in  the
organizations  without  being
unnoticed  by  the  IT  departments.
Two  dummies.
There  might  be  data,  there
will  be  data  exfiltration
where  these  employees  diverge
sensitive  information  into  these,
um,  large  language  models.
This  is  a  big  risk  because  I
call  it  the  familiarity  bias.
You  are  familiar  with
these  identities,  oh,  these
are  my  employees,  but  the
activities  of  these  employees
are  not  being  tracked.
That  is  where  you  have  on
-track  software  as  a  service.
There's  a  free  software
on  the  internet.
An  employee  sees  that  software  on
the  internet,  downloads  it,  and  use
his  office  credentials  to  access
these  resources  without  being  noticed.
Let's  go  to  the  bottom  quadrant
to  the  left,  the  unknown  known.
The  unknown  known,  I  like  to
call  it,  um,  The  ghost  access
is  basically  like  seeing  your
infrastructure  on  a  dashboard
on  fire  without  knowing  who
lit  the  matches  or  without
knowing  the  cause  of  the  fire.
This  is  the  unknown
known,  the  unused  roles,
misconfiguration,  policy  gaps.
Recently,  where,  um,  a  retail
company,  yeah,  I  think  Mark  and
Spencer  through  third  party  was
briefed  as  a  result  of  third  party.
And  this  is  because  the  third  party,
for  example,  it  wasn't  known  that
it  was  through  the  third  party.
For  example,  through  the  third
party,  hackers  breached  into
Mark  and  Spencer's  system.
And  this  was  a  ransomware  attack.
Mark  and  Spencer  were
experiencing  some  fluctuations.
within  their  systems  without
knowing  what  exactly  has  or
what  caused  these  fluctuations.
So  this  is  a  case  of  unknown  known.
The  biggest  headache  of
SISOs  is  the  unknown  unknown.
I  call  this  the  invisible
people,  or  invisible
identities  in  visible  spaces.
this  is  where  we  you  can't  we  can't
I  identify  the  who  is  assessing  the
system,  neither  can  we  monitor  this.
For  example,  I  would
like  to  give  an  example.
Recently,  the  Lega  Aid  Agency
also  experienced  breach  where  their
system  was  assessed  and  hacked,
breached  with  personal  information,
personal  identifiable  information
of  Le  people  requesting  legal
aids  were  exposed,  information  for
the  past  15  years  were  exposed.
This  was  difficult  for  legal
aid  agency  to  know  because  at
that  time  it  was  an  antiquated
system,  an  abandoned  system,  so
there  was  no  way  they  could  even
track  or  know  what  was  going  on.
Another  recent  one  is  the  case
of  NHS  Trusts  were  through  a
vulnerability  of  their  third
-party  endpoint  manager,
mobile  device  management.
They  were  also  hacked  as  well.
And  then  these  hackers  gained  access
to  information  about  the  devices,
the  mobile  devices,  the  IMEI
numbers,  and  even  tokens  as  well.
which  could  even  be  used  in
the  long  run  for  impersonation.
So  now  we  can  see  the  risk  of
this  when  there's  no  synergy  or
interaction  between  our  identity
and  access  management  and
observability  tools  it  provides
a  big  vacuum  in  our  organization
and  an  easy  way  for  hackers  to
gain  access  into  our  systems.
I
understand  that  many  organizations
are  looking  at  investing  in  identity
tools,  identity  and  access  management
tools,  observability  tools,  but  let's
not  also  forget  that  there  are  lots
of  barriers  that  has  hindered  this.
Organizations  operating  complex
infrastructure,  like  you  have  a
hybrid  system,  you  have  on -premise
systems,  you  have  some  in  the  cloud.
So  Thank  you.
Thank  you.
It's  difficult  to  manage.
You  have  your  active
directory  somewhere.
It's  not  synchronized  to
your  intra -active  directory.
Or,  I  gave  an  example  where  in  an
organization,  um,  about  60  percent
of,  60  percent  of,  about  60  percent
of  organizations  state  that  they  have
21  disparate  identities  per  user.
Thank  you  for  watching.
information  or  systems  in  silos.
They  are  not  even  communicating
with  each  other  or  we  have  a
security  incident  if  incident
event  management  tool  which  is
not  communicating  with  the  identity
and  access  management  tool.
Let's  not  also  forget  costs.
Cost  is  a  big  problem  because
when  you  sometimes  will  purchase
this  cloud  infrastructure  we  are
told  we  need  to  purchase  licenses.
In  long  run,  we  also  told,
Oh,  there's  an  add -on
license  we  have  to  purchase.
So  this  keeps  on  incurring
costs  or  we  keep  incurring
costs  in  our  organization.
But  if  you  look  at  this  cost,
sometimes  some  organizations  may
want  to  invest  in  these  tools,
but  step  back  until  a  breach
or  a  security  mishap  happens.
And  then  they  are  now  on  their  toes
on  investing  on  this  infrastructure.
So  these  are  big  barriers  in  our
identity  and  our  identity  aware
observability  tools  and  operations.
So  how  do  we  observe  assets
before  it  becomes  a  breach?
The  first  thing  I  will
say  is  to  always  correlate
identity  with  system  events.
Let  identities  and  management  tools,
let  your  logs,  your  your  identity
and  access  management  tools  interacts
for  example  you  have  your  microsoft
sentinels  your  your  intra  id  you
should  have  these  tools  communicating
audit  permissions  in  real  time  this
era  we  are  in  is  no  more  about
static  role -based  access  controls
now  permission  should  be  audited
based  on  several  signals  based
on  location,  device  compliance,
the  identity  of  the  users,  all
these  brought  together  and  this
should  be  done  in  real  time.
For  example,  before  a  user  signs
in,  there  should  be  like,  to  be
able  to  assess  the  state  of  the
user  at  that  point  in  time  before
that  user  can  assess  any  resource.
There  should  be  detection
of  insider  threats.
Incorporate  tools  that  can  easily
check  for  the  use  of  shadow  AI.
scan  our  systems  and  see  different
resources  that  are  not  meant
to  be  used  in  our  environment.
Incorporate  tools  that  can
implement  data  loss  preventions
in  your  organization  to  avoid
exfiltration  of  sensitive  information.
Align  with  Zero  Trust.
As  I  said  earlier,  identity
is  our  new  perimeter.
So  we  should  always  assume
breach  and  always  verify  every
identity  before  they  can  gain
access  into  our  resources.
And  of  course,  we  should  enforce
least  privilege  compliance.
We  do  lots  of,  we
have  DEVRA  compliance.
From  our  health,  for  example,
we  have  HIPAA,  we  have  GDPR,  we
have  NIST,  we  have  many  of  them.
We  should  be  compliant  to,  to
these  rules  and  regulations.
And  this  will  also  help  us
in  auditing  and  checking  for
loopholes  in  our  organizations.
This  will  help  us  check  out  and
review  our  assets  and  see  what
is  lagging  behind  in  our  system.
Thank  you.
I  wouldn't  want  to  call  names,
but  we  have  lots  of  tools  that  we
can  use  now  in  our  organizations.
We  have  the  Microsoft
Defender  for  cloud  apps.
You  can  use  it  to  scan  your  cloud
environment  to  see  what  applications
are  being  used  in  your  environment.
We  have  Sentinel,  good
security,  um,  security  incident
and  event  management  tools.
We  have  data  governance  tools,
data  governance  and  compliance
tools  like  the  Microsoft  Pub.
Um,  um,  um,  um,  um,  um,  um.
But  I  know  that  thing  I  would
like  to  say  is  not  about  having
these  tools  is  about  knowing
that  uh,  we  are  sure  that  these
tools  are  interacting  with  each
order  and  are  not  in  silo.
I  have  stated  all  these
frameworks,  but  at  the  same
time,  let's  also  know  that  this
is  not  like  a  hundred  percent.
Where  in  which  your  system
wouldn't  be  breached  in  any  way.
That  is  why  there  should  also  be
need  for  good  incident  response.
We  should  be  able  to  contain
and  recover  quickly  from  any
breach  that  happens  in  our
environment  or  in  our  organization.
Matured  cyber  security  isn't
about  how  many  attacks  you
stopped  or  how  many  cyber  attacks
you've  been  able  to  manage.
What  it  is  also  about  How  you
are  able  to  contain  and  recover
from  any  form  of  breach  your
experience  because  some  of  these
breaches  are  actually  unavoidable.
For  example,  I  gave  an  example
about  NHS,  NHS  Trust  encountered
a  breach  as  a  result  of  a
vulnerability  within  their  third  party
mobile  device  management  software.
so  that  is  why  we  all  need  to
have  think  about  having  good  incident
response  plan  in  our  organization
i'll  also  now  draw  attention  to  this
let's  take  time  in  our  organization
let's  rethink  about  our  observability
our  identity  and  access  management
because  access  isn't  a  checkbox
anymore  It  is  now  an  attack  surface
and  observability  without  access  is
like  a  security  theater  because  you
are  just  watching  without  knowing
who  is  assessing  your  resources,
what  activities  are  going  on.
So  I  would  like  to  say  with
this,  I  enjoin  everyone  to
look  into  this,  look  at  the
organization,  check  what's  going  on.
is  going  on  and  how  to
improve  in  an  identity  and
observability  aware  environment.
Thank  you.