Good morning.
Good afternoon, everyone.
I'm Ash Lakshmi, currently
working in DT data.
US with over 22 years of
experience in quality engineering,
especially specialized in testing,
architecture, health plan systems,
and enterprise integration.
Throughout my career I have played
a. Pivotal role in ensuring seamless
implementation of enterprise application,
accelerating healthcare system
transformations, and enhancing compliance
through advanced test automation strategy.
I'm here to be to talk
about how observability can
transform quality assurance in.
Health insurance platforms with over two
decades in IT and quality engineering.
I have firsthand how traditional QA
falls short in today's fast moving,
highly regulated healthcare environments.
That's why this talks about
evolving from testing to.
Observing and how that
shift unlocks mass U value.
It can be for providers, it is for
members and any payers actually
in a health insurance platform.
The industry is in such a way that
where trust, complaints and experience
are not negotiated, but we need.
Monitoring strategies that are
not just reactive, but proactive,
insightful, and actionable.
Okay.
Now why observability matters.
Let's start with why.
The healthcare sector today
loses an average of 43% in
revenue during system outages.
The difference between having and
not having observatory tools, the
mean time to resolve is 68 minutes
without observability, but with
observability it is just 12 minutes.
And then there is uptime
expectation, availability of the
systems, which is 99.99 percentage.
This is not just a target, it is
a necessity for member experience,
trust, and the regulatory compliance.
In other words,
observability is not luxury.
It's a. Survival tool.
Okay, let's think of an example
In a health insurance, a parent is
trying to update their insurance
coverage for their child's surgery.
They log into the member portal and
portal crashes and doesn't provide
that information what they need.
It was dumb.
It's a failed promise.
What is an experience of a member?
Emotionally the person is trying to
go going through the surgery, whereas
from an IT support standpoint, as
a payer, we are not able to provide
that service what they needed.
It.
It's a failed promise.
So that is our observability, is how we
prevent these moments and make it more
user experience, member experience,
provide a smooth transition journey.
That is all it's about here actually.
Okay.
Now what is the observability Trinity?
It is not just about logging.
Metrics logs and traces actually.
Okay.
How this is categorized into,
let's take about the metrics.
What are the quantifiable insights?
Think about dashboards.
Think about claim processing tank by
complexity, prior authorization, approval
rates, member portal latency during open
enrollment, or a peak enrollment period.
Actually.
And then logs.
It tells the story behind system events,
which is vital for audits, compliance,
and debugging a member access their data.
Where the log shows what PHA
data, PA data has been accessed.
It also narrates a detailed
error locks when a provider
lookup fails what it failed.
HIPAA compliance.
Okay.
Anything on audit trail, which will
show it and log offers context as
well as a compliance coverage, and
then traces, it connects the dot,
showing that end to end journey.
What does it mean?
It is, it claims will go
through multiple systems.
And my in a PA architecture where
20 plus microservices, which will go
through it, checking that eligibility,
checking that provider provider validity.
And then what bene what is
the pricing configuration?
What benefits has been applied?
Do it does they need any oath?
What is the status of the claim?
It's a end-to-end journey, which is, goes
through with, through various services.
And then all the, each
step it monitors and trace
to track the
processing details of it.
Okay?
So in fact, traces are vital
and distributed a architecture,
especially with APAs third party
systems and legacy bridges.
Okay?
Together they empower.
Teams to monitor, diagnose,
and optimize complex workflow.
Now coming about regulatory benefits.
Okay?
Observability is not a
compliance enabler anymore.
It is a regulatory, which is a mandatory
requirement actually, especially
think about HIPAA audit readiness.
Tracking who access PHA and when, or
being able to trace every step of a
claims journey or even automatically
preserving access evidence
during regulatory investigations.
It's not about fixing things
fast, but also providing you
are doing the right things.
Q eight teams often overlook this.
Observability isn't just.
Technical.
It's a legal armor.
Okay.
Where then coming on to
other, what are the metrics?
Which they measure it, right?
Hipaa audit readiness, claims,
processing verifications, SLA,
documentations, evidence, preservations.
All those are, being part of
that comp compliance benefit,
which is being monitored
now.
Now, let's think about some of
the metrics in the real claims
processing auto adjudication rate.
Obviously, system need to handle the
amount of claims, what we received, and
what is our ajudication success rate.
First time, first pass, resolution
percentage, average processing duration.
Here are rates by claim type.
It's all about the claims data
processing data, which needs to be
measured from a metrics standpoint.
Member experience, portal availability.
I was sharing an example of member
portal available for a surgery.
It is important
authentication success rate.
If you're searching for a
provider, what accuracy is the
right provider being shown?
And right.
Services being offered.
And then session duration metrics.
Okay.
Average session, how long it takes
to that member is there in the
portal, which they can use it.
And then system performance last,
which is a database query, a PA
response time infrastructure, resource
utilization, and batch processing.
Completion rates.
Okay?
This is where domain specific
observability makes a difference.
You can't improve what you can't measure.
And these kps directly linked to cost,
compliance and customer satisfaction.
Now the question comes up,
how do you implement it?
Here is how to make it happen.
Assess your gaps and critical
systems instrument them setting
up metrics, logs and tracers.
Centralize everything
into a single platform.
Use unified observability platforms
to correlate events, visualize
it, create dashboards tailored
by roles, compliance operations.
It is and automate AI driven
anomaly detection and predictive
alerts to RCA root cause
analysis, automated remediation.
We can do it from an
automation standpoint.
This roadmap shifts QA from
a reactive call center to a
proactive reliability enabler.
Okay, now let's talk about how
observability heading actually.
Okay.
The industry wide, there are tools
such as Datadog, Dynatrace, Splunk.
Multiple tools available in the
market, which provides all specialized
categor specialized capabilities for
monitoring regulated healthcare systems.
Okay, now, from a yay standpoint, okay.
How this observability is heading.
It is one is anomaly detection.
That means identify the fraud or
the slowdowns in claim workflows.
Before users notice, predictive
alert your forecasting system,
stress before it crashes, member
access, provider access, or anything.
Then root cause analysis cut down
days of debugging into minutes,
self-healing, automatically restart
services or rewrote request so that
member or a provider, or any processing
provides a smooth experience.
A doesn't replace teams, it empowers them
to move from firefighting to foresight.
Okay.
Let me take a case study of
Anthem Blue Cross Blue Shield.
The challenge, what they
face it is they were.
Frequently facing portal outages which
passes a delays averaging 12 day claim.
Processing delays 12 days and
outages affecting 15 million users.
They implemented distributed tracing
across 200 plus services and built real
time dashboards with claims pipelines.
What is the result mean?
Time to resolution dropped
from 45 to five minutes.
And claim processing time
down by 62 percentage.
So it's a lessons start with high
impact business areas and see how
trust cross-functional teams improve
their observability or options.
Okay, now challenges, right?
It's this is the main, we
know what is a problem.
We know what is a solution.
What challenges we have to address it.
One is security concerns.
Balancing observability with
P-H-A-P-H-A must be protected
even while at observing it.
Fast management storing logs and
traces add up and you need policies
till how long you should keep it
to monitor and do that analysis.
Then legacy system I. You need to
have a minimal disruptions, and
many of those legacy systems may not
be built for observability teams.
Do they have skills you may need?
We need to provide training, qa,
ops teams, all those criticalities
to be built out actually.
So PACE yourself built incrementally.
Use pilot services to prove value.
Okay, so what did, what is the next
step from an point of view standpoint?
Right here is what I recommend,
assess, start with one critical
services, like a claims or
eligibility or a member quota.
Do a pilot of it, instrument
it, track metrics, add logs, map
traces, and then try to scale
based on pilot's, learning rollout,
observability across the platform.
And then try to optimize with create
dashboards, apply a align with
compliance, or you can adjust based on it.
And don't forget QA ops.
Security and product must partner
in this journey, let observability
become our invisible advantage.
So to conclude it, observability isn't
just a tool set, it's a mindset shift.
It redefines qa.
It's how we shift from defect
detection to experience protection.
From compliance, stress to audit,
confidence from reactive to predicting.
Okay.
If you would like to explore
further or need guidance, feel
free to, I have provided an email.
Feel free to reach out.
I'm happy to help.
Thank you.
Thanks.