Hello everyone.
This is Kumar.
I have about 20 plus years of experience
in the IT industry, working as a lead
software engineer at Mini of Technologies.
Prior to this, I worked at IBM and TCS.
Today I will be discussing the
topic, observability driven return
on investment, unifying multi-cloud
data for actionable intelligence.
In today's rapidly evolving
digital landscape, most of us are
operating in a cloud environment.
This brings incredible opportunities, but
also significant challenges, particularly
when it comes to integrating data
across those different cloud platforms.
In this session, we'll explore how
to turn multi-cloud complexity into.
A powerful competitive advantage.
We'll demonstrate how our
comprehensive framework delivers
measurable business outcome.
By leveraging AI driven automation to
reduce complexity and cut expenses,
we'll also show how organization using
our approach have optimized cross cloud
data pipelines with decreased latency.
Enabling faster decision making
through real time insights.
By the end of this presentation, you
will understand how leading enterprise
are achieving substantial ROI through
effect two multi-cloud data unification.
The multicloud reality 87 percentage of
enterprise are using multicloud platform.
This highlights the widespread recognition
of the benefit of the multi-cloud.
Things like avoiding vendor lock
in, optimizing cost by choosing
the best cloud for each workload
and increasing the resiliency.
However, this widespread
adoption comes with challenges.
42 percentage of organizations face a
significant cross cloud data barriers.
Think about the complexity of the
how data spread across AWS is Azure
Cloud and Google Cloud and may
be even some on-premises systems.
The good news is that optimized
integration can lead to significant
benefits organizations see.
On average, a 63 percentage
of reduction in cloud expense
with optimized integration.
This is from the things like
eliminating data duplication,
automating process, and making more
efficient use of cloud resources.
Furthermore, effective cross cloud
pipelines, acceleration making, we
see a 78 percentage improvement.
This critical in today's fast paced
business, then being able to react
quickly to changes in the market
can be a major competi to advantage.
Our research clearly
shows that while cloud.
Adoption continues to accelerate.
Many organizations struggle with
integration barriers that prevent
them from realizing the full
potential of their cloud investments.
That's where our framework
comes in business outcome.
Across industries in healthcare, we
have seen organizations achieve a 99
percentage of HIPAA complaints rate.
We also see a 73 percentage reduction
in the patient data retrieval
times leading to enhanced care
coordination through unified records.
Imagine the impact on patient care when
doctors can access complete and up to
date information quickly and easily.
In financial services, our
framework has enabled 82
percentage faster fraud detection.
This translates directly to significant
cost saving and reduce the cost real time.
Cross cloud analytics, improve
customer risk assessment, allowing
for more information station
about lending and investment.
Finally, in the government sector, we
have seen 91 percentage improvement.
In data sharing, this leads to
enhanced security protocols and
streamlined citizen services.
Think about how much more efficient
government agencies can easily
share information and collaborate.
These outcomes clearly demonstrate
that effective data integration
strategies deliver measurable
improvements in the efficiency.
Complaints, security and
customer experience, AI
driven integration framework.
Let's dive into a core of our solution,
our AI driven integration framework.
This framework is designed to
a dramatically simplifies cross
cloud integration by leveraging the
power of artificial intelligence.
The foundation is built on
standardized connectors.
These are prebuilt and custom
API integrations that enables
seamless communication between
different cloud platforms.
Think of them as a universal translators
that allow different systems to talk to
each other regardless of their technology.
Adaptive security is
another critical component.
This involves automated complaints
and threat detection, continuously
monitoring and responding to changing
security and complaints requirements.
In today's threat landscape, this level
of proactive security is essential.
Finally we have intelligent orchestration.
This is where AI comes into automatically
optimize workflow based on real time
performance metrics and business
needs, the system lens and adapts
ensuring that your integration is
always running at peak efficiency.
This layer approach ensures
a robust, scalable, and
intelligent integration solution.
Implementation challenges and solutions.
Implementing cross Cloud integration
is not without its challenges.
Security concerns are
another major hurdle.
We mitigate this with end to an
encryption and zero trust are securing
all touch points governance requirement.
Can also be complex.
You need to ensure data quality,
consistency, and compliance
across all our clouds.
Our framework provides prevent solutions
for each of these obstacles, enabling
organizations to overcome implementation
and achieve successful outcomes.
We have learned from numerous deployments.
And built those lessons into our approach.
Real time station acceleration.
One of the most transformation
benefits of our cross cloud
integration framework is the dramatic
acceleration of station making process.
In today's world, speed is essential.
Automated response are
another key benefit.
Our framework automates 93 percentage of
protein conditions freeing up your team
to focus on more strategic initiatives.
This is enabled by event driven
workflows and self optimizing
systems that react automatically to.
Changes in the environment.
Reduce latency is crucial for
real time decision making.
We achieve an 81 percentage
decrease in data transfer time
through optimizer traffic, quoing,
and smart catching strategies.
This ensures that data is available
when and where it's needed.
Security first integration approach.
Data classification.
Encryption is the first line of defense.
We automatically categorize data
sensitivity and apply appropriate
encryption at the rest and transit
across all cloud boundaries.
This ensures that your data is
protected no matter where it is.
Continuous monitoring and auditing
is essential for detecting
and responding to threats.
We deploy AI powered anomaly
detection with real time alerts.
This gives you visibility into
everything that's happening in the
environment, this comprehensive strategy.
Has enabled organizations to achieve
both robust security and seamless
integration objectives that were
previously seen as a conflicting
priorities in multi-cloud architectures
case study global financial institution.
To illustrate the power of our framework,
let's look at the real case study.
This is a global financial institution
with operations in 43 countries.
Their challenges was that they had
data across six clouds preventing
a unified customer review.
This made it difficult to
understand their customer needs.
Our solution was to implement.
A cross cloud data fabric
with AI driven integration.
This created a unified customer
data platform that enabled real
time analytics across all platforms.
The results were remarkable.
They achieved a 4 21 percentage,
ROI with the first year.
Primarily through fraud prevention,
operational efficiencies, and
improved customer retention.
They also saw a 92 percentage
faster fraud detection rate.
This case study demonstrate the
significant business value that
can be achieved through effect two.
Cross cloud data integration,
automated complaints management.
Policy definition allows for
centralized complaints, rules that are
translated to cloud specific controls.
This ensures consistency and
reduce the risk of error.
Automated enforcement involves
continuous verification and
remediation of policy violations.
The system automatically monitors
for complaints and takes action
in any issue are detected.
Audit and reporting provides
comprehensive documentation and
evidence generation for complaints.
Audits, this simplifies the audit process
and reduce the button on your team.
Measurement framework.
To truly understand the value of
cross cloud integration, you need a
comprehensive RY measurement framework.
It's not just about cost saving,
it's about broader business impact or
methodology involves key categories,
cost reduction, operational efficiency.
Addition, velocity, risk
mitigation, and customer experience.
This provides a holistic view of RYI.
As you can see, while cost reduction is
important, the highest RYI often comes
from risk mitigation through improved
security and complaints, customer
experience improvements also deliver.
It's written through increased
loyalty and lifetime value.
Happy customers are more likely to stay
with you and recommend you to others.
By measuring RYI across the file
categories, you can get complete
picture of the value of your cross
cloud integration initiatives.
Implementation roadmap and next steps.
Implementing Cross Cloud integration
is a journey, not a destination.
It's the best approach in a phase
manner to deliver incremental value.
The first phase is assessment strategy.
This involves evaluating
your current cloud landscape.
Defining your business
objectives and developing a
tailored integration strategy.
Key activities include cloud
inventory mapping, data flow
analysis, and RI target definition.
The second phase is foundation building.
This is where you implement the
core integration architecture
and security framework.
This includes data fabric deployment.
Security control implementation and
governance framework establishment.
The final phase is it expansion.
This evolves progressively
extending integration across
additional workload and clouds.
Thank you all for your time.
I appreciate the opportunity
to share this with you today.
Thank you once again.