Hi everyone.
Welcome to conference
42 Observability 2025.
My name is VMs Kris and I work
as a senior software engineer at
Walmart, where I primarily work
in infrastructure engineering.
And today I'll be presenting
on cloud native observability,
building visible, resilient,
and scalable enterprise systems.
So this talk dives into how advanced
monitoring analytics transform
enterprise systems in modern day.
Cloud native architectures.
So this is a topic which is close to
my work on AI driven API Resilience.
So the next 30 minutes, we'll explore
the shift from traditional monitoring
to observability, real world metrics,
the pillars of observability and
practical implementation strategies.
So let's get started.
So what it takes from monitoring
terms, ability, let's begin
with the fundamental comparison.
Traditional monitoring
focuses on predefined metrics.
So think about an CPU stage or
a request counts, which are a
limited, have a limited context.
So now we need to, which collects
displays and, data from specific sources.
It often creates silos where teams
see disconnected components leading to
reactive fixes after users are impacted,
reacts to predefined alerts or thresholds
notifying users when something is a mess.
Contract to this, we have a
cloud native observability.
It gives us a holistic view through
metrics, logs, traces, unifying
visibility across microservices.
This enables proactive detection, so just
imagine a catching a latency spike just
before it affects users and faster root
cause analysis, which is critical and
distributed systems across the industry
with this kind of high volume traffic.
So what is the relation between.
The observability and monitoring.
So observability can seen as an extension
of monitoring where monitoring provides
the data, and observability provides
a deeper insights and understanding.
Monitoring is a necessary component
of observability, but observability
goes beyond the scope of traditional
monitoring practices enables us
for proactive investigation and
resolution of issues by analyzing them.
As a system behavior and
identifying root causes.
In essence, monitoring tells
you when something is wrong,
but while observability tells
you why and how to fix that.
So now let's see some real
world implementation metrics.
So these are some tangible results.
Practical implementation has delivered a
40% faster resolution time for incidents,
which is down from hours to minutes.
Thanks to the correlated data and
studies show that 25% re resource
efficiency is achieved by optimizing
infrastructure utilization directly
impacting 35% of database load reduction.
And what about the detection speed?
It's almost around 200 millisecond
milliseconds, which is near time.
An identification and it supports
58% faster incident detection goal.
These metrics come from production
systems handling complex scenarios
during Thanksgiving, black Friday,
and holiday traffic peak times.
So these stats rely on tools
which are pulled up from
Dynatrace and GCP Stack Driver.
So moving on.
Next we have.
Few pillars for observability.
So let's observe this triangle.
Every small triangle is important to get
the details from an atomic level to an
holistic point of view of an application.
So observability, rest on these three
pillars, metrics, logs and traces.
Water metrics.
So metrics are quantifiable.
So think about a latency or an error
rates that are tracked in real time.
So these are your systems.
Vital signs, logs are timestamped.
Records of events and errors offering a
detailed audit trial, for instance, in a
microservice failure, logs pinpoint to the
exact state change and also pinpoint to
the exact line of code which went wrong.
And moving onto the traces, these are like
these map from end to end request path
revealing dependencies, broad bottlenecks.
So in the distributed setup, a single
request might span around to 10 services.
So these traces help us see the
full picture in API Resiliency work.
Prometheus is used for metrics
ELK, four logs and JA for traces.
This thread enables to proactively manage
85% faster issue resolution, which is a
key metric for enterprise scalability.
And now let's see how it behaves in a
stateless was a stateful services I.
We need to differentiate between the
observability in these two services.
So what is it?
Stateless services.
Think about load balanced
APIs, which focus on throughput
latency, andal resource use.
So we monitor these with
horizontal scaling in mind.
So the benefits of these are simplified,
scaling, easy to troubleshoot
in case of an individual issues.
So now, whereas coming to the
state, full services like databases,
which require tracking persistence,
metrics like replication, health
consistency, and storage performance.
So for an example, in Google Cloud
Spanner, we ensure that, the data
deliverability is across multi regions.
The benefits of this are users
experience continuity in that usage.
It's a rich personalization and
potentially more complex features.
When all these get added and coming
to observability strategies, they
may vary notably between stateless
and stateful services due to their
differing approaches to the state
management stateless services, which
are easier to scale demand, greater
focus on tracing individual requests.
And analyzing errors in contrast to the
state full services, which require a
broader view that captures persistent
state and ensures session continuity.
And now the shared patterns include
health probes and anomaly deduction.
Implementing of these to balance
the stateless API performance with
stateful database reliability, it'll
support us in 25% of latency reduction.
So this dual approach is critical
for hybrid cloud native systems,
and then comes the distributed
tracing implementation.
So what is this one?
So distributed tracing is a
cornerstone of observability.
First instrument.
Your code.
Add a trace context propagation
using libraries like open
telemetry across service calls.
Next, configure intelligent sampling.
Capture a hundred percent
of critical parts.
But just as a side note, do
not sample a lot of traffic.
Just sample.
The data, which you want to do
it, say one in thousand requests.
So we need to include both normal
and exceptional patterns and
then centralize the pipeline
with a scalable infrastructure.
Think about something as a Kafka
or a GCB per sub to ingest all
this data and trace it out.
So this process millions of spans daily.
And finally perform the
root cause analysis.
Visualize traces in JG to spot
bottlenecks, because these ties
directly to your 85% resolution metrics
from studies at an industry level.
So another key topic is
API Gateway observability.
So what is that?
So API Gateway observability refers
to the ability to monitor, measure,
and gain actionable insights into the
behavior, performance, and health of
API traffic as it flows through an API
gateway, it helps ensure that the APIs
are reliable, secure, and performant.
But now why exactly the API
Gateway Observability matters.
This acts as the entry point for
microservices in distributed systems.
The gateway is where the request ends from
the external world to the internal world.
So the API Gateways
are observability hubs.
Where we can get track traffic insights,
request volumes, service dependencies,
and rate limiting effectiveness.
So these traffic volumes could vary
from managing few hundred requests per
second to tens of thousands of requests
per second during our peak times.
And this provides a centralized control
plane for routing, authentication,
rate limiting and caching.
So what does observability enables?
In the API gateways, it gives us real
time visibility into the API traffic
issue detection, whether it might be
latency errors, anonymous auditing and
compliance, and also security monitoring.
So when I say security
monitoring, that is the key.
It monitors authentication
events and attack patterns.
Which we can, give them
to the InfoSec team.
Hey, these are the, attacks coming up.
So there are a few other
performance metrics like latency and
throughput, which are very critical.
So 25% latency restriction could
be achieved by optimizing gateway
routing, which is a direct
application of this particular
slide through API gateways with.
Native observability.
What is that?
So how can we achieve that?
So we can do that by Azure, API
Management plus some application
insights and Epic E plus A Stack
Driver or Kong Engine EngineX,
TONY, with Prometheus and Grafana.
So these are the tools and there are
like other tools like G-C-P-A-P-I,
gateway with Integrated monitoring
Dashboards makes this actionable too.
So are there any gateway specific
challenges you are facing?
Let's see.
Yeah, so best practices include enable
structured access logs with AL IDs.
So these IDs help us
relate from an end to end.
Monitoring of what happened
for that particular request.
And also use rate limiting and
circuit breakers with metrics exposure
instrument your GA API gateway with
tracing head dust, which includes
request id and also transparent.
Monitor latency percentiles such
as P 50, P 95, P 99 for the SLO
enforcement track End-to-end transaction
parts using distributed tracing.
So moving on.
Next we have an observability
pipeline design.
A robust observability
pipeline has four stages.
Collection gathers telemetry
from services and infrastructure.
Think of agents in this case on
each and every node processing of
normalization and filtering data.
So stream processes are used to
reduce noise to keep only critical
signals for a few hundred millisecond
milliseconds detection space.
That's an as an example.
So this is a kind of filtering out the
additional noise or to pull out the
exact data, which we are looking for.
And then storage uses tried strategies,
so hot storage for recent data, cold
storage for archives, which helps
us in balancing cost and access.
Aligning with 25% of resource efficiency.
Now visualization turns
data into dashboards.
There are many tools like Grafana
to spot anonymous in real time,
supporting 40% faster resolution.
These pipelines become the
backbone, our system, and now we
have high availability strategies.
So what are high availability strategies?
High availability ensures minimal
service disruption and maximum uptime.
From an observability perspective,
the ability to detect, understand and
response to failures is critical to
achieving true resilience and scalability.
High availability is a non-negotiable
in a distributor system, so for that,
we deploy collectors and storage
across multiple availability zones
to avoid single point of failure.
So what about the residency
and failover visibility?
We need to monitor at a node level,
zone level, and even at regional level
for residency and track failover events
and measure meantime to recovery,
which is termed as MTTR in the industry
levels, and then alert on degraded
clusters or failed availability zones.
And now how to monitor across a cross
zone or a region observability for
a multi-cloud high availability.
So these rails to correlate the metrics
logs and trace across the clouds detect
latency between regions and audit cross
cloud failover success and data sync.
Integrity designed for
graceful degradation, which
helps us in reduce tele.
If any backend fails, ensure core
functionality, test this during your
P loads to get all the corner cases.
But that might be, again,
our own individual case.
If your system behaves well during low p
ds, then to get all the common cases, then
yes, of course we can go ahead with that.
And then we need to do a local buffering
temporarily which temporarily stores
metrics when any connection drops,
or a multi chanting alerts, ensuring
teams getting notifications via Slack
email and also PagerDuty alerts.
So these.
Strategies underpin 50% of our
downtime reduction, which are
critical for enterprise resilience.
And now how do we do a capacity
planning and what are the
optimizing steps we need to perform?
Capacity planning starts with historical
patterns, aggregate all the metrics over
the months to understand utilization.
Ideal data in this case spans.
Over six months of the API traffic and
then forecast this demand with machine
learning, predict seasonal spikes
like Thanksgiving, black Friday, or
holiday day traffic, which helps us
optimizing resource allocation and then
optimize dynamically using auto-scaling,
balancing cost and performance, which
helps in continuous improvement.
Of refining these models aligning
approximately 25% utilization
of resource efficiency.
And now for the continuous implement
improvement we need to establish
a feedback loops to regularly
compare for casted projections
against the actual consumption
patterns, redefining prediction
models and allocation strategies.
And now what is, what about
the implementation roadmap?
So let's outline this roadmap.
Start with foundational building,
set up metrics with Prometheus
and centralized logging with ELK.
Define your SLIs and
SLOs for core services.
Then move on to the advanced capabilities.
Deploy JAAR for tracing
across microservices and build
custom dashboards for teams.
In the optimization phase, add an
automate detection with AI and automate
remediation for common issues, which are
building for 58 of our incident detection.
As per industry research, this
phased approach has guided
40% resolution improvement.
Plan to start with one service and scale.
Always remember, start small and scale.
This will reduce the impacts
that any new changes brings in.
And that wraps our journey to
the cloud native observability.
We have covered the shift from
monitoring real world metrics,
pillars, and implementation strategies.
Thank you all for your attention and I
hope everybody enjoy the session today.
Thanks a lot.