Hey everyone, this is Joshua Goum.
I have been in the software industry
for more than 13 years in development
and quality engineering space.
Today I'll be talking about the
triple threat, which is a technologist
reducing the testing costs.
Primarily we'll talk about the
generative ai, predictive analytics and
self-healing frameworks, how transforming
their to the testing landscape for
forward thinking organizations.
The traditional testing limitations we
are talking about time and test creation.
Manual script consumes
valuable engineering resources.
Teams struggle with the coverage gaps.
When you have a manual testers creating
the test scripts, you are going to
have the coverage gaps and reactive.
Defect detection problems.
Discover too late critical issues
to reach production environment.
When you have a P one issues
in production, it's going to,
damage the trust of the customer.
Also, it's going to impact that
top line or bottom line revenues.
And the third one is the
high maintenance overhead.
When you have the automation scripts
which breaks with the U changes, our false
positives drain the resources and trust.
So we, the solution for all
this problems is our solution.
What we're talking about is the A
testing triangle with the generative
AI and predictive analytics
and self-healing frameworks.
The first one is a gender dua, where you
can create a comprehensive test script
autonomously identifying the edge cases.
Human testers often miss, so when you,
obviously, when you create the gender
dua, the test scripts, it's going to have
a, better coverage than the manual test.
Test case script creation.
The predictive analytics leverage
historical data to focus testing
resources on high risk areas
with a greater potential impact.
What we are talking about is whatever
areas having, when gather the historical
data and see where you have higher P
one bucks, which is causing the revenue,
and you can deploy your resources there.
The third one is the
self-healing frameworks, right?
Automatically adapt to UA changes,
eliminates the false positives
and maintenance and test integrity
without manual intervention.
When you have all these three, you will
have the, if you if you go through the
numbers right, by reducing the manual test
creation by up to 70%, cutting maintenance
cost by 65% and accelerating release
cycle by 40%, instead of looking at a.
Testing as a bottleneck, then you are
looking at it as a competitive advantage.
The results is the high quality release,
faster time to market, and dramatically
lowering the testing costs across
your entire development pipeline.
So the first one is generative ia, right?
The before generative IA before when
you have a time consuming manual
script creation requiring specialized
expertise coverage gaps, leaving
critical scenarios untested and
excessive developer hours devoted
from the feature development variable
quality dependent on the individual.
Tester skill levels right after
the generative wave, we are talking
about a power skip generation
in minutes instead of days.
Comprehensive coverage, including edge
cases, human affirm needs and development
resource allocated to high value
innovation and consistent enterprise
grade quality across all test suits, not
just one area where you have the experts.
The second one is a predictive analytics.
What is what it is like an
anticipating the issues, right?
Risk identification, right?
High risk models flagged
before deployment.
Using the historical data, you can
identify the what is the high risk areas.
And focus testing their resources
directed to vulnerable areas and,
defect prevention, critical issues
caught before production, a score
patterns, and complex metrics.
And you can follow this
through this cycle.
Over a period of time you are going
to refine and get a better results.
The third one we are talking about
is self feeling frameworks, right?
Automated maintenance where U UA
changes, breaks, existing tests, right?
A demands, failure patterns, and
test scripts automatically updated.
Fix verified without human intervention.
There is multiple tools available
as of today in the market.
You can see what works
best for your needs.
You are talking about the real
world results by industry, right?
You can see across healthcare
or FinTech or e-commerce, right?
Test case.
Test case creation time is
reduced by almost like 70%.
Defect detection is increased by 40%, and
maintenance hours decreased by almost 80%.
That this is a grade.
We are talking about time savings
of 74% and 63% of cost reduction,
and 40, 41% of defect prevention
and 3.5 x of coverage increment.
Now how it can be implemented, right?
You are talking about architectural
integration patterns, right?
First standalone implementation, right?
Begin with the isolated tools.
Test E each AI component
independently before integration.
Then you can do the portion integration.
Connect to components, build confidence
in the approach with the, in a limited
scope, full ecosystem integration, right?
Implement complete feedback loop.
Allow all components to
share data and insights.
Obviously you cannot a hundred
percent rely on the ai.
You need to have ethical AI
governance framework where you have a
transparency, light clear documentation
of AI decisions, explainable test
generation, logic editable, prediction,
rational and accuracy, right?
Regular validation against human
experts, continuous model retraining.
Confidence scoring for predictions.
The third one is a human oversight the
finalization authority with the QA leads.
Regular review of AA performance over
rate capability for all automated actions.
Next one is a tool chain
integration approach, right?
Where you have the a PA
integration in the first place.
We are connecting through
standard rest interfaces.
Then you have the pipeline embeddings
with integrating into CACD workflows.
Then you have the data sharing where
you are gathering all the data,
extra centralized matrix repository,
like elastic search or some kind of
repository, UN unified dashboards, right?
Create a comprehensive
visualization layer, right?
It can be Grafana, Splunk,
or something else, right?
The implementation roadmap, what
we are talking about, the phase
one is a foundation, right?
Selecting tools.
Obviously you have hundreds
of tools or maybe thousands of
tools available in the market.
You have to see what is the right fit
for your needs and your enterprise.
Establish the baseline metrics.
Try shell team members in
shell deployment, right?
Implement individual components,
validate results against control
groups and integration, right?
Connect component feedback loops.
Monitor system performance, then you
can expand scale across teams, refine
process, document best practices.
When you do these things right, the
key takeaways where we are talking
about is the AI synergy, right?
The combination of technologies
create greater impact than
individual tools, right?
Like obviously each EA tool will
bring what we bring to the table is
going to have a different result.
But when you combine all different
technologies are different tools,
you are going to have a greater
impact and proven results, right?
Real world implementation
demonstrates significant return
investment across industries.
When these three technologies.
Together implemented.
We already seen so many,
enterprise level results.
Enterprise level companies
giving, getting the better
results proven results with this.
And practical pathways.
Smart small with a modular
implementation before full integration
and human partnership, right?
A enhances human testers
rather than replacing them.
With that, I'm done.
Thank you very much.