Good morning.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Siva Prakash.
It's a pleasure to be here.
With two decades in the IT industry,
I have dedicated the last four
years specifically to navigating the
intricate technological landscapes of
the financial and insurance sectors.
During this time, I have seen
firsthand the evolution of systems.
The explosion of data and the
mounting pressure for absolute
reliability and security.
Today I want to talk about a
transformative approach that addresses one
of the most pressing issues in our field.
Cloud native observability
financial institution are the
bedrock of our economy, processing
trillions of transactions annually
through increasingly complex.
Distributed architecture, this
complexity while enabling innovations
being unprecedented, observability
challenges, the stark reality is
that traditional monitoring approach
often detect a mere one to two
percentage of critical anomalies.
Think about that 98 percentage of
potential issues might be lurking, unseen.
This can and does lead to significant.
Downtime costs, customer dissatisfaction
and serious compliance viol violations.
But what if we could flip that statistics?
That's precisely what I'm here to discuss.
We will explore how cutting edge
cloud native observability solutions,
particularly those harnessing the power
of graph based topology analysis and
behavioral analytics, are fundamentally
changing financial systems monitoring.
We are aiming for and achieving up to 99.4
percentage accuracy in identifying system
anomalies while simultaneously making
a massive dent in operational noise by
reducing false alerts by 87 percentage.
Let's spend a few moments dissecting
the current monitoring challenge because
understanding the problem deeply is.
Appreciating the solution.
As this slide illustrates,
it's a multifaceted issue.
Number one, low detection rate.
I mentioned the alarming one to 2%
detection rate for critical anomalies.
Anomalies.
There is not just a statistics,
it is a significant business risk.
It means that by the time an issue
is manually discovered, it may
have already impacted customers
or critical financial processes.
Alert fatigue for the
anomalies that are detected.
Traditional system often vol,
they generate an excessive
number of false alert positives.
My colleagues in operation often
tell me they are drowning in alerts.
This alert fatigue is dangerous.
Critical alerts get missed because teams
are desensitized or simply overwhelmed.
System complexity.
Financial systems today
are no longer simple.
Monolithic application.
They have evolved into incredibly
intricate webs of microservices,
APIs, and distributed databases.
We are talking thousands
of interdependencies.
Trying to manually map or understand this
with all tools is like trying to navigate
labyrinth blindfolded financial impact.
The direct consequence of this
shortcomings is significant.
Downtime costs, but it's
more than just that.
It's reputational damage, loss of customer
trust, and the ever looming threat of
regulatory penalties for non-compliance.
So why are traditional tools failing us?
Predominantly, they rely on
threshold based monitoring.
You set a static limit CP usage above
x percentage response time over y
millisecond, but in a. Cloud native world,
these thresholds are often too rigid.
They don't understand the
content context or the complex
relationship between the component.
This leads to those BL critical
blind spots and makes troubleshooting
are reactive, a resource intensive
and often frustrating process.
This brings us to our solution,
starting with a foundational
element, graph based ology analysis.
Imagine creating a dynamic
living and breathing blueprint
of your entire financial systems.
That's what this is.
It's about understanding the
who, what, where, and how.
Your sensitive interactions, the process
unfold in logical steps, data collections.
First, we gather comprehensive
elementary, that include logs, detailed
metrics, and distributed tracers.
From every single component in
your system, be it in a, be it
an application, a microservice, a
database, or a piece of infrastructure.
Number two, graph construction.
This is where the real
intelligence come into play.
We don't just collect data.
We use it to map out all
service dependencies and
their intricate relationship.
This construct, a graph model, a
visual and analytical representation
of your systems topology.
Think of it like a social
networking for your services.
We see who took talks to whom, how
often, how politically pattern analysis.
With this dynamic graph, we can
analyze how services interact
under normal condition, and more
importantly, identify behavioral
patterns that deviate from this norm.
Patterns that are anomalous.
For instance, a service suddenly
trying to communicate with another
service it has never interacted with
before, or a critical pathway showing
unusual latency, intelligent editing.
This allows for highly targeted
notification because we
understand the relationship.
The alert come with rich
context, helping teams.
Understand the blast radius and
potential upstream downstream impact.
This also feeds into risk assessment,
helping prioritize issues.
The true power here, and I have seen this
make a huge difference, is its ability
to reveal those hidden connections and
dependencies that often go in notice.
This allows us to identify anomalies
that conventional detection methods with
their siloed views would invariably miss.
Sequently, we can precisely target
the root cause of issues rather
than just firefighting the symptoms.
This shift from reactive to proactive
is a game change changer, especially in
preventing those fast escalating failure
that can ripple financial operations
hand in line with our graph
based apologies or behavior.
And these frameworks, if the
graph tells us how components are.
Interconnected Behavioral analytics
tells us how they should be behaving
within that structure and critically
when they start to deviate.
This framework is a continuous loop
number first metric collection.
We are gathering over 300 different
system metrics in a real time
from across your environment.
This provides a rich,
multidimensional view of.
This is where it gets really smart.
The system does not rely on
predefined static thresholds.
Instead, it uses machine learning to
establish normal operational pattern
for your specific environment.
Creating dynamic baseline that
continuously adapt to changing
condition and seasonality.
What's normal on a Monday morning might
be different from a Friday afternoon
during options expire, for example.
Number three, contextual analysis.
When deviation from this learned
baseline occur, the framework
evaluates their significance.
It considers the context what
else is happening in the system?
How does this deviation relate to others?
Is this a minor isolated blip or a
statistically significant pattern?
That could be the early
warning sign of a larger issue.
Number four, deviation detection.
Based on the contextual analysis, the
system identify even subtle anomalies
that might be indicative of potential
failure, often long before they would
breach a traditional static threshold.
The crucial differentiator
here is the move away from
those rigid static threshold.
As I mentioned, static thresholds
often lead to a flood of false
positives or conversely mis
emerging issues until it's too late.
Our behavioral analytics approach
by focusing on subtle deviation
from learn norms, achieve early
detection rate that are impressive.
5.3 times higher than typical
industry standard in my whole
years in finance and insurance.
Ability to get ahead of an issue to
detect it in fancy has consistently
be been a key factor in maintain,
maintaining stability and trust.
These are not just theoretical advantages.
The performance metrics speaks volumes
as you can see from this comparison.
Let's first look at the
anomaly detection rate.
Our solution represented by the
lighter bar achieves a 99.4%
accuracy in detecting anomalies.
Compare that to the very low single
digits of additional monitoring.
That's a monumentally.
Now consider the false positive rate.
We have achieved an 87%
reduction in false alerts.
Imagine the impact on your operation
team, less noise, less wasted effort, and
the renewed ability to focus on genuine
issues that require their expertise.
This also the rebuilds plus in
the monitoring system itself.
Early detection, it is normally measured
in ours, is significantly enhanced.
This crucial lead time gives times a much
teams a much better chance to investigate,
mitigate, and resolve problems
before they impact users or escalate
into major incidents and critically
look at un unidentified failures.
There is a dramatic decrease
here translating to a 76.
Percentage increase in detecting
previously unidentified failure pattern.
This means fewer unexpected outages,
enhanced system reliability, and
a more resilient infrastructure
Overall, this proactive discovery
of unknown failure, more invaluable
for continuous improvement.
Financial systems are data factories.
They generate absolutely volumes
of tele data logs, metric prices,
often reaching data scale.
Handling this sheer volume
efficiently is a significant
engineering challenge in itself.
Slow processing or inefficient
storage can negate the benefit of
even one, the smartest analytics.
Our cloudnative platform is specifically
architecture to manage deluge effectively.
It employs intelligent data filtering,
which is crucial for prioritizing
the most relevant telemetry.
Not all data is created equal when
it comes to detecting anomalies.
And our system knows how to focus
on the signals that matters.
Adaptive compression techniques
are used to optimize storage
utilization significantly, keeping
costs manageable without sacrificing
access to technical, historical data.
This enables real-time analysis, providing
immediate insights into system behavior.
The result of this intelligent data
management is processing speed up to 42
times faster than traditional solutions.
The speed combined with optimized
storage and cost efficiency is vital.
In finance, data insights
are often time sensitive.
The ability to process and analyze
vast data sets quickly is fundamental
to maintaining a competitive
edge and operational stability.
Ultimately, these techniques, technical
advancements, must translate into
tangible business value, and they do.
We are seeing.
A remarkable 94% reduction in monitoring
infrastructure, maintenance cost.
This is not just a small saving.
It frees up significant budget that
can be reinvested into innovation
or other strategic initiatives,
and 82% improvement in scalability.
This ensures your system can
handle peak transaction, period.
Think market open Black Friday
for retail banking or month end
batch processing reliably and
without performance degradation.
71% faster response in incident resolution
capabilities, faster detection, better
context and root cost analysis, all
contribute to minimizing downtime
costs, and importantly, limiting any
negative impact on your customer.
And 68% enhanced mapping of
cross service dependencies.
This deep understanding is crucial
for proactive risk management,
preventing those cascading failure
that can spread rapidly through
interconnected financial system.
These results are not
confined to a lab projects in.
It showcases a real success across.
Diverse financial institutions.
We share a few example.
Consider Global Investment Bank.
They were struggling with a sprawling
estate of 12,000 microservices.
By implementing our solution, they
reduced their mean time to resolution.
NTTR by an incredible 65%
in virtually eliminated 94%
percentage of their false alert.
The bottom line impact
approximately three point.
$2 million saved annually
in operational cost.
Then there's regional credit unit.
Their challenge was improving
system availability and
proactively addressing issues.
They saw their availability
jump from 99.2 percentage to an
outstanding 99.97 percentage.
Furthermore, they were able to
detect potential failure before they
impacted customers in 98 percentage
of cases, and as a bonus reduce their
monitoring staff requirement by 40%.
An insurance provider faced
a dual challenge of rapidly
increasing transaction volumes,
2.5 times more, and the need to
reduce critical I 73% decrease.
Critical incident frequency and
significantly enhance the regulatory
compliance reporting through automatic
anomaly documentation across these
and other implementation financial
institution have experienced
on an average of 59% decrease.
In meantime to resolution, I'm an
TR, while simultaneously improving
system reliability by 83%.
These figures under the
consistent and significant value.
Very good.
Irrespective of an organization size
or the specific complexity of its IT
environment, we recognize that adopting
a new observability paradigm is a
journey, not a flip off, a switch.
That's why we champion a strategic
asset, a carefully phased implementation
approach designed to minimize disruption
and accelerate your time to value.
This is not.
About a Big Bang deployment.
It's about high success.
Our proven method methodology typically
unfolds as follows, number one,
assessment phase two to three weeks.
This is crucial starting point.
We conduct a pro system in perform
detailed topology mapping of your existing
environment and carry out a comprehensive
monitoring gap analysis this and shows
we understand your unique landscape.
Two ILI deployment.
Three to four weeks armed with
insight from the assessment.
We then focus the implementation on the
set of your cost most critical services.
This allows us to establish initial
baselines, demonstrate value quickly,
and gather learnings in a control manner.
Number three, expanded
rollouts four to six weeks.
Based on the success and learning from
the pilot, we then scale the solution
to your full production environment.
This phase includes careful, alert tuning
to align with your operational workflows.
Four is optimization it.
It is an ongoing one.
Observability is not a one-time setup.
This phase involves continuous
requirement, refinement of
detection, algorithms, dashboards,
and integration to ensure the
solution evolves with your system,
and delivers lasting effectiveness.
This structured approach, beginning with
that comprehensive assessment, allows
for a targeted and efficient pilot, which
in turn paves the way for a smoother,
more successful scale development,
ensuring buy in and minimizing a race.
A natural and important question is
always, who will this integrate with
our existing complex technology stack?
Our solution is architected
for flexibility and seamless
integration cloud platform.
We provide native deep integration
with all major cloud providers, AWS,
Azure GCP, including leveraging their
auto-scaling capabilities for efficiency.
We also support on-prem environment.
Application layer.
Our instrumentation is language
agnostic, meaning we can monitor diverse
application portfolios often without
recurring extensive code modification.
We fully support open telemetry,
which is key for future proofing
and avoiding vendor lock-in, and
also offer zero code integration
options for many common technologies.
Data stores, we offer
specialized connectors.
Providing deep visibility into both
SQL and no SQL database performance,
including query performance
analysis and tools for capacity
planning, security and compliance.
This is non-negotiable
in the financial sector.
Our architecture is designed
to be SOC to PCI and GDPR.
It features end to and encryption
and robust role-based access controls
to ensure your sensitive telemetry
data is handled securely and meets
stringent regulatory requirement.
This versatile architecture ensures
that we can fit into your world rather
than forcing you to fit into ours.
Providing comprehensive visibility
across your entire aspect.
So how can you embark on this journey to
transform your observability capabilities?
We offer several pathways to get
started, failure to your needs.
Schedule a complimentary
assessment allows us to help you
understand your current state.
We can book a system topology assessment
to pinpoint specific monitoring gaps
and identify clear opportunities for
improvement within your environment.
Request a custom demo seeing is
believing we can provide a tailored
demonstration perhaps using an
now anonymized sample data that
reflects your kind of environment.
To help you visualize the direct benefits
and how this would look and feel for your
teams, download our implementation guide.
For those who like to
dive into the details.
We have a comprehensive implementation
guide packed with best practices
specifically curated for.
Financial system, join our
community, connect with peers.
We facilitate a community where you
can share insights and learn from
other financial institutions that are
also on the journey to implementing
advanced observability solutions.
We are genuinely passionate about helping
financial institutions like yours.
Achieve this new frontier of 99%
anomaly detection, accuracy, and
dramatically improve system reliability.
Our dedicated financial services team is
ready and eager to collaborate with you.
We will work side by side to design a
implementation plan medically tailored
to your specific environment, your unique
challenges, and your strategy requirement.
That's it.
Here comes the end of the slide.
Thank you very much for your
time and attention today.
It's been a privilege to share who
the potent combination of craft-based
monitoring and behavioral analytics is
truly revolutionizing observability within
the demanding context of financial system.
I hope this has provided you with
valuable insight into what's possible.
I'm now very happy to
open the floor and answer.
Any questions that you may have.
Thank you so much again.