Hey, good morning everyone.
This is Anbu.
I'm a Senior Technical
Product manager at T-Mobile.
I lead initiatives around large
scale digital commerce systems.
That's millions of customers
across multiple platforms like
web, mobile, and in store.
Today.
I will share how observability is
at core of making async event-driven
commerce systems reliable and scalable.
We will look at how we have approached
this at T-Mobile from architectural
patterns to debugging techniques and the
key lessons we have learned along the way.
Whether you're building distributed
systems, managing reliability, or
designing customer journeys, I hope this
talk gives you practical takeaways you
can apply to your own async environment.
Let me start this with, a statement,
in a world we are living in a world
where milliseconds definitely matter.
What do you, what do is, basically
let's say a customer is shopping
on a website and then while
checking out there's a delay.
And then.
He can decide to abandon
the cart and then, we can
potentially lose that customer.
We live in a world where
conversion rates matter and
observability is no longer optional.
It's foundational.
Let me give you an overview of why
we have to shift to Async, to really
drive the omnichannel demands.
Observability, make observability ob
to, to shift from seeing, to async.
The thing that matters most to me is
the observability, because that's the
key of making the shift sustainable.
Know today, digital shoppers, like I
said, expect everything to be fast,
personalized, and seamless, whether
they're online or in store or mobile.
The level of responsiveness pushes us to
move away from synchronous architectures
that block, or fail under pressure.
The challenge is how do we maintain
visibility and trust when everything
runs asynchronously and independently?
That's where observability
becomes critical.
It's our lens into this complex world.
Synchronous systems are like daisy.
Change, one broken link, then
everything falls or fails.
When we switch to async, we get the scale
of flexibility but at the same time, we
also lose the comfort of linear flows.
Failures don't scream in async
flows, but they just whisper.
And if you're not listening to
the right tools, you miss them.
That's the trade off.
We must solve
rise of asynchronous commerce.
I will, you know what's why are we
shifting from synchronous to asynchronous?
The main reason is the demand, demand
and the personalization, rise of
headless microservices and even brokers.
Omnichannel isn't just a buzzword,
it's how customers behave.
Now, I'll tell you an example.
Someone you know, browses on a
mobile and then adds it to the cart.
Then he walks into the store and then he
wanted to check it out with the agent.
This means our system must be loosely
coupled, but tightly coordinated.
Async communication helps achieve
this thanks to our microservices
and event driven designs.
But now we need visibility
across all those hops.
I'll give you an overview.
I'll just explain a use case that
we have implemented or that we
are going to implement in Tmobile.
At T-Mobile the most busiest time
in T-Mobile is during N-P-I-N-P-I
is basically the new product
launches, especially in September
when Apple launches a device.
We almost get a hundred K orders that day.
That's the most busiest day for us,
then Thanksgiving or Christmas or New
Year, and, in one of the NPIs, I think
last year what happened in the first
15 minutes because of the flush of
orders, the payment system was done.
We were in a state where the
orders were not submitted.
Because today what happens in T-Mobile
is when you build a car, go to check
out, and then once you make the payment,
then only you can submit an order.
But because of it, like we built
substitute breakers, which did
not break the system message.
But what happened was at
least the payment was broken.
And then the customers were struck there
saying, Hey, oops, something went wrong.
And they were not able
to submit the order.
That made us think, do we really
need payments to be synchronous?
There are.
We can definitely go async as well.
That's when we, that's where,
we thought hey let's start.
We all, it's Async is not something new.
Today we already have this Async for Bois,
Bois is bring your own so not bring it on
I'm sorry, is buy online pickup in store.
At T-Mobile we implemented.
Even driven architectures to
support this Bois and Async.
We are designing this and
probably by this NPI, we wanted to
implement this async payment flow.
These flows are unpredictable, a payment,
like I said, a payment may succeed in
three seconds or time out after 30.
And then for Bois inventory is
critical thing 'cause inventory
might change mid transaction.
So what we do for Bo PC is
basically, again, to reserve.
We make a soft reservation call.
For inventory.
And then when customer walks into the
store, we make a hard reservation call.
So all of these calls are tightly coupled.
That's when we thought, hey,
let's do something asing so that
customers can be served in purpose.
And then we had events,
to coordinate all of this.
But it only works if we can see
them happening in real time.
What makes this async hard to.
Observe, regular synchronous calls, we
can log their request response or we can
use lot of tools in Splunk, debug them.
But async flows are, invisible
flows or, we have tools that, that
there, there aren't really many
tools that weren't, that were and
designed to be, to support Async.
Imagine, you imagine trying to follow up
a story where each sentence is told by
a different person at a different time.
That's what it looks like.
Debugging, acing flows, you don't
know, there a lot of events are coming
up and then you listen to the events
and then you process the things.
So the lack of casualty this caused,
that makes traditional monitoring in FHU.
So we need tools to capture relationships,
timing, and internet across systems.
So to me, observability has four pillars.
Distributed caching.
Distributed tracing.
Distributed tracing is something,
you have to, you need to trace events
across services using span correlations.
You need to correlate them.
And then event audits and replay
reconstruct workflows, for
debugging and root corner analysis.
When something goes stronger, you should
be able to reconstruct the workflows
and then debug and find an RCA.
And then consistent monitoring,
validate that business outcomes
are eventually completed.
And we have a lot of domain
dashboards which provide visibility.
Using business centric
metrics and language
in sing systems, right?
Observability isn't about
tracking just technical metrics.
It must reflect the
business journey end to end.
Here's how we approach it
through our four key, four key
pillars, distributed tracing.
We use, in T-Mobile we use tools like
for distributor tracing, we use tools
like open telemetry, to inject trace
context into a request and events.
This lets us correlate
span across microservices.
Even when communication is event based.
When something breaks, we can follow
the trace path and pinpoint the
exact hot way it failed or slow down.
It's a backbone for debugging.
Asy flows, coming to event audits
and replay, async, async flows.
Don't leave a clean lock tray.
So we log constructed events with context.
User id order Id.
Sometimes timestamps
event type, et cetera.
This allows us to replay what
happened during an issue.
Not only does this help with RCA, but
we can also retry failed process without
impacting other parts of the system.
And for consistency monitoring, what
we did was about validating the entire
business transaction was compliant, but
it not just the services are running.
For example, an order placed, you know
what happens when an order is placed?
We reserve an inventory and payment
is confirmed, and then whether
shipment has been initiated or not.
We track the completion of these workflows
across time, services and systems,
even when events are out of order.
Domain dashboards, we build dashboards
that use business language orders.
Whether the pickup is done or not,
whether the payment is in which state,
whether it's in retre or not, whether
inventory check, has been done or not.
These make observability actionable
for non-engineers, like our product
manager is support teams and operations
can understand what's going on
without diving into locks and traces.
So go domain dashboards are really
helpful to, all the team members.
Let me walk you over a book flow,
this is what typically happens
when customer place an order.
What we do is we trigger a, we trigger
an event to validate the inventory, and
then we trigger events to notify store
that, hey, an order is coming up, and then
we trigger an event for pickup children.
These are all independent
services, working in parallel.
Unlike, if it is, if someone logs
into T-Mobile dot com and place
an order, it's all one by one.
Like basically once order is submitted,
then the next step is payment is set, and
then after that it goes to the warehouse.
And then warehouse takes its own
suite time to dispatch the item.
But whereas in case of pop is everything
is async you like right from a payment.
Payment is not acing, sorry.
And the event, the store
notifications are acing.
The validations are acing, and the
pickup sheet, everything is acing, and
for Async and for async payment, right?
Like I mentioned, while customer like
what the main problem that we faced
during last NPA was orders were struck
because the system was done because
of an unexpected volume of orders.
And then what we are
thinking how can we solve it?
What we have been thinking is, retrying
is one option, but when the system is
down, you can't even, that would not help.
So what we're thinking is we
wanted to recouple this payment
processing from the order submission.
So our plan was, when the customer is
present, when a customer does a payment,
since it takes longer than expected.
So we wanted to put on a queue.
Then process it, asing and then
order submission also would be
async only after the payment is
successful, we will process the order.
But let's say if the order is
not successful, if the payment is
not successful, then we want to
trigger a notification to customer,
send a text message or an email
asking to reenter the payment.
And only after the payment is
confirmed, the order would be submitted.
So this way both the payment processing
and the order submission are, as so
we generate an order number and give
it back to customer, like customer is.
Customer doesn't know what's
happening in the background.
He just knows that okay, an order
is submitted, and he wrote an email
saying that, Hey, your order is
submitted and we are working on it.
But in the background, we validate
the payment and if it goes through,
then only we submit the order.
But if the payment doesn't go
through, then we again send a
notification to customer two.
Reenter the cuts.
So this way customers are not
blocked and we are able to capture
the orders and then, process them.
With Async Payments, the best thing
is customers get an instant feedback,
after the order is placed behind
the scenes we are, we check the card
validity, and then we check for fraud.
And we check whether the
card has funds or not.
And if something fails, we fall back
without disrupting the user flow.
Here observability means monitoring
the state excuses, try tracing
failures and ensuring consistency
without sacrificing speed.
So let me, I think we, we spoke
a lot about ing, we really need
tools and techniques through
which we can trace them.
I will go through few tools that we use
at T-Mobile that to track these events.
Open telemetry, open Telemetry is
used to capture and correlate spans
across distributed services and events.
So this is our go-to standard
for distributed tracing.
It allows us to inject trace
series and span context into each
service call and even message.
Even when systems communicate
asynchronously, whether it's an a p
call or an internal microservice call,
or a Kafka message, we tie them all
back to a single customer transaction.
This is critical for our, finding out
what went wrong, especially, in complex
clothes when something goes wrong.
Know, we use a lot of if you want
me, if we have a lot of tools into
the way we monitor open telemetry.
We have SDKs we like in the
web, like in ui we use no Js
and Java, Python, et cetera.
And then at Commerce system
we use data Ho we use Jagger.
We have Grafana.
Grafana is actually.
A lot for our backend
services that we use.
And then sometimes if we, if the service
are hosted on AWS, we use AWS X-ray.
And then for Kafka, like Kafka is actually
central to our async architecture 'cause
it access backbone for event transport.
Here also an observe.
What matters is observability.
So how we monitor, what we monitor,
how we monitor the Q depth, to detect
the backlogs and the consumer lag,
to catch up slow or star services.
And then the throughput, like to
understand how much is a system load.
So what what tools we use here
is, Kafka manager, it manages
the topics, the queues, and also
the clusters, it's deprecated.
I know, but we used to use it
now we also use Grafana, to do a
visualization of Kafka throughput
and partition lag and message drops.
And then we use borough, a consumer lag
monitoring tool for Kafka, error rates for
retrace to catch failing event handlers.
These metrics, help us to detect not
just failures, but also performance
degradation before it impacts users and.
Custom event entry play dashboards.
These dashboards are our internal
dashboards which help to track
and order from end to end, right?
From adding the service to the cart until
it's checked out again, we use Kibana
here, we use Meta Base and then we use
Power bi, and then we use Grafana also.
What are the sources for this?
We use business events that are
business event logs from Kafka
consumers or even gateways.
And then, we use telemetry
systems, all of this.
And how do I measure success?
When I move from sync to async,
how do I measure the success?
The success is basically
today we support the boat.
Like on average we have about 7 million
customers logging into T-Mobile dot com.
Like we registered those
many number of tokens.
But eventually when you look at
the cards so from 7 million, only
one 30 K cards are being created.
Okay?
And all of one 30 k the actual
orders come down to 30 5K.
But when we used asing things, what
we have seen, if you look at the BPI
orders we have seen the checkout rate.
Let's say out of those one 30
k, one 30 K to 30 k, it's almost
one to one inch to four ratio.
But if we look out the BPI
orders are more faster checkout.
Like it's not one inch to four, it's
three to four, like out of let's say we
had, let's say we had a thousand orders.
So the Poppi cards that
are built are only 4,000.
Now this led us to lower abandonment.
The Bois on Bois.
If I see, I can trace that
the card to order conversion
rate is significantly higher.
In case of Bois.
And then we what happened with Async?
We are during the peak time, like
I said NPI we are 97% available.
So even promotional peaks, sometimes
we give promotions saying that, Hey,
buy one, get one, or, to attract
customers saying that, Hey you are
putting in, you get these offer.
So even when we announced those
promotional things tho at that
times also we were almost close
to a hundred percent available.
You see the results
speak themselves faster.
Checkouts mean, higher conversion
and lower abundant rate
shows how we improve trust.
At high uptime during traffic
spikes proves that resilience and
scalability can go ahead, go hand
in hand if observability is right.
I think to, again, you, you have to
when you move from seeing to e right?
You have to do some trade offs.
I hope you all know
what this cap the means.
Cap the means, see for consistency,
every re returns the most recent, right?
Okay.
Availability.
Every request receives a response, and
then partition tolerance system continues
to operate despite network failures.
Yeah, you'll have to trade off,
when you have to be consistent, then
your availability might be lost.
If you're on a syn, synchronous
systems, you'll be consistent.
Because you, you wait for it, it takes
10 seconds or 15 seconds, you'll get that
response back and the customer is present.
So it is very much consistent,
but availability, right?
Like I said, during peak time, gone,
like if you're bombarding it with a lot
of requests, then the system is gone.
But when you move from sync to async,
consistency, I would not say you'll have
to a hundred percent compromise, but.
You might have to make a little
compromise, like I said, right?
So since we do everything
asynchronously, what happens?
Customer I, a device and an accessory,
and then he submit an order, but
by the time he come to the store.
If within the store if there
are no accessories, then you
know, we have to trade off.
Same saying that, hey, you can
only buy a device because it's
access event of out of stock.
It's a little inconsistent, but still,
we try to again keep up the inventory up
to date and make sure that the customer
gets what he pay, what he orders for.
But again, you'll have to trade
off, between availability versus,
consistency and then what we do, right?
What we do.
And in our solution, when we
move from sync to acing, the
important thing is, add potency.
When we, when we make sure if some
failure happens, we have to suppress
this duplicate side effects, let's
say a payment failed, then you
shouldn't continuously charge customer
you should not charge three times.
Make sure that if customer is charged
once, then you don't charge him at all.
And then worsening, tracking changes
and ensuring correct state the solution,
and then compensating transactions.
So if something goes wrong, then we
undo, or mitigate the fail steps.
One of the core, one of the core,
thi one of the core tradeoffs
in distributed systems, is
explained very well by this cap.
The, it tells us, we can only choose
between two of three guarantees.
Like either, cons if you want
to out of these three, right?
The consistency, availability,
partition tolerance, you can only
choose two between sync versus ing.
If it is sync, then it is consistent
and it is partition tolerant.
But if it is asing, then it's
available and then partition tolerant.
And in a high scale event driven commerce
partition tolerance is non-negotiable.
Failures will happen.
So we typically prioritize
availability, meaning we must relax.
Strict consistency.
This leads to eventual consistency.
Data will convert, but not in
instantly to manage this effectively.
We, like I said, we use
a lot of techniques.
We design the services that are I
important so that, repeated events
don't cause duplicate effects.
For example, if payment confirmation
is sent twice we shouldn't
charge the customer again.
We ensure that the RET trays are safe.
And then versioning, we attach
version numbers to entities
like orders of payments.
This helps us detect and
resolve these conditions.
If two systems try to update the same
entities simultaneously, the version
ensures only the correct one is applied.
And then compensating transactions.
We, when things go wrong,
we don't roll back.
We instead, we emit events to
undo the mitigation issues.
For example, if an order was confirmed,
but payment later failed, we aim at a
cancellation event and restore inventory.
Like I said, observability
plays a critical role here.
It alerts us when events fail out of sync.
Tree tray are piling up, or
state transitions don't complete.
Without the availability,
we wouldn't know.
Consistency is broken until
a customer complains with it.
We can react in near real time
and fix issues proactively.
Yeah.
How do we really test the acing systems?
How do we simulate delays, how
do we simulate message losses?
How do we take an action to restart them?
How do we again validate retry,
logic, fallbacks and ency,
focus, again, monitoring.
How do we monitor the Q depth?
How do we monitor, detect the backlogs?
How do we latency, how
do we track the delays?
And then how do we make sure
the events sequencer correct
and complete the testing?
Asynchronous systems is fundamentally
different from traditional applications.
It's not just checking about
individual service or EPAs.
It's about testing the system
behavior over time, under
pressure, and across boundaries.
Let's break it down.
Simulated failures.
We simulate the real world
scenario such as delayed customers.
What happens if a service is slow?
Or if the service is slow
to process a message?
And then what happens
if the message is lost?
What if even never reaches a
destination due to a transit and outage?
And then service, let's say, how
does the system behave when one
component research, media event, this
helps validate our retry, duplicate
duplication, and fallback mechanisms
according, actually work in the practice.
These things work in
practice, but not in theory.
Monitoring essentials.
Asy observability means watching
the systems as connected.
Draft of event flows,
not isolated services.
We focus on Q depth, and where, large
backlogs may indicate low consumers
or broken processs processing latency.
Now, are events being handled
with acceptable time windows?
If not, where's the bottleneck?
Casual chains, we can trace a customer's
order from placement to fulfillment.
Missing links could mean drop
events or unhandled failures.
A common pitfall is thinking a
green dashboard means everything is
okay and in asing systems, services
might be up, but flow is broken.
That's why we don't just, test endpoints,
which as the system end to end,
you know, what lessons we have learned
when we implemented Async, I'll wrap up.
The major lessons that we have learned
from building scaling Async commerce
systems designed for traceability, I. I
always emphasize this, you have to, when
you're building a system, you build the
design on how you want to trace them.
Tracing isn't something
you can bolt on later.
Most of the things we feel that,
we let's implement a design, and
then tracing can be done later.
But for Asing, I would recommend,
first you think of tracing.
How do you want to trace the events
and then it has to be intentional.
This means, using consistent trace IDs,
structural logging, and participating.
And propagating context across services
and event handlers from the start.
If you skip this early, you will struggle,
debug, monitor, and support your systems
as it trust me, it's very hard if you
wanted to think about tracing it then.
So always design, looking at how
you want to trace them, and then
accept and plan for eventual
consistency in distributed systems.
Chasing perfect real consistency will
hurt your availability and scalability.
Instead, we have learned to embrace
eventual consistency and engineer
around it using strategies like
operations, compensating transactions.
Observability is what
keeps us honest there.
It lets us know when consistency breaks
and help us to fix it proactively.
Again, I would say align
metrics to business events.
This is key for making observability
useful beyond engineering.
Developers care about
locks, spans and error, but.
Product managers and support teams care
about orders, not shipping payments,
truck in retre or event or syncing.
So building dashboards and alerts
that helps speak up the language.
It shows how turn it shows, how
you turn observability from a dev
tool into an organizational asset.
I would, I would like to conclude saying
that, as in commerce, architectures
give us what modern demand, scalability,
flexibility, and resilience.
They allow different parts of the
business to move at their own pace.
Orders can be taken while
payments are still processing.
Inventory can update independently,
and notifications can be retried
without blocking the user.
But here's a catch.
What that flexibility comes,
it comes with the complexity.
Things happen in parallel
in different systems.
At unpredictable times.
If we can't see across these
flows, we are flying by it.
That's why observability isn't.
Just the technical layer.
It's a strategic enabler.
It's what allows us to build fast,
recover faster, and continuously
improve when observability is built.
We don't want just to operate, we
understand, when something grow,
wide, grow and what to do next.
That's how we maintain trust in
the customer experience, even
when the backend gets messy.
So as we build asynchronous.
Commerce event driven systems.
Let's make sure observability
stays a first class citizen.
It's the difference between hopping
things work and knowing they do.
And thank you very much for patiently
listening on this, and please let me know,
like when you are building, when you're
building anything acing, I'm happy to.
Help.
And I, I hope decision gives you practical
insights about building and operating
async commerce systems with confidence.
And if you're working on similar
architectures or facing any challenges, I
would love to continue this conversation.
Feel free to reach me via email
or connect me on LinkedIn.
Thank you.
Bye-bye.
Have a good day.