Hello everyone.
I'm pr data solution
architect with Quantified.
So I have over 10 years of experience
in designing cloud native analytics
platforms for several different
customers specifically on AWS.
And in working with customers from
different domains, I've repeatedly
seen a common pattern, which is
services are often were misapplied.
So specifically when it comes
to observability, it leads to
a lot of bad outcomes, which is
it leads to blind spots, alert,
fatigue, balloon cough, and mis.
So today at QU Con 42 we will keep
it at a very high level and focus
mainly on real world monitoring
and observability use cases.
In today's cloud first managed services
promises, agility, accountability,
and reduced operational overhead.
And these services have become
the foundation of modern
digital and data architectures.
And the ease of adoption often masks a
very critical risk, which is misalignment
between the service capabilities
and actual workload requirements.
So when cloud services are selected
without clear understanding of their
intended function in context, they can
definitely introduce long-term friction
and it costs teams valuable time,
capacity, and financial resources so
that by the end of the session, we will
have a clear mapping of the requirement
tool choices, so that we never over or
under provision our telemetry stack.
And it addition framework that will
help us wa it and see complexity and
granularity and best practices and common
pitfalls to watch out as we build and
optimize our observability layer in AWS.
So what is observability?
So observability is nothing but the
measure of internal state of the system.
By examining outputs such as
logs, metrics, and traces,
it's not about just monitoring.
It's about deep insight and
understanding the system.
And its main purpose is to
empower teams to direct, diagnose,
and resolve issues faster.
So it helps improve reliability,
performance, and user satisfaction.
So when it comes to cloud platforms,
cloud and data platforms, we have a lot
of microservices, serverless functions,
distributed pipelines, and observability
is connected tissue that holds the
modern data architectures together.
So without it blind spots emerge
lead to increasing downtime.
User frustration and loss of trust.
So from a strategic standpoint,
observability is the foundation for
cloud analytics platform and it enables
real time decision making, compliance
assurance, and proactive optimization.
So here are some core
pillars of observability.
So one is logs second is
metrics, and third is traces.
So let's understand each one of these.
Locks are nothing but in immutable
records of events that have occurred
within the system, such as error
messages, user actions, state
changes it locks provide granular,
timestamped context and are vital for
post-incident analysis and auditing.
When it comes to metrics quantitative
measurements taken at interval,
for example, we take CP usage.
So it's a quantitative
metric that 80% is utilized.
Memory, it's a quantitative metric.
Request counts error rates, right?
These are all, something we call
metrics and these are compact
and efficient for trend analysis.
How's the CCP utilization over time?
How's the performance over time?
So this is something the metrics are going
to be really helpful in such scenario.
And the last one is traces.
So tracers show the journey of
a single request for example,
across various services.
So it catches the latency.
And this is very critical
for understanding complex
and interconnected systems.
And it'll definitely help
with the root cause analysis.
So let's understand some of
the core services in AWS.
The very first one is CloudWatch.
So when it comes to capabilities
it is used for lock collection.
Metric aggregation customizable dashboards
for alarms and automated actions.
The general use case is general
purpose monitoring, alerting,
and automated responses.
So CloudWatch is a foundational
observability tool provided by AWS.
So it'll allow us to gather all these
logs, metrics and define these dashboards.
We will also have an ability to
configure customer alarms, proactive
alerts, and automated remediation.
So it's a versatile and integrate
seamlessly across various AWS services.
Making it very ideal for monitoring
and basic troubleshooting.
So when it comes to x-ray end-to-end
tracing requests through distributed
application detail, insights into
microservice interaction, and
it's mainly used for debugging and
performance optimization of these
microservices so we can understand.
Which microservices is taking
more time versus the one that
is acting up very quickly.
So it's a very helpful service
and offering that AWS has.
So the next one is the managed Grafana.
Capabilities wise, it's very
rich in terms of visualization.
It provides seamless integration
with multiple AWS services.
As well as multiple open source
databases, it'll provide real
time dashboards and analytics.
So majorly this managed Grafana is used
for real time visualization of system
metrics and logs for operational insight.
The next one is a BI offering.
So QuickSight, it's
it's called QuickSight.
It's a very popular tool and, the
cab are, it's a bi service offering.
It's not really an observability tool,
but it provides interactive dashboards in
insightful analytics and natural language
query processing using QuickSight queue.
So the use case wise, it is used for
business intelligence and analytics
reporting with periodic data refresh.
It's not real time though.
And the last one is
restore for Open Telemetry.
So capabilities include standardized
instrumentation and data collection
across various platforms.
So it's a vendor neutral
broad comparability.
So it provides a unified observability
across our diverse application stacks.
So here is another list of
expanded AWS observability tools.
The first one is cloud rail.
So CloudTrail audits every a PA action
in AWS account essential for governance
compliance tracking and tracking changes.
So it locks any unauthorized attempt
to access something or and it keeps
the log of various services interacting
with each other, or, the users
trying to access certain services.
It'll try to keep track
of all those actions.
AWS config on the other hand continuously
monitors the resource configuration.
It ensures adherence to the
regulatory standards and DevOps crew.
It uses ML to detect anomalies in the
application, suggesting root causes.
And remediations, it's a very
helpful tool and trusted advisor.
It evaluates our AWS setup.
Again, as best practices for cost,
security and performance and provide
recommendations compute optimizer so it
recommends the most efficient compute
a resource based on our usage patterns.
And finally, inspector, it automates
the the security scans on EC2
Lambda Uncon container workloads.
So let's understand now
some architecture patterns.
Centralized telemetry pipelines.
So we collect a store process
observability data from various
sources in a centralized manner using
services like S3 and open search.
And when it comes to real time
monitoring, so let's say if you
want to enable live dashboards.
And alert alerts using tools like
Grafana and CloudWatch for immediate
visibility into system performance.
In this scenario, like Grafana
and CloudWatch stands out.
Along with that, we can use multiple
other services, which can be easily
integrated to send notifications
like S-N-S-S-E-S, et cetera.
And for AI ML integration.
So it's recommended to leverage
AWS SageMaker and bedrock to apply
machine learning models for prior
to analysis on automatic automated
diagnostics and anomaly detection.
So for automated response implement
automated remediation and scaling
using AWS Lambda and eBridge, it'll
help us quickly address, issue,
and maintain the reliability.
As it is mentioned a robust observability
architecture, centralizes the data
powers real time monitoring and
leverages ai and automate the response
for resilience and scalability.
So now let's understand what is
function and what is friction.
So it's a framework that we
should keep in mind when.
Selecting cloud managed services
and it's very important to
follow this approach, right?
So function is when tools we
pick, accelerate, insight, and
integrate seamlessly at scale.
So observability tools empower
teams by providing clear,
fast, and aligned insights.
On the other hand, friction is when.
Tool introduces the
noise lag and complexity.
So it often come hinders team ability
and causes delays and confusion
and ultimately a higher cause.
So looking through function versus
friction lens, it'll help teams to choose
observability tools that drives the
operational excellence by maximizing the
insights and minimizing the complexity.
Now let's take a look at
the examples of function.
So the very first one is using
CloudWatch alarms for real time alerts.
So it's a very good function.
So it's recommended and best practice.
To use cloud wash to collect
metrics logs and visualize the data
using cloud wash data dashboards.
And we can also have trigger alarm
for EC2 monitoring Lambda metrics,
container insights and cost tracking.
So it's a very helpful
tool in this context.
Cloud wash definitely acts, adds
a function and it's, whenever
we have such use case, it's
recommended to go with CloudWatch.
And the next one is X-ray for
pinpointing service bottlenecks.
So let's say we have a web of
microservices that's that are, and we
don't know, like what is taking more time.
So in such scenarios x-ray provides a
distributed tracing for microservices.
And it'll help us debug
the performance issues.
Traces API, gateway lambda flows
and visualize the service maps.
So it's a great tool and it'll help
identify bottlenecks very easily.
So it's another example of function
and my favorite one is Grafana
Dashboard for live performance views.
So not only just for
observability, but for monitoring.
Iot many other use cases.
So Grafana or Managed Grafana enables
live dashboards from cloud Wash
Prometheus and several data sources.
You can name it.
Used in N Cs solar tracking service
level objective and anomaly detection.
And open telemetry for
unified instrumentation.
It provides standardized instrumentation
across applications like E-C-S-E-K-S
or hybrid environments, sending data
to CloudWatch or third party tools.
So these tools overall reduce time to
detect and time to resolve provides
actionable and high value insights
that drive the operational excellence.
Let's see some examples of friction.
So let's say if you use QuickSight
for realtime monitoring, right?
So QuickSight is not a real
realtime tool that we can use.
So using QuickSight for
realtime monitoring, definitely
there is going to be a lag.
And it, it is due to the nature
of QuickSight batch processing.
Approach that it makes it un unsuitable
for time sensitive monitoring and
scaling CloudWatch logs without structured
queries, acquiring challenges due
to unstructured log data, leading to
reduced visibility and insights and,
overlapping tools without integration.
So tools, sprawl causing fragmented
data and complexity, and it hinders
collaboration and efficiency.
Friction arises when tools
are misapplied, architectures,
fragment, or signal overwhelm teams.
So it leads to delays
confusion and higher cost.
So what is the role of
genis and observability?
So today there is a lot of
hype about AI and it definitely
has a role in observability.
So one is credit to
analytics, to forecast issues.
That's more of a machine learning.
So we use machine learning to predict
problems and system failures before they
occur, and enable proactive remediation.
And automated diagnostic
tools suggest root causes.
So we can use the AI powered analysis
of logs, metrics, and traces to
quickly identify root causes of
issues and can help accelerate
troubleshooting and resolution.
And we can also use natural language
processing to simplify inserts.
Allow users to ask questions about
system performance and behavior in plan.
So it'll help us generate tailored
visualizations and reports.
And then smart alert
alerting to reduce noise.
So we use machine learning to
intelligently filter and prioritize
alerts to reduce alert static and ensure
teams focus on most critical issues.
So Gen AI or machine learning when
it comes to observability they
are ready to foresight, accelerate
diagnostics and enabling simpler,
more intuitive access to the insights.
So earlier when we discussed function
with friction, we discussed and
understood how choosing the wrong tool
can impact overall objectives, right?
So here we'll discuss, some of the common
pitfalls and how we can mitigate them.
Siloed tools.
So observability tools that are
not integrated leads to fragmented
data and reduced data visibility.
So it'll cause all fat.
Overwhelming number of alerts, distract
and desensitize teams, and they'll
hinder effective response And reactive
troubleshooting, relying on manual time
consuming process to diagnose and resolve
issues rather than proactive prevention.
And addressing this common pitfalls
upfront ensures observability
and strengthens the operation
without overwhelming teams through
centralized pipelines, automated
alerts, and design time observability
integration coming to best practices.
So it's important to
implement observability early.
Always incorporate observability
capabilities into your architecture
and design process from the start
rather than bolting it later.
So align SLOs and SLIs service
level objectives and service level
indicators to the business goals.
Ensure observability metrics and
targets are closely tied to the KPIs
that drive the organization's success.
It's very important.
And leverage automation wherever
possible, and machine learning.
Automating observability tasks
like a large generation root
cause analysis help optimize and
improve efficiency and accuracy.
And last but not least focus on
continuously improving reviewing
and optimizing the pipelines.
So regularly assessing the
pipelines or tools and processes
to identify areas for improvement
and ensure they remain relevant.
So observability thrives when baked
into the architecture, so aligned to the
business value, consistently refined,
and for efficiency and relevance.
In this slide, we'll talk about real
world use cases, various use cases are
applicable for I'm just discussing a
few of them, which is manufacturing iot.
So help monitor sensor sticker, predict
to maintenance optimized uptime.
So for financial platforms, trace
transaction, direct fraud, and mantra
e-commerce track conversions, right?
So monitor customer journeys,
AB test performance.
Many other things.
Real world example shows how
observability drives operational,
financial, and customer outcomes from
factory floor to the online storefront.
So in summary, observability enables
scalable, resilient, and reliable systems.
It's very crucial for modern
data and cloud native systems.
It'll enable teams to maintain
reliability, performance, and trust.
And so AWS offers powerful suit of
observability tools like CloudWatch,
X-Ray Grafana that provide diverse
per perspectives on system health.
And from a best practice standpoint we
can definitely rely leverage gen ai.
To a strategic advantage by
following observability best
practices and leveraging power of ai.
And machine learning organizations can
bring strategic strategic advantage
through real time insights spread
to analytics and automated response.
So it is very important for
modern cloud native system and
AWS provides a comprehensive
observability tool sets and by.
Combining it with best practices
that latest AI capabilities.
So yeah.
So finally as we conclude, so
observability in AWS it's very
not just AWS but any cloud
offering, it's very important.
It's a very crucial capability for
modern data architectures and solutions.
It enables teams to maintain
reliability, performance, and trust.
And using some of the, approaches,
recommendations, and best practices we
can build scalable and res resilient and
reliable systems that can drive strategic
advantages through real time inserts
prior to analytics and automated response.
Thank you.