All right.
Hey guys.
Good day.
I'm here to talk about observability
with Kafka, and how do you make sure that
you treat observability as a first class
citizen when you're dealing with Kafka,
and how do you ensure visibility at scale?
Kafka, as we know, is a backbone
for modern data streaming and any
messaging ecosystems at this point.
So anything as soon as.
If you talk about Kafka, you'll
want to talk about observability
because if your Kafka cluster fails.
It's gonna be a good problem.
So let's talk about how you can add
observability to your Kafka ecosystem.
Using the MELT Stack as how I like
to call it, melt is an acronym for
metrics, events, logs, and traces.
And we are gonna talk
about all four of those.
For Kafka let's start why
Kafka needs observability.
As you can see here, server
rack in the photo here.
Basically what this is trying to tell
you is that Kafka is not just one server.
It's almost always a conglomerate
of servers working together.
As a cluster to ensure high
availability and reliability and
replication for your data sets.
It has become a critical infrastructure
for a lot of data streaming systems.
So an early detection is really critical.
You wanna understand if there are,
there is gonna be a broker crash.
If there is gonna, there is a lot of
memory pressure if there is a replication
lag, if their consumers are lagging.
Things like that.
It also helps with fast
troubleshooting, right?
If you have proper observability set
up for your Kafka clusters and your
producers and consumers it makes
it a little easier for anybody and
everyone to actually troubleshoot.
The problems when they occur, and
maybe sometimes even before they occur.
Yeah, troubleshooting.
And then because you have all those
metrics, you will be able to dig
deep into the performance insights
for the cluster and understand
how your clusters performing.
Is it doing really well?
Where are the bottlenecks?
Where are the issues?
What the heat map looks
like, things like that.
So let's get into it.
Let's talk about the meld stack, right?
We, I just introduced it earlier and we
are gonna talk about it a little more.
In this pyramid, if you see the
basis is the metrics, right?
We wanna make sure that we gather all
the metrics from Kafka and we are gonna
talk about those what the metrics are.
These are basically
numerical measurements.
Next is the events, and we
are gonna talk about all of
those in a little more detail.
So bear with me while I
go through these things.
Events are things like, actually,
let's talk about metrics first.
Metrics are the numerical
measurements of what, of whatever
is happening within your system.
Those are metrics which are
exposed via the, Kafka brokers.
They Kafka has a lot of, metrics that
it exposes out of the box by default.
And you can use things like Prometheus
and Prometheus exporters to convert them
into a proper open, telemetric compatible
formats or Prometheus compatible formats
and expose all those MBE outside.
Those are just the metrics
that you want to share.
See, and those will give you
the performance traits, the
functionality traits, and what's
going on within your ecosystem.
Events are something like.
Hey, my broker crashed.
It's restarting.
Something happened in the cluster.
My disc is around 70% full.
I should probably generate an
alert so that I can add more
disc space to the cluster.
My network throughput
is probably saturated.
I need to think about either
adding more servers and
rebalancing on the server servers.
Or I have to think about how do
I scale up the network eco the
network end points or the switches.
So all of those could be events.
Generally, the events from Kafka
are not exposed by the brokers.
They'll probably be part
of the logs and metrics.
So there will be no explicit discussion
around those that we make, but.
Think about it, right?
That there are certain things
that could be care categorized
as events within Kafka.
Nowadays people are even deploying Kafka
on Kubernetes, so all the Kubernetes
events could be related as well.
When there is a network change, when
the pod moves, when the pod crashes,
when the pod restarts, all those events
might be correlatable to your Kafka.
Performance and impacts on
their day-to-day working of
that Kafka cluster as well.
Event events are really helpful
optional, but helpful logs
not at all optional, right?
You'll want logs from your
Kafka brokers no matter what.
You'll want your Kafka logs from somewhere
your in your client codes as well.
You want all of them talk?
Take a look at my older
older talks that I have.
You will want all those logs
aggregated into an aggregation system.
Instead of having five aggregated
systems, or five, five different
systems for logs have maybe one.
Where you get all that stuff
back and you can actually track
them and search them easily.
Logs are critical, super critical traces.
So these function, not at the
Kafka broker level, but at the
client level, more or less.
The whole point of these things existing
and traces are more like, Hey, I'm
gonna add a watermark to every one of
my message, and I'll see that wherever
I see that message flowing, I'll be able
to track the entire workflow from there.
And that's the whole purpose of traces.
One, it gives you how much time
did it spend in particular.
Specific client if it, if there
was some processing going on.
Second, it also traces, like I
said, it traces the entire workflow
for you, where was all, where
all was this message located?
What all hops did it take and
how did it end up eventually?
So traces optional, but again, good
to have a detailed view of what
your functional system is doing
instead of the operat, instead of the
operational system, how that's doing.
That will give you your pyramid of the
melt stack, the top end, the complete
observability for 360 degree visibility
in your Kafka cluster ecosystem.
Tool chain recommendations are
generally hard and I don't like to
make tool chain recommendations.
But this is where I'm diverging
because I love Prometheus.
Open source community sponsored, community
run, community driven, log aggregation.
TSDB platform, not log, but metrics,
aggregation, TSDB time series database.
Open telemetry.
Again, as the name says, open,
that's a standard at this point.
Everybody wants to use that.
Everybody uses that.
And because it's a standard, it's
easily you can move from Promeus
to Prometheus to something else
in future if you really need to.
And still say compatible if they
support the open telemetry formats.
So that's something which I'll
say is critical that you want
to have in your ecosystem.
Grafana is one of my recommendations
just because I love Grafana.
That's all right.
It has nothing to do with the open
source, although they have an open
source view and they have an open
source component that they allow
you everybody to use in the world.
But I just love Grafana.
It's easy.
It's much more manageable.
It directly talks to Prometheus, it
talks to Elastic if it really needed to.
There are like multiple ecosystems that
it can plug in with and still display
your beautiful graphs as you need them.
Grafana, it's, let's d start
diving into the meld stack now.
Metrics system, health
indicators, what are they?
As I just referencing earlier, these
are like numerical measurements that
indicate your health of the system,
the performance of the system, what
it's doing at that point, all those.
Points of interest that you
would have in the ecosystem.
Those are co, those are basically metrics.
How many requests did I process?
Is my disc back pressure?
Is my network thread count enough to
tolerate the incoming brush of requests
from the producers and consumers?
That's where, that's the
data that you want, and those
are all coming from metrics.
Replication, lags metrics, consumer
lag metrics, all that stuff is metrics.
They matter because they fail
from the basis of your view
and observability into Kafka.
So they are super important forms.
The baseline foundations offer
pyramid of observability.
So yeah, make sure you
have metrics available.
Events.
These are the second things which we want,
which we briefly talked about, right?
Discrete state changes, right?
For Kubernetes or crashes or restarts.
There is a rollout, there
is a new deployment.
500 different things can happen.
Those are all events.
Similar for Kafka, right?
You could have a broker crash, you
could have a deployment, you could
have a maintenance window where
your Kafka cluster is rolling.
So all that stuff are
events for you, right?
And those will provide you the
context to why your metrics are
spiking at some point of time.
So for example, let's say you
started a initiated a rollout for
your cluster and you're rolling one
broker by after the other, right?
So there will be latency spikes,
which you'll see from your producers,
and then twin latencies will suffer
and they are suffering because
you're clear rolling the cluster.
There's no other correlation.
More, more or less, right?
And.
If you see metrics by themselves in
that window, you'll probably not be
able to understand why that's happening.
Once you add an event to it, the
mixture, you'll be able to see, oh, okay.
The latency spiked because
my cluster was rolling.
I had a new power restart, and it
took up some time for it to get
pro promoted itself to leaders.
Things happened in, and the latency kicked
up a notch for a few milliseconds, right?
That's where it, that's important.
Logs like we talked, it's, they're
timestamped, they're detailed records of
activities that the system was performing.
So yeah, if there is any error, if there
is a error stack, Java error stack, that
all comes out through your server logs.
Things like authentications,
authorizations, whatever is
happening within your system.
Those will be tracked through the logs.
Depends on the velocity of
the logs that you choose.
But yeah, again, you can go as granular
as you want and keep or keep it as
informatic, informational, as you want.
They matter a lot because metrics, plus
logs, plus events, those are the way how
you determine what your system is doing,
why your system is doing all that stuff.
And it's important for Kafka as well.
A big example of this could be,
hey, if there was a controller
election, what happened?
If there is frequent client
disconnections, what's going on?
If there is a producer loop, when the
producer is producing, if the network
who was backing up, if your disc was
backing up, what was going on, those kind
of things can be exposed via the logs.
Some of it is visible through the metrics.
Sure.
But once you get, get to see
the symptom, you'll want to see
why that symptom's occurring.
And that's gonna happen with the
logs, only with the logs, traces as
we talked about it's at the functional
layer, so you may consider it as
optional, but you'll want to think
about an end-to-end request flow,
and that's where traces shine, right?
It's not about.
Kafka anymore.
This is more like your application
and your business logic.
A lot of customers do use it and
generally they had add headers
to the Kafka message itself.
So Kafka headers, every
message has a header.
You can probably basically
add a header header row in
there and have that watermark.
Persists throughout the scope
of that life, of that message.
And wherever it goes, wherever
it's read, that Kafka header can
basically just say, Hey I came here.
So that watermark will persist
in all those processing systems.
Whatever you use on top of Kafka, they
will tell you that this message came here.
So yeah, it helps with
transaction flows specifically.
Like I said, you would want to
use all four of the MEL signals.
They have complimentary perspectives.
Not neither one of them
are enough by themselves.
Right metrics will help you
determine anomalies in real time.
Events will tie those anomalies to
specific changes if there are logs, will
provide you deep details for debugging
and understanding if there was no
anomaly, what happened in the system
so that you can see what's going on.
And traces will actually help you
visualize the end-to-end paths above
Kafka at some point of time in the
business layer so that you can understand
what's going on to give you a holistic
view of what's going on in your system.
Yeah, you want complete picture,
you want complimentary perspectives.
That's why all signals are
more or less important.
You choose which ones
are the best ones to use.
To start with, my recommendation would
be start with metrics at a bare minimum
and logs at a bare minimum, and then
graduate from there into the events
and the tracing systems beyond that.
Alright, let's talk about, let's dig a
little deeper and into the Kafka metrics.
This is one of the big goals for
observability and you will wanna make
sure that you have enough Kafka metrics.
But Kafka can sometimes overwhelm
you with a lot of metrics.
The last time I was counting and
it was like a fair two, three years
ago, Kafka had about 3,500 MBS
that had exposed almost 3,500 mbs.
Again, permutation and combinations
included not just the unique MBE names,
but yeah, permutations for all the data.
And that was very bare minimum cluster
that I was running on my home server.
So yeah, it has a lot of data that it
spits out a lot of time series that will
create, and you will have to make sure.
That you are cherry picking
the right ones that you need.
Not everything is as important
as something like replication
lag, for example, right?
Or CPU consumption or network IO load.
How much is the network thread usage?
Those kind of things are really
important to start with, the biggest
key indicators, like I said, right?
Replication, health,
partition distribution, how
well are they distributed?
How well are the leaders distributed?
So you'll want to make
sure you understand those.
You should not have a very hot
broker where a lot of partitions
just concentrate together as a leader
and the others are sitting idle.
You'll want those leadership to
get distributed, and you can use
various tools for all that, right?
This is not a Kafka admin talk, which
we are talking about, but you'll want
to make sure that you have enough.
Capacity available on each of these
brokers and those capacity being utilized
almost evenly as much as possible so
that your cluster can shine the way
it should as a cluster and should
not get throttled by a single broker.
Error rates very important.
How many requests failed?
How many fetch requests failed?
How many produced requests failed?
Maybe something failed in replication.
I wanna understand that.
What are the error indicators
and what all those things mean?
Probably something more important, but
you'll prob you'll want to understand
those things to get more clear picture
of how your Kafka cluster is performing.
I have mentioned network utilization
like multiple times already, right?
Network utilization is by far the
most precious resource that you'll
want to monitor for a Kafka cluster.
Everything's network right in the end.
Kafka is replicating a data
back in the background.
Between multiple brokers across
the replica across the replicas
that you allow it to, the number
of replicas that you configure it
for those will need network, right?
Enough network capacity.
So if you're producing at a thousand
wags per second, or 125 megabytes
per second, you are probably already
using most of the capacity available
in the one gigabit ethernet port.
You would probably want a 10 gigabit
that SFP port on your Kafka brokers.
Again, not getting into the
hardware, but you have to understand
the capacity requirements.
At what scale your Kafka
cluster is operating.
If it's a small scale cluster,
it doesn't matter, right?
One gigabit per second ethernet
port probably will work.
Probably need a bonded
port for that, right?
And network one gigabit
per second bonded port.
That might give you around
101, 1.5 gigabits per second.
But it depends, right?
Again, your use case, your scenarios, how
much your utilization is that is gonna
be told by, or that is the answer which
you're gonna get from your metrics, right?
So make sure you have those.
How do you instrument those?
So this is way more important.
Now I've been talking about
why those are important, but
how do you instrument those?
Kafka exposes all those mbe,
they're called mbs, and those
MBS are exposed via GMX.
So you enable GMX metrics on
all the brokers and clients.
Technically if you want the client
metrics, but brokers you definitely
want, deploy a metrics scraper, right?
Something like a Prometheus.
JMX exporter is awesome.
Recently it has been getting a
lot more attention than it was
getting like three years ago.
So it's improving a lot.
It's basically the whole point of
A-A-G-M-X exporter is to convert
the JMXM beans and convert them
from a Java centric format to more.
TTP compatible format, if I may, right?
It's a very weird analogy, but yeah.
The JMX gets converted into a metrics
endpoint, which is an s ttp STTP
endpoint on a specific port where it
generates a single page and all those
lines it generates in there are metrics.
That's it right now when you deploy those.
The Kafka brokers will expose those
metrics, which are scrapable right
now, your Prometheus endpoint or
Prometheus server or some other server,
whatever you're using, they'll have
to go and scrape all those endpoints
from all the brokers and gather
them into one single server, right?
So you'll want to make sure that is done.
For clients specifically, and this is
where, newer versions of Kafka Shines.
Kafka added the feature where
clients can actually ship their
metrics, some of their metrics.
The really important ones, at least to
the Kafka broker for exposition, right?
The, that's called Kip seven 14, and it
was available in Kafka 3.7 and above.
So if you're using 3.7 and above.
You have Kip seven 14 already available.
We'll probably wanna implement that one.
One abstract class that they
provided, and then it'll be able
to expose it via open telemetry or
Prometheus based exposition formats.
So you'll be able to centrally collect
the client metrics coming from all
your clients directly from the brokers.
So you would not have to
instrument Kafka and all its
consumers or all its producers.
With JMX, you'll probably just have
to do it for the Kafka cluster and
it'll give you the most important
metrics from your clients as well.
Pretty recent change, but this
has an awesome game changer event.
So yeah, simple Flow Kafka, it
exposes the metrics in JMX format.
You go through the the telemetry
collectors, open Telemetry or Prometheus,
GMX, they are interoperable with
the open telemetry format as well.
Prometheus.
Scrapes, the Kafka endpoint, the Kafka
Open Telemetry, or the Prometheus Exporter
endpoint and stores that time series
data within itself, Grafana basically
connects to Prometheus and exposes that
data as pretty graphs or dashboards.
We are not gonna talk about events
too much because events are in
between the metrics and the logs
where some of the events can be.
Decrypted for lack of a better
term, from the metrics itself.
So basically, if your system is not
available or your broker's not online,
it could mean that it either crashed
or it went down, or this is an event
for a broker role of some kind, right?
Similarly there are things like there is a
replication issue, probably logs are gonna
tell you all that stuff much more cleaner.
There is no inherent.
It built way to expose
Kafka events as such.
So you'll have to rely on a mixture
of logs and metrics to get some of
those event related features available.
So we, I'm gonna talk about logs
directly and just wanna tell you why
events is not present in the slide deck.
Kafka logs.
This is the observability another
observability goal, right?
Again, and one of the more important
ones gives you detailed troubleshooting.
Logs are really rich and this, they
will tell you why the errors occurred,
what you're seeing in the metrics.
And so these are really important systems.
Whenever there's an error, whenever
there's an issue, any stack trace,
every stack trace is important, and
this is where logs will help you.
RCAs cannot be completed without logs.
Don't even think about it if you
don't have the logs available.
So yeah, they are really important.
And another thing which I would say is
when you are exposing logs.
Probably expose them as chase on values
if you can with and I think I'm probably
gonna talk about that in a moment.
Yeah, there you go.
Alright.
I'll get to that in a minute.
Minute.
So when you're talking about the logs
they'll give you the error details,
they'll give you the state changes
again, goes back to the events.
Controller elections, partition
movements, leadership changes, all
that stuff are, could be technically
labeled as events, so you'll want to
extract them from the logs itself.
Hence logs are important.
Client activity, it will tell you
what the client activity looks like.
If you're connecting to older brokers
or older clients per se, those things,
one of those big things, right?
Then they'll come up as
the logs also as well.
So yeah, all those things are important.
Instrumentation.
So you want your logs to be
really high quality, right?
Log four J was the standard for Kafka.
If I remember correctly with 4.0 and
above I think they moved to lock four
J two, but even the lock four J was
patched version for Kafka specifically,
it was not the standard lock four J
version, which had the big CV a while ago.
Use the JSON if you can structure
it format like js ON because
they are really helpful for any
machine to parse those messages.
Otherwise, you'll have to
create all those parsers.
Parcel formatting is not that easy.
So I, believe me, I've tried
to do that in metricbeat and
things like that, or Logbeat.
It takes a while to go through
and ensure every use case is
actually handled and enough.
So yeah, set a log, four
J properties well enough.
If you have JSON available use JSO,
it'll be much more easier to par for
the machines and get that stuff done.
Yes, it'll swell up your log volume.
Yes.
But it helps your machines and
to understand all that stuff.
Deploy something like
filebeat, definitely right.
You will want the collectors to
stream it to a central location so
that they don't have to go to each
broker every time there is an issue.
That will not be sustainable.
Once you go beyond a single cluster, as
soon as even if you have two clusters,
it's gonna be untenable, right?
You want them to be shipped to
a central location filterable
by the brokers, the clusters.
All that stuff has to filterable, right?
So it should be available.
Retention strategy is important.
Don't set a retention
strategy to seven days.
It's not enough.
I can tell you very confidently because
I've done that did not bode well for me.
So yeah, seven days not a good idea.
And that was like few years ago
for me, so I was still naive.
Hey, who needs more than seven days?
Both the logs.
That's not the way how it goes.
You'll need logs to be
more than seven days.
Definitely.
A good way to understand how
long will you need the logs
would be something like, Hey.
What time do I allow my application
teams to actually come back to me
and ask for issues and referrals
and debugs into the issues, right?
Deep dives into the issues.
So if it's something like around 30
days, you'll probably want like 45
days worth of logs to be retained
and then phased out after that.
There are ways to do maybe
keep some of them in the heart.
Storage, keep some in the warm
storage so that, and maybe export
them out to the cold storage after
a while so that you don't have to
delete all of them, but reduce costs.
So that's also possible, but again,
establish a retention strategy.
You'll want to think about it.
There are great talks on the internet
around how do you want to talk about
the retention strategy for logs
and cost implications around that.
So check those out.
Simple implementation would be Kafka,
log files, structure logs, json if you
can something like an Open Telemetry
collector or a filebeat or a, yeah,
Filebeat is probably the right one.
Grafana.
Loki, I love Grafana.
As I said, as a company.
They introduced another
product called Grafana.
Loki.
This is more like a Grafana, but not
for metrics, but for logs, right?
Excellent product.
Check that out if you want.
And then Grafana ui of course, to
search and filter through those logs.
This is not to say that you
have to use this exact stack.
You can mix and match how you,
you can replace these components
with something else that you
already have or your enterprise.
So please feel free.
Do not think that these are.
The set guidelines or parameters
that you're gonna follow, right?
You can change and mix and
match how you, however you like.
Traces, like I said, is the
last part of this thing, right?
The whole workflow.
But this is more at the application
level, tracking, not at the Kafka level
tracking, but it gives you end-to-end
visibility of what's happening, where
each message is going, how much is the
latency if there is bottleneck, which
process, which service is causing all
that bottleneck if there is a failure.
Where is it?
Where is that failure system, right?
So that you can actually understand what
is going on in your e ecosystem, Rob?
The message journey, right?
Like I said, producer produces a message.
It should have a watermark.
It goes to the Kafka broker.
Broker persists it, it keeps it forever.
There could be one consumer
receiving that message.
There could be 10 consumers
So that can it could be a one to
one to many flow, or one-to-one
flow, or one to three flow.
It doesn't matter the fan, or it could
be as large as you want with Kafka.
So that's the beauty.
But with watermarking, you'll be able to
actually trace all those paths as well.
So really important there if you are
into those kinds of things and your
company and the organization wants that.
From an instrumentation perspective,
like what we talked about, you have
to have that context propagation.
So they will attach identifiers,
watermarks to the message headers
and consumers will continue
to continue the same trace.
They'll use the same identifier
and add whatever need they
need to add for the span.
There is an auto instrumentation
available with open telemetry.
I don't wanna go into detail around
that, but there is a really good blog
about that in the Open Telemetry website.
So check that out.
So instrument clients with open telemetry
collector will actually receive all
that spans via are OTLP protocol.
Things like jeager, zipkin or
similar systems can actually store
and process those trace data sets.
And Grafana in the etiquette can, again,
visualize those traces with span details.
So again, on you, however you
want to implement it, these are
options which are available.
You can go and find better
options if you have.
Please don't think that Grafana
is the only option in the world.
I, as I said, these are my
preferences, which I use, but
you can use whatever you like.
Another example, so this is
a good example for a trace.
I just wanted to include it, that,
hey, when you're tracing what happens
right when you produce a message?
Five milliseconds spent there
in that trace, that span
will say five milliseconds.
It stayed within the Kafka
queue for about 50 milliseconds.
We message waiting in the broker.
Then a consumer came in and
it consumed the message.
It pulled it and it started processing it.
Maybe 10 seconds to consume,
maybe 200 seconds to process, 200
milliseconds to process, sorry.
So all that stuff adds up.
Those spans will tell you where
the hot area is, and if you have
some processing performance issues,
that's where you look at it.
So melt, going back to the whole thing.
Metrics shows you symptoms.
Latencies, dropping latencies,
replication, statuses, all that stuff.
Metrics, events.
Has my broker restarted?
Is the leadership changed?
Is there a partition reassignment ongoing?
Is there a replication ongoing?
All that stuff are events, logs, error
messages, what's going on in my system?
Are there client disconnections?
Are there issues related to replication?
Is there an issue related
to the disc logs, traces?
Where's my message?
What's my message doing?
Where is it all being consumed
from and produced from?
I wanna know all that stuff
that's traces for you.
A practical implementation, again,
my example, my preferred way,
because I've been dealing with these
systems for a really long time.
You can choose your, pick
your poison, if I may.
Open telemetry when neutral.
So it's basically just default.
For me at this point, 'cause it's
vendor agnostic, it doesn't care.
Prometheus has support for that.
Prometheus also has A GMX exporter,
which the community built pretty good.
It's it has really good query language,
it has really good alerting as well.
And it's a really nice TSTB, which
scales really well and performs
really well under pressure as well.
Grafana Unified Dashboarding.
Any signals, alerts can also go
into Grafana, so pick your poison.
Promeus can do it.
Grafana can do it.
Choose whichever you one you like.
Using Melt for Kafka, it'll get you
better detection of errors, quicker
analysis for root cal root causes.
Probably up to around 40% fewer
incidents depending on how you
instrument it, how you alert on it,
and all those things considered.
And definitely way more confidence
when you are managing, not one, not
two, but many Kafka clusters at scale.
Yeah.
So key takeaways for me is always
been the synergy of signals.
Use the combination, right?
The melt stack is important.
Use the ones which are most important
for you, and then instrument
the other ones as needed, right?
I love open source tooling.
You can pick your
choices however you like.
It gives you much better visibility if
you instrument the entire stack, but
you can choose or start with metrics
and logs and that will give you more
than enough to start off and manage
your Kafka clusters with confidence.
These are some of the helpful resources,
which are just, this is more like an
appendix but I just wanted to call out.
There is a JMX monitoring stat that me
and one of some of my friends built.
It's been, it has really good Kafka
dashboards available and really
good Kafka meets configurations,
which are tuned for performance.
Tuned for dashboarding and most
critical signals and things like that.
Take a look if that helps.
Good.
But there are other numerous dashboards,
numerous Prometheus configurations
available in the interwebs.
So you can use your, choose your
pick, whichever one you like.
Some of the metrics that you wanna
consider from a broker perspective,
these are probably the ones which I
consider as the most important metrics
of all types for our brokers, right?
There could be others, there
are numerous other metrics, yes.
But these are the things which I
see is as the most important ones.
Take a look, go through it, pause
the video here and go through that.
These are the common client metrics,
which I say again, the most important
ones, which you should have.
It is a method out of the producer,
the consumer, the connect, all three
of them actually EMS out those metrics.
Probably get those as a baseline
if you're building your own right.
So all these metrics are important if you
are building your own right, if you're
not using the JMX monitoring stack.
JMX monitoring stacks already has most
of these already in building, right?
So if you go through that good,
you're already set, right?
But if you want to use your own, you
want to use your own or roll your own
and will learn, this is how you start.
So coming back to the common client
metrics, these are the ones which
you'll want producer metrics.
These are the ones which I
consider as the most important.
There are more more metrics than these.
So yeah choose accordingly and enough.
Consumer metrics.
This is a little small, but yeah.
These are the ones which I'll
want you to start off with.
Don't hesitate to co collect more from the
clients because they don't have so many.
For the Kafka brokers, there's too many.
So just be careful about that.
And that's the, that's me guys.
Thanks a lot for listening,
and if you have any questions,
feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you.