Hi everybody.
My name is Jason Z. I'm
so happy to be here.
Thank you for joining today.
Session Today we're gonna talk about
about measuring the performance
of servers application with
generative A models and Amazon bed.
My name is Hazel Science
and I am from Guatemala.
I am an AWS serverless hero.
I am really passionate about se talking
serverless all the time, so you can find
me in AWS community Days Summits and all
text related events in Latin America.
And.
I'm also the creator of q virtual
assistant that helps and try
to revolution how is the way
that we are learning about AWS.
So I write also technical articles, so
if you want to go and see my content
and or even just connect with me to.
Talk about several desk.
Please follow me on my media.
This is the, I leave the QR in here for.
You can follow me and I'll
be glad to talk to you.
So let's get started.
What we are going to learn today, because
there was a really fancy table in the.
Talk today, but what is really what
we want to learn here, so I don't know
about you, but when I started to learn
about GAI, like a couple of years back
I started to test all the different,
models that come to the market, right?
Like everybody else, I started testing
and when I start evaluate them, I
see the publicity and say something
like this in the image in here.
So in all the ads they create,
like I want an image that can say
this about an eye, for example,
and create something like this.
And what's so awesome?
So I say, oh, this is great.
I wanna test this.
But when I started to test it, I realized
that my image, it wasn't exactly the same
as the ad. I didn't know that happened
to you, but it happened to me a lot.
And I was really frustrated and skinny.
Something like this, like I have a
character with three mouths instead
of one and, or sometimes even I
have more hands or more legs than
a character or something like that.
I just started thinking about I want
to build application with Gen ai.
Not only that, right?
For me, but actually
use it in my business.
So it's supposed to be easy and
straightforward, and they never
should fail and sound easy, right?
But for some reason it wasn't.
So why so hard?
When I started to actually build and
incorporate this different tools on it,
I realized that, and I learned that with
Gene AI application, it is different
about where we are used to work before.
Why?
Because in my previous systems related
with banking e-commerce and all the
different kind of application, all
that program were deterministic.
And what is that?
That means that when I send an input,
I always get the same output because
the logic inside the program, it was.
Like a bunch of ifs.
Let's say if I, you give me
a one, I will return you.
The word yes.
If you give me a two, I
will return you the word no.
So every time that I say one, I'm
gonna have the same answer, and
every time I say two, I'm gonna
have exactly the same answer.
So everything is the
same one and over again.
But now is different.
With Gene AI application, we have
a pro, a program that is based in.
Probabilities.
It is probabilistic
what this concept mean.
That means that I can have
the same input over and over
again but my output may change.
Why?
Because the models were actually
going to give you as an answer
is based about the probabilities.
That could be the right answer.
I. So the models have so much
information that they not always
going to return you the same.
Probably a hundred percent.
Ask the same question and the model
know that 98% of that that users like
what one kind of question they're
gonna provide you that answer.
Yeah.
But it's probably not the one you want.
Because you could be the 2% that it
wasn't looking that answer, right?
That's why is more difficult to actually
create an application that give you,
that, provide to the users the output that
you want based on probability, and that
opens a new door for me when I started to
actually build this kind of application.
Said.
Okay, now I know the problem.
I know why so hard and evaluate
a little bit in more details.
So now that I know that my previous
application was deterministic, that
I know that is fixed result, that it
depends on fixed rules because it's was
a bunch of it, is it always the same?
So I know what it works
in my previous projects.
An example of this, it could
be like a binary search and all
that kind of application that
is already out there, right?
But prob probabilistic.
I don't have fix the result.
I don't have the same rules all the time.
It depends about, not only about what is
the outcome that I want, it's about what
the model that I'm used, because each
model is trained with different data.
So the output that can provide
me there are different.
So now I have a new variable that I need
to consider what model I actually I do
need in my business for actually can.
Get the output that I need, right?
And it may vary each time
that I ask the same question.
So if I have a hundred user,
then I send the same question.
I'm not always going
to get the same answer.
So what kind of examples
are the can I have in here?
What I have all the ML models like
Amazon, Nova Cloud chapter bt.
Every model is different.
Every model processed
information differently and
collects different kind of data.
So that's why their outputs change.
So if I still do want to have application
with Gene ai, because I do, because.
I need to have it in my business
to actually grow and take all
the capabilities that Gene AI
offers to me into my business.
What should be my goal?
How can I knowing that I have this
kind of challenge, can I face it?
So the first thing that we
need to understand is what
are the AI objectives because.
It is important to be aware of
that in a business decision.
So the first one, I want quality.
I don't want to have an
image with three mounts.
I want that my output, they always have
in the high quality that the user needs.
My user needs, right?
So that's an important fact.
The second.
The second one is I want
the best performance.
I don't know if this happened to
you, but I use some of these tools
and when I create in one model,
I get the answer really fast.
And when I test the other one, it
was more slow that the previous
one, and maybe it's the lowest
and the quality is not that good.
So which one should I use?
Was the faster right and the best quality.
But it comes to, into a balance
because you don't only want that
new application be a hundred percent
accurate all the time, but I want to,
this application should be fast because
I don't want my users go to the author.
To the other company to get
the information that I want
to provide them, right?
And for that I need to be fast.
So performance is really important here.
And the other one that is maybe not
that impactful to the users but is
impactful to my business is that
there needs to be cost effective.
So I want to have that this
application have high quality.
We need to have best, the best performance
into the in the market, but I also.
Need to be careful with my prices because
with my cost itself, because gen AI is
expensive, the model use is expensive.
So I need to be wise when I select
what model should I use, and I
need to be aware that maybe I don't
need such intelligent models for
some tasks, but for others I do.
So I need to learn how to balance that.
Okay.
And with that, if I get the three,
these three key objectives, I'm going to
create a fully good gen AI application.
Okay.
So to get here, we need to
understand what are the building
blocks that CON consists on?
General applications.
No.
Because it is a little different.
If you have experience creating another
kind of application, like a e-commerce
application or a banking application
with g ai is a little different.
And this is why, this is the
blocks that we have to start.
We have the confidential model hub.
This part of the application,
it, it has the communication.
Of the models itself.
So what models are you going
to use in your application?
Because in some cases we
want to build our own model.
In other cases, we're gonna use the
one that we already have in the market
and it's, that is good, but this
is the phase when you decide that.
Okay.
The second part is the data foundation.
Do you remember that?
I said that all the models has.
Different outputs because
the data is different.
So in your business is the same.
I can have business that it provides
the same service, that another 10
company, but it's mine is gonna be
different because my data is different.
It provides something new to the
users and that is why this other
layer is really important, because
depends on the quality of your data.
Your application, the quality of
your application will be different.
The third layer is about
model adapting and prompting.
And this is something really important.
We, you can have the data that you
need, you can select the best model
you can, but if you don't know what
is the right prompt to use that model.
You will probably will
not get the best results.
So this is the point when prompt
engineering is come to the game
and start changing the things.
Okay?
The other part is Gene AIOps.
You already know what the true layer basic
of a of an A gene application, right?
But to actually have a successful
application running with different cycles
of deployment, you need to get in place,
your software development lifecycle,
and that is this part of Gene AI Ops.
How are you going to
deploy that application?
You are gonna use a infrastructure as
a code for that all that kind of stuff.
And what is the continue, did you gonna
have into different versions and all that?
And something that is important and we
cannot forget about that, is that you
already have probably, you already have
some application with your clients.
They already know, and they are familiar
how this application's going to be
connected to your new application
that is powered with gene ai.
So that is the other block that
we need to take in consideration.
And this part, and to this point, we
know what are the components that are
part of a good gene AI application.
Okay?
But we need to add something else in here.
We need to keep in mind that if you
gonna have this kind of application, you
need to have in place a good government
and you need to have the country plan.
What is that?
You need to be aware about your user,
what kinda access they can have,
what the security you gonna have
in your application to not be be
attacked and all that kind of stuff.
But counterplan, it's gonna be the
one they can help you to improve
your application into the future.
Okay.
Why?
Because it's open this world that
has been called observability and
it allows you to actually, you can
monitor what is going on in all the
different blocks that I disrupt for.
Okay.
And for the last layer then the last
block that we're gonna have in here is
not that it's not important because it is.
All the infrastructure that is
running below this application
that it make it to actually work.
So in this session, we're going
to see, and we're gonna focus
only in these three blocks.
We are gonna focus in the
foundational model hub.
How do the models actually, we
can collect information from
them and all the data foundation.
Okay.
And we're gonna talk about.
Observability And why observability?
Because if we want to have this, the
three objectives of this applications,
the quality, the cost, and the
performance, we need to be, before we
can decide what we use, we need to be
aware what we need, how our application
is being, how is working behind.
Because with each interaction, I can
learn about it and I can improve it.
For the gene I application,
this is the key factor.
If you don't observe what is going on
in your application, you can improve it.
So you're probably gonna be left behind
because the other companies, they
are watching their own application
and they're improving itself.
In some cases, they're gonna
take the decision about, I'm
going to change the model.
I'm going to change.
I'm going to improve my prompting.
I'm going to change my data because
I'm not providing the data that I need.
That kind of decision needs to base
on numbers and numbers is going to be
provided to you using observability.
Okay.
This is an example about what
is a foundational model health
like in a high level, right?
You can have a gene application and
you're gonna have a gene AI gateway
that is going to be the point of access
for all your gene AI components that
is gonna be part of their application.
That could be like, you can use
models in Amazon Bedrock, for example.
Or you can create your own models.
You remember that?
I said you can have those.
Yeah, you can have both.
You can choose to have your own
model created from scratch, or you
can start using the tools that is
already in the market like Amazon
better that it provides you the comp,
the capability to, you can use the.
Other models out there from
Cloud for yeah, Tropic Lama Nova.
You can use all that models just
by using the Amazon Metro, API, for
example, and in some way you can have
the benefit of all the different models
using just one language to do it right.
And the other part it was the
enhancement of data connotation.
That is one example of that
is our wrap application.
So when you talk about gene AI project
applications, you need to put your data.
To this application for they can
answer or they can use it to train
and provide you outputs that you need
that will be custom to your clients.
So that's why it's so important
how you are going to provide that
information to the application.
And the rat comes up.
You can have ETL process.
You can have applications
like Confluence, JIRA GitHub.
You can have a different input
that's going to provide that
information to your customers.
You can even have document PDF files,
c, s, B, files, whatever you need.
That is your data.
Even you can have APIs and you can have
databases that you need to provide that
information to your application for the
action can using to be trained, right?
So in here that comes to concept one,
the Amazon Belt drug knowledge base that
will allow you to have all the different,
files that I was mentioned before,
like easily get all that information
together, put it in a vector database,
and the models can actually use that
database to get the information right.
You can have actions, you can have
tools that you can incorporate in here.
But the main goal is to get your data
right and you can also have Amazon
bedroom Gogos that is going to be
the one that helps you to not only
have the information, but to protect
yourself and protect your data.
To be reading, read it, and mal intent.
For some of the users, for example,
what kind it, I don't know, but
they can be like the informa, the
sensitive data from your customers.
It's just something that you get in
your data, but you don't want that that
application can have it or you don't want.
Yeah.
So you don't want your application.
Another application can have that
information because it's protected.
So you can do it with guardrail, okay, so
what are the key, what we need to follow
to actually implement observability?
We need to have these
four layers in place.
One, the company level.
You need to have metrics
in your infrastructure.
You need to have invocation errors,
latency utilization, because to order
to identify, to have a performance
issue, you should know how your.
Resources is performing.
So you need these metrics.
Yeah.
Layer two, you're gonna get
metrics from and the traces.
So when you work with models
you, the traces come be really
important because you need to know.
What actually is gonna happen when
the user asks for something and all
the different stuff that is related
with all the different components.
So this is why it came.
Important part layer three, the
metrics and analysis related to Gores.
How many how many users try to get
sensitive data for customer, how many
users can actually get trying to get.
Information about your cast or
something that is important.
That is something that you need to
keep an eye because you probably need
to change the way that your data is
being populated to, to your models.
And the fourth and last
one is the user feedback.
The user and feedback is important
because when you are interacting,
let's say like a chat bot.
If the answer that provided to the
user it wasn't good enough, the
user can give you that feedback
and can say, yes, I, it was good.
I don't like it, I hate it.
All of that kinda stuff.
You can get it from there and you can
improve yourself because remember,
each time you have an answer, it's
gonna be a different answer and
could be a good one that satisfied
what the user need or can be another
one that it doesn't do it at all.
Okay.
So that's why the before
layer is important.
You can do it if you already have an
application, you can do it step by step.
So you can start step one.
Then pro plan to have this layer two,
the layer three, and the level four,
but the it is in this order because
it is important that you start to
do and you need to when you start.
The science, your application, you
need to be aware that this is the road
that you must follow to actually can
have the most observability and the
most decision data related, improve.
And for this example, I'm
going to use Amazon CloudWatch.
That is a service for AWS that is
used to collect all the, not only
the logs, but also trace and collect
all the information from our s from
the services that is involved in
this in this kind of application.
Okay.
So with that, we can do it a demo.
If you want to do it yourself, you
can do it, you can just scan this.
I will try to give the link.
But you can download in video.
I create a small application in GitHub,
and you can just download it, you can
clone it, you can deploy it in your
own AWS account, and you can start.
Just deploy it, use it, and start
to see the dashboard about how
you are collecting the data.
Okay.
Okay, so let's take a look about the team.
Something that is important in here
is that, to actually, if you're going
to use some bad, you need to collect
your metrics and that is not at
the default picture that is turned.
You need to go and do it yourself.
I'm doing it in here really fast,
only to see how simple it is.
You can send it to a, an extra
bucket or you can send it directly
to, to cloud only to CloudWatch.
The target that you can have
all the different inputs that
the models are actually working.
So if you see here, I'm gonna, in
here in the example, you're gonna
have an API that is a expert music.
So you can ask it
anything about the music.
And each time the user sent a question a
model is being indicate at the backend.
You will get the answer about
that question, and if you go to
see now you, I turn off the logs.
If you see here, you can get now
the information about that request.
You will note what model was involved.
You can know what is the a, the
question that the user made, what
is the answer that the model provide
and most, and really important, the
token that's being used in here.
It's gonna help you to get what
exactly the same, the cost that is
is getting to you by using this.
For example, if you want to compare to
a different model, you can have the same
implication to two different models.
You can count the tokens and you will
know which one was more expensive
or which one takes the longest
while the latency and all that.
And only like enabling that part.
Okay.
The other kind of of metrics is
the one you use with x-ray and
you use with CloudWatch, and
you use also with CloudTrail.
In this example I have in the Lambda, I
use a specific trace to actually can be
aware the timing that is consuming the.
All the different steps in the function.
And in the ripple you can see the
example and you will get the information
not only to the invocation, the
time that the Lambda takes to run,
but you will also know how long the
Lambda takes to execute the model.
And you will know the timing
of the metrics, for example.
So in here, if you see if I can
go, if it can go to CloudWatch.
See the, now you are capturing all
the different locks in here and you,
we can go to x-ray because it is
instrumented to x-ray and you can see
that you're not only gonna get what
is the locks inside the Lambda, but
you also get this kind of diagram.
They show you what all
are, all the different.
Services in both to get that answer.
Okay.
So this is the cool part that you
have like different all is separate.
You have the trace at the level
of the code that you need and
you can go much deep as you like
and you need in your business.
Okay?
So what kind of the, lambda, I
recommend that I always have this,
the one that I use in the models
itself that is really important.
The logs that you see in the
beginning about what's the
answer to the models itself.
And with that, you can also make
something really cool in, in cloud
that is related with the dashboard.
So by the fold, you can go
and create this dashboard.
You only select that you want to have.
Like bedrock dashboard and you
will have the in implication
of the models, the input token.
And in here it, this kind provides
you a visual when you can have
the comparation between the
different model that you're using.
If you have, for example, like
10 models that you, you will
actually be able to see it.
Okay.
So this is only the implementation
of phase of layer one and
layer two for layer three.
That is part of the guardrails.
And number four, that
is an end user input.
I didn't have it in the demo, but
it's like the next steps that you can
have with this basic observability.
Okay.
So with that I said I,
so with that's all that I have.
Really thank you to be here.
I'm really, sLA to be part of.
With that, I am that will be all.
I'm really proud to be here in
this space, so let's connect
with me and have a nice day.
Thanks for watching.
Bye-bye.