Hello all.
I'm Na Kala.
I'm excited to talk to you today about
how Cloud is evolving and also more
importantly, how we can bring together
different cloud platforms and make
them work seamlessly and securely.
We'll be discussing four main key points.
In this presentation the first one is
AI driven, API Management, followed
by confidential computing, zero
trust and event driven architectures.
These are game changes for any of
the industry that is already into
multiple clouds or that is going
to invest into multiple clouds.
Moving on to the very first
slide, multi-cloud reality.
94% of enterprises use
multi-cloud platforms.
They'll be using AWS Azure or Google
Cloud to leverage specific capabilities.
The advantage is that vendor lockin is
totally avoided, but the cons is that,
integration issues exist because the
by the data communication to and fro
between the systems needs some effective
and comprehensive integration strategy.
And mostly will be facing data
synchronization hurdles, which will
lead to implementation delays and also,
which will lead to budget overruns.
And also there'll be many issues.
With security policies because
each cloud will come with its own
security and we need to create a
unified security policy that can be
used to overcome any of the issues.
Okay.
Moving on to the second slide.
Benefits of effective cloud integration.
So as long as we have a comprehensive
integration strategy, the deployment
rate will be faster and we can
see 30 to 40% of improvement.
And also there'll be grade agility.
Agility is directly proportional
to marketer around or business turn
turnaround because we will build and,
deployed things faster, so that will give
a positive impact to the whole business.
And also resilience, especially during
service interruptions will be benefited.
I identified few of the
integration complexity challenges
that will be commonly faced.
One thing the main thing is that with each
cloud edition the integration complexity
will be increased by at least 70%.
And also each cloud will have
different security models.
AWS will have its own model and
Google Cloud will have its own model.
We have to make sure that the
security policies is correctly, are
correctly laid as discussed before.
And also there'll be a lot of
inconsistencies with the a p
structures and authentication
and authorization mechanisms.
And also there'll be differences between
data formats and storage mechanisms.
AI driven API management platforms.
There are mainly efficiency gains
and governance benefits, and this
is not a traditional approach.
This is AI driven, so the
bugs will be decreased.
And also the overall, implementation
time will be cut down and there'll be
several other benefits for few of the
benefits are identified and written here.
So reduction in API design improvement in
overall API, usability metrics and also
reduction in MA manual documentation.
Efforts and benefits are mostly related
to performance optimizations and also
related to compliance and security.
So we can see policy violations
reduction, compliance verification,
time improvement, and then latency
through traffic optimization reduction
and also resource provisioning.
Costs will get reduced.
And moving on to the next
slide enhanced security through
AI driven a BI management.
So there are in this chart.
The dark color ones are a traditional
approach, and the lighter color ones the
green the bright green ones belong to
ai, a approach or AI enhanced approach.
So have the they will be reduction
in false positive rate and
also exploitation reduction.
So we'll be able to, du reduce
exploitation by detecting them early and
also attack detection will be showing a
positive impact when we go with AI models.
So overall on an average 78.3
successful exploitation effort attempt.
And then, machine learning models
can detect up to 93% of API
based attacks while maintaining
false positive rates below 4%.
So AI driven is more secure and
also it'll mitigate more protection
vulnerabilities before even the
exploitation items are occurred.
And before even the traditional methods
or traditional strategies kick in,
AI will take care of most of them.
And confidential computing.
So confidential computing
mostly rotates around the
concept of half data is secured.
So data, when data is in use,
AI models will secure it even
more even more in a better way.
When I mean in use, it's nothing but
being in transit, but data at rest.
We will be predicting it either based
using traditional or security model.
So traditional or AI based security model.
So data addressed, sophisticated
encryption algorithms, protect
store data from unauthorized
access and data in transit.
T-L-S-S-S.
S SL protocols and encrypted
channel safeguard data during
transmission and data in use.
Hardware based ttes
create secure enclaves.
That product data during computation
and complete protection, comprehensive
security framework ensures data remains
encrypted throughout its entire lifecycle.
These specialized enclaves whatever
we are discussing about, especially
for data in use or for TES maintain
encryption during during active
computational process, creating a
secure, isolated environment that.
Prevents otherized access.
So even for users or system
administrators or cloud service
themselves will not have access.
So this is more secure and confidential
computing performance breakthrough.
So it is 33 times more fast.
Organizations implementing confidential
computing for analytics and their AI
workloads have reported up to 33 x fast.
Processing and hardware enforced security.
The tes Predict application from
attacks with privileged system access,
effectively mitigating threats from any
of the administrators, hypervisors BIOS
and OS and other operating systems.
Expanded capabilities also exist.
So Intel's third SGX implementations
have expanded secure memory capacity
from 1 28 MB 2 5 12 gb dramatically
increasing the scope of workloads that
benefit from hardware based protection.
Industry applications of confidential
computing healthcare, definitely
healthcare organizations can securely
process a PHI in the cloud while
maintaining HIPAA con compliance.
Enabling advanced analytics on patient
data by disclosing all the sensitive
in information and financial services.
Like financial institutions
can perform complex analytics.
And research collaboration.
Federated learning frameworks allow
multiple organizations to collectively
train AI models on their combined data
sets while mathematically guaranteeing
that no party can access the original
data from other participants.
Zero trust architecture.
So never trust, always verify.
Zero trust architecture
principle is that it will.
Require a continuous authentication and
authorization of all entities regardless
of their location or network connection.
So least privilege access
will be enforced here.
So minimum necessary permissions and
then isolated network zones by workload.
And also it'll calculate all the
real time behavior analytics.
And then we, it'll have lot of
identity verification principles, like
advanced authentication frameworks
and also custom authentication
frameworks that can be used.
So this approach replaces all
the traditional security with a
model that is Zooms breach and
verifies each request as though it
originates from untrusted network.
It continuously keeps pinging us
and verifying us which is great.
This is definitely having a lot of impact.
And pros on every everybody's business.
Organization implementations experience
of frameworks, experience 43% reduction
in successful network introductions,
37% reduction in security incident
response costs, and 29% decrease in
overall security management overhead.
And also advanced authentication
frameworks reported a 92% success rate in
pre preventing credential based attacks.
While organizations employing real
time behavior analytics detected
suspicious activities, 73% faster
than those using periodic security
scanning approaches, event driven
architectures for real time integrations.
So event driven architectures mostly,
or rotate around using system bus and
using subscribers, publishers, and making
the tasks even more fast and easier.
So even generation system changes trigger
events and routes them to subscribers
and subscribers React to the events.
Also there'll be state synchronization
where system will maintain
consistency across all the services
and keep updating the right data
and also getting the right data.
Even architecture is loosely coupled.
It supports real time data synchronization
across drivers cloud environments.
So whenever there is a change,
immediately through through the
bus, you can kick off the change.
Organizations imple implementing
EDA frameworks experience a 58%
reduction in data integr integrated
latency compared to traditional
scheduled batch processing approaches.
Just a second.
Yep.
And the performance metrics I gave few
of the performance metrics in the slide.
So what is the latency reduction and
how many events will we processed per
second message delivery guarantee,
responsiveness increase, incident
reduction maintenance cost reduction.
So this architectural approach allows
organizations to build responsive
systems that immediately react
to business events as they occur.
I would say this is more proactive in
nature and it'll be very much helpful for
industries to use them as their real time
or near near real time most of the time.
Financial services industrial, IOD
and global Enterprises are heavily
using all the EDI architectures.
And then for financial
services, 63% faster.
An anomaly detection for
production for potential fraud
scenarios and industrial iot.
There is a 88% improvement in real time
processing capability, enabling monitoring
systems to process data from over 25,000
sensors with a sub-second response time.
And also for the Global Enterprises,
there is a 71% reduction in
cross-regional data inconsistencies
while using EDA, which is really great.
And overall the future of the secure
platform integration is all the four
aspects that we have discussed right now.
We have to create a framework in such
a way that all of these, at all of
these key points that we have covered
are balanced in each and every strategy
that we come up for the organization.
So as organization continues their
digital transformational journeys
these approaches will become
increasingly essential components of
a strategic technology foundation.
Thank you all.
That's my take.