Good morning everyone.
Today I'm excited to present our work on
AI power observability and semiconductor
design, and how it's driving real time
insights and up to 40% fast design cycles
through advanced monitoring and analytics.
So let's begin by looking at the
challenges our industry faces.
Currently, 87% of our
semiconductor projects experience
delays and exceeding budgets.
Often by several million dollars.
These setbacks have a direct impact
on time to market profitability
and innovation velocity.
But here's the opportunity.
With AI driven, we have a potential
to reduce design cycles by 40%.
Fundamentally changing the pace and
efficiency of chief development now.
Exactly.
Do we have.
AI observability.
The approach delivers tangible
improvements in design cycle time, power
consumption, and manufacturing yield.
These aren't just metrics.
They transfer directly into a faster
product launches, lower operational cost,
and better performing chips in the field.
So let's drive into how we achieve this.
First, design automation monitoring.
Our AI powered monitoring system
significantly reduces design, providing
real time feedback to catch issues early
by optimizing workload dynamically.
And then we announce computational
efficiency across teams second
productive telemetric systems.
We use real time pattern recognition to
detect critical design anomalies with
multidimensional data and sensor networks,
we reduce physical testing needs while
improving fall detection electricity.
Third, automated design rule verification.
Our tools achieve improved error
detection by continuously scanning and
learning from complex design patterns.
AI not only flags issues, but
suggest mark context of our fixes and
optimization based in industry standards.
Four, performance and power optimization.
Through real time monitoring, we deliver
immediate throughput improvements
and intelligent power management.
We are enabling active frequency,
scaling action, and proactive
thermal management, all critical
for modern power, low power designs.
Fifth simulation.
Using digital twin environments, we
achieve near total test coverage,
enabling massive power simulations.
This reduces cycle time and
integrates insight across electrical,
thermal, and mechanical domains.
Sixth yield optimization.
We are tapping into over a
hundred process parameters
through manufacturing, telemetry.
Machine learning helps identify
different patterns with higher accuracy
and enables automated unit for higher
yields and reduced calibration.
Seventh edge device performance.
Our system collects telemetry
from deployed chips under
real world conditions.
This enables dynamic optimization, boost
ML performance, and extends battery
life without sacrificing functionality.
So how do we implement all of this?
The roadmap assessment phase, we
start with detailed cap analysis
and define measurable KPIs.
Integration phase.
Next, we roll out Observ tools with
minimal workflow disruption backed by
team training, third optimization phase.
Finally, we use AI insight to define
process, build productive models,
and share knowledge across products.
In conclusion, AI power is
no longer a feature concept.
It's practical.
I impact solution that is already
arriving faster, design cycles,
better products, and smart engine.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time and
thank you for listening.