Hey everyone, this is Krishna Gal. I'm
a senior software engineer working at
Meta in the ads privacy infra team.
I work closely in the intersection
of privacy, infrastructure and
scalable distributed systems at Meta.
Today I'll walk you through
why observability is becoming
absolutely foundational to
privacy aware infrastructures,
especially at hyper massive scale.
Like the ones being dealt at.
Big tech companies.
We'll talk about the challenges,
architectural patterns, real world
examples from companies like Meta and
what the future looks like in this domain.
And that's what the agenda here covers.
We'll also go over the key use cases
that we have in privacy systems from
the perspective of observability
and also the architectural
patterns, benefits, and other.
Major advancements in this area.
So now what are privacy aware systems?
Privacy aware systems were
initially designed to ensure that
user data is handled correctly.
It's very important in today's age to
be aware and also respect the user's
consent in handling user data across.
Service or a whole company stack as well.
Since privacy and regulations are
tightening every day across multiple
countries, these, the systems are a
part of a broader initiative, which
is also called Privacy Aware, infra
across the industry, which aims to
embed privacy deeply into the technical
fabric of the company's infra.
Now, what does observability mean?
Observability.
In systems engineering, it meant
inferring in internal system
states from external outputs.
That includes three primarily key
pillars, logs, metrics, and traces
In privacy, infra specifically, it's
about reconstructing who touched a
user's data y and whether they were
allowed to touch that user data.
Think of it as the ability to
reconstruct a privacy black box
recording for every interaction.
That's critical when regulators or
users ask What happened to my data?
That's exactly what observability
helps tackle in case of privacy
aware infra coming to why privacy
aware info needs observability.
Data privacy today is under.
Regulatory scrutiny some of which are
G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A, India's DPDP, and now.
These fines are really high.
If you're caught not complying to
these regulations, it could be up to
4% of your global company revenue.
But what's more important
than fines is trust.
Your customers or users would just
stop trusting your services if you
do not handle and respect their
privacy well, and it's not embedded
well in your company's infra.
But that's more important
than fines and user trust.
It's also very important for a company to
be able to answer to their customers who
access their data, what is going on with
their data and where it's being used for.
That's where observability comes
in, not just for uptime or latency,
but to trace audit and enforce
data policies in real time.
Real time is the key here.
Now we'll touch upon a few.
Really important key use
cases in the privacy world.
In terms of your observability there
are five real world use cases that we
encounter on a daily basis at scale.
First is data lineage, which is basically
tracking the entire flow of user data.
It could start from where was
it generated, who processed it,
and was it shared externally?
The other use case is consent
propagation, which is basically if a
user re revokes their consent in one ui.
We need to ensure all systems
respond to that in real time.
One lagging cache could
cause a compliance failure.
To give you an example, for instance,
if a user is okay with sharing their
location for showing, let's say,
personalized ads to them, and later
they go and update their, settings
to not share their location anymore.
We have to make sure that for whatever
cases their location was being used
for, let's say for some kind of data
modeling or some kind of machine learning
model or training use cases, right?
We have to go and make sure that
the user's location data is wiped
out from those models completely.
That's what consent propagation is.
The other use case is purpose limitation.
Data collected for personalization
should not be used for targeting
or training ML models, as I
said, without explicit consent.
The other use case that we can
think of is anomaly detection,
for instance, login from a new
location or accessing full history.
Are these use cases expected?
Is there a policy mismatch somewhere?
All these.
Questions could be answered really
well if there's a very well oiled
observability machine embedded
in the whole privacy scenario.
And then the last use case that I
could come up with is policy drift
monitoring, which is basically
over time does enforcement.
We can, our system silently
bypassing updated constraints.
All these questions should be
answerable via privacy of our infra
and without observability, it's not
possible to answer these questions.
Each of these need traceability
or adaptability, and in many
cases, automated enforcement.
Now coming to what other system design
challenges at implementing observability
at such a big scale of privacy infra.
First is volume.
At hyperscale, you are dealing
with billions of log events
daily and petabytes of data.
To be able to process all of
this and generate meaningful
observability out of this whole
privacy data is a massive challenge.
The second part is speed.
In this case, you could, you cannot
take hours or days to process this
data since most of these services
that a lot of these billion.
Customer companies deal
with are realtime use cases.
So you need to handle and observability
at the speed of subsecond latency.
The other design challenge that one
needs to deal with is granularity.
Observability must be at a per user
level, not just per system level.
Since every user's privacy settings,
privacy comfort is very different.
It also depends on the
ecosystem they are in.
So it has to happen at a per use user
in some cases per impression level.
The last part is security.
Observability data itself is very
sensitive since it contains a
lot of information about how the
user interacted with the system,
details about the user et cetera.
So it must not leak PII or
personally identifiable information.
As it'll amplify the risk further
and be a loss at compliance.
So we need to design the speed,
scale, and security all at once.
Coming to what the architectural patterns
you've observed in this industry.
So to be able to build observability
for privacy, the first thing
is event driven lineage.
We use services or systems such as
Kafka or any kind of pub sub, system
to track data flows in real time.
The second part of the co whole
ecosystem is consent aware tagging
where we try to map every data payload
to a specific purpose and scope.
By pur, what I mean by purpose and scope
here is we mark every data with what
kind of systems can absorb that data.
For instance, if it's.
An ads ecosystem and a user has revoked
their cons, has not given their consent
to the service to use it, to use,
let's say, their location for it.
We have to tag their location data to not
be specifically used for ad systems and
maybe be able to use it for other systems.
So consentable tagging
is very important here.
The third part is embedded policy engines.
There has to be a lot of runtime guard
checks if data access aligns with consent.
The fourth part is
cryptographic audit trails.
Maybe use Merkel trees or blockchain
style structures for immutable verifiable
logs which help in audit trails and are
also cryptographic at the same time too.
As we spoke.
Observability itself is a very
sensitive privacy use case.
These patterns are not just theoretical,
they're being deployed in production by
privacy focused teams across Vic Tech.
Now, coming to some of the case studies
especially lineage data lineage at scale,
take to take an example of let's say meta.
Linear systems track data across
thousands of internal sources.
Consent status propagates within
the data and policy engines enforce
compliance throughout these data sources.
These systems power realtime
visualizations of how data moves
and are used by auditors, legal and
engineering teams alike to be able to.
Figure out if there's any kind of privacy
leaks or if there's any kind of policy
dilution or if there's any kind of misses.
All these things are enabled through
observability at such massive hyperscale.
What used to take days of queuing
logs is now automated in real time.
This enables almost a 40 to 50% reduction
in audit prep time across several inter
internal teams at meta if applied at in
the right ways using observability for
such privacy aware infras structures.
Now, what are the benefits
of privacy observability?
Faster audits as we spoke about
it, reduce which reduce compliance
friction, and build confidence
with not just the regulators, but
with legal, with customers itself.
They enable reduced fine risk which
basically helps in early detection
of misuse of what, and he hence
prohibit any kind of escalation.
It also helps, provide enough team, enough
time for teams to fix those at scale.
Third part is internal trust.
Developers have visibility
into how their systems behave.
So it's not just the end con consumer,
but internally developers are confident
of where and what is happening with a
certain kind of data, with observability.
And then the last part is safer.
ML only compliant data reaches
downstream models, reducing the risk
of training or unauthorized input.
In short, observability reduces both
legal and operational risk while
improving the system hygiene incredibly.
Coming to what the future looks like
in this domain there are still a lot
of exciting open areas of research
in privacy aware infrastructure.
Looking specifically from the lens
of observability, we can, let's say,
use machine learning models to detect
privacy anomalies in real time.
And to be, to enable real
time observability while these
models are being trained.
The inferred data is a big challenge in
itself to be able to observe systems.
Become policy enforcement
systems both at the same time.
That's again, a big area of research.
The third part could be should we
standardize policy observability like we
did with open telemetry for system traces.
There's no industry standard at
the moment, especially to handle
this at scale and in a very
compliant and standard manner.
This is a huge area, in my opinion,
where researchers and developers
could invest heavily with.
The goal is to move from the fact
of inspection to real time Automatic
enforcement in a privacy control plane
and observability helps move there faster.
In conclusion observability in
privacy infra is not optional anymore.
If you can't see it, you can't enforce it.
That's the that's my takeaway from.
My experience working in this domain
as systems scale only observable
systems can remain compliant, ethical,
and trustworthy at the same time.
And the investments we make
today are what will power
responsible innovation tomorrow.
Thank you.