Are you a small team with minimum budget
not being able to spend on enterprise
gate applications, but at the same
time, you want to gain some really
useful insights about your system.
This talk is just for you.
I know that distributed systems are
very complex and tracing issues in a
distributed system is very difficult,
and at the same time, enterprise
solutions, although very helpful, are very
expensive, especially for small teams.
So in this talk, my
objective is going to be.
How to build minimum observability
stack and Kubernetes, keeping the
costs low, while also gaining some
useful insights about your system,
and finally, avoiding some obvious
pitfalls when that you can run into
while designing some of these systems.
So let's get started now.
Before getting into the actual tools
and how to set up the actual stack,
I would like to discuss what I call
the four pillars of observability.
First is logging.
Logging is the process of tracking
specific events in your application.
Now these help you answer questions
like, what is happening in my system?
Second, we have metrics.
Metrics is nothing but numerical
measurements for performance
of your system over time.
They really help you quantify the
performance of your system so they
can help you answering questions like,
how is my system behaving over time?
The third is tracing.
Now tracing is the process of
looking at your system, looking at
the flow of request in your system.
Now, if you're someone who is aiming
for P 99 performance or really high
performance system tracing will
help you identifying the specific
bottlenecks in your application.
So that you can target that specific
area, reduce the latency, and
increase the overall performance.
Now dashboard is nothing but visual
representation of all the data that
you're aggregating in all these pillars
and showing it in one particular
dashboard so that you can act on that
information as quickly as possible.
So they help you answering
questions like, how quickly can
we act upon identifying an issue?
Now for all these pillars I have
identified one of the most popular
tools that are available, open source.
Starting with logging flu, nd
is one of the most popular log
aggregator found in open source.
In the open source
community for monitoring.
We have Prometheus.
Prometheus is arguably one of the most
used components in a Kubernetes clusters
for aggregating your metrics data.
Coming back, coming to tracing,
we have a tool called Yeager.
I could also find other tools
like Open Telemetry, but Yeager
is one of the most easy to set
up especially for smaller teams.
And finally, coming to dashboards.
Grafana is arguably one of the most
used open source tools for setting up
dashboards for your observability stack.
Now we are going to look at how to
set up each and every single one of
these components in your stack with
the minimum amount of steps starting
with logging, you can, if you have a
Kubernetes cluster, you can directly
run this command cube serial l apply.
This will pull the Yam L file that is
written by the Fluentd team itself.
This will make sure that your
cluster is always running the latest
version of the flu ND components.
Coming back to Helm.
If you're someone who's using
Helm inside your cluster, you
can also run this Helm Command.
This will pull the helm
charts directly from the Helm
repository that Fluent maintains.
It'll install it in your cluster.
Once you have the component running,
you can have your applications push your
logs directly to this aggregator where
it exposes the Port 2, 4, 2 to four.
And the best practice I would
recommend is to use JSON log so
that it's easier for parsing per
fluent D. Next up, we have metrics.
Now if you're someone who uses
helm, you can run this command.
This pulls the Prometheus components
directly from the helm charts helm
repository and installs it directly
in your Kubernetes clusters.
Once you have that running,
you can use your applications.
With, you can use the client libraries
available in different programming
languages like go Java, Python,
c plus, and directly export your
data into the metrics endpoint.
Finally, you would also
have to do one more step.
You would have to specify the
targets for your application.
So in this example, I'm overriding
the values dot yammer file into
my helm config and specifying
where exactly my applications lie
application lies within the cluster.
So in my example, this is
in my app service, which is
expo exposing a port 80 80.
In your case, maybe be the DNS of your
application itself coming to tracing.
This is you can either install it
via, directly by the Kubernetes
l file that Yeager provides, or
you can also use Helm as the other
steps that we have seen so far.
Once you do that, you will
have a Yeager agent running
inside your Kubernetes cluster.
Once you have that, you can have, again,
you can use the client libraries available
in different programming languages.
Export the data directly to the
yeager's collector endpoint.
Now, this is an example from the
Python Library where I'm specifying
the host name for my Yeager agent.
There's nothing but the service
name inside the Kubernetes cluster.
This is usually the port where
Yeager exposes its particular
exporter endpoint, which is 6 8, 3 1.
In your case, if it is different.
If it is a different one,
you can use that one.
Now.
Finally, we have the dashboard wherein
we provide a visual representation for
the data that we have collected so far.
So you can either get your Grafana
components running directly via
the Kubernetes AML file or the
helm as we have seen so far.
Once you have that, you need to
specify data sources for your
Grafana plus Grafana component.
Now, data sources may be the Prometheus,
which is the metrics, the Yeager, which
is nothing but the tracing data that
you've collected, and also the logs
that you're collecting from the fluid
D. So in this example, I'm overriding
the values dot yaml file inside the
help config and specifying the data
source for my Prometheus component.
So this will make sure that whatever
data that I'm collecting inside the
Prometheus component is available in
my dashboard on the Grafana component.
Now, once you have this observability
stack set up, there are some of
the best practices and some of the
lessons some of the obvious pitfalls
that I would want you to avoid.
First one is avoid alert fatigue.
Now I've seen this with multiple teams
setting up alerts for every single
issues that pop up in their applications.
Once you do that, you get so many
alerts that soon it can, it it's
no longer a signal, but it becomes
noise, so you are more likely
to miss some useful information.
Now, this exactly happened in my previous
company wherein we set up alerts for
every single issues, and soon enough.
The mailbox, our and mailbox of our
entire team was so full that we stopped
receiving alerts altogether and we were
more likely to miss some useful alerts.
So I would want you to be very specific on
what issues that you want to track and set
up alerts only for those issues and for
other issues you can get away with setting
up logging inside your fluency component.
Now the second pitfall that I would want
you to avoid is don't over sample metrics.
Now, what that means is control
the frequency of data that you're
sending to the metrics endpoint.
Now what this means is do not send data
too frequent, for example, every second.
Now, this also depends on the type of
systems that you are supporting, but
having a good balance is always better
because if you're sending data too often.
It soon becomes noise rather than
signal, so you're more likely
to miss some useful information.
So it's better to send data at a frequent
rate rather than at an acceptable
rate, rather than very frequent.
So something like one
minute is a good balance.
Finally, dashboard hygiene is
one of the biggest mistakes
that SRE engineers often make.
What they think is, the more data we
provide on the dashboard, the better
insights that we can extract from it.
That is actually far from truth, far from
the truth, because the more data that
you provide, the more noise you create.
So more likely you are to
miss some useful information.
So what I would recommend is
based on the individual that
you're creating the dashboard for.
Keep the data that you're providing,
very focused for that individual.
So for example, if you're providing
the dashboard for a manager, have data
that provides a 10,000 feet overview of
the system rather than providing very
specific data inside the application.
So you keep the noise outside
and you provide more signals
for that particular individual.
Similarly if you're
creating a dashboard for.
A developer, I would ask, I would want
you to provide data that's giving a more
deeper look into the application itself.
Like something like the logging aggregator
would be a good use for developers.
So based on the individual that
you're creating the dashboard for,
keep the data very focused for that
particular individual so that you
don't create more noise and you
provide some useful insights Now.
Quickly giving a summary of
what we have discussed so far.
We discussed the four pillars of
observability, starting with logging.
This helps you answer questions like, what
is happening in my system so that I can
identify any issues that are going on.
Looking at the logs itself, metrics helps
you answer questions like, how can I
quantify the performance of my system?
Coming to tracing helps you answer
questions like, what, where is the
bottleneck in my system so that I can
target a specific area and increase
the overall performance of my system?
And dashboards are nothing.
But providing a visual representation
of the data that you have created
so that you can identify issues in
a particular area and you can act
on that quickly as soon as possible.
I hope that this talk was helpful, that
it provided you with the minimum amount
of steps for getting an observability
stack running in your system.
And if you want to discuss more on
this topic, and this is my LinkedIn
this is my GitHub and this is my
blog where I post similar software
engineering content content that
I learn on a day by day basis.
Thank you.