Hello, very good morning.
This is LaMi gta and I'm working in a
Starbucks as a senior data engineer.
So I have a total like 14 years
of experience in IT industry.
So today we are going to talk
about DataOps accelerating
digital transformation through
data centric methodologist.
Okay here, the evolving software
development landscape organizations
are increasingly recognizing data
as a strategic asset rather than
mely an operational byproduct.
This paradigm shift has a new
methodologies that bridge the
traditional gap between data management
and application development process.
The emergence of data oriented
application development represents a
significant achievement significant
advancement in this direction.
Offering a comprehensive framework that
integrates data engineering principles
with software dev development practices.
As it's occurred, DataOps extends the
collaborative principles of Dev DevOps
to encompass data centric operations.
Creating cohesive ecosystem where
data pipelines are treated with
the Swm reader on automation
as a code deployment pipelines.
Okay, this methodology encompasses
automated data pipeline construction
continues integration and deployment for
data workflows, robust data governance
frameworks, cross-functional collaboration
and comprehensive monitoring systems.
The significance of DataOps
lies in its ability to address
several persistence challenges in
modern application development.
The need for the high quality data
delivered at speed, alignment between
technical and business stakeholders,
and the increasing complexity of
data ecosystems, cloud environment.
As organizations prioritize data driven
decision making, adopting data ops
has transitioned from competitive to
advanced to your business necessity.
This examinees that theoretical
foundations implementation strategies
and measurable outcomes of data.
Data DataOps methodologies across Val
various organization context by analyzing
both technical and organizational
dimensions of data ops adoption.
This study seeks to provide a
comprehensive understanding of best
practices, common challenges, and future
directions in this rapidly evolving field.
Okay.
The next one, evaluation of tra.
So the here the traditional data
management, the violation from the
traditional data management practices
to dev data ops follows a trajectory
parallel to software development.
From waterfall methodologies to Agile
and DevOps approaches, the traditional
data management relied heavily on
centralized data warehousing with
the rigid extract, transformation and
load, which is called ETL processes,
creating significant bottlenecks
between data generation utilization.
These legacy approaches predominant
through through the early two
thousands were characterized by.
Siloed teams, manual handoffs,
and the lengthy development cycles
that could span months or even
years for complex data initiatives.
Next, the big data era, the big data era.
So the exponential exponential growth
in data volume, ity and velocity
brought about by digital transformation
initiatives expose the limitations
of these conventional approaches.
The emergence of big data technologies
in the mid 22 thousands provided
new technical capabilities, but
simultaneously introduced additional
complexity in data pipelines.
Next DevOps revolution.
And organizations struggled
to derive timely insights from
their expanding data assets.
A new paradigm became necessarily
to accommodate both the technical
requirements of modern data
architectures and the business
need for rapid it value delivery.
So the next the data ops emergence.
The data organically around to 2015.
As practitioners begin applying lessons
from software engineering representative,
technological shift and fundamental
rethinking of how data teams operate,
collaborate, and deliver value.
So according to the recent industry
research industry, research
organizations is implementing
data ops methodologies have.
Reported up to 70% reduction in data
deliveries and data related defects.
This marked improvement and efficiency
and quality underscores the transform made
two potential of data ops in contemporary
software engineering practices.
Next.
So what are the fundamental
principles of data ops?
One the conceptual framework of data
ops is built upon several foundation
principles that collectively enable enable
efficient, reliable data operations.
So here the first one is
automation and orchestration.
So data ops data ops emphasis automating
repetitive task across the data lifecycle,
including acquisition transformation,
extends the, extends to orchestration.
Coordinating multiple data process
and workflows to ensure proper
sequencing and dependency management.
So next it's A-C-S-E-D for data.
So we, it's a continuous integration,
continuous delivery for data.
So similar to code focus, this currently
integrating data changes automatically
testing their validity and impact and
deploying them to production environments
through standardized processes.
Next so was control and reproducibility.
Reproducibility, DataOps
advocates for a version control
of logic and analytical models.
This worsening ensures reproducibility
the ability to recreate and recreate any
previous state of the data ecosystems.
Next, quality by design rather
than treating quality as an
afterthought data ops integrates
quality validation pipeline.
So implementing automation testing
and monitoring to the detect anomalies
before they impact downstream consumers.
So these four interconnector principles
create a fund of foundation for
efficient, reliable and scalable data
system that can quickly adopt to,
to changing business requirements.
Next it's a core components of
data data ops, architecture.
So the core components of
our core components are so
monitoring and observability.
So comprehensive monitoring extends
beyond infrastructure to encompass
data, core data quality, lineage
tracking, performance metrics business
outcome, alignment, and self-healing.
Capabilities implementation typically
involves specialized data, observability
tools, comp, complementing traditional
infrastructure monitoring, often employing
sa statistical methods to establish
standard patterns and detect anomalies.
So the advanced teams implements
observability as code, ensuring monitoring
evolves alongside data systems to maintain
visibility during architectural changes.
Next, it's a cross-functional
collaboration.
So DataOps requires collaboration
across traditionally separate domains.
The data mesh paradigm has emerged
as an influential model for
organizing teams around data domains
rather than technical functions.
Other effective structures include
DataOps Centers for centers of excellence.
Data product teams and guild models
successful collaboration framework, share
clear ownership definitions, service
level agreements, documented interfaces,
and regular synchronization mechanisms.
Next data governance frameworks.
The modern data ops
implements governance as code.
So where the policies are codified,
version control and automatically
enforced within pipelines, the key
components includes automated metadata
management systems, policy enforcement
engines self-service government tools,
and the granular access controls.
So implementation follows
if federated model where.
The central T Central teams
established frameworks, while
domain teams define specific rules
relevant to their data domains.
Next, CSE integration for data workflows,
the continuous integration, continuous
development for data workflows adopts.
Software development
practices to data operations.
This integration encompasses
virtual control for the pipeline
components and automated code
correctness and data quality testing
and control deployment strategies
like blue, green, or can releases.
So the data specific CSAD pipelines
include additional impact analysis
and continuity testing stages.
With specialized patterns, like the
expand contract approach, enabling
non braking schema changes data.
Next, the data pipeline
automation mechanisms.
So the data pipeline automation
forms the foundation of data ops,
transforming manual processes
into streamlined workflows.
Modern implementations lowered
container radiation technologies like
Docker for consistent environments
and orchestration tools such as Apache
Airflow Perfect and Dragster for
defining complex workflows as a code.
So specialized tools for data
transformations like depth and stream
processing frameworks such as Apache
Kafka, addresses, spec specific needs.
At the same time, cloud providers
offer manager services this
simplify implementation with
the prebuilt connectors and the
serverless execution models.
So DataOps Architecture integrates these
components into a system where data
pipelines receive the same engineering
engineering rigor as application code.
Modern implementations use the
business to simplify deployment while
enhancing scalability and resilience.
So the next one, the implementation
strategies and best practices.
So here the organizations must cultivate
a data driven culture with a psychological
safety that encourages experimentation.
The cross-functional
literacy and the clear data.
Product ownership models are essential
prerequisites for eliminating
our fund data and ensuring proper
stewardship across the data lab cycle.
So effective implementations
follow follow a phased approach.
So far there are assessment
phase, file phase, expansion
phase, and maturity phase.
So now we are talking about what is what
are the different phases involved here?
The assessment phase, the ba it kinds
like benchmark capabilities, identity
bo identify bottlenecks, established
baseline metrics, and define success
criteria aligned with the business
outcomes, and that it selects a
high value use case, build essential
capabilities while delivering results
and create proof points for stakeholders.
And the next expansion phase.
So in the, in this expansion phase, we
extend implementation across priority
data domains, develop repeatable playbooks
and the next it's a maturity phase.
So establish continuous improvement
processes, benchmark against industry
strands, and maintain alignment
with the strategic objectives.
So the successful data ops
requires executive sponsorship as
a strategic business initiative,
not just a technical project.
It's not it's not just technical project.
Cultivate a data-driven culture
where, and with a clear data, product
ownership and accountability frameworks.
So the organization frequently
encounter challenges with legacy system
integration, skill gaps, go governance
concerns and cultural resistance.
The successful implementation addresses
these these, the abstraction layers
for legacy systems, cross training
programs, automated compliance checks
and change management initiatives,
emphasizing education and early wins.
S the next one is some
measuring data ops success.
So the measuring there, how we
can measure the data ops success
in the four different elements.
It's a pipeline performance,
data quality, and time to
insight and research utilization.
So we have a there is 65% improvement
in build success rates and deployment
frequency through automated workflows
and continuous integration processes.
So the data quality, so we are like
on our like 48% enhancements in
data completeness, accuracy, and the
consistency through systematic validation
protocols and automated testing.
So the time to instance insight.
There is a 70% reduction in analytical
cycle times, dramatically accelerating
decision velocity and the builder
responsiveness to emerging opportunities
and the resource utilization.
So there is like 42% improvement
in infrastructure efficiency
and cost optimization through
intelligent workload management
and cloud resource optimization.
Yeah.
Measuring the DataOps success requires a
multi-dimensional approach is balancing
technical metrics and business outcomes.
The DataOps maturity model provides
the structured framework for evaluating
capabilities across six dimensions from ad
hoc level one, two, optimize level five.
Next economic implementation
imp implications of data ops.
DataOps requires that capture
direct financial impacts and
a bro broader value creation.
So these frameworks analyze
implementation, operational,
and transition cost against
the structured benefit taxonomy
beyond simple ROA calculation.
Leading organizations employ sophisticated
economic models including net present
value analysis and real options valuation.
To accurately capture the full economic
impact of data ops initiatives.
So the data ops in data ops enhance
operational efficiency through process
automation, which is which which can
reducing manual effort by 40 to 60%
for routine task and error detection.
Which is following the shift
left principle to minimize
the costly remediation cost.
Sorry.
Next it's resource
utilization optimization.
So particularly in cloud environments
and reduced overhead coordination,
so it is decreasing of meetings and
status communications by up to 30%
through transparent automated tracking.
The global data ops market says was
valued at approximately $2.1 billion
in 2023, and is projected to reach 10.5
billion billion dollars by 20 20, 20 30.
So the long-term sustainability
derives from self self-reinforcing
improvement cycles rather
than one time efficiency gain.
Critical aspects includes technical
depth management, which is systematically
addressed, suboptimal suboptimal
solutions, knowledge preservation,
which is reducing organizational
dependence on specific individuals
and economic adaptability, rapidly
adjusting to changing business
requirements and market conditions.
Next DataOps Emerging Technologies.
Here the integration with artificial
inte intelligence, integration
with artificial intelligence
and machine learning workflows.
So the convergence of DataOps
and a ML workflows has led to
integrated practices often terms.
AA Ops or M ML enabled data ops.
The key integration points include future
store, that pro detection capabilities
that identify when explainability
frameworks that trace predictions through
models to underlying data transformations.
Next edge computing.
So the edge computing introduces
unique data ops challenges
requiring specialized approaches.
These include efficient data filtering
and aggregation, inter intermittent
connectivity management through
store and forward architectures and
model deployment mechanisms that can
package and verify AI ML models across
heterogeneous edge developments.
Time next, the real time data
processing challenges and solutions.
The realtime pro processing requirements
have driven significant innovation
in the DataOps methodologies, stream
processing architectures using
technologies like Apache Kafka, and Flink
Flinger from the foundation, typically
employing Lambda or Kapa patterns.
Advanced implementations addresses
state management challenges
through distributed state stores.
Implement sophisticated back
pressure handling and employ
specialized testing methodologies
like chios engineering and next.
So the impact of cloud native
architectures, the cloud native
architectures has transformed data data
ops implementation patterns, shifting
focus from infrastructure management
to service composition, serverless
computing, and, containerization provide
consistent execution environments
while infrastructure as code has as
code has become standard practice.
So the multi-cloud strategies introduce
additional complexity address through
meta data driven architectures that
separate logical data flows from
physical implementational details.
Okay.
And then next, next slide.
So the ethical and
regulatory consideration.
So here, the first one is the
data privacy implications.
So the data ops practices directly
impact privacy production capabilities.
Privacy by design, by, by design
principles increasingly influence
implementations with requirements like
data minimization data minimization.
And integrated directly into
pipeline specifications.
Advanced techno techniques including
dynamic data masking and home
homomorphic encryption have become
standard components in privacy.
Conscious tool chains.
The modern consent management tracks
permissions as metadata following long
set personal data while jurisdictional
routing capabilities dynamically apply.
Different processing rules based
on data, subject, location,
and applicable regulation.
Next regulatory complaints.
The effective strategies employ
unified frameworks, addressing common
principles while handling jurisdiction
specific requirements Through
configurable rules, organizations
implement geo-fencing capabilities to
enforce data residency requirements.
Automated lifecycle controls for
consistent retention management and
the comprehensive lineage tracking
that documents each transformation
and access to reg regulated data
and next ethical processing.
So the ethical consideration have
gained prominence as organization
recognized the potential for unintended
consequences from automated systems.
Bias.
Direct bias detection and mitigation
capabilities are increasingly
incorporated into pipelines with fairness,
metrics, integrated data integrated
into data quality frameworks so that
transparency mechanisms have evolved
beyond the technical documentation
to include accessible explanations
for different stakeholders While.
Continuous ethic.
Ethics monitoring systems compare current
processing behavior against baseline
parameters to detect ethical drift.
Next, accountability.
So it extends beyond specific regulatory
concerns to broader governance
objectives impact AXA assessments.
Frameworks were increasingly
integrated into workflows, particularly
for high risk applications.
Organizations implement human in the loop
checkpoints through orchestrated approval
workflows, documentation automation to
maintain accurate operational records
and vendor assessment controls that
provide consistent governance across the
entire data supply system supply chain.
Okay.
The next one, real world
applications of data DataOps.
So there are plenty of services using
the DataOps DataOps applications.
The first one we can talk
about financial services.
The organizations on undergoing
digital transformations have lowered
DataOps to modernize legacy systems
while maintaining business continuity.
Financial solutions like JP Morgan
Chase have implemented data ops to
consolidate disparate data sources,
enabling realtime fraud detection
and the personalized customer
experiences while meeting while meeting
string and regulatory requirements.
And the next field, it's healthcare.
The healthcare provides have adopted
data ops to improve pa PA patient
outcomes and operational efficiency.
Mayo Clinic's implementation integrated
clinical, operational and financial
data streams to enable predictive
analytics for patient admissions,
resource allocation and treatment
effectiveness while maintaining
H-I-P-A-A compliance through automated
governance tools governance controls.
Next its manufacturing, so
manufacturing companies have deployed
data ops production processes.
Process through throughout
iot integration.
Simons uses DataOps methodologies to
process sensor data from production
environment, enabling predictive
maintenance that has reduced downtime
by 30% while improving product quality
through real time process adjustments.
Okay, and the next, next we can talk about
what is the future directions of data ops.
So the evolving methodology.
Next, the first one, like the
evolving methodologies, the emerging
trends, reshaping DataOps include
declarative pipeline specification
approaches that define desired outcomes
rather than specific steps and the
contracts that co codify expectations
between producers and con consumers.
Self-healing pipelines with
automated remediation capabilities.
And democratization.
Democratization of DataOps through
low code and no code platforms that
make development accessibilities
to non specialized specialists.
The technical disruption,
several technologies show
potential for significant
disruption to current practices.
The knowledge graphs and the semantic
technologies are gaining adoption
for complex integration scenario.
Quantum computing presence possibilities
for the specific processing challenges.
Synthetic data technologies are
advancing for privacy, pre preserving
development, and anonymous systems
provided by powered by Reinforcement
Learning, learning show promise for
self-optimizing data, infrastructures.
Next, integration with
the other disciplines.
The DevOps will likely see deeper
integration with MOPS and DevOps
DevOps, creating unified frameworks
and spanning spanning the entire
digital value chain and expect
extending beyond enterprise boundaries.
So finally, I conclude that the data
ops represents a transfer May two
paraic shift in how organization.
Conceptualize, implement and manage their
data ecosystems by integrating software
engineering principles with the data
management practices, data practices,
data ops addresses, addresses the critical
challenges of data velocity, quality and
governance that have historically limited
the business value of data initiatives.
Mature DataOps implementations deliver
benefits across multiple dimensions.
Which are like technical gains via
reduce it cycle times and improve
quality economic advantages through
optimize resource allocation and cost
reduction and the strategic value
creation through enhanced organization
agility and innovation capacity.
The future evaluation of DataOps
will like likely see deeper
integration with adjacent
disciplines like ML ops and DevOps.
Increase autonomy autonomy through
AI powered self optimization and
expanded scope to en income encompas
cross organization data ecosystems for
organizations committed to becoming.
Truly data driven and data ops
provides not just a framework for
transforming data from passive asset
into a active driver of business value.
So that's how I brought the data ops.
Thanks for giving opportunity,
and if you have any questions,
please reach out to me.
Thank you.
Have a good day.