Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining me today at Con 42.
My name is, and I'm honored to present
on the topic of transforming public
sector observability using artificial
intelligence and business intelligence
with over 12 years of experience.
As I said, the business objects
business warehouse and Power BI
specialist and experience on having on
working on Microsoft Power BI Stack.
I've led digital transformation
initiatives for major enterprises,
including Nestle, USA, Siemens, and artex.
Currently I serve as a principal
developer and analyst at I Global Tech.
Where I focus on bridging the gap
between the technical data solutions
and real world public sector needs.
Today's session is designed to equip you
with the understanding and tools needed
to evolve the public sector observability.
We'll explore how to use ai, bi,
and modern data platforms to convert
the fragmented system telemetry into
actionable intelligence that improves
service delivery and public trust.
Observability challenge when we come
up to the observability challenge.
Let's begin by acknowledging
the the core challenges faced
by public sector agencies.
First complexity overload.
Data is being generated across
the multiple disconnected systems,
including mainframes, modern cloud
platforms, and and customer databases.
This fragmented environment makes
it incredibly difficult to gain
a full picture of operations.
Second visibility gaps key insights are
often buried within individual systems.
These silos prevent leaders from
understanding the end-to-end
flow of services and outcomes.
For example, the performance
issues in a backend tax processing
system might go undetected until
constraints begin experiencing delays.
And the third one would be
the reactive operations.
Too often most of the enterprises only.
Become aware of issues after
a disruption has occurred.
And this not only reduces the service
quality, but also erodes the customer's
trust and and the agency's ability
to fulfill its mission effectively
modern observative framework to.
To address these challenges, we
introduce a modern observative framework
which is built in four pillars.
First one would be the business
intelligence, where we use the
business BI tools like Power bi to
transform the disparate law, raw
data into dashboards and score.
And this enables decision makers to
proactively monitor and manage services.
Second one would be the AI
powered artificial intelligence
which plays a critical role in
predicting the system behaviors.
Identifying the hidden patterns
or finding out the anomalies, and
recommending the preventative actions.
Machine learning models detect
issues before they escalate.
Third one would be the data integration
where true observability requires merging
data from all systems regardless of vendor
location or format into a single view.
This unified approach of allows for
seamless data analysis across agencies.
And the fourth one would be the
core monitoring where we have the
comprehensive collection of metrics.
Which are very, which are pretty
continuous and and continuous logs, traces
and events without a robust telemetry.
Foundation it is impossible to gain
real visibility into the health and
and the performance of the services.
These frameworks allows the
public sector teams to shift
from reactor to the predictive
Operations Technical Foundation.
So let's, when we explore this
framework, it is, which is technically
implemented at the data collection,
where we establish the pipelines.
To acquire the telemetry data from
legacy on-prem systems to cloud services,
third party APIs and IOT devices.
This requires the co connectors,
agents, or integration services
that that normalize the data.
And a centralized analytics engine often
built using star spark Databricks similar
platforms, processing incoming telemetry.
It correlates logs with
performance metrics and
generates insights in real time.
The next one would be the storage.
For compliance purposes, we store
data in secure cloud-based data lakes.
Or warehouses.
Solutions like Azure data Lake or
Snowflake are ideal because they
offer the encryption for data and
and which has also have the role
based access and max accountability.
Next one would be the visualization
where dashboards are tailored
to specific agency roles.
Which includes these agency roles.
When we talk about the agency
roles, it's like the role based
role based, access related dashboard
where it involves executive level,
operational level, and technical level.
Power BI and Tableau and SAP
business objects serve these needs by
offering the customizable real time
visual layers that align with KPIs.
This layered architecture ensures that
the data is being trusted, timely,
and actionable based, actionable
insights for the enterprises.
Transformation success stories.
Here are the three real world
examples, which I, based on my
experience, which I would highlight
the effectiveness of this framework.
First one would be the legacy
migration where we revolutionize
the nest USA's outdated monitoring
infrastructure with seamless integration
of modern observability tools.
And also.
The aging.
We Nestle used to have the aging
monitoring system that couldn't scale or
provide the cross-functional visibility.
We introduced the modern
observability tools indicated
with their existing landscape.
This resulted in a 40% faster
incident response time and and
significantly improved the IT
and business team collaboration.
Next one would be the would be sware.
We created the cross-platform
observability ecosystem that merged 12
plus data streams into a unified view.
And this gave Siemens the
operational leaders the ability
to see end-to-end service health,
reducing the system downtime by 35%.
Next one would be the, with Arthrex,
where the company needed a way to identify
the performance degradation before it
affected operations, where we implemented
an AI driven no detection system
that flagged early signs of failure.
Then this way a solution prevented
almost 28 major incidents in a year and
saved up to $1.5 million in potential
downtime cost, downtime costs, and
to, and to avoid the disruptions.
These stories show how the
observatory goes beyond the monitoring
and it empowers the predictive
operations implementation roadmap.
Where we implementing the observability
in public sector organizations
requires a systematic phased approach.
And and the first one would be the
assessment where we evaluate the current
monitoring capabilities, where we begin
conducting the detailed inventory of
of your existing monitoring tools, data
sources and workflows, evaluate gaps,
redundancies, and compliance risks.
The.
Stage should also I mean involve the
cross-functional teams to understand
their their burning issues of the
bottlenecks that they're gonna face
when they're trying to implement
the, implement This, data points
architecture would be the second step
where we design the observability
architecture based on the assessment.
Define which telemetry
signals need to be collected.
The a TL workflows is needed and
ai ml models to be deployed storage
schemas and visual interfaces.
Prioritize, prioritizing this
modular and scalable design.
And the third one would be
the implementation where
we roll out in phases.
Start with the proof of concept in a
high priority service and such as backend
and emergency response systems and and
con configuring the alerting rules AI
triggers and dashboards where we use
the agile sprints to a iterate quickly.
And the adoption would be the fourth
one where we, where the technology alone
doesn't guarantee success, where we
trade staff on the observability tools
establish documentation and onboard
executive champions create feedback loops
and continuous me measure usage, system
performance, and user satisfaction.
So by this roadmap, the agencies can
avoid and our enterprises can avoid.
Most of the companies can avoid
the analysis para paralysis and and
achieve the, measurable progress
in three to six months, or the
desired time period, which we, which
during the product planning phase.
The next one would be the technology
stack where this gives you the effective
observability on well integrated
technology stack which has a bunch
of tools where which is, describes
the, describes its own importance on
performing the front end and and backend
calculations, and also back, and also
performing the machine learning stuff.
Power bi, which is a leading
visualization platform where it
provides the customizable dashboards
that pull in realtime data through APIs
and direct query and import models.
Power BI also supports the role level
security, which is also added for the
sensitive public sector data or and
on and also in private organizations,
SAP business objects, which is, which
remains critical for agencies that
require a governed enterprise reporting.
Compliance based scheduling and
complex report logic where where
most of the semantic model has been
performed in business objects and
s business objects has disparate.
Values, and connecting to disparate
data sources which integrates
with the S-A-P-E-C-C-I, which is a
backend business warehouse and other
ERP systems, Azure, and Snowflake,
which serves as a infrastructure
and the data warehouse layers.
Azure supports identity management.
Data pipelines and AI services.
Snowflake provides a fast, scalable
storage and built-in support for
semi-structured and unstructured data.
So Databricks, which powers advanced
machine learning, it supports time
series forecasting, anomaly detection,
and NLP on on logs or customer feedback.
So this Databricks.
Notebooks also allow for the flexible
experimentation by data scientists,
and this stack is chosen, not for
the technical strength, but also
for the compliance, scalability,
and long-term cost effectiveness.
ROA metrics.
When agencies invest in observability
and measurable outcomes what can
they expect is what this showcases.
The, our observability solutions
majorly deliver the measurable returns
across key performance indicators.
With significant improvements in
operational efficiency and service
quality, the fast flow incident re
resolution would be the highest KPI, which
would instead of spending the spending
hours diagnosing root causes, teams can
ask, isolate issues in minutes using
correlation dashboards and AI alerts.
We have seen resolution
times drop by up to 50%.
So improved uptime
would be the second KPI.
With with the productive alerts
and proactive maintenance uptime
SLAs improved dramatically.
This means the fewer customer
complaints and higher service
continuity and better audit readiness.
Increased staff productivity would
be the third one where analysts
and engineers spend less time
annually stitching together data
with the centralized dashboards and
they've, they majorly focus on the
improvements rather than firefighting.
Reduce the operational costs.
Where, which, in which reduces
the manual interventions contact
escalations and downtime related
penalties in several projects.
A total all operational costs
dropped by 20% within a year.
So higher customer satisfaction where
the customers, most of the customers
don't notice when things go right,
but they do when the systems fail.
Improving the uptime and,
responsiveness, enhances public
trust and stakeholder confidence.
Typically the investment in observability
pays for itself within nine to 12 months.
Next one would be the common
implementation challenges where the.
Security complaints where the
public companies public assure
companies must come, must comply
with stringent data regulations.
It's essential to choose tools that
are FedRAMP and FSMA compliant and
and implement strict access controls
across your observability stack.
And second would be the data integration
complexity where legacy systems often
lack APIs or standardized formats.
Teams need to build custom ETL
pipelines, use middleware, and
sometimes reverse engineer logs.
Data integration is the hardest
part, but also the most rewarding.
The next one would be the
cultural resistance or where
observability shift the most.
Cultural resistance or organizational
adoption where most of the.
Observability shifts
the way people work it.
It requires transparency,
accountability, and data literacy.
Some teams may resist change, fearing
loss of control and increased scrutiny.
That's why the executive
sponsorship and and cross training
is more significant and vital.
Next one would be the budget constraints
where where a, where most of the
companies often operate within tight
budgets and long procurement cycles.
Start with the high ROI pilot and
measure value early and secure.
The incremental funding to scale further.
Anticipating these challenges allows
for the smoother implementation
and higher adoption rates.
Next steps would be.
Would be to find out the
observability of your organization.
To bring the observability
to the, your organization.
Here are the practical steps where
observability assessment, which evaluates
your current monitoring capabilities and
identify the key gaps where we, where
it, where it is needed to run a two to
four week internal review to evaluate
what's being monitored and what's
missing, and who owns which data streams.
Map out the telemetry architecture.
And next one would be this would be
the pilot implementation where we
select the pilot use case, where we
choose a high visibility service such
as the customer portal, performance.
Distributor, if there is any distribution,
monitoring, or emergency services
response team or something like that.
And demonstrate a tangible
which demonstrate the tangible
results within 30 to 60 days.
And also building the strategic roadmap
where we develop the phased approach to
full observability implementation, where
we define short, midterm, long-term goals,
which includes tool standardization, AI
model expansion, and training models.
And, ensure the alignment with
the agency's digital strategy.
Investment in training and literacy
would be the, another observability
where we, which also comes under
the cap capability building.
And this observability is, it's for
the analysts leadership and operations
team, and we offering the workshops.
Create document, creating the
documentation and fostering for
the cultural culture of the data
driven decision making would be
the best one under this category.
And also it also if the
internal bandwidth is limited.
Then it's considered to be engaging the
experienced partner to accelerate the
design, deployment and change management.
So transformation doesn't have to
be big bang but start with one one
use case, and then I. Deliver the
success and scale it interactively.
Thank you for spending
this time with me today.
I hope you know, have a clear vision
of how AI and business intelligence
can elevate observability across
public sector organizations.
Whether you're just a beginning or a
scaling existing efforts, the opportunity
is vast and the impact is real.
I welcome your your questions and and
thanks for connecting and let's work
together to transform the vis into
the visibility into mission success.
Thank you.