Welcome everyone, and
thank you for joining.
I'm Anish.
Today's session will focus on how
modular architecture can be a catalyst
for scaling, agility, maintainability,
and performance in enterprise platforms.
We'll examine the core
principles of modularity, compare
implementation strategies, and look
at real world applications and.
Quantifiable outcomes, especially
in service heavy domains.
Let's understand modular architecture.
Modular architecture decomposes
large applications into
discrete self-funding modules.
Each encompassing a specific
business capability.
These modules interact via
stable interfaces, particularly
a or messaging brokers.
Why this matters?
It supports independent lifecycle
management, built deploy, and scale.
It aligns development with domain
boundaries, especially when
using domain driven design DTT.
It simplifies testing and CICD pipelines
by reducing blast previous of changes.
Think of each module as a ED context.
It owns its own stake logic and can evolve
independently making it a natural fit for.
Cloud native systems.
Let's break down the fundamental
rates of our modular system.
The core characteristics
first, encapsulation.
Encapsulation prevents tight coupling
by hiding internal implementation.
For example, our customer
module should expose only what's
necessary, see a customer profile
API and hide how it aggregates.
Loyalty points, high cohesion.
All functionalities within a
module should serve one purpose.
A well designed order module should
not handle customer notifications.
Loose coupling modules communicate a
synchronously or via table contracts.
This encourages event driven
architectures, which decouple execution
and increase fall tolerance interface
stability interfaces, example.
The rest graph or GRPC must
remain stable across versions.
Tools open API or proto above schemas
are essential for maintaining version
control and backward compatibility.
Here's what to keep in mind
when designing modular systems.
First, separation of concerns,
divide responsibilities logically.
Ui, business logic, data persistence.
Must be handled independently.
For instance, don't mix billing
logic into a product catalog module.
Standardized interfaces, use rest or GIPC
with versioning and schema contracts,
employ tools, Kong or API gateway
for managing and securing interfaces.
Scalability by design, each
module can scale independently.
Payments module can scale three
times more than a literally
static health center module.
Saving cost and improving throughput.
Reusability, shared libraries or
common services, example or audit
login should be extracted as reusable
components or SDKs port isolation.
If the inventory service fails, the
checkout should still proceed with.
Estimated quantities or cash data.
This is fault tolerance in action.
Maintainability.
Modularity allows you to migrate
tech stacks incrementally.
Example, you can refactor one
module from PHP two, no JS without
affecting the rest of the system.
Let's look at the implementation
parts, microservices, architecture.
Each service has its own code
base, DB deployment pipeline.
I for domains with strong service
boundaries, tools, humanities, SST
o Docker, spring Road, et cetera.
Modular monoliths, a single deployable
unit, but internally organized as modules.
Great for early stage teams, or
when deployment overhead needs to be
minimized, can evolve into microservices.
When maturity grows, plugin architectures
core system loads or injects new features
at one time, common NCMS E-Commerce
engines with the magnet or data platform.
STRANA enables feature toggles a
testing, and third party integration.
Use decision mattresses based
on deployment frequency, team
size, service criticality.
To choose the appropriate architecture.
Enterprise platforms benefit in
measurable ways, faster development.
Modular CICD pipelines means teams can
release independently less bottlenecks,
fewer cross team dependencies.
Performance optimization, lightweight
modules enable caching, asing
processing, and targeted load balancing.
Think of a high volume pricing service
tuned independently from the backend.
Simplified art maintenance easier to
isolate and debug issues, telemetry
tools, ANA and open telemetry shine
when service emit consistent metrics.
Technology.
Agno one module could run
no GS while another run.
Python modularity enables.
GL services without
sacrificing consistency.
To illustrate the practical
application of modular architecture
principles, consider an enterprise
e-commerce platform that successfully
implemented a modular are approach.
Product catalog module migrated
to a standalone service with
Elasticsearch based indexing.
This reduced query time
by 47% and allowed for.
Passing ingestion.
Pipelines.
Customer management, modernizing
customer onboarding, allowed targeted
performance improvements, resulted in
40 to 60% reduction in form abandonment.
Order processing.
Adopted CQRS pattern
to separate operations.
Enable 99.99% uptime with intelligent
retries and circuit breakers.
A module introduced modular AI
based recommendation engine using
a plug and play architecture enable
15% increase in product discovery
through personalized rankings.
This shows how modular enable
modularity enables both scalability
and feature experimentation.
Here are the benefits of modular approach.
Faster time to market features, ship
faster with smaller focused teams.
Implementation speed.
New capabilities can be added
without disrupting existing ones.
Resource utilization teams manage their
own workloads and backlogs, increasing
throughput team autonomy, developers
own modules end to end, leading to
more accountability and innovation.
This approach is key for
scaling engineering orgs beyond
a few cross-functional teams.
It's strong, easy.
These are the challenges
and considerations.
Initial complexity, setting up module
boundaries, defining contracts,
and building pipelines take effort
early investment is required.
Next, performance overhead.
Too many services.
Talking to each other
can increase latency.
Use techniques, bulk heads, caching,
message batching and connection Pooling.
Organizational alignment
without clarity and ownership.
Team scan unintentionally.
Couple modules establish clear
domain ownership supported by tools
backstage or compass for visibility.
Here are the best practices for adoption.
Start with domain modeling.
Use DVD to define module
boundaries, tools, even storming
or context max help here.
Interface governance.
Use API re registries, schema
violation and contract testing.
Example, fact incremental migration.
Don't big bank manufacture.
Extract one module, define KPIs.
Validate outcomes, then proceed.
Feature toggles help automate everything.
CICD Code quality checks API,
lending and runtime policies.
This supports consistency
and security at scale.
To summarize balance agility with
stability, modular architecture allows
innovation without compromising system
health support, sustainable evolution.
Code bases, infra and teams
can evolve independently, gain
a competitive edge faster.
Reiteration cycles lower risk, and.
Greater developer productivity of
enterprise platforms is modular,
composable, and scalable by default.
Thank you for your attention.
I would love to hear your questions,
whether they are about module boundaries,
migration tooling, or team structures.
Feel free to connect me with me.