Everyone.
In today's session we'll develop into
the fascinating world of observability
in modern pressure trading platforms.
These systems, which handle vast amounts
of market data and execute rates in
microseconds face immense challenges
when it comes to maintaining performance.
As the complexity of high frequency
trading increases, traditional monitoring
solutions are no longer sufficient.
Through this discussion, we'll explore
how advanced observability tools
like distributed tracing, machine
learning driven anomaly detection,
cloud native observability, pipelines,
transforming how we monitor.
Let's dive into how observability is
revolutionizing high trading and shaping
the future of treasury operations.
Hello, I'm OU and senior with over 23
years of experience in the investment
banking technology domain, specializing
in delivering high performance, cost
effective technology solutions tailored
to meet complex definite needs.
Across fixed trading, risk management,
regulatory compliance, client reporting,
and having worked with industry
leading products such as Ion Sunguard,
fast intrad Trade Web, Bloomberg,
and specialized like Wall Street.
Which is a product of Aon.
I have involved in design, development
and optimization of a trading strategies,
leverage advanced quantitative
models and market data analytics.
My work includes implementing
high frequency trading algorithms,
market making strategies.
Trading strategies that have
significantly improved execution,
efficiency and profitability.
My product knowledge or experience
encompasses a range of financial
products, including US treasuries.
Be it swift messages or ISO
related packs or messages.
I have extensive experience
supporting all of them.
Both my career, I have built reputation
for managing lining and optimizing
advanced technology infrastructures that.
Deep dive into how this availability is
revolutionizing high sequential trading
and shaping the future of how pressure
operations will be vulnerability in
modern pressuring trading platforms.
So drawing from my experience building
and ture at major financial institutions.
I will share how modern observability
practices are revolutionizing operations
in systems where reliability directly
impacts the financial outcome.
Okay, we'll examine how observability
solutions monitor systems processing
each 0.4 terabytes of market data
daily with algorithmic engines.
0.5% of treasury at
speeds of 45 microseconds.
Unbelievable amount of data that is being.
Join me as we dive into the
technical components that
enable this performance and.
Of the modern training
more than 8.4 terabytes.
We recently implemented database
using KD, which used to process
about three to 600 million a day.
For several dealer to dealer markets,
52.5% of algo trading algorithm,
big trading percentage of tertiary
trade executed by the algorithms.
We also try to integrate smart
order router, which process more
than 75% in few of the exchanges.
Famous like Nasdaq.
A broker dealer and and
these are the exchanges.
Execution is
latency.
85 key messages per second.
That's the throughput of market
data in the peak conditions.
The pure volume and velocity of modern
pressure trading creates unprecedented
observability challenges with microsecond
level predict making and execution.
Predictional monitoring
approaches simply cannot.
These systems operate at a scale
where even minor performance
and degradations can result in
significant financial demand.
Moving on to the next slide.
So attributed RAC in treasury training.
So basically this is the empty mean
time to resolution or resolution.
Implementation of distributed tracing
across trading microservices has
TR by 78%, enabling faster response
and critical trading operations.
End-to-end visibility races now connect
across previously siloed components,
providing transparency from market data.
Very key for locking the trades where
you place an order and it has to get
filled to get the right match place.
Analytics identify bottlenecks in the
trading pipeline, allowing for targeted
optimizations that have improved
average execution times by 23% low.
Tracing ads less than 2.5
microseconds of overhead.
Maintaining critical performance while
providing observability, distributed
ing has transformed troubleshooting
trading platforms, enabling teams to
follow transactions across complex,
massive microservice architectures
without compromising performance.
Anomaly detection within learning.
So our ML powered anomaly detection
systems that achieve 85% accuracy in
identifying trading pattern deviations.
This capability has prevented
millions in potential trading losses.
By detecting market dislocations,
execution anomalies, compliance issues
before they impact trading outcomes.
The system continuously learns from both
normal operations and detected anomalies,
improving detection accuracy over time
while maintaining performance under.
So as the diagram illustrates realtime
pattern recognition identifies market
anomalies within microseconds, the
historical baseline comparison,
compare current normalized patterns,
false positive reductions, learning
algorithms, minimize alert, automated
response actions, triggers, safeguards.
So here I wanna touch upon the need for
observability for trade surveillance
and spoofing in this fast evolving
landscape of treasury trading.
The need for robust trade surveillance
and observability has never been more
critical with high frequency systems.
Executing thousands of trades per second.
The ability to monitor and track every
transaction in real time is essential
for ensuring market integrity, regulatory
compliance, and risk mitigation.
Surveillance systems
identify potential market.
Fraud or compliance violations.
While observability tools provide
end-to-end visibility into the
trading process, allowing firms
to detect anomalies, optimize
performance, and minimize latency,
the integration of machine learning
for anomaly detection combined.
Market activity and the system health.
This powerful combination ensures
that trading platforms are not
only operationally efficient,
but also compliant with evolving
regulations in modern treasury
trading platforms, mobility growth.
Beyond this monitoring because proactive
approach that helps organizations
detect potential issues before
they affect the trading outcomes.
Ensuring that systems can continue
to operate at a scale with
the reliability and security.
Moving on to the next slide, cloud
native observability pipelines.
So today we have ma on web services.
Today we have GP we.
So our cloud native observability
pipelines have transformed
monitoring increasing capabilities
by almost 30% while reducing
operational cost by percent.
These pipelines process over 36
million metric data points per
minute, enabling real-time visibility
across global trading operations.
By separating collection from
processing and storage, the architecture
maintains a resilience during market
volatility when observability becomes
most critical, depends on all these.
So it's like data collection,
processing, enrichment, storage and
indexing, visualization and alert.
So by data collection, the invest
metric logs, traces from the system
at source, process enrichment like
izing data with business metadata
and producing the noise storage.
Optimizing for both realtime
queries and historical analysis.
K db the pick database or MongoDB, the
NoSQL database are completely efficient
and for such observability pipelines.
Moving on to the next slide.
Smart Router integration, as the.
Algorithmic trading where, be it the
dealer to dealer or a dealer to fly
market, the algorithm Smart order
decides how the order would get routed
based on the, and it's smartly tax
and allocate the is required by the.
Round time measurement, continuous
monitoring of auto transmission
and acknowledgement agency venue
responsiveness, measuring performance
variations between paying destinations,
flip page analysis, realtime comparison
of expected results, execution prices.
This is very key because sometimes
the mass the smart order router
may or may not execute, add the
desire to fill for that particular
instance, which the Desco wants.
So the realtime comparison of the expected
versus actual execution crisis is very
critical, which has to be observed.
This integration creates powerful
feedback loops that continuously
optimize order routing decisions
based on real-time performance data.
Our implementation has improved overall
execution quality by 17%, while reducing
diverse selection by monitoring venue
specific patterns that might indicate
information leakage or toxic flow.
Moving on to the next slide.
So this is basically the system latency
variations that is described here where
the heat load is shown by the light
orange and baseline latency in the red.
The pressure trading systems
experience latency variations of up
to 20% under three flow conditions,
particularly during the market openings.
Economic announcements, auctions.
Any key IPOs that go online.
Observability solutions must
adapt to these variations
without introducing performance.
In, in this, if you notice at 9:00 AM 9:30
AM the peak volatility latency is gone.
During it has gone down and
during the market close.
Quantum computing advances,
cryptographic protections.
Trading platforms are implementing
quantum resistant approaches to
monitoring these techniques ensure the
sensitively trading data remains secure.
Even as cryptographic standards.
You all early implementations
have demonstrated that quantum
resistant approaches can be.
Integrated with minimal performance
impact by providing future
proof security guarantees.
Homomorphic encryption, enabling analysis
of encrypted metrics without decryption,
maintaining privacy while allowing
alerting on sensitive trading data.
This technology for both compliance
with data regulations while.
Quantum random number
generation leveraging quantum
approach.
Implementing lattice based cryptographic
algorithms to secure monitoring data
against potential quantum attacks.
These algorithms ensure that today's
encrypted observability data remains
protected against decryption.
This is the post Quantum.
On the next slide.
Blockchain based audit systems
blockchain based audit systems are
transforming ti market infrastructure
by creating the immutable records
of all trading activities.
Systems have reconciliation cost by
82% while providing near realtime
catch visibility across the parties.
Integration of observability data with
blockchain records creates powerful new
capabilities for regulatory reporting,
compliance monitoring, allowing for
automated deduction of potential market
manipulation or trading goal violations.
So realtime settlement visibility
plans, packing of lifecycle,
trade lifecycle is the key.
Back in straight through process
rates will impact the reader books,
which may or may not be found
out until the end of the day.
So this is very critical.
Reduce reconciliation needs single
source of across counter parties.
Enhanced compliance,
monitoring, compliance, and
regulatory are becoming big.
All these iso, all the standards
are becoming really big.
So automated re.
And as I mentioned earlier,
immutable audit trail,
graphically secured transaction.
So what are the challenges
in observability?
Performance impact data volume
management, signal versus noise.
So observability instrumentation adds
overhead that can affect vacancy.
Solutions include strategic
sampling, brand circuit monitoring.
Design specifically for ultra low
latency environments, data volume
management systems generate terabytes
of telemetry data processing.
This volume is in real time queries,
sophisticated pipelines and storage
solutions optimized for time series.
Data effective implementations
use steered storage approaches.
The hot data kept in memory and
cold data automatically archive
cost effective storage while
maintaining query capabilities.
KDB, which I explained couple of
slides earlier, was one of the key
databases which we have implemented in
the past that has proven to proven to
mitigate such data volume management.
Advanced correlation contextualization
techniques combined with machine
learning help identify fully
actionable insights among the noise
of normal market fluctuations.
Addressing these challenges require a
balanced approach that considers both
technical and business requirements, the
most successful implementations, line
availability strategies with specific.
So what are.
And conclusions, the future of pressure
trading observability lies systems
that not only monitor, but impact
organizations, especially the financial
organizations, that capabilities will
gain significants and efficiency,
compliance, and ultimately profitability.
So assessment.
Then comes the architecture design,
develop observability framework that
minimizes performance impact, progressive
implementation, deploy instrumentation
and phase validating performances at each
stage, and continuous optimization refine
based on operational insights and evolving
creating factors mean time to, me,
quality, lower operational,
past and enhanced risk as market
complex increases becomes not just
an operational but competitive
necess and, that's pretty much it.
We conclude this presentation.
Thank you for taking time to listen
to this presentation and if you have
any questions or any suggestions or
any recommendations, do reach out to
me on the contact details provided in.