Hi.
Welcome everybody.
Today I'm going to discuss about
observability in the evolution of AI
and error network infrastructure, how
the network observability powers the
backbone of artificial LI systems,
and why it matters of the future
of hyper performance computing.
My name is Basra.
I was graduated from University India.
I worked in a couple of networking and
observability companies where I have seen
firsthand how this matters, starting from
the enterprise internet to all the way to
AI networks, which are prevalent nowadays.
In 1960s, aquanet, that was a
packet switching network, which
was formed to facilitate research.
Internet in research
institutions and universities.
So that was the foundation for
of modern internet with very
rudimentary monitoring tools.
It has interface message processing,
console networking, control center
tools, and CP debugging tools,
ping like utilities and so on.
In 1980 to 2000, the evolution of s
network management protocol had happened.
That was a net for, to, it was
a standard tool for monitoring
the network performance and
health metrics in 2002, 2015.
That's where most cloud related.
Revolution happened.
So in 2002 to 2015, the agent based
monitoring which is installed on
VMs or containers like JX data, but
Datadog agents software as service
delivery, reduce infrastructure.
But then.
Like New Relic p Datadog
dashboard and visualizations
have become a common practice.
Real time dashboards become very
standard like Datadog and Stack Driver.
Lifting systems like Threshold, threshold
based, an anomaly detection alerts
like CloudWatch, Jix, integration with
DevOps, tools like PagerDuty, slack,
CICD, and Systems Multi-Cloud monitoring.
2012 to 15 tools like Datadog and Stack
Driver 2015 to now new AI era tools.
There.
Develop on top of whatever the
cloud environments have it.
Pretty much like they're advanced
in terms of network networking.
Observability like Datadog to collect
unified metrics logs, security with the
AI based directing Grafana Pros, low key.
These are open source stack for
metrics, logs, and visualization.
Open telemetry.
Open standard for collecting
crisis metrics and logs arise.
AI fi, AA production model monitoring,
drift detection, explainability.
Dynatrace full stack
observability with determinist.
K again, the cloud providers like
A-W-S-G-C-P Azure, they have native
tools integration integrated in their
cloud environments for observability.
So this is the history of
the observability tools.
Those have happened from the old internet.
Still our.
Why network observability matters for
ea, there are very, some of the very
common reasons are like performance
guarantee, pay failure, domain
isolation, resource optimization,
security assurance, et cetera.
Performance guarantees for EAA
involves setting and enforcing.
Measurable benchmarks for model accuracy,
response time, scalability, and resource
utilization throughout the AI life cycle.
This guarantee ensures that AI
systems may define service level
objectives under varying workloads
and real world conditions.
And establishing such guarantees
is critical for building trust,
ensuring reliability, and aligning a
outputs with business or regulatory
expectations, a failure domain.
Isolation failure domain isolation.
AI refers to the practice of designing
AI systems so that failures in one
component, such as data ingestion,
model training, or inference do not
cascade and impact the entire pipeline.
By segmenting the system into
independent fault tolerant
domains, teams can contain issues.
Simplify, debugging and maintain
overall system resilience.
This approach is essential for ensuring
high availability and durability in
complex and distributed environments.
Resource optimization.
This source optimization AI
focuses on efficiently managing
computational storage and manage memory
resources across the AI life cycle.
From data processing and model
training to deployment and inference
techniques such as model pruning,
quantization hardware acceleration,
and all cloud scheduling help reduce
costs while maintaining performance
effective resource optimization.
Ensure scalability.
Lowers environmental impact and
maximizes investments security which is
very important in AA networks because
AA networks are always susceptible.
They're vulnerable to security threats.
Security assurance in AA involves
implementing measures to protect
systems from threats such as
data breaches, model theft.
Serial effects and unauthorized access.
It includes securing training
data, ensuring model integrity,
enforcing access controls, and
regularly editing system behavior.
Strong security assurance is critical
for maintaining trust complaints and
the safety deployment of a AI in since
two and high stakes environments.
Is not good.
Visual, there is a visual scale
challenge, in networking observability.
The full stack visibility in AA re
refers to a comprehensive monitoring and
understanding of the entire AA pipeline.
From data ingestion and pre-processing
to model training, deployment, and
inference, it allows teams to track
data quality, model performance, and
infrastructure usage in real time,
ensuring transparency and accountability.
This visibility is crucial for
detecting biases, managing drift,
and maintaining the reliability and
ethical integrity of AA systems.
Excuse me.
Distributed tracing.
Distributed tracing in the AI
provides visibility into the flow of
data and execution across different
components of an AI system, such
as data pipelines, model training
services, APIs, and inference engines.
It enables teams to track requests
and processing steps and end to end
help helping identifying latency,
bottlenecks, or failures across.
Distributed environments.
This traceability is crucial for
debugging, optimizing performance
and ensuring accountability
in complex AI workflows.
Realtime telemetry this is an advanced
version of monitoring this in AI
involves the continuous collection
and monitoring of metrics, logs and
events from AI systems as they operate.
It provides immediate insights into
model performance, data, quality,
system health, and user interactions.
This enables the rapid detection
of anomalies, supports proactive
maintenance, and ensures a systems remain
reliable, efficient, and aligned with
expectations In dynamic environments,
hardware level metrics in EA refers
to the monitoring of low level system
indicators such as G-P-U-C-P utilization.
Memory, bandwidth, power consumption,
temperature, and disk input.
Output.
These metrics are critical for
understanding the resource demands
of EA workloads, optimizing
performance and preventing
hardware bottleneck or failures.
By analyzing hardware level data,
teams can fine tune model deployments,
improve efficiency, and ensure
sustainable scaling of AI operations.
Inside the modern network
like the port speed.
Once upon a time, if it was a
hundred gig, it was a revolution.
But nowadays I speak, there are
systems which are being developed
with 800 gig port speed, a single
box in networking as 51.2 terabytes
per second processing capability,
data processing capability such as
the speed, because that is the speed.
Required by AA systems extraordinary
volume of data packets, processes daily
with the large scale AI infrastructure.
Ultra low latency, near
instantaneous response are very
critical for synchronizing.
Network training, reliability, of
course, the finance availability,
essential for uninterrupted model
training and inference operations.
So the network has become a very
crucial comprising of speed, latency.
Reliability, and throughput.
Observability.
So metrics with metrics.
They provide quantitative data
on system performance and health.
A specific metrics include model accuracy,
latency, throughput, data drift, and
resource utilization, which help track how
will the AI systems meet its objectives.
These metrics enable teams to
quickly detect anomalies, optimize
model behavior, and maintain
reliable, scalable AI deployments.
Logs provide detailed timestamp records
of discre events within a system.
Such as data processing steps, model
training, isolation address, and user
interactions, logs of rich, contextual
information that helps diagnose
issues, press failures, and understand
the sequence of actions leading to
a problem in a comprehensive logging
is variation for editing, debugging
complex workflows, and ensuring
transparency throughout the AI life cycle.
Processing AA captured the detailed
end to engineer requests or data as
they move through various components
of an AA system such as data inges
model training and inference services.
They help map the sequence and timing
of operations, revealing dependency
dependencies and pinpointing
where delays are errors occur.
Expressing is crucial for diagnosing
performance issues, understanding
system behavior, and ensuring a
smooth, relatable, a workflows
in distributed AI environments.
Programmable telemetry revolution.
Telemetry has become a rich
monitoring tools like Google,
RPC, and various other products.
Lot of companies are developing telemetry
tools, but traditional monitoring
focuses on correcting and analyzing
predefined system metrics like CPU use
a memory consumption dis, and network
traffic to ensure infrastructure and
applications surrounding smoothly.
It often delays on threshold based
alerts and periodic checks to detect
failures or performance issues, while
effective for basic operational health.
Traditional monitoring likes the deep
contextual insights needed for complex
modern AI or distributor systems.
Modern telemetry such as GRPC goes beyond
traditional monitoring by continuously
correcting rich high resolution data,
including metrics, logs, and events.
Traces, of course, from all
layers of a system in real time.
It leverages advanced analytics,
machine learning and automation to
provide deeper insights into system
behavior, detect anomalies, and predict
issues before they impact users.
This approach is essential for
managing complex distributed AI
systems and dynamic cloud environments
with greater accuracy and agility.
Self-healing network architectures.
So the networks no longer should no longer
need to wait for healing for a human.
They have to self-heal so that
they will be resilient, they will
be available they'll be hype.
They will be crossing high throughput.
So detect self-healing network
architectures, detect operational
efficient issues by continuously
monitoring network health through
real time telemetry, including
metrics, logs, and distributed traces.
They use automated anomaly detection.
A analytics and predefined rules
to identify faults, performance,
degradations, or security threats
without human intervention.
Once detected, these systems can trigger
automatic remediation actions, like
re rerouting the traffic, restarting
services, or adjusting configurations, or
to maintain optimal network performance
and minimize downtime in self-feeding.
Network architecture analysis
plays a critical role.
By processing the continuous
stream of telemetry data to
identify patterns, anomalies, and
root causes of network issues.
This involves yay and machine learning
algorithms to correlate metrics,
logs, and traces across distributed
components, enabling real-time
diagnosis, failures, diagnosis of
failures, or performance degradations.
Effective analysis allows the
system to prioritize incidents,
predict potential faults, and make
informations for automated recovery,
thereby minimizing human intervention
and ensuring network resilience.
The execute phase involves automatically
carrying out corrective actions once an
issue has been detected and analyzed.
This can include tasks
like traffic around fault.
No.
Restarting the failed services,
adjusting configurations, or
scaling resources dynamically.
Education is driven by prefin playbooks.
A power decision engines are
orchestration tools enabling the
network to quickly recover from fault
and maintain continuous reliable
operation without manual intervention.
In healing networks, the decide
phase involves evaluating the analyze
data to determine the most effective
remediation action, the decision making.
Process liberates serial GOs policy
rules and historical incident knowledge
to select the best course of action,
whether to isolate a faulty component,
trigger, create failover, or a play
configuration change, accurate in time,
limitations, or crucial for minimizing
downtime, preventing cascading failures,
and maintaining overall network stability.
These are various different
flows that happen.
AA networks model training in AI is the
process of teaching a machine learning
algorithm to recognize patterns in
data by adjusting its parameters to
improve performance on a specific task.
Parameters serving in EAA is the process
of effectively delivering trained model
parameters to influence systems to
enable fast and scalable predictions.
Data ingestion is the process
of collecting, importing, and
processing raw data from various
sources into your system.
For analysis are a model.
Training inference in AI is the
process where a trained model makes
predictions orions based on new RNC data.
Of course visibility is a very
challenge because to observe the
networks, we need to have visibility.
So that is a still challenge in
some areas, like hardware opacity.
Challenges in AA systems refers to the.
Difficulty of understanding and
optimizing how underlying hardware
like GPU TPU or Specialist Accelerators
affect AI model performance due to
limited visibility in the into hardware
operations and complex interactions
between software and hardware layers.
Hardware is made from made up.
Hardware is made by different vendors.
They follow different
protocols, different procedures.
So it's a common standard to.
Digging into the hardware is a challenge.
Cross-domain correlation in AI system
refers to identifying and analyzing
relationships between data events or
behaviors across different domains or
components, such as combining in insights
from user behavior system logs, network
metrics to improve model accuracy, detect
anomalies, or enhance decision making.
Scale limitations in observability.
Challenges refer to the difficulties in
collecting, processing, and analyzing
massive volumes of telemetry data
generated by large distributed AI systems.
As systems grow our traditional tools
administered with data storage, real-time
processing, and maintaining low latency
insights, making it harder to achieve.
Comprehensive visibility and timely
troubleshooting power coming.
These limitations require scalable
architectures and intelligent data
sampling or aggregation techniques.
How the future of observable networks,
so a powered observability leverages
artificial intelligence and machine
learning to automatically collect.
To analyze and interpret vast amounts of
telemetry data, such as metrics, logs,
and traces to detect anomalies, predict
failures, and provide actionable insights.
This approach enhances traditional
monitoring by enabling faster root
cause analysis, proactive issue
resolution, and smart addition making
in complex AI and distributed systems.
AL level telemetry refer to the
monitoring and collection of detailed
performance and health data directly
from the hardware chip, such as
CPUs, GPUs, or AI accelerators.
This includes metrics like power,
uses, temperature clock speeds.
Cache hits or misses and hardware
interrupts, providing deep visibility
into how the physical hardware
operates and impacts a workloads.
Such fine-grain telemetry is
essential for optimizing performance.
Detecting hardware falls early and
improving overall system reliability.
Excuse me.
Intent based observability in AI focuses
on aligning monitoring and analysis
tools with the desired business or
operational outcomes By interpreting
the system's intent behaviors,
instead of just collecting raw data,
it uses AI to understand whether the
system actions meet pre-define goals,
enabling a prior to detection of
deviations and automated adjustments.
This approach helps ensure
AI systems remain aligned.
With user expectations and business
objectives in dynamic environments.
For example, instead of checking how
the CPU sales is, it's a business based
policy, are we serving the 4K quality
to the important users in Euro region?
So that is the business objective.
Based on that, we can take
corrective actions in the observable.
Digital twin networks are virtual replicas
of physical network infrastructure that
simulate their behavior, performance,
and interactions in real time.
They enable a testing, monitoring,
and optimizing network operations
by mirroring live conditions
without impacting the actual system.
So this technology helps in predictive
maintenance, capacity planning,
and accelerating troubleshooting
in complex networking environments.
So in a closing note, our network
observability has become a, it plays a
key role in planning, maintaining, and
maintaining networks for high
resiliency by processing of throughput.
Ultra latency and so on.
So this network durability is very
important in the coming years of a based
networks, which are very low latency
and high performance computing networks.
Thank you.