Good morning everyone.
I'm PK, and today we'll explore
how an event driven observability
layer can finally light up the blind
spots between ECA and the MA teams.
Think of this session as
journey from today's file.
Drop headaches to your future where
design changes surface in real time.
Before.
They burn either schedule
or budget or both.
Here is map.
We'll begin with collaboration gap.
Why late found issues are still the norm?
Then we'll find defined
that event driven vision.
We'll unpack three core building
blocks named Schema audit.
And library sync and two cross cutting
enablers, taxonomy and resilience.
A quick architecture walkthrough
shows how it all fits.
We look at pilot projects,
technical and business KPIs.
Finally, we'll touch
on monitoring roadmap.
By the end, you will see
exactly where to start.
Your own tool chain.
Let's ground the problem even in 2025.
Most hardware programs pass files
between ECA and MA at a gated milestones.
A study across eight boards
found over 10 snapshots per spin.
Each snapshot a potential rerouting.
Industry data shows that late
reworking inflates cost eight to 10%
and drag schedules four to six weeks.
People end up in detective mode, which
file version, which variant who change
the key part when that fog sets in.
Design energy shifts from.
Innovation to forensic triage.
That's the gap we must close.
Hope you all agree with me.
Here's a story you'll recognize.
Mid program mechanical changes at
chais rib by three millimeters.
Yeah, it's just three millimeters.
Keyboard strengths.
But ECA keeps routing blissfully unaware.
A week later, the ya screams and suddenly
you are starting at a 250 K wrist
pin and a six week slip as a sample.
Numbers root cause isnt bad tools.
It's timing of information, isn't it?
The insight actually
arrived too late to matter.
So why events first, they are push-based.
A tool emits a lightweight message.
The instance something meaningful happens.
Second events or context reach.
Bundle geometry, hashes,
user IDs, variant tax.
Third context leads downstreams check
file automatically, and third even flows
through a broker that is resilient.
If M card is done, ECA can
keep publishing the system.
Replace.
Once MCA is back, the bottom line is.
Decision that used to wait.
This now happens in minutes.
Our first billing block
is a shared schema.
Every ECA change or MCA update
follows the same contract item id,
revision id, geometry, hash user.
Timestamp.
Optional blocks.
Capture CC variance for bomb options.
Tools.
Validate locally mal informed
events, never leave the workstation.
Consistent structure is what lets hundreds
of tools speak one language without.
Back at the code
Second, audit, logging every event
also lands in an immutable store.
We track general workflow,
security, file access logs.
Who changed what and when These logs.
Cut your cost time from hours,
two minutes and satisfy the
traceability mandate in medical
and automation automotive hardware.
They are exportable to CSV
for compliance reviews.
No more screenshot archeology,
and it's library sync.
Third library synchronization.
Using ECA ed Library xml, we run
export library, sync Library, and multi
revision check-ins that keeps symbols
and footprints aligned across tools like
OrCAD, Allegro, and nx, where they live.
The status file success
flag becomes another event.
So analytics can spot its tail footprint
before it sneaks into schematic.
Now we layer two crosscut enablers,
geometry events, board outline,
key ports, mounting holes.
Component events like placement moves,
part swaps analysis, events like DFM or
thermal rule results during the projects.
Lightweight heuristics, nothing exotic,
mostly DUM, and the bonds cut irrelevant.
Charter by 54%.
That means engineers only see
the signal, not the noise.
Of course, events are great
until something starts so we
embed back pressure and replay.
If MCAT goes offline, the broker
queues safely and replace on recovery.
Compensating transactions, rollback
partial rights, A checksum, verifier
blocks, corrupt payloads, and a
circuit breaker isolate flaky.
PLM APIs.
The net result observability
you can actually trust at scale.
Putting it together, ECA and MA, published
into a Kafka broker stream processor,
compare events, geometry, deltas, and
bomb differences kind of violation.
Go to dashboard and chat channels.
The audit store captures
everything for legal traceability.
This isn't a science project.
These components are all off the shelf
here.
How a key out violation plays out.
MA publishes an m, a update, rib added.
Stream processor compares
geometry hash key out strike rule.
Engine flax, out of bound ECA and mca.
Both get a slapping with a 3D overlay
minute er, the change not base.
Yes, that's the magic instant
context rich feedback.
Let's look at the numbers
from pilot board changes.
Revision lead time dropped
from seven days to three days.
Second example, part number approvals
from four down to a day and half, and
board spins fell from three to two.
Those are scheduled wins.
Your CFO can bank
on the business side.
Time to decision, snapshot
count and conflict resolution
all improve by 60 plus percent.
Less churn means fewer
Friday night scrambles.
Lower expense and happier
engineers finally, which were
HR metrics will confirm, right?
Observability can't be blind to itself.
Grafana tracks events,
volume and broker lag.
Active workspace shows 3D Deltas.
Kibana lets you grab every payload
server, monitor config watches for DB
connection losses and deadlocks ping
ops only when threshold or breached.
That's how we keep the pipeline
healthy long after launch day.
Roll out in four phases.
Phase one, capture bomb outline
events, low noise, instant value.
Phase two, add constraints
and variant events.
Phase three, inline
DFM, and thermal checks.
Phase four feed.
Suppliers and manufacturing
within the same streams.
Each phase is incremental.
You harvest our ROI return investment.
Before moving on.
If your scars to save you,
your paying, start small.
Too many events too soon.
Erodes trust.
Govern schema versions.
Yep.
Nothing breaks.
Integration faster than
silent field changes.
Align ECA and MCA naming
conventions on day one.
Invest early in broker observability like
lag metrics or your early warning radar.
Thank you.
That's the journey from blind
Spots to real time clarity.
Thanks for writing up the room with me.
Have a wonderful rest of the day.