Hi everyone.
I'm Anastasia, and today I want to
share my view on how open source can be
not just useful, but also profitable.
And when we hear open source, many people
think it means free, but open source, it's
about being open, not about being free.
And who am I or why?
You can trust me.
I'm co-founder and chief operating
officer at Epic Max, where we
built in support open source and
commercial project with V js.
I started my open source journey
at 17 with Linux community and I
spent more than 10 years in frontend
development and project management.
I also was the chief editor of the
Open Source Magazine user in Linux for
three years, and as you can see, I'm
really not great at choosing usernames.
And what you'll learn today.
First I want to share with you our
story in epic marks how much time and
money we spent on opensource projects.
Then I will show you three key
parts of successful opensource
projects and seven ization models
with real and really cute examples.
I will show you a stage of any open
source project and which model fits
best for each stage, and how to attract
users depending on stage that you allow.
And in the end of my talk of I will
show you our biggest mistake, key
lessons we learn and what we do
now with our open source projects.
And let's try to understand how
must open and source project starts.
Usually start like this.
This tool doesn't work the way I
want, so I want to build my own.
And if your goal is to
make your work easier.
So helpful with the community.
It's a great idea.
Just forgot for forget monetization.
You need to enjoy it.
You can build what you love.
No limit, no pressure.
But if you want to turn your open source
project into a business, you need to
start thinking like a business founder.
And you need to choose
your strategy from day one.
I believe only monetized
project can be successful.
And for building good product, you need
to invest a lot of time energy and money.
And if everything depend only on
you, you will hit a wall one day
and ask yourself honestly, is your
project a hobby or a business?
And for hobby project, it's a great
opportunity to learn new skills,
to connect with the community
and build your portfolio and
maybe find a great job one day.
But if you want to build a business,
it can grow your name bring you a real
income, but you need to have a clear plan.
And let me tell you how it
all started in epic max.
Our company was founded by a
developer who didn't want to
code loan, so he hired others.
Classic story for technical companies.
And we had no portfolio, no
public project because all our
previous work was under NDA.
So we can show it, but we have a lot
of love for VGS and opensource ideas.
So we said, let's build something
opensource, let's show to our potential
clients and ourselves that we can
build something real, something cool.
And this is how Used Economy was born.
It's a set of ready to use dashboard page.
And in just few days it becomes the
first most popular rep on GitHub.
And it help us attract first
commercial clients for our company
and have confidence in ourselves.
And it was great result.
But we maybe we can stop
on this and just continue.
Concentrate on more commercial side of our
company, but we continue in two direction.
We working on client's project using
ZE tool set and sometimes use our
views to guide when we didn't push
it a lot, but sometimes we use it
for our client's project, but more
most of our client use own tool set.
Other.
Admin templates or just some frameworks
and we continue development and
support of our open source product
and invested money and time for it.
And later that year, we publish it a
small open source project at Big Spins.
It's a set of flood and animations
built only with CSS and to be honest,
we did it just because we wanted
to play around with CSS animations.
And then we understood that our
admin panel had a lot of components
and in a couple of year we decided
to move them into separate library.
And that's how VKI was born.
And in October this year, we started free
online meetups for front-end developers,
not only with UJS but yeah, it UJS talks.
And at first we made it because we want
to stay like a team and all our developers
live different countries, but then some
popular speakers start joining us and our
meetups become regular and more public.
And if you want to join us like a speaker
or just a deep, please write me, I'll
send you everything about it and let show
you some numbers that we have for now.
For admin, we have around 2000 forks and
more than 10,000 stars for epic spin.
We have 360 forks and almost 4,000 stars.
For review, QI, we have
354 forks and 3,600 stars.
And for future desktops, we have
around 200 calendar subscribers
and around 40, 50 people live.
And let's do some quick calculation to
understand how much it would cost you.
Take your developers hour rate and
taxes and multiply it by numbers.
We number of hours we spent
on our open source projects.
I use this average
mid-level developer rate.
For Spain in this year, because
I live in Spain, I use it for
calculation to give you a clear
understanding of the potential cost.
It's not same with our spending, but
more or less maybe we can say that
yes, maybe it's something like that.
And we spend more than 4,000
hours for, and it can cost you.
90,000 euro and you can ask me why
it's so much, because it wasn't
just one version of product.
It was was three different version of use.
Two admins.
You need to do some redesign work
because eight years ago we had.
Different design styles and trends.
You need to fix a lot of bugs.
You need to support community do some
discussion and discord work on docs,
and it's a lot of additional work,
not only development of product.
And you'll create not only product,
you'll create a technical depth.
For AP experience, we spend
around 470 hours and it can
cost you around 10,000 euro.
And why did it take so many hours?
Because.
Same, it didn't just finished
with like a pet project because
we need to have some landing page.
We need to pay for design work and
fix some bug and continue supporting.
And for VT QI, we spent
more than 22,000 hours.
And using this average rate,
it can cost you almost half of.
Million Euroes so much.
And for view talks, I
think we spent nothing.
And for now, I think we spent
around four hours per month for
everything to organize online event.
And yes, we had more visibility and
we looked better than other agencies.
But we could have achieved more.
So what went wrong?
Why do some open source project
make money and others don't?
And the answer, simple, successful
project have a strategy.
And without a strategy, I want
to say that I. Any open source
project is just expensive hobby.
And if you want to build open source
seriously, you need to have this skill.
First you need to have brutal
honesty with yourself and, let me
share with you the three kinks.
The must have parts of any
successful open source journey.
The first kink, it's strong idea.
Your product should solve a real problem.
And how can you understand?
Is it enough strong?
You need to talk to people.
Ask as developers for feedback.
You can ask open source, community
people here, super friendly, super open.
You can watch what other people do, what
your competitors doing, and maybe catch
some ideas or understand what they did
wrong and just interpret their mistake.
Second key is active
community and contributors.
You need to engage people
and then you can grow.
And I'm absolutely sure that.
Solid developers move slower and
always stuck in their own mind.
And you can have real feedback only
from community because people use
your quote in wrong, unexpected ways.
And it's great because it's
how you can grow your product.
And I believe that having 50 small
contributors betters and have three
full-time developers that you pay and
the last kink is sustainable monetization
model is your long-term strategy.
And let's try to understand how can
you make money with open source?
You need to choose the right model,
let's say with seven of them.
And to make it simple and
fun, let's imagine you don't
trade code, you make choose.
And first meditation model is open core.
Free shoes.
Premium comfort.
You give people free shoes for
walking around the city, but
if they want better comfort and
stringent material they need to pay.
And real examples in GitLab
Grafana, elastic Short, this model
best for projects that have a
clear line between basic and pro.
And good part of this model, you
can attract many users because
you can show something for free.
They can test it, and you
have flexible monetization.
You control and decide what to sell.
But it's hard to draw the line
between free and paid functions.
And it's really important because
if you close everything, maybe don't
want to you can't find contributors.
If you are open too much, maybe
don't nobody want to pay and you
need to maintain two versions.
It's will create a big technical debt
and you'll can have this problem with
big cloud providers that they can
host your opensource project make
some money and never pay you back.
Maybe you heard about some stories,
we use big cloud providers,
and the next model is SaaS free
shoes, paid cleaning and delivery.
People can take your shoes and clean
them by themself, but if they want
clean ready shoes, deliver every
week, you can offer this service.
Real example in tech.
GitHub Cloud Next Studio, Docker Hub.
This model best for those who
can offer host support and
a good part of this model.
You will have recurring venue.
It's great for business.
You can plan something, maybe
hire a team, and it fully open
source and community friendly.
But it requires a lot of investment for
infrastructure and customer support.
Next model, dual li free
for walks, paid for work.
You can wear the shoes in the park for
free, but if you are waiter walking 12
hours per day, you need a special version.
You need to pay for it.
And real example in tech, my security
edge agreed this model best for tools
used by companies and good parts
and developers use it for free and
they happy and companies should pay.
And you have protection from
big cloud, selling your product
without paying, but you need clear
leads terms and maybe lawyers.
Next model.
Supporting consulting shoes
are free, but help is paid.
You give the shoes for free,
but if someone wants you to
come check the feet change the
install, they pay for your help.
Real examples, in Tech, it's
a redhead ut QI Next cloud.
This model best for teams that
can work directly with client
and good part of this model.
You'll have high value client and
trust and long-term relationships.
But it's not easy to scale
because it depend on people
and on your personal brand.
And you still sell human
hours, not product usage.
It's a big limit and it's hard to scale.
Next, model, plug and send.
Marketplace base shoes are
free decoration or cost money.
You give basic black shocks for free,
but if someone wants to have red
laces, they can buy them separately.
And real example, in WordPress and
Grafana, this model best for project where
you can add some extra and people pay
only for what they need and they happy.
And you can grow into a big
and full ecosystem if you have
a lot of different plugins.
But you need to be community
or it won't work because maybe
your plugin can be a bit cheap.
It hard to control plugin
quality and consistency if you.
Sponsorship.
You make shoes and kind
people support you.
You say, I make some shoes for everyone.
Please support me.
And people donate because
they love what you do.
And real examples and blender.
This model best for project with
strong community and good part of
this model, you kept everything fully
open source and you can build strong
emotional connection with community.
You can maybe build some offline events.
Bad parts.
It's low and stable income and
hard to plan growth or hire team.
Maybe you saw cases where some open source
project got a big sponsor, started hiring
people and invest a lot, and then the
sponsor put out and thing got really sad.
And the last model that we want to
discuss, it's courses and education.
You make sure and teach others.
You keep working on your open
source shoes, but you also teach
other how to make similar ones.
Use online courses, host webinars,
and office certification.
Real example in Tech, Linux
Foundation in View School.
This model best for experts and community
leaders and good parts of this model.
You'll have stable income.
It's great, and you can build a
strong personal and project brands.
And maybe if you decide to build
something else in future, it's
great because you already have
some community and some audience.
But you need to spend time
and money to build content.
And you need to have teaching and
speaking skills, but I believe you can
build it and maybe it can be distraction
from product development, but this
model I think it's easy to delegate it.
You just can find some people
with this experience and they
can create content for you.
So what is the best model?
As saw this, it's no one perfect transfer.
Most successful project used two or
three MO models together, for example.
Next, use SA consulting and support
models, tower use listing and sponsors and
hardware and Grafana use open core plugins
and hoisting and how to choose the model.
I think you need to understand
where you now and let's try to
understand which stage of open source
product and which model fits best.
First stage, early stage you just
started and your goal here at
good users get feedback and build
community around your product.
What matters here?
Yes, it's easy to start, but you
need to build trust and you need
to focus on value, not money yet,
and good models for this stage.
It's sponsorship and maybe you can
use GitHub accelerator program.
I think they still don't have dates
for application for this year.
Maybe.
Next month and if you build
something with AI in title yes,
maybe it's a good suit for you.
You can use educational model,
create some videos, blocks, and give
talks, and you can do consulting.
So where do you find first users?
If you're on early stage,
you need to follow some baby
steps and please don't wait.
For the lunch and something like
1000 stars on GitHub, you need to
start sharing your story early, even
before your publish your project.
Because people love the protest
and people love the stories.
You can start with your idea that
if you, only have idea for now.
You can start create
some content around it.
Show it in some social media in
LinkedIn or Twitter or Instagram,
even if you have some audience.
You can start post on Reddit or
Medium, join some Discord communities
and you can start creating some
audience for your future product.
And it's important to share
your values and goals because
I think we all buy something.
I believe we support only products
that connected with our values.
And if you start sharing it, you can
have some early supporters and then
early clients, you can do consulting.
You need to be visible and helpful and
ask for real feedback, not only for stars.
And real feedback can come
from some consulting work.
You can offer some free help.
But please always set clear boundaries.
For example, if you build something
like Time Check for companies, you
can offer three free consultations.
For example, first consultation for
Setting Everything app second for train.
Employees and the last
one for some QA session.
And if they want you to build some custom
solution or continuous technical support,
then you can offer some paid consultant.
And you can become, maybe
shouldn't become a speaker.
And even small online meetups can give you
some early users and zen future clients.
And even one good offline talk
can give you a lot of users,
contributors, and future clients.
And, you can look in for some small
events in your city, maybe online
events that we have in my company.
I heard a lot of other companies
have something like that.
And next stage maybe is the
most interesting growing stage.
You already have some users and
your goals here start earning
money and scale the project.
What matters here?
You need to show people clearly reason,
a reason to pay, not just please
support me and you need to have.
Simple pricing and you need
to build repeatable income.
Not only one of donation even, it's big.
It's better if you have small,
but a recurring donations.
Good models here.
It's open core SaaS and marketplace,
and you need to split the feature
in two groups, like free for
everyone and premium for teams.
Where do you find paying users?
You need to start with your current users.
Talk to them, ask what they paid for.
Use some onboarding emails, discord
channels, feedback calls, and you need to
turn early adopters into early clients.
And you need to promote your your product
with real results because you already have
some users, some case studies you need
to create content post video, but more
focused on solutions and success stories.
And you can create some
partnership program.
If your product match to bigger
ecosystem, you can collaborate with
others, maybe agencies or product
companies serving the same audience.
For example, I know about
partnership program in for VS.
For next, for example.
You can go for some.
Websites for your ecosystem and try
to build something that you can have
clients and maybe like just users.
But it's a great opportunity
to start open yourself to other
people in your ecosystem and.
Maybe it is the most wanted stage.
It's business stage when
companies use your product.
And Yoko here it's stable
income and enterprise clients.
What important here?
You need to have great li
security and compliance.
You need to create clear
business contract your.
Company should looks like a serious
business that big companies can trust
and you need to offer long-term support.
Good models here is to lead and
support and consulting and open
source open core plus CLA, how to
grow and find users at this stage.
You need to go where your clients are.
For example, some tech conferences
B2B events, and you can partner with
agents that serve your audience.
And you need to show yourself like a
solution, not only product you need
to, explain to business how your
tool can save their money, time,
and reduce risk because it's so
important for enterprise companies.
You need to showcase studies, benchmarks,
create some immigration guides offer
an audit, maybe start offering free
audits and do it like wait and.
You need to start hire right people
with open source experience for sales.
Yes, maybe you already have a big
team of developers QA specialists or
managers, but you need to have right
person for sales, community manager.
Content manager maybe, and
generation specialist said, you
need to start doing some boring
stuff that may be nobody in tech.
Love it.
You need to create.
Call, emails, do some
demos, onboarding calls.
It's more like doing
regular commercial business.
But if you want to grow on this
stage, you need to do that because
you have a lot of competitors,
not only in open source world.
On this stage, you compete with,
commercial project and they have
a lot of benefits for business.
You need to show that you can offer
serious support long-term relationship.
You understand how business works.
You need to have some business
and sales skills for this stage.
And if you did everything and
still want to grow further, you.
Need to find new markets,
maybe new countries.
Maybe it's right moment to hire
business development manager.
And you need to do upselling.
Look into your client's database.
Ensure you need to create
some database in CRM.
You need to, work with it and
try to understand what you can
sell for your current clients.
Maybe you can offer more extra
features, more consulting services,
some custom development, and you can
start looking for big fish in like cloud
providers and create big partnerships.
It's.
Sometime it's so expensive, but
maybe it's right moment to do that.
If you already have some
income and it's more or less
regular, you can try to invest.
But like carefully and then
you will have great results.
And back to our story in Epic max.
Yes.
After eight years in open source,
we still on early stage, and if you
find yourself in the same situation,
please don't be stuck and frustrated.
And yes, for us it could have cost
us much less, but, let's try to
understand where did we go wrong.
We didn't have strategy or clear goals
before investing for each product.
And we have three different
projects and we need to create
a strategy for each product.
It's not just one open source strategy,
and if you have couple of project
you need to separate your strategy.
We expect that our developers can
choose tasks based on business
impact, not on the interest, but
honestly, if we didn't understand our
goals, how could they understand it?
And we had lack of real
experience using our product.
In commercial project, yes, we had
some clients with our products,
but it's not enough for having.
Good feedback and for improving our
product, for staying competitive
with others because yes, still for
us, we have some big competitors
and we didn't use it enough.
We believed if we build
something, user will come.
And yes, we had some user and you saw it.
It's really not bad results.
But in mining, it's still zero.
We was focused only on quote, on no
on business strategy or marketing.
And if we can merge everything that
I said before in one sentence, we
treated the project like a hobby.
No financial planning, no donation set up.
Still, we don't have it.
No budgeting, no strategy sessions
because it's something about like
business, not about open source, but
we invested in all of our project,
like commercial projects, but.
To be honest, we made a lot of mistakes,
but we also did a few think really right.
We built a strong team.
We used our open source project like
sandbox for all our new developers
to test and are onboard them.
And I think it's great results for us.
I think all our developers are super
cool, super technically skilled.
Because I think it's not enough
to have two, maybe three steps of
technical interview for understand
is it great match to your company?
'cause it's not only about technical
side of person, it's a lot of soft skill.
And maybe same vibe with us.
And for us it was really important to
find people with open source experience.
And we have great team for now.
I think we was focused, we
choose one small technology
and never looked, to others.
We use only view JS for development
and it gave us a clear niche
and help it to sell for now.
And we built trust in partnership
in the view ecosystem.
We start doing some partnership with
Beautify and Prime View that maybe,
yeah, we can say they our competitors,
but I believe in open source world.
We don't have competitors.
We all partners and we finally
recognized our mistake and
started doing something in.
Strategy for now, we almost
stop on non-strategic investment
in open source project.
We focused more on view integrations,
not only on creating some new
components or fixing bug, and
we stopped to be in silence.
We started writing some
articles, posting speaking on
conferences and hosting on events.
And what's next is this shift might
finally move us to growing stage
where we can have some stable income.
And in this moment, smart investment
truly makes sense and maybe we can create
some paid product like ready to use
package based on use stick admin maybe
for FinTech for example, or legal tech.
And maybe we can create some
examples and plugins for
Marketplace and sell them based on.
But this time we absolutely want to start
with strategic planning, clear financial
model and real contributor involvement.
It's that idea to do everything internal
and let me share with you some key
takeaways I want to leave to you.
Open source needs more than just code.
It needs strategy and clear goals.
You need to choose human monetization
model early based on your stage, and
you need to focus on community first.
But never forget the business
side and like marketing side.
You need to hire right people in
the right moment and do sales like
abroad if you want to have money.
Mistakes are part of
every open source journey.
Just don't stay stuck and it's never
too late toing, rebuild and grow your
product and I believe you can do it.
And thank you so much for your attention.
If you like the talk, you
can connect me on LinkedIn.
If you didn't, please connect
me anyway and tell me why.
And if you have any question
or ideas, I'd love to chat.
And thank you for being here.
Thank you for your attention to
opensource community and goodbye.