Welcome everyone to our discussion.
This is Ra Pala.
Today we'll be discussing the
topic, mastering observability
and distributed Systems.
This is an important topic for analytics
leaders navigating complex environments.
Today we will explore the strategic
approach to achieving true visibility,
generating meaningful insights,
and driving impactful action
across your distributor systems.
The key is developing a comprehensive
observability strategy that goes beyond
just monitoring, it's about unlocking
the full potential of your idea.
To drive business outcomes, we will dive
into the critical capabilities required
and share our real world examples of
how leading organizations are putting
observability into practice, right?
By the end I'm sure you'll have
a clear roadmap for elevating
observability as a strategic imperative
within your own organization.
So let's get started.
Let me dive into slide number two here.
So the business case for
observability is clear.
It delivers faster incident resolution.
Cost savings and improved
customer satisfaction.
Observability helps reduce meantime
to resolution by 73%, allowing us to
identify and fix issues more quickly.
It also leads to 42% cost savings
by optimizing our infrastructure
spend and reducing waste.
Most importantly, observability
drives a 91% increase.
And customer satisfaction through
better user examples or experiences.
A 99.99% availability targets
translates to 22 minutes of
allowable downtime per month.
As you see in the picture right
here, these metrics demonstrate the
tangible benefits of investing in
observability for our organization.
With observability, we can proactively
monitor our systems, rapidly, troubleshoot
our problems, and continuously
improve the services we deliver to our
customers and clients across the world.
As you look at this slide,
traditional monitoring focuses
on known issues with predefined
metrics and threshold based alerts.
This is reactive approach.
In contrast, modern observability
aims to uncover unknown unknowns
and through high cardinality
telemetry and context rich insights.
This allows for more
proactive troubleshooting.
The key differences are that
observability deals with the unknown,
uses more comprehensive data, and
provides deeper context to drive
faster problem solving, right?
Observability gives you a more complex.
Complete picture of your systems,
allowing you to be proactive rather
than just reacting to the issues.
With observability, you gain a more,
complete picture of your systems, allowing
you to be proactive, like I mentioned,
rather than just reacting to the issues.
And also with observability, you can
gain visibility into the unknown and
unknowns that traditional monitoring
may miss leading to a better overall
system health and performance output.
This slide.
As you can see, observability is
a key capability that allows us to
understand the health and performance
of our systems and applications.
Again, it provides three main benefits.
Basically business insights giving us
visibility into the user journeys and
behaviors to inform product decisions.
Operational intelligence, helping
us detect patterns and anomalies
in systems behavior to quickly
identify and resolve issues.
Telemetry, foundation, essentially
providing the underlying data,
sources of traces, logs, and metrics
that power the other two areas.
Observability is not just a technical
capability, but also a strategic
data product that can deliver
value across the organization.
All right.
As you can see, we have there are
four pillars of observability.
They are the key data sources that
provide visibility to the health
and performance of a system.
Metrics gives us the quantitative
measurements over time, like CPU, memory,
latency and throughput as you can see
logs provide detailed event records with
timestamp and structured data process.
Show the request flows across
the services, helping us
improve performance bot.
Whereas events capture the state changes
and transitions like deployments and
configuration changes together, these four
pillars gives us a comprehensive view into
the behavior and operating of our systems.
Now observability is critical
for understanding complex
systems and identifying issues
before they impact the business.
Analytics capabilities, like interactive
data exploration, machine learning driven
anomaly detection, and predictive insights
can significantly enhance observability.
Data exploration allows you to query
across all your telemetry data to
uncover hidden patterns and trends.
Pattern recognition uses machine learning
can automatically detect anomalies
that may indicate emerging problems.
Correlating business and technical
data provides important context to
understand the impact of issues.
Predictive analytics can forecast
potential issues before they
actually occur, allowing you
to get ahead of the problems.
These analytics capabilities gives us
a deeper, more proactive observability
into your own systems and processes.
Alright, now this slide outlines the key
components of a scalable observability
architecture and also the infrastructure.
The instrumentation layer includes
tools like Open Telemetry agents and
SDKs to capture observability data
from applications and infrastructure.
The collection and transport layer,
ingest the data using technologies like,
excuse me, Kafka, Panis, and Flint.
The storage and processing layer stores
the data in time series databases
and distributed tracing systems.
Finally, the analysis and visualization
layer, as you can see, provides
dashboards, notebooks, and alerting
to make sense of observability data.
Each of these layers plays a critical
role in building an end-to-end
observability pipeline that can scale
to handle growing volumes of data.
In your systems.
As you can see, the tooling landscape
for observability and monitoring
is broad with many different
tools and technologies available.
This slide provides a gallery of some of
the major players in the space, including.
PROEs Grafana Elastic Search
Open Telemetry, Jagger, Datadog,
new Relic, and Dynatrace.
These tools cover a range of
capabilities from metrics collection and
visualization to distributing, tracing
to full stack observability platforms.
When choosing tools for your observability
stack, it's important to evaluate the
specific needs of your organization
and architecture and how well each
tool fits those requirements, right?
Some key factors to consider are ease
of use, scalability, integrations,
and oral cost and complexity.
The right combination of tools can
provide deep visibility into the
health and performance of your systems,
enabling faster, troubleshooting,
and better patient making right now.
Rolling onto the next slide.
This slide outlines for common
pitfalls that organizations offer
encounter when managing their IT
operations and monitoring systems.
The first pitfall is data deluge
collecting vast amounts of
data without a clear purpose.
Leading to an overall overwhelming
signal to noise ratio that makes it
difficult to extract meaningful insights.
The second pitfall is Tools Pro, having
a fragmented visibility across multiple
platforms, making it challenging
to correlate and connect the data.
The third pitfall is SLO ownership.
Where the platform teams work in
isolation, limiting the cross-functional
insights and collaboration needed
to effectively address issues.
The fourth pitfall is alert fatigue
where teams are bombarded with too
many notifications, many of which are
low value and disruptive, leading to a
lack of focus on the critical issues.
These are the common challenges that
organizations need to be aware of and
proactively address to improve their IT
operations and monitoring capabilities.
Moving on to the slide number 10 here.
Observability is a key capability that
organizations need to measure over time.
This slide outlines a four stage
maturity roadmap for observability.
At the reactive stage, we are simply
responding to S after they have
already, being impacted by the business.
The proactive stage is about
identifying issues as they emerge
before they cause major disruptions.
In the analytical stage, we gain
a deeper understanding of patterns
and dependencies in our systems.
The ultimate goal is to reach the
predictive stage where we can forecast
issues before they even occur.
Going to the next slide.
As you see most of the analytics leaders,
our role is to bridge the gap between the
technical and business domains, right?
Translating the telemetry and
insights as we gather into
the tangible business impact.
And we need to architect the data
driven feedback loops that correct the
insights we uncover to meaningful action
and change within the organization.
As championing cross-functional
collaboration is a key here.
Breaking down silos between the
teams and getting everyone aligned
around a shared understanding of
the data is a very key point here.
Ultimately, our goal is to drive a
data literacy and culture empowering
everyone in the organization to
leverage insights as we surface to make
better and more informed decisions.
The sliding material here is
basically about the key takeaways
from our discussion today for
driving value from observability.
First, we need to clearly define
the business outcomes we want to
achieve and link our observability
efforts to those metrics.
Second.
We should start small by prior
prioritizing high impact services,
then scale our observability
capabilities incrementally over time.
Building cross-functional teams that blend
analytics and operations expertise will
be crucial for driving maximum value.
And the finally, the last STA is we
need to evolve our observability.
Maturity, step by step following the clear
roadmap to reach our desired future state.
So these steps will help ensure
our observability investments
deliver meaningful business
impact across the platforms.
And this last slide for today
as part of the session, thank
you for all joining us today.
Exploring how analytics
drives observability maturity.
We appreciate your time engagement
throughout this presentation as you
continue on your observability journey.
Please don't hesitate to reach
out if you have any questions.
We are always here to support you.
Let me know if there's
anything else I can do to help.
As you work to advance your
observability capabilities.
Thank you all and thank you Keff 42
for giving me this opportunity to
walk through the observability topic.
Thank you.
I.