Hello everyone.
This is working as c network
security engineer at SoFi.
Today I'll be talking about a
critical but of an overlooked
security challenge that is threat
modeling for observability systems.
While we have become experts at securing
our applications and infrastructure.
Monitoring and observability tools
often operate in a security blind spot.
This presentation will show you
how to identify, prioritize, and
mitigate security risks that could
turn your observability systems from
security assets into attack vectors.
So understanding the observability
blind side, let's start with
the uncomfortable truth.
Adversaries are strategically targeting
the gaps in our observability coverage.
So think about it from
an attacker perspective.
If you can't see it, you can't defend it.
The first major issue is that threat
actors methodologically exploit
areas where observability coverage
is insufficient or non-existent.
They're not randomly probing.
They're specifically looking for the dark
corners of your infrastructure where their
activities won't be logged or monitored.
The second thing, your observability
data itself becomes intelligence for
attackers, those publicly accessible
metric logs and prices that help you
troubleshoot, they inadvertently reveal
your system architecture, service
dependencies, and potential entry points.
It's like leaving a blueprint of
your house on the front porch.
Finally.
Requires continuous reassessment.
Even if you have robust observability
today, hidden vulnerabilities
evolve with your system.
That dashboard you deployed six months
ago might now be exploring sensitive data.
You didn't anticipate the
traditional observability triad.
So before we dive into the security
threats, let's establish our foundation.
The traditional observability
thread consists of three pillars.
Metrics provide numerical representations
of the system behavior over the time.
These include performance indicators,
resource utilization, and error rates.
They're great for understanding
trends and setting All alerts.
Logs are timestamped records of
discrete events within your system
so they can capture error messages,
access attempt, and state changes.
Logs are your detailed forensic trial.
So the traces show to end-to-end request
flows across the distributed systems.
The real service dependencies,
latency, bottlenecks, and errors
propagate through your architecture.
Here's the security challenge.
Each of these pillars can become an
attack vector, if not properly secure.
Your metrics can leak
architectural information.
Your logs might contain install
data, and your traces can reveal
business logic and the data flows.
So coming to the security risks
in observability pipelines,
now let's examine where the
vulnerabilities typically emerge.
In observability pipelines, I want
you to think of your observability
infrastructure as a three layer cake.
Each layer represents un security
challenge at the collection points.
Unsecured agents and collectors expose
entry points into your infrastructure.
We see outdated agent software
running with excessive privileges.
And transmitting data over
unencrypted challenge channels.
So these agents often have deep access
to your systems to collect telemetry,
making them attractive targets.
The transport layer is where the data
is in transit, becomes vulnerable to
interception, missing TLS encryption,
poor certificate management, and weak
cipher suits create opportunities
for man in the middle attacks.
Remember, this data is flowing
continuously across your network.
Finally, storage systems create
centralized high value targets.
Insufficient access controls means
that compromising that your monitoring
system could expose your data from
across your enter infrastructure and
patch vulnerabilities in time series
databases and improper data contingent
policies compound these risks.
Now moving to the threat actor
motivations, understand why attackers
target observability systems
help us defend more effectively.
Let me walk you through four
primary motivations, recognizance.
Is often your first goal.
Attackers leverage exposed metrics
to map your infrastructure.
They can identify several locations,
software versions, and potential entry
points through misconfigured dashboards.
Your Grafana dashboard might betly
showing them exactly what they
need to plan their attack in.
The data.
Exfiltration becomes possible
when sensitive information
gets embedded in logs.
PII secrets the access to
against accidentally logged
to create both compliance
violations and security breaches.
I've seen API keys database credentials,
and potential data flowing through
log strings in plain text alert
actic in a particular indic tactic.
Three T deliberately trigger the false
positives to overwhelm your alert systems.
When your team is dealing with
hundreds of false arounds,
they'll miss the one real security
incident happening simultaneously.
Finally, leaving off the land attacks.
Use your legitimate observability
tools as attack infrastructure.
Monitoring systems with elevated
privileges becomes perfect
vehicles for lateral moment.
The attacker doesn't need
to bring their own tools.
They use yours.
So mapping the attack surfaces,
coming to the effective threat
modeling requires systemic,
systematic attack surface mapping.
This isn't a one time exercise.
It's an ongoing process that
evolves with your infrastructure.
Start by identifying assets.
Document all observability
components in your architecture.
Map the data flow between the collectors,
processors, and the visualization tools.
Include a third party services cloud
monitoring tools and custom dashboards.
Next, define the trust boundaries.
Establish a very aware the data
crosses security domains, and
determine which components have
privileged access to sensitive systems.
Your Prometheus server might need
access to multiple environments.
That's a trust boundary,
which worth scrutinizing.
Enate entry points catalog
all the interfaces exposed
to buy your monitoring tools.
Consider the API endpoints
dashboards, agent communication
channels, and web hook receivers.
Each one is potential attack vector.
Finally, prioritize the threats based
on the potential impact and likelihood
focus your remediation efforts on
critical observability components.
First, a compromised central
logging system has different
implications than a compromised edge.
Monitoring agent monitor.
Now let's dive into this stride
for observability systems.
Let's apply the Stride Threat
modeling framework specifically
for observability systems.
This table shows how each stride category
manifests in monitoring infrastructure and
provide targeted mitigation strategies.
Poofing in observability
means false metric injection.
Attackers could send fabricated
metrics to SCU via monitoring
data or hide their activities.
Strong authentication for all agents
prevents unauthorized data submission.
Tampering involves modify telemetry data
in transit or addressed cryptographic
integrity checks, ensures data hasn't
been altered between collection and
storage repudiation covers, or when.
Audit logs are deleted or modified, so
the immutable logging pipelines prevent
attackers from covering their attacks.
Information disclosure happens
when sensitive metrics are
exposed to the unauthorized users.
Strict access controls on dashboards
and APIs prevent the data leakage.
Denial of service.
Targets your observability
infrastructure itself overloaded.
Collectors can blind
you to actual attacks.
Rate limiting and redundancy.
Maintain monitoring availability.
Elevation of privilege often involves
compromised monitoring agents
that have excessive permissions.
The least privileged principle
limits the damage from the agent.
Compromise.
Now, let's.
Dive into real world attack scenarios.
Let me walk you through a real
world attack scenario that
demonstrates how observability
system can become the attack vector.
And then rather than the defense
mechanism, the attack begins
in initial access through an
outdated Grafana instance.
The attacker exploits unknown
vulnerability and gains access
to public dashboards that expose
internal infrastructure details.
From those dashboards, they can
learn about your network topology
and service dependencies, and
also the tech technology stack.
Next comes the credential theft.
The attacker discovers that API
keys are being logged in the plain
text in your application logs.
Because your monitoring service
accounts have excessive permissions,
perhaps they were granted broad
access for easier configuration.
These credentials provide
significant access.
Prometheus server then becomes the.
Private point for lateral moment
because it needs to scrape metrics from
your, from across your infrastructure.
It has network access to
multiple environments.
This attackers uses the legitimate
access to move from your monitoring
network into production systems.
Finally, the data exfiltration
occurs through custom metric
queries that extract sensitive data.
The beauty of this.
Attack from adversary perspective
is that the ex exfiltration blends
perfectly with normal monitoring traffic.
Your network monitoring tools
see legitimate Prometheus
queries, not the data theft.
Now the coming to the securing
observability pipelines.
Now let's establish security
baselines for observability pipelines.
These are in the suggestions.
They're the requirements
for secure monitoring.
100% encrypted telemetry.
All the monitoring data must be used.
Must use the TLS in
transit, no exceptions.
I've seen too many environments where
metrics flow unencrypted because
it's just internal monitoring data.
Two-factor authentication
for dashboards access.
Requires multi-factor authentication
for all the monitoring in interfaces.
Your observability dashboard contains
as much as sensitive information
as your production systems.
So 30 day maximum rotation schedule
for monitoring credentials, service
accounts, and the API case should
rotate regularly long-lived Credentials
in monitoring systems are security
risks, zero secrets and logs.
The tolerable number of credentials
in telemetry data is zero.
Implement log scrubbing and the
secret detection to prevent the
accidental credential exposure.
Now let's dive into building
the alert resilience.
Alert resilience is crucial because
attackers often target your notification
system to hide their activities.
Here's how to build robust alerting,
implement signal to noise filtering
by developing correlation rules
that reduces false positives.
Group related alerts to prevent the alert.
And when your team stops trusting
alerts, attacker swings, establish
alert tires with severity based
routing For notifications, critical
security alerts mean bypassing
normal throttling mechanisms.
Your security instance shouldn't get
lost in the queue of performing alerts,
performance alerts, employ anomaly
detection in machine learning based.
Detection in unusual patterns.
Baseline normal behaviors
before deploying and alerting.
The attackers often operate within
normal parameters to avoid detection.
Most importantly, protect your
alert mechanism themselves.
Treat notification system
as critical infrastructure.
Secure your slack web books, email
servers, and paging systems with the
same rigor as your public applications.
Now let's dive into the action
plan from Blind Sports to insight.
Let me leave you with a concrete
action plan to transform your
observability from a potential
liability into a security asset.
First, conduct an observability
threat assessment.
Map your current monitoring architecture
using the frameworks we discussed today.
Identify all the components, data
flows, and the trust boundaries.
Secondly, the.
To implement the security control
systematically secure the data at
collection, transport, and storage phases.
Don't try to do everything at once.
Prioritize based on risk.
Third, integrate with security operations.
Align your monitoring and security teams.
Your observability data should feed
your security operation center, and
your security team should help secure
your monitoring infrastructure.
Finally measure your
security effectiveness.
Track security metrics for continuous
improvement, monitor failed
authentication, attempts on dashboards,
credential rotation for compliance, and
the time to detect your security events.
The goal is transformation.
Turn your observability
infrastructure from a blind spot
into a security force multiplier.
So thank you for your attention.
Remember, secure Observability isn't
just of protecting your monitoring tools.
It's about ensuring that your ability
to detect and respond to threat remains
intact when you are needed it the most.
Thank you all for paying
attention to this.