Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Observability 2025.
I am Vanga PR Kambala, a senior
DevOps engineer with 15 plus
years of experience in it.
I started working as a network engineer
in both enterprise and data center
domains, and then moved to cloud as
a DevOps engineer and now working as
a senior DevOps engineer implementing
DevOps and DevSecOps methodologies.
For deploying infrastructure into
AWS using services like compute,
storage databases, serverless
infrastructure, and as well as contain
based application infrastructure.
And I also have experience across
domains like multiage finance,
healthcare insurance, and e-commerce.
The topic I chose today is logging
in the age of cost, cutting
smart strategies to reduce bills.
Over the last decade, companies migrated
a lot of their workloads to cloud because
of ease of use, high availability,
fault tolerance, and scalability.
And also cloud provided mean
exponentially fast path for moving
from ideation to like implementation
compared to traditional data centers.
All this moving to cloud, like
there is a lot of cost incurred.
So the latest buzzword is
finops, where cost optimization
is like a top most strategy.
And logging is one such a aspects
where cost optimization is looked at.
So today we will dive into how
like industry leaders like Uber
Airbnb and Slack implemented,
like their cost implementation,
cost optimization strategies.
Reducing 70% of their bills
while retaining the same level of
debugging capabilities and as well
as like monitoring capabilities.
So let's dive into that.
Let's see.
Like I'm in what like causes all
this cost crisis for logging.
As per the research like available openly
Airbnb, like spent like 1.2 millions
a year for stale, unused debug data.
So there is a research that state
states that, like for all the logging
that is generated, only 30% is used for
all the queries and like monitoring.
Any meaningful operations like
an enterprise can do, and rest
of the 70% is sitting there in
the storage costing enterprises
like a premium without any use.
So this problem even compounds with
microservice architecture because each
microservice generates its own logs.
Yeah, we will look into how Airbnb
mitigated and how like we'll
also look into other companies
on different strategies of
cost optimization for logging.
But yeah, this is what causes
like a costing for logging a lot.
So that's going to the next slide.
So here we will look at why why the costs
are spiraling out of control for logging.
So mainly the first one would
be microservice explosion.
So we moved from monolith architecture
to microservices architecture which
created like, a lot of services and
those services, like independent
leads generate lot of log streams.
So creating the, all those log streams
and like I'm maintaining them paid
for exponential log generation,
log creation and log storage.
Which added to our exponential costs.
And then cloud vendors like
have a the pricing at both
ingestion and storage level.
So you're getting double charge
so you'll be charged for per GB
while you're ingesting the data.
And as well as while you're storing
that data for later retrieval purpose.
And then there are some development
practices where some applications
or some enterprises like users or
developers still have debug level kind
logs enabled in production, which is
not recommended because debug generates
a lot of log data, which is not used
most of the times unless there is.
An alert or there is something that
needs to be troubleshoot, enabling
debug log level is not advised because
that increases the sheer volume of like
logs, it generates and 90% of the time
or 99% of the time, it is not needed.
And then there is lack
of governance, right?
Like where there are no clear
policies on how log collection should
work, and what are the optimization
strategies and inconsistencies caused
to excessive logging and excessive
logging caused to an excessive storage.
So it concurs again, cost at both
levels, like for ingestion and storage.
So we'll look into the first strategy,
which is implementation sampling.
So Uber had a big breakthrough, like Uber
we mentioned 70% of the logs generated
are unused with respect to debug.
On it's almost like 95% that is unused.
So what Uber did was like, it
implemented a sampling mechanism and
using that sampling mechanism, it was
only retaining 5% of the debug logs
that is generated discarding 95% of
like 95% of them, which helped them
like, save around $8 million annually.
This was published in s Econ 2022.
So yeah, while they were doing that,
they still retained their logs, like they
were only sampling like M and DBA blogs.
So they were reducing the noise while
keeping the effective logs that are needed
for maintenance of the infrastructure.
So there are three different kinds of
implementer implementation approaches
for this head-based sampling.
So where the decision is
made at the log generation as
itself, so like source, right?
Like wherever, like the microservices,
our infrastructure components
are used at that place itself.
There is a sampling mechanism used where
it drops 95% of like other debug data.
Whereas there is another approach to
it, like tail based sampling mechanism
where the decision is made after
the trace is completed and ingested
in like at the ingestion process.
So Uber implemented this and saved like
all saved 8 million in cost for lobbying.
Then there is level based sampling
mechanism where like it can use like
at different rates at different log
levels, which is also one of the widely
used approaches for best practices.
Like we should always preserve
error and like fatal log levels.
That is what helps us for effective
troubleshooting and creeping track
of what services went down and
alerting and other stuff and all.
So we should never be
sampling error and fatal logs.
You can start, like sampling can
be done from one to 10% for debugs.
And info levels info level of logs.
But like you can always start at 10%
and then build your way up to 1%.
And also we have to use like I
inconsistent sampling consistent
sampling methodologies and also service
boundaries for effective sampling.
Here we look into a second strategy,
which is called noise filtering.
Like we said 70, like out of
like a hundred percent of the
logs, 70% is just noise that is
generated that is never used.
So slack and counted similar kind of
situation where there were like health
check logs that were not meaningful
to them, but they're still kept on,
accumulated by the logging like in methods
they had, which incurred both ingestion
cost and as well as storage cost.
So Slack implemented the fluid fluent
bit filtering mechanism where like they
dropped all the health check data that
was not necessary, which dramatically
reduced their cost by 15% with zero
impact in their day-to-day operations.
So generally the common nice sources
would be health check endpoints,
ping health or status like endpoints.
And then there are repeated connection
timeouts that are not critical.
And also we don't need to maintain all
the successful authentication logs.
And there are some service to service
communications between the services
that you can drop and not retain.
So filtering is one of the most
effective mechanisms because you can
just drop the logs that you don't need
effectively helping in cost optimization.
And also it's effective when you're able
to identify systematic noise sources
that you can filter out at ingestion
layer itself, so you're not ingesting
them as well as like I'm installing
them, saving a lot of the cost there.
There is another strategy like that we
can use, like this is the earlier too we
were looking at like generation like log
generation level and ingestion level.
This comes at storage level.
So there are there is a storage
strategy the three tier storage
strategy that you can implement.
So it can be classified into hot
storage, warm storage, and closed cloud.
Sorry, cold storage.
So hot storage is something
like for a week of logs, right?
So anything from today to last seven
days can be a hot storage, like
stored in elastic search which helps.
To query, which helps for a better
query rates and retrieval rates.
And for anything between seven to 30
days is less queried compared to the
ones that are queried in hot storage.
So we store them under a warm storage
using standard S3 buckets, which has
balanced cost and performance ratio.
After 30 days most of the applications
are like an enterprises won't need to
like, have logging data that is like
readily variable every for day-to-day use.
So we can move that to glacier
storage where the cost would
be very less for retaining.
But you should be careful
while doing that because.
Grier data is really tough because of
like less retrieval speeds for data.
But Shopify implemented one of
these this approach, and they
were able to save 60% in their
retention costs and, they were yeah.
Like generally, like they needed
like the com anything logs for
like beyond 30 days for compliance.
So that is the reason
they're retaining it.
But yeah, this reduced around dramatically
their retention cost, like for logging,
and there is the fourth strategy, which
shifts your logging cost to personal cost.
So in a way razor pay, one of India's
major payment gateway was able to like,
opt for an open source solution like.
Grafana Loki instead of Splunk, and
thereby they saved around 200 K dollars.
So like Splunk was costing
them like, $250,000.
Whereas graph Grafana and Loki
implementation just costed them $50,000
because of how like Loki's architecture is
cost effective while using S3 for storage.
But this comes at a cost like from from
a operations perspective where you will
have to have a subject matter experts
implementing the solutions to maintain
the infrastructure for open source
where you'll not have enter application
support or like I vendor support.
So that is the cost that you'll
be incurring, but definitely
reducing your logging costs.
So we will look at like a real world
case study that Uber implemented.
So Uber had a challenge where there
are like 250,000 spot jobs that run
daily generated around 200 TB data.
So that.
Storing that data is very costly.
So they came up with the compressor,
CLP, which is called compressor log com,
compressor Log Pro, like process where
they achieved a compression of 1 69 ish
to one ratio, thereby reducing their
costs from 1.8 million to 10 k. Annually,
so that is 99% production in cost.
So they implemented like an compression
mechanism of compression logs and
were able to like and achieve this
remarkable feat of reducing their cost.
And while like this also helped so
this compression compress log processor
solution also helped them query the
logs without decompressing them.
So there was no, there was no
deterioration in their querying
and like monitoring needs.
So another best practices like for
logging is like I'm in structured logging.
So if you see the example here on the
left side like it is an unstructured
logging where an user is trying to create
or sign up for a new account, but using
like an email address that is already
signed up for that particular service.
On the right side, like the same
thing for a structured log using
A-J-S-O-N, which contains all the
metadata and timing information.
So the right side structured data
helps us like come into query better.
And so like the more we have like I
structured logs like the better for
us I mean from operations perspective
and as well as storage perspective.
Because it helps in compression.
So we can look at at the bottom
we see all the things that
structured logging data can provide.
So it enables precise filtering
because you can target, based on the
metadata, you can select a few fields
and target filtering based on that.
Also it improves better compression
mechanism of just how structurally
it organized and then it enhances
your query performance as well.
Like apart from like your regular queries,
you can use JQ and other queries as well.
And there is more metadata and more
fields that you can query on and
retrieve the data in efficient way.
And also, which also paves
ways for better automation.
So for optimization success you'll
have to have financial metrics,
operational metrics and volume
metrics optimized properly.
Whereas financial metrics will
have your monthly ingestion costs,
storage, like cost per tier.
Also total GB ingested because as
like we discussed earlier, clouds
charge at GB ingestion level as well.
And like also I mean at the storage level
coming to operations you have to see
like how fast so when we are implementing
all these strategies, you'll have to
always make sure how fast like your.
Query responses because that
is what matters at the time of
troubleshooting or I'm looking into
services on what is happening there.
If you if something went wrong there,
and then and you'll have to also make
sure that log is available and with all
the sampling mechanism you're doing, how
effectively you're able to detect that
or, and then the volume metrics like.
You have to look at like daily volume
trends and as well as like how much
is filtered versus retained, and
from all this, like how much like
storage costs like you're incurring.
So the key is actually establishing
baselines before implementing
these changes and then tracking
improvements over the time.
So with all this strategies
like noise I mean filtering
and sampling and everything.
There are com some common pitfalls
and we have to be like, let's
look at how we can avoid them.
So anything like, that is aggressive or
like I'm an overdoing will cause an issue.
So over an aggressive filtering
will always have some repercussions,
so you might be losing some
critical debug information.
Also, always while doing sampling and
filtering always start conservatively,
then increase gradually based
on and what you're seeing and
always and make sure that you.
Preserve error and like fatal level
logs, you are not filtering them
out or you're not sampling them.
Make sure you retain them completely.
And then while sampling, you'll have
sampling bias because just because of how
we are sampling mechanism is implemented.
Like you might miss some of the
infrequent like events that come up.
In your logs?
The solution would be like, using some
trace aware sampling mechanisms, and also
you can implement a safeguard like by
triggering like I'm in full tri triggering
stopping of sampling by using an alert.
So if you see a alert,
like then stop sampling.
Like you can implement
certain triggers and do that.
And then like I'm in a cold storage
query performance retrieving data from
cold storage is really painful, so you
can't write a query it's not easy to
write querying mechanism to pull data
or retrieve data from cold storage.
So design your queries in such
a way that you are not accessing
cold storage for your queries.
Mostly you're using hot and
like your warm storages.
Also you can implement some of
the rehydration workflows of
moving the cold storage data
into one or standby for better.
Like I'm querying like, speeds.
So now we will look at a
cost optimization roadmap.
From looking at all these strategies
what can be done for this to be
implemented in your organization?
So first you'll have
to assess and analyze.
So you'll have to look at immediately you
can look at your log volume and audit,
like how much volume you're seeing.
And then isolate five to 10 log
streams that are like our log sources
that are causing like really high
volume of logs and then calculate how
much you're spending on those logs.
And set up like, dashboards
see what are your quick wins?
And implement some kind of like
the strategies like we discussed
earlier, either filtering or
like an sampling, et cetera.
And like after while you monitor that,
like I'm gonna get to a conclusion
after 30 days, you can start
implementing like we discussed, right?
Like you can start implementing
health check filtering, log sampling,
and then for storage needs, you can
do three tier, three tier storage.
And also we looked at I'm
insert an open source logs.
And in long run and you can always have
some strategic strategic initiatives like
we discussed open source alternatives
and advanced compression techniques
like UBA did with CLP and, or you can
always have like a log-based metric
alerting and you can bring most
training for cost optimization and
culture around that in your enterprise.
So that concludes how
we can save in logging.
So there are other essential
tools you can look at.
For example, data Datadog management
cost management site, and as well
as all the open source applications
like Grafana, ELK, et cetera.
And there is CLP Open Source if
you want to implement it at the
same time, like on vendor specific
stuff you can see in Datadog.
And Uber also maintains a good
treasure of a CLP technical papers.
Which is a blog and that has
all the technical papers where
you can read through on how they
implemented that successfully.
And the same way cloud service
providers also have best practices
of white papers, like AWS and GCP.
And then there are always conferences
like SR Econ and Lisa conferences and
even our con 42 like we are doing as
of today, where they talk about these
situations and have make us aware.
Then there are like, cloud native
foundations communities or your
internal communities that you can
discuss and get like better approaches.
That's it for today, and thank you.