Hello everyone.
Topic of this session is turning
synthetic traces into gold by scaling
monitoring for critical user journeys.
I am EP Kumar.
I'm a principal engineer in
Salesforce, and I belong to the
Monitoring Cloud organization.
Our organization provides a
single stop solution catering to
all the observability needs of
different Salesforce applications.
So we have many stacks for
metrics, events, locks, and traces.
To give a little bit context about
the scale at which we operate we are
responsible for providing observability
for over a million hosting containers.
More than 2000 teams and 13,000 developers
are actively engaged on our platform.
To give a little bit idea about the.
Telemetry volume that we handle
around one 40 billion times series.
Every hour, more than 300 billion
spans a day and more than one
petabytes of log volume every day
critical user journeys.
Now what are what are there really, right?
I like to define them as
hunting down hero flows.
Basically they are a way to be able to.
Identify end user's journey, emulate it.
And often these end user journeys
are high value request flows.
They are customer facing and
business critical experiences, so
potentially revenue impacting as well.
Now, typically such
external user action flows.
Often traverses through multiple
service in your infrastructure.
And this is especially true in today's
world of microservices, where you have
a plethora of microservices and each
microservice enables a specific function
or a feature, and therefore it becomes
so much harder to actually pinpoint where
an issue lies when an incident occurs.
It also emphasizes the need
to have robust monitoring.
To ensure availability and performance
of such key critical transaction
flows, and this is where distributed
tracing can come in and really shine.
For folks who are not aware of
distributed tracing distributed
tracing is a way by which you can
track individual request flows as they
travels through different services.
Typically, each of these requests are
tracked by a unique grid or a trace id.
We will delve a little deep into
semantics of distributed tracing
to understand this topic better.
Now, how can distributed
tracing help with cgs?
It can help you answer very key
questions, for example, which are
the services that I involve in my
critical path, and what are the health.
Of these critical CUJ transactions.
Now, these user journey flows often
evolve by because they new features
get added and therefore it becomes
important to be able to keep track of it.
And tracing can help identify these
unwanted, unsafe access patterns as well.
And.
Since you're track like tracking
individual requests, it can
help you identify where exactly
the performance bottleneck is.
And by doing so, it can reduce the time
to remediate, time to detect issues.
And I cannot emphasize this enough,
but instrumenting applications
carefully on your CUJ park becomes
so much more important because.
Those give you golden signals on
where exactly an issue might lie.
Often this means that you go in manually
instrument one span at a time and add
value to your to the traces themselves,
right on that particular request flow.
A little bit on our tracer platform.
Our platform provides disable tracing
for all the Salesforce services.
We are a centralized collection of
tracers, and we understand that these
user journeys, the source of it can
come from different things, right?
Different regions, different
application stacks and so forth.
So we have the ability to collect
spans from different a PM agents, from
managed frameworks, from infrastructure
layers, such as service mesh.
Which is especially true for
our Kubernetes workloads.
And we have tracing enable
on our integration test a
little bit on the scale.
We handle per, on the per minute basis,
we handle around 300 million spans.
And we have around 10 million unique
traces that gets reported every minute.
Let's briefly try to understand
the semantics of disability
tracing because that will help
us understand this topic better.
So consider a individual request
flow that goes across five different
applications, S one to S five.
Each of these services would emit
a certain record or an event, which
is often referred to as a span.
And a span record has few
characteristics, for example.
Take the take S one.
It has three spans at Ms. Ad and
h. Now each span has a start time a
duration of the span and which operation
within the service does it represent.
It can also have various other
metadata associated with it.
And each of these services would
independently send their SPAN records.
And all of these SPAN records remember,
are tied to a single Geo ID or a trace
id, and they all are, say, collected
to some kind of collection framework
and end up on the tracing backend.
Okay.
Once they arrive at the tracing
backend, you can actually now show a
nice waterfall representation, which
is a hierarchy representation of the
request flow by first overlaying or
placing the root span under which
you start displaying the child span.
The placement of the child span
is based on the start time of that
particular span, and the width of
the span is generally indicative of
the duration of this particular span.
Now with this, you can track
each and every request that is
happening on your infrastructure.
Now, how does context
propagation happens now?
Each of the spans that the services Emett
needs to be tied up to the same trace id.
Now that happens through context
propagation, through transport headers.
Consider this example where application
one is talking to application two.
Say it's an HCTP post call as part of the
post call, it'll send in some headers.
We at Salesforce today use B three
headers for legacy reasons, but you can
use ot open elementary headers as well.
As the trace contact is propagated to the
next hop, say in this case, application
two, when it generates a new span, it'll
use this context propagated to it to start
a span with the same request trace ID as
the caller which is the application one.
And that's how every record in
the request path gets stitched
up to the same presiding.
The sampling flag is quite important
because the sampling flag basically
would mean whether you are going
to collect that per trace or not.
If it is set to zero, even though the
context fabrication happens generally,
this application two would not emit
that span to the collection endpoint.
This is often done to reduce the overall
volume of the trace data that you collect.
How can you enable now CS
with distributed tracing?
You can do that with synthetic test.
So when you are enabling, synthetic
test, you always are enabling it
with a hundred percent sampling.
That means you, you firstly,
enable tracing on these synthetic
tests and ensure that all of these
synthetic tests are sample with 100%.
That means you don't drop
any kind of trace, right?
So each of your synthetic tests
that is emulating the request flow
is completely captured, right?
And with that, you can actually now do
things like real time browser monitoring,
a PM monitoring, DNS monitoring,
and so many other things, right?
And overall, it gives you a
performance and availability
from an outside in perspective,
which is what you really want.
How would you do that?
Firstly, you need to have a framework
to be able to enable you to do
this, so you need to build one.
But consider this case wherein you
are having a test a synthetic test.
And each of the synthetic test
would have a set of steps and each
step would emit its own trace.
So remember all these steps would be
emitting their own trace and these traces
are TA getting tied to the same test id.
Also, these steps are
generally, are like templates.
On these templates.
You can apply different variables
for example, you want a test to
be run from Europe, from Japan,
some US, so you can have the same.
Test definition, but you can apply, you
can have different kind of variables that
gets supplied onto this the step and the
emulation of that particular user journey
happens from that particular region.
So that's how you can enable it.
But once you enable your synthetic, you
can give this particular kind of view
where you show individual execution runs.
And when you try to drill down on
a particular execution run, it will
show associated trace IDs with it.
You can click on the trace IDs
and that will give it to the, take
you to the same waterfall view.
The graph here, if it's one,
it shows a successful run.
And if it's a minus one,
it shows a failure, right?
And you can drill down to that
particular taste to see where
the failure had happened.
So at a very.
Raw or a level, you can actually
track the execution at a trace level.
But is it useful to actually track it?
Yeah, it is.
But you can probably do more, right?
You can do things like aggregating these
traces to get more meaningful insights.
For example, consider this
case wherein you're doing a.
Create account transaction.
You can see that with a metric.
Generally it takes around 85 milliseconds
for this operation to complete,
but you don't know exactly where it
is spending most of your time in.
Through tracing that particular flow
has different services involved,
like app or storage or attend db.
But you don't know exactly where
the time is being well spent, so
you look at similar looking traces.
Aggregate them, and you can give a time
series view like this which will say that,
okay, authentication operation is the
one which is taking the most time, right?
This is a very powerful view
by which you can quickly drill
down towards a problematic.
Or where the problem is
actually having, right?
This same view.
Now, you can have not just for latency
degradation, but even for errors.
So also you can slice and
d this data as you choose.
For example, you can have this
contributors for a particular
step across different runs.
You can have this particular graph
or different variables for say only
for Japan location or a US location.
You want to see how the
contribution looks like and where
exactly the issue is happening.
That can be done as well.
You can overlay this with some kind
of baseline performance to see.
Changes or trends that has happened
week or month over month Overall,
you can quickly find out where the
possibility of optimization lies by
identifying the faulty service which
is causing the performance degradation.
You can also do more
with trace segregation.
You can create a directed graph
representation of the flow of the request.
Like this, right?
You basically are giving a directed
graph representation of how the
request was flowing and what the health
of those individual requests were
looking at an aggregated level, right?
For example, you had 72.
Runs of a particular test, out of
which as they were going across
different services started failing.
When the core was calling Salesforce
app 12 of them failed, right?
Remember, all these traces
are already sampled, so you're
already collecting them.
You're not dropping anything.
So you can get a, you can
enable a view like this to be
able to get nice quick view of.
How the flow of the request is happening
and where exactly an issue might lie.
I would also like to emphasize
the need for on demand tracing.
Sometimes when in user flows, there
may be one user which has some
issue, and you may want to actually
enable tracing for a specific user,
so have mechanisms to enable that.
We have created our phone framework
to actually enable it and sometimes.
Issues are sparse and sporadic, and
they happen maybe only at certain time
of the day that you're not aware of.
Long-term tracing is also sometimes
important and have the ability to do that.
We also have a, have the ability to
do instance waste tracing because
you deploy multiple instances.
Each instance may be tied to a
tenant and one instance might be
the one which is having issue.
So you can enable tracing on a particular
instance and then the critical user
journey flow through that instance can
capture what exactly might be happening.
Yeah.
And with that, I would like
to conclude my talk here.
Thank you everyone.
I.