All right.
Welcome to instrumenting
at 10 years per second.
Today I'll talk about a new
approach that we've developed to
accelerate manual instrumentation.
Now, auto instrumentation will
get you 80% there, but that
last 20% manual instrumentation.
Takes a lot longer, 10 years in
our case, roughly, but manual
instrumentation really increases
your ability to deeply understand
what your system is doing and why.
Now we piloted this approach
successfully with one of our neuro
microservices, and we're looking
forward to spreading this approach
across the rest of the microservices
in our fleet, and I'm really excited
to share this approach with you today.
A little about me.
My name, I'm Jean Mark Wright.
I'm a staff engineer at Wave.
We're.
I Lead Observability at Wave.
We're building an operating
system for small business owners.
We really want to take the tedium
and the complexity out of running
the business so that small business
owners can focus on what they do best.
So we provide a suite of products to
ensure that small business owners, can
really thrive at what they are doing.
Now, today I'll talk about the problem
of accelerating manual instrumentation.
What we're trying to do is we're really
trying to dramatically increase the pace
at which you can manually instrument
your service and which in turn is gonna
really improve the data that's available
for doing investigations and really
understanding what your system is doing.
So I'll talk about.
Our solution.
I'll talk about how it works and
then I'll close off with some next
steps in terms of what we thought of.
But first, lemme tell you a story.
I tell you this story
because for two reasons.
First, it demonstrates the
power and value of high quality.
Manual instrumentation.
And then secondly, it really motivates
why we want to spend and invest a
lot of engineering time and effort to
ensure that all engineers have access
to this high quality instrumentation.
Once upon a time our on-call engineer
was minding his own business,
but then he realized something
that was particularly disturbing.
He realized that our system was given
access to a premium feature for free.
This feature allowed users to connect
their bank accounts and import their
transactions into our accounting product.
A costly feature for our
business, but very convenient
and critical for business owners.
This feature is called Transaction Import
Now, transaction import is one of several
features that users have access to.
The problem is that transaction
import is a premium feature.
Typically folks would purchase
our pro plan, which gives access
to transaction import, along
with some other premium features.
And we also had this special legacy plan
that would also give access to transaction
import for some of our existing users.
But it wasn't live as yet.
And then finally, we also had this startup
plan, which all customers were initialized
on once they had completed onboarding.
This startup plan gave
access to free features.
It didn't give access to transaction
import, which is a premium feature, but
whatever we needed to dig in, understand
what was going on quickly so we could
stop the leak of this premium feature.
Now, fortunately for our on-call engineer,
this application was really special.
It had auto instrumentation, so all
our services, our databases, our
caches, they were all instrumented.
We got that for free using Datadog, right?
But, and so we also had metrics, right?
We have a PM metrics, we're getting
latency, throughput, error metrics.
We also had distributed tracing, so
you could actually trace a request
all the way from our API down to the
service that fulfilled that request.
And we also had logs, meh.
One thing that really set this system
apart was the fact that it had really
high quality manual instrumentation.
So auto instrumentation is the stuff
that you get out of the box, right?
So from your vendor, like
Datadog or whatever your
vendor is, are open telemetry.
You'll get instrumentation for your
databases, for your caches, for the
different transports that you use.
But manual instrumentation.
Manual instrumentation is what you
are adding from your application.
But it's this instrumentation.
That made this app particularly special.
What it meant is that we could
actually peel back the layers.
We could really inspect the system state.
We could ask thoughtful questions, and
we could really interrogate the system's
behavior to really understand what the
system was doing, why it was doing it,
why it made the choices that it made.
But let's get back to the story.
So our on-call engineer, he noticed
that we're giving a premium feature
away for free, and he's trying to figure
out, we're all trying to figure out
why is the system doing this right?
So our investigation took us to
an endpoint called initialized.
Business.
Now, initialized business is responsible
for putting customers on a plan after
they've successfully onboarded with us.
Now the plan is what gives you
access to the features, right?
And after onboarding, the initialized
endpoint would put a customer,
would put the customer on a plan.
So by default, customers
are put on our start plan.
So eventually I talked about this
legacy plan that we had as well.
Eventually, we'd support putting
users on a legacy plan, which
would give access to transaction
import, but we weren't there yet.
But with the manual instrumentation
that we added, it meant that we could
really dive deep to understand exactly.
What this endpoint was doing, we could
really examine the data that was processed
to better understand the system state.
So not only could we look at common
attributes like user, we could ask
bigger questions so we could ask, Hey.
What plan was initialized for this user?
Or we could look at, okay, once the
plan has initialized for, has been
in, has been initialized for the user,
what features did we give to that user?
And we could look at the country that
the user was being initialized from.
There were bevy of different attributes
that we could look at, and all of
this data we had access to in our
traces, in our errors, and in our logs.
So a key question that came up.
Was, did we initialize the right plan?
We know that when users onboard,
we're supposed to be putting
them on the start plan, right?
So one key question that we had to ask,
and we probably started with first, was,
did we put the users on the start plan?
The good thing is that because we
had manually instrumented our system
and we have all of this high quality
data available to us, we could
actually interrogate our quest in.
We could actually interrogate our traces.
We could ask our system this question.
So we could say, looking
at recent traces, which.
Plan, have we been assigning to our users?
And see here, we've actually
graphed that with our traces.
We've broken down our
traces and essentially asked
our system that question.
And when you look at the result here,
you can see in the bottom left corner
of the graph that we're actually
correctly assigning the starter plan.
So that's actually expected.
We know customers are supposed to be put
on a starter plan by default, so it looks
like the system is doing that correctly.
But somehow users are still getting
access to this premium feature.
Maybe let's open a specific trace.
Let's look at the span tags and then let's
look at each of these attributes in turn.
So we know the user ID is fine.
That's not the most
important thing for us.
Now, the country's okay.
The plan.
We saw that yes, we're actually putting
the customer on the starter plan.
We're a little concerned about features
because we know transaction import is in
that list of features that the user got.
And that's not expected, but,
wait, what's this feature group
thing and why does it's a legacy.
So it looks like we're initializing
the startup plan, but we're
using a legacy feature group.
That's weird.
What's a feature group?
So it turns out that we actually don't
assign plans directly to features.
What we do is that we actually put
features into a feature group, and then
we point the plan to the feature group.
So what our instrumentation was telling
us is that we were initializing the right
plan, but the incorrect feature group.
So the feature group correctly defined
the set of features, so the legacy feature
group, because it represents the legacy
plan, essentially it has transaction
import in that list of features.
But what we were doing wrong is
that the start plan was somehow
incorrectly pointing to the legacy plan.
What should have been happening was
the startup plan should be pointing to
the start feature group, which would've
correctly pointed to the list of features.
That's really interesting.
There's so much information we're able
to glean just looking at our traces
and looking at the data that's there.
So the theory we have now is that the
start plan is incorrectly pointing.
To the legacy feature
group, and that's incorrect.
But can we ask our system, what
feature group have you been assigning?
Turns out we actually can, we
can confirm that with our traces.
We can ask our system, what feature
group have you been assigning?
And if we graph that, you can actually see
from the graph that run about the 23rd.
We started incorrectly assigning
the legacy plan to users.
So all along you can see that
we're assigning the start of
sorry, the start of feature group.
All along you can see we're assigning
the start of feature group, but
somewhere around the 23rd you can
see that we've started adding, we've
started initializing the legacy
feature group and just like that.
A little quality manual
instrumentation, saves the day.
So our on-call engineer discovered we
were giving features away for free.
We jumped into Datadog, put our
manual instrumentation to work.
We interrogated the system
using traces, and within 12
minutes we found the problem.
It was a data corruption issue.
There was a problem with
the data in our database.
We weren't pointing to the right
pieces of data properly, right?
Our starter plan was pointing to
this incorrect legacy feature group.
Now, it only took us a few minutes
to fix the data in the database,
but after 15 minutes, we had
debugged and fixed the premium leak.
That is the power of
manual instrumentation.
So you might say that's a great outcome.
Lots of great manual
instrumentation, debugging and
fixing a problem in 15 minutes.
So what's the problem then?
The good news is that we had
one really well instrumented,
microservice, the bad news.
We had one.
Really well instrumented microservice.
There are about 40 others,
so during the year.
A year and a half that the
service was being developed, the
engineers manually instrumented it.
So if we say that it took three
months to completely add that manual
instrumentation, conservative estimate,
if we assume it takes three months
to instrument each existing service,
three months times 40 services gives
us 120 months, which is 10 years.
And yes, we could paralyze the work,
but it would still take us years.
So what we decided to do was to do a pilot
with one of our new American services.
We thought let's try and accelerate
manual instrumentation for them.
Now in order to do that,
we looked at two things.
The first thing we looked at
was the component interaction.
So when a request comes into the
application, several components
collaborate to fulfill that request.
So in our application, we
typically have API components.
We have services that capture our business
logic, and we also have repositories
that handle an abstract persistence.
So Initialized business endpoint, for
instance, there was an API component.
Which would call a service method
on, or a subscription service.
And then that subscription service
would call one or more repositories.
So in this example, you can see the
subscription service initialized
business method is calling the
plan repository dot get method, and
it's also calling the subscription
repository that create method.
So that's the first
thing that we looked at.
We thought about the
component interaction and.
It seemed like this was a piece
of the puzzle because what we're
trying to do is we're trying to
figure out how can we accelerate
the pace of manual instrumentation?
How can we really help engineers to get
to a point where there's little or no
manual instrumentation, but we've got
to a point where there's a lot more?
How can we automate this process?
So we looked at the component interaction.
That was one piece of the puzzle.
The other piece of the puzzle that
we thought about was the data.
That's exchanged.
So there's a lot of data
exchange in the process.
So for example, when the subscription
API Initialized Business Method calls the
subscription service initialized business
method, there's a lot of data that's
passed between those two components.
So the subscription API passes
a business ID, passes a user ID
country, and a business name.
And similarly, when the service
calls or repositories data is also
passed between those components.
Now, it would be great if we could
let engineers specify the data that
they're interested in capturing.
So if they could say, I wanna capture a
business id, user ID the business name.
So if they could tell us the data that
they wanted to capture, then what we could
do is we could look at these components,
because now what these components
represent is a great opportunity
to insert some capturing logic.
So if we're able to actually wrap each
of these components, then we could
capture the data that the teams need.
So what we're saying here is that
we're looking at the application stack.
We're looking at the different
components that are used to
fulfill our request, right?
And we know that data gets passed
in between those components.
So what we're thinking is if we
let engineers specify and say, Hey.
This is the data that I want to capture.
Then we could create hooks or
we could wrap those components
and just capture the data that
engineers have asked us to collect.
So what we did was we started
with this configuration.
I.
Tell us what data you want to capture.
So maybe they wanna capture the
business id, user ID and the country.
And then what we did is that we took
this notion of the configuration and
then we converted that into code.
So here's a sample configuration.
We call this a telemetric
capture configuration.
Now, with this configuration, they can
specify a load or disallowed field names,
field types, and since it's written
in Python, we can also add support
for data classes for dictionaries.
And for each of these properties
that you're seeing here, there's
an equivalent disallowed one.
So for example, looking at allowed
field names, there's a disallowed
field names or disallowed field types.
So again, using this, engineers could
know very succinctly specify, this is the
data that we want you to capture, right?
And they don't have to worry about where
and which component is handling that data.
They could focus on the data that's
exchanged, and then we would provide
the hooks and wrap each of those
components that they have, and then
capture all the data that they've
access to capture in this configuration.
So in terms of wrapping the component
methods, we know that we needed to
inject some logic to capture the, to
capture to we need, we know we needed
to inject some logic before their
function was called to capture inputs.
So in this example, when the subscription
API is calling the subscription services
Initialized Business method, we know,
as you've seen that comment there,
we know we need to insert some logic.
Before that to capture that business
ID and capture that user id.
But then the thing is, we can't
go modifying all of their code
because that's not sustainable.
So we needed to turn to an advanced
language feature of Python to help
us do this, to help us do this.
Capturing logic behind the scenes without
having to go and modify everybody's code.
So what we wanted to do is we really
wanted to look at the data that was being
passed between the components, right?
So here, the subscription API is
passing a business ID and a user
ID to the subscription service.
And what we wanted to do is look
at the data and once it's, once
that data is specified in the
configuration, then we will capture it.
So in terms of the actual
component wrapping.
Python has a, Python, has a
wonderful notion for doing this.
It's called meta classes.
So a meta class is a class that is
responsible for creating a class,
which is a mouthful of a definition.
But essentially what that means is that we
could create a class that is responsible
for, that could be used to make.
Any class or component that
an engineer wanted to make.
So the subscription API, we could use
our meta class and our meta class could
modify the creation of the subscription
API or the subscription repository
or the subscription service, and then
we could insert our logic, right?
So the meta class gives us this
perfect opportunity to wrap their
functions, and then that allows
us to do capturing logic, right?
And then.
We can call their original function.
So if we look at this simple example
here, what we're doing is that
we're looping over each function.
And then we're defining a new
function that captures telemetry.
And then what we do is that we
call their original function.
And then finally, we replace the original
function with our modified function.
So now what is gonna happen is
that every time someone calls their
function, it will call our logic first.
So in that example, we're looking at.
The initialized business method
on the subscription service.
So what we would've done here is that
we would've wrapped that initialized
business method on the subscription
service, so that what we do is that first
we look at the inputs that are coming
into that initialized business method.
We check if those inputs
are in the configuration.
And if they're in the configuration,
then we'll just capture those
inputs for the engineer.
And then after we've captured those
inputs, we can go ahead and let the
application resume as it would normally.
So then we will call their
logic so that the rest of the
application functions normally.
Here we have a quick example
of how the meta class is used.
So here you can see the
subscription service specifies
that it wants to use the service.
Meta class.
Meta class, right?
And that's how it gets used.
And once an engineer has added
this meta class to their component.
We are now automatically
wrapping their component, right?
And once they have defined the telemetric
capture configuration, which specifies
the data that they want us to capture,
then our meta class will get to work.
Once this initialized business method gets
called, we consult our configuration that
they've provided and look at the inputs.
Okay, you've got a business ID coming in,
let's check if it's in the configuration.
And if it's in the configuration, then
we'll just go ahead and capture it.
And then because this manual
instrumentation process is now becoming
a little bit more magical, one other
thing that we did was also to add
a coverage report that provides,
is provides insights on what gets
captured and what doesn't get captured.
So what you're seeing here is it
will go through each component,
it will go through each method.
It will list each input for each
method, and it will tell you check
box, yes, this is getting covered.
No, this is not getting covered.
And with this simple approach,
regardless of which component
handles the data, we can capture it.
So now engineers can focus on the
data that they want to capture.
They focus on the data, not where.
Not which component, they just focus
on the data that needs to be captured.
And once that's clearly specified,
we will do the heavy lifting.
We will automate the capturing
of the manual instrumentation.
We call it config, accelerated custom
instrumentation, or case I for short.
Now in our pilot, we were able to move the
instrumentation of the new microservice.
From 1% all the way up to about 60%.
Now, this vastly increased the data
and the telemetry that was available
to them for investigating, debugging
and demystifying their system behavior.
So after we actually developed
kci, it took us less than a week
to get the configuration in place.
All of this really accelerated
the manual instrumentation.
They didn't have to spend the time.
Going through manually
instrument in their code.
It didn't take them three months,
it didn't take them six months, it
didn't take them a year because we've
developed this config, accelerated
custom instrumentation, and they can
easily specify with configuration
the data that they want to capture.
That's something that we were able to
work with them and get done in record
time, what does this actually mean
in terms of debugging their systems?
So for instance, if they're
looking at errors, they can
actually break that apart.
It's not just errors.
They can break that apart by
various dimensions based on the
data that the application handles.
So in this example.
They're breaking those errors
down by the event type, which
reveals that the majority of errors
are updated event types, right?
And there's many other dimensions
that they could break the different
errors apart by, and they could
combine all of these things.
And the reason that this is important
is that, just as you remember that
story that we told about our on-call
engineer trying to figure out
why do we have this premium leak?
This is really important to have a lot
of high quality manual instrumentation
because that's what's gonna help you
when you're trying to debug your system.
You're looking at some
kind of degradation.
In this case we're looking at arrows, but
you're able to break that apart so you
can start to draw different boundaries
to understand exactly which segment
of your customers are being affected.
And similarly, if they
were looking at latency.
Another quick example is not just latency.
They can actually break that down.
So in this example, we're showing
a graph where they're looking at
the latency, but they're breaking
that down by the Kafka topic.
And here they can see that, okay,
apparently the Kafka, the company Kafka
topic is taking longer to process it.
It seems to have, a lot more peaks than
some of the other topics that they have.
And.
All of this data that they have available
to them, all of this quality manual
instrumentation that we're talking about
isn't just available in their traces.
It's also there in their logs and
it's also in their errors, right?
They get this high fidelity wherever
they're using and accessing the telemetry.
I. That's the power of manual
instrumentation and we've
accelerated it for them using ksa.
Now, in terms of what's next for us, we're
thinking about scaling up for the other
40 plus services that we need to capture.
So some of the things we're
thinking about there is, in this.
In this talk I talked about a service
meta class, and we only looked at
one of the components in our pilot.
We looked at one of the component types
that they had, which are services,
which holds our business logic.
But we're looking at making that
component agnostic so that we have
meta class, we have a meta class.
Know that it doesn't matter
what component type you have.
We'll be able to capture and
hook into that component and
capture the telemetry for you.
Another thing we're working on is you'll
see in this talk that we focus on inputs.
So you know when the API called the
service, we talked about the inputs, but
we haven't actually started to capture
outputs, and that's something that
we're interested in looking to as well.
Another thing that we're really
excited to look at is thinking about
how we can actually use LLMs to help
accelerate the pace of doing and
installing this integration, right?
Because what we really want to do is we
really want to tighten the feedback loop
between adding the instrumentation and
seeing the value of that instrumentation
and seeing what you can do.
For example, in Datadog, we really want
to tighten that loop, engineers can
really get a clearer picture of that.
And we really want to use
LMS to help us do that.
And because we're a small team
as well, it really helps us scale
our impact and scale our voices.
I. And then finally, we later found
out that data log actually has some
abilities in their DD Trace Library
to propagate telemetry between spans.
And so that's something that we're very
interested to looking into as well.
All right.
And that has brought us to
the end of the talk here.
Instrument in at 10 years for a second.
I want to thank you for tuning in.
The best way to find me is
probably on LinkedIn Jaw mark.
I also blog at JY 13 hash node dev.
But I'd really like to thank you for
coming and listening to our talk.
I hope you really enjoy the rest of
the talks at Con 42 and looking forward
to hearing, hearing from all of you.
If you have.
Ideas if you've done something
similar or if you just want to
chat about observability, I love
to geek out about observability.
So looking forward to hearing from you.
Thanks.
Bye-bye.