Hi everyone.
My greetings to you all as this
conference can be viewed by
across, by via the worldwide.
I'm just giving without the time zone.
Some maybe in good morning, good
afternoon, and good evening.
So I just want to say my
greetings to you all and myself.
I am seeing you as man, and I'm
currently working in Fidelity
investment as senior manager and.
I just want to walk you through
the observability the micro, the
observability, micro in the microservices.
How we really evolve from the
basic, traditional and with
current situation where we are.
And if we imply, if we empower that
observability with more AI enablement
tools, how we are going to leverage
and what we can envision the future.
Way of operation mechanism.
That's the intent of the
whole my presentation.
It's basically called as
AI powered observability in
microservices architecture.
Okay.
It's beyond metrics where we
started from initially, but
now where we are landing now.
So just let us get into the presentation.
I will go very quick on the introduction.
As currently in the tradition we
used to have monolithic applications
and now we are moving toward
the microservices architecture.
We started with the monolithic
traditional monitoring approaches,
basically like alerts, some set
of threshold alerts to give the
infrastructure health and everything.
That is our start of our basic
health monitoring systems.
We call now, we are moving into more.
Microservices distributor systems.
So the traditional mechanism
that we applied are nowhere
able to meet the today's needs.
Hence, we are transformed
or transformed or evolved.
As we move from one technical to
another involvement the same way the
operation management has been evolving
from one decade to another time span.
So this is basically my intent is to
say, Hey, now we are in the AI era.
If we apply, if we enable this
observability with the AI features,
how we can really make it more better.
We actually, if you speak, we are already
leveraging that, but still I would really
want to call out here basically with
my experience, how this observability
is so important and how the AI can
really help observatory more in future.
That's the intent of this.
I would like to even see the framework
that we can build upon and then practice
that observability as we go on with
new things coming up, and that will
eventually help us a lot on ongoing.
That's the intent of this whole exercise.
I will just start with my first,
the evolution of observability.
You know that we initially
started with the traditional
monitoring where, and then.
Monolithic application as I called
out before, we have to have an
alerts or some sort of basic alerts.
He's a. Database is down or it's up,
or is a basic alert system that was
making, basically the administrator
used to get, and basically they act
upon that alerts and work on that is
called the traditional monitoring.
From there, we evolve into the next
set, and that is a very important,
which I will take a little more time on.
What is the basic observability in?
In observability, we have three main
factors, the three pillars, the metrics.
Logs and traces metrics, it
gives a very high level overview.
Of the system, the CP usage, the
threshold times basically the response
times or the error rate, the memory
usages, everything of the application
the infrastructure, basically it's
a high level coming to the logs.
It's a granular level of the view.
It more tells about the events,
the basically the warning, the
information, messages and everything.
It's more of a granular
view of this system.
Okay.
Then we have the traces,
basically how a request is
traversing within the application.
Is there any blockers for that?
It's basically to trace the the requests
that are incoming to the application.
So these are the three categories
of application these categories.
Of the data points that we used to
collect to understand, and that was
our initial basic observability that
we, from where the other system we
started, then we categorized into
three sectors and we started using
them as our base for a very long term.
The basic, these three
were very long term.
We've been using them.
And now the initial observability is
basically like you get an alert, you get
a metrics or your data, you collect the
data of metrics or logs and everything.
And then based on that, we have to
take a reactor approach basically.
Yes.
What needed to be done for now, that
is our trend where it used to be.
Now given this new let us
take around five years, maybe.
No I think I will go with 10, 7, 8 years.
Once we started this cloud.
S infrastructure coming up, we
really had a more better enhanced
version of the observability.
Where the cloud platforms are really put
a very good focus on this because they
know that these are the very key factors
for any cloud provider that if they
don't provide the infrastructure health.
To the consumers, they'll not be
really being sustaining the market.
So they really focus on the observability.
They enhanced it in such a way that they
take a next step, not just collecting
the data, not just collecting the data.
They applied some sort of pattern
analysis on this to understand what
is a peak time of a usage of a system.
What is the low time or
what is the what is the non.
What do you call, I can
say non-working hours.
How, what are the maintenance
hours we can come?
So this analysis has helped us to
come with the maintenance hours to
know what is the peak hours, how to
manage the resources based on that.
This is the AI enhanced observability
is I don't I, the reason why I call
this a ns, this started using this
data, analyzing them and applying
some thought process of what we can
take a predictive approach like, hey.
This is a time in a day, a very high peak.
Covers are the how we can apply
a resource optimization there.
What are the things that I can
do in the maintenance, which
I should not in a peak hours.
That type of predictive analysis has
helped us to know where we need to
do maintain hours, where we need to
increase the resource that is the
advantage of this enhanced observative.
The next one, which I want to call out is.
Not just manual intervention of
increasing the resource and everything.
Now think about if I can really
make autoscaling horizonal
scaling or vertical scaling.
If you remember, in cloud, we have right
now based on the peak hours or based
on the season, like a Thanksgiving,
where Amazon has a high volume of
data, consumers hitting the system,
they know that they need to scale out.
At that moment of time and they need
to crunch back at the once it is done,
so it's basically self-healing system.
It's basically self feeling based on the
data, analyzing the predictor analysis,
and then applying a healing system.
And that is what is, so where we started
from just collecting the data, which
is our traditional, now where we are is
we are taking the data, applying our AI
enablement, and then taking a measures
without even a manual intervention.
Hence, this is a real.
Evolution of an Observ team.
That's what I want to call from, where
we started from where we are now, and
where we can go more further on this.
Let me go to the next slide.
The three pillars.
These three pillars as I called
out the metrics the sorry, metrics,
logs, and traces as I called out.
Metrics, high level overview it
call more talks about CPU U stages
and or the pa. Basically it has the
data related to the infrastructure.
Then the logs is basically about a
granular level of what are the usages and.
Sorry, my mistake.
Granular usage of the information,
including error and everything.
And then the other one is basically the
traces, the request flow and everything.
Okay.
These are the basic thing.
No.
If these three pillars, if we live as is,
we could have not achieved where we are.
We have really transformed them, these
metrics and the logs and applied more.
Frameworks or I know I can
say more technical innovations
are done on this three.
In order to see that, how we can
leverage, for example, metrics, CPU
stages apply the historical data pattern
recognition so that we can know when
to scale out, when to, not to scale out
logs, what type of errors are coming up.
Basically to see which is,
this will help us to know.
What is a frequent error or frequent
issues that are coming up and how we can
really proactively take a measures on it.
For example, database, many people are
hitting at one time and the database
not reachable, so they can really take
a proactive measures based on the logs.
Seeing that granular above that
information, the system traces basically
which features are used more frequently,
how we can scale out that microservices
more than the ones which are not used.
So this is something an intelligence.
Getting applied onto the tree
and making them more mature.
So that will help us for our, take
us more life, more smoother, because
if we have issues, we are day and
day out, we cannot burn ourselves.
But if you apply intelligence on
this and make our life more easy,
and that will help eventually the
operations, more simple, easy to manage.
One of the important thing about
the observability is the SLOs.
So I will even want to share one
of my recent experience on this
technical methods, so we know we have
a technical, and when we know there's
a business, unless we map this too.
There'll never be a there'll never
be a for example a consensus.
For example, if I want to enhance
my observability with more of with
my, more of my knowledge with more
of my implementation, unless I get
a business value of it out of it, I
cannot really do an investment on this.
So basically what I really want
to sell is, unless you really.
Correlate what your technical metrics,
data that capturing to the business KPIs.
There will never be a buy-in for us
to really invest a lot on Observ.
It comes with the cost.
Observability comes with the
cost, and the cost need to be.
Need to be approved by the
business and the business.
Need to see the value out of it.
What we are doing here.
And that value can only be correlated
unless we can measure one, unless we map
the business KPIs with what we are doing.
For example, user customer satisfaction.
What I'm taking, the
customer satisfaction.
Customer satisfaction comes with
a latency, unless you have a data.
To really capture the latency issues
in your systems, you cannot really
assess, gauge the customer satisfaction.
Another one is to put capacity, same
thing, then the revenue per transaction.
Unless you know what is the cost
on revenue, cost on transaction per
transaction, per participant, or for
the, for a customer or for a business
order, we cannot really assess.
How much our systems are used sometime.
If the order takes long time,
it means we are not able to make
within, we cannot scale up ourself.
So this combination is very important and.
To get, to improve, sustain our
observability and pro and to
apply our practice on a long, we
definitely need a business approval.
And the business can only approve
unless we show the value of what we
are doing and how it can help the
application and how it can help them
from their sales pitch point of view.
What we are doing, that's
what is, for example cloud.
When they share, they will definitely
tell, hey, how we are going how our
observability practices are helping you.
Unless then you'll not ever
go and make yourself as a cus
customer to the cloud provider.
In the same way for any application,
unless we have the metrics, data and
observability, all this logs properly
enhanced and how we are leveraging.
And which the customer will never
be able to come to our systems.
That's the intent of the SLO.
We really need to have a precise mapping
of this business, K ps, stored technical
metrics, logs, and everything places so
that we really have a good value benefit.
And then only we can really sustain
the practice of observability within
our system as it'll be very, because
it comes with a cost, and cost cannot
be done without a business approach.
Now coming to the implementation
framework, what I really want
to call here is building a
mature observative framework.
It is not just an observative,
cannot be done just on one day.
It is need to build as a building blocks.
You need to start collecting the data.
Then you need to apply some
set of validation checks.
Today you are going to apply the
observability checks, like collecting
the logs, collecting the matrix data,
collecting the tracers and everything.
Now, think about as we go on.
We may build new microservices, so we
need to ensure some controls to ensure
that observability checks are being
part of that existing development.
For example, a new microservices.
If we don't ensure the value sanity
check on that new micro and is
getting deployed to production, we
may ensure and end up in an issue.
So we need to ensure that the
implementation required for
observability is being applied.
As part of the build, CICD
pipelines, we can apply new checks
like sonar code coverage checks.
That's not a basic, but logs
basically integration testing.
There are a lot of means of testing where
we can ensure as a check list has these
are been done that will help us to sustain
this observative practice a long term.
Then coming to the intelligent analysis,
basically what I'm saying is applying the.
Models, ml or machine learning models, or
you can say AI or AI algorithms to ensure
that how we can leverage this collected
data and do the predictive analysis.
And then finally, AI ops, basically Remi,
predictive and based on predictive, how
we can make them self-healing system.
That is the basic implementation
of the framework, Steve.
Progressing.
Each layer of the period builds
on the capabilities below it.
Creating an observability practice that
evolves with your organization needs.
So based on our organization needs, we
need to ensure that we do have everything
in place and we do maintain that.
And even though when a new application
is coming, or the new services are
coming within the organization or
buildup, we need to ensure that we are.
Making as a process that every
developer or every business has
this observability checks and hence
the team at an organization level
who maintains this operations.
They are really having this controls and
checks so that there's no, just an example
of penetration testing if we don't have a
proper metrics to ensure that a pen test.
Mechanisms not there.
Then we may be prone to a vulnerability.
Hence, these are some of the important
things that we need to imply in our
framework and then continue, and
that will sustain for our practice.
Some of the open source systems
on observability is graph.
I have, they are telemetry.
There are a lot of tools here, which
I can list at kin and everything.
But one of the important tools
which I like most and I've
been personally using is graph.
It really gives excellent.
View visualization of the
underneath metrics locks
place the predictor analysis.
It even provides the suggestions.
What we can do, and it even the, one
of the important other, the allowable
factor that I, for me is the dashboards
based on the custom, based on the user.
You can really build your own dashboard.
I may be interested in metrics
analyst, the other person may
be interested in log analysis.
The other person may be, so you can
build your dashboards, focusing on
where you are interested and that
really gives a visualization and even.
Helping in you can even
build your own data.
It has its own supporting query language
and that is really a very valuable thing
that helps a lot for us to even query
the data that we want to assess or get
pitch the historical data and everything.
That's a very good, so what I really
want to say from this slide is.
We started with this
observability concept.
Now we are in a stage where there's a
vast amount of tools built upon, and every
tool has been has its own capability.
We just need to plug in that tool into
our system based on our automation
needs, customize it, and see that we
have the complete system in place.
So the framework that I talked about
previously, that is what you really
want from your observability, what you
really want to capture, and how you can
map that into a tool which is already,
like Grafana is an open source tool.
You can apply it, customize it,
and make your system, and then you
need to practice this, basically
sustain that observability.
The other important thing about this
observability is a contextual alerting.
Okay?
Initially, we used to get in normal
alerts, Hey, this is alert and our
production database is getting down.
That was a basic alert.
You used to get in emails.
Now with this new technology
at your mobile, you can get it.
There's something on you doesn't need.
People used to sit in front of
the system in the traditional,
like they were like shift wise.
People used to sit in front
of the system watching.
Now that's not required.
With this new technology we are able
to get the alerts on your mobile.
That's ideally need to create
the technology advancement,
but not only just that one.
Right now I can, because
I'm experiencing that.
It'll even suggest you what is a similar
incident happened previously and what
was the action done previously and how we
can suggest, say if a person who is on a
on call and he got an alert saying that,
Hey, there's something happened, contact,
he will have a provision from the alert
itself to refer to the previous incident
that was previously done and see how we
can, it's, this is a contextual alerting.
Basically you got an alert.
But at the same time, it is giving
a history of the previous alerts
for you to refer, and you can even
delegate to a right person who has
previously worked on a similar incident.
If he is available, you can even
delegate that incident to that person.
So for a faster resolution,
this is all else.
Before it was not the case.
We don't know who worked on a similar
issue, but now we have a history
of data and it even suggesting us,
Hey, there is a previous history.
These other steps are executed and
this is what we can do and is the
person available in the system, let
us go and reach the person so it's
more of faster resolution of incident.
This is all helps us
for faster resolution.
I just want to take more just
take a intelligent routing
that is also very important.
We have many people in the system
who are monitoring the operations.
Not everyone is dedicated
to for all the people.
There are certain set of sector
people who are very privileged.
Experience.
So they will get those alerts.
We can even delegate which alert to go
home so that we have a proper incident
management done in the right time so
that the MT the meantime to resolution.
It gets resolved.
It gets reduced drastically.
Before it was like one day, two day.
Just an example, I'm giving now in
hours, we are able to reduce in hours.
This is all because how.
How we are able to apply our
intelligence on our lessons.
It is basically lessons learned
from previous experience.
Where are our bottlenecks?
Where are our improvement areas?
How we can apply this
AI models and into that.
And so that we can make ourself.
It's more of, as we go on, we will
improve, and I don't know, tomorrow
it could be a mechanism where.
With this new robots and everything,
things may be more changing, but
contextual editing is basically
helping you to give the history
data and even provide the people
whom you can delegate the requests.
Yeah.
Sorry, I just, I went ahead before my,
this is, what is the outcome of that?
Context reduction in the fast incident,
MTR reduction, predictive accuracy.
So based on the all alerts, you
can predict what could be the issue
based on the previous history.
Also, then collaboration as I just called
out, there's an improved collaboration
between, because you know whom to
reach, you know whom to delegate.
It's an increase and ready you are.
Instead of just putting on one person,
you're delegating it to the right people.
So concurrent issues can
also be resolved with this.
Now the very important thing about
this is a next phase, which I
thought right now we started with
traditional, then we went to this
what you call the basic observability.
Then we went to the enhanced
version, then the self feeling.
Now think about the generate ai.
Now this is a new version.
Think about in observability Grafana,
understand if we built a chat bot.
And which can help us.
You can question, I got an incident and
I want to understand what can I do here?
It is giving you based on the previous
historical data, how, what are steps to
be done and it even shows you some set of
previous incidents so that you can really
understand, apply so that it basically
leveraging the previous historical data.
Just an example.
The other one is incident.
You get an incident,
someone locks an incident.
But here, based on this.
Generally if a similar incident
happened, you can really accumulatively
build up a very good summary and it
can make the user to understand, hey,
this could be possible, these reasons,
and this is where is a major problem.
So most frequently when this
incident comes, this is the
area of a fixed measure be done.
So can you, can I check that one?
It basically helps.
To identify the root cause analysis
very quicker with the summary.
Basically, it brings all the incidents of
together and gives the summary of what are
the fixes done across and what is a common
fix mostly done so that you can really
first go and attack that, fix that issue.
That is basically the incident
summary, and the other one is.
Suggestion, as I said, what are
the suggestion based on historical?
So if we bring the generator AI
into the system, not just AI models
and everything, even now apply the
generator on the historical data,
you really making more better.
Even a new person who is very new
to system, he doesn't need to really
aware, he doesn't need to go with
the KT sessions and everything.
We can just say, Hey, use the
chat bot, get the information,
and you are on your own.
That is more like you're making everyone
a new person, an independent by with
this, all this data because no one
needs any information from a person.
Everything information
is in the historical.
You just need to grab it,
understand, and apply your thoughts.
The last one is basically, as I
said, observability is basically
a discipline you can say.
As we, when we build a new application
within our ordination, you need
to ensure that the discipline
is followed across in all the
applications so that we have a proper
operation, KPS data being collected.
And if this practice has been
applied concurrently or con, not
concurrently or con, the right word is
ensuring that discipline is followed.
Consistently across within, then
you are really preparing yourself
for a better application, operation
management for your organization.
So that your operation cost will
come down drastically because your
incident management coming down the
turnaround your predictor analysis
accuracy has been very good.
Everything.
So your operation cost, then the
cost of the quality is getting down.
Then that will improve a lot of.
Thing to enhance, use a breathing space
to enhance our application more further.
So hence how an observability
can make our life more smoother.
Because if the, if we don't have proper
operation management, hence the cost of
quality can in, if it increases, then.
From a budget point of view, we
may not be able to have a fund to
improve our application features.
Whether we need to put more
effort to retain and sustain our
application existing, we are not
in a position to scale up our
application for the future needs.
Hence, that's the reason this is.