Hello everyone.
I am N Krisna.
I'm a technical architect with
more than 11 years of experience.
I worked on a WS services as a
developer administrator and I'm
working as an architect, for a
S Services, DevOps DevSecOps.
I also work on automations
of all these services.
For performance improvement and
producing the cost to the clients.
today I'm going to discuss about the
topic, observability with open telemetry.
So this technical discussion will
focus on observability principles
and implementing open telemetry
in our modern distributed systems.
Let's get started.
this is the agenda for today.
First, we'll, focus on.
Understanding the observability,
by learning foundations and
key concepts of observability.
Then we'll deep dive with different
types of, tele data types.
And collection methods.
Later we'll focus on the architecture
of Open Telemetry components and
implementation part, which covers open
telemetry essentials as a thought topic.
And the fourth topic would be the data
sources of open telemetry on how can
we integrate open telemetry with other
systems, other tools in our application.
Let's get started with the deep dive.
Before we start, in details, let's focus
on the foundations of observability.
we talk more about tele
data over this, discussion.
So let's talk about
what is telemetry data.
Basically, it's like a collection
and transmission of logs, events and
measurements from various systems.
Could be remote systems or distributed
systems to a central monitoring place.
Analysis.
Once we collect this, data
would be used to locate the
potential problems in the systems.
So basically, DevOps
focus on, two metrics.
any, which looks into these two metrics.
One is called MT td, and another is MTTR.
mean time to detection.
this is a time taken
to identify the issue.
And MTTR like mean time to resolve.
This is a time taken to resolve the
issue after the issue is detected.
So identifying and resolving,
these are the two metrics that are
being measured by organizations.
How quickly we are able to identify
the issue and how quickly we
are able to resolve the issue.
Monitoring methods.
So we'll be collecting different types
of telemetry data, as we discussed
in the previous, slide, right?
So what type of data we
are going to collect.
So the first one is, red method.
the R represents rate E represents
errors, D represents duration rate.
So the number of requests coming
into the system per second,
like requests per second.
Transactions per second error.
The number of failed transactions
or requests in our application
or a system and the duration.
So the response time, may be per request
or per transaction from our system.
And the second method is use method.
In this, it focuses on
utilization of the resources.
Like resource ation, like how much
of CPU used, how much disc is used?
Saturation, like a Q length, for example.
Network packets or network
requests are queing up errors.
So it could be hardware or
software related errors.
Say for example, discre
error, discre IO error.
These are all called as, errors.
Four golden signals.
this method is, recommended by Google
in their set liability documentation.
So four golden, signals, covers the
first, first three, collections,
like red plus saturation.
So the first topic is in
this one is the latency.
the processing time, the delay
happening in the system traffic,
the request volume coming into the
system, that errors the failure rates
in the application of the system,
saturation in the system load, that is
happening within our operating system.
Sir, it would be an overall
system or the application.
And, core web bottles.
Okay.
This is mainly focusing on the web UI or
user interfaces or webpages or websites.
The previous, three methods, what
we focused are, they focus on the
system, the infrastructure side,
system side and services side.
But core web metals will focus on, the
web, user interface, user experiences.
The LCP, the largest.
Content.
Full paint.
It measures loading performance.
FID first input, delay measures,
responsiveness to user, interactions.
CLS accumulate to layout, shift
measures, visual, stability during
the load of the particular webpage.
Now let's talk about,
Tracks known issues and it is best for,
a small systems and monolith systems.
And it shows when the issue occurs.
When it comes to observability,
it's a practical approach.
It uncovers unknown unknowns ideal for
complex systems, and it shows where,
when, and why that issue happened.
So observability gives us more
quicker way of identifying the
issue and resolving the issue.
And tele data type.
So we talked about what is tele data, what
we collect, and what type of data it is.
So there are, different
types of tele data.
one is metrics.
it it, just explains about
the quantitative measurements,
like what is happening.
it comes with numbers, basically.
Okay.
logs.
So it's like timestamped events
that, are decoded in the system.
So what happened when it happened?
Okay.
Traces like this is very important
when we talk about observability.
so it gives us end-to-end request
journey within our application.
So suppose I have five APAs.
So the trace would help us to
identify which APAs performing slow,
or which a PA is actually broken.
Okay?
So it explains about where
the bottle is profiles.
So this will identify.
The resource level diagnostics, why my
system is slow, either it is, because
of CPU utilizations or maybe garbage,
corrections happening during that time.
So this profiling will help us to
identify the resource level diagnostics.
this is the, this slide explains
about a pictorial, way of, your
observability in the motor systems.
So here, you see the application could
be in public, cloud, and the on prime.
And we receive various, tele data.
So we call this melt, informs e for
events and for logs and D traces.
And this, these, collected metrics
would be pushed into observability
solution, which we are going
to, look in, future slides.
And different teams like developers,
monitoring ops, security ops would be
depending on the solution to identify
any issues and to resolve the problems.
Okay?
And this is, just overall
picture of how observability
will be in our, modern systems.
how can we collect these, metrics?
So there are two collection metrics,
actually push method and scrape method.
The push method is like
applications will actively send
the metrics to the collection
endpoint or TCP or UDP protocols.
in this picture you see the backend
services is, sending the metric
to, stats D. Stats D is in turn
sending, that particular metric to
graphite, which is a time database.
Scrape method is something where
applications expose metrics.
For collectors.
So basically, applications
won't push the data.
Instead the collection, services,
the data collectors would pull
the data from the applications.
Here in this example, pro
is actually scraping the
metrics from this application.
So basically we can say it's
actually pulling the data,
from the backend service.
So when can we choose scrape?
When can we choose push?
So choose scrape when, you're using,
Kubernetes or dynamic environments
and preferred, centralized, control
of your all the log management and
when apps can expose HT pinpoints.
Okay.
so basically, yeah, your apps has,
option to expose their end points.
Especially choose the scraping choose
push when apps are shortlived and the
real time metrics are required for us,
and apps run in restricted networks.
So in scrape method, the, the apps
that has HT p endpoint exposure,
yes, the script can be used, but
when apps are running within the
restrict networks and they have no
option to expose their endpoints.
So use the push method now.
we entered into, introduction
to Open Telemetry.
open Telemetry is a open source framework,
which standardizes generation collection
and management of, telemetry data.
It's A-C-N-C-F project.
Basically it's incubated under
Cloud NATO Computing Foundation.
So same foundation is actually
managing, Kubernetes as well.
The key benefits of Open Telemetry are
it's vendor neutral and it supports,
cross languages and multiple languages,
and it provides standardization of,
data collection and it covers a lot of,
metrics like.
Logs metrics, traces into, one framework
and let's, look at, the open architecture.
So the architecture of Work
Telemetry has these, main components.
Instrumentation, libraries, receivers,
collectors, processors, OTLP, protocol
and exporters, instrumentation libraries.
So these, will enhance applications to
generate the telemetry data so that the
application scan pump various metrics,
logs C to open telemetry, and then the
receivers are the ones which will collect
the telemetry data from various sources.
There could be applications as well.
Collectors, they receive a process
and export the tele data processes.
These processes will man plate
the data which was received and
they transform before actually
exporting them to backend services.
OT LB protocol.
It's a standardized protocol
for transforming and
transmitting the telemetry data.
Export, whatever the data that
has been mand and transformed by
processors, the data would be exported
to external observability backs,
open telemetry collector.
This is a very important,
component of open telemetry.
It is a centralized executable that
receives processes and exports.
Tele data to multiple targets,
protocol support.
It works with all the popular
open source, tele protocols.
It acts as an intermediate tree
between, the applications and
the backend, analysis tools.
And it reduces the, resource
consumption, centralize the
configurations, and it'll improve the.
Now we'll talk about,
collector components.
The components of the collector, the
receivers, processors, and exporters.
Receivers would be the entry points for
tele data and they accept various formats.
Processors, would be.
Manipulating the receive data by filtering
or enriching or sampling the data and
send it to the exporters and the exporters
would actually send the process data
back to the backend systems for analysis.
And there are two more components, are
part of optional components of collector.
Connectors, they facilitate the
connection or communication between
the pipelines and they transform,
different, signal types enable a
multi-stage processing flows, extensions.
Basically, they enrich the
component capabilities and
the performance analysis and.
This is a simple, a typical
collector pipeline could be.
So the receivers would be receiving
the data from various sources and
they send it to the processors, which
the process in turn will, transform
the data and send it to the exporters
and the pipeline can have multiple
receivers, multiple processes, and
multiple, exporters in a single pipeline.
And so we are talking about,
open Telemetry would receive the,
telemetry data from various sources.
So what are those data sources?
Typical data sources of, open telemetry
are application instrumentation.
Basically apps using the sdk.
So they send the telemetry data,
log CS metrics to, open telemetry.
So basically applications
are one of the data sources.
And the next ones could be service mesh.
So the traffic metrics and
traces from, the service.
But, mesh tools like SIO
are one of the data sources.
The next one could be node level metrics.
So data from, so this is from, Kubernetes.
the data coming from ATE about
the nodes and running pods
are also the data sources.
Kubernetes events, cluster events,
providing insights into system activities.
This is also one of the data source.
And the other, sources for, open
telemetry are logging demands.
Flu and fluent, which will
collect the data of the logs.
So basically they collect the logs from
the containers within the cluster and
they forward the logs to, open, telemetry.
And various metrics coming from cloud
providers like AWS and GCP and liveliness
and readiness, data, which is, which we
call probes and health checks that are
coming from, Kubernetes clusters and
the container, runtime data, like the
metrics about container, states and,
resource usage of those containers can
also be, sources for open telemetry.
And coming to the implementation
approach for open telemetry.
so there are two ways,
auto instrumentation and
manual instrumentation.
So automatic instrumentation, basically
it's a call, auto instrumentation,
like we can get started immediately for
the visibility of the, entire system.
And, it, it needs less, development
effort as it's a great start point for
the teams to get started to know about
telemetry and, implementation and when
it comes to manual instrumentation.
So here, it gives us more flexibility
to customize the metrics and it gives
us the precise control and we can
focus on business specific insights and
gives us flexibility as we discussed.
So it gives us, what we need and
why we need and when we need.
So the manual instrumentation,
all, it takes effort.
It gives us, the control
on what we want to see.
And this is, the entire,
full observability stack.
So start from the bottom
instrumentation, like adding the code.
like SDK to your application code,
and then the collection starts.
The data collection starts from Open
Telemetry, and then they have to be stored
somewhere in Prometheus, lowkey tempo.
These are different tools based
upon the type of the telemetry
data We'll see in the next slides.
And Grafana is, a dashboard
for visualization.
So this is the simple pyramid, which
explains the entire, observability
stack for any, application system.
Yeah.
typical observation, observability
stack components, like the collector,
like our, open telemetry collector.
Is like a, tracing
system, tracing collected.
So basically it is actually a
distributed, tracing system for a request.
so it explains us how that particular
request had the journey in our system.
Loki, it's like law aggregation
platform, for centralized
log management, Prometheus.
It's basically a storage.
Okay.
It's a time series database for metrics
collection and storage at the end.
Grafana.
so this is going to give a web UI for,
visualization, dashboards and alerting.
And the next slide.
so this slide actually is going
to give you a overall picture.
So this slide on the right side,
it explains so we have a VM
one and VM two, and the data is
actually coming from two VMs.
the fluent bit, if you see here, the
fluent bit is running on both VMs.
So basically it's a log corrector.
It sends the logs to the,
open telemetry collector.
The open tele to connector, would be
actually, collecting the logs, like
coming from and d and other metrics
coming from the VM two, like other
metrics, for example, for node metrics.
So node exporter would send
different metrics, so those
metrics would be sent to M Okay.
And, in the backend, the,
entire data would be.
Host into Grafana database, sorry,
into Grafana user interface.
So here, the applications only interact
with the open tele to correct it.
So they don't know.
In the backend there is, low key.
There is Mimi, there is Grafana.
So applications simply
interact with open telemetry.
but that's what they see in the backend.
Open telemetry collector.
Knows, okay, the log should
be sent to Loki and the
metrics should be sent to Mia.
So in this way, it reduces
a lot of complexity, for the
applications, to interact.
So integration is very less here.
it would be very faster and
easy, to implement, open
telemetry in the applications.
that's all, from my side.
And thank you for your time.
A.