Hey.
Hi.
This is, I like process of experience
into the data housing such as SSIS
tool Informatica Under, and also
having experience in the reporting
tools such as SRS Pyramid reporting.
Today I'm going to be, discuss our, the
serverless revolution, how the cloud-based
shared data integration is transforming
the enterprise data management.
Cloud-based data integration has image
as a transformative force in enterprise
data management revolutionized how our
nation handles the exceptional growth
of our data across the separate sources.
With a global data creation projected
to reach 1 75 gtz by 2025, companies
now struggle with integrating data from
an average of full disparate sources.
Organization implementing cloud
integration solutions reported
30 to 40% direction in the total
cost of ownership and up to 60%.
Four.
So inside competitor traditional
methods, unlike convention on
the six solutions, requiring
eight to 12 months of deployment.
Cloud integration for deployment times,
averaging just six to eight weeks while
providing significant uptime improvements.
Let me go to the slide.
So the paradigm shift in enterprise
data management, we have a
traditional integration on the cloud.
Integrations on-prem solutions dominated
80 by 88% of the entire enterprise
integration market in 2010 declining
to the approximately that 5% by 2022.
The systems present a significant
limitations with over 70% of organization
reporting scalability, constraints and
integration phase during the peak periods.
And coming to the cloud integration, if
you see here, like the cloud platform
supported workload variations of 2200,
300% with the without a performance
integration, organizations nowadays,
organizations are opting cloud integration
reports 70% direction in their primary
times, and 85% decrease in net related
incidents with the subsequent growth
projected and when coming to the cost
benefits of the cloud integration, if we
see here on the chart, like we have the
cost category on traditional integrations.
And the cloud integration
on the directions.
If you see the the interest
cost, traditional integrations
is a hundred percent.
And when it comes to the cloud
integration, it's 55.6 50 to 65,
and reduction is 35 point 35 to 45.
And coming to the maintenance in the
duration integration, it's 20 to 25.
And the cloud integration, it's
some to 10 and reductions is 62, 65.
When come into the development
that in duration integration,
it's a hundred percent.
Cloud integration for 2
2 16 and ion is 40 to 50.
And total cost of the ownership
it's traditional is a hundred,
and the cloud integration is 60
to 70, and election is 30 to 40.
Come, let's move to the initial slide.
So if you see here this this
are the evolution of the data
integration technologies.
So the first one is the
traditional ETL error.
So manually will process request an
average of 40 percent of 40 develop
per hours for integration on premises.
Solution dominated 80% on
integration market in 2010.
So when coming to the second
point, it's a transition period.
And the third point is the
cloud native integration.
And the fourth one is the feature
productions like back 1 25 or 80%
of the operation will add up to the
clause based integration platform
as a primary integration strategy.
Okay, so let me show the chart here.
If you look into the chart
here, the enterprise application
education market growth.
So if you look at like 2022, it's
25% and like 2024, it's like more
than near two 35% down 20, 26, et
cetera have grown to around 40%.
Year two and 2028, it's going
to be between 50% and 2030.
Expectations is like around
like more than 65 plus.
So let's move to the next slide.
Like if, here in the next slide we have
the leading cloud integration platforms.
So we have a different cloud integration
platforms such as a WS Q and the
Microsoft Azure Data Factory and the
Google Cloud data of a data flow.
This platform collectively control
over 70% of authentication platforms.
Are they continuity, evolving rapidly
with the numerous features releasing,
including emission learning based data.
Quality monitoring on the
automated all edge tracking.
So let me move on to the next steps slide.
So if you move to the next
slide, like here, like we have
the customer satisfaction with
the cloud integration platforms.
It see the a Ws view like it's 4.5 or
the five on the other data factories 4.3
and the Google cloud data flow is 4.4.
So let me move on to the next slide.
So if you come to the next slide, like
here we have several less architectures.
The new para, if you see the diagram
we have a automatics scaling.
So which hand the launch volume
regions and within the second cost
optimization development focus management.
And let me move on to the next slide.
If you see here, like we do have like
even driven integration benefits.
If you see here even reduction means
triggers based on the data changes or
schedule events on the automated process.
Authentication workflows without the
manual intervention and coming to
the real time analytics enables data.
Yeah, insights from the process.
Data and data ion upgrades flow through
the head pipeline within the minutes.
Let me move on to the next slide.
So if you see here, like in the
slide, like we have the financial
services sector implementations.
What are the integration
challenges on the cloud solution?
Challenges on them results achieved.
So this case demonstrates
the transformation potential
of cloud integration in a
highly regulated environments.
The majority of the financial
institutions implementing similar
solutions report enhanced analytical
capabilities with the dramatically
link decreased time to insight compared
to the previous premises systems.
If you see, if you go to
the next slide, like we have
healthcare sector implementations.
So the initial integration challenges
for the healthcare ethical sector and
the cloud integration approach, what they
follow and what are the transformation
achieve in this particular healthcare
sector on the ongoing benefits.
As a Highland reports, more than 80%
of healthcare products are implemented,
some type of the cloud service, such as
applications, infrastructure, or deferred
from services enabling sustainable
improvements in both operational
efficiency and quality of care.
Let me move on to the next slide.
We do have the manufacturing
sector implementations, I water
data collections and cloud
integration, predictive analytics,
and the operational improvements.
So like the multinational manufacturing
corporate implemented cloud based
integrations to transform their
operations through comprehensive
data collection analysis.
Let me move to the next slide.
We have the implementation success
factors, like the first one is
the phase migration approach.
And the second one is the hybrid
architecture during the transitions.
And the third one is the designed
data governance and the executive
sponsorship and the common success
pattern emerge from the cloud.
Integration across industries,
organizations that follow the
best practice of consistently
achieve better outcomes with the
fewer implementation challenges.
Let me move on to the next slide.
Like the feature of the
enterprise data management.
So if you see here, like AI integration,
machine learning algorithms, which
increase the automated data mapping
transformations and the quality
management reducing manual effort
while improve the accuracy and
duty change the data structures.
N let me move on to the next slide.
Multi-cloud integrations.
Organizations will increasingly
adopt to the integration statuses
that span multiple cloud products.
Last one is the real time, everything.
The ship, they the ship toward
the real time data process and
will accelerate for the batch.
Interesting approaches increasing,
replaced by the streaming architectures
that enables ate insights and
action based on current data.
To conclude like the cloud-based
data integrations represents a
fundamental transformation in.
How enterprise managers process and
the value of from their data assets.
As this technology continue to evolve,
they will increasingly become the
foundation upon the nation, build
their data strategies, enabling them
to harness the full potential of
their information as increasingly
data driven business landscape.
That's all about it.
If you have questions you can
ping me in the LinkedIn or
like you can reach me at Gmail.
Gmail.com.
Thanks for giving me this opportunity.