Hello everyone.
Welcome to the session.
I am Superman Maade.
Today we are going to talk about
observability in the cloud, especially
in the banking domain, how it
enhances the security and trust.
Let's explore how the observability
transforms security and compliance
in cloud-based banking systems.
We will go through some practical
frameworks, real world examples and
technical solutions for today's most
pressing financial technology challenges.
Let's begin with the landscape of banking.
It.
We have traditional infrastructures
where banks completely relied
on-premises data centers with the
full control or all the systems with
the recent changes in the cloud.
Organizations began moving selective
workloads to cloud providers while
maintaining critical systems in-house.
Still, this hybrid transition is somewhat
a better when compared to maintaining
the criticality at the in on-premises
and still leveraging the cloud solutions.
But there are for some modern
financial institutions.
Completely leveraging the
distributor, microservices, and
serverless architecture for agility.
The call services cloud native banking.
This is where we have this.
The need for advanced monitoring
across all the layers becomes
essential for the security and
the compliance that comes with the
observability first approach here.
Let's look at some of the challenges
in the banking, especially when
you're talking about the banks.
We have some financial institutions
face its very stringent compliance
requirements from the Basil 3G DPR,
and regional banking authorities.
This regulatory pressure is always there.
As the applications infrastructures are
changing their, the way they are built,
distributed architecture makes it very
complicated because it creates a complex
dependencies across the services, and
traditional monitoring cannot work here.
The surface is also very increasing
because the application landscape
is moving towards multiple cloud
providers and multiple regions.
We are increasing the surface of the
application and thereby we are seeing
the security complexity as well.
At the same time, the most important
the data, see where in the banks
must maintain a strict control or
where and how the customer financial
data flows and precise and forth.
We need to resolve all these
things in this modern architecture.
So how do we build this observability?
So what are the tools
that we have right now?
We collect a lot of information, the real
time quantable measurements like that
track the system performance, resource
utilization, and the customer transaction
volumes across the banking platform.
The applications that provides logs, a
comprehensive chronological records that
we see, a system of events, a system
of incidents and financial transactions
that provide a detailed audit address.
And we have addresses from end to end
visibility of transaction pathways
across the distribution, microservices,
capturing the dependencies,
latencies in the payment processing.
All these three will make this
observability, this robust observability
framework that ensures the complete
visibility into your banking
infrastructure, strengthening the
security posture, maintaining the
regulatory compliance, and identifying
potential issues before they impact the
customer experience or a data integrity.
Let's look at some of the benefits of the
cloud observability in security view, so
we can, we have an opportunity to find
out these suspicious patterns early.
We can identify these suspicions,
patterns, anomalies before
they become breach and with.
Quickly trace the sources, the
ability to make where the source and
the scope of the security instances
across the distribution systems.
We can reduce the
investigation time as well.
Visualize all the service connections
and potential vulnerability points, makes
it attack surface mapping easy so that
you can pinpoint where the problem is
there even after the incident, the post
incident of 4 0 6 make it very easy.
For because of this, maintaining
the comprehensive audit trials for
thorough security investigations
in the view of the compliance
and governance, let's take
some of the advantages.
We have a end-to-end monitoring across
all the banking infrastructures that
enables a complete transparency into
data flows and system interactions.
And we have a real time automated
compliance validations that
ensure the agendas to the bases.
3G DPR and local regulatory frameworks.
A flexible observative framework
allows the rapid real element to
evolving regulatory requirements
without system redesign.
Immutable audit trials and compliance
artifacts provide a comprehensive
evidence for regulatory examinations.
When you're talking about technical
terms, a technical framework, how we could
actually implement a cloud observability.
Here are the four steps we can say that.
The instrumentation, collection
and storage and analysis.
When it comes to the instrumentation, we
need to make our code more intelligent.
How do we do that?
Strategically integrate sophisticated
telemetry code through the critical
banking application and infrastructure
components for a comprehensive visibility.
This integration makes
the code intelligent.
NF two.
Give the sources and give the traces so
that we can trace them easily and identify
this observability, make it better.
How do we collect, not just
collecting it, we need to make
and normalize these metrics as
well also, but how do we do that?
Let's establish a robust.
A fault tolerant data pipeline
to efficiently gather anomal
is metrics, logs, traces from
various diverse banking systems.
We need to keep work on the storage
as well because the data differe
is very important at the bank.
So we need to deploy a
regulatory compliant, highly
secure data repositories.
With a granular retention policies
that satisfy both operational
and the compliance requirements.
Let's leverage and machine learning
algorithms for analysis to correlate
the data streams and detect the
security anomalies and identify
any performance opportunities.
Optimizations there
here.
We are just going through one of
the case study from a retail bank.
It's a real world example of
case where the challenge was
the payment processing system.
A breach went undetected.
There was a payment processing
system breach, and it went undetected
for 72 hours, is very critical,
but this could actually happen
with the traditional wandering.
So in this case, the bank has adopted
the implementing the distributor
tracing across cloud microservices
with anomaly detection, resulting
it to detect the any instances under
five minutes with a 99.8 accuracy.
So this has prevented almost mean 4.2
million in fraud losses, maintained
regulatory complaints at the same time.
Written on investment cloud observable.
Let's talk about some statistics
that we have received so far.
How did the instance reduction happening
after this observability implementation?
There are 62 percentage reduction, meaning
a very few security breaches and complex
violations when in a case of issue.
How fast we are responding back, the
response time has increased to 78% because
we know the complete infrastructure and
we can visualize where the and problem
is, we can increase the, that actually
saves the amount of savings at the
bank that roughly around $3.8 million.
In the audit purpose, okay.
We have a lot of documentation,
reduction in compliance.
Documentation effort is there because
we have a comprehensive analysis of the
logs, which is there, which is actually
making 41 percentage reduction in the
maintaining the documentation efforts that
actually increases the audit efficiency.
Let's look at some of the best
practices for a banking observable.
When you want to think, implement
the observability at the bank or
applications, we should see these
things in the beginning itself.
The build observable into
your architecture from the
beginning, not as afterthought.
We need to create this business
context of mapping the technical
metrics as to a banking business
outcomes and the customer experience.
We should be having that map ready.
Lot of a powered, and
our tools are available.
Let's leverage them, leverage the mission
learning, and to detect the anomalies
in the complex banking transactions.
At the same time, we should be
focusing on the cost management.
This implemented data sampling
strategies to balance this observability
needs with the cloud expenses.
And finally look at the next steps,
how the observability journey goes.
Let's start with the assessment.
If you wanted to implement this
observability at your end, these
are the steps you need to follow.
The first one is always
with the assessment.
Evaluate your current visibility gaps
across the cloud banking infrastructure.
Focus on high risk transaction paths
first, then do a pilot implementation.
Deploy observability tools in
one critical banking service.
Measure the security and
compliance improvements.
Let's roll out to the enterprise level.
Scaling it to the enterprise level is
next comes extend the AB observability
across all the banking systems integrated
with existing security operations.
We need to continue this journey.
The continu of continuation of
the optimization refine your
observability strategy as banking
technologies and threats evolve.
This is a repeated process.
We need to do that.
Thanks for your time.
If you have any questions if you
wanted to touch base with me,
please feel to connect with me.
I'm happy to help that.
Thank you so much for your time again.