Okay, so let's go right into the
presentation writing custom EVPF
programs for observability purposes.
What exactly is EVPF?
The extended Berkeley packet filter is an
evolution of the original BPF technology.
It extends the capabilities of BPF by.
Providing a more powerful and
flexible way to perform more features
like dynamic tracing, network
analysis, performance monitoring.
But mainly how it does this is by
providing a framework for you to
write kernel compatible sandbox.
Programs that can be executed directly in
your kernel space without modifying the
kernel code itself, or without running
a file of any security protocols, you
get a flexible tool you that you can
use to program observability control
or enhance your kernel behavior.
So looking here, we see the
architecture, basically the process
by which the EVPF program is created
and is loaded to the kernel space.
So basically you start with the C
source or like a c program EBPF program.
And then this program is converted
to by code before being, converted
to birth code by the compiler the
compiler before being attached into
the or loaded into the kernel space
and attached to either hooks or events
or system calls as the case may be.
So between between the
compiler and the loader page.
Verifier goes through your programs
to ensure that, okay, there are
no loops, there are no out of
memory or any security protocols.
And then this makes it a compatible,
a kind of compatible program
that can be executed as machine
code within the kernel space.
Why is E-B-P-F-A game
changer for observability?
It's because you get that flexibility,
you get that ability to basically
execute code within your NEL space.
This gives you nel level visibility,
something that you can use to
like able to get custom metrics
way before any user space.
Application might see it.
You get them like almost
immediately in run time.
As the operations are being
executed, you get that visibility.
You get no code instrument.
No, there's no code instrumentation
need, no manual instrumentation is
needed for you to get this visibility.
Because yeah, EPF is a clinical
compatible tool or technology.
Basically, it works for.
Most or any kernel version, and you do not
need to basically create or mess with your
security, the security of your kernel.
Also low overhead.
As we said earlier, everything gets
compiled or extended to machine code.
And all your scripts, however,
flexible, gets compiled into the machine
code that is executed at runtime at
the same time as your operations,
basically real world use cases.
So a lot of companies have used this tool.
A lot of companies have extended
this tool creating using it as a
foundation for tracing system calls,
network visibility, performance
profile lead, security monitoring.
And I linked in some examples from
Netflix, apple, basically what
they have done with this tool.
We have a demo with, I added
in a GitHub link, so if that
is useful to us, but let's see.
This is the GitHub link where the code
instructions on how to basically set your
environment to test the EVPF code as well.
U usually, or like for this particular
one, you just need an instance.
I'm going to be using, aWS instance,
prettier micro or, yeah, that, and that's
all I need to just test these two demos.
First, the packet log, which
would basically which would
basically get traffic packets
and log it in to a BPF map.
So let's just see how that works.
I have already done this already.
Put up the environment basically
so we can just test this.
Just basically sending in packets,
sending in traffic packets,
and then we'll see that this.
Has been a BPF map has been
generated for us in packet counters
and packet events, and we can be
able to see this particular ones.
This BPF map is accessible to
NEL space, but also accessible
to the user space as well.
It can be exported, it can be pushed
towards your, your observability
tools like Prometheus and Graph,
basically with user space tools.
But then for this particular
demo, we used C program,
the C program to basically pass the
packet information from our traffic.
Log that data into basic BPF map and with
the counter also to, to count to basically
generate metrics, just costal metrics
like a counter get the packet size.
Also put that in there as well.
So once you do this, once you
like put down your logic, your
EVPF logic, you then load it.
Like I said earlier, you compile it.
This is the compiling stage.
You compiled it, loaded it into this
interface, and then yeah, you could
immediately see that it has been loaded.
This is the packet of server.
And then we have tested it and seen that.
Okay, it.
The map has been created and been
stored in the kernel space where it
can be accessed by user space programs.
But then that is not the only
way to create or to utilize.
Your EBPF programs, you can create
native C-E-B-P-F programs, but there
are also extensions such as Python
extensions, go rust in BCC Cilium library.
And then I, this extensions offer,
like abstractions of the base code.
They help you basically do more.
With your EVPF programs
make it easier for you.
However, they also have their performance
cost, basically because you get more
delayed execution and a larger footprint.
We'll see this with our next demo
where we use the BCC BCC tool to,
create E an EVPF program in Python.
So this is the Python code.
You can see that BCC is imported
and then used in passing your
main VPF programming and logic.
And then that is now used to
initialize and process events.
Within the code instructions.
So this particular code traces first
we'll pull up an in JX web service
and then we'll add some files into it.
And then you can trace the access, you
can trace user access to those files.
Basically just login or.
Accessing the files and
generating metrics from that.
I have done all this installing
testing creating the HTML
files that we would then trace.
I've done all this in the
Ubuntu instance, so we just.
Start that up and then try and test it.
Let's go with the load test instead.
So the load test of our inject
web service in another terminal,
and then it's basically mixed
like a hundred requests to all.
Different pages and
then we can see it here.
The operations, this is our BPF program.
Basically reacting and basically
carrying out our program logic
for the a hundred requests.
That is that service receives
the program.
Logic is up to you.
You can.
Whatever you want to do
with that information.
Whatever you want to do with the
visibility or the access to the
visibility that you have, whether you
want to create custom metrics from
that, whether you want to export the
data directly to your observability
tools, your analysis tools, whether
you just want that information logged.
EBPF gives you the access.
And gives you the ability to program
your custom logic into the NEL space.
So we have seen two demos now.
One, using native c programming to
create, to create, eVPF program and
attach that to the kernel space.
Another using Python basically.
And then as we saw, we didn't need
to load or to attach manually the
Python BC, C program did that at
runtime for the Python execution.
Yeah.
So extending EVPF, like I said earlier,
you have either those custom metrics
or you have the BPPF the BP BPF map
basically with your data and you
can export this, you can, utilize
it with a user space application.
However you need for extending EVPF.
There's a wide range of tools.
Open Telemetry has one.
Promeus has one.
Grafana has one.
Basically all this based on EVPF and
utilizing this revolutionary technology
that gives you access to corner space.
For your observability tools,
your observability tooling.
So here we see a kind of ecosystem
map, basically looking at all the
projects, XD case that are available
to you for whatever use case you have
for observability and monitoring.
We have pixie.
Gimme a moment.
We have Pixie, which is a
Kubernetes observability tool.
Basically takes away the need for manual
instrumentation as it is based on EVPF.
You have Parker, which gives you
continuous system profiling Periscope,
another continuous profiling platform.
Deep Flow has automated
observability with tracing, and
you have network tools like Cilium.
Hopefully.
Which gives you like that networking
for your Kubernetes Kubernetes purposes.
There are also program management tools.
You have Leaf BPF man and
bleb, basically this ecosystem.
Your EBPF ecosystem is,
has a wide range of.
Variety of tolling, variety of management
and optimization tools that you can use
to better to better utilize and optimize
observability networking or security
across your across your infrastructure.
Here I linked in some, so more
learning docs, basically to see
more on how EVPF came to be on the
infrastructure of EPF, on basically
learning how to utilize EVPF more.
And then an article EVPF for Frank,
which basically goes through how how.
Startups or how companies take
giants like apple and Netflix
are using EBPF for their tools.
This is the end of my presentation.
The GitHub links slides as well,
will be made available to you.
So thank you very much for taking the
time to go through to this presentation.