Greetings, everyone.
Welcome to Con 42 Observability 2025.
My name is Ravin Kana, a senior
software engineer who focuses on
cloud native automation and large
scale data processing pipelines.
Our topic is adaptive parallelism
insights, which I'll ABB appreciate
as a PIX after this introduction.
A PIX combines Open standard Telemetry
with a compact graph neural network
so that an A WSD function workflow can
learn to tune itself while it's running.
By the end of this session, you
will understand three things.
First, how we capture branch level
data without rewriting business code.
Second, how a small model converts
that data into useful guidance.
And third, how a closed loop safely
applies the guidance to reduce.
Latency and cost while keeping
every decision auditable to begin,
serverless fan outs offer near
instant elasticity at three problems
surface as scale grows first.
Latency clips arise because a few slow
branches delay the entire workflow.
Even a single hotspot can push the
entire service level agreement.
Second, tracing gaps appear because
high level dashboards average a branch
specific anomalies, which means engineers
cannot pinpoint trouble quickly.
Third, cost spikes emerge
when hidden retries.
Cold starts infra the monthly
without obvious warning.
These pains led us to frame
three guiding questions.
Question one asked how to collect
fine-grained telemetry from every
branch while adding minimal overhead.
Question two considers whether a
lightweight artificial intelligence
model can digest that stream quickly
enough to make timely recommendations.
Question three asks.
How to apply those recommendations during
a live run without breaking confidence
limits or financial guard rates.
The rest of the talk answers each
questions inter contextually.
Many enterprise workloads such as data
enrichment, ETL, retries and compliance
reaction depend on the map state pattern
inside AWS Dev functions to fan out toss.
Limitations acknowledge the native
execution history application programming
interface shows only course events,
which hides branch behavior that matters.
Standardization helps because
open telemetry, the leading vendor
neutral format for traces, metrics,
and logs let us instrument once
and analyzed anywhere in parallel.
CloudWatch EMF Embedded metric
format adds structured counters
inside Lambda logs without agents.
Research to date often targets
virtual machine clusters with
reinforcement learning less.
Focus has landed on dynamic
state machine graphs.
Where topology changes every minute
opportunity identified graph neural
networks accelerate reasoning over
graphs whose notes and edges evolve
rapidly so they fit our fan out scenario.
A PIX therefore unites detailed
telemetry open standards, and a
compact graph neural network into one
practical flows loop control system.
The picture at right shows
the flow of data and control.
Starting at the top, the
instrumentation layer adds an
open telemetry span to every task.
Parallel and map branch spans a carry,
chunk ID and the same wrapper logs,
counters, such as payload by three.
Try count close, cold start time by
using CloudWatch embedded metric format.
Next, the telemetry pipeline since spans
over the open telemetry protocol to
a collector running on AWS four gate.
The collector passes real time streams
into Kinesis Data File Host, which
fuels live dashboards in Amazon
managed Grafana, and it also stores
raw records as Parquet files in Amazon.
Simple storage surveys for deep analysis.
Moving downward sales maker Serverless
hosts a two layer graph neural network.
With about 1.2 million
parameters every 60 seconds.
The model consumes the latest window
of branch metric and predicts an
ideal chunk size plus confidence and
projected cost and latency impact.
Even bridge then delivers third
influence inference to a Lambda callback.
The callback applies guardrail checks
and if they pass patches, the running
map state through the step function
update application programming interface.
Finally, governance is preserved because
each inference has hashed, stored in
systems managed parameter store, and
according into subsequent spans, giving
auditors a full lineage from decision
to outcome, automation must be safe.
So the controller enforce three
boundaries before any change.
First, the chink change window limits are
adjustment to 25% within five minutes.
Which prevents oscillation.
Second, the concurrency cap ensures
the new chunk size keeps total
lambda concurrency below the account
quota minus a safety buffer re
retrieved from parameter store.
Third, the rollback trigger
monitors 95th percentile latency and
total errors if both rise for two
consecutive windows, the controller
reverts to the prior Chang size.
Together these safeguards let the
model explore improvements while
guaranteeing that production stability
and cost limits remain intact.
We measure first because
insight depends on data quality.
Span emission adds about two
millisecond per invocation, negligible
overhead for data processing tasks
that often run for seconds after
capture the open telemetry collector.
Batches spans, pushes them to can
assist data file hose and writes
fully ity regards to Amazon.
S3 visualization follows where managed
Grafana converts those streams into
live heat maps highlighting slow or
throated branches within seconds.
Flexibility matters and because every
interference interface follows open
standards, teams can replace Grafana
with another dashboard or root.
Par K files into S3 for any
analytical platform or without
revising revisiting application code.
XP experience shows that this
separation accelerates debugging
and gives finance teams precise cost
attribution tied to trace identifiers.
Evaluation used three workloads.
Synthetic uniform contains 10 terabytes
of uniformly sized one megabyte ard.
Synthetic skewed SS also spans
10 terabytes, but injects 5%
larger records up to 10 megabytes.
Two fourth of slower processing
live enterprise entity data.
For example, like contractual
data represents three terabytes
of anonymized production updates.
Baseline compared were static
patching at 1000 items.
Dynamic sub three partitioning that
splits branches about two gigabytes
and a PIX adaptive chunking metrics.
Metrics tracked include 50th.
90th and 95th percentile latency
OB cost in United States dollars.
And throttle error
counts reading the table.
Adaptive chunking shows the lowest
latency across all the percentile and
the lowest cost for every workload.
For synthetic skewed throttle errors
drop from 47 under static patching
to F five under API X, demonstrating
resilience against uneven regard sizes.
Live Enterprise data follows the same
trend with active chunking, cutting
both dry tile latency and cost while
reducing throttles from 24 to three.
In summary, real time tuning
delivers consistent performance
gains and tangible cost savings.
Five lessons for anyone who wants to
replicate EPX first Sample generously
capturing every span during peak
windows, so retry storms are visible down
sample later to trim storage if needed.
Second, activate guardrails because
the 25% cap on chunk changes smooths
workload burst and prevents isolation.
Third connect costs.
Publishing dollar Deltas alongside
trace identifiers quickly gained
trust from finance stakeholders.
Fourth, inspect retry patterns since
high retry counts, often pinpoint hard
partitions or downstream rate limits.
Pair re try count with chunk identifiers
made those hotspot obvious Fifth.
Retrain weekly because as new
entity types enter production, the
graph neural network must adapt
to maintain prediction accuracy.
Collectively, these practices turn a
PIX from prototype into a production
service adapted by multiple teams.
Every study has limitations, cold
start, variability per persist.
Even with Snap start, residual
jitter can influence daily
latency and may exaggerate gains.
Synthetic bias is possible because
synthetic workloads, while realistic may
overlook extreme traffic patterns found
in the divide for future work will replay
full production traces to close that gap.
Model rate remains risk.
Shifting data distributions
can erode predictions quality.
So automated drift alerts
trigger retraining whenever
crosses a person threshold.
Recognizing these limits helps
others decide whether A PIX fits
their environment and guides our
roadmap for continued validation.
In closing, adaptive parallelism
insights turns detailed.
Telemetry into timely recommendations
that update step functions, workflow
safely benefited, delivered teams
gain faster executions, lower compute
bills, and complete audit trail
without changing business logic.
Next steps we intend to coordinate
turning across multiple workflows that
share concurrency limits and explore web
assembly based span features extraction
to reduce overhead even further.
Appreciation.
Thank you for your attention.
Your questions and feedback through
conference forums are welcome and I look
forward to hearing how you apply adaptive
observability in your own pipelines.
Thank you.