Good evening everyone.
I'm Bra Haredi Ham, a developer with
the Department of Veterans Office.
Today I'm excited to share
how advanced Observability is
transforming healthcare IT system.
In the next 15 minutes, we'll explore
why observability is the backbone
of resilient distributed healthcare
systems, diving into challenges,
solutions, and real world impacts.
Let's get started.
Healthcare depends on complex,
interconnected IT systems, but 73% of
the organization lack comprehensive
visibility into these distributed systems.
These visibility gaps can lead to
delays or disruptions in patient care.
For example this chart shows how
73% of healthcare organizations
struggle with the system.
Blind sport
Advanced Observative framework
address this by reducing the
meantime of the resolution by 84%.
This means issues are identified and
fixed faster, minimizing patient impact.
Additionally.
Integrated distributed tracing
with the clinical workflow, cut
troubleshooting time by 67%, allowing
IT teams to focus on proactive care.
This graph highlights the
dramatic drop in resolution time.
Let's compare traditional monitoring
with the advanced observability
and see why this shift is critical.
Traditional monitoring in healthcare
often relies on basic system level
metrics like CP usage without context.
This leads to fragmented visibility,
reactive troubleshooting, and no
correlation with the clinical workflows.
For instance, a system crash might only
be noticed after it delays patient care.
In contrast, advanced Observability
provides end-to-end visibility
across care pathways, unified tracing
of patient journeys and proactive
analytics to prevent disruptions.
It directly links system health
to patient outcomes, ensuring
it issues don't compromise care.
This dashboard shows how observability
integrate metrics for real-time insights.
This is a shift in game changer
for healthcare reliability.
Healthcare observability is
not just about tech, it's about
patient safety and compliance.
First, we need HIPAA and GDPR
complaints, monitoring and encryption,
audit trials, and role-based
access to productions, to data.
Second, analytics musing technical metrics
to critical outcomes so we can prioritize
issues that affect patient directly.
For example, a CS slow system could
delay critical care and observability.
Help us catch that in real time.
Here is an example of HIPA
compliance monitoring interface.
Finally, high availability
is non-negotiable.
We need fault tolerance system with 99.99%
up, down, and automated failover to ensure
critical visibility even during outages.
This requirement to ensure observability
support life critical systems.
Let's look at the real world example
of how this principle were applied
in one critical care scenario.
Unpredicted system latency across
interconnected services was slowing
responses times putting patients at risk.
To address this, we
implemented end to end.
Distributed tracing with custom
in infrastructure across all
clinic service boundaries.
As a result, a 67% reduction in
troubleshooting time, allowing
us to resolve issues before they
escalated to clinical disruptions.
This means faster, safer care delivery.
This graph shows the drop in
troubleshooting time post implementation.
This case study shows how observability
directly improves patient outcomes.
Next, let's see how observability
performs under pressure.
Like during p peak load,
during high traffic period peak time
volumes systems are under immense strain.
Our data shows system reliability
dropping by 75% at peak load
without proper observability.
This chart shows the reliability
dipping as patient volume spikes.
By implementing advanced telemetry
collections, we achieved a 58%
improvement in system reliability.
During this period, real-time adjustment
based on observability data prevented
service degradation, ensuring critical
healthcare operations continue smoothly.
This highlights how observability
maintains stability when it matters most.
Now let's explore how
AI is revolutionizing
observability in healthcare.
AIOps is transforming
healthcare observability first.
Predictive analysis can anticipate system
failures 24 to 48 hours in advance with
the 93% accuracy, allowing proactive
fixes before patient care is implemented.
This model predict failure
with high accuracy.
Yes.
Second intelligent filter reduces false
post to alarms by 71%, focusing IT
teams on clinically significant issues.
Finally, automated remediation
enable self-healing system resolving
complex issues in minutes and
cutting it interventions by 64%.
This dashboard prioritize critical
alerts AIOps, make observability
smarter and more efficient.
Let's see how HBase
observability takes this further.
HBase observability brings monitoring
close to the point of care.
It reduces latency by 83%, enable
critical distance in milliseconds.
It also ensure continuous monitoring
during network disruptions vital
for unrepped uninterrupted care.
This shows age monitoring in action.
Additionally, local data processing
enhance privacy complaints by
handling since two data at the source.
Finally, real time anomaly detection
at the point of care lets clinicians
address issues before the affect patients.
So how do we implement this?
Let's look at the strategy.
Implementing observability
requires a structured approach.
First assessment.
For assessment, it requires audit
existing systems, identify gaps
in clinical workflows, and define
healthcare specific requirements.
Next, implementation.
Deploying distributor pricing,
integrate metric logs, and
traces into unified platform and
ensure HIP and GDR compliance.
This workflow outlines
our implementation steps.
Finally, adoption train clinical and
IT staff foster a data driven culture
and build a cross functional responses.
Teams this strategy ensure observability
aligned with the patient care priorities.
Let's see how these components
fit into a broader framework.
Our healthcare observability framework
has three layers, the technical metrics
layer, monitoring infrastructure
applications, and the network with
the healthcare specific threshold For
critical care, the business impact layer
correlate system performance with patient
outcomes, optimizing treatment, timing.
The compliance layer ensure
continuous HIPAA and GDPR
complaints with automated reporting.
Let's wrap up with the key take ofs
to summarize advance observability,
reduce meantime to resolution by 84%
and boost system reliability by 76%
directly improving clinical outcomes.
It must be a core architecture
principle, not an afterthought.
We need to link technical metrics
to patient care and design solutions
with the compliance first, by
providing observability, we built
resilient systems that save time.
Thank you for your attention.
Observability is the backbone of
a reliable healthcare system, and
I hope this presentation showed
a transformative potential.
Thank you.