Hello everyone.
Welcome to Comp 42 20 25.
My name is Webpa and today I'll
walk you through how retrieval
augmented generation, also known
as drag, offers a huge improvement
over conventional chatbots and
the enterprise support domain,
especially when it comes to accuracy,
scalability, and knowledge integration.
We'll first understand how like
traditional chat botts work traditional
chatbots even the more modern ones that
use intent classification or basic NLP
rely on static knowledge and like hardcode
hardcoded flows or pre-train models with
limited ability to adapt they're built
using rule-based systems that scales
poorly and can easily break on edge cases.
They're trained on like a snapshot of
data, which becomes absolute very quickly.
And the session state management is often
brittle or non-existent making multi-tone
context attention weak or absent.
So in other words, none of these scale.
In real world customer service
environment where like data is.
Continuously evolving and there
are diverse user queries every day.
As a result this causes
a maintenance overhead.
You need to manually update
knowledge bases continuously.
And there is a risk of hallucination
when the model doesn't know the
answer, but still guesses it.
And the most critical one, like the
system can't handle novel or low frequency
queries because they're explicitly
encoded in the training set or a dialog
tree which creates a feedback loop.
Loop of high operational
overhead and poor user trust.
Here comes rag in the picture and rag
shifts the paradigm by introducing
real time document retrieval as
the very first step to response
generation in the chat bots.
The first step involves understanding
the query the user has asked, or using
advanced transformers with semantic.
Later the query is embedded via bird or
sentence transformers then matched against
a vector store like F-A-I-S-S or pine Cone
or Westpa to retrieve the top K passages.
And once those latest information
is retrieved this data is fed
into the prompt for language model
enabling like a grounded generation.
And in case if the data updates
are detected in any of those while
receiving any of these data, the delta
of those information gets in text
automatically and gets made and is then
made available in the next retrieval
cycle and saving the efforts on fine
tuning the models again and again.
Along with that like traditional
bots typically fail at handling
composite or like multi intent
queries due to linear dial up flows
and like limited memory as well.
Rag in the situation introduces
a multi-stage reasoning.
So the way it works is like the
complex inputs are passed into smaller
structured sub-questions into using
semantic and syntactic segmentations.
And then each component is
independently and individually
queried against the vector store.
The system then can pull from multiple
domains or knowledge clusters, and then
the retrieve snippets are fused using
either concatenation or specialized
summarization layer fusion in decoder.
Then the language model generates a
comprehensive, unified answer that
covers all parts of the inputs.
Something like, which is very difficult
to achieve with a traditional bot.
Later.
Due to all this applications prag
is able to achieve a higher accuracy
over traditional chat bots and LLM
models because of its ability to
ground responses with real data.
The language model is conditioned
on retrieved documents.
So the outputs are based on actual
enterprise knowledge and not the
parametric memory or like the
stale memory, which is out of date.
And in this situation, if let's say the
relevant documents for some outage or
downtime aren't retrieved the system
can return, fall to fallback messages or
uncertainty signals instead of guessing,
improving the trust and transparency.
Along with that rag systems can estimate
confidence based on retrieval scores and
response entropy, enabling you to set
threshold enabling you to set thresholds.
And escalate uncertain responses or ask
clarifying questions in situations when
the model is not able to, or if the
estimate con if the estimated confidence
level is below the set threshold.
Apart from like the ask accuracy
aspect of the rag, rag based system,
the other very big benefit that rag
based chatbot brings in improving
the user experience that it can.
We augmented with session level memory,
with using embeddings or key value stores.
So basically what it can do is then it
can track user intent, slot fills, and
previous interactions to maintain context
even across like multi tone conversations.
This in turn results
and dramatically more.
Coherent dialogue flows and like
higher task completion rates.
He elevating the user's experience apart
from this in a domain of customer support.
Even like the advanced automation
there will be a point when some
conversation needs escalations.
And in this situation, having an
AI agent that is able to store
context and intent and intent.
In those situations, the handoff to
human agents helps in bringing the
human agent up to the speed of the
issue very quickly because the rag
based system has all the context
and intents already stored in there.
Its database.
So with RAG, we can achieve like a
structured handoff to the human agents
through delivering a package with.
History retrieved document
and generated responses.
An agent no longer needs to ask questions
again and again or dig for background.
They get full context, including
the intent chain and prior decision
points so that they are already up to
the speed with the customer's issue.
This in turn reduces average
handling time for a of a customer
and improves both agent satisfaction
and first time resolution.
Rates.
For, from a design view these
all can be easily integrated with
any of the CRM applications that
any organization is using for the
support operations in their company.
And so in, in order to make sure your, a
rag based bot is up to date with all the
knowledge and all the latest information.
And this is all because like in
a live system document, in the
knowledge base are bound to change.
So in order to make sure your rag
based chat bot is always up to date
we need to establish a continuous
knowledge update pipelines.
So as soon as like content, like policy,
document or support articles is updated.
In the source systems like Confluence
or any of the CMS, system that the
company is using, it needs to get
ingested and queued for reprocessing.
And once that happens, a background
job should vectorize these content
using embedding models like BGE mini,
LM, et cetera, and then update the
semantic index in a vector database
like F-I-A-F-A-I-S-S or any of the
corresponding data vector databases.
Later.
So what this does is like later,
whenever a user query comes in, the
retriever immediately surfaces the
latest relevant content, ensuring
the response reflects the current
state without any model fine tuning.
And the generator model conditions its
output on the updated context, enabling
it to answer questions about the new
feature poli or any of the policy
changes or known issue on the same
day the document subject was changed.
So the response will always be with
respect to the latest updated data.
So all this is works fine in the
ideal world but in order to have
like a performance or like a well
running rag based chat bot we need to
have a quality data knowledge base.
Because racks performance, I would
say is directly tied to the quality
of the knowledge base you have.
So in other words, this is a situation
of where like you put in garbage
and you will get a garbage out.
So in order to make sure like that
doesn't happen sorry that doesn't happen.
We need to make sure all the
redundant data or near duplicate
documents or contents are
removed from the content base.
And other ways we can do is like
normalizing conflicting entries.
That can in some way con confuse the
retrieval mechanism as well as the
LLM models in generating response.
There should be a structured KB
using clear topical taxonomy with
fallback links in situation if
the content is not available.
Along with that, like there should be
metadata tagging for all the content
so that it's easily available for
filtering and at the time of retrie.
So this is like a high level
information about like the technical
technology stacks involved in
each layer of rag based chat bot.
For knowledge base.
There should be proper document
vectorization and metadata
tagging for easy retrieval.
The retrieval systems should be
should be equipped with vector
databases and semantic search
for the models to easily select.
Then the language model can be any of the
l LMS that are out in there in the market
for actually generating the responses.
And the last piece is the security which
is the most crucial one because, even
after the retrievals there should be
one layer of access controls and query
filtering that should be in place to
make sure there is no data breach and
an un unauthorized data does not get
sent or gets displayed to the customers.
So now coming to the future avenues of
rad based chat bots since it's context
awareness and and working with real
time data, it has opened door to a very
hyper-personalized and behavior aware.
Support experience.
Customers there can be customer
specific retrieval, basically
segmenting vector indexes per
customer profile or organization.
Along with that it can also detect
anomalies and usage logs because and
these logs can be readily made available
to these, to these chat bots so that
it can predict some sort of outage.
And then proactively surface health.
This is one of the use cases
we are currently working on.
And our goal is to achieve
a state where we detect an
outage even before it happens.
Along with that since the models are
connected with live data even if, let's
say a bot has been trained or has been
embedded with one language, since it's it
can always retrieve new information it is
possible to have the bot respond in any
other language as per the user's need,
which makes it perfect for a organization
which has a global presence and has
customer base spread across the growth.
And along with this, the next
evolution in multimodal rag where
inputs and and retrieve content
are just not limited to text.
Some of the emerging capabilities
currently we have is the
visual search and retrieval.
Basically customer uploads an image
and then the rag model tries to find
a match against the corresponding
visual kbs example, like a photo of
damaged product a error screenshot
that the customer just uploaded.
And based on that, it is able to
troubleshoot and based on that, the
chat bot is able to troubleshoot
what the customer issue is.
Apart from that retrieving instructional
videos based on any text that customer
provided so that it can provide more
helpful information or resources to
the customer to solve their issues.
And later it could be like a fusion
of both text and video and vice versa.
That, can be implemented with the
rag based chat bots architecturally
and technically these for us to
for us to enable these features we
need to have some sort of vision.
ENC coders.
Example I think clip and blip two
are some of the widely used encoders
that out there in the market.
And some sort of cross model retrievers.
Which will for sure help in expanding
the use cases for Rag Beyond Text.
Now here are some stats that we
collected that shows a tangible
improvement in customer support
operations across multiple KPIs.
These have directly impacted operational
efficiency and customer satisfaction.
These efficiency gains stem primarily
from improved first contract resolution,
as you can see, has a number of
around 75 to 85% compared to 45 to 55.
And also the reduced need of
clarification exchange is another
thing that has proven that the rag
based model has been tremendously
very helpful in enhancing the user's
experience while trying to find support.
To wrap up the evolution for traditional
AI chat bots to rag powered system
reference represents a transform,
transformative advancement and
the customer support technology.
Since it enables like grounded real time
answer that scales with knowledge changes.
So the customers are always, given
like the latest information it reduces
the retraining cycles and lowers the
operational overhead, which saves
any enterprise organizations a lot of
money context continuity, even across
long interaction so that customers
don't get irritated in explaining
the same things again and again.
And, the use cases are still like,
since it's an evolving technology,
there are many more room for
more evolution in this domain.
So thank you so much
everyone for your time.
I'll be happy to answer any question
regarding RAG and how it can be used
to improve customer support operations.
Thank you.