Hello everyone.
I'm Chidi and I'm here to talk
about something that's haunted.
Many data teams like broken dashboards
that look fine, but silently lie.
In this talk, I will walk you through
our journey from those chaotic moments
to building a mature observability
framework for data quality assurance.
This isn't just about testing, it's
all about regaining trust in our data.
By building an observability QA culture
problem statement, our dashboards
looked polished, but under the hood
we have the data issues like silent
pipeline failures and schema drift,
which leads to misleading KPIs.
By the time stakeholders flagged
inconsistencies, it was often too late.
This created confusion, delayed decisions.
And Erod a trust in analytics.
Shiny dashboards, shaky truth.
We had sleek analytic dashboards that
suddenly began giving incorrect insights.
What you see isn't always what you get.
Our data looked fine on the surface,
but was rotten underneath leading
to bad decisions and lost trust.
There were hidden data issues.
Undetected schema changes and
silent pipeline failures introduced
errors into these metrics.
These issues were hidden behind the
scenes with no immediate visible signs.
By the time someone noticed
damage was already done, and
the last is eroding trust.
Stakeholders grew vary of the data.
Once a dashboard tells a lie,
every report becomes a suspect.
Data teams morale clenched.
As more time went into fight
fighting than delivering value.
In fact, industry surveys show
data downtime, which can consume
over 30% of their data teams time
and erode confidence in analytics.
And here comes see real production pain
points, delayed detection and firefights.
Because issues weren't quarterly,
we often operated in reactive mode
by discovering errors only when a
stakeholder raised a concern, this
meant frantic late night troubleshooting
sessions fixed on the fly patches
and data fire drills that burned out.
The team eventually brittle
validations at scale.
The few data quality rules we had
would often break whenever data volume
spiked or new fields were added.
They weren't scalable at all.
Writing exhaustive tests for thousands
of data assets was impractical
with a traditional approach.
The result, blind spots where
bad data could slip in unchecked,
silent pipeline failures.
In some cases, jobs failed or only
partially succeeded without load errors.
Data stopped updating our certain
records didn't load, and we didn't
find out until days later when
someone noticed a bi bizarre trend.
And then next comes POO test coverage.
Our existing data checks were minimal
and brittle, so we might test a couple
of critical tables or use basic QA
scripts, but many assumptions went
untested with hundreds of tables.
We simply didn't cover everything.
And the last is undetected schema drift.
Small upstream changes like a
renamed column or change data
format broke our data silently.
Pipelines kept running, but
key fields got misaligned.
We had no immediate alerts for schema
changes, so reports quietly went wrong.
Moving on to wide traditional qf,
failed pipeline, not equal to software.
Traditionally, data QF was
treated as a one-time checkbox.
We would often test queries or ETLs during
development and assume if the pipeline
ran without error, the data must be fine.
Unlike application qa, there is
little continuous testing once a
code has been moved into production,
but that's a grail mistake.
Incomplete testing data is fluid and
evolving, but our tests were static.
We checked a few sample outputs
or verified logic on day one,
but as data changed over months,
those tests didn't adapt.
We lacked coverage for new
edge cases and evolving data
patterns not built for scale.
Maintain data quality by
manually scripting tests for
every table was unsustainable.
If you have thousand plus tables,
writing even five simple checks per table
means thousands of tasks to code and
update, which is clearly unrealistic.
Traditional QA approaches buckled
under the volume and complexity of
modern data QA processes in silos.
Our QA happened mostly before
deployment, separated from monitoring.
Once pipelines were live, there was a gap.
We had no built-in feedback
loop from production.
Data behavior.
Back to qa.
The first indicator of trouble was often
a user complaint that read it Monday, 8:00
AM Slack message about the broken data.
In practice, a lot of QA relied on manual
checks, eyeballing a report, or running
a SQL snippet to spot check the results.
This doesn't scale our cat settle issues
because human eyeballs can't watch
thousands of metrics in real time.
In summary, our old QA approach
was too shallow and too slow.
It failed to catch the very issues that
mattered because it wasn't continuous
automated or intelligent enough.
We needed a new start.
Moving on to Pvo two observability,
talking about the light bulb movement.
Our turning point was realizing
that we had to treat the data
pipelines like production
software in software engineering.
You wouldn't deploy an app
without monitoring and logging.
Why were we running data
systems in the dark?
This lead us to adopt observability
principles for data qa.
But what actually is observability?
It's our ability to fully understand
what's happening inside a system by
looking at its outputs, be it logs,
metrics, and traces in a data context.
Observability means instrumenting
pipelines, so we can monitor data health
end to end instead of assuming the
data is fine, we actively watch for.
Signs of trouble.
And in the new approach, we treat
data as a code where we began adding
telemetry everywhere, logging each
stage of the ETL, measuring row counts
and crossing times and tracing data
flows from source to the dashboard.
Now, when something went
wrong, it wouldn't be silent.
We would have breadcrumbs to follow.
And the real time alerts where
observability lettuce detect failures
and anomalies before users do.
For example, we set up automated alerts
for when a daily load dint run, or when a
metric deviated beyond the normal range.
No more waiting weeks
to discard a problem.
The system would tell us as an
article, put it without observability.
You're essentially blind to the data
failures, proactive QA via monitoring.
This P vote was essentially
blending QA with operations.
Instead of QA being a one-off gate, it
became an ongoing process of monitoring
data quality in the production.
Our data quality checks now ran
continuously, and any violation
triggered the same kind of response
as a site outage would be in DevOps.
We moved from firefighting to
early detection and prevention.
Now the key principles of observability
in data qa, we added pervasive visibility
to instrument everything, be it locks,
metrics, traces, every pipeline step.
Now emits locks and metrics, which
are quantitative measures like row
counts, latencies, or error dates.
We also implemented tracing to
track data flow across services.
These three pillars, locks,
metrics, and traces are the
foundation of observability.
They let us ask what's happening
inside our data pipelines
at any given point in time?
Fail fast.
Fail safe.
Finally, we embraced a philosophy
from software testing Fail fast.
If the data is bad, better to stop
the pipeline or flag it immediately
than to quietly push 40 data onward.
By halting and errors and
rerouting to a recovery process.
We prevent bad data
from polluting reports.
In practice, this meant designating
certain tests as critical.
If they fail, they stop the line and
alert preventing the downstream harm.
Data lineage and impact analysis.
A key principle we adopted is
maintaining data lineage visibility.
Lineage is a map of how data
flows from source to the target.
When a problem arises in a data
set, lineage tells us what upstream
source might have caused it and which
downstream reports might be affected.
This is critical for rapid root
cause analysis and for deciding
who needs to be involved.
We built lineage tracking so that
no data issue remains a mystery as
we can trace it across the pipeline.
Data quality checks as code.
We embedded automated tests directly
into our pipelines using tools
like DBT or great expectations.
We define the expectations.
Example, no one else in critical columns.
And the transaction amount should
be between dollar and $10,000
that run whenever data is updated.
If data violates an expectation,
the pipeline can fail fast rather
than propagate the bad data.
QA isn't a separate fees anymore.
It's baked into each data transformation.
Continuous monitoring of the data health.
We monitor key data, health
indicators 24 by seven.
This includes freshness.
Like, is data up to date the volume?
Did we get all the records or
some are missing distribution.
Our values within the normal
ranges and schema changes.
Did someone add or remove a column?
By tracking these, we catch anomalies
like sudden drops in row counts or
unexpected null spikes immediately.
Alerting and incident response.
Observability isn't just about passive
monitoring, it's active alerting.
We configured threshold based and
anomaly based alerts that pays
the team when something goes off.
For instance, if a daily sales table
usually has a hundred K rows and
today has zero and alert fires, if an
ETL job doesn't run by its scheduled
time, we get notified this way.
Data issues trigger a response, just
like application downtime would.
Our goal is to be the first to know
about the data issues, not at the last.
Moving on to the tools and techniques,
used, great expectations, csar go-to
framework for the data validation.
Great.
Expectations let's us define the
expectations about our data, like
constraints or quality rules.
In a read WA, we implemented great
expectation checkpoints in our pipelines.
Say for example, after data load, we
automatically verify the row counts.
Valid ranges, NU percentages.
This catches bad data pretty much
early rather than at the latest stage.
And the next is DBT, the data build tool.
We leverage DBT not only for
transforming data, but also
for its testing capabilities.
DBT allows SQ SQL tests on your models.
We wrote tests to ensure dimension
tables aren't missing keys, or that
reference data matches expected values.
DBTs integration with version control
meant our data tests are code reviewed and
versioned, just like our transformations.
It promotes the philosophy of
treating data pipeline code with
the same rigor as application code.
And the next is open telemetry.
We instrumented our custom data
pipeline code with open telemetry
for unified tracing and metrics.
Open telemetry is an open standard
for collecting telemetry data.
By using it, we could export
pipeline runtime metrics, like
how long each stage took, how
many records have been processed.
And distributed traces that followed a
data record from injection to output.
This was huge for debugging.
If a job was slow or failed, we could
trace exactly where it has happened.
And for monitoring and visualization,
we use Prometheus and Grafana.
All those metrics and
locks had to go somewhere.
We set up Prometheus to scrape
and store pipeline metrics
like row counts durations.
Or error counts and Grafana dashboards
to visualize them in real time.
Our Grafana dashboards became our data
pipeline control center showing the health
of each data flow at a glance green.
If all good, ready anomalies, for
example, we have chats for daily record
counts per table with alert thresholds
if they deviate from historical norms.
Our new process can be visualized
as a pipeline with built-in quality
gates and monitoring at every step.
Here is a high level architecture,
data sources, and ingestion.
Data flows in from various sources,
be databases, APIs, or files.
As it's ingested, we
generate logs and metrics.
Example, source record counts,
staging and validation checks.
In staging areas, we run great
expectation suites On raw data.
Example, check that all expected
columns are present and values.
Make sense?
If a critical expectation fails.
Say a primary key column, nus.
We flag it immediately and
hold processing for that.
Moving on to transformation
and linear tracking.
As data moves through transformation jobs,
be it ETL or ELT, EJA is instrumented
with tracing via open telemetry.
We propagate a trace ID so that all events
for a particular pipeline run are being
linked at key transformation points.
We include assertion tests via
DBT tests or custom scripts
to ensure business rules hold.
For example, after joining
tables with test, that row
counts didn't unexpectedly drop.
We also log metadata about schema
versions and data statistics at
each step, monitoring and alerting.
All pipelines push their
metrics to a monitoring system.
For instance, after each load, a
pipeline sends the row count and
execution duration metrics to promeus.
Similarly, any warnings or errors
are locked our central log index with
context, say for example, pipeline
name or the data asset affected.
This layer acts an observability
hub aggregating signals
from all the pipelines.
BI layer and dashboards, the
transform data lands in our warehouse.
Example, BigQuery.
Even here, we leverage
built-in auditing features.
For example, using BigQuery information
schema to detect if any schema changes
occurred or the number of bytes
processed by each query, feeding
those stats back into our monitor.
When the BA dashboard finally queries
this data, we have confidence that it
passed all previous quality checks.
The output dashboards now
have an implicit trust score.
If a dashboard is live, it means
all the upstream data quality tests
have been passed and no anomalies
were detected in the pipeline.
If something was wrong, either the data
never made it here, or the dashboard
is showing an alert annotation.
We also built features to annotate
reports if upstream data is
stale or under investigation.
Lessons learned and best
practices, trust, but verify.
We learned that assuming data
is correct is very dangerous.
Even if a pipeline doesn't
crash, the data can be wrong.
Now our motto is trust but
verify always at every step.
Build verification into your process
so you are never blindly trusting
a perfect looking dashboard.
Observability is a team sport.
Getting to observability maturity
wasn't just a tech implementation,
it was a cultural shift.
We aligned data engineers, Q analysts,
and even analysis on the idea that data
qualities everyone's responsibility.
I. Sharing observability dashboards
with a wider team helped everyone
rally around the data trust.
Start with your pain points.
We didn't implement everything overnight.
We targeted the worst pain points.
First example, a critical dashboard that
kept breaking or a frequently changing
source schema and put observability there.
This yielded quick wins
that built momentum.
For instance, catching a major
schema change in real time prevented
a KPA outage immediately proving
the value of this approach.
The best practice is to iteratively build
your observability, focusing on areas of
highest risk, automate and standardize.
Humans can scale to check hundreds
of tables daily, but machine
scan, we invested in automation
for testing and monitoring.
Okay.
Templates and frameworks like
reusable Great Expectation
Suites and DBT test macros.
That helped standardize RQA.
This way, every new data sets get, say
based on quality checklist out of the box.
Standardization also
means clear expectations.
Everyone knows what past QA
means in measurable terms.
Three data incidents like software
incidents, a big lesson respond to
data problems with the same urgency
and process as application outages.
That means having oncall rotations,
incident tracking, root cause
analysis, and preventative follow-ups.
For us, this led to systematic fixes.
Example, after a data incident, we
would add a new test or improving
monitoring to prevent a repeat.
Over time, this proactive
stance greatly reduce the fight.
Fighting observability is
not a one and done project.
We continuously refine
our checks and alerts.
We review false alarms to
adjust thresholds and analyze
misses to add new tasks.
Our data and systems evolve, so our
observability must evolve to you.
One best practice is to hold regular
data quality review meetings.
To reliability review meetings
to assess what's working and what
isn't in our observability setup.
Finally, we made it to a point to
celebrate when our system catches issues.
Every prevented bad dashboard or
saved hours of troubleshooting is a
win for the team and the business.
This positive reinforcement kept
the team motivated to maintain
a high bar for the data quality.
It also helped in getting buy-in
from the leadership to continue
investing in data observability.
Nothing speaks louder than
prevented crisis and call to action.
Assess your data QA today.
Take a hard look at your
current data quality processes.
Are you catching issues early or are you
relying on end users to spa the mistakes?
Identify one nightmare
scenario in our organizations.
Be it a dashboard that broke or a
critical pipeline that failed silently.
That's your candidate
for an observ makeover.
Embed and embrace observability
if you haven't already.
Start instrumenting your data pipelines.
Even simple steps can pay off enabling
logging if, if it's not on set up.
The basic alerts for data
freshness or volume changes.
Write a few great expectation
tasks for a key table.
Treat your data pipelines with
the same care as live products.
Remember, data is a new software.
It deserves the same level of monitoring
and qa, and leverage the available tools.
You don't have to build
everything from scratch.
Open source tools and
frameworks are at your disposal.
Try out great expectations to
kickstart your data testing.
Use your existing a PM monitoring
tools or cloud monitoring
tool, track pipeline jobs.
Explore what your data warehouse offers.
Many have information schema tables
or built-in logging you can tap
into The ecosystem is pretty rich.
Pick a pain point and
apply a tool to address it.
Make it a team effort.
Encourage a culture where data quality
is part of the definition of done.
Involve QA engineers in
pipeline design and involve data
engineers in quality monitoring.
Perhaps create a data observ
task force, RNA Pilot project.
Share the improvements and
insights with stakeholders.
When people see more relatable
dashboards, they'll become
advocates for this approach.
Thank you for giving me this opportunity.
I.