Everyone, thanks for joining.
My name is Der Hoja and
I'm a DevOps lead in IBM.
So today I'm gonna talk about unwilling
the power of observability using
fluent be in a WS E case environment.
So as part of this topic, the
we are going to talk about.
The power of observability
in our daily life.
So as the cloud applications scale
across the cluster guiding gaining
visibility into into our cloud
environment becomes extremely difficult
as the application loads scale.
And when the application complexity
increases because of the scalability.
It is getting very difficult
to get into the of.
Of the application.
So it is so in the session, like we will
unveil how to harness the true power of
possibility in our a WC case environment
using fuel and weight which is like a,
which is like a lightweight processor
which is built for modern architecture.
And also we will learn how fluent
bit can actually efficiently.
Efficiently collect power filter and
and analyze and route the logs from
our containers platform and and like
how it routes to like how it routes
the Kubernetes metadata also and stream
them into into restorations like Amazon
CloudWatch S3 or open search or any
observability backend of a choice.
And so we'll break down also the real
world use cases in this session and how
we deploy in in the real world scenario.
So we'll be covering the demo
also as part of this session.
So now we'll talk about the observability.
What is observability?
Observability is like ability
to measure the internal state
by examining the outputs.
So the key pillar of
observability like a log.
Mattresses and events, right?
And the traces basically.
And observability is very important
in our modern architecture because
EKS in, in that today's presentation,
we are talking in the context of
the EKS cluster and EKS cluster in
AWS around the complex workload.
So observability will help to
track the performance, health, and
usage patterns across the services.
And also the, also across
the notes and the pods.
And also it also provides the visibility
into the control plane and also the
data plane notes data plane events.
And also it helps to detect the pro
pod crashes and any node pressure.
It'll help us detect that.
And also it helps to monitor the CPO
memory disc related mattresses also.
Observability in EKS.
We'll talk about it now.
EKS is like a fully managed Kubernetes
service by AWS and it supports native
tools for, monitoring and logging.
So a case s logs, everything.
Basically it logs application logs
and systems and Kubernetes logs.
So we have these kind of logs.
We have any any case environment, and
we have mattresses like CPU Ma and
also we can have custom metrics also.
Also and everything is like traceable.
So we have whatever the
requests are coming in.
And going out, like request
flows and performance monitoring,
like performance tracing.
We have everything we can trace
and it is and basically this fluent
bit help us to trace all the logs
and and performance mattresses.
So that is the advantage of having
fluent bit as a log processor
in a WC case environment.
So now we'll talk about
the next fluent bit.
So what does fluent bit.
Mean, so fluent Bit is like a
lightweight log processor, and it's like
a forwarder, which allows to collect
the data and logs from our different
sources and it'll enrich them and
filter them and send it to the multiple
destinations like CloudWatch and like
a Kinesis data fire hose S3 bucket.
Or it can also route it to
Amazon Open set service as well.
And be, and like it can be used to
ship logs to various destinations.
But in, in this presentation, we'll be
focusing on forwarding the logs to to
do CloudWatch, with the, in the demo.
So now we'll talk about why
fluent bit is important.
So fluent bit is like a. Critical
collection layer, and it performs
several essential functions.
So what Fluent width does?
Fluent width does the collection for us.
So when we say collection, so
it'll capture the logs from a
different containers and and also
the endpoints and it'll enrich them.
Enrich stem means like we can augment
the logs augment the log data with the
Kubernetes metadata, we can append we can
enrich it and we can append additional
information to the logs, and we can
add custom tags, we can add contextual
information also to, to the logs.
And also we can transform
the locks, right?
So we like, we can do structuring,
we can do filtering, and we can
also mask sensitive information
from the logs as well.
That is what it does.
And the fourth one is routing.
So we can direct the logs to appropriate
destination based on the content namespace
and any other attribute which we specify.
So we can route it based
on that, those attributes.
So how the fluent weight
works, that is the next topic.
So Fluent Weight works.
So it, it has a log sources
locks, basically originate from
different sources like containers
and log files or system D, right?
So these are the log sources from
where it will collect the locks.
And we have a input plugin.
So input plugin, basically these
input plugins collect the locks.
And and then we have a parsers.
So parsers are basically the transformers.
So they transform the logs into a
structure Metadata, basically we use
JSON passing, and then we have filters.
So filters will enrich the logs and it
will, or it'll remove the specify specific
logs from the specific data from the logs.
And then we have buffers.
So buffers is basically a temporary
storage where we are storing the locks in
a ma or disk in case of a high throughput.
Or network delay.
And then we have output plugin.
So output plugin is basically to push
process logs to external location
like Elasticsearch or Amazon S3,
or Kafka or Kinesis Fire hose.
So now we will talk about the setup
to set up the fluent bit we need to
collect the logs from containers.
So to do that we need an IAM roll.
So I role we need which will be
attached to our cluster notes.
So we will be using a service account for
that to achieve rollback access control.
And also we will be in the demo.
We'll see how we will set up the flow
bit as a demo set to send the logs to
the CloudWatch to the CloudWatch logs.
So we'll be creating the log group.
And also we'll be having log stream,
so we'll be configuring these
things as part of the help chart.
So we'll see that as part of the
demo that we are, will be using
fluent help chart to, to deploy
to do install the fluent bit.
So we'll see that and, and also
we'll be using YDC connector.
Alright.
OIDC provider to which
needs to be created.
And also we will need, for I am role,
we need to create the IM policy.
So it is part of a prerequisite.
So we will be creating
the IAM policy upfront.
And also I'll be using
vs code for the demo.
So I'm already installing E-K-C-T-L,
cube, CTL, and helm and GI B on
my machine so that I can make
the demo more more, more doable.
Just wanted to make sure that we,
once we have a prerequisites in
place, it'll be easier to follow the
instructions, which I mention here.
So now we'll come to the demo.
So as part of the demo setup we will
we will also need the log server.
So apart from the pre prerequisites
we discussed, so we need to, once
the prerequisite setup is completed,
we need to have a application
which needs, which will, which
we'll be using to route the logs.
So to do that we will we'll be
using the log server, like an
Ionix server to generate the
logs, and then we will forward the
service to our local environment.
And we will use call command to do that.
So to, to make the request.
And also what we'll do is we
will be watching the logs locally
and also we'll be routing those
logs too to the CloudWatch logs.
To the cloud log group.
So we will do that in a three terminal.
So in the terminal one, we'll be
using we'll be using, we will be
using the terminal to forward the
logger server traffic locally.
And then and we'll be route, I mean
making a port forwarding to that.
And then in the second terminal,
we'll be watching the logs locally.
And the third time we will
be making the call request.
So we, and then we will be seeing like
whatever the logs we are seeing in a
local machine, we will be also forwarding
it to the CloudWatch locker room.
So this is what we are going to see.
And then once everything is
completed we'll see all the logs
going to the CloudWatch log group
as mentioned here in the screen.
So it is like a sample.
But we will see the
similar thing in our demo.
So now let's get to the demo.
We will start the demo now.
So as part of the demo, I'm
going to further instructions.
There are several things
we are going to do.
So first we are going to create
the Kubernetes cluster first.
So for creating the Kubernetes
cluster, we have a EKS config
YAML file, which we can see here.
And as part of this yaml it
is a cluster configuration.
So we are going to create a ees
cluster with the name ees cluster demo.
And and it is a configuration, so I'm
not going to go into the detail of that.
So I'm going to create
the ees cluster first.
And then so I'm going to, run e case CT
command to, to create the EGA cluster.
So here's the point.
So as soon as I execute this command, you
can see that it is creating a cluster.
So we will look into the
cloud formation stack.
I'll just go move to that.
So it is creating all the dependencies,
for example, net gateway subnet routes and
route tables, control plane, et cetera.
It seems like there are several components
being created, so it is almost done.
So we'll just wait for a
couple of more minutes.
We can see that the creation of the
cluster is completed and we can see
the associated sub components as part
of the cluster is also completed.
So here all the sub components,
you can see like route tables,
internet gateway, and and control,
plane n Gateway, et cetera.
All the dependent components
have been created now.
So we are good with the cluster
creation process, which is
a prerequisite for the demo.
So I did that as an extra step so that
I can demonstrate end-to-end demo here.
So now we will go to the next step.
The next step is we'll
update the q config.
So that we can access the cluster.
So I will just, just execute
the command for that.
Okay.
I will just go here.
So we'll see here, I think a few
things happening behind the scene.
So I think we need to watch
cluster again, maybe three.
Let's give a minute and let me look
at what's happening at the code.
Yeah, so now it is trying to create,
it's trying to create the add-ons
that is VPCC and I and Q proxy.
So it is trying to create that.
So we may have one-on-one
more stack coming in.
So we, before we access the
cluster using, cLI, we need
to have this process finished.
Then we can continue on that.
So as we say, as we can see, it is it
escalated on the cloud formation stack.
So we need to wait for a few more
minutes until that is completed.
So I'll just show you.
We can see that the cluster dependent
dependencies is also being created.
So we can, we seen the load
group is also created now,
which we can see on the screen.
That stack is also completed,
which is a dependency here.
So that is good.
Now we will, we can see that.
So I, hopefully we should be
able to access the cluster now.
So I'll just switch to VS.
Code.
Yes.
Code
so we can
Yeah, we can see here, right?
That, the.
It is showing that cluster
dependency is being created.
So we we will go to the this point and
now we will just execute the command
to access the cluster and here go.
So let's say.
You can see that plus was created
and we can, we are able to exit
the pos which are already created.
So that's a good step.
Now, the next step would be we will
create the namespace fluent bit as part
of this demo, as we are going to deploy
all the resources in the fluent namespace.
So we will go here and execute.
The one cube, it'll create
namespace fluid bit.
Oh, it seems fluent namespace is created.
So that's great.
Now we will go ahead and we will
create the YDC provider now so that
we can associate the service account
with the YDC provider later on.
So first we'll create our YDC
provider as that we can associate
the cluster to the YDC provider.
So I'm going to execute
the EK CT L command.
So as part of this process,
EK CT is a prerequisite.
So we need to have the EK
CT installed on machine.
I have already taken care of that.
Now I'm going to execute EK
CT command to to associate.
I am ODC provider with the
cluster, and this is Dan.
So it has created an I am Open 80
connector provider for the cluster.
That's great.
I will go to the next step.
So next step is we'll create a am
service account so that we can have a
little back access control in place.
So I'm going to execute
the command for that.
So in order to do that, we need to
have a, IM policy created in place.
Which is a prerequisite.
And I have already taken care of that
as part of the prerequisite earlier.
So I'm going to just execute
the command and I will walk
through the, policy later on.
So here we can see.
So here is I'm creating the AM
service account in the fluent with
the Fluent Withs, a name, and I'm
attaching the policy which is EESS
Cluster Demo Policy which I'll show
it to you here how I created it.
So I'm executing this comment now.
And it'll create a stack
here in cloud formation.
And I will show you how it looks like.
We can see that there's
another stack is created.
There is a, in case IT cluster
demo IM service account.
So that is the.
That is a new new cloud commission
stack is being created right
now, and it is in progress.
I will just quickly show you where
it where I've created the policy.
So I go to IN and go to, I am here.
And will go to the policies.
So as part of the policy, I'll just, so I
have created this EKS cluster demo policy
and I'm giving the full access to this
CloudWatch logs as part of this demo.
So that is what I did and I created
this in advance so that we can,
attach this policy to the IM role.
So I'll just go back to cloud
formation stack, as so that
I can show the next steps.
So we'll go back here and you can see
that AM service account is also created.
So the cloud formation sticks.
It says create complete.
So we are good now.
So I'll just go back to my V code and
to execute further the commands here,
go to the V code and I'm excluding next.
Next commands now.
So now since we have IM service account
created, so I'm going to just describe
it and see whether AM service's
account is created properly or not.
And I'm going to access it.
So I'm going to,
to describe my service account here.
So I'm saying yes, it is
created so we can see that.
So it is, it has created this,
it is associated with this role.
So the role is also created as part
of this process and, the name is
fluent with essay, so that's good.
Now as part of the next step
so I just wanted to highlight
that I executed Cube CT Command.
So Cube, CTLE xe also needs to
be installed similar to E-K-C-T-L
as a part of the prerequisites.
So we need to take care of that.
Now as part of the next step I will need
to install hand charts for fluent bit.
To the helm report so that we can
and so once the helm was really
add the helm report for one bit
and then we'll update it so that
we can access helm charts for that.
So I'm going to execute
helm commands for that.
So as part of the Prerequisites,
prerequisites, helm also should
be installed on the machine.
So I'll go here and, i'll just go here and
I'm just adding ham repo for the
fluent bit, so my, that is good.
Is now I'm going to update the.
So we'll be going here and updating.
So update is completed.
That's great.
So we go to the next step.
Now since PU is updated now, we'll install
the flowing bit using home commands.
So we have.
I am going to for that.
So here is the helm command.
So it says Helm upgrade, install one bit.
So it is creating installing the fluent
bit release and then it is space flow bit.
Service account we are not creating
because it's all, I already took care of
that and we are just giving the service
account name, which is already there.
And CloudWatch is going to be
enabled through, and we are going
to create this in US East one region
and it is going to check if the
log group name is there or not.
So it's going to set the log
group name if it is not created.
And then it is going to, we
are setting the stream for from
flu and with, from fluent demo.
So all that cloud watch logs will be
will be with this stream prefix name.
And then we are seeing the
region should be assist one.
So this execute is command.
So it says affluent bit does not exist.
So installing it now, so
we have to wait few minutes
right now it is executed, so that's great.
Now as part of the next step,
for the demo purposes, we need
to create a demo namespace.
So I'm going to create a new namespace
demo where we will be installing our app.
So we will just, first, we are going
to create the demo namespace space.
So demo namespace is created.
That's good.
Now.
What we need to do is so since we
executed health commands earlier,
so as part of the health command,
it has also created the config maps.
So we already discussed like
what the config map does.
So we have fluent bit
configuration stored there.
So we need to update
fluent bid configuration.
So that we are just telling fluent bit
what to output and where it has to go.
So I'll just quickly show
you what needs to be done.
So here I'll just execute this command.
Fluent added cm config map, fluent
bit hyphen fluent bit namespace.
So now we can see
it has created.
I just click issue here since
it does, I'll put it in not pad.
I just see how we can do it here now.
In
so we can see the the fluent bit lock.
This is the.
The fluent bit configuration,
config map configuration here.
So this is what we see.
So as part of this process, I need
to so this is the configuration
looks like so this is a config map
configuration and fluent for fluent bit.
So I'm going to update the, the outputs
because I don't need Elasticsearch here.
So I'm going to add outputs
for, because we are going to
output our logs to car watch.
So I'm going to add, add
output condition there.
So I'm just adding my open
condition there is to make sure.
So here we go.
I am.
So we can see that I have
updated the configuration as to
output the logs to CLO locks.
So it is going to.
I put it in US S two, and this is going
to the log drop name and log stream.
Name prefix is going to be from and
auto grid to true if it is not created.
So that is good.
Just check again.
How it is looking.
So my output is good.
That's good.
So I'm good.
So I just checked it quickly.
Now I'm export of the next step.
I'm going to I'm going to deploy.
My,
so as part of the next step we will
be restarting the dam set for the
fluent bit to check to check on it.
First we need to restart.
First we have to, we are restarting
because we updated the confi map.
So it is important to restart it so
that it gets the updated configuration.
Now, after I restarted the po I'm going
to check the pods associated with that
and making sure if they're created it,
sorry.
I am checking.
Yes, there are.
The new bots are created.
Now I'm going to check the logs for that
just to make sure.
That it is outputting, so
making sure there are no errors.
So I think it is good.
So we can see that log streaming
is creating and everything
is looking good and no error.
So it is outputting it to the
appropriate, cloud wash law group.
And it is creating the log stream.
So that's great.
So as, so I'm going to click the screen,
and now as part of the next step,
I'm going to I'm going to deploy the
AIX server as a sample application.
So I'm to execute the command
for that, and I already have the,
an server configuration here.
Which I'm going to show here.
That is a log server if I show here,
so that is a log server and it is ionix
type, like match levels app ionix.
So I'm going to deploy this so
that we can forward the logs and
then we can follow the locks.
So I'm going to apply this.
So that's great.
So we, and we have a exposed server
service for log server as well.
So that is great.
Now as part of the next step, we
will open another terminal to do
port to do port forwarding the locks.
So I'll be executing the command for that.
I am executing the command here.
So here I'm doing a port port port
forwarding for this hour to port 84.
So this is done.
It is forwarding other
logs from 80, 80 to 80.
So that's good.
Now we'll do the next step.
Now we'll open one more
terminal to check the logs.
So I've done, I create another
terminal here and I am executing
a command to check the logs.
So on this terminal, we will be checking
the locks whenever we make a request.
So that is good.
Now we'll go to the next step.
And as part of the next step, we
are going to make a call request.
To code 80 80 and we will see if
if it is able to, follow the locks.
So I'll be executing the command for that.
So now I'm executing the command.
So for that, I opened another vice
gentleman and I'm making a request.
So here we can see that,
this is welcome to Ionix.
So we are able to hit Endpoint
local Host 80 80, and we can see
here and it is forwarding the logs.
So that is great.
Now we will go to CloudWatch and
see if it is forwarding the locks
there or not to check on that.
So I will be showing you
the Clovis Locks now.
Now we can see that CLA logs here.
Here we can see in US West two, there
is a output location we mentioned.
So it is creating the log
group EKS application logs.
I think that is the log group name we
gave and is created that with that name.
And we specified the log stream.
So it was from.
And we can see that it is
outputting the logs here.
So today it is 27th in
UTC time, so 27th May.
So it is outputting the logs here and
we can see that we see all the log logs
here, coming here, so that it's good.
So now, whatever, whenever we
are making the call request,
it is outputting the log here.
So that is a great great success here.
As part of the next step what we can
do is we can see these CloudWatch
logs in a cloud rush dashboard.
So I have I'll walk you
through the process as well.
So here we go to the CloudWatch
dashboard, and I have already created
CloudWatch Dashboard as part of this demo.
So ES Locks is a dashboard name.
So if I click on it, it is going to.
Show us the logs.
We can see so it is, we are
streaming the log for this
log web name application logs.
So this is the log web name we gave
and it is showing the logs, other,
the logs coming to the CloudWatch.
It is just display it here so that we can
make the meaningful information out of it.
So similarly, like it is just one, but
we can have multiple filters and multiple
log groups we can create and so that
we can output the data accordingly.
And we can also customize this logs
based on the different metrics type,
for example, CPO, memory desk like
several parameters are there so we
can create different mattresses.
And we can output to the different
logs and we can display it
accordingly so that we can make the
meaningful information out of it.
So we can see, for example, like
we have, we are at the different
point of time, we have a different
type of logs like different and
like number of requests hitting.
So that is the information we can
make out of it as part of this demo.
So now this is the end of the demo.
Now we'll talk about
the real world examples.
So let's look at them one by one.
So first, now we'll talk
about the real world examples.
So let's look at them one by one.
So first one we will talk about.
Is the FinTech client.
So FinTech client needed a centralized
logging system to, so that the challenge
was to there were microservices running
in a e case environment and the bank
needed a, like a log aggregation solution.
To comply with the financial audits.
And also audit trails and also,
and so that they can access the
log, access these logs easily.
So the solution was given in
terms of fluent bit, can be
deployed as a diamond set.
On e case notes and we'll configure the
ENT bit to to tail the container logs
and them with the Kubernetes metadata.
And then forwarding all the logs
to to Amazon CloudWatch logs.
So this was a solution given
and the result was amazing.
So the, the bank got the centralized
logging system and it got access
to, to all the logs, which helped
them to improve troubleshooting.
And it increased the
efficiency for the bank.
And they got the operational
visibility as well.
And they were getting automated
alerts for for everything.
And it gave them no fast,
faster incident response.
So that was a success story for the bank.
So the second one second one use,
second use case is about, steaming
logs to Amazon Open Search company.
So there was a SaaS monitoring
provider the customer.
So the company needed like a scalable
low latency solution to, to index the
logs from the Kubernetes environment
and so that they can basically allow,
so that they can query the locks.
In, in real time.
That was the main challenge they had.
So the solution was like they use
fluent bit as a to collect the logs
and then they will increase the, all
the logs with the Kubernetes metadata.
And then as part of the streaming, like
outputting the logs, they output the logs
to Amazon open set service and then build
the Kibana dashboards on top of it so that
they can query these logs in real time.
So the result the output was amazing.
They were able to get near realtime
log availability and which improved the
monitoring and troubleshooting for them.
And also customer gained like in
like very good realtime experience
and and the analytics capabilities.
And also the operational overhead
was reduced with this process.
The third use case is about about
online, online gaming platform client.
So they were having they wanted to forward
the logs to a third party service company.
So they were using Datadog
service initially to route
the logs from ES to Datadog.
But they wanted to make it more efficient.
So the, and they wanted to find a
way so that e case container logs can
be can be sent to Datadog without.
Impacting the cluster performance.
That was the main challenge.
So the solution given was like they
deployed the fluent bit as a with the
SGTP plugin which was configured for
data for Datadog API, and then filters
for applied to reduce ansl log volume.
And the production.
And also they use Kubernetes metadata
to, in to to enhance the locks.
So the result was they use the log
ingestion cost through the selective
filtering, and then also it helped them
to improve the debugging experience.
So that was a very good benefit they got.
And also they got the seamless
integration with this, with the Datadog.
So that was a very good.
Success story for them.
Now, the fourth one is about is a
success story of a healthcare provider.
So this is a real world example where they
were having the challenge was like for
healthcare client they have to maintain
hipaa compliance, which is required
for collecting and retention, retaining
the logs from the ized workloads.
So that was the.
A challenge.
So the solution was to, they
deployed fluent bit as a diamond set.
To collect the container logs.
And then and also then they needed
Linux audit logs as well via
system input plugin, and then logs
were forwarded to a dedicated S3
bucket for the long-term retention.
And also security team also used
like Splunk to ingest from S3
for foreign forensic analysis.
So this was the solution, given the
benefit of this was like they ensure
compliance with regulatory requirements,
the HPA requirements they had,
they were able to comply with them.
And also it was a very cost effective
and very effective for investing the,
investigating the incidents also.
So that worked really.
For them.
So the fifth one is multi-tenant
logging in a, in in a company.
So they had they had a
they had a multi-tenant
multi-tenant Kubernetes cluster.
So they had multiple name spaces and
parts were running in multiple namespace.
So they wanted to, they wanted to ship
the locks in an isolated way and making
sure they are shipped in a secure they
shipped in a secure manner, part tenant.
So the solution was fluent bit was
deployed as a demonstr with the filters
to add tenant labels based on namespace
and then routing rules for configured.
To send the logs to a separate
na to separate Grafana low key
tenants using the lock output plugin
with the tenant specific URLs.
That was done.
And then the result was amazing.
They were able to get the multi-tenant
lock isolation without the need
for separating the cluster.
And then and it simplified
the platform operations with
centralized logging system.
And the centralized logging
management for them.
So these were the real world
examples you wanted to discuss here.
And now we'll talk about the references.
So have referred to AWS official
documentation to prepare this.
And and thank you very much
for being part of this session.
And and please let me know if you
need, if you have any questions.
Thank you.