Hi, my name is Mark Zu.
I'm a lead infrastructure engineer at
Bottas Labs, an L two Bitcoin startup.
I'm here today to speak about seeing
beyond signatures and how we set up
a federated motorcycle of mobility.
So the first question
is, what are multi six?
A popular saying by Bitcoin MAL would
be your keys, not your keys, your
Bitcoin, not your Keys, not your Bitcoin.
We ask ourselves, what is the
true purpose of a multisig?
The purpose of a multisig is spread out
your tax surface by requiring things
like visits between multiple locations
to sign a transaction, possibly multiple
states, multiple hardware vendors.
Deployed across different
validator sets across the globe.
That is what multis seeds are expressed.
The attack surface of that enhances
the security of users funds, basically,
that is what multis seeds are.
The problem here is the
invincible complexity when
signatures are needed from 12.
F. Once seven signatures are needed
from 12 validators across four
continents and only three show up, how
do you even begin to monitor for that?
How do you debug that?
Or do you actually need to know
what validators are online?
Are they receiving the transaction?
Is the man filled up?
Are you under attack?
These are the questions you ask yourself.
Is there a network of prob problem?
Is there a problem within the protocol?
And you do not know the answers to
this question if you do not have
enhanced monitoring and observability.
The multisig mage just details what
basically happens with within the mo.
It's three out of three mode sleep
between Alex, Bob, and Charlie.
To get the transaction signed.
We see the transaction being
initialized, the hash being generated,
the signature collection process, the
signature aggregation process, and the
signature verification process before
the transaction is being executed.
That's what is actually happening
and for all of this to happen, we
need our operators to be active.
We need unload to be healthy
for these to actually, so we can
actually have an IMO League up time.
What do we actually monitor for?
Currently, we monitor for transactions
such as we monitor for signature
accounts, wallet balances.
What is the current
state of the hot wallet?
state of the core wallet?
But the things that remain hidden
across multiple network and protocols,
as have seen is we do not actually
know how we can monitor for the
signature collection pattern.
Who signs what and when.
What node has been active?
What node has signed the most blocks
and pushed for the most transaction?
What is the network topology held?
What is the cryptographic performance
and what bottlenecks currently exist
in the proof generation process?
These are things we need
to monitor for and observe.
These are very key indicators here.
We discussed the Anto
of Refrige signature.
It just shows the two steps that dance
nobody sees because basically users just.
They have the idea that, yes, my funds
are secured and protected, and yes,
that's idea, but this just, those are
the technical implementation across
different networks and protocols.
We just have the 12 step down that entails
the verification process and transaction
flow within a multi sleek operation.
Now we ask ourselves a
question, why does observability
matter in federated networks?
We've, we have the issue of fragmented
systems across operators where node
operators are, we have the ability to run
isolated node in different environments.
That act of decentralization where
nodes are completely isolated.
We have a, when operational
silence equals slow recovery time.
If you do no monitor for
operational excellence and
operational resilience, then you'll
definitely have slow recovery time.
You would not be able to get
your network up and running.
With failures that you do not track
caused by timeout or slow signers
result in slow block production
as a result of block chain holds.
These are things you need to observe for.
These are things, this is why
of Ability matter because of
the stability of the network.
Essentially the true, a
true federated of ability.
Would mean it operator maintains
independence while contributing
to a shared availability layer.
What U utility can we can be used
to enhance that shared availability
layer where the goal is to ensure
real time insights, identifi
bottlenecks, and increasing the
flexability without out sacrificing
the true core of decentralization.
We introduced Grafana Alloy.
Here as the tool you being used,
tested, and proven as the documentation
suggests, Grafana Alloy combines the
strength of leading collectors in one
place, whether observing applications,
infrastructure, or boots, Grafana
Alloy can collect it process and export
telemetry signals to skill and future
proof your observability approach.
This is picked up and referenced
directly from your application, be it
profiling your applications or knowing.
The telemetry flow
within the applications.
Grafana Allo is the
tool for this and this.
It's vendor friendly.
It's it can be used as open source.
It can be loaded as a side card.
This is basically the approach
you would want to take in run when
trying to get federated of ability.
How can we utilize it?
Grafana alloy with its features.
Here we discuss the features of
Grafana Alloy, where it comes to
centralized logging with low key.
Metrics.
Getting the metrics which permits
remote ability traces with open
telemetry and also inbuilt profilers.
So these show us deep visibility into
our systems and show the visibility into
our networks and can be configured to
feed our specific use cases as we do
not have control of these independent
and isolated operators Essentially.
What is the deployment architecture?
As I earlier said, as we do not
have control of these independent
operators, each operator is allowed
to dare own our, with its own
configuration, fine tuned to it, to its
infrastructure, whether it Kubernetes,
dock bare metal or cloud native.
The operator is fine tuned to run
their own particular configuration.
We have centralized loss of ability.
Despite the local confi, all
data flow shared are good, are
shared, good shared endpoint.
Basically, we have a centralized look
key endpoint for getting all of the, and
aggregating all of the logs for Loki,
getting and aggregating all of the metrics
for perimeters and also temp for tracing.
We utilize security and autonomy
well in, we use to cognize access
to the secure endpoint of getting
all of the logs and metrics.
For or for the, for pure visibility
and autonomy into the system,
what can you see and do From this?
We are able to get live
operational insight from knowing
who is the slower sign and.
It.
It's detecting the internal
life of each participant.
Each mo, each operator in the multi end
Tories show how requests propagate that
cross signer highlighting performance
and pointing out failures in real time.
With this, we're able to monitor
for failures in real time with
and fine tuning the rights alert
system as service level indicators.
Before the problem, we had blind spots in
signature collection hours of debugging.
Field transaction, trying to get
individual logs sent over various form.
The logs and are unstructured network
issues are discovered too late and
malicious notes are allowed to participate
in the network while being unchecked.
But with this we have full visibility.
We have real time insights into the.
Into the system we have, we are now
proactive with our issues detection.
We ensure complete transaction life cycle
and we ensure security all of the network.
Basically.
Here we discuss the key benefits delivered
the operational excellence, security,
trust, and the federated approach.
We just highlight a few feature a few key
points on all of these key benefits of.
Federated approach, monitoring and
getting pure visibility into your systems.
Basically, I'll let us discuss with
questions and possible questions that
can come up when setting up these, like
what are the, what are our external
big validators operational pain points?
What are their biggest pain points?
What more monitoring gaps
do we have in our network?
Because the net monitoring
gaps are network specific.
How do we analyze the monitoring
gap within us, our federated
network, and how can we customize
this open source approach?
To our infrastructure.
I'll end it here and I would leave
my email attached for any more
questions you might have, and I'm
always happy to discuss this further.
Thank you very much.