Hello everyone and welcome
to Con 42 Observability 2025.
My name is Ashwin and I'm
joined by my colleague Devan.
I'm a senior engineering manager
at Adobe, and Devan is a product
manager in our payments organization.
Together we have spent years
building and scaling, high volume
commerce and payments platform.
Today's stock is titled
beyond the Dashboard Building
End-to-End, observability for
Commerce and Payment Systems.
I want to start with a question.
How many of you have experienced that
sinking feeling when your revenue drops,
but all your dashboards show green?
Your servers are up, your APIs
are responding, but somehow
there is a loss in your business.
That's exactly the problem
we are here to solve today.
During the course of this talk, we'll
talk to you on a journey from reactive
monitoring to proactive business
observability, sharing real world
examples, practical frameworks and
lessons learned from managing commerce
and payments platforms at Adobe.
Let's dive in.
Let me start by putting this
challenge in a perspective with
some numbers that might shock you.
First, let's talk about downtime costs.
Amazon loses $220,000 per
minute during downtime.
It's in, its, that's not a typo.
$220,000 Every single minute test systems
are down, but it's not just about downtime
during peak traffic periods numbers.
Get even most staggering Shopify processes
around 4.6 million in orders per minute
during Black Friday peak traffic.
Imagine the pressure on
their engineering teams.
Every second of degraded
performance could cost millions.
And here's perhaps the
most sobering statistics.
62% of customers abandon their purchase.
After just one failed payment attempt.
They don't retry, they don't call support.
They just leave, and many
of them never come back.
This brings us to the
key insight in commerce.
Observability isn't just about
uptime, it's about survival.
When your payment systems fail,
you're not just dealing with an
engineering problem, you're dealing
with an existential business threat.
These aren't theoretical numbers.
Every minute your systems are degraded.
Every failure failed
payment that goes unnoticed.
Every customer who hits an error,
that's direct revenue loss.
And unlike other types of applications
in commerce, there's no such
thing as acceptable downtime.
Before we dive deep, let
me quickly establish our
credentials at Adobe Commerce.
We are scaling platforms that handle
millions of daily transactions.
We have designed end-to-end
observability architecture
for complex commerce platform.
Most importantly, we have survived
the real world Battle Scars.
Black Friday, cyber Monday, chaos
meeting payment mandates like three Ds.
Many geospecific mandates where every
second counts and failure isn't an option.
We are here to share what we
have learned in the trenches.
Now let's talk about the fundamental
shift we need to make in how
we think about observability.
Traditional monitoring focuses
on basic service health checks.
It answers simple uptime
questions like is my service app.
It looks at the CPU and memory usage
response time metrics and HDP error
rates like four XX codes, five x exports.
This is the foundation, but in
commerce it's not nearly enough.
Commerce Observability takes a
completely different approach.
It tracks the complete customer
journey and business outcomes.
It monitors the end-to-end experience
from customer's perspective instead
of asking, is my service up?
Commerce Observability asks the question
that actually matters to your business.
Can customers complete purchase
because your checkout API might be
responding with 200 status codes,
but if there's a bug in the payment
flow, customers still can't buy.
Is the fraud detection,
blocking good customers?
Your fraud system might be working
perfectly from a technical standpoint
but if it's too aggressive, you
are losing legitimate revenue.
What's the actual customer experience?
Maybe your API is so fast,
but the front end is broken.
Our payment forms aren't loading.
Customers are frustrated.
Are payment failures
causing involuntary churn?
This is particularly concerning
for a subscription business.
Your billing system might appear
healthy, but customers could be churning
silently due to failed payments.
We'll talk about this
a little later as well.
And here's one that's often overlooked.
Are customers able to edit
their wallets correctly?
Sometimes.
Something as simple as updating
payment information can become
a revenue killer if it's broken.
Now, let me show you what full
funnel observability actually
looks like in practice.
This is the complete customer
transaction journey, and we need
observability at every single step.
Let let's walk through the journey
from a customer's perspective.
It starts with product discovery.
When a customer lands on your
site and starts browsing.
Here we are monitoring page, load
times, and search performance.
If your product pages are slow
or search isn't working, we are,
you are losing customers before
they even find what they want.
Next is car tradition.
The customer decides they want
something and adds it to the cart.
We monitor API response time here
because if the add to card button
doesn't respond quickly, customer
will assume it's broken and leave.
Then we hit the checkout process.
Here we are monitoring form validation,
and payment method selection.
Every friction point here
directly impacts conversion.
If customers can't easily select their
payment methods, or if form validation
is confusing, they'll abandon.
Authorization and fraud is
where the complexity increases.
Here there are many data points
that will have to be monitored.
We are monitoring risk engine
decisions and payment approval rates.
Your fraud detection needs to be smart
enough to block bad actors while keeping
it smooth for the good customers.
And the balance here directly
impacts your revenue.
Finally, order fulfillment,
confirmation and order processing
even after payment succeeds.
If customers don't get proper
confirmation or if there are issues
with auto processing, you'll get
chargebacks and customer support tickets.
The key insight is that each touch point
represents critical revenue impact.
A failure at any step doesn't
just affect that step.
It affects your entire conversion funnel.
This is why we need observability
across the complete journey, not
just at individual service endpoint.
Now let's look at this from a subscription
business perspective, because the
observability challenges are quite
different when you're dealing with
recurring revenue and subscriptions.
There are different data points and
metrics that need to be observed.
This is a typical subscription
lifecycle journey, and every
step is a potential failure point
that impacts ERR and retention.
Unlike one time transactions.
Subscription businesses have to
worry about the entire customer
journey, not just a single purchase.
Let's walk around this cycle.
It starts with trial signup.
We are monitoring conversion metrics
and onboarding friction points.
If users can't easily sign up
for trials or if the onboarding
process is confusing, you are losing
potential subscribers before they
even experience your product value.
Moving to free to paid
conversion, this is critical.
We monitor payment, set up success
rates and method preferences.
Many potential customers drop off
here, not because they don't want to
pay, but because the payment method
or the payment setup process is
too complicated or doesn't support
their preferred payment method.
Here it is critical to measure
payment method usage rates.
And also when a new payment methods,
for example, cloud Now or LPMs
are launched, how they're adopted.
Then we have the billing cycle.
This is where many subscription
businesses get caught off guard.
We monitor recurring billing
events and schedule accuracy.
A missed billing event, for
example, or an incorrect scheduling.
Can cause revenue delays
or customer confusion.
For example, if our billing system
is not able to charge the user for a
month, entitled internet system might
remove access after a gray period,
even though the user is at no fault.
Payment processing is where the technical
complexity really starts showing up.
We are monitoring multiple different
gateway performances and authorization
rates in subscription payment failures
are particularly damaging because
they can cause involuntary churn.
Customers who want to stay.
I can't because their
payment failed renewal.
The next step here is the renewal
step, which is at the moment of
truth for retention rates and
involuntary return prevention.
This is where silent failures
can be devastating, but this
is also an opportunity for us
to ride size subscriptions.
Maybe a customer needs to be downgraded
so that their their plan is right sized.
Rather than churn out completely.
So without proper observability into their
usage patterns and payment behavior, we
will miss these retention opportunities.
Finally, usage and expansion.
We monitor feature adoption and
upgrade revenue opportunities here.
Understanding how customers use our
product helps us identify expansion
opportunities and even preventing churn.
The key insight here is that subscription
observability requires monitoring
through the entire customer lifetime,
not just individual transactions.
Each step in the cycle compounds
over time, making the impact of
failures much more significant than
in traditional e-commerce business.
Now let's talk about how the traditional
three pillars of observability.
That's metrics, logs, and traces
will look when you're dealing with
commerce and subscription businesses.
First pillar, which is metrics.
So beyond system health instead of just
tracking CPU and memory usage, we need to
track revenue flow and business outcomes.
We will have to focus on
customer-centric measurements.
This means revenue flow metrics
like a RR conversion rates.
These tell you about your business
health, not just your system.
Health payment success rate by processors.
Because a 99% success rate with one
processor might be 85 with another.
And that difference is
millions in revenue.
And then customer lifecycle metrics
like churn and LTV, these help you
understand the long term impact of
the technical decisions that you make.
And time to value percentage.
How long does it take customers
to get value from your
product after they sign up?
Alright, second pillar.
Logs with business context.
Traditional logs tell you what happened.
Technically, I. Commerce logs need
to capture decision, reasoning
and customer journey context.
They need to link technical
events to business impact.
This includes payment processor
responses, not just payment failed, but
why it failed and what that means for
specific customer journey breadcrumbs.
That is basically understanding
the full path a customer took
before they encounter an issue.
Then business decision reasoning.
Why did the fraud engine
block this transaction?
What data points led to the decision and
the revenue weighted error classification?
Not all errors are equal.
Some cost you more money than others.
Let's look at the third pillar.
This traces across, revenue
systems we need to follow.
Complete transaction flows across
all systems that affect revenue.
This isn't just about following a
request through your microservices.
It's about mapping dependencies
that affect your business.
This means end-to-end transaction
flows from customers, click.
To the money in the bank
payment gateway dependencies.
Understanding how third party
services impact your revenue
is also quite important.
Third party services.
Let's say when add in or PayPal
has issues, how does that affect
your business and your customers?
And now talking about subscription
lifecycle traffic tracking, we
will have to follow the customer's
entire journey, like we looked
looked at it a few slides up before
from trial to renewal to expansion.
The key insight is that Commerce
Observability requests all three
pillars to work together to give you a
complete picture of both your technical
systems and your business outcomes.
All the slides about bring us
to this fundamental mind shift.
From reactive monitoring to proactive
observability, reactive monitoring wage
for problems to surface you'll alert when
services down, customer complaints have
gone up and then revenue is already lost.
But proactive observability detects
patterns before they impact customers.
You can detect degradation patterns
predict failure cascades implement
automated remediation and operate
in revenue protection mode.
Here's the difference.
Instead of waiting for customers
to complain about failed payments a
proactive observability can detect
a 2% increase in payment failures.
And this can predict that this
could become a 20% involuntary term.
This will give us time to fix it before it
starts impacting our business In commerce,
reactive means revenues already lost.
Proactive means we are
protecting the revenue.
To drive this further home.
Let's look at a real world example of why
this proactive mindset is so critical.
This is about what we call a
silent killer of subscription
business, involuntary churn.
Let's start with the problem.
20 to 40% of total churn in a
subscription business is involuntary.
These are failed payments that silently
destroy subscriber basis without warning.
Think about that.
Nearly half of your customer
losses might not be because of
customers wanting to leave, but
because of payment system failures.
The re renewal failure rate is at a
staggering five to 18% of subscriptions
failing at each billing cycle.
That means one in eight of your customers
might not renew successfully, not
because they don't want your product, but
because their payment didn't go through.
And now let's look at this impact.
On a global scale, so this would
be around 118 billion lost globally
in 2020 due to payment failures.
This creates massive revenue
hemorrhage across entire industries.
That's not just a technical
problem, that's an economic crisis.
Here's the observability challenge.
Traditional monitoring
creates a blind spot.
Your systems will show healthy
when customers quietly, oil
customers will quietly disappear.
Your billing systems report success.
Your APIs are responding, your
databases are performing well,
but customers are churning silent.
The most critical issue
is zero time visibility.
Zero real time visibility.
Most businesses discover churn
after customers have already gone.
By the time you realize there's a
problem, you've lost not just revenue,
but customer relationships that
took months or even years to build.
This is a perfect example of
why traditional monitoring
will fail in commerce.
Our subscription businesses, all
your technical metrics can be green.
While your business is bleeding money.
You need observability that focuses on
business outcome, not just system health.
This is why we need a proactive
approach like we discussed earlier
that can detect payment issues sooner
so that more customers can be saved
and more revenue can be protected.
This brings us to one of the
most challenging aspects of
commerce observability, which is
dealing with unknown unknowns.
These are problems you
don't even know to look for.
Let me contrast that
with two, two approaches.
The traditional approach is reactive.
Teams define known failure modes upfront
and creates alerts for expected problems.
This relies on reactive monitoring.
While alert triggers after
impact, it'll contain blind spots
for unexpected or novel issues.
Investigations are typically
manual and slow, and it focuses on
infrastructure or service health.
Traditional monitoring will
answer questions like, are
all services returning 200?
Okay?
Is the memory usage within limits?
But here's the problem.
This approach, miss misses the
business critical issues that
you never thought to monitor.
Unknown detection takes a
completely different approach.
Proactive intelligent systems
surface insights from patterns
you didn't know to look for.
This includes anomaly detection on
both business and system metrics,
not just CPU spikes, but unexpected
drop in conversion rates are unusual
payment patterns, for example.
Previous in France may be
failing for certain card types.
Your systems are still healthy,
as this might be a very small dip
for a small subset of your users.
But in the overall revenue scheme,
this is still a revenue loss.
Which goes unnoticed and could
have been easily avoided if you're
looking for these unknown unknowns.
Cross system correlation of logs, events
and telemetries will help you understand
how issues in one system might be
causing problems in another behavioral
pattern recognition to flag outliers like
say, detecting when customer behavior
changes in ways that might indicate
that may, there may be some problem.
For which reason the customer
are changing their behaviors.
And we should also look at how to
automate root cause analysis with
investigating while investigating
workflows system that can trace problems
back to their source automatically
instead of asking, are services healthy?
Unknown detection asks, why
is the conversion dropping?
What things that we didn't expect?
The key insight is
captured in this question.
What we thing is happening that
we didn't think to monitor.
In commerce, the most expensive problems
are often the ones you never saw coming.
A payment processor starts
declining certain types of cards.
Fraud detection rule suddenly
flags legitimate customers upfront.
End.
Checkout update breaks the checkout
workflow in a specific browser
or a specific in-app experience.
These are issues that can cost millions
before you even realize they exist.
This is why modern commerce
observability needs to be intelligent
and proactive, not just reactive.
Now let's get practical with
lessons from the trenches.
What you should do, start with the
subscriber's journey, not system
architecture, instrument for ERR
outcomes, not just technical health.
Create runbooks with churn impact context
so your team knows about the business.
Impact immediately.
And test your observability during
billing cycles when you need it the most.
What not to do.
Don't alert on everything.
Focus on revenue and churn impact.
Don't ignore payment
processor dependencies or
other external dependencies.
Don't forget about in-app mobile
experience metrics and don't neglect
customer success team communication.
They're often the first
to hear about issues.
The key insight here
is effective commerce.
Observability is as much about process
and communication as it is about.
Tech technology and the stack that
we use, one of the biggest challenges
in commerce, observability isn't
technical, it's also organizational.
Getting everyone on the same page, I.
The challenge is that different
teams have different priorities.
Engineering most typically always
focuses on system uptime and performance.
Product cares about feature
adoption and retention.
BU and finance organizations
care about ERR churn.
And churn reduction.
Customer success team wants
seamless billing experience
at a very low call volume.
The solution here is an alignment
around shared business outcomes.
We have to create shared dashboards
with the error context so everyone
sees the same business metrics.
You have to implement cross-functional
incident response for payment
issues, not and treat, not just
treat them as engineering problems.
We should use revenue impact scoring for
all alerts so teams understand business
priority and hold regular business
reviews of subscription health metrics
when everyone understands how their work
connects to revenue and customer success.
Observability becomes a
shared responsibility, not
just an engineering tool.
And speaking of that product
perspective and a non-engineering
perspective let me now hand it over
to my colleague Dave Wang, who will
share insights on observability from
a product manager's perspective.
Take it over everyone.