Hi, this is Sheika Ana.
Welcome to conference 42.
Today I'm here to present about
unlocking operational efficiency
and collaboration in nonprofit
with Salesforce nonprofit cloud.
There are some of the key
non-profit challenges today.
One is like time constraints, data silos,
and communication gap time constraints.
Nonprofit often find themselves
to stretch with the limited budget
and the staff and the constant
pressure to do more with the less.
Can be overwhelmed, like time, valuable
time, and the resources get consumed
in administrative tasks like manual
data entry and some other manual,
manual work and leaving like less
times for the mission critical works.
And the program delivery this time
crunches or takes away from the
organization ability to focus on the
core purpose and maximize its impact.
And when it comes to data silos, main,
many nonprofit relies on patchworks to
spread the system and the tools to manage
their operations from the donor management
to program tracking to the outreach.
This approach leads to the disjoint of
data, like making it difficult to get
comprehensive view of an organization,
activities and communication gap.
The disconnect between various
teams and information sources with
nonprofit can create like a significant
COL collaborative collaboration.
Challenges and program staff may
lack of a real time visibility
and outcomes and the performance.
While leadership may struggle to.
Coordinate the efforts and the track,
the progress of across the organization.
This lack of transparency and alignment
can be like co cross, cross-functional
collaboration prevents, like sharing
the best practices and make it harder
to demonstrate the organization
collective impact to the stakeholders.
And this.
This affects to the challenges can
be determined to the non-profit
ability to fulfill its mission.
Donuts and inefficient use of
resources and critical funding can
be undermined the organization in the
long term sustainability and impact.
So today I want to introduce
a non-profit cloud which was
provided by the Salesforce.
So Salesforce non-profit cloud.
Assess these pain points by providing
like undefined cloud-based platform that
breaks down the data silos, automates
the manual processes, and crossed.
Sorry.
Cross team collaboration
and real time visibility.
This empowerment of a nonprofit free
up the time, resources and improve the
donors valuable time and demonstrate a
measurable outcomes, ultimately helping
them overcome their unit challenges
and unlock their full potential.
Like purpose of a platform built platform
like Salesforce, nonprofit, cloud is
comprehensive and a cloud-based platform
designed specifically to the unique
needs of a nonprofit sector sectors.
It goes beyond generic CRM solutions
offered and a set of features and
the functionalities that address
in the common pain point faced by
non-profit organization like this.
Purpose of built approach ensures
non-profit Cloud provides the right
tools and capabilities to help
non-profits non-profits streamline
their operations and enhance.
The donor consistency.
Engagement, and demonstrate
the measurable impacts.
And the platform is deeply aligned with
the nonprofit missions, empowering them
to work more efficiently and effectively.
And this is like cloud-based
solution, like Salesforce.
Nonprofit is a cloud-based
platform, which means it's hosted
and maintained by Salesforce and.
This offers several key advantages
of a non-profit like accessibility.
Accessibility, meaning like the
platform can access from anywhere
or any device, and enabling a
remote and mobile collaboration.
Another one is scalability.
The cloud-based infrastructure
can easily accommodate.
A growth and changing the needs with
the burden and the hardware of it.
Maintenance and reliability, like
Salesforce's industry leading cloud
infrastructure ensures the high
availability and secure and disaster
recovery, giving a nonprofit peace
of mind and automatic updates.
The platform is continuously updated
with the latest features and the security
enhancements, keeping nonprofit up
to date with the need for the manual.
Manual upgrades and customizable
system like Salesforce, not nonprofit.
Cloud is highly customizable
platform, allowing like a non-profit.
To its specific requirements.
And this flexibility ensures that
the system aligns with organization
of a unique workflow, data needs
and reporting requirements.
And nonprofit can configure the platform
to match their branding, streamline
and their operational pro processes.
And.
Integrate with other critical systems.
They use this level of customization,
empowers them the maximum value
of the platform, and ensure a
seamless fit with their existing
infrastructure way of working.
And by providing the purpose of built.
Our cloud-based customizable solution,
Salesforce nonprofit Cloud helps overcome
the challenges and timely constraints
of data silos and communication gaps,
and ultimately enabling them focus
on their mission-driven impacts.
And the next slide, which I'm talking
about streamlining our operations
Salesforce nonprofit cloud can
help streamlining operations by.
Automate the task.
Automate task means automates many
manual time consuming tasks that
often burden a nonprofit organization
like from donor management or
fundraising to the volunteer.
Coordination and program management
and the platform can streamline
these processes and eliminate
the needs and the data entry.
For example, the platform can
continuously, can automatically
generate the donor donation receipts
and schedule reoccurring donor payments
and send a personalized acknowledgement.
This free of the valuable staff time
to ensure like consistent, efficient,
handle way handling the critical
administrative responsibilities.
And the other one is
tracking the progress.
Like nonprofit Cloud provides
centralized hub to tracking the
organization progress and perform
across all the programs innovatively.
And this platform offers the real time
dashboards and reporting tools that
can give the stakeholders from the.
Program manager to execute leadership
and comprehensive reporting and the
key and comprehensive key view of a
key metrics and outcomes like this.
Visibility allows the
nonprofit to monitor.
The impact of their program and
identify the areas to improve and
make the data driven decisions
to enhance their effectiveness.
Like tracking the progress also
enables like nonprofit to better
communicate to their impact donor and
grant makers and other stakeholders.
Other one is the find information
with all of the organization data.
And the information stored in a single
place like Unified Platform Salesforce
nonprofit Cloud can make it easy for
the staff, like to quickly find the
information they need, whether the donor
contact details or program outcomes or
the volunteer engagement history and
the platform is a powerful like search
of a data management capabilities.
Ensure like critical data to.
Do a read only accessible.
And this streamline access of
information empowers like nonprofit
team to collaborate more effectively
and make informed decisions and provide
a better service to their consistents.
Another one is like gendered
reports, like nonprofit cloud.
Was robust reporting and analytics
capability allows the organization to
generate comprehensive reports that
showcase their impact and performance.
And the platform offers a wide range of
prebuilt reports, templates as well, and
that ability to create a custom reports to
the organization for the specific needs.
And these reports can be used to
demonstrate organization progress.
To the donors or grant makers and
other stakeholders, like helping secure
the critical fundings and support
additional, additionally, and the
reporting tools enable nonprofit to
identify the trends and track the key
performance indicators and make their
data-driven adjustments to their program.
And the strategies, like by automating
tasks and tracking pro progress
facilitates the information access.
And generates the impactful
reports like Salesforce.
Nonprofit, cloud helps streamlining
the operations and the focus, what
matters most delivering on their
mission to driving a meaningful changes.
And the next slide is
enhance donor relation.
What does that mean?
Like enhances donor relation?
Salesforce nonprofit can engage
the donor relation in many ways.
Like few of them are like personalized
donor engagement, which means like
Salesforce non nonprofit cloud enable
the nonprofit build stronger and
more personalized relationships with
the donors and the platform Donor
management capability allows the
organization to capture and centralize
the detailed donor information, including
giving the history, communication,
preference, and the area of interest.
This is a deep understanding of
Donor allows the nonprofit to their
outreach and engagement strategies and
ensure that each donor feel valued.
And connect it to the organization.
Mission nonprofit can send the
personalized communication recommended.
I like, like recommended target
at donors donation opportunities.
And this provides a more
personalized experience.
And other one is like Steamlined
donation management, like nonprofit cloud
simplifies and streamlines the donation
management progress, making it easier.
For the donors to
support the organization.
The platform offers a range of
donations and CHA channels, including
online and giving mobile, giving and
reoccurring donations and providing
donors to option to contribute.
And additionally, this platform
automatically generates
or donate receipts, track
gifts gift matchings, sorry.
And matching manages the donor
acknowledgements and ensure a streamlined,
efficient donation experience.
This streamlined process not only
enhance the donor experience, but also
helps them nonprofit, maintain accurate
donor records, better management
and their fundraising efforts.
Another one is like donor
cultivates and ation.
By leveraging the insight and
the data capture of the nonprofit
organization can more effectively
cultivate and retain their donor base.
And the platform segmentation and the
communication tool enables nonprofit
to create a targeted campaigns and
engagement strategies based on the
donor characteristics and given
patterns and the area of interest.
This personalized approach helps
a nonprofit deep dive or the
relation with the donors and loyalty
and increase the likelihood to
repeat the increased donations.
The platform also provides the
visibility to the donor and allowing
nonprofit to proactively address any
donor concerns or or any given reports.
Like other one is like donor
reporting and analytics.
Nonprofit nonprofit cloud robust
reporting analytics capabilities
empowers the organization to gain the
deeper insight into the donor base.
And nonprofit can generate a comprehensive
donor reports track the key metrics such
as donor life and value and accuse the
cost and identifying the trend and the
opportunities of the donor engagement.
These insights help the nonprofit to make
data-driven decisions and optimize their
fundraising strategies and demonstrate
the impact of the donor outreach
efforts to both current and potential
supporters By enhancing this engagement,
streamlining donation management,
and cultivating the donor relation,
provide the actionable donor insight.
Salesforce nonprofit cloud helps the
nonprofit build stronger, more sustainable
Turner community that supports the
mission and drive the great impact.
And the next slide is about boost.
The team collaborate.
Like the Boost team collaborate is
like centralized data information.
Like a nonprofit provides the centralized
platform to store accessing all of an
organization data and the information.
This includes donor records,
program details, volunteering
information, and more.
By having a single unified system,
team member can easily find the data
they need to reduce the time spent
on searching across multiple systems.
And the spreadsheets, like other one is
improve the visibility and transparency,
like platform dashboards and reporting
tools offers the team like greater
visibility into the organization,
activities, progress and performance.
This transparency allows for the better
alignment as everyone can see, the same
data information, and understand the
organization priorities and the goals.
And other point is like enhanced
communication and coordination.
Like nonprofit cloud collaborates
features such as task assignments and
activity feeds and real time updates and
enabling the teams to communicate more
effectively and coordinate their efforts.
Team members can stay informed and
share updates and collaborate on the
projects and more aligned workforce.
And other point is like streamline
workflow process by automating many
administrative like by automating
many administrative processes.
By automating, standardized the
workflows and non-profit cloud helps
the team to work more ev effectively.
And this frees up the time and the
resource that can redirect it towards
the mission and critical activities, and
further enhance the team, collaborative,
and productivity, and integrate ecosystem.
An integrated ecosystem like non-profit
cloud seamlessly integrates and
by providing the centralized data
hub and improving the visibility
and the transparency, enhance the
communication and coordinating the
streaming workflow and integrate the
other essential tools like Salesforce.
Nonprofit Cloud helps the team
collaboratively and more effectively.
And ultimately driving the greater impact
and achieving their goals of like the
organization goals in a timely manner.
And and the data.
And the next slide is about the data
driven making organization that utilize
a nonprofit consistently and experience
the significant improvement across
the essential performance metrics.
And this empowers the strategization
making, maximize the mission impact
and through the actionable insight
that donor re retention within an
organization is 45% with without
Salesforce, and 75 per 72% with
Salesforce, which is like 60% improvement.
And the program efficiency is
52% without Salesforce, and 83%
with Salesforce transforming.
Operations and the reporting speed is
38% without Salesforce, and 91% with
Salesforce, which significantly reduce
the preparation time preparation time.
And the other one is staff satisfaction
is 61% without Salesforce, and 85%
with Salesforce enhance the team
moral morals and work in a better way.
And the next slide is
about implementation.
The journey of a Salesforce nonprofit
cloud includes includes so I split
this into different parts, like
one is the discovery and planning,
meaning understanding the nonprofit
unique needs, goals, and the pain
points to the deeply discovered
sessions with the key stakeholders.
And access the organization, current
technologies and the landscape, and
identify the areas of improvement
to integrate with the nonprofit
cloud, and develop the comprehensive
implementation plan and align
with the nonprofit strategy.
Objective timelines and define the project
scope, and identify the key milestones
and clear the roles and establish
the clear roles and responsibilities
for the implementation team.
And other one is like configuration
and setup, like customize, customize
the nonprofit cloud to match the
organization's specific workflow and
data requirements and reporting needs.
And other one is like migrating the
existing data from the legacy system
into nonprofit cloud and ensure
the data accuracy and integrity and
integrate the nonprofit cloud with.
Other relational tools systems
used by organizations such as
online donation platform or
voluntary management softwares.
Another one is implement the robust,
secure measure, like user access
control and data governance policies
to protect sensitive information.
Another point is like
training and adoption.
Like developing a comprehensive training
program to educate the nonprofit staff
on the Salesforce cloud platform.
It features and the best practices
for utilization and provide ongoing
support and the guidance to ensure
smooth and transition and increase
the user adoption and the ident.
Identify the Empower super user.
With the organization who can serve as
a champ and mentor of their colleagues
and gather the feedback and continuously
refine the training materials, use
support resource based on the other needs
and the feedback and ongoing support.
Like establishing the dedicated support
team or a partnership with the Salesforce
implementation to provide ongoing
technical assistance and troubleshooting
and issue resolution and like continuously
monitoring the platform identify areas
to improve or implement the enhancement
updates as needed, and provide the
regular check-ins and the status
reviews to ensure the nonprofit platform
continues to align with the organization.
And evolving goals and the
requirements, and offering the
ongoing trainings and the development
opportunities to help nonprofit staff
stay up to date with the platform.
Latest features and capabilities.
Like by carefully navigating through
these key stages, the implementation
journey of a nonprofit can ensure.
A successful Salesforce non non-profit
cloud development and maximum platform
benefits and drive the sustainable
impact to their organization
and the communities they sell.
And the next slide I want to talk
about the success story, like success
story like nonprofit environments and
nonprofit dedicated to the environment
convention and sustainability.
Challenge challenge, streamlined
volunteer management and enhance donor
engagement and improve the campaign
tracking across the multiple chapters.
And other point is like sales for
solution implement, implementing the
Salesforce nonprofit cloud to unify
the unified data, automate workflow,
and gain real time visibility.
And the key.
Key performance metrics.
And the next point is about results.
Transform the field operation with
a nonprofit cloud boosting the
volunteer coordination efficiency
by 45% and increasing the donor
resistance by 28% through the
personalized engagement strategies
and leverage nonprofit cloud reporting
analytics to improve the campaigning
performance of tracking by 65%.
Enabling the organization to the better
measure and impact of the environment
and consolidate the data from the
multiple chapters into a single
platform allows the better across
collaboration and 40% increasing the
number of joint conversation project
undertaken and youth education funding.
Like nonprofit youth education fund
and an organization that provides
education, resource and scholarship
to the under underserved communities
and challenge is enhanced students and
the donor management and streamlined
program I. And reporting and improve the
collaborate across the multiple regions.
And that's more about the success story.
And the next slide I'm talking
about return on investment written
on investment, but op operational
efficiency and significant re
reduction of the administrative
workload allow the staff to concern
on the mission critical activities.
Data integrity, not able to improve
inequality of a consistency information
like facilitating more meaningful
re relations relationships, and
fundraising impact consider considerably
increasing the donation revenue through
the enhanced donor engagements and
organization that implement nonprofit
cloud generally achieve a positive return
of investments with the first year.
And the benefit continues,
accumulate as a team, make full
use of platform capabilities.
And the next slide is ready
to transform your nonprofit.
Salesforce committee sorry.
Commit, committed to empower the
nonprofits like yours to achieve your
missions and maximize your impact.
We offer a. Variety of engagement
options to help to get the stated
with the Salesforce nonprofit
like schedule, schedule a demo,
like experience experience.
Nonprofit cloud is an action with
an organization actual data, and our
dedicated nonprofit specialization
specialist will guide you through that.
Specialized demo showcasing how
the platform can address a specific
challenges and requirements.
This is an opportunity to see the
power of a sales force firsthand
and ensure the transformative
impact it have in your operations.
And the other point is
like assessment workshop.
Discover how Salesforce can be
to address the unique challenges
in his collaborative workshops.
Our experts will work closely with your
team to conduct and comprehensive as
assessments of your existing process,
data management and technology needs.
Together we'll identify the areas where
like Salesforce can drive most meaningful
improvement and laying the groundwork
for the successful implementation.
Like other point is like implementation
planning, develop a strategy roadmap
that ensures a long-term success.
For your mission and our team
will work with you closely to
create the implementation plan.
And outlining the necessary steps
and timeline resources required
seamlessly integrate Salesforce
nonprofit into our organization.
This collaborative approach ensures that
Salesforce Investment Alliance with the
strategy, goals and sustainable impact
and connect with the dedicated nonprofit
specialist today emerges the transforming.
Journey towards the maximum
impact and through the streamlined
approach and enhance collaboration
that's more about nonprofit.
There are a lot of to talk about
nonprofit, but in limited time, this is
what I can tell to the team or everyone.
Thank you.