Hi everyone.
I'm Raho.
I'm currently a senior product manager
at Microsoft and I work on cloud
native monitoring and troubleshooting.
I'm excited to present to you today's
talk on shrinking the observability table.
We are gonna discuss several strategies
on how you can optimize your cloud
native monitoring costs while at the
same time maintaining the insights.
So let's jump right in.
Today we are gonna be diving into yeah,
the critical topic of observability costs.
And this is focused on cloud,
native and Cuban environments.
As we explore strategies for
cost effective monitoring, it's
also essential to recognize
the balance between maintaining
visibility and managing expenses.
I'll guide you through some of the
innovative approaches that can help
organizations optimize their observability
practices without sacrificing the
insights they need to operate efficiently.
This is gonna be our agenda, but
today we'll start off with why we
see costs rising in this field.
We'll discuss a framework
on how we can cut the waste.
We are gonna do a deep dive on
some of the specific aspects of
cloud native monitoring, which is
the control plane, the nodes, the
pods, and the network monitoring.
I'll discuss a few tools and dashboards
that can help and we'll end with a few
key takeaways and action plan so that you
can go start acting right away on this.
So first off why am I here?
Why are we talking about this?
Observability can cost up to 40%
of the bill sometimes even more.
And given how dynamic cloud native
environments are, the number of
microservices, the spin up, the spin down,
there's just a lot of data generated.
Sometimes it's even beyond your control,
what data is collected, what is generated.
So it's important to realize the
difference between a regular VM
or another host monitoring versus
cloud native monitoring, where some
things are just out of control.
The second important point is the
fact that there is a lot of data,
but not all the data is useful.
There may not be valuable insights
in all the data that you collect,
so it's important that we build
smart and efficient strategies so
that you can only collect what you
want and get the best value data.
At the bottom I have a sample example of
what the cost breakdown can look like.
Here we have the observability,
the networking, the compute,
and the storage costs.
Of course, this is just a presentative
example but you can see that it can cost
a lot, especially if you're not mindful of
the things that, that you're collecting.
Where are we spending all this money?
There's three or four different categories
where I have seen that enterprises
spend most of the dollars in collecting
observability and monitoring metrics.
The first one, high ity custom metrics.
Most of the tools out there charge
a different fee or a different
pricing for these custom metrics.
They're extremely high cardinality,
which means they have labels like
the user ID and things like that.
The second one is a long log retention,
depending on how if it's 30 days, 90 days
it could spike up the bill pretty badly.
And also verbose logging.
If you have extremely verbose logs like
debug logs and other logs configured,
it's gonna be spending a lot of your money
just collecting Yeah, these verbose logs.
The third thing that I've seen is the
same data gets replicated multiple
times to different destinations.
That could, of course spike a
pay cost to and all when you're
sending data across the network
to different regions or otherwise.
That could also accrue expensive,
both egress and storage fees too.
So now let's get into the
framework that I had promised.
So the first important thing to realize
is we have to collect what matters.
And here the service level
objectives are most important as
compared to all the different logs.
You have to start with the
service level objectives.
That is the main metric which affects
users, and that's what users are seeing.
And then you have to
choose the right signal.
So in terms of the signal
itself and the value metrics
are the most important signal.
They help in alerting the make
sure that the services are up and
running, if not that you're alerted.
The second is traces.
So now you have a flow of
like how the data goes from a
different, from one service to
another, and that helps you debug.
And the last is logs when in a service
you can go and debug what's going wrong.
The third one is you have to tune
your retention and aggregation.
Retention is how long it is stored,
and aggregation is, yeah, how do you
make sense of this data and wherever
possible, consolidate and offload.
Move your data to a cold
storage if it's not useful.
So again, summarizing metrics are the
most important signal and in terms of the
value they provide, followed by traces.
Followed by logs.
So now we'll dive into the important parts
of specifically Kubernetes monitoring.
So like I had mentioned, there's
four different components.
The control plane, the nodes, the
pods, and the network monitoring.
Again when monitoring the control plane,
the important thing is the precision.
Instead of ingesting full logs, we should
focus on managed service metrics such as
the API latency and the health checks.
Sampling or summarizing logs can
help reduce data volume while
providing valuable insights.
And again, alerts should be based on
deviations from the expected behavior and
not on based on static thresholds, which
allows for more responsive monitoring.
It's also important to understand
why control plane insights are
important because they are the
brain of Kubernetes monitoring.
And if the control plane is down,
nothing else can function and you
cannot make any updates to the system.
Below I have some of the examples
like the a p you can see that,
see lag and the throttling rates.
Now let's get to the notes.
For smarter node monitoring, it's
essential to track only the key metrics
that truly reflect the system Health,
such as the CCP usage, memory usage, and
disc io avoid getting bogged down with
poor process metrics unless you're in a
debugging or troubleshooting scenario.
Monitoring node degradation through
heartbeats and node ready transitions
can provide early warnings of
potential issues without overwhelming
your data collection effort.
Yeah, and again like I said, you
do not need to provide, collect
all the metrics you can only
collect when something has changed.
So here we wanna touch upon something
important, which is the adoption
and the use of open telemetry.
Again.
Optimizing metrics with open
telemetry can significantly
enhance our observability strategy.
By using explicit aggregation temporality,
we can better manage the data volume
and you can filter some of the labels
to reduce the cardinality and that,
and limit your custom metrics to
only business critical parts, like I
mentioned, that can accrue a lot of costs.
This approach not only saves
costs, it also helps to improve the
clarity of the data that we collect.
So now we go to the port level
visibility like we discussed
in the cloud native world.
It could be a lot of different
microservices that's spin up and spin
down, and it's important to be optimizing
for the port costs, port monitoring costs.
So first one.
Achieving port level visibility
without the noise, it is a ch
challenge that we can tackle.
And by filtering logs at the source,
we can exclude unnecessary data such
as health checks and static endpoints.
Utilizing labels to correlate
telemetry with services enhances
our ability to analyze performance.
And like I mentioned before, adopting
telemetry or open telemetry for auto
tagging and structured tracing can
streamline this process and also improve,
the last one, the network course.
When it comes to networking observability,
it's important to focus on the big issues.
Tracking connection, failures and GNS
resolution problems, which are pretty
common, can provide critical insights
into the network health using sampling
flow routes such as net flow or IP fix.
You can manage data volume
while still capturing essential
information wherever possible.
Also, adopt the EBPF based
tooling, which can offer more
efficient monitoring solutions.
The last one, which I want to touch upon
is not one of this, but is based on the
third party tooling that, that you use.
Wherever you have your data ensure
that you're not duplicating the
telemetry across different tools
and wherever possible filter at the
source, which is ship filtered logs,
whether you're using crabb crop or
fluent parcels, send them when you're
making an analysis to make an analysis
based on the dollar cost per gv four.
Logs and traces and for metrics.
Some of the cases, it could be
the number of metrics shipped.
So below there's a table
which shows different tools
and what is the cost per gb?
What this analysis helps in understanding.
Yeah.
Which is the tool you should be using.
Where should you be sending what?
I wanna present a quick
case study of a customer.
Again, this is a fictional customer,
no specific customer in mind where
implementing some of the strategies they
were able to reduce 40% of their costs
without losing the important telemetry
that they need for troubleshooting.
So by dropping unnecessary health check
logs and by reducing their velocity
levels, they streamlined their data
collection by transitioning from raw
latency logs to Prometheus system grams.
They had the same essential insights
while moving cold observability
data to low object storage
further reducing their expenses.
It's again, you can see how the reduction
in the logs, metrics and traces.
And how it changed before and after.
The monthly dollar cost
is just an example.
It's not the exact dollar cost.
It's crucial to understand what you're
given up when making changes to your
observability Strategy sampling does
not necessarily mean losing visibility.
It's a strategic reduction.
Shortening retention periods
can be effective for most
active monitoring scenarios.
The keys to balance data fidelity
with the trade offs in both
engineering resources and costs.
Like you can see there is a curve and
at some point you lose the value of
adding more metrics or more telemetry.
It's important to understand
what trade offs you are signing
up for, and then deciding
accordingly how you deal with them.
Like I discussed, now we wanna
discuss how you implement this at
your organization and your team.
First off, you have to have a cost
aware observability dashboard.
You have to visualize this
cost per telemetry type, like
I showed in some of the list.
How much do the logs,
metrics, and traces cost?
The second you have to then
attribute it to the different teams.
That are using this telemetry.
So you have to add the tags for the
specific teams and make sure that they,
those chargebacks are at least visible.
And in many cases, the tools
also integrate with the building
export APIs, which are helpful
in building this dashboard.
The second step is you have to
have an observability budget.
It's a proactive step towards
managing costs effectively.
Setting a cap on expenses per cluster per
month for telemetry is almost essential.
Establishing quota for log volume and
custom metrics can help enforce those
limits and it can utilize tools like
flow and Bit and low key, which can
help in maintaining this constraints and
ensuring compliance within your budget.
Here is a framework for your cost
optimization checklist and how you can go
about implementing some of this so that
you can satisfy your observability budget.
First start by dropping any
unused metrics and logs.
That's a drop phase.
Then you shorten retention
periods wherever possible.
If you do not need the logs beyond
30 days of your organization
doesn't have this kind of a
policy, you don't really need them.
For some of the metrics, you can store
them for longer and for logs you can
store them for shorter filter the
telemetry, the source, like I mentioned,
whether it's pods or any other place
for it, just saves in both the compute
time as well as the storage costs and
consolidate tools wherever possible.
And last but not least, make sure you tune
your alert rules to minimize the noise.
We'll also be talking about
it a little bit more now.
First off, I wanted to point out
something with the high card edge metrics.
So wherever possible avoid storing the
labels like user ID or UU ID in your
metrics and use things like tire region
status code, which are both more useful.
And it saves cost too.
Yeah, you can reduce your series
count, which essentially reduces
your Prometheus storage cost.
Now we'll get to the alerts.
Yeah.
De detoxifying your alert noise
is essential for maintaining
effective monitoring.
Here the funnel approach, which is
moving from raw data to filtered,
to routed to actionable alerts, it
is, can streamline your process.
So first off, focus on alerting only
for SLO violations or customer impact.
So start with your alerts.
At the customer impact, which
will both reduce your fatigue and
improve your mean time to recovery.
And yeah, this strategic approach enhances
the overall observability of effectiveness
of your observability efforts,
like I mentioned.
Yeah.
It's important to understand
that observability doesn't
mean logging everything.
Instead, we focus on capturing
valuable signals that provide
insights of system performance.
We prioritizing quality over quantity,
we can keep the cost manageable while
also gaining the insights necessary
to maintain operational excellence.
Once again, focus on the valuable signals,
not the raw volume of data collected.
Just because I collect a lot
of data doesn't mean I have all
the insights that I will need.
The second thing here is important to
note is the fact that sometimes when you
have a lot of this data, it's not easy
to sift through it or to understand.
It's almost like finding
a needle in a haystack.
So just because you have
it doesn't always help.
Yeah like we discussed, so
the end to end observability
flows look something like this.
You start with ingesting the
data, then you process it and
either aggregate it or filter it.
Then you store it and you alert
on it and then optimize on it.
It's important to tag a dollar
value at each stage to measure the
ROI of doing each of the steps.
And yeah, you can, this is essentially a
loop where you iterate to make sure that
you're within your budget and you're also
getting the most value from your data.
I want to end with some of the recommended
tools that I would suggest you check out.
First off, when it comes to
metrics, Prometheus with Anos
is super anos, as the storage is
super helpful, our cortex as well.
You can explore fluent bit for
log filtering in the source.
Open Telemetry, SDKs and collector
for both traces, metrics and logs.
Grafana dashboards are super
helpful for visualizations.
They're both easy to build and
also there's lots of open source
dashboards that you can use.
And EBPF tools like Cilium PC, they
help for network observability.
So once again, I'd like to
reemphasize what we discussed.
These are some of the
common pitfalls to avoid.
You don't have to log everything.
Make sure that you're sampling or
filtering ensure that you're using
the right retention settings for
your telemetry to not duplicate
telemetry to multiple destinations.
Make sure that you have no
met high coordinative metrics.
Metrics which are have,
which increase your bills.
And also alerting on static thresholds.
This could lead to a lot of alert fatigue.
Yeah.
In closing, remember this mantra,
better signals lead to better,
lower cost and happier engineers.
By focusing on the quality of our
observability data, we can enhance
our operational efficiency while
also managing expenses effectively.
And let's strive for a balance that
supports both our technical needs
and our budgetary constraints.
Thanks everyone.
Hope you found this useful.