Hello everyone.
I'm Paulette Baer.
I'm a DevOps engineer
and a technical blogger.
Today I'm so excited to talk about
synthetic monitoring for modern systems.
So let's first understand why
synthetic monitoring, what
problem does it really solve?
Imagine you wake up to a flood
of emails, support ticket,
frustrated users, and lost revenue.
That's what happened with us once.
We had a payment gateway, API, which
crashed at two M, and we found out only
when 50 customers complained about it.
So what if we could catch all
those problem before they happen?
That's what synthetic monitoring
does, and I'll show you how.
So now what is synthetic monitoring?
Synthetic monitoring simulates the
user's interaction with your system.
Think of it as a robot, acting
like your customers, like clicking
through your website, submitting
forms, calling your APIs 24 into
seven even when you are asleep.
And it does all this taste every one
minutes, five minutes, or whatever
the timeframe you choose and from
different places around the world.
Now what is a problem with
traditional monitoring?
So traditional monitoring
waits for something to break,
and it's reactive process.
On the other hand, synthetic
monitoring is proactive.
It doesn't wait for real
users to find out the problem.
So that's the power of
synthetic monitoring.
Now, why synthetic monitoring matters?
So I've got three key reasons for that.
First.
In today's world, our systems
are getting super complex.
We have lots of microservices, serverless
applications, and APIs and second users.
Expectations are higher than ever.
Users want everything to be instant.
2024 is studied.
Said that just two seconds delay can make
20% of your customer leave your website.
Right, and four online is stored.
The data, say the downtime can even
cost you a hundred thousand dollars
per hour, and that's a lot of money.
Third, we have got our
customers all around the world.
Your app might be used by customers
in Canada, USA, or India, so
we want to make sure it works
for everyone from everywhere.
Now synthetic monitoring trends in 2025.
So as of 2024, the global synthetic
monitoring market valued at $1.42
billion, and it is expected to reach
about $3.78 billion by 2033 with
the annual growth rate of 11.5%.
Now what's driving this growth?
So let's see these points.
So first, rapid cloud adoptions.
Companies are moving to the cloud because
it's faster, easier, and it can help
us save cost compared to data centers.
Also, now company wants new solution for
monitoring, better ways to monitoring.
So they are adopting
synthetic monitoring now.
Monitoring tools have integrated AI
and ml, now they find out the issues
much faster and with accuracy using ai.
And third, there's a big shift going on
from reactive to proactive monitoring.
So now companies are aiming
to identify and fix issues
before even the real customer.
So now let's see what are the types
of synthetic monitoring we have?
So first we have got API Monitors
so IT test backend end points and
make sure it is up and running it.
Test your APIs and make sure it
returns 200 successful response and
it is not failing so you can monitor
your critical APIs using this.
API monitors.
Yeah.
Now second is browser based monitoring.
So it simulates what a real user would do.
So it'll click on add to card button.
It'll place data, it'll make the payment.
So all those browser related tests you
can do using browser based monitoring.
Now, scripted monitors, so this type
of monitors follow some fixed steps.
Like what a customer's
user journey looks like.
It'll log into a account, it'll place
the order, maybe add to cart and all
those flow one by one, step by step.
And to end that to that, you can
test with a scripted monitors meters.
Now, ping monitors, so ping
monitors is used to check the
availability of your servers.
Are they online?
Is there any.
Network error that you can
check using ping monitors.
Now come SSL and TLS certificate monitors.
So this monitor ensures safety certificate
of your websites, whether the certificate
has expired or valid, that you can check
using SSL and TLS certificate monitor.
Us now, we have learned so many
things about synthetic monitoring.
Now see how to implement
synthetic monitoring.
So I've got you three
steps to implement it.
First thing is identify critical users
journey and transactions and API.
So identify the problem,
what your users want.
So for example, for.
Healthcare applications.
Users want to have it
always up and running.
They want to access to their
prescription, they want to book
appointment with their doctors.
So this is a critical user journey
and you can't afford downtime in that.
So make sure you test such a scenarios.
So once you identify the
critical user's journey, now
next step is create the script.
Create the scripts for end-to-end
flow, what users would do one by.
And the third point is
select the monitoring tools.
There are several monitoring
tools available in the market.
See what works for you for your use case.
And the fourth step is schedule test to
run 24 to seven from global locations.
So this flow that we have seen, you can
test it every one hour to make sure if
in the last hour it fell, then you can
set up some alerts that you will receive
when your team can take action on that.
So schedule alerts and monitor it
24 into sevens from global location.
If your users are based in USA,
then test it from USA if you
have got your users globally.
Then test it from multiple locations.
Now, last step is analyze the data
regularly to optimize performance.
So once you have data in last 24 hours
for how many times your system failed
and what were the reasons of it.
So once you find out the issue in
your system, you can plan to fix
it so it doesn't break next time.
Now, tools for synthetic monitoring.
So there are many tools available
in the synthetic monitoring, new
Relic, Dynatrace, Datadog, but all
these tools have some features in
common that you should look for.
So first is multi-region testing.
So you can test your APIs and system from
around the world and multiple locations.
Then observability integrations
so you can integrate your other.
Logs into the observability, like
for your systems, logs, stresses and
metrics, and then AI driven insights.
So you can use AI to find
the patterns in your logs.
If you have a huge logs and there
is some application failing,
you cannot pinpoint the problem.
Then you can use AI to
pinpoint the problem.
So I have used this features one, for
one of my Java application, there was
an null pointed exception and there was
a huge code base I couldn't identify
from where it is failing using ai.
It just given me the exact
method name where it is failing.
So use AI and it also gives you some
tips how you can solve this problem
and improve your system's performance.
Now, custom scripting SU support.
So all this tool have scripting support.
You can write your scripts for
your test and nots, Python and
different programming languages.
Now, TIFs for writing synthetic tests.
So there are some best practices
you, you should follow when
you are writing scripting.
So test from multiple region.
We already talk about you should test
it for multiple region if you're.
Users are best globally,
then set realistic threshold.
And so it is very important for your
non-critical application you can afford
if it fails one or two times in a day.
But for critical ones like
payment or banking, you don't
want it to be down even once.
So set threshold realistically now
focus alerts on critical issues.
If you keep setting up alerts for
everything, then you will be overwhelmed
by the alerts and there is a chance
you will miss the critical one.
So always set up alerts
only for critical issues.
Now, validate end-to-end flows, so
you have to validate end-to-end flows.
It doesn't work if add to
card feature is working or.
Order placing is working.
You have to make sure user is able
to log in, add to cart, place, order,
and able to complete the payment.
So always validate end
to end user's journey.
Okay, now key takeaways.
So the main problem, the synthetic
monitoring solves this, it catches
issues before your customers or user do.
So have it implemented and
focus on critical user journey.
What is critical for you?
As I said, for healthcare, it may be
booking appointment with the doctors
or accessing their prescription.
And for banking it may be transferring
funds from one accounts to another and
integrate with your observability stacks.
So you may have logs pure
AWS Cloud Kubernetes.
Or different kinds of logs
so you can integrate it with
your observability stack.
And the last, and not least,
leverage AI to predictive insights.
AI is really helpful when you have got
lots of logs, metrics, and presses.
It can pinpoint the problem,
it can suggest tips to improve
the performance of your system.
Thank you so much for your time.
If you have got any question,
please don't hesitate to reach me.
You can reach out to me through LinkedIn.
Here is the QR code on the screen.
Thank you.
Thank you so much.