Hi everyone.
My name is Alex Hang.
I'm welcome to Comfort two.
I'll talking today about using
the activity logs to predict user
behavior and improve experience.
So what are we talking about?
How can you use it to
predict the user activity?
I try to predict the next activity
of a user based on his previous
activity logs and see how can
you optimize the application?
Why am I doing this well?
Because I want to optimize the
applications to make sure that the
server has resources and to make sure
that the user has the best experience.
I. How am I going to do it?
By adding machine learning in the
application machine learning that
will analyze the activity logs and
some examples to see why you are here.
That'll be the most important part.
But first, a bit of theory.
What's ai?
What's machine learning?
Are those fancy names?
What do they do for you?
We know that activity logs are stored
past active, past actions for users.
Machine learning models are
trained on historical data.
I think you heard about machine
learning about AI in the past few.
Months, years maybe heard of ai.
And you know that there are a lot of
models such as neur networks, long short
term memory, transformers, some other
things can be used to predict activities,
to predict tasks, to predict numbers
and sequences and some other things.
How much machine learning model works?
They let's say they want to
build a system to classify.
An image and say it's a cat or a dog.
How?
I give him 10,000 images of dogs
and that has images of cats.
I'm gonna ask you something right now.
Which one's a cat?
Which one's a dog here?
That's a stupid question.
Of course everybody knows,
which is a dog, which is a cat.
Now he comes a hard question.
How do you know that?
How do you know which is
a cat and which is a dog?
I'm just curious.
I'll give you 10 seconds
to think a bit about it.
The point is a dog, obviously,
but how do you know that?
Did you took the image and analyze it?
Does it have small eyes or big eyes?
Does it have big teeth or small teeth?
Does it have white
skin, white, fall black?
No, you didn't do that.
Okay, come on.
You just saw the image and it's a dog.
How do you know that this one is
more tweaky than you might think?
Actually, you know it because you saw.
Thousands of dogs in your life.
Okay?
You know how a dog looks like,
but you don't spend time to
say, how does it look like?
How are it seals?
How is it mud?
How are his?
How is his nose?
Or whatever.
You don't do that, so you just know.
Your brain is trained to recognize
which is which, because you saw them.
This is exactly how machine
learning models work.
They're using training data to build
complex models in inside memory,
and they're using those models
in order to recognize patterns.
This is what they're doing and
they're doing, using them to predict,
to classify some other things.
So we gonna feed training data
to the machine learning model.
And then once the training is done, you'll
see in a few seconds how training is done.
We'll proceed to testing.
We're gonna give him 100 images,
other images of cats and dogs.
How do we know which is which?
The model should already know,
which is which I'm going to ask
him, which is a cat, which is a dog.
Let's say the data of 100 images,
he managed to classify correctly,
80 of them and 20 are wrong.
In that case, the accuracy is 80%.
The compute accuracy, I'll
say the accuracy is 80%.
I'm happy, if not back to training.
Okay, so how do I use it right now?
I have a few machine
learning models to try.
The first and most common
was linear regression.
The linear regression is not
good for what I want here.
I told you that I want to try to predict
the next action that the user would take.
The linear regression is good for
predicting linear things, how well
it'll take points, let's say the stock
market, the value that the stock market
had in the past two 10 years, and to
try to predict the next value of the
stock market based on historic data.
That's what the integration is doing.
The decision to be used to classify
things well, it'll be good for
classification between cats and
dogs, actually, but not really.
But it'll be good for other
types of classifications.
More simple ones.
Let's say that you want to classify
a text and say if it's English
or French or other language.
It'll take a look.
It'll take a look at the verb,
so the pronouns that some things
I need to try to classify it.
Okay.
The random four is a more
complex decision tree.
It's a collection of decision trees.
This also used for classifications.
We're not going to use it today.
And here comes tricky,
key part, newer network.
This is what we're going to use today.
Neur networks are very good
because they're adaptive.
They can easily adapt to change.
They can easily adapt to patterns,
that can recognize images, that can
do a lot of things, and they're very
versatile, but they're a big black box.
We don't really know from the
outside how they're building
the models and other things.
So now I'm going to ask
you a simple question.
I asked you two slides ago, how did
you know if that is a cat or a dog?
And you said, I just know it.
What if I tell you it's
not really like that?
Of course, for you it's like that.
I just know it's a dog.
Okay, but how do you know that?
He comes a tricky part.
Our brain is structured
like a neur network.
Actually, let me put this right.
The Neur network is
structured like our brain.
The Neur network is built because the
computer scientist, which built it 20
years ago or more than that, sorry.
Ago, something like
this said you know what?
Let's try to mimic the human brain.
How does the human brain work?
We have the input layer.
What is the input in your brain?
Your senses.
You have your eyes, your ears, you
have the, you can touch things,
you can feel things, whatever.
This is the input.
What's the output?
You can do an action.
You can move your hand, you can
speak, you can close your eyes.
You can do whatever you want.
What's the hidden layer then
where that your actual, your
brain is built out of nuance.
This is where the term neuro
network comes from nuances.
Nuances are small cells inside your brain.
You have billions or actually trillions of
them, and those nuances are communicating
between each other, forming super
complex networks in which electrical
currents are circulating and they're
communicating with them with each other.
Millions of times per second,
to create your thought, your
feelings, and other things.
This is what Neuronets
are trying to replicate.
But instead of using cells,
because we can build living cells,
we're going to use functions.
Some small objects functions, classes,
which have a function in them.
It'll be called activation
functions in a second.
What that means, because I wanna
explain right now, those are functions
that are communicating with each
other, each one of them doing a
specific task and showing the results.
Then the final layer would filter
this and give you a final result.
So it's basically like a human brain.
So why do we try to do this?
As I told you, I want to be able
to predict the next action of
a user, but you're going to ask
me why do you want to do that?
Good question.
I want this because I want to personalize
app experience, how to optimize some
common workflows and to identify
which are the common workflow for each
user, and to optimize them, and how
to predict user actions to prepare for
increased workload and specific services.
How do I do this?
Let's give the setup.
Let's say that you have
a user activity logs.
We predicting real time, which
tasks user perform so that we
can predict some usage per task.
We'll be this more new network to
predict the next action for user and some
other alternatives can be a statistical
approach to not go into new net.
To just go on statistics and say out of
100 users, 40 of them are going from home
to newsfeed and from newsfeed to messages.
Okay, that could work, but
it'll no longer be personalized.
There will be some sign of some
sort of a generic optimization.
I want to do something deeper.
I want to do personalized
applications for each user and to
predict for each user activity.
So how I'm going to do this 10 flow.
Okay.
I'm going to say what?
Yeah.
Is a framework built by Google and
maintained by them for building and
running machine learning models.
Why do I, why did I choose 10 though?
Because it can be used to, you can
use existing pre-train models, you
can retrain existing models and can
develop new machine learning models.
You can quickly train new models.
You can adapt various models
that exist and can run it
on server or in the browser.
And this is the main thing why
I chose 10 Flow, because I have
some other alternatives too.
But I want TensorFlow because
they also provide us a browser
solution, a JavaScript solution.
So instead of putting more
pressure on the server.
I try to transfer the workload on
the front end here because to be
something per users, I told you
my task here is to do something
per user to predict his workload.
I want to see what the user will
do what actions he will take, and
the most importantly, how is this?
How should the system react if
I know the next action for user?
I can pre, I can prefetch
some data for it.
I can predict what data he will need.
I can predict the server load for
that and some with other things.
This is why I want TensorFlow,
because I have a TensorFlow JS
JavaScript alternative, and one
more reason is that it's already
used by hundreds of top companies.
I won't even mention them.
What I told you here.
You might think that I'm repeating myself
when I said I can use existing Python
models or I can retrain existing models.
You say, isn't it the same?
Not really.
I can take an existing model already
built by Google, by Amazon, by Meta,
by Adobe, by whatever other huge
company, and use it if it's free.
They're usually published.
Some gonna be published on Hugging Face.
It's one of the most common
websites, hugging face.
Or I can take that model and
simply put it in TensorFlow
and use it for my application.
If you go on TensorFlow website, you
can see that they're already using.
Of them.
But let's say that I have
a more specific use case.
Let's say that Google built a
model to identify cats and dogs.
I'll tell you again,
I'll give that example.
Let's say that somebody built it.
Somebody at a random university
or a random company built it.
Okay, what am I doing with it?
I want it, but I want
something more specific.
I want to be able to identify
cats, dogs, and rabbits.
I can't use that model because he
doesn't know what a rabbit looks like.
So how can I do that?
I take that model and I retrain it.
I retrain the model that they built, and
I give him 10,000 images of rabbits, and I
hope that I'll be able to get the accuracy
on all three classes and secure and
identify catch docs and rabbit and so on.
If that doesn't work, I will
develop my new model from scratch.
I say, okay, leave aside what those guys
built and let me build my own model.
So I will try to show you right
now something I told you about
the models regression decision
three Random forest neur network.
What if I tell you that a newer network
can be so adaptive that can do the
things that the other ones can also do?
Yeah, I'm serious.
Linear regressions, I told you
are exam for approximating things.
Guess what?
You are not.
Oxygen also approximating things.
So how am I going to do that?
I'm going to be the basic
regression example to approximate
the next number in a function.
Let's say have a function or two x
minus one or something like this.
But I won't add the computer, which
is a function, and I'm going to
approximate using a new network.
Obviously the best example, building a
regression, but I'm trying to mimic a
linear regression with an EO network.
Exact exactly in a second.
Why am I telling you this?
I'm going to import it as.
I'm to define the model,
which is sequential.
Exactly.
The data is sequential.
I know all the numbers.
0, 1, 2, 3, whatever.
We're gonna add hidden
layers to the model.
I told you earlier.
This is basically the brain.
The hidden layers are
the brain of the model.
This is what's thinking
and taking decisions.
I'm going to compile the model.
In a few seconds what those things,
loss optimiz and other things mean.
I'm going to define our
import training data.
This is the tricky part.
Now I'm going to define the data.
I'm saying in value minus one, the
form function is minus three in value.
Zero is minus one in one, it's
one in two, it's three, and so on.
So now the question will
be, which is the function?
It's pretty hard to find it out,
but once the model is trained, she
can easily predict it and say, okay,
if in this point it's like this.
Okay.
And then I'll ask him.
What would be the value of
the function in point 20?
And the model will say, okay, based
on the function, it'll be whatever,
it'll be 35 or something like this.
I dunno, I'm not good at math.
I didn't compute it, I just
showed you a random number.
But this is how the model will work.
You try to predict the value
of the function in point 20.
So why do I show you this?
'cause this stuff is not
what I want with the user.
Let's say today.
Let's say that in the second
the user is at page home.
Then he's at newsfeed,
then he's at messages.
Then where will he be in the
next two actions or two actions,
or four actions or so on?
So this is what we're going to do
today, our next price prediction system.
Let's say the user goes from home to
newsfeed to messages to marketplace to
newsfeed, and where does he go next?
I can do a statistical approach
or I can use the newer network to
say, okay, predict me the next page
in which the user will be, this
is what I want to do right now.
How.
I'm going to gather required
data from activity logs because
I know what the user is doing.
I told you most of the
applications were destroyed.
And to transform the data for training
and to initiate the model, train the
model, and use it to predict how,
let me give the practical example.
Let's start writing code.
This is why we can Q Actually,
until now, this was all theory.
Now let's start playing.
So we have a lightweight now,
just application web around
the machine learning app.
We have 10 for model, wanting
to predict the next action,
and we predict the actions.
Then the predict actions will be
used to preload data when ensure
several resources are available.
So how do we get the data?
Let's say that we just
write in memory right now.
I don't want to stress the network
or something we, cause no, let's
just have an array network, which
will mimic the activity log.
So how do we train and run the model?
This is pseudo code, basically three
us just to psdo code, and I give the
actual code in the next five, six slides.
First of all, we're going
to transform the data.
We're going to initiate the model,
train the model, and then we're
going to use it to predict the page.
So how do we do each of those steps?
How do we transform the data?
You have the number of pages that the
application has, let's say 10 pages.
Can I just pass to the model?
Something like home newsfeed
messages shop contact.
No, I can't.
Why?
Newer networks don't really
work to okay with strings.
It just, they can't just
handle words or strings.
We have other models which are
way too complex for us right now
because we are not AI engineers.
We're just software engineers right now.
And, there are more complex
models, which are handling strings.
Some of them are GPT transformers.
Both might have heard of them
on the news, but that's way too
complicated for us right now.
So what we're going to focus on
right now is the Neur network.
So in order to give the Neur network some
data that it can process, we're going
to transform all the data to numbers.
And here we go.
This is what we do here by
transforming into numbers.
We'll just say Page news.
Suite is number one.
Page home is number two.
Page messages is number three,
and so on, and got transformed
this to a vector to a 10.
Basically what we're doing right now
is called the one hot ENC coding.
That's what this is called.
One hot encoding.
This is how tensile flow accepts data.
This is the best way to handle the data.
Tensile flow.
The name tensile means actually vector.
It's some sort.
The 10 is actually some sort of a vector.
It's a more, it's a more powerful
vector using machine learning to
pass data from one led to another.
But basically it's a wrap
around the vector or in way.
So now this is the most important one.
This slide and the next one are
the ones where we came here.
So this how we initiate the model.
We say it's a sequential model, I told you
already, and we add layers to the model.
What are those layers?
I told you in the example we
have nuance, newer network.
So why now add two layers of nuance.
Both of are dance layers because
they have the nuance dance in
general, and this is the tricky part.
First we had the layer with
the activation function level.
This activation level.
What is this layer?
It's rectified linear unit.
This is something that is used in the
Neur network in the internal layers.
I can give you material behind this.
You should search online
for activation functions.
There are.
A lot of them, each one
with each pros and cons.
The most common size are
value gel, and for the final
layer you usually use softmax.
In the last layer softmax.
Softmax is the function that would
take the data from the previous
layer and try to put it in a class
or in a result, we try to classify
it basically, and this is how we're
going to obtain our final result.
The first layer here, we try to act as.
The email layer, which will calculate
things and stuff like this, and the final
layer with Softmax, we try to basically
take the results, make them linear, and
use them to predict the next action.
And we're going to take this and compile
it now, compile the model and can use it.
You can see on the slide here what
you can change here on your example.
You can search online for of this,
how to change the activation,
how to change the units to
optimize the loss and the metrics.
So what do I have right now?
I have the model.
But what is this model?
This is the brain of the system.
Considerably.
You just saw a newborn puppy or a
newborn cat, or a newborn animal.
What can a newborn puppy do?
Nothing.
He can just breed and eat.
And that's all.
Other than that, he doesn't know
how to do anything, but he still
has the brain in it, but the brain
doesn't know how to do anything.
It's same for puppies,
for little cats, for.
Kids for humans, for every,
for everyone with the brain.
So right now we built the brain
of the system, but it's stupid.
He doesn't know how to do anything.
We need to teach him how to do stuff.
So here comes the training part.
We are training the model by
giving him data, using the
fit function model that fit.
We're giving the user the activity,
log the labels, which are the basic,
which is the metrics, and we are
going to see if it can predict them.
If you can predict the next action of a
user, so we're gonna specify 100 epoch.
So try to train your model 100 times
and the batch sizes, how many items
you take in each batch for training.
And now that we are the finish, we
have the model, we have the brain.
The brain has been trained, we can
actually use it to predict, we have
the function model that predict.
And again, to give the user the current
history and tell the model, Hey, this
is the current history, which is the
next item that the user will access.
Tell me and what I going
to do with this result.
Whatever you want, you can pull
out the next assets based on this.
Let's say that you know that the
user will now go to page messages.
If you know that the next page is
messages, you can easily do the
request the server while app is
idle and pull out the way the data
so that when the user clicks on
messages, they approval instantly.
'cause all the data is
already there in the memo.
We can use it to detect
anomalies, user flows.
We can use it to predict the server
workload or some other things.
That was the tricky key part,
doing the actual prediction.
If you're on the full code, you can see
it on a GitHub, I give you here also
the source code, and you see the how to
initiate the model, how to navigate, how
to process the data, how to train the
model, how to predict and how to print it.
If you have any questions, please
feel free to contact me on my email,
my website, my on the conference
website to whatever you want.
And feel free to ask questions.
And thank you very much for attending
Comfort Two, and have a nice day everyone.