Okay.
Hello everyone.
My name is Saddi.
I work at ETG and I am currently
lead the front end team.
I mainly work on improving front tops,
the wax and other technical areas
in the transport product department.
So what are we going to talk about today?
Not long time ago, we
had a typical situation.
With one of our products, something
broke following best practices.
We returned the service off and
on again, but it didn't help.
It also didn't help that there were
no errors in sent and we did not know
where to look to for the problem.
Only after some time, we found out
that the problem wasn't with us at all.
One of our teams that depended
on our service through our common
integration layer, released an update.
Their CPU usage suddenly
increased and this affected
our system without us noticing.
This story made me think how
we can, I really know that the
product works and works properly.
Recently, our team launched
a new product car rental.
The service is available for B2B
partners and corporate clients.
We launched this service.
I decided to approach this problem more
thoughtfully, so how we can know that
the products works and works properly.
The simplest way is to type the
application address in the browser
and see that everything works, pages
open request present, and gone.
But you'll agree that checking
the application this way
every time is impossible.
Especially when support comes to
us and say everything is broken.
In this case, there is no
point in checking anything.
We're already down and losing money.
We want something that instead of
support, our clients will tell us in
time that something is going wrong
and your developer should take a
look before the application crashes.
As you might guess, I'm talking about
the three pillars of observability,
metrics, traces, end locks based
on which we can understand what
happening with our application.
So now we will learn what is observability
and what is monitoring, what are
the key difference between them?
What's the metrics and what types
are there pure technical metrics?
How SLA different from SLO and
SLI and what is an observability
passport and how does it help?
So let's let's start with the basics.
What is the metric and
what types are there?
Let's start with a simple definition.
A metric is an iCal indicator
that measures a cer certain
aspect of system operation.
For example, page load time,
number of errors or presentation of
successful requests to the server.
End goal metrics help us measure,
understand, and improve our applications.
What types of metrics are there?
For example technical ones.
Technical metrics describe the internal
processes of the system they're
most often needed by developers
to understand what's happening
under the hood of your application.
For example, CPU usage, RAM usage
peer response time, and go on then
are also business metrics that show
how efficiently the application
helps achieve business goals.
For example, conversion in purchase
organization, user retention, or
for example, giving you per user.
But there are also metrics that difficult
to attribute the one category because they
affect both technical and business sites.
They are also called hybrid metrics, for
example performance and page load speed.
The well known web vitals by Google.
One hand metrics describe purely technical
characteristics of your application page,
load speed reaction time, et cetera.
But in the end, all this affect cell
user experience and in search in
search results, which can affect your
business wallet, or, for example,
the number of errors in the system.
Frequent errors, areno users, and increase
the load on support and can affect
business metrics such as user tention.
Another good example of hybrid metrics,
which lay between developers and business
can be availability and availability.
Medics, S-L-A-S-L-O and SLA.
This set of metrics focuses on measuring
fulfillment of commitments to deliver high
quality, reliable, and stable services.
What does it mean and why is it needed?
So SLA service level agreement
is an agreement about providing
a level of service made between
business and development.
For example, agreements commit that
the service will be available 99
and 9% of the time during amount.
SLA in this case is used as a
formalization of business expectations.
SLO service level objective is an internal
goal related to system availability.
SLL defines more detailed indicators that
developers focus in their daily work.
For example, API response API response
time should not exceed the 200
milliseconds for 95% of requests.
SLL helps technical teams focus on what
is important for their users and set
realistic benchmarks for monitoring.
SLA service level indicator
is directly a metric that
measures the fulfillment of SLO.
This is a numerical indicator
based on monitoring data.
For example, if SLO says that 95%
of request should be proposed in
200 milliseconds, then SLI is the
percentage request that actually fit.
Within this time.
How do this medics help to solve problems?
Availability metrics help developers
evaluate the current service level.
You know exactly how your
performance goals match reality.
They help prioritize tasks.
For example, if the availability
level approaches the SA boundary,
this is a signal to immediately
address the problem and help
communicate with business metrics.
Allow you to talk to business in the
language of goals and priorities.
Explaining how technical
problems can affect users.
A special place in working with
SLO is occupied by error budget.
This is concept that helps establish
a balance between stability and the
speed of implementing new features.
How does it work?
Error budget is the alert level
of deviations that you can
afford to stay within SLO limits.
For example, if your SLO is
99 and 9% of trackable time,
then your error budget is 0.1%.
What does error budget affect?
First, it determines priorities.
If error budget is almost exhausted, the
implementation of new feature is frozen,
and the team focuses on solving problems.
Therefore error budget can be used
as part of sprint planning and to
avoid chaotic switching between tasks.
Second, it simplifies decision making.
For example, you can explain to business
that implementing a risky feature now is
a DI direct pass to violating your SLA.
And third, it help find balance.
If error budget is not exhausted, the team
can safely experiment with new features
result fear of breaking production,
and you have already.
Notice it that collecting
metrics is not enough.
This is the main difference between
regular monitoring and observability.
Metrics should be mandatory dynamically
anticipating trends and proactively
acting to prevent negative outcomes.
When you have just set up Ming,
you can answer the question, is
the system working as expected?
You looked at the medics.
Yes, requests are going through no
errors, and if the load is increased
monitoring will show you an alert.
But if your system has the properly
property of observability, then you can
already answer the question, why does
the system work in the way it works?
For example, after launch time the
load increases and during this time,
it's better to not release anything.
And this is will help you more when
you're analyzing complex incidents.
In the end, ator helps understand
that something's broke.
Observability helps figure
out why it's happening.
So now that we'll know everything we
learned let's turn to our mind question.
How can I understand that
product works and works properly?
Now, we know that this question consists
of two parts, how to understand that it
works, the part related to monitoring and
how to understand that it works properly.
The part about observability in general.
When I asked myself this question, I
thought that I needed just the page in
Confluence or a folder with benchmark.
From where I can see everything that
I want to know about my application.
Of course, without ever
thinking, I call this list of
links, observability, passport.
So what's my, so what's an insight
of my observability passport?
The first things I set up was,
of course, an error tracker.
In our case, it's Sentry, but
it can be absolutely anything.
Whatever you like.
Even a simple concern log.
The main things is that this solution
should let you understand that something
went wrong and you know how to fix it.
Next, after finishing quiz
monitoring part, it's time
to think about observability.
Would it be enough to close the question
of errors by catching and analyze them?
Analysis is good, but still setting
up work in such way that errors do
not occur at all is another level.
How to achieve this obviously conduct
analysis before an error occurs, and that
means we need to analyze the court itself.
The range of tools for this is simply
huge from basic s and test runners,
providing cut coverage metrics to static
analyzers, detecting vulnerabilities
in the app and its dependencies.
And if test and coverage are more
about monitoring, then finding
and analyzing vulnerabilities
is more about observability.
One of such tools that allow
analyzing found vulnerabilities,
which we use is the defect Dodger.
Defect dodger offers many
metrics to get visual information
about trends and insights of
vulnerabilities in your organization.
Similar to 99 and 9% availability
targets, defect dodger helps set
SLA specifically for resolving
issue based on their severity.
In our case, obviously the SLO for the
number of critical vulnerabilities in
production is zero, and the time to fix
already found ones seven days, which by
the way, the facto suggests by default.
Then based on the criticality of the found
problem and the basis of your agreements
in the team the problem is taken into
work and should be fixed within a certain
period, which corresponds to your SLA.
All right.
Coly, this tool vary, but the main idea is
using SLAs to manage application stability
like API availability centric errors or
code big discount it to, it always comes
down to the following set of actions.
It dify area to monitor API
errors, vulnerabilities, and go on.
Define error boundaries.
What?
Devi deviates from normal behavior.
Set an error budget, acceptable
tolerance level, collect your
errors, metrics, and go on.
Visualize data in dashboards, set up
alerts as needed, and assign owners and
define response protocols for incidents.
Of course, the observability passport
will not complete will not be complete
without collecting basic medics such as
memory consumption, CPO load, or others.
In our case provided by the pro
client package, and it'll also not
be complete without informative
logs from our application.
As logs are rec, are records of events.
They're easy to create.
For example, a simple concern.
Log logs give us detailed
information about specific types
of events that interested us.
For example, logging all requests.com
to our application or that we make.
But logging as a rule happens only
within one component of the system
for which we are responsible.
We write type of intent application,
therefore we can add login only here.
theEnd might be the responsibility
of the completely different team and
they made write logs at their purpose.
But as you understand, there are
cases when error secure and one
component of the system is not enough.
The reason maybe much deeper to
understand and you need the whole picture.
This is where traces comes to help.
Traces are similar to logs but except
that is, is a summary list of all
events from all involved components.
Often to ensure the correct output
of logs from different components.
They use some global identifiers
that allow taking the pass of
the request to all components.
Like request ID or slash id.
And to collect all this beautifully
into a nice graph you can connect
tools like Open Telemetry plus Jagger.
Next, another related concept
of logs is profiling like logs.
Profiles are records of some emails
within one component only profiles use
the most detailed information about
what is happening under the hood.
Most often profiles are used
to analyze bottlenecks along
the path of your request.
The part of the request that takes
the longest to execute is most likely
can be optimized to speed up the time
of your entire request for profile.
We also use senti.
We look at similar dashboards.
We see which endpoints and
pages work the longest and they
to profiles for improvement.
Okay, updating the passport and the
cherry on top is or why is product
analytics, how users use your application.
That's it.
You choose events in your application
that you want to track, and based
on them, you build a typical user
scenarios for your application.
Then together with your product
owner, you decide what this means and
how to improve the user experience.
So that they make a decision to buy
your product faster, even though product
analytics is as far as possible from the
technical indicators of the application.
We managed to catch several
cases in practice for not
properly working components.
For example the currency switching
even integrated rated an extra
trigger and we realized that the
component was not working correctly.
Or for example, an EBIT that should only
trigger on the listing page for some
reason it was sent on the booking page.
We also figured this out and
found a problem in the cash.
And that's basically it.
We add to the past per the SLA for
availability, which we talked about
earlier, test coverage and swagger.
And my passport is ready.
Now having such a passport, I can
generally find out the domain of
my application for a quick checkup.
I can track errors by their name, see
the number of events for certain period,
and receive detailed information.
The user data, browser calls, stack
request responses, and on I can collect
and analyze system logs for quick
identification and resolution of problems.
I can receive real time indicators
of performance and system status,
response time, aggregate, or
resource usage, and et cetera.
I can see the number of potential
vulnerabilities, assess the
risk and take proper action.
I can see metrics collected directed from
the container such as the amount of memory
used or the number of open connections.
I track which service characteristics
like availability or latency
have SLO define and monitor their
performance against those targets.
I monitor the error budget, align with
SLO targets to balance availability
with feature delivery, and I can
see the current percentage of code
that is covered by unit tests.
And I can see the current swag you're
describing, the IPI for other services.
And that's all.
That's all for my site.
Thank you for your attention, help you.
This observability passport also will
help you build your applications.
Bye.