Hi everyone.
I'm Marmo.
I'm currently working as a senior
software engineer at Nvidia, and
I'm very excited about this talk.
And the topic is open telemetry
or open tele solving absorbability
problems for creating new ones.
Let's get started.
The agenda of this topic of the talk is
I will start with the basic introduction
about mental, elementary, and later we'll
into the promise and kind of issues solve.
And later we'll go over the reality
of open telemetry and the problems
the new problems it creates, and and
we'll also discuss about whether does
Open Telemetry makes sense and the
strategies for taming some of the
issues the open telemetry opens up.
And finally, the feature
outlook and the conclusion.
So at first the introduction open Tele
is a collection of a PS and SDKs that
would help users to instrument generate
and collect and export the tele data.
It covers all basic absorbability
signals like metrics, logs, and traces.
If you look into the picture at the left
hand side the open provides a different
a PS SDKs to instrument application.
At the middle, you have a
open Telemetry character.
The Open Telemetry character is very
powerful aggregator that could basically
collect your metrics and send to a
different absorbability backends.
For example ME metrics can be sent
to some of the third party vendors
like graph and Cloud Datadog.
Similarly, locks can be sent to
Elasticsearch Splunk tracers could
be sent to different other vendors.
And the promise and the core
problems on the open solves.
The first most important is
the vendor lock in elimination
pre open telemetry world.
Every third party vendor has a different
proprietary agents for the SDS APIs
and Open Telemetry solve this problem.
So you can basically instrument once
your application and you can send
to whatever third party vendor or
whatever backend you wanna send to.
And the other problem it
solved is unified standards.
It standardized different open standards
like it combined open tracing and open
sensors, and it also standardized tele
collection across different languages.
And the other problem it solved
is complete signal coverage.
As I mentioned before it supports
instrumenting and collecting
metrics, traces, and logs.
And also it solves the problem
of co correlating these
signals to analyze the deeper.
And the other problem it solved
is suppression of con concerns.
It decoupled meta collect telemetric
collection from the analysis.
Yeah, as I mentioned, the open
telemetry is very powerful aggregator
and you can also choose any
compatible backend you want to choose.
And the other important problem
it solved is auto instrumentation
before open telemetry here.
If you wanna, instrument your
code to collect different signals.
You need to write a lot of boiler plate
and custom code and open telemetry.
In many of the cases it provides
auto instrumentation capabilities.
And instead of writing any code, you
can just start exporting over telemetry.
And it also had very
good community adoption.
It's one of the second largest
active CNCF project, and it has
very active roadmap given all the
advantages and problems it solved.
It also contributed to some new problems.
So in reality users and community adapters
have been facing different problems.
The first one is technology, ma if you
look at, to if you look at the open
telemetry documentation if you want to get
started with you'll be worried with the
different technologies like SDKs and APIs.
So it it has too many layers of
indirection and abstractions and also
architecturally it's quite complex.
Each component has its own unique
configurations and different
a lot of components, lot of
exporters, process tickets.
It's not very easy to get started.
And the other problem is the language
implementation in inconsistencies.
So one of the pro, one of the
problems open telemetry solve is if
you, and if your dev environment is
polyglot, it unifies how you collect,
how you instrument your telemetry.
But in reality when you are implementing
augment Elementary in your environment.
There are tricks and trips.
Each language has, and
there are implementation
consistencies inconsistencies.
And the other problem is
the maturity spectrum.
Different components are at
different maturity levels.
For example if you consider the broader
signals tracing is the most most matured.
And later comes the
metrics and the logging.
Logging is very recent entrant.
And it was only when, only recently.
And also getting sorted, decided
as a top barrier to adoption.
And also, yeah, it's very difficult
to debug when something goes wrong.
Problems across instrumentation,
col collection, export.
And other is the character configurations.
So you'll be basically, you'll
see a very big a ML configurations
and mismatched component names.
And sometimes you need to
configure our own authentication.
And they will see lots of
connect connectivity issues.
So if you want to get something
resolved with the community and if
you are trying to file an issue you'll
be bonds between a different reports.
So given the problems it solves and the
kind of implementation challenges we have
seen when does Open telemetry make sense?
So it makes sense when you have, when when
you are organization has a very large and
diverse technology stacks and you wanna
standardize across these environments.
And it helps when value exceeds
the implementation complexity.
So you need to take a call and
look at the tradeoffs there.
And also if your automation is looking
for a very strong rental, neutral
telemetry collection and exporters,
then open telemetry makes sense.
It would be a very long-term investment
and you will have a lot of flexibility
in the observability providers.
It also makes sense.
Very very makes sense.
In the cloud data environments, it
is very ideal for distributed systems
under monitoring container containerized
applications like Kubernetes.
It also provides it makes sense where
you have data flexibility requirements
where you need to have good control over
your data collection and the routing.
And they also need the filtering
capabilities to reduce nice and costs.
And you wanna add custom tag
for your automation searching.
So how do you strategize
and obtain the tele issues?
So you can start with auto
instrumentation options.
Big, you can begin with language
specific auto instrumentation.
For example, in E case E case is
AWS managed Kubernetes service.
So it has open telemetry characters
that they can use by default.
And also you can start with the
more matured signals like as I
mentioned before tracing is the
most matured open telemetry signal.
So you can start with that and later and
expand to metrics and logs and also try to
follow the latest best practices leverage
semantic connections and optimize the
attributes and the labels you're using.
And further faster the troubleshooting.
You can also use the local exporters.
It also makes sense to do implementation
instead of going for one big bank
adoption, it can start small and iterate.
You can focus on critical
user flow at first and expand
gradually as an expertise grows.
And also we can depend on
the community resources.
Instead of only depending on documentation
I can look into community resources
like blogs and different talks.
You can depend on those.
And also vendor distributions can for
adoption, for example, recently Grafana
Cloud has come up with their own open
telemetry folk called Grafana Ally.
So it makes implementation
adoption little easier.
Also, there are lot, lots of active
community support and extinctions.
So we can make use of those to
come out to overcome some of the
challenges and some of the tele.
The open telemetry creates our
future outlook and beyond there
are lots of promising developments.
One is semantic is reaching stability.
This is very promising development
and the Open Telemetry collector
is also approaching version one.
This is a very powerful aggregator
and besides tracing logs and metrics
profiling has been becoming very popular.
Pen telemetry is also adapting that
signal and it's planning to support it.
And gene Absorbability is also integration
within Open Telemetry ecosystem.
It's also promising
the ongoing challenges.
There are still many challenges
like documentation problems
complexity management and
standardizing different test cases.
Given all this open telemetry
is still the number one solution
for your observable needs.
If you're looking for a strong go
neutral all comprehensive solution.
Thank you.
Thank you all for your attention.