Hi everyone, this is Sheika.
I work for Guidewire Software.
I'm a project manager there.
I've been with Guidewire.
I've been working in the property
and casualty industry for the last
10 years, and today I'm here to talk
about how observable systems have.
These cloud-based identity systems
today let you see exactly what's
happening to your identity checks.
And they do this by using smart
checking of the biometrics.
Maybe it's fingerprinting, facial
recognition or voice recognition.
There's also AI involved that
analyzes the process to identify
any issues and improvements.
And then we have blockchain
technology to ensure everything
is transparent and it's secure.
The observable systems help the
team identify issues much more
quickly, and that reduces the time.
Time taken to identify a problem by 87%.
That means the systems have less downtime.
We have quicker resolution and response,
and we have better user experience, which
adds to system reliability and resilience.
So observability observable identity
systems give realtime insight into the
entire verification process at the code.
These systems use instrumentation, meaning
they capture important data points as
users go through the verification journey.
This could include biometrics, system
response time, or error patterns.
And all this data is then fed into
the monitoring and alerting tools that
help teams detect issues like a failed
verification or as suspicious login.
And as they, and we can record it, we
can get to know about this in real time
rather than waiting for hours and getting
to know it about hours or days later.
And we don't stop there.
There's also a technical layer involved.
These systems also translate that
raw data into meaningful business
insights to help insurers make smart
decisions around security, process
improvements and customer experience.
For example, let's say insurers
can use this information to
spot security risk early on.
It helps us to modify, oh.
Optimize.
It helps an insurance company
to optimize the customer
journey by removing bottlenecks.
It also justifies investments in
better tools or infrastructure
based on hard data.
In short, we can definitely say that
the observability turns what used to
be a black box into a clear process,
driven in a data driven process
that improved customer experience.
Modern.
These this modern observability has taken
fraud detection to a really next level.
Unlike traditional monitoring, these
systems can now detect even sophisticated
swooping attacks like fake IDs or
deep fakes with 99.99% accuracy.
And they do it in near.
In a real time.
In real time.
This is a huge leap forward giving
businesses, including insurance
companies, a much stronger protection
against fraud and reducing the time
it takes to respond to threats.
Moving on to operational improvements,
to observability observable.
I systems don't just improve security,
but they also offer a lot of.
Operational benefits by giving systems,
giving teams deep visibility into
system performance to help spot and
fix issues before it affects customers.
And this includes capabilities
like transaction tracing,
which helps identify failures.
Early on and helps to understand
why the slowdowns are happening.
It also helps us, helps in capacity
planning to anticipate and prepare
for usage spikes, and also supports
continuous improvement by turning
system data into actionable insights.
And in short, they help operations
run smoother, faster, and more
in a more proactive fashion.
Dispute tracing lets a user track a
single request as it moves to the multiple
web services, multiple microservices
involved in the verification process.
And this helps, one, understand how
each part of the system is performing
and where delays of failures accurate.
Let's go through an example here.
Let's say the ex, let's go through an
identity verification example here.
Imagine a user is going through an
online identity verification process.
Here's how distributed tracing
works across the different
microservices in what?
First they'll use a
document, upload servers.
So the user uploads, the IT
document and tracing captures
how long the document took and
whether the files were successfully
received or there were any errors.
If there were errors, it
also captures the logs.
Then we use the document
verification validation service.
The document is then scanned,
is now scanned for authenticity,
expiration, and tampering.
At this step, the tracing, so shows
if the validation passed or failed
and how much processing it took.
Then we use the biometric matching
service Here, the user takes a selfie
for face match and tracing logs, the
image capture comparison time, and
the confidence score of the match.
The full service is the
data verification service.
The personal info is verified
against a third party sources.
For example, it could be
government databases, it could
be credit bureaus, et cetera.
Here, the tracing records, each
external call and how long they took,
helping spot third party delays.
Last, but the not the least is the
risk assessment engine and all the
results are fed into a risk engine
that calculates a trust score.
Here tracing shows how data flowed
in, how rules were applied, and
if any step triggered risk flag.
Now you must be wondering why it matters.
It matters because with distributed
tracing, we can pinpoint slow services.
Let's say if the biometric
matching is consistently lagging,
it can help us identify that.
It can also spot failures early on.
For example, if the document
validation service is crashing into
intermittently, it'll it'll help us
to identify that it also helps improve
performance and also deliver a smoother
customer experience by solving issues
before users are impacted by it.
Moving on to the advanced correlation
techniques for identity events,
advanced corelation techniques help.
Connect related events across
different identity verification steps.
Turning individual data points
into a clear actionable story.
Let's take a real world example.
Let's say a user is going
through verification.
The document scan is successful,
the biometric matches slightly off,
and the database check returns.
Inconsistent data alone, each
event might seem fine, but.
Or just slightly usual or slightly
unusual, but when correlated or
connected together, they could indicate
a spoofing attempt or an identity fraud.
So how it works, correlation engine
connects events from across the
system, document scanning, biometrics,
checks, backend validations, et
cetera, using machine learning.
They built normal behavioral patterns.
Example, time taken, device
type and match scores.
When patterns deviate even slightly,
the system flags it early for review.
Why it matters, it helps detect complex
fraud patterns that would be invisible
if each component were reviewed In
isolation, it reduces FA reduces false
positives by understanding context.
Enables proactive proactive
action, stopping problems before
they escalate or affect users.
There's also behavioral there's also
behavioral based anomaly detection.
So behavioral based anomaly detection
is about spotting unusual user
behavior that could signal fraud
or security threats even when
credentials are correct, how it works.
First we establish the
behavioral baselines.
The system learns what normal looks
like for each user or a group such
as typical logging times usual.
Devices, locations, common pattern and
document uploads and biometric processes.
Then we apply machine
learning tools to it.
These tools monitor user activity
in real time and compare it to the
established bake line, looking for subtle
deviations faster than normal form.
Repeated, failed biometric
attempts, loggings from
unusual locations and devices.
After that, we calculate the risk scores.
Each action is scored based
on how risky it seems.
The more behavior devis from the
norm, the higher the risk score then
will trigger adaptive authentication
based on the risk scores.
So the risk goes.
Across a certain threshold, the system
can ask for additional verification.
Like in OTP flag, the session
for manual review or block the
action entirely looks too risky.
Why?
It matters because behavioral
based detect goes beyond static
rules or password checks.
It helps catch sophisticated attacks
by focusing on how users behave and
not just what credentials they use.
But with all this information, which
we, behavioral information which we
capture, we also need to take care of.
Privacy.
So implementing observable identity
systems means walking a fine line
between comprehensive monitoring
and user privacy protection.
The key points here, which we need to take
care of is the comprehensive monitoring
needs to ensure strong security and smooth
operations system need to capture detailed
telemetry like user activities, system
performance, and authentication behavior.
We need to take into
account privacy ations.
However, this data often includes
sensitive user information, to limit
what's collected, to only what's necessary
and anonymize or encrypt personal data,
we need to have a balanced approach.
The goal is to find the right
balance, enabling visibility for fraud
detection and troubleshooting without
overstepping privacy businesses.
This includes being transparent about
what data is collected, providing
controls and opts applicable, and
designing systems with privacy.
By default.
If we can say a successful identity,
observability strategy should
deliver security and insight,
but also earning gives a trust
through responsible data practices.
Now let's talk about the roadmap for.
The implementation of these verification
systems, implementing and observable
identity systems is a phase journey.
It's just not a one-time setup.
It evolves across five key stages.
First is the assessment stage.
We start by evaluating the current
capabilities, what telemetry already
being collected, where are the blind
spots in IDD verification, and are
there any tools and gaps in monitoring?
The idea here is to establish a clear
baseline and identify quick wins.
Next will be the instrumentation.
Now we add instrumentation to capture
detailed data across identity workflows.
Example, document upload,
biometric mash, third party
verification, and risk scoring.
We need to make sure we make all steps
traceable with real time data points.
Then we do the integration.
We introduce automated alerts and
adaptive responses, high risk behavior
triggers, setup, authentication,
system error, notify relevant teams.
Instantly.
The idea has to reduce manual
intervention and improve response times.
It's the refinement time,
the refinement step.
We need to continuously improve, and we
can do that by tuning machine learning
models for behavioral based detection.
Updating baselines as user behavior,
evolve and expanding visibility
to new components or channels.
The goal here is to optimize
accuracy, reduce false positives,
and support scalability.
The full implementation can take
any time between six months to 12
months, but if we try the incremental
approach, we can start getting the start
utilizing the benefits within two to.
The key takeaways and next steps.
The first is the measurable benefits 87,
80 7% reduction in meantime to reduction
shows real power of observable systems,
enhanced data detection accuracy through
advanced techniques like behavioral
analysis and event go relation operational
gains to transaction tracing, capacity
planning, and improvement transforms raw.
Telemetry into business intelligence to
better security and process decisions.
We need to make sure that we have
a right balance, privacy balance.
Effective observability requires a
careful balance between monitoring
and data production systems aligned
by privacy, with privacy by default,
respecting user data while ensuring
security, anonymization transparency and
regulatory compliance are non-negotiable.
Mean to use a holistic approach,
need to combine instrumentation
monitoring, machine learning based
analytics, and adaptive authentication
across the identity lifecycle.
Need to support distributed
tracing across microservices.
The journey we need to
have a strategic journey.
Implementation is phased, begins with
assessment that moves to instrumentation
integration automation, definement.
The full rollout takes six to 12
months, but we can see the benefits
within two to three months itself
if we use the incremental approach.
Thanks everyone for having,
that's all I had for today.
Thanks everyone for listening
to this presentation.