Hey everyone.
Thanks so much for joining today.
Before we go further, a little
bit about me, I am Dennis Tomer
de, and welcome to my talk.
And my talk is dashboards
are not dramas anymore.
So let's start.
Have you ever been right in the middle
of debugging a critical production issue
and when suddenly you get a message?
From someone in finance saying, Hey,
our cloud bill just increased by $5,000.
What happened?
Yeah, that syncing feeling
isn't pleasant, right?
All of a sudden you are not
just trying to fix the problem.
You are also stressed about how much
monitoring tools you are using might
be cost while you are solving it.
Now in theory, monitoring our
system should be straightforward.
Ideally, it'll give us clear visibility
to catch issues before users do
help us quickly develop problems
when they occur, give us insight
into our system performance, and
also help us plan capacity needs,
and sometimes source stakeholders
that everything's running smoothly.
Sound reasonable, doesn't it?
But the reality in most cloud
environment is quite different.
We often end up in what I called the
monitoring fear cycle, as you can see in
this slide, which looks something like
we deploy a new service and set up basic
monitoring, then an incident happened.
When we realize our visibility
isn't enough, so we add more
metrics, logs, tracing, but then
cloud bill spike unexpectedly.
So someone from finance
team ask us to cut costs.
So we scale back monitoring.
But again, another incident happened
and be back to the Esquire one.
This cycle repeats again
and this in justly.
I personally seen this happen.
A team I work with built great dashboards
for their service, the tracking
everything from response time and
error rates to database transformation.
But as their service grew from
10 to 50, their monitoring
cost increased dramatically.
Eventually they had to delete
many dashboards and sample their
metrics at only 10% to manage costs.
Yeah, so there are some
points of practical impact.
First one is self sensor engineering
don't create the dashboards they
need because they're afraid of costs.
Second one is delayed detentions.
Go unnoticed longer because we are
not collecting the right data we want.
Third one is blind debugging.
Sometime when problem occur, we lack the
visibility to solve the them quickly.
Fourth one, crisis monitoring.
We only turn on the full monitoring
during emergencies, which is exactly
when we don't need extra stress.
Fifth one is knowledge gap.
New team member never learned to
use observability tool because
it seems as a scare resources.
Let me show you how this play out
in a typical incident response.
For example, consider how this
play out in a typical incident.
As you can see in this slide at
10:00 AM users report slowness.
But there are no early volume.
By 10 15, the team start looking at
basic metrics, but they have no idea,
and then they request permission to
enable detail details monitoring,
which only happen at after 30 minutes.
After waiting another 30 minutes
for data, they finally pin pinpoint
the database bottleneck at 11:15
AM So resolve the issue by.
After 15 minute, but the next
day monitoring is scaled back
down again to save cost, like
nearly two hours of impact.
Mostly just wasting for visibility.
It's not just incident every day
development suffer to, I have
seen many developers avoid adding
essential custom metrics because
it, its needs management approvals.
Team often settle for generic
dashboards that don't match their needs.
Historical data is quickly deleted, making
them exporting trends Im impossible.
Logging levels are set so high so they
miss valuable debugging information.
Also, all because of cost concern.
That's not right.
I also once was a senior engineer.
Spent three hours optimizing
monitoring just to save $200 per month.
A clear misuse of valuable time and worst
off, all these costs are unpredictable.
Sometime it's 200, sometime
is 300, sometime's 500.
These are unpredictables.
Traffic spikes or bug unexpectedly.
Inhale your monitoring bills overnight.
So exactly what, why, exactly.
Why is monitoring so expensive?
It boils down to how cloud and platform
observability typically is worse.
First agent, collect your data
from servers, then send it off to
the central collection services.
Data is stored, indexed, and run
curries, though the dashboard alert,
this is, and so this architecture
create four separate cost drivers.
First one is data transfer.
Moving data from your instance to
monitoring service, which is cost money,
especially across different regions,
all to the different third party tools.
Second one is ingest processing.
Passing, transforming and
indexing monitoring data,
required more compute resources.
And third one is storage.
Keeping your data available for queries,
especially at higher resolutions.
And last one is query cost.
Sometime providers even charge
for your own, accessing your
own data, which is not correct.
This cost structure for us to build
compromised monitoring system.
As you can see in this slide, how much
code we have to write to get some little
bit idea and also how much it is complex.
And another one you can see
is this setup, alerting.
This is also too much complex to
just set up an alert, a simple task.
So what's the alternative?
The key is making observability
a built-in feature for your in
infrastructure, but not expensive.
Add-on in a fixed cloud model.
Fixed first cloud model monitoring
become part of the platform mat
logs and T traces are collected
automatically without additional charge.
There are no data transfer fees, retention
periods are predictable and included and
curing your data doesn't extra charge.
So that's the good way.
Yeah.
So let me show you what this
look like with Seamless, a
fixed cost cloud platform.
I have working with, as you
can see in the dashboard slide,
which you create a server.
Dashboards covering CPU memories,
disc io and network performance
and more With thir 30 days of high
resolution historical data, there are
no setup, no additional cost, and no
complicated pricing that look good.
Yeah.
Also look logs work similarly, again,
without not worrying about the charges.
Here's the difference between
make in the real world incident
management at 10 and 10:00 AM
monitoring catches issu immediately.
Then firing an early alert within minutes.
Detailed metrics are accessible and
allow team to quickly identify a
database connection issue by after
10 minutes, the issue is fully
resolved immediately after that Word.
Afterward the team easily create
an additional data board to
track this scenario better.
All without cost worries.
This means the issue is resolved in
25 minutes instead of nearly two hours
waiting for, to get some ideas reducing.
And this co this will also reduce
stress and improving outcomes.
Ultimately observability should
tend to be something we fear.
It should be something
we rely on every day.
Whether you are exploring, like
platform or rethinking your current
setup, the goal should be clear.
After all, you can't fix what you
can't see, and you'll never look
if you are scared of the bills.
So thanks so much.
Thank you so much as this and this is
a prerecorded session, so if you have
any questions or any doubt regarding
this talk or want to chat about new
tech or developer problems, feel free
to ping me up on the LinkedIn or tutor
and these are my handles, so bye-bye.
Thank you everyone.