Hi.
Welcome to the session of OB Observ 2.0.
Much more than just logs,
mattress and crisis.
Hi, this is Neil Sha,
a DevOps community guy.
I work as a Toyota advocate and
middleware, and I also organize
a lot of communities around
DevOps in my local region like.
Google Cloud, CNCF, HashiCorp,
another, more than Encrypt plus
hackathons and have given talks
in 10 plus conferences, including
platform con, KCDQ, con Linux phase.
So coming to our student's
agenda is evolution.
Open tele role, reducing
downtime with order collector.
ML in already optimizing already
cost AI driven future and takeaways.
So seeing the ation observ already
around 2015 people were also
using the monolith applications.
So they were using tools like
material and Grafana, and then it
came the era of tele explosion.
A lot of data coming out from
application infra and things, and there
are a lot of chaos, leaks of data.
So it created a scenario where a
lot of data is there, but it becomes
very challenging to tackle that.
Annie, around 20 30, 20 23.
The era of AI came and people are using
AI to improve their observing spectrum.
So from firefighting to force it.
Imagine a scenario where it's 2:00 AM
you and your application production
is down and there are tons of data
floating out, and you don't know
actually what you need to dig in and.
It takes a lot of manual effort
for that to understand the problem
and meanwhile there is downtime.
It also affects the business cable.
Now we in a better world, we also
already system NetX software is early.
You have AI flag the growing
risk before any outrageous.
You act proactively avoiding
the incident altogether.
Firefighting to force availability
0.0 from, we have shifted from
DIQ to predictive just like this.
We don't want manual troubleshooting.
We want auto explain incidents so that
we don't need to hurry at the last
time and do a lot of things manually.
Next comes the enhanced capabilities.
There are correlation contextualization,
so there is automatic data
correlation from front end to back.
There is AI ion, there is extra root cause
because coming with a lot of automation
of ai, we have required a lot of kids.
That helps us to understand
and have a better root cause.
In today's journey and 2.0 we have, or
we'll covering the evaluation already.
Actually we covered.
We'll cover the rise of open
Telemetry ml, LLM, already
reason downtime with collector.
We understand how the
order connector works.
We'll also see the cutting costs
with smarter ingestion and that
will be AI driven future already.
So here's the evaluation.
Also already.
So there are a lot of sea load
data sources, sea load being
there are a bunch of data.
We don't know actually what to do
that with that we are performing
annual root cross analysis.
A lot of time we are growing
telemetry volume leading to
higher cost and complexities.
Then come the evolution.
Unified Telemetry with Open Telemetry.
It comes with proactive anoma
reduction with insights and
also optimize data pipelines.
Then it came the rise of Open Telemetry.
Open tele before Open Telemetry.
The thing was people were using
and collecting a lot of data,
but it was in different format.
So if a person A wants to share their
data with person B, it was not compatible
and it was creating a lot of chaos.
Then the Rise Open came, it created
a vendor over those framework
for collecting telemetry data.
Next is Rise Open.
Open Telemetry is one of the biggest
project of ENCF after Kubernetes.
So if you go and search on CNCF, a
lot of people are contributing to Open
Telemetry and a lot of people are using
open Telemetry in their application back
ends backs for observative purposes.
Why open telemetry?
Because it created a unified standardized.
Way for instrumentation.
It created a easier correlation
between different signals.
It created a freedom to route data to
multiple backends and automated platforms.
Next was extensible
processor and exporters.
What it created an impact on is introduced
a lot of engineering from monitoring.
It enable a smarter pipeline
for data processing.
IT form the foundation of AI driven
platforms or systems or collector.
So collector is the core function or
collective core component of open.
It consists of three major things.
That is receiver, processor,
exporter, receivers, patches,
the data from your application.
Processors transform the data in
which manner you need to feed to expo.
You need to feed to some SaaS.
Stacking an exporter.
Does that expose the data to
some of the SaaS platform?
Like middleware is a full stack platform
and if you want to understand more on
hotel collector, you can scan this code,
you can, there will be a blog on that and
it's detailed blog on hotel collector.
Next ml and there are a lot of
anomalies that are detected by ML model.
They also detect a lot of in
incident patterns when before
we were not able to do that.
And it also prioritize in an incident
based on severity and impact production.
LLM also have a summarized incidents
in human readable language.
Also predict the potential future
issue based on the historical patterns.
If you see LLM was already then, some of
the major things are monitoring mattresses
or performance and also improving
that actually issue identification.
And also health and reliability
enhancement MLS are ransom,
the from passive monitoring to
intelligent problem solving.
So what are the key
data types in other 2.0?
What are the events?
Then?
Its profiles, dependencies and EVPF.
The EVPF changed a lot of things because.
It can fetch the data from the ker
level, all the request data, and it
can also figure out a lot of things,
which posts are open on, which
packets are transforming which roots,
all the things are triggered by it,
and all the things can be tracked
from the, is a level of security.
So comparing the features already
2.0 with the traditional already.
So I just wanted to have overview
for you to better understand
how the different things works.
And the first thing is log collection.
I will just go on one of two.
Example.
So log collection was manual,
it was fragmented by 2.0.
It created automated pipelines
and it was centralized.
And similar manner, the feature,
different features have been
changed, so already cost explosion.
So there are a lot of data, massive
telemetry growth due to a lot of
microservices, which needs a use
storage, and it also costs a lot storing
everything, every log, but mattress
traces even when much of it is irrelevant.
Traditional already models are not
designed for cloud native scalability.
Key cost drivers are high, currently
trics logs and over assembling of crisis.
It resulted in increase infrastructure
spend, slow, a query analysis,
performance and noise, unnecessary
noise, unmanageable noise.
Then comes smarter data pipelines.
So they have to reduce the noise.
In middleware, we have a feature
called ingestion control pipeline that
helps to exclude the unnecessary logs
from being stored to storage, like
S3 bucket or some external storage.
So what are the key strategies?
Some of the key strategies are dynamic
sampling, filtering, and deduplication.
Aggregation edge processing.
So these are some of the techniques
and strategies that help to reduce the
noise and also helps reduce the cost.
These are the benefits that I
already covered and what are
the AI and the future already.
So one of the main major thing
that I love over here is to
consider a scenario where you have.
Alert that your CPU is increased.
CPU utilization is more than 80%,
and the thing is you need to increase
the storage or double down the CPU.
So the alert will be, you have
80% plus CP utilization, and if
you want to double down the CPU,
you just press you just click yes.
The CP should double down.
Double down, so it helps a lot of things.
Next is AI assist root cause.
AI can also help a lot of things to
understand better and to do a thing.
A lot of automated things.
And it also nowadays, people are
also using LLM already to improve the
performance of LLMs that they are using.
This is a future, A already trends.
In 2025, we have covered
almost major of the themes, AI
integration, open telemetry, ai,
workload, automations and all.
So what are the outcomes from ai?
And future already is faster recovery
from incidents, greater reliability
and engineer focus on innovation
instead of manual monitoring.
If you want a detailed log on
2.0, you can scan this code.
There is a detailed blog
covering all the spec on of 2.0.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn or
any platform if you have some queries.
Thank you for listening to me.
Hope you have a great day here.