Hello everyone.
This is ra.
I'm working as a principal software
engineer at and t. Today I'm going to
talk about scaling observability for
real-time personalization engines.
So let's get into the talk.
Let me share.
So first let's talk about why
observability matters for personalization.
So that's the first question, right?
So personalization drives
engagements and they get revenue.
For example, companies that accelerate
personalization, they see to, they
see up to 40% of more revenue costs.
And as, as basically users respond
for highly relevant contents, right?
So they got to be good at observability
to reach that personalization revenue
growth and for the real time experiences,
the, there, there is zero room for errors.
Users always expect the response
to be minimally seconds, and there
shouldn't be any deviation of the
content that present to the customer.
So the so the delays or
failures that directly hurt the
satisfaction and conversions.
Apart from that, there is like complex ML
decisions that need validations, right?
So whenever we present the
recommendations to the customers,
we gotta see are we presenting the
right content at the right time?
Are we having any issues while
presenting the content to the customers?
Is lack of insight.
Is provisionally equal to lost
users trust and missed opportunity.
We got to be careful on while in the
recommendation engine there it's basically
for personalization engine products.
Apart from that, there is competitive
edge when we are collecting these
metrics, logs, traces, that helps
continue to improve algorithms and
user experiences altogether, right?
So we gotta keeping our personalization
engine a step ahead in the competition
from other other competitors,
whoever is in the same phase as
personalized engine product level.
So these so observability overall
is like very important and it's,
plays a key role for personalization.
So next we are going to talk about
at the same time there are challenges
to, to get to this observability for
real time machine learning systems.
As I said observability is
important for personalization.
At the same time, there are a couple
challenges it has so basically like
the personalization systems, how
these complex distributed pipelines.
Where there are many components will get
involved, like services, data pipelines,
ML models, and all those components.
So we got to be good track of these,
all the logs traces and metrics.
Otherwise we get lost.
So end-to-end tracking
should be important.
So the second complexity we could see
is like there would be high data volume,
like millions of events could come for
the real time events when the users are
interacting with the website, right?
So these real time without adding latency
we got to capture these telemetry logs.
Which is difficult part.
So that's one more challenge.
And these ML decisions is
like a black box thing.
We don't know when there is a drop of
drop of growth to the recommendations we,
what we are suggesting to the customer.
So it's hard to track like whether
the recommendation is driving the
recommendations properly or our rules
have been executing properly or we
lost anything or the source systems or
capturing the data, what we wanted for
the specific user behavior and et cetera.
So this stacking of these ML
models fail loose is also hard.
And these personalization.
Now architecture is like
multi-channel user journey.
Sometimes like user can come
to the website at the same time
he can go to the store or he
can browse through mobile apps.
So all sorts of these
channels will be there.
We got to be track the customer throughout
these multiple channels so that we can
stitch the user properly and we can
troubleshoot if anything goes wrong.
So Observ, everybody place a challenge
here for multichannel user journey.
And the fifth challenge is going
to be the latency sensitivity.
So we all saying like an observability
and tag these metrics and things, but
at the same time it's not that easy.
Without without having I. Heavy
overhead on these telemetric
collections and things.
So we know, we all know that
the, it is important to collect
the data but at what cost?
Like we got to see how we maintain
lightweight real time engines.
So that's one thing.
The latency and sensitivity
is going to be challenged.
Yeah.
Now and next we are going to talk
about a. System architecture overview.
So this is a typical
representation architecture
for real time personalization.
Engines like where the request
comes into APIs the three APIs, and
it goes to decision engine where
that recommendation takes place.
From there, it get interacts with
the model service where models been
retain and rules been executed.
And these model service interact with
the data report where the user profiles
or what or whatnot are the content
recommendations will be placed in.
So meanwhile there is an event ingestion
will happen where the users user interface
event streams to these event ingestions
will happen, for example, through Kafka.
These event tions will be
happening into the model.
So all these components multiple component
attractions the metrics, logs, traces
all together to be feeding or ingested.
Into the centralized
observability pipeline.
So this is a typical system architecture
for these personalization engines in
thel services like ingestion, pipelines,
station engine, API layer data, and
then all together all these telemetry
sources to be it in to aggregate the
data and ingest them into observability
pipeline, which is centralized.
So this is how the observability
comes into the picture for
for personalization engines.
And now we go to the scaling observability
in a real time architecture, right?
So I. As we speak, like this is
really high scale architectures
in a real time real time event,
conceptions and personalization.
So end to end tracing is very important.
User coming to and the a p is getting hit.
And then it interact with model,
interface and trying to interact
with data data we post to face
the data and execute the rules.
And enabling end-to-end visibility of
each personalization response is critical.
And the second thing is
unified instrumentation.
Like we got to adopt open telemetry as
DK across services for standard metrics.
Logs and trace collection is important
unified instrumentation so a PS
instrument code once and export
telemetry to multiple back backend.
So we got to be like,
unified instrumentation
instead of bits and pieces.
And the second, third thing
is high throughput metrics.
There would be as we speak, like
millions of events could could
happen in production environments.
When the application been
accessed by external users, right?
So we already have a time series
database like Prometheus and and all
sorts of metrics to be collected.
Aggregate and avoid overwhelming
storage, for example, like compute
percentile, latencies and sample
fine-grained events as such thing.
So high throughput metrics are very
important to be collected and log
aggregation, like streaming logs Jason
structure logs and the model decision
into a central system like elk.
So whenever we got issues double
two, troubleshooting through
these kind of a and cloud logging
things would be easy for us.
Like we can track them as like user
sessions and through trace IDs and things.
And the last thing is like scalable
storage and retention, like employee, a
backend that can handle high data volumes
like scalable observability platform
or data lake or long term analysis.
So we need to ensure retention
policy sometimes when we want
to go back to the time and then
review what was the trend and.
What was that issue is about?
So historical trends can be analyzed
without infin storage growth.
So we gotta be careful about
scalability of storage as well.
Part of these real time architecture
when we are scaling for observability.
And the and the other thing is like
key metrics that matter, right?
So there will be these key metrics which
are important for the troubleshoot.
We got to be collected.
One is like latency and throughput,
like measures how fast and how
many recommendations we are saw.
And, at now, how much SLA you would
personalize the APIs been responding
and how APIs been interacting with the
model interface or for the data reports?
LA throughput one thing to be a key
metric for us for observability.
And the second thing is
error rates and timeout.
So we always got to watch out
for five accessories or four
accessories and and are we.
Returning any default content or default
recommendations to the customers and
all that data help us, like when we see
when our conversion rates are go down
and any, all of these spikes indicate
issues in the ML service or data layer.
So error rates and timeouts
is one thing as a key metric.
We got to be log.
And the other thing is engagement
metrics, tie observability to business
KPIs, like we got to be engaged, click
through rates and conversion rates
dwell time, et cetera, in real time.
And so a drop in engagement might
signal always personalization isn't
happening fine to the customer.
So there is a drop in the
conversion rate and system.
So that's engagement metrics
is one of the important thing.
And another thing is model
performance indicator.
So custom metrics like ML model itself.
Example, the confidence score
distribution of recommendations.
Or frequency of each model, variant
being used on drift metrics, comparing
live input data to training data.
These help detect when the
model's quantity is degrading.
Model performance indicator is
also a good thing a good key
metric for us for the observation.
And another is like resource utilization.
So always we got to keep an eye
in our infrastructure level.
What is the CPU consumption?
What is the memory consumption
and what is the throughput to our
steam like example Kafka topics
and what are the key lens in it?
So all sorts of things.
We got to be, keep an eye on it to
ensure infrastructure can always
hand load Certain changes could
explain like performance outlets.
So these are the key metrics
that the, that, that matter.
For us.
And let's jump into tracing
the personalization journey.
So as part of this personalized
personalized engines architecture
the journey how easy do we can
trace that is the thing, right?
So we got to distribute trace example like
when, when a user visits personalization
content and a trace follows through
the request, so the request through the
API to the decision engine and into the
model, so we sent to the database, right?
So we got to be each segment level.
We got to have a trace record.
So we will know like how the
interaction is happening among
these components with the handshake.
Apart from that w in
telemetry for tracing.
We can, you, we got have these w in
telemetry logs, traces and metrics
together where we have to have these
tracing in recommendation engine level.
And after that we got to have in a model
interface and you enter at DB level.
We will, we got, we chunked
it into different levels to
track what is happening and in
which layer it is happening to.
It'll be easy later to visualize the
call flow and bottleneck identification.
So traces always help to pinpoint
which layer is taking time.
For example, where API is taking
this much milliseconds and your.
DB interaction is taking this much
level and your model interfaces
interaction is taking this much level.
So it gives a clear, in depth
view of those metrics alone.
It enables targeted optimization for us.
And other thing is like
correlating with user action.
When we are tracing these user
requests through session IDs or trace
IDs, so it always like correlate,
we can correlate the break comes of
that request like this, a low score
correlating a pool experience, for
example, user size, scale recommendation.
We can easily identify throughout
that trace and we can provide
like visual context for debugging.
So correlating with user actions
is one of the good thing for
tracing and sampling strategy.
So for example, trace every
request may be infeasible, right?
So we got to go by batches wise
categorize wise, collect traces
for a normal scenarios and
represent to slice of traffic.
So this keeps like overhead low
while enduring us to collect traces.
So sampling strategy is like one,
one good tracing for personal
personalization journeys.
And the other is like logging for making.
So whenever we have logging comes
into picture for observation, we
gotta have a rich and structured logs.
Logging in a personalization engine
should capture key imports, outputs
of the ML engine for each request.
So log details like user ID or relevant
features like which brackets segments
customer fall into, and maybe an
explanation score or a reason could.
Could be possible.
If you're available these kind of rich
and structure logs help us later to make
our life easy when we troubleshoot issues.
Apart from that, like we can enable
root cause analysis, like when something
goes wrong we, we always show like
relevant content to the customer, right?
So logs can reveal what
the customer model saw.
And for instance log might show
input or user segment is now like.
That means like it didn't give the
response as anticipated, give bad
default recommendation to the customer.
So root cause analysis, it enables us when
we follow through these logging properly.
And we have a trace log correlation,
integrate logs with tracing context.
As earlier we talk whenever the
movement request comes in, everything,
the trace completely goes with the
trace ID or session ID or request id.
Through that we can easily track at
these distributes distributed traces
so you can jump into associated logs
across services for the same request.
So it would be easy to raise,
log with these correlation IDs.
Other is anonymize the protect,
anonymize and protect data.
So logging always we feel just
simply log, but always we got to
take care of any sensitive data.
Are we logging?
And because of GDPR concerns and other
things and observability platform
should enforce data handling policy.
So while still giving the engineers.
Enough info to troubleshoot.
So we got to be careful while logging.
As we have a freedom to
have enough to troubleshoot.
At the same time, we gotta be
cautious about sensitive data
of the customers to be logged.
Another is like use log levels wisely.
So whether you go with info log or error
log or warning log and and we don't
need to, we don't need to like, puff up.
The logs like always make sure
only warning level at what
level we have to give and error.
Error logging type which log
patterns we need to be log.
So it could be, it would be
easy when we segregate, when
we troubleshoot in the logs.
Always the go faster and then
warning and then info for help.
And the other thing is like scaling
observability patterns and best practices.
So avoid metrics overload always
practices like avoid metrics overload.
Be mindful.
Of metric cardinality, for example.
This metric labeled with
every user or item id, right?
So it would be a huge for each
customer if we log for each user.
So we got to be aggregate them
as a category wise or percentile,
latency wise or something like that.
So to be smart so we can we
can avoid the overload in such
a way if we go with the login.
And raise and log sampling.
Sampling we can go with the sampling
of couple requests and then we see the
pattern and we can group them as so we
can go with reduce noise and cost for it.
So while retaining diagnostic power.
Exactly.
So trace and log sampling as
a pattern we got to follow.
And batching and B, buffering.
So use characters like ING
telemetry characters, so Kafka
and buffer telemetry data, batch
taste, exports, and sending chunks.
So the application is in block or
sending each span, so buffer logs to
avoid disk Iwo becoming bottleneck.
So that's one thing.
And scalable storage and
querying, implement a tiered
storage observability data.
So recent data stays fast.
Queryable stores and everything
would be like, fast enough if we
have a storage and querying properly.
And other thing is like a
resiliency of observability.
Systems like T, your monitoring
pipeline, whatever that pipeline is
about and critical part of the system.
Scale out your metrics and logging
backends, always set up alerts.
Don't forget about it.
And observability systems themselves.
Example, if the log forward lags or
from the is behind and observability
outage can be especially painful
during a production incident so we
got to be mindful of that as well.
And the other thing is like
incident observability in action.
The scenario.
Is like silent model drifting.
It is when it tells about it a story of
which is an incident of observability
interaction imagine an engagement
of an engagement gradually drop over
a week for personalization field.
When we are.
Showing a component to the customer
and it's its engagement got dropped.
Then component crashed but
component didn't crash.
And B less visibility of those
components by the customers.
But the recommendations
became lesser relevant.
So without observability, this
scenario is hard to tag down what was
happening to that components, right?
So detection through metrics and alerts.
So without strong observability,
setup, an alert tried.
When click through rate or it
got deeper, 10% below baseline.
At the same time, the custom model
drift metrics showed the distribution.
So input have, has shifted from
training data, but this correlation
hinted the model was no longer
turned to current user behavior.
So through that detection also it
was, it become hard to identify
what was happening, right?
And the next is like using
tracers to pinpoint impact.
So engineers pulled up to distribute
at tracers for user session and they
analyze the things and the tracers
show normal latency and everything.
A pattern image, like many users
received a default content.
So that's where the table light in.
So it indicated that model was unsure
and it fall back to the default content,
which is recommended to the customers.
So root cause, logs.
So the other thing is we could see
the logs as earlier we discussed.
What is a good good things or
metrics, key metrics to log.
So we, we used to log for
a model as well whether.
We recommended a personalized
recommendation or a default content
recommended to the customer.
We could see in the logs like,
always the default content being
recommended because customer is not
falling into a specific segment.
So that's where the dev identified,
like they see like upstream
whether etel is collecting the
customer's segment properly.
Example, customer segment
is if age is greater than 30
and recommend this content.
So the age attribute profile
attribute is missing to be collection.
So that's where that would cause
light and they identify through that.
Logs played a key role there
and the resolution and takeaway.
So thanks for observability.
The team being identified the issue of
root cause yours, and they fix the ETL
things and postmodern showed prior to
their observability tools, like after,
after the observability they three x
times they debugging time got sailed.
And all those metrics
were, are looking awesome.
So this is Abu story of
observability as a sample way.
And the other is like tools and
stack in action like, open Telemetry.
So there are multiple tools like
part of these personalization
engines we gotta use.
There are a stack of tools which
we are going to talk right now.
So open telemetry is one of
the thing that is a open source
standard for instrumentation.
So it use, its collects metrics,
traces, logs in a unified way.
So we, it has it come up, it comes up
with SDK so we can we can integrate
this into personalized microservices
and allowing easy export of telemetry.
And other is like Prometheus and Grafana.
So all the metrics can be blend in
and and they even that, that heavy
load at a scale it can easily and
Grafana provides like dashboards,
visualization, and from all the
requests high rates of requests as well.
And we have distributed rein system.
So Jaguar kin is deployed for tracing,
so receiving spans from open telemetry
engineers, so distributed tracing
system jargon, kin are upgrade.
So we can use those tools and logging
pipeline example, elk elastic log session
and Kibana where we use like session IDs
or user IDs that can be easily tracked and
traced down even with multiple channels.
That request comes through.
We can stitch that customer
request through and we can
easily troubleshoot those.
And other thing is like advanced.
There are a PM and advanced tools
like in addition to these open source
tools, there are Dynatrace Datadog
the, these a PM solutions provide very
good very good anomaly detection on
metrics and a assisted boost cause
analysis and the tools can completely
the DIY stack by catching sub subtle.
Issues.
So these are the tool stack.
We have through, and there is
this this is the same thing,
like what are the tools enabling
observability scale, instrumentational
and telemetry collection.
We can use the open telemetry and
for metrics collection dashboards,
we can use Prometheus Grafana.
And for distributed tracing,
we can use Jaguar Grafana tempo
and log aggregation and search.
We use Elastic Elk Stack and for
advanced monitoring and a PM as
we discussing time now, trace and
Log or New Relic they're too good.
And for trays, log storage at Scale.
Kafka Open Telemetry
Collector, or Click House.
At, on data Lake those are, those,
these are the good tools that could
be helpful for personalization
engine built in products.
So these tools really
helpful for observability.
Another is like platform impact of
scaled observability, so if we use this
observability in a better way, so the
impacts are going to be like, dramatic
reduction in outages, so there won't be
much outages like, now with the robust
observability issues are caught and
resolved faster, and one case study
saw that no resolution of these issues
could be like, improved by 75% after
adopting modern observability practices.
So it's really helps for
reduction in outages.
And another is like improved
performance and reliability.
The team can identify bottlenecks
and they can clearly see through
where exactly we fall back in the
performance stage and they can improve
those company's performance so they
can easily solve the customer issues.
And that, that is important thing in
the real time real time environment.
To deliver the quick thing with no issues.
There is like higher
competence and deployment.
So observability data gave
developers a good boost.
Like it's not even internal developers and
for the external customers as well, like
push updates faster, they know whenever a
new model to be introduced and new future
come in they immediately can incorporate
and they could see how it's behaving.
So this improved the velocity of
experimentation, personalization.
And other is like a better
alignment with the business goals.
So because telemetry was tied
into engagement metrics, right?
So the platform team now speaks the
same language as product owners, they
can demonstrate how the latency been
improved and everything so better.
So we got to be now the product
owners and business goals and
developers could be aligned properly
when we have a proper observability.
So cost worth has been benefits
managed, like initially adding
so much instrumentation raise it.
Concerns about like cost.
Hey we got to bring that tool
and this tool, and now we have
this cost been increased and
everything, but at what cost?
These all things, or in fact it,
it brought a lot of observability.
So a lot of insight to what's
happening in our product.
So sometimes putting money on those
tools is like what, while when compared
to the revenue, what we are going to
get after we have a good good product.
And next is like lessons
learned and best practices.
So always build in
observability from day one.
So don't bottom monitoring later.
So design personalization systems
with observability in mind.
So always keep always don't
think about performance thing.
Always think about observability
once we deploy any product into the
production or we got to always think
like how easily we can track, like
to troubleshoot if an issue comes in.
So that's one thing.
And treat logs, metrics
status as first class citizen.
So all three telemetry
types hand in hand goes.
So we got to be detailed logging of
the important components and things.
So always treat those things
as first class agents.
And other is like design for
visibility, non just performance.
So always whenever whenever we do
something to developers, they always
think how can I improve the performance?
They always keep that, you
always wear that suit of how
can I improve the performance?
What we got to be there is other side
we got to see is like observability.
So how better coding I can done
in part of observability so
that, logging and all the systems
interactions, how can properly can go.
And what are tools I built
in to track these ones?
I push into the pro and there is
like import the team, the data.
Train new engineers or data scientists
importance of observability and
new knowledge on these testing and
tools, and encourage the culture so
that this makes incidents response
more collaborative and effective.
So it can be easily fixable and
troubleshoot and improve our product
health and others like irate and
improve like observability is not set.
Not set and forget it.
Continuously refine what you monitor, so
today you built in something to monitor
dashboards or or logging and anything.
But tomorrow you introduce one
new use case and new feature.
So you got to adapt to that and
enhance that properly so that new
use cases can be track even properly.
And final thoughts and call to action.
Observability is product critical.
So it's basically in the
real time ML environments.
Monitoring isn't just an ops
concern, it directly influences user
experience and trusting of product.
So we always get to be careful.
So observability is a product critical
and trust through a transparency.
So whenever, as we earlier discuss
that model, always this model model or
recommendation engine part is a black box.
Whether we always recommending
the right content at right
time to the customers or not.
Proper observations, having at model
level is the key so that we can clearly
see through what is going on and why
the conversion rate been dropped down.
And take action, like one way
to your current observability in
your current projects which are
projects you guys working on.
And take a look back, step back and look
at the observability, what all we have
and when things fall back things go bad.
How can I immediately fix and how can I
keep my product healthy so that it can
bring more revenue, without without any
inter intervene to the production floors
and there is like continuous improvement.
So scaling observability
is an ongoing journey.
So use telemetry site and devices
improvements both them up.
So we got to always continuously
improve metrics, cases and
all those things in product.
And call to action.
So we always embrace the mindset
that if you can't measure it,
so you can't improve it, right?
So bring a clarity to the complexity
of realtime personalization.
So by observing its model, so
your personalization ending and
your users will thank you later.
So once you have this mindset
suit yourself for the observation.
Okay guys, sir, thank you.
That's all from my end and you
can reach me for anything to my
LinkedIn profile and you guys have
a wonderful rest of conference.
Thank you.