Hello everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
Before we dive in, let me
quickly introduce myself.
My name is Di Duran and I'm a technical
architect with over 15 years of experience
in IT industry, including the last 10
years, focused specifically on aviation
technology over the past decade.
I have had the opportunity to work closely
on large scale digital transformation
projects within the aviation sector,
particularly in areas like predictive
maintenance, aircraft system integration,
and data driven operational optimization.
Through this work, I've seen
how the industry is evolving.
Moving from traditional reactive
maintenance models toward smarter
predictive systems that leverage
real time data and machine learning.
One of the most powerful enablers
of this shift is digital twin
technology, and that's exactly
what we will be focusing today,
how digital twins are driving.
The next revolution in aircraft
observability, modern aircraft
generates more than 200,000 data
points and up to 1.2 terabytes of
operational data every single day.
That's a huge data.
That's a massive opportunity
and also a challenge.
Digital twin technology unlocks
that data's potential by creating
virtual replicas of aircraft systems.
These twins monitor, simulate and
predict aircraft health with failure
prediction accuracy of 97.3 percentage.
That's not a science fiction
that is happening now and today
I will show you how this works.
What benefits it brings and
how industries beyond aviations
are adopting the same tool.
Let's begin with what makes
digital twins so powerful.
First, complete visibility.
Digital twins replicates the full aircraft
environment providing observability
across every component, like mechanical,
electrical, and environmental.
Next one is predictive analysis.
Twins can identify failure pattern
28 days in advance, which gives
maintenance team a long runway to
address issues before they escalate.
System integration is key.
Twins correlate data from thousands of
SOS into one unified operational picture.
Finally, real-time monitoring These
systems continuously process telemetry
data throughout the entire flight
phase, not just during inspection.
This combination of depth integration
and immediacy is what sets digital twins
Apart from traditional monitoring system,
the impact of unified absorbability
is measurable, dramatic.
Digital twins reduce the mean time to
detect issues by nearly 90 percentage.
That is faster identification of problem.
Meantime to resolve drops over 76.
Percentage meaning issues are not only
detected sooner, but resolve faster.
There is a 61.8 percentage reduction
in emergency maintenance, and perhaps
more significantly that is an 84.6
percentage decrease in a OG events,
which are extremely costly disruptions.
This shift from fragmented
monitoring systems to unified
digital twin platform creates this
kind of operational efficiency.
So how do digital twins
get such deep insights?
It starts with multimodal telemetry,
vibration analysis, which uses high
frequency sensors to detect tiny
deviations down to 0.05 millimeter, often
indicating early stage bearing wear.
At a 20 K kilohertz sampling rate,
no subtile vibration goes unnoticed.
Thermal imaging monitors temperature
patterns, identifying electrical falls
or fluid leaks with 0.1 degree Celsius
resolution and full spectrum analysis.
We catch problems that
traditional sensors miss.
Acoustic monitoring brings in sound.
AI algorithms analyze
frequencies beyond human hearing.
With ultrasonic detection and pattern
matching anomalies are identified well
before they become audible or dangerous.
All this data, vibration, heat sound.
Are fused by advanced algorithms
to create one unified signal even
when individual sensors look normal.
These algorithms can detect combined
patterns that indicates future failure.
Let's look at three examples that
prove power of digital twins.
A major European carrier
implemented digital twins
across 137 aircraft in one year.
They saw a 93 percentage drop in
unexpected component failures.
They prevented 18 flight
cancellation by catching early
signs of fuel bump detection.
Which is approximately save over 4.3
million Euro in a OG cost and North
American cargo operator integrated
engine and system monitoring.
Despite legacy integration cha
challenges, they reduced maintenance
cost by 23 percentage and extended
component life by 14 percentage.
An Asian regional airline used
a digital twins to detect a PU
failure patent 21 days earlier than
traditional systems with AR guided
repairs and predictive part management.
They cut maintenance turnaround
time by 42 percentage.
No matter the size or region,
digital twins are delivering
measurable, written off investment
and operational improvement.
Digital twins observability
relies not just sensor.
But also intelligent architecture
onboard its computing allows raw data
to be processed on the aircraft itself.
Even in mid-flight, these distributed
nodes can detect anomal immediately.
Data filtering algorithms reduce
transmission by 87 percentage only
the most relevant data gets sent.
Saving bandwidth.
And avoiding Overloads Secure
Transmission System uses multi-channel
communication for resiliency for cloud
integration, which enables fleet wide data
aggregation and analyze on the ground.
This edge to cloud architecture en
enables continuous observability.
Even in remote environments
or during connectivity gaps,
digital twins data becomes even
more powerful when made with
visual through augmented reality.
Failure probability mapping uses
historical and real time data to
create component specific risk maps.
Technicians knows exactly where to look.
Visual translations, which converts
complex analytics into simple overlays.
No need to interpret drought data.
AR procedure guidance provides
interactive repair man manuals
or instructions directly in the
technician's field of view, which
reduce error rates by 76.2 percentage.
These tools have cut maintenance.
By over 34 percentage.
While improving consistency and
quality, technicians are no longer
reacting, they are anticipated.
As with any advanced technology,
there are challenges.
Data accuracy must exceed 98.7 percentage.
Recurs constant calibration.
A small sensor drift can lead to
a false alert or missed problem.
Legacy integration is complex.
Most airlines uses over 14
plus different legacy systems.
Many built decades ago.
APIs and middleware become
essentials to unify the ecosystem.
Telemetry flight is tough.
Extreme temperatures and vibrations
with demand, redundant sensors
and advanced error correction to
maintain data fidelity, but by
tracking these heads on airlines
achieve faster return of investment
and greater long-term reliability.
Implementing digital twins is
not an overnight process, but
it can be phased strategically.
Assessment phase start by evaluating
existing systems and data gaps.
Prioritize systems with
the highest failure impact.
Data foundation, deploy the
sensors, build storage, and
standardize acquisition protocols.
Ensure the data integrity from the start
twin development, which creates
model of critical system.
Train them.
Historical data and integrate AI
and operational expansion scale
to full aircraft and integrate
with maintenance systems.
The total implementation takes 18
to 24 months, but many airlines see
early written of investment within
seven to nine months long before.
The full rollout is complete.
What's exciting is that aviation now
influencing other in industries in power
generation turbines are monitored with
the same techniques used in engines,
which is delivering 93.6 percentage
prediction accuracy and cutting
unplanned outages by 42 percentage.
In medical equipment, digital twins
predicts scanner maintenance needs,
which is reducing scan cancellation
by 71.8 percentage in manufacturing
production lines, uses predictive
analytics to detect processors, which is
reducing defects by over 37 percentage.
The reliability and safety standards
pioneered in aviation are now being
applied to industries where uptime
is critical, and failure is costly.
Let's wrap up with some key takeaways.
Digital twins deliver transformational
observability with 97.3
percentage predictive accuracy.
Integration is the linchpin.
Success requires bridging a legacy system,
but the written off investment is real.
With an 84.6 percentage reduction
in a OG events, the investment
pays for itself quickly.
Looking ahead, technologies
like quantum computing.
And next gen Mission learning will push
prediction accuracy to 99.8 percentage.
We also expect broader standardization
with organizations like airing,
driving adoption across manufacturers
and maintenance providers.
This will make digital twins
easier to implement scale.
And share across the industry.
Thank you all for your time and attention.
The future of aviation maintenance
is intelligent, predictive, and
interconnected, and digital twins are
at the heart of the transformation.
Thanks again.