Greetings for the day.
Thank you for joining today's
session where we will explore how
platform engineering can bridge the
gap between the promise of digital
transformation and its actual impact.
I'm marnic a platform architect.
Meet my co-presenter.
Hello, I'm Trata, and I'm a
student as well as a digital
transformation enthusiast.
We bring prospective from both
the business and technology sites.
So we look at transformation not just as
a buzzword, but as an operating model that
delivers scale, agility, and resilience.
Digital transformation leads every
corporate agenda, but many organization
finds that the impact is very limited.
Why?
There are many reasons to
it, but just to quote a few.
One of the reason is there are
too many silos, duplications, and
a legacy complexity that exist
in the organization's ecosystem.
They struggle to scale cost efficiently.
There is often a lack of agility
that prevents launching new
products faster and quickly.
So while business demands speed and
innovation, technology often gets drawn
in complexity, that's where platform
engineering provides a digital platform.
So now what is a platform?
A platform is more than technology.
It's a reusable digital foundation.
It abstracts away complexity, standardizes
how we operate and accelerates innovation.
Think of it like town planning.
Instead of building random houses,
we design roads, utilities, and rules
that let the city grow efficiently.
Similarly, platforms enable business
and engineering teams to build at
speed and scale types of platforms.
We break platform strategy
into four categories.
Engineering platform it as
a service for developers.
This is about developer efficiency.
By offering self-service infrastructure
pipelines and monitoring, we reduce
friction and repetitive tasks.
Developers can then focus on building
business value instead of plumbing.
It's about moving from
firefighting to value creation.
Second business capabilities
platform business as a
service for speed and agility.
Think of this as the business
engine, instead of fragmented IT
solutions, business capabilities
are bundled as reusable services.
This allows rapid product launches,
agility in responding to change,
and a modular architecture that
embraces continuous transformation.
Data, platform data as a service,
empowering insights and experimentation.
Data is the oil of modern enterprises.
A data platform enables
discovery, creation, and
consumption of data products.
With proper governance, with real
type pipelines, it drives insights,
experimentation, and decision making.
This is how organizations unlock
data-driven culture at a scale.
Customer experience platform journey
as a service, enabling consistent
and personalized experiences.
Here, the focus shifts to the end user.
A CX platform unifies the
customer journey across channels.
One profile, consistent personalization,
seamless onboarding of partners.
It's about delivering one brand,
one experience, irrespective of
channel or partner ecosystem.
Each there builds on the other,
creating a full stack digital backbone.
Platform thinking is not about building
one of tools or isolated think systems.
It's about designing reusable capabilities
that can be shared across the enterprise.
Delivery infrastructure.
Instead of every team setting up their
own CICD pipelines, cloud accounts,
and monitoring, the platform team
provides them as a ready to use secure
foundation, API, and architecture
remediation service boundaries, gateways,
and even driven architectures are made
consistent, so product teams don't
reinvent governance every single time.
Self-service data.
Data is packaged as products, clean,
discoverable, and ready for consumption.
Teams no longer hunt for data sets.
They simply subscribe to them,
experimentation and telemetry.
New ideas can be tested safely
with real time telemetry,
feature toggles and control roll.
So innovation becomes
responsible and scalable.
Customer touch points,
every customer interaction.
Whether web app or partner portal
feels seamless because platforms ensure
consistency in the personalization,
routing, and content strategy.
So the outcome delivering faster, build
ecosystems, gain insights, experiment
responsibly, consistent experience.
This is the power of platform thinking.
It shifts organizations from
fragmented delivery to enterprise
wise scalability and resilience.
So what is digital transformation?
This evolution is the journey just from
simply convert to automate, to transform.
So now let's discuss this three terms,
which are often used interchangeably.
Digitization, convert analog to digital.
It's just like scanning paper.
Digitalization, automate existing
workflows and digital transformation.
Reman reimagining how business
creates and delivers value
with technology at the core.
Now let's discuss why platforms matter.
For digital transformation, a system
centric approach slows us down.
Applications are siloed,
integrations are brittle.
A platform approach changes the game.
Speed and agility through self-service
capabilities, scalability and
resilience via cloud native
foundations simplification.
So teams focus on business value and
innovation at scale, unlocking new
business models and revenue systems.
Now I hand over to my core speaker
to talk about this particular problem
statement in the healthcare domain.
Now, so far, we have understood
the various terminologies about
what is platform thinking approach,
and what is platform engineering
along with digital transformation.
Now, let's understand and pick up a use
case in a healthcare domain, which is
related to the invoice processing, and
how do we apply what we have learned
so far to this problem statement to
digitally transform their business?
Here goes the use case.
So medical invoicing today is highly
manual, paper driven and error prone
processing, which processes over a
million of documents weekly with a
significant dependency on human effort.
Each invoice requires manual.
Physical verification of signature and
stamps and manual forwarding to claims
management team and various other
departments for further processing.
This results in a heavily manual
operations that demands significant
number of full-time resources for
end-to-end processing the claims.
Area is growing in the
various geographies.
As you say, the market size is
significantly large in the North
America, Europe, AsiaPac Pacific.
Now, while we have understood the current
state of this problem, how are we tackling
this problem in the today's world?
Let's understand what kind
of inefficiencies it brings.
To the system first, it brings
lot of operational inefficiencies
in a way that, first, the invoice
processing consumes substantial
manual hours on a monthly basis.
Second, this leads to the high
susceptibility to data entry
errors and fraudulent claims.
Third, there is a limited
accessibility and a real time
visibility to stakeholders.
Fourth, this has increased cost to serve.
Reimbursements and reduce
provider satisfaction.
In addition to that, there is
also a challenge associated with
scalability and susceptibility.
The current system cannot scale
with increasing invoice volumes.
There is a dependency on paper-based
workflows, which contradicts
digital and environmental goals.
Inefficient workflows strain, both
operational budgets and compliance
postures, which leads to claim
denials and delay in reimbursements.
Now what we are trying to propose
is a flow, which is built.
Using a platform thinking
approach and how we have digitally
transformed the entire ecosystem.
Let's see, so there are multiple
personas which are using this
particular digi digitally transform
flow for the invoice processing.
We have various personas, right
from the healthcare organization
to the insurance organization.
Along with the partner channel, who
also helps to analyze and actually
process the claims for the healthcare
organization as a third party supporters.
And in addition, we also have a internal
admin and a support team who are using
our digital transformation process.
The workflow.
Now, let's see how the health healthcare
organization wanted to, who wanted to.
Process the claims via uploading the
invoices will happen in this workflow.
In the digitally transformed workflow, so
first, the healthcare organization uploads
a bunch of invoices for claim processing
through a web portal interface, which
is provided by this invoicing system.
Second, the batch of invoices are
verified for sanity checks and
it'll get stored in a cloud storage.
Third, each invoice is scanned via
OCR and NLP solutions to extract.
The required information, and this is
where we actually do the digitalization.
The fourth step is extracting the
signature and stamps available for each
invoice via deep learning solutions
and save it again on the cloud storage.
Next it moves to the next
department wherein the government
representative will audit and verify
the signature and stamps manually.
And provide an approval.
Please note that here we have
introduced human in the loop so as to
avoid any fraudulent at this stage.
Upon approval, the invoice
batch will be sent to claims
department for further processing.
The insurance company representative will
take the invoices for further validation.
And either approve, reject, or ask
for more information for the claim
processing, and the UpToDate status
will be reflected on the web portal.
If the claim is approved by insurance
company, the payment workflow
will be triggered via payment
interface and the amount will be
credited to the patient's account.
If the approver requires any additional
information about the invoice, it'll
be moved to the on hold status.
However, in case the claim is considered
as fraud or due to insufficient
documentation, it'll be reported as
rejected, and this is how the current
manual process is entirely digitized using
a platform thinking approach along with
applying the digital transformation lens.
Our strategic focus here is very clear.
We move from digitization to
digitalization and then entirely
transforming the workflow
into digital transformation.
The shift is from manual to
digital transformation, embed
AI to detect fraud and ensure
compliance, transform the invoicing
journey end to end with automation
enabling scalability and accuracy.
C. Let's also discuss the key
milestones in this transformation.
This journey unfolds in phases.
Start the value stream mapping and
launching the e-invoicing platform.
Integrate O-C-R-N-L-P and fraud detection.
Automate workflows across stakeholders.
Deploy real-time dashboards finally
expand across networks and geographies.
Each milestone builds maturity
and unlock measurable value.
Let's quickly have a
glance at the roadmap.
Our roadmap runs as a multi-year
program scaling from core implementation
to full ecosystem adoption.
Importantly, this solution evolve to be an
industry agnostic and platform agnostic.
This means the lessons from medical
invoices we will apply to further extend
it to other industries like insurance,
retail, as well as finance, and many more.
Now let's understand here that how we
have enabled the digital transformation
using platform thinking lens.
Let's consider the same use case that
we are discussing now, which was a paper
heavy labor intensive and prone to errors.
Now applying platform thinking
transformation into this we made it
digital first and AI enabled workflow.
There is a shared ingestion layer
for all invoices, whether it is from
hospitals, insurance partners, or
government entities, which comes
through a single digital portal.
This ensures consistency and traceability.
The customer interacts via two channels.
One is a web portal and others a chatbot
for submission of their invoices.
Second, there is a u
reusable data services.
So instead of manual entry, O-C-R-N-L-P
engines are automating the entire
metadata extraction signature, and
staff stamp validation process.
These services aren't built for
one team, but they are reusable
across various departments, be
it claims compliance, or audit.
Third is a validation as a service, the
AI models and human in the loop framework.
Validates invoices against business rules.
The fraud detection and anomaly
checks run as a shared capability.
Fourth is a claim processing
platform wherein we are routing,
auditing, approvals, and
the entire payment gateways.
They run through an orchestrated
workflow, which is designed
as modular trace and scalable.
The final on the top is the experience
layer wherein the customer's
insurance and the regulators.
Get real time status updates via chatbots,
as well as real time dashboards to
which delivers transparency and trust.
The shift is profound.
Instead of switching together fragmented
workflows, we build a platform backbone.
Instead of scaling people linearly,
we scale capabilities exponentially.
Instead of operational risk, we
build compliance into the process.
By design, there is a sense of
enabling digital transformation through
platform thinking, which converts a
broken manual journey into a future
proof reusable capability stack that
can extend beyond medical invoicing
to the entire insurance ecosystem.
Now let's see how we
can define the success.
While there are ma many
measures through which we can.
Define as well as measure the success.
We think these are the three
important dimensions, which should
be definitely considered while
we define the success metrics.
The first is the customer metrics.
Second is the business value wherein
we ensure fraud reduction, compliance
by design and lower cost to serve.
And third, an important aspect
of it is an operational metric.
Wherein we will measure the system uptime,
which is nothing but the availability of
the system, the accuracy of the system,
fraud detection rates, and the throughput.
Success is when customer,
business and operations are all
aligned on measurable impact.
So our message is simple.
Platform engineering is the
backbone of digital transformation.
It bridges the gap between
ambition and reality.
Enabling organizations to move
faster, safer, and smarter.
We appreciate your time
and attention today.
We hope our perspective adds
value, and today's session
leaves you with fresh insights.
Happy learning.
Thank you.