Hello everyone.
I'm Michel Moto, but
everyone call me Mitch.
I'm a developer advocate at me platform,
and today I will talk about platform
engineering and AI and cognitive lots.
I started to work at 2004 and I
become a developer guy in 2015.
I love to share knowledge about platform
engineer, developer experience in cloud
native, but also about sustainability.
I'm one of the organizer of cloud
Native Days, Italy, a conference related
to cloud native topic here in Italy.
And I founded a couple of community.
I co-founded a couple of community
one, it's developer life,
it's Italian community to help
people to join in our field.
And the second one, it's Green of Italia,
a community related to green software.
I'm ACF Ambassador and.
Advisory board member of Dev Network.
I talk about these kind of
topics because it's part of my
daily work, but also a passion.
I love to help people to reduce
the complexity and also improve
the developer experience.
And I think that better developer
experience can create happier
and more productive developer.
I want to start with this chart.
The first date in this
chart, it's the 2004.
I started to work in 2004
and when I started to work,
my profession was webmaster.
I'm not know if it's an international
world, but at the end it's a person
that can create application website on
internet to create the application you
need just to know a language like PHP.
HTML and CSS and after that you need
just to create your software drag and
drop your folder from local to the server
and you are deploy at your application.
Online was very different.
During the time there are complexity
to manage all the staff increase,
and our ability to manage the
complexity is low than the complexity.
This is why in the last 15, 20 years,
there is a lot of new job position and
job roles because the before in 2004.
You need just to know a language and you
can do all the stuff by yourself today.
You need the other people to
manage the design, to manage the
front end, the backend, but also
the cloud, the automation, the
pipeline, the testing, and so on.
I love this sentence, but
I think that is not true.
At the end I think that Kubernetes,
of course it's complex, but it's
not too hard to understand because
at the end it's just a tool.
The real complexity to
create application today.
It's for example, the scalability that we
want to have, the distribution, but also
the data that we use, the integration,
the interoperability, the user experience.
But also the security and the privacy and
the AI and machine learning now and so on.
If we look in the cloud native,
we can sort this maybe, it's
the CNCF landscape at the end.
It's chart with a lot of
different technology inside.
When you want to create a new cloud
native application, you can find a lot
of open source project in this landscape
and you can choose it to create stuff.
Just an example, if you want to
have a new a PA gateway, you can go
here in the right session and you
can find 20 different API gateway.
Of course, it's not easier.
For you understand.
The different between
20 different project.
And for this season, you need to study.
After that, you need to choose.
And after you choose our right
project, you need to improve
your knowledge about the tool.
If you want to create an application
today, you need to know a lot of
different tool and you need to
have a lot of different knowledge.
In the left side, in the list, I put also
the automation and the SCI and CD tools.
Some of you can say that is
not a tool to improve the
complexity, and I agree with you.
But of course if you want to have
automation or continuous integration
and delivery in your project, you
need to know new tools, understand
it, and after that use it.
It's part of the cognitive law.
When we talk about cognitive
load, we talk about the mental
effort required to process
information and complete that task.
There is three different
type of cognitive load.
The first of one, it's intrinsic.
It's at the end that not
really complex of a task.
Some tasks are hard.
You need to have knowledge
to do that, and that's it.
You can reduce without any kind of
trick, this kind of cognitive load.
Of course, if you study, you improve
your knowledge, you can reduce
using structured learning, but in
other case, it's part of the work.
The second one, it's related
to the cognitive law that
you use to improve yourself.
For example, effort that you use
to learn and understand better
a task or to learn new stuff.
To complete that task and this
kind of cognitive load can be
good because I improve yourself.
For example, if we talk about
CICD, that we look in the previous
slide if you want to know how to
create a pipeline and manage all
the automation, your application.
This load can be a German load and
this could because you after study
can understand new tools exp explore
new stuff and expand your knowledge.
The last one, it's all the cognitive
law, not related to your knowledge
and the tools and let me say new
tools that you want to learn, but
it's related to unnecessary effort.
For example, coset by port
tools, ENT processes, and so on.
Of course systems are not
intuitive or process with.
Too many step or unclear workflow
or tools with operate UI or a lot
of information, unclear docs can
increase this kind of cognitive loans.
And our goal is try to reduce this
kind of cognitive load because
it's the only one that we can
improve without any kind of fish.
Just to do a very clear example.
As a developer, you
need a new environment.
20 years ago, you can create by yourself
and with a drag and drop, you can
upload your project and your done.
Today you need to ask, in the
majority of the case in a structured
companies to our colleagues in ops
team, for example, and it can it
have the permission and the knowledge
to create the environment for you.
After the request, the ops guy can
create the resource configuration.
The configuration of environments,
for example, variable seeker and so
on, create the right network, set up
the security set up and many others.
After that, it can provide to
you analysis and you can out your
application, but sometimes is not
the upper in the same team or in
the same desk or in the same room.
You need to ask this kind of with a
request on Jira, Asana and other system.
And of course the answer is not
very fast because the ops team,
maybe in the meantime other stuff
do, can be on vacation and so on.
And of course this is,
it's part of a poor.
Develop experience.
For this reason, we can introduce
the platform engineering.
When we talk about platform engineering,
we can say that it's a software
engineering discipline focused on
the development of self service,
tool chain service and processes.
It's based on these six
keywords, let me say.
The first one, it's try to
centralize all the stuff.
For example, manage all the
project and all the source of
your project in a single place.
The second one, it's try to
automate create automation about
all the stuff, industrialize and
automate the entire DevOp cycle.
The third one, it's simplicity.
Try to solve complex task and
integration, for example, with
the cloud in a very simple way.
And the four, the efficiency.
Try to avoid bottleneck to organization
like the stuff that we saw before.
But also try to improve the quality
because of course if you put in your
application completely automation,
you can insert in the pipeline, for
example, quality check and also order
stuff that can provide to you a good and
improve the quality of your software.
But all this stuff need
to be self-service.
The developers need to use all the
stuff in our cell service mode.
At the end, the idea about platform
engineering is try to reduce the
complexity of your application
because in this way you can
have the ability to manage it.
When we look at platform engineering,
the majority of the people looks just
at the internal developer portal and the
orchestrator just for the infrastructure.
But I think that it's more than that.
For example, in the left side, you
have your internal developer portal
with a new I-O-C-L-I or API or
maybe ai with a different feature
like the software catalog store
scorecard dashboard, and so on.
In the middle you have the platform
orchestrator that can help the people
that use the internal developer
portal to manage the right side.
In the right side.
We have in the bottom, of course, the
infrastructure can be, for example,
cloud services, but also AI provider.
And the infrastructure platform can
be, for example, Kubernetes, but also
container managed services or functions
or so on, and the DevOps platform.
In the DevOps platform you
have, for example, GI, but
also pipeline, the tracing, the
monitoring, the testing and so on.
But I think that there are very
interesting part on these images.
The yellow part, the application
assets and possibility.
For example, the poss ability to have
out of the box API gateways or a API
portal or Evans portal system to manage
a automatization and authentication, but
also microservices, a PI or Evan or cast.
Software or marketplace, let me say
software catalog or marketplace,
but also system to create and
manage microphone and so on.
Of course, the data, it's a very
important part, and have a data control
plane can be good with system like
fast data, but also data catalog.
Also, crowd systems can be very
good to improve the velocity
and reduce the cognitive loan.
And of course the AI.
When we talk about ai, for sure, we talk
about LLM, but also speech, ai, multimodal
and other system like the AI agent to
manage all the stuff that you can need.
This kind of architecture that
we saw in the previous slide can
open a new, very powerful concept.
The concept of circular economy.
They, it's very simple.
Let's imagine a team that need
microservices to make payments.
Of course there is no microservices around
and they start to develop the system from
zero at the end of the development cycle.
They have a system based on talker, for
example, to create a manage payment.
You can call API, this API can
get, I don't know, the credit
number the card credit number and
after that he can make payments.
After that, he, they do
the work in this way.
If another team need to create the same
system, they need to start from zero.
But if they create a good
documentation, they can be create a
general software that can be reused.
They can put this service in a
marketplace or software catalog.
Another team that need the same
stuff can get this component
and use it without use effort.
Of course, sometimes the new team need to.
Change stuff, add new possibility,
add new functionality.
And of course, if the functionality
it's related to the payment, they
can change the code, update the
documentation, and release a new
version, for example, to support PayPal.
But if they need another functionality,
like a system to create invoice
after the payments, they can get the
payment system from the team one.
After that, create the system to create
invoice and put together and use it.
Another team, of course, can get
only the payment system, the invoice
system, but or get some stuff and
after that, create new stuff or improve
the stuff that already used exist.
Of course, this kind of circular economy
can be very good for your developer
because the this kind of system can
reduce a lot of the community load
inside your team because they don't need.
To create from zero each time
the stuff, but they can use and
reuse stuff created by orders.
Of course.
To do this, they need to have a good
documentation and a good product.
Okay.
Of course, when we talk about ai, we
need to talk about some stuff that
can help the developer to reduce
the cognitive load using the ai.
Of course we look a lot around and
there is a lot of different tools that
can improve the ai, but for example.
AI assisted devs can reduce the
manual task and all your developer
to have a focus on their creativity.
If an AI can manage some task
for your developer, simple
task, can repetitive task.
The developer are free
to create other stuff.
For example, in this kind of of
AI example, we can talk also about
code generation and debugging.
The developer can use a tool to create
code for computation or debugging
and to reduce the cognitive load.
But another important stuff, it's
related to let me say documentation.
Okay.
For example, a developer can ask
to AI to have information about
functionality, documentation, and so on.
Of course, this kind of system can be
created by a rag power AI system, and
we call it conversational dev device.
If you have all this stuff in
your system all interconnected,
you can have assist devs in real
time using conversational direct.
DDI is if a developer need to make some
manual task, he can ask to an AI and AI
can do the task for your developer, or
if a developer have problems with some
stuff, can ask to the AI and so on.
When we imagine this kind of plaque for
my image, this kind of very simple draw.
In the top, we have the platform.
In the right we have the AI.
In the left, we have the person that
want to use this kind of of system.
In this example for example we can
talk about a couple of different stuff.
The first one, it's if a developer need to
have information he can ask to ai r inside
the AI Iraq you have for example, LLM,
but also all the documentation related
to your application and your platform.
And of course the AI have context about
your technology, your feature, and so on.
And he can.
The AI cannot answer to your developer.
Of course, we can add to the AI in
the rug also the logs in the specific
configuration of your platform.
Of course, if we have all
the configuration and all the
stuff centralized and in the
platform, we can provide all this
configuration to the ai and with the
documentation the AI can understand.
What your platform do and all the
stuff related to your platform.
Just an example, if you provide all the
documentation with all the code error
about your services to the ai, and after
that you provide all the logs to the ai.
A developer can ask, you can
find in the logs of my platform
any warning or any error, and of
course they, I can say yes or no.
If yes, you can ask, okay which
kind of error or warning you find in
the logs and how I can resolve it.
If you think about that, you can think
that the AI have all the information
about the Earth that happens.
About why it happened because in the
documentation you have all the information
and can be a very good system to reduce
a lot the cognitive load of your teams.
Just a practical team.
Of course, this is a theoretical talks.
I'm hope that you enjoy it.
But of course you, we need to
understand how we can start
with platform engineer and ai.
The first one, it's the first
question that you need to do.
It's why why you need to adopting a
platform or why you need to adopt.
AI platform of course, which kind
of problem you want to solve,
what problem you want to solve.
Of course, if you work in a very large
company, you have different business unit.
Different business unit have different
problems, and of course you can start
to solve all the problem together.
You need to choose the a couple.
You need to create priority and choose
the problem that you want to solve in this
case, for example what capability should
my platform have in the beginning can be
a good question, and of course how this
kind of change can impact your business.
Of course, you need to understand
if you already have metrics.
Choose metrics to use and of
course, try to understand if
your platform, initiative and AI
initiative can improve your metrics.
When we talk about metrics as suggestion
that I get from Graziano cast is try to
not define at all the metrics because,
for sure if you write code, if you have
a company, you already have the metrics.
For example, in the case that
we saw in the beginning of this
presentation, a metrics can be if
a developer need a new environment,
how many minutes, hours, days.
He need to wait a new environment.
That can be a good metrics and you
don't need to define new metrics.
It's perfect for you if you define that.
The reason to adopt the platform
initiative can be create
the environment very fast.
And the first stuff, it's
permitted developer to have.
Self service platform to
create a new environment.
This is, its geometric of course.
When you start this kind of initiative,
you need also to talk with all
interesting people to understand.
All the company that can have
benefit from your initiative.
And of course you need to find methods
that can be used by the world company.
It's just not deployment frequency.
You need to find the right
way to use the right metrics.
And of course you need to evaluate
the progress of this metrics
during the time because sometimes
new technologies can improve in
the phos period the productivity
and reduce the cognitive load.
But in the long run adding new
functionality and modify out
this kind of new technology work,
that metrics during the long time
can be less than the beginning.
Of course, your goal, it's try to look
at the metrics during the long run.
And try to look the metrics for the
technical part, but also identify
business value because, the business
is part of our job in any case.
Okay.
A couple of general suggestions.
Try to invest time to sell service
experience for developers related
to platform, but also to ai.
Try to align your technology
closely with business objective.
I know sometime it's hard because if you
are a tech person, you look at tech part.
If you're a business person,
you look at the business part.
But the best companies work.
When tech and business align it, try to
support the change because the people,
not all the people are ready to change,
and sometimes you need to be patient
and try to create tutors and guidance
to help these people to change with you.
In any case, it's related to platform
ai, but also if you don't use this kind
of technology I think that the, one of
the majority stuff, it's try to include
the collaboration because when the people
work together, you can avoid common pit
fails and try to create, solution that
the people can enjoy using, because
I think that the most important part,
if you look at developer experience,
if you look at platform engineer, but
also if you look at ai, the first goal,
it's try to create a good ecosystem
to the developer and try to improve.
The quality of the tool that the
developer use to create stuff.
Of course there is a lot of resources.
The first one is the platform model.
Maybe you know it, there is link here
if you don't know nothing about platform
by suggesting it's starting from here.
But another very interesting to blog post.
It's this expanding that all
of the platform engineering.
You can find the link here.
I use a lot of ideas about
this blog post in this talks.
But in the blog post, you can
find a lot of good information.
And that's it.
Here you can find my, for me, if you
want to leave a feedback I love read
it and try to improve for the future.
Of course, if you have any suggestion
to improve the talk or to add
new part, please let me know.
You can feel free to add me on
LinkedIn and Social Network.
You can find me as a Mission
Mohabi or Mitch Moha or on GitHub.
If you have any question, I here for you.
Thank you and bye-bye.