Hello everyone.
Welcome.
This is working as lead technology,
having 20 years experience
mostly in, financial services.
I'm glad here to speak about
platform engineering security
in financial services.
security is yeah, critical
and constantly evolving topic.
Industry financial services, storm of
threats in 25 from sophisticated AI
attacks, the primary security threats,
phishing and social engineering.
Ransomware insider threats.
Third party and supply changes.
How we are going to provide
security and financial services.
build resident multi talent, multi-tenant
infrastructure that balances unprecedented
security demands with rapid innovation
for financial institutions migrating
to cloud native architectures.
The agenda, evolution of platform
security from traditional infrastructure
to self-service ecosystems with zero
trust architecture, multi-tenant
architecture, isolation boundaries,
service MIS technologies, and secure
by default configurations, container
orchestration, microservices, bernet,
security strategies, admission control.
Security code
policy framework integration,
identity management and observability
access controls, threat detection
complaints about automation.
The evolution of platform security.
Modern platform engineering has
transformed from traditional
infrastructure management to creating
sophisticated self-service ecosystems
that empower development teams.
While strict security controls
financial services, organizations
face unique challenges, stringent
regulatory requirements.
Cyber attacks
I requirements need for business agility.
Security code Multitenant
financial services require careful
of isolation, boundaries, data
segregation, and access control,
implementing sophisticated
micro segmentation strategies
that create defense in depth
at every layer of the stack.
Service miss technologies enabling fine
grain traffic control and the integration
of all interservice communication
within mutual transfer layer services
and policy driven access control.
by
legitimate exceptions, transform
security, enable of innovation service.
ME technologies have emerged as
a current store of secure multi.
Platform in financing, enabling
fine grain traffic control, precise
routing and loading balancing between
services with comprehensive policy
enforcement and end-to-end encryption.
mutual LS for all service to
service communication, ensuring
data confidentiality and integrating
when you're using, encryption and
description, make sure it'll follow that.
the patents while transforming that
data from one system to other system,
from starting to ending portable
security policies that travel with
workloads, ensuring consistent production
regardless of deployment location.
It has to follow the same workloads and
ensuring the consist protection regardless
of the deployment locations, wherever its
transmitting, it has rules, regulations,
container orchestration, security,
Comprehensive, security strategy.
Kubernetes has become the
standard for container
orchestration in financial services.
If we see all the organization,
they're following the Kubernetes
with the microservice nowadays,
but its flexible demand.
Careful security considerations.
Platform engineers develop strategies
that address every aspect of the
container life, image scanning
and vulnerability management.
Secure configuration under, deployment,
runtime protection and monitoring.
They cloud and for the image scanning
and nowadays the document systems game.
So it'll load, the of data into their
systems and, with, random, they can
able to provide the corresponding
document, admission controllers,
enforce policies that prevent.
Configuration from, entering production.
If you see that, admission controls
here, we can provide the, and, based
on that, only the particular, runtime
monitoring, detecting anomalous
behavior that might indicate Compromise
Pro-active transforming security
from reactive incident response.
To predict threat prevention
admission controllers.
Survey the critical gatekeepers
in financial services platforms,
enforcing policies that prevent
insecure configuration from
entering production environment.
When it's layer elevation, each
and every layer have the specific
validations to make sure it'll, hundred
percent the test cases will cause.
That way they're going to
implement checks, everything
from resource limits to security
contract, ensuring workloads meets.
organizational standards policy
and certain automatically rejects
non-compliant workloads and provides
clear feedback mediation steps so that
it, those noncompliant workloads details
because all validation complaints,
reporting and security analysis so that
if something happens, they can go back
to the history and they'll verify it
to track the, where it's, violating.
G and security as a code, in
the DevOps systems, everywhere.
They're the gi.
So gi closely platform
teams, infrastructure.
Infrastructure as a code, as code.
treating rigorous review process
policy as code codifying, security
requirement, ways that missions can
enforce and humans can understand.
progressive Security Gate, validating.
Before changes, secure scanning,
integrating vulnerabilities and
compliance scanning throughout
the deployment pipelines.
If you have even major
critical minor info level.
Making it and providing so that
the security, most of the Secur
99, 99 0.99%
repeatable deployment patterns that
eliminates configuration drift and
ensure consistent security controls.
Identity and the access management.
At scale.
Managing identities across complex
financial services ecosystems
require sophisticated approaches
that balance security with usability,
identity lifecycle management,
automatically provisioning under.
De provisioning access based on the
author, authoritative sources attribute
require access evolving beyond role-based
models to consider context for fine
grain permissions, mission identity
management, implementing robust patterns
for managing services, account, a, keys,
passwords, and other non-human identities.
Incident platform
of telemetry data.
Platform engineers must build systems
that transform this data into actionable
security intelligence in distributed
tracing, providing visibility into
complex request flow, enabling teams
to understand not just what happened,
but why and how security information
and event management creating.
And correlate platform event with
security signals drastically reducing
detection and investigation time.
Automated response, implementing workflows
that contain threats while gathering
evidence for later analysis.
What are the compliance, automations.
Meeting requirement efficiently.
Efficiently.
Financial services organizations
face complexity requirements that
traditionally required manually
processes and extensive documentation.
Platform Mini are automate,
complaints through continuous
monitoring and, evidence
collection, automated as assessment
against regulatory requirements.
Generation immutable investigation
verification, from, in
platform while reducing
and,
Friction.
the most secure platforms
provides no value.
Developers can't use it efficiently.
Platform needs to focus intensively
on creating developer experiences
that make secure choices, the EEG
choices, self-service capabilities,
enabling developer, to provision.
While automating policy source
security requirements are meting,
writing developers will archite
solution without, cons concerning
innovation through templates, examples,
and automated tools, feedback.
Monitoring how developers interact with
platform capabilities and where friction
occurs to continuously refined offerings.
This approach allows developers
to focus on business logic
rather than infrastructure
building for the future.
Architecture a threat landscape
and regulatory continues to evolve.
Platform architecture and can
adapt without reconstruction.
Platform engineering build
evolutionary through modular and
clear interfaces, comprehensive
testing, engineering practices,
updateable security controls as well.
Engineering for security.
Engineering practice platform teams
understand systems, behavior, relevant
weaknesses before attackers can them.
One is control experiments, failure,
injections, observ analysis, security
Harding, the path forward platform
Engineering, security, and financial
services represent critical discipline.
That continues to evolve rapidly.
Success requires balancing,
completing demands.
One is security and usability, creating
security systems that developers can.
Second is complaints and agility.
Meeting regulatory requirements
while enabling rapid innovation so
it won't lead further complexion.
Standardization and innovation,
providing consistent patterns
that don't any creative solutions
so that it'll be adaptive.
Understand so that it'll be easy to
use in the financial, security systems.
Ent future addressing current rates
while building adaptable architectures.
Whenever we are adding that, current
threats, if you're considering it
has to support for the future also
to restrict as well by embracing
security as a fundamental platform
capability rather than and feature
platform engineering teams questioning
their organization for success in your
increasingly complex digital landscape.
Thank you all for giving
me the opportunity.