Hello, everyone.
before I begin, I want to thank
Mark and the con 42 team for
providing this opportunity.
More importantly, thank you everyone
watching the conference live.
Or the recording time is valuable,
and you have so many options
what to do with your time.
But you choose this
opportunity to learn with me.
So thank you.
And let's start the presentation.
Okay, the topic of my presentation
is optimizing offer management
through enterprise application
integration, also known as E.
A.
I.
But before we dive into the topic,
I just want to introduce myself.
Want you guys to know my,
what my background is.
My name is Vamsi and I have about 18
years of experience in solution design,
business analysis, and product management.
I do have a postgraduate
degree in business management,
specializing in IT and marketing.
Interestingly, I also have a
bachelor's degree in technology and
electrical engineering, and it's from
one of the top colleges in India.
The last 10 years of my experience
though has been at DirecTV.
It's a satellite and
streaming services provider.
At DirecTV, I drive solutioning in
the offers and decisioning space.
I should say I'm fortunate that
at DirecTV, I had the opportunity
to live through the change and,
maybe we can even call it paradigm
shift off how customers viewed
content on their televisions, right?
So earlier, where it was beamed
in via satellite through the dish
to now, customers view content
on streaming over the top.
So that's another area of great
interest for me, but perhaps
a topic for another day.
Now to wrap up, I've also previously
worked as a software developer
building order management software.
And I've also done sales for cloud
solutions, including infrastructure as
a service and software as a service.
So let's jump in now.
So here's how we're going to go today.
The agenda.
First, we will look at when do businesses
need to focus on offer management and
what do they have to do to get there?
And then what's the need or what's the
business imperative for integration?
Then I'll introduce what
enterprise application
integration is, also known as EAI.
We'll talk about some types
of application integration.
And then I'm going to cover some
best practices and methodologies
that can be used to implement E.
A.
I and my favorite part
of the presentation.
The case studies.
I wanted to share some case studies
that I came across of companies
that have successfully implemented.
So we'll talk about those.
And then, if businesses do want to
go down the road of implementing,
I want to highlight what the
implementation road map will look like.
And, we'll talk about what the
benefits that businesses can reap
out of doing such an implementation.
Finally, we'll tie everything
together with, offer management
and then we'll conclude.
So let's jump in.
Okay, so when do businesses need
to optimize offer management?
so imagine this scenario, imagine
a new business that just started.
in the initial stages, it needs
only a few internal software,
say an accounting program, a CRM
and an email automation tool.
Now, let's say the marketing team comes
to the sales team and says, Hey, we want
to launch this email marketing campaign.
Can we get a list of prospects, right?
So the smaller business will have
these smaller systems and maybe
they're from different vendors.
And so there is no integration
between each other.
So someone from the marketing team
will have to go in person and, talk
to someone from the sales team and ask
them to pull this list of prospects.
That person will then have to go
into the CRM and pull this list and
send it to the request and so on.
So It takes a lot of transactions
or iterations for the marketing
team to be able to get the data.
And then generate the email campaign.
So that's how they run their businesses.
And perhaps it's okay at a smaller scale,
but what happens when these businesses
grow, and customers increasingly have
high expectations of personalized offers.
And there is a need for customers
to relate to the brand and they want
to have this consistent, seamless
experience across different channels
through which they interact with,
with the business, whether they're
going on to the website or to the app
or, they're walking into the storage.
that business has a retail store, so they
want to drive this interconnected business
experience across various channels.
the businesses, they want to make
sure these customers come back.
They want them to be loyal.
They want them to make repeat purchases.
Okay.
And they want to increase
the overall customer value.
And this has been proven by studies.
There are research papers that
have proved that, 91 percent
of consumers prefer brands that
recognize and provide relevant offers.
this, ties into the desire of
customers wanting, personalized offers.
Now, how do companies scale, right?
So in order for companies to scale, they
must start implementing more systems.
they add HR software, a
content management system.
Maybe some billing and payment
solutions and, some marketing automation
tool, data analytics, supply chain
inventory, instant messaging, and
the list can, it can go on now.
All of these systems grow within a
business as it scales and any business
that experience this level of scaling
needs a way to connect and rearrange
applications so that the data is shared
and businesses can provide value out of
connecting all of these applications.
And on, customer loyalty, customer
loyalty isn't just granted.
It must be earned.
And that is where enterprise
application integration comes in.
It helps provide that
integration between these apps.
Now, why does it matter?
Why is integration needed?
What is the business imperative
for integration again?
Imagine the situation where
the marketing team wants to
launch a campaign based on it.
previous purchase history for customers.
So imagine marketing team having access
to that kind of purchase history.
Or let's say they want to launch
an email giveaway of a product
and they have real time access
to the inventory of the product.
all of this helps having that kind
of consistent view of whether it's
customer data or company product data,
supply chain data, having that kind
of view for marketeers, it really
helps in making their decisions.
making their campaigns alive and
then, the ideas flow through, instead
if there is no such integration,
all of these systems are siloed.
So there are specific individuals or
teams that have access to a specific
system, but all of that is leading
to a fragmented experience because
the customer data, where the orders
where the customer orders are placed,
they're in the order management system.
The payments are in the payment
and invoices and the leads are
in this year and the customer
interactions are elsewhere.
And so if there are these are siloed,
then there is no value driven out of it.
And then the marketing team or the
sales team or the customer service
team, they struggle to make sense
with outdated or conflicting data.
So that's where you know,
integration would help.
Now again, imagine a campaign
has been created, they want
to get through approvals.
So typical way would be to go up the chain
and have executives approve the campaign
and typically that would require someone
to log into the campaign management system
and approve the campaign or, maybe send
them an email and have them respond.
Do an email with approval, but how
would, if the integration is built
straight into the instant messaging?
So as soon as campaign is created,
the, the messages go into, the, to,
to instant messaging, and then it
goes out to the executives, Through
I am at seeking their approval.
So for them, it's a one click experience
for the executives, and it makes it much
faster to go through the bottom line
again, being that, process of integration.
It helps remove these bottlenecks
and in several of these
business processes as well.
Now we know a marketeers rely
heavily on analytics, right?
So business gather information from
customers at every interactions.
Each interaction is a data point and
having that kind of view of data in a
single place real time makes the job
of marketeers or analysts that much
more easier and much more efficient.
So I'll talk more when we discuss
the case study, but each interaction,
it doesn't have to be limited.
All of these interactions
can be connected.
Integrated together into a
single view of all analytics and,
integration can make that happen
now from a sales perspective, right?
I've told you I've done sales before.
So I know how hard it is
for me as a salesperson.
When we call it the prospect to
realize that they've already made a
purchase, And that happened probably
because the lead didn't flow through
to me in time, as a salesperson.
So having, again, that kind of interaction
from the CRM to the sales team, it helps
nurture leads quickly in a timely manner.
And if leads, they're not
nurtured on time, then we know
conversion rates take a hit.
Now, I also want to talk more about
personalization for marketeers
to be able to do personalization.
If there is no integration, they have
to rely on manual segmentation and
often what happens is that manual
segmentation, it's not real time.
So data gets outdated fast.
So by the time the campaign is
launched, the segmentation has changed,
or the customer has moved and so
on, So again, having that kind of
real time access to data will help
marketeers react to changes real time.
And, provide effective personalized
offers to the customer.
So there are studies again, that say
if there is poor integration, there's a
loss of about 20 to 30 percent revenue.
And, so all of this is where,
enterprise application integration,
comes into picture and it helps.
So now, let's talk a bit about that.
what is EAI?
what's the definition of
enterprise application integration?
the definition is that it refers to the
seamless connection and coordination
of various software applications.
But the way I see it is, it
addresses lack of communication.
So if you look at the diagram here,
there are several applications, right?
There's a CRM, there's a supply
chain management, there is a ERP, the
catalog, there is several applications.
So how do all of these tie together
and how does the data flow through
for business to make sense?
And that's where EAI comes in.
What it does is it enables real time
data exchange between these systems.
And breaking down the silos.
So they're no longer
individual systems alone.
You know that the data in a meaningful
way is transferred and translated across
all these different systems and available
for business users to make decisions.
So again, the data is being
replicated, but it's not really.
Duplicate it in that
it resides everywhere.
the data flow is real time and
more importantly, though, it
facilitates that kind of agility
in responding to market changes.
So the moment business needs to react to
market change, the data is already there
and they're able to make reactive decision
instead of having to fetch data from
a different system and then go through
an analysis and then make that change.
okay, now there are a couple of different
types of integration that can happen.
I just want to briefly touch on that.
I listed them, here, so there is a
presentation integration that primarily
deals with, having a UI level integration.
So it merges, one or more applications,
but it's more at the UI level, right?
So it, so it's also referred to as
screen scraping in some context.
while this method is still employed in
some places, it's considered outdated.
The advantage obviously is that
there is a unified user interface.
So all of the information
is available in one place.
So perhaps, it is appropriate for
smaller applications, but then it
definitely is outdated and there
is not a lot of sophistication.
So it cannot be a comprehensive
integration and a lot of customization
might have to be, built in, the second
type of application integration It's
called the business process integration.
Now, let's take an example.
The CRM system, right?
It has the information about invoices.
And if it is integrated directly with
the order management system, as soon
as the order is placed in the order
management, the order data flows through
and the invoice is generated, right?
or think of another scenario.
Think of, let's say, as soon
as an order is placed, it's
connected to the scheduling system.
So if, something requires a technician to
go and install something, Then that data
that flows through scheduling system and
the scheduling also happens seamlessly
at the same time, an order is placed.
So the advantage clearly with business
process integration is that it enhances,
and improves efficiency, right?
Like I said, the installation
example, as soon as the order
is placed, the installation is
scheduled or the order info is sent
to the warehouse for fulfillment.
Now, all of these happens due to the,
the kind of business process integration.
So when that happens, it helps Automate
routine task and teams can, concentrate
on, more high value tasks, right?
So there are some challenges with
business process integration.
Anytime we are integrating
two systems, there are those
integration touch points, that is
a potential security vulnerability.
But of course, it can be taken care
by using, appropriate methodologies.
Also, it can have a system wide
impact in case of one system failure.
So there is that.
for example, if the order management
system fails, all of the other
systems that rely on data from
this, cannot function, right?
So it's like a single point failure.
But again, a smart, thought out
architecture can address such pitfalls.
So now the other type of, integration,
it's called the data integration.
This is where the data is transformed
in a way that systems Then at the data
generated in one system can be understood
and interpreted by other systems.
So the advantage there being that
it enhances data quality because
the data is refined to be able to
be interpreted by other systems.
There is also, that improved
collaboration between them and.
Also, in terms of analytics, it helps,
having a kind of data consistency and
data quality and overall, it improves
a lot of, efficiency in processes.
obviously there are challenges
with it, but mostly has to
do deal with data quality.
if the data is not maintained
properly, then that lack of quality,
rolls from one system into the other.
yeah.
that's something that can be, avoided.
Now, the last kind of, application
integration is, it's called
the communication, integration.
It's called the communication integration.
It's a type of integration where a lot
of middleware technologies, like APIs,
microservices, where the benefits are
that some of the solutions are flexible
and can be implemented regardless
of platform where it is deployed.
So it may be on cloud
or on premises, right?
There is also scalability, right?
Not having to replace the whole
thing, but just scale those
integrations quickly, Also, it helps
with asynchronous communication.
As in the previous example, if one
system fails, it doesn't have to
immediately impact other systems,
of course, there are challenges
with that in that it's more complex.
So we need to take care of how
technologies are utilized, and it may
require some, specialized expertise
during implementation and maintenance.
So there could be that performance
impact, especially handling large volumes.
But again, nothing that cannot
be handled by making some smart
choices in terms of scalability.
Now, there are some security risks.
Anytime an API is exposed, we need
to make sure that has the appropriate
security functions built in.
So that takes care of any vulnerabilities.
Now, okay, now that we learned
about what and what is EAI,
let's talk about some of the.
Best practices.
So there are a couple of
different, methodologies.
I don't want to deep dive into each
of those, but just high level, right?
There are a couple of
different methodologies.
So one, it's called the
point to point integration.
This is when one application can
just talk to another application
through a one to one integration.
This is, of course, not scalable,
because over time it builds up to
multiple one to one integration.
And Then there's a hub
and spoke model, right?
Where the hub is used to facilitate.
data transformation across
different applications, so it's
much faster, but it's also complex.
Then, there is the bus integration
methodology where all the participating
applications in the bus integrations,
they have common standards.
So that's the way they communicate.
Then there's also middleware, which is
some form of application integration.
Where there is some logic that can
be built within the middleware.
So it's abstracted into that middle layer.
So businesses choose to
replace vendors in the future.
they can do so easily.
the last one, but I think most
widely used right now in the industry
is the microservices integration
and what microservices are.
They use across most enterprises
now, and these are lightweight
applications that each service single
functions, and they are lightweight.
And due to the fact it and
due to that fact, they can
be deployed anywhere, right?
So they can be deployed on
the cloud or serverless.
So this is a very nimble, very agile,
way, these microservices are very
agile and very nimble that they can
be built to achieve, these kind of
integrations, between various systems.
So these are certain methodologies
that can be used, but Regardless
of the methodology, the best
practice for businesses or
organizations implementing E.
A.
I.
Is to have clear objectives in mind.
So so they need to make sure
they're aligned on what is the
desired, business outcome, right?
And also go through this kind
of comprehensive planning
with all stakeholders, right?
Whether it's finance, management.
Legal, IT, marketing,
sales, everyone's right.
So now the next thing is, as we are
navigating the complexities of new
technologies like AI, internet of
things, blockchain, now businesses
need to arrive at some kind of industry
standards so that these are interoperable.
So again, Like I was saying, if a business
desires to switch out a vendor, they
should be able to do so without having
to rewrite the whole business logic.
So that is something that
needs to be taken care of.
we already talked about having the data
quality and consistency that so that's
an everyday job that people need to do.
And definitely businesses, they
need to implement agile practices.
For development or for ongoing
optimization, then they're using, E.
A.
I.
Okay, so this is a slide
I want to talk about.
I came across a couple of
different case studies where
companies have implemented E.
A.
I.
Sephora.
I think most of us would know
that it's a retailer of cosmetics
and beauty products, but actually
they want to be more than that.
they want to build that experience.
They want to build a global beauty
community, delivering those in
store experiences, building that
connection with the customer.
So that's what they decide to do.
But, they were in a situation where
they had these disparate systems,
whether it's managing affiliates in
each region, the each country had
their own affiliate relationships and
each of them were managed separately.
And then there was also the data, right?
Sephora did not know that a
customer making a purchase in the
store that had previously browsed
a certain product on their app.
they did not have any of that view and
that's when, Sephora what they did is
they implemented EAI, where they brought
together all the customer information.
So now, they are able to recognize
the customer, when a customer
walks into the store from, Sephora.
they know that with the app, they're
able to recognize that customer and
they're able to provide those proactive
recommendations saying, Hey, perhaps
you're interested in these products
and show them relevant reviews.
And so they're able to do
that with by implementing.
that really helped them with
increasing their conversion rates.
Also, talking about affiliates, they
were able to consolidate all the
affiliates across different regions.
And, in managing their
relationships in a single place.
So that also led to a lot of
cost savings and rise in average.
Order value from these affiliates.
so that was a good, implementation Now,
I also know about another company shell,
that use this kind of implementation
Shell they have different loyalty programs
like v rewards go plus Fuel rewards.
There are different loyalty programs
across different regions, but then, for
their pricing analysts to be able to
launch an initiative, they had trouble
curating the data from, across these
loyalty programs and make a decision.
So Once they implemented EAI, though,
they were able to get to this data.
So their pricing analysts were able to
decide, for example, this particular gas
station, are they getting more customers
who are just driving along the road?
Or, they're getting customers
who live in the area, right?
So that level of data was available
for the pricing analyst so they can
make, appropriate pricing decisions.
again, these are some really
good success stories where
companies have implemented EAI.
And again, there is studies that back
this up, implementing AI businesses
have reported 29 percent increase in
open rates for emails and also where
this helps is, it's also helps in
reducing acquisition costs, right?
because companies are no longer, they're
no longer sending this mass market
emails, they're sending more personalized
emails based on, customer interactions.
and that is made possible.
Due to having this integration
of data across applications.
So, all Okay.
Now, I did want to talk about
the implementation roadmap for E.
I.
it has about four phases planning,
modeling, implementation, and
then the maintenance phase.
Planning phase.
It's where the applications
are identified.
You know what kind of applications
need to be integrated?
What is the current infrastructure?
What is the scope?
What do we want to achieve?
And also select the
appropriate methodology, right?
Then in the modeling phase,
that's where we decide what is
the integration architecture?
What business processes do
we really want to integrate?
And how do we want to map the data so
that it is consistent across systems?
So that kind of data modeling
happens in the modeling phase.
And, at the end of that, we have a
project plan as well as a blueprint.
To be able to do that implementation,
then comes the implementation phase where
businesses are actually implementing
those connectors and adapters,
implementing that data transformation,
integrating those processes.
And then, of course, testing
it to make sure the desired
business outcome is achieved and
then last the maintenance phase.
Of course, when it's implemented, it's You
know, being able to monitor and manage.
And if there are errors or anything being
able to fix those, that's part of that.
Also, for businesses, we all know that
you know that needs have all right.
So how do those changes get incorporated
back into the system into AI?
that is the maintenance phase.
And, that's also provide support
and troubleshooting for users.
Okay, now by implementing E I,
there are, of course, tangible
benefits for businesses.
These are quantifiable real benefits.
There is increased
customer retention loyalty.
There is revenue growth.
We talked about it.
Customers no longer want this generic.
Content or generic offering they want
to be able to relate to the business.
So businesses are investing in, reaping
benefits of personalized offers in a
way that when a customer is presented
an offer and if they accept or
decline it, every action they take.
Companies get the data to be able
to suggest the next best, action.
and all of these are being made
possible again through EAI having
that kind of access to the data.
So there is definitely a lot
of cost savings because of
the operational efficiency.
Nowhere we talked about where one person
doesn't have to go into multiple systems,
but that the data is available across,
in order to make those decisions faster.
we talked about having
reduced acquisition costs.
Yeah.
Okay.
So now just to reiterate the benefits
that offer management can get by using E.
A.
I.
there's personalization, where businesses
track customer behavior and preferences.
They can boost engagement.
So there are companies that are,
offering interactive features in
their apps and gamification and
all of this made possible with E.
A.
I.
Convenience.
Of course, customer, if they make an
online purchase and earn some rewards,
they should be able to redeem those
immediately when they walk into a store.
So it provides that
convenience to customers.
And again, for marketers, all of these
interactions lead to Valuable data
that can, drive insights and further
improve the loyalty program, right?
and earn that customer, loyalty.
Okay, I think that's it.
I want to leave everyone with this
thought, how, in this competitive market,
I strongly believe EAI is a very powerful
framework of tools and processes.
Of course, for optimizing customer
management, providing them the
right offers, giving them more
personalized offers, deciding
what the next best action is.
all of these resulting and, driving
business growth, and it becomes important
that by integrating data and system across
enterprise, they can deliver this kind
of consistent experience and increase
the revenue and earn that, loyalty
with that.
I think I'm at the end
of my presentation again.
Thank you everyone for listening in.
I really appreciate each one of you.
Thank you.