The future of work, engaged
leadership, and empowered teams.
I am passionate about this topic.
And why?
Because I hate waste.
I hate when people's work is wasted.
I hate when people's careers are wasted.
I hate when the project that they worked
so hard on, they worked nights and
weekends, and then that project gets
canceled and all that work was wasted.
Oh, it hurts me to see people suffer
because they feel like their work
is wasted, not worth anything.
I have been very fortunate.
I have had wonderful opportunities and
I love my work and I was able to lead
teams to deliver innovative products.
My team delivered the first commercial
version of RPC, a revolutionary mechanism
for devices to talk to one another.
I've led teams who love to come to work.
They were inspired to
propose new features.
They were excited to deliver products
that people would line up to buy.
I'm Leslie Martinich, and I'm going
to talk about why we need RPC.
New types of leadership, and
you'll see that in just a minute.
But part of the reason is that
technology and society have changed.
Society has changed dramatically because
of COVID and technology has allowed us
choices that we did not have before.
Now we need a new kind of leadership, a
leadership that will see teams delivering
products faster and more happily.
because they own their projects.
A leadership that will inspire teams to
aspire to targets that they previously
didn't even believe were possible.
Leadership that builds careers,
leadership that builds companies,
leadership that builds entire industries.
So what is the problem and why do
we need a new type of leadership?
here's one reason.
Currently, 65 percent of
employees are not engaged.
And of those, 20 percent are
actively disengaged, which means that
they've got one foot out the door.
They don't enjoy their work.
They don't even come to
work if they can avoid it.
They're not focused on
getting anything done.
They're just there, if
they're there at all.
Only 20 percent are actively engaged.
We want everybody to be actively
engaged, but right now only 20
percent are actively engaged.
That's just not going to cut it.
We need everybody to be actively engaged.
Leaders goal is our, leaders have
a goal, and that's to hire and
retain a productive workforce.
So here we have a productive
workforce looking all happy because
they're getting their project done.
They're getting their work done.
They're seeing the light
of day with their project.
they're happy about that.
But what is the big challenge?
Why, and especially for remote workplaces,
why are people not engaged right now?
the number one issue is trust.
That's the challenge.
For the workplace of the future.
And that's what we're talking about.
The future of work, the
future of work requires trust.
Trust can boost productivity by up to 50%.
It can improve retention by up to 65%.
And that is huge.
And it can boost the speed
of decision making as well.
What are the economics of trust?
When trust goes up, the speed of product
delivery goes up and the costs go down.
When trust goes down, the speed
goes down and the costs go way up.
Think of the amount of money
it costs and the slowdown in
speed that it costs you and me.
To go through an airport since
the 11th of September in 2001.
Now people don't trust
each other on airplanes.
We don't trust that everybody
is a reliable flying partner.
And so we have all these TSA security
places and security lines to go through.
What's the, what are the costs of that?
Oh my gosh.
Putting in gigantic scanners in
every airport, in every country
in the world, putting in all
sorts of logistics to handle that.
Hiring all sorts of security agents,
not to mention their dogs, but all
sorts of security agents to manage
people going through lines in airports.
That is a lot.
When, when Warren Buffett wanted to buy,
a company called McLean Distribution from
Walmart, he sat down with the Walmart
executives and had a two hour meeting.
They trusted one another.
They came to a conclusion based
on that two hour meeting, and
the deal closed in one month.
There's no wasting of months.
of due diligence, of
millions of attorney's fees.
Trust made that faster
and much lower costs.
So I just wanted to give you that
example of how trust can enable
things to go so much faster.
So people want choices, but leaders
still want control and that's a problem.
And it's a problem because the leaders are
focused on the management side of things.
They're focused on, they go to
training for leadership development
for meeting management, product
management, risk management, performance
management, and all sorts of things
with the word management in there.
And they're all important,
but they're all about control.
And that's It's not getting
to what makes employees happy.
They're very, these are very
last century things and Jack
Welch's style no longer works.
So here's a thought from
Steve Jobs that I like.
Management is about persuading people to
do things they do not want to do, while
leadership is about inspiring people.
to do things they never
thought they could.
I love that quote.
that's just so right.
So trust also requires ethical behavior.
You don't trust people who you
perceive to be unethical, taking,
making shortcuts, not doing things
that you consider trustworthy.
that's the word, trustworthy.
So the ethical challenges are taking
shortcuts, financial considerations,
maybe it's cheaper if we take
this shortcut, and then there's
also political considerations.
So let's talk a minute about
ethical behavior, and this will
be a, really fast lesson in the
history of the philosophy of ethics.
So ethics is a practice of
making choices and decisions.
You make one choice, it's fine.
It's an ethical choice and you
make another choice and maybe
it's a not so ethical choice.
but ethical behavior results in trust and
it results in a lot less risk of disaster.
So let's look at this
history of philosophy.
So philosophers try to
understand how the world works.
So with each time there's a new.
area of understanding than yet
another leaf sprouts on this tree.
So we start at the bottom, with,
say metaphysics and physics.
And we have some philosophers
trying to understand those ancient
Greek philosophers, and then
they get that down a little bit.
And then, we move on to mechanics
and then the tree branch on the
right is logic and then linguistics.
And then out of that sprouts
artificial intelligence.
Each time we get a pretty good
understanding of one of the branches
of this tree or one set of leaves,
a new set of leaves sprouts.
So out of logic and a few
other things comes linguistics.
And out of linguistics and
logic and a few other things
comes artificial intelligence.
We're going to look at that more
central branch, the one with ethics.
It's up top, and let's take
that, take a look at that.
And we're going to talk about
four philosophers who are
critical in the history of ethics.
The first is Aristotle, way down at the
bottom left, and then Immanuel Kant, and
then Jeremy Bentham and John Stuart Mill.
So let's start with Aristotle.
Aristotle and Plato's the guy on
the left there, Aristotle and Plato
were concerned with virtue and
character and practical wisdom.
Remember, philosophers are always
trying to figure out how the
world works, how people work.
What does it mean to be a good person?
What does it mean to be a person?
And so they were consider, concerned
about virtue and character.
And I want to reduce that for you for, to
make your job to be ethical really quick.
So you have one question to
ask, can you sleep at night?
So when you're faced
with an ethical dilemma.
You might try asking, can I sleep
at night if I make this choice?
Okay.
The next guy up is Immanuel Kant, a German
philosopher who lived in the 18th century.
And he was very concerned
about duties and rights.
He had a focus on standards
and the categorical imperative.
And categorical means in all cases.
categorically.
Declare this to be false, whatever, in
all cases, I declare this to be false,
categorical means that, in all cases,
an imperative, something that has to be.
So a quick question to ask yourself
when you're considering Kant's
offering to the ethical tree
is, what if everybody did this?
That's the category, that's the
categorical part, everybody.
What if everybody did this?
That's a good question to ask.
And then we come to Jeremy Bentham and
John Stuart Mill, late 18th century
to early 19th century, and they, and
John, Jeremy Bentham came up with the
idea of utilitarianism, and he was all
about happiness, and so he was looking
for what was the greatest good for
the greatest number, or Alternatively,
what's the least harm to people?
So Bentham and Mill really laid
out and defined the ethical
concepts of utilitarianism.
now you have three questions to
ask yourself, three approaches when
you're faced with any ethical dilemma.
Can I sleep at night?
What if everybody did this?
And what's the greatest good
for the greatest number?
And I.
I think these are writer downers,
you should write these down because
you can ask yourself or just
take a picture of your screen.
You can ask yourself these
questions whenever you're
faced with an ethical dilemma.
And usually at least one of them is
going to work out to be useful to you to
think about which path you should take.
So let's look at the Challenger disaster.
Happened in 1986.
And this is a picture of the
scaffolding, and that's the gray tubing
you can see with ice forming on it.
And right behind that is one of the
rocket boosters right behind it.
It is a really cold that morning that the
Challenger is getting ready to take off.
So here is the situation.
This was the coldest ever launch date.
The previous cold temperature
had been 53 degrees Fahrenheit.
The forecast temperature for that
day is 38, I'm sorry, 28 degrees
Fahrenheit, which is below freezing.
NASA and their supplier, Morton Thiokol,
which I'll call Morton Thiokol Engineers,
get together the, or have a conference
call the night before to discuss
the O rings and cold temperatures.
For And Morton Thiokol engineers know
that they really haven't tested their
O rings in these cold temperatures,
but they don't really expect them
to seal properly in that cold.
They expect them to be, not
pliable enough to seal properly.
So the Morton Thiokol engineers
recommend against the launch.
They come to an impasse in their
discussions, so they take a recess.
And after the recess, the Morton
Thiokol group said that their
evidence was inconclusive, so go
ahead and proceed with the launch.
Now, we all know what happened, This
is an O ring, just to, just to give
you a sense of how big they are.
When I first heard about this disaster,
which was the day it happened.
I thought O rings were probably something
that were about the size of a bracelet.
but that O ring was too cold to seal,
and it allowed hot gases to pass through.
Not good.
So after the launch, after 68
seconds, the entire rocket ship was
engulfed in flaming hot propellant.
And in 71 seconds Once
the Challenger exploded,
it was a terrible day.
So what would you have done if you
were a Morton Thiokol engineer?
And you could ask yourself about what your
recommendations would be, and you can ask
yourself, if I make this recommendation,
will I be able to sleep at night?
Or, what if everybody made recommendations
like this or took risks like this?
Or, you can ask yourself, what's the
greatest good for the greatest number?
Yeah.
what happened?
they come back from their recess, and
the Martin Thakal engineers say, it's
inconclusive, we don't really have
the data because we've never tested
the O rings at this temperature.
Whoever made the final decision to, to
launch, did they not take the engineer's
concerns seriously, or did they want
to take a shortcut so they wouldn't
be blamed for holding up the launch?
This was a, a launch that had
been delayed many times already.
People were anxious to
get this off the ground.
This was the first.
Space Shuttle launch that
involved a teacher in space.
So every school room in the country
is watching this as it happens.
Every parent was watching
this as it happened.
It was something that had a great
deal of publicity and everyone
was excited to see it happen.
And so everybody's looking
at TVs and then it blows up.
what happened to make, to allow
them to make that decision?
I don't know.
I think it's important to consider
how to communicate effectively.
Now, you don't want to be Chicken
Little running around yelling, Oh, this
guy is falling, this guy is falling.
Every time you see a risk.
You wouldn't be able to, get
out of the house in the morning
if everything were a risk.
Also, you don't want to be the
old lady who waits till the damage
happens and then says, Injured?
I told you But you didn't listen.
Call 1 800 BOO HOO.
You don't want to be
either of those people.
You don't want to lose your credibility
by claiming everything's a disaster
before you know for sure it is.
You don't want to be chicken little
over there and you don't want to
just salt and wait until the disaster
happens and then say, I told them
They should have listened to me.
that's not.
Not gonna win you any points.
So communicating is everyone's job.
It's important for the leaders to
communicate, but it's also important
for the individual contributors to
communicate because the individual
contributor is probably the one who
knows best when there is a risk.
When there is a risk of making a
decision, and that is the ethical
dilemma, what decision shall we make?
when they have to communicate to
their leaders what the risks are
so that the leaders understand
them and take them seriously.
So in order to do that communication,
you need to understand what
your audience cares about.
What is important to them.
Put the communication in their terms.
So here's an example of
a way to communicate.
I know we all want to help this
launch proceed smoothly, and we
all want the Challenger to launch
and return to Earth safely.
In order for us to feel confident
that can happen, we need to wait
until the temperature is warmer.
That would be a way of communicating
it, a way of communicating it.
Communicating that you understand that
the other person wants to get this launch
off but they want to get it off safely.
And so you're not confident that can
happen until the temperature is warmer.
That communicates that.
That's not just the leader's job, it's
everybody's job to learn to communicate.
So know what your audience cares about.
In this case, NASA cared about you.
NASA was the audience.
They cared about getting
this launch off the ground.
Of course, everybody was anticipating it.
They'd already been delayed and delayed,
and they didn't want to be delayed again.
So they wanted it to take off.
And then, once you understand what
the other person, your audience, cares
about, then you put it in their terms.
I know you care about this.
Getting this launch off and helping
people to come back smoothly.
So what's your action after I've
just talked about all these things?
Your action is to become
a trusted, engaged leader.
What does that involve?
That involves,
first, behaving in an ethical manner.
And I told you the three
questions you could ask yourself.
Will I be able to sleep at night?
What's the greatest good
for the greatest number?
And, what if everybody did this?
what if everybody took these shortcuts?
The world would be
pretty crazy pretty soon.
becoming a trusted, engaged
leader takes practice.
You need to practice those
ethical behaviors, making
decisions in an ethical manner.
You need to learn to be an engaged
leader, and that means to be present.
Being there, being present, you're
not, when someone's talking to you,
you're not looking at your devices,
you're not looking over their
shoulder to see if somebody more
important is coming down the hall.
You're not, checking your watch.
You're not saying, I got to run.
I've got more meetings.
Of course you have more meetings.
You always have more meetings, but be
present when someone is talking to you.
Be respectful.
That's number two.
When an employee brings you a
problem, you don't, and you think
It's not serious and you don't
just say, Oh, you worry too much.
It's not a serious problem.
Instead, be respectful and say,
I see that's a concern to you.
Tell me more about that.
Okay.
Now that's easy.
So when you're thinking,
this guy must be crazy.
He's worrying about everything.
Instead, pull this one
out of your back pocket.
I see that's a concern to you.
Tell me more about that.
And the third one is to listen.
When an employee brings you an
idea and you think the idea is
wacko, say, I see you think that
feature X would improve the product.
Tell me more.
How can we implement that
without bumping the schedule?
Don't just say, I don't
think we can do that.
It's just not going to
fit in the schedule.
Instead, listen and ask
for more information rather
than just dismissing them.
Listen when they bring you ideas.
I see you think that feature
would improve the product.
Tell me more.
And can you figure out how
we could implement that
without bumping the schedule?
This is just something you can say.
To not just be dismissive of the
employee, but listening to them.
And then this is the really fun part.
Listening gives you
opportunities for creativity.
So somebody may come up with a really
good idea, but you didn't see how it could
be done without bumping the schedule.
And that's what you care.
You care about the schedule.
You want it done on time, right?
no, you just not even going to
entertain ideas for new features.
But instead, listen to them.
Maybe they have a way of implementing
that without bumping the schedule.
Another aspect of being an engaged
leader is to enlist your team.
Enlist your team.
You hired them because they were smart.
You hired them because they were talented.
You didn't hire a bunch of dummies.
Enlist them to help solve some of the
problems, to help define some of the
processes that you're going to use, to
help them define some of the products.
Instead of you mapping out the
architecture, the chunks of work, the
dependencies, the schedule, everything,
and then just saying, okay, here, you do
this chunk and I need it in five days.
You do this chunk, and by the way,
Joe has to finish his chunk of
work before Susie can start hers.
Now, you don't map it out and tell
people just what to do without really
helping, without really letting
them help with, that definition.
So instead, you enlist them.
They're smart.
They're talented.
So ask them to help you.
Say, here, we have an opportunity
to work on this project.
Here are the basic outlines and
constraints, like it has to be done
in time for this big trade show.
but you enlist them and you ask
them how they would architect it.
How they would define it.
How they would, break down the chunks.
Who the chunks would get assigned to.
Ask the people who wants
these chunks of work.
and then work together to come up with
a reasonable schedule and remember
that they're going to count into their
schedule just how long it would take
them to do that work without being
interrupted by other people asking
them questions, without meetings,
without emails, without all sorts of
things that just get in their way.
So put buffer in there and then ask them.
Okay.
you wanted five days.
How about if I give you eight
days, will that work for you?
Oh yeah.
That'll work for me.
That's good.
Now I'm the engineer.
I own the product.
I own this because I only thought I needed
five days and my boss gave me eight.
So great.
I'm all on board with that and
help your team become empowered.
And that takes practice.
here are the outcomes when you are an
engaged leader and you empower your team.
You have trust.
You have empowered teams.
You've improved retention.
And let's just take a moment
here to talk about retention.
Retention has the opportunity
for huge cost savings.
If you have a problem with people
leaving and really bad retention,
then you have a huge expense.
Let me give you an example.
Suppose your employees make, on average,
between their salaries and their benefits,
let's just say they make 175, 000 each.
And 10 of them quit in the last
year, so you had to pay them.
Replace 10 employees.
So the formula is, you take
their salary, and you double it.
And that's your cost to replace them.
It does not include their salary.
It's just the cost of the recruiters
working, the cost of the hiring
manager, reviewing resumes, interviewing
people, making the offer, negotiating
it, it's the cost of the team members
doing the interview, getting, and a
huge cost is the team members working
to get the new person up to speed.
That's, it takes weeks, months.
So getting the new person
up to speed is a big cost.
if you have 10 employees at 175, 000
each, times 10, that's 1, 750, 000.
Times two, because it takes weeks.
That's 2x the salary to, replace them.
That's 3, 500, 000, 3, 500, 000 per year.
So what if engaged
leaders could do better?
They could improve that by half.
Say only five people
quit the following year.
That saves you 1, 750, 000.
That's a lot of money.
So retention.
And building an engaged team and
having a productive, happy, empowered
team can save you a lot of money.
So that's a, retention is
a really good outcome here.
And then it's easier for you to recruit.
That's the next outcome, recruiting.
So when your employees are burned out
and disengaged, You really don't want
them interviewing potential candidates
because they're not really happy
about working here, and that's going
to show no matter what they think.
but when you have a trusted team, an
engaged and empowered team, and they,
a team that owns its projects and can
hardly wait to work on them, then,
that shows through to the candidates.
Also, The team will tell other
people in the community, wow,
this is a great place to work.
I really love it.
My boss is fantastic.
So the recruitment becomes so much
easier if you have trust, engaged
leaders and empowered teams.
And of course you have
better productivity.
just imagine if you will, a
workplace where everyone felt heard.
That'd be nice.
A workplace where everyone felt seen
and a workplace where everyone
felt like their dias and their
work mattered, like they mattered.
That would be nice.
That's what you get with a
trusted workplace, empowered
teams, and engaged leaders.
It's a great thing.
I've experienced it.
Everyone loves it.
Just take some time, practice these
skills and you can have that too.
So if there's questions, I'm
always happy to answer questions.
I put up my LinkedIn connection and I
put up my email and my mobile phone.
So thank you very much for your
attention and Just let me know
if you've got some questions.
I hope you have a wonderful day.
Thanks.