Hi everyone.
My name is Piotr Zaniewski.
I'm a head of engineering
enablement at Loft Labs.
And today I will talk to
you about architecting.
developer platforms.
We'll focus specifically on
infrastructure developer platforms.
We will talk about design principles
and tools used in building those.
This will be heavily Kubernetes centric.
And I also have a really cool demo.
So a little bit about me.
I specialize in all the cloud native
ecosystem, Kubernetes, Docker.
Linux and so on.
I typically spend way more free
time on tweaking my dot files and
working with NeoVim than I should
have, but it's a lot of fun.
As I mentioned, I work at Loft Labs.
Go ahead and check them out if
you would like to Work with the
cluster or other cool projects.
the easiest way to contact me is to go
to my web page cloud rumble dot net or
simply, send me an invite on LinkedIn.
So before we jump into the building
of the platform architecting it, let's
actually talk about what platform is.
And the way I like to do this is
like contrasting it or putting it in
the context of existing knowledge.
So for me, there are
three kinds of platforms.
One is a business platform.
If you have used an application
like Uber or DoorDash, those are
really platforms for consumers.
They enable both consumers and vendors
to connect and sell their services.
So that's it.
That's a platform that is essentially a
product that is consumed by the end user.
Another type of platform is
the domain specific platform.
So those are typically services
that encapsulate cross cutting
functionality for user facing services.
A good example is if you have,
let's say, An application that has
a map functionality would like to
put this map functionality like
geofencing, translating addresses
and so on into a separate service.
And then this would be your platform.
The developers can use.
And finally, we have a third
kinds of platforms, which are
domain agnostic platforms.
So this is the one that we
are going to talk about today.
And the way to define those is
those are really building blocks
that provide essential tools.
They can be infrastructure focus, like the
one we'll talk about today, or they can
be older, domain agnostic, something that
doesn't fall into your business domain,
security related platforms and so on.
All right.
So with this definitions out of the way,
Let's talk about why this is useful.
What's the point of building platforms?
Imagine somebody has already
access to cloud like AWS or Azure.
Why do they need something on top of that?
The simple answer is that cloud
infrastructure or infrastructure
in general is built for everyone.
Is not built for your
developers specifically is
built for everyone in mind.
So every customer of Azure would need to
find themselves in the cloud services.
So they might provide way too
much than your developers need.
So thus, we need to simplifies the
resources management and isolate
only those features that are useful.
And important and actually empower our
developers rather than expose everything.
this in turn increases development
efficiency because developers
don't have to spend time learning
Kubernetes or learning all
kinds of complex cloud services.
They can just rely on the internal
platform to provide them what they need.
platforms are also typically
built in scalability in mind.
So they are from ground
up, scalable and reliable.
And this is something that
clouds, of course, already have.
But when you design your own platform,
that's probably the concern that you
will think about at the very beginning.
So what are the building blocks of a
typical cloud native developer platform?
those are not exclusive all the building
blocks, but also the ones that you
would see in most modern platform.
So first of all, you have a some
form of self service portal.
This portal can be a web
interface like we will see in
the demo, but it can be a script.
It can be a program.
It can be a web interface.
API directly exposed to an endpoint.
At the end of the day, this is really
encapsulating APIs and making it
simpler to access services and execute
repeatable tasks like provisioning a
service, executing a test, and so on.
creating a femoral testing
environment and so on.
Finally, a second point is really the key.
And I would like to emphasize this
in this talk, but the platforms are
really an additional abstraction
layer over an existing APIs and
they provide the programmatic APIs
for developers to interact with.
Again, self service portal could be
one way of doing it, but you can also
directly, access APIs if you need it.
Automated workflows.
So think of GitOps and similar principles.
Platforms by design would use those
to automate the data flow within
the pipeline of whatever tasks are
necessary from developers to execute.
Developers can provision a service.
And then the way it happens is
that it uses behind the scenes
tools like Argo maybe, or GitOps.
That automate the whole provisioning
process, monitoring and observability.
this is not platform specific,
but it's very important.
Specifically, in the age of
distributed systems, monitoring and
observability, ability to roll back
and maybe perform canary deployments
or similar things is really critical.
So baking it in the platform is
something that we see, Every time
and this is a very important building
block security and governance controls.
I would also bundle here isolation.
So if you have a platform that needs
to isolate workloads from a tenant to
tenant, then you might use services
like the cluster internally to
isolate and achieve multi tenancy.
you want to use products, maybe a Falco
or others to harden your security and
provide an end product that is secure.
in a way that corresponds
to your compliance rules.
This also means providing
audit trails or other things.
So those are things that you don't
necessarily see as a developer, but
those are important building blocks.
And finally, platform is ever evolving.
Platform is a product.
It is going to continuously
evolve with your users.
You need to have an organizational
structure around platform that
controls its improvement, its
evolution and its features.
So those are six building blocks
that are definitely important to
see in any successful platform.
Best practices.
or successful platforms.
As I mentioned earlier, API
driven is the key point.
If you look at AWS, Azure, Google,
or any other successful cloud
platform, the way they provide access
to their services is through API.
You might, of course,
consume it through a UI.
But on a large scale, there's an A.
P.
I.
Responsible for driving your
decisions within the cloud.
You can create a cloud
service, manipulated and do
all kinds of things through A.
P.
I.
And I think having an A.
P.
I.
Driven mindset in building your
platforms is the key to success, and
it sets you up on the path to success.
Cloud native principles.
This, of course, means designing
The platforms to be friendly
to cloud native applications.
So things like containerizing
orchestration, leveraging
various cloud native projects
that falls into this bucket.
And as I mentioned earlier, GitOps
workflow or some form of automated
rollbacks now releases a B testing and,
following GitOps principles one way or
the other is definitely something that
will ensure success of your platform.
What is an API?
Let's just make a quick refresher.
So API stands for application
programming interface and is really
a set of rules and protocols for
building and interacting with software.
So I emphasize those two words
here, interface and interacting.
this is how typically the logic is driven.
And if you design your platform thinking,
how my developers would interface with the
Set of services and API's are provide I
provide and how would they how would the
API's interact with existing software?
So you have kind of a.
Pipeline idea.
At one end, you have a developers
teams that use whatever interface
is comfortable for them.
And then at the other hand, you
have some outbound, processes that
interact with various software.
Let's say Argo or, deploy
something to Kubernetes.
So if you have this mindset of having
an API pipeline, It really helps
design a very healthy platform.
So why it all matters?
Why do we want to have a platform?
And why do we want to
follow an API driven design?
First of all, this
simplifies a lot of things.
You can hide or create an
obstruction that exactly,
corresponds to your developers needs.
You can standardize on
existing standards, HTTP, GRPC.
You can use something
that's already there.
You don't need to invent a
new communication protocols.
It helps automate all kinds of tasks on
various levels and layers of automation.
And finally, APIs are very good
at scaling, and you can also
secure them relatively easily.
A brief reminder, I want to
repeat that platform is a product.
So this simplistic diagram really
shows that the way you design a
platform is not different than
designing any other product.
So you want to understand
your customer's needs.
You want to design something that fulfills
a need or two, test it, implement it,
and deliver it to your customers, gather
feedback, improve on it, rinse and repeat.
The platform should be
approached in the same way.
So let's transition to a demo.
During this demo, I want you to think of
the principles we just discussed and see
how they translate to an actual platform.
So we are going to see how platform
can empower developers, how it uses
cloud native principles, is API driven,
and is baked by GitOps workflow.
So let's transition to a demo.
I am going to wear a
different, different hats.
So now I am starting as
developer, what on the screen.
is my developer world.
This is my application.
It's called, Azure Storage Blob Reader.
And the task of this application is
to read the content of Azure Blob
Storage and display it on the screen.
I might not know too much about
Kubernetes or cloud services.
My knowledge of containerization ends
with this very simple Dockerfile.
Right here.
Maybe somebody from platform
team helped me create it.
But that's about it.
So my application is a Node.
js app.
We don't need to go in detail.
In code.
I just wanted to show you that me as
developer, that's what I spend my time on.
I am creating new features every day.
I run tests.
I make sure that everything works.
And then I'm using cloud native
services and cloud services in
conjunction with my application.
But the most important part here, that's
where I would feel most comfortable.
I don't need to deal with
all the cloud complexity.
All right, so that's the developer.
So the developer.
Now I would like to deploy
this application and test it.
I want to see if
everything works correctly.
So how do I do it?
Remember from our principles, we
are actually using service portal.
So here for this demo, I am using port.
Unfortunately, port still
doesn't have dark mode.
Apologies for that.
I tried to keep everything in
dark mode for presentation.
Regardless, we can see, as developers,
that we have two actions in our homepage.
One, it says cross plane storage
account reader, and we can create
it, and another one for removing it.
this is the extent of the
knowledge I need to have in order
to create my infrastructure.
let's kick it.
When I hit create, it asks me some
variables, not many, just three
that I might be interested in.
One is connection string,
how I want to name it.
Another one is my image, maybe I
want to iterate on the new versions
of the image and I can bump it.
An application port.
I am happy to accept the defaults and
behind the scenes what's happening port
in this case would actually kick off
a CICD pipeline, which in turn creates
a PR that creates a necessary file.
Okay, so this step is
really just for convenience.
We could have manually create a
file, but we did it through port.
as developers, we interact with
port or with backstage, and we
actually create various things.
let's see what's happening.
If we refresh this, we should see
in a moment that there is a pull
request being created by port.
I don't know why it doesn't auto refresh
yet, maybe a good feature request.
So now we have a pull request into
a repository called apps deployment.
So let's see.
Let's click on our pull request.
All right, so we can
see some details again.
This is from a developer point of view.
I can interact with this
and read various things.
I can see logs and runs and whatnot.
That's not important at this point.
But here I have a link to my repository.
As you can see, we have apps deployment.
This repository is specifically
designed to deploy my application.
So now I am changing my hats to
becoming a platform team or maybe an
admin, and I can see, oh, there's a
new PR on a deployment repository.
By the way, this action is
obviously not mandatory.
You can skip the PR review, but I
want to show you that it's possible.
So what does this PR do?
This PR creates a single YAML file.
We talked about API and
this is the API in action.
The API we all agreed on is
the Kubernetes style API.
So both platform engineers and
developers agree that the way we're
going to talk to each other and the
way we're going to make things happen
is by standardizing on Kubernetes API.
Why a Kubernetes API?
There are various reasons.
Kubernetes already exists
and has strong ecosystem.
Kubernetes lends itself very well
to designing custom APIs using CRDs.
And the list goes on.
So how does this file look like?
You can see this file has API version,
which if you're familiar with Kubernetes,
you will know it has kind, which is
a custom resource definition kind.
So this is an app claim.
It has some names and
labels, and it also has spec.
It follows the Kubernetes API
design, which is spec and status.
And within the spec, Those are
the parameters you might remember.
We specified in port when
we triggered the service.
So we have a namespace
which we couldn't specify.
This namespace is hard coded for our team.
And then we have those parameters.
So this simple YAML file is all
what it's necessary to create our
application, create associated cloud
infrastructure, and other things.
All right.
So let me show you one
more thing before we move.
I'm going to trigger Argo CD.
So here I just have a
handy script to do this.
So I just type just launch Argo and
you will see that inside of Argo CD,
there is not much happening just yet.
Let me log in real quick.
We have a simple bootstrap application
and this Argo CD app Observes
the apps deployment repository.
The one we just seen a moment ago and
the one which we opened the PR to.
So for now we have this empty app.
Nothing happens.
Okay.
So far so good.
Let's approve the PR.
Let's pretend that I reviewed it and
we're going to merge it right now.
When we merge the PR, we will see in
a moment that Argo will pick it up.
I will help Argo by refreshing the screen
real quick and things start happening.
We will see there's a lot of new
resources that are being created
just from the small configuration
YAML that I submitted through API.
So we have app claim, which is
exactly the YAML that we've seen
earlier with some Kubernetes
annotations and additional code.
Kubernetes added stuff, but you
can recognize the spec here and
little our parameters and so
on and the kind API up claim.
So we have applied it to the cluster.
Okay, so how come we have
all those things right here?
We'll talk about this later, but
let's go back to being a developer.
Remember, one thing I did
is I went through my port, I
created, clicked create, and how
do I know if my app is ready?
Maybe I wanted to go and
grab a coffee, but my goal is
really to test my application.
Okay, what's a better way than
create a Slack notification?
And as you can see here in my
channel, I have an app notify.
That I might be subscribed to and I
have a notification and it tells me your
application is deployed to localhost.
Okay, let's give it a go.
Indeed, we have Kubernetes demo.
Let me make it a little bit bigger.
So this is my application.
That's my storage, Azure
Storage Account Reader.
So now it's working, but there
are no documents found inside.
And just to prove to you that we have all
the architecture, all the infrastructure
here, If we go to Azure for a moment,
you can see that we have platform demo,
which is the resource group that is being
deployed and sorry for all the jumping.
But going back to, you can see that
one of the resources that we've
deployed is actually resource group.
So it is corresponding to
my resource group in Azure.
We also have vcluster, slug and some
other stuff that's called object.
It's quite some resources that we as
developers didn't need to specify.
All right, so you can see here
we have platform demo storage.
This is our storage bucket.
If you're not familiar with Azure, storage
bucket is like an S3 bucket in AWS.
And inside of it, we have a
simple container called sample
blob, which is currently empty.
There's nothing here.
But our app works and we as developers.
Just needed to click one button.
Okay.
So how do we test this
API all the way down?
Let's go back now.
By the way, you can see here.
we have cross plane resources.
Cross plane is the magic behind
creating all the cloud infrastructure.
And then we also have here an NS,
which is a Kubernetes cluster viewer.
We can see all the events and we
will look at this a little later.
But for now, let's again switch
hearts and let's become a developer.
So now I don't want to use get ups.
I don't want to use,
something complicated.
I just want to quickly create
something that I can test my app.
So my app needs an actual file that is
inside of the blob and storage account.
So what I can do is I can use
your catalog, apply that file.
And I go to examples folder.
And here I have a blob content dot Yama.
We'll see its content in a second,
but remember, it's just an API.
So I want to create a blob content inside
of my newly created infrastructure.
And let's see what happens.
So it says created.
If we go back to our web page
and refresh now, you can see that
our storage block leader actually
reads the content of a file.
Hello, 24 platform engineering and just
to prove it to you that the file is here.
You can see, indeed, there's an example
file present in my storage account.
from the developer's point of view,
I was able to very easily spin
up the infrastructure, create my
application, and do everything that
is necessary to interact with it.
Let's go back real quick to
the application and see what's
happening inside of my application.
But if we go to namespaces, you can see
that there's a DevOps team namespace.
And inside of it, I have a
three replicas of my app full.
And I have also a cluster
and some coordinates.
So why do I have the cluster?
Let's imagine that the developer we
tested this, but we also want to.
Maybe we are a little bit more
Kubernetes savvy and we want
to experiment with Kubernetes.
But of course, we Our kubernetes is
populated by other tenants, and we don't
really want to get in anybody's way.
Maybe we want to create and try out new
English controller or something else.
And here, if you go back quickly to our
slack notification, it tells us that
we have here a dedicated V cluster.
So if I have a big cluster CLI, Slack
tells me, Hey, this is your big cluster.
You can connect to it and you can do
whatever you want in this big cluster.
So let me open a new window.
I can connect.
And as you can see, we are connected.
I can, for example, run maybe a debug
port or I can run, any other port
or create any other part they want.
And this would be interacting
with my future cluster.
So we're not only given the developer
the Testing ephemeral environment.
We also given them, their own fully
fledged virtual Kubernetes cluster
where they can test whatever they want.
So they don't have to open
tickets and keep following up.
So we are escalating the ability for
developers, to use various testing tools.
All right, let's, close it.
Let's go back to our regular cluster.
And we have seen the whole
flow so far as a developer.
I am very happy.
I didn't need to interact with any of it.
I can see my application clearly.
and I can test it.
I can also additionally look at
the observation log, so you can
open Grafana, which is a dedicated
Grafana dashboard just for me.
And as you can see now, just
a little bit of data here.
It's a dashboard that maybe my
platform team prepared, and it only
observes my namespace and my vcluster.
And then I can see what's happening.
Maybe I want to tweak resource
quotas and so on in my application.
So we can see we are giving
developers various tools, and they
are All automatically deployed.
We don't need to create
a ticket or anything.
We just deployed all of
this that you've seen.
We have deployed from this small yaml file
we've seen earlier, which is this guy.
Okay, so now we're How did it all happen?
Where is the secret sauce?
Obviously, the complexity
cannot completely disappear.
So there is definitely
complexity somewhere.
So let's open a composition.
So what I'm doing here, I'm using cross
plane and cross plane composition.
As you can see, it's 285 lines of YAML.
And as a platform team, this is my task.
I am encapsulating and hiding
this composition, this, complexity
inside of a composition.
I'm hiding it away.
From developers.
So let's see what this
composition has inside.
So if we go for name, you can see
it has an account service ingress
and also deployment namespace.
Those are all Kubernetes resources.
It has the cluster.
Resource group container
and so on and so forth.
So all those things are deployed for
us by cross plane, and we can hide
all the complexity using those tools.
So you can go and read all the file.
I will leave a link somewhere in the
presentation, so you can see it later
and you check the repository for it.
But that's how it works.
But this is.
Again, I'm putting a heart
of a platform engineer.
That's how, that's how
we can make it happen.
That's how we can make it possible.
All right.
So now I'm done as a developer.
I don't want to deal with this anymore.
I have tested.
I successfully tested everything.
And now I want to delete.
All the infrastructure, including
all the Kubernetes resources.
So as you might imagine, there is
another action that I can perform in my
port here, namely delete the resource.
So I am just selecting
the right repository.
And I have to give here a file name.
So I'm not deleting accidentally
somebody else's file.
Click delete.
And as you can imagine,
that opens another PR.
We need to wait a second
for another PR to arrive.
And once we approve this PR,
everything will be cleanly removed,
including our cloud infrastructure,
as well as Kubernetes resources.
So that is a really, lean flow
implementing the principles we were
talking about and, showing you how
potentially you could implement
an infrastructure platform, and
expose it to your developers.
Again, let's pretend I've reviewed it.
What it does, it just simply
removes the file, but there's
nothing crazy happening here.
It's a simple GitHub action,
confirm, and we are done.
So with this done, if I go back
to Argo and refresh, you can see
that everything could be gone or
is in the process of being deleted.
And we can go also here, you can
see on the left hand side, all
the cross plane resources are
also being currently removed.
My application is being removed.
Everything is cleanly done.
All right.
That was hopefully, showing you
well, how you can do this, but let's
quickly go back to presentation and
let's, summarize what we've just seen.
So what tools have we used?
We have used Kubernetes and we used
it not as a Container orchestration,
but we use this as a control plane.
We've leveraged Kubernetes A.
P.
I.
Friends and foremost, and we used it
to reconcile everything and anything.
We used also the cluster to give
our developers, virtual Kubernetes
cluster if they need a little bit more.
to play around with or test.
We have used cross plane to deploy
everything and reconcile our deployments
to keep it synchronized with the
desired state with the actual state.
And we have used various
cross plane providers.
Providers are like telephone
providers that you can target
various infrastructure.
We have used Azure provider.
We have used cross plane
functions, Kubernetes, Helm, HTTP.
So that's like Lego building
blocks, which you can target.
We have used Port, which is a
developer portal similar to Backstage,
and we let our developers interact
with Port rather than, directly
interacting with the YAML file.
I want to emphasize it is possible
to directly interact with YAML
or even to directly interact with
Kubernetes API, depending on the need
and the level of, our developers,
knowledge about Kubernetes.
We've used GitHub and specifically used
it as an interface driving the exchange
between the platform team and developers.
And we used the.
Messaging system.
as prs, we use PRS as messaging systems.
Our prs are actionable messages that
developers send to platform team.
They review it and then, magic happens.
For GitHubs, we used Argo cd.
We could have used flax or other
mechanism, but Argo CD because of its ui,
was nice to show it and believe it or not.
All this that I showed you is running
on my local kind Kubernetes cluster,
which is Kubernetes in Docker.
So I was able to encapsulate all
those things inside of my Kubernetes.
You can, of course, run it in Docker.
in a cloud somewhere like in AKS, EKS or
GCP, and you can do this equally well.
All right.
So that was tooling.
Let's look at a helpful diagram,
that will again, guide us through
the journey that we just saw.
And I would like to pinpoint
certain aspects here.
So we started by being a developer.
We interacted with the portal and then
we accessed the UI and we created a
triggered, creating of our ephemeral
testing environment, including our
app, this in turn triggered action
to git and our git repository.
Received, an action or triggered an
action as a third step, this PR, was
reviewed by platform engineers approving.
We have committed those changes to
a repository where Argo reconciled
it, applied it to a cluster,
and from there, Crossplane Bye.
Bye.
Talk to Kubernetes API and used CRDs and
various other mechanisms to reconcile all
the infrastructure and the application.
This in turn resulted in provisioning
vCluster, provisioning our application,
which is various Kubernetes resources,
and also provisioning cloud services.
So that's just a quick overview
of what we have done in the demo.
in conclusion, what we were able to do.
We reduced friction for
developers to almost zero.
The only touch point that developers had
to have with the infrastructure was a
PR approval from somebody from platform
team, but we could very easily eliminate
this PR approval and then we would have
actual zero friction in the whole process.
We eliminated waiting times related to
Tickets because we anticipated that our
developers might need a little bit more
experiment with and we have added the
cluster that gives them essentially admin
level privileges, virtual cluster, and
they don't need to ask us constantly.
Hey, can you create this for me?
Can you create that for me?
So we have both cater to the immediate
needs of testing and application.
And we also gave them A little playground
that is encapsulated just for the team
or just for the person that does the PR.
We have used the Git PR as a unified
interface between platform and
developer teams, and we encapsulated
the API calls to the Kubernetes.
Those API calls are in the form of YAML.
This is just configuration, but at the
end, those are instructions for the
Kubernetes API and other projects like
Crossplane to do something with it.
And the magic is in the collaboration
part where platform team prepared
something up front, which is a cross
plane composition and all the setup.
And then developers were able to
collaborate by executing various APIs.
We have also followed zero trust security
principles because our developers
didn't need any access to Azure.
They can, but we've encapsulated it
to a point where the developers simply
interacted only with API through
Kubernetes without even knowing
that there's Kubernetes behind it.
They just apply files and work
with files and configuration and
then achieve certain results.
And we didn't even mention AI once.
So the key take away from this
presentation is really to think
of designing developer platforms,
whether they are infrastructure
or other types of platforms.
Think about it like designing an API.
API is really a data pipeline.
It has input.
It has outputs.
It has various.
mutations that happen along the way.
And if you think about how your API should
look like and how you design and craft the
contract between developers and platform
team, that's a recipe for success.
Thank you for your attention.
Thank you for your time.
please enjoy the rest of the conference.
if you would like to reach out to me.
You can visit my web page, CloudRumble.
net, or simply connect me,
connect with me on LinkedIn.
And I would be really interested to hear
your thoughts about Kubernetes, platforms,
and all the tools that we've used.