Hello everyone.
My name is, I have t years of experience
in Enterprise Cloud technologies with
a strong focus on data engineering
analytics and I also have the more than
15 years of deep industry expertise
working across various sectors to drive
innovation, performance, and value
through the data driven solutions.
Today we are going to talk about that.
Data services and below the
topics we are going to cover,
let's move to agenda Today.
We'll expose some of the key challenges
enterprise face in modern integration
with a special focus on SAP system.
We'll drive into the SAP World
Data Services for examine how,
what data are transforming
integration by enabling seamless
data exchange across the platforms.
In this scenario, we will look
at the performance optimization
techniques, explore real world case
studies, and discuss how mobile
and the third party integrations
are driving greater efficiency and
adoption across the industries.
Let's move on to the next one.
For modern enterprise integration
challenges, large augmentation often
operate across five to 15 distinct
systems are more than that one.
With every new system added
complexity does not just
increase, it grows exponentially.
Create what researchers
call integration depth.
Some of the common challenges included
middleware dependency, which drives
up cost to heterogeneous environment,
massive data volumes that create
the bottlenecks at the interface
boundaries, pushing performance
recommend to the limit security weakness.
Explicitly when exposing sens or
high confidential data to the modern
cloud-based application complexity and
return data transformation as a different
system often represent the same business
concept in entirely different ways.
Integration method often lead
to what we call ity integration.
The tangle, a fragile and expensive
web of connection that's become
harder to maintain over time.
Let's move the next further integration
and distance aggression cycles.
Enterprises often move between cycle
of consultation and fragmentation
driven by the evolving business needs.
According to the research by Lee and May.
Each new system added indication
pain point does not just increase.
They multiply creating,
escalating complexity across
the enterprise landscape.
In two days, always on economy,
that demand has shifted toward the
real time access to zero latency
or maybe with near zero latency.
Even small delays can impact decision
making, customer experience, and
overall operational efficiency.
With that one, the evaluation, SAP
integration Flats, SAP integration,
has gone through the several key stages
on over the time in the past or early,
early, SAP in the beginning of the custom
SAP web program and bad jobs were used.
This work well for basis
needs, but lack of flexibility
for in real time operations.
Traditional integration.
Next middleware layers and the
connectors were introduced with the
effective, with the cured specialized
expertise and often create silos.
Access systems.
What data service error today?
The data service presenter.
A major shift delivering restful,
standardized A PA overall STTP,
enabling seamless, scalable, and modern
integration platform first approach.
Finally, integration has evolved to
the platform first model where security
scaling, more monitoring and error
handling, or managed centrally at
the platform level, not individually
at the error integration point.
To move on the next slide.
The what Data Service
architecture Overview.
What data Extend Rest principle to meet
the unique needs of SAP environments.
First, it use entity modeling that
aligns directly with SAP application
layer, ensuring your natural fit
for enterprise data structures.
Second, all data provides
metadata descriptions.
Making service, self-documenting and
easier for developers to understand
and consume that it supports standard
CT P operations, including get post,
put and delete, ensuring seamless
integration across modern applications.
Finally, what data definition can
consumed by third party application
while preserving rich business
semantics, enabling consistent
meaning and context across platform.
Let's talk about that benefit and
benefit of that water data approach.
Let's look at some of the key
benefits of the word data First.
Democratize data access operating
under the principle of connect once re
often reuse often, which significantly
improves efficiency and scalability.
Second, it reduce integrity complexity of
offering consistent interfaces, simplified
security, and broad compatibility
through the JSN and Excel support that.
It takes a developer friendly approach
by using restful patents familiar to
most developer and align aligning closely
with the S-A-P-I-P first strategy.
Finally, all data brings strong
technical advantages, including
flexible querying and simplified entity
relationship model that can fully
leverage SAP HANA in memory patterns.
Let's talk about the performance
automations and techniques.
Scale performance in more that
is achieved through several
key optimization techniques.
Select filtering, selective filtering,
imagination support, response
to comparison, batch processing
filtering is this user server.
Site filtering which dollar filter
expression to only the what necessary,
and avoiding un unnecessary data loads.
Imagination support.
Implemented using dollar skip
and dollar top parameters.
This ensure large data sets are
delivered in smaller, manageable chunks.
Response comparison, algorithm,
compass data payloads,
and significantly reduce bandwidth
usages, batch processing, multiple
operation or consolidating into
the single call, minimizing network
power rate and improving efficiency.
With these techniques, response time
can drop to as low as 700 milliseconds
even for complex data scenarios.
Let's talk about a advantage
of automation techniques.
Let's move on the next topic.
Now let's focus on two advanced
automation techniques that take all
data performance to the next level.
Selective field projection,
delta core capabilities.
For the selector fields projection.
Using the store selection option, we
can retain only the recurred field
rather than that entire dataset.
This prevents unnecessary data
transfer and keeps payload size
minimal delta query capabilities.
This allows use to fetch only
the data that has changed since
the last synchronization point.
It's particularly valuable for the large
dataset with the frequent updates as
it is a significant reduced bandwidth
usage and improve significant efficiency.
Together these techniques ensure
faster performance and more scalable
integration, especially in the
data heavy interface environment.
And let's talk about the implementation
case studies and metrics.
This graph highlights the metrics across
key industry sectors, manufacturing,
retail, financing, service, and
healthcare, showing the real world I
impact of the door data integration.
Case studies confirm several benefits,
reduce development, maintenance for
cost through the standardized, reusable
A ps, aps improved user satisfaction.
Faster response time and
smarter, smoother interaction.
These results demonstrate how data
service are driving measurable efficiency
and business value across industries.
Let's talk about the
industry specific benefits.
In continuation with the previous
slide, let's now explore how modern
integration delivers measurable
benefits across the various industries.
Manufacturing industries achieved
32 percentage fewer parts
shortage through the real time
supply chain synchronization.
Retail industries improved inventory
accuracy from 82 to 98.5 percentage
enabling better stock management
and customer satisfaction.
Financial service enable faster compliance
and greater agility in launching the
new services healthcare providers, and
80% of reduction of integration relay
related data errors, ensuring better
patient care and operational efficiency.
And how we are going to connect with the
mobile, mobile and third part application
integration, the key feature of that one.
Now let's look at the how
all data supports mobile
and third part integration.
All data are low SAP data to be
consumed directly by mobile application
using JS N and HCDP protocols.
This means we no longer rely on
S-A-B-G-A or legacy RFC based approaches.
Complexity and integration.
Integration overhead.
Additionally, the simplified
authentication and the seamless
data delivery significantly boost
user adoption, making the overall
experience much more in-build and
efficiency for the business user
and developers, mobile integration.
Let's talk about the mobile
indication architecture.
Let's expose the mobile
index architecture.
This architecture follows your laid
approach, starting from the SAP
backend, exposing data through the old
data services, passing through that
robust security layer, and finally
reaching the mobile application.
Support mobile first strategies enabling
users to ex execute critical business
process beyond technical reports.
At the same time, it ensure strong
complaints and enterprise grade
security with non-negotiable
and modern IT landscape.
The key takeaways of the world of concept.
To wrap up, let's summarize
the key takeaway from the
today's discussion on all data.
First, all data strikes the right balance
between SAP safety functionality, and
industry standard protocols making
its versatile enterprise integration.
Second, both the development and
maintenance effort are significantly
reduced, allowing team to focus on
developing business value rather than
the managing complex integration.
With the proper optimization, enterprise
grade is fully achievable, ensuring
variable and scalable operations.
Fourth, real world examples across
industries clearly demonstrate ever
efficiency, gain, and cost reduction.
And most importantly, more data
enables through digital transformation
seamlessly connecting SAP system
with the modern cloud platform and
mobility or third party applications.
Business to stay agile and
competitive on digital in first world.
Thank you.
Thank you all of your
time and attention today.
I hope this session has offered
valuable insight into the how our data
service can drive efficiently and nice
performance and transform enterprise
enabling business transformation.
One second.
Thank you for joining me and I
truly appreciate your participation.
Bye.