Hello everyone.
My name is Paula.
I'm a principal engineer at Zscaler.
And before Zscaler, I was in Adobe for
almost 11 years, working on multiple
products from Adobe Sign PDF, Adobe
X to Adobe Xpr, and also enterprise
solutions like Adobe Experience Manager.
Today I'll be walking you through
how to design tokens can evolve from
a design tool into true platform
infrastructure and a scalable,
multiple platform design systems.
So the big problem in
fragmentation, right?
Traditional design system
phase fragmentation, static
style guides don't scale.
Hand of create frozen drift and siloed
implementation result in inconsistent
user experiences, works manual design
works, aids to a technical date.
This fragmentation.
Starts three groups.
Basically, the customer expect
consistent branded journeys.
Engineers want automation and governance
and designers needs as a leading,
but without the manual overhead,
without alignment, all three suffers.
So here is the paradigm shift
tokens as infrastructure.
So design tokens represents a cept
instead of just a static fellows.
We treat design decisions as
programmable infrastructure.
These decisions becomes version able
to reusable and aligned with platform
engineering Principles like automation
and sales service bookings are.
These design tokens basically
are structured in hierarchy.
The role values evolve
into global semantic, and
finally, the component tokens.
This progressive abstractions provide
flexibility while ensuring consistency
and a single source of truth.
How this orchestration
pipeline works, right?
Tokens are defined in
source format, ization.
They're transformed fi the build pipelines
into platform specific targets like the
CSS variables, SWIFT code or Android xmo.
One definitions, many output.
Then the team composition.
I took in for system enable automated
team generations multi-brand identity,
light, dark modes and accessible
driven teams can all be created
without duplicating definitions.
In our use case at Zscaler we have our
system design system called Nimbus.
We were able to consulate repositories
and implementing tokens which
reduce the bundle size by two 40
kilobytes and improve the first
Contentful paint, which is also a very
important web vital to almost 18%.
Then GitHub's workflows and types
of users and developers experience.
This is the case study, if forced
500 enterprise rolled out tokens
across seven product lines and
three acquisitions Result seven, 3%
sew designing stances, 40% foster
feature development, and a hundred
percent automated WIC gap compliance.
Then, so when you talk about governance
and compliance the governance
ensures the trust decision, schema,
validation, and forces standard.
Automated contrast testing
guarantees accessibility.
The peer approval bring in
cross-functional alignment and
documentation updates automatically.
And this is the how the lifecycle
works for the whole token system.
If formal lifecycle answers,
evolution without the cows token
moves through the creation, review,
distribution, monitoring, and
structured deprecation process, this
balance, innovation and stability.
From the developers ex perspective,
the difference is night and day before
we have scattered hard coded values.
And after that, now we have type
safe tokens id auto complete
and single source of truth.
The, we all definitely
have a lot of challenges.
Adoption is never smooth.
Resist chains, legal systems
complicate integrations and
the governance may seem risky.
Risky, but with code mods, phase
rollout, schema validation and proof
points, these challenges are solvable.
And how if phase rollout works right,
you start with the audits and standards,
then set up the foundation report.
Run a pilot, then scale and
automate pipelines, finally
drive continuous improvements.
What are the key takeaway
from all of this?
Tokens are infrastructure,
not just the styling.
They deliver a single source of
truth, automated compliance, and
measuring efficiency against.
The call to action assessor design system
maturity starts with a focus pilot and
build governance alongside architecture.
This is how we scale design system
for future, and I always say design
token source to your API contract
between the design and development.
So hope you all like the
presentation and thanks.