Hello everyone.
My name is Amit Ara.
I'm software engineering manager with
more than 20 plus years of experience.
Today I have pleasure to talk about how
we can engineer a real time translation
platform system that allow truly seamless
communication across languages and
why engineering behind them is just
as important as the AI model themself.
Interconnected world where conversation
happened across borders every second.
IT language is still one of the
biggest barrier to collaboration,
learning, and even safety.
My goal is to show how scalable AI
Infras can bridge that gap and why
translation is moving from being a
convenience to becoming a mission critical
infrastructure for our digital economy.
Okay, so let's first set the stage.
So real time translation platform are
not just research experiment anymore,
they're becoming essential part of
how people communicate globally.
The expectations are very high.
So we are talking about processing
millions of conversation daily.
We have to support more
than 40 plus languages.
We have to hit transition accuracy
above 85% and all of this in.
A very small response time
of under 200 milliseconds.
So traditional translation tool simply
cannot meet the scale and the latency
requirement we're talking about, which
is where the next frontier lies at
the intersection of the advanced AI
models and robust system engineering.
To make sure that we are able to
build this platform must address
four interdependent imperatives.
The first is performance.
The latency has to be very low and
with a very high throughput, users
shouldn't feel any lag in such a system.
The second one is the scalability.
We have to support millions of
concurrence sessions across the globe.
And the system.
And this platform has to be very reliable.
It has to be available even
during failures or heavy loads.
And finally, the accuracy, and it
has to preserve the context, making
sure that meaning is not lost.
People might use idioms,
they might use slang.
They switch languages during mid
sentences or speak in mix of languages.
To build this platform.
The challenge is not to optimize
just one of these things.
All four of these should work together
really well to make sure that platform
is production ready and is usable.
So fun part.
Let's talk about building this one.
So first let's talk
about the architecture.
So the real time translation
systems are typically organized
as the modeler microservice.
Each one does one thing,
but does it really well.
So if we talk about the workflow.
So speech first goes through
your automatic speech
organization to become text.
Then we do pre-processing,
which normalize the text.
After that, we use neural machine
translation, convert insert to
the target language, and then
post-processing cleans up.
And finally we will have text to speech
that generates natural audio output.
So we will keep each of these steps
separate in and so that we can
independently scale, we can upgrade
them, we can monitor these components
without breaking the entire pipeline.
So the modularity is the backbone of the
performance and throughput optimization.
So now coming to the deployment,
how are we gonna do that?
So models are packaged into containers and
we will them by platforms like Kubernetes.
This will give us version control.
We can run domain specific models side
by side with a channel purpose one.
It also enables safe deployments.
We can use bluegreen strategies.
We can run new and old models in
power and roll back instantly.
If something goes wrong, we
can employ Canadian releases.
We gradually rule out updates
to small percent of the users.
See how it.
Does performance wise, and
then if everything is well,
we scale it to everyone.
So this will ensure we never
disrupt mission critical use cases.
So this is very important that centralized
cloud processing is not enough.
Imagine a user in India or Africa
need, they need a sub 200 millisecond
latency, and if you're sending
everything back to US data center,
we'll never meet our requirements.
So that's where edge computing comes in.
We will deploy all these moder
components, A SR and MT ETTS
components closer to the users.
We can reduce the latency by 40%.
We can cut our upstream
bandwidth usage by almost 60%.
And most importantly, we keep the
sensitive data within the local
judication, which helps with the
regulatory compliance each country has.
So if you think about this, edge
computing isn't optional or nice
to have for the system, it's a
fundamental part of the system.
So next is data and hardware.
On the data side, we use streaming
pipeline like Kafka and flank for
load latency, ingestions and batch
pipelines for retraining and analytics.
So on the hardware side, the GPUs
are the bottlenecks, so we have to
make sure that we do efficient GPU
scheduling so the multi multiple
models don't collide during peak loads.
And we use caching aggressively to,
for the common phrases, domain specific
terms, user dictionary to speed up
translation while improving accuracy.
This combination keep the system
both fast and the cost Absent
now, like none of this will
matter if you don't know what's
happening in your production system.
So telemetry is a nervous system, is the
most important part of your platform.
We have to track metrics like latency.
We should track throughput,
accuracy, error rates.
We use dis tracing to pinpoints.
What are the bottlenecks
across microservices.
And we then we feed this user
correction back into the system
to improve accuracy over time.
We have.
For full tolerance, we design
for ancy across regions.
We allow graceful degradation by
falling back to simpler models.
When cheap use are scars, we build
self-healing, automated restart load
balancing when the service fails.
So residency has to.
Be engineered, designed, and
from the start of the platform,
we have to incorporate those.
And it doesn't have to,
it's not accidental.
So it has to be very intentional.
It has to be in the start of the
system and it has to engineer
it from in the whole platform.
So another fun thing let's look
at some of the real world impact.
Of this real time translation platforms.
So in healthcare if there's
a miscommunication between
provide and patient, it can be
a matter of life and a death.
So a hospital system deployed domain
specific medical translation models
at the edge nodes inside hospitals.
And as far as the impact is concerned,
a 35% reduction in critical medical
communication errors that directly improve
patient safety and treatment outcomes.
This is a clear example where
translation literally saves life.
No.
We all have seen this one as education.
In online classroom we have
diverse student population.
They often of, they often struggle
with the language barriers.
So by integrating real time captioning
and translation into the video
conferencing platforms, students are.
Were able to fully participate
regardless of the native language.
The results were more inclusive
accessible learning environment,
and there's no student left behind
because of the language barriers.
So finally coming to the
enterprise Collaboration.
So global team lose efficiency
to the language caps.
You're having meeting across international
teams by embedding, so by embedding
real time translation directly into
the platforms like Teams and Slack.
Your organization can see more
than 40 plus improvements in
collaboration effectiveness.
This can translate to faster
decisions, fewer misunderstanding
that happens, and better outcomes
for international projects.
So from these use cases and from the the
previous slides and previous experiences.
So these are the best
practices that emerge.
First is like you design for ity.
You always do one thing and
you do one thing really well.
You're able to independently
scale individually update that.
Components like separate a SR
and mt TTS we talked about.
Here's hybrid cloud strategy as well as.
Edge architecture, which is a must
have for real time translation system.
You automate your deployments using CICD.
You have to prioritize, and
that's a must have observability.
With the full tracing and feedback
loops, you have to plan it and see
from the start assume this will happen.
Plan for it and make
sure it's implemented.
Like GPU scar.
So you have to optimize for GP usage,
you have to aggressively use caching.
And I think one of the most
important thing is you have to
support contextual translations.
Because the meaning matters more
than the literal words substitutions.
So at the high level, these are
the principle that make translation
platform reliable at scale.
Okay, future direction.
Looking ahead, the
possibilities are exciting.
Imagine we can build personalized
translation models, which are tuned
to individual users and organizations.
We can.
Create those context aware
nmt that uses conversation
history to improve the fidelity.
We can have the ed learning at the edge
that allow training without sending
the con the sensitive data, which
you don't want to send to the cloud.
We can have multi moderate translation.
We can combining speech, text, even visual
will unlock such a richer understanding.
And we must prioritize sustainability,
optimizing g pure workloads,
full lower energy consumptions.
So the future of translation is
intelligent, adaptive, and green.
So let's bring it all together.
So engineering realtime translation
platform is both an AI challenge
and a system engineering challenge.
It requires low latency, pipelines fault
and architecture, T resource management,
robust observability when done right.
These platforms saves life in
healthcare, democratize educations,
and ate global collaboration.
So overall translation is not just
convenience anymore, it's infrastructure.
For digital,
thank you so much.