Hi everyone.
I'm Manoja, and today we're exploring
how to build AI platforms that
actually work in prediction systems,
handling millions of realtime
decisions without breaking down.
We'll understand the engineering
practices that separate successful
AI platforms from failed experiments.
We'll cover the complete lifecycle
designing containerized ML
pipelines, implementing efficient
models, serving architectures,
establishing observability frameworks.
Building self-healing, fault
tolerant infrastructure.
These are theoretical concepts.
These are proven practices from
real deployments processing
millions of requests daily with
measurable business impact.
The transition from traditional
software to AI driven platforms
introduces fundamental changes.
AI platforms must handle compute intensive
GPU workloads, massive real-time data
ingestion models, lifecycle management.
Dynamic scaling requirements for
computer vision applications, autonomous
systems, surveillance, quality control.
These challenges are amplified.
Processing visual data at scale
with millisecond response time
requires a resilient engineering
foundation, integrating automation,
scalability, and observability.
Traditional DevOps provides
static point but is insufficient.
Three foundational principles guide
success infrastructure as code.
Using terraform or cloud formation
enables consistent replication of
GPU enabled environments and version
control infrastructure evolution.
GitHub's workflows treat GIT as the
single source of truth with automated
synchronization tools, ensuring
immutable deployments and automated
rollbacks automated testing strategies.
Require specialized frameworks for
data validation, model validation, and
integration tests for end-to-end pipeline
Workflows fundamentally different
from traditional software testing.
Containerization delivers reproducibility
and modularity through modular pipelines
with separate containers for ingestion,
pre-processing, training, and inference.
GPU enable enablement.
Leverages Nvidia Docker runtime
and Kubernetes device plugins while
version bills ensure deterministic
bills tied to GI comets.
Kubernetes orchestration handles
spot scheduling with GPU constraints,
horizontal autoscaling for inference,
workloads, and node pools optimized
for different pipeline stages.
Here's how this works in practice.
Data ingestion bots.
Pull video streams from IOT sensors.
Pre-processing pods apply
transformations like normalization
and augmentation model training pods.
Leverage distributed
GPUs and inference pods.
Serve predictions via
REST or GRPC endpoints.
This enterprise scale vision system
creates an end-to-end pipeline efficiently
processing visual data while maintaining
high availability and performance.
Serving models at a low latency
while ensuring reliability requires
specific deployment patterns.
Bluegreen deployments run new
model versions parallel with old
ones switching traffic seamlessly.
Canary releases gradually
rollout model to user subsets.
Shadow deployments test model in
product production environments
without exposing outputs to users.
Each pattern addresses different risk
tolerance and validation requirements
for production model updates.
Three Key optimizations delivered dramatic
performance improvements, batching
and fairness Request groups multiple
requests to maximize GPU utilization
and reduce per request overhead.
Model caching and W starts keep frequency
access models in memory, eliminating
cold start latency, accelerated serving
frameworks like Tenser rt, Triton
inference server, and tot serve optimized
model execution on specified hardware.
These optimizations typically provide
three to five x throughput improvements
while reducing latency from 200
milliseconds to 15 milliseconds.
Observability transcends infrastructure
monitoring by incorporating model and
data centric metrics across three layers.
Infrastructure metrics tracks,
C-P-U-G-P-U, utilization,
memory and network throughput.
Pipeline monitoring covers success
rates, Q latencies and data integrity
checks, model observability,
monitors, prediction, drift latency,
error rates, and famous metrics.
This comprehensive approach
enables detection anomalies before
they impact users such as GPU
saturation, rising inference,
latency, or degraded model accuracy.
The tooling ecosystem combines
traditional and ML specific monitoring.
Prometheus plus Grafana provide
comprehensive infrastructure
dashboards, tracking resources, usage.
And System Health Open Telemetry
enables distributed tracing
across ML pipelines, identifying
bottlenecks and latency issues.
Custom ML monitoring tools like YAPS
eyes, AI handle data drift and bias
detection coupling observability with
alert thresholds, enable systems to detect
and respond to anomalies automatically.
Resilient platforms must recover
automatically without manual intervention.
Through several mechanisms.
Kubernetes liveness readiness probes
automatically restart failing containers.
When health check fails cluster
auto-scaling dynamically adjust compute
resources based on workload demands.
Chaos Engineering uses using tools
like chaos mesh injects failures
to violate system resilience
under unexpected conditions.
These mechanisms ensure continuous
service availability and
optimal resource utilization.
Eliminate single point of failure
requires comprehensive distribution.
Distributed processing pipelines
ensure no single point of failure
by distributing workloads across
multiple nodes and regions.
Geo-redundant clusters support
global AI workloads with
multi-region deployments for disaster
recovery and low latency serving.
Event driven recovery provides automated
rerouting of workloads on node failure
through event based orchestration systems.
Organization, imple implementing
these principles report
significant improvement, 99.9%.
Uptime and reliability.
SLA.
Compliance in production AI systems means
less than nine hours downtime per year.
Deployment velocity measured in ours,
model updates deployed within hours
versus weeks in traditional workflows.
20 to 40% cost reduction through optimized
GPU scheduling and resource allocation.
Increased developer productivity
teams focus on in innovation
instead of firefighting operations.
These are, these metrics demonstrate
clear business value, justifying
implementation complexity, the conversions
of platform engineering and ML ops.
Represents a paradigm shift enabling
faster time to market through accelerated
delivery of AI products via streamlined
deployment, pipelines and automated
workflows, reduced operational overhead
with lower maintenance costs, through
comprehensive automation of routine tasks
and self feeling systems sustained trust
with enhanced confidence in AI systems.
By ensuring transparency, fairness,
and consistent performance.
These practices extend beyond computer
vision to NLP recommendation systems
and generative ai, where real time
processing is equally critical.
Building resilient AI platforms
at scale is fundamentally about
engineering trust into AI systems
through containerized ML pipelines
efficient model serving architecture.
Comprehensive observability and
self-healing infrastructure organizations
deploy computer vision systems that
are both high, perform high performing,
and relatable by applying modern
platform engineering principles,
infrastructure as code GitHubs.
Automated testing and fault
tolerant design enterprises achieve
operational resilience while
unlocking faster innovation cycles
and enhanced developer productivity.
As such, your current AI de deployment
practices prioritize containerization and
monitoring as foundational capabilities
and implement automation testing
for both infrastructure and models.
As realtime AI continues transforming
industries, the ability of ability to
engineer resilience, scalable platforms
will define the next generation
of enterprise success stories.
Thank you.