Hello everyone.
This is Tawa.
I'm a senior network engineer, senior
network delivery lead at Cairos
Technologies based out of Dallas, Texas.
Today I'm going to talk about
building prediction ready,
ML based network routing,
and we discuss about traditional
routing, ML based routing, compare
both ML and the traditional routing.
Also, I'll talk about, how to train
models and the real case studies.
And then also ROI.
And in implementing ML based routing,
the evolving network routing landscape
routing protocols like B-G-P-O-S-P-F
have been around for decades.
They are reliable, but they were
designed for a different time.
They use fixed rules.
They take too long to recover
when something breaks and still.
Rely a lot on manual
tuning from engineers.
In today's world of cloud
microservices and real time
application, that's not good enough.
We need something smarter, faster, and
more adaptive to the current scenarios.
ML based routing coming
to the core concept.
ML based routing brings flexibility,
which is the key, instead of
relying on the fixed rules, ML
system learns from network data.
They watch traffic spot
patterns and make predictions.
That means they can route traffic
more intelligently, balance, speed,
cost, and reliability all at once.
They can even direct
unusual patterns that might.
Mean a failure or a system or a
security issue, and the best part,
they get better as they learn and
adapt to the current environment.
Coming to the technical
architecture of the ML based
routing, let's see how it works.
First, collect data collection.
We collect telemetry, all the
signals from the network, like
latency packet loss, and throughput.
That data goes into a pipeline that
cleans it up and makes it usable.
Then we have the ML training system where
models are built, tested, and stored.
Finally, we have inference system,
which applies those models in real
time to make routing decisions.
And of course, we always keep fallbacks
and safety switches so that the network
stays stable if something goes wrong.
Let's compare ML based routing
versus traditional routing.
Traditional routing is rule-based.
It reacts only after a problem happens.
ML routing is smarter.
It took it.
It looks at hundreds of factors,
predicts issues before they even happen
and can reroute traffic proactively.
So instead of waiting for
something to break, the network
can fix itself in advance.
Coming to data collection and
model training approaches.
Data is the fuel here.
We need to collect everything, link
usage, latency, packet loss, application
patterns, and even things like time of
the day and scheduled maintenance when
it comes to training data options like
supervised learning, using parts, past
best practices to train the models and
reinforcement learning where the model
tries things and learns by feedback.
Or the hybrid approach, we can mixing m
by mixing ml with traditional routing,
the this is the better and most diverse.
Diverse the data and the smarter the model
coming to the production
deployment patterns.
You don't just slip a switch and hand
over your network to ML just overnight.
It actually need to go rolled out
through a phased manner, coming to the
first phase, which is the shadow mode.
ML makes decisions, but only on papers.
Advisory mode, ML suggests routes.
And when, and the engineers
need to approve them.
And selective automation, which
is a third phase ml, takes over
certain traffic, like critical
data, non-critical data and certain
regions which are of low criticality.
And then coming to the final phase,
which is a full automation ml, runs the
show with all protocols as a backup.
This step-by-step approach builds
trust and avoids surprises.
Coming to monitoring observability
challenges monitoring ml routing isn't
just about checking if links are up.
We also need to see how the model
is doing, how accurate it is,
whether it's drifting, and how
confident it is in each decision.
Dashboards need to show side-by-side
comparisons of ML and traditional
routes and explain why the
model picked a certain path.
This transparency builds confidence
and helps operators trust their system.
Coming to security consideration for
ML routing, security is a very key.
If someone poisons your data,
they can mess with your routes.
If they figure out your
model, they can exploit it.
So we need to product.
En encrypt the telemetry, validate
inputs, use anomaly detection, and make
sure there's always a human override.
In short, the smarter the system,
the smarter the security has to be.
Operational considerations.
Running ML routing day to
day brings new challenges.
What happens if the model suddenly
starts making weird choices?
What if conference drops?
What if telemetry breaks?
We need run books for all these things,
like how to roll back to a safer
version, how to gradually shift traffic,
how to retrain after an incident.
Think of it like adding a
new playbook to your knock.
But m but for ML in specific
failures, real world case studies,
let's look at the real examples.
In financial services, ML routing cut
latency spikes by almost 70% and saved
millions in circuit costs in e-commerce.
ML reduced page load time by
30% during traffic peaks and
cut manual interventions by 95%.
But they were challenges,
compliance concern, false
alarms and model performance
dropping during unusual events.
The payoff is real, but you need patience
and good planning to for a success.
ML implementation.
RI.
Assessment and risk management.
Leaders always ask two things.
What do we gain?
What do we risk?
On the gain side, we see faster recovery,
low la, lower latency, less manual
work, which means real cost savings.
On the other side, there are skill
gaps, data issues, model drift.
The answer is balanced, failed, phase
rolled rollouts, strong fallbacks,
and training your team to handle both
ML and traditional routing together.
Implementation, roadmap
and best practices.
Phase one, get the telemetry
and baseline in place.
Coming to the phase two shadow model
testing and phase three limited
rollout for non-critical traffics.
And phase four is the full deployment
with automation and retraining pipelines
coming to the team.
Structure and skills.
This only works if you have right people.
You need network engineers, data
scientists, platform engineers and
ops teams all working together, each
bringing in different skill sets
and and you need cross training so
they understand each other's world.
To close.
Here are key points.
ML routing is ready enough
for the real use cases.
Hybrid approaches like ML plus traditional
routing work best in today's scenario.
Operations monitoring and people
matter as much as the tech.
The future is very clear.
Networks will become
self-healing and adaptive.
The teams that start now will
be the ones leading the future.
Thank you for this opportunity.