Hello, everyone.
Thank you for taking the time
out of your day to be here.
I'm delighted to be here today
to talk about crafting an
effective developer roadmap.
This process is essential for ensuring
that our development efforts are
aligned with our business goals.
and can effectively address
the challenges our teams face.
A little bit about myself.
As a seasoned product manager, I have
honed my skills in leading both front
end and back end product development.
Currently, I play a pivotal role
at Bestech, a fintech firm, where
I drive the product strategy
for our communications division.
I've also worked at firms such
as AWS, where I orchestrated the
product strategy for automating
AWS infrastructure deployment.
At Newmark, I headed their product
department, successfully leading a
website redesign on Microsoft Azure
and establishing a dedicated team on
customer centric product development.
I also worked at Moody's, where I was
head of deploying cloud data leaks
on the AWS tech stack, enhancing ETL
processes and data analytics capabilities.
I'm also committed to
fostering innovation.
I actively serve as a board member,
providing strategic direction and
technical acumen to enhance the growth
trajectory of a company by the name
of Yieldwink's digital platform.
We have a jam packed agenda,
so let's get started.
Let's get started.
We'll start by understanding the
fundamental importance of roadmaps.
A roadmap serves as a strategic
guide that outlines the direction and
priorities for our development efforts.
It's not just a plan, but a communication
tool that aligns everyone in the
organization, from stakeholders
to developers, on what needs to be
achieved and how we intend to get there.
It's a product strategy.
It's crucial to have
a solid understanding.
Of our business and
organizational strategies.
These strategies provide the foundation
upon which we build our product plans.
They help us understand the broader
goals of the organization and
ensure that our development efforts
are contributing to these goals.
Let me give you a concrete example.
Suppose our company's overarching
strategy is to increase revenue
by 20 percent over the next year.
Bye.
For our product strategy, this means
we need to align our development
efforts with these revenue focus goals.
We might prioritize building features
that improve cross sell, up sell,
like showing customers premium plans,
or help with renewal probabilities.
By aligning our product strategy
with the company's revenue goals,
we ensure that every piece of code
written And every feature developed
is a step towards achieving these
broader business objectives.
This alignment not only helps in
achieving our revenue targets, but
also ensures that our development
efforts are recognized as valuable
contributions to the company's success.
Concepts of life.
Let's take a practical case study.
Our case study today focuses
on a significant challenge.
A made up company has been facing.
They are a marketing led company,
and communication in the form of
emails is a very big revenue driver.
But the business problem is, it
takes too long for us to get email
communications out to our customers.
This delay in communication affects
our business in several critical ways.
Firstly, let's frame the problem clearly.
The time it currently takes from
conceptualizing an email campaign
by our marketers to engineers
actually delivering it to our
customers is longer than we desire.
This lag impacts our ability to respond
quickly to market opportunities, customer
feedback, and competitive pressures.
It means that by time our emails
reach our customers, the information
might already be outdated, reducing
its relevance and effectiveness.
Now let's talk about the business
value if we solve this problem.
The faster we can get our email
communications out, the quicker
we can realize revenue or
increase our monthly active users.
In other words, reducing the
time to value is crucial.
This case study, framed by how might
we statement, how might we deliver
an email communication in under
an hour, when given this problem.
Will guide us through the process of
identifying pain points, prioritizing
them and developing actionable solutions.
By addressing this challenge, we not only
improve our operational efficiency, but
also drive significant business outcomes.
perform a current state assessment
of our technology stack.
We won't be going over technical details
today, but just high level frameworks.
For today's case study, we'll focus,
we'll be focusing on reviewing a part of
our marketing technology stack, focusing
on the email communication process.
This assessment involves a deep dive
into our existing tools, processes,
and capabilities, and how well
they support our business outcomes.
To get a comprehensive view, we
interviewed different personas involved
in this email communication workflow.
These personas include marketers,
engineers, and customer
support representatives.
To better understand the high level
pains and needs within this process, we
utilize the Jobs to be Done framework.
This framework helps us focus on what each
persona is trying to achieve, the obstacle
they face, and the outcomes they desire.
By framing our understanding around
their jobs, we gain valuable insight into
their key pain points and motivations.
Analyzing the feedback from
these interviews through the
Jobs to be Done lens, we decided
to focus on the engineers.
Why engineers?
Because they play a critical role
in the development and deployment
of the systems that enable
faster dissemination of emails.
By addressing the engineers pain
points first, we can streamline
the entire email delivery process.
This will allow us to release email
communications to customers more quickly.
which directly supports our company's
goals of increasing revenue.
The clear understanding of our
current state and the personas
we're focusing on, we can now define
our vision and success criteria.
This vision acts as our target
destination, while the success
criteria provide measurable
benchmarks to track our progress.
Our vision is to enable the engineering
team to deliver email communications
to customers in under an hour.
Achieving this will significantly
improve our operational efficiency
and align with our company's strategic
goal of increasing revenue by
facilitating quicker market responses
and enhancing customer engagement.
To set clear success criteria, we need
to outline specific measurable goals that
indicate progress towards our vision.
These criteria might include
what listed to your left.
You might want to include reduction
in email delivery time, which is
decreasing the time it takes to
deliver an email campaign from several
days or weeks to under an hour.
We might want to focus on increasing
engineering productivity, enhancing
system reliability, or focusing
on stakeholder satisfaction.
So increasing satisfaction levels
among marketing and customer support
teams by providing faster and more
reliable email communication tools.
Or we focus on none of the
above or all of the above.
Next,
we have our how might me
statement on the left.
Walk through the developer
journey and identify the pain
points experience at each stage.
At this stage, we list out the
common engineering development
journeys and ask them to list out
all pain points based in these areas.
As it relates to deploying
an email communication.
That is what in the middle of the screen.
Next, The tool of choice here is
Miro, but you can use whatever
tool works for you and your team.
The journey here includes
requirements gathering.
Here, engineers often face challenges like
unclear requirements, changing priorities,
and lack of stakeholder alignment.
These issues can lead to
significant delays and rework.
Moving on to development.
During development, pain points
might include inadequate tooling,
technical debt, and integration issues.
These factors can hinder productivity
and extend development cycles.
Next, we have UAT or
user acceptance testing.
In this phase, engineers may encounter
challenges like insufficient testing
environments, poor test data quality,
and limited feedback loops, all
of which can delay deployment.
You then have deployment.
Deployment pain points often involve
complex deployment processes, manual
interventions, and configuration errors.
These issues can lead to failed
deployment times or failed
deployments and increased downtime.
And then we have monitoring.
Post deployment monitoring can be
hampered by inadequate monitoring
tools, lack of real time alerts,
and insufficient metrics.
This makes it difficult to quickly
identify and resolve issues.
Identifying these pain points is
crucial as it allows us to focus on
the areas that need the most attention.
Once we've listed the pain points, the
next step is to vote on their severity.
We take each sticky from the prior slide
and categorize each pain point as high,
medium, or low severity based on the
impact it has on our ability to deliver
email communication in under an hour.
Remember to always tie it back
to the problem we are solving.
The voting process helps us prioritize
the issues that have the most
significant impact on our goals.
So for example, a pain point like unclear
requirements might be rated as high
severity because it affects multiple
stages of the development process.
So how might we decrease time to value?
Severity ratings, we then plot these
pain points on a quadrant chart.
But now the team will help us estimate
how high or low the effort might be
in solving some of these problems.
The y axis represents impact and
the x axis represents effort.
This categorization helps us
identify what on the top right
quadrant Which is major wins.
These are high impact and high effort.
These are critical issues that
require significant investment but
will greatly benefit the project.
What you see next to that is quick wins.
High impact and low effort.
These are the low hanging fruit
that can be addressed quickly
to yield immediate benefits.
Below that we see fill ins.
Low impact and low effort.
These are the nice to have
improvements that can be tackled
when there's extra capacity.
Next to that, we have money
pits, low impact, high effort.
They should be deprioritized
as they consume resources
without significant benefits.
You'd be surprised at how many
organizations have money pit items
in their backlog and end the year
with very low value delivered.
Focusing on the high impact areas
first ensures that we are making the
most effective use of our resources.
Now that we know what problems
we need to solve, we can start
our product discovery phase.
In this phase, we focus on high
level discovery without getting
into the technical details yet.
This involves brainstorming
potential solutions and defining
the scope of our initiatives.
Here are the steps we typically
follow during product discovery.
Brainstorming solutions.
Defining epics, clear acceptance
criteria, prioritizing epics,
and then creating a road map.
Now let's double click on some of these.
brainstorming solutions.
We gather a diverse team of stakeholders,
including engineering, product
managers, and business analysts, to
brainstorm possible solutions for the
identified high impact pain points.
This Creative approach ensures that
we consider various perspectives
and come up with innovative ideas.
Finding epics.
We then consolidate these
ideas into high level epics.
An epic is a large body of work
that can be broken down into
smaller tasks or user stories.
For instance, if a major pain
point may be the lack of a
development testing environment,
an epic might be establishment of
developing testing environment.
You then want to set acceptance criteria.
For each EPIC, we define
clear acceptance criteria.
These criteria outline what success
looks like for each EPIC and
provide a way to measure whether the
solution meets the desired outcomes.
For example, the acceptance
criteria for our established, the
establishment of development testing
environment a significant reduction
in bugs and issues post deployment.
And then we want to prioritize epics.
After the finding the epics and their
acceptance criteria, we prioritize them
based on their impact and feasibility.
This prioritization helps us focus
on the most critical issues first,
ensuring that we deliver maximum
value as quickly as possible.
And finally, we create a high
level roadmap that outlines a
sequence of epics we plan to tackle.
This roadmap serves as a strategic
plan that guides our development
efforts over the next quarter or year.
This roadmap is a living document,
always subject to change as new
challenges arise and priorities shift.
However, it provides a structured
plan that aligns our development
efforts with our strategic goals.
I always recommend using now
next and later as the first
presentation of the roadmap.
While you start to flesh out the
actual work this entails to provide
accurate estimations of delivery.
This product discovery phase is crucial
because it ensures that we have a clear
and actionable plan for addressing
the high impact pain points first.
By involving a diverse team in the
brainstorming process and setting clear
acceptance criteria, we can develop
solutions that are both innovative
and aligned with our strategic goals.
Once our plan is finalized, the product
manager can collaborate with the engineers
to further refine the work details.
Initially, we may focus on the
minimum viable product or MVP
version of the plan, ensuring it
effectively addresses the problems
and aligns with our business goals.
On the right is an example
timeline for breaking down the
plan before we start writing our
technical requirement documents
and entering them into the backlog.
From roadmap to backlog.
Finally, the product manager translates
these roadmap items into detailed
product requirement documents.
These documents are then used to create
user stories that populate our backlog.
This ensures that the development
team has a clear, Prioritize
list of tasks to work on.
This process ensures that every user
story is aligned with the overall
strategic goals and addresses the
critical pain points identified earlier.
To summarize, we've explored the
journey from identifying pain points to
creating a detailed developer roadmap.
By focusing on the most critical
challenges first and developing
actionable solutions, We can ensure
that our development efforts are
aligned with our business goals
and deliver the maximum impact.
This structured approach helps
us navigate the complexities of
software development and continuously
improve our processes and outcomes.
Thank you for your attention.
I hope this session has provided you
with valuable insights into creating
an effective developer roadmap.