Hello everyone.
I'm Var, the lead full stack engineer
company agency with more than something
years of experie in the tech industry.
I'm passionate about creating
seamless and secure solutions.
I may work focus on key areas
like full stack development, cloud
technologies, application security,
risk analysis, and a integration.
With that, let's get started
with the today's topic.
Automating infrastructure to scale
for enhanced developer experience.
With the advent of cloud technology,
multi applications are divided
into multiple microservices, which
of which runs multiple instances.
Managing such a huge number
of instances creates a
administrative overhead platform.
Teams are struggling to manage
increasingly complex cloud native
infrastructure while supporting
thousands of developers.
And applications across
distributed environments.
The recent research across one point, some
proper engineering team shows that almost
seven three percentage report difficulties
in balancing infrastructure complexity
with the developer experience traditional
manual approach, proving inadequate for
the modern scale requirements and growing
technical depth from quick fix solutions.
The impact of infrastructure
complexity, we can categorize
mainly into three groups.
First one is developer productivity,
and secondly, operational burden.
And finally, business agility.
Other developer productivity developers
often spend the valuable time in
infrastructure, resources, and navigating
complex system and platform tools on
an average of almost 4.7 hours per
week lasting to infrastructure release.
And almost 42% of feature data are
attributed to platform bottlenecks
and platform disor, made by manual
processes and support tickets.
Almost 60 big percentage of
platform engineer Spain and
react to troubleshooting, growing
backlog of platform improvements.
Slow infrastructure provisioning and
scaling directly impacts time to market.
Infrastructure delays contribute towards
38% longer recycles and competitive
disadvantage in fast moving markets.
Traditional platform approaches
cannot scale to meet the demand of
modern cloud native development.
At enterprise scale,
the AA port platform engineering
opportunity, 58% of faster
development is achieved by
reducing the deployment cycle time.
Through a power automation and
intelligent orchestration, 67 percentage
of provisioning speeds achieved by
decrease in infrastructure provisioning
time with the intelligent resource
allocation and predictive scaling, and
70 on percentage of system liability
improvement in overall system reliability
through predictive maintenance and
automated remediation analysis of AI
enhance platform implementation shows.
Remarkable improvements in operational
efficiency compared to traditional
platform management approaches.
AA driven developer experience
transformation platform teams
implementing a power self-service
capabilities, report dramatic improvements
and developer experience metrics.
Almost 64% of production in the
developer rate times for infrastructure
resources, and 52% decreasing support
tickets and platform related questions.
And 78% of improvement in
developer satisfaction scores
across EA implementation.
These improvements directly
correlate with the increased
development velocity and reduce
time to market for any new features.
Addressing the scalability challenge
with the EAA manual scaling in initial
cloud data is manually adjust the
resources based on the anticipated need.
And now leading towards that, all
provisioning are performance issues.
This approach has the hours of response
time on inefficient research utilization.
Let's talk about inefficient
research utilization.
When an instance is finding with the
zero percentage use of CPU and memory
multiple instance of same surfaces
running with the low ation in this case,
are, these resources can reuse for.
Any the services that needs
additional insurance to be spinned up.
Let's about the manual scaling.
Let's talk about rule based automation.
This is a very common approach in
the current market time, and this
actually, this is actually providing
basic automation with fixed thresholds
and predetermined scaling rules, and
it provides very good implements, but
lack, adaptability, rule-based approach.
Resulted in moderate
improvement, but still records
significant human intervention.
Then finally, let's talk
about a port orchestration.
This is an advanced approach with
intelligent system that can learn
from the usage patterns, predict
needs and autonomously optimize
infrastructure in real time, a
orchestration results in minutes instead
of spending hours of scaling, that's
providing almost 99.9 availability.
During peak months case studies from
high growth organization, RAM said that
a platform engineering team dramatically
reduces infras scaling response time
while maintaining exceptional reliability.
Kubernetes optimization through EA
Kubernetes orchestration enhance with
EA driven resource management, delivers
significant operational and cast benefits.
We can get intelligent pod placement
based on historical performance data,
automated node scaling that anticipate
workload changes, self feeling
capability that reduce mean time
to respond by almost 61 percentage.
And finally, proactive detection
of potential cluster level issues.
So these are some of the operation
improvement that we can achieve.
And 40, so 43 percentage of.
Better reduction in the resource
utilization cluster and 56 percentage
of reduction in the infrastructure
cost by maximum resource utilization
and 37 percentage of increase in
application performance, and finally
able to handle almost three times
of workloads on the same hardware.
These are some of the business
outcomes that we can achieve
a power self service
platform capabilities.
Intelligence infrastructure provision,
automated configuration management,
adaptive developer portals,
proactive security compliance.
These are some of the major capabilities
of a power cell service platform.
We can use a natural language
infrastructure code, which are again
translated to properly configured
resources with the AI systems
that detect any configuration
drips and such as optimizations.
And automatically remediating
new issues before they impact
even the production environments.
Personal interfaces that learn
from the downer behavior to surface
relevant resources, documentations,
and optimization suggestions based
on project context and continuous
scanning of infrastructure as a code
for any security vulnerabilities.
It'll provide remediation solutions.
So these capabilities starts of the
developer experience from frustration to
friction productivity, while maintaining
the anthrop grade security and reliability
case study, global financial servicing
firm, almost supporting 28 hundreds
of developers across three for the
application teams with a critical
ability requirement and very strict
regulatory compliance needed.
Very big challenge.
NA platform solution was implemented by,
started with implementing in self-service
infrastructure provisioning, followed
by applying NA based anomaly direction
for performance issues, and finally
creating automatic compliance validation
for all the deployments that result
almost eight to 3% reduction in the
infrastructure promotion time, and 43
percentage of, I'm sorry, almost 47%
of decrease in production incidents.
And our four millions in annual
savings per cloud infrastructure cost.
Let's talk about implementation.
Implementation has four phased.
First starts with assessment and
opportunity identification phase
and foundation building phase,
targeted a implementation phase, and
finally scaling optimization phase.
How to assess and identify opportunities.
Start with the evaluate current
platform capabilities and bottlenecks
and analyst developer experience
pain points followed by identify
high impact automating opportunities.
This is something we will actually
start with and finally define
clear success metrics and KPIs.
This is to progress.
This is to track the
progress for the process.
How to build a foundation, implement
comprehensive observability for
ai, turning data, standardize
infrastructure as code practice,
develop AP first approach for all
platform services, and create platform
team AI capability development plan,
and how to implement target daily.
Start with deploy intelligent resource
provisioning capabilities, then implement
predictive scaling for critical workloads.
Create a power developer self service
portal, and finally establish feedback
loops for continuous improvements.
Next, how to scale and optimize.
First, extend a capabilities across all
the platform services, then implement
advance predict to maintenance.
Integrate with continuous integration
and continuous deployment for intelligent
deployment pipelines and file develop.
Organization specific GA models these
phase approach and choose measurable
progress while building the foundation
for comprehensive AI platform engineering.
Let's talk about what are the common
implementing challenges and how,
what are the mitigation strategies?
Insufficient quality data for AI training
skills gap in platform engineering team.
Assistance to automation from operations.
Team integration, complexity
with legacy systems.
Concerns about ai decision transparency.
These are some of the common
implementation challenges.
Let's talk about how
we can mitigate these.
Begin with enhanced observ implementation.
Use synthetic data and simulations
while building real data set.
Establish a education program
partner with specialized consultants.
Manage a services as a
transaction strategy.
Start with human loop approach.
Demonstrate the value through
metrics, create clear upskilling
pathways, then create abstraction
layers with the well different APAs.
Implement incremental monetization use
of AI to generate integration adapters,
implement explainable area approaches.
Maintain comprehensive logging.
And create capabilities
for any critical systems.
Key takeaways, the future
of a driven platform.
Engineering organizations implementing
AI platforms, seeing dramatic I
improvements and developer productivity,
operation efficiency, and business
agility begin with targeted AI
capabilities that address your most
stream pain point by building the
foundation for comprehensive automation.
AI adapter, a power platform engineering
are achieving almost two to three
times of better developer productivity
and significant no operation cost.
The international AI into platform
engineering is not just optimization.
It's a funda, fun, fundamental shift.
How do we deliver and scale
infrastructure for the.
Thank you so much for
joining for my session.
I truly enjoyed sharing my insights
on Adrian Quantum Engineering,
automating infrastructure at Scale
for enhanced developer experience.
Thank you again for the invitation and
for organizing such a well done event.
Thank you.