Today, I will tell you how to save
more than 1, 000, 000 yearly on IT.
1, 000, 000 is enough
to buy 20 Tesla Model 3.
1, 000, 000 in cash, if you put
it 100 bills next to each other.
The resulting line will stretch from
one and a half kilometer, or one mile,
if you're from the United States.
Oh my god!
Wow!
It's a lot of money, because I've
calculated it for a company which
spends about five million dollars on IT.
So we are talking about savings around 20
percent and this scales up the bigger the
company, the bigger the saving will be.
Okay, so let's begin by understanding
what platform engineering is all about.
It's a relatively new IT field
that evolved from DevOps, aimed
at boosting developer team
productivity, incorporating security,
compliance, cost, and reliability.
Runtime observability, and other elements.
The idea is to abstract those elements.
So the developers can, for example,
launch new working environment
within seconds without worrying about
technology integration or application
integration with observability tools.
In simple words, if you treat your
developers as you normally treat your
clients, and think about how to serve
those developers, how to simplify the
process of building and maintaining
applications, So the developers and
ops guys can do better their job,
which is delivering business value.
You will become a platform engineer.
Okay, so platform engineering
isn't merely about technology.
It's fundamentally an
organizational change.
It's about how various IT teams
collaborate with developer teams
and business application teams.
Why is it mainly an organizational change?
because of need to establish a
platform in the organization.
You need to meet several conditions.
First of all, you need to have
clear responsibilities, which
must be defined for the platform
team and for the other teams.
This is an organizational stuff.
Secondly, the platform team needs to have
the authority To define and implement
those responsibilities across DevOps tool
set, ensuring that responsibilities are
not duplicated across multiple teams.
Those are purely organizational stuff.
In terms of technology, you need to
organize the SecOps tools, you need to put
orchestrators and you need to have fitting
DevOps tools into your platform services.
So the service oriented
approach and product mindset
in a platform team is crucial.
Platforms should give a space for
developers to communicate their
needs and the platform needs to
provide it in an organized way.
This shift is also technological,
since it requires a structured approach
to DevOps tools, to automation,
orchestration, and to avoid chaos and
enforce those clear responsibilities.
Within the rules, within the permission
rules, rule set in those tools, you can
think about platforms as building a system
to build and maintain other systems.
And to build such a system platform,
a platform team needs to have certain
organizational and technological
power enhanced in your company.
Okay, so how do you approach
platform engineering?
It should be treated like any
other product development.
You start by analyzing user
needs, in this case the developers
are your users, and tailor the
platform to fit the organization
rather than the other way around.
You shouldn't tailor
organization to fit the platform.
This includes planning the platform
architecture, defining services,
Migration tools and deciding on
user interfaces for the platform.
Like whatever a JIRA or internal developer
portal you will use for interacting
with your developers as a platform team.
Ultimately, the deployment phase is
involve changing team structure, setting
business metrics to measure benefits and
defining service level agreements, SLAs.
Maintenance then focuses on delivering
services to developers and ensuring
the platform adds business value,
assessed through SLA and the feedback.
In summary, while the technological
aspects are really essential, the analysis
phase is crucial and it defines how the
platform team integrates and operates
within the organization, ensuring that
platform effectiveness and alignment is
with the business goal of the platform.
Platform engineers, in simple words, are
not focusing on DevOps tools, but they
are focusing on the developers needs.
Okay, does it look complicated?
Yeah, if you do it for the first time,
it is complicated, but don't worry.
You can catch like four years experience
in this matter just within a few hours.
I've spent four years building internal
developer platforms as a manager of
several platforms and advisor to the
people who did it for the first time.
Recently, I've released an online course
on platform engineering for managers.
In this course.
I provide you with end to end guidance
how to approach internal developer
platform, starting with cognitive load
analysis through platform services and
architecture design, ending up with
success measures, case studies, and
selling points so you can convince
your organization that platform should
be built and should be invested in.
Okay, let's go back to the topic.
so how will our IT work after
introduction of platform engineering
principles and building your platform?
We'll review it from two
perspectives, which we are addressing.
First is organizational perspective
and organizational results,
and the technology behind.
So as organizational result, first,
and the most important one, Stream
aligned teams can finally focus
fully on delivering business value.
They do not wait for resources
necessary for SDLC process.
They are provisioned with
the tools within a minute.
They also don't need to configure
those tools on or understand
how they work in details.
They simply use those tools
without fighting at the high
entry, high level entry barrier.
are being forced to manage
those tools by themselves.
We also know exactly who is responsible
for what in software delivery lifecycle.
We have communication channels
planned, and we have defined services
provisioned by platform team, addressing
the very cognitive load that the
stream aligned team may have, both
organizational and technical ones.
If it sounds too theoretical
right now, yeah, you're right.
So time for an example how the
things may look like if you
have a nicely done platform.
so imagine we have a new stream
aligned team in a company.
Our existing team wants to
deliver a new application.
Having a platform, they can simply express
their need through a dedicated channel.
Hey, we are going to build a new software.
The software will be created in Java.
There will be a data storage
needed and exposition to open
network to our end users.
We are going to integrate our app
with core banking system, regulatory
system, So on, and we will be
handling like thousand transactions
daily, mostly from Polish locations.
This is what they say for the portal.
And based on such requests for
a dedicated channel, it can be
portal, it can be other way around.
It's time for Platform Team to
provision the Stream Aligned
team with all the resources and
capabilities to create, release,
and maintain their new application.
So in this matter, Platform Team
is responsible for to ensure
that all the team members of the
StreamAlign team have access to the
repository of their new application.
In this repository, they will
find a demo service with the
language they provided that they
are going to use building the app.
This demo service has already to use CICD
pipelines, which are deploying this demo
application into their dedicated space
or dedicated environments in Kubernetes.
It can be namespace, it can be
dedicated clusters, sometimes
it can be even virtual machine.
music ends And this demo service
are already integrated with all the
observability capabilities, logging,
monitoring, tracing, where the users
can simply go in, log, and define their
own dashboards in a very simple way.
Alerts, filters, things like that.
This demo service is already
connected to the database.
This demo service is
already exposing some API.
This demo service is already
publishing and consuming some topics.
And finally, the team members receive a
detailed instruction how to use all of
those tools in order to build applications
starting from this demo service.
What is crucial that all this
is done in a matter of minutes
through platform orchestrators.
Mature Platforms has all of this
automated and triggered, simply
triggered by the request on the portal.
So the platform engineers
are not even present.
Like in person, in this, in the
service provisioning, having
everything provisioned at once,
a StreamAligned team can focus
fully on the application delivery.
They can create the application
and publish it to end users
from the very first day.
They don't need to spend time
on configuring environment.
on specifying how network
connections should look like.
No, nothing like that happens.
Because on those areas, developers
may not be experts and getting all
the requirements and collect all
of this data and gather wrap all
the tools is simply time consuming.
So platform should do it.
Okay, so a quick look on
technology perspective right now.
First, at the bottom layer,
there is DevSecOps layer.
We have, here we have an order, like no
duplicating technologies and capabilities.
Covering each step of
software delivery lifecycle.
This is what most of the
companies already have.
Maybe not always organized.
Not always non duplicating.
Not always automated.
But this is what you are going to
find in most of the big companies.
What platform engineering introduces
is orchestration and interface layer.
In orchestration, you will find a
definition of platform services and
scripts, which makes changes in each tool
on the bottom layer, on DevSecOps layer.
to provide a managed
service to StreamAlign team.
If you take the previous example, the
provisioning example, for those will be
a script making changes in Kubernetes
namespaces, creating databases,
creating indexes in observability,
creating a repository, moving the demo
service to the repository, and so on.
At the top level, we have an interface
layer, where you can find either a portal,
It's a specified channel which developers
can state their needs in a structured
way and expect a structured outcome.
It does not always need to
be a backstage instance.
It does not need to be a portal.
Sometimes simple APIs or even
simple JIRA tickets are enough.
However, it's better to use tools
which are dedicated to it because
they have more capabilities once
the platform grows its maturity.
And probably we are going to see
AI and chatbots here in this layer
very soon from platform engineering,
community, I already know that things
like that are already happening.
Okay, but a million dollar?
Really?
Huh?
20 percent of IT budget can be
saved using those principles?
Yeah.
Let me prove it.
Okay, so imagine you have 10
application teams in your company.
Okay.
Each team has more or less six developers.
Average salary of one
developer is like 50 an hour.
Juniors are going to be paid
less, seniors, probably more,
and each team is creating one
application release per month.
So we have 12 application releases
every year and releasing this
application takes one week of the
team involvement on the technical
stuff, like creating environments,
connecting application to observability
tools, securing the application.
implementing, network integration with
other systems, testing if it works,
running on the whole company to find
right people to create your database, to
create your Kafka topic, things like that.
More or less bootstrapping
all the SDLC tool set.
For applications which are quite
a long time in the company,
it will be less than one week.
But for applications which are new,
Or the teams, which are new, it
will be much more than one week.
So blended together, it will be one week
and because of no platform services.
So because the teams need to configure
technical things every time before the
release, the overall cost, because of lack
of platform is 1, 440, 000 every year.
In this case, it's 15, 20 percent of
overall budget in such a company on IT.
Yeah, it's a lot of money.
So the game is really worth to play.
Okay, let me know how much your
platforms saved you time and money.
And if your developers are happy
about your current DevSecOps
toolset responsibilities and
things, if they are not bottleneck.
And if they do, let me know
because maybe I will be able
to help you with the platform.
Bye.