Hello everyone.
This is Shankar.
I'm here to present my topic on
the Platform Engineers Hidden
Network Challenge, especially
to talk about the multicast in
the cloud native environments.
Traditionally the multicast is proven
to reduce the bandwidth consumption
in the the on-prem environments,
but the major cloud providers.
Most of them don't
natively support multicast.
So I'm gonna be talking about the
pros and cons of multicast and some
of the alternate options that could
potentially be implemented within
the the cloud native environments.
So when I say multicast
what exactly it means?
It's replicating the same
data to multiple recipients.
So since the data and the same data
is being received by the multiple
in-house typically where this helps.
If we consider unicast,
it's one-to-one, right?
Sender sends the packet
to see what gets it.
So for that to happen, they have
to establish a session initially.
And if we assume hundreds or thousands
of receivers and one sender that
single sender has to build hundred or
thousands of TCP sessions with each
one of them, which is CPU Intensive.
So you're literally wasting.
The resource of the sender
just by establishing these
sessions which is efficient.
So the better approach is using malca.
We use one sender since the packet.
To the multicast group and whoever
joins that group, the receivers,
they start receiving the packets.
And there is no session between the sender
and receiver who are joins the group.
They get those packets, and if you
leave, you're out of the stream.
So you could consider the multicast
as an example of probably a radio
stream or a TV channel streaming.
Where the broadcaster broadcast the
channel, the programs on the channel
and who are like, if you tune, tune
into that channel, you start seeing
the picture in your TV and whoever
joins the channel, they'll be able to
see the same thing at that given time.
And same thing with the radio,
like the radio broadcaster
streams on a certain frequency.
And if you tune the
radio to that frequency.
You start listening the sounds
or whatever broadcast is done.
So it's the same concept like
the multicast one center streams
data and whoever joins the group
they start receiving the data.
There's the, though there's a dramatic
efficiency gain but implementing that
in the large scale virtual environments.
Has been complex and difficult
which is why I think it's still
not yet need to be supported in
some of the major cloud providers.
So what are the critical barriers, right?
That broke multicast state explosion
and software defined networks.
When we talk about multicast the
elements that are in the network
have to maintain a forwarding table.
And since and it has to be
consistent across the network
infrastructure in the cloud.
And as the, as there is if you have
multiple resources or the receivers
joining and leaving the group, there's a
huge amount of calculations that happen.
So this could stress out the control
plane of the the backend infrastructure.
So that could be.
One reason that could potentially prevent
multicast being implemented in this
wide network of public cloud security.
Another consideration.
Typically the cloud native platforms
this strictly depend on the
multi-tenancy with the different clients.
Our customer workloads running the
shared fiscal infrastructure in the
backend, but they're typically separated.
There is no leakage of data or
the resource don't get shared into
the other customers, environment.
But the.
Multicast designed to be operated
under one administrative control.
So there could be a potential
that the the data could leak into
the other tenant's environments.
So that probably one reason
that the multicast could
potentially be not implemented.
The other thing is the operational
complexity and automation challenges.
With unicast, you can
define it, static routing.
But when it comes to multicast
it's dynamically changing behavior.
It's, which is hard to predict and
as I said, they it potentially.
Causes a lot of recalculations
in the forwarding table and a lot
of stress in the control plane.
So that's another reason the
fourth one performance degradation
in the virtual environments.
Theoretically multicast reduces
the the bandwidth consumption,
but the com but it comes with
the complexity of implementation.
And there's the processing of multicast
package through the virtual environments
could potentially be far reaching or
maybe it exceeds the bandwidth savings.
And the fifth one is the the architecture
mismatch with the cloud native patents.
So the microservices they emphasize
loosely on the loose coupling.
And they express explicit service
boundaries, but when it comes to
multicast, it's implicit coupling between
the publisher and the subscribers.
Those are like the five constraints
that could potentially has been
restricting the multicast to be
natively supported in the cloud.
And how.
How having the multicast restricted
in this cloud it, it could
impact infrastructure automation.
One would be the migration challenges.
So many financial data telecommunication
media streaming services, heavily
relying on multicast for the
efficient data distribution.
As most of their models depend on one
couple centers, multiple receivers.
But when it needs to be, when it
needs to be brought into the the
the cloud native it changed like the
legacy application moving into the.
Changes the whole infrastructure
architecture because as it's not natively
supported, so if you're moving from
on-prem legacy app, which is a multicast
based into cloud yeah that's where.
Since there is no native support from
multicast in the cloud you would have
to employ some alternate solutions.
So which kind of becomes complex and
that could result in migration challenges
and infrastructure as code, right?
Like terraform and cloud formations.
There is, as there is no direct resource
natively supported, so you cannot directly
implement using the declarative approach.
Rather you have to have some complex
workarounds through custom scripts.
And that kinda breaks the process.
The platform engineers rely on like
the consistent repeatable code that
we kinda rely on with the state files.
That kind of probably gets lacked.
So those could be two of the impacts
the infrastructure mission can
have with the missing multicast,
native multicast supporting.
Cloud container
orchestration complications.
So service discovery service discovery
and Kubernetes typically depends
on the DNS, which is like the point
to point communication patterns.
Applications that generally use
multicast for dynamic service discovery.
They must be modified to work with the
Kubernetes service abstraction model.
So that's one challenge that
if you're gonna go from.
Legacy app to like the microservices
that could be a huge change that needs
to be considered security policy gaps.
You can apply security policies
for part to part communications.
But the Kubernetes security process
do not control the multicast traffic.
And that could be, huh.
Potential security gap that
could be left pod lifecycles.
The pods lifecycle management the
pods could be created, destroyed
pretty quickly even before the
multicast recalculations happen.
So that could be one complication.
If you want to implement.
Multicast within the Kubernetes
in the cloud native environment.
So does that mean like
we cannot do multicast?
I would say there are a couple approaches
that could be employed though a little
complex and have their pros and cons.
But they, there could be few
approaches that could be taken.
One is at the application level
itself within the developers actually
take that network layer into the
application like code, the the
membership, the group membership
management the message delivery and
error handling within that application.
And they actually maintain the
whole communication from center to
receivers within the application.
Though it increases the complexity,
but it does provide with an approach
where you could generally move
migrate your applications into cloud.
But the overhead of network
now falls under the developers.
And also with the networking
layer added into the application
there could be performance issues.
As well.
The other approach that we can
employ is creating over networks.
So there, there are a couple vendors
that do support over networks within
the public cloud environments.
So the one way is to build let's say.
You have a marketplace router that
you can deploy and you can build
the GRE tunnels from the host and
the receivers, I mean from the
center end receivers to that cloud
router, which can as a central point.
And then build BGP between the end
house to that centralized router.
And then the sender
sends the package to the.
Router and you can configure like
the pim which kind of manages
the whole multicast protocol.
That's one way that it can be achieved.
Though as I said it, it has its
own complexity, but it is one way
that you can take off that overhead
from the application and bring it
back into the the network layer.
Compared to what we've discussed earlier
about application level replication,
There are, there, there are a couple
cloud native alterna approaches that
could potentially be reviewed as well.
Mainly the messaging services like.
Amazon SQS cloud pop sub they
provide reliable scalpel message
delivery and if properly planned
and designed potentially the cloud
native approach could be avoided.
The network approach could be avoided
and potentially the application
will be, can be built more of
with the cloud native resources.
And if there is an application
like the content delivery networks.
If the application relies on the
content distribution rather than
real time data, then every cloud
provider provides support CDN.
So that could be one
that could be employed.
And and there are like
software defense solutions.
Like the industries now, the
network industries coming up with
some of the solutions that could
potentially be supported in the cloud
as well, like a market solutions.
So that, that could be one option that
we could potentially see in the future.
Okay.
So though we have the workarounds,
but it, it does have its own cons and
first one is the complex workaround.
Like even if you try to do it overly
or apply it in the application.
The lack of native multicast
support it forces the development
teams to learn new things and try
to inculcate into the application.
The whole developer experience gets
affected and it might slow down the
software lifecycle, like the software
development lifecycle as well.
Environment inconsistency.
You might be having a legacy
application that locally.
Works fine.
But with the with the alternate approach
that we try to implement in the cloud.
So there's, there could be this huge
disconnect between the application,
the on-prem to what it's working now
in the in the cloud native and the
in the public cloud with alternate
solutions that you implement.
And also the testing.
The testing and the
legacy would differ a lot.
When it comes to the solution
implemented in the cloud.
So these are some of the challenges
that we might come across if
implemented the alternate way of
implementing the multicast in the cloud
and operational overhead and complexity.
So
monitoring, complexity, and,
capacity planning challenges and
multiple communication patterns.
So monitoring becomes complex with
the multicast because monitoring and
troubleshooting actually given you
would be implementing different rather
than using a cloud native now we'll be
implementing multiple, overlay networks
with, implementing overlay network with
the different vendor elements in it.
So it'll be hard to figure out where
the issue is, and also like monitoring
different elements centrally that
becomes a huge problem And capacity
planning given the multicast if you
implementing the application it would
be hard to know what's the usage and
the scaling becomes difficult if it is
managed entirely within the application.
So that's another
challenge that could arise.
Implementing the alternate solutions.
So it typically affects
in higher costs, right?
Higher costs.
Incident resolution become longer
and there could be SLAs being missed,
service disruptions, production issues.
It, you could implement with
alterna approaches, but there are
complexities and there are it, its
own cons that come along with it.
As I mentioned, the future
prospects and emerging technologies.
SGN native multi multicast protocols.
So the vendors the networking, networking
vendors are probably gonna be building
something that could natively support
in future within the cloud environments
or maybe something that could be not
implemented across the wide area network.
In the cloud, but potentially limited to a
certain scope for a specific purpose that
could be option that could be implemented.
And with the advancement of some
of the nicks, like the smart nicks
and the data processing units
that could help potentially reduce
the the challenges that we see in
the the virtualized environments.
That could potentially reduce the the
performance issues that multicast posts in
the cloud environments and maybe service
mesh integrations like ST on console.
There's been great advancements
and potentially that's one area
that could, can have like multicast
like functionality in future, one
cloud native option that could.
Being researched is serverless
event in architectures.
Because I think with so many issues that
we could come across with the alternate
approaches like doing multicast within
the application or doing the OA networks.
As in increases as it in
introduces complexity.
I think going with the cloud native
approach or redesigning your applications
to be more cloud native probably
would be the going forward and as
serverless even architectures could
be something that could be employed.
And yeah, as I mentioned, you could
the cloud native alternates is
one option that could be employed.
Sorry.
The operational complexity and
architectural constraints in the cloud
environment, the total con of cost of
ownership include not just resource
consumption, but also operational overhead
and development complexity, and the future
of efficient group communication in cloud
environment likely lies in solutions
Design specifically for software defines
centrally controlled architectures.
Rather than adaptions of
traditional distribution protocols.
That ends my topic.
Thank you all for listening.
Thanks.