Hello.
Good morning or good afternoon everyone.
My name is LaMi.
I'm a senior E at DevOps,
lead of cloud lead.
I have experience that spans both
traditional middleware administration and
modern cloud native technologies making
me versatile technology who consistently
cloud scalable infrastructure solutions.
Let me begin with the scenario.
Imagine a hurricane making a landfall
nine one call volume search dispatch
systems are under stress and every
second of downtime could cost lives.
When we think about emergency
response, whether it's dispatching
ambulances, coordinating firefighters,
or managing disaster relief,
downtime is simply not an option.
Today.
In this talk, I'll share how platform
engineering a practice often associated
with enterprise ID can fundamentally
transform emergency response terms into
cloud native platforms that save lives.
In this agenda.
First we'll begin with foundations
of platform engineering and why
they matter for emergency systems.
Then drive into self-service
infrastructure and developer experience.
Third, operational ex excellence patterns
from orchestration to observability, and
finally, organizational studies that make
this platform sustainable and adoptable.
The challenge.
Unlike traditional enterprise
applications, emergency systems can't
afford even seconds of downtime.
They must scale instantly during
crisis, integrate with legacy
and government systems, and still
comply with strict regulations.
Think of what happens when a
hurricane hits call volumes spike.
Dispatch systems much as much
spawn in milli milliseconds
and for you could cost lives.
Traditional deployment model models
will with long cycles and manual
process simply can't keep up.
We need a new paradigm.
The paradigm shift before platform
engineering deployment took two weeks.
Errors of frequent and
redundancy was limited.
Operation teams are isolated,
infrastructure is inconsistent,
and geographic CIE and
special knowledge is required.
And platform.
After platform engineering,
we achieved three minutes.
Selfer, self-service provisioning.
Golden paths with built-in per
practices had 99% reduction.
The configurators consistent
patterns across 200 plus
microservices, multi-region
deployment by default and hide out
complexity from application teams.
The shift creates multiplier effect.
Emergency teams can focus on their
mission on saving lives, struck
firefighting infrastructure,
coming to develop a portal.
Portal is heart of our
self-service platform.
It acts as a primary interface for
emergency response teams, a place
where they request infrastructure,
deploy services, monitor their systems.
Instead of waiting weeks from manual
approvals or writing low level scripts
now have a simple gateway that abstracts
complexity and towards consistency.
Here we discuss about Golden
Park templates, self service
catalog, and service scorecards.
We'll dive in deep into these, all these
three points, golden part templates.
Golden paths are pre-approved.
Template that developers follow to
provision applications and services.
They're embedded with security
observability and compliance best
practices By default, why import
for emergency response during a
disaster, developers don't have time
to figure out how to configure network
trucking, encryption and logging.
Golden Path ensure all services meet
baseline requirements automatically.
Let's take an example.
A new emergency microservice can
be deployed in under three minutes
using a Golden Path template.
It comes pre-wire with centralized logging
TLS, security and modern dashboards.
No manual work is needed.
One of such example is Backstage,
which is Spotify's open source
developer portal, often used
for Golden Park implementations.
Golden Pass.
Might also include hand check templates,
Terraform modules or Kubernetes AML
blueprints and pre prebuilt guardrails.
Coming to service catalog, the service
catalog is like a minimum where teams
can pick the infrastructure and services
they need without open tickets are
relying on ops teams, self-service,
provisioning of databases, messages,
queues, and caches, object storage,
and other cloud native components.
These are all what it offers.
Each entry in the catalog comes
with built in process like hipaa
NIST, and local regulations coming
to emergency response scenario.
One of the example is suppose
an incident occurs that requires
scaling up realtime event.
Few of Q4 incoming calls instead days
of provisioning an engineer Kafka
cluster from the service catalog and
has means pre-configured for resilience.
Some of the tools and examples are.
HashiCorp Terraform Cloud Cross or a
W Service catalog often powered the
backend coming to service scorecards.
Scorecards are provide realtime
metrics on health, reliability,
and compliance of each service.
Think of it as a report card for
every microservice, what they measure.
Reliability, uptime error
rates mean time to recover.
They also offer security and compliance.
They also measure performance latency,
throughput and resource utilization.
Some of the examples of pros and
Grafana metrics visualization,
open telemetry for traces.
The conclusion is the developers
portal is not just a dashboard,
it's productivity engine.
Golden paths.
Where Golden Paths provide saves.
Foster deployments service catalog
gives instant access to critical
infrastructure and service.
Scorecards realtime visibility.
The result is what took two
weeks now takes three minutes,
coming to IAC and GI tops,
which are core for the, for this
infrastructure, everything is defined
as code and managed to GitHubs.
We have full version control drift
detection with hundred percent
coverage and 73% of deviations auto
remediated immutable infrastructure
patterns mean no ad hoc changes.
Let's dive deep into the infrastructures
code and DevOps infrastructures
in code and DevOps, a backbone of
reliable cloud native platforms.
The transform how they, how we
build, deploy, and manage emergency
response systems with consistency
and trust are on negotiable.
Let's break down in these practices
and why they are critical.
What is infrastructure as a code ISC means
we infrastructure in code now through
manual, not through manual flick or ad
hoc scripts, everything from Kubernetes
cluster load balance to IM rules is
written as declarative configuration
file stored in version control.
This enables consistency,
automation, and version control.
Every infrastructure change is
tracked like code without history
or differences and rollback ability.
Coming to consistency, same ation of
is across different a like dev and
production automation development.
Deployments happen via CA CD,
pipelines without human error.
Some example tools are cloud agno
agnostic, ISC tool project resources
like AWS Azure, Google Cloud platform.
And also some other example is
Ansible often use it for conservation
management and small scale provisioning.
A Terraform module, take an example.
A Terraform module provisions five
Kubernetes testers across different
regions with identical settings,
ensuring complaints and resilience.
When a new node pool is added to the
hand of the disaster load is done
by updating coding gi, not manually.
What is GitHubs?
GitHub's Accents a infrastructure
is a code by using GitHubs as single
source of truth for both infrastructure
and application deployment.
Any change to infrastructure
or application manifest must
be committed to git a GitHub
controller like August City Flex.
Continuously reconcile live cluster
state with clash state in Git.
This provides auditability, automatic
detection and safer deployments.
What is auditability?
Every change has an other committee
history and approval workflow.
Coming to automated D detection, if
someone changes the resource directly
in the cluster, GIS reverse is back.
And these deployments are also safer
where changes are tested, be reviewed
and rolled out inconsistently.
So my example tools
are Argo CD and Flux CD
coming to.
Key benefits of these emergency
response systems are reliability,
speed, resilience, and compliance.
In short, IAC ensures
that our infrastructure is
reproducible and predictable.
While GitHubs ensures that our operations
are automated and audible together, they
make sure emergency systems stay online,
secure, and ready to handle demand
spikes when every second truly matters.
Coming to multi cluster orchestration.
Imagine a flood knocking
out an anti-D data center.
The system must continue
running without missing a beat.
Resilience is critical.
Multi, multi cluster orchestration issues
that from one, if one region goes down
due to a flood power outage, or cyber
attacks, as services continues seamlessly,
we receive workloads across fire regions.
Maintain active clusters and pro travel
to near the nearest healthy endpoint.
Multi coming to multi cluster
orchestration architecture,
we have failover cluster.
We operate multiple Kubernetes
clusters per region.
The this design ensures that if one
cluster goes down to hardware failure,
software, bug, or even a there disaster,
another cluster seamlessly takes over.
Automated failure mechanisms
synchronize straight, straightforward
workloads across clusters.
This means data is not lost and operations
can assume within minimum disruption.
By Thereal isolation, we
prevent cascading failure.
For example, an issue in one region
does not spill and impact others,
which is crucial in emergencies.
Multiple clusters per region.
Within each region, we
maintain more than one cluster.
It supports active two configurations
where both clusters are live share
load, and improve availability and fault
tolerance During peak load, for example,
a certain 8800% spike in emergency
calls during the disaster resources are
automatically distributed across clusters.
These balances, performance and
ensures fosters possible response
time for first responders.
Regional balances coming to
regional balances with redundancy.
Each region is frontend by regional
role balances, which is distributed
incoming traffic among clusters.
These load balances
themselves are redundant.
If one fails another, instantly
takes over, ensuring there's
no single point of failure.
They also support intelligent
routing, sending request to region.
Emergency services with failover.
Each individual emergency service such as
dispatching, geolocation, or medical trial
systems is designed, built at failover.
For example, the primary
instance of a dispatch service
in cluster becomes unavailable.
The system automatically roads to a
secondary instance in cluster B without
manual intervention coming to Global
Traffic Management and failover.
In this one of the key
component of the architecture.
The reason level we use global
traffic managers like DNS Road, a
cloud native global load balancing
the systems direct user request
to the nearest healthy region.
Ensuring edge optimized routing with
sub mil 50 millisecond latency for
entire region becomes unavailable.
For instance, due to disaster,
natural disaster, global routing,
automatic failures to another region.
To summarize, this architecture
combines failover at every level,
service cluster, regional and global
intelligent traffic management.
This result is a platform that is
a resilient complaint and ready
to further unexpected failures.
This architecture ensures that
sub 50 millisecond dispatch
response times globally.
Coming to service mesh
integration, a service mesh adds
another layers of resilience.
It automatically traffic to healthy
services using breaking to stop
cascading failures and enforce
mutual TL security for zero trust.
Security, even partial failures
does not have system availability.
A must for life critical operations.
Coming to observability, of
course, you can't operate at
the scale without visibility.
You can't fix what you can't see,
or observability platform ES 2.3
million metrics per minute, ands 90%
of alert accuracy through machine
learning and animal detection.
This enables less than 30 seconds.
Coming to policy as cloud security
and governance are non-negotiable.
Governance should not slow teams down.
By adding, by admitting policy.
As code security and compliance are
enforced automatically, we enforce
runtime policies automatically.
Con, continuously validate against
frameworks like HIPA and secure the
supply chain with and pro checks.
Example, take an example.
A deployment violates, sometimes
security is blocked without
requir manual intervention.
This approach, governance without
slowing teams down, security and
complaints are built in default.
Coming to platform team, organization.
Enabled by 12 platform team
supporting more than 80 developers.
Platform gathering feedback,
engineer with application teams.
Four, not doing things.
It's about enabling others to move safely.
Measuring platform success.
Is how do we measure success?
Developer experience is improved 67%
faster time to production, 70% fewer
stock support operational metrics,
19% availability, and 78% decrease.
In meantime to response repay.
There 30% reduction in
emergency response time.
Increase in future delivery
velocity and 65% decrease in.
Ultimately, these are not just numbers.
They represent faster resources,
better outcomes, and save lives.
The key takeaways to close.
Service.
Key takeaways are self-service
infrastructure unlocks, agility, platform
obstructions, reduce cognitive load and
golden path, enforce best practices.
The journey does not start
with boiling the ocean.
Begin with what?
Golden path, measure
rigorously and expand.
When platform engineering meets
emergency response, technology
directly translates to human impact.
That's why this work matters.
Thank you.