Hello, everyone, and
welcome to our session.
Let me start this session
with a bold statement.
The next big revolution in platform
engineering isn't about a new tool.
It's about reimagining the
entire concept of a platform.
My name is Martin Sarkovsky.
I'm a senior solutions architect
with AWS and have a long history in
designing and also building platforms.
And today with me is Marina Burkhardt,
also solutions architect at AWS.
And Marina has a strong DevOps
background and experience in
administrating and operating platforms.
And we both as solutions architects
are very much interested in
building the platform of the future.
So today we want to share our perspective
on the future of platform engineering.
But first, let's look back.
Why are we doing this?
Why are we building platforms?
And what are platforms?
I would define it as a group of
technologies that are used in as a base.
And upon this base, upon this
platform, we can develop application
processes and other technologies.
So we basically build some
common components that handle
a lot of generic stuff.
And on top of that, we can build
something that is special and unique.
and we know this is a concept that
has been used in many industries
and they were very successful with.
using platforms to
transformize their business.
How does it work with software?
let's think of the main goals of
platforms in software development.
It's about increasing the
development speed and still
meeting all the requirements
that you get for our software.
And in order to have this right balance
between Very high speed and high quality
and meeting all the requirements.
We need something that is helping us.
We need abstractions.
And often those abstractions
come with standardizations.
platforms often enforce standards.
And if I talk about standards,
I often hear people saying that
standards are taking away all
the nice freedom and flexibility.
Because people think of
standards as limitations.
But I would say, and this is an old
statement now, it's quite the opposite.
Standards actually enable innovation.
Standards help you to scale and
standards remove all the friction.
I want to give you a few examples
where I believe that is true.
think of this as a highly
standardized piece of paper.
210 by 297 millimeters.
it's not roughly 200 by 300 millimeters.
No, it is exactly 210 by 297 millimeters.
Which is, by the way, exactly
one sixteenth of a square meter.
And this standard, 210 by 297
millimeters, It's called DIN A4.
And I believe it's a great standard.
Because if we're talking about
DIN A4, no one has to argue how
big that piece of paper will be.
We can rely on a certain size.
And we can build something
that is supporting that.
we have fitting envelopes, we
have folders, drawers, pockets, we
all know how to build something.
the right size for them.
We can even build printers, fax
machines, but we don't do that anymore.
But, like all those, things that work
together with that piece of paper.
And yes, if we have that
standardized piece of paper, we
have to adjust to that standard.
So if we write a letter and I have this
very long sentence in mind, I have to
use a line break because of 210 by 297.
if I want to draw a picture, I have
to accommodate that into this format.
But think about it.
Does that really limit
you in writing texts?
Does that limit you in drawing pictures?
we have seen great texts.
We have seen a lot of
art on a piece of paper.
Standardized text.
piece of paper.
And we have the same with technology.
let me give you one
example, very low level.
we are using HTTP to make sure
that our browsers can talk to
web servers, to other computers.
And we are using this standard everywhere.
So actually we can't imagine
a world without that standard.
yeah, there are some limitations.
There are some standardizations
in, in, in HTTP.
but this standard actually has
enabled the internet and it never
put a limit to the innovations.
that we are seeing
today with the internet.
So we have to realize a few
things, locking things down
and agreeing on a few things.
can actually help us.
It can boost innovation and it
can boost creativity because those
standards and abstractions, they
help us to remove the cognitive
overload we would have otherwise.
So they help us with increasing the
speed of development and they also help
us to still meet all the requirements.
So if we want to be successful
with software development, We need
kind of abstractions and standards.
So we need those platforms.
But there are many platforms and
platform engineering is a term nowadays.
So what makes a platform a great platform?
Marina will explain some of the key
characteristics for a successful platform.
there isn't a golden answer
to Martin's question.
But at least I brought you here three
different characteristics that I think and
consider that every single great platform
should have in order to be successful.
So let's dive into those ones.
As we just mentioned, platforms are
going to come with abstractions.
So that means abstractions and
standards are going to be in place.
And you might think that those
are going to limit you, but
actually totally the opposite.
A platform should be an enabler.
A platform should hide the complexity
and should make it easier to use.
And in order to achieve that, you should
have a high level of transparency and
you make usage of shared information.
components.
So a platform shouldn't be a black box.
A platform should have a high level
of documentation so that every single
person out there in the different teams
can read that documentation, understand
how the doc and understand how the
components were built and which one
was the intention of the usage of them.
And also you can, Make the code of
the platform open source, at least
internally for your different teams.
And with a combination of two, of those
two, those things, you're going to
create a shared responsibility feeling
across the different teams, which at the
end is going to be beneficial for you.
Nevertheless, you do not
want to reinvent the wheel.
So that means you would like to have those
components that you built shared across
the whole platform so that multiple teams
can benefit of those components as well.
Second characteristics, from great
platform is that you would like that
your platform is also extensible.
So that means you do not have to foresee
which are the features that every
single team is going to need in the
future, but at least stay flexible in
such a way that you can learn, which
one are the technologies that they
are using, learn about the new tools
that every team might implement or use
from time to time, and also stay alert
about different architectural patterns.
There are trends in the industry
and in the market out there.
So that means you do not wanna, force
anyone to use a specific pattern,
tool, technology integration, but make
and, or build the platform in such a
way that it's attractive for multiple
teams and all the teams actually to
really make usage of your platform.
When that happens, More and more teams
are going to, use or want to implement
things on top of your platform, and
therefore you would like to be able
to scale that platform as well.
And that would be able just if you have
a high level of automation in place.
So you can use infrastructure as code,
like for example, AWS, in CDK to just
Make usage of the possibility of having
a great automation and keep the pace of
new teams onboarding in your platform.
The third characteristic is
that you would like that your
platform is also evolutionary.
So that means you do not want to
have a platform that is static.
You want something dynamic that keeps
the pace of technology out there.
With the time you would like that this
platform actually reduces the TCO.
So the total cost of ownership
make it more efficient and
more performant as well.
And with the time it should be
easier and easier to use as well.
How do you achieve this
evolutionary characteristic?
By treating the platform as a product.
So that means having a product mindset.
Nevertheless, something that
experience taught me is that you
can have the best intentions.
You could have the best, specialist
knowledgeable in a specific topic,
but if you do not have mechanisms in
place, there's no way that you can
say, So you can scale this across
your organization and have the
impact that you would like to have.
Therefore, I brought you four different
characteristics, of those mechanisms that
I would invite you to think and consider
when building and designing your platform.
Being the first one about abstractions.
So we want to build a platform in such
a way that It has the complexity, but
it has a high level of transparency so
that everyone is going to be able to
know how those components were built.
You would like to have some same defaults,
so having the possibility to set some,
values per default that helps the teams to
reduce the mistakes, to reduce the errors,
but at the same time, have a high level
of flexibility because you were going
to, give them a set of configurations
that are already properly set it up.
The third abstraction is about automation.
So you would like to keep the
pace of technology, but increase
the speed of every development.
and at the same time, reduce
the friction of the processes.
And last but not least, those platforms
should actually help you with some
control security things related.
So we want to help you to, or to enforce.
Compliance measures and follow
any regulation that you have to
take in consideration related to
the market and the industry that
you are part of while having this
high level of share responsibility
across the whole different teams.
And the question here would be, whom is
this platform actually going to enable?
And here, I want to talk
about a great quote from Peter
Gillett Moss from ThoughtWorks.
He said, the platforms are a very
great way for centralizing expertise.
But he also said you cannot
centralize innovation.
You have to leave that to the teams
that are the closest to the customer.
Because those teams, they
obviously have the best ideas.
And they will build innovation
on top of a platform.
Let's think about those teams,
that are doing the innovation.
how do those innovative
teams actually work?
usually those teams are
small and self sufficient.
So that means they can do most
or maybe all of their work
independently from all the other
teams that are also doing innovation.
And they can make most or all
of their decisions on their own.
Let's think about this.
Autonomies, teams.
on a platform.
How does that work?
Here, we need to talk about the
centralized versus decentralized approach.
Let me start with the maybe more
traditional centralized approach.
We have a platform and that
platform is designed and also
operated by a platform team.
And of course, we learned the
platform needs to be evolutionary.
So we have to add new features
to our platform all the time.
And in a perfect world.
Your platform team would anticipate
every single feature request and they
would implement all the features before
someone even asked about the feature.
But now let's look back to the reality.
So in reality, it's different.
In reality, app teams often request
a new feature, and they want this
feature as soon as possible because
they need it for the innovation.
And then your platform team needs
to understand this new feature.
And then the platform team needs
to build the new feature and all
of this while operating a central
platform that is growing a lot.
So you're basically moving the
cognitive load from the app
team down to the platform team.
And if you get more and more app
teams doing this, What will happen?
You will overload the platform
team and your platform team
will become your bottleneck.
Because what are we doing here?
We are not only centralizing
expertise, we are also trying to
centralize the platform innovation.
How does it work for a
decentralized platform approach?
in that approach, the platform
team is designing blueprints
as a platform component.
And all the app teams, they can use
these blueprints and they can use them
and create their own versions of that.
So we actually put a bit
more responsibility into
the hands of the developers.
So the developers, the app teams,
they own the entire lifecycle of
the application, including all
that they're using as a base.
And, you could think maybe they have now
the cognitive overload, but they don't
get this cognitive overload because
platform components, the blueprints,
they are using abstractions that
are provided by the platform team.
So they basically don't have to reinvent
everything and build it from scratch.
They can build upon those abstractions.
So they don't get this cognitive
overload to understand.
The full stack completely from the
beginning, so app teams can operate their
own stack, but they still meet all the
central requirements, and if required,
they can evolve the stack, maybe on their
own or together with the platform team.
So what are we doing here?
We are centralizing the
expertise into those blueprints.
But then we decentralize the
innovation to the app teams.
Let's think that a bit through.
How would that work in reality?
if we have this shared responsibility
between app teams and platform
team, Who's doing what, who is
responsible for what part of this deck?
here we need to talk about
ownership patterns and Marina
will discuss a few of them.
So there are different approaches.
And I brought you three of the
ownership patterns that I've seen the
most with our AWS customers in the
way they have treated the productive
workloads in their AWS accounts.
By being the first one,
treating the whole AWS system.
Account itself as the platform.
And the way you can imagine this is
like by having an AWS account vending
machine that is going to be owned by the
platform engineering team, but it's going
to provide AWS accounts with already
some, building blocks and components
defined and deployed in the AWS account
to every single team out there in your
organization that needs an AWS account
in order to run the resources needed for
the different projects and use cases.
And those components might be
related to networking, observability,
security, or anything out
there that comes to your mind.
Where the platform engineering team
is going to, for the networking, for
example, design the whole network, like.
how many VPCs is going to, that account
is going to have, how many subnets
what's, how does the routing table
for example, look like, and so on
related to observability, you might
have already some, I don't know, logs
defines metric, some dashboard, all of
the, all of this may be in CloudWatch
and also specify and already implement
some security mechanisms in that account
How can this platform engineering build?
such a vending machine through,
for example, the usage of AWS,
organizations, AWS config, CloudWatch,
and IIM, for example, as well.
The second ownership pattern
is related to managed clusters.
Where in the other approach, you had a
higher level of flexibility, but lower
level of abstraction that might not
really be needed by every single team.
Like for example, a team that runs
some containers, would not really.
Care about what's the VPC that it's
already there in place in the AWS account,
but instead having a possibility to just
run the containers in a cluster that
it's already managed by another team.
So that means, They still would like
to have those standards components to
networking and observability, but tailored
specifically for a managed cluster.
So for example, they would like to have
some health checks, or maybe have the
possibility to monitor how many containers
are running the, in the whole, Cluster
itself, or maybe have some possibility
to manage the users that are going to
have access to the cluster and also some
input and output rules for the whole,
container itself that it's running there.
So this option is going to have
a lower level of flexibility, but
a higher level of abstraction.
And the third ownership pattern is related
to the deployable application patterns.
So this is like providing blueprints,
like providing some AWS CDK constructs.
this might be For you not resonate as
a platform and rather like blueprints
and guidelines on how to deploy things.
But this is yet another ownership
pattern for a platform itself.
And this is pretty much a
modern way also of treating it.
Then I also seen.
A lot of times we're actually the teams
that might benefit the most of this are
the high performing teams are the ones
that are already used to work with,
for example, AWS accounts and need some
blueprints that helps them to deploy some
applications faster with some standards.
that are well defined in there with some
architectural patterns, as well that
might help them to reduce the development
time and improve already, the possibility
of building something on top as well.
Having now those three ownership patterns
in mind, I would like to hand over
to Martin, who is going to actually
explain how, by having the possibility
and the freedom of different patterns,
you do not have to force How can I
use any team in order to implement
and make usage of this platform?
you don't have to decide
exclusively what pattern to use.
You get the freedom of choice.
Let me show you how that could work.
Let's imagine we have this
platform team and they're dealing
with, let's say, four teams.
And these are decentralized dev teams.
first of all of our teams get
those pre configured accounts
from the account vending machine.
And, team one is perfectly
fine with that account.
So they get this pre configured
account as a base level platform,
and they build everything else on
top of that, completely on their own.
team two is different.
They use those managed clusters.
And on top of that, They also want to
have those deployable patterns, maybe
in a cluster that could be a hand chart.
team three, deploys the application
into a managed cluster, but they
don't need all those patterns on top.
They have their own way of doing things.
And team four, let's say
they are the serverless game.
So they use those templated patterns
for serverless applications in
their pre configured account.
now we have four different
ways of doing things.
Let's reimagine the term platform.
All of this is your platform.
Some parts of your platform are more
central, like the account vending
or maybe the managed cluster.
And some parts are more
decentralized, like all those
deployable application patterns.
And so on.
And by giving all the teams the freedom
of choice, you don't have to force a team
to follow one approach that might work
for you, but that wouldn't work for them.
So the idea is to make the platform not
too restrictive, but make the platform
open to innovation and innovation.
and to development.
And I can recommend working towards
those decentralized teams with shared
patterns and services as a platform.
And you can see those blueprints that are
shared on your platform as a golden path.
Maybe this concept of a golden
path is very well known, and maybe
also the concept of a paved road.
And let's see those
blueprints as a golden path.
on a paved road.
While this is the golden path,
there's still a bit room to do
things differently on a paved road.
So that's your opinionated and
supported way of using technology.
So this is the way to make it for
the teams as easy as possible to use
technology and to use your platform.
But we want to be flexible.
So if someone has an alternative
idea, let them go with left or right.
from that golden path on the paved
road still, to a certain degree.
there are still guardrails,
outside of that paved road.
Maybe this idea will open another
road, maybe a new shortcut,
maybe, this improvement will
even be your new golden path.
So basically treat your platform as a
product, make it similar to your product
development, have a product mindset.
When building your platform, how can
you do that while we can learn from the
development of open source software?
products because they
follow the same principles.
So whenever you build something for
your platform, make it versioned.
So a version piece of software that
can be evolved by the user community,
maybe make the platform team as the
main contributor, but allow other
ones to contribute and create their
own version, make it decentralized.
So every component should have
an independent life cycle that
makes the scaling much easier
because you have smaller pieces.
And, it also reduced the blast radius and
dependencies and so on and make it usable.
So if you have this product mindset that
we just discussed, you would create good
accessibility, like good documentation,
scaffolding, a CLI, a UI integration,
and so on, and then make it customizable.
So be open to changes.
Allow someone to
parameterize your product.
your platform components, allow to
choose escape hatches, if possible,
let them fork it, let them change it.
If they need, don't build a black box,
make it transparent, make it a white box.
Don't hide the implementation of your
platform because people rely on it
and then make it self https: otter.
ai so everything should be fully
automated as much as possible.
So everything can be requested
and deployed via APIs.
So that is an evolutionary
platform, guided by the principles
of open source development.
And one last thing to mention here,
always stay ahead with your platform.
So we discussed this, a platform
will always build on a certain base,
like the AWS Cloud, for instance.
And we also discussed that
your platform should evolve.
But here's one thing to remember.
The base where you built your
platform on does also evolve.
So if you don't evolve your platform,
the things that you're building on top of
that base, and you don't adapt it to the
base, you will have a sinking platform.
A platform that has no
true benefits anymore.
Maybe the platform even makes
it more difficult to do things,
compared to the native approach.
So that will be a platform was a
burden and no one wants to use that.
So if you always evolve your platform
and you're always adapted to the base,
you will have something that we would
call a floating platform, a platform
that is always ahead of the base.
And that is a platform
that offers true benefits.
to all the users of the platform.
So a platform that enables all your teams.
So our recommendation is always
build floating platforms.
What did we learn today?
So standards are not limitations.
Often I would say they
are the key to innovation.
So don't build a platform for the
sake of having a platform, for the
sake of doing platform engineering.
Build a platform that enables
all the users your teams.
A platform that is
extensible and evolutionary.
And always think about decentralization of
the platform, the centralized blueprints.
And if you do that, make it work.
As flexible as possible, build a
golden path, but be flexible and
always stay ahead with your platform.
Thanks a lot for listening
to our talk today.
we really value your feedback.
there are two links, how you can reach us.
we're happy to discuss that
concept even further with you.
And if you have some feedback for
us, if you liked what we told you
today, There's a feedback link.
We're happy to hear your feedback.
It only takes 15 seconds
to fill out the survey.
Thank you so much for joining us today.