Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Conf42 and this talk about
DevOps 12 factor and platform engineering.
We're going to dig into
the history of DevOps.
We're going to really look
at what I believe its true
origins are and where they lie.
and we are going to talk about
where this practice has evolved to.
Today, this is probably the third
iteration of this talk that I've given.
It used to be called DevOps,
12 factor and open source.
And as the industry has
just adopted new patterns.
around what's mainstream and what's
really helping developers with their
flow and with their productivity.
I've updated this talk, along with it.
So this is where we are now in 2024, where
we're talking about platform engineering.
We're building multi cloud developer
platforms where we create our
code and we're deliver our code.
And we've evolved this practice of
platform engineering, which is really
the the work that it takes to put
together all the various tools and
pieces of the platform, the different
permutations of platforms that we have,
has now evolved into this practice.
And so that's what we're going
to be talking about today.
My name is Justin Riak and I've been
around for a little while at this point,
having had several different roles,
but I really started focusing mostly on
developer productivity over the last.
Five years or so, there's a lot
that's happened in this space around
developer experience and, seeking the
type of better productivity outcomes
that can happen when we invest very
heavily in developer experience.
And so if you've seen any of
my recent work, that's mostly
what I've been focused on.
Now I'm currently the head of dev rel
for Cortex, where we ship an internal
developer portal, that type of pattern,
that internal developer portal pattern,
I truly believe is the most important.
Pattern right now, helping people
move from a orchestration stage of
their platform to a choreography
stage of their platform.
And always happy to talk more about that.
So where did DevOps come from?
Where did it begin?
this is the commonly accepted place,
at least for the words, right?
DevOps days, Belgium, Patrick
Dubois DevOps days, 2009, right?
This is the first time that we've
heard this coin termed, but I think
that DevOps started long before this.
And I think it started with a mindset,
and I think it's this mindset, that it's
no longer the big beating the small.
But the fast beating the slow, okay, this
quote, you've probably seen it or some
version of it associated with DevOps.
This has become I think the rallying
cry for DevOps, but it really, this
is talking about throughput and this
is talking about agility, right?
This is talking about, it's
no longer the big, monolithic
organizations that are gobbling
up all of the market share, right?
The small, fast, disruptive startups are
the ones that kind of come out of nowhere.
And this mindset started long
before that quote, right?
When it's something that I like to
refer to as the ancient business wisdom
of, in this case, the 1970s and 80s,
more specifically the work of Dr.
Ellie Goldrott and the
theory of constraints.
Now, I know that we can come back
even further and talk about The
work that was being done with
statistical process control, W.
Edwards Deming, if you've read Beyond
the Goal, was a huge influence to
GoldRot's work, and you absolutely
will find Deming's work all over what
we're doing right now with platform and
DevOps and even artificial intelligence.
but this talk is going to focus mostly
on theory of constraints and why.
It's important to DevOps and
how it's shaped a lot of the,
the underlying themes of DevOps.
So if you're not familiar with Dr.
Goldrod or the book, the goal, Dr.
Goldrod was a physicist turned,
business analyst, so to speak.
and he realized his big intellectual leap
that was such a bit of genius was that
you could apply the rules of physics,
as they work within complex machinery.
to business, right?
You could take the same terminology and
the same basics, physics, principles,
and you could turn around and map
that to the way that an organization.
And in this case, a
production and manufacturing
organization can work and flow.
Now this book, the goal is
not some business textbook.
Okay.
I think that's part of its appeal.
It is a fictional account.
of a VP manufacturing who's
struggling within their company
to keep pace with competition.
a change agent is introduced to
the business, somebody with a
theory with an understanding of
the theory of constraints, and they
use that to transform the business.
now, if you're not familiar with
the goal, you're probably familiar
with the Phoenix project at this
point, at least in these crowds.
And you should know that Gene
Kim will be the first to tell you
that the Phoenix project is just
a retelling of the goal, right?
Except now through the eyes of DevOps.
But it's talking about, it's teaching the
theory of constraints, the same theory of
constraints that was taught in the goal.
Format wise, it's also
very similar, right?
This book, again, is
not a business textbook.
It is a page turning business
fiction, not, fiction novel about,
in this case, a VP of engineering.
moving through a major migration,
and struggling, a change agent comes
in and introduces DevOps principles
and saves the business, right?
So another great way to learn
about the theory of constraints.
Okay, what is the theory of constraints
and how does it relate to DevOps?
How did it start helping us with
this, fast beating the slow?
Mindset.
there's a lot to the
theory of constraints.
Okay.
And essentially, it's a theory that
says that a system will never be able
to perform better than its constraints.
And sometimes we can
use those constraints.
Sometimes we can put constraints
in a system to try to achieve
better flow within that system.
Where it relates, I think most
directly to DevOps is in, defining
any complex machine, according
to three different basic.
bits of its anatomy, right?
The cost, right?
The energy associated with making this
machine do what it's supposed to do.
the throughput, right?
that machine actually doing its job,
doing what the machine is supposed to do.
And then the inventory, right?
The raw materials, the pieces, the
individual parts that work together at a
cost to create throughput for the machine.
All right.
So theory of constraints defines
machinery according to these
three types of inventory.
Cost, throughput, excuse me,
these types of anatomy, cost,
throughput, and inventory.
All right, now, if we take a
quick intellectual leap, what
did these components map to
in a software organization?
All right, in a software organization,
cost is still cost, right?
This is FTE, the full
time engineering hours.
This is hands on keyboard writing code.
this is the cost, the personnel costs,
the tool cost of actually creating it.
Inventory is the code itself.
That's the raw materials that we're hoping
to manufacture into something that will
hopefully be lucrative for our business.
Now the throughput of any business, and
a software business certainly, is money.
Because what is the job of
the machinery of a business?
It's to make money.
So when we are talking about these three
parts of the Theory of Constraints,
In terms of a software engineering
business, cost is still cost.
Inventory is code and throughput is money.
Okay.
Now, the big mind shift that happens
in the goal and then the theory of
constraints is that Western businesses
tend to prioritize costs as the most
important part of this machinery.
And that's why you see short
term solutions like layoffs
and things like that happening.
But if you look at the long term
success of a lot of those, initiatives
like layoffs, for instance, and other
types of cost cutting initiatives, They
are almost universally unsuccessful
in the longterm, unless there's a
complimentary plan to either maintain
or improve throughput in order.
In other words, the business's ability to
keep creating its product and doing what
it does and continuing to be lucrative.
You have to prioritize that, right?
a layoff is generally just a bandaid.
And if we look beneath the
surface, it can actually be very
detrimental to, to throughput.
When we have things like brain drain
in the organization, we have to later
hire new people when we realized we
laid off too many, has been happening
over the last year or so in our
industry because of AI and over
indexing on things like that, right?
So we actually hurt our throughput with
some of these cost cutting initiatives.
The important part of the theory
of constraints is that throughput
is the most important part.
The machine must keep doing
its job better and better.
Now, how does that translate to
the way that we deliver software?
All right, if the inventory's code.
And the cost is that developer
engineer actually writing code,
putting that code together.
then the throughput is the distance
between the time that the developer
is creating that code and the time
that code is no longer work in
progress and is out in the market,
making money for that business.
Anything in the middle, any time
that cost is still being expended to
work on assembling inventory and that
inventory has not yet been released.
That is all waste.
That's all friction.
And there's so many things that
can go wrong before we actually
release that code to production.
So are we starting to pick
up on something here, right?
A huge part of DevOps has been reducing
the distance between hands on keyboard
and creating the product and getting
that product actually out to market
and making money for the business.
I come from a time, a lot
of us come from a time.
When you would write your code,
you create a jar file or whatever.
You literally copy it onto a disc.
You walk it to another
part of the organization.
They pull that down to some testing
system and they pull it into some,
which probably doesn't match the system
that you were developing in any way.
and when they release that, there's really
not a guarantee that it's going to work
the same way in production, because back
then the production systems didn't really,
there's not a lot of guarantee that they
match the systems that we were testing,
the conditions were the same, right?
So we were talking weeks, between
being able to actually create
this code and being able to
release that code out to market.
Okay.
So this right here, prioritization of
throughput and reducing the distance
between the creation of code from
inventory and costs to actually creating
throughput for the business and money.
This is what we must prioritize.
This is what we're trying to optimize.
And that's very much what DevOps tells us
this, that the only initiatives that will
positively impact long term performance
are the ones that will increase throughput
while simultaneously decreasing cost,
everything else is not going to have
the long term effect that you want.
unless you think you can
break the laws of physics.
This is also where continuous
improvement comes in.
Okay.
we're also dealing with this inventory
that's sitting there, in between the time
that it's created and that it's released
out to production and making money for
the business is susceptible to entropy.
Second law of thermodynamics
and rot, right?
We see this in different forms
with code, code rot, like we've
heard that term before, but that
can mean different things, right?
That can mean like a dependency,
going out of date or some
vulnerability, being released.
And now we have to stop what we
were doing, working on this one
part of the code and make sure that
we remediate this vulnerability.
And if any of this happens while
this code is work in progress
and in flight, this can increase
greatly, increase the distance.
Between the time that we are
actually releasing the time
that we're writing code.
so this is where this notion of
continuous improvement also comes in.
it's battling entropy, right?
Sort of battling this ever present
sort of force that adds all this
variability to our work in progress
because nothing ever really sits still.
So as long as we're continually improving.
Something we're fine.
we're effectively outrunning entropy.
And that's where this, notion of
continuous improvement and moreover,
that it doesn't really matter what
you're improving as long as you're
improving something, because then
you're, you are using feedback to outrun.
Now, this is where this came from
the DevOps conveyor belt, right?
The, all this theory around, all
right, how do we shorten this distance
between hands on keyboard to actually
creating money for the business?
and how do we make sure that we're
prioritizing throughput, right?
this looks very much like the DevOps
conveyor belt at this point, right?
Always move forward.
Even if we break something, just release
a fix right afterwards, make sure that
our deployment frequency can be high.
that's our deployment
frequency Dora metric, right?
how often are we actually
able to get our code, out?
And so we have this wonderful conveyor
belt with all these different, this is
just one small, permutation and set of
technologies that might be representative
of a typical DevOps pipeline.
But this is where we, this
is why we got here, right?
Was because of prioritization of
throughput, because we needed to
build systems that could create
cultures of continuous improvement.
And could create high velocity,
constantly releasing types of systems.
Okay.
So why did free software become so much of
what's underpinning these platforms today?
Why is it, why is open source like
so essential, to being able to
build these types of platforms?
I really think about it in terms of the
friction created when we do something
without transparency and without
ubiquitous accessibility to our work.
And when we do something with that level
of transparency and when we make our work
available to as many people as possible, I
love to use, the story of Pythagoras here
to tell, I think, the cautionary tale.
I think, most of us are familiar with
Pythagoras, or at least the Pythagorean
theorem, a squared plus b squared
equals c squared, way to calculate
the hypotenuse of a right triangle.
But of course, Pythagoras, made, All,
so many, not all, but so many of the
contributions to modern geometry.
And more importantly, at the time when
he was teaching geometry and around 700
BC in the city of Crotone, which is in
modern day, Southern, Southern Italy,
Pythagoras ran a school of geometry and
there were two, a circles of the school.
There was the inner circle called
the, Mathematiquae or the learners.
And this was like the
inner circle of the school.
And these were the only folks
that were really allowed to learn
geometry and practice geometry.
Then you had the outer circle of
the school called the acoustematics
or the listeners, right?
And they were not allowed.
they were actually more sort of Aaron
running errands and stuff like that
and chores and stuff for the school.
They were really more like staff.
And then you had everybody else
who was not even allowed into
the school of geometry at all.
Now, geometry at the time, 700 ish BC.
Yeah.
In Crotone, this was the force
that was responsible for civic
infrastructure, running water, housing,
shelter, all the things that you
needed to build a modern city, right?
All that infrastructure, was, you
needed geometry to make this work.
And this sort of esoteric math
and language was being taught by
Pythagoras in this very secretive way.
All right.
And made a lot of people very unhappy,
which we'll get to in a moment.
Meanwhile, you look at somebody like Sir
Isaac Newton, who took what he learned and
published it, in what was possibly one of
the first engineering public domain works.
I like to think of this as one of
the first examples of something that
would be considered open source.
This was the publication
of Principia Mathematica.
This was Isaac Newton's, learnings and
math that he made available for to other
practitioners, to other people who wanted
to be able to take these principles and
apply them to their own work, right?
this is a much better type of
spirit, but it's also a much more
frictionless type of spirit, right?
This allows much more
accessibility to the knowledge.
And allows people to be more
free in the way that they create
whatever it is that they're doing.
Another great example of these open
societies, the Florentine Bodega,
where sculptors and painters and
artists and craftspeople would all
meet together to discuss what was
going on and to learn from one another.
Leonardo da Vinci was discovered
in one of these bodegas.
A more modern example
could be a Parisian salon.
again, an open forum where, different
people from society could talk
about the issues of the day in
an open and transparent manner.
These types of gatherings, and this way
of doing things in a more transparent
parent manner, this is why open source
makes so much more sense for building
large, scaled, cloud platforms and
the things that we build with it now.
Could you imagine, If something
like the TCP protocol, for
instance, were closed, right?
if what you had to run underneath
your cloud infrastructure and
networking were a closed protocol
that you had to somehow light, I
think nothing that we have would work.
Look at the Linux operating
system, the proliferation of the
Linux server operating system.
How much further, it's been able to
bring, DevOps, how much we've been
able to do, from an operating system
perspective, at every level of scale.
certainly there are some closed and
proprietary licenses for Linux, but
overall this is open source, right?
things did not end well
for Pythagoras, right?
Yeah.
There was a nobleman at the
time who felt that he should be
included in the Pythagorean school,
that he should learn geometry.
His name was Cylon, actually.
and Cylon would run Pythagoras out of
town, murder tons of his own students, and
ultimately Pythagoras would die in exile.
And we don't really have full
attribution for all of Pythagoras work.
It's actually very hard for us
to know how much of this work was
created by him, other mathematicians,
because, again, all of this was done
without any type of transparency.
Open source was essential to taking these
principles of frictionless development
and deployment that would build what
we think of now as modern DevOps and
platform engineering in removing access
to this, in, in, in removing, barriers
to accessibility to the software.
And making sure that we could build
these systems in a very frictionless.
And so now we have this, terrifying,
post Cambrian explosion of all of these
other types of solutions that come
together to build a modern cloud platform.
We have all of these different
solutions for database and streaming
and messaging and application definition
and API gateways and service proxies
for all of these different pieces.
And some permutation now of
these different pieces of many
times open source software.
is what we now refer to as our platform.
Now, to take advantage of this, to
take advantage of this new way of
deployment, this more ubiquitous and
portable means of deployment, we have
to start thinking differently about
the way that we write our software.
We actually have to code differently if we
want to take full advantage of this more
portable means of deploying our software.
The good news is there's a wonderful
framework that's already available
for this called the 12 factors.
It was put together by folks
from Haruku and other very well
known people in the industry.
And it's a very easy to understand
framework for reducing the amount of
friction in your cloud deployments.
Thanks.
Now, I won't make the claim that like
every successful cloud deployment has
to be fully 12 factor that is not true,
but there is an indirect relationship
between the amount of friction that you
will experience in doing your deployment
and in operating and maintaining
your code in these environments
and how 12 factory your app is.
In other words, the less 12 factor it
is, the more friction, the more tech
debt, the more toil you should expect.
When you're pushing this
app into production.
So of course it does behoove you to
get as far as you can, with these.
So what are they?
we go across different, characteristics
of the code itself, but in every, in
every factor, the important thing to
remember is really the goal of it, and
that is to keep the code portable and
accessible and visible, no matter what
type of platform it's running in and
no matter what cloud it's running on.
All right, so these are things
like, for instance, tracking all
of our code in one single revision
control, doing many deploys out of
that one single code base, right?
As opposed to, that way, that one
code base can very easily become a
trigger to launch a CI job or a full
deployment pipeline if we need to.
And any changes, can be triggered
off of that single code base as well.
All right.
dependencies explicitly declare
and isolate dependencies.
This is where, the shift in not
including dependencies as part of
our build has happened over the
last really couple of decades.
this is where we've got better ways now,
things like package Jason, in NPM, for
instance, that allow us to have these
really powerful and semantic versioning
controlled ways of declaring dependencies.
and that they're explicitly declared
and that they are isolated so
that no matter what, that part
of the supply chain can always be
rebuilt for the app in any cloud.
We want to store config
in the environment, right?
And more specifically, as we, as
you've seen, we've moved back to
the old environment variables.
And the reason for that is because
they're so Ubiquitous in every
sort of POSIX, operating system.
We have a concept of them.
So again, multi cloud, multi
platform, multi operating system.
We can use environment variables and
they're super easy to manipulate.
from outside of the platform.
So now that all of our code these
days is buried in, some cloud image
with some Kubernetes node deployed
on it was some Kubernetes job running
inside of it, like how many layers
of abstraction between us and the app
now to make all of this multi cloud
stuff possible, it's easy to manipulate
those environment variables from some
outsider at administrating system, right?
Within the operating system.
And it's ubiquitous.
Treat backing services as
attached resources, right?
Any type of database, media source,
anything like that should be
considered an attached resource.
And we, this is not a brand new pattern.
Like this is more like enforcing
patterns, like for instance, J and D I.
or other patterns that would create
abstraction between resources that
are needed by the application.
and, and the application itself, right?
How can we, decouple those things,
but also make it very easy for the
app to have access to those back
backing services when it needs to.
Separating our build and run stages.
Okay, CI versus CD, right?
making sure that our build and all of our,
inner work, Is happening in one, process
and then our stage to actually run the
code, which will be handled by automation
ultimately, and some other operating
platform, is separate, execute our app is
one or more stateless processes because
again, stateless processes are easy
to view and they're easy to manipulate
from an operating system perspective
from some outside administrating, agent.
Whether that's Kubernetes or
whatever, export services via port
binding, TCP, it's ubiquitous.
We've all got it.
So use port binding specifically as a
way to publish and export services so
that we can all agree on that model and
it'll work in every cloud, whether we're
talking about, security groups or we're
talking about ingress controlling, right?
As long as everything's happening over
TCP ports and we're using port binding,
then we're all speaking the same language.
Scale out via the process
model with concurrency.
Instead, by taking the processes that
are stateless processes, we are now
able to do that, which is great because
now we can scale those processes across
multiple containers, across multiple
clouds, and work out at any scale.
Make sure that our services
are 100 percent disposable.
Fast startup, graceful shutdown again,
so that we can pick the service up, run
it in some cloud, destroy it when we
don't need it anymore and leave no trace.
We, ultimate portability, dev prod parody.
a lot of folks love to talk about Docker
being this thing that's really, Improved.
I was sped up the way that, that we
can, get a quick operating system
layer and do something with our app.
And that's really important.
But another textbook problem that
was solved by Docker was this parody
between development and product
and production systems, right?
Again, I mentioned that when I.
was coming up as a developer,
like a lot of us were.
This was never guaranteed.
We were literally running physically
different services, servers, I should say.
you had to make, someone had to make
sure that, that config was synced
between those services and it never was.
and as a result, you
didn't have this parity.
And so the tests might pass in a QA
environment or staging environment,
you move to production, some tiny
thing is different, and the whole
thing crashes, and everybody's, in
a fire drill for the whole weekend.
And that was just what it was.
Docker helped us solve for this
big time by being able to provide
ubiquitous operating system layers
that would be common no matter where
we were deploying our app, logs,
treating our logs like event streams.
I mentioned those abstraction
layers before, right?
please don't make your admins log into
five different layers of abstraction
just to get visibility on what's
happening with your app, right?
Your app should be
Broadcasting its events.
It shouldn't be writing
to some log file locally.
It should be pushing those logs
out to some aggregator, Datadog,
whatever it is, that makes it very
easy to get access to those metrics.
And then finally, any admin or management
tasks that need to be run across the app,
there should be a one off process again,
so that this admin process can be run.
And even automated in the long
run by ubiquitous orchestration.
All right.
so great.
We've done all this stuff, right?
we have all this fantastic open source.
That's given us this amazing ability
to decompose into microservices.
And now we're, we were just
deploying the multi cloud and
everything's so simple and great.
No, not remotely.
all of this freedom and portability.
Has led in many cases to more
complexity and disorganization, right?
we really over indexed on velocity,
and we didn't always take the right
time to make sure that we were
doing things in an organized way.
And this leads to unnecessary friction
and toil for developers, because
this is the state of the art for
most companies right now, right?
We have, if you look at the bottom
of this slide, all these different
monoliths and many services
and microservices and things.
that are owned by different
engineering managers that were
worked on by different silos.
And they're all getting managed
over like spreadsheets or confluence
wikis or something like that, right?
These lagging systems of record that
then somebody has to go back and update.
And so of course they never get updated.
And so they're always out of date.
And so we don't know who owns what, we
don't know where our dependencies are.
we ended up tracking with things
that look like this, we have
our GitHub repos and our service
names and our Slack channels, but.
When anything has to change in this
ever growing service catalog, it
becomes so brittle and a system that,
that makes it very difficult for cross
functionally teams to understand and get
any type of usefulness out of, right?
So it's just bad.
So we need to be
rethinking this now, right?
we've now moved into a level
of platform engineering where
we have to take that step from.
orchestration and organization of our
services to true choreography, right?
We need to be able to add our final
layer of abstraction, which I believe
is the internal developer portal, right?
So what we're doing at cortex,
what's been done at backstage, right?
We need a single non lagging real time,
continuously monitoring system of record
that's accessible by every engineer.
And that can be used to align
standards and ownership and service
quality across the organization.
And if you'd like to learn more
about that pattern, in particular,
we are having the world's first
ever, conference in person conference
dedicated to internal developer portals.
It's happening in New
York city on October 24th.
and we would love to see you there
and talk more about this solution.
Thanks so much for your time.
I really appreciate it and enjoy
the rest of the conference.