My name is Nikita Melnikov.
I am VP of engineering at Atlantic money.
and today we'll talk about affordable
concurrency, about financial
systems, about its challenges.
And, how to use Acro model
to solve everything we need
in, this kind of systems.
So about me, as I've said before, I'm
VP of engineering at Atlantic money.
Also, I am Axe Sync of Bank and
the Axe Sync of Investments.
I have more than 10 years in FinTech.
I was working on high load systems.
So we have more than 300,
000 surplus per second.
And also I love Scala,
Golang, Postgres and Kafka.
Let's begin.
Let's take a look on the agenda.
we will cover a few topics.
So we'll go from, the problem.
Do the solution that I propose.
So the problem is about
financial transactions and,
what problems could we have?
after that, we will shift to traditional
approach and their limitations.
And, we, of course, speak
about a synchronous processing
about Kafka, how to implement a
synchronous processing using Kafka.
Why do we need it?
How it could help us.
And the main topic is actor model.
Of course.
let's start.
So what is financial transaction?
we will use our company as an
example, and, we will review the
standard process for our cases.
A customer can create
a transfer in our app.
So for example, you want to
send 100 to 90 euros to someone.
you're creating the transfer in our
app, you send 100 payment to our app
and we can send euros to your recipient.
Let's simplify it a bit.
So we are waiting for dollars.
We run some checks, we send euros.
Sounds simple, right?
but in fact, what happens
in the real world?
First of all.
As we discussed before, customer creates
USD to Euro transfer system, waits
for USD the same as before, right?
System writes the payment details.
So we should know, when we've
got your payment, amount, sender,
recipient, your bank information, and
any other information that we need.
After that system runs on checks.
What checks?
For example, we must check sanction lists.
We should check your payment
in our anti fraud system.
We should check your payment limits.
We should calculate fees and many
more, as many as you can imagine.
Of course, we have to exchange
currencies to send another
currency to your recipient.
And finally, we can send
EUR to the recipient.
Where is the problem?
Of course, there can be many
problems in terms of compliance,
operations, finance, and so on.
But we will review only one
technical problem today.
The problem is lost update.
Let's take a look on the diagram.
What happens here?
So when transfer system receive
your payment, we should find
proper transfer in the database.
After finding, we should check
the sender and the recipient.
For example, in our compliance service,
we are getting, okay, everything is fine.
So we can go further.
We are processing the request,
doing some correlations, applying
fees, exchanging currencies.
And finally, we should
update the transfers.
So just to set the status,
let everything is fine.
So we've paid out, the
money for your recipient.
Where are the problem?
The problem is When compliance
system decided to cancel the transfer
at the same time, while we are
processing the original transfer.
So the process looks mostly the same,
but after successful checks in compliance
service can decide to cancel the transfer.
So it hits in point transfer slash
cancel, and we should select transfer for
restriction and update transfer as well.
Let's take a look on the
transactions here on the left.
We have compliance
transaction on the right.
We have our payment, to our system.
So we are starting the transaction.
We are selecting transfer.
We are getting result.
So result of the same.
So ID one status created, everything
should be fine in both transactions.
After that, we are setting
different statuses for compliance.
We should set status
canceled for our payment.
We should set status payment received.
Okay, cool.
We're committing the changes.
Where is the problem?
The problem is here.
If we will select transfer right
after these changes, we can get.
undefined status.
So because we have two concurrent
transactions, and we don't know
what exactly we want to have
at the end, we cannot guarantee
the order of the statuses.
So the status can be undefined, it
can be cancelled, it can be payment
received, or any other, of course.
Let's try to solve it.
And we'll talk about For additional
approaches, of course, I don't
have the time to provide all
possible options, how to solve it.
And also we are limited by a
technology that we use now.
let's imagine we have
postgres database, right?
And we can solve it like, in,
in that way, we have database
transaction, how it looks like.
The same as before, we're
starting the transaction.
We are selecting transfer for update
now, and we can commit the changes.
Everything is okay, but let's try
to implement it on the diagram.
So this is the same diagram as before,
except just the one small thing.
In fact, just to selecting the transfer,
we are selecting it for update.
we are starting in from,
payment receiving process.
So we're selecting for update.
We're checking sender and recipient.
Everything is fine.
At that moment, compliance system decided
to cancel and restrict transferred.
It does select for updates as well.
but it should wait until we have
one open transaction for update for
one single row or for many rows.
Postgres knows that everything
should be blocked until the
first process will be completed.
so the one, the first process when we are
receiving the payment is, painting now.
So we are selected transfer.
We are doing some calculations.
We are working on the processing and
finally we do update on the step six.
Once we committed changes, we can
continue with the second process.
We're selecting, we already sent
select for update, requests from
compliance service to our database.
And, we were waiting for the
result and now the result is
finally here and we can continue.
everything is solved actually.
So everything is super simple here.
So there are only two,
database transactions.
We don't have any new abstractions or any
new tools, but where's the limitation?
Let's make a quick calculation.
So let's imagine we have processing time,
average processing time, five seconds.
And we have 100 operations per second.
That means that we should
have 500 active transactions.
Doesn't seem complicated, right?
Authors definitely could handle this.
And yes and no.
there are two drawbacks.
First of all, is resources.
we have many active transactions.
that do nothing actually, because we
are waiting, we are going to external
services, we are writing some audit data,
we are getting data from another service.
So many things.
So while, we do this transaction
is active, and we cannot work with
this, locked row, for example,
with this And the second point
is about your connection pools.
So I believe most of you have a
connection pooling system in your apps.
So for example, it can be limited up
to 16 connections to your Postgres
instance and, everything should be fine
actually, because we have different
transfers, but the problem will be
if you have multiple concurrent.
Transactions in the database,
let's imagine we have 16 concurrent
process at the same time.
So that means that the first.
Connection will be acquired
bar by actual transaction.
So we are, we got the
result from the database.
We start doing something, we are
processing it to five seconds.
And finally we can
release during this time.
The second operation will be
waiting and the third and the
fifth and the sixth and so on.
the.
Contention of the, on the lock and on
the database, in fact, if we want to
work with, the same transfer, it will be
quite a problem because at the end you
can end up with, just, empty connection
pool because every connection is busy.
and you cannot run anything
else on these connection pools.
You cannot serve customers request.
You cannot serve in other transfers.
here's the problem.
Okay.
Let's try to solve it in, in
other way, let's try locks.
Of course, locks can be implemented in
different systems in different ways.
But in fact, we'll today,
we'll talk about local locks.
And there's the muted locks.
Let's start with local locks.
in Golang, it can be done
via just a mutex object.
How it works.
we should run something on the transfer.
We are trying to acquire the mutex.
And defer a function to unlock it.
if mutex was already locked,
The goroutine will be.
We'll be painting, actually, we will
wait until, the log will be resolved.
Everything is simple, right?
But the problem is obvious, actually.
if you have multiple nodes, You have
multiple endpoints or processes or
whatever, or maybe, your consistent
rotor on engine X or any, another
balancer was broken or after start,
you can end up with, this scheme.
So one node holds a lock
local lock for one transfer.
And the knock note too, got a request
for the same transfer with different That
means that locks doesn't work at all.
So you don't need it.
let's try another approach.
So this is about distributed locks.
of course it's become a bit, a bit
complex because you shouldn't produce
a new infrastructure things here.
And also you should understand how
it works and your engineers as well.
So let's start with the diagram.
So the key difference actually
is that instead of just a
Mutex in a single node application, you
have distributed lock manager, how it
works, node one can request for lock in a
lock manager, and if it was not acquired
by another process, we can run the lock.
If node two, will try to
request the same lock.
It will wait so it works the same so if
node one has the access it can safely
access some resources and If everything
is done So we can just release the lock
and right after that lock manager will
run the lock to the second node Everything
is super simple here About storages,
actually, there are a lot of options.
We will just, just name a few.
Hazelcast, Zookeeper, etcd,
Console, Redis, whatever you need,
whatever you know, whatever you
like, so you can use everything.
what about limitations here?
Limitations are quite, Quite
complex, actually, because, under
load, it can be quite challenging
to understand how the system will
work because of problem of ordering.
So let's imagine you have multiple nodes,
for example, a cluster with 16 nodes.
they can be placed in a different
zones, in a different data centers, in
a different networks, because of many,
things just have different timing to
access your, lock manager, for example,
Hazelcast, or, for example, Zookeeper.
this is the first problem.
So we can't understand why we've got
the lock to the note that, for example,
call it later than the first one.
So it is quite challenging to
understand how it works just
because of problem of the ordering.
Timeouts.
there are actually multiple timeouts.
So first of all, it is
log acquisition timeout.
So we.
As a engineer should understand.
So I trying to get a
lock in our lock manager.
we should be able to, set some time
out because we cannot wait, infinite
time for this log because it just,
it will just hang in the process.
and, we should understand how
to set this time out, how to
wear and see this time out.
And, the second point is how
to manage this time out when
we already acquired the lock.
let's imagine we've spent three seconds
to wait for a lock and now we should
limit the time, when we process, when we
run actual logic, backends logic, right?
and we already have two points here.
So we should respect timeouts.
We should, respect holding timeouts and we
should understand how to work with them.
What should we do if
we didn't get the lock?
Probably everything should be fine, right?
So we just didn't do anything.
What if we got the lock, but we
lost the lock or the process was
crashed when we hold the lock?
this is challenging actually, so because
you should respect it in your code.
So every process should understand
that it can be, it can be dropped.
And the server can fail and
how to restore the process.
And you should understand this
partial state that was in, that was
implemented during the lock holding.
And, of course, potential deadlocks.
That means that, for example, we
want to hold a lock for transfer, for
check, for customer, for recipient,
and, The modify the state, we
need to touch every object there.
and potentially it can be challenging
to understand and to go and see
that there is no deadlock installed.
Deadlock is when, for example,
we've got a lock for transfer.
We are trying to get lock for recipient,
but other process started with the
recipient and after the transfer.
So the second.
The second transaction got a lock
for cpn and after that it's trying
to get a lock for transfer, but it
holds in this lock is for this, the
first note for the first process.
and it is quite challenging and, I don't
know how to guarantee that there is no
deadlocks at all instead of just, testing.
But, testing is super complex
in distributed systems.
So I don't have so many times to
test distributed system on my own.
Okay.
Let's write the switch to
a synchronous processing.
Let's.
First, define what the transfer model is.
Actually, it is a finite
state machine, right?
because transfer has multiple statuses,
State transitions occur via commons.
Each state defines a load commons and
commons trigger actions and state changes.
That's all.
So finish state machine is same, right?
So it's just a, switching before
states because of something, because
of some events or commons or whatever.
So we cannot go from payment received
to payment waiting just because,
it's impossible in our domain.
Let's take a look on the code First of
all, let's define transfer for simplicity.
It could have only ID
and status What is face?
I'm here being a state machine.
So we have a transfer created.
We have common receive payment
and we can move our transfer
to payment received, right?
So let's define statuses.
We have created payment, received
checks, sent checks, painting and so on.
So all our tree of choices and,
transitions from status to status.
And of course we need to define a command.
So a command is something that can
happen in your, in your application.
It can be done via HTTP endpoints,
your PC endpoints, broker
messages, time or whatever.
in fact, we need just something to
tell to the transfer that it should
move from one step to another.
and let's take a look on the code.
How would we handle this?
But in this common, of course, we,
we won't review everything here.
We will start with something super simple.
So payment, receive payment common.
First of all, we should check the status.
Got to simplify it.
We ignore error handling
here, error cases and so on.
So just the pure logic.
We should check the status.
we've got a receive payment command.
We know that status should
be only status created.
If not, we should throw some error.
We need to write payment details.
We have to set status.
We have to save the state.
And we should tell to the transfer
that we need to run some checks
to move the transfer further.
Okay.
Thank you.
You're welcome.
Cool.
Requirements for asynchronous processing.
So now we know the model.
Now we understand the transfer
is actual FAST SAM model.
And, we need comments, we need messages.
we need states.
Let's, make some
requirements for our system.
First of all, we need
communication through messages.
messages are comments
or events or whatever.
This is something that we can tell
from one service to another service
that, it needs to run something.
Also, we need one at a
time message handling.
That means that if we got a command
for transfer A, only one command
can be executed for this transfer.
If we have the second, it
should be queued somehow.
Also, we need durable message store.
That means that we should keep our
messages for some time because of,
node failures, location, failures,
data centers, handlers, and many more
because of many reasons, actually.
So because of we, we would need
to replay messages somehow.
Maybe we need analytics, maybe we
deployed something broken and we need
to restore the state, on, on some.
Date or time, and let's take a closer
on communication through messages.
Actually, here is super simple, right?
So we have a producer, we have
a consumer, we have something in
the middle to deliver messages.
Let's call it message broker.
producers send messages to broker
deliver messages to consumer.
Consumer tells to the broker that
everything is fine, so we can continue.
And producer can send another message.
The same one at a time message handling.
So we already discussed, right?
So we want to send three messages,
but at the same time, message
consumer can handle only one.
Our transfer queue is something that
can order the messages by producing
time, delivering message one by
one to the consumer, and Transfer
queues should wait until we've got
acknowledgement of that message was
processed and everything is fine.
And the same for message
two, for message three.
we can think about it as a lock.
So we, we have written something to
the queue one by one, and it will
be consumed by the consumer one
by one as well, in the same order.
Thank you.
Durable message store.
So it can be, there can be a lot of
examples actually, because we have many
things that can break our system, right?
So we need just, something
to replay the message.
If our message consumer was broken or
even if external service system is broken.
That's all.
Okay.
Let's talk about Kafka.
And of course.
Kafka is one of my favorite
technologies overall.
So yeah, let's begin with some
basics because we need it just
to understand how it works.
Kafka have topic as a root
entity, in the architecture.
So topic is just a feed.
It, can contain multiple partitions, one,
two, three, four, five, Unlimited, of
course, like a reasonably unlimited, and
Kafka is, distributed system by default.
So it can be, deployed in multiple, in
multiple servers in multiple locations.
So let's just think that we
have free brokers and they can
coordinate the data somehow.
So one topic has three
partitions, and each partition
will be placed on the broker.
Of course, there are replication,
some guarantees, some settings,
but we don't need it for today.
About partition of sense, as I
told before, so we can think about
this message queue as a, as a lock.
So partition one partition can have
Message zero, message one, message
three, and, partition is the,
actually the sequence of the messages.
So one topic can have multiple partitions.
One partition can have multiple
messages ordered by, date time.
About routing.
the most interesting topic here.
Let's think about
producers and partitions.
Let's imagine we have multiple producers.
And we have multiple partitions.
So how can we know,
where to place a message?
Because a partitions can be
written, in concurrent mode.
So we can write to partition
one and partition two, multiple
messages at the same time.
There is no problem.
there are multiple options.
First of all, of course, it is possible.
around Robin.
This is we will write the partition
zero, partition one, partition
three, partition zero, partition
one, partition three, and so on.
But the interesting thing here is
what exactly we need is the key.
Kafka will calculate a hash of the
key and the message for the key
will be placed into the partition.
So for example, we have
a transfer message.
We have a key equals to transfer ID ABC.
So if producer one and producer
two, we'll write the same message
with the same key to the topic.
So that means that both messages
will be placed into one partition
into the same partition.
So this is.
this is the thing that we should keep in
mind, because this is, how it will help
us to solve overall concurrency things.
And let's speak about producer guarantees.
There are a lot of settings.
So of course, Kafka is
a quite complex system.
in terms of, how to, set up it
properly and correctly, but let's
speak about the most simple things.
we have an ax setting.
So that means that when producer
right message to the topic.
We can set this ACK settings, if it equals
to zero, no ACK management is needed.
So that means that Kafka, leader
instance will get the message
and said, okay, I've got it.
Everything is okay.
Of course, it has low latency
because we don't write anything
to the disk or in other servers.
And of course, there is no delivery
guarantees because, if we get, if we
have a call to Kafka with x0, Kafka
said that, okay, everything is fine.
So I got the message.
And right after that, the
leader replica failed.
That means that there is no message
still because we didn't wait for that.
X ones, meaning the leader
acknowledges the right in case of
leader failure, data loss is possible.
So in this case, so the leader
replica will tell to the producer
that, okay, I got your message.
I written everything to, to my
store and, but if the failure
will occur, data loss is possible.
As I said here on the slide.
And that's all in sync replica.
So does it mean that all
followers of their, leader,
should acknowledge the message?
Of course it has highest
durability and highest latency.
Okay.
let's revisit our requirements
for a synchronous processing.
Again, communication through messages
done, the durable message store done.
One at a time message can be,
this is interesting thing.
Consumer requirements.
We want to have one at a
time message processing.
Each transfer should be
processed by a single consumer.
Consumers should be able
to scale horizontally.
And now we have an
abstraction as consumer group.
So we want to scale our application
by servers horizontally.
So It is super simple in Kafka, actually.
So we have a topic, we have multiple
partitions, we have consumer group.
So we can tell Kafka that, this
instance, this consumer, is
related to consumer group A.
and when we Deploy two instances,
this, the same consumer group
will be respected in, in Kafka.
So partition one will be, distributed
to consumer instance one, partition
two and three to consumer instance two.
here's the limitation.
So you can't have.
Consumer instances, more than a
number of partitions in your topic.
So just keep in mind, if you have,
for example, 16 partitions in your
topic, the maximum number of your
applications, application instances
in the same group will be 16 as
well, and we've got everything we
need messaging system using Kafka.
So here is everything that we,
We decided to change, right?
So we combined the system from,
abstractions that Kafka provides to us.
their units, For producers, we have
compliance commons, we have verification
commons, we have payments commons,
we have many commons producers.
We have partitions for our transfer
topic, for transfer A, for transfer B,
for transfer C, and we have consumers.
So here is on the diagram, we have a
routine of how we can handle and going
see one at time processing, right?
Because in the consumer group, we
go and see that, the order of events
within a single partition is ordered.
Also, we have consumer groups,
so we can handle multiple
partitions at the same time.
And there is no option to get the, Message
for transfer in multiple consumers at
the same time, just because of routing,
because we have, because Kafka will route.
transfer a into partition one,
transfer B into partition, do you
transfer C into partition three?
And that's all.
Okay.
what about the actor model actually here?
let's review.
It's core concepts.
First of all, actor is
a fundamental units.
A single message passing, state
isolation, sequential message
processing, location transparency,
fault tolerance, and scalability.
It can be implemented in our
asynchronous system, right?
Most of this, but let's
do important disclaimer.
This is not full implementation of actor
model as Erlang or Kafka or maybe another
framework, we will use the actor model as
a concept here just to build the system.
There is no need to implement all feature
because we don't need supervision,
location, transparency, et cetera, because
we just don't need it because Kafka
got, all complexity, into their domain.
So we could think about
actors as a product.
processor of commons with some
mailbox of messages for processing
and for and state isolation in our
actual state of the transfer or
maybe user or recipient or whatever.
we only need the fact that we
can, Interact within, messages.
We have state isolation.
We have sequential message processing.
We call it a one at a time message
processing before we have full
tolerance because if our server will
fail, consumer, and restarted after,
it will join consumer group and
Kafka will rebalance, We'll rebalance
partitions over new set of consumers
and of course, scalability, so we can
deploy as many consumers as we want.
Of course, it, it has a limitation up
to the number of, of, topic partitions.
Okay.
Let's try to implement
Acro model in our system.
Yeah.
We will ignore some things
of factor model here.
It's just an inspiration and how
it can be implemented in, in a
tool that can help us to build it.
Let's start with interfaces.
So we have, we need to have a storage.
the storage is quite simple.
So we have to create a, new, just to
produce a new structure to work with that.
So key here is for a key as for a state.
So new, get, and put,
everything is simple.
and as we discussed
before, we have a package.
Postgres, it can be sharded, maybe
not, so it doesn't matter, so it
can be Cassandra, it can be whatever
you need, even local caches, Redis,
just MongoDB, whatever you need.
We have an actor, so actor
should have just one single
function, it should be receive.
Receive function gets state and comment.
And should return new state.
So if it's just a function that knows
about current state and the comment
and produces new state or a force
error mailbox, this is after mailbox
for our Kafka, we have to know about
key state and comment, and that's all.
So we will deploy our application.
And we will start consuming,
messages from, transfer topic.
And, this actor mailbox, we'll know about,
roads in key state and comment to call
actor and the fourth common producer.
Common producer is something
just to tell to, to a actor
about a new common for message.
So of course it should know
about key and column as well.
So for example, through this interface,
we can tell to, compliance system
or even self transfer, topic about
a, Hey, you have a new comment here.
Oh yeah.
And this is about what,
what this types means here.
Kafka consumer, actually,
everything is super simple here.
So record, Kafka record, has a key
and has a value key and value, just
the pure area of bytes and the soul.
So we have to somehow to decode
it into the time that we need.
also we have a storage,
so we will try to get.
the state from storage, if
it's not found, we will try to
create a new, new stage here.
After that, we pass state and
comment into, actor and we are
getting new state, that's all.
So everything we need is
just to update the state.
And here is the problem.
of course, we have a database and Kafka.
So that means that we have a
problem with double writes.
Double write problem is when you
have a Postgres in Kafka and you
cannot go and see the transaction
here because if Postgres will fail,
overall, transaction will fail.
If Kafka will fail, we write, we
write state to Postgres, but we
cannot send, messages to Kafka.
So let's adjust.
our code a bit.
It goes old box pattern.
Actually, it's quite popular.
So I believe many of you know about it.
so we have a new transfer, new
transaction, and our storage should take
transaction as a, as an argument as well.
Everything we need is to produce not
only new state, but effects as well.
Effect is something that
should be executed later.
For example, thinking to Kafka.
in our case, we have new state
and array of facts, and we need
to persist everything altogether
in one single transaction.
So there is no Kafka at all.
If you need to send something to
compliance, actor or user actor, you can
just put everything in your database.
Here is, everything is solved actually.
but the last thing is how to deliver
your messages from Postgres to Kafka.
actually you have many choices
since you have a Debezium, you
have Debezium connector, so it can
listen for while log and, deliver
messages to Kafka in your topic.
Also, you can write your own,
your way, how to manage this.
It's just up to you.
Another important thing is about toxic
messages, as we discussed before,
we will try to consume the message.
If something goes wrong, for example,
we've got a transfer common, receive
payment, but payment was already received.
So that means that, we should.
return some error and ignore the message.
And of course, if you have a large
core base or many developers, so it's
possible that you potentially can miss
something, and, process it incorrectly.
here can be toxic messages.
Of course, if you can, you can
build, many things on top of it,
but, let's discuss it a bit later.
toxic messages are messages
that cannot be proceed.
messages.
can be caused by incorrect message
format, incorrect message version,
incorrect message data, or logic errors.
For example, incorrect actor state
and incorrect message processing.
What to do with that?
So for example, you can
implement, Delayed messages.
You can implement a counter in
some system just to count how many
times your external service failed.
And right after that, you can
mark your message as a toxic.
So you cannot process it,
10 times in 10 seconds.
That means that it should be toxic or,
division by zero, or, incorrect status
for your state or anything else, actually.
So the fact that, that.
The toxic messages are messages
that you should ignore, but
you should handle it somehow.
So this is just a simple,
dead letters queue.
So that means that, new state,
after receive method returned.
Toxic error, and we want to
handle this letter somehow later.
So this is dead letters queue
right in the Kafka as well.
And, we are producing the same
record to, dead letters queue.
We can run some monitoring analytics,
anomaly detection and many more.
And let's, let's review final
implementation for Kafka consumer.
That's before we have.
We have state and storage.
We have new state effects and error.
If error is toxic, so we can
send it to dead letters for
investigation or for alerting.
And, we have our box
pattern here and that's all.
So actually this is implementation
for your Kafka consumer to work
with, It was a transfer or with
your actor, everything's done here.
And, let's just take a look
on a small function here.
So this is.
Or how to handle comments, in
your transfer actor as an example.
we've got received payment comment.
for example, we already checked
that the status is a payment waiting
or another status that we need.
we are computing new state
by applying payment details.
We are creating new side effects.
for example, send checks command
to, transfer to move it further.
And, we can produce new transfer
and, for analytic purposes and
return just a new state and effect.
That's all.
So this is the whole, infrastructure
logic for, for your actor.
That's all.
So you can reach with your own logic.
And, everything, all complexity
is not here, isn't Kafka.
So your code is quite simple here.
let's make a conclusion here.
so by combining principles of actor model.
And Kafka is a messaging backbone
with its own partners, of course, with
additional, deployment unit, that's Kafka
servers and, things that you need, to,
to set up Kafka correctly, actually,
for example, Amazon MSK does it pretty
well, actually, and, all concurrency,
Issues can be handled by Kafka just
because you're writing, imperative
code, you're doing things one by one.
You don't need to think about,
Hey, here can be another product.
So we need to lock it somehow.
So we have a, just a key of messages
and a synchronous communication.
So that means that we can just place a
comment for a transfer in order with Q.
And, order topic in order to partition
in the topic and, your transfer
consumer will handle it one by one.
And that means that you just
evaded concurrency at all.
So there is no locks.
The, there is no concurrent,
And that the based on elections,
you don't need to think about,
I, I need to go for some data.
data can be inconsistent.
If you need something, just
place a comment and the, another
actor can tell the result back.
So everything you need, just, finish
state machine for your entity, or even
if you, maybe you don't need, FSM at all.
So you have simple counter,
you have, dead letters check.
actually it doesn't need, actors at all.
So there is a lot of options how to,
how to manage concurrency, but this
approach, help us just to avoid it at all.
Thank you.
And questions.