Hello everyone.
I'm Kumar and I'm excited to share my
insights gain from two decades of hands-on
experience in technology and engineering.
Throughout my 20 year journey, I've had
the privilege of working on diverse transf
transformation projects that has shaped
my understanding of platform engineering.
At scale.
Today, I will share one of our
most impactful implementations.
Healthcare analytics and
that is platform engineering.
At scale building cloud native
data infrastructure for one
40 terabyte of data monthly.
Healthcare analytics.
Healthcare organizations
face unique data engineering challenges.
Managing hundreds of terabytes of
sensitive data monthly while maintaining
HIPAA and GDPR compliance create
significant complexity combined with
legacy system constraints, demands for
self-service analytics, and the need
to integrate diverse data domains.
These challenges directly impact
medical innovation and patient care.
Modern platform engineering
solutions have become essential to
address these critical barriers.
As a Fortune 500 biopharma company, legacy
infrastructure, severely constrained
research capabilities, the platform
access only 15% of available healthcare
data sources with the researchers
facing two hour query rate times.
The monolithic system couldn't scale to
meet growing data demands effectively
limiting innovation and delay
potential medical break breakthroughs.
Our platform engineering transformation,
increased month monthly processing
capacity from 15 terabyte to one
40 terabyte reducing processing
time by 80% and accelerating drug
discovery timelines by 4.2 months per.
We developed a platform as a product
approach, treating infrastructure
as a product with research and
clinical teams as customers.
By implementing self-service capabilities
and automation, we achieved 67%
faster development velocity and
reduced processing time by 80%.
The platform integrated compliance.
Requirement directly into infrastructure
code while enabling team to access
resource without engineering bottlenecks.
This transformation delivered $2.3 million
in annual cost savings and increased
workload capacity, demonstrating the
value of treating platforms as products
rather than just infrastructure.
Our healthcare data platform leverages
a W Services to process our one 40
terabyte of monthly data efficiently.
Through automated e retail pipelines,
multi-zone data architecture, and
dynamic scaling capabilities, we
achieved an 80% reduction in processing
time, the platforms metadata driven
framework, and choose data quality
while maintaining HIPAA compliance.
Through built-in security controls,
this architecture uses S3 Amazon
Redshift to store to access the data
and Amazon S3 to store the data.
There is also addition layer in
between, which is nothing but the
copy command you can use to load data
directly into the Amazon Redshift.
Our INFRAS infrastructure as code
approach integrates compliance
and automation directly into our
development deployment pipelines.
Through automated infrastructure
provisioning and self-service capabilities
we have achieved faster developer velocity
and seamless scaling from 15 terabyte
to one 40 terabyte monthly capacity.
Platform's compliance as code approach
and embeds regulatory requirements
infrastructure, while automated
scaling and optimization have delivered
major cost, annual cost savings.
This transformation reduce deployment
times while maintaining consistent
security controls across environments.
Our platform engineering
initiatives delivered significant
outcomes across key metrics.
We achieved an 80% reduction in
processing time through automation,
increased workload capacity by
three 40%, and realized $2.3
million in annual cost savings.
Developer velocity improved by 67%
through self service capabilities.
Monthly processing capacity scaled
from 15 terabyte to one 40 terabyte.
These results demonstrate the substantial
impact of our platform transformation.
Our platform transformation
delivered significant
healthcare innovation outcomes.
Drug discovery timelines accelerated
by 4.2 months per compound per month.
Through faster data processing, clinical
research accuracy improved by 45 40
5% through enhanced data integration.
While clinical trial success rate
increased by 23% through improved
data accessibility, these results
demonstrate tangible impact on healthcare
innovation and research efficiency.
And our platform engineering approach
creates infrastructure as a code with
research and clinical team as customers.
The mindset shift transformed our
delivery model and team interaction,
enabling healthcare teams to focus on
innovation rather than infrastructure.
Our legacy to cloud near transformation
followed five key phases.
Assessment, evaluated capabilities
and defined target architecture,
foundation, established cloud,
environment and compliance frameworks.
Migration.
Executed workload transition
using blue, green, deployments,
optimization, refined architecture,
and enhanced cell service capabilities.
Innovation, expanded platform
capabilities with advanced
analytics and ML integration.
This phased approach enables
seamless transformation.
While maintaining operational continuity,
we face key challenges, including
organizational resistance,
skill gaps, legacy integration
requirements, compliance concerns.
Balancing standard ideation with
flexibility solutions included executive
champions driving cultural change,
embedded platform engineers phased
migration with clear metrics, compliance
as code implementation and golden parts
with escape patches for edge cases.
This comprehensive approach address both
technical and organizational challenges.
The implementation focused
on four practical strategies.
Start small and scale fast with
defined high value use cases.
Embed compliance into platform
automation and CICD pipelines.
Measure platform value through clear
KPIs, including developer velocity
and resource utilization, and build
internal community through feedback
forums and train training programs.
These approaches grow successful
platform adoption and continuously
success in healthcare.
Platform engineering requires four
key elements, product, mindset,
self-service, acceleration, automated
compliance, and meaningful metrics.
Tracking these principles enable
our platform to deliver 80% faster
processing and accelerated healthcare
innovation through improved.
Clinical research accuracy
and drug discovery timelines.