Thanks for joining me.
My name is Samuel Barufi and I'm
a Principal Solutions Architect
with Amazon Web Services.
Today I'll be presenting about how
you can craft a secure and scalable
generative AI solution using AWS services.
My goal is to show some open source code
and open source solution that allows
you and your platform engineering teams
to potentially have your own private
solution to expedite with Gen AI.
So let's get started.
So this is a very common
scenario across any road that.
It's pretty much uses technology.
You're probably spending hours and
hours writing repetitive tasks, writing,
repetitive code snippets, emails to your
manager, maybe reports to your leadership,
creating different proposals if you're
working on consultancy, and it's a lot
of tedious and it's overwhelming, right?
The image just illustrate how potentially
all of us feel on a normal day, as we a
believer and progress on our job duties.
but what if we could find solutions
that are private, secure, and available
for us and our teams to really
alleviate the border, the boredom of
those repetitive solutions, right?
We're all familiar with tools like
such, HDBT, Cloud, and perplexity
and many other ones that have become
very popular in the last two years.
so my goal is not to show you
a replacement of those tools,
but potentially you will find.
show you an architecture and a
solution that is open source that you
can build on top of that and really
have full control of your data and
security and deploy that on AWS.
So because this is platform engineering
conference, it's important to set the
context a little bit on how potentially
a solution like the one I'm about to
present could help platform engineer
or platform engineering teams.
so it's very important that
platform engineers focus on.
As a catalyst for developer
productivity, right?
So you want to enable a
lot of self servicing.
solutions and really reduce
operational bottlenecks.
generative AI really allows you
to become a much more productive
developer and platform engineer.
You also want to navigate the
complex, of modern tech stack.
AWS is an example that we have over 200.
services and getting in depth and
getting to know really then, it takes
a lot of effort and Gen AI can help
us expedite that learning curve.
you also want to balance
innovation with stability.
We don't just want to move as fast
as possible with no stability because
they'll probably give us some downturn.
that is another goal that you should
have, and he wants to, he wanna ensure
consistent security and compliance,
and that is potentially one of the
main points or why potentially you
should consider, building a solution
for your team that have full control
rather than buying something outside.
or if you're not comfortable,
it's completely up to your
choice and you wanna enhance your
customers, which are developers.
You wanna enhance their
experience by using your platform.
So with that said, at a very high
level, what I'm going to show to you
today, both from a solution architecture
pattern and a UI is you're going to
have a, a place, a UI, or you can input
text and images, that, that solution
is hosted within your own AWS account
with your own security controls.
And you have full control about the data
and, the authorization, who authenticated
it, who has permissions of the solution.
Once the, that data is processed, you're
going to send to some AWS services
that we're going to talk today, like
Bedrock, where it allows you to.
Call large language models or
multimodality models, on a pay as you
go per token input and output token.
So you're going to have that processing
and generation for you, and then you are
going to have the polished content, right?
So what I'm going to do next, I will show
you some capabilities of the solution
that is that I have open source as part
of the AWS samples GitHub repository.
And, just keep in mind, this is not
a, recommendation for you to just
use the solution that is available on
GitHub as it is, but also for you to
look at it and build on top of that.
Also look at the solution as an
architecture pattern for potentially
building applications for your teams,
for your platform engineer teams
with a similar capability, because
it does solve a lot of the problems
that generative AI have posed to
us in the last couple of years.
So let's just look what this
solution could look like.
So the idea of this solution
is you're going to have a UI.
the UI is going to be authenticated.
So you're going to be able to create
users and each users is going to have
its own secure sandbox environment.
In this case, what on the demo here,
you have a playground platform,
which is a very simple place
where you can input some text.
You can select models.
Right now, the solution supports
cloud models for Entropic.
through AWS Bedrock.
So in this demo, you can see
that it has a couple of things
that are really important.
First of them, first of them is, you
are authenticated into the solution.
Second is it supports the
streaming of your response, right?
So you're going to send a prompt
like right upon about New York, that
response is going to be streaming
from, AWS account into the UI here,
and then you are able to manipulate,
copy and do whatever you want, right?
That is really important.
So that is just one of the
capabilities is Playground, but
Playground, there is nothing new.
It's just a way for you to maybe
do some testing and play around.
The really, important benefit of this UI,
if you think about it, or this solution
is the capability of create templates.
Templates are nothing more than
a way for you to create prompts.
So if you're familiar with generative
AI, it's really important that
you do a lot of prompt engineering
for whatever you're trying to do.
So in the example on the screen, let's say
you want to create a prompt that is really
good at Creating product names, right?
I know it's a simplistic example, but
you can think about anything here, right?
So what the tool allows you to do
is to create templates that can
be reused after the fact by you.
Or if you decide by other people, you
can see that the templates allows you to
have a visibility of public and private.
What the public and private means
is public means only people.
They are authenticated to your deployed
solution who have access, but every user
within that deployment will have access
to it, the user needs to be authenticated.
A private visibility means only you as
the creator will be able to consume that.
and you can create prompts.
You are going to allow you to
input, a model selection that you
have, curated that prompt for.
A system prompt giving a specific
instruction and finally the user data.
If you see here on the
user data and putting.
the input data between, curly brackets and
the dollar sign, that is just an automatic
variable that when you're going to be
able to consume the template, I'm going
to show in a moment, when you consume the
template, whatever data you're going to
be providing is going to automatically
replace that variable for you.
And you have easy searchability.
as a user now, you can either
consume already curated or created
templates from your team, or you
can create your own templates or
make those templates available for
your team by setting as public here.
But it's important to highlight public
just doesn't mean that anyone outside
the internet will be able to access.
It's just within your deployed solution
here, users who have authenticated
will be able to consume that
within this box of authentication.
Once you have created the templates,
you can go into the activity tab and you
are able to select specific, prompts.
In this case, I will show you
an example that I want to use
the product naming pro template.
So I want to create names for my product.
I select the product template, and
then they give a description, right?
Descriptions like, Hey, I want
you to create a noise canceller,
headphone, headless headphone.
how do I actually create that?
So you'll be able to see that what
happens here, he actually sends to AWS
and Bedrock, the whole prompt curated with
your data, and he provides you with the
proper output, and then you can inspect.
What is those, what that template,
if you're an advanced user can
inspect what that template is adding,
like the system prompt and what
is getting replaced the input data
with whatever information, right?
and you were able to change those
advanced settings of every time
you do the inference, right?
So now from your teams, these become
very interesting because It allows
you to have multiple templates that
a user can be an export, but it can
share the template and that prompt with
other people for easy of consumption.
Another very important feature
of the solution is the capability
of providing images as an input.
All those core three models that the
solution is currently using from Entropiq.
support what is called the multi
modality, meaning it supports
text and also image as inputs.
So in this case, I have uploaded
a headphone picture and I've said,
could you please describe the
image uploaded in details to me?
And you can see it describes in detail.
Now I'm using the playground here,
but this vision capability can
also be added into the template.
I can have a template that has
curated prompt and once I consume
the template on the activity, I can
input images that enhance my data,
input, to the system itself, right?
so far you were able to see how you
can easily check the playground,
how you can create templates,
which are curated prompts, how
you can consume those templates.
a common thing that these generative
AI solutions provide is the capability
of using a chat conversation, right?
So the tool also provides you
with the ability to use chat.
And as you might expect, the chat
allows you to also select templates.
So you can keep a history, you can keep
the context of your conversation of the
first prompt in this example, here in
using again, the product naming template.
And I've asked with a specific
description and it was sent to the model.
And I received some, answers back and
I can say, the names are good, but
could you please come up with five?
more different names that are a bit more
catchy and are great for marketing, right?
And you can see that I will send it again.
the context and all of that is being baked
already from the back in the backend that
we're going to demonstrate in a moment.
And if you are an advanced user and you
want to choose different temperature or
top K or top P, you have that capability.
We haven't talked about another capability
of this tool, which is the history.
Every time you use the playground.
the activity, and the activity
or templates, that data will be
stored on a database that you have
control within your AWS account and
you can check the history, right?
So you have the capability.
so far we, I've shown you the capabilities
and the end product, but okay, you've
seen the capabilities, you've seen, the
potential, the benefits of this tool.
But you might be asking me right now.
how does this work under the hood?
What is the architecture that you've put
in place in order to make this happen with
the streaming, with the authentication and
all that, how much does the cost, right?
How can you be so sure that
it's cost efficient, right?
So those are all very good, great.
Those are very great questions.
And my intent for the next, maybe
15 minutes is to really answer
some of those questions to you.
So the solution here.
So the name of the solution that we
have open source, and I'm going to
share you with some of the links and
some of the calls that you can see
the solution aims to, the name of the
solution is employee productivity,
improve employee productivity with
generative AI assistant example.
That is the name of the solution.
What it aims to do is to automate a
lot of the repetitive tasks with AI.
And it's all built on
AWS serverless services.
We're going to talk
about that in a moment.
And Bedrock.
We're also going to talk about Bedrock
in a moment if you're not familiar.
The benefits is it
boosts your productivity.
It really streamlines workflows
with the reusability of templates.
It is scalable because you're going to
be able to have one user or 5, 000 users.
And the application should scale.
With those, growth of users because
the serverless capability and it's open
source with a very simple deployment
that I'm gonna show on the demo, the
instructions and on GitHub for you.
but remember, this is
an architecture partner.
It's not a full fledged solution.
I'm not here selling the solution as for
you to go and deploy in production and
say okay, Sam has told me to do this.
It's already, this is an architecture
pattern that you can look at example,
build more features, build new
capabilities, change specific settings
to meet your customer, your own company
demands or requirements and so forth.
Let's talk about some of the services
that we've used into the solution
before I share an architecture diagram.
So here are a list of all the services
that are going to be used if you deploy
the solution on your AWS account.
So you can see a list of nine services.
so let's just start with a very,
I'm not going to, I'm not going to
go and explain depth of services.
My goal here is just to show at a high
level why we are using all these services.
So all these services have in
mind the idea to be pay as you go.
So we are not going to
provision any services.
You're not going to have any commitments
for, months or years of consumption.
It's literally pay as you go.
So as your growth.
If, your usage grow, your cost
is going to grow with that
and also decrease with that.
So because this solution is a fully
API driven architecture, we are using
Amazon API gateway for all the REST API.
So every time you are saving a new
template, every time you're trying to
retrieve your history, every time you are,
sending a new data to the model itself,
it's saving that data using REST API.
Thanks.
But then the second flavor of API gateway,
which is a service on AWS is WebSocket.
And this is a very important service
because on the solution, that the
data, every time you send some,
requests to the solution, the data is
getting streamed back into your UI.
And the way this is done
is by creating a WebSocket.
So each user and each web page that he
used, It's gonna create a web socket
connection to, API gateway, and then API
Gateway Web Socket will actually use a
Lambda to call whatever services in this
case bedrock in order to retrieve the
response that is generated by the larger
language models and send back to your, ey.
We have S3 here.
S3 is used in a couple places.
So first it hosts the ui.
The UI is built on React.
so the UI, it's stored there.
And then it's also used every
time you upload new images for
the multimodality capability.
It's using S3 to store those
objects, those files for you.
Cognito is our IDP service.
So Cognito is where you have
the capability of signing into
the system, having a password
authentication and authorization.
And Cognito integrates really heavily
with the REST API and WebSocket API.
So every time you're trying to
call those APIs, you need to be
authenticated and provide a token to it.
And all the code that I'm going to
share with you that is available
open source on the AWS Samples GitHub
have that description and capability.
Sean ddb here is the database of choice.
Is a NoSQL database
available for Pay As You Go?
super scalable solution on AWS
DB here is storing everything.
Is it storing your chats?
Is storing your, templates,
is storing your history.
everything that there is,
data that is being stored.
MDB is that, that, that database.
And because this mdb.
by default is encrypted and it's going
to be deployed on your own account.
You have full control of the data
premises, and how you decide to
encrypt, or, your, maybe you just want
to keep X amount of, you just want
to keep data for X amount of days.
You have that capability as well.
Two, three more services here.
we have CloudFront.
I'm just going to jump on CloudFront,
which is the content delivered
network capability to host our UI.
So the UI is going to be hosted
on S3 and CloudFront to make that
available across multiple servers
around the world that AWS has access.
So when your users access those,
it makes it very easy to consume.
It also does the HTTPS
encryption on your front end.
WAF then is integrated with CloudFront and
you see an architecture diagram to then,
create, security rules for avoiding, DDoS
attacks, SQL injection attacks, cross
site scripts attacking, maybe you want
to limit, the access into your system for
specific countries or maybe block some
countries, WAF gives you the capability.
And then finally, it's Bedrock.
And I have a couple of slides for
Bedrock because really this is the
generative AI solution that allows,
this whole architecture to be put
in place and be super, useful.
So Bedrock is the easiest way to build
and scale generative AI applications
with foundational models on AWS.
Bedrock is a very feature rich
solution for this specific use case.
And this architecture that I'm showing
to you is we are using Bedrock to
inference large language models,
foundational models through a single API.
So the solutions by now only supports
entropic cloud and cloud models.
Bedrock has support for, dozens
of different large language
models from different providers.
And you can use a single API that you
literally can test the prompt and the data
for whatever model that is available in
Bedrock and receive the response, right?
So that's what we're using, the
capabilities and the benefits of using
Bedrock is if you're familiar, the
amount of computational that takes
for, For any person to host a large
language model, it's quite significant.
So what we are doing here is we are
letting AWS manage all that compute
and you have a pay as you go approach,
meaning you're every time you send
an inference to Bedrock, you're going
to be paying on different models.
We have different costs and that can be
checked into the AWS, pricing page for
Bedrock, and you're going to be paying for
the input tokens and the output tokens.
What are the benefits?
First, you don't need to pay for
all the computational, GPUs to be
up and running 24 7, but also it
allows you to have a pay as you go.
So if today you have a lot of users
consuming this platform, you're going
to pay for whatever they consume.
if in the next month you don't
have anything, you're not going
to pay anything for bedrock.
No data is stored.
No data is used for training any models
on bedrock that is documented and
is, is a guarantee that AWS makes all
the data that you sent are your data.
We don't, AWS doesn't store
and AWS doesn't use for
training any future models.
So it's full control, private
privacy by default, and it doesn't
use any of the data moving forward.
the solution itself uses a combination of
different models from Bedrock, but mostly
focusing on models that are from Entropic.
Entropic is one of the leading
research labs that AWS and Amazon
have invested and partnered very
heavily, and it's available on portal.
On Bedrock, they have this quadtree.
model family in this case currently.
And by the way, depending when you're
watching this presentation, it might have
changed because new models are coming
up very often, but as we speak on, and
recording on August 22nd, four models of
the COD3 family are available on Bedrock,
which the most powerful one is COD3.
5 Sonnet, which is one of the
best models in the industry.
Not just the best model for Entropic.
all of them have vision capability.
Each of these models are going
to have different pricing.
Opus being the most expensive
one, the biggest one, but it's
still on the CoD 3 family.
And of course CoD 3.
5 is the most intelligent
because it's on the 3.
5.
Entropic has already announced that
they're going to be coming up with 3.
5 Haiku, which is the
smallest model and 3.
5 Opus, which is still going
to be the largest model.
Which you probably expect to be one
of the most intelligent models, but
that is not available there The tool
allows you to pick those models, right?
and if you remember from my demo, you
can just look back, you can just pick
whatever model you want from Cloud
and you know depending on The prompt
and the capabilities you require,
you might choose to go with 3.
5 sonnet or cloud free hyco, because
that is what actually going to, provides
you with the biggest, intelligence,
that pricing needs to be kept in mind.
So this is the full
architecture of the solution.
Finally, what you can see
here is you have on the top.
Hopefully you can see
here, let me just move.
Oh, let's sorry.
Let's move my mouse.
I don't know if you see my mouse.
I don't think you can see
my mouse and I apologize.
but what I meant to, oh,
you can see my mouse here.
if you see here on the top, the web
application flower, the cloud front and
S3, by the way, I'm looking on the side
because that's where I have my monitor.
that's where the UI is hosted, right?
So the UI is a React application.
that is just using MD
framework and components.
and you can look at the code,
you can change the code,
you can create your own UI.
But this architecture is using React,
we are just creating the static files,
starting the static files, HTML, CSS,
and JavaScript on S3, and then having
CloudFront creating an endpoint for us
that is distributed across the AWS Edge
locations for CloudFront, and putting
in WAF to make that application secure.
Then everything else here where
you see the REST API calls.
So every time, for example, you
need to create a template or you
need to save a history or you need
to retrieve the history, the way
it works, you have API Gateway.
And by the way, I didn't talk about
Lambda, I just realized, but API Gateway
integrates very easily with Lambda.
Lambda is the serverless compute
function as a service solution on AWS.
It allows you to write a small code.
for whatever language.
In this case, there are, in this
architecture, there are lambda functions
being written in Python, lambda
functions being written in JavaScript.
You can choose for other languages.
So every time you invoke an API behind
the scenes API gate, we invoke the lambda
might be running for like maybe four,
400 milliseconds, 700 milliseconds.
You're only going to pay for whatever
milliseconds that is running.
let's say you are creating a new template.
The way it works is.
You call the REST API, you
need to be authenticated.
So you can see Cognito here is
doing an authentication for you.
If you're not authenticated,
you cannot, call, that API.
You might be, you, if you try to
call the API, you're going to get a.
deny requests, because that is by
default being done by API gateway
and API gateway has integration
with Cognito by default, right?
So all that layer of authentication
is being done on the Cognito and
API gateway, which is something
that AWS provides to you.
but the other capability, which
is really important one is on the
bottom here, and you can see where
you have API gateway app socket.
So when you log in into the UI and
you send any type of request into
the solution itself, the way it
works, the user is going to create
a WebSocket into the API gateway.
Then the user is going to
start using that connection of
WebSocket to send the request.
That request will go to a Lambda.
The Lambda will therefore call Bedrock
with whatever model you define on the UI.
Bedrock will process and do the inference
and charge you by input and output tokens.
That is going to be sent back,
to the API Gateway WebSocket.
And then API Gateway WebSocket
will know which socket connection
that user requested the data.
You put that back in and send to the UI.
All of that is encrypted end to
end on the WebSocket connection.
And if you have any images from the
multimodality capability, you're
going to upload them into S3.
At the end of the time of inference,
this Lambda Python streaming is going
to download from S3 and send to Bedrock.
So that is the capabilities and how
you configure, this application.
And I'm going to show you in a
moment that this is all done with
this, a few commands should easily
deploy this end to end solution.
So let me talk about costs, right?
And so it's important to highlight
that this cost is public available,
on the back on the AWS pricing
page, but it might change, right?
This cost is also based on the U.
S.
East 1 region.
Different regions might have
different prices for services.
So you might need to take in
consideration if you plan to
deploy this in another region.
But, how I decided to provide you
with a, highlight of how much this
solution would estimate and by
the way, it's just an estimate.
There is some variables that is very
hard to estimate is, let's think
that your deployment to have 50 users
and each of those 50 users, we use
this tool around five times a day.
And every time they use the tool,
they're going to input around 500 input
tokens and 200 output tokens, right?
This is just an, a scenario
I'm trying to put together.
So you understand what
you can see here is.
The other AWS services cost is
always going to remain the same.
This is the WAF, this is the
Dynadb, this is API gateway.
This is always going to remain the same
for this estimate, but the more users
and the more consumption you have, this
might increase a little bit more, right?
so just keep that in mind because,
but it's not going to be exponentially
more, it depends on how you're doing.
If you go to the GitHub page and I'm going
to share, you can look at the pricing
calculator that I've shared, and then you
can just add your, specific inputs or even
email me if you have any questions and
I'm happy to help you do the calculation.
But what you can see here that
depending on the model you use, and
by the way, you can use a combination
of models, but I'm just putting in
these specific, the specific slide.
Let's say if you only use core 3
haiku for all those three, you 50
users and five times a day, the
whole, the total cost of application.
It's literally only 19.
32, which is much more cost efficient
than, for example, a subscription
for one of these GNI chat solutions,
that are out there, which normally
would cost 20 plus dollars, right?
Plus you have full access, full control
of your data on your own AWS account.
You can choose different models.
So for example, I would
highly recommend using quad 3.
5 sonnet, which is the
most intelligent model.
And you can see that it equates to 50
and 20 cents, 26 cents a month, right?
Country Opus, of course, going
to be the most expensive because
It's, it's the largest model that
Entropic has made available, but
it's one of the most impressive
as one, especially when Cloud 3.
5 Opus is going to be made available.
So that is what I wanted
to show to you about cost.
but in terms of.
In terms of what can you do now?
So here you can just click on that
button off the open source repository.
You are able to just click
on that button, navigate.
I'm going to show in a
moment, I have a demo.
It's not going to be a demo.
It's just going to be show.
it's going to be a demo of the tool
and show you the GitHub page, but by
clicking the GitHub page or scanning the
secure code, you're going to see all the
details that I've shown to you today.
Even the GIFs that are here for the.
The tool itself, how do you deploy, how
do you make changes, the architecture
diagram, it's all made available.
So it's a very simple and easy
to deploy on your AWS account.
It's going to have the
benefits of pay as you go.
It's going to be secure and
deployed on your own AWS account.
So let's jump into a demo now and
then we'll finalize the presentation.
Awesome.
just very quickly, I just
want to show you the GitHub.
So if you go to the GitHub page, feel free
to start the GitHub, project if you like.
but if you scroll down, you're
going to see a lot of, information.
So you can see, for example, the
summary, we talked about the benefits
that I've presented to you today talks
about, why we've created the solution,
why it's using, why it's useful as an
architecture pattern, but potentially
as a starting place, for you and
your internal teams, and they scroll
down, you can see the architecture
diagram that are presented to you.
so you can look at these, please feel free
to ask questions, reach out if you want.
and then it talks about the
code itself, the structure of
the GitHub repository, right?
So we have a folder for the
backend where all the information
for the backend is stored.
we are using SAM, serverless
application model, framework to
actually deploy this whole solution.
Behind the scenes, it's just
file formation, It just deploys
a CloudFormation for you and
it created all those resources.
and then you have the front end folder.
The front end folder is just, literally
the React application that gets deployed.
but because we wanted to make it easier
for people to deploy, we have created
this shell script called deploy.
sh.
And I'll show you instructions how you
can easily deploy this into your account.
The deploy.
sh not only deploys the back end,
but also deploys the front end.
And that also So if you want, it
deploys the default templates,
and the default prompt templates
that comes with the solution.
So if I look at the templates that are
available on the default templates,
adjacent, if you're not interested in
that, or if you want to add, you can just
change and modify the specific format of
this Jason and rerun the deployment and
you create the templates that are there.
you can see some of the requisites
that it requires for you to deploy this
solution if you're running locally.
So you need like Python, you need AWS
SAN, you need a Linux environment.
Or if you're on Windows, you should
have Windows sub Linux system.
You need PyJS and you need JQ.
And of course you need to enable the
Bedrock models on your AWS account.
Here it goes into instructions
on how to deploy locally.
You can see that we have the deploy
a sage script that you can set
the regions, you can deploy this,
whatever region you wanna make.
If you want to be sure that you
have a good solution, we want to
make sure the best solution is.
This is the solution that
I used for my everything.
You can go to Xcode.
command with just the region And email,
by the way, this email is required because
this is going to be the admin user that
is going to be used for your application.
you use just the single command and
the simple command you run and pretty
much deploy everything front end,
back end, log, create a user for
you, create a temporary password,
and upload the templates as well.
But if you just want to deploy the backend
or you just want to deploy the front
end, you can use these commands, but you
can also use these commands to delete.
If you want to delete everything,
you just run the deploy dash delete,
and you'll delete all that for you.
So it goes into details here.
You can also use cloud
shell to deploy this.
So if you don't want to deploy
locally, you can just run cloud shell.
And if you're not familiar, what
cloud shell is literally just go
here and you click on this button.
this is culture.
So this is called shell.
It's just a Linux environment that
you have access for free on AWS and
you can use this Linux environment
following these specific instructions.
Please do follow these specific
instructions to use as the deployment.
So you can use cloud shell and so forth.
So if we scroll down, you can also use
cloud nine if you want, which is just
an idea available in AWS to deploy.
So you have instruction for that.
Once he finalizes, you should
see a screenshot similar to this.
That has been deployed successfully.
Once it has been deployed successfully,
you're going to give the URL from
the cloud front and then your user
and then your password, right?
And then once you log in for the first
time, you ask you to change that.
The other thing that it
shows you is the gifts.
So you can see all the
gifts that I've presented.
If you want to showcase your team members
or tests, you can see all the gifts that
I presented to you are available here.
And then you have an
estimate monthly cost.
And remember when I talk about the pricing
for bedrock, you can click here and you
can look at the different model providers.
For example, if you go to entropic models,
you can see each price for a thousand
input tokens and a thousand output tokens.
It's available there.
And then finally, the last thing
I want to show you on cost.
So let me scroll down.
We have this pricing page here.
So if you click on this calculator,
You'll be able to see this calculator,
which gives you the idea, and you
can see this for US, it's one region.
But if you want to change for the
remaining services, not Bedrock, because
currently Bedrock is not supported on
the pricing calculator or database.
For anything else, you can
change the variables and you can
get, receive your own estimate.
and of course, here are some
more recommendations, like if you
want to contribute or like key
considerations in terms of security,
it's all described here in depth.
but here's the tool.
So like the way it works, the tool,
I'll show you just do a quick demo.
You need to log in here, right?
So you just put your email here.
I already have a user, so I'm just
going to log in behind the scenes is
authenticating with Cognito, right?
And on the playground, I
can just ask a question.
Another thing, another feature
that I haven't mentioned that I
think is important to highlight, it
has support for full code syntax.
So let's say I want to write a code.
create a CloudFormation template, where
I have a EC2 name test and a new VPC.
You can define the CIDR
rank for the VPC, right?
I can send these.
Here I can choose the model, right?
I'm just going to use Cloud 3.
5 SONET because it's the best model.
And here, when I click submit
behind the scenes, remember
it's calling my web socket.
And then it's changed, it's calling
the WebSocket, the Lambda, and you
can see it actually, proper formats,
the CloudFormation template, my
CloudFormation template is YAML, so
you can see here if I scroll down,
it has created, the template for me.
This is you creating the
templates, creating the EC2
instances, creating the outputs.
The cool thing here, and even
gives you the explanation.
The good thing here is you
have these buttons here.
So any cleaning click cop all, it was
going to cop all the output for you.
But if you have code, you can
just click on the copy here and
it just called the copy for you.
So it's easier if you're not put
on an ID or something like that.
but the chat is pretty cool, right?
So let's say I have
this chat and let's say.
I have this, let's actually do this.
Let's talk to chat and let's say,
create some Python code that has some.
Very bad bugs because I want
to see if I can fix, right?
So let's just ask my chat to
create that Python code, right?
The first time I send the
message might take a while.
The reason it takes a while is
because it needs to create some of
the database entries, but every future
interaction is a little bit faster.
So it has created the code.
So what I want to do, I'm
going to copy this code.
And I create a new chat and I have
this template, which calls Python
bug fix, and I'm going to paste
the code here and let's see if my
template, which, it comes by default.
And this tool helps me
fix Python bug codes.
I can just, and this is just an
example that potentially has.
as a platform engineer, you'll
be dealing quite a lot, right?
So you can see that he
provided the code snip.
It has a few issues and issues, but
that's, here's the correct version.
I don't know.
I haven't gone through this
just hypothetical example.
You can see this specific fix here.
It talks about the problems in
the original code and so forth.
You can say, okay, this is great.
Could you rewrite this in Node.
js, JavaScript for me, right?
So the same code.
So the chat will keep the conversational
context so he knows I've talked about
it, and I can finalize, say, summarize
our conversation so far, please.
And you can see it's
streaming very quickly.
I've, if you look here, the model
I'm choosing is quad three haiku,
and that is the model I'm using.
So it talks about the
conversation, what I've taught.
So we talk, the conversation
summarizes that I provide a
Python code in my analysis.
issues, then I provided the correct code.
Then you asked me to rewrite
from Python to JavaScript and
finally provide the JavaScript
code with the proper information.
so I could use just a template.
You can see the template
is here just as its own.
And if you look at the template, if
you go here and look at the template,
you can click at this option to clone.
I don't want to clone, but if
you want to add it, you can see
that the template it just sets.
a system prompt saying your text to
analyze provided by the encoded snippet
and identify any bugs and so forth, right?
And it's using the cloud three model,
and so forth is just, here is just
the input data to provide, right?
I can clone.
So you can see, okay, it's a
copy and I can save a new one.
And it forces me to save
as private because there is
already one that is public.
So this is the capability I want to show.
Hopefully this makes sense.
Please reach out on LinkedIn if you have
any questions, shoot me an email and happy
to provide you some guidance on how to
deploy these and build on top of that.
generative AI provides a lot of limitless
capabilities for us builders and platform
engineers to build on top of that.
So thank you so much for taking
the time and watching my session.
have a great rest of your
day and hope to see you soon.
Bye bye.