So guys, let's get started.
As I said before, Lux is
a live blow of our system.
They can record everything.
What just be once, it can be good
thing, bad thing, routine, and unusual.
As loggers has different levels
like warning, error and stuff.
But when you running a modern platform,
you generate not just hundreds, but
millions of low entries every single day.
So we gotta separate available signals
like em, emerging outage or a security
incident from all the background noise.
That's where embedded contact
agents really come in.
The challenge of logs, think
about the scale of the problem.
In the microservices based architecture,
each service produces logs.
Multiply that by dozens of services.
Multi, multiple environment.
It can be like staging,
production, QA as well.
We have different countries
they locate in different regions
like Europe, Asia, and us.
And as I said before, it we, since we use
microservices their amount can be like.
Thousands at least.
For example, when it comes to find
company, like as I know, Netflix
has 700 at least just let's imagine
how many of them has Google.
So most of those logs are boring things.
Like for an example, connection
open or user disconnected, or
some web socket is open and stuff.
User logged in, cache kit and stuff.
It can be a lot.
But hidden on those streams are
the needles and the hashtag.
The early signs of something going
wrong, maybe just request as timing.
More than usual, maybe login
failures are increasing.
For a specific country, probably some
database chart is slower than the rest.
It's not really something important,
but when we have huge amount of
them is getting the problem, so
we got recognized when it's okay
and when finding them is a noise.
Is a real challenge.
And why is it's really hard?
Local analysis is hard for free reasons.
As I said before, we have huge volume.
You simply cannot you cannot have humans
reading through millions of entries.
Even automated dashboards
can be overwhelming and.
Heterogeneity, just let's imagine
it's really frequent ation and one
team is using some strict structure
using js o with some specific keys,
but some other just using simple
string and it's creating the case.
And the third, the lack of context.
The, a single error message means
nothing without knowing what
cells are happening in the system.
Timeout may be fine, maybe it's
happening frequently, and team know
what's happening, but when it happens
during checkout your e-commerce system
on a Black Friday, it's a huge problem.
So traditional tools
don't give us the context.
They just tell us accurate, and
it's up to us what we gonna do.
And we have, by the way, some
classical approaches what people use.
The first one, first hold based rules.
For example, when we have more than
a hundred errors in a minute, we
got sent an alert to the slack.
Or any other messenger
to check it on our graph.
And so it's simple and easy to
implement, but it often creates
alerts when nothing is truly wrong.
And sometimes it misses subtle issues.
For example, when developer is
doing something important and he
gotta change, he gotta change his
context and check what's happening.
It's getting problematic.
The second statistical methods
using moving averages re
that scores to reactivations.
These are useful for metrics like
latency or throughput, but they don't
understand logs in their semantic sense.
And of course the third one.
Basic ML models like isolation forest,
or clustering these three logs as a data
points and try to identify outliers.
It's promising, but the models often
break down when new types of logs appear,
which is actually when we need them most
because we learn on the logs that we saw
before and why classical approaches fail.
So why do this method
fail in the practice?
They create too many false positives.
If every little deviation triggers an
alert, engineers stop paying attention.
We we've, we had all the situation,
the pages goes off, you look
and it's something harmless.
They like business context.
As I said before.
They gotta change their context and
have poor generalization When the system
encounter something new, classical models
simply say, I don't know what is that?
Which either means they
ignore it or they overreact.
In short, this approach
has flu us with noise.
While missing a signals
we really care about.
And let's enter our
embedded context agents.
What is alternative?
This is where embedded
context really come in.
Instead of positive, and
passive rules or static models.
We embedded small intelligent components
directly into Observ JT Pipeline.
These agents are.
They embedded, they live inside our
system, analyzing logs in real time.
The second one, contextual.
They add business and
system context to every log.
And autonomous agents, they don't
just look at the data, they act alert,
correlate, even fix small problems.
In this case, we don't need to to
change the context of developer.
It's like moving from passive CCTV
camera to an active security guard.
And what does an agent do?
So step one, it ingest logs in real time.
Step two, it enriches them with context.
That means attaching metadata, like
which service, which deployment,
which user, which region.
And step three, it analyzes this
enriched logs using ML models,
embeddings, or pattern recognition.
And step four.
It acts data might mean raising
an hour cluster, an anomaly
with previous incident, or even
recommending an automated mitigation.
It's not about just seeing data,
it's about understanding it
and taking the right next step.
So to make it more clear,
let's use an analogy.
For example, let's consider the mall where
we have security cards, and in the mall we
have cameras that can observe everywhere.
And it can check that people walking
shops, opening deliveries happening.
That's useful, but it
cannot be interpreted.
So for that, we need some
guy who will check everything
and says, what's happening?
The guard doesn't just watch, they
interpret if someone is walking around
the night in a closed mall, that's
suspicious and he need to react.
But the same person walking on
a Black Friday during a sale.
Nobody will pay attention.
There's different context, makes logs
without agents are just raw video, but
logs with agents are actionable insights.
So let's talk a little
bit about architecture.
Initially it'll be something
simple, but later we will deep dive.
Regarding system architecture, how
it looks like logs are ingested.
For tools, it can be like fluid
D logs test or open telemetry.
There are a lot of solutions.
So they go through contextual enrichment,
really, agents at metadata, like
user id, region deployment details.
And the next one is detection core.
It can be all the things that we discussed
before, like classical approaches, but
as well it can be ML models that analyze
the sequence of logs and look for ena.
And finally the action layer.
This is where alerts are raised,
dashboards updated in some cases at
automated response or trigger it.
It's a pipeline in jest and
reach, analyze and connect.
So in the next slide, we'll take a look.
Some primitive architecture, a
lot of details are omitted but
some of them I will just consider.
So let's imagine this pipeline.
We have a few things.
The architecture on the screen illustrates
full end to end and a malo detection.
That system processes logs from multiple
sources and enriches, then individual
information, applies machine learning,
and finally roads to result in the
different destinations and for visibility.
Action automation.
The first one is, as I
said before, log sources.
The pipeline begins with
a diverse resources.
It can be some application
logs regarding APIs, like air
performance transactions as well.
It can be some infrastructure
logs like service containers,
cloud resources and stuff.
And the third thing is, security thing.
For example, when we have like
assess attempts or Audi trials or
firewall events, and this represent
a whole telemetry of the system.
The second step, this
is a local collector.
It can be, for example, open
telemetry or fluent geo and stuff.
A log collector normalizes and
ships the logs in real time.
Fluent tea, for example, responsible
for collecting log files.
Parsing them and applying
lightweight transformations.
It gives us when we have different
format to standard standardizes
this ensure consistent structure
and reduces noise before ingestion.
The next step is message bus.
Guys that we have billions of logs
every day and we need to send them
somehow without breaking the system.
So the solution here can be
some message bus, and in my
opinion, the best one is Kafka.
When we normalize the logs,
then we push them to Kafka.
Message Bus Kafka provides
durable, scalable, high throughput
streaming, and decouples produces
local collector from consumers.
Analysis engine enables replay
and breath pressure handling in
case of downstream slowdowns.
And the next step is embedded
contact station and the core sheets.
The embedded context agent, which
orchestrate normal detection.
It consists three main layers.
The first one, contact enrichment ends.
It can be like metadata session info, user
device contact, and the stuff helps models
understand the story behind raw evens.
ML models is ation.
Forest detect outliers in high dimension
data and out encoder reconstruct
normal patterns, flag deviations.
But by the way here may be
used as well LLM based models.
It can be a little bit problematic.
And later in this presentation I will
explain why, but it provides semantic
semantic interpretation, animal
reasoning, and correlation across logs.
So decision layer, aggregate
result from multiple models.
And applies rules for an logic to
classify, lys, determine d severity
type and the required response.
Of course, the next step is
backend services, where we need to
orchestrate everything, what we got.
In the previous layer this component
act as a hub, that roads classified ano
analyst into different destinations.
It can be, for example, some dashboards
like Grafana, Kibana and stuff.
And for example, wanting understand
that this is something urgent we can
notify by Slack and other messages.
As well, we need to keep this data somehow
to, to use it again, and for this purpose.
We have a databases like Postgres,
Radis and elastic search and stuff.
And for example, we can react on it.
At the moment.
And for that we can use like
Kubernetes auto mitigation.
It triggers workflow, for example,
scaling ports, a flow that will
detected or blocking an IP.
If instructions suspected
reduces MTTR mean to recovery
to eliminate manual steps.
Or some other actions can be
done on the programming language.
And the last step is end users that
get this information and can react.
So this architecture provides resilience,
scalable, and intelligent animal
detection pipeline, local collection and
normalization, and ensure clean data.
Kafka guarantee scalable streaming
and reply and EBITDA engine
combined context, ML and decisions
and output ensure both human
visibility and automated remediation.
It balances the real time detection with
historical analysis and automated action,
making it suitable for modern cloud
native and security crucial environments.
So now let's take a look on
detection Core ML models.
Detection core uses a
combination of techniques.
For example, out encoders, compress
and reconstruct lock patterns.
Plug in anything that doesn't fit.
Isolation forest are great
for identifying outliers.
Log bird brings transformer based s and
capturing the semantic meanings of logs.
For example, we have as well deep lock
use LSTM to model sequence of log events.
And by combining these agents
can handle both structured and un
structured logs, as well as a new
pattern we've never seen before.
Let's talk about
multi-agent collaboration.
Another important point, we don't rely
on a simple agent to do everything.
Instead, we use specialized agents.
One focuses on network traffic,
another on authentication pattern,
another on performance metrics.
They, each of them act as a domain
expert, but they can of course,
collaborate with shared bus, can
be usually kaf or a similar system.
And together they can form a
system of small, specialized.
Experts.
For example, let's take a
look on different agents.
We have three main Skinners.
The first one, for example, when we
got some problem like 500 TTP, when
we did some order, the agent compares
this with MBX of non neuro classes.
Not much.
It's in new, so it raises anomaly flack.
This gets an attention of DevOps before
an error spreads without the agent.
This error might just be borrowed in
a thousand of line of logs and gone
notice until customers complain.
The next scenarios when we have,
for example suspicious logs like the
authentication agent notices a spike in
the login attempts from region, we don't.
Really, you usually see the activity.
We need to enrich a metadata.
For example, we see same API
range, same data frame or timeframe
and hundreds of flights logins.
It's not just technical error,
it's potential and tech.
And by flagging it early, we can prevent
account takeover of data breaches.
And the last scenario that I would
consider is early performance warning.
For example, sometimes the
system interest looks fine.
Like we don't have problem with RAM or
CPU and latency Dashboards are green, but
agents are noticing more and more looks
like slow query detected individually.
It doesn't trigger an
alert, but trend is obvious.
The performance agent raises
an normally alert, something is
degrading and engineers can fix
it before it becomes an outage.
This is power of context and
sequence based detection.
So let's take a look more about ML models.
For example, deep log we got in 2017.
It's a pioneer sequence
based on ly detection.
So it's a kind of recent
technologies special log brought.
It's 2021, applied to transform to logs.
Log AI from Microsoft as an
open source library for log
par and antibody detection.
And as well there is a dent
free, for example, that helps
build streaming log templates.
This is a building blocks and agent.
Combine them with domain specific
context, so I didn't say something before.
Some about LLM, like charge
GPT where it can be fit.
This is actually a very good
thing for example, analyzing.
Patterns and human friendly language
that makes a great tool for engineers
as well day to day activity, but it
has some limitations, unfortunately.
For example, it's not real time.
Do you know how it's happening?
We are doing some kind of request and we
got a wait until we got the full request.
Yeah, it doesn't
continuously monitor logs.
It only works when you ask.
And it's really hard to scale 2
million of logs line per minute.
You would spend a fortune trying
to process all logs with this way.
And finally, there are
issues of privacy and cost.
As guys, it costs a lot, many
logs, contain sensitive data, send
sending everything to large models,
not always safe and affordable.
Of course we can use like local
models, but still it's not like a
thing that can resolve everything,
now let's compare a little bit chat.
GPT or LLM, but l ML agents
that we discussed before.
The reality is following LLM and
ML agents serve different purposes.
For example, agents, they can be
real time, they can be scalable,
they can be domain specific, cheaper.
But Chad GPT is a great explanation
of course, but still it's not
suitable for billions of re requests.
But the best thing we can
use, like a hybrid approach, I
think this is the best setup.
Agents continuously scan and
detect analyst in real time.
They raises alerts, feed dashboards,
and trigger automations with
something serious is found.
But when we're talking about LLM, it
helping engineers quickly understand
what's happening, summarizing patterns
and suggesting possible root causes.
I guess this approach will
give us the best results.
So let's take a look a little bit
benefits from embedded context agents.
What are the benefits of
using cabinet context agents?
Easy.
They reduce noise by
filtering out false positives.
They operate in real time, giving
you early detection and extensible.
You can add new engines for new domains.
They integrate seamlessly with the
DevOps workflows and CICD pipelines and
bring intelligent closers to the data.
Let's take a look.
Some challenges.
But let's be honest, it's not easy.
There are challenges like training models,
especially when it comes to the LLM based.
It can be expensive.
Context must always be on up to date.
New deployments, new
services, snowflakes confis.
Explainability is hard in if
an agent says this, an anomaly
engineer want to know why?
And agent coordination is tricky.
Multiple agents might
overlap or even conflict.
This is serious.
While we still solve as a community, let's
take a look a bit the future Directions.
First rack, four locks.
Combining retrieval of similar
incidents with generative models.
The second self-healing systems agents
that don't just detect animals but also
fix simple issues an automatically, as
I said before, for example, with the
Kubernetes that can kill the ports,
but it's still not something huge.
And the third federated anomaly detection
agent across cluster, sharing their
knowledge to improve detection globally.
This is where the field is going, and it's
very exciting time to be working on it.
Let's take a look a little bit.
The use cases, for example, when
I was talking about DevOps for
DevOps, agents are game changing.
Imagine a deployment pipeline
as a new version roll out.
Agents watch the logs in the real time.
If unusual error spike beyond
what expected during the world
they adjusted automatically fly
or even roll back the deployment.
This reduces downtime
and makes releases safer.
And for example.
It can be used as well for security.
Agent provide another layer of defense.
They monitor login pattern,
user behavior and error errors.
If they detect an ly, say a sudden burst
of failed logins or unusual, API calls
from a specific region, they raise an
alert by coaching this, by catching
this early, you can prevent incident
before they escalate into breaches.
So let's me conclude.
Logs by themselves are just noise.
But by the embedded context, agents
logs are transformed with the
meaningful and actionable signals.
These agents bring context, intelligence
and autonomy into log analysis.
And for example, if we combine it
with like systems like Charge GPT
or other LLM, they empower engineers
to detect, understand, and respond
to problems faster than ever before.
And most likely, this is the
future of platform engineering.
Smarter, more proactive,
more adaptive systems.
So thank you all for your attention.