Hi.
I am Satish Gola.
I bring over 17 years of IT experience
with nine plus years deeply focused
on Vow vault implementations across
both commercial and r and d in the
lifecycle life sciences industry.
I have led global rollouts, legacy
migrations and automation initiatives
that streamlined operations for top
pharma clients like Bristol and Mayor.
BMS and Pfizer.
Today I'm here to walk you through how
platform thinking combined with AI and
structured content is fundamentally
changing the way regulated submissions
are delivered, especially in high
stake areas like rare diseases.
So let's dive in.
Let's start with a problem on an average
bringing a therapy to market, which
takes around several years, especially
more like 10 years, and shockingly,
40% of the time is spent on managing
documentation, but not innovation.
So every day of delay means we are losing
close to one to 3 million every day.
And more importantly, patients are
waiting and a single clinical document
has to go through six to eight review
cycles and abortion conflicts, or
which are like constant pain point,
these inefficiencies at months and
sometimes years to the entire process.
Why the traditional approaches fail.
Today's regulatory and content process
are slowed down by paperwork, disconnected
systems, and lack of coordinations.
Teams in clinical, regulatory
and commercial areas often
work in an isolation, leading
miscommunication and repeated works.
Even a small content change can
trigger full re-approval cycles,
and within each country demand.
It has different localized documents,
things getting harder and harder.
Day by day, but there is a better way.
How can we make this better?
By connecting the platforms that unify
teams and tools and reusable content
blocks that adopt to different markets
without starting from sketch, and then
automated workflows that reduce back
and forth, speed up and approvals.
The opportunity is very clear.
We need to engineer efficiency.
By moving static documents to
structured content platforms,
we gain a massive speed.
This think reusable building
blocks, workflow automations,
and global scalability.
This is not digitalization.
It's about transforming the
way the life sciences work.
Modern platforms like we all
are leading this transformation.
Contents content as component
means documentation can
be reused across markets.
Workflow automations allows
for parallel reviews and.
Fast track approvals and the integration
layer connects clinical, regulatory
safety and commercial functions
which is breaking many barriers.
What's the result?
It's like faster, more compliment,
compliant like it, it makes more
the submissions more compliant.
Let's talk about key technologies
driving this transformation.
A powered quality checks, which spots
errors before they become any bottlenecks.
Cloud native collaboration allows global
teams to work on the same content in
real time, and by integrating real world
data, documents can evolve dynamically
as outcomes or any safety data changes.
So all these technologies, they bring
both speed and precision during a global
health emergency, which usually takes
six months, a regulatory submission
was just completed in eight days.
Can you believe this?
How?
Of pre-approved templates and then
parallel approval parallel workflow
workflows across 22 agencies, real-time
collaboration and automated localization.
What's the end result?
Patients got an access to the
treatment five months sooner.
Which usually takes six months.
It was completed in eight days.
We have a, another case study
for global launch efficiency.
A mid-sized biopharma had a challenge.
Launching it in 18 markets
within a small regulatory team.
With platform-based authoring,
reusable submission components and
automated translations, the acute
simultaneous launches cutting the
localization timelines by 40%.
This is the impact, which
is now becoming the norm.
Let's measure the business impact.
Let's look at the numbers.
So it's gonna be 50% faster document
lifecycles through smarter workflows.
And then 40% of localization, which
enables multiple markets at once and
80, 85% fewer safety findings, which
improves the complaints and how,
you know how much it's gonna save.
It's gonna save close to 2.5
million per therapy and per day.
These are not just stats.
These this is a real ROI.
So what's next?
It's a, it's the future.
AI and regulatory intelligence
is gonna be the future.
A will power predictive
regulatory analysis.
It's gonna scan thousands of submissions
to guide strategy and it's gonna
automatically draft any structured data,
which is gonna save 60% of the authoring
time, and it's gonna perform the dynamic
risk assessments as well, adopting to
changing the regulations in real time.
So a is gonna transform the regulatory
completely from reactive to proactive.
So next we are gonna discuss
about how these rare disease
approvals can be accelerated.
Rare diseases, right?
Which needs a speed.
With the platforms, what we have now it's
gonna be adaptive trial documents that,
that update as patient data changes.
And then patient reported outcomes
integrated directly and real time
core reviews with the agencies.
So these advances are helping reduce
approval time by almost eight 28%.
Getting critical therapies to to
those who need the more, let's
look at the implementation roadmap.
This here is how to get started.
We have to do an assessment, understand
your current pain points, and then
foundation building set up your platform
and set up the governance, and then
process integration, connect clinical
studies, safety and regulatory systems.
And then we ought to do a scaling, expand
across the teams and bring in an AA.
Quick wins come early, and
scalability ensures long-term success.
Let's look at the change
management consideration.
This is not just tech, right?
It's just a cultural shift.
Others become content engineers, and
then teams must learn the structured
authoring and the new workflows.
We all know that change is hard,
but with the, with all the executive
support that we have, it's gonna,
it's, we are gonna manage it.
It becomes very pretty manageable.
And then remember, this is
not just admin work, it's a
strategic content engineering,
which fuels a lot of innovation.
What are the key takeaways?
Let's recap the four key ideas.
Time is lives every day, saved to
help patients, and then platform
thinking, which drives scale and speed.
Global by design launch in all
markets very faster, in a quicker way.
And then a exhilaration turns
bottlenecks into breakthroughs.
The companies that master these will
lead to the next wave in life senses.
So what you can do next, you can
benchmark your current document cycle
times, identify reuse opportunities,
map your existing tech stack.
Start with high value areas.
Evaluate platforms like OW, vault
and Plan a phase rollout every day.
We save in regulatory means,
getting life changing, treat.
Every day we save in regulatory, which
means getting a life changing treatments
to patients in a much, much faster way.
And I would like to thank you
for providing this opportunity.
I really appreciate your support and I
got a chance to represent this innovative.
So thanks everyone and I
really appreciate your support.