Hello everyone.
This is, and I'll be sharing how
we've modernized a legacy fixed
income index system using cloud
native platform engineering.
This was a major transformation
effort that addressed both technical
and organizational challenges.
I'll walk you through the challenges
we faced, the modernization
strategy, the technical architecture.
The results we achieved and
finally the lessons we learned.
By the end, I hope you will see how
Cloud native engineering can unlock
real performance and agility in a
heavily regulated financial environment.
Here is the roadmap for the presentation.
We will start with the legacy
system challenges that forced
us to rethink our approach.
Then we will go into the modernization
strategy we adopted, followed by
the technical architecture we built.
I'll then share the implementation
journey and results and wrap up with
lessons learned and future directions.
Let's start with the problems
we were trying to solve.
Our legacy fixed income
index system had grown.
Increasingly fragile.
For example, monthly index rebalancing
required longer maintenance dose.
During that time, clients
could not access critical data,
which directly impacted CLIs.
At the same time, data volumes grew
five times in just three years.
The system simply couldn't
process that influx efficiently.
Index calculations often
took 30 minutes or more.
During peak times, which is unacceptable
when unacceptable, when clients
needed near real time results.
Finally, scalability
was a huge limitation.
The monolithic system couldn't handle
sudden spikes in demand, such as quarter
and reporting or market volatility events.
This wasn't just an IT problem.
It directly affected client satisfaction,
SLS, and even revenue opportunities.
Clearly, something had to change.
We needed a strategy that didn't just
patch problems, but Rema, but reimagined
the whole foundation to solve this.
We adopted a platform
engineering approach that meant.
Building a foundation that supported
both stability and innovation.
We could not afford outages, so we moved
step by step with zero downtime goals.
Infrastructure as code was insured,
has insured every enrollment.
Its consistent, automated and auditable.
We applied domain design, for example.
Pricing logic became its own
service decoupled from reporting CSC
pipelines, we introduced automated
pipelines, so code changes went from
weeks of manual promotion to hours.
For instance, we used Docker to
containerize every component, making
it portable and easier to scale.
We redesigned workflows to be a
synchronous, which prevented bottleneck
and security Compliance was integrated
directly into the deployment process,
so previously we had a giant
monolith one code base manually
deployed scaling by buying bigger
boxes and running nightly batches.
Now we run domain based, domain
bounded microservices, deployed with
GitHubs, even driven architecture,
multi-region redundancy, and
auto scaling in Kubernetes.
Think of it like moving from a single
massive mainframe to an ecosystem of
small, specialized teams of workers
who can scale up or down instantly.
This was not just a technology upgrade.
It fundamentally changed how
we could deliver features
and respond to client needs.
Let's break down what
those components look like.
Kubernetes and airflow implementation.
Along alongside Kubernetes,
we introduced Apache Airflow
as our workflow orchestrator.
While Kubernetes handle infrastructure,
scaling airflow gave us a
framework to manage the sequence
of steps in index calculation.
We built containerized adapters to
connect to multiple data providers like
Bloomberg, because they were stateless,
we could scale them independently.
Airflow triggered tasks to pull issuer
and bond metadata from multiple providers.
Next tasks collected real time and
end of day bond prices, ensuring data
quality checks before proceeding.
Calculation engine ports
spun up based on workload.
For example, at month end,
the system ought to scale to
30 ports for calculations.
Then scale down overnight for persistence.
We chose time series databases
that were optimized for financial
tick data and are critical for
both accuracy and performance.
The A PL layer included both rest and
graph QL supporting both diverse clients.
Compliance checks like masking restricted
securities happen directly at the API.
Service mass gave us fine-grain traffic
control, encryption, and observability.
If one service failed, we could trace
exactly where and why airlock orchestrated
the workflow end to end, starting
from ingestion, ingesting difference
data and prices, and validate quality.
The followed by not triggering
calculations on Kubernetes
ports as a third step generating
reports and violations.
Lastly, publishing to APIs and
downstream customers the entire world.
Orchestration was done by airflow.
Airflow gave us a dag view.
Every step was visible,
retriable and auditable.
Using these directed as cyclic graphs.
Let's say if pricing data
failed, calculations paused
automatically until conducted.
Think of Kubernetes as the engine and
airflow as the conductor, making sure
the orchestra plays in the right order.
Together these components form a
resilient and flexible backbone for
our system, critical system components.
Kafka decoupled processing instead of
requests piling up in a queue, Kafka
smoothened our spikes and preserved state.
If one node failed during one stress
test, Kafka handled three times expected
peak loads without dropping a message.
With Redis, we cut database reads by 90%.
That meant sub millisecond
access to frequently used data.
With cross region
replication for resilience,
Kubernetes features like stateful
sets for order deployment, network
policies for regulatory boundaries
and horizontal power auto scaling for
elasticity have been implemented here,
for example, during volatile market days.
The system automatically scaled
to handle 20 times more concurrent
calculations without service degradation.
At simple.
The performance improvements, we saw
an 88% reduction in calculation time.
What used to take 30 minutes
now takes under five.
Scheduled downtime was eliminated.
Clients could access the system
continuously even during rebalancing.
And we could now support 20 times
more concurrent calculations, directly
improving client SLS added with airflow
orchestration, which not only did
calculations run faster, but the entire
workflow pipeline from to publishing
became more reliable and auditable.
These weren't just technical wins.
They directly improved the client.
Ls even reduced operational risk and gave
product teams the ability to launch in
indexes that weren't even possible before.
The migration approach was
executed in four phases.
As a phase one, we set up cloud
infrastructure with compliance baked in.
Infrastructure as a code CICD
and monitoring as phase two.
We migrated historical data.
We used dual right patterns and
built a data validation framework.
Every bond reference data and prices
were checked across all and new systems
before going live as part of phase three.
We decomposed the monolith
extracting services gradually.
Using the strangler pattern, we peeled
services off one by one, running both
in parallel until they are stable.
When we decomposed services,
airflow became the glue
between old and new systems.
For example, the reference data
was still in Legacy database while
calculations moved to Kubernetes.
Airflow orchestrated across both worlds.
During this transition, which
actually let us migrate step by
step without breaking workflows.
As the last phase, we cut over
with blue green deployments.
We ran systems in parallel and
only decommissioned legacy.
After full confidence at every
stage, we made sure business
operations were not stopped.
The key was that clients
never saw disruption for them.
The system just got faster.
And more reliable
technology.
Transformation was only
half the story here.
We also had to transform the organization.
We created a dedicated platform
team that functioned as an
internal service provider.
We invested in developer experience
building self-service portals that
standardized container environments.
Of waiting weeks for servers, developers
had a self-service portal, needed a
database, just one click needed a dev
enrollment done in minutes, we ran
internal tech talks, paid developers with
platform engineers, and created runbooks.
So teams were not dependent on
specialists without these cultural and
organization organizational changes.
The technical success would
not have been sustainable.
Key takeaways, performance
transformation was the major key here.
Overall, we are eight times faster.
We are doing eight, eight times
faster calculations with no downtime.
We improved clients trust and
enable entirely new products.
By automating compliance in
CICD, we reduced audit stress.
While deploying more frequently,
we cut time to market for custom
products by 70%, allowing teams to focus
on innovation instead of firefighting
infrastructure as the next steps.
We are now exploring machine learning
for anomaly detection in market data.
To catch issues before they impact trends.
For example, if a bond price
suddenly spikes out of historical
range, mission learning can flag
it before impacting calculations.
We are considering multi-cloud
deployment strategies for resilience
against provider outages that is
critical for regulated markets.
We are enhancing self-service
capabilities so business users can
request infrastructure directly.
The goal is that a business analyst
can spin up a test index enrollment
without calling the application team.
We are also looking at extending airflow
D to support streaming workflows, for
example, regarding intra calculations
when new market data costs, et
cetera, show the journey is ongoing.
But the foundation we have built
sets up for continuous innovation.
This modernization was as
much about people and process
as it was about technology.
It showed that with the right
foundation, even legacy financial
systems can be reimagined.
Thank you for your time.
I look forward to collaborating on
building the next way of resilient
and scalable financial platforms.