Hi everyone.
My name is Bar.
I'm currently working as senior
Salesforce consultant with over
nine years of experience in
Salesforce and cloud technologies.
Over these many years, I have
delivered Salesforce implementations,
cloud integrations, and AI driven
solutions across industries such as
finance, healthcare, and registry.
In today's session, I will
walk you through the topic,
architecting AI native platforms.
This talk will focus on how
infrastructure, workloads, and governance
come together to make AI work at scale.
We'll also look at real
world implementation
patterns and future threats.
By the end of this session, you will
have a clear understanding of the
challenges, best practices, and takeaways.
For building scalable AI native platforms,
the infrastructure imperative,
the starting point for AI
initiative is infrastructure.
Without the right infrastructure, most
AI projects remain in experimental
phases and fail to reach production.
AI requires compute intensive gps.
High performance networking
and scalable storage.
There are two risks to highlight here.
First, organization that embrace
infrastructure can achieve a
competitive advantage, deploying
AI models faster and more reliably.
Second, those that focus on
experiments without production.
Ready infrastructure fall into
what I call the experimental cloud.
This means AI never skills beyond pilots.
So the message is clear.
Create infrastructure as
the foundation of your ai.
Understanding AI workload characteristics.
A workloads are very different
from traditional applications.
Training workloads require massive
parallel processing where GPU Shine
inference workloads, on the other
hand, focus on speed and scalability.
Think of recommendation engines,
chart bots, fraud detection models.
They need millisecond responses.
This means infrastructure must.
Consider both sides.
Training environments that are compute
heavy and inference environment
that are lightweight, but scalable.
If we don't understand
workload characteristics, we
risk over provisioning, under
utilization and spiraling costs.
Data pipeline, I. Data is the fuel of ai
without well-structured and governed data
pipelines, even the most sophisticated
models will fit a robust data pipeline.
Ensures data is collected, lean,
transformed, and served consistent.
Future stores are becoming
a critical component.
They allow teams to reuse
features across models.
Ensure data consists stream processing.
Add another dimension, real time insights.
For example, in fraud detection, if data
pipelines lack even by a few cycles,
the opportunity to stop fraud is lost.
Infrastructure patterns
for scalable model trade.
Scaling model training is not driver.
We face challenges in resource management,
container isolation, and network topology.
Kubernetes and container orchestration
solve many of these challenges,
but GPU scheduling, network
optimization and distributed training
strategies are equally important.
For example, let's say distributed data
parallelism allow us to train large models
across the multiple GPUs while tolerance
mechanism ensure that even if one not
fail, training continues the seamless.
Resource management challenges.
Managing resources is a balancing act.
The key challenges include allocating
GPU and CPU resources effectively.
Isolating workloads
through containerization.
Designing network topologies
that support high data building
system T to hardware failure.
If resource management is not
handled properly, fast train
rocket and innovation slows.
That's why AI n native two platform.
Must embed resource governance from day
GPU and CPU optimization.
AI workloads often involve
a mix of CPUs and GPUs.
CPUs are great for general purposes
tasks while GPUs accelerate
metrics, heavy competitions in
model training and inference.
The challenge is in optimizing utilization
of both eternal genius resources.
Scheduling ensures that workload are
directed to the right compute layer.
This improves efficiency and lowers cost.
For instance, lightweight reprocessing
me run on CPUs while the heavy
model training runs on gpu.
Data pipeline architectures, modern
AI platforms rely on advanced data
pipelines, a future store, ensure that
right data is consistently available
for training and inference frame
processing, handles real time data,
allowing systems to react immediately.
The architecture must balance
batch and real-time processing.
Batch pipelines are great for large
historical data sets while stream
pipelines ensure responsiveness.
Together they provide a comprehensive data
bone backbone for ai YouTube platforms.
Observability and monitoring for ai.
Unlike traditional systems, AI platform
requires observability and multiple
levels, infrastructure, data, and models.
We need to monitor GPU, utilization,
pipeline Health, and most
importantly, model performance.
Metrics such as accuracy, precision,
recall, fairness indicator
must be continuously tried.
Observability help us detect entire
drift bias and performance degradation
early, preventing the costly failures,
real world implementation patterns.
AI native platform.
Looks very different across industries.
Some examples, high frequency trading.
It requires ultra load latency,
infrastructure, and real time pipelines.
Content recommendation, it
needs scalable system that
personalized the individual level.
Healthcare here.
It particularly focuses on compliance,
accuracy, and ethical safeguards.
These industry specific examples
demand us that there is no one size
fits at the level of AI platform
Architecture must align with
business goals and complex needs.
Performance optimization.
Performance optimization is about making
sure resources are used efficient.
These involves optimizing GBU memory
usage, improving storage performance
with MVM and tuning models,
serving layers to reduce latency.
For example, batching interface request
can reduce overhead while catching the
frequently accessed futures improve.
Small optimizations at scale
create massive performance scales.
Security and governance in AI platform
in AI platforms cannot succeed without
robust security and governance.
These include.
Protecting models from ARISAL
attacks, ensuring data privacy and
implementing role-based access.
Governance also means ethical
oversight, making sure AI decisions
are transparent, explainable and T with
regulations such as GDPR and hiphop.
Future trends in AI infrastructure.
Looking here, several trends will
shape AI native platforms, each AI
bringing intelligence closer to the
source of that quantum computing,
unlocking optimization problems.
Traditional hardware struggles
with Pneumo, morphic computing.
Mimicking the human brain for efficiency.
Automated EML and explainable
AI democratizing ai while
keeping it transparent.
These trends will transform the way
we think about scale and adoption.
Building the roadmap for the
foundation of AI driven innovation.
Implement AI native platform successfully.
Organizations particularly need a roadmap.
These include short term wins,
such as building feature tools,
medium term goals, like integrating
observability and long-term strategies
like adopting hr, quantum compute.
The roadmap should balance
innovation with governance,
ensuring sustainable AI adoption.
Key takeaways and the conclusion.
Coning AI native platform is able uniting
infrastructure, workloads, and governance.
Here are the key takeaways.
Infrastructure is the
foundation of scalable.
Understanding workload characteristics
for effective design data pipelines
are the backbone of reliable ai.
Observability ensures continuous implement
governance, build trust and compliance
future trends, demand ongoing division.
Thank you for joining this session.
I hope this helps you.
Strategically about
building a to platform.
Thank you.