Hello everyone and thank
you for joining me today.
My name is Heh Bja and I'm a software
engineering leader creating enterprise
software solution from the last 15 years.
Currently my work is focused on HCM and
FinTech space, creating solution that
provide small and the medium business
workers, which are SMBs the backbone
for US economy with the tools they
need to focus on their jobs without.
Taking the burden for
the financial stress.
The topic for our session is how
to architect Scalable platform for
financial wellness for employees through
the HCM and the FinTech integration.
This is just not a technical
problem to solve or a challenge.
This is a growing financial stress
into the ecosystem industry.
For employees and they're directly
impacting their productivity
engagement and also impacting
employer for the employer retention.
Traditionally, HCM system
often operates in the isolation
from financial wellness tools.
What are we going to explore today?
How to bridge that gap?
Build a unique opportunity to
reimagine how workforce data and the
financial insight can work together.
To create a meaningful
employee experience.
So let's spend some time, maybe 15,
20 minutes with deep dive into the
business use cases for this integration,
the technical architecture required
to build our scalable and the secure
platform, the core principles, and
some of the business use cases.
Let's start with the business use case,
the impact for the financial asset.
The impact for the financial stresses
are very much well documented.
Employees who are experiences financial
difficulties demonstrate decreased
focus, increase healthcare utilization,
and the higher turnover rates.
The core issue of the problem
is the missed opportunities.
Here, most enterprise architecture treat
workforce management and the financial
wellness as a completely separate domain.
They work in isolation, meaning the missed
critical chances to provide intervention
and support when needed the most to
the workers on the technical front.
All modernized enterprise must
navigate complex requirement,
maintain strict privacy standards,
and ensure a seamless user experience
across a variety of different and
often cross-functional use cases.
To build our effective platform, we
need a strong technical foundation.
There are few core pillars for the
architecture that we have to follow.
Whenever actually we are thinking about to
moving any data, we need a sophisticated
data orchestration layer, which just goes
beyond the traditional ETL processes.
A key part of this is privacy
design as we deal with the employee
data, which is more sensitive.
We want to make sure that all our platform
are deal with the privacy and security in
the mind from the day one central of this
is the event driven communication pattern.
All the modernized platform
need real data for the workforce
event, like when employee salary
changes new benefit enrollments.
They move, that means their
effective dating are changing their
performance reviews, which can trigger
the relevant financial wellness
intervention or an opportunity.
Our communication layer must handle
both synchronous and the asynchronous
pattern effectively, and we can achieve
this using even streaming platform
like Kafka, which is widely used
across the industries as the backbone
for our hybrid communication model.
When we architect the system, we can
leverage a number of proven design
pattern to address specific challenges.
These are not unique.
This has been used in the multiple
industries, so we can learn from there.
Number one is architecture,
which allow us.
That how are core business logic to
remain independent of the integrations
providing the clear interfaces for
the external system for integration.
This is vital for a system that connect
with the various different providers.
Second is the API Gateway pattern,
which provides a single entry
point for all of our integration
offering unified authentication,
how to throttle the request rail.
And monitor and tracking.
The lastly is circuit brick
or circuit breaker pattern,
which is crucial for stability.
It's prevent cascading failures and ensure
graceful degradation of functionality.
When a connected system
experiences any issue.
In case of any failure, we can
look into more advanced topic
like data mesh architecture for
organization with complex data needs.
Privacy and the security consolidation,
as I said in the past, these are
the must consolidation we should
take Whenever we're talking about
the HCM and the financial system.
Whenever we're dealing with the
employee financial data, privacy
and security are paramount.
We should adopt.
In fact, we must adopt a zero
trust architecture, authenticating
authorization, each and every request.
We should know regardless of.
What is the source?
Who is trying to accept the data?
This provides the gran control, which
is essential for the financial data.
We should also implement
multi-layer encryption.
We should encrypt data
at all stages and rest.
While in transit, even while in use
through the advanced encryption techniques
token piece authentication, which also
allows to support custom roles find
grade and access control, and with
token scope to the specific data types.
And finally, we must
practice data minimization.
We should actively minimize data exchange
to only what is absolutely necessary
for the specific business functions.
Let's talk about what AI.
Can play a role here.
AI can make those systems more proactive.
It can transform our reactive
financial wellness program into
our proactive intervention systems.
By analyzing the pattern, by looking
into the workforce data and the financial
behavior, AI model can definitely
identify employees who are at risk for
financial stress before it become a
crisis for them and impact their home.
Capabilities.
We can also do this without
centralized sensitive data by using
federating learning approaches.
AI can also leverage NLP techniques
to analyze communication pattern for
stress indicator and a behavioral
analytics to extent beyond direct
financial data to include metrics
like productivity sick leave.
These are, these are the scoring
and the metrics we should.
Aligned to each and every
worker in their workforce.
The goal is to use realtime scoring
system to enable the immediate
response to identified risk factor.
The feedback loop is
very much critical here.
In fact, that's that's a key for the ai.
We learn from our system and continuously
refine the accuracy and effectiveness
for our AI models over time.
Another one of the important applications
for HCM FinTech integration is.
Personalized nudging.
We can leverage the combination of
workforce context and the financial
data to deliver precise, timely,
and the very relevant information.
For example, if I imply situation
changes, take example, they can
promote, then they need, immediate
changes to their retirement
contribution or some other financial
decision they have to take care of.
Or if something happened in their family
or there's a time for enrolled for the
new benefit or a new deadline, which
could change their personalized decisions.
So these kind of situations we should
handle with the right kind of nudges.
We should also look into the
behavioral economics also, and
also for the effective delivery, we
should use multi-channel approach.
It can be SMS, it can be the mobile apps.
It can be through the notification
also, so we can nudges worker
with the right information at the
right time for all the workflows.
Moving beyond traditional batch processing
and even, even architecture enable
immediate response to the employee life
event as financial stress indicator
that we spoke about in the last site.
The key component of these architecture
includes event sourcing pattern that
captured the complete history of an
employee financial wellness journey.
Stream processing for real time analysis
of the workforce even as they occur.
And carefully design event schema that
support the evolution over the time.
By building a system with
massive durability, we ensure
critical events are never lost.
This approach allows for the
powerful cross system correlation
connecting workforce, even with
the financial behavior pattern
to provide real time analysis.
Let's look into the microservice design.
The microservice design is the perfect for
this kind of platform because it's allowed
them to evolve rapidly while maintaining
the system reliability and scalability.
This is a particularly valuable
when we are integrating with.
Diverse and complex set of and
the financial service provider.
We designed our service boundaries to
align with the business capabilities
rather than the technical consideration.
We have to find a balance between
performance and the reliability in
our interservice communication model.
Our API design should abstract
implementation details while
providing flexibility for
different integration scenarios.
For data consistency, we should
consider eventual consistency pattern
for appropriate data types and for our
surface discovery to enable dynamic
scaling and the deployment pattern
that will handle the variable demands.
Our reality for our many enterprises
that the core system are legacy.
We hardly change the system and upgrade
the system sometime as, as pricey,
sometime as need more, more investment or
they're, they, they're hard to upgrade.
This system often lacks
the modern API capability.
They are still using the old
data format and very limited
real time integration option.
So what are the solution approaches?
We can modernize our ETL with the
change data capture techniques and
build data transformation layer to
map between legacy format and the
modern API and use adapter pattern.
To isolate the legacy integration logic.
We must also accommodate batch processing
windows with catching strategies,
time to live and build a comprehensive
error handling and the retrial logic.
Let's touch base a little bit
of compliance and regulatory
architecture, consolidation.
Also, compliance is not a side project.
It's it required.
It's a core architectural
consolidation, and we should adopt
it from the day one, like security.
We need a robust data governance
framework, and a consent management
is critical because we are talking
about the employee person leader.
We should.
Take their consent to use their
data for the different purposes.
We need clear data retention policies.
Also that balance regulatory requirement
with operational needs using automated
management of prevent compliance
gap and also audit trails must that
must be in detail, inimitable to
support regulatory examiner and
the legal discovery processes.
We should build these capabilities into
our platform from start to reduce the
compliance burden and improve accuracy.
Whenever we serving the large
employee population, performance
optimization is a constant challenge.
Our architecture decision
must anticipate peak uses.
When is the time where we have like the
high load, maybe the year end, maybe
the quarter trend, or maybe whenever
there payroll runs to talk about the
peak while maintaining the responsive
performance during the normal operations?
Our scalability strategies include.
Multi-tiered caching architecture
optimized for different users patterns,
database charting strategies that
account for the diverse access patterns,
using CDNs for financial execution
materials and the load balancing
that considers the stateful nature
of financial wellness interactions.
We must also ensure our performance
monitoring extent beyond simple
infrastructure metrics to include
business relevant measurements.
Let's look at a few examples
of this pattern in action.
Let's talk about a healthcare
organization, a healthcare organization
that started small by connecting emergency
saving program to their payroll system.
This focus approach, established core
integration pattern and demonstrated
value before they expanded to the more
complex feature resulting in significant
improvement in the employee financial
resilience, a technology company.
Leverage a microservice architecture
to create personalized financial
education program that adopted.
To the employee career trajectories,
their event driven approach enable real
time responses to promotions and the
equity investing events, which improved
retirement saving participation, a
manufacturing organization that adopted
adapted pattern to integrate modern
financial wellness capabilities without
disturbing their established HR processes.
This shows how architecture pattern
can enable innovation even without
within a constrained technical.
Environment and a financial services
company face unique compliance challenges.
They use sophisticated consent
management and the data governance
pattern to provide valuable
employee benefit while maintaining
the strict regulatory compliance.
I. As we look into the future, we'll
see separate ER emerging technologies
that continue to shape this space,
including the advanced AI capabilities
beyond simple pattern equalization,
blockchain for trust, transparency
in the quantum resistant encryption.
We also anticipate greater API
standardization across the HM
and the FinTech industries.
To build truly sustainable
platform, we need to follow
some key success principles.
Start with the career use case and the
success metrics designed for privacy
and security from the beginning.
Leverage event driven pattern for
responsiveness and maintain marginalized
architecture that can support evolution.
Ultimately, this integration is
more than just a technical project.
It isn't app opport to reimagine how
technology supports human potential.
Does take us to the end.
Thank you so much.
I appreciate you all
taking some time to listen.
Thank you so much.