Hello, and thanks for joining
my presentation on building
agent AI platforms, lessons from
Autonomous mortgage processing.
If you talk to someone who went
through getting a mortgage, they
would typically say it was like being
stuck in a bureaucratic quicksand for
about two months, but this is what
industry leaders are now thinking.
What if this entire time.
The process could run by itself.
What if instead of humans shuffling
papers between departments, you
had intelligent systems that could
actually think through problems and
also coordinate with each other?
Now this is exactly what I want
to talk to you about today.
I am now gonna in the, and I have
spent over a decade providing solutions
to various business functions across
the financial industry, and I've
also spent the last few years.
Watching this space evolve from
a real equal idea to something
that's actually transforming how
complex business process work.
Just to set the context, let me
give you a scenario that's happening
right now in the mortgage industry.
Let's say someone applies for a loan on
a Friday evening, and by Monday morning,
the system could have already verified
their income through multiple sources.
Ordered and reviewed property appraisals.
Reviewed their flood zone data,
coordinate with insurance providers and
flagged any potential compliance issues.
All the weekend when everyone
was sleeping, AI agents could
have been working together
like a well orchestrated team.
This is not science fiction anymore.
This is what Agentic systems can do today.
So let's talk about what makes
these systems different, because
I think there's a lot of confusion
out there, especially when people
hear what agent AI actually means.
Think about the AI tools you use today.
Maybe charge GPD or some other
automation in your company.
You ask it something,
it gives you an answer.
You feed it data, it processes data, but
you're always the one driving it, right?
You are the conductor and the AI is
just the instrument of your orchestra.
Agent AI is now completely
flipping that perception.
Imagine if your AI could actually
understand the bigger picture of what
you are trying to accomplish, and then it
can go figure out how to make it happen.
Should I talk to other systems?
Should I make decisions when roadblocks
come up or learning something new?
When old steps are predetermined,
actions are not working.
Now here's a real world example.
Traditional systems break
whenever they encounter something
accepted, and that's a known fact.
Let's say someone applies for a
mortgage and their primary incomes comes
from, not from traditional sources of
income, but from cryptocurrency mining.
Now, this is something the
system has not seen before.
A traditional rule-based system would
just stop and then gives out, give out
an error message and wait for manual
intervention to come and fix it.
However, in an agent system.
The agent would itself recognize that
this is an income verification challenge,
research IRS guidelines on crypto income.
Look for similar cases in historical data.
Maybe it can even try consulting
external tax services.
And then once it identifies all
the solution, it may create its own
verification pathway on the flight.
It can also document this new approach,
so future crypto income cases can get
handled automatically without going
through all this identification process.
That's the difference.
It's not just about processing the
data, it's actually thinking through
problems just like we humans do.
Now, let's take the next few minutes.
I, during this time, I want
to walk you through six areas
that I think are crucial.
If you're con seriously considering
building these kind of systems, and I'm
going to be honest with you, I'm going
to talk about what doesn't work just as
much as what works because the failures
are far more instructive than the
successes in my own personal experience.
Let's start by providing a sense of just
how complex these mortgage workflows are.
I, over the years, I actually sat down
and mapped out a typical mortgage process.
And a typical mortgage process has
47 separate and discrete steps.
Yes, it is 47 and this is, and now
you know why your mortgage takes so
much time to process, end-to-end.
Each of these steps require human
judgment and they're all interconnected
in the complex dependency chains.
You got income verification talking to
employment verification, which feeds
into credit analysis, which in turn
impacts risk assessment and which in
turn affects the pricing, which again,
in turn, appliance compliance checks.
Now all of this is happening across
multiple systems, and these systems
were built years apart or sometimes
even decades apart, and they were
not designed to work together.
And here's a scenario that
plays perfectly, that captures
the old way of doing things.
Imagine an applicant whose employer
recently switched payroll companies
and which happens, and we've been
through such situations as well.
The new payroll systems outputs
data in a completely different
format than what the company
expects in the traditional process.
This application sits
in a queue for weeks.
While the user or the agent behind
human agent behind the scenes will
manually figure out on how to interpret
the new format, they make phone calls,
they reach out to other teams or maybe
even vendors to get clarification,
and eventually they build a solution.
Meanwhile, dozens of other applications
from employees of the same company might
be piling up behind the scenes and they
all will be having the same problem.
Now with the Agen approach, instead,
when the income verification agent
encounters this new format, it
automatically recognizes the pattern
item, multiple verification pathways.
And within our words, it has
established a new integration protocol.
It then shares knowledge across
the systems so that all future
applications from this employer.
Get processed seamlessly and successfully.
Now, if you look at compare
both scenarios, it is not about
making older process faster.
It is about reimagining how the
entire business workflow operates.
It takes a lot of change, not just
from technology, but also from how we
understand these processes going forward.
Now I want to dive into the
technical side of the architecture.
If you want to build one of these
systems, there are three architectural
foundations that you have to get right.
You miss any one of them and
the whole thing falls apart.
So each and every part of
this architecture is crucial
for the success of Agent TKI.
Now component number one
is workflow orchestration.
One mistake that I see everybody
make constantly is on this aspect.
They start with a simple cubase system
because they feel the process very
straightforward, like agent A finishes
since message to agent B. Agent B
finishes then sends a message to agency.
Straightforward sounds reasonable.
But when you hit a scenario where,
again, going back to the example
of a mortgage, you're processing
a mortgage for a property in a
flood zone during hurricane season.
Suddenly you need property inspection.
Flood insurance verification,
evac evacuation route analysis,
and updated property violations.
All of them should be running
concurrently, and all of them
are dependent on each other.
And all of them have completely different
processing trendlines now in a simple
queue system, everything will get locked
up because they're on all on different
timelines and different, dependencies.
You need an orchestration that can
handle dynamic dependencies, resource
contention, and resource scenarios.
It's like the difference between a traffic
light and an air traffic control system.
One is straightforward,
rule-based, not complex.
The other requires a lot of
intelligence behind the scenes.
The second component is
event driven communication.
Think of events as the nervous
system of these platforms.
And here's how it works.
When a credit score gets updated
during processing, the credit agent
broadcasts a credit score updated event.
Now, the risk assessment agent sees this
and immediately recalculates loan terms.
The pricing agent then
adjusts interest rates.
The compliance agents checks
regulatory boundaries.
All of this happens automatically
in parallel and within milliseconds.
The beauty of this architecture is that
none of these agents have to know about
each other and what these each other,
what other agents actually are doing.
They just respond to relevant systems.
To their relevance events
in their own systems.
It's like having a really
sophisticated gossip network where
everyone pays attention to the
rumors that they only care about,
and we all know how that works.
The third component is
ML Pipeline integration.
This isn't a typical machine learning
setup where you run models on
historical data and generate reports.
We are talking about
real time interference.
That deeply integrates into
the business process itself.
Think of a fraud detection model
that's analyzing every document that
you upload, every phone call that
you made, or every API interaction
that is happening within the system.
The model maintains conference scores
that change dynamically, and whenever
the confidence drops below a certain
threshold, it can automatically trigger
additional verification steps without
human involvement, or it can involve
a human, human until a verification
agent is brought up to speed.
Now let's dive deeper into event driven
architecture, because this is where
I see a lot of systems either succeed
brilliantly or fail spectacularly.
Now picture a si situation, I think, which
we have been all which would've all been
in at one point of time in our career.
It's 2:00 AM on a Saturday, and
your property valuation service goes
down, or any service for that matter.
Maybe it's a data center power outage.
Maybe it's a network issue.
It doesn't matter for the
purpose of this conversation.
In a traditional system, every single
mortgage application requiring property
evaluation would fail immediately and
thereby causing a massive backlog,
which would require, triaging and
teams looking into it on a Monday
morning through a crisis response.
In a well designed, event driven
system, those property valuation
requests just queued gracefully.
Whenever the issue is troubleshot and
the service comes back online, the entire
backlog gets processed automatically.
Now you have zero data loss and there is
zero manual intervention and no customers
calling in angry on a Monday morning
because your system is well designed
through an event driven architecture.
Now.
Is the trick is in getting the,
architecture and design, right?
You need to design your events with
just the right amount of information.
Too little context and your agents
can't make intelligent decisions.
And if you provide too much context, you
create the problem of tight coupling that
might kill your scalability in the future.
And in a typical market system, you
might have 4,000 and even greater
than 5,000 different event types.
And each has to be
carefully crafted for every.
In a significant event that occurs
during your mortgage process.
For example, an income verification
completed event includes only the
verified amount, confidence score,
verification method, and any other
anomalies that it may have encountered.
But it should not contain
the raw bank statements.
This keeps the agent loosely cud while
enabling even smart coordination.
Now one of the other benefits
of event driven architecture
is that you essentially get a
flight recorder, or a black box
for your entire business process.
When something goes wrong and
something always goes wrong in it.
You can replay the exact sequence
of events and see precisely why
and where a decision went sideways.
And for regulated industries,
especially financial industries,
this is absolute good.
I want to get a quick reality check.
We need to talk about.
All the ways the systems can break,
because if you're thinking about
building one, you need to know what
you're getting into and what are the
possibilities that it might break.
One instance is every organization
has legacy integration, nightmares.
For example, mainframe is something
that is still not dispensable
in the financial industry.
And I want to talk about the mainframe
legacy integration nightmare.
That's a scenario where this is
scenario where most developers and even
platform engineers, get nightmares.
You are building this beautiful,
modern agent system, and then
you discover that some loan data
or metadata lives on a mainframe
system, which was built in the 1980s.
And there are no APIs.
You just get one batch file every day
that contains, the previous updated,
the previous days updated data.
And the data formats are in
such a way that even XMLs
look like modern technology.
You end up building, what can be
called as a legacy translation agent
where an entire AI system whose job
is to just speak mainframe day to day.
It converts modern event streams
into formats that would've been even
cutting edge technology and translates
the responses back into something
other agents also can understand.
Now, this agent will act as a bridge
between your legacy systems and
then the modern agent AI systems.
Sometimes these translation agents
becomes the most sophisticated
component in your entire component.
The next one is state
management complexity.
Now, here's a fun challenge where
in a distributed state management,
you know long running process or a
problem, mortgage applications can
stay active for 60 days or more.
Sometimes your rate log may extend
even for 90 days or 180 days, or even
360 days depending upon the contract
you hold with your mortgage provider.
Now, during this time, applications
can change, applicants can change,
property values can fluctuate,
interest rates can shift, and even
new regulations can come into effect.
Now, a dozens of autonomous agents
have to be synchronized because
each of these aspects are handled
by different autonomous agents.
Now the naive approach is to store.
Every current state that you have in
a database somewhere so that when an
agent crashes and restarts, especially
in a distributed systems, you will have
context which you did not have before.
You end up needing something
like even sourcing, where you
store every single thing that
ever happened to an application.
Any agent can rebuild its
complete understanding just
by replaying the events team.
The third challenge is
scalability optimization.
Credit analysis for a standard W2
employee might take 30 seconds,
but that is just one piece of
the pie of mortgage applicants.
But when you throw in self-employed
applicants, you have multiple, they
may have multiple, they have stock
income, they may have cryptocurrency
income, and also international
assets, and suddenly you are looking
at 20 minutes of processing time.
But how do you plan for an infrastructure
with that kind of variability?
You need adaptive resource allocation
that can monitor agent behavior patterns
and automatically spin up capacity when
complex cases start hitting the system.
Now during the tax season,
which also aligns with the,
summer school of summer season.
Mortgage applications spike and the
systems might actually scale your
income verification capacity by 300%.
And this is without anyone touching a
configuration file to scale up or scale
down, and all happening intelligently
and automatically behind the scenes.
Now in financial services and
really any regulated industry,
you can't just say the AI did it.
Every decision has to be explainable,
auditable, and legally defensible.
And this is not only a nightmare
situation, but also a necessary situation
for all these regulated industries.
Now imagine a regulator walks in
and asks about why a loan denial
that happened eight months ago, and
what was the reason In traditional
systems, that's days of forensic work.
Detective work going through
log files and database records,
and there is no guarantee that
you'll actually find everything.
But with proper decision provenance
architecture, you can pull up a complete
decision tree in seconds, which agents
were involved, what data they accessed,
and which algorithms ran, and what
business rules are fired, and even
the exact model versions that were
active at the moment, which gives you
a picture on why a decision was taken.
At the moment, it was taken.
This level of transparency the agents
provides is actually better than what
most human driven processes can offer.
Now, mortgage industry, like any other
financial industry, is very dynamic
in nature, and the compliance side of
the industry is very dynamic as well.
Now.
Compliance and regulations
change constantly and often
with very such short notice.
New guidelines for cryptocurrency income
verification might come and they may
require implementation within 30 days.
Now instead of rushing code changes into
production, a well-designed compliance
agent can monitor regulatory fees,
automatically adjust business rules,
and even run impact simulation before
changes can take effect in production.
Now data minimization
becomes very critical.
Your credit scoring agent never needs
to full see full bank statements.
They can just view aggregated spending
patterns and derive data from it.
Your identity verification agent
confirms identity and then they can
immediately discard your biometric data.
This architecture not only
protects the privacy, but it also
enables intelligent processing.
Now I want to take a moment to
talk about the different types
of monitoring and observability.
Monitoring agent systems is like
monitoring a team of consultants
rather than monitoring servers.
This fundamental approach in our thinking
has to will play a critical role while
implementing agent TK in our organization.
You care less about CCP utilization
and more about decisions,
quality and business outcomes.
Just like human agent for example, you
might track agent confidence patterns.
If your property evaluation agent
suddenly starts expressing low
confidence in its decision, then you
would have to take it as a signal
to either adjust market volatility.
Or newer property types that
the data hasn't seen yet.
Or data quality issues with vendor feeds,
which can offer open if vendor feeds
actually change or vendor systems change.
Now all of this gives you a early
warning before problems start
hitting customer experience.
The metrics that matter.
Most are things like, are agents making
decisions that lead to successful ones?
Are they catching risks that human
underwriters might miss, or even
processing times improvement while
is the quality is staying high.
One critical metric is
decision reversal rate.
Now, how often your human agents
are disagreeing with the AI agents?
Now when the disagreement rate or the
reversal rate is high, then you know.
That one particular AI
agent requires attention.
It may be a data training issue, or
there may be fundamentally some other
issue that needs to be addressed.
And then you can bring your
that particular AI agent offline
while you work on bring, propping
it up to a required threshold.
I would like to take a moment to
share some practical lessons about
infrastructure that can save you, not
only money, but also, months of pain.
In case of our deployment complexity
organizations still, most of them
have a blue green deployment approach.
In the case of a blue green deployment.
It becomes incredibly tricky when
long running processes, especially in
mortgage applications where application
can take 30 days into processing.
Now when an application is taking
30 days of processing, how do you
deploy a sec critical security update?
And how do you update agent versions
without breaking the applications in
process or applications in flight?
Now this is where you need
versioned agent deployment.
Where each agent version can handle
requests from older process versions,
new applications get newer agents,
existing applications will continue,
still continue with the older agents.
Now this can be understood with an example
like think of a restaurant menu where
meals, where your previous orders meals
are still getting prepared while you
work on updating your restaurant panel.
The next aspect is configuration,
and this is also configuration
management is also key.
Now, make your agents pull configuration
from external systems at runtime.
This means you can adjust business
rules, update model parameters, or even
modified decision thresholds without
deploying any code or any downtime.
During the early pandemic lending
criteria almost changed daily.
But ha without.
But having runtime configuration
management was the key differentiator
between organizations that
was able to adapt quickly and
that was also falling behind.
Now.
This is the organization.
Culture factors are equally and critically
important, just like a technical factors.
This is where most technical
teams fail entirely.
The technology is often the easy part
for a technologist, but getting people
and the organization to adapt is
much harder and actually very harder.
Picture a change management scenario.
Your most experienced mortgage
Generat has been doing.
Their job for 20 years now,
they can spot problems that are
not captured in any rule book.
They're, they know how to handle
end scenarios or they know
how to handle new scenarios.
Their initial reaction to
autonomous agents is probably
going to be met with skepticism
or even challenged with hostility.
The successful approach
is not to force adoption.
But to involve them in every step of
the decision making process and also
in every step of making the system
better turn them into agent trainers
rather than a competitor, and then
they can help identify edge cases and
also teach nuanced decision making
patterns to the AI when domain experts.
Like an experienced underwriter become
invested in improving your system
rather than competing everything,
it actually changes the whole
landscape and changes everything.
You also need people who understand
distributed systems and machine
learning and mortgage underwriting.
These.
Unicorn skills don't exist in
traditional job descriptions.
Cross training domain experts
often work better than trying to
hire people who know everything.
This helps with employee retention
within the organization as well.
Third aspect is governance,
balance and oversight.
Now, having a governance balance
and avoiding the extreme is also
one of the important factors
micromanaging every agent decision.
Kills the autonomy and the, and and it
defeats the purpose of having an agent
AI in your organization, but zero.
Our site also is unacceptable
and brings in a lot of risk.
Exception based monitoring is where
you find the right balance agents
operating independently, but they
alert humans when they hit a situation
outside their confidence boundaries.
The next topic is about future
directions and emerging patterns.
The future will get even more indus.
Interesting.
We are starting to see emergent
behaviors where agents develop
their own coordination strategy even
without explicit instructions or
explicit programming, for instance.
Fraud detection agent might learn
to tip off an income verification
agent when it spots suspicious
patterns, or create collaborative
investigation workflows where more
it is more effective for both agents
to work together than working alone.
These emergent behaviors often
surprise even the engineers who
built the system, and this is where.
The industry is actually heading
towards the next aspect is large
language model integration.
Now, large language models are
actually a game changer and
have become a game changer.
Imagine telling your system new
regulations require additional
verification for properties in flood zone,
and having it automatically understand
and implement the necessary changes
across all relevant agents is necessary.
We are now moving towards.
LLM interface for business where it
can automatically manage the rules,
directing the business processes.
Now the last aspect is
cross organizational agents.
The next frontier is also agents
that work across company boundaries
and not working within company silo.
Imagine mortgage processing where your
agents coordinate directly with AI
agents or human agents from external
vendors like title companies or insurance
providers, or appraisal services.
And they can all work together seamlessly
while maintaining security and privacy
requirements and not compromising any
compliance and regulatory standards.
Now the architecture patterns that we've
discussed right now is not limited to
just mortgage or financial industry.
The use case applies well
beyond the financial industry.
For example, healthcare organizations
are using similar approaches
for patient care coordination.
Supply chain companies are also
building agent networks that
automatically adapt to disruptions.
Any complex multi-step processes with lots
of coordination requirement is actually
a good candidate for agent automation.
Now whether you are processing loans
or managing patient care, or even
optimizing supply chains, the core
principle is going to be the same.
For all of them.
Autonomous agents, event driven
communication, comprehensive
observability and adapt orchestration,
all pillars of a good architecture
and governance framework.
I want to leave everyone with four
lessons that can actually save
you from most common failures.
The first one is.
Orchestration.
Orchestration is everything.
I would suggest not to underestimate
any coordination complexity.
Simple cubase systems will break
when the real world scenario start.
It may work well.
During your, initial testing or initial
deployment, but as long for long-term
usage, it's going to start breaking.
For H case scenarios or for newer
scenarios, you need to invest in
sophisticated orchestration from day one.
The second one is you need to have
observability from the very beginning.
Audit trails have to be built.
You need to have decision transparency
and regulatory adaptations should be built
directly into your system architecture.
Compliance is not something
that you can add later.
You it has to be incorrect
incorporated from day one.
The third one is
compliance isn't optional.
You need to you need, if you can't see
your agents, what they're doing, you
can't trust them with critical processes.
So you need to build comprehensive
monitoring into your architecture.
And this comprehensive monitoring
should be any critical first
step and not an afterthought
after building your applications.
Now the final thought is we are at the
beginning of a very fundamental shift.
How complex business
processes are working now.
Agent DKI platforms aren't
just automating existing tasks.
They are actually re-imagining
entire industries.
The organizations who are figuring
or understanding and figuring this
out first will have the significant
market competitive advantage.
Actually thanks for
spending time with me today.
I am hoping this presentation
gives you a practical foundation
for thinking about how to build
agent ai and in your own context.
If you're considering building
these kinds of systems, my advice
is to start small and focus on
solid architectural foundations.
And do not be afraid to fail fast
because it is only from these failures
that you can build solid applications.
The patterns I've shared with you today
should give you a roadmap for avoiding
some of the most common pitfalls that
most organizations go through when
they start on the Gent AI Road roadmap.
My final thought is the future belongs
to those organizations that can actually
successfully blend human expertise
with autonomous AI capabilities.
The technical patterns we have discussed
here today is just going to provide you
a blueprint for building that future.
Thank you.