Hello everyone.
This is here.
I work as a software engineer at Meta.
Today I'm going to discuss about
engineering scale with infrastructure.
So primarily looking
at various challenges.
The current ecosystem of software
engineering is facing essentially the
increasing complex digital landscape.
Crowd spending is projected to
increase by six 78 billion by 2024.
Platform engineering is extremely
important in this context of for a cloud
adoption and infrastructure management.
So what are the various things that are
extremely important when we are talking
about platform engineering revolution?
So faster deployments.
Obviously we talk about all the
microservice architectures, cloud
deployments at scale and stuff like that.
So eventually.
Develop productivity and also
engineering excellence almost always
depends on how fast we can deploy
things into production, right?
These are some of the architectural
constructs that can help
significantly increase fast
deployment to almost like 40%.
And also reduce overhead in terms
of processes manual steps and all
the operational overhead that are
necessary, right at the same time.
Increasing their satisfaction.
Obviously developer productivity, they're
able to deploy the code, run the code.
Release our features much faster.
Definitely increases the developer
satisfaction significantly.
Definitely this is more in incre
incremental gains across the stack.
An amazing opportunity to transform
any development organization into the
evolving landscape of deployments.
And let's talk more about what
is this flash mom approach?
First approach.
So what does it actually mean?
Again, looking at the
current challenge, right?
So there is definitely a lot of gap
between, what developers need to build
and what they need to know to build it.
So essentially more what they want
to build and obviously what they
need to build it essentially, right?
So traditionally DevOps models often
burden developers with infrastructure
concerns like creative cognitive
workloads and slowing innovation, right?
So what are we trying to achieve?
Self-service infrastructure,
you engineers or.
Developers should be able to
provision their resources.
VMs run their workloads at scale, manage
configurations, mostly self-serving,
without even going through the complex
processes of ticketing systems or
various other things, but obviously
reducing a lot of that trial in
terms of, whatever is necessary.
How do we make that more self
service model and obviously
some kind of a golden path.
Predefined, optimized pathways guide
to through common scenarios in open.
That can help with all the best practice,
how do we develop a code, how do we
get the infrastructure necessary to,
develop, deploy, test, and all the
different constructs of it, software
development, central governments.
And also obviously, one extremely
important aspect of it is
like the more freedom we have.
It's also extremely important
that we have that enough
controls checks in place anyway.
It's more defensive mechanism.
Obviously want to make sure.
Leave lease on security principle and
obviously whoever needs to have the
access, they can have the access, but
obviously we need to make sure that
there is a balance between giving
more flexibility at the same time.
Also making sure that security,
privacy complex things are also
in are are also in place in a way.
So let's talk about architectural
patterns for multi-cloud success.
Again, the most important thing is
that a lot of companies are evolving
into not single cloud environments.
And now obviously every cloud has its
own game positives and so primarily.
Eventually a lot of companies are evolving
into using this multi-cloud architecture.
So looking at various architectural
patterns that are used currently in
the industry, one one pattern that
we use usually see is like hub and
spoke model, essentially more like a,
a. Central Flo from Hub manages core
services like authorization, monitoring,
governance, all these found foundational
components that are necessary for
building any strong software stack.
It's like a, it becomes a common hub and
obviously you build services on profit.
And the next important thing is once
you build all the services, what is
necessary for them to communicate?
So it's like there is various constructs
or various platforms that are already
built with the service integrations like
ETO and various other things essentially.
When you go into the multi-services
or microservices kind of
environments, all these things
will become extremely important.
The developers doesn't have to
really think about how do we, how
does the orchestration between
the systems are happening?
Obviously, all these existing
tools will really help
accelerate the development a lot.
One of that is like a, providing
that consistent networking,
interservice communication service
measures like, TO and all that and
Kubernetes kind of environment are
extremely useful and important.
And the other important thing is they have
a policy as a code frameworks, essentially
more like governance rules are actually
codified and obviously more automatically
enforced, and compliance without a
manual direction, which makes it much
more easier to run systems that scale.
And these are, again, a very high level
constructs of what are the important
artificial patterns that have seen are
extremely in any cloud environments.
Let's talk about.
Next, let's talk about how do we
optimize developer experience in a
world where development is changing.
I know how we code is
changing pretty significantly.
It's extremely important to give
the freedom for the developers
to, build at scale faster and all
those good things about, how can
they test it, deploy it at scale.
Providing all this framework extreme,
but there's a few things I would touch
upon the similar aspect of it, as most
importantly, intelligent code AI tools.
If you look at right now, it's like
it's all lot of gen AI tools are
extremely useful exhaust industry,
like industry like something like we
have a GitHub co. Like a lot of similar
things where you know, all the other
LMS also have similar tools as well.
So these are.
Proven to be extremely useful in building
some kind of a boiler plate code.
Whether it is like building some
test cases for whatever code
we have written and obviously
helping provide custom insights.
So how do we fix the code with any bugs?
And it, they, things are evolving
and also providing a lot, but
these tools are getting much
better as well as they get better.
The user in developer productivity is
also significantly increasing a lot.
And the next important thing is
like CACD models, but we need
to have a strong CACD system.
But again, what does A CCD mean?
And automated testing
pipelines, whenever developer.
Pushes a code, a strong
enforcement of testing all the
core components as unit tests.
And obviously we have some
kind of integration test
the code deployment as well.
So having that necessary checks and
balances would, we, would really improve
our on aspect of it at the same time.
We have right checks to make sure
that, quality code is getting into
production and other important
aspects, self, et cetera.
Things can go wrong all the time, right?
So I think how can we build our
system such that when something
really goes bad, it can self heal.
It can be like it.
It can be as simple as saying some,
the new build that is deployed into
production, we have some kind of some kind
of a cannery kind of deployments, right?
In that case, if some new build
doesn't work really well, it self
heals and also go, goes back to
the previously healthy build.
So that's one example of how can we
build infrastructure or deployment
pipelines, which can really
improve the developer experience.
At the same time, we have
that star stable software star
running in production without any
interaction at any point of time.
These are a few things I want to touch on.
Want to see how can we build
strong developer confidence.
And it is a lot of unnecessary, all
of the developer, the best thing
they're good at is like building code.
So obviously providing that opportunity
to build strong code and also giving
all the tools and infrastructure
to accelerate that and support
that is the best thing that we can
provide in any cloud environment.
So that's one few things I
want to touch upon this aspect.
The next thing is, so
infrastructure code care.
So since we are taking care of the
developer experience, they're able to
build the code, deploy the code, test
the code, and then extremely important
aspect of is like now we need to
also look at where it gets deployed.
So basically you are trying to
deploy things essentially, right?
So it gets into some vm, some kind of a
Kubernetes environment or various other
constructs, or like a microservice.
In a cloud kind of environment.
So in that case the most
important thing is like that.
Now we are dealing with all the hardware
of it, like all the VMs and how do we
deploy as a microservice, whether it
is allow like a docker containers or
all that in the construct Kubernetes.
So we have something like small
parts and stuff like that.
So how do we package them?
How do you deploy them?
These are extremely important constructs
when you go into this at scale deployment.
So building that, there are a
few things I wanted to touch
upon in the same aspect like.
Building this infrastructure as
called a few things like in a
moderate template, libraries, and so
this is more when we want to build
reusable components, again, it's more
there are various constructs to it.
So basically autoscaling, the
infrastructure is one part of it.
If we are exceed some limits of the
infrastructure, obviously we can
have some kind of templates which
can kick in and, expand as service.
For example, that this,
there is some construction.
Our workloads are not more than what
we have currently purchased from cloud,
and we can have those con controls
and checks to essentially expand our
infrastructure in a way that we have more
compute available to run our workloads.
Similarly, GI Tops workflows is an
extremely important role as well.
Again, the same thing, providing
audit trail of what has went
and what is rolled back, and all
those other good things there.
Again, the other important thing is
after we have provided all this as
scale components, again, extremely
important thing is we have to look
at the complex scaling as well.
So just making sure that whatever
libraries that we're building as part of
the infrastructure deployment is they're
all security tested, is like a lot of
other tools that can help us build even
for the, as simple as docker containers
or what the Kubernetes environment we.
Can have some kind of automatic tools
that can scan these containers and make
sure that none of the libraries that
are built and has some known library
vulnerabilities and make sure that.
These are compliant and secure
before they're put in production.
So that is one aspect of it, which
are extremely important in a way.
And once we touched upon that,
first we talked about developer,
how can we make him agile and make
him faster, and stuff like that.
And talked about what are the constructs
of, infrastructure, how can we.
Build an infrastructure which is robust
and compliant and all those good stuff.
Now, once we have all those important
things started out, next important
thing is like how do we make what
we built is successful, right?
So there are various metrics
that I look that we can look at
is technical metrics obviously.
So I think from the
technical aspect of it.
So how fast are we deploying, right?
The mean and lead time of the change.
So know, mean, time to record if
things and things go bad, how fast we
can refer from it, and key insights.
What are the failure rates looking like?
So these are all like very good or
important technical metrics that
would eventually provide us insights
into how fast we are deploying code,
how fast we are reacting to change.
How fast we are able to, roll
back and, make sure there is less
downtime to the customers, right?
So extremely important aspects of it.
And the other important thing we need
to think about is like business metrics.
Now we look at the technical
construct of it, then we need to look
at the com business aspect of it.
So how much we are spending.
What is the cost for deployment,
ation rates and how much time it
is taking for us to go to market.
I know for example, in traditionally
in the past, when the custom vendor
is, less or no no cloud in a way.
Like a lot of companies used to
build their own data centers.
Know, scaling the infrastructure is.
The relatively difficult aspect of it
because hardware has to be procured from
somewhere and also provisioned and all
those other good things have to happen.
So before we can start utilizing
it for an AI thing, right?
In that aspect, I think.
But if you look at in the cloud,
you know how fast or how agile
we can adapt to new changes.
Like for example, I have to deploy
a new feature which are, or a
new product, for example, where,
how fast we can get it to market.
And obviously to think about an
aspect where I need to release a
product in some other country, right?
It becomes extremely easy or I
don't have to buy hardware from
a different country or whatever
is the good things there, right?
So I think it becomes
extremely easy for us to.
And think about those kind of things.
How are we progressing?
How easy it is.
Are those, some of those metrics
are extremely important as well.
Other thing is develop now we
have built the robot systems.
How do we know, the developers are
really enjoying it or it's becoming
really a painful work experience.
So obviously some of the things that we
could do is look at the surveys, get the
feedback, try to see what is, what are
the pain points and improve on it, right?
Obviously know, I think it's, we have
to improve our product and obviously
we know on a HAL concept, what are the.
Good things that these systems like
our cloud systems can bring in.
And every every system is different and we
have to adapt to the surveys and feedbacks
and make it better or better time.
And now let's touch up on some
important aspects of, the.
What are the emerging trends in
this cloud infrastructure, right?
Platform engineering.
There are a few things
I want to touch on here.
One is like AI power operate, right?
Machine learning models.
Now AI is everywhere.
I think AI is disrupting
a lot of industries.
I think this is also an extremely
important industry, in my opinion,
where a can play a big role.
No, A AI can be able to predict resources
based on existing lit and other co.
Other constructs of it can really
provide, predict what are the needs
of the future, optimize cost, provide
insights, provide suggestions, how do
we improve our cost, apply models, and
I feel like there is a strong importance
that AI can bring into this cloud
platform engineering stuff where it can
improve significantly in my opinion.
Another important aspect is a Jira Trust
engine Securities should be essential.
Part of the cloud platforms is extremely
important, that it becomes the next
number one or, important thing while we
are building this microservices framework
in a more like a cloud environment.
And yeah, one of the important
construct is zero trust.
We start with something considering
that, people have lead next,
pardon me, edge competing support.
Platforms now.
Now this is again, running
on the edge, right?
So more like the iot and realtime.
I think this is all
picking up really well.
I think in terms of, increasing compute
speed and providing that vision and
also providing that capability to run
it with increased networks and all that.
I think iot realtime process is
also has a signal opportunity here.
And now let's talk about how do we
implement these strategies, right?
Obviously we can't really go from
A to B directly and there has to
be some kind of evolution here.
So in my opinion, we start
with a phase approach.
You start with pillar teams, you
start with a some form small teams,
test out, build a real, the base
infrastructure and hello teams to
get add out to this new framework.
Now, whether it is about Microsoft.
Versus framework or if we are building
Kubernetes platform, have some opportunity
to build some base core constructs.
For example, we can have something
like, how do we deploy things?
There is like a various things you can do.
Like you can do some kind of canary
deployments, blue grade deployments.
It's a construct that you
can build into the platform.
The next thing is like what is a
consistent way for the software teams to.
Build their packages and deploy them
into the, so for example, if you take
Kubernetes as a Kubernetes environment
this is again, providing that opportunity
is also having that base layer of platform
built that let cus let team set out this
framework and, provide that opportunities
for engineers to also come in and
contribute to it and make it better.
I feel that is an eventual process.
We start with a few teams, pilot
them and identify what are the
other things that we can make it
improve and you progress on other.
Next important thing is once we have
enough confidence with all the poor
pilot teams, then we start about
socializing with broader teams.
Functional cross-functional teams and also
thinking about how can we make it a shared
ownership now is like this is a platform.
Obviously people can come in
and contribute and improve on
it, and also extend on it and
all those good things, right?
So where other people's, other
teams can also extend it and we
have that big ecosystem of platform.
Within the company.
Yeah.
The next important thing is again, as
I was kept on saying it's a continuous
evolution, things can improve, things
can extend based on the feedback,
we keep improving the platform now.
We keep using it and improving
it based on the rates.
Now, next important thing I want
to touch upon is, so this is a
complexity gap I want to talk about.
So we have operational
tooling built and deploy.
If you look at this like we have
operational tooling and what
all person need to know, there
are knowledge and contracts.
End-to-end responsibility.
So I think this is just
giving a high level view.
What is the intersection?
Operational tooling.
You need operational tooling
for the developers to build
and deploy at the same time.
Operational tooling for
knowledge and conflict, right?
So if you look at this suite, what of
a cognitive load on the cus load on the
developers, it's more like what are all
the things that are extremely important,
if you look at the midpoint where it kind
of merges in, it becomes a collective
responsibility essentially, right?
So that is an extremely sweet spot there.
So now let's talk about
multi-cloud governance, right?
Then again, once we have a strong
system, fundamental foundation and
billing all these good things, extremely
important thing, as I was mentioning
before, is having that security
and compliance in place as well.
So two important two or three
things which are like a lookout.
Things we need to think about is like
inconsistent security controls is
having, without having right policies
in place, it becomes extremely difficult
now calls management, when we move
to cloud, there could be a lot of
offerings, a lot of tools and risk
things that can happen and cost can.
Cost is an important factor
when we use these things.
So having that management
and cost management strategy
is also very important.
And obviously co. Other thing is
less compliance, so making sure that
we are based on the industry we are
in, we are compliant, and making
have the, having that right controls
in places is also very important.
Things that we need to think about.
The next important thing is like
self-service infrastructure.
Why do we need self-service
kind of information, right?
So now if you look at the graph on the
left is like traditional approaching time.
Used to take long time compliance
issues, used to take long
time and developer wait time.
Obviously we talked about some
of the aspects of, traditional
approach of having that data centers.
And next thing is like
platform engineering.
Now we can, we are building
for the cloud, right?
So how can these improve?
Is what we touched upon so far.
So it's more like how can we self-service
infrastructure, it can drastically or
dramatically increase the production times
and obviously provide that insights into
compliance issues and also then improve
the developer productivity over time.
So then I want to touch
upon some golden parts.
How do we balance control and freedom?
So when we give freedom, or there
are a lot of things like, with.
Freedom is a lot of responsibility.
It's extremely important to have right
controls in place so that, yeah, every,
all the things will run as per the
security compliance guidelines, right?
So the, so having that right controls
also will help with few of the
things that I want to touch upon.
He's can, developers can
reducing cognitive load.
They have, they can just
build business logic.
They don't have to really think about,
what are the infrastructure developments,
accelerate development cycles, and
obviously they are more important.
How they want to apply un develop, right?
So I think that's a good thing.
They are.
And they're good at it and
providing that opportunity.
And the other thing is like
consistent implementation.
Having that structured patterns,
ensure security is also very important
and flexible boundaries, right?
When providing guidance
is all for customization.
When there is a new requirement, obviously
demand can debate from standard pattern.
So there are a few golden parts
that we can provide, right?
What do we think of the
future of cloud work?
So I strongly believe it's more
than a technical evolution.
I think the way it's the pace at
which it is improving is significant.
And I would say, so I would say is this
has transformed a lot of industries.
I would say providing that agility
to the developers and the faster
go to market, various things.
So I think the path definitely
is very clear in our robust
platform engineering capabilities.
Will definitely be the future.
And building those foundational
components across the stock are
extremely important for the success.
So those are all the basic constructs
I want to touch for this talk.
Thank you very much everyone.
Have a nice day.
See?