Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My name is NH Kku ti and I'm
a cybersecurity professional
with experience in securing
cloud platforms, data protection
applications, APIs, and AI workloads.
Over the past decade, I've been
deeply involved in securing
enterprise scale systems across
multicloud AWS Azure and GC.
P.
Over the years I've specialized in
embedding security directly into
the development and deployment
process, what we now call DevSecOps.
I've had the opportunity to design and
implement automated security pipelines
where these pipelines that deliver
compliance checks, vulnerability scanning.
Real time threat detection and
robust data security controls.
My work has focused on making security
scalable and repeatable so that controls
are not dependent on manual checks, are
manual reviews, but are codified into
CSCD pipelines, giving faster feedbacks
feedback while maintaining exactly this.
Strong compliance and protection.
My work has focused not just
on vulnerability reduction or
vulnerability remediation, but also
on ensuring data protection and
privacy compliance, aligning within
the frameworks we use PCI or CIS
benchmarks, or NIST and GDPR, et cetera.
I've also contributed to API and data
security initiatives within Akamai.
Defining strategies for sensitive data
handling, tokenization, safeguarding
privacy safeguards while onboarding
workloads for continuous monitoring.
I've also worked on ai security
initiatives applying policies and
maintaining monitoring to safeguard
AI models and protecting AI models
and data and workloads from a new
or evolving or emerging threats.
Today's talk building pro proof pipelines,
security as code for platform engineering.
It focuses on a challenge.
I have repeatedly encountered security,
data protection and privacy too
often treated as a final gate instead
of being embedded from the start.
That's why I have been passionate about
the promoting security as code, a cultural
and technical shift where policy scans.
Data protection and compliance
checks are codified and
automated inside the pipeline.
This not only improves security postures
and privacy controls, but also a
accelerates innovation, making security an
enabler, not a not instead of a blocker.
So that's a bit about who I am.
And why this topic matters to me.
Let's take a quick look
at what we'll cover today.
So you know exactly where we had added
the dual L mandate of
platform engineering.
Platform Engineering teams today
feels a dual responsibility
delivering infrastructure and
applications at scale with speed while
ensuring security and compliance.
Business stakeholders demands rapid
innovation, faster development
deployments and continuous delivery.
Whereas while regulators and
security and customers expect secure
compliant and resilient platforms,
this tension creates a friction.
Developers want agility, and while
security teams emphasize control, security
as a code aims to bridge this gap,
I have one use case.
Consider a service deployment
pipeline where applications
needs to scale on demand.
By embedding security scanning
directly into the CSCD workflow teams
can identify vulnerabilities in AWS
Lambda or Azure functions before
they release to the production.
This entire thing, allowss development
teams to maintain team deliver speed
while still adhering to the compliance
frameworks like NIST or CIS, et cetera.
The third slide, let's go to the
check on the security As a code
proven transformation security.
As code changes the paradigm, security
becomes an enabler, not a blocker.
If you look at the slide,
there is a 65% reduction in
vulnerabilities reaching production.
50% faster time to market, 45%
improvement in compliance scores.
The data shows 78% of organizations
accelerate remediation when
adopting security as score word
the problem.
Security as an afterthought.
Traditional security approaches rely
heavily on manual checks or manual
reviews and late stage testing.
By the time vulnerabilities are
discovered, the code is nearly production
ready, leading to expensive work.
Security and development teams often
operate in silos with different
priorities, creating delays and friction.
The results vulnerability is reached.
Production remediation cycles
are extended, and compliance
postures are weakened.
I wanna give you one example in one
of my pipelines, we used we used to
rely on manual security sign-offs
at the end of the release cycle.
This meant vulnerabilities in terraform
infrastructure or container based images
caught too late causing production delays.
By the time fixes were made, release
timelines had already slipped,
creating frustration for both
developers and security teams.
This is one example.
So how do we make this real?
Let's break it down into the core
pillars of security as a core.
If we look at the slide.
A comprehensive approach that
integrates security at every stage
of the development life cycle.
These are the core pillars
the holistic framework.
It covers automated security
integration, server security,
infrastructure security, intelligent
risk management, secrets management.
Each of these pillars ensures
security is continuous,
automated and developer friendly.
Let's deep.
Let's dive deeper into the first pillar.
Automated security integration
shifts security from manual checks or
manual reviews to continuous protection.
Detect 85% of critical vulnerabilities
before release compared to
just 23% with manual checks.
Tools.
You could see that on the right side.
GitLab, security scanning, Azure DevOps,
security, 45 AWS Inspector, et cetera.
If you look at the, from reactive to
proactive security, there are two things.
Traditional approach and
security as a code approach.
Traditional approach security is
being as a final gate, lengthy
remediation cycles, deployment delays.
Security was a development,
always tension.
Whereas security as a code approach
would make a lot of difference.
There's security at every stage, real
time feedback loops, automated remediation
collaborative security cultures.
Now let's look at how this applies to
serverless and cloud infrastructure.
This is pillar two, serverless
and infrastructure security.
Serverless adoption is surging, but
function level protection is critical.
Security as a code enables vulnerability
detection in serverless functions.
Automated policy enforcement,
real-time validation during deployment
policy as a code.
Frameworks prevent 92% of
common cloud misconfigurations.
But embedded scans is alone is not enough.
Teams often face alert fatigue.
That's where intelligent
risk management comes in.
Pillar three.
Risk management and secrets protection.
A smart alerting and contextual
risk scoring, reduced noise by 60%.
Secret scanning stops 99.7%
of hardcoded secrets before
it gets into the production.
Tools you could use actually car
Wal AWS, secrets Manager, nyk,
or Gate Guardian, et cetera.
I would like to give one example here
in one, one of, in one integration
we used Git Guardian to detect
Hardcoded Secrets in GitLab re reports.
Findings were piped into ServiceNow CV
workflow, where contextual prioritizations
helped us fix critical exposures
immediately while ignoring low risk noise.
I
now, let's see how real
enterprises are already proving
the value of security as code.
The real world enterprise, case
studies, financial services, integrated
fortify, and ways or prisma for reduced
remediation time from weeks to hours.
Healthcare.
They, some of them used Azure
DevOps plus policy as a code.
That led to 70% fewer HIPA audits,
audit failures coming in retail AWS
Inspector in Serverless that led to 50%
reduction in incidents during peak season.
I
Beyond security wins.
What's the business value?
Let's talk our why.
Measuring success, ROI of security as code
security as code delivers measurable
business outcomes, faster delivery,
stronger compliance complaints like.
SOC two PCI dss hipaa, GDPR, et cetera.
Lower costs audit prep, patching,
rollbacks, and all this includes,
and cost savings come from
fever brand breaches, right?
Unless less rework.
For example, when we automated Prisma,
serialized scannings or any security
solution, scannings compliance teams
cut audit preparation time by 50%,
saving hundreds of hours, and ensuring
PCI evidence was always up to date.
So how do organizations
actually implement this?
Let's look at the roadmap,
implementation roadmap.
There are four phases.
Phase one foundation where it
gives pipeline scanning, baselines,
trainings, phase two integration.
Policy as a code secrets
detection feedback, hope loops,
phase three, optimization.
Intelligent.
Risk dashboards, automated remediation,
phase four, maturity, continuous
improvement, chaos, engineering,
threat modeling, automation, et cetera.
Of course, the journey does not stop here.
The future of security
code is even more exciting.
Let's look at the next slide.
The future of platform engineering
with security has core.
You could see on the slides emerging
trends, platform engineering evolution.
Emerging trend trends would be, AI
powered vulnerability prediction,
automated threat modeling, zero
trust, pipeline architecture,
runtime application, self protection.
These will further reduce manual
work and strengthen resilience,
whereas platform engineering evolution,
but security as code represents
the natural conversions of
DevOps velocity with enterprise
grade resilience and empowering.
With platform engineering, DevOps,
security architects, infrastructure leads.
I have one example I
would like to share it.
We have already piloting AI driven anomaly
detection for API traffic in aka it helps
differentiate normal versus suspicious
API behavior, reducing false positive use
and strength in data privacy safeguards.
Let's wrap this up with a big takeaway.
Conclusion.
Security can no longer be bolted on.
It must be owned into pipeline
of benefits.
With this faster delivery, fewer
vulnerabilities in production,
stronger communi compliance
brochure, measurable cost of savings.
Final example.
I would say closing example.
By embedding security across
serverless APIs, containers, IAC
and AI workloads, organization,
organizations, or organizations can
innovate at scale without sacrificing
compliance or data protection.
Finally, for enterprises striving
for both speed and safety, security
as code is no longer optional.
It's essential.
Thank you.