Hello everyone.
I'm Anmar Karu.
I've worked in the identity and access
management domain for more than 10 years.
In that time, I've led programs
in identity governance, privileged
access, and cloud security.
What I've learned from my experience is I
am isn't just about passing audits, it's
about building trust and enabling agility.
With that being said, here
is what I'm gonna cover.
As part of this today's presentation,
first I'll talk about the challenges
in modern platforms, then how I'm
gonna talk about how identities
have evolved, how zero trust,
automation and self-service can help.
Finally, I'll share
results and future trends.
So you can see not just where I am today,
but where it's going to be in the future.
So let's start with the.
Challenges.
In, in the current state cloud
platforms bring speed, but
they also introduce new risks.
All security models like VPNs and
firewalls they don't work anymore.
Developers won't kick access.
Security teams want tight control
and auditors want clear evidence.
This often leads.
A patchwork of tools that adds
confusion instead of solving problems.
So the question is, how do we keep things
secure without slowing the business down?
The answer is to make identity the
heart of security, because as stated
in Gartner's report, identity is the
new security boundary Every login.
Every a PA call, every device
check is an access decision.
Most breaches happen because of
weak or unmanaged identities,
strong IAM changes that.
Automated access reviews remove
manual work and stop audit issues.
Vaulting protects admin accounts.
Single sign-on makes
life easier for users.
That's the key difference between
I am blocking progress and I am
driving it to see why I am matters
most or I am matters so much.
Let's look at how it
has changed over time.
We have more through three phases.
The first one being the traditional
enterprise identity, where there is
a centralized ad and VPNs then happen
the cloud description where hundreds
of microservices with their own rules.
Now infrastructure as code, where access
rules change as fast as the code itself.
The result is a need for zero trust
and a P first identity platforms.
And with that shift zero trust IAM
isn't optional, it's essential.
Let's see what it looks
like in Practice Zero Trust.
I am.
Let's talk about what is Zero Trust.
It basically means every request
is checked every single time.
Some examples that I've listed
as part of my presentation
is contractors get temporary.
Control access with MFA and
just in time provisioning
with an access request system.
If an app is connected,
access is granted right away.
If not, a service is
created automatically.
So it's still tracked in
multi-cloud environments.
Identity platforms like IGA, PAM and
so work together as one control plane.
These use cases reduce risk.
And make access
predictable and controlled.
Now let's look at the tools
and the platform and the
patterns that make them work.
To deliver zero trust in practice,
you need the right tools and patterns.
Key results come from automated
access reviews, pom pam vaulting
and SSO integrations in some
environments like Kubernetes.
Teams use namespace isolation
or automated policy validation.
I focus more on I aim, but the
principle is always the same and
force least privilege and validate
the access before it's granted.
And once you have those patents
in place, the next step is to make
compliance continuous instead of one-off.
In the past, compliance meant big
review cycles and analyst spreadsheets.
Now we can make it continuous by
treating compliance like code, which
means checklists built into workflows,
automated reminders, reports that
are audit auditory all the time.
This doesn't just cut audit hours, it
builds trust that compliance is always on.
Not just checked once or twice
a year, and automation like this
doesn't just help with compliance.
It improves everyday
identity operations too.
Here is what an identity
automation can deliver.
Zero audit flags, thanks to automated
reviews, documentation improvements.
And reports that are built, which would
save hundreds of hours of time, identity
intelligence, which would, you know
generate the access recommendations
for for the reviewers to make an
effective access review decision before
before an access is kept or revoked.
With that being said, this is,
we are at a phase where this
is all data driven, accurate,
efficient, and trusted and better.
Im also makes life easier for
developers because that it's clear that
developers can't wait weeks for access.
Self-service solves that.
Think about service catalogs.
Automated key management or
simple web-based account creation.
Developers move faster,
security, stress and control,
and tickets code on that Balance.
Speed with safety empowers developers
without compromising on the governance.
Here is an industry case study that
shows what it looks like in action.
In healthcare, the challenge,
the common challenge that we see
is managing access of patient's
data while staying by compliant.
The solution used zero trust, automated
provisioning and self-service patterns.
The result provisioning time
dropped from days to under 12 hours.
Incidents went down and audit
preparation got much faster.
And whether it's healthcare, finance, or
technology, the lesson is always the same.
Automation plus zero trust
equals faster and safer access.
Now let's bring these results
into one clear framework.
Here is how I measure success
security machines, zero audit flags.
Operations means weaker
testing, fewer poisoning errors.
Compliance means the number of reports
that were automated, which would I
turn save hundreds of hours per each
business cycle, and the business impact
dozens of new applications that were
onboarded without slowing the delivery.
So I am isn't just about audits, it's
about reducing errors, saving time,
and enabling the faster delivery.
And finally, let's look at
where I am is going next.
As we look ahead, in my experience, I'm
noticing three big trends that stand out.
The first one being the converged
iam, which means identity governance
platforms and privileged access
platforms will no longer be separates.
They'll unify into one platform
giving a complete view of
human and mission identities.
The second one being
automation first governance.
Reviews.
Evidence collection and policy
checks will move from manual work
to always on automat automation.
And the third one being identity in ai.
As AI becomes part of our daily
operations, I a must evolve to govern
both people and intelligent agents.
That's where non-human
identities comes into picture.
Now, NHA governance is equally
critical because there has been a
lot of intelligent agents that have
been spun up on a day-to-day basis.
The end goal is, I am, that feels
invisible, always working in the
background, always enforcing trust and
never slowing people down, and that's
the real future of identity security,
not as a barrier, but as an enabler.
Once Gartner said, identity
is a new perimeter.
Perimeter and trust is a new currency.
Thank you for your time today and
after more than a decade in I am.
I can say this with confidence, that
identity is no longer just it plumbing.
It's the foundation of
secure and agile platforms.
Thank you.