Hi myself.
S I do have 10 plus experience
in healthcare integration world.
Currently I'm working
for Henry Ford Health.
Today I would like to start with my
topic as in a building t healthcare
modality platforms for the engineering
epic ride share integration at a scale.
And simply saying that basically we
have an epic EHR systems I would like
to integrate with ride share platform
with the integration for the patient.
So this is about the topic.
About the topic.
So I would like to explain here are
the few agenda items that I would
like to cover in this topic, is that
technical architecture, overview
engineering challenges and microservices
implementation and security observability
and machine learning ops in healthcare.
So these are the agenda items I
would like to cover in the topic.
Now beginning about the how this Epic
integration platform works like an, I
want to give an example how the real
world example, it'll gain a better
explanation about in terms of that.
So let me begin with the problem
that affects a millions of
patients in the United States.
One in five patients either
misses or delays, delays.
Simply because they don't have
any reliable transportation.
Now imagine this is not in
just on a regular checkup.
Think if you, if any dialysis patient or
if any patient, or if a cancer patient
are attending a chemotherapy even missing
in a one appointment, that could be
in a life threatening for the patient.
So it can, it may to have
serious health consequences.
More our hospital visits and
even shorten the life expectancy.
And also it would create an additional
burden to the patient on the like if,
on the insurance as well, because if the
patient doesn't show at the insurance,
the hospital that the provider gonna
put as a no-show, and that would
even charge also for the patient.
So without.
Go without attending to any kind of, any
treatment or not seeing an appointment.
Either way the patient might be lost.
So the thing is that the
challenge is very clear here.
We would like to tell how the solution
is, like healthcare isn't just about
what happens inside the hospital.
It is also a board making sure
patients can actually get there.
Our visions our vision is straightforward
that we want to bridge Epic EHR
record system to the hospital, already
used to manage appointments, the
patient data with the everyday ride
share platform with Uber and Lyft.
The goal for every patient, reliable
in complete and timely way to reach
their care and to the hospital and
get the better patient outcome.
In terms of platform, the if you see
about the numbers the daily, like
6.5 million daily patients, record
exchange the process secured across
the systems and 2,400 plus health
system connected through the platform.
Moving to another another topic here, how
this entire epic ride share integration
challenges, like how it is integrated.
There are some core components
that been involved in this
Epic integration platform.
So Epic Smart Fire, which is like in a
standard, it's fire, is a fast resources,
which is now a trend in healthcare
basically where you will get the patient
access the data within a. Using rest API.
Earlier we used to have an HL seven
version two Dox and three dox.
Now with the file value, it can be, it
is in a set of data standard using a
json with an XML content that can be
used to exchange for this platform.
And, in terms of an architecture,
when you talk in terms of technical
side epic smart and five set standards
like in a grammar for healthcare,
basically it would be like in a.
Communication language easily.
We thought it would be a
doctor's patient's systems, all
speaking different languages.
Now, ride share a p is like an uber relief
warrant built for healthcare platform.
So they were designed for a consumer nce.
So quick pickup is that estimated
arrival time, but they don't
have a built in compliance, the
protection to send to medical data.
So that is where there the
integration layer comes.
Here, this layer acts as in a bridge.
Basically it's like a translator
with a security guard combined.
It makes sure the data flow correctly,
quickly, and securely between Epic
and the ride share system platform
like either Uber, other Lyft.
And moving to the second agenda
topic, is one core engineering
challenges, basically.
So in the core engineering challenges, we
have a bidirectional API flow management
system and fall tolerance implementation.
So now let's talk about the
core engineering challenges.
The first bidirectional API flow, which
Epic needs to share an appointment
detail and a patient can text of the
ride share information that needs to be.
Single things like a driver location,
estimated arrival, and a drop of
confirmation on the both sides.
They need to be constantly sync
between I pick and the patient.
And at the same time, the
app also need to be aware.
So the second the the fault
tolerance implementation is that.
What if the lift goes down, like the
system needs to instantly switch to
another provider, like in a Uber or
without any patient even noticing.
It's like in a, just in a GPS
rerouting you instantly, when
a road is closed, automatically
you'll get in a reroute option.
A the estimated arrival
is like five minutes.
So you can choose this particular map
and you go, where the care must be
also continue without any interruption.
When Lyft goes down,
automatically Uber picks up.
So that kinda platform that we
need to switch based upon that.
And there is a third that most
important is that the HIPAA compliant
data problems, so every single
ride request involves more than 47.
Sensitive variables like a patient name
like entire PHI, which comes as an patient
name, appointment type and pick up type.
Pick up an address, notes, and
put all the mobility needs.
Each one must be an encrypted logged
and auditable and nothing can.
Slip through the cracks, basically.
When in terms of these hip up compliance,
these are abstract challenges.
They're directly impact whether the
patient makes its dialysis today or
in a cancer, or a cancer treatment.
So the, any difference can
make a line between good health
and serious complications.
So this is why engineering isn't
just about a clever code, its
about the patient lives, depending
upon the system that we design.
So moving to the next topic is like an
overall how this, entire platform was
like in a core microservice architecture.
There are like in a, some of the core
components like epic integrations and
transport orchestrators and provider
gateway and patient profile compliance
and age, and there are event bus Kafka.
We have an in the Kafka, where's an
accounting platform system basically
for a Kafka realtime events where you'll
get and transportation request state
changes, appointment updates from Epic.
Driver locations and ET updates
and even the compliance related
to the audit trail as well.
And another component is a PostgreSQL for
transactions, where it gives a complete
registry and billing reconciliation
data and compliance and documentation
and configuration management.
So read of performance like
patient transportation profiles.
Here the data to make this work reliable.
The microservices and event driven
approach with the Kafka, we can
stream events the patient books
when a driver updates their status.
Our ears gives an instant hookup,
such as whether the patient needs a
wheelchair access or that, that gives,
that helps the patient basically.
And this is in a, this
is like an separation.
A powerful where instant,
one giant system trying to.
To do everything, each microservices
like in a specialized hospital wing,
one wing for emergency care and another
for lab test, and another for surgery,
and another for radiology oncology, each
has its own team and its operates on own
services, but apart from that, they're
all connected base secure hallways.
This design means each services can
scale and independently suddenly
for more patient need rides.
During a flu season, the ride
matching services can scale up
without slowing down everything else.
So it's not just an elegant, that
architecture of micro, it's a,
it's always a board, ensures that
patients can depend on these rights
and every time, no matter what it is.
So moving to another agenda.
Topic here is that Kubernetes
orchestrations and SRE practices.
So here we come categorize as a four
components, like in a multi region
deployment, auto scaling, and automated
failover, and can already deployments.
So our system runs on multi
regions on AWS deployment.
Think it, we have a backup
hospitals in different cities if
one goes offline and patients are
automatically routed to another.
Okay.
So care continues without a delay.
We also use a predictive autoscaling.
This means.
Which this means we study
historical clinic loads.
For example, flu season brings
more patients, so the system at
medically scales capacity in advance.
For example, in the COVID we might see
this, if you have more number of patients,
that's also, you can take in a COVID
real world example that auto scales.
If you have more patients
affected with COVID-19 and.
That is one of the best example
to explain for auto scaling.
So not only flu season then
there is an active cluster.
Meaning to our more systems run
at the same time, even if one
fails and automatically another
node pick ups like continuously.
If another node fails, there
would be another backup node.
So when we roll out few, when we
roll out few new features, we don't
push them to every one at once.
We use canary deployments and
just like in a hospital might.
Test a new procedure with a small
group of patients, making it as
a standards practice together.
So these approaches, like 99
point, whatever, these approaches,
like four approaches, which
gives 99.9% as an uptime.
But in healthcare uptime is,
uptime, isn't about convenience.
It's about saving lives.
Moving to another agenda topic.
So security engineering and
zero trust architecture.
So in this also we cover like the
four major components like data.
Protection and authentication and
authorization and network security.
So when dealing with the
patient data, the security.
Security isn't an optional, so
it's in a foundation for a patient.
Healthcare, when we use a zero trust.
Security, which means that
every request must prove itself
no matter where it comes from.
So like checking every visit
at the hospital door, even the
various staff badge or anything.
So no matter what endpoint that
we are getting, so either internal
or external application that is
hinted heating the application.
So we always interest based.
Rotator based tokens encrypt all the
data with a S 2 56 encryption for all
the data transit in force or two and PKC.
On the network side, we
secured the traffic with TLS
and web application firewalls.
But beyond security observability, it's
just a critical, we need a visibility
of both technical and clinical access.
If the API slows down, that's an it's
an ID problem, but if dialysis right
is late, that's an a clinical problem.
It could harm a patient.
So our monitoring separates this signals
so the right team response quickly.
So if we even measure a custom
SLM metrics that tides timelines
directly due, timelines directly to
medical schedule because in one of
the system performance is about and
just number just number and a board.
It's about the patient getting a
care what they need and on time.
So I would like to move to another topic.
The machine learning ops with the
challenges in healthcare, transportation.
This is the other topic that we are
gonna cover in this Also, there are
some of the core components in order
for this thing, like data collection.
Future engineering and model
deployment and con compliant
deployment and continuous monitoring.
So now as a boom of AI and
machine learning also plays a role
improving the healthcare mobility.
Our pipeline moves from data
collection into a feature engineering.
Model development and deployment,
and finally monitoring.
But healthcare brings a unique challenge.
Patient data is often in incomplete,
and transparency in critical, and
clinicians need to understand why the
AI system is made as a recommendation
despite these challenges, the impact
significant in our deployments.
AI help to reduce the
patient no-show by 42%.
Here is in a simple example, I suppose
the system learns that Mr. John Doe often
cancels the rates on Monday morning.
A can proactively schedule a
backup for that ride and send a
reminder reducing, risk mis care.
So in healthcare mobility, every
predictive or step A takes a sense of one
more patient, get there an appointment
on time leading to a better outcome.
So if you see here the plat, the platform
what are the graph that you would use
in the successful, 10 x graph spikes
during the weather emergencies and
processing 15 million transportation
even in monthly and reduce 42% I
was discussing in the previously.
So moving to, oh the design
the design on the platform.
So let me share the real case
study on this platform reliability
metrics and engineering impact.
At a midsize hospital in Chicago,
about 40% of dialysis patients are
missing an appointment each month.
Because of un reliability transport,
that's the nearly half of the patient
unable to get a life saving treatment.
We implemented this platform
integrating with Epic scheduling
directly with Lyft, API Patient needs
like an wheelchair access for care.
Notes we are mapped automatically
into a right request during
a Midwest Tom in Chicago.
So the system held a strong thanks
to multi-region failover, even
in harsh conditions as well.
So the patients still got their
own appointments and the results
were dramatic, and NoShow has
been dropped almost like 40%.
If you calculate in with just
15% in six months the patients
reported higher satisfaction.
When we integrated this epic rates side
platform, clinicians also received about
20 hours each month because they no longer
had manually coordinated the transport.
And also the insurance companies,
which are the, whatever the providers
charge for the insurance for.
If you don't show as a no show
that may be also charged, right?
So that also reduces a
little bit dropped as well.
So moving to another topic here the key
takeaways of the platform engineering.
Here we have four components like
design API, clinical workforce and
manage sensitive data across the
systems and implement healthcare
compliant in CICD pipeline.
And also align monitoring with
the clinical requirements as well.
So for an engineer, there are
like whatever the four topics
and the big lessons here.
First, API in healthcare must be
designed around a patient care,
not just in a data exchange.
Every call impacts that real lives.
Second appliance, isn't
this something you.
TAG or later, CRCD pipelines must automate
approvals and audits from the beginning.
The third is that governance
of sensitive data is critical.
Every piece of a patient
information must be addressable.
I end to end basically.
And finally, the observability needs
to be served on both IT and clinicians.
Team, it's not enough to
know if the system is fast.
We need to know if the patient actually
got their own appointment in end time.
So these day, these four takeaways.
That shows that building of in healthcare
means thinking beyond the code.
It's about designing the system
that protects scale and heal
for this entire platform.
So moving to another topic that I would
like to end with the entire my topic.
It's an end basically I would like
to put my closing statement about
this Epic integration platform
with Uber or Lyft or whatever.
So we are not just solving a
technology problem here, we are just
addressing healthcare equity problem.
Too many patients miss care
because of transportation fail.
For a platform engineers, the
challenges is to embrace compliances
and security and reliability.
The design drivers not blockers.
This is a mindset where.
What the system makes like this possible.
And here is a moral memorable
point that I would like to leave
in this entire presentation.
So in healthcare uptime isn't just a
metric, it's a lifeline, basically.
And this system we build don't
just move data code, they move the
patients, they keep the treatment.
And track and they save the lives.
And that's why this works matter.
And thank you for giving this opportunity.
I would like to close my presentation.