Hello everyone.
Welcome to this session on Engineering
Intelligence Transforming Healthcare
with BI and AI from Data to Outcomes.
I'm Ali Krishna.
I go by Krishna, and I'm from
the institution of Electronics
and telecommunication engineers.
In today's talk, I'll share how platform
engineering is reshaping healthcare.
Helping us turn raw, fragmented
data into intelligent insights
that drive measurable outcomes.
We'll explore how clinical, operational
and financial domains are converging
under a single vision, intelligent
healthcare systems that don't just
process data, but actively improve
care, delivery and patient experience.
Now healthcare is in the midst
of a fundamental transformation
driven by platform engineering.
For decades, hospitals struggled
with the siloed systems.
Data fragmentation and
inefficient workflows.
But now AI and BI form the backbone
of intelligent healthcare systems.
We are witnessing standardized integration
replacing patchwork legacy systems.
Platform engineers are the architects of
this revolution, designing systems that
unify diverse data and enable innovation.
Most importantly, we are moving from
technology pilots and aspirations
to measurable outcomes, reducing
costs, improving clinical accuracy,
and enhancing patient satisfaction.
Throughout this session, I'll show you
how these capabilities are engineered
at scale and how they are already
changing the healthcare ecosystem.
Here is the agenda, and this
is our roadmap for today.
We'll start by discussing the
current healthcare engineering
challenges, issues like a data
fragmentation, lack of interoperability
and integration complexity.
Then I'll walk you through the
BI and AI platform architecture.
What makes it scalable,
secure, and compliant?
Next I'll share real world case
studies where hospitals and health
systems achieved a measurable impact
both clinically and financially.
And finally, we'll wrap up with adoption
strategies and explore future paradigms
what healthcare intelligence might
look like in the next coming decade.
So let's begin.
The challenges.
The average health system today operates
more than 16 different platforms, and most
of them using incompatible data models.
This is a challenge.
Over 80% of healthcare data is
unstructured, locked away in physician
notes imaging or scan PDFs, and
it's growing nearly 50% every year.
On top of this, compliance frameworks
hipaa, GDPR, and new AA regulations
add multiple layers of complexity.
And when it comes to interoperability,
only 30% of hospitals have
achieved meaningful integration
despite regulatory mandates.
These engineering barriers slow down
innovation, and unless we address them.
Potential of healthcare
data will remain untapped.
Modern healthcare intelligence
platform is not a single tool.
It's a layered ecosystem.
Firstly, the data integration
layer built with the FHIR based
APIs, realtime streaming, and ETL
or E three pipelines that unify.
Structured and unstructured data.
Secondly the analytics processing layer
where NLP extracts meaning from text
dashboards provide actionable visibility
and machine learning models, predict
patient risk or resource needs, and
finally, the delivery infrastructure.
Ensuring secure role-based access,
seamless workflow integration and
explainable AI so that clinicians
trust and adopt these tools.
When all these layers come together, the
platform becomes more than a data system.
It becomes a realtime intelligence
engine for the healthcare.
At the heart of modern healthcare
platforms is FHIR, which is stamped
as a fast healthcare interoperability.
Resources.
FHIR has become an essential standard
for healthcare integration because.
Speaks the language of today's developers
using restful API framework instead of
outdated rigid data exchange format.
And this restful API framework
is very popular and known by
most of today's developers.
And since the year 2021, adoption
has skyrocketed by nearly 87%.
Hospitals that use FHIR see
integration projects completed
63% faster than by using HL seven.
And critically organizations
realize over three times the
written on investment because data
flows more freely across systems.
FHAR is not just a technical standard,
it's the bridge that enables.
Secure, granular and scalable access to
both structured and document-based data.
It lays the foundation for everything
from clinical analytics to AI deployment.
Now, clinical intelligence covered by
AI is no longer an experimental field.
It's real, and it's
delivering results really.
In dermatology, AI achieves over
95% diagnostic accuracy compared
to 86% for human dermatologists.
In radiology, AI reduces false negatives
for lung module detection by 26%
directly impacting cancer diagnosis
and survival rates, and in pathology.
AI speeds diagnosis by 60%,
maintaining near perfect accuracy.
But these breakthroughs
don't happen in isolation.
No.
Platform engineers make them practical
by embedding AI models into clinical
workflows so that physicians see
decision support to clean their
systems just at their fingertips
without disrupting care delivery.
This is how we scale intelligence rather
than leaving it in just research labs.
Let's see guest study here.
Here's a real world
example, a medical center.
The emergency department faced severe
overcrowding and longboarding times,
so they built an integrated BI and AI
platform tailored for ED operations.
So the results were transformative.
Boarding time for admitted patients
dropped by 32%, and trash was accelerated
by 41%, powered by AI driven production.
And the system generated over $4.2
million in annual savings through
smarter resource utilization.
The key was not just
analytics, but integration.
We connected real time
capacity management there.
Predictive analytics and machine learning
triage into one unified platform.
So this is engineering intelligence
in action, solving a real operational
bottleneck with measurable outcomes.
Financial intelligence is another area
where AI is proving game changing.
Revenue cycle operations traditionally
suffer from inefficiencies,
delays, and preventable denials.
But with PI and ai, we are changing
that NLP extracts Billing critical data,
buried in unstructured clinical notes.
NLPs popular for doing this kind of task.
FLAG claims that are likely to be
denied before they're even submitted.
Automated coding ensures compliance
and maximizes the reimbursement.
And BA dashboards track revenue
leakage in real time, something
that used to take months to uncover.
So the impact, a 67% drop in denied
claims, a 23% boost in real claim claims.
And a 12% increase in overall revenue.
This is financial engineering
applied to healthcare, turning hidden
insufficiency into a tangible value.
Now, one of the biggest engineering
challenge is unstructured data in
terms of clinical notes, discharge
summaries, referral letters.
Over 80% of valuable clinical
insight is hidden in these documents.
Natural language processing or NLP
allows us to extract this information
with over 92% accuracy techniques like
named entity recognition, sentimental
analysis, and medical calls of
detection term unstructured text into
structured FHIR compliant resources.
These structured insights can then
power population, health analytics,
quality reporting, or even AI
driven clinical decision supports.
And today's NLP pipelines
reach 94% occupant accuracy in
medical terminology extraction.
That means we are unlocking knowledge
that was once inaccessible and
making it available for real time.
Intele now.
Healthcare transformation is
not just about operations, it's
about the patient experience.
BI and AI enable truly
personalized engagement.
And as I have previously mentioned,
AI came into a great companion
for bi now, resulting in great
success, greater success.
So predictive care pathways, identify when
and how to intervene for each patient.
Optimizing outcomes and
avoiding unnecessary visits.
And NLP powered outreach
increases response rates by 78%
compared to generic messages.
Ensuring patients are more engaged
and proactive in their care.
And AI driven virtual health assistance
provide 24 by seven triage and support.
Reducing care while extending the
reach of clinicians nowadays, everybody
knows is virtual health assistance.
So picking up and very widely popular.
And together these tools enable
personalized medicine at scale,
giving patients the right care at
the right time and in the right way.
And building these platforms is not easy.
Success depends on matching
solutions to organizational
readiness, and it is not just having
a great or high-end technologies.
Implementing these technologies
together is a real challenge.
And coming to the readiness of
the organizations, a low readiness
environment should start small, like
with small pilot programs and simpler
tools while focusing on building data
quality and cultural readiness and
high readiness organizations with
infrastructure and expertise in place can
go further deploying advanced analytics.
Machine learning and
enterprise wide intelligence
platforms across all settings.
The success factors are consistent,
cross-functional collaboration
between technical and clinical
teams, incremental rollouts and
clear ROI metrics defined upfront.
So the pitfalls are also clear, focusing
on technology instead of the problem.
Underestimating the importance of
data quality and failing to integrate
tools into clinical workflows.
One shouldn't ignore these things when
building systems engineering successes,
less about the tools themselves and
more about how we align the them with
the people, processes, and outcomes.
Looking ahead several emerging paradigms
will shape the next decade of healthcare
intelligence, federated learning.
Where AI models are trained across
multiple institutions without
sharing raw data, protecting privacy,
while enabling collaborations.
SOA models can be trained
in a different institution.
Different similar institution like yours,
but just without without exposing the
actual data, ambient intelligence, sensor
rich environments, the document encounters
automatically reducing the administrative
burden on clinicians and multimodal AI
combining imaging, text sensor data, and
genomics into unified patient insight.
Creating a 360 degree view of health.
And finally, AI regulation compliance,
ensuring that every system we build is
transparent, explainable, and auditable.
These paradigms are not futuristic.
They're already taking shape and
platform engineers will be the ones to
make the operational at school here.
We are at the end of our
presentation in the last slide.
Let's wrap up.
Okay.
To wrap up A-F-H-A-R based integration and
standardized APIs are no longer optional.
They are the foundation of
modern healthcare platforms.
The true measure of success is
measurable outcomes, clinical
improvements, operational efficiencies,
and financial games that prove ROI.
And most importantly, sustainable
change comes from cross-functional
collaboration, tech technical experts,
working hand in hand clinicians to
deliver practical, usable solutions.
The future of healthcare engineering
is not just about building more
advanced technology, it's just about
the building intelligent systems
that amplify human capabilities and
transform patient outcomes at scale.
That's it.
Thank you.
Thank you all for my presentation.