Hello everyone.
My name is Lata Putar Laka,
and I'm currently working as a
senior, a and developer at the
US Food and Drug Administration.
I bring 18 years of experience in the
financial and healthcare industries.
Having worked extensively as a
QA automation architect, I have a
strong background in automation.
Quality assurance and
process optimization.
Today I focus on leveraging low-code
platforms to accelerate application
development, streamline workflows,
and deliver scalable solutions
that meet complex business needs.
My deep industry knowledge, combined
with low-code expertise, allows me
to build efficient, compliant and
user-friendly applications that drive
innovation and operational experience.
I am passionate about creating scalable
applications using visual development
tools, enabling me to rapidly deliver
powerful solutions that bridge the gap
between business needs and technology.
By minimizing traditional
coding, I help accelerate project
delivery, improve collaboration,
and drive digital transformation.
I enjoy turning complex problems
into simple automated workflows that
empower teams and enhance productivity.
I am excited to take you through
a journey of transformation from
the fragmented manual process.
That have long slowed down clinical
research to a future where automation
and low-code platform drive
agility, precision, and innovation.
We are going to explore how modern
clinical research operations can
evolve through smart platform
engineering, leveraging low-code
technologies and automation to
remove inefficiencies, reduce human
error, and ultimately accelerate the
delivery of medical breakthrough.
Our goal is not only improve research
outcomes, but to positively impact
patient care, faster, smarter,
and with greater reliability.
Let's dive in.
To understand why automation and low-code
platforms are so critical, we first
need to acknowledge the challenges that
currently plague clinical research.
Despite being the engine of
medical innovation, clinical
research operations are still
bogged down by three major issues.
First, there's paperwork overload.
Many teams still rely on paper
forms, manual data entry,
and physical documentation.
This creates bottlenecks, increase the
risk of human error, and add significant
time and cost to every phase of research.
Second, regulatory complexity.
Navigating complaints, requirements across
ethics boards, government agencies, and
institutional review boards is not only
time consuming, but resource intensive.
It creates a massive administration burden
that distracts from actual research.
And finally, fragmented data systems.
Researchers are constantly switching
between siloed systems, EHRs,
lab systems, trial management
platforms just to reconcile data.
Instead of analyzing results,
they are stuck performing tedious
data integration task at the,
and the image here tells a story.
Brilliant minds are stuck under
piles of administrative work
when they should be innovating.
This is the reality we aim to transform.
Even though research teams are highly
skilled and deeply committed to
advancing science, the reality is
they are spending far too much time on
administrative work instead of research.
Let me share some numbers that
illustrate the challenges.
60% of research coordinators
time is consumed by documentation
and manual data entry.
That time they could be spending
engaging with patients or focusing
on trial execution, but instead they
are managing forms, spreadsheets,
and disconnected systems.
On average, a researcher has to log
into three to five different systems
each day just to complete core task
that adds unnecessary complexity,
drains time, and increases the
chance of data inconsistencies,
and the impact is significant.
25% of clinical trials are delayed not
because of scientific barriers, but
due to the administrative bottlenecks.
That's one.
In our four trials, potentially
life-saving treatments slowed
down by outdated workflows.
These inefficiencies are
more than frustrating.
They directly delay patient's
access to new therapies.
Clearly, it's time to reimagine the
way research workflows are designed and
executed, and that's where automation
and low-code platforms come in.
Now that we have seen the challenges,
let's talk about our vision.
We believe clinical research
platforms should no longer be
a source of frustration, but
instead a source of empowerment.
Our goal is to build platforms
that are modular, automated, and
integrated modular so that they can
evolve with research needs, adapting
without requiring full results.
Automated to remove repetitive
to manual task, freeing up
researchers to focus on the science.
And integrated so that data flow
seamlessly across systems, reducing
friction and improving accuracy.
Ultimately, we want researchers to
spend less time wrestling with tools
and more time doing what they do
best, innovating, experimenting, and
pushing the boundaries of science.
Technology should handle
complexity behind the scenes.
That's the heart of our approach, using
smart automation and low-code platforms
to make the heart vision a reality.
We are not just solving
human efficiencies, we are
accelerating medical progress.
Now let's talk about how we can
bring this vision to life, and
that's through low-code platforms.
Low code is a game changer because
it allows research organizations
to rapidly build and evolve
applications without requiring
deep software development skills.
There are three powerful benefits.
One rapid prototyping.
Research teams can test and deploy
new workflows in days, not months.
This speed means we can spend faster than.
New to new trial needs, regulatory
changes or process improvements without
wasting for traditional IT talent.
Second is the customizability.
No two clinical trails are exactly alike.
Low-code platforms allow for
flexible configurations, so each
workflow can be tailored to the
unique needs of the study without
rebuilding everything from scratch.
Third and last, accessibility, perhaps
most importantly, low-code makes
digital transformation more inclusive.
Even non-technical stakeholders like
clinical coordinators, regulatory
leads, can take part in designing
workflows that meet their day-to-day.
Operational needs.
So in essence, local enables smarter,
faster, and more collaborative innovation,
and it's one of the most effective ways to
remove friction from research operations.
This case study really brings
a transformation to life.
Let's start with the challenges before
implementation, which are all too
familiar across many research teams.
The first one is a manual data
entry meant that staff were
entering patient information into
spreadsheets, a slow error from process
that created data about clinics.
Startup delays occurred because trial
immunization depended on fragmented
systems and manual approvals offered
dragging timelines out of weeks.
And complaints are nightmares where
audits require weeks of staff time
to manually gather, validate, and
compile documentation for regulators.
Now look at the impact after implementing
low-code automation, electronic
data capture replaced manual forms
with automated systems, improving
data accuracy and reducing delays.
Streamlined startup.
Automated workflows
meant trial minimization.
Time dropped from weeks to just pace,
and finally, the continuous complaints.
With real-time monitoring and
built-in audit trials, staff could
meet regulatory requirements without
the chaos and last minute scrambles.
This shift didn't just improve efficiency.
It fundamentally changed how the
team worked, enabling them to
move faster with few errors and
more confidence in compliance.
Now let's take a look at how
this solution comes together.
From a technical perspective, we have
built a modular platform architecture
where each component is designed to
work independently at, seamlessly
integrates with the rest of the system.
First, we have data capture.
This is where clinical data enters
the system either through electronic
forms, APIs, or direct system input.
It ensures accuracy right from the start.
The integration engine connects diverse
tools like EHRs, lab systems, and third
party software into a unified workflow.
This eliminates the
friction of siloed systems.
With workflow automation, we streamline
routine tasks like documenting,
routing, notifications and approval
ing, reducing human intervention,
and speeding up timelines.
Complaints man.
Monitoring is a built in, so audits and
checks can be done in real time, and
we maintain a clear audit trial without
needing extra effort from the team.
Finally, the analytics dashboard gives
stakeholders clear visibility into
performance, bottlenecks and trends,
allowing for faster data-driven decisions.
The key takeaway here is flexibility.
Each component is independently
deployable, meaning we can scale or adapt
to changing regulatory and clinical needs
without overhauling the entire system.
This slide highlights one of
the most powerful shifts enabled
by our platform, moving from
periodic to continuous compliance.
Traditionally, complaints relies
on scheduled audits, which are
reactive and time consuming.
But with automation, we
take a proactive approach.
Real time validation rules
captures inconsistencies as
data is entered, preventing
errors before they can snowball.
Automated crosschecks can run behind the
scenes continuously, comparing data across
systems to flag discrepancies early.
Comprehensive audit tile trials are
automatically generated, sharing every
system interaction, and making it easy
to trace what happened, when and by whom.
And we have automated complaints
reporting, which can instantly
produce regulatory documents.
No more scrambling for audits.
The result, we have seen error
rates reduced by 87%, and compliance
preference time cut by 65%.
That means fewer surprises, less
manual burden, and significantly
faster audit readiness, all
without sacrificing a rigor.
Technology alone is rarely enough to
de drive successful transformation,
especially in risk adverse clinical
environments where change can be
met with hesitation or resistance.
This line or this slide outlines
key human factors that ensures
smooth platform adoption.
Stakeholder buy-in early engagement
with researchers, coordinators,
and regulatory staff is critical.
This involvement helps.
Align platform features with
real on the ground needs rather
than relying on assumptions.
When people heard and involved,
they more invested in success.
Change management.
Rolling out new technology
can disrupt workflows.
So structured training programs
and phase rollouts are essential.
These approaches minimum disruption
and build user confidence
step-by-step, promoting progressive
success, user-centric design.
Our interfaces are designed for usability
across Tyler's technical skill levels,
so that users feel encouraged to adapt
the platform rather than resist it.
Intuitive two, design reduces friction
and fosters positive user experience.
Pilot programs starting its small
control trials, allows us to
demonstrate tangible value earlier.
This builds trust and creates
internal champions who advocate
for wider implementation later.
Addressing these human factors alongside
the technology itself is vital for truly
successful transformation in healthcare
and clinical environments, resistance
to changes common due to concerns
around complaints and operational risks.
Our approach specifically targets these
barriers with four key strategies.
Regulatory alignment.
We demonstrate however automation
tools enhance compliance
rather than compromising it.
This helps elevate fears that
new technology will create
regulatory issues, it improvements
rather than overwhelming users.
With big challenge at our at once
we roll out improvements gradually.
This phased approach helps staff adapt
more comfortably and reduces resistance.
Outcome Deco documentation.
We rigorously track and can document the
positive results of platform adoption.
This builds confidence among stakeholders
by showing tangible benefits.
Executive sponsorship.
The last one.
Securing strong leadership
support is crucial.
Executive sponsors help overcome
organizational in error and drive
monument for change from the top.
By addressing compliance concerns,
providing clear evidence of benefits,
and managing change clear carefully.
We help healthcare organizations
move past the resistance and
successfully adapt new platforms.
This slide highlights the
measurable business outcomes
that demonstrate the return on
investment from platform transition.
In clinical research environments,
reduced admin time by 42%.
Automating administrative task reduces
overhead freeing research staff to
focus more on science and patient
care rather than by paperwork faster.
Trial setup by 65% By streamlining
workflows through automation, we
shorten the time from protocol
approval for the first patient,
enrollment accelerating trial.
Fewer data queries, 87%.
Automated validation at the point of
data entry significantly cuts down on
data clarification, request, improving
data quality and reducing delays.
Audit readiness automation
provides compliance documentation
on demand, greatly reducing
the need for manual compliance
during automation, during audits.
Together these outcomes drive faster
trial timelines, lower operational
cost, and ultimately enable quicker
delivery of treatments to patients.
This slide highlights the measurable
business outcomes that demonstrate
the return on investment from
platform transmission into
clinical research environments.
A reduced admin time by 42%.
Automating administrative task,
reduce overhead, freeing research
staff to focus more on science and
patient care rather than paperwork.
Faster trial setup by streamline
workflows through automation.
We shorten the time from protocol
approval to the first patient,
enrollment and accelerating trial
initiation, fewer data queries.
Automated validation at the point of
data entry significantly cuts down on
data clarification, request, improving
data quality and reducing delays.
Audit Readiness automation provides
complaints to documentation on de
demand greatly reducing the need
for manual comply during audits.
Together these outcomes drive
faster timelines, lower operational
calls, and ultimately enable quicker
delivery of treatment to patients.
This slide highlights three
transformative trends shaping the
future of clinical research platforms.
AI driven analytics machine learning
algorithms will enable early
detection of patterns in trial data.
This leads to smarter decision making and
the potential to product patient outcomes
more accurately improving trial success.
Blockchain for compliance immutable
ledgers provided by blockchain
technology will enhance transparency
and trust among all stakeholders.
This will simplify compliance
management, especially for multi-site
and international trials, ensuring
data integrity and audit readiness.
Global interability.
As research expands across borders,
platforms must integrate seamlessly
with diverse healthcare systems and
navigate varying regulatory frameworks.
This will facilitate smoother
collaboration and data sharing worldwide
accelerating medical advancements.
These innovations promise to make clinical
research faster, more relatable, and
more collaborative on a global scale.
This slide emphasizes the shift in
clinical research platforms from
being tools solely for researchers to
platforms that actually engage patients.
The next generation on platforms
will facilitate direct patient
reporting via mobile and variable
devices, enabling real time data
capture beyond traditional settings.
They will support real wide evidence
collection, gathering data from
everyday environments to better
reflect actual patient experience.
Patients will benefit from patient
directed trail matching, where
the personal health data helps
identify relevant clinical trials.
Additionally.
Transparency DA dashboards will provide
patients with ongoing insights into
trial progress and impacts fostering
trust and engagement overall.
This evolution democratizes research
participation leading to richer,
more diverse data sets than better
represent real wide conditions and
ultimately improve study overcomes.
This slide highlights the significant
benefits clinical research
platforms can achieve by moving
from manual process to automation.
Faster trials, automation accelerates
discovery and process, speeding up
the development of new treatments
and getting them to patients sooner.
Better data, automated platforms
generate higher quality, more
consistent evidence, enabling more
reliable and actionable conclusions.
Improve lives.
Ultimately, these advancements
lead to medical innovations that
improve patient outcomes and
contribute to a healthier world.
In summary, embracing automation not
only streamlines operation, but also
enhances data integrity and drives
meaningful improvements in healthcare.
As we explore today, the future of
clinical research platform lies in
leveraging, cutting edge tech, cutting
edge technologies and patient-centric
approaches to transform how trials are
conducted and how data is utilized.
AI-driven analytics enable us to detect
patterns earlier and predict patients
outcomes more accurately, making
decision making smarter and faster.
Chain technology ensures transparency
and trust, simplifying complaints
across global multi-site trials.
With global interoperability, we can
integrate diverse healthcare system and
regulatory frameworks, making cross border
research more seamless and efficient.
Equally important is the shift
towards patient-centered platforms.
Empowering patients through direct
reporting, real world evidence
collection personalized trail
matching and transparency dashboards.
This demo democratization of research
participation will generate richer and
more diverse demands reflecting real
world con conditions better than ever.
The journey from manual kiosk to automated
excellence promises, remarkable rewards,
accelerated trials, high quality data,
and most importantly, improved live
lives through medical innovation.
Together these advances will drive a
new era in clinical research, one that
is faster, more reliable, and more
inclusive, ultimately bringing us closer
to better health outcomes for all.
Thank you for your attention.
I'm happy to take any questions.