Today, I'm going to talk about
building efficient and frugal image
data processing pipelines, which is
based on my experience in Amazon.
And this is the agenda.
we will first overview the image
processing use cases in the
large, in the large industry.
the most challenges that we face,
the current state of art solution and
the future invasion we have it for.
And here there are so many examples of
the application of image data, medical
imaging, object recognition for vehicles,
product image and recommendation
for social media and e commerce.
and recently due to AI, its
importance continues to grow, for
multimodal AI training specifically.
most of the challenges come
from large image data sites.
the high storage cost, for storing
vast amounts of image data and
very intense computation when
processing the, image data.
Image quality and the time it
consumes is very long as well.
Sometimes it can become a bottom leg
of the infrastructure for any real
time and time sensitive applications.
and network bandwidth, transforming
those data over network is very
expensive and costly as well.
And most of the time we are
very limited on those resources.
And the goal of this efficient and
frugal pipeline is very important,
such as we're able to minimize the
processing time and optimize the storage
costs and utilization, to have all
Better resource allocation throughput.
The first important thing is
choosing the right image formats.
there are several popular image formats
to consider, but each with its own
advantages and trade off, mostly in
terms of compression and image quality.
there's there.
Here are some commonly used image
formats, like such as, JPEG is the
popular choice for photographers and
the image with complex color gradients.
it offers a good balance between
file size and image quality.
whereas PNG is more versatile
and lossless, suitable for images
with sharp edges and transparency.
And I feel like I would like to go
more details about this popular choice.
JPEG, which we'll be using a lot in
our image processing infrastructure
is known for joined photographic,
photographic experts group, which
actually I'm new to this as well.
it's widely used lossy compression
format for photographers and, As I said,
it has the good balance between the
size and the quality, and also supports
adjustable compression level, allowing
for fine grained control over the tradeoff
between file size and image quality.
it's widely used in web
browsers and editing software.
And the PNG, also new to me, Portable
Network Graphics, that is, unlike
JPEG, PNG preserves all image
data, ensuring that no quality is
lost even after multiple edits.
It supports a wider range of colors and
transparency than JPEG, making it very
ideal for logos, icons, and graphics.
And there is some breakdown of
the next generation image formats.
Yeah, I think, for example,
WebP, that's all for both
lossy and lossless compression.
H, like HIC, that was high efficiency
video coding for compression.
and AVIF.
that's based on the AV1 video codec.
it's very promising, even better
than compression that WebP and HIC.
in the realm of image compression,
there's a fundamental trade off
between file size and image quality.
mostly, Like for the low C compression,
it can achieve higher compression ratios.
and it's achieved by selectively
discarding some image data.
It's mostly suitable for application
where minor quality loss is acceptable,
for lossless compression that will come,
that will pr Preserve all image data, but
resolve in larger size is mostly ideal for
application where image fidelity is very
critical, such as medical and archive.
Sometimes, there are.
Yeah, there's a bunch of recommended
compression libraries and tools provide
pre built functionality for encoding and
decoding various image formats that enable
efficient compression and decompression
of image with our application,
mostly including the algorithm and
hardware acceleration capabilities,
which can have an improvement
of the performance.
And this also isolated to the logical
image handling process, which can lead
us to focus on our business use case
when dealing with image processing
here is a way to choose the right image
formats using adaptive compression.
that.
The adaptive compression that can
optimize image storage and the
bandwidth by dynamically adjusting
compression levels based on the
contact and the quality requirements.
Yeah, this is the benefits can
provide us good, better user
experience and cost saving.
And this is how it works.
It will first do the analysis of the
content to identify areas with varying
levels of detail and the complexity.
Based on that, it will have different
compression level, such as smooth
background can be compressed more,
while faces and edges need to compress
less to preserve the visual quality.
And then, then the last is final
encoded image, to a smaller size will
maintain the acceptable, the quality
and the, when it came to infrastructure
is very popular to leveraging cloud
native services for cloud storage
and other, and other system, system
handling that I will go over later.
yeah, cloud computing offers, significant,
offers lots of service that will enhance
the efficiency and the cost effective
of the image processing pipelines, and
these are the popular choices, it will
offer the benefits of, scalability
to Durability, cost effectiveness,
and accessibility, and the image data
can be assessed from anywhere with an
internet connection, facilitating the
collaboration and remote processing.
and we are also using a lot of serverless
computing for on demand image processing.
the popular choice is AWS Lambda.
Yeah, we'll be using AWS Lambda mostly.
and, this is more like we can run
code in response to events without
provisioning and managing servers.
and also these on demand execution
model is good for image processing
such as resizing, resizing, thumbnail
generation, and format conversion.
There are also cloud based image
processing APIs that is very handy, such
as, yeah, we'll be using recognition a
lot, but, comparably Google and Azure
also offer a similar service like that.
and, it helps us with the object
detection, image classification, facial
recognition, and contact or moderation.
Yeah, which is save us a lot of effort
building and maintaining our own models.
And here are some strategy
for optimizing cloud costs.
using spot instance that take advantage
of unused cloud computing capacity.
having the right size resources,
choosing the appropriate instance
type that can match the workload
to, and to avoid over provisioning.
Okay.
Leverage reserved instance, which is
committed to using specific instance
tabs for longer duration, and we can
get discount pricing of that, and, yeah,
monitor and analyze user pattern so
we can identify where we can optimize.
iteratively, budget alert.
Yeah, definitely having the alert to
notify when the cloud spending is exceed
the limits, which can happen quite often.
Data per and distribute processing and the
parallelism, which is also very helpful.
that is how we divided an image
data into smaller chunks and the
process in parallel to achieve
better throughput and efficiency.
And this approach allows us to
leverage the combined processing power
of multiple machines and definitely
speed up our pipeline in the end.
I can give an example of the parallel
task for image processing, such as, such
as we can break the task into independent
subtasks, Resizing, filtering, feature
extraction, and you're able to do these
independent steps, simultaneously, Or in
a concurrent manner, And, optional, if
necessary, we can synchronize the result
of the subtax and obtain the final output.
When it comes to distribute processing
and parallelism, there are also
several, known frameworks that, we can
leverage, Apache Spark, the versatile
distributed computing framework well
suited for the big data processing.
It offers high level APIs for working
with large data sets, and, Dusk
is a flexible library for parallel
program, parallel computing in Python.
and Ray, is a general purpose
cluster computing framework that is
good at, it offers a simple API for
parallelizing Python code and supports
various machine learning library.
These frameworks provide the tools
and abstractions to distribute your
image processing workload across
multiple machines and enable you to
process large data sets efficiently.
And next one is containerization
and orchestration.
Yeah, these two technologies can
simplify the deployment and the
management of image processing pipelines,
such as the containerization like
Docker allows you to package your
application and dependency into portable
containers, and these containers can
run consistently across different
environments, ensuring reproductivity,
reproductivity reproducible and
eliminating compatibility issues and
orchestration, such as Kubernetes,
automating the deployment, scaling and the
management of continualized applications.
this will simplify the process of
deploying your image processing pipeline
across multiple machines and ensure that
they run real, real, Reliably, rather
reliable, even in the face of failures.
And continuous optimization and the cost
motor cost monitoring, as is the crucial
part to, help us remain efficient and
budget friendly, performing tools, happy
you to identify performance bottlenecks by
measuring the execution time of different
stage, once we identify any bottom
like, Bottom next, we can apply various
techniques such as algorithm improvements,
using more efficient algorithm or data
structure, hardware acceleration, leverage
GPU or specialized hardware accelerator.
to offload computationally
intensive tasks.
Parameter tuning, which is like
experiment with different parameter
settings to find the optimal
configuration for the workload.
Yeah, and, caching and memorization
are also very valuable to optimizing
the image processing pipelines.
for caching, we will store the
result of expansive operation.
and this is very beneficial for image
transformations and feature expressions,
feature extractions, which is applied
repeatedly to the same images.
Memorization, will cache function
calls result based on input arguments,
providing redundant computations
when a function is called multiple
times with the same inputs.
And, yeah, this is how mostly we, to,
we are doing for the computationally
intensive and frequent repeated
operations for optimization.
The cloud providers also offer a lot
of tools to service to track resources,
usage and associated costs, which
can, which will give us valuable
insights in the financial footprint
and, yeah, there's a lot of them.
And, we mostly using cloud
watch from a double eyes.
yeah, and it help us to gain the
better visibility into our cloud
experience and make informed decision,
most of the time in the important
business leadership meetings,
the future of image processing is
very, bright with lots of, With lots
of advanced, advanced progress in
artificial intelligence and machine
learning, lots of techniques like deep
learning and neural networks can enabling
sophisticated image analysis tasks.
however, the image
processing technologies is.
can cause some ethical implications,
such as privacy, bias, and transparency.
They need to be carefully addressed
to ensure the responsible and
ethical use of image data.
yeah, that's a hard and controversial
topic where to strike the
balance between the innovation
and the ethical considerations.
for now, we will be evaluating the race
based case by case, mostly about who
our, how, who are the customers of our
images, and based on how much benefits
we can bring to them and, the risks that
we're going to take, to make the, to
make the balance and informal choice.
Here is the overview of
my, of my presentation.
First, we go through the image data
use cases and its applications.
and second, we go through what is the main
challenge, with the large image datasets.
And then we go through the
state of the art solution.
Which in the industry, regarding to
having the right formats, compression
techniques, using cloud native
services, distribute processing and
parallelism, container and orchestration.
And how to optimize and monitor the cost.
and then we through more provocative
thoughts about the future applying,
about the image processing, choices
that we need to make in order to achieve
both innovation and safety measure.
so here, so here.
Yeah.
Thank you so much for, participating
this, this presentation.
And, here is my contact detail.
so feel free to contact me for any
questions and the future follow up.
If you want to collaborate more on the
image processing pipeline and, have, hope
you have a good time at the conference.