Hello everyone.
I am Ajani.
We are here to talk about how to
build an intelligent platform.
Over the years at IBM and at and
t, I've seen what it takes to run
some of the most demanding high
scale platforms in the world.
At IBM, we work.
Multiple enterprise clients building
hybrid cloud platforms at and TI
was part of projects operating at
telecom scale where millions of
customers rely on services 24 by seven.
That experience taught me an important
lesson, so the infrastructure doesn't
just need to scale in size, it also
needs to scale in intelligence.
So that's what we'll talk about
here today, how we can use AI driven
observability and self-healing to make
platforms resilient and future ready.
So picture this, it's 3:00 AM
and it get a call for incident.
So you log into dashboards.
CPU looks fine, memory looks
stable, and you dive into logs.
Millions of lines and traces
missing half of the context.
By the time you correlated the pieces,
the customer impact is already done
and maybe there might be an outage.
So that's the world.
World.
So lots of data, little insight.
So our goal here is to flip that
equation and fear for alarms
and faster root cause detection.
Ideally, no calls at 3:00 AM
So let's look at the agenda.
So to get there, what should we do?
We have to build intelligence intelligent
platforms and use AI where it is essential
to scale and identify problems beforehand.
And how do we architect and implement this
air driven observability in the systems.
Advance anomaly detection and what
goes beyond simple thresholds.
And then we will look at self-healing
infrastructure, which closes the loop.
And finally, an implementation roadmap
with real examples from my work.
And by the end, you'll have a sense
of not just of the why, but also how.
Okay, let's move ahead.
So e evolution of, the platforms, right?
So let's rewind a bit.
At IBMI worked on the enterprise
platform where infrastructure
meant racks of servers, VMware
clusters, or private clouds.
So it was all about uptime,
patching, and careful provisioning.
Fast forward.
The platform supporting millions of API
calls every second for telecom services.
We had to manage real time traffic,
scaling microservices across the hybrid
environments while meeting the strict SLS.
The, this shows the journey of the
platform engineering from managing
the servers to managing the cloud, to
now enabling intelligent platforms.
It's no longer enough to
provision the infrastructure.
The platform itself has to detect,
diagnose, and in some cases heal itself.
That's the future.
So the observability is a foundation
of resilience, but traditional
observability has major flas scale
metrics, logs, traces, work grade
when you are running tens of services.
But when you are running services in
thousands, metrics spike constantly.
So log logs, just looking at
the logs is going to be noisy.
90% of them doesn't matter.
So the traces are fragmented.
So I've seen teams at
and t drowning in alerts.
Each microservices produces alarms,
and most of them are false positives.
So instead of helping
observability becomes distraction.
So the challenge is this.
How do you.
Extract signal from noises.
How do you go from data
overload to real insight?
Okay, that's where AI driven
observability comes in.
So AI is how we bridge the gap, how
it changes the pillars, metrics.
So these are the four pillars.
So the metrics AI looks for
the subtle drifts, seasonality,
and predictive spikes and logs.
NLP models sift through millions
of lines to highlight the unusual
patterns in the error messages.
And then traces the graph.
Graph analysis connects transactions
across the services showing
cause, causality, and not just
correlation instead of C of alerts.
AI gives you context.
It doesn't just tell
you something is wrong.
It suggests what's wrong and where
it started and why it's spreading.
So think of it like moving from RAs
CCTV footage to smart assistant that
points out the suspicion suspicious
activity before it escalates.
Okay, so think about this.
How do we build this?
At and t, our architecture
looks something like this.
So data ingestion, so streaming streams of
APIs, network logs and metrics pipelines,
and then there's a processing layer.
The tools like Kafka, spark
and flunk handling millions of
events are requests per second.
And then there are AI ML models
trained to detect anomalies,
forecast the demand, and.
Correlating the incidents before
they occur and integration
and coming to integration.
The results are pushed back into existing
systems, dashboards, and incident
management, or even CICD pipelines.
So integrating anomaly detection
to our CICD pipelines instead
of deploying the broken builds.
And discovering the problems.
Later, we flagged the regression early.
That meant our saved fewer customer
visible issues and better reliability,
and coming to advanced anomaly detection.
Thresholds are built blunt instruments.
AI gives us more refined tools.
Time series forecast, time series
forecasting, so predict future,
future loads and degradation.
Graph based correlation, NLP on logs, for
example, in telecom signaling services.
So a service might show
tiny latency increase.
Humans would miss it.
An AI model trained in historical outages
can flag it precursor to a major issue.
So that's the difference between
firefighting after the outage
versus preventing it all together
And then comes the root cause analysis.
So root cause analysis is where AI shines.
Traditionally.
Root cause analysis means hours of
bridges on no calls and networking
teams, database teams, application
teams, all sitting together on call
for hours and hours together to
come up to what caused this issue.
AI changes this by mapping dependencies.
And it can highlight one failing
node that triggered thousand
downstream alarms at and t using
AI enhanced dependency mapping.
Cut our RCA time def dramatically.
So from ours, two mere minutes.
Thus the difference between a four
hour outage to a 20 minute hiccup.
So let's talk about self-healing.
Infrastructure detection is great,
but the next step is healing.
Think of infrastructure
is like immune system.
I,
it fights back.
The cycle looks like this.
Detect anomalies, diagnose the.
Problem, root cause.
Decide on remediation and then learn, feed
the results back to the model example,
as an example, automatically restarting
a failure container, scaling APIs during
peak, promotional events like Apple.
Apple release launch, so on and
so forth, and isolating dependency
before taking down the system.
Of course, we can guardrail,
we can add guardrails like
thresholds, approvals, audit logs.
Automation must be
powerful, but also safe.
How do you adapt AI driven observability?
The roadmap usually looks like this.
Assess your observability gaps.
Run a pilot.
Start a small, maybe one critical service.
Start on a critical service, then scale it
across multiple services and environments.
The long term maintenance, continuously
refining the models, learn from the
incidents, and then the key, incremental
key is in the incremental progress.
You don't need to.
I, you don't need a big bang.
Transformation.
Start from where the pain is the greatest.
So where are we heading?
I see three trends.
So reinforcement learning applied
to operations systems that optimize
themselves by trial and feedback.
Safety aware automation.
Balancing autonomy with guardrails
and then industry-wide adaptation
of self-healing by default,
where resilience isn't an add-on,
but a core design principle.
This is the future of
platform engineering.
Okay, let me leave you with this thought.
The future of platform engineering
is not about fighting outages.
It's about building fireproof systems.
AI driven observability, self-healing
infrastructure helps us move from reactive
firefighting to proactive reliability.
It's about giving engineers more time to
innovate and less chasing around the logs.
Thank you.