Hi.
Good morning everyone.
Good evening.
I'm Christian Chu.
I have 20 years of experience in it,
so most of the, my experience belongs
to data migrations and data handling.
And I different have plenty of
expertise in different areas like
financial, automobile, energy,
healthcare, different platforms.
I worked on it.
I have gained a lot of good experience
on data migrations and data handling
projects like heterogeneous data and very
large quantity of data used to handle.
And I work with the data governance and
it supports and controls and everything.
I worked on it.
They like ET tools I worked on now
data stage, Informatica, SSIS, talent,
these, the tools, which they are
developer and new to me is to use.
And I used those.
I do have good knowledge on those
tools and what are the data?
I work on it so generated by the tools
and as per the business requirements.
So I handle a lot of big teams.
Like I used to manage the
team around the 12 people on
onshore and put people offshore.
We have a onshore offshore model.
And so most of the area I used
to work on data handling side
ETLE projects, most of things and
that too in migration and banking
projects like JP Morgan and US Bank.
Those banking side, I work around it.
Most of these migration projects like
MSP two BS promotions and those areas
and coming back to investment sites.
I work with the, currently I'm working
with Fidelity Investments that,
where it's also cloud-based creation
project, which I'm handling right now.
So it's dealing with all four Okay.
Plans and those stuff.
Okay.
And in my career I used different
BM databases like sql Teradata, DB
two and Cloud basis databases like
Databricks Snowflakes and Azure sql.
So these are areas I
work on different tools.
I work on it.
Most of the tools I used to upgrade myself
with new technologies and to furnish
the new requirement to the projects.
And beside that is automation side.
I use the PI spark to get this
good quality of data by using the
PI spark automation tools and set
the turn project I'm using and jc.
So with those two also,
we are doing automation.
Where we can do the declaration.
There are a lot of validations out
there, so many checks out there.
So on capturing screenshots and
validating those logs and everything
is done by the JC automation
tool means automation script.
Yeah.
And beside that I work around on data.
As you mentioned.
I work on lot of times and cloud outside.
So here I'm going to give a presentation.
Building self-service, data platform and
engineering schedule infrastructure for
developers, our companies and those stuff.
And coming to the outline of this
project is the evaluation of platform
engineering has fundamentally
transformed how organization of
projects, data infrastructure.
Slope step, how does infrastructure
is developing in that, in
terms of data approaches?
So day by day there are new challenges
new challenges we have to face and we need
to know, incorporate those new challenges
and we need to come up some solutions.
So to do that, we have good
infrastructure on that.
And the traditional ETL operations
are being reimagined and self-service
platforms that empower, develop developers
while maintaining the enterprise
grade reliability and governances.
Yeah.
And the same time, we need to maintain
the traditional et operations as
well being we need to take as a
foundation of those and we need to.
Based we need to build a new
infrastructure and new ideologies
and we need to transform from the
traditional ETL new ETL cloud-based
or self-service data platforms.
Yeah, this is, this slide tells you
about the platform engineering ERs.
Like product oriented thinking
and developer integration and
balancing cable and complexity.
The first point is product
orientation training.
The platform engineering represents a
chip from the traditional infrastructure
management to the product oriented.
Thinking about internal capabilities.
And and the second one,
develop integration.
The most effective data platform feels
natural to application and developers and
integrating with familiar CACD and process
and established pattern sec, continuous
integration and condition deployment.
Third process will be there whenever
the development is done with a
code deployment and code built.
They'll push this code into the CACD
pipelines where it'll take auto it'll go
for the pull request and where we then
the code will apply into the code and
then seamlessly the process will develop.
Coming to the other point is balancing
complexity and it's modern platform must
be sophisticated enough to enterprise
scale processing while reminding simple
enough to general purpose developers.
And see it is modern data
platform is handing it, the
database, huge data is coming out.
So like more transactions, more
legacy data that the tool that
the selfless server infrastructure
should be sophisticated enough
too, handle those situations.
First thing, while reminding is
simple enough to general purpose
of develop this transformation
is from solid data engineering to
platform driven approaches reflects.
Border industry trends towards
DevOp integration and self
service capabilities, eliminating
traditional handoff between teams.
So by doing, once we did the automation
of data moving, or it's a CS, CD and other
stuff, so as of now, we are depending in
each team, like hand up between the teams
one, like TLC one, LC in the process.
Once we one step is done,
we'll go to the second step.
The parallel also, people work.
But going forward by using this
list transformation to the latest
technologies or data handling things.
So those kind of dependencies we
are going to eliminate actually in
between the teams dependencies, so
the architectural foundations for TL.
So what could be the
architecture foundations for
extract transformation loading.
Okay.
Building effective self-service
data platform requires architecture
platform that accommodate both current
requirements and feature growth.
The m and the foundation
typically centers on below points.
So first thing is that building
effect to self service data platforms.
It should handle the current requirement
as well as the previous requirements, sir.
So migrating the legacy data or current
handling the current transactions that.
It should good enough to
handle the previous answer
feature requirement as well.
The foundation typically is
microservices architecture that
decompose the data processor into
discrete composed components and
containers orchestration platform
like Bernet, providing the Runtime
Foundation and carefully selected data
processing engines like Apache Airflow.
These control schedulers and security
and make sure that you know the usage
of data and security point of view.
Make sure that, we are a
secured security level.
Also, we need to give you a lot
of permissions as to provide
to the customer and people.
The challenges lies in the abstracting
bernet complexity from end users
while processing access to that.
It's the powerful scheduling and
resourcing management capabilities.
Sir, that's the main challenging.
What current industry is facing, starting
Bernet complexity from end user side
and while processing, reserving access
to the powerful scheduling and resource
management capabilities, sir? So if you
give the wrong wrong means the person who
is not into the team or is not part of the
project, if you give the access to him.
Their issues will come at the same
time if you give access to end user.
So there're going to be tremendous
data leakage will be there if you don't
know if you go to the wrong hands.
There is a issues will be there and
there's more come, comes under the
resource management capabilities.
And here this slide talks about
metadata driven pipeline architecture.
So the pipeline architecture means
before going insert slide, as I would
like to give you I insights of this.
So pipeline.
So how that design, the Azure
pipeline is designed the, my
previous projects, so there have
the data from the different sources.
They'll pull it to the, and
they'll put it to the landing
zone, landing two integration
zone integration to the target.
So for each from sources to,
they have their one pipeline
and the landing two integrate.
Raw two landing zone, they have one.
And planning to integration tool
curated and there is a different
pipeline should be there.
So these are all integrated by each level.
So in integration, our planning
to integration, they have some
ETL transactions will be performed
and integration tool curated.
There is different level of
transactions will be performed.
Okay, coming back to this slide.
Metadata, data driven architecture,
the concept of metadata driven,
ETL represents foundation.
Fundamentally shifted from the impressive
programming models to they declared
to approach us that separate business
logic from the implementation details.
So that's what I just now mentioned.
So traditionally we used manually,
we need to load the data and
we need to welfare manually.
We need to place the data.
So then we need to process from the
implementation details, like from
business logics, from implementation
details means like metadata.
And running the interpretations
and optimizations.
So we need to follow these approaches.
Like a structure.
Metadata means that pipelines defined
through the structure metadata describing
the transformation data called the
requirement and operational parameters.
So as mentioned, the data is transformed
one and John two other drone and
the data quality requirements also.
So when you, the site is moving
from the rock integration, the data
quality, also we need to verify
the data quality is coming up.
As per the requirement is coming or not.
These kind of checks we need to
perform and operational parameters.
Also, we need to give proper settings
like if any realtime data is coming out.
So those transactions, how to handle
bulk data handling, and that design
is you need such a way that you
know, if any sharing loads coming.
So you need to a new transformation, new
approaches has to be handled on that.
And runtime, interpretations platform
and the runtime, interpretation
metadata to generate and execute
appropriate programming workflows.
So the runtime interpretation means
generate metadata to generate and execute
the appropriate process workflows.
So I mentioned that the different
pipelines will be there and
we have a airflow deck where
we need to go and trigger it.
Manual.
Also, we can trigger the
pipelines, just this workflows.
Also, we need to, once all
development is done and QA is done,
then make sure that once is moved
to production is appropriately.
Those are workflows running continuously
without any issues, sir. Okay.
Opportunity for the parallel
parallelization coaching
and resource optimization.
Sir. Here if 20 people close are
working, this should not any breakage
or any wall or things like performance
issues did not come and coaching.
Any, process every time we have to
if any newcomers coming we need to
make sure that, documentation is
pro correctly maintained on each and
every step so that if any new changes
comes so we make sure that we take it
from there, wherever the last step.
So that documentation ing we should
maintain and if newcomers are coming,
if new people are joining the team.
So we need to use the coaching on them.
Means we need to mentoring
them and resource optimization.
So make sure that who are using the
project and they should have correct
issues and we should have correct
combination of people who is working
on the access and those stuff.
So this, we need to do the resource
optimizations and make sure that the
current confirmation of the systems
and infrastructure we are using those.
Also.
Also, we need to make sure that it's
part of implement and transformation,
implementation of architecture.
And this approach makes pipelines
more maintainable and less prone to
implementation errors since their
focus on business requirements
rather than the technical details.
So if you maintain all these steps
like structural metadata, runtime,
integration, ation, by doing this more,
there is no issues with the maintenance
and no error errors, no implementation
errors, and only focus on the business
requirements rather than the technical.
Integration with the
CACD and DevOps workflow.
So Mo, most of the time nowadays so
what are the development is done?
So directly straight away is going
for, they're using the CACD integration
tool and DevOps support of devs.
So once a developer extract the
data pipeline, deploy into the
flow, similar patterns, establish
application deployment, including.
Portion control automation
testing and staging deployments.
Road steel.
So by using this is continuous
integration deployment.
We can control this we can do this
like portion controlling and from our
previous version to current version
and latest version, those we can do the
washer controlling automation testing.
So nowadays, no manual
testing is happening.
So most of everywhere,
once the code is deployed.
So we have existing test scenarios and
test code source there where when our
code is available to give the pre request
test pre request test data will be there.
Insert the data and on the test route,
we'll get automation testing will be done.
And based on based scenarios and less
than manual effects and stage deployments,
whenever, a deployment is done.
So they'll wait for approvals
and they'll waiting.
Stating means they waiting for
deployments and means one by one, one
by one, and deployments will happen.
So roll back bilities If something goes
wrong in indication part, there is a
capacity, we can roll back those latest
versions and we will keep it as a world
version to make sure that business is
not impacting, get based workflows have
become this become the defecto standard.
For managing infrastructure and
application code, the platforms must
extend these patterns to pipeline
definition and related to articles.
Yeah.
And continuous in integration
pipelines for data processing.
Present unique challenges captured
to the traditional application to CAC
and extending execution timelines.
Yeah.
Cloud native AP integration patterns.
That's also one of the data platforms
servicing AP integration as well.
Modern data platforms master seamlessly
integrated with the cloud native
services while providing consistent
abstraction that provide vendor locking.
Okay, here we have three topics
I would like to cover here.
One is Azure Data Factory Integration data
Databricks Integration, A P Principles.
So first one is the Azure
Data Factory integration.
Platform should be simplify data
factory pipelines creation while
representing access to the advanced
features when needed, typically
through the template based approaches.
Yeah, and Databricks integration
is here, requires careful
consideration of a cluster management.
Notebook deployment and job orchestration
pattern and automatic automated
pro make carefully consideration.
So we should not create, make sure that
the cluster management, what cluster we
are using and job orchestrations we are
using, like what notebook we are using.
So those kind of cloning while doing
the cloning should do the correct
cloning and cement correctly.
Coming to a PA design principles
a restful intersection interfaces
with clear resources model and
consist handling error handling.
Provide the predictive
tive experience graph.
QR implementations can offer
more flexible query capabilities.
Here, the AP design, also interests
will be there with a clear resource
model and consistent error handling.
So if we use, we used to use the a p
services right there most of the times,
the error fee issues since it is a cloud
native integration to make sure that
whatever the configurations notes we
are giving those request should be, make
sure that it's and clearly is defined.
So that will provide any errors.
Yeah.
Apache Airflow Accession
Foundation, this is one of the
kind of where airflow is placed.
Size, road awareness and Apache Airflow
Service has a physician backbone for
many modern data platforms, as you told
the IT and crucial role, Apache Airflow.
Duty.
It's a Python native two approach
and extensive ecosystem integrations.
So airflow.
Airflow.
So we can integrate it with
the latest latest tools.
So environments we can do it.
And it have Python based
native, it's a Python based
it's a Python is more emerging.
So the airflow also, that's the
Python native approach, right?
So that's easy to use.
Actually.
And the key implementation concern
inclusion is multi-tenancy and resource
isolation and DAG generation that
deploy pattern deployment patterns
and custom operator development
and monitoring and integration.
So the DAG generation deployment
patterns and their DS jobs.
So our generations and the
deployment patterns, development
patterns so based on the development
and how many Ds are required.
So we need to identify, we need
to schedule that pattern also to
make sure that in correct order
and monitoring and directing
integration for one job is triggered.
Then the monitoring will be
there, and if there's any
failure, there could be any locks.
While running.
Also, we can see the logs and make
sure that what is issue and for this
completed and what stage it is, those
we can monitor them as well, rather
than requiring users to write Python
deck definition directly successfully.
Platforms typically provides high
level abstractions that generate
air for d from metadata definition.
So metadata definition itself there's a
generated air four tax will be created.
And we can use those patterns and we can
start using those into our development
and we can schedule it actually
infrastructure as a code for ETL
development and infrastructure as a
code and principle transformation,
ETL development for manual error
from process to automated repeated
procedures to integrate it naturally
with the software development workflows.
Tag workflow.
And here there's three three
points I like to discuss here.
One is Terraform modules and
helm charts, GI Tops Flow.
The Terraform modules are encapsulated
common infrastructure patterns for
data processing workflows, enabling
teams to deploy the complex,
multiple, multi-service through the
simple configuration declarations.
And by, by using helm charts, provide the
Bernet native approaches to infrastructure
as code that align with containers on
the data processing or pressures and
through the deployments and coming to
top our workflows, infrastructure changes
triggered by the commit kit repositories,
creating audit trials and enable
sophisticated approval workflow through.
Tools like ango, cd, and Flux.
Work for data quality.
That's this is the one of the
critical role is the data assurance.
Data Quality testing represents
fundamental requirement for
the enterprise data platforms.
Such traditional testing
approaches often through.
In inadequate for modern
data processing workflows.
Yes, comprehensive testing strategies
includes, testing with data
generation and integrion testing
in container based environments.
In my validation testing for back
backward compatibility, performance
testing, performance regression
testing with the baseline.
Comparison.
So by using these four levels of testing
and make sure that whatever the data is
handling and processing as data quality
would be data quality will bev perfect.
And unlike traditional software
testing where the mock object can
simulate external dependencies,
data crossing tests often required
representative to data sets that
capture the complexity and each cases.
Present in the production data?
Yeah.
Production data means production
data is final data, so it should
not any issues in errors in data.
So by doing the good quality of checks, we
can avoid errors in the production, data
monitoring and observability of standards.
There are four ways of we are doing
the monitoring and distributed testing
and mattress collections and log
aggregations in digital directing.
By using these four we are monitoring
and observability standards.
And here comprehensive monitoring and
observability capitals are essential for
the maintaining reliable data platform.
Operating it enterprise scale.
Enterprise level, and distributing
pricing is a critical for understanding
complex data processing workflows
that span multi multiple service
services and processing stages.
System like Gear and Kin provides
a detailed execution visibility and
went to mattress corrections time
series and databases like influx db
provider efficient storage and querying
cables of both technical performance
in indicators and business relevant
process outcomes coming to the log
aggregations tool, like Elastic Research
and Splunk, and high volume of data.
And log output with sophisticated such and
analysis capabilities for rapid problem
identification coming to intelligent Yeah.
By aggregations, by using this bunk
research is a very quick we can come
issue where exactly is happening, and
intelligent alerting, sophisticated
alert correlation escalations policies
like ML based anomaly detecting and.
Subject issues are reducing the, yeah
real world implementation experience
practice implementation of self-service
data platform across the, and diversity
enterprise and environment provides
the valuable insights c to both
architectural pattern and organizational
changes management strategies.
So here the industry specific challenges
are included financial services, like
appliances, data governance and risk
management requirements, and healthcare,
coming to healthcare like HIPAA
complaints, patient privacy and Alexis
and banking fraud detections, realtime
processing core system integrations.
And those we need to see alien
operational s and disaster require.
And airlines, sorry.
Operational alliances and the
disaster require capabilties.
Yeah.
And developer experience
and load connections.
The source of self-service data platform
ultimately depends on their ability
to reduce the loads for development.
Teams while providing the powerful data
processing capabilities like lead tool
design, like well designated CLA tools
for flow establishment conventions
for pat parameter handling, output
formatting and error reporting with the
compress help system and conversions.
So by using this CLA digital tool
so we can perform all this on.
Like handling output, formatting,
error, reporting, all this
things, we can handle this.
And web interfaces must provide
ation of complex data processing
workflow while enabling sophisticated
ations and monitoring ties.
Sir documentation interactive document is
system that combines explanatory content.
That executable example provides
effective learning experience.
Governance and compliance and
platform architecture, so data
lineage, audit, logging, and access
control and privacy production.
So as I mentioned, so data governance and
compliance is very key to the company.
Based on that, only if you speak
openly, the stock market and all
the stuff will be based on that.
This ambulance only, so there is no
data leak or they maintain all standards
so that all the business is doing.
All standards will be on, accounting
will be there year and the data
line automatically capture the data
flow information as a pipeline and
execute, maintain detailed records
of source submissions and designation
for the compliance reporting.
And access controls integrated with
the enterprise entity system while
providing the fine permissions through
VAC systems for dynamic ations.
Audit logging capture the compress
records for all user actions, data
access and configuration changes
with sufficient detail for complaint
reporting, privacy protection, sorry.
Regulatory requirement like
D-P-R-C-C-P-A through the authorization
data discovery classification,
an normalizations and delete
capabilities, deletion capabilities.
So go data governance and complaints
are the key for the company.
So by using these four things that,
that these architecture office, like
the data line, access control, audit,
logging, and privacy protections.
And this is the feature ions
and conclusion of this task and
transformations of aging here.
The emerging patterns of our
wireless computing for more
efficient resource affiliation one
and machine learning integration
with model electric management.
Yes.
And real time processing and ties with
the steam processing fire frameworks and
edge computing scenarios spanning cloud
and edge environment and a port platform
operations for optimization monitoring.
And these are all patterns and new
technologies and new to do the data
handlings and data transformations
from the legacy to the new one.
To success.
Yeah.
Building the effective self
service data plan is required, is a
holistic approach that balance the
technical, sophisticated, and user
experience considerations the most.
Successful implementation treat
platform development as a product
development with the clear user
persons, interactive implement cycles,
and comprehensive feedback mechanism.
And operations organizations
that successfully implement
comprehensive data platform.
That strategies, again, significant
competitive advantage through the improved
developer productivity, faster time to
market, and more reliable operations.
These are all key to
success directions actually.
Yeah.
Thank you.
And thank you for giving opportunity to
present myself and my work and giving
thoughts on it and I'm happy to share
my experience and presentation here.
Thank you very much.