Hi, everyone.
I'm Ankit Virmani.
I am an ethical AI and data
engineering specialist.
today I'll be talking about the backend
AI solution and what goes into making it.
the backend AI part for a very
exciting solution that all three
of us will be presenting, today.
And this solution will focus on
how we can use the marriage between
artificial intelligence, software
development, and human computer
interaction principles to help EV1A,
extraordinary ability, green card,
achievers, potential achievers, and sorry.
achieve their dream by learning through
this chat bot over to you, Tina.
Hi everyone.
I'm Tina Gada.
I'm a senior UX designer for Vanguard.
and today I will be presenting about how a
user experience and design works in a chat
bot for EB1A, bot, as well as I will be
talking about how the human psychic works
in terms of, response and the process.
Reply for any chatbot experiences.
Also how development cycle works and
integration of AI with human computer
interaction within the mobile device.
So I will be talking more
details about it over to you.
Namaste.
Hello, everyone.
I'm Namashree Chandrana.
I am a mobile application development
expert focusing on building applications,
which, enhances user performance.
And there'll be, I will be discussing
about how did we integrate our
client and backend to talk with
LLM models to get responses, smart
responses, from, The rag model.
and, yeah, I'll also be focusing on
just telling tools that we used for, our
client side and backend side as well.
Thanks so much.
Tina, do you mind putting the slides?
Sure.
All three of us are very excited to be
here and the solution that we are going
to talk about today called the intelligent
conversational system for personalized
EB1A guidance and service discovery.
Why we came through this solution was
because, based on the market survey
we did, it is becoming increasingly
difficult to get concise, consolidated,
and, accurate information about
EV1A, which is also called the
Extraordinary Ability Green Card,
as information is scattered online.
So we thought, how about we bring together
Manifested in chat
bot.
And that's why it's called an
intelligent conversational system.
It's intelligent because it brings
the intelligence of talking.
A human, it's conversational
because it's a bot and it's a system
because it's a conglomeration of
UI, AI, and, software development.
So we'll be talking about all those
three components in their capacity
throughout this, presentation.
Can you go to the next slide, Tina?
So I think we've already done the speaker
introduction, so we can skip that.
We'll talk a little bit about the
background, then how we had to
implement the Retrieval Augmented
Generation from an AI standpoint.
And then Namaste, we'll talk
about the mobile application
with AI user experience.
Tina will shed some light on how the user
experience integrates with everything.
We'll talk about the final product
from challenges that we see while
bringing all these three components
together and what we are thinking
about from the future aspect.
So as I was talking about
the background before.
Ev1a expert bot was created to
simplify the complications that
Ev1a has been in state as of today.
And some of those complications,
are stemmed from the fact that there
is so much information online, some
of it accurate, some of it not.
And most of it is the time investment that
needs to be made to find a single correct
source of truth So we wanted to cut down
the cycles of time That are required for
someone to get their queries answered
and we thought what if we take All the
correct data all the nice good quality
data that's available All the wisdom from
someone who's really knowledgeable in this
space, bring that together in a bot and
then have that manifest as an intelligent
conversational product or even, aspirin.
we recognize need of something accessible,
which is something easy to use.
Personalized guidance, because
being extraordinary is about being
different from others, being different
from others, being, being unique.
And with uniqueness comes the need
of having a personalized solution, a
personalized guidance, easy to use.
We did not want users to invest time in
figuring out what to do, rather than get
the, get answers to the question, and a
24 7 tool available for talent worldwide.
So those were the core tenets of
why we designed this board and
what we designed this board on.
And as I was mentioning before, this
bot is a unique combination of three
schools of thought, Artifact and Dungeon.
mobile application and,
and, user experience.
Let's talk about the
artificial intelligence part.
usually, large language models
operate on a huge corpus of
data, that they're trained on.
And, they might or might not have all
the information that while we were
designing the B1A conversational system,
this was manifested as hallucination.
And based on the testing that we did a lot
of times, then we would ask the question,
we would promptly understand that the
answers that we got weren't accurate.
to alleviate that concern that we had
during the initial development stages,
we understood that we will have to
ground the model using a technology
called Retrieval Augmented Generation
or a methodology rather to call, that's
called Retrieval Augmented Generation.
What it does is it retrieves the relevant
information from the document we feed
into the system, augments the prompt
with that retrieved information, And
then goes to the line language model
with the prompt and the retrieved
information to get the accurate answer.
So the important part here is the model
is not using its own intelligence,
but it's using the intelligence from
the retrieved information that we have
given to the model using a document.
Now we know, or now we can expect the
kind of information we are going to get.
So this is called grounding, where we are
grounding the model with the information.
And this meant that all three
of us had to scout for a lot of
good accurate documentation about
various aspects of EV1A and feed
that into the model as document.
whatever I just said is presented on
the slide in form of these four boxes.
User issues a query, Knowledge Retrieval
System uses that query to fetch accurate
document, information from accurate
document that we've already fed before.
And then that fetched information
augments the user input.
Now you have the prompt
plus that information.
And that goes to the LLM model.
And the model uses the augmented
information to give the answer.
So this was a central
basis for the backend.
Information that the bot would present on
the front end using software, development.
Over to the next slide.
So this is the end to end design
for the mobile application, that
number three will walk us through.
Which shows you the interface between
user, backend, and the middleware.
Namaste, over to you.
Thank you so much, Ankit.
so yeah, for, for this slide I
will be discussing, specifically
the primary feature of the
application, which is getting back
the response, for a user query.
I will break this
discussion into two parts.
First, the client side
and the server side.
For the client side, we have
currently just launched the
application for iOS users.
So the app is natively developed
using Swift, SwiftUI, and
follows a TCA architecture.
The core feature of the app is the
chatbot, which addresses the primary
issue that we identified before.
This is where the user
interacts with the chatbot.
It sends a request to our backend,
and then our backend is responsible
to fetch the Correct response for
us and get it back to the client.
we will be discussing more about the
different screens that we have on
the client side on our next slide.
but I'll just move on to
the server side for now.
The server is built using node JS with
JavaScript as a programming language.
And it handles key functions like
user authentication, listening
to the request from the client,
and also fetching the responses.
So just as a user journeys upon receiving
a request from the client side, the
server performs prompt engineering.
So this is to ensure that the response
that we get from a RAG model is
in the right format that we want.
to make this request, we, the back
end request it to the LLM model for
processing, and the back end continuously
monitors these requests because it
takes some time to fetch the response
back as LLM model takes time to,
process the query, and once that is
ready, we get it back on our back end,
again, clean it up for the client side
and then send it back to the client.
And to do the right LLM model, we just
experimented with different models that
were available and went ahead with one
of the popular ones that is available.
And this was purely based on
the ease of integration and
the responses and the accuracy.
now I'll just pass on to Tina to talk
about the user experience of our app.
Thank you so much, Namaste.
from the user experience standpoint, I
think one of the key element that I was
primarily focused on is taking the user
interviews, making sure that the prospect
E B 1 A client or applicant who is looking
for, Information online, or it could be
a traditional way where they are reaching
out to our mentors or professional
lawyers for getting all the information.
How would we, how would they want to
process this information and what are the
key, responses that they are looking for?
So that was the first initial
task where I was trying to gather
as many information as possible.
The, another thing which
was playing an advantageous.
We already have a very good tool
such as chat GPT and custom, GPT
available and their mobile application.
So one of the very key feature which
helped me was how the UI elements are
working, what are the things that they
are doing as a part of the competitive
analysis, which could be leveraged.
So that certain things, certain elements
that they are doing, we are trying to
leverage those elements as a part of
the application design and based on the
close collaboration with the development,
such as that was we and understanding
how the request response are working,
what is the response time that we are
getting and how would we, Showcase
that response time in our UI pattern.
That was something which
was very important.
but, looking at the screen, we have
a very simple flow where users, if
they are coming to the application
for the first time, they would be
seeing and they have to register to
the app and use the sign up feature.
But once they are signed up and they
come to the app, they have to log in the.
Screen, log in and use the application.
And the first time experiences since
user would be seeing the dashboard,
where we are providing them the
questions such as what are the most
big question or what are the questions
that we have known that users are
asking based out of our research.
And we have populated those questions as a
part of our first user experience screen.
And upon clicking on any of the given
screen, given questions or entering
certain question in a certain way, this
responses is very accurately provided
where we are giving a summarization
of each and every responses, and then
bulleted point of the sub-task or the
action item that they might be, able
to do it and follow the certain steps.
Over here, there were a couple of things
that we had focused, is brand guidelines
since everything was from the scratch.
So the brand guideline and visual
hierarchy was completely managed by,
me in a way where we are building the
entire design system, the coding, which
was done in a swift design because of
which it was easier so that all the
guidelines which we have followed is iOS.
These and ensuring the consistency
across differently and, making sure
that we are focusing on accessibility
and inclusivity, with respect to the
colors that we have choose and making
sure that each and every, contrast
guidelines has been followed to make
this mobile application accessible,
user friendly, as well as preparing
them to have a very good friendly
experience at the past response time.
What do you get?
Thanks.
Can you go to the next slide, please?
Yeah, so this slide elucidates some
of the challenges that we face.
accuracy of the model, as I was
mentioning before, large language models
are trained on a corpus of data and it
is expected for them, to hallucinate.
So we had to use retrieval
augmented generation to avoid
some of the hallucinated
responses that we were getting.
And it was imperative for us to do so
because this board endeavors to provide
accurate information about each one.
Namaste,
do you want to take up the
rest of the challenge regarding
the software development?
Yes, definitely.
I will cover the faster response request
response and the issues with integration
of LLM model and the application.
So I'm going to talk
about this both together.
One of the primary issues that we faced
was the response time, and also, the
requests that we sent to our model
were usually airing out if you're just
trying to fetch the request in one go.
And this was basically because,
the APIs had some token limits set.
Per minute, for the current here,
or, that we were on for that model,
therefore, report repeated requests
to the model often surpass the token
limit, hence airing out our requests.
Therefore, to solve this issue, we
added an exponential backoff to our
backend, to request to our LL model.
And that actually helped us to
decrease the response time to around
five to seven seconds, which was.
10 to 15 seconds before.
this also helped reduce the error
rate because it, it solved the
challenge where it, allowed us to
not reach the token limit or minute,
because of the exponential back off.
although we are still not at a
two or three second, which is
ideal, for, users, to get, Get
a response, but that's something
for future that we want to cover.
but for now we still were able to
decrease it almost 10 seconds from
what we were initially, over to you,
Tina, for the rest of the challenges.
There are a couple of things that
we wanted to focus on is ensuring
the consistency across the platform.
So currently, we only have iOS
device and in future, we would be
planning to have Android as well
as the web application where it's
more accessible across different
platform based on the user's need.
So that's one thing, which, is
challenging because every devices
was the be and, to maintain that
consistency, something that we are.
Figuring out, handling the
user feedback and iteration.
So in the current functionality, we
do not have any way where users can
provide their, detail of feedback
about how the interaction is happening.
What are the things that they
can like possibly follow?
And that's something, which is
limiting of another application.
And that's what we want to focus on.
And.
Balancing the aesthetic and
the functionality part of it.
So there are three key challenges.
That is, what we are working towards.
Over to you, Namasthi.
yeah, for future work, we are currently
focusing on just personalized guidance.
That's something we already provide
with our AI model, but just more
towards, any action items that we
could auto generate for our users.
That is something that we are looking for,
that would help in their EV1A journey.
obviously the implementation, that's
something that Tina already talked about.
Implementation of Android and
web applications currently
available just on iOS.
having a voiceover functionality as
well, this is, To reduce the typing
time and also improve accessibility
of the application as well.
and yeah, some reminders and notifications
of to do's that would be generated
out of personal guidance, feature, and
also designing for global audiences.
Currently, the application is just
released to us, audiences and it's not,
unable for like global, audiences or
something that is again, We're targeting
for because any money, like any individual
can apply for EB one, it, it could be
even if they're outside of United States.
So that's something also we are looking
to go blow global in the future.
Yeah, that's about it.
I think.
Thank you.
Thanks.
I must be.
Thanks, Tina.
Thank you.
I hope all of you enjoyed.
The idea, the thought and the work that
we have put in into the solution, we
deliberately did not go into the specific,
the actual NLM module, the tooling, et
cetera, because we wanted to keep it
very, neutral and objective and wanted
to showcase our overall approach on what
happens when three different individuals
with three different skill sets.
Come together to solve a problem that
is so prominent and common in today's
world using ai using ui using using
software development and a common
skill that all of us have which is
naturally In addition to artificial
intelligence to solve this problem.
We do hope that you you like that
presentation once again Thank you
Etc.
Please feel free to reach out to us
You we would be more than happy to,
to walk you through the specific.
thanks once again, everyone, and
have a good rest of your day.
Thank you.