Hello, everybody.
Welcome to our talk, Principles of Team
Topologies and Platform Engineering.
hello everyone.
My name is Valionchev and, over the past
seven years or so, I've been working very
closely with Jansu, building platforms in
many different environments, different.
Business domains, different technologies.
We're not going to talk only about
platforms in the cloud native context.
We're going to cover platforms
in any other kind of context.
That's me.
Over to you Jansu to tell us about you.
My name is Jansu.
I'm an architect in Red Hat and as
Val said that I'm mainly focusing
on building the platforms that help
organizations that fits for their
needs and goals and their purposes.
And also, helping to, build the
platform teams that are like high
functioning, self sufficient and
able to maintain and sustain the
platforms that we built together.
Let's start that.
Let's start.
I'm actually representing here
Team Topologist and leading
the team at Team Topologist.
I'll let Johnson talk about it.
It's so cool.
If you haven't heard about, Team
Topologies, or, if you haven't had a
chance to read it, we highly suggest you
to do it because it is one of the best
product management book and best, one
of the best leadership book out there.
If you want to know more, you can
go to the website teamtopologies.
com or, if you like what you read and
if you like what you hear today, you
can also contact us to learn more.
but.
Unfortunately, we have 30
minutes in here, so we are not
going to deep dive on the book.
We just assume that you have an interest
in that and you already read it.
So we're going to focus on the principles
coming from team topologies and how this
helps us to guide, to build a platform
that actually helps the organizations.
Let's start, let's talk about platforms.
One of the things that I learned early
on is that it's really important to align
on what we mean when we say platforms.
Most of the times that we start talking
about platforms, many people think
about Kubernetes or like container.
And while they are right, because
Kubernetes literally, the definition
is an open source platform that,
that runs the containerized
services, It is not just Kubernetes.
So only having a Kubernetes cluster
having in our organization is not gonna
exactly help us what we want to, when
we are thinking about platform, we
need to go beyond the Kubernetes and
like we need to think about maybe some
commercial of the shelf products and
infrastructure or some other services.
We either build or get from outside.
So we need to broaden our perspective
when we are thinking about platform
and talking a little bit above,
not just on the tooling side.
So for that, we need to align on
this and that's why while it's
gonna give us like what we mean
when actually we say platforms.
Yeah, platform is a loaded term.
everybody means something else.
And go and ask a Salesforce consultant
in Ontario that they have a platform.
And it's probably correct from a
King's policy principles point of view.
the platform is a thing that
is existing with the sole
purpose of these three, things.
a platform needs to
accelerate the flow of value.
It simplifies things, it accelerates,
the work that development teams,
application teams are doing.
It needs to reduce cognitive load for the
people that are consuming the platform.
So it needs to reduce the cognitive load
in the whole, socio technical system.
And last but not least, it needs
to enable substantial autonomy of
the teams that are consuming it.
because we all want that.
We want autonomous product teams
that are able to deliver vast value.
and a platform needs to
fulfill all these three jobs.
Again, it needs to accelerate flow
value, it needs to reduce the cognitive
load, and it needs to allow for
substantial autonomy of the teams.
Now, platform is an ambiguous term.
Platform team is an even
more ambiguous term.
And a lot of people use it, not
necessarily, Referring to the way, we use
it in Team Topology's concept, context.
from Team Topology's perspective, the
platform team is a grouping of many teams.
It is not necessarily one team.
A lot of people say a platform team and
they mean a department that happens to be
responsible for some platform services.
In Team Topology's, it is a grouping
of teams, different team types.
It could be streamlined teams, it could
be complicated, subsystem teams, and they
have the purpose to produce a product,
a platform service that is consumable
and easy, make it easy for, developers,
people consuming it, let's say the team
consuming it to deliver value fast.
Before we dive in into the
principles to achieve actually.
we want to just a little,
just in the words of cautious.
So we're gonna, we don't have enough
time to dive into all the principles,
but, we are mainly, we decided to
mainly talking about the value that we
get out of these principles based on
our experiences in the field with the
different organizations and how we can
actually, a little bit of guidance on how
that you can also achieve the same thing.
But what we actually want to do is to.
Act like the great artists.
We want you to, not steal
them, but, I'm sorry.
We want you to, Don't
copy them, steal them.
Don't copy them.
Sorry.
Yes.
We don't want you to copy them as well,
but we want you to steal with creativity.
we are hoping that these principles
and this discussion will inspire you
to come up with your own principles
that can, That can actually achieve
what you are sent to achieve, what
you are, where you want to go.
So you'll, with that, these
are the principles that we
are going to go through.
we're going to get the slides as well.
We're going to publish them
so you can also go through
them, as on your time, time.
And, we all have our own favorite
principles among those things.
So I will hand over to Val to start
with his new favorite principle.
Oh, sorry.
Yes.
Thank you.
So the first principle we're gonna talk
about is the team is the smallest unit
of delivery, and that quite often is
very much misunderstood by leaders.
I see more and more leaders that are
focused on developer productivity.
Their focus on developer experience
and that subtle change in language,
forces them to look at individuals.
And when you look at individuals,
you're not necessarily
achieving the best results.
From a team topology perspective,
the smallest units you need to
deal with as a leader is the team.
Productivity, impact, experience,
all of these things should
be measured on a team level.
The value of your platform should
be measured on the team level.
Because if the team is the unit
that delivers the value, delivers
the product, produces product and
delivers it to, to your end customer.
So let's start by changing
a little bit the language.
Instead of speaking about
developer productivity, let's speak
about development productivity.
Instead of speaking about developer
experience, let's talk about
development experience and let's
start shifting the focus on the team.
And the other principle is the
platform reduces cognitive load
and accelerates flow of value.
So the first question that we need to
answer is that we really need a platform.
If you're thinking about the
definition that Val gave us.
platforms are basically here
to be a catalyst of effects,
efficiency and effectiveness.
It should provide, I don't know,
easy to use, tools, some clear
guidelines and helping developers to
reduce, reduce their cognitive load.
If your platform fails to achieve
these two key benefits, it may
not just justify its existing.
So a couple of years ago, we were
working with this, organization
and they formed a platform team.
And they were really coming from
a good place with good intentions.
They identified some common services,
and they wanted to take that load from
their developers and provide some easy to
use, off the shelf type services to them.
Soon enough, they became a
blocker because they were not
really, following the good path.
way of, providing services, they
became this, blocker and bottleneck.
So actually, if you look overall,
instead of they are really reducing the
cognitive load, they did the opposite.
and they really didn't give the
benefit that, they, they sent
to achieve at the beginning.
And just because that's your immense
money on time, it doesn't mean that
you should actually push for this.
If you are really failing at these
two key benefits, like providing them
and maybe should start re evaluate
and, maybe even decommission that
platform and start from scratch.
Yeah, to be or not to be, that's
the biggest question to ask about
platforms and, in Team Topology's
sense, we speak about the thinnest
viable platform, which is, what's the
minimum implementation you need to do?
quite often we see.
product owners or teams trying to build
magnificent castles and, something
really big when the developer actually
needs a skateboard or just a tent.
so do or not try to, allow this kind of
anti pattern to trick you into building a
platform that actually becomes a botanic.
Remember the three jobs
that the platform have.
It has, from the morphology's
perspective, it needs to accelerate value.
it needs to reduce the cognitive load.
It needs to be easy to
consume by, your developers.
So how do you actually do that?
cognitive load should be the main
factor that drives your decision making.
You need to focus again, the
smallest unit is the key.
So we're talking about a team
of teams designs, not roles and
responsibilities within a team.
How do we distribute the work across
multiple different teams, within the
design that we are meeting in order to
reduce the cognitive load in the system
as a whole and accelerate the value in
the whole system, this so sociotechnical
system, what you see there on, on
the images, one of the teams we were
working with, building a very complex.
platform that took, several
dozens of teams to develop.
And what on the wall is
the domain driven design.
This is event storming.
the same technique that you apply in
order to build sound microservices,
sound cloud native designs, you can
also apply it on your platforms.
And it allows you to define good
boundaries for different platform teams.
Different teams that are going to build
platform services to accelerate the value
for the teams consuming the platforms.
Another technique that we found, really
useful to reduce the cognitive load is
worldly mapping, because it allows you
on one hand side to again, identify
the different boundaries of services,
looking at the value chain, that you
would need to build, but it also allows
you to make, build or buy decisions.
So if something is available as a
commodity, don't spend time and effort.
and actually they, the whole, creativity.
of one of your teams, go ahead and buy it.
I have worked with an organization in the
past that build their own service mesh.
For Christ's sake, why?
I, if it makes such a huge,
differentiation for you and you build
something that does not exist on the
market, which is far on the left,
okay, go ahead, invest and build it.
But if you're building exactly what
already exists, do yourself a favor.
Just take it off the shelf.
Have somebody configure it.
And conceal it, or you could even conceal
it as a service from the marketplace.
So that going back to what
Giles was talking about earlier.
Should this platform exist?
What's the minimum version
of it that should exist?
Don't try to build a magnificent castle
if a tent or a caravan is good enough.
And the other principle is treating
the platforms as a product.
This became super popular.
It became like really, quite popular
recently, and it is all right to
be popular, actually, because it
emphasized to, the importance of, the
importance of applying the same level
of attention and chair and strategic
thinking, that, transcripting.
That you would apply to a, any
customer facing product applying the
same attention, care, and strategic
thinking into your platform.
Basically, it puts your users in the
center and design some pla design a
platform that actually your user would
like to use, would, would like to,
come and use that they find their real
platform and then very compelling.
So by viewing the platform
as a product we commit.
We're coming to have a continuous
improvement, like gathering the
user feedback and iterating on
features of the platform to have a
better usability and effectiveness.
So this mindset helps you to ensure that
the platform remains relevant, valuable,
and aligned with the needs of your users.
and align with the teams that is actually
get a benefit off the platform, which
drives the actually satisfaction for that.
Just like the any product that actually
you are buying, like you are paying money.
You should also think the same
way for your platforms as well.
No one is pushing for
you to buy a product.
No one is, you are not going
to use any product that is not
relevant to this technology or
not making anything easy for you.
So you should think the same.
you should bring the same mindset to your
platform development approach and making
sure that actually your platform is,
simplifying the needs for your end users,
be, creating and creating an experience
that actually based on their needs and
Sounds like a very convoluted term.
Let's pull it apart and look
in practice what it means.
True.
Okay, so the real needs,
the real customers.
As I said that this platform as a
product mindset puts the user, in
the center and understand, what
kind of needs that our users, what
kind of things that our users need.
So in order to do that, we need to
really answer the question, the type
of questions like, who is our customer?
Like what?
What do they need today?
And what kind of things that
they are trying to achieve and
they are using our platform.
So in this picture that you
are seeing, there is a, what
we call like user interview.
So we are talking with the user and
understanding, how they are today,
interacting with the platform.
What is their expectation
from the platform?
How they would like to, what
kind of features or services
that they would like to.
See, so that we understand what is
their motivation, what is the pain
points, what kind of opportunities
that we have to bring to the platform,
so that we can actually address the
user needs, so the actual user needs.
And we don't really have one
user of a platform, so different
users have different needs.
So probably needs to talk about
different customer groups.
And that was more about,
different needs people may have.
So, when we are building a platform,
and when we are treating our
platform as a product, we really,
need to meet our users needs.
And as you said that there might
be not just one type of users.
Our organization says.
Multiple teams and different
teams with different needs.
So a couple of years ago we were working
with this government agency and they
want to build a platform to address
their all developers and build something
that all the developers can benefit off.
And together we identified a couple of
different personas, different developers,
which was actually quite brilliant
and enlightening for me as well.
So during our interviews, during
our engagements with the developers,
we identified, one of these
personas was, for example, what
we can call default pet users.
So there were some developers
who would like to just consume
the platform services, not really
interested in how those services are
made or how they can, I don't know,
change stuff or bring new stuff.
So they just want to consume this.
services and like they want to
follow some standard pets, but
it is becomes quite famous.
it's called like golden pets.
They just want to follow this
golden pads and bring their
implications to the platform,
consume the services and that's all.
Like our platform needs to address
this kind of developers needs.
And there was this another persona,
what we can call Adaptive users.
So adaptive users are like, they're happy
about what you provide, but they also
want to tweak a little bit things to
have a better fit for their own project.
So you need to think about how
you can build services that are
configurable and address their needs.
If you think about this golden path,
for example, this type of persona is.
Let's say they're happy with how, how they
build their application on the platform,
happy they have the containerization
work, but they maybe want to, bring
this, they want to tweak the testing
bits because their use case requires
something a little bit different, and you
need to address, bring this flexibility
and freedom to them so that they can
actually, They can actually achieve
what they need from your platform.
So they, they were quite happy when
actually we bring these services in a
reusable components, a configurable way.
They will say Oh, that's great.
I can tweak the things that I need and
I can get the things that I, there's
off the shelf things that actually also.
No, I need, and I can bring
those things together and achieve
my, achieve what I said to do.
And that was on the other side
of the, spectrum, what we can
call these like innovative users.
They were like always on the edge,
following the new, new products or the
new, frameworks coming in and they want to
try these things to see if they want, if
this is more, helpful for their projects,
if it's going to make their life easier.
So you need to have this kind of
balance in your platform and address
also give them enough flexible
flexibility and freedom to, to
make them this kind of experiments.
And also set them a way to, contribute
their learning to the platform back
so that everybody can actually get
benefit of what they learned, what
they experimented and what they say.
So when we say that we treat platform as
a product, we must recognize that we have
different type of users and what we, This
one size fits all might not actually,
wouldn't work, but it would never work.
One size fits all in this, in this
platform concept is not going to help us.
So we have different teams with different
needs and a successful implementation of
platform can address all these, needs.
And I can already imagine some
of the questions in the chat.
you keep talking about the team
being the smallest unit and you
keep referring to us focusing on
the developers and talking to them.
the team is still the smallest unit,
but you need to talk to individual
users, you need to talk to individual
developers in order to understand
different perspectives on the experience
that is happening within the team.
but don't forget that principle,
it's really important.
The team is the smallest unit.
And, while you need to treat the
platform as a product and go and talk to
individual representatives of the team,
what you want to focus on is how this
developer freedom For how this development
freedom, applies to the individual teams.
And the way you do this, you don't
build a platform for everyone.
in marketing, they say, you should
try to build a product for everyone.
You build nothing for no one.
so the same is valid for platforms.
When you build a platform, identify the
different groups of teams that are somehow
similar, they may be working in the same
domain, using the same technology stack.
Take one of them as a representative
and try to build with them.
Because if you build something that
works for them, most probably with
some little tweaks here and there,
it is going to work for everyone.
Choose a team that you're going
to serve and build the thinnest
viable platform for them.
Again, it could be as
simple as a wiki page.
What you see here is, from a
few years ago, I think this
is in the winter of 2018.
We were working in Finland with an
insurance organization and what in this
room on the left table, the long table,
you have a bunch of people and they are
actually one streamlined team building
an application and one enabling team.
That is helping this streamline
team to understand all of the
architectural patterns and good
practices they need to follow.
and on the right hand side, on the
table in the corner, you see the
representatives of the platform team.
So what is, what's happening
there was that they worked for a
period of time together, which in.
team topology terms,
we call collaboration.
it's a close collaboration between
two teams and the platform team built
just the thinnest viable platform that
this application team needed in order
to run their application production,
to develop it and deploy it and
run it in production, nothing else.
The product owner had a lot of
drive, I could build this and that.
And we asked them, don't do it.
If you have an idea about a new platform
service to build, go and ask the team.
It's just there on the other table.
Would they use it?
What they actually need?
would it make their life easier?
Would it speed their development?
And if yes, build it.
If not, put it somewhere on the
backlog and we can talk about
it when somebody asks for it.
another aspect of creating a
platform as a product is if you
think about it, real life, the more
competition there is amongst products.
The better those products become,
and I'm not saying that Coke
is better or Pepsi is better.
It's definitely not good for your
health, but the fact is, whenever
you have products that, are in
a competitive environment, they
keep getting better and better.
Think about Android and iPhones.
they get better because of that
competition to offer a better
experience, more value to their users.
You want something similar when
it comes to platform services.
some people call this.
Make the platform optional,
make your product use optional.
some people will say, but no,
we're in a secure environment.
We cannot make it optional.
That's fine.
Think about making the service optional.
So it still needs to be on that platform.
Maybe somebody will come up with a better
idea of how that service can be designed.
Open up that opportunity for internal
competition in a healthy way so
that your platform services really
fulfill the three jobs we talked
about, making more independent and
empowered, reducing the cognitive load
and speeding up the flow of value.
And don't forget, as we talked about,
it's a little bit earlier with,
the slide about worldly mapping.
Everything in our life, and
technology including, is evolving.
It gets better and better, and eventually,
things we considered innovation ten
years ago, they are a commodity.
Don't build a commodity.
Figure out which platform services
can be consumed from outside,
and focus on building platform
services that actually makes sense.
because he said something really
important and true about platforms.
for your information, there's a lot
more to platforms than people think.
Platforms are like onions.
Onions have layers.
Platforms have layers too.
And, I think, I'll go back
to the slide that I presented
earlier about the platform team.
Remember, we said a platform
team is actually a grouping
of multiple different teams.
You have Stream Aligned teams
building their own service,
their own platform service.
Those platform teams, they have cognitive
load, hey, they have their own needs.
If you think about the generic
representation of the technology stack
in a company, in an organization,
You would have, a three layered cake.
Top layer being the applications,
the middle layer being some platform
services, which could be quite a lot.
And you could have quite a
lot of platform teams here.
and then you have the infrastructure.
But wait a second.
why do we try to make the life of the
StreamAlign product development teams,
the teams building applications easier
by exposing services and we don't do
this for the developers of the platform?
Developer of a platform
is still a developer.
Development experience needs to
focus on reducing cognitive load,
making things easier for the people
building the platform as well.
So platform engineering, I
would argue, should focus also
on the infrastructure layer.
You should think about how can I make
infrastructure services consumable,
easy to, to identify, easy to consume,
just like the way the platform,
developers are trying to make the life
of the application developers easy.
So think about layers.
It's not just one platform,
it's multiple platforms.
Each one, consumes the one from below
all the way to your final customer.
With when we are talking about like the
multiple teams, having the communication
between multiple teams can be hard.
Thinking about like why we are
building APIs between services to
actually make the communications better
and can also think the same, same
logic with the, between the teams.
So, we can find what about team topology
is called team API about what the team
is about, what they are working on,
what kind of capabilities they are
serving, what kind of, what kind of
things, what kind of services they have
in the road map, so that if one team
would like to consume a service from
the other team, they can actually, read
the team API, understand what they're
about and actually get their results.
And so find their way without
actually, really trying to increase the
communication lines between the team.
So team API has a really nice, template
on the team topologies GitHub page.
If you would like to, if you'd like
to check it, it seems so simple, but
it is quite powerful when actually
these teams are getting team numbers
are getting increased and increased.
Since we are talking about teams
and also mentioned about this, how
platforms are evolved over time.
we need to acknowledge that every
product at the beginning, especially
that they might have, they might
be not so intuitive or not easy.
Enough for the end users.
So platform may come with their own this
kind of complexities and learning curve.
So we need to actually bridge
the, bridge this gap between
platform and it's end users.
And that's where the
enabling team concepts.
comes into play.
So their responsibility is to, enable
the users to get the, to consume
the platform services, leverage the
platform services better and easier.
And, while the enabling team is helping,
enable the team, enable the development
team, they also get more insights about
how the development team is consuming the
platform, how, what they can, what kind
of services that they would need, what is
their daily challenges, and they can also
feed this into back to the platform team.
How you can form an enabling team could
vary, but It could be something like a
couple of individuals from platform teams
and working with the development teams.
But the important thing is that, that
collaboration should be time box.
It shouldn't be like a, Commands and
months long collaboration, because
one is collaboration is expensive.
That means these individuals are
away from their platform services
development, roles, but also that
this development teams will start
become more and more dependable to
those individuals in enabling team.
The aim of this team is to bring these
development teams and make them self
sufficient, enable them enough to
consume the platform and, and, basically
continue evolving the platform for
the better based on their learning.
Is there anything you want to add, Mel?
no, I would jump to the next principle
because we are, quite ahead in time.
So the last principle we're
going to talk about is that,
Team topology is about evolution.
It is, tracking the evolution of teams.
It's not about labeling the teams.
If you're just looking for
labels, look in other places.
Team topology is a verb.
It is a continuous effort.
And the easiest way for me to illustrate
this is by making sourdough bread.
We all love sourdough bread, or
majority of people love sourdough bread.
And if you ever tried to make
sourdough, It's a continuous
effort of perfection, every single
time you try to make it better.
In the beginning, it might be a very.
Very different, very hard and not
necessarily giving you the right results.
So in topologies, applying topologies
to your organization is the same thing.
Just like you need bread every single
day, you may need every single day to,
to tackle the challenges of another team.
Because you have a lot of teams, you
have complex architectures that are
developed with a big number of themes.
you can't change things.
One team at a time, you can't
change things as a big bank.
You need to take it as a continuous
effort, looking at the patterns, looking
at how you can make things better and
better with what you're uncovering.
So that was the last principle.
And I'll leave you with this statement
that we want to make with Johnson here.
We want to advocate and argue that
platform engineering is a culture
of building platform services.
That are focused on these four things.
They're easy to consume.
They reduce the cognitive
load of those consuming them.
They are continuously being involved.
And they're economically viable.
If you approach platform engineering like
this, and borrow, like an artist, from
all these principles that we shared, that
come from the Team Topologies book and
the community, You are going to succeed
and you're going to be the next success
story about how platform engineering
changed, the future of an organization.
So with this, we're going to leave you.
Thank you for listening to us,
can reach to us with, my email or
LinkedIn, or you can also book time
as well, if you want to discuss more.
This, so thank you for that.
Thank you everyone.
Bye bye.