Hello, everyone, and welcome to my session
about platform engineering untold truths.
For sure, many of you are already
familiar with the classic narrative behind
the concept of platform engineering,
where infrastructure orchestration
is at the core of every platform.
In this talk, I want to present
a new way of looking at platform.
It's not that the current view is
wrong, but rather we'll try to extend
what we commonly refer to as platforms
today to include other important
assets for today's digital company.
Let me introduce myself briefly.
My name is Graziano from Italy.
I'm a Developer Relations Engineer
at MIA Platform, and I focus on
sharing the wonderful things the
cloud native world has to offer.
At MIA Platform, we offer a digital
platform builder to the market, which is
one of the tools available for building
what we will be discussing today.
If you'd like to stay in touch with
me, you can find me on LinkedIn or
GitHub, and if you are interested to,
In this and other cloud native topics,
I invite you to visit the NeoPlatform
blog or my website at GrazianoCast.
com.
Don't worry, I'll provide links to all
my contacts in the final feedback form.
Let's start with a somewhat
provocative statement.
Platform engineering is the
natural evolution of DevOps.
Don't get me wrong, I'm not saying that
to DevOps long life platform engineering.
In fact, DevOps practices
are more alive than ever.
And it's thanks to this vitality
that platform engineering
is gaining momentum today.
What I mean by this statement is
that platform engineering emerges
as a methodology to industrialize
the practices, making them
more accessible and practical.
But why?
Why do we need to make it more accessible?
What's the point of making
something accessible that
worked well until recently?
After all, platform engineering has only
been discussed for a couple of years,
while DevOps has been around since 2007.
The typical phrase you hear when talking
about DevOps is You build it, you run it.
Coined by Werner Vogels,
CTO of Amazon, in 2006.
He explained how putting developers
in front of operational challenges
brought numerous benefits to
Amazon's production chain.
However, a lot of A lot has changed
since 2006, including technology, but
then we dealt with virtual machine and
were far from tools like Kubernetes and
other subsequent wave of cloud native
technologies to give you an idea today.
The CNCF landscape includes 119
projects and more than 1, 800 code
repositories, ranging from libraries
and frameworks to utilities and more.
The increasing technological
capabilities at our disposal makes
it seem like a huge advantage.
At first glance, however, being surrounded
by a multitude of tools that often do
similar or completely different things get
actually become an obstacle to innovation.
Imagine you are on a hike following
a straight path for hours.
Perhaps interrupted by
a few folks in the road.
Suddenly you find yourself facing
hundreds of different paths all at once.
You might think what an adventure, but
you'd probably also admit that getting
lost in such a scenario is a real risk.
This abundance of options
can hinder innovation.
To illustrate this concept, I used
a simple example, but there are
psychological theories on cognitive
load that highlight these aspects.
Cognitive load is not something to
underestimate, especially for so called
knowledge workers, which includes
developers and anyone with a job title
related to the technological field.
This explains why platform engineering
emerged and why the adoption of
platform of cloud native technologies
and the box practices, of course,
needs to be industrialized in this.
In this slide, you can see
a quote from Gartner paper
that summarizes this concept.
the platform engineering to shift the
burden from the platform users, of course,
Who are the developers by uploading it
onto a tool that is the platform itself.
The EDP or internal developer
platform is the tangible result
of applying platform engineering.
To understand what IDP is and what benefit
it brings, let first explore what a
platform is in its most general sense.
Think of an organization whose
business is to create software.
Typically, these organizations are
structured into development teams
that vary in size and, are often
cross functional to some extent.
Typically, the organization
grows, or it dies.
If it's business includes
involves multiple teams, each
team will have its own ownership
off their respective product.
Now, it's easy to imagine that in such
a company, even though different teams
to work on different products, they
still share a series of For example,
all teams will have boundaries set by
the higher ranks of the organization.
Therefore, it's likely that all
applications will use the same type
of database, be built with a pool of
two or three programming languages or
frameworks, and use common monitoring
tools and libraries, for example.
All these common aspects within
an organization, when taken.
Rationalized and combined using an
as a service approach in a common and
accessible place for everyone within the
organization constitute the platform.
The goal of applying these methodologies
to provide the developers with
everything they need to do their jobs
in a self service manner without having
to deal with the countless service
requests or inventing the wheel.
This image illustrates the concept.
translate, what we have discussed to the
experiences of going the grocery shopping.
In this example, we are using platform
engineering when, we know what we
need and we can take it from the
shelves, go to the self checkout,
pay and live completely on your own.
We are not using it if, When we get to
the checkout, despite knowing what we
need, we have to wait in line and rely
on someone else to enable us to pay.
Now, everything we have talked about
doesn't grow on trees and certainly isn't
something that can be done in a day.
We can also rationalize the role
involved within the platform and
divide them into Three main groups.
The first groups are the creators,
and these are those who initially
adopt a technology or build
something that will be later made
available for everyone to reuse.
They create building blocks that are then
used to construct more complex products.
They can also be
considered and re adopted.
There's especially if
building these blocks involves
experimenting with new tools and
technologies for the organization.
The second groups are the composer,
which are those who benefits from
the building blocks provided within
the platform to create digital
products or even more complex systems.
They, there isn't a strict separation
between the creators and composer.
The work of a composer today can become
the building block of for someone else
tomorrow, making them a creator as well.
Finally, there are the curators
of platform engineering.
They simply, sorry, they simplify
the cooperation between creators and
composer by providing tools, making
the work of creator accessible,
sharing best practices and more.
The cooperation between these three roles
ensure that the platform is a place where
the values is created to understand this.
Let's take the example
of a furniture making.
Okay.
The platform is our woodworking shop and
the curator or platform engineers are the
ones who ensure that all the tools in the
shop are properly Perfectly functioning
for what the user will need to do.
they bring in new tools and
create best practices for the use.
For example, there are, then there
are the carpenters who use these
tools to create pieces of four meters.
For example, here you can see a drawer.
They are the creators.
our platform stands to this example.
These drawers is then taken by
other carpenters who in this case
act as composer and they create
a chest of drawers, for example.
And at this point, the work of this
last group of carpenters can become a
Building block itself, since the newly
assembled chest of drawers can be used
to build something more complex, like a
kitchen, just create a vicious cycle of
value and sharing within the platform.
Translating this example in the world
of software development, the individual
building block provided by platform
engineering could be, for example,
I don't know, a Kubernetes cluster
with all necessary configuration,
a cross plane CRD, a Kafka topic,
an API to perform payments, or
even a completely new application
accessible to users, for example.
That woodworking shop is our
EDP, and the facilities it offers
could be a catalog where all
composable resources are available.
A monitoring system to track all the
activities of all the microservices
are CLI to view log introduction,
for example, and many others.
This cycle can be seen as a circular
economy in software development, where
resources are continuously reused and
repurposed, leading to a more efficient
and sustainable development process.
We know what a platform is, why we need
it and how to use it to create value.
But in the end, what does
this platform look like?
First, let me say that, it is, Much
more complex than what I'm about to
present, because each adoption of this
methodology is tailored to the adoption
to the adopters need, making each journey
unique with specific characteristics
that vary from use case to use case.
However, let's try to provide
a good abstraction of what.
can be considered a platform.
First of all, we have our software
delivery pipeline divided into
product teams that build a
digital product on one side.
On the other hand, there are various
dependencies that these product teams
need to manage, including, for example,
infrastructure, cloud providers,
and other such systems, and so on.
Our platform sits between the delivery
teams and their dependencies, and
is made up of various components.
First of all, there are several
interfaces that allow us to interact
with the platform on multiple levels.
Imagine, for example, a Web UI,
a set of APIs, a CLI, and so on.
Then there is the heart of the
platform, the control plane, which
is responsible for orchestrating all
the processes within the platform.
And finally, we have the components that
interact with the infrastructure provider.
Allowing developers to have runtime
environments on demand, for example, by
clicking by simply clicking on a button
on a web UI without having to open service
request and wait for someone to intervene.
Or there is the part.
of the platform that handles orchestration
and simplified adoption of DevOps
tools, such as, for example, pipeline.
This includes providing pre built
pipeline to integrate into your
system, tracing and monitoring systems,
secret management, and testing.
For example, it could provide
access to direct time with Intel.
telepresence, for example.
And so in this context, we will have,
cloud engineers who will create automation
for the infrastructure providers.
This ensure that, this services
can be used in a self service
manner with as little friction
as possible for the developers.
Developers use the platform
and the capability it provides
to build digital products.
And finally, we are, and finally
there are the platform engineers
who orchestrate the work of the
previous two roles and ensure that
everything run as smoothly as possible.
For example, they define best practices,
golden path, documentation of advocates
for the platform and handle all
aspects that fall under the umbrella
of platform as a product methodology.
And this is the most common
representation of what a platform is.
For example, I recommend looking at
the platform web paper by CNCF, which
presents platform in a very similar way.
Platform engineering is often only
associated with infrastructure and
DevOps simplification, with the
primary goal of providing developers
with a self service platform.
But is that enough to cover the
entire value chain to efficiently
deliver a product and application?
The point is that by focusing too
much on applications, And the tools
around them, we overlook the fact
that today's software is built on much
more than just run time it's run on.
While the current platform
engineering practices efficaciously
address many aspects of simplifying
people's lives, there are other
areas that require attention.
Data, ML, API.
Security, privacy and others are
crucial for better software product
lifecycle by relying platform engineering
only to the infrastructure aspects.
We run the risk of creating the
new barriers between platform
engineers and developers similar to
the barriers that exist in the past
between operations and developers.
Digital products as they are crafted
today are based on data, business logic,
and the know how and experience gained by
the organization, both from technological
and business domain perspective.
These are important assets that must
be included and valued within the
platform as composable resources that
can be leveraged to generate value.
With the representation of platform,
we had focused on the automation
aspect of the infrastructure,
which was central to the sheen.
What we aim to do with this
different vision of platform is
to give space to and value these
assets that was mentioned before.
The first added benefit is composability.
Both in terms of application accessibility
and application composability.
By accessibility, we can range
from an API gateway to access the
application endpoint, to portals that
expose documentation and describe
capabilities, making our software
usable from the outside, for example.
This also includes composable logic
for solving a business problem,
which can involve using, for example,
orchestrators as building blocks to
manage sagas in a standardized way,
creating and managing the microphone
tents or providing a marketplace within
the platform for elements that can be
used to build a more complex solution.
Last but not least are the data.
A digital product is unlikely to
succeed without a data platform.
Therefore, the platform should
include tools like, data catalog
to improve data discoverability,
a control plane to monitor data
flows in real time from source to
destination, allowing for stopping,
resuming and analyzing these flows.
And providing an approach for
building data fabric within the
platform by adding these two elements.
We achieve a more modern vision of a
platform that includes all the resources
related to creating digital products.
Now, the million dollar question.
We are in the boom of
artificial intelligence.
Could I avoid bringing up AI?
Of course not.
I'll just spend a few words to
introduce what AI is today and what its
future prospects are in this context.
The vision I want to present, I want to
present is not much about how platforms
are useful Or will be for building
AI powered application, but rather
a perspective where AI is one of the
interfaces that platform provides us
with an intelligent yet simple interface
that allow us to use natural language,
we can elevate the platform user
experience and consequently the developer
experience to a whole new level from
simple device to conversational device.
Imagine having a virtual assistant that
speaks like you and respond as you would
with the added benefit of perfectly
understanding the context of your
platform because it is your platform.
Now, imagine what you could do with such
an assistant that know your data models.
They are lineage and the pipeline that
managed that, it knows the tools you can
use the best practices for using them
and they call them path designed to help
you assume designed to help you use.
them optimally within
the platform context.
It also know every item in the marketplace
of building blocks you can use and
can provide advice on how to integrate
them, including how others have done so.
You can see that, I don't know,
troubleshooting production issues or
conducting a POC in such a context is
on a whole different level than now.
We have reached the end of the
presentation and I'd like to
recap what we have talked about.
Covered and what I hope you have taken
away from this session first, the software
industry and the digital product creation
sector are undergoing a transformation.
We have moved from project with
outcomes that could be afford to be
isolated to the necessity of having
everything be integrable and integrated
within a clear and defined context.
This is where the need of platform arises.
Second, and this is the core of this talk,
platform engineering encompasses more
aspects of digital application creation,
not just infrastructure and DevOps.
Finally, I don't know if artificial
intelligence, we take our jobs,
but, I, but I think that if
integrated into our platform, it can
elevate the developer experience.
So we provide to our decks
to an entirely new level.
So let's give credit where credit is due.
First of all, I want to mention my CTO,
Giulio Ruggiero, who was the first to
formulate these concepts and present them
during the keynote at Platformosphere,
the Italian conference dedicated to
end development of digital platforms.
Then, this concept were also brought to
the platform working group of the CNCF
and just, Some weeks ago, an article was
published and that delves deeper into
the topics we have discussed today, and
so I highly recommend you to read it.
Thank you for being here with
me to discuss these topics.
Here you will also find my
contact information if you
want to stay in touch with me.
And there is a dedicated space for
questions on the topic, which I'll try to
answer on LinkedIn or via email privately.
Additionally, you can find my website
and the platform blog where there
are articles and other talks on this
and other more or less technical
topics in the cloud native world.
Last but not least, in the feedback form,
you can find direct link to all resources
mentioned during this presentation.
Thank you all for listening to
me and a special thanks to Conf42
organizer for having me today.
Bye.