Welcome.
Welcome everyone.
Today we are going to explore a unique
and holistic framework for UX design.
We will be looking at how ancient
wisdom of the chakra system can be
applied to modern digital product
design and create more meaningful
and human-centered experience.
Now, I have a question to ask you guys.
Do you have unresolved
feelings or anxiety about.
Is my idea complete enough?
Are people enjoying my product or
have I covered all my use cases?
Now let's focus on, have I
covered all my use cases?
That sounds tense, right?
I want to shift the focus and talk about
particular subset of the use cases, edge
cases, because we often forget about that.
I want us to figure out how we can design
products for the whole human experience.
Talking about the human experience.
Hi, I am Prish.
I am a human computer interaction
expert based in New York City, and I'm
a person who wants to try everything.
I'm a person who is looking for
always finding new tools all the time.
I. Love it when it works, and
I also hate it when it doesn't.
I am an easily be easily trustable person.
I'm very sure that I resonate with a
lot of you guys today, and that is why
I want us to look at how we can create
solutions that touch on all the edge cases
of the human experience chakra system.
I am going to apply it as a
framework for conscious design in ux.
I'm very sure that all of you have
heard about these chakras, whether
reading about it in yoga, meditation,
ancient Hindu text, or even when
watching and reading Japanese manga.
Yes, they are in Japanese manga as well.
So are we just building for clicks?
As designers, we are often
pushed to focus on metrics, but
what is the impact of our work?
Metrics often is a success measured
by engagement, go conversion rate
retention, but all of this can lead to
addictive patterns, digital anxiety, and
a disconnect from the real human needs.
Conscious design, ask us to look beyond
the surface level interaction and consider
the user's entire experience emotionally,
intellectually, and even spiritually.
Designing with awareness, empathy,
and a deeper understanding of
users' holistic wellbeing will
create a very well-rounded product.
Let's briefly touch on the
foundations of this framework.
The chakra system is an ancient
model for understanding ourselves.
It's the word chakra is derived from
Sanskrit, which means wheel or a disc, and
it's about connectedness and it's about
revolving and going around and repeating.
They're considered energy centers
in the body each corresponding to
different aspects of our physical,
emotional, and psychological be.
There are seven main chakras in
our Hindu mythology, and they're
arranged vertically from the base of
the spine to the crown of the head.
Think of it as a map of human experience,
and it's not about believing in literal
energy centers, but about using the
system as a powerful metaphor to ensure
we are designing for the whole person.
Each chakra represents a core human need.
Here are the seven chakras and
the core need they represent.
You can see how they build upon each
other, just Maslow's hierarchy of needs
from basic survival to higher purpose.
The first chakra, which is at
the base of the human spine,
is root chakra called muha.
It's about security,
survival, and stability.
The one above it called
sacral chakra, Swedish tanana.
It's about creativity,
pleasure, and emotions.
The next one called the solar plexus
Chakra, also known as manipura.
It's about power will
self-esteem, and being in control,
controlling the environment.
Controlling yourself.
The next one is heart chakra, and
all of these next four chakras are
going beyond yourself, beyond your
human body, and embarking into
the social aspects of human need.
It's about connection with your
world, your people, and beyond that.
So the heart chakra, also known as anhata,
is about love, connection, and empathy.
And understanding people
beyond you and yourself.
Love for yourself and love for others.
Throat chakra, also known as
vta, it's about communication,
truth and self-expression.
It's not about voice,
it's about communication.
Are you able to express what you feel?
Third, a chakra, also known as ajna.
It's about intuition,
wisdom, and imagination.
And the last one is crown
chakra, also known as Sahara.
It's about spirituality,
purpose, and unity.
Let's map these needs directly to UX
design principles, one by one, and how
we can use these ancient wisdom methods.
To activate connections of
people with our digital products.
So the first chakra, the root
chakra, also called mul tarara.
It's about security and survival.
The core needs for this is, does this
product feel safe, stable and reliable.
Core UX principles you can
use here are usability.
Is the product easy to use
and navigate reliability?
Does it work as expected or does it
have any bugs or crashes and security?
Is my data safe?
Is my privacy respected?
Everything starts at the root.
If the user doesn't feel safe, or
if the product constantly crashes
and fails, they will leave.
They will never create a bond
between your product and themselves.
This is the foundation
of the user's trust.
This corresponds to the most basic
level of usability heuristics.
For an example, if a banking app inside
that you must have a rock solid security
and in it should be incredibly reliable.
If it fails here, no
other feature matters.
The next one is Sacral chakra,
also known as Swedish Tanana.
It's about creativity and pleasure.
Once the basics are covered, we
move on to how the product feels.
The core needs for this is the product
enjoyable and aesthetically pleasing?
Is it a CHO to use or is it a pleasure?
The UX principles that you
can use here are aesthetics.
Is the visual design appealing
and appropriate joy of use?
Does the product create
moments of delight?
Like micro interactions or animations, or
are we celebrating small victories there?
And creativity Does the product
allow for users' expression?
This is where beautiful design, satisfying
animations and features that empower
users' creativity come into play.
For example, Instagram's filter
and creative tools allow users
to express themselves, making
them experiencing pleasure.
The next one is slow, so sorry.
Solar Plexus Chakra.
That's a mouthful.
The Solar Plexus Chakra, also known as
Money Pura is about power and self-esteem.
The core need for this is,
does this product make me
freely capable and in control?
This chakra is about the
user sense of agency.
A well-designed product should
feel like powerful tool in user's
hand and not a confusing maze.
That is a burden to use, and
then they have to fight through
just to get basic work out of it.
User control and freedom users
can easily undo mistakes.
Can they customize their experiences?
The next principle you
can use is efficiency.
Does the product help users
A, achieve their goals
effectively and feel productive?
The next one you can use is empowerment,
which is does this tool make users
feel smarter and more powerful?
We empower users by giving them clear
controls, customization options,
and efficient part to their goals.
For example.
A project management tool like
Notion or Asana empowers users
by giving them control over their
workflow and complex lives and make
them feel organized and capable.
This is where it activates
their solar Plexus chara.
The next one, as I said, is beyond you.
It's now creating experiences and
connections with you and the world.
It's the heart chakra.
Also known as anhata.
It's about love and connection.
The core need for this chakra is does
this product connect me with others?
Does the company care about me?
It's not only just me connecting
to the world is if your product
is able to connect with me.
The UX principles that you
can use here are empathy.
Does the design show an understanding
of the user's feeling and context?
Community.
Does this product foster a sense
of belonging and connection
between the users and support?
Is it easy to get help?
Does the customer support
feel human and caring?
This is often what is not
happening in the world anymore.
If you are stuck in a problem,
you are stuck with an AI agent.
This is where we move from
individual to the collective.
We are social creators.
Great UX Design fosters community
and shows that the company behind
the product genuinely cares for its
users through thoughtful support
and empathetic design choices.
For example, social features, community
forums, and genuinely helping and
being empathetic to customer service,
all caters to the human chakra.
It creates a bonding between
you and the product, and you.
This is really important
to activate heart chakra.
The next one is throw chakra or vta.
It's also about communication and
truth, not just communication.
It's about honesty.
The core need for this chakra
is the product's, communication,
clear, honest, and transparent.
The UX principles that you
can use here is clarity.
Is the copy free of jargon and
easy to understand honesty.
Is the pricing transparent?
Are there hidden features?
Are all the features described accurately?
What is the feedback that
I'm getting from the system?
Does the system provide clear
feedback for all the user actions?
Is it showing me fake statuses or
is the real system's health that
is being shown on the system?
Now as we move to the higher,
more subtle aspects of ux, the
throat chakra is about product's.
Voice tone, trust is built on
clear and honest communication.
So this is where the UX writing
information architecture and how you
communicate with the users are critical.
An example for this could be a
product with clear error messages.
Transparent pricing and straightforward
language bills, trust, and ensuring
that the users feels respected
and it's not taken for granted.
The sixth Chakra is the third I chakra,
also called Ajna, such a nice name.
It's about intuition and wisdom.
The core need for this chakra is
does this product feel intuitive?
Like it anticipates my need.
Is it proactive?
Is it taking things care?
It is it taking care of things before
I can even imagine a truly great
experience feels almost magical.
This is the goal of the third eye chakra.
The UX principles that you can use here
are intuitiveness can use as accomplished
task without conscious effort.
Personalization.
Does the experience adapt to
individual needs, or is it always
that I have to start from scratch
every time I want to use it?
Does it save my status and context
and then jumps me right into action
when I, where I left off continuity.
If I leave my task on one system, does
it take me at the same state when I open
the application on a different system?
If I leave my playlist running on my
phone, can I continue the same song on my
computer when I log into the same system?
Anticipation.
Does the product surface the right
information at the right time?
This is achieved through deep
user research, smart defaults, and
effective personalizations that
makes user feel seen and understood.
For example, a music streaming
services that create a perfect playlist
based on your listening habits feels
like it's reading your mind now.
It is also at the same time
activating your second.
And your heart chakras as well.
And this is where you can see activating
multiple chakras at the same time.
If through your product experience you
can create a deeper magical bonding with
your product and your users, that's why
it's very important, not just us, just
focus on one chara at a time, but try to.
Activate as many as chakras as possible.
The last chakra is about
knowledge, purpose, and your flow.
This is called the crown chakra.
It sits above your body
in a true ancient sense.
It's also called ra.
The core needs for this.
Principle is, does this product
help me achieve a state of
flow or a higher purpose?
This is a pinnacle of
user experience design.
This is where the product
transcends into a function and
becomes a transformative tool.
At this level, the user is so
eng endorsed and empowered that
the product helps them achieve
something truly meaningful to them.
Something they probably didn't even think
of when they started using this product.
A lot of creative tools
sit in crown chakras.
Some of the UX princip that you
can use here are Flow State.
Does the tool allow for deep
uninterrupted focus transformation?
Does the product help users grow
or achieve meaningful goals or
meaning does the product aligns
with the user's value now?
For example a well-designed writing
app that minimizes distractions
and allow author to enter in a
state of flow clairvoyance and
becoming a seamless extension of
their creative process is a perfect
fitting for activating this chakra.
Once you activate this chakra through
your experiences, users and users
can create what they're imagining or
something that they haven't even imagined.
And creativity just flows out.
So I want to summarize all the seven
chakras into how it is it important
for designing for the whole human.
The more chakras you activate, the
more connection you can build, the
more effect that you can have on the
user, as well as their environment
as well, and their creativity.
The chakra system provides a
holistic checklist for the UX design.
It encourages us to move beyond
the basic usability and metrics.
By designing for these core human
needs, we can create products
that are not only successful, but
truly add value to people's life.
In the end, I just want you
to leave with these questions.
This you can use always as
guiding principles when activating
chakras through your products.
Is it reliable?
Is it enjoyable?
Is it empowering?
Is it connecting?
Is it clear?
Is it intuitive?
Is it transformative?
And if you can activate all the chakras,
you will truly create a great product.
Thank you.
Bye.