Hi everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My name is Bin Aja and I'm
a DevOps lead within IBM.
Today.
Today we are going to talk about
ethical AI deployment at scale.
And like we are going to discuss about
the platform engineering approaches.
So today we are going to dive
into one of the most critical
challenges in modern tech which
is ethical AI deployment at scale.
This is not the theoretical discussion.
It is like a hard engineering problem,
which we are facing every day.
And the key to solving this problem is to,
it lies with us like platform engineers.
So our, over the few minutes we will move
from understanding the core dilemma we are
facing to the tangible ROI of solving it.
And finally we'll be talking about
like a practical blueprint for building
ethical safeguards, which is directly
into the fabric of our AI platforms.
So let's get started.
So today we are seeing is 83% of
enterprise accelerate AI integration
and platform team are facing
more lot of pressure to deploy
AI responsibly and maintaining.
The velocity as well.
So this session, how we are embedding like
ethical AI safeguards into the deployment
process and so that we can create
the pipeline faster and most lively.
And so that AI systems so that we
can the stakeholder trust, right?
So now we have a platform
engineer dilemma, right?
The dilemma we all recognize,
like we are caught between a two.
Powerful challenges which seems
to be like opposing forces, right?
On the one hand we are facing
like the velocity pressure and so
that we need to ship the product
faster and support more models.
And on the other hand the other
hand, we have a non-negotiable
mandate for responsible ai.
So we must embed like a fairness.
Avoid biases and protect
the privacy as well.
And also and also ensuring
the compliance, right?
So the consequences of getting things
wrong are severe and it, and like
a reputational damage is there.
And there are regulatory fines
and also a total loss of user
trust if things go wrong.
So the old mantra used to be like.
We can go fast and break things,
but in today's world, breaking
things, breaking people.
So the challenge here is like, how do we
maintain a balance between a breakneck
speed without breaking our commitments?
So now we are going to talk about
the ROI of ethical AI platforms.
The good news is that it
is not just a cost center.
Ethical AI platforms building these
platforms deliver like a massive and
measurable return on investments.
So think about it like what happens
when you automate ethical checks.
First you accelerate the velocity.
That is the benefit we get.
And like by catching issues
early in the pipeline, we
avoid the mass massive delays.
And also we avoid the rework.
Required when problems are
found late in the production.
So it leads to it leads to the
improvement in the deployment efficiency.
So we see two 86% improvement
in deployment efficiency, right?
And the second one is like we
are de-risking the deployment.
So automated testing is leading
to 89% detection rate for bias
issues pre-production and 84%
enhancement and compliance.
So that is a big achievement.
This is not just about avoiding fines.
It is more about getting more
user trust and this trust
translate into adoption, right?
So as we can see like organizations
are like there, there's a 92% increase
in sustainable AI adoption these days.
And because developers are
trusting the platform and end
user is trusting the outward.
So this is how ethics becomes, right?
A competitive advantage, not a bottleneck.
So that's why it is important
that we integrate ethics.
Into the picture.
So now we will talk about
automated ethical testing in
the next slide in the pipelines.
So how do we achieve it?
It starts by shifting left.
Ethical testing must be automated
and integrated into the pipelines.
This means treating and ethical
failures like a build failure.
Or a unit test failure.
So as soon as a model is committed,
the pipeline should be automatically
run it against the battery of test.
And we should check for a statistical
parity differences and equal opportunity.
And and also using using tools like AI
Fairness 360 or lan, we can achieve that.
And the key here is the process
should be automate and mandatory.
It is like a quality gate.
If the model does not pass this
gate and the bias check the
pill should fail automatically.
And this moves ethical validation
from manual to automated validation
and so that we can automate this week
long processes and we can and we can
also reduce validation cycle by 55%.
Oh, like close to 56%
and 91% rapid issues.
And it all mitigation effectiveness
also, and this is this is the
foundation here and making like
ethics is like a non-negotiable
part of the definition of done.
So now we will talk about talking about
the platform native vehicle frameworks.
If you talk about the tools, so
tools are not just enough, right?
We need to build a, like a platform
framework which means like a big banking
ethics into the infrastructure we provide.
So we need to bake ethical
frameworks into it.
So instead of asking every development
team to figure out on their own, if
we can, if the platform team provides
like a curated, pre-approved ethical,
tooling as a service we offer.
So what we can do is we can standardize
model cards, which will auto-populate
the fairness metrics, right?
Second one we can do is we can
pre-build compliance data pipelines
with the anonymization building, right?
Third one is we can provide the approved
libraries for bias mitigation, right?
So provide, by providing these,
services like this as like a managed
services, we ensure like a consistency
into the product and we reduce the
cognitive load for product teams.
And also we guarantee every model
deployed into our platform meets like
baseline ethical standard by default.
So we make the right way and we make the
things right way and in the easy way.
Now we are going to talk about the case
study for a healthcare AI platform.
So let's make like a concrete
healthcare study discussion.
So the stake here could
be could not be higher.
We are dealing with a lot of patient
data and health data, so the platform
team implemented these one of the
platform team implemented these exact
principles, which we just talked
about, and they embedded like a ethical
testing for bias in diagnostic models.
And built the privacy preserving data
workflow directly into the platform.
And and it gives 67% reduction in the
privacy incidents, and it gives like
a 79% increase in clinical trust.
And 92% sustainable a adoption
and 74% fewer bias concern,
which is a big achievement.
Now so the doctor could focus, on a
patient care because they trusted the
platform more and at time ensured that the
model was fair and data was safe, right?
So now we are going to talk about
the cloud scale ethical monitoring.
By implementing monitoring
in place, it helps a lot.
So how, so deployment is not just
about finishing the line, right?
It is more about how
we can, how model can.
Like model can degrade in the real world
through model drift and data drift, right?
So what was fair yesterday might
not be the, might not be fair today.
This is where cloud scale
ethical monitoring helps.
So we need to monitor pipelines.
So we need to monitor productions
in the real time and like by.
Like by monitoring like real time events
which has probably been processed like
thousands of events per second, right?
And checking for drift and and
violations against our ethical baselines.
So we should be monitoring all of these.
And for that we need a
dedicated monitoring stack.
So perhaps using tools like Fiddler.
Or s core which like the, we can grade,
we can achieve the great outcomes.
Like the outcome is to detect
91% violations we can detect and
it'll improve the response time.
Like we can increase, like you
can get a 78% faster incident
response time with the help of this.
So like automated alerting and
remediation workflows, engage the
right teams immediately whenever
the potential issues arise.
So now a critical question
is like, who decide?
What is fair, right?
So the, it cannot be like an
emerging decision made in a vacuum.
Like what, who decide what is fair?
This is where the cross-functional
governance is very much essential.
We need to build a, like a lightweight
council with legal compliance,
ethics and business, right?
With the business representatives.
The job here is to define what our.
What are like, what are
the fairness thresholds?
What is our definition of bias?
So our job as a platform
engineer is to encode that.
Into the policy as a code and so that
we can turn their human decisions
into automated gates in our pipeline.
Like that's why we are saying like a
policy as a code and the CO and this
kind of collaboration which will make
the system more scalable and estimate,
and it is why organization using this.
Model report I'll get 75% better
project success rate and 91%
effectiveness in the mitigating issues.
So now it is very important, like
we build our ethical a platform.
So how do we do that, right?
So for that we need to define
the platform requirements.
We need to integrate ethics
into the CICD pipelines.
And then we have to develop
operation monitoring, right?
So first we need to, pick one
high visibility model and audit
it and create audit it for a
single metric like gender bias.
And then tool up, like
experiment with the.
Then we do experiment with one open
source framework and run it manually
or model and see what it finds.
Then we can third, integrate it like
and add like a single ethical test for
a non-blocking check into our pipeline
and let developers see the report.
And then fourth, like we can mandate like
we can graduate the test like a blocking
it for our critical applications, right?
And then we can add more tasks into it.
And then we can develop operational
monitoring into it and formalize our
governance council which is not a journey.
It is like a journey, not a one stop.
Like another flip you
with the project, right?
So it is, it takes time to
develop the monitoring in place.
So the key takeaway here is indeed.
Ethical AI into it.
Don't append.
So ethical AI s should be more
infrastructure components or not.
It should not be an afterthought
or add on to an existing platform.
And we should automate the validation
building automated ethical AI
testing, like ethical testing into
CICP pipelines to catch issues
early without slowing deployment.
And that is like govern through platform.
So implement like a platform
native governance, which is
scales with our AI initiatives.
And it was through like with
the regulatory requirements.
So when it is done right, the ethical
ai framework don't slow the deployment.
It accelerate the sustainable AI
option by building confidence into the
system and increasing the user trust.
So thank you for attending and please
let me know if you have any questions.