I'm here to present in the
platform engineering for FinTech.
We want to specifically discuss about
database architecture in FinTech and
how this distributed database starting
works, replication and scaling, and
how it helps the FinTech industry.
As we all know, modern FinTech platforms
track air platform engineering solutions
that can process massive transaction
volumes during peak events in milliseconds
while maintaining the accuracy.
Also, the availability, so as financial
services scale globally across different
regions and environments which have
different regulatory requirements.
Platform teams must architect
distributed database system that
supports retail, blanking trading,
digital balance, and payment
processing at unprecedented volumes.
So the agenda of this PPT
is split into the six parts.
First we will discuss about the platform
engineering foundation how it evolved
around in the financial infrastructure.
How the requirements
are captured and scaled.
And what is the role of a
database architecture here.
Then we will look at deeply
into the database strategies.
We will start with the
database strategy strategies.
We have a different starting strategies
like horizontal partnering, partitioning.
Geographic or regulatory spreading
on operational management, right?
So there are replication models,
which can be synchronous or hybrid.
Whichever suits for the financial
tech industries and consistency
model, consistency models, strong
consistency, eventual consistency
and cashflow, consistency for
different financial context.
So then the architectural patterns, how
these database, and driven architectures
are used, like even driven architecture,
microservices, cqrs, and even sourcing.
Then we look at some case studies and
feature directions where this platform
at FinTech goes with respect to database
and especially distributed database.
So let's dive in.
As the evolution of financial
infrastructure, we know the financial
industry has undergo a significant
transformation over the years on how
it approaches the data management
and system architecture, right?
So example, traditional banking
system built on monolithic
architectures at first have given a
way to, given way to a distributor
systems and cloud native platforms.
Recently, platform engineering has
emerged a critical discipline and focused
on creative self-service capabilities.
Modern FinTech platforms face multifaceted
challenges recurring Highlander
scalability while maintaining the asset
properties, which is critical for five.
FinTech industries.
High frequency trade trading
system must process market data and
execute trades within microseconds.
Digital banking platforms need to handle
millions of simultaneous user at a time.
Payment processes must validate and settle
transaction across multiple currencies
and different countries, and which have
a different regulatory jurisdiction
while maintaining the perfect accuracy.
So this is our revolution of the
financial industry over the years
and the need now we will understand
the scale requirements, right?
So accuracy and audit, auditability,
financial transaction, demand up,
accuracy, auditability, and permanence.
Zero margin for error is
acceptable in calculation and
comprehensive logging is mandated
by regulatory and run requirements.
Extreme usage spikes, financial platforms
must adaptably handle extreme usage
spikes triggered by market events,
product launches, or seasonal activities
like tax season or height trading day.
And due to global events the
architecture must ensure.
Consistent performance through
robust auto-scaling capabilities.
And there is geographical distribution
comes into play as well because
we have to comply with the data
resiliency loss across diverse
jurisdiction of different countries.
Coupled with the need for
low latencies global access
mandates, multi-regional database
deployments for financial services.
With this in mind, the database
from monolithic evolved into
database distributed database in
the FinTech industries, and it is
critical role, it is playing critical
role in serving the consumers.
As well as keeping the
regulatory requirements, right?
So we will look at the different
strategies involved in this.
First, the shredding strategies.
So under the shredding strategies, the
horizontal partnering in partitioning
in financial context, right?
By distributing data across multiple
database instances, sh shredding enables
linear scalability while maintaining
the low latency QE performance.
The primary challenges lies in
maintaining the transactional
integrity across shared boundaries.
So user based sharding is one of the
most common in financial platform
because this partitioning based on user
data or echo number can be executed
or operate within the single shot.
And all the information can be in single
shot of a particular user, however.
Operations spanning multiple user
accounts like payment from one account
to another which involves different
charge repair, sophisticated distributed
transaction management to maintain
performance as well as consistency.
So there is also a geographic
and regulatory sharding.
First thing may be a regulation.
Regional compliance system care, right?
Geographic writing enables that
strategy enables that regulatory
requirements, which aligns the
database distribution with the
regulatory requirements, ensuring.
Customer data remains within specific
geographic boundaries, right?
So then it can, it also enables
the cross power transaction if you
have a geographic trading sharding
payments between regions involved.
Data showed in different geographical
chart require complex routing logic
and transaction coordination protocols.
Time based Charlie historical transaction
data is critical in FinTech for the
statements, tax purposes, and others.
That can be partitioned by data
ranges, enabling efficient archival
and compliance reporting while keeping
recent data in high performance charts.
Effective chart management requires
automated tools and processes that
handle operational complexity,
including monitoring systems that
track shared health performance
metrics and capacity utilization.
Short rebalancing represent on of the
most complex operational challenges
as user bases grow unevenly.
Our transaction pay 10 changes due to
various recent, so the next one is the
replication models for high availability.
So our, the replication models
can be a synchronous or hybrid.
We will look at the
synchronous replication first.
Synchronous replication
for financial accuracy.
Synchronous replication provides the
strongest to consistency guarantees,
ensuring all replicas contained.
Identical data at any point in time.
This is essential for critical financial
operation where inconsistencies
could result in financial
losses or regulatory violation.
Right?
Operation must be confirmed by all
replicas before the transaction
is even considered complete.
Ensure any replica can
immediately take over without
data loss during primary failure.
Introduces additional latency and
complexity due to this, especially when it
is across different geographical location.
Also, multi-master synchronous
replication presence, additional
complicate comp complexities.
In while doing the conflict resolution.
So then there is an asynchronous
enables financial asynchronous
PLA replication enables financial
platforms to achieve global scale while
maintaining acceptable performance.
Operations are committed to
the primary database and then
propagate to replica synchronously.
It reduces the right latency
significantly and enable geographic
distribution of real operations easily.
Introduce possibility of temporary data.
Inconsistencies between replicas requires
careful monitoring of replication,
lag needs, sophisticated conflict
direction and resolution mechanism.
If you are using a synchronous
replication, which is the downside,
hybrid replication strategies modern
financial platform often implement
these kind of hybrid aches combining
synchronous and synchronous replication
based on data classification.
So this gives more
beneficial of both worlds.
Critical financial data uses synchronous
replication within a region and
thus a synchronous across region.
Less critical data may use
a synchronous replication.
Exclusively sophisticated data
classification and routing
system application must stand
in different consistency models
for different data types.
So then there is the consistency
models in financial system,
there is strong consistency.
Essential for code ranking system,
trading system, and payment processing
where accuracy is paramount.
All nodes see the same data at the same
time, require sophisticated coordination
protocol, prioritize consistency over
stability, ual consistency, better
performance for analytics, reporting
and customer facing application.
Tolerate temporary inconsistencies
require conflict resolution.
Mechanism needs monitoring
for replication lag.
Casual consistency.
So it's a middle ground for
complex financial workflows,
ensures casually related operation.
Maintain order, allows unrelated
operation to can be reorder, requires
timestamp and dependency tracking.
So moving onto the next topic,
which is architectural pattern
for financial scalability.
First architectural pattern we can
take as event driven architecture.
It is essential for building a scalable
financial platform that handle complex
multi-step processes while maintaining
loose coupling between services.
Even sourcing provides complete audit
trials for regulatory complaints.
S careful attention to event
ordering and delivery guarantees.
Even streaming platform like
Kafka have become central to
many financial architecture.
For this reason, microservices
architecture is paramount for any arc,
but it is more paramount to financial.
FinTech org as well.
It enables financial problems to organize
complex business logic into manageable
independently deployable services.
Domain driven design helps identify
appropriate service boundaries
require sophisticated transaction
management across service boundaries.
Service MIS technologies provide essential
capabilities for security and monitoring.
Then we have secures command
query responsibility, segregation.
Which separates command processing
from query processing, optimizing
each for specific requirements, right?
Operation.
Focus on maintaining consistency and
business role while read operation.
Optimize for performance and user
experience enables specialist three
models for different use cases.
Then there is e sourcing benefit.
It compliments the CQRS by
providing reliable mechanism for
propagating state changes even
generated by command processing.
Update read models are
synchronously, provides natural
audit trails for compliance.
Enables creation of new read models
from historical even streams, requires
sophisticated, even processing
pipelines to implement this.
Then there is an important topic in
the FinTech industry which is always
a talk as security and compliance.
Which is critical for the FinTech
industry while maintaining the
customer data and information.
So there is an encryption
and data production.
Financial data occurs production
both at risk as well as in transit.
Transparent data encryption are for
stored data, secure communication
between our system components, hardware
security models for key management.
Access control, fine grain mechanism.
Ensure data is only accessible to
authorized user, road based and attribute
based access control MFA, multifactor
authentication for sensitive systems, road
level and carbon level security policy
also being implemented in various places.
Regulatory complaints.
Financial platforms must
comply with numerous frameworks
and data Ency requirement.
Private privacy regulations like G
gt, GTPR, detailed audit, logging,
logging and reporting capabilities
for tax purposes and others.
So we will look at the case
studies, real world implementation,
high frequency trading platform.
Major investment bank, implemented
distributed architecture, acquiring
microsecond latencies, and perfect
consistency, geographic distribution
with co-located databases,
instances hybrid approach, which we
discussed in the previous slides.
Combining synchronous application
within region and as synchronous
across different region, sub
millisecond and performance monitoring.
With automated resource allocation,
digital banking platform leading
digital banking platform.
Built globally distributed
architecture, supporting millions of
customer sh trying strategy based on
geography, location and account type.
Human driven architecture with
comprehensive human sourcing, eventual
consistency for user experience and strong
consistency for financial operations.
Money transfer stuff, payment processing
network, global processor handling peak
volumes with sub-second authorization
times combination of graphicy and
merchant based Strat, which is user based
Strat real time fraud reduction with
machine learning, disaster recovery,
redirecting reprocessing within seconds.
So where the future hits too, right?
With all this infu in
financial platform engineering.
Cloud native database technologies, right?
Evolution towards technology, designed
for distributed container environment,
serverless database, eliminating
operational overhead, multi-cloud
strategies, balancing performance,
cost and compliance, integrated
security and compliance capabilities.
Also as talk of the towns NA
and ML integration as well,
and quantum security, right?
Transformative capabilities being
integrated directly into database system.
Automated performance tuning and
anomaly reduction by a real time
fraud reduction and risk assessment.
Quantum resistant cryptographic
algorithms is being researched and
then hybrid security approaches
during transition period.
So that's all for the presentation today.
Thank you.
Thanks for listening to this.