Welcome to the conference.
Welcome to building
developer driven platforms.
I'm going to share some experiences,
some things that I've learned along
the way and really excited about it.
And I'm hoping that those things
that I've learned can help shape
automation and UI for your platform.
But before I convince you of all
of the things that I've learned,
let me tell you about myself and
how I've learned these things.
Elliot Clark.
I'm the founder and CEO of Batteries
Included, an engineer at heart who's
building on top of Kubernetes, a
source available product that we'll
be releasing out of Stealth soon.
I hope to have more to
tell you about that soon.
But before founding Batteries Included,
I've done a lot of things and helped a
lot of engineers build a lot of systems
that have given me a lot of, good lessons.
I worked at Facebook where I
worked in ads, dev efficiency,
and distributed, data stores.
Before that I worked at Cloudera
where I was an open source
committer to Apache HBase.
I got to see open source be adopted by
enterprise and got to help them pull
open source and really understand it.
I've done a few startups before and
before those startups, I got to help
other developers when I was at, Microsoft
building, C sharp tools and WPF.
So I've really had a career of
helping engineers build systems,
mostly distributed systems, but
lots of lots of good experiences
of what can build the best, most
productive systems in the world.
While we're thinking about a
developer driven platform and
what a good one looks like, it's
helpful to have some goals, right?
Some things to strive for,
things that we want to do better.
Your goals and the things that
you want from your technology
will obviously be very personal.
It'll be something that your
company, your team, your project,
feel, feels individually.
But almost every platform at some
time will have these as goals or
these will be part of their goals
or everyone will agree that a
platform should include these, right?
So we'll include these just as our generic
goals and you'll see how they mostly align
with that, with your experiences, I hope.
So for this platform, what's the goal?
Let's try and strive for greatness, right?
Let's try and help our users,
our developers build sustainable
and maintainable software.
That's good.
Not just now, but is good for
the business in the future.
And let's help them speed up so that
the time it takes from them having.
Some thought, something they crazy idea
that they think might work to it, actually
being out there in the world, how let's
make that faster, but let's also do that
in a way that doesn't break things, right?
Let's do that in a way that
keeps everything reliable.
And anytime things are broken,
let's help them fix that.
Fast so that we maintain that
reliability and that uptime, right?
If we do that as a platform,
I think we've done well.
we've sped everyone up.
We've helped them.
We've done good things.
These goals though are often
seen as in conflict, right?
The, how do I speed up developers?
Is oftentimes in direct conflict with how
do I make sustainable software, right?
I don't want to add metrics.
I want to go faster.
keeping things from breaking also
often means that you need to do extra
work, which can be seen as slowing
down the time from idea to production.
I think it's helpful to, to look
at times when things go wrong as
a way for us to learn in where we
can make better platforms, right?
Where we can make platforms
that really lead the way.
So if we think about it, what's the
number one cause of incidents, right?
what do platforms let through?
what causes downtime?
Overwhelmingly, there's
one source, one big, giant
source, that's the root cause of
most downtimes, of most, errors.
There, there's one thing that kind of
changes and causes most of the incidents.
It's developers.
Developers are the root cause.
We're the things that change the software.
The, The hardware will add
one plus one almost forever.
The software is where humans get involved
and it's where things often go wrong.
So if we want to understand
and build a good platform, we
have to dive deeper into it.
into developers and how does
that risk come with them and
how do we make it better?
I think of the things that slip through
the cracks, the issues that come from
developers as being in two buckets,
not understanding or not testing.
let me explain what I
mean by both of those.
For me, understanding is the grokking,
is the deep conceptual knowledge.
The, you can explain every principle
of something to the scientific
level where you can prove it.
We don't often get to understand the
business problem, the distributed system,
the edge cases in that kind of depth.
So oftentimes instead of fully
understanding and enumerating
every possible outcome and input,
we write tests that say, that
test is green, so I am pretty sure
that everything is going to work.
Right?
. So there, there are two sides, two ways
to make it where you're sure that you've
written something that is good software.
and there's some give and take, right?
You can't write a test without some
understanding, and in writing a test,
you often gain more understanding.
So there, there's a back and
forth of the two of them.
So it's often really interesting
to bucket what went wrong
into one of these two causes.
So you can go back and
say, what should we do?
Testing is a lot more than just,
you didn't write a unit test, right?
Testing is, you didn't have an
integration test that tested those
systems together and showed what
happens when things go wrong.
It's, Not checking that you can
actually restore your backups.
How recently have you made sure
that you're able to fail over to
your redundant systems, right?
There's a lot of testing to make sure
that things that you're never going
to fully understand are still working
and still operating as you expect,
but testing falls through the cracks.
But oftentimes as developers
we're too eager to say, I can just
write one more test when really
it's, we didn't understand, right?
If you're holding the tool upside down,
unit tests after the fact won't help you.
If you didn't know what winning and
losing looks like, it's really hard
to write a unit test that says you
got a good result or a bad result.
oftentimes, It's much
more than that, right?
Knowing that we didn't have to
even try this very hard solution.
We could have tried the much easier
thing over there is much more
impactful and is much better, right?
We didn't understand that this path
wasn't the one to take 10 choices ago.
Or we didn't understand where this
path was going to lead us when we
changed size or scale up or down.
So with those kind of two buckets,
let's go through an exercise where
we talk about one specific example.
And in the example, we'll try and
just walk through what happens.
And.
figure out where the causes and the
things that we can do better are.
And then we'll take that to use it
to learn to make a better platform.
So for this example, we'll
choose just about any enterprise,
setting where there's a new
product team coming on, right?
The new product team is going to write
some new data to a database that's
already existing and they need some help.
So a junior or mid level DevOps engineer
joins the effort and writes a set of code.
In that code, they add a user to
the database permissions list.
And they say, Oh, I'm gonna, I know you
were going to be writing some more data.
So let's make sure that we also
increase the size of production storage.
thinking ahead.
I like it.
They're doing great things.
They're making sure production is
going to be stable in the future.
But in doing that, they make a mistake in
the production environment and they change
the size to also include the wrong units.
So rather than asking for a few
million bytes, they're asking for
a few trillion gigabytes, right?
But you say, don't worry,
we have a CI pipeline.
So they test their change locally.
They push the pull request out.
All of the test environments
will pass because all of the test
environments use a different size.
Production is the only one
that has all of the data.
Everything's green.
So an engineer on the project
approves the pull request.
They don't fully look at the code.
They look at the green check marks.
Off you go.
Through the pipeline it goes,
it gets deployed to production.
In the best case, this fails our
production pipeline and everything stops.
No more developer changes can
make its way through our pipeline.
Someone has to go debug the issue.
Oh, shit.
revert the change, start
other changes flowing forward.
In the worst case, pods actually
go down and capacity issues happen.
But we tested everything.
We used automated CI.
what's the cause?
what went wrong?
I think that's a really
interesting thought.
Lots of things went wrong, right?
I think one of the most
fundamental was that we had
Two different changes together.
Why did we have two
different changes together?
Because it's much easier for developers
to put two different changes together
so that the friction of testing and
deploy tools is only paid for once.
they didn't fully understand the schema.
When does it need, A
unit, when does it not?
How many does the unit say?
When is it applied?
Those things.
Our system didn't test for environments.
It tested for
production like environments,
but not exactly production.
Other signals that didn't have anything
to do with the changing size or production
were trusted much more than going and
looking at the code, because the green
check marks said everything was good.
The people who did the code review did
their best, but they're not experts in
YAML or platforms or what will happen
if this is wrong, nor should they be.
And then after everything went wrong,
we didn't have an understanding
of What changed to roll back?
What change caused problems?
What problems were part of this
change and what change was good
for other parts of the code?
Our system didn't understand.
With all of this going wrong, it feels
really easy to go write a bunch of
tests that say this won't happen again.
But I would say there's
something better we can do.
There were two changes that they wanted
to make that were hard and scary.
Can we make that better?
Can we make that something
that's not hard and scary?
yes, we can.
We can make a tool for that.
Can we make a tool to
add users to databases?
Sure.
I can make a UI that loads the YAML.
knows the schema, will validate the
input, will ensure that we test the
size changes in the correct environment.
This will never happen again for
a size change or for a adding a
user change because we've written
a tool that's automated that
will never let this happen again.
We can repeat that over and over again
to build ourselves a set of tools.
Because we know the
inputs that are required.
We know the changes that are scary
and we've constrained them in ways
that they're not nearly as scary.
I think this is a really
powerful way of taking
the incidents that we find
and building new guardrails.
you can't go crazy with it.
You can't build guardrails and never
let any developer make some change.
So we have to have some mental model.
How do we think about when
we need a tool that will add
automation and add some structure?
And when do we let there be free flow
of developers moving things around?
For me, I have a mental
model of rock climbers.
you're a rock climber and you
want to go test yourself, test
your grip strength, can I do this?
You go bouldering.
You go to your local bouldering gym
and you climb one, two,
three meters into the air.
If you fall, there's nothing to catch you.
But you're following a small
distance on the padded floor.
You have a small chance
of any, anything bad.
That works great.
No, no need for safety nets,
nothing to slow you down.
No harnesses to keep you from
moving the way you want to.
you start climbing the mountain,
you start going into production.
You don't want to make
those changes as freely.
You don't want to jump around.
Do you want to have some safety
harnesses that it means everything's
a little more controlled.
The thing that's scary is when
you do that in production.
Don't do that in production.
if we take all of these things that
have gone wrong, these ways that we
can see developers either needing help,
needing places where they can go faster,
places where we can make a tool to
make things better or easier for them,
We can all learn together, right?
We can take the patterns that show up.
We can take the things that are common
and say, Hey, those are industry
wide, those are humanity wide.
How can we learn from those?
and for me, those are the
really interesting part.
and so I just have kind
of four, four quick ones,
They don't work for everybody, but
hopefully they'll work for you.
the first is don't use modals
where you care about accuracy.
Don't use pop ups where
you care about accuracy.
Don't use them where you want
the user to think in depth.
When you see a pop up, your initial
reaction is to try and make it go away.
I want it to be done.
So if we're designing platforms and we
say, here's a pop up that says, are you
sure you want to delete this database?
We're trying to make sure
that this is a safe thing.
a user's reaction is going to be,
please make this pop up go away.
So instead, if you want to encourage
safe UI, Don't use a modal for that.
Use a full page.
Ask them to read something.
Ask them to scroll.
Works very well.
One of the other big things
is moving validation early
and earlier into the cycle.
Makes it so that validation
is skipped less often.
Skipping or ignoring errors is one of the
biggest causes of issues of tech debt.
And so if you want people to react and
react well to feedback, putting that
feedback earlier and earlier into the
development cycle works really well.
So rather than after commit hook,
tell them that field was wrong.
added in a linter that's
running at code change time.
The earlier you can get it into the
validation, the more you can put it into
a UI that shows them that, the better.
While you're building platforms or
while you're operating platforms,
things are going to change.
Things are going to, react to
new inputs, to new changes.
Being able to go back and say who
changed what, when, is super critical.
Showing people
that users X, Y, and Z
changed these three things,
just combined together makes it for an
amazing experience debugging, but also
helps new developers while they're using
your platform, see what's happened before.
Showing kind of the inner workings
of a platform helps so that the
users never have to break into that
layer of abstraction because they
understand just enough to know that
the abstraction is working well.
So those are some of the patterns that
I've seen that I really think work well.
I'd love to hear what UI patterns
you've seen, what you've seen that
makes production better, what you've
seen that makes, development faster.
and if any of these kind of solutions or
patterns sound good to you, We're building
Batteries Included, a fair source, all
inclusive infrastructure platform, that,
like I said, hopefully is releasing soon.
you can sign up to get early access right
now on the website, or you can email me to
get a personal demo and get early access.
thank you very much for coming to the
talk and for coming for the conference.
I hope you've had a good day.
Bye bye.