Hello, I'm Robert Kelly, VP of
technology enablement at Liatrio.
Liatrio is an enterprise technology
modernization consultancy.
A lot of what we do, or what our team
gets to do is, what we traditionally
call DevOps app modernization, but.
I really like, to think, it's how we
describe platform engineering today.
I'm really excited to be
here with comp 42 today.
this is the first time I've given
this talk, so I'm absolutely
going to be looking for feedback
from you and, from others.
I'm looking forward to starting
the conversation today about
all things platform, platform
engineering and the challenges we're
seeing within large, companies.
Enterprise technology organizations.
like I said, I'll be starting the
discussion here, about why platforms need
to be small, no matter how large they are,
try to keep it a little bit light hearted.
And, I think, going for
around 15 minutes here.
So let's get going.
so
what is a platform?
I wanted to give my perspective
here, maybe set the stage, make sure
we're on the same page here, but
the platform definition, I'm not
trying to redefine anything here.
I'll use some of the definitions
that are out in the wild today.
platform has become overloaded.
If we say platform, it may mean one
thing to you, may mean something
to me, something to someone else.
But, we've been building platforms
for years, and really lately, over
the past few years, we've been trying
to give it a lot more, deliberate
attention, especially at the enterprise.
CNCF platform, white paper says.
A platform for cloud native computing is
an integrated collection of capabilities
defined and presented according to
the needs of the platform users.
that CNCF platform white
paper, check it out.
It's awesome.
A lot of great folks put a
lot of awesome time into that.
so check it out.
That, paper also says that, it quotes
the Martin Fowler's definition of
a platform, which I really like.
A digital platform is a foundation of
self service APIs, tools, services,
knowledge, and support, which are
arranged as a compelling internal product.
I think we're looking at
those as the foundational
platform definitions for today.
And we're going to use that
as the, a starting point.
I want to take a little
bit of a deeper dive there.
I want to say.
Really, platforms provide abstractions.
They are providing, abstractions in a way
that they're abstracting away complexity
of the underlying systems, processes,
allowing its users to interact with a
simplified, more accessible interface.
really, platforms are giving us, should
be, giving us an easier way to do things.
the platform is an easy button, right?
maybe not.
Is it really?
So are platforms always
a simpler solution?
Do they always give us
something easier to work with?
If I called, the customers of your
platform and asked, is platform easy?
What would they say?
So the point here is if a platform is
making something more difficult, then
it would be otherwise if the platform
or the team who built the platform were
not in the way, then we're not helping.
Okay, Why is this?
Why is this?
platforms are disruptive technologies,
and this is where I want to spend a
little bit of time digging in a little
bit, understanding why platforms
are disruptive, why I think the
disruptive anyway, and what that means.
So because platforms are providing
automation, golden paths, templates,
and other capabilities, the intent
is to offer the organization a
better way of building and shipping
software and digital services.
Then if they didn't exist.
So the idea here is get the platform
out there and provide more value.
Okay, but why, why is disruptive
technology so important?
Why is the idea here?
something I want to look at.
here's a quote for, from Clayton
Christensen's book, the innovators
dilemma, products based on
disruptive technologies are typically
cheaper, simpler, smaller, and
frequently more convenient to use.
Okay.
that might not be the way you
describe your platform today, but
let's dig in here a little bit.
So what I think is important is that
we've been building these platforms
for years, but maybe we haven't
realized that we're innovating or
building disruptive technologies.
So the challenge is much of the platform
technology that's being augmented
or abstracted is actually toil,
or difficult enterprise processes.
The disruptive tech isn't.
It's replacing AWS specifically, but it
is disrupting the enterprise processes
that would otherwise be much more painful
for the team's building technology.
So that's where most of the value is.
Most of the value of the platform
is abstracting away those painful
enterprise toil or other processes
that are just really making it
more difficult to deliver software.
So platforms have become disruptive.
But I think they've become
disruptive in the wrong way.
Let's talk about that for a moment.
So why isn't the platform easy?
Why isn't the disruptive technology
providing a compelling product
for its customers or the platform
engineers building the platform?
So today, most enterprise platforms
have evolved over time to fit
the current operating structure
of a larger organization.
So this is Conway's Law.
If you're not familiar with Conway's
Law suggests that the way a company
or team is structured will heavily
influence the architecture or the
products or systems it creates.
for instance, if an org is divided
into three teams that each handle a
different part of the project, that
final product is likely going to consist
of three different modules that reflect
the boundaries between those teams.
So let's say over time, DevOps team
has grown, or maybe it hasn't grown
to support the enterprise and the
platform has likely grown as well,
trying to keep up, the DevOps team
might potentially, or maybe even the
DevOps org likely owns the tooling and
processes to build and deploy enterprise
applications and infrastructure.
There are potentially hundreds of tools
spread out across dozens of automation
paths here to build out this platform.
And when you hear about cognitive
load, platforms have become
synonymous with the term tool sprawl.
And we're really asking platform
teams to become experts in integrating
all of the latest tools rather than
collaboratively solving business problems.
And that's really the goal.
And so this path today isn't sustainable.
So to summarize this a bit.
The platform has had a snowball effect
and in many cases become a monolith,
just like other enterprise applications.
let's take a look at this.
let's break it down.
Really.
if we're looking at the platform
as a monolith, it really
doesn't have to be a monolith.
And this is a bit of an
opinionated view that I have here.
and I'd like to discuss it further.
feel free to reach out.
We can talk anytime.
When we look at a platform
here at a higher level.
Where you understand that really it's
a sum of several platform capabilities.
We've got internal developer
portals, CI CD pipelines, security
tools, observability, cloud
infrastructure, FinOps governance.
Now AI ML is growing like crazy.
These capabilities vary in complexity
in their own areas, really.
Today, some, are tools that are purchased,
some are built and supported internally.
we're just dealing with a lot here, right?
So the focus of the platform
is really expanding to provide
delivery teams what they need to
get their products to production.
But looking at it as one
platform is really where we
find some of the challenges now.
So looking at it, one platform,
here as is really just a lot.
So it's really just too much.
And it's too much for one,
certainly for one team to manage.
And if we've got a DevOps team
that's grown over time and, and
really to support hundreds of
tools, it's just unsustainable.
So rather than looking at the
platform as one big thing for one
team or, really even for, Two teams,
we should make a conscious decision
to break it up and provide a better
experience to our enterprise customers.
So this is where I say
platforms must be small.
And let me take a deeper dive here.
we can't look at all of the capabilities
in this platform as again, a single
platform, it's a platform of platforms.
And this is where I said,
platform is overloaded.
How many times have I said platform?
It's too many, right?
but again, this platform of platform could
be supported by several platform teams.
Each of those platforms provide important
capabilities to its customers, and even
though they may need to be on their
own product roadmap, how we ask our
teams or customers to interact with
them shouldn't be distinctly different.
And the platform just
shouldn't feel large.
So for listening.
It's all about accessibility
when it comes to it.
So let's look at that a little bit here.
this could be us starting small and
we may need to start really small,
just like any monolithic, application
we might want to break down.
We need to treat the
platform the same way.
A good starting point here is
the thinnest viable platform.
And this is defined here in the
book, Team Topology's awesome book.
And, Team Topology states, a TVP is
a careful balance between keeping a
platform small and ensuring that the
platform is helping to accelerate
and simplify software delivery
for teams building the platform.
and to summarize that, we can explain
the platform or TVP as the smallest
set of APIs, documentation, or tools
needed to accelerate teams delivery.
And in some cases, version 1.
0 of a platform is just a wiki page.
So keeping things very
small is super important.
this image on the left is not a
picture of a platform, but it's a
picture of a team interaction model.
So this highlights how a platform team
is providing a capability of their
product as a service for other teams.
As the platform might grow, and more
features are added, that doesn't mean
that the team using the platform need
to change the way that they're working
to adopt these new capabilities.
So self service tools like internal
developer platforms and APIs give
us a more common platform interface.
Things feel the same.
It's a standard way to adopt new features.
So we get back to having that
easy button for customers.
and at that point, there is minimal
lift to adopt those new capabilities.
So the platform feels small, regardless
of how much work goes into the platform
tooling or automation behind the scenes.
To boil it down here, this means
breaking up the monolithic platform.
It comes down to, we need a
strategy and a plan to break it up.
there's going to be some work done
in value stream mapping, domain
driven design, to understand what
the platform's boundaries are and
how many platforms do we really have.
And even though we haven't treated
the platform as a product before, we
need to make the effort and investment
to supply, to support it properly.
As platform teams.
If we're working with the
platform, we need to redefine
what it means to own the platform.
Probably means raising the bar on platform
standards, treating everything as code,
really leaning in on APIs and self
service, and maybe relearning how we're
building applications in our platforms.
This means getting real user feedback,
understanding who our customers are,
and really measuring the use of the
platform to find out what metrics are
really important there, And things like
opening up, inner sourcing and pull
requests so that the internal community
can, support the app applications and
platforms along with the teams, and the
platform teams that are traditionally
building them and really just finding
a more modern working model that,
that just works for the organization.
So that's a big change, a lot of lift,
and a lot to look at once, right?
that's it.
Thank you.
Again, easy, right?
No, that it's all I've got today,
but I really just wanted to start a
conversation and start small and get the
discussion started, get some feedback.
hope you got a lot from
this today and, hope we can,
connect, and have a discussion.
So again, connect with me, Robert Kelly,
DFW on LinkedIn or email robertatleatriot.
com.
And thanks again.