Hey, good morning everyone.
Welcome to Platform
Engineering Conference.
My name is,
I have over 14 years of experience as a
platform architect in the IT industry.
I'm here to give a presentation on the
building production ready rag systems,
platform engineer strategies for
enterprise knowledge infrastructure.
So before going to that, I
would like to know, I would
like to discuss about the rag.
what is rag?
RAG is stands rag in AI stands for
the re travel argument generation.
A technique where a generative model,
such as a large language model, first
drives relevant information from external
sources before generating responses.
Improving factual accuracy and relevance.
The code concept behind the RAG
is it combines the traditional
information retrieval systems.
It'll search the databases with
the generat, with the generated
capabilities of lms instead of relying
ly on static PRETRAINED data sets.
RAG allows in AI to dynamically.
Access up to date information
are domain specific content and
incorporated into its output.
How is rags going to work?
So a user submit a prompter query
the system such as our retro
relevant information snips from
the designated large base or data
sets, which might include internal
documents, PDFs, emails, our web data.
These retrial snip nets are passed as
context alongside the prompt to the LLM.
The LLM generates its response,
grounded in both its modern knowledge
and the most relevant retried facts.
So as enterprise scales, their
use of LLMs, they encounter two
critical challenges, hallucinations.
The first one, which is.
Rate as high as 27% and
outdated training data.
So the re travel argument generation
has emerged as a powerful architectural
solution, bridging the gap between
static model origin and realtime
information by coupling generated AI
with enterprise scale large repositories.
Rack Systems enable reliable, accurate,
and context responses at scale.
The Enterprise Rack Challenge
over deploying production ready
rack systems in enterprise
environment is far from trivial.
Because platform engineers must
design architectures that can handle
terabytes up to 10 or plus repositories.
You subsecond query response times and
maintain 95% uptime while supporting
10,000 plus concurrent users.
This article explores the platform
engineering strategies needed to
operationalize rag pipelines at
scale, focusing on infrastructure.
Performance, reliability,
security, and cost optimization.
when we come to the infrastructure
architecture, scaling a rag for
the enterprise is a big challenge.
The backbone of any rag system is
its vector database, which stores
embedding self enterprise knowledge
for the travel to achieve enterprise
scale, reliability and throughput.
Platform engineer must design.
Based on these four concepts, first
distributor, vector databases, and
next is load balancing strategies.
Part of one is hybrid storage models,
and fourth is the elastic scaling.
These are the four pillars
when we are building a rack
system for the enterprises.
When we come to the distributed vector
databases, shedding embeddings across
nodes, ensure horizontal scalability
systems like Vate, pine, cone, and Fan
provide different tradeoffs between
scalability, query latency, and cost.
So these are the various vector data
databases, which we can use when we
are building a rag for the enterprise.
Now, when it comes to the load balancing,
is very important to handle the
upscale or vertical scale, requests.
So the balances must intelligently
route queries across database
clusters, pipelines, and LLM
instances to minimize bottlenecks.
So load balances must play an important
role to retrieve your results.
Then the second is storage.
Third one is, sorry.
Third one is hybrid storage.
So when the storage comes into picture,
we were combining the SSDs based
hard storage for frequently accessed
embeddings with coal data and is
both performance and cost efficiency.
And the last one is Elastic scaling.
Kubernetes deployments allow rack
components, vector stores and
traverse, rankers and LMS to scale
independently based on demand.
Now the second part is performance
optimization, so we need to get, we need
to optimize our query set so that we will
get the results in a subsequent second.
So the query latency, should
we need to get it below two
seconds to retry your results.
So the near, because we, in
enterprise, we used to get the real
time responses from rack systems.
So reducing query times from eight to
12 seconds to under second subsecond
under two seconds, it requires a
multi-layer optimization strategy.
So to our, to give these sub two second
response time for any rank systems, we
have to focus on these four pillars.
One is catching strategies, so your
que much must be catched in and, catch
with the hash ash, hash value and query
level, catching for repeated requests and
embedding level catching for frequently,
documents significantly reduced.
Redundant competition.
And the next one is hierarchical re
travel using a two-step travel process
filtering, followed by fine range ranking,
minimize unnecessary vector comparisons.
The third one is resource allocation.
This which is a. Which is also a
place, a vital role, GPV accelerated
with travel and dynamic model routing.
For example, small L LMS for
lightweight queries, large LMS for
complex queries, balance, speed with
cost, and the hybrid cloud deployment.
So the deployment we can choose
is a hybrid cloud, so locating the
travel and interference pipelines
closer to data sources via edge
deployments or regional clusters.
Reduces the latency.
And when we go to the next slide, reliable
engineering, which is 99% availability,
which is a must for the rag systems.
The resell features of resilient
two failures across multiple
layers, databases, inference,
pipelines, and orchestration.
The key practices include monitoring and
observability fault tolerance, Charles
engineering, ci, and CD automation.
When it comes to the monitoring and
observability, we need to collect the
metrics across embedding throughput
vector, such latency LLM, inference,
time and system resource utilization.
Tools we should use as ERs,
Grafana, et cetera, and telemetry
is an essential tool too.
For monitoring and observability.
Next, when it comes to the fault
tolerance, so implement the replica of the
clusters so that at any time any automated
failure happens, it'll automatically
go back to the other region or other
failure in point to give you results.
So check pointing of embeds to recover
from outages with minimal downtime.
This is the main, motto
for the fall tolerance.
When it comes to the Charles
Engineering regularly stress test
trial pipelines under simulated
note values, our network partition
to validate reliability exemptions.
So always we need to focus when we
do, deploy the rag models, we can also
check the stress systems test as well.
So all these pipelines should be automated
and deployed through CICD process.
We need to keep your was control
mechanisms for all your rack pipelines.
It comes to next security and
compliance, which is a trustworthy
for the enterprises security.
So given the current days,
we need to secure our data.
Enterprise data because of the sensitivity
and ence issues are non-negotiable.
Production Ready Rack Systems must
integrate zero trust architecture
encryption from end to end, and
must focus on trials and the
data governance Integration too.
Zero trust architectures means in
encrypt least privilege access across
all rack components and ensure no
implicit trust between services.
The encryption to end so encrypt
embeds at rest and in transit.
To safeguard your S two data.
Audit trials must be happens,
and it needs to be compliance
with SOX two and IS 4 27 0 0 1.
The data governance integration,
ensure rack pipelines, respect
existing enterprise data governance
frameworks, including retention
policies and access controls.
Cost management.
So after security and compliance comes
to the cost management for optimizing
your resources at scale, enterprises
often face skying costs as rack systems
scale, achieving up to 60% cost.
DUCTION requires intelligence,
resource optimization, auto scaling,
LLM, inference endpoints under
travel services and sourcers.
Resources match demand without pro
or provisioning, the more tiring
using smaller open social lamps for
routine queries and reserving premium.
API calls for high value
use cases, cut cost.
Brushed ling.
Vendor negotiations, which will also play
a crucial role when we want, to reduce
the cost for the rag systems enterprise.
Managing 10 terabytes or terabyte
pository should leverage scale to
secure volume discounts with vector
database and cloud service vendors.
Workload placement, balancing
between on-premises, GPUs, part cloud
incentives and manage vector services,
minimizes compute and storage expenses.
The real world case studies,
proven patterns at scale.
So over the last few years, more
than 50% Prise implementations
success patterns have emerged.
85% user adoption rates using this
rag model achieved by integrating
seamlessly into existing enterprise
workflows like Slack Bot CRM plugins,
knowledge portals, 200 to 400%.
ROI in 18 months, driven by practic
gains, reduce support costs, and faster
data missing making These implementations
also demonstrate proven architecture
blueprints, modular pipelines that
combine vector databases, orchestrators
and inference layers, allowing gradual
scaling with that wholesale system.
Rewrites when it comes to the external
frameworks for the platform engineers.
We need to succeed the rag model
and the production deployments.
Platform engineers should
adapt section frameworks.
The first one is vector picture design.
Your right picture should involve any
vector database for your vector, such as
this is your first component when you are
designing your rag company rag systems.
In the enterprise level, so this
is, vector search will establish
embedding, update, IES trading
logic and ranking algorithms
aligned with the business needs.
Next, your deployment should be automated.
Use infrastructure as a code like
Terraform or health to standardize
rack deployments across environments.
Your deployment should be
seamless and automated.
Using your Terraform call
performance benchmarking, create
benchmarks, measuring end-to-end
latency with travel accuracy
and throughput under peak load.
So you need to do your performance
testing before deploying your rag models
so that you will be aware of how your
rag is, re your response is coming.
On a huge terabytes of data
request, so operational excellence.
Define SLAs.
What is your availability?
99.9% and less than two.
Second response time.
And minimizing your whatever
rates and latency that align
with the enterprise expectation.
This will comes under
operational excellence.
So the four, as I discussed, these
are the main core architecture
components in any rag model.
First is ingest.
How you'll ingesting your data.
Next is Vector database,
how you are retrieving or
searching your query request.
And now the third one is retrieval
how you want to retrieve your output.
Next is you getting the
ranking of the output.
And finally, LLM in France.
Event and architecture integrates these
components while maintaining separation of
concerns, allowing each element to scale
independently based on demand patterns.
This module approach enables enterprise
to upgrade individual components
without disrupting the entire system
performance benchmarking framework,
rack system performance benchmarking.
So platform English should
focus on these key five metrics.
First is end-to-end query latency
under various load conditions, accuracy
compared to ground truth system
throughput at peak, concurrent user
levels, resource utilization across
compute, memory and storage, cost
per query at different scale points.
These benchmarks provide the
foundation for continuous
automation and capacity planning.
Security implementation checklist.
So when we go into the security of
data, you need to implement this
authentication and authorization.
You need to protect your data,
and you have you, you need to
compile your data with all these.
and is O 27 0 0 1, certified
authentication authorization, implement
WATH 2.4 or OIDC for user authentication.
Enforce role-based access control
for all rag components integrated
with the enterprise solutions.
These are the three best practices we
need to follow when we are deploying
your rag models and enterprise level.
And make sure you those RA
models are securely deployed.
the data protection at rest and
transient must be encrypted.
Using a 2 56 algorithm, implement
TLS 1.34 protocol for all service,
authentication or communications.
Apply data masking for sensitive
information in logs so that you can
use your, role based access control.
Compliance.
Maintain detailed audit logs
for all system interactions.
Implement retention policies
aligned with regulated requirements,
conduct regular security
assessment and penetration testing.
Implementing these security measures,
ensure that rack systems meet and price
compliance requirements while protecting
data through the generation process.
And the last slide when
we come to the conclusion.
The rag represents a paradigm
shift in endocrin knowledge
infrastructure, transforming static
K models into dynamic context.
Our systems for platform engineers
challenge lies not only in implementing
pipelines, but also in scaling how you
are going to scale your rag models.
You have to design your
architecture both to be scaled
in vertically and horizontally.
And implementing best security practices
like we discussed, we need to mu we
need to follow the proper protocols.
And optimizing them for production.
By mastering infrastructure design,
performance optimization, reliable
engineering, security and cost management,
platform engineers can build production
ready rack systems that deliver business
value adaption and generate to and
generate miserable ROI and raise that.
Adapt.
These strategies will not only overcome
the limitations of traditional.
But also unlock a new era of AI
driven knowledge, access, reliable,
scalable, and future proof.
That's all.
Any questions.
Thank you.
Thank you for providing this opportunity.