There was a time, not that long ago,
in fact, as recent as six years,
when hybrid DNS required setting
up a DNS solution in the cloud.
This was a quintessential example
of an AWS customer performing
unappreciated heavy lifting until the
severe Route 53 resolver came around.
Welcome to CONF22 Platform
Engineering Conference and thank
you for attending the session.
I'm Arthur Siddiqui, Senior Principal
Software Engineer at Silicon Valley
Bank, Division of First Citizens Bank.
The agenda will cover the original
problem statement when there
wasn't an adequate offer from AWS.
I will introduce the Route23 resolver
service and explain the key concepts.
It will be followed by a solution for
hybrid DNS for multi account setup.
In addition, I'll elaborate on the key
design considerations as well as native
security tools that are available to us.
I'll wrap it up by talking about
a new capability released this
year called Route23 Profiles.
Until the time Route 53 Resolver was
announced, customers had two paths, choose
a marketplace product or come up with
a custom solution to set up hybrid DNS.
The latter, while likely to
be more economical, relied on
setting up DNS servers on EC2s.
The responsibility of setting up
resiliency also fell on the customer.
All these challenges we have
created when ROC 53 Resolver
was announced six years ago.
Before I delve into this topic,
let me do a quick sidebar.
When a BPC is provisioned, the
DOT2 IP is reserved to resolve DS
queries originating from the BPC.
For example, if a VPC has a CIDR of 10.
0.
0 23, the IP 10.
2 is what provides the data's resolution.
This is why, historically, it used to
be called a 2 or a plus 2 resolver.
This has all along been
a default feature of VPC.
It should be noted that if a VPC
has multiple siders, it is the
primary sider where the plus two IP
is what's used for DNS resolution.
Circling back to Route V3 Resolver,
it was announced in November 2018.
This offering was specifically
targeted to simplify DNS for
the hybrid cloud use case.
Any enterprise that ventures into
cloud will almost always have
a hybrid network that is having
both on prem and cloud presence.
This means there is a requirement for on
prem network to resolve workloads in AWS.
Similarly, resources in AWS may
have a requirement to resolve
private DNS records on prem.
This requirement is solved by the
introduction of the Resolver Endpoints.
There are two types of endpoints,
inbound and outbound, and this
terminology is from AWS standpoint.
Inbound Resolver Endpoint is for queries
coming to AWS from on prem network.
It is used to resolve BBC
resources for on prem.
It is important to note that on prem
DNS Must issue recursive instead
of I trade up queries for the
Route three resolvers in market.
Eight points.
On the other hand, VAR Resolver
eight points of queries going
from AWS to Auburn network.
It is used to resolve
private DS records on prem.
These result endpoint manifests at
Elastic Network Interface or ENI.
Therefore, the best practice.
It should provision these endpoints
in every AZ that the VPC spans to.
While I expect the audience
will use infrastructure as code,
the console screenshot is to
illustrate some of the key points.
As Route 53 Resolver is a regional
service and a VPC resource, it
should land in a shared service
account such as Core Network.
As this is an ENI, it
requires a security group.
For the Inbound Resolver Endpoint,
Security Inbound Rules should be open
for 423 for both TCP and UDP protocol.
On the flip side, for Outbound
Resolver Endpoint, Security
Outbound Rules should be open for
423 for both TCP and UDP protocol.
This example shows a VPC
spanning two available resolvers.
The default behavior when provisionally
informed for AWS to grab an IP from
the subject of VPC or alternative.
Alternatively, one can
specify IP from the subnet.
Needless to say, these ENI
get a allocated private ips
out all points are
complemented with a 40 rule.
This 40 rule applies to BBT
traffic destined for on-prem.
This is why on prem NIDA servers need
to be configured under this rule.
In this case, the on prem
NIDA server is listed as 10.
50.
Circling back to the comment how
ENIs are created when Resolver
informs the provision, here
the diagram shows four ENIs.
This is a VPC finding two available zones,
and hence we have a pair of inbound and
outbound And Alva enforce respectively.
And then this shows how this heed
inbound rule should look like For the
inbound endpoint, only traffic on 4 53
promote TCP and UDP protocol is allowed.
This rule assumes that on-prem network is
using a Class A CI of 10.000 slash eight.
There are two other key points that talked
about before we can look at the design.
The first one is, once the resolver
endpoints have been provisioned
in a shared service account, the
question arises, how would it be
shared across the spoke accounts?
Enter Resource Access Manager, or RAM.
This is an AWS service that has a
goal of sharing resources across
accounts within the AWS organization.
Route 23 resolver is one of
many types supported by RAM.
Some of the other examples are
system manager, parameters,
RDS cluster, backup loss, etc.
The second key point is to
understand the concept of a BPC
association to private hostage zones.
In this case, private hostage zones
across all spoke accounts will
need to be associated with a BPC
and shared service account where
the endpoints were provisioned.
It will allow shared service
accounts to resolve private DNS
records across all spoke accounts.
This design encapsulates
the top up to this point.
In the top, it depicts a shared service
account where resolver endpoints have been
provisioned and have UPC spanning two AZs.
In the first use case indicated by blue
arrows, the request originates on prem.
An on prem user is looking up a resource
in one of the two spoke accounts.
On prem DNS server will forward a
request to the resolver's inbox endpoint.
Since the private host zone of spoke
accounts are associated with the VPC
network account, resolution of private
records such as EC2 is possible.
In the second use case indicated
by orange arrows, Request is
originating in a Spoke account.
The EC2 resource is looking
up an on prem system.
There is a forwarding rule for
corporate domain, let's say star.
com42.
io, associated with the
resolver's outbound rule.
In addition, this forwarding
rule is shared with Spoke VPCs
via Resource Access Manager.
The outbound endpoint.
are also configured with the
IP of on prem DNS server.
Early in the deck, IP of on prem
DNS server was set up as 10.
50.
It is important to call out that while
what we have talked so far achieved
DNS resolution in the hybrid setup,
isolation of VPCs still applies.
How packet flows between VPCs is
still needs a networking construct.
That construct is Transit Gateway.
Similarly, networking path between on
prem and edge VPC of a network account
will either via VPN or direct connect.
When it comes to DNS setup, there
are two security tools that should
be a part of your ecosystem.
GuardDuty is the first one.
A server is not a big fan of.
It, to me, represents the pinnacle of how
security products should be delivered.
Single click of a button to enable it,
and it passes through three sets of logs,
including DNS, to identify threats such
as data exfiltration through DNS queries.
Over the years, this service
has had enhancements and extends
its reach into specific services
such as S3, EKS, and RDS.
Security Duel is a Rocket
3 resolver DNS Firewall.
This is a relatively new service
and was announced in early 2021.
It provides the capability to
regulate outbound DNS traffic
originating in the VPCs.
It supports both AWS Managed Domain
Lists as well as the custom one.
Managed Lists is a good way when looking
to reduce a service's DNS traffic.
As with any typical firewall, there
are three action types that can be
configured, allow, block, and alert.
This action can be applicable to
a specific DNS record type or a
broader firewall rule that will
apply to all DNS record types.
The last subtopic I would like to talk
about is the announcement from last April.
AWS announced a new capability
called Route 33 Profiles.
The value proposition is that a profile
allows bundling up private hosting
zone associations, forwarding roles,
and even DNS firewall rule groups.
This profile can then be shared
via Resource Access Manager across
accounts in AWS organization.
While I haven't had a chance to
play with this capability, it
will certainly make the hybrid
design both simpler and cleaner.
There is no escaping DNS and
everyone just expects it to work.
Therefore, to be, to implement a
solution in a resilient manner using
AWS managed services is an excellent
position to take as a platform engineer.