This is Sunil.
Little introduction about me.
I'm a seasoned database administrator,
worked on different technologies
across different multinationals
at different geographies.
Today I'm going to talk about machine
learning power database resilience
predictive analytics for 99.98.
Oracle Cloud availability.
So basically the cost of downtime for any
database is permitted nine over $9,000.
And financially the impact
is huge, the whole year.
So by doing machine learning based
anatomy detection, you can early
detect the issues and take a preventive
action and improve the uptime overall.
Basically deep learning
performance metrics.
It helps you, it helps the model.
Recognize the pattern first, and
then in five second intervals,
it keeps judging what is the
analysis on the pattern going on.
And then what are the invisible
sectors available to leverage
the neural networks in the whole.
Machine system.
Then optimizing the Oracle cluster
and reinforcement learning.
That's how the entire cycle works.
Monitor, learn, optimize, validate,
keep doing the same during
networks for data guard tuning.
This is again, for the high availability
as well as scalability by using
synchronized duplication, minimal
performance impact and fast the company.
Like within seconds.
So ROI is return on investment
of machine learning resilience.
It's 287% ROI in eight months payback
time with 99.98% availability.
So that's huge in my understanding.
Again, the predictive auto scaling
benefits, because like we said, the
machine learning, there's a model
to learn and optimize accordingly.
The overall goal is to reduce the cost by
not compromising on the availability of
the performance of the entire solution.
There are case studies where 99.98
availability is achieved in financial
services, healthcare, retail, and
basically all the line of businesses
across, the different modules, the
scalable AI framework, is it like it
can't be scaled to any level by horizontal
vertical using cross architecture
compatibility, automated and all
detection add engineer productivity
overall by using machine learning.
So transforming database resilience.
It's discover, implement, optimize,
and achieve the goal, which is.
Is close to a hundred percent
availability, but we, there are a
few percentage or less than a percent
non unforeseen issues that can occur.
Thanks a lot for your time and I hope
you could have some idea about the
topic we wanted to discuss today.
Thank you again.