Hello, everyone.
I am Gaurav Mittal.
I am currently working with Thermo Fisher
Scientific as a data science manager.
Today, I'm going to present a
talk on email attachment security.
I'll see you next time.
Thank you for joining my call.
I would like to highlight
a business scenario today.
like most of the organizations,
they are tend to send emails to
their customers, having attachments.
Now consider a scenario like where,
it's an insurance organization.
They are sending you a
renter insurance document.
Or when it comes to medical,
industry, they are sending you
medical receipts or some, some of
your PII data as an attachment.
Even today's world, some countries,
they are sending e visa in your
email as an attachment, which
contains your passport information.
All this information,
they are very sensitive.
It's your PII data, which, is prone
to, phishing email fraud attack.
And, how, what kind of risk,
we have so few of the risk,
as I have highlighted here.
Like the most common, risk is
like man in the middle attacks.
What happens, the email server,
what is sending the email,
that is not very secure.
And, in between there
can be, it can be hacked.
And your information, which
is very sensitive, it can
be, hacked by the hackers.
Or, maybe there is not inadequate,
there is not, encryption.
proper encryption being utilized.
there are no antivirus
softwares installed.
the emails when they are in transaction,
it may be possible the authors,
they can get unauthorized access.
To the transmission they can go through
The attachments and your information is
prompt fraud now What is the solution
for it how we can achieve it so we can
overcome the frauds by implementing data
security in data security world There
are a few common terms like authorization
Authentication is like, like only
the users which is having appropriate
access You They can log in and they can
view, those, particular information.
Authorization is like you
are curbing the role access.
So like only if you have some
specific role, you can, avail
this much of information.
It depends on your role, like you
can view the information content and
the most commonly used is encryption.
So in encryption, we, what we do,
either we use the data masking or we,
like encrypt the data using, key in
AWS, there's a service like AWS KMS.
So what happens like the plaintext it
is being encrypted using a key and the
customer at the receiving side is being
provided a decrypt key to so that only
the like reliable customer whom we want
to send the information is having the
key to decrypt and view the contents.
So that's how we can secure it.
Now the question is, okay, we
have learned about the frauds.
We have learned about data security, but
how we can secure the email attachments.
So in the email attachments, like the most
common way is okay, you educate the users,
you show the awareness, the organizations,
they are installing antivirus softwares.
But from our end, like when we are sending
the emails to our customers, what we can
do, we can use, the encryption at our
end, which the most common technology is
like data masking or password protection.
In that case, like when the users,
they are receiving the emails,
they have to, type a password, then
only they can view the content.
Otherwise, even if the emails they
are being forwarded to a wrong
email, wrong person, he like that
fraud guy cannot open the email.
So your sensitive
information is still secure.
The other way what we
can do is access control.
So in the access control, we can
actually control the time period
for which this information, the
attachment, what we are sending is
accessible beyond that time period.
Actually, this attachment just
shows, okay, link is, does not exist.
The validity is over coming
to the implementation side.
Okay.
How we can actually implement it.
The very simple solution, what I want to
depict today is using PyMiniGip library.
It's an open source library
provided by, Python and the
installation is also quite simple.
Now, what happens PyMiniGip library,
what it does, you have a file.
When you use PyMiniGip library,
it actually creates a folder which
is a zipped folder and that zipped
folder is when you try to unzip
it, it will ask you a password.
Now only the reliable person who
is having the password can open it.
So we are going to implement first layer
of security using PyMiniGip library.
So there is a method like compress, there
are three arguments as I have shown below.
Like you need to provide your source
file destination then what is the
destination file where you want to?
Keep this zip file folder.
What is the password you want to provide?
So Password is something like you can
keep Information which only dead person
know like his date of birth or like
last four digits of his cell number or
something like that if you are going to
apply this then this information only
the person know and they can They can
easily open the file Secondly, they are
not going to reach back to you again
and again asking, Hey, can you reset
my password or something like that?
It's an easy way to implement it.
And the last argument is a level to what
level you want to compress the file.
So there is a zero to
10, 10 being the highest.
Okay.
we have learned about PyMiniJib library.
This library can help in jibbing the,
like in, creating a password for it.
But if we are talking about AWS
infrastructure, how we can do it.
So in AWS Lambda, where you
generally write the code, there
is a way you can create a layer
for this particular library.
The installation is quite simple.
this library you can install using pip
command, it's a single line command.
And when you install it in your local, You
can attach it as a layer as I have shown
in on the right hand side bottom part.
So once you, in your Lambda, if you have
to click on, like uploading a layer, which
is, which will be a zip file archive.
And when you upload it, you will
be able to use the Pyminijip
library in your source code.
So we have talked about encryption, which
is through Pyminijip library and in AWS
Lambda function, we will create a layer.
But how to make sure about access control.
in S3 we have a concept S3 PD signed, URL.
This pre-signed URL is basically,
like if there are S3 objects, we
want to provide access to some third
person without changing the IM policy
or providing any AWS credentials.
There is a bypass route.
You just provide that person a
temporary access by generating
a pre signed URL and you.
And on this URL you can actually control.
The validity for how long you are that
person can access this particular object.
to control the access, there
are actually, three ways.
like for example, if you are
generating the signed URL through
IAM instance profile, the URL
will be valid for only six hours.
If you are using AWS SDA service,
which is security token service.
The URL can be valid till 36 hours
and the last the longest is like
through IAM user The URL will
be valid for seven working days.
Like we can achieve several
benefits out of it as I mentioned
here Like it's completely secure.
We are not sharing any AWS credentials.
It's just a single URL And you decide
whom you want to grant the access.
Okay, you are sending it in your email.
And the third user, they can, through
this URL, you are granting the access.
Okay, you can upload or
you can download the file.
This is how, pre signed
URL email looks like.
If you look this particular email,
there is actually no attachment.
Okay.
And secondly, when, when you
click on this particular, email
link, it'll ask you a password.
So that password only the person
whom you, we are sending the
email, only that person knows.
And the last part is we are also
actually controlling the access till
how long this URL should be valid based
on the way you are creating it, it can,
it, the URL ranges from six hours to.
Like seven working days
though.
So we have, protected the file using
PI mini JIP, and we have, performed
access control also to send the
service to send the, like a file
now this password protected file,
we can use AWS SCS service, which is
send email service and, send email
service, it has some, like features.
So you need to create a verified
identity whom you are going to send
email and to whom you want to send.
Actually, those can be verified
on unverified identities.
So all the email addresses, then they
need not to be verified, but there is
one constraint in SES service, which
is like only 40 emails per second.
They can be sent.
I would like to show you the
final code in the final code.
If you look, the first line I am using
the PyMiniGip library, which is just going
to compress a CSV file and I am providing
password, compressed level, everything.
Once this file is being compressed
using PyMiniGip, I am going to
generate a signed URL for it.
And I am, using it through Im users.
So I was having the option to
put it for seven working days,
which is what I've used here.
And SES service, as I mentioned, it
has a limit of 40, emails per second.
So I, I thought okay, why not
to, put one, second delay, in
between each and every email.
But it purely depends on your
implementation, how you want to do it.
But time.
sleep we can use, in between sending the
emails to make sure we are not, leaching
the throttling limit of, SCS service.
The final architecture
will look like this here.
it's completely built in AWS.
There is a CSV file.
Okay.
Using PyMiniJib library, you
have, encrypted it, a password.
Okay.
like a zip folder is there when you
click on it, it will ask you a password.
there is a pre signed URL.
This pre signed URL is valid
for a certain time limit.
And through SCS service, I am
going to send it to verified
or unverified accounts.
Now, the whole advantage of it is
even, even today, if this, emails.
They are being sent to wrong person.
They won't be knowing like,
what is the password for it?
Only the reliable person, they know it.
And secondly, we are also
putting a time limit.
Okay.
That for this particular time,
only this emails, they are valid.
And the third, the most, important feature
here is if I go back, see, if you look
in the emails, there is no attachment.
Okay.
So from the Lambda function,
when we have to send emails, The
attachments, they take some time to
attach, but here you are just, it's
just a URL, what we are sending.
So that transfer time has,
significantly reduced and
Lambda is pay as you go service.
So we are actually saving some amount
through our implementation also.
So no attachments are there.
this is all about me and,
like I have written an article
also on this particular topic.
feel free to go through it.
And, this is my Twitter, gautamM85
in case of any questions, anything,
please feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you.