Good morning, good afternoon, everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
I am excited to discuss how AI
and robotics are changing the
way we disassemble products,
which is a crucial step in making
our economy more sustainable.
By improving how we take products apart,
we can recover valuable materials, reduce
waste, and better protect our environment.
Let's start by understanding the
complexity of modern products.
Today's devices, such as smartphones,
laptops, and even cars, are
made from a mix of materials.
These include plastics, metals,
and rare elements, all of which
are tightly packed together.
For example, a single smartphone
contains over 60 different elements.
including precious metals like gold and
silver, as well as rare earth enamel.
These are critical for its electronics.
Because these materials are so
tightly integrated, it's hard to
separate them once the product
reaches the end of its life.
The complexity often leads to valuable
components being discarded, which not
only causes economy losses, but also
harms the environment by increasing waste.
The challenge we face is how to
effectively assemble these products
to recover the materials inside.
This is where AI and robotics come in.
By making the assembly process more
efficient, we can recover more materials
and reduce the impact on the environment.
The approach helps keep valuable
materials in use and minimize
the need of new raw material,
which often require environmental
damaging extraction processes.
Thank you.
Now let's talk about importance
of efficient assembly.
Research has shown that up to 80 percent
of a product's environment impact is
determined at the stage of design.
This means that how we design
products plays a huge role in
their overall sustainability.
But even with the best design, we will
still need efficient assembly processes to
reclaim and recycle materials effectively.
Consider the example of electronic device.
batteries.
These batteries are made up of
various valuable materials, including
lithium, cobalt, and nickel.
If we can efficiently disassemble
these batteries, we can recover
these materials and reuse them in
new batteries or other products.
These, this reduces the need for
mining, which is often associated with
significant environmental damage, such as
habitat destruction and water pollution.
To achieve this advanced
AI robotics are essential.
AI can analyze the structure and material
composition of a material in real
time, figuring out the best way to take
it apart from damaging the material.
Robotics guided by this AI can
then execute the disassembly with
precision, ensuring that each
component is carefully removed.
For instance, robots can be equipped
with sensors that detect the type
of material they are handling,
allowing them to adjust their grip or
cutting techniques to avoid damage.
damaging the materials.
This combination of AI and robotics
makes it possible to recover
more material with less waste.
which is critical for moving toward
a circular economy where products and
material are reused as much as possible.
Now, let's talk about AI
and robotics in disassembly.
Let's explore how, AI and robotics are
transforming the disassembly processes,
advanced AI system, particularly those
based GPT are capable of analyzing
complex product design and determining the
most efficient way to disassemble them.
For example, AI can help identify
different types of screws, fasteners,
and adhesives used in electronics, which
are often difficult to remove without
damaging the surrounding components with
the help of machine learning algorithms.
Robots can be trained to recognize
these different elements and use the
appropriate tools to remove them.
This capability is crucial in
industries like electronics recycling,
where preserving the integrity of
components such as circuit boards and
processors is vital for their use.
Industries that have adopted AI driven
assembly have seen a significant increase
in the retrieval of usable components.
For instance, some companies reported
a 30 percent increase in the amount of
valuable materials they can recover.
This aesthetics, it's a has
real world implication for both
economy and the environment.
By recovering more materials, companies
can reduce their reliance on new
raw materials, which often come with
high environment and financial cost.
Another example in cycling of
automotive parts where AI driven
system can disassemble components
like engine and transmission.
with a level of precision that minimizes
waste and maximize the recovery of
metals such as aluminum and steel.
These materials can then be modified
down and reused in new products,
reducing the need of energy
intensive mining and processing.
The impact of integrating AI
and robotics into disassembling
processes is substantial.
These technologies not only reduce the
environmental footprint of products,
We use every day, but also support the
broader goals of a circular economy.
For example, companies that have
implemented EINR's disassembly
report up to a 50 percent
improvement in metal recovery rates.
This improvement has several
important implications.
First, it reduces the need for
extracting new raw material,
which is often associated with
significant environmental degradation.
Mining for materials like copper,
gold, and lithium, for example,
can lead to deforestation, soil
erosion, and water pollution.
Second, better material recovery
means that more of these materials
can be reused in new products.
reducing the overall demand
for virgin materials.
This is not only conserves natural
resources, but also lowers the
carbon footprint associated with
the production of new materials.
For instance, recycling aluminum saves
up to 95 percent of the energy required
to produce new aluminum from raw bauxite.
AI also helps improve the
sorting of materials during
the disassembly processes.
ensuring that the cycling
products are higher quality.
For example, AI systems can identify and
separate different type of plastic based
on their chemical composition, ensuring
that recycled plastics are pure enough to
be used in high quality applications such
as automotive or construction industry.
Despite this advancement, we
still face several challenges
in current assembly practices.
One major challenge is high
rate of resources wastage with
inefficient recycling methods.
Traditional recycling methods,
such as shredding, often mix
materials together, making it
difficult to separate them for use.
This combination can significantly
reduce the value of recycled materials.
For example, when electronics are
shredded, metals and plastic can
become mixed together, making it
difficult to separate them later.
ha.
This not only reduces the efficiency of
recycling processes, but also results in
more materials being sent to landfills.
Additionally, many products are not
designed with disassembly in mind, which
make the recycling process even harder.
For instance, some products use glue and
adhesive that make it nearly impossible to
separate components without damaging them.
EIN Robotics offers solutions to
these problems by automatically.
processes and using intelligent
separate materials more efficiently.
For example, AI can optimize the order
in which components are removed, ensuring
that valuable materials are recovered
without being missed or contaminated.
In addition, robots can be equipped
with advanced tools that can carefully
cut or unscrew components without
damaging the material, further improving
the quality of recovered material.
To see how these technologies
work in practice, let's look
at some real world examples.
In one case study, it is cycling.
The robots were equipped with additional
vision systems and machine learning
algorithms that allowed them to
identify and remove valuable components
such as processors, memory chips,
and batteries with great precision.
This led to a 40 percent increase in
the recovery of valuable materials,
which were then sold back to
manufacturing for use in new products.
Another example comes from the
automotive industry, where an AI
guided systems are used to disassemble
electric vehicle batteries.
The system was able to carefully
separate the different materials,
including lithium, cobalt, and
nickel, with minimal contamination.
This not only reduced the cost of
recycling, but also ensured that
the recovered materials were of
high enough quality to be used.
in new batteries.
This type of closed loop recycling
system is essential for reducing
the environmental impact of battery
production and supporting the growth
of the electric vehicle market.
These cases study shows that how AI
and robotics are not just theoretically
concept, they are practically
solutions that are already making
a difference in the real world.
By adopting these technologies, companies
can improve their sustainability effort,
and they can while also benefiting
economically from the recovery
and reuse of valuable materials.
Looking to the future, AI enhanced
assembly is set to play an even
bigger role in making manufacturing
and recycling more sustainable.
As these technologies continue
to advance, they will be able to
handle a wide range of products
and materials more efficiently.
For example, future AI systems
Could analyze the composition of
material in real time, allowing
even more precise disassembly.
This could be particularly useful in
industries like electronics, where
the rapid race of technological change
means the new materials and designs
are constantly being introduced.
Additionally, advance in robotics could
lead to the development of new tools and
technologies for disassembly products
that are currently too complex or
labor intensive to recycle efficiently.
Ultimately, the goal is to create
a circular economy where methods
are continuously used and basis
minimize the vision of sustainable
future is within our reach.
Thanks to the advancement in AI and
robotics by continuing to innovate
and integrate these technologies,
we can build a world where
economic growth and environmental
responsibility go hand in hand.
Thank you for your attention.
I hope this presentation has
given you a better understanding.
how AI and robotics can help us
achieve a more sustainable future.
I am happy to answer any
question you may have.
Thank you.