Greetings of today, everyone.
My name is Rahul Gti.
Thanks for being here.
Let's get started.
Right away.
Every minute of every day, a silent,
invisible war is being fought.
It's not a physical battlefield,
but across the digital networks
that power our global economy.
The enemy is sophisticated,
relentless, and increasingly automated.
I am talking of course
about financial fraud.
The slide here quotes a figure
of $32 billion in global losses,
but the reality is the problem is
accelerating at an alarming rate.
Recent data from the US Federal
Trade Commission, a stagger.
In 2024 alone reported consumer
losses to fraud in the us.
Jumped over $12.5 billion, a 25%
increase in just one year, and that's
just what's reported by the consumers.
On the organizational side, a 2025
survey from the Association for Financial
Professionals found that a staggering
79% of the organizations were victims
of payment fraud attempts last year.
This isn't just a numbers game,
it's technological arms race.
More than 70% of the executives
expect financial crime to increase
in 2025, citing the increased use of
AI backed criminals as a top reason
the old defense systems are failing.
The nature of the threat
has fundamentally changed.
The data shows while the number of
fraud reports has remained stable,
the percentage of people who actually
lost money in an attack jumped
from 27% to 38% in a single year.
This means fraudsters are becoming
far more effective in each attempt.
This isn't a volume problem anymore.
It's a sophistication problem.
So today I'm here to talk
about how we engineer the front
lines of this new battlefield.
It's no longer about writing better rules.
It's about building
fundamentally better platforms.
We will explore how to architect and build
resilient AI powered systems that can not
only detect, but anticipate and dismantle
sophisticated fraud at massive scale.
So let's look at the
evolution of fraud detection.
For decades, fraud detection was a game
of cat and mouse played in slow motion.
A new fraud pattern would emerge.
Analysts would study it, write
a new rule and deploy it.
This is the world of traditional
rule-based systems, but these
systems are fundamentally brittle.
Their inflexibility meant we were
always one step behind the criminals.
Their reliance on grid thresholds led
to high false positive rates, which
weren't just a technical problem.
They were a customer experience nightmare
blocking legitimate transactions,
and creating unnecessary friction.
And these false positives have a real
cost, not just in customer frustration,
but an operational overhead, a cost
we later quantified at nearly $5
million a year in our own operations.
Furthermore, these systems
suffered from a limited context.
They could see a single transaction,
but not the broader sinister
pattern it was a part of, and as
transaction volumes exploded with
rise of digital finance, these rigid
rule engines simply couldn't scale.
This brings us to the platform
engineering imperative.
To win this fight, we can't just
deploy a machine learning model.
We must build a comprehensive end-to-end
platform that handles the entire life
cycle from data ingestion, real-time
processing to model deployment,
monitoring, and security and compliance.
It's a foundational shift from writing
rules to engineering intelligence.
Drill foundations.
So what does this platform
actually look like?
Let's walk through the critical
architectural blueprint.
These five core layers work in
concert to deliver real time
decisions in milliseconds.
It all starts with data.
The data ingestion layer is our gateway
to outside world responsible for
collecting massive varieties of data
streams, transaction data, customer
profiles, device information, and even
external threat intelligence feeds.
It's the foundation of everything
that follows ensuring data quality
and consistency from the beginning.
Next is the central nervous system stream
processing engine for real time detection.
We can't wait for the data
to land in the database.
We need to analyze it in flight
where frameworks like Apache Kafka
and Apache Flink are critical.
For those unfamiliar, think of
Kafka as highly durable, scalable
commit log for streaming data.
It allows us to publish and
subscribe to data streams reliably.
Acting as a buffer and decoupling our
data producers from data consumers.
So Flink then acts as the computational
engine on top of these streams.
The third component is one of the
most critical for production ml.
The feature store, this is our
centralized single source of truth
for machine learning features.
It is essentially a dual database system
with an offline component for training and
low latency online component for serving.
It ensures the exact same feature logic.
Is used for both training our models
and serving predictions in real time.
This is absolutely essential to
prevent a notorious problem in
ML lops called Training Serving
sku, where inconsistencies between
training and production data
silently degrade model performance.
Once we have the models,
we need to manage them.
The model Registry is a version control
repository for our trained models.
It's not just storage, it's the control
plane that allows our serving layer to
deploy multiple models simultaneously.
Run A by B tests to see which
performs better and execute gradual
rollouts or instant rollbacks if a
model isn't performing as expected.
Finally, the AI doesn't
always have the last word.
The decision engine is where mission
intelligence meets human expertise.
It takes the model's prediction
scores and combines them with
configurable business rules.
This allows our fraud analysts to fine
tune the platform's response, like
triggering a step up authentication
or flagging an account for review
without writing a single line of code.
This isn't just a logical diagram,
it's a blueprint for agility.
By using an event bus like
Kafka to connect these
components, we decouple them.
So let's see how this
platform performs under fire.
The attack didn't start with the
bank, it started with the whisper.
So a fraudster gains access to consumers
credentials via a phishing campaign.
But instead of smash and
grab, they play a long game.
So from days 1, 2, 3, a small,
seemingly innocent test transactions,
a rule-based system sees nothing
wrong, they start adding new pace,
but cleverly with their names, similar
to existing ones to avoid suspicion.
This is done in days four to five.
On day six, the attack, this is
where our platform's architecture
becomes the hero of the story.
The data ingestion layer didn't just see
the transactions, it saw the context,
it saw the new device fingerprint, the
unusual login location, and the ri.
Mouse moments that were
uncharacteristic of the real customers.
The stream processing engine
analyzed this data in real time
as the new pays were added.
The feature store provided
the crucial history context.
This customer had never added
multiple pays in such a short period.
This was a clear behavioral, an anomaly.
Our end symbol of models served.
The model registry picked upon
this pattern of the behavior.
It wasn't one single event that
was suspicious, but the sequence
of events over the several days.
Finally, the decision engine
orchestrated the response instead
of a simple block, it triggered a
step up authentication challenge.
The fraudster of course, couldn't pass it.
The transfers were blocked
and the account was secured.
The key takeaway here is that no
single rule could have caught this.
The fraud wasn't in one transaction.
It was in the narrative
of the user's behavior.
Over six days, our platform was able
to read that narrative in real time.
Now let's dig a little bit deeper
into the multi-cloud architecture.
A platform this critical cannot
be dependent on a single provider.
We operate in multi-cloud environment,
and this is deliberate strategic
choice for several key reasons.
First.
Avoiding vendor lock-in by building our
core services using portable technologies
containers and Kubernetes, we retain
the flexibility to deploy components
across different cloud providers.
This allows us to choose the best
service for the job without being
tied to a single ecosystem, giving
our organization leverage and ensure
our critical capabilities are not
subject to the fate of a single vendor.
Second, resiliency and redundancy.
An outage in one cloud region
or over an entire provider
won't bring our platform down.
We can route traffic and fail
over services to another cloud,
which is essential for meeting
our 99.99% availability.
Target third, regulatory
and compliance needs.
Different jurisdictions have different.
Data residency requirements.
A multi-cloud architecture allows
us to process and store the data in
specific geographic locations to meet
those complex regulatory demands.
Of course this isn't easy.
It requires sophisticated engineering
for data application and secure the.
Cross cloud networking and unified
monitoring plane to provide a single pane
of glass across all the environments.
The challenges listed here, which
are replication, networking,
monitoring, are exactly why a platform
engineering mindset is so critical.
Now let's take a look at the
data engineering part of it.
At the heart of any great AI system
is a great data engineering For
a financial institution, data is
often scattered across decades of
legacy systems from one core banking
platforms to mobile applications.
The first challenge is
creating a unified data lake.
Data lake is a centralized repository.
That allows us to ingest and store vast
amounts of structured, semi-structured and
unstructured data in its native format.
It becomes the single source of
truth, breaking down data silos, and
enabling the holistic analysis required
for the advanced fraud detection.
This architecture allows
us to embrace the.
Extract, load and transform paradigm.
We ingest the raw data first in its full.
This gives us our data scientists
extra freedom to explore and
engineer new types of features
without being constrained by rigid
predefined schema, which dramatically
accelerates our ability to innovate.
With our data unified, the next step is
to transform it into intelligent signals
or features for our models and to do the
same in real time streaming aggregations.
This is about creating features
that capture behavior over time.
We use our stream processing engine
to compute metrics on the flight.
Like transaction count in the last
five minutes, or average transaction
amount over the last 24 hours.
These time window features
are incredibly powerful for
detecting changes in the behavior.
Then comes the graph based features.
This is where things
get really interesting.
Fraud is rarely a solo activity.
It is a network phenomenon.
By modeling our data as a graph where
customers, accounts and devices are nodes
and transactions are edges, we can compute
features that describes user's position
and relationships within that network.
This allows us to uncover hidden
connections and coordinated activity
that would otherwise be invisible.
And then comes the external enrichment.
We enrich our internal data in real
time with external feeds, pulling in
device reputation scores, IP geolocation
data, and threat intelligence too.
Add even more context
to every transaction.
With graph features, we fundamentally
change the question we are asking.
We move from assessing an individual
in isolation to assessing an individual
in the context of their entire network.
And as we are about to see that change
in perspective makes all the difference.
Now let's get back to our case study.
We blocked the initial.
Fraudulent transfer, but the
investigation was just beginning.
Remember those new pays?
The fraudster added, our
graph algorithms went to work.
They revealed that these
weren't just random accounts.
They were connected to a hidden
network of 47 other accounts across
12 different financial institutions
all created in same two week window.
The graph showed classic signs
of frauding circular money flows
between accounts, shared device
fingerprints, despite different
registered addresses and suspicious.
Temporal correlations and
account creation times.
We weren't fighting a lone wolf.
We are fighting an organized
network simultaneously.
Our real time streaming aggregations
were lighting up like a Christmas tree.
The login velocity from
compromised accounts.
It was up to 400% compared to
customer's six month baseline.
The transaction time shifted from
the customer's typical business
hours to late at night, and our
behavioral biometrics models detected
85% deviation in mouse patterns from
the customer's established profile.
This wasn't just a different
location, it was a different person.
These features computed.
Under 50 milliseconds were the critical
signals that allowed us just not to block
one transfer, but to proactively identify
and dismantle an entire fraud network
preventing an estimated $2.3 million in
losses across the affected institutions.
So this case study demonstrates
a powerful virtuous cycle.
The real time platform stops bleeding.
So building rate models requires
just more than algorithms.
It requires a robust infrastructure
that empowers data scientists
to move from idea to production
With speed and conference, our ML
infrastructure is built on four pillars.
Majorly first sandbox
experimentation platform.
This is where data scientists can safely
explore new data sets, test new feature
ideas, and iterate on models without
impacting production environment.
Second distributed training.
Modern fraud models are massive and
are trained on terabytes of data.
Are distributed training infrastructure.
Allows us to paralyze this process
across clusters of GPUs, reducing
training time from weeks to just ours.
Third automated ML pipelines model
is just not one and done artifact.
It's a living system that needs
to be constantly refreshed.
Our automated ML pipelines handle
the entire life cycle of retraining.
Validation and deployment, and
also ensuring our models never go
stale and are continuously learning
from the latest fraud patterns.
And finally, and most
critically low latency serving.
A prediction that arrives
too late is useless.
Our serving infrastructure is
architected for extreme performance
with model replicas deployed across
multiple availability zones and
automatic failover, all to ensure we
can deliver predictions and well under.
A hundred milliseconds, which is RSLA.
We retreat our ML lifecycle, not
as a research project, but as a
software engineering discipline.
Our infrastructure is designed
to be a model factory.
Enabling us to industrialize with
process of taking promising idea from
a data scientists notebook and turning
it into a hardened production grade
asset that serves millions of customers.
Platform that processes this
much of sensitive financial
data must be a fortress.
A security poster is built
on principle of defense.
In depth, defense in depth is
a strategy that uses multiple
overlapping security measures.
The idea is that if one layer is breached,
another is there to stop the attack.
It is about creating redundancy.
In our defenses and assuming that
no single control is perfect, we
don't add security at the end.
It's embedded in every
architectural decision we make
at the network security layer.
We use a zero trust.
Principles and microsegmentation to
ensure that components can talk to
each other if explicitly authorized.
All communications are encrypted
at the data security layer.
All data is encrypted, both in
transit and addressed with strict
key management protocols that meet
regulatory requirements, access control.
It is being governed by the principle
of least privilege using fine-grained,
role-based access control to ensure
people and services can only access
the data they absolutely need.
And then we maintain the
comprehensive audit logging of every
action taken on the platform for
compliance and forensic analysis.
Let's get into.
The federated learning infrastructure.
So far we have talked about what
we can do with our own data, but
the most sophisticated fraud drinks
don't target one institution.
They attack the entire
financial ecosystem.
What if we couldn't fight back?
This is the promise of federated learning.
It's a machine learning technique
that allows multiple organizations to
collaboratively train a shade model
without ever exposing or exchanging
their raw, sensitive customer data.
The process is iterative.
A central server sends a global model
to each participating institution.
Each institution trains that model
locally on its own private data.
They then send the model
updates, the learned parameters.
Not the data back to the server.
They then send only the model updates,
the learned parameters then the server
aggregates these updates to improve
the global model, which is then sent
back for the next round building.
This is a massive technical
undertaking, but the vision is powerful.
Now let's take a look at the
even driven microservices and
biometric systems integration.
To make all of this work at scale,
we need an architecture that is
flexible, resilient, and scalable.
We have built our platform on an even
driven microservices architecture
in an event driven architecture.
Or EDA services don't make
direct calls to each other.
Instead, they communicate asynchronously
by producing and consuming events.
For example, when a transaction occur,
the ingestion service simply publishes
a transaction, created even downstream
services like our feature engineering
and, model interference services.
Subscribe to that event
and react accordingly.
This decoupling makes the system
incredibly resilient and scalable As
services can fail and scale independently.
We implement this using advanced patterns.
Even sourcing means we store the full
history of all state changes as immutable
sequence of events in an append only log.
This gives us perfect unchangeable
audit trail and allows us to reconstruct
the state of any entity at any
point in time, which is invaluable
for four and six and debugging.
By adopting this, we get a
perfect audit log for free.
For regulators.
This is the gold standard to manage
transactions that span multiple services.
We use the Sega pattern.
A Sega is a sequence
of local transactions.
If any step fails, the Sega
executes compensating transactions
to undo the preceding steps.
This ensures data consistency across
our distributed system without using
slow blocking two face commits, making
our system far more resilient to.
Partial failures that are inevitable
in large scale environment.
And we are exploring blockchain
integration, not for currency,
but it's for original purpose
shared immutable ledger.
This can provide a cryptographically
secure tamper proof audit trail
for high value transactions.
Creating a single source of truth that
is verifiable by multiple parties.
Observability and
performance optimization.
Our strategy is built on three pillars.
Metrics give us the high level
quantitative view, transaction throughput
model accuracy, and CP utilization.
Logging provides us the.
Ground truth, detailed record of what
happened during a specific transaction.
And distributed tracing is the
magic that ties it all together.
It allows us to follow single
request as it jumps across.
A dozen different microservices
letting us pinpoint exactly where
bottlenecks or failures are occurring
and the results speak for themselves.
We achieved median of median or
P 50 latency of 47 milliseconds
even for our 99th percentile.
The slowest 1% of requests.
We are at 89 milliseconds.
Within our a hundred milliseconds SLA, we
focus on both because the P 99 represents
the experience of our un luckiest users.
And, keeping that tail latency
low is critical for consistently
good experience for everyone.
The platform can peak of 45
transactions per second and
maintains 99.99% of availability.
Now at the end of the day.
All this engineering effort is only
valuable if it delivers a real business
impact, and it does for a mid-sized
bank processing, close to 50 billion.
Dollars in transactions.
This platform translates to a
27.2 million in prevented annual
losses by reducing false positives.
We have unblocked 52 plus.
52,000 legitimate transactions
daily improving the customer
experience and saving 4.8 million
dollars in associated service costs.
The ROI is clear, three 40% in the first
year alone, rising to five 80% in the
second year as operational savings.
And of course the customer retention.
Benefits also kick in.
So as you can see, there is
a jump in the second year.
This shows the compounding
value of the platform approach.
The initial return comes from
stopping fraud, but the long-term
sustained value comes from making
the entire business run better.
Reducing the operational friction and
also improving the customer loyalty.
But of course, this arms race never stops.
We are actively exploring the
new next wave of technologies to
stay ahead of these fraudsters.
By using this advanced AI
techniques, generative AI offers
incredible new possibilities.
We can use it to generate highly realistic
synthetic data to train our models on
our rare fraud patterns they have never
seen before, or, even use large language
models to help panelists investigate the
case faster, and also quantum computing
while it's still on the horizon.
Quantum computing holds the potential
to solve optimization and pattern
recognition problems that are in
traceable for classical computers today.
And also we are exploring into
the edge computing and 5G.
So this would allow us to
take the decisions faster.
Building these platforms is
a marathon, not a sprint.
It requires a deep commitment to
engineering excellence, a platform,
first mindset, and a relentless
focus on delivering business value.
The war against fraud is one
we cannot effort to lose.
And with resilient, intelligent
platforms, it's a war we can win.
Thank you.