And thank you for joining today's session.
My name is Josh Thomas and I'm currently,
leading engineering and architecture
for commerce and financial systems.
Over the years, I worked on subscription
building, payment optimization, and large
scale enterprise integrations across.
Platforms like zoa, Recurly,
Stripe, Oracle, and Salesforce.
Today I'm excited to share how platform
engineering principles can transform
payment systems from a call center
into aerial competitive advantage.
Going to the next slide
start with today's junta.
Here's how I will be spending the time.
On this presentation, we'll start with the
evolution of payment infrastructure, how
we have gone from monolithic processors
to distributed e driven systems.
Next, I'll walk you through
the core principles of platform
engineering applied to payments.
Then we will look at how
to design for resiliency.
C because payments will fail and the key.
Factories, like how you can do
pay payment failure recording.
After that I will, I highlight
the observability and
complaints part of things.
Two areas where I think the
teams are usually slowed down.
Whereas if it's not built into the
platform, but if it's built into the
platform, it can actually delivery.
And finally we will talk about
scaling across different business
models, B2C, B2B, usage based billing.
By the end of this talk you'll see how
modern platforms can directly drive
revenue, retention, and customer trust.
Okay, so to start off
with we can see like how.
A traditional payment system was a
platform driven approach, looks like.
So these are some of the
differences they can see.
So traditionally payment systems were seen
as an unknowable cost of doing business.
They were brittle, manual, full of tribal
knowledge locked into specific teams.
Adding a new feature or a payment
method took months and when some
failure up, up happened, there was like
no visibility into what went wrong.
Whereas in contrast like if you look at
a platform driven approach, you can see
we build like self-service infrastructure
that abstracts a complexity.
The automated recovery process that are
building doesn't need firefighting, right?
'Cause everybody knows when
the systems goes wrong.
And then it, we can easily start looking
at what is runbook and then see like
how we can start the recovery process.
So we reduce the friction and product
teams can fast launch much faster, right?
So these are something that are there.
Because of this, I think you.
Don't have to worry too much
about things going wrong.
You can always focus on what next to
add or what features to be added, right?
So payments will stop being,
becoming a overhead and they'll
become a level of growth moving on.
So you can look at what happened, right?
Like an evolution of
payment infrastructure.
So let's take a step back and
see like how payment structure,
payment infrastructure has evolved.
We started with a monolithic processors,
one provider, tightly coupled systems,
zero flexibility as companies expanded
the integrated multiple providers payment
processors like Braintree, Stripe Arion.
But each recruited custom integration
code leading to duplicated effort.
So one payment processor will work
one way, the other payment processors
will work another way, right?
So it was a mix of lot of APIs
and different architectures.
So then next stage was evolved into like
more API first services providers begin.
Offering abstraction layers and
teams still had to handle all the
failures, but still it was a good
step in the right direction, right?
But today leading companies
are more looking at like event
driven payment platforms, right?
Where like it's distributor architectures,
recovery of server of ty and self service
are baked in from the start, right?
So the shift is really clear,
like how things have evolved.
From a monolithic to more like event
driven payment platforms where like you
get notified of what all happens, right?
So that's what brings in the structure
in the payment infrastructure.
So come moving on.
You can look at like
core platform engineering
principles for payments, right?
So one of the things that
we always look at it is.
So can we abstract a complexity so that
it's not really part of everything, right?
So product teams really need
not know, like everything.
Every minute details of,
say we saw MasterCard of a
local payment method, right?
So how can we really abstract
all those things in in, in
the engineering layers, right?
So second, like how we can build like
a self-service by default, right?
So that like engineering teams
are not involved in each product
launches or pricing changes or
payment method launches, right?
So it's more like configuration
based that any product team can do.
So third is like confluence, right?
Like how do you make sure treating
like regulations as a separate
process where we have a lot of
that UAT and backend process.
How can we directly embed them into
the infrastructure and the APIs have
proper auditing and logging, right?
And then how can we really create a paved
rod, which is like optimize default.
Common payment scenarios while
allowing flexibility are needed, right?
So basically building not our complex
systems, but building a system in
such a way that we can customize
as needed, but not to support
like our customizations, right?
So that it's easy to
maintain the code as well.
So looking at the architecture, right?
So let's.
I look at like how, what all
things are really needed in
a payment platform, right?
So one of the things that we always look
at is you need like a gateway, right?
Like you only unified enterprise
that can abstract multiple providers.
So say in the case of Stripe, Braintree,
each of them has different APAs and
different way of handling things, right?
But if you have a gateway which
can talk to that it's more like
providing that flexibility right?
From a. Engineering standpoint, or from
a product standpoint, you have a payment
processor or a payment provider, and then
you just call the same payment gateway
and payment Gateway has a complexity to
make those transformation that is needed
for each of those processing layers.
So that's one, one way of abstracting it
and then having a unified interface then.
Subscription engine, right?
So subscription engine is the
core of a subscription business.
So where like you start creating the
subscriptions and subscriptions has, each
subscription has like a life cycle, right?
So you have, it can be a monthly, it can
be an annual, it can be a bundle or like
different pricing for price points, right?
Baked into the subscription.
So subscription engine has abstracts all
the logic of so making sure like you build
the right customer at the right billing
period and consolidate that have, if there
are discounts taken into concentration,
taxes and other stuff, right?
So that's the responsibility
of subscription engine.
Then even processing, that's
core for any system, right?
So whether it is like a third party
systems or like systems within, right?
If then there is an action happening,
say like an order is created or like
a subscription is renewed, right?
That sort of becomes
like your event, right?
And then that based on that event, you may
have five to 10 actions to take, right?
So maybe like sending out a notification,
sending it for payment collection.
Making sure GL is posted, phaser, and
then the revenues also allocated, right?
So there are things which can do, which
need not be like really tightly coupled
synchronous transaction process, right?
So this, all, this can be an even
driven process where like all
the systems or microservices get
notified and then they can do the
step that is needed of them, right?
And the last part is
revenue recovery, right?
So any systems, right there
will be failures, right?
And in case of a payment usually once
you have a subscription, you have payment
method that would, that card could expire.
There may not be enough amount
in the card to make the payment.
So there are multiple use
cases that can happen.
So it's always.
Good to have an automatic re try
mechanism built into the platform so that
we are able to collect the amount and
recover the revenue from the customer.
Moving on.
How do you really build
resilient systems, right?
So one of the things that we
always see is like payment services
always need to have 99.99, right?
So it can be like fin nines or three
nines or like a single nine, right?
So that's the minimum that is
needed because anytime there is
a downtime for a payment systems,
you can see how it impacts, right?
So it is if you look at this,
even the single night, right?
You can have only eight
hours of downtime per year.
That is like across 365 days, right?
So the systems has to be
like highly resilient.
It has to be reliable, it
has to scale on its own.
Based on the customer needs as well
as the traffic on the site, right?
And other systems should not be
able to bring it down, right?
So that, that's a core and that, and
there are multiple services involved in
this payment flow or checkout process.
Then we have to make sure this
applies to all the services, right?
So it's not only one service being up
and running, like what other services
are there in the order to cash flow.
They have to be all up and running.
And it needs to be resilient all the time.
So how do you really achieve this?
So one of the things that we can always
think about is like, how do you really
try to do circuit breakers, right?
So if you think like there are
some systems failing, like how
can we really not add too much of
load into those systems, right?
And then start throwing a right
away so that we don't bring down
those systems as well, right?
So that is one, one way
to think about it, right?
And then how can have like
a. Fallback process, right?
Because sometimes the customer would
be having the money in the card, right?
It may be some other process
that failed on our side.
So how do you make sure like you.
Instead of having the customer go
through the, in their flow and doing a
checkout, how can we make sure, like we
can redo reprocessing on our side, like
a fallback processing, give them access
to the product, and then maybe collect
the money at the later point of time.
So how do you build like compensation
handling or fallback processing, right?
So that's something that will be
really useful when you think about it.
And then.
Other thing is like more of on
like on the retry logic, right?
How do you really think about retry?
How you can learn from the all
the failures in the system.
Try to look at the data that
we have and then see how we
can build like an indulgent.
Processing right.
With AI in mind.
It's always good to have those
models learn from the data that
you already have, and then come up
with a lot with a model which can
predict like what is the intelligent
retry or what time to retry right?
For those payments to be successful.
So there is a lot of use cases
that we can bring AI in When you're
thinking about Ian payment systems.
So this is like a case study that we
have put together which, which sort
of shows like how it happens, right?
So before the platform engineering 15%
of the subscription payments fail on
first attempt manual retry process.
Like all best guesses.
Like you cannot, like infinite,
do infinite retries, right?
It always has to be like
a way that you retry.
Maybe four or five times, right?
Like in a 20 day period.
Because the more retries you do on failed
cards, visa, MasterCard, or any of these
payment networks will try to say, okay,
you are trying to charge a customer the
wrong way or like you will be getting
fined because you're trying to retry on
cases where we are not supposed to retry.
So there are.
Lack of visibility into what are
the different error codes and
then not processing them properly.
And then there is no visibility into
how the performance is going, right?
Like recovery performance, are we like
able to collect most of the payments or
are we collecting on the third attempt or
the fifth attempt or 10th attempt, right?
There is no real lack of there
is no real visibility into what's
happening and to say the truth, right?
40% of the recovery rate.
On failed payments.
It's not a big number, right?
So it should be like a higher
number because these are customers
who are subscribers and they're
supposed to pay the company, right?
So that's where I think this becomes
a what do you call, big revenue level
for any companies to focus on and
then build engineering around it.
So coming back to like, how do you.
Get it right.
Like with the platform implementation,
we start doing like smart algorithms
and we try consider all the data, right?
Because all this failure has lot
of data associated with this.
Like whether it's from a MasterCard,
visa networks or from the payment
processes, there is a lot of error
codes and vertical patterns available,
which we can really look at and
say, okay, this, if the payment.
This set code, these are retrial error
and this and retread at on say Friday
at this time this could be successful.
So those are the things.
And then there is always this a
b testing frameworks for retry
strategy that could be applied.
So you can always bucket some.
Variations, right?
Like for the payment ries, and
then try to learn from them, right?
So it's even though the data subjects like
as long as unless you try that out, right?
Like you'll never know whether, how it's
successful and it's how it's come compare
to like our current strategy, right?
So it's always better to do like
an ab testing and then figure
out what is the window right?
And then try to do more
payment retries in that window.
Then it's always a smart idea to have
a real time monitor because without
monitoring it's really difficult
to really bring out what is the.
Level of success rate
that coming in, right?
So like you have to always be
on top of it trying to monitor
how the retries are working.
And then if there are cases, like if
we are reliant on an AM model, there
are always chances that sometimes it
may not be like doing it right way.
Right?
Or the, what do you call the ret?
Or the success rates
would've started going down.
So it's always better to keep
track of whether the model is
trending in the right direction and
then make changes based on that.
And if you look at the 78% success
rate, like we were bring, bring about
close to 40% increase in the success
rate and then that sort of translate
to millions in recover revenue.
Okay, so I mean to complaints, right?
So complaints.
Is something that I think it's always
feared the engineering teams because it
adds a lot of overhead to the systems.
You have to make sure
you audit the systems.
You have to build like more data
validation or data checks in, right?
So it's always a paying for.
To think about like compliance if Yeah.
It's becomes like an afterthought, right?
But I think if you start thinking
about compliance and bake it into
the platform, then it becomes
such, such an easy thing, right?
One of the things is like
a tokenization service.
So secure APIs that handles payment data.
Because one of the things with the
tokenization is you don't, you're not
exposing the customer what do you call it?
Payment, credit card information, right?
So it's.
Always best, like as a
company, not to have anything.
So that's where I think
the hosted fields comes in.
So if you're using Stripe, Zuora,
or Curly, like everybody has
hosted payment method field.
So like you just have to have the STK.
Load the JavaScript and then
they take care of getting the
payment and credit card numbers,
and then they tokenize it for us.
And then we just use the token right
as whenever we want to charge the
customer or do any transaction on
that particular credit card so that
we are not storing that information.
And then it makes it easier for our
systems to be not non PCI stuff, right?
Because we are not
handling any of those data.
Then infrastructure as a code.
So it's always good to have this
infrastructure of code from the starting
itself because with all the cloud pass
platforms, it's easier to build in a
terraform infrastructure as code ability.
So that like you, it's easy
to scale, it's easy to spin
up new environments, and then.
Putting more rail guards, right?
So that not not all the engineering
team have access to critical data and
everything is controlled by the IAC
code and not through manually access
through directly through ui, right?
So it's easy from an auditing standpoint
to really make sure, okay, everything is
done through code and then all the code.
Deployments happen through
like an approval process,
like a CMC process, right?
So that's what the, it brings in.
And then building in the automated
compliance testing, right?
So we can always automate
a lot of these things.
We can have frameworks, automated
security scanning, done like once every
month or once every quarter, right?
Just to make sure like all
the systems are still adhering
to all the complex standards.
Moving on the observability, right?
So this is one of the main
interesting things, right?
In the, in current world if you
need to build a resilient system,
you need to know what's happening
within your system, right?
And if you want to know what's
happening with your system,
you need to like really start.
Looking at how we can build in
observability from the start, right?
So if you are looking at platforms
like Splunk, NewRelic, right?
Like they, they give us a lot of
visibility into what's happening within
like the containers, like the CPUs.
What is the CPUs?
What is the memory usage, right?
So what if they're not enough or
are they spinning up new instances
because the current instance size
is not able to handle, right?
So all these things.
Need to be monitored so that
we can be sure we are building
in the right direction.
So that's where I think the it has
to be part of the, all the services
that we build in the, in, in the
engineering landscape, right?
So that we know what is the health metrics
and what is the AP tech score if there
is a, is there a higher error rate?
Are there any anomalies?
So all this can be identified and
the good thing with having the proper
observability is like you can notify
the right people at the right time.
And then the team to come in and then
look at their it's easy for them to
do look at, okay, trace there and then
figure out, okay, this is because of
this issue, so let's either roll back
the changes or increase the instance
size or like the memory, right?
So that's how we think about it, right?
So that's where.
Observability becomes very important
so that you can easily identify issues
and then take resolution steps, right?
As and when an issue happens.
So how do you really scale payment
platforms across business models?
So there are, really three
core business models, right?
One is like B2C, where I think you.
Directly deal with your customers.
So any customer that lands on
your site, if they want to buy a
subscription or something, you are
directly dealing with the customers.
So there will be millions of customers,
millions of payment methods a lot
of transactions happening, right?
Because it's like a B2B.
In those cases, I think we have
to really track like how the user
is progressing through the funnel.
How do you really do AB testing
based on different flows?
If some people like different
payment methods, right?
Is that is it better to have a
different payment method highlighted
here versus another payment method?
So based on platform geo, like
we should be able to surface
different payment methods.
Localized payment method is like also
one of the important things because a
lot of when in New Look becoming a log
global company a lot of the payment
methods that is that people are familiar
in US may not be the same ones that is
very famous in other countries, right?
So it's always, needed to look
at those platforms to enable
those localized payment methods.
For in UPI for India, it's UPI
and for Mexico at MercadoPago.
So there are like different things, right?
And then how do you make it simplified
so that there is not much hoops in that?
The second thing is like
B2B enterprise platforms.
This is like more enterprise
to enterprise, right?
So you, your customers are enterprise
where they are trying to like
when the sales team is trying to
pitch them, okay, hey, these are
the products that we are selling.
This is the pricing or
the product catalog.
And these are the different combination,
different products that we sell.
And then this may be like a.
Combination of a onetime charge
set up fee subscriptions along with
amendments and some usage based, right?
So those, these are some things
that they try to sell customers.
So here, I think it's, the complexity
is more on the billing hierarchy.
It's, it may not be the number
of what you call subscriptions.
This will be more on the complexity of
how the products pricings are handled.
And then how do you really integrate
it with, if there a procurement system,
supply chain and other things, right?
Like those are, and multi entity
invoicing capabilities, right?
So that's the complexity there.
One of the things like other thing
is like usage based billing, right?
So this can happen for both B2C and B2B.
So this is like getting like
really what do you call used by
all the companies because of the
way gen AI has come out, right?
So everybody's talking about
tokens and lot of things are all
like now based on usages, right?
So like there are different models
in, even in the health industry
where I think we are using like these
many number of, sessions, then how
do you build the customer, right?
Or do you build the insurance, right?
So that a usage based building is
important where I think on one side
you have to track like what are the
usages different usage patterns of
the customers and how do you really
map it to like the systems, right?
Like the subscription
platforms where I think.
Usage.
This can be mapped to how much
they need to be invoiced, right?
So that, that is something, and
how do you really use the new
predictive building kind of thing.
And how the pricing rules to map this
usages to the building side of things.
Moving on.
So I, we just want to spend
a little bit more time on the
usage based billing because.
I think that's where a lot of
teams have felt complexity.
There is a high volume
even ingestion, right?
Because usages can happen, like
in the case of let's say just
the token based things, right?
Like that we have people use APIs, so
you have to keep track of it and there
will a lot of events coming in, right?
How do you really aggregate all
this data across different systems?
How do you have these complex metering
abstractions for areas pattern?
Do you do daily load or
a month monthly load.
That's something that
is always tricky, right?
And so one of the things that we
do, like from a platform side of
thing will be like to have a pre
predefined dimensions and metrics.
And then having a self-service way of
dimensions that we can register so that
everybody can say, okay, this much.
Ma to this much.
And then also give them like the usage
estimation, API, so that they can self
service and then even the customers
can see how much they have used and
then how much they have to pay right.
In the next billing cycle.
So that's or if the billing is like
upfront, then they have to make sure,
okay, we cut taxes and then they pay
more, and then they get more access.
So that's the way that we are
thinking about it, and then this
is becoming the norm nowadays.
So that's why I think everybody is
interested in knowing how to really
do like the usage based building.
And how do you think about
like building from a developer
experience perspective, right?
Like for payment systems.
So it's always like a,
API first design approach.
So I think that's like a pattern
that has been around for years
and all the developers are
really accepted this, right?
And then people are familiar.
Everybody knows how to use APIs,
REST APIs or GraphQL, right?
So this this is like pretty
common standard nowadays.
And also like developer tooling, right?
So people, like it's, if you want
people to start using in their
own languages and it's make it's
always good to have builds STKs.
So s STKs or CLA tools and sandboxes are
a good way for bringing in new developers
to start interacting with your product
or start building against yours, right?
So whenever you start building, like
with, again, say like you want to
build an integration with Stripe.
Recurly, like you always try to see
like whether there's an STK that we
can just directly integrate, right?
Just import the STK and
then start building.
So you don't have to write
like that last code, right?
Of like transforming the rest a
p or the request and response.
So one of the things important is those
STKs has to be maintained so that as,
as soon as like the new version comes
in, we have to make sure like the
STKs or like CS are up updated, right?
That's the thing with it.
But I think that's one good way.
The documentation,
that's always important.
Because anybody, if you don't have a
big support team or anything, right?
It's always better to have
a proper documentation.
So that anybody, any developer can
just go in and say, okay, this is
the request, this is the response,
this is how you call our API.
And then it helps you.
And then having a developer portal with
like best practices, payment resources
the who are the touch what you call kiger
resources the whom they can reach out to.
And there are templates
and tools available, right?
So that's, these are something
that is like across, right?
This is not specific to payment system.
This is across, anybody.
Any team that we want to work
on developing new solutions,
this is some best practices.
So how do you measure the success, right?
Like beyond the type.
A lot of the things from a platform
status, like developer velocity, how
do you roll out new features, right?
That's something that
we try to see, right?
Like from an engineering standpoint,
how fast can we work on the business
initiatives and how fast we can
do how much effort is being put?
So that we are not, always asking like
engineering teams to do the work, right?
How much things can be like done
in a self-service way so that like
we build UI based solutions or what
do you call API based solutions,
which I think where product teams
can execute on their own, right?
So that like the teams are not involved.
And then the call team, right?
Like how can we reduce the number
of incidents that happens, right?
So basically making sure like.
When we are building something,
we have proper call TX in place
regression that can be run, right?
So that they, they are always up to
the standards that we are expecting.
That's on the engineering side, but
coming to business impact, right?
There is always the revenue
recovery, which is tied two
millions of dollars, right?
So it's always we have to make
sure like we have, we are tracking
it very closely and trying to see
like how much payments we can do.
That other is a conversion, which is
more like a checkout success rate, right?
Like how, there will be like a hundred
people going through the checkout process.
If only 10 people are placing an
order, that means like the success
rate, like 90 per 90 people are like
falling out right in the funnel.
How do you make sure how
we can improve that, right?
Is it something that is because of the
what do you call friction in the funnel?
Is that something that
we can improve on, right?
Are there like things which are
not clear to the customer how to
add payment method and all that?
How can we reduce that friction?
That's something that we always look at.
Other than there's like the retention.
So retention is really important and
a lot depends on the product also.
So like the.
If the student likes the product or
the customer likes the product, then
they will keep coming back, right?
And then they will be
renewing the subscription.
So it's always better to make
sure, like how healthy is that
interaction with the customer?
And how can, if the user is not using
it for a long time, then how can
we really bring him back by sending
him notification, giving him like,
say, okay, hey, these are the best
things like that can, how we can
use, utilize the platform, right?
So sort trying to bring
him on the product.
So we are almost reaching then.
So what are the key takeaways, right?
Let's try to wrap up and then I think this
is like, how do you have to like really
start looking with developer experience
because they are the first ones who will
be trying to interact with all these
payment platforms or other things, right?
So if the platform isn't usable, like
the adoption really fails, right?
You have to just always make sure,
like everything is easy to use.
From a design standpoint, I think
you have to always design for a
failure, recovery or resiliency.
So because like systems will fail,
that will be like, there are so
many partners or like interactions
that happen on a payment flow.
So it's always better to
always design for failures.
Know what are the failures like you do
like a failure mode analysis, right?
FMA.
And then try to figure out what
are the failure points and then
take actions based on that.
Then a bit complaints, right?
Like third one was like, we are
like, so that like teams are
not really way down by all this.
And like PCI related overhead, right?
And then always try to.
The technical and the business metrics,
so that a team is aware of what are
the business interests that's, that
needs to be the core of the system
and then we build towards that, right?
So that's what I think there is
always that need to know, like
what is the real goal of business?
And then what are they really focused on?
And then how can we build
solutions in such a way that it
aligns with the business goals.
Yeah.
So this is like how you move,
like payments from a cost center
to becoming growth engine, right?
Being the real part of the business.
Yeah.
So thank you for spending
the time with me.
I think hope you guys learned something
new and then happy for the opportunity.
Have a good day.
Bye.