Hello everyone.
My name is bu.
As a DevSecOps and multi-cloud
architect, I spent the last 19 years
helping companies architects secure and
optimize their cloud infrastructure.
I have had the opportunity to
lead some incredible projects
from innovating JA based solutions
for AIOps to re-engineering high
performance payment systems.
The topic I'm here to discuss today is.
One.
I am deeply passionate about
building secure AI platforms,
especially as they become more
central to our work these days.
The rapid adoption of a is not just
a technical technology shift, it's a
fundamental change how we operate and with
it comes a new set of security challenges.
The traditional models
simply can't handle.
The race to deploy a at scale
is on, but it's creating some
major security challenges.
We have always relied on traditional
perimeter based security model,
which assumes that anything
inside our network is safe.
That approach is simply not
enough anymore, especially when a
platforms span multiple clouds, edge
locations and hybrid environments.
The world way of thinking where we
built a strong wall around our data
center is completely inadequate when
our data and models are everywhere.
A workloads also introduce new.
And unique threats that targets
the very heart of the technology.
These includes model poisoning where
malicious data is used to corrupt a
model during training data poisoning,
which involves injecting bad data
into the training set to manipulate
the output advisable attacks, which
are specially crafted input designed
to cause a model to de misclassify.
And model extraction attacks where an
attacker reconstructs a proprietary model.
By observing its outputs, the
risk is where risks are high.
A security incident could lead
to compromised models, stolen
intellectual property, and
serious regulatory violations.
The stakes are, have been higher.
The solution is a fundamental shift
to a zero trust model, security model.
The model operates on principle
of never trust, always verify.
Instead of trusting based on the
location, we verify every single
transaction and interaction, we
will explore how this perm shift.
Can help us to build a resilient
and secure platform that we need.
As the diagram on the slide suggest zero.
Trust is complete.
Parm shift instead of the old method
trust, but verify mindset, we now must
assume every component, service and
data flow is potentially compromised.
This is critical distinction.
We are shifting from reactive
stance to proactive one.
We are not just looking for
threats, we are designing our
system to be designed from scratch.
This approach is built
on three core principles.
Verify explicitly, never assume
trust based on location or IP
address every request, every action.
Must be authenticated and authorized use
least privileged access grant, only the
minimal permission necessary for the task.
This dramatically reduces
the potential blast radius of
compromised account or service.
Assume a breach always operate under
the assumption that an attacker
is already inside your network.
This forces us to.
Design our systems with containment
and rapid response in mind.
A workload make this
particularly challenging.
A single machine learning pipeline
might involve dozens of interconnected
services from data ingestion
systems to feature stores, training
orchestrators and model registries.
Applying these principles to that
kind of complexity is crucial.
And it requires us to think
about security in layers.
The first and most critical layer
of zero trust architecture is
identity and access management.
For a, this goes beyond
just authenticating users.
We need to manage the identity of
services, models, and even data itself.
This is because a workloads
often involves a complex.
Complex web of service to
service communication, not
just a person who logged in.
Let's break in.
Break down three key components here.
Service identity management.
Each service must processes a
cryptographically verifiable identity that
can be validated across all interactions.
This is.
Important as a workload span, multiple
environment, mutual TLS authentication.
This ensures that every
communication between microservices
is encrypted and authenticated.
It's a fundamental way to make sure that
only authorized services can talk to each
other, preventing compromised service from
freely moving throughout your network.
Certificate management a's platform
requires automated certificate
rotation, a secure distribution,
key distribution, and revocation
mechanism that operates at scale.
The challenge intensifies when
training job may scale from single
node to hundreds of workers within a
minutes requires an identity system
that can handle this dynamic scale.
N Network segment.
The second layer is network
segmentation and mis microsegmentation.
We need to move beyond simple VLANs to
isolated individual workloads, tenant
environments, and data processing stages.
This is about creating secure
isolated zones within your network
regardless of physical location.
This is tricky because a workloads
have unique networking needs, like
high throughput communication, CL For
GPU communication, these requirements
often conflicts with the traditional
network security controls that might
introduce an acceptable latency.
The solution lies in using
software defined networking.
That can be dynamically create a
security communication channels
between authorized services while
blocking all unauthorized access.
The third layer is data
security and model protection.
This is arguably the most
critical aspect of a security.
A model is only trustworthy
as the data it was trained on.
And compromised data can result
in biased, unreliable, or
maliciously manipulated models.
This s layer focus focuses on
protecting the life blood of a systems,
the data and models themselves.
Let's look at three essential components.
Data line is tracking.
It is essential that every piece of
training data be tracked back to its
source with the cryptographic verification
of its integrity through through
throughout the process of pipeline.
This is our primary defense
against data poisoning attacks,
feature storage, security.
Centralized repositories of machine
learning features require sophisticated
access controls that understand the
sensitivity of different data types.
We need.
We need fine grained permissions at
feature level to prevent unauthorized
access and extra filtration.
So model specific attack protection.
This involves defense a against
model extraction attacks.
That attempts to steal intellectual
property and advisable attacks designed
to cause model misclassification.
Additionally, while standard encryption
is must for a workloads, we must need
to consider more advanced materials
like homo graphic encryption, secure
multi-party competition to protect
data while it's being competed.
The meta methods are complex, but
offer a high degree of protection
for sensitive competitions.
Now let's combine the last two layers,
runtime, security, and observability.
Securing a platforms at runtime
demand a different approach.
A workload often run for
extensive periods, consume
significant resources and require.
Privileged access to specialized
hardware like GPUs, which increases
the potential for a breach.
Our monitoring must be accurately
differentiated between legitimate
behavior, like a burst resource
consumption, and subtile
signs of security breach.
This leads us to the final
layer, the comprehensive
monitoring and observability.
We need to track data quality,
model performance, infrastructure,
health simultaneously.
This means using a specific monitoring.
This tracks metrics that indicates
potential security compromises, such
as model accuracy, degradation, unusual
query patterns, robust log aggregation.
We need to process extensive
logging output from triaging jobs,
high volume access logs from model
servicing systems and specialized
GPU performance metrics at scale.
Specific incident response, we must
have a specific runbook for a scenarios.
This includes procedures
for model rollbacks.
Responding to data breach that involves
compromised training data and automated
quarantine of compromised workloads.
So where do you start?
A phased incremental approach is key.
You can't do everything at once.
Service, identity and
management begin here.
By implementing mutual TLS authentication
between AA services and establishing
the certificate management process,
this provides immediate security
benefits network segmentation.
Next, move to next network segmentation.
Start with the broad network policies
that isolate between different types of
a workloads and then gradually implement
more sophisticated microsegmentation.
As you learn more about your traffic
pattern, data security controls for
data security, begin with the data
classification and lineage tracking
before you implement more complex
controls like Homo Graphic encryption,
our security multi-platform competition.
Secure multi-party competition.
Remember this is not just a technical
challenge, it's a cultural one.
You have to work closely with data
scientist who may view security controls
as absolute to rapid innovation,
obstacle to the rapid innovation.
The goal is to design security
controls that enhance, not
hinder their productivity.
Now let's talk about the specific
technologies and tools that are
essential for building a security.
Secure a platform based
on zero test model.
The technology choices you may
significantly impact both of
your security effectiveness and
operative com operational complexity.
Platform engineers must evaluate their
tools for their compatibility with
the, a specific requirement like GPU
scheduling, high performance networking,
and specialized storage systems.
First consider service me Technologies.
Tools like SDO are AWS app mesh provides
more critical capabilities for service
to service authentication and encryption.
They are the backbone of Zero test
network, allowing you to enforce
granular security policies without
changing the application code itself.
However, it's vital to test your workload.
To ensure that they don't
introduce unacceptable latency
that could cripple performance.
Next, we have container orchestration.
Kubernetes is the defacto standard,
but for a you, your cluster often
requires a specialized node pools with
D resources, high bandwidth networking
and large scale storage attachments.
These are not your typical web server
workloads and your orchestration platform
must be able to manage these specialized
hardware equipment effectively.
Finally, you need to robust
observability platforms.
These platforms must be able to handle the
unique monitoring requirements of a. This
goes beyond standard CPU and me memory
metrics to include include things like
GPU, utilization training, loss calls and
model servicing, latency distribution.
Without this level of detail,
you can't accurately monitor the
health and security of a systems.
A major concern with zero trust is
the potential performance impact as
a workload, incredibly sensitive, and
to latency and throughput degradation.
But there are ways to
optimize encryption overhead.
Select algorithm optimize algorithms
optimized for high throughput scenarios.
And leverage hardware acceleration
encryption capabilities in modern
processor processors and network cards.
This moves the heavy lift from
software to specialized hardware
authorization latency, cash
authentication tokens, and use
efficient authorization engines.
You can also consider.
Authentication delegation where a trusted
proxy service handle authentication
for high frequency operations and
reduce the workload on your servers
services network policy impact.
Benchmark your policy implementation
with rep, representative
workloads to find bottlenecks.
Consider.
A graduated security model where
performance sensitive communication
receive streamlined processing, monitoring
overhead use a sampling strategy and a
synchronous logging to maintain visibility
without slowing down your systems.
It's about getting the right data, not all
the data, and processing it in a way that.
Doesn't bottleneck your operations
as a platform become more
integrated into our businesses.
They also fall under a growing number
of complex regulatory frameworks.
We are not just talking about traditional
regulations like G-G-D-P-R, HIPAA anymore.
We also have to deal with the new
emerging a specific legislations.
These frameworks require secure controls
that not only offer technical protection,
but also provide a clear path to
comprehend com compliance verification.
Some of the key challenges we face
in this area include data resilience.
Data residency requirements for
global platform and the need of
region specific security controls.
The Zero trust approach helps
us address these challenges, but
also introduce a new complexities.
For instance, audit logging become
more even critical in a environment
where a training processes.
May run for an extended period and
generate massive amount of operational
data we need to able to process
and analyze this data at scale.
Furthermore, new a regulation regulations
are introducing requirement for model
com explainability and transparency.
This means our security monitoring
systems must be able to provide a
detailed visibility into a model
decision making process, all
while protecting sensitive data.
It's delegate balance between
providing a transparency and
maintaining confidentiality.
Looking ahead.
The in intersection of zero trust and AI
security is evolving at a rapid space.
To stay ahead of emerging threats
platform engineers need to
keep an eye on few key trends.
First, there is a con
confidential computing.
This technology uses hardware based
security capabilities to enhance.
To enable security model training
and interfa inference on under
untrusted infrastructure.
It's a game changer for data
protection and workload isolation,
as it fundamentally cha changes
how we approach these problems.
Next, we have a learning.
This approach reduces debt exposure.
To keep training data and decentralized,
it creates a new challenge
managing a security of complex
distributed systems that require
sophisticated security orchestration.
We also seeing the rise of AI power,
secu power security emerging tools can
help automate zero security, zero trust,
policy enforcement, and incident response.
For AA platforms, this is crucial for
handling the scale and complexity of
modern systems and helps to reduce
operational burdens on our teams.
Finally, a more long term consideration
is post quantum cryptography.
While we may be years away
for practical quantum threats,
it is never too early for.
Platform engineers to begin considering
post quantum implementation to ensure
long-term security of AA systems.
In summary, implementing zero trust for
AI platform represents a fundamental
shift in how the organization
approach infrastructure security.
We can't rely on world security models.
We must build resiliency into
infrastructure from the ground up.
The unique characteristics of a workloads
require these specialized approaches.
Success requires close collaboration
between platform engineering,
security, and a development teams.
Security cannot be afterthought.
It might, it must be designed into
the platform architecture from the
ground up, the investment payoff
in many years, in many ways.
You may gain better visibility
into your a operations.
Your compliance posture improves and you
achieve more reliable system performance
is to focus on incremental improvement
rather than wholesale transformation.
Each security control you add provides
immediate value while building towards
more comprehensive architecture.
Looking ahead.
We'll see emerging technologies like
confidential computing and federated
learning fundamentally change the, how
we think about data production and a
power security tools will help us to
automate policy enforcement at scale.
Okay.
Thank you for listening to me.
If you have any questions, you can reach
out to me in my LinkedIn at through email.