Hello, everyone.
Thanks for joining me today at
Conf 42 Platform Engineering.
I hope you're having a good
time so far and learning a ton.
I know, myself, I'm definitely
learning from all the others.
Let's try to keep it going.
Today I want to share with you a
technique that is called pre martem
that can be used to hack the future.
But why should we care about that?
projects fail sometimes.
Maybe not yours, maybe you have
been lucky in your career so far
and none of the projects you've
worked on failed the project.
But it's quite a typical scenario.
Most people have had failure in
the past, and while we don't like
that, it's something that do happen.
In fact, 74 percent of all IT
projects fail, depending on definition
of failure, obviously, and they
don't all end up burning in flame.
Sometime it may be just some delays,
sometime could be some feature missing,
issues at the launch, and you have to
fix them in the firefighting for a few
weeks before it can come back to normal.
So you can deal with
failure when it happens.
Obviously, much better to prevent
the failure from happening in the
first place, or reducing the risk
of such failure as much as possible.
So the technique I want to share
with you, it's called a premortem.
Let's get into that.
What's a premortem?
It's actually a risk discovery
technique that you do as a group.
So it's similar to a brainstorming.
It's really similar to a parse more temp,
actually, but we use a two step process.
First, we set up a scenario,
which is a hypothetical future,
where the project have failed.
So if your project launched,
for example, on May 4th,
that's how you would set it up.
You would, as a group, you
would say, we are now May 4th.
The project was launched last week.
It's a complete failure, whatever.
What should we do now?
How this, how did this happen?
That's what you asked yourself.
What did go wrong?
So it's really the same as a, post mortem.
You ask what went wrong and
why, but you do that before
the failure actually happening.
That's why it's also
similar to brainstorming.
You want to get a lot of, ideas out.
Using this framing, it's actually
prove, proven to increase the ability
to identify reason for future outcome.
So there's been studies on that
using this kind of framing.
better at that than just asking what could
go wrong without the framing around it.
So while it's simple to
do, as I've described, you
already know how to do that.
From my experience, there are some ways
that you can get more out of this process,
and there are also some things that if
you do, you will pretty much get nothing
out of it, or it even could cause harm.
to the project or your
company culture, anything.
So it's important to, do
some stuff correctly and some
stuff to not do it at all.
Let me share that with you
based on my own experience.
First thing is much better to have a small
team doing that, a small group setting.
Like much, pretty much all
brainstorming technique.
The bigger the group, the
less people will share.
also have less time for everybody.
It's time consuming if you
want everybody to talk.
So it's much better to do that
in a small group as possible.
That said, you want to also
have diversity of thought.
So you don't want to have only
like three DevOps engineer doing
that exercise because they will all
have most likely same perspective.
You will get less idea.
So again, similar to when you do.
brainstorming, you want to
have diversity of thought.
So different people, not too many, but
different people, different background,
different part of the company, as long
as they are relevant to the project.
So you could have a project manager,
you could have a salesperson,
potentially, you could have a engineer,
different people in engineering,
depending on what you are doing in
the project, try to have a variety.
So you get diversity of views.
That said, some don't.
So don't problem solve.
That's something I've seen often
and again, especially with engineer.
We like to solve problem.
That's basically our job.
Just solve problem all the time.
So as soon as somebody say
something, often you will have some
engineer that will go in and say
how we can prevent that problem.
You have to stop them right now.
Like you don't want to get into
a situation where you spend all
your time solving one problem.
what you want to do at this stage
is really just get as much problem
as possible, as much possible
risk, as much potential problem,
because they may not happen.
So you just want to get them out.
So you keep note of the problem, but
you prevent people from solving it.
It's not the right time.
we'll do that at the later stage
in the project life cycle, but
right now don't problem solve.
Also, don't reject anything.
Don't throw away.
That's a big issue.
Anytime you are brainstorming,
if you start to tell people their
idea is stupid, obviously they
will stay quiet and stop sharing.
So you don't want to do that.
You want to keep everything coming in.
Encourage.
Just list everything.
Something I've seen an example of
that at elsewhere, other, place.
Somebody said that cause of project
failure could be that the CEO
die before the project launch.
So that may seem forefetched.
Not sure what you can do about it as an
engineer or anybody on the team really.
Maybe you don't have to care about that,
but in any case, don't reject that.
Just list it.
Thank you, we can move on.
That said, instead of rejecting
if it's a too wide problem that is
raised, you can keep asking why.
So try to get deeper into the
problem to get more value out of it.
For example, if somebody says
that, maybe the project failed
because the server crashed.
you can ask more questions like,
what do you mean by server crash?
Was it like overloaded?
Was it actually a card that had an issue?
And, The server application failed,
was it too many users login at first,
too much account creation, like try to
get more and list them out, basically,
but don't, if you see that it is a
problem that is vague and high level,
and you could see that there could be
multiple reasons why this happened.
Then keep digging, ask why, so you can
get as many specific problems as possible.
Also, all along the journey, when you
do the primordium, at the beginning
and during it as well, remind people
what the goal is for this exercise.
So the goal is to gather ideas,
not solve them, no stupid
ideas, all ideas are welcome.
The goal is to gather ideas.
a list of potential problems in
advance so we can act on them.
So sometime I've seen that, people
are getting pessimistic because
they just keep hearing about all
the way things can burn down.
so remind them that the purpose of
that is to list everything that could
happen, doesn't mean it will happen.
And hopefully thanks to this activity,
they will not happen because you Raise
the problem in advance so you can then
build your project plan or address that
anyway Later on but at least you are
better tooled To solve the problem.
So it's important to remind people
of that all along and also at the
end after everybody Brought all
the point you just remind them.
Thanks.
Now we have all these issue.
We much better suited to solve
the problem and not have a
project that failed So then what?
You've done that, you've spent a few
hours listing everything, you have a long
list of words and ideas and everything.
So from that, you need
to adjust your plan.
So the first thing is to group and clean
up all the items you have on that list.
So this possible that people you were
talking and they mentioned, basically
the same problem, different way.
So you could have different
way of saying the same thing.
You group them together.
you can try to like previous
example where you keep asking why.
So you may end up with a bunch
of problem or potential risk that
are different, but could result
in the same, behavior in the end.
So you may still want to group
them together, make it easier
to tackle and think about that.
So you group and clean up item.
If there are stuff, that were not clear,
or you don't remember, it's fine to go
back to the people that brought the idea.
If you remember, you can clarify, but the
goal is to have a clean list of items.
Then you assess the risk of each of them.
Again, if the risk is CEO could
die, maybe not much you can do
about it as an engineer, but also,
maybe that's not the biggest problem
that will come if the CEO dies.
Maybe it will not be.
project launch failed, the whole company
might be in jeopardy, so maybe, not
a big risk, for the project itself.
some risks you may ignore, some risks
may be ready for fetch, so you have to
use your own judgment, talk with people,
see, like, how likely risks are, because
obviously, That's always the trade off.
If you prevent all the possible risks,
it will take forever to build that.
So you have to be strategic about
it and only address the most
likely risk that you've listed.
And then you share your risk
mitigation plan with everybody.
It's important to follow up with people
that did the exercise in the first place.
Of course, you can share with
whoever is relevant, but, to close
the loop with them, they were the
one that brought all the issues.
So it's good to follow up
with them saying, Hey, thanks
for participating in this.
We now have this big list of issues.
We grouped them, we've looked at them.
Here is the plan to address
the one that we deem to be most
likely are worth fixing for that.
It's possible to, say that,
this one is really unlikely.
We can solve later on.
Things like that, but to have a plan and
share it with people and how to address
that, this will well actually prevent the
project from failing from this scenario,
but also give more confidence, everybody
in the team about the chance of success.
So seeing that, Oh, We had
that big list of issues.
And yeah, I see that this
plan will address them.
We will have that person
work on this problem.
We are taking consideration about scaling
issue as we build the backend services.
like all this stuff will be in the plan.
So people will be much more
motivated about the project.
the morale will be higher.
So even just that in itself is
a benefit and you can prevent
failure just because people are
more optimistic about the outcome.
And that's pretty much that.
So thank you everyone for joining.
My name is Laurent.
I'm happy to discuss further during the
conference in the networking, section.
And if you want to follow up
with me, stay in touch, happy to
chat about this and other stuff.
Thanks again and enjoy the
rest of the conference.