Good afternoon everyone.
It's a real pleasure to be here
to share insights on platform
engineering for AI forward healthcare
native mobile architecture.
For the last decade, healthcare
has shifted from being hospital
centered to being increasingly
mobile and patient center.
Mobile health devices are now essential
for remote monitoring, telemedicine,
and personal health management.
Along with the and with the YAY
integration, these platforms are
becoming intelligent companions that
help doctors empower patients and make
more, and make care more proactive.
My name is Tri, and in this session
and in this session, I will, I'll walk
through you how platform engineering
native, mobile architecture, and embedded
AI combined to deliver scalable, secure,
transformative healthcare applications.
For instance, during COVID-19 triage
apps help hospitals manage patients,
manage patient flow by flagging
urgent use cases remotely before
patients even arrive 80 years.
The mo, the movement showed how
digital platforms can save, can
directly save lives when internet
for scale and intelligence.
Let's go to the agenda.
So in this in this agenda we'll
be covering about we'll be
having a brief introduction.
In this introduction we'll cover
about the convergence of platform
engineering and healthcare technology.
The second slide will be covering about
native mobile architecture, the foundation
of healthcare platform engineering.
Embedded AI integration, transforming
AI health, healthcare delivery
through intelligent platforms,
HIPA complaints and security.
Why architecture must embed
privacy and trust real time health
monitoring is one more aspect.
Engineering platforms for country.
For continuous care.
And the other aspect is clinical
decision support, enhanced
care, quality and outcomes.
And the last point is
the future directions.
Emerging technologies drive
healthcare's Next evolution.
Along the way we will also highlight
areas like patient engagement,
scalability, and strategy will benefit.
So in the, in this slide, we'll be
talking about the convergence of platform
engineering and healthcare technology,
healthcare systems healthcare systems
worldwide face major challenges like
aging population, rising chronic diseases,
illness, and worst stage capacit.
Traditional models of care can't
keep up with these demands.
This is where platform engineering
plays a pre pivotal role.
Instead of building isolated apps,
we design platforms reusable,
scalable, and secure foundation that
can serve multiple healthcare needs.
This shift means developing
reusable components instead
of reinventing the wheel.
And also using standard standardized
interfaces so hospitals, devices,
and insurance can connect seamlessly.
And the other aspect is building
scalable architectures that rely that
reliably handle millions of patients.
This mindset prioritizes reliability,
observability and maintainability, all
of each align perfectly with healthcare.
Healthcare's needs for consistent,
safe, and auditable systems.
So a UK hospital demo, a UK hospital
network demonstrated this when need
built a single shared platform for
appointments, telemedicines, and
vaccine, and vaccination track tracking.
By using components across apps, they
cut development time significantly
and improved system scalability.
So in this slide, we'll be
talking about the native mobile
architecture, MO foundation for
healthcare platform engineering.
Why is native architecture
so critical in healthcare?
Because here, performance and
reliability can literally mean the
difference between life and day.
Native mobile health, native
mobile development enables
real time responsiveness for
for alerts and monitoring.
Latencies are unacceptable when
the patient's heart rate drops.
Enterprise grade security is also one
more aspect through enterprise grade
security enhances deeper o integration
with encryption and secure storage.
The other aspect is hardware integration.
With glucose monitors, ECGs and blood
pressure cuffs, offline capabilities
that allow critical features to
work in low network and rural areas.
This makes native architecture
the better for safe and
dependable healthcare platforms.
For example, an Android based diabetes
care app connected directly with the
Bluetooth enabled glucose monitors.
Patients receive instant
alert for abnormal readings.
While doctors get accurate and secure data
streams, that immediacy would not have
been possible with a hybrid app approach.
So in this slide, we'll be talking about.
Embedded.
Yay.
Integration, transforming
healthcare delivery.
Yay, yay.
Transform healthcare platforms
from reactive tools to be to prior
to tools instead of taking the
addition instead of taking some
actions after something has happened.
It's like a proactive thing.
We try to stop, we try to
predict the things and stop
the things before happening.
So with frameworks like tensor Floor
Light, we can now run machine learning
models on mobile and mobile devices
themselves, keeping sensitive data
private, while enabling faster analysis.
Some of the most powerful capabilities
include predictive analytics to start to
spot early warning signs of healthcare
de deterioration, personalized care
recommendations, tune to each patient
data, clinical condition support.
Offering evidence-based suggestions for
doctors this shift, this shifts healthcare
from waiting for problems to arise
to anticipating them and intervening.
Early in India, a mobile iCare app
used embedded air to detect diabetic
pathy from smartphone images.
Rural clinics often lacking
eye specialists could suddenly
screen and refer patients early,
preventing available blindness.
In this slide we'll be talking about
the HIPAA con HIPAA compliance.
In this slide, we'll be talking
about HIPAA complaints and security.
Architecture in EA powered
healthcare platforms in healthcare
compliance isn't optional.
It's foundational.
Every platform must guarantee data
encryption, both in rest and in transit.
Access control with role-based
permissions, biometrics, and multi
multifactor authentication are they trace
that log every data interactions securely.
Some YA models here are even
trained to operate on encrypt data.
Through advanced methods further
enhancing privacy, the most effective
platform, build these compliance
measures into the architecture itself.
Ensuring every application develop
developed generates them automatically.
We saw this with the US tele
telemedicine provider that restricted
test result access strictly to
physicians, not administrative staff.
This not only helped them meet HIPAA
standards, but also standardize, but also
increase patient trust in the platform.
The next slide we'll be talking about real
time health monitoring engineering plan.
Engineering platforms for
continuous use, healthcare is
no longer confined to hospitals.
Patients expect 24 7 monitoring where
they are when wherever they are.
Platforms must support sensor integration
with variables and implantables edge
computing to analyze signals locally
without waiting for the cloud.
Intelligent alerts that adapt to patient
baselines reducing false positive.
This approach enables continuous.
Proactive care and ensure issues
are caught early for instance,
cardiac patients in Japan used to
connect TCG patches that detected
abnormal rhythms instantly, doctors
could intervene before emergencies
escalated, reducing hospitalization,
and improving patient outcomes.
The next slide talks about
the clinical vision support.
Yay.
Enhanced care quality.
CL clinicians, clinic clinicians
faced overwhelming amounts of data.
AI helps by augmenting the decision
making, which supports evidence based.
The recommendation aligned with
clinical guideline guiding guidelines.
Risk str risk stratification to
identify high risk patients, medication
management to detect drug interactions,
diagnostic assistance with analysis
of labs, imaging and symptoms.
Yeah, it doesn't replace doctors, but it
frees them to focus more on, on patients.
For instance at Memorial
Sloan ing Oncology.
Yay.
Yay based system.
Suggested chemotherapy options based
on thousands of clinical guidelines.
Doctors still made the addition
but the CO, but the AEA showed
critical time and reduced error risk.
Here in the next slide, we'll
be talking about the patient
engagement and accessibility.
A strong platform must
empower patient directly.
This means inclusive design
with large fonts, wise input,
and high contrast moves.
AI powered translation for multilingual
support, adaptive content tailored
to patient literacy levels.
When patients can understand and
manage their health outcomes improve.
So like in Brazil, a multi-lingual
chatbot, Delaware medical advice.
In Portuguese, Spanish, and
local ECTs by breaking language
barriers it gave undeserved
communities better access to care.
So even people who don't understand the
language, because of this multilingual
cha chat board, they can understand what
the gadget is telling them kind of stuff.
So in this slide we'll be talking
about the scalability and performance
engineering from healthcare integration.
As adoption growth, healthcare
platforms must remain reliable at scale.
This requires.
MI Microservice architecture for
independent scaling cloud, cloud
native deployment for elastic capacity,
database optimization for fast,
massive data handling, robust APIs to
integrate diverse healthcare systems.
Performance monitoring to issues
proactively sca, scalability issues.
Platforms can serve populations,
not just individual clinics.
So for instance, during,
cOVID-19 vaccine dollars.
Scheduling platforms scaled overnight to
manage millions of appointments across
entire countries without any downtime.
In the next slide, we'll be talking
about implementation strategies from
concept to clinical deployment building.
Building platforms is only
part of the challenge.
Deploying them safely into clinical
environments is equally critical.
This means using agile methods, adapted
for regulatory cycles, conducting
clinical validation with diverse
patient populations, running pilot
programs to test safely in controlled
settings, supporting change management
through staff training and gradual.
Success depends not just on
technology, but also on the adoption.
Adoption and trust.
A US Children's Hospital
piloted its asthma management
app with just 50 families.
After refining the experience, they
safely expanded it to 10,000 patients.
That's a great big breakthrough.
So in this slide we'll be talking
about the future directions
of emerging technologies and
healthcare platform evolution.
Evolution.
The future of healthcare platforms
is being shaped by emerging
technologies like a JA computing
to run advanced models locally.
Federal learning pertain.
Federated learning, retain models
collaboratively without sharing raw data,
augmented reality to support doctors
during surgery or patient care wise.
First, attendance for natural
hands-free interaction.
These advances will make more
intelligent, accessible, and personal.
For example, surgeons in
Toronto use the air headsets to
overlay imaging on live anatomy.
Reducing surgery times
and improved accuracy.
Here we talk about the strategic benefits
of AI powered healthcare platforms.
AI powered platforms create
values across the healthcare
system like clinical efficiency.
By automating this task patient
engagement through personalized insights.
Care coordination by connecting providers
preventive care, using predictive
analysis, resource optimization for
staff and supply chains, regulatory
compliance via automated reporting.
The impact extends beyond patients to
the entire healthcare system in Germany,
and AI scheduling system optimized nurse
shifts reducing overtime by 20% while
maintaining the quality of healthcare.
So this is a conclusion.
The strategic Im imperative of this one
is to wrap up platform engineering use of
the foundation for healthcare, use of the
foundation healthcare system requires,
and also native mobile development
provides respon, responsiveness,
security, and device integration.
And apart from that embedded AI transforms
platforms into intelligent companies.
Together these approaches make healthcare
safer, smarter, and more scalable.
Singapore has already shown this
with the national AI powered
health apps, which unify patients
records, monitoring and services.
This demonstrates how
platform engineering can be.
It can be a true strategic imperative,
not just a technical choice.
Thank you all for your time and attention.
The convergence of platform
engineering, native mobile design
and AI is not just about apps.
It's about team engineer
healthcare itself.
I hope this session gives gives
you a clear perspective on now.
The foundation's enable platform that
truly make a difference in people's lives.
I would like to take your, I would like to
thank you all for giving me an opportunity
to provide, to present this topic.
Thank you.
Have a good day.