Good morning.
Good afternoon, everyone.
My name is Ra.
I'm excited to be with you today.
I'm currently working for
Amazon as a data engineer.
I am.
My main focus is on building
next generation of data platform.
Today I want to talk about a topic
that quickly becoming crucial in
our industry, how generative AI
is fundamentally cha changing the
way we approach data integration.
This isn't about just new tool
or incremental change, it's
our complete paradigm shift.
The title of my talk is Scalable,
code Free, ETL, how Generative AI
is Redefining Data Integration.
And it's a topic that's very
relevant to anyone involved in data
platforms, engineering, or analytics.
I'm looking forward to walking you
through how this technology works,
showing you some real world results,
and discussing what it means for
the future of platform engineering.
So before we dive into the solution,
let's acknowledge the problems
we are all too familiar with.
The image of tire looking
developer says It solved.
Organizations today face
significant hurdles with
traditional E detailed processes.
The first major problem is the manual
coding burden, creating a new data
pipeline from scratch request deep.
Technical expertise and specialized
engineering skills for each one, which
creates a body link in the workflow.
The number of new pipelines a
business can create is limited by
the number of engineers available.
This is a major friction point.
This leads directly to the second problem.
A high technical learning curve.
The people who need the data most,
the data analyst and business users
often can't get it themselves because
they lack the technical skills.
They must rely on a small,
specialized team of engineers,
which delays insights and slowly
it slows down the entire business.
This dependency creates a communication
gap and significant time lag.
And finally, there is
the operational overhead.
A data pipeline isn't a
one on one on done project.
It requires continuous maintenance,
troubleshooting, and optimization,
which drains valuable resources and
time from your engineering team.
This constant upkeep prevents teams
from focusing on innovation, so we
are stuck in a cycle of building and
maintaining which limits our ability to
respond to new business needs quickly.
Generative AI is the key to
solving these challenges.
It's a fundamental shift
moving us from a code centric
world to a conversational one.
Imagine telling the system in plain
English exactly what you need.
That's the first step.
Translating natural language to
your pipeline, you can express
your data needs without any SQL
or transformation code required.
This empowers a much broader group
of users to interact with data.
The magic happens with intent recognition.
The AI doesn't just look for keywords.
It understands the business
intent behind your request.
For example, if you say, show me sales
strength, the AI understands you need
a time series analysis with specific
aggregations, not just a simple query.
It translates the business goal into
correct technical specification.
The system handles the entire
workflow automatically, which is
what we call automatic execution.
It doesn't just generate the code, it
handles the deployment and continuous
monitoring of the pipeline without any
manual intervention from an engineer.
This is a huge leap in efficiency
and it gets smarter with every use.
This is the concept of
continuous learning over time.
The system builds a knowledge
base unique to your organization,
learning your specific data assets,
and common integration pattern.
This makes it more efficient
and accurate over time, and
it's a self-improving system.
This entire paradigm shift
is about democratizing data.
It puts data integration
capability directly in the
hands of who need insights.
So let's take a closer look at
what's happening behind the scenes.
This is the architectural
breakdown of AI driven ETL system.
It all starts with the
natural language interface.
This is the user phrasing.
Front end users can simply type or speak
their data request just as they would.
Do a search engine or a chat bot.
This is where the initial intent is
captured, and the system can even
prove contextual assistance to help
the user formulate their request
more clearly, the request is then
passed to the semantic password.
This is the core intelligence layer.
It breaks down the request
interpreting and mapping it to this.
Specific data entities,
their relationships, and the
transformation we have asked for.
For example, if you ask for sales
by product, the passer knows to
map sales to specific sales table
and product to a product table.
It understands the relationship
between these entities and
what you want to do with them.
The output from the passer
goes to the execution planner.
This component is a strategist.
It takes the past information and
figures out the most efficient
way to execute the pipeline.
It considers factors like the size
of the data, available, resources,
and your company's governance
policies to create an optimized plan.
This step is critical for ensuring
performance and scalability.
Finally, the runtime engine
puts the plan into action.
It takes the optimized plan and translates
it into actual executable code for
a variety of processing frameworks.
Whether that says part job, a series
of SQL queries, or something else, the
runtime engine ensures the pipeline
runs correctly and efficiently
translating the plan into the correct
syntax for the underlying technology.
Let's make this concept even more concrete
by walking through a practical example.
A business user, perhaps from the
marketing team, needs a specific report.
Instead of submitting a ticket to the
data team and waiting for weeks, they
simply type the request into the system.
The request is clear
plain English sentence.
The AI understands the full
context of the request.
It recognizes that total sales
needs a sum function that.
Product category is a group by
class, and the top 10 customers
require a rank or limit class.
It also understands the time
dimension for the comparison logic.
This is far more sophisticated
than a simple search function.
This deep understanding allows it to
generate complete, optimized logic.
This isn't just a simple query, it's
a full fledged operational pipeline,
which scheduling transformation rules
and output formatting built in this.
This system creates all the necessary code
and logic to make this request a reality.
The final product is a production
ready workflow that is automatically
deployed and ready to run.
This pipeline is ready to
execute, and it's even set up with
monitoring and notification, so
the user is informed of its status.
The best part, the entire process takes
minutes instead of days, and the users
never have to write a single line of code.
To move from a cool demo to a robust
enterprise ready platform, a few
critical, comprehensive needed.
It's a combination of a solid
foundation, powerful processing,
and strong operational capabilities.
In the foundation layer, the
system must have a comprehensive
understanding of your data landscape.
This requires metadata discovery,
which automatically scans and
catalogs all data sources.
So the AI knows what's available
and how it's structured.
We also need a strong credential
management system to securely handle
authentication and maintain zero trust
principles, the processing layers.
Ensure the system is
efficient and powerful.
Intelligent catching prevents the
same work from being done over
and over by catching results and
minimizing redundant processing.
This is especially important
for frequently run reports.
It also supports real-time processing with
stream based pipelines from time sensitive
applications like fraud detection or
live dashboards on the operational layer.
Data lineage tracking is a key component
for governance and troubleshooting.
The system automatically creates a
trail of how data moves, which is vital
for audits, debugging, and ensuring
data quality and API orchestration
is what allows the system to connect
and coordinate with all the various
systems and services in a modern
enterprise, ensuring seamless data
movement across disparate systems.
These components work together to
create a platform that balances
flexibility with governance.
Let's examine a real world case study
from a financial services company.
This is a great example.
Because of the complexity of
the data environment and strict
regulatory requirements, they
face significant challenges.
Their data landscape was
immense and fragment.
Fragmented with over 300 data
sources across legacy systems
and modern cloud platform.
The industry's regulatory reporting
requirements meant that any new
data pipeline needed to handle
high complex transformations.
The result was that the average time
to implement a new data pipeline was
a staggering three weeks, and the
limited data engineering resources
were constantly a bottleneck,
unable to keep up with the demand.
After implementing an AI driven EL
system, the results were transformative.
The time to create a new pipeline was
reduced to a matter of hours, not weeks.
This meant the business could get
new reports and insights much faster.
They found that 85% of their common
integration tasks could be completed
without a single line of coding.
The impact on the team was huge.
Data analysts who were previously reliant
on engineers were able to create their
own pipelines with natural language.
This led to a 40% reduction in
the data engineering backlog as
the team was freed up to focus on
more complex strategic projects.
And for a regulatory industry like
financial services, the automatic
lineage documentation was a critical
benefit, ensuring improved compliance
and making orders much easier.
Here is another powerful case study from
the e-commerce sector, which highlights
this value of speed and agility.
The company's goal was to reduce the time
it took to analyze customer behavior with.
Traditional methods.
It took five days to build a pipeline,
which was a huge delay in a fast moving
market with the AI driven system, that
time dropped to a staggering 30 minutes,
allowing the marketing team to react
to market changes almost in real time.
This is a massive competitive advantage.
This led to a huge leap
in user empowerment.
The marketing team, a
group of business users.
Created over 75 pipelines on their own,
completely reminding the dependency
on the data engineering team.
This is a perfect example of what
it means to democratize data.
The system proved to
be incredibly scalable.
It handles over 500 daily tasks and
processes, a massive amount of data, 12
terabytes across 30 different system.
This shows that technology
can handle enterprise level,
scale data and complexity.
I, many leaders from the company have
also significantly saw the improvement.
They went from waiting weeks for
data to be being self-sufficient.
They were able to respond to market
changes in hours instead of weeks
because they had the power to create
and modify pipeline themselves.
These aren't just
isolated success stories.
The data shows a clear
pattern of improvement.
The first bar on the graph
shows a dramatic reduction
in pipeline creation time.
The average time was reduced by
96% from days, two hours, which
is a massive leap in agility.
The second bar shows a similar
trend for engineering hours.
There was an 89, 80 7% reduction
in the number of hours required.
Per pipeline.
This frees up your most skilled resources
to work on more complex strategic
projects, rather than spending their
time on manual repetitive tasks.
We also see a significant decrease
in pipeline errors, a 33% reduction.
This is a direct result
of the system's ability.
To generate optimized and consistent
code with built-in validation, which
is far less error than manual coding.
The most exciting data point for me is
that 85% of business users could create
simple pipelines with no training.
This is a powerful testament
to the systems user
friendliness and accessibility.
The data shows that the promise of
democratizing data is not just a
theory, it's a measurable reality.
These benchmarks are based on aggregated
data from 12 enterprise implementations
across a variety of sectors.
So we know this is a consistent finding.
Let's look beyond the numbers at
the broader organizational impact.
This technology directly impacts
your a accelerated time to
insight, the time it takes.
To create a new data workflow is reduced
from weeks to minutes, which enables
faster, more agile business decisions.
This is crucial for staying
competitive in today's market.
It also leads to
cross-functional empowerment.
When business users can create their
own data pipelines, they are no longer
bottlenecked by a single department.
This frees up your data engineers to focus
on more complex, high value tasks like
building the underlying platform itself.
From a financial perspective, you can
expect significant cost reduction.
The technology offers elastic
resource utilization and automatic
optimization, which leads to a 30
to 50% lower total cost of ownership
compared to traditional ETL solution.
And finally, you get a significant
reduction in technical rate.
The automatically generated
pipelines are consistent.
Documented and have governance built
in, which makes them much easier to
manage and maintain in the long run.
The system also adapts to a new data
source and transformation needs without
requiring you to record everything.
So how do you get started on this journey?
It's important to approach this
strategically with a clear roadmap.
The first phase is
discovery and assessment.
You need to take full inventory
of your existing data sources
and integration points.
Don't try to tackle everything at once.
Instead, identify a few high value,
low complexity use cases that
are perfect for an initial pilot.
You also need to establish clear success
metrics and baseline measurements to
show the value of the new approach.
Next, a pilot deployment is critical.
Implement the AI ETL system for those
two to three selected use cases.
Train a small initial group of
both technical and business users
and make sure you validate the
results against your traditional
methods to prove its effectiveness.
This phase is all about
building confidence and buying.
Once the pilot proves its value,
you can scale and optimize.
You will expand the system to
more data domains and use cases.
This is also where you integrate
with your existing governance
frameworks and establish a center
of excellence for knowledge sharing
to ensure widespread adoption.
The final stage is full enterprise
integration, where the ETL AI
ETL system becomes your standard
approach for data integration.
You can then progressively migrate
your legacy pipelines to the
new system using usage analytics
for continuous improvement.
It is important to be realistic about
the challenges and consideration.
This is a new technology, and
there are a few hurdles to keep
in mind on the technical side.
While the system handles most
tasks, a few highly specialized
or complex transformation must
still require a coding extension.
You can't expect AI to
handle every edge case.
Perfectly from day one and for extremely
large data volumes, some performance
tuning of the AI generated pipeline
might be needed to achieve optimal speed.
Additionally, legacy system
integration can be a challenge.
Older systems without modern
a PS may require you to build
additional con connectors to get
them to work with the platform.
On the organizational side, your data
governance processes will need to evolve.
To support this new self-service
model, you will need to think
about how to manage a high volume
of high user generator pipelines.
The roles of your data needs
will also significantly change.
They'll shift from writing code
to focusing on architecture,
governance, and oversight
becoming true platform specialist.
Finally, while the system is core free,
you'll still need to provide training
and adoption guidance for users on how
to effectively communicate in their
data requirements to the AI systems.
To summarize, generative AI is not
just an incremental improvement to ETL.
It's a fundamental transformation.
The ability to use natural language to
create data pipelines is a game changer.
The business impact is
real and measurable.
We have seen significant cost savings
and huge reductions in development
time with some organizations seeing
over 90% reductions in development
time and significant cost savings.
This technology democratizes
data access, which is one of
the most powerful outcomes.
It empowers business users to be
self-sufficient and get the insight they
need without waiting on a technical team.
My final advice is to is to start
small and scale strategically.
Don't try to boil ocean.
Begin with a few well-defined use cases.
Prove the value and then expand
your implementation as your team's
confidence and capabilities grow.
This is the future of data integration.
It's about making data accessible to
everyone in your organization, and I hope
this presentation has given you a solid
understanding of how that can be achieved.
Thank you.