Hello everyone, and welcome to
today's talk on demystifying RQX.
My name is Hari Krishna.
I work as an engineer.
Senior enterprise applications engineer
at a med school, and I'll be your
guide through this practical survey.
Oracle E Business Suite or EBS, is
a comprehensive enterprise software
solution used by organizations worldwide.
So as platform engineers, we understand
RISE components is crucial for successful
implementation and maintenance.
So let's dive in and explore
reports, interfaces, converters,
and extensions in Oracle EBS.
Before that, what is RISE?
RISE stands for Reports, Interfaces,
Conversions, and Extensions.
it's a framework, critical for
customization of, Oracle EBS.
the modular approach of RISE helps
platform engineers adapt Oracle EBS
to meet evolving business demands,
improving scalability and automation.
This allows for smoother integration
into a platform centric architecture.
So let's start with reports.
So reports are a critical aspect of Oracle
EBS providing insights into business data.
So there are three, mainly three
types of reports, which, which
are like standard reports, custom
reports and ad hoc reports.
and the standard reports are pre built,
while you install Oracle or get the
product from Oracle, there are some
standard reports which Oracle gives you,
which is respective of the module, which,
with whatever module you get it, right?
and, while the custom reports are,
tailored for the specific needs,
obviously, every company which gets
it, they have their own requirements.
And Those, that's where the customer
reports come into picture with the
specific business needs and ad hoc
reports provide real time data analysis.
So when designing reports, consider data
sources, formatting and user requirements.
So best practices include using, Oracle,
suggested tools, reporting tools like
Oracle has their own report builder.
for to create Oracle reports, and
they have BA publisher and Oracle
BA, Business Intelligence Enterprise,
edition is also available, but it's
very rarely used, but, it's very less
used, but mostly, it's BA publisher.
I recommend BA publisher in Oracle, so.
let's get to interfaces now.
So interfaces enable communication
between, any system to any system, right?
it's a general terminology to use
for across all types of products.
if we are talking about EBS,
so it's a communication between
EBS and external systems.
So we have API based interfaces, file
based interfaces and messaging interfaces.
API based interfaces use web
interfaces, sorry, API uses
web services and RESTful APIs.
file based interfaces involve
data exchange through files.
And, messaging interfaces
use queues or topics.
When, when designing interfaces,
consider, Data formats for, data
formats, security and error handling.
these are critical things which you
need to look into for the security
workers because someone is trying to
get into your system or you are trying
to get into someone else's system.
There could be a lot of security
things in between or the firewalls.
that needs to be taken care of.
so, integrations tools such as Oracle
Integration Clouds, or Oracle SoaSuite.
are being used, very, nowadays, so
platform engineering real relies heavily
on seamless integration across systems.
So a PS and interfaces ensure
fluid communication between
Oracle EPS and various platforms.
So now let's get on to conversions.
Conversions involve data migration,
transformation, or loading, like type
of conversions include data migration.
Data warehousing and data archiving.
plan carefully considering data
quality, formatting and validation use.
gen we generally use Oracle, data
loading tools such as Oracle Data
Pump, Oracle SQL Loader, et cetera.
those are commonly used, for when
we do anything like into Oracle.
So if you are migrating something from a
different, interface application and it's
being shut down, you want to move the data
into Oracle, these tools are preferred.
um, for platform engineers here, the
efficient data migration strategies
are key to ensure a seeming transition
to modernize cloud based platform.
So conversion efforts directly,
impact a lot in the system because.
the s what, when you say about, when
you talk about a system, it's all data.
if there is data, there is a product
type, that's a system which runs around.
If there is, if the data was corrupted,
then it's, then, it's a big impact on,
on everything, which is running below it.
So, conversion plays a
critical role in there.
let's, move on to extensions now.
Extensions, enhance Oracle EBS
functionality through customizations.
Generally, modifications are like adding
new features to the existing one, right?
You need to extend the
existing functionality.
you can do in some ways.
Those things are extensions, like type
of extensions include custom tables,
you want to create custom tables.
You want to create custom
forms, like create a form.
You have standard forms, but you want to
create something which is, which has this
form data and some other custom data.
You want to load it there
and have something there.
You can still create custom
forms and custom work groups
like article as workflow window.
It's got it.
In the, but you can create a custom
workflow of every company has its own,
for example, approval workflow, right?
There could be three levels of
approvals or there could be 10
levels or there could be 15 levels.
Oracle allows you to create
custom workflows as well.
So these are, these all
come under, extensions.
So type of, Oracle
Customization Guidelines.
we, and we, but creating, while creating,
extensions, we strictly need to follow
Oracle Customization Guidelines and
use tools like Oracle Application
Extension or Oracle JDeveloper.
And there are some setups which need
to do, keeping that in mind that
Oracle releases patches, every, twice
a year, if you don't follow the correct
process, aligned by Oracle, all your
changes, the custom changes will be
wiped out and you'll need to install
them again or create them again.
that's one thing you need to keep in mind.
So
when, so I, so
generally the, I did a small survey
and I got some information from
like from internet and here and
there, which is that most of the
manufacturing companies who are using
Oracle EBS, like using supply chain
P2P, O2C have saved almost 75 millions
through improved reporting services.
That's creating custom reports, and,
those kind of thing and retail chain
save 12 million via optimized supply
chain interfaces, financial institutes
changed, like financial institutes have
a lot of data, and it's a different kind
of data, which includes awards, grants,
and, all those things, so those in,
in those, in those cases, reports play
a lot of, Lot of big role and it has,
as per the analytics, it says that 99.
9 data accuracy post migration
for financial institutions.
So pharmaceutical company like save 15
million through extension customization.
yeah, when I said financial institution,
it's not, I just said reports, but it even
the data migration, it has a lot of data,
but Oracle is very seamless that you can.
You can migrate it, you have best services
given and, loadings after, you, the data
accuracy post migration was considerably
good is what the case study says.
So the real world example illustrates
how RISE customizations when
applied within platform can yield
substantial savings, so efficiency
gains and competency advantages.
While working with RISE components,
there are common challenges, which arise.
I just want to, highlight it
here so that it will be helpful.
there are some common challenges
which may arise to the data quality
issues, the integration complexity
issues, integration complexity issues.
My slide is stuck.
Yeah, integration complexity
issues and performance optimization
are just a few to work on these.
So leverage Oracle documentation.
Engage with the Oracle community
and following the best practices.
there is a community with
Oracle, which is support.
oracle.
com.
you can always have your questions
posted or you can reach Oracle
for any, anything you wanted.
that depends on the agreement
you have with Oracle, like your
company or yourself with the Oracle.
yeah, it's always recommended to
follow best practices and, don't
have a clear strategy and structured
approach for anything you do, with
respect to a father is competent.
So so balance customization needs with
system maintainability and future upgrade.
So if you do something, if you follow
good processes and create something,
which is, which comes, under the Oracle
guidelines, it's easy to maintain the
future, and, some and, future upgrades.
Oracle Club is said.
Oracle Club have the system
twice a year, so it, it's.
It will be easy to maintain or
easy to, easy to, look at the
applications and, get it down time.
So platform engineering practices
thrive to on interactive
iterative development cycles.
Leveraging agile methodologies for
wise customizations ensures faster
development, minimal downtime,
and adaptive platform solutions.
So that's one thing you
need to make it out of.
yeah, I think, I hope you got an overview
of what Oracle RISE components are
and how important and critical they
are, for successful implementation
of, Enterprise Business Suite.
the Oracle RISE frameworks will offer,
offers a powerful and flexible method
of customization e business suite,
allowing organizations to maximize.
Value of the ERP systems by leveraging
reports, interfaces, conversions and
extensions effectively businesses
can enhance system functionality,
optimize operations and reduce costs.
For platform engineers, RISE plays
a critical role in ensuring seamless
integration across multiple systems.
Improving data flow and supporting
platform scalability as trends
like micro services Cloud native
development and AI integration
continue to shape this industry.
So organizations that embrace RISE
customizations within platform
engineering can expect to see
significant gains in efficiency,
flexibility, and competitive advantage.
So now is the time to explore how RISE
can transform your platform architecture
meet the evolving demands of A modern
distal enterprise for further learning.
I recommend exploring article
university courses, article
documentations and online forums.
You can get, there are a lot of
documentation on the online and,
there is a lot of help in online
because article is not new and that
it's been in market for a long time.
And there are so many people
who are willing to help.
So thank you for your
attention and I welcome.
your questions you want to post,
I'll try to get back, but feel free,
feel free to ask any questions.
let me know if you have any doubts.
Thank you.