Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
Today I'm going to talk about
an interesting topic from
dashboard to defenses building
autonomous resilience at scale.
I want to start with something
we have all experienced.
Imagine it's two in the
morning, your phone buses.
You have just been paged.
You pull yourself out of the bat.
Look at that.
Dashboards try to make sense of graphs
and scramble to contain the problem.
And in that moment, how many of you
have thought, why can't the system just.
This itself.
That's exactly the journey I
want to share with you today.
How we can move beyond watching
problems and start building
system that defend themselves
in production environment,
especially at scale.
The 2:00 AM pager is not sustainable.
Dashboards solve problems,
but they don't act.
And while we have all seen heroic
firefighting from engineers,
this model simply doesn't scale.
When you are sell, when
you are serving billions of
requests, the mandate is clear.
We must engineer reliability into
the system itself, not leave it to
the humans to keep everything alive.
Let's start with observability.
The world wave was.
To collect everything, build endless
dashboards, and hope someone noticed
the right spike at the right time.
But let's be honest, humans can't pass
millions of data point in real time.
The new way is SL world driven signals
tied directly to user experience.
We don't just measure CPU or memory, we
measure whether user really succeeded.
That means tracking P 95, request
latency, overall availability
and checkout success rate.
We then set VOS and we use error
budget to decide when to release
quickly and when to slow down.
These turns reliability into
something measurable and actionable
to make observability very useful.
We use proven patterns.
We use SL OS and error budgets
as the release gatekeepers.
We follow red golden
signals and used frameworks.
To ensure consistency
across every service.
Each service has a single golden
dashboard, not dent, so engineers
know exactly where to look.
We take an open telemetry first approach,
so metrics, traces, and locks all
flow through the standard pipeline.
And we enrich metrics
with trace IDs like that.
So an engineer can jump
directly from a latency spike
to the trace that explains it.
This makes observative
more than just data.
It makes, it's a foundation of automation.
Metric traces and locks are
only valuable if they are scale.
For tracing, we propagate W three
trace contacts across every service,
and we use tail based sampling.
So we always keep the interesting data,
the errors, and the outliers for locks.
We use structure json, we redact
sensitive data at the collector, and
we route locks by severity so we can.
We can look into what is necessary
and don't log unnecessary noises.
When these three pillars work
together, you get correlated
telemetry that you can trust.
Agility also has to
extend beyond the backend.
We need change awareness Every deployment.
Every feature flag toggle, so up
as annotations on the dashboards.
That way when the latest pump jumps or
error spikes, we can immediately see
if it lines up with the new release.
We need client visibility,
real user monitoring.
Tell us about load times layout, saved,
browser crashes, broken experiences.
We also need edge visibility.
CDN metrics show us cash, hit ratio
and edge error rates, et cetera.
And finally, we track capacity
and cost before cost saturation,
before it becomes an outage.
And we take.
We take telemetry with the
team and service ownership
to make the cost visible.
This way, we aren't just monitoring
the backend, we are just monitoring the
end-to-end experience and business impact
dashboards alone are still
reactive unless you add prediction.
Static threshold always fails because
what is normal is always changing.
So we build capacity anomaly detector
that learn usage patterns and
alerts before we hit hot limits.
We then added AA models that
forecast latency spikes and
correlated logs, metrics, and
traces to find out root cost faster.
We also have models which deducts
error spikes based on capacity
and like right incoming requests
and treat the issues early.
One of the most powerful innovation
was using the browser JavaScript
error as an anomaly signal.
If a rollout suddenly increases
JSR, the system automatically rolls
back itself before user even notice.
That observability turning
into practical defense
observability only matters if
the alerts lead to an action.
The worldwide was an alert, fires your
human, wakes up, your human, then looked
into the dashboard and mitigate the issue.
That is very slow.
The new way is alerts are just alerts are
used as a controlled signals, so system
identifies the issue and auto corrects.
If a dependence is slow, a circuit
could breaker trips immediately.
If error budget bonds too fast, a new
deployment rolls back automatically.
We use multi bond rate alerts,
some of direct fast spikes,
and others direct slow leaks.
And we only page humans.
When there is a real user impact,
everything else routes to a chat or
tickets, which will be handled offline.
This keeps human focused on the
problem that really matters,
not everything, not noises.
To build a trust, we use a
tire strategy for automation.
Tire one covers safe and
reversible actions like
throttles and circuit breakers.
These always run automatically.
Tire two covers progressive changes
like Softing Regional traffic.
These can start automatically,
but allow for human oversight.
Tire three covers
complex or new incidents.
The system notifies a human.
But also provides runbooks and contacts
to accelerate the fixed faster.
This approach ensures that
automation handles the EC 80%
while human focus on the hard 20%.
Our automation also relies on
proven resilience patterns.
Multiple patterns described here,
the circuit breaker pattern.
Use to stop cascading failures,
bulk heads, isolates, failures.
So one service can't take down everything.
Retry with exponential.
Back off NCS, we don't overwhelm services
that are recovering failover and load
balancing strategies automatically.
Route traffic around unhealthy regions.
And cars and saga patterns help us
scale while maintaining consistency
across distributed transaction.
These patterns form our defense playbook.
Delivery pipelines are not just
about speed, they're about safety.
Manual deployments, get manual deployment
gate, slow us down and address.
Human misclicks, human approved
without contacts, so we build
fully automated pipelines.
Every release goes through a canary
deployment, progressive rollouts,
and automatic rollout, automatic
rollback when new error spike
happen, or SLOs are breached.
We shifted human review from
pre-deployment approvals to
post-deployment analysis when real
system behavior is available, the result,
faster velocity and safer production
pipelines have become resilience engines.
Another critical safeguard is.
Dynamic rate limiting.
Many of our incidents were not
caused by infrastructure failure,
but by workload anomalies.
Your buggy line spams request
our internal batch of floods.
Our APAs static limits always
fails because they don't adopt.
So we build adoptive throttling
that learns normal tropic
per client per endpoint.
Detect sudden deviations and contain
runway workloads automatically.
This mechanism alone has prevented
nearly 30% of our major incident.
Every safeguard we have today was
born from scar tissue, A cascading
outage gave us circuit breakers.
Yeah.
Bad config rollout gave
us progressive deployment.
Yeah.
Runway client gave us a tive
throttling, so we made it cultural.
Every postmortem as two things.
Could this have been auto detected?
Could it have been auto mitigated?
If the answer is yes, we build it.
That's how U turn.
Pain into progress, and
engineers always toil.
The hardest part of all this
is trust engineers, worry
automation, engineers worry.
Automation might make things worse, so
we build it progressively in data mode.
Automation only logs what it have done.
In suggest mode, it recommends action,
but waits for human approval only.
In autonomous mode.
It does act independently, always
within guardrails, every action is
transparent, reversible, and explainable.
Over the time engineers saw that
the automation was actually.
More reliable than a
tired human at 2:00 AM.
2:00 AM trust won't be declared.
It was earned.
Resilient has to go
beyond technical metrics.
It might tie back to business outcomes.
We run UI keep alive to
continuously check front end flows.
We track Java, JavaScript errors.
In the browser as a
frontend anomaly signals.
Most importantly, we watch
business KPIs like card A abandon
and revenue impact, et cetera.
If a release looks technically fine,
but causes amendment to spike, the
system rolled back automatically.
Reliability isn't just
keeping service green.
It is protecting both user and business.
When you connect it all
together, the blueprint is clear.
Metrics become actionable signals.
Alerts become closed.
Loop mitigations.
Deployments evolve into
autonomous pipelines.
Limits become adoptive safeguards.
Firefighting turns into
positive automation.
And fear of automation becomes trust.
That's how you evolve from
the dashboard to defenses.
So let me leave you with this.
Reliability is not PagerDuty.
Reliability is not dashboard
Reliability is autonomous resilience.
Every incident is a chance to automate.
Every scar is a chance to
build defense step by step.
You can build system that don't
just monitor themself, but
systems that defend themself.
Thank you.