Welcome to Conf42 and welcome to billions
of records in MySQL lessons learned.
I'm very excited to walk you through
my experience working with bigger
data sets with billions of records in
MySQL, as you can see on the screen.
And I hope you will learn
something from my talk.
So let's get right into it.
To begin with, I would like
to show you two queries.
One query is a query searching
for data without an eta sign.
And the second query is searching for
data with an eta sign in Boolean mode.
These queries are something that is known
as queries with a full text search index.
Such queries are very prevalent in
MySQL when we are searching for data
in using the full text search index.
Meaning that our queries using the index
will have the match against clauses.
As you can see, they have
match against something.
And if your query is Runs under my scale,
and if it has such clauses, it is most
likely using the full text search index.
And the full text search index
means that it's privy to all kinds
of behavior that you would likely,
most likely wouldn't expect.
In this case.
One query completes very
quick and the other time out.
And the reason behind this is
that because the second query has
a bug within itself, the bug is.
It has a number that you can see on
your screen and the core reason behind
this bug, I assume I found this bug
somewhere around in 2014 or 2015 when
I was building a data breach search
engine, which I will also share with you.
The core reason behind this bug
is that I assume the query takes
a different path within a database
and as such the query times out.
Again, this is some weird
behavior within MariaDB.
So this is a glance of something you
will see during this talk, but before
we get too much into the stock, I
should probably introduce myself.
My name is Lukas.
I'm an author.
I am originally a security guy, but
I switched to databases a couple
of years ago, I wrote a book titled
Hacking MySQL, Breaking, Optimizing
and Securing MySQL for Your Use Case,
which can be accessed at hackingmysql.
com.
And I've built one of the most prominent
Databricks search engines to this day.
I run BridgeDirectory.
com, which is a Databricks search engine,
which in essence makes you able to
provide your email address, username, IP
address, or whatever details you want.
And then runs a search through
stolen and leaked data to tell you
whether you are at risk or not.
I also very frequently blog in
various blocks including bridge
directory, my own blog, I blogged
for archetype when it existed.
There was a SQL client, a block
for DB visualizer, Redgate,
and other mediums as well.
Aside from that, I also have a
YouTube channel called Database Dive.
If anyone wants to have a gander
through YouTube videos depicting
databases, you're more than welcome to.
And I also found bugs in MySQL.
And I also run my own blog that
you can see on screen as well.
So the agenda for this talk right
here would be performance basics.
I'm going to walk you through engines
available in MySQL, how to optimize
schema and data types, how to
optimize your data for performance.
Security, how to optimize for big data
and security, how to work with your
backups, how to optimize your backups.
We're gonna get a glance, a look into
advanced MySQL features and have some
tools to improve performance as well.
So starting from the bottom
we have performance basics.
Now to follow along with this,
you would have to have some
sort of minimal understanding of
MySQL or databases in general.
So when I, when you see some sort of
titles here on the screen, such as my.
cnf, these are most likely file names
that are related to the database.
I will try to explain as they come across.
So for example, my.
ini or my.
cnf is a configuration file that you
use to configure your MySQL database
and configuring your server means that
you glance through the documentation.
Get the parameters applicable
to your storage engine for your
database because all databases
come with certain storage engines.
For MySQL, the primary
storage engine is InnoDB.
And InnoDB has a couple of
parameters that you need to optimize.
That is the buffer pool.
InnoDB buffer pool size, that's
the InnoDB log file size.
And some other parameters
such as InnoDB flush log at
transaction commits and so on.
After these parameters have been
optimized you only search for what
you need so that your database
is not very busy to begin with.
So if you search for example one book with
a limit one clause, if you only need to
return one book, your database doesn't
scan through maybe 15, 000 or 20, 000
books and returns the results faster.
If you use MySQL, you should consider
using InnoDB, which is the primary
storage engine, which is going to be
used by all MySQL database anyway.
But if you changed the storage engine for
whatever reason, please switch it back,
because MySAM, as you probably changed it
to, is not a very reliable storage engine.
And most of the features that have
been available within that storage
engine have been available within
Maria, within InnoDB as well.
And also you need to follow
performance best practices.
Performance best practices can
often be found on the same YouTube
channels, for example, at 1.
hiron on documentation or by
reading just simple blogs.
So after you have your what's about.
The basics, right?
You need to change, you need to
choose your storage engines or
change them for that matter, right?
So the majority of you who will be
using MySQL or MariaDB or Percona
server or whatever you use, you're
going to be using InnoDB or ExtraDB,
which is one of the primary storage
engines available within MySQL.
And There are a couple of other
options as you can see on the screen.
There is MySAM, there is Memory, there is
CSV, there is Archive, there is Blackhole,
and if you use MariaDB, there are gonna be
a couple of other options such as Connect.
If you use Percona Server, you might
be able to see instead of InnoDB, you
maybe use ExtraDB as you can see here.
ExtraDB is essentially the same
as InnoDB, but With a couple of
enhancements choose storage engines
carefully, depending on your use case.
It's, it depends on what kind
of storage engine will you need.
Most of you for most of your use
cases will need InnoDB, but if you
really need to count the exact count
of rows within all of your tables.
Sometimes you may put mySum into the
mix, but again, I wouldn't recommend
using mySum for anything else than
just counting rows in your table
because it's not meant for that.
The only thing that it is good for is
counting rows within a table because
mySum, it stores the internal row count
of the table in its metadata, which
InnoDB does not, which is why, which is
precisely the reason why InnoDB cannot
show the exact row count of your of
the rows in your table with MySAM can.
So anyway, after you chose the storage
engine, You need to optimize the schema.
Here you need to keep in
mind a couple of principles.
Keep things simple, no matter what you're
working with, keeping things simple will
alleviate you for most of the problems.
Avoid innovating, avoid inventing new
things, inventing new stuff changing
things where this is not necessary.
Adhere to the documentation
because will answer most of
the questions that you have.
And if you have any further questions,
you can consider visiting conferences
like this one, or you can consider
asking questions on Stack Overflow.
I think they have even the DBA Stack
Exchange Forum, or whatever it's called.
And people are very active there, and
you will get your answers answered your
questions answered relatively quickly.
Now, the other thing you can do is
there is certain parameters that
you can, for example, disable, for
example, strict trans tables or strict
all tables for automated truncation.
So that means that if your data is too
long to be entered into a database,
it will be automatically truncated and
MySQL will not come back with any errors.
Again, this is not applicable for
all use cases, but Maybe for you it
is you may also choose to avoid text
values, which means that your data will
not cover as much space on the disk.
And keep in mind that also, as I said,
all data types come with essential
data space on the disk, right?
VARCHAR data types, they will occupy
most likely the length in bytes
plus one or two bytes on the disk.
And so on.
If you run bigger datasets, this is
another issue that you need to deal with.
For this thing, you need to to load data
in, you would need to avoid big overhead.
That means that you should avoid
using insert queries and using,
and use load data in file.
If possible, it has a lots of
available parameters that you can use.
As you can see on the screen, you can
set the character set, you can set
what your fields will be terminated by.
This is a typo here, it's, it should
be terminated by, lines terminated by,
or escaped by, and yada, yada, yada.
It helps your database understand what
kind of raw data you're working with.
And if you're working with raw data,
the good thing is with your database,
is that It inserts data instantly into
your database as opposed to insert
statements when they have to go through a
bunch of operations to just insert data.
They have to unlock the database,
check for data integrity, insert
data, prepare the database for
the next insert, and yada yada.
And do this for every
insert, so it takes up time.
Another thing that you
can do is partitioning.
So partitioning is very useful if you run,
for example, data breach search engines.
When you have bigger data sets, So
partitioning, in essence, what it means
is you split your table into smaller
tables that are treated as smaller
tables by your application, but your
database still sees them as a whole.
So on one level, they're treated
as, let's say, smaller tables when
you need to search through them,
but when you need to work with them,
they're still one intact table.
And this is why they are so much bigger
when you see their size on the disk.
Because if you have, for example,
five partitions your table size
will most likely be five times
bigger than ordinary size, right?
And this is why people working with
MySQL with big data sets, They often
run out of space or do something, run
out of, run into issues similar to that.
So they most likely run into issues
working with big data because one
thing they don't understand, certain
functionality of certain queries,
such as alter table which alter
table, how it works internally
is it makes a copy of the disk.
So when you need to update
data with alter table.
It makes a copy of the table on the disk,
it updates that copy, and then it swaps
the newly created table on the disk with
your original table, which means that it
most likely for tables that have a lot
of data, it will be a lot it will consume
a lot of time, basically, and if you
don't have enough space on the disk, for
example, if your table is, 200 gigabytes.
And if you have only 57 gigabytes of space
on the disk, you will run out of space.
So what some people do is instead
of running update queries when
they need to update data because
they need to run update queries
with alter table, which would make
a copy of the table on the disk.
They, in essence, make
use of the default clause.
So the default clause is used when you
create a table and you set a default
value of a column to some value.
That means, in your database's point
of view that means that one column that
you set, or more columns, whatever the
count is for you, one or more columns
has a value that is already preset.
And it doesn't need to be updated, right?
The second thing you need to keep in mind
are the character sets and collations.
So these character sets and
collations, they directly depend
on the kind of data that you are
storing in the database, right?
So if you're using, for example,
Arabic data sets, right?
So you will need to make use
of Arabic character sets.
if you're using, I don't
know, Hebrew datasets, right?
You need to make use of
Hebrew character sets.
But in most cases, you will need
to use UTF 8 MB4 Unicode CI, which
is the original form of Unicode.
And please don't use UTF because
this is not really UTF 8.
You will see because original UTF 8
with 4 bytes per character it supports
4 bytes per character, as I said, right?
But UTF 8 in MySQL, it supports only
3 bytes per character, which means
that some queries can error out.
Especially if you're working with
big data, that can be a concern.
If you add columns after, if you
add columns into a table and the
column is the last column, it will
be wise to apply some sort of hacks
called setSessionAlterAlgorithm,
which on the screen, which means
that you set the algorithm of
the alter query to instant.
And when you set the alter algorithm to
instant, the column, if it is the last
column you add to the table is added
instantly, but is and without any IO
on the disk or whatever, but it only
works in newer MariaDB versions, right?
And such hacks can be found all across
the documentation and all across
Stack Overflow, so please look around.
So after you optimize your data for
MySQL or your MySQL for big data,
whatever is around you also need
to backup your bigger datasets.
Backing up 1 billion rows in
MySQL isn't a very useful task
and isn't a very easy task.
So let's say it like that, because
MySQL dump, it likely won't work.
It will back up your datasets and
you will be able to restore them.
But the first thing that's going
to happen is your file will
going to be exceedingly large.
And the second thing this is
going to happen is that the time
that you need to recover the data
will also be out of proportion.
Like you will need to wait a week,
two weeks, three weeks, or even a
month, or even your query will even
timeout because, the second thing
you need to take into account is
that the backups have multiple types.
They can be physical,
which means that you.
Take backups of physical
files within your database.
They can be logical, which means that
you take backups of queries, recreate
data inside of your database and so on.
But with big data sets, the
problem is that these things,
they all come with overhead.
And basically to avoid that, you need
to make use of queries like select
into out file and load data in file.
These two queries, in essence,
they back up raw data sets.
So select into out file will in
essence select every row in a table
and load it into a file, which for the
first part is significantly smaller
than files with logical backups.
That is with INSERT, INTO statements,
CREATE TABLE statements, whatever.
And LOADDATA and FILE will be used
to load the data into a database.
Backups taken with SELECT, INTO, OUT
file and backed up with LOADDATA and FILE
have significantly less overhead than
those taken with logical MySQL dumps.
So this is something you
need to keep in mind.
In In some cases, you also need to
keep in mind some advanced features
such as the default clause can be
used in place of an update clause
sometimes, as I mentioned before, right?
If you need to use a unique index, that
means that if you need to get rid of some
values in a column, And that column is
pretty large that that means that MySQL
again will have to make use of the Altar
query, which in essence copies your data
into another table and then swaps it over.
To avoid all this, you can
use unique sort features.
That means that you in essence
run Linux or Cygwin on Windows.
And then load your data into a
text file using the same select
into out file or whatever.
And then basically utilize sort unique,
sort with a unique flag, and then
specify your file into some other file.
And this command that you can see on your
screen right now is, it will it will drop
all of the duplicates from that file.
So in essence, you will load into your
database the data without duplicates.
You can sometimes use insert ignore
instead of insert, which means that you
will ignore some errors or all errors
that may occur when inserting data.
That may be useful when you're
inserting into some columns
instead of all columns or whatever.
And you can also delete data according
to time periods if it's necessary.
So if you use, for example, queries like
delete from something for a portion of
time period, from this to that, it will
also delete rows relatively quickly.
Also, you can make use of the truncate
clause, which means that in essence,
your table will be truncated, which
means in other words, all rows
within that table will be deleted.
And such queries are significantly
faster than using the delete clause
because they don't come with as much
overhead for your database as well.
And the last thing that you need to keep
in mind is that if you use the InnoDB
storage engine, you are able to kill
queries using the show process list query.
So if you, for example, if you run a
Databricks search engine if you run a
Databricks search engine and someone,
and you forgot to rate limit, let's say,
or do something like that, and someone,
some genius decides to run 10 million
queries at once, and your application
obviously lags out because there is a
lot of strain on the database, you can
use InnoDB to basically show the queries,
use queries like show process list, They
will return the IDs of the queries that
are currently running in the database
and then you can just kill them one
by one or just all of them at once by
using kill statement named kill and then
ID and then your query will be killed
killed no longer exist in the database
and then you can, your application will
be less laggy and then you can implement
your load balancers, your rate limiters,
whatever, and then you can go on.
The tools that you may
need to use is are varied.
The most likely tool most useful
tool for your use case will be you
yourself because nobody knows your
database better than you, right?
If you run a MariaDB also has tools such
as MariaDB Secure Installation, MySQL
Secure Installation, there's a symlink.
And these tools will walk you through
a couple of things that you may need
to do to secure your database instance.
And if your queries are slow, MariaDB and
MySQL have such things as The slow query
log that you, it logs all slow queries,
advanced users of MySQL will also know
that there is such thing as the MySQL
enterprise edition, which in essence is
enterprise edition of MySQL, which is
a firewall and an audit appliance, if I
remember correctly, it costs thousands
of dollars, if I remember correctly, but
But it lets you further secure MySQL.
Aside from the Enterprise Edition,
there's tools like DbVisualizer, ArcType,
which is now a part of ClickHouse.
There's RedGate Monitor, there's
ClusterControl by several
nines, and et cetera, et cetera.
So these things, some of them
act as SQL clients, for example,
DbVisualizer and ArcType.
Some of them act as, double as SQL
editors, the same DbVisualizer, right?
They let you edit your data
as if it was a spreadsheet.
Some of you monitor, some of them monitor
other things and et cetera, et cetera.
So aside from using tools there's
such thing as a Schrodinger's
paradox that you may be, maybe
heard of, and maybe not heard of.
So in the database world there is
such thing as a data definition files,
which is FRM files, which you can see
on the screen and then the data files.
So FRM files, in essence, they.
They contain information about
the data files, and the data
files contain the data itself.
In some situations, in very rare
situations, if you insert bigger
datasets into MySQL, and your, for
example, electricity goes out, you may
be able to see that your data file is
missing, but the FRAM file still exists.
And that will be the case of
the Schrodinger's Paradox, where
Your database sees the table
existing, but you cannot drop it.
In order to drop it, you need to most
likely shut down the database instance.
You can just add the data file to your
data directory and the database in
question, and then just drop it like that.
And there's a bunch of other
ways, but I will not get into that
because we simply don't have time.
But thank you.
So this was my speech and this was the
things I learned and I wanted to share
when working with billions of rows and
bigger data sets in MySQL and MariaDB.
And I would be very grateful if you could
share some feedback of my, from our talk.
That is on my website slash feedback.
So lucasvilleacres.
com slash feedback.
It will direct you to a
Google form, which you can.
Which I would ask you to fill out,
it takes one or two minutes, and then
I will see if I am a good speaker or
not, and what I can improve, and so on.
And also, I would suggest you to
visit my website, breachdirectory.
com, to in essence check if you
are at risk of identity theft.
Put your email address into the
data breach search engine, and
it will run a search through a
bunch of known data breaches.
And the return with results.
Aside from that keep in touch with the
documentation, blogs, database, YouTube
channels, such as Database Dive and
so on, and you should be good to go.
So thank you so much for watching.
I hope you enjoyed this talk and I hope
you will enjoy upcoming talks as well.
Thank you.