Hello, my name is Community.
I'm working as a senior
manager at Micro Technologies.
I'm a leading, I'm leading team
of student developers who support
enterprise applications such as Team
Center, rapid Response and building
RPA tools, using UiPath, robotic
process automations, and our team also.
Includes dashboard development
using Power BI and Tableau.
Today I'm going to discuss about how,
why, how, and why we should build
scalable platforms for developers
in general.
Engineering teams spent around like
40% of their time on the infrastructure
tasks, especially for deployments.
60% of this time can be reduced
using integrated development
platform engineering tools and
IDPs also helps us to increase
our delivery rate by three times.
So typical key challenges
in platform engineering.
Looks like they have disconnected tools
with inefficiencies and lot of repetitive.
Manual tasks, and we always need
to upgrade our skillset because
this requests special knowledge
and lack of standardization
also causes quality issues and
knowledge gaps for any tool.
We always have resistance
to adapt especially for new
platforms and workflows.
It's always difficult to scale
the teams, especially when
we have multi-skilled teams.
In addition to that, there are overbearing
issues with respect to complexity
of softwares, especially when we
are using microservice architectures
and multi clouds deployments.
So today every company is using
multiple clouds, including AWS.
Azure or any kind of leading cloud
deployment and complex dependency
management distributor system challenges.
These are all related to all
the complexity of softwares.
In addition to that, developers
has lot of issues with respect
to inconsistent workflows, a lot
of infrastructure dependencies.
Standardization problems, all these
things leading to cognitive overheads.
So this sentence reduces the productivity
and increases the time to market.
So platform engineering
integrated platform engineering
solves these problems.
All the challenges by creating
internal development platforms,
we call it as I, dps.
So always focuses on the developers.
They, we want to give some
time back to developers.
So developers, we need to think
about fitting them in the driver's
seat wherever it is possible.
These IDPs helps us to automate
manual tasks, which can reduce
tasks and it all these IDPs comes
with clear APIs and interfaces.
They have, they also comes with
lot of services and workflows,
prebuilt services and workflows.
Because IDP is also platform engineering.
Tools also comes with lot of metrics
where we can use the metrics to
adapt, increase the efficiency, and
also in term like we can increase the
developer development satisfaction.
So core components in the
platform engineering starts with
self-service infrastructure.
It's a key component for IDPs, which
will help to reduce the wait time, remove
the bottlenecks, they'll improve the
teams, empower the teams, and reduce the
deployment complexities by 60% or more.
So integrated toolkit is a core
component which has key components
such as version control, security
scanning, performance testing, compliance
checks and deployment automations.
They helps in increasing the productivity
and develop developer components
like I mentioned earlier.
Observability and monitoring frameworks.
This is a key factor for platform
engineering, which comes with logging
metrics, traces, and also some of the
advanced capabilities like how to detect
the anomalies, interactive visualization
and proactive alerting with automation.
So here are the best industry,
best platform engineering tools
like, like I mentioned earlier,
each component has its own flavors.
So self-service infrastructure,
Kubernetes, Terraform, omi, cross plan.
These are the tools widely used for
CICD, Argo C Teton, GitHub actions,
Jenkins X. These are the tools managers
for CICD, for observability, especially
for metrics, parameters, Grafana,
open Telemetry, Datadog, other tools
for incident and service management.
Backstage, human tech query are the tools.
And finally, for security, we
can use vault OPA and sync.
So what are the strategies we
should use for implementing?
So for develop, for developers
centric, we need to follow the best
practices, a PA design following
the A PA design principles and
command line tools for automations.
So establishing metrics, this is
a key 'cause we need to monitor
active users and deployments
time and how much platform usage.
In addition to that, we should
monitor productivity metrics
and satisfaction metrics.
So
another strategy is.
Creating feedback loops.
So we should be analyzing the,
collecting the data usage data errors,
performance metrics, gather the feedback,
analyze the patterns, and identify the
improvements, and we should communicate
the plan to gain the confidence.
Finally, we need to deliver
the improvements based
on the constant feedback.
So this is a cycle we need to continue.
To evolve in the platform
engineering implementations.
So now I'm going to explain
about few success stories.
The first story is
about e-commerce change.
The biggest challenge they faced up
is like how to scale up the team.
So they build the platform in
engineering tool by building the
platform, focusing on provisioning
standard development environment.
Integrated CICD pipeline
automation and centralized
observator observability metrics.
So this helped this e-commerce chain.
They increased the feature velocity
by three times and they reduced the
production bug by 75% and they have fewer
deployment failures and that improved
60% of their deployment failures.
Pure deployment failures.
Of course, it comes up with
the developer satisfaction.
The next success story is
financial services firm.
So they struggle with operational
overheads, manual security reviews, audit
trials, and change management processes.
They create a lot of bottlenecks and they
delayed the future religious by month.
So that's a good challenge they have.
So they developed the platform
by embedding complaints, enabling
automated security and policy
as a code implementation.
They adapted and self-service
provisioning, which helped
them to available on demand.
Finally, the register overhead by
50% and improved the time to market.
And less security incidents.
The third success story is with the
technology startup by enabling golden
parts in the ideas and by automating
onboarding and technology flexibility.
The startup company scaled from
10 to hundred users, and this
is achieved by investing in the
platform engineering early in the.
Growth journey.
Okay.
Lot of times we have the confusion
about platform engineering, DevOps,
and software relat engineering.
So here are the key differences.
Platform engineering main goal
is to build internet development
platforms to make it consistent.
Whereas DevOps focuses on the bridging the
gap between development and operations.
Software Reliability engineering focuses
on the reliability of the software.
And there are different tools
in the market and different
metrics for each section.
So like I outlined here, like platform
engineering focuses on the productivity
and adoption, whereas SRE focuses
on uptime and latency, and DevOps
focuses on MTTR and deploy frequencies.
So these DI disciplines.
Often overlap, but they
have distant focus.
Okay.
What is the future of how is
how this platform engineering
is going to evolve in future?
The biggest challenge currently
is how can we how can we work
on the multi-cloud environments?
So basically enabling workload
portability between the cloud providers.
If we can achieve that
is the biggest success.
I think things are
going in that direction.
The next biggest thing is lot of
Gene and a agent DK Innovations.
They helps this platform engineering in
big way, cell LMS for code generation,
intelligent automation, robotic process
automation, predictive analysis.
So that looks promising
for future innovation.
And finally.
These tools should move beyond reactive
operations to proactive capacity planning.
So that way we can sustainably
impact, we can do, make sustainable
impact on the platform operations.
Okay?
How do we build platform engineering?
And what are the strategies
we should be using?
First and foremost, we need to
have clear vision of the future and
understand the problem statement.
Always start with a narrow scope,
then we can scale it up and focus on
building the team with unique skillset
by using the observability metrics,
constantly measure the success and
evolve continuously and keep on getting
feedback from developers to innovate
the key, key takeaways.
From the platform engineering
perspective is it's no.
It is complexity of
today's software ecosystem.
It is demanding the need
of platform engineering.
Successful platforms prioritize
on the developer needs.
They establish clear metrics for
adoption and increase the productivity.
As I mentioned earlier.
Always start with narrow
scope and scale it.
Finally, platform engineering
is not an optional anymore.
It is a foundation for software
excellence given the direction
of future citizen development and
lot of, non code environments.
Thank you.