Hello.
Hi everyone.
Good afternoon.
it's pleasure to be here today.
My session is about very exiting
area, using the blockchain technology
to reinvent master data management.
Where does this matter?
Because master data is like a patient
identities in healthcare or customer, and
the product data in enterprise systems is
a backbone of all the digital operations.
If this foundation is insecure and
consistent and reliable, everything
build on top of it becomes fragile.
In my role at LabCorp, I have worked
hands-on with these challenges and I
will show how we solve them by combining
the blockchain with the enterprise MBM.
By the end, you will see how
the distributed, immutable, and
encrypted platforms can transform
enterprise data management.
What are the traditional MDM chart
data consistency issues with the
traditional MDM and the security
vulnerabilities and performance
bottleneck in compliance complexity.
Traditional MDM started simple,
mostly as a database Consolidation
are data consolidation.
But modern enterprises operates across
multiple geographies and multiple
clouds and dges of the applications.
That creates four big pain
points, data consistency.
The if the two systems update, the
customer recorded the same time, you
often get the conflicts are drift.
Second is security.
Centralized.
MDM is a huge target, one breach.
under the attacker controls
all the master data.
Then the third one is,
which is performance.
As a data grows exponentially,
systems slows down.
And the fourth one, final one
is compliance competencies.
regulated industries like
healthcare and finance, requests,
detailed audit trails and lineage.
Most legacy systems will these
futures on or afterwards.
So she makes them fragile.
These challenges show us
why we need new foundation.
Blockchain is for mainly four
categories, immutability and
consensus driven updates, and built in
cryptographic security and transparency.
Blockchain directly addresses
these four pain points.
First one is immutability
means that once, once data is
started, it can be tampered with.
That is automatic.
Second one is consensus means that no
single system decides multiple nodes
must agree before the data changes, which
removes the single points of the failure.
The third one is built in security
through cryptography, ensures
authenticity and confidentiality.
And final one is transparency.
Every participant can see and
verify the state of the data.
In short, blockchains DNA is natural
fit for the problems of MDM faces today.
In traditional systems, this
means keeping the logs and backups
and complex access monitoring.
but in the blockchain,
immutability is built in.
Once the transaction is written, it's
mathematically locked into the chain.
If anyone tries to change it, the system
will reject it because the cryptographic
ash no longer matches these turns audit
trails from the complex manual process
into something automatic under tramp
proof consensus is about the agreement.
In centralized system.
The database administrator or single
system can approve the changes.
That's a convenient but risky act.
With the blockchain, multiple independent
nodes must agree on the change.
We use a practical Biogen time
fault tolerance mechanism, which
can tolerate even third, one.
Third of the nodes being
compromised, still remain reliable.
This critical for.
Resilience.
It means the platform can withstand
failures and cyber attacks
are insider threats and skill.
Deep data, trustworthy.
Every transaction is signed with a digital
signature, sadly, who performed it.
Data is encrypted both in
the rest and in the transit.
So that's much stronger and simple
than managing thousands of individual
keys in short securities over
into the fabric of the system.
Transparency is about the trust
in many industries and disputes
arise because each party maintains
their own version of the truth.
For example, in supply chains, one
partner might claim and update.
Was made while another
says that it wasn't.
With the blockchain, everyone who has
access to see sees the same verified
ledger that reduces the disputes,
increases the collaboration, and builds
confidence across teams and organizations.
Transparency doesn't mean loss of privacy.
Data is encrypted, but the fact
that the transaction is happened
is visual to authorize parties.
Hyperledger Fabric is the one
of the thing, and attribution
based encryption is another one.
IPFS is for large storage, large
data storage, and work to J-W-T-T-L-S
1.3 for the modern security.
So we build our MDM platform
only carefully selected.
Stack at the core is a Hyperledger
FA fabric, a permissioned blockchain.
Ideal for enterprise use
for fine-grained access.
We use attribute waste encryption, which
enforces the policy, set the data level
for storage, large data objects, going
to IPFS and a PPP two P file system.
And while the blockchain only keeps
the cryptographic fingerprints.
of those files keeping
the ledger efficient.
Finally, we secure everything with modern
protocols or the two for authentication.
The WTS for session management,
TLS 1.34, encrypted communication.
Together, these technologies give
us both power and practicality.
Our architecture is layered, for the
clarity and the scalability at the top.
Presentation layer exposes the
rest and drop graph ql APAs
Enterprises can integrate easily.
The next one is application layer.
It contains the business logic
in the form of smart contracts,
what Hyperledger calls chain code.
And the con layer, con sense layer
ensures the agreement using the PFBT and
the data layer combines the blockchain
metadata, IPFF, IP IPFS payloads and the
ready caches for the for fast retrieval.
And at the base infrastructure layer runs.
On the Kubernetes clusters across the
availability dunes for the failover and
the scaling, each layer specialized,
but together they form a resilient hole.
We didn't jump straight into production
in the phase one, we built a proof
of concept, which is basically
crowd operations, consensus testing
and performance benchmarking that
validated the blockchain potential.
In phase two, we.
Piloted with the real workloads and
developing smart contracts and the
optimizing throughput, we also deployed
the attribute based encryption.
Finally in the phase three phase of
production, building infrastructure
as a code, and setting up monitoring
with the different tools and
designing disaster recovery processes.
And this strategy changed the
journey, minimized the risks, and
ensure the enterprise readiness.
3090 9.9 percentage, 60 percentage.
The results are enter, enterprise grade.
Our platform processes, or the 3000
transactions per second delivers
99.9 percentage of time and includes
the data access by 60 percentage.
But the performance only the part of the
inventory compliance is automated and
smart contracts enforce retention policies
and every change is logged immutably.
In short, we didn't just
match the traditional MDM.
We exceeded in this, in scale and
reliability and trustworthiness.
Security implementation.
How, security implemented in
defense, in depth a S 2 56 at
rest and the TLS 1.3 in transit.
We protect the data at two levels,
a s 2 56 encryption for storage and
TLS 1.3 for all the communication.
This ensures both the stored and
the transmitted data for secure.
And the second one is digitals.
Every transaction is digitally signed
and so we know what exactly who
performed it and can be prevent further
remediation and zero knowledge proofs.
And for highly institute
operations we use.
Zero knowledge proofs.
This lets someone to prove
they are authorized without
revealing the actual data.
It's a security without
flexible or, exposure.
Instead of static rules, we use
the attributes based encryption.
For example, only doctors with oncology
specialization and active license can
access the oncology data policies drive
access, not the manual permissions.
The second one is dynamic
policy evaluation.
Access is evaluated in, if
someone's status is changed,
their access changes instantly.
No manual updates are needed.
Immutable,
all access events are logged immutably
on the blockchain preventing that,
providing the regulator Reg Regulat
with the tamper proof Oddity system.
Third one is to treat me medication.
DDOS protection.
We use multi-level rare limiting
and failover to observe the of the
service attempts without downtime.
Insider threat prevention.
The second one is in
insider threat prevention.
No single administrator can override
the system because the blockchain
requests distributed consensus.
even insider attacks are prevented.
The third one is data leakage prevention.
We integrated enterprise gate DLP tools
to stop the unauthorized data extraction,
adding it another layer of the safety.
Data retention policies is the
automated compliance framework.
Within that data retention policies,
the smart contracts automatically
enforce the retention rules.
No manual cleanups, no mis deadlines.
Then the second one is comprehensive
access, logging, even accesses
logged mutable on the blockchain,
creating a reliable audit trail.
And the third one is
complete data lineage.
We can trace the data across,
its entire life cycle.
Who created it, who modified
it where it is used?
Suppose the right to be forgotten
with the cryptographic deletion,
then HIPAA compliance and enhance it.
Protection for the sensitive
health information such compliance,
building suppression of the duties,
ensuring financial accountabilities.
Blue green deployments.
We run two identical production
in environment side by side.
When the updates are needed, we switch
the traffic from blue to green, ensuring
the zero downtime, and then cany.
Religious new smart contracts are deployed
fast to the small subset of the no.
If issues appears, we can roll back
automatically before the problem spreads.
Then future flags.
Third one is future flags.
We can turn the futures on or
off selectively in production.
This lets us test the real world
behavior without putting the entire
system at risk monitoring and
observability the CPU and memory and
disc, and the network access for all.
No.
And predictor Analytics helps us
spot problems before they cause the
outages and application metrics.
The second one is application metrics.
We measure the transaction throughput,
latency, error rates, and business KPAs.
Then the third one is block saying
basic metrics, and we monitor the
consensus participation and blockchain
propagation times and chain growth
rates to ensure the ledger itself.
Is running smoothly.
Incident response, how the
incidents are tracked and how the
incidents responses are captured.
Automated detection, machine learning and
anatomy detection, smart detection spot,
usually, activity escalation procedures.
We have clear escalation paths
and automated notifications.
The right people are elected quickly.
Support motion buses post process.
Every incident is thoroughly
analyzed and lessons are added to
our runbooks and making the systems
smarter and stronger over the time.
And to conclude the future data management
is distributed, encrypted, and immutable.
Blockchain based MDM
is no longer a theory.
It's running in production
today, solving real challenges.
It gives the enterprises safe.
Platform that is faster, more
secure, more compliant than
the legacy systems at LabCorp.
This journey has just begin, but the
results already show the tremendous value.
I hope today's session give you
very clear picture that way the
blockchain D matters, and how it can
help your organizations build res
resilient future ready data platforms.
Thank you.