Hello everyone.
Good morning or good evening,
depending on your location.
I am TU and I have 23 years of
experience in data engineering, AI and
a ML. Cloud Technologies, enterprise
bi, and in manufacturing industries.
It is a pleasure to be here at
Platform Engineering Conference.
Today I'm going to take you through
the journey of building scalable AI ML
platform for industrial iot, specifically
through a cloud native approach for
predictive maintenance infrastructure.
This session combines of my 23 years
of experience in enterprise school data
platform with real world lessons from
industrial transformation projects.
Let's get started.
Here is the agenda for today's conference.
The industrial iot landscape.
Challenges and opportunities evolving
from reactive to predictive maintenance.
The business use case for ai, ML
powered maintenance core architectural
patterns for iot platform success.
Cloud native platform
components for industrial iot
edge computing integrations.
ML Pipeline orchestration for predictive
maintenance developer experience,
enabling data science team case
studies for multi-site manufacturing
implementation roadmap, and key
takeaway for platform engineers.
The industrial IOT landscape,
challenges and opportunities
industrial iot has transformed how
manufacturing environment operates.
In industrial iot, we see 1.52,
2.3 data bytes of daily sensor
data is flowing from distributed
sites, each with mix of device.
Protocol and requirements.
The opportunity here is huge, but
the challenges are from unifying
heterogeneous data stream to
meeting strict uptime requirement.
Our mission as a platform engineer is
to turn this raw data into actionable
intelligence while keeping the
enterprise system reliability intact.
Evolving from reactive to
predictive maintenance.
Here we have four types of maintenance,
reactive scheduled maintenance,
conditional based maintenance.
Finally, AI driven predictive maintenance.
Let's start with reactive maintenance.
Traditionally, reactive maintenance has
been fixing the things after they file,
which needs more downtime and unplanned
production disruptions will cost you
more than it came Schedule maintenance.
Which is often meant fixing too early or
too late, which is also not best practice.
Next is conditional base maintenance.
Maintenance, which improve
the things, but still lack of
foresight and some limitations
are there in this method as well.
The final only is AI driven.
Predictive maintenance
is the game changer.
It's giving you eight to 10.
12 days of advanced warning with
almost 90% prediction accuracy.
But to get there, we need infrastructures
that supports this evolution and
helps organizational changes both
technologically as well as culturally,
the business use case for AI
powered predictive maintenance.
Here are the game changing results.
Downtime reduction.
Ines implementing AI driven maintenance
have reported 50% reduction in downtime,
which is half the machine offline time
compared to before return on investment.
Perhaps most impressive is
385% return on investment.
These projects don't just play themselves,
they multiply the value delivered.
Next is.
Predict prediction accuracy.
Model M and models can predict equipment
failure with 89%, 89.7% accuracy.
This means engineers and operators
can get clear, timely, alert.
The last is early.
Warning alert, these models can provide
eight to 12 days of advanced warning,
which is critical for planning downtime
and avoiding production disruptions.
This aren't just nice to have a metrics.
This trans, they translate directly
into operational and financial win.
That is why 60% of industrial
manufacturing or investing in
predictive maintenance platform.
Here.
The question is, how do
we build them at scale
core architectural pattern
for iot platform success?
It start with architectural
choice, multi-tier processing.
Use edge device for quick real-time
decisions, and then use cloud for
deeper and more complex analysis.
Sometimes mix of both.
Hybrid is the best to balance
speed and heavy workloads.
Second is even driven architectures
instead of waiting in a line,
data is handled as even happens.
This lets systems smoothly manage
challenges, data volumes, and
unexpected, sudden surge of many
sensors, auto-scaling infrastructures.
Kubernetes driven elastic city
for peak loads, which means system
dynamically can scale up or scale
down to match the demand and workload.
The last one is distributed
storage strategies.
This keeps, data is different layer.
Hot storage for faster access to
real-time A and cold storage for
keeping older historical data used
in a training and long-term analysis.
These patents provide the backbone
of the scalable resilience platform,
cloud native platform
component for industrial iot.
From ingestion to association,
every layers matters.
Let's start with data addition layer.
It connects machines and sensor using
standard protocol like O-P-C-U-A-M-Q-T,
and Modbus and stream streams data
with tools like Kafka and puls.
Next is storage and processing layer.
Source sensor data in time series database
and large scale data lakes like Snowflake
and Databricks ML orchestration layer.
It automates model training with tools
like Cube flow or ML flow, and manages
reusable features in features stores.
The last is application layer.
It provide graphical QL, API and
rest a PA for data access and powered
real time dashboard with alerts.
The key is loose coupling so that
each layer can evolve independently,
each computing integrations.
Bringing AI to the source, one
of the most powerful enable.
Enabler here is edge computing.
Here are the some key
benefits of edge computing.
Critical alerts are handled up to
75 to 80% quicker only important
data is sent for reducing network.
Network load and bandwidth
systems keeps working.
Even if the internet connectivity
drops, press pre-processing edge.
We'll cut down the expense of cloud usage.
Next is platform engineer considerations.
Deploy ML model efficiently on the device
with limited memory and processing power.
Update edge device remotely
without manual inter intervention.
Ensure data is exchanged safely
using mutual authentication
and secure communication.
Keep the data consistent between
edge device and the cloud.
Even unreliable connections.
Even with unreliable connections.
The ultimate goal is here, seamless
data flow between Edge and the cloud.
Cloud platform.
ML Pipeline orchestration
for predictive maintenance.
Predictive maintenance is not
just about the models, it is about
the full lifecycle development.
Start with data collections, gather
the real-time mission signals
such as vibrations, temperatures,
pressure, et cetera, from iot sensor.
Second is processing clean,
normalize and extract meaningful
patterns from raw sensor data.
Third is train the ML model.
Use historical data to build algorithm
that predict occupant failures for this
validation against real world failure.
Test the model predictions against actual
breakdown events to ensure accuracy.
Fifth deployment into production.
Integrate the model into live
system for real time failure.
Productions prediction.
Last one is monitoring continuous,
continuously track the accuracy,
data drift and retain when
the performance declines.
Automation, observability and
governance needs to be built.
Every stage.
Developer experience
enabling data science team.
Data scientists should focus on
the model, not on the plumbing.
That means self-service infrastructure
give the data scientist on demand access
to scalable compute, storage and tools
without waiting on operation teams.
Next is automated CICD for ml.
Streamline the model development
with pipeline, that auto test version
control and auto deploy ML code.
Last one is manage the feature stores.
It provides centralized, reusable system
for consistent feature engineering
across training and production systems.
Yes, strong developer experience
accelerate adoption and productivity
while maintaining the governance.
Case studies, multi-site, multi-site
manufacturing implementations.
Let me bring this to life with some
real time use case studies, a global
manufacturer with 37 facilities
and 12 different equipment vendor,
and a major downtime challenges.
Our platform solution is
to use the hybrid cloud.
Which is AWS and Azure architecture,
snowflake analytics, cube flow
pipeline, and the custom adapters
Here are the end results.
43, 42 times 40, 42%.
Downtime reduction, 4.3 million.
Annual saving, 93% model deployment
success rate, and a 2.5 times
productivity boost for data science team.
Implementation roadmap for
platform evolutionary strategy.
We approach this in different phases.
First, to start with foundations,
it takes three to four months
of connectivity, building basic
pipeline, and data governance.
Second ML deployment, it takes
two to three months for feature
engineering training and initial
deployment scale and optimize.
This process takes four to six
months of edge integration, advanced
automation, enterprise integrations.
Last one is enterprise.
Expansion.
This is ongoing process platform as
a service offering multi-site ana
analytics and continuous evaluations.
This phased strategy delivers value early
while building towards full maturity.
Here are some key for platform
engineers, architecture matters, design
end-to-end system that simultaneously
handle data from sensor to insight,
ensuring scalability, resilience,
and edge and cloud integrations.
Next is developer experience
drives adoption, provide a
simple and secure abstractions.
So that data science scientists
can focus on the models without
wrestling with infrastructure team.
Last one is incremental wins,
which means start small scale.
Small meaning begin with small,
which has a high return on investment
use case, and then scale globally
using model modular platform that.
Adopt to new needs and technologies.
The most successful platform aren't
just a technical achievement.
They are enabler of organizational
transformation from reactive
to predictive operations.
Thank you for time today.
I look forward for your questions
and discussions about how
we can shape the future for
predictive maintenance together.
See you later.
Bye.