Hello everyone.
My name is Pastor Gole and I am
a software engineer at Google.
Today I'll be presenting a talk on
building bulletproof AI systems from
container kiosk to production paradise.
The journey is often described as a
nightmare a chaotic world of containers,
configurations, and last minute fires.
We are here to change that narrative.
In this session we'll explore
how to transform that deployment
narrative into a production paradise.
We'll look at battle tested
architectural patents that will help
you build bulletproof AI platforms that
actually deliver on their promises.
Let's start by acknowledging the
reality of enterprise AI deployment.
Many organizations, despite
their best effort, run into
significant hurdles that lead.
To delays and even project failures.
These challenges generally
fall into three categories.
The first is environment inconsistencies.
We have all heard it like,
but it works on my machine.
This syndrome leads to the
unpredictable behavior.
When models move from a data
scientist laptop to a staging or a
production environment, inconsistent
libraries, dependencies, and even
hard work can cause the morals to
behave different or fail entirely.
The next are the manual
deployment processes.
These are often error prone, incredibly
time consuming, and create bottlenecks.
They frequently rely on specialized
knowledge of a few key individuals.
If that person is on vacation, good
luck deploying that critical update.
And finally, this leads to the production
fires those late night emergencies caused
by unforeseen discrepancies between
what was tested and what is now live.
These fires not only burn out our
teams, but also erode confidence
in the AI initiatives themselves.
The result is a deployment cycle that
stretches from days into works, or
even months drastically diminishing
the returns of our AI system.
So what does a production
paradise look like?
Leading organizations have already
transformed their AI deployment
processes and the results are dramatic.
Success isn't just about avoiding failure.
It's about creating a streamlined,
efficient, and reliable system.
Imagine reducing your model deployment
time from weeks to may hours.
Think about cutting configuration drifts.
And errors by as much as 80%.
This is achievable.
We are talking about true deployment
to production parity, which eliminates
those nasty late night surprises.
Furthermore, success means having
scalable infrastructure that grows with
demand without breaking your budget.
It means empowering your data scientists
with a self-service platforms,
allowing them to innovate faster.
All while maintaining the governance
and control the business needs.
This is the paradise we are aiming for.
Okay, now let's look at what the
session mode map will look like.
How did we get here?
I have structured our journey
today into four key parts.
This is your part to AI platform success.
First, we'll dive into
containerization strategies.
Specifically help ER and Kubernetes can
eliminate environment inconsistencies.
Next, we will cover infrastructure as
core patterns using Terraform and help
to prevent my configuration drifts.
Then we'll explore GitHub's workflows
to automate our pipelines and
make them version and trustworthy.
Finally, we'll look at
real world ROI data.
From organizations that have successfully
implemented these patterns at scale,
our foundation begins
with containerization.
This is what solves the classic.
It works on my machine problem
by unpacking and packaging our
models with all their dependencies,
libraries, and runtime configurations
into a single portable unit.
But AI workloads have unique needs.
That generalization approaches
often don't address.
We need to think about GPU acceleration
and access to other specialized hardware.
We are often dealing with very large model
artifacts that can be gigabytes in size,
which has implications for image storage
and memory requirements, and our inference
and scaling patterns are often very
difficult from traditional web services.
The impact of getting this right is huge.
As a principal, Mr. Engineer at Forbes
500 financial services company, put
it containerization, reduces our model
deployment failure by 65% and eliminates
an entire class of environment rated bugs.
This is the power of a solid
container foundation To build on that
foundation, we need to use docker
patterns that are optimized for ai.
Let's look at three key ones.
First, multi-stage builds.
This involves using separate development
and production stages in a Docker file.
This results in the much smaller,
more secure final image, leading to
faster pools, a reduced attack surface,
and lower resource consumption.
Second, the hardware aware base images.
Don't use a generic base
image for everything.
Use Cuda enabled base images.
Especially for your GPU workloads
to get maximum performance for
CPU based inference services,
use CPU optimized images.
This simple step can drastically
improve performance and minimize cost.
And the third, a smart
layer caching strategy.
Structure your DOC files to
maximize build cash hits.
This means placing stable dependencies
like system packages at the beginning
of the file and frequently changing code
like your model artifacts towards the end.
Together.
These patterns significantly reduce
image size and build times accelerating
then entire development cycle.
Once we have a optimized containers,
we need a way to manage the mat scale.
This is where Kubernetes comes up.
A Kubernetes provides an orchestration
layer that makes our contained rise.
AI deployments truly
production ready kuban it is.
Gives us powerful capabilities
like horizontal part auto scaling.
This allows us to automatically scale
our inference services based on CPU
Memory, our even custom metrics, like the
number of prediction requests per second.
This ensures we have the capacity to
meet demand without over provisioning
resources for our expensive hardware.
We can use GPU, no pools
and resource quotas.
This allows us to efficiently and
fairly allocate these costly GPU
resources across multiple teams and
workloads, ensuring maximum utilization.
Finally, Kubernetes enables
advanced deployment strategies
like can redeployments.
We can gradually roll out our new
model versions to a small subset of
users, monitor their performance.
And then proceed with a full
rollout, significantly reducing
the risk of a bad deployment.
Now let's move to an next pillar
infrastructure as a code or I-A-C-I-A-C
transform your AI platform and
from a fragile, manually configured
snowflake system into a reproducible
version, controlled and automated one.
The key benefit is environment parity.
With IEC, you can create identical
deployments, development, testing,
and production environments
with a click of a button.
Eliminating the it works in dev surprises.
IEC is also your key to
boost disaster recovery.
If an outage occurs, you can rebuild
the entire platform, reducing
downtime from days to hours.
It also ensures consistent compliance
and governance by allowing you.
B to implement security controls
and access patterns as code applied
uniformly across all departments.
Terraform patterns for AI
infrastructure is very important
when implementing IESE for ai.
Terraform is a fantastic tool.
Let's look at three battle
tested Terraform patterns.
First, a module based architecture.
Instead of writing monolithic
configurations, define reusable
infrastructure modules for common
air components like model, race,
inference, clusters, or feature stores.
This promotes consistency, accelerates
development, and simplifies maintenance.
Second, a clear environment
pro promotion strategy.
Use separate directories or
terraform workspaces to manage
your different environments.
This ensures that.
Identical configurations
are applied consistently.
As you promote changes through your
CI slash CD pipelines, minimizing
discrepancies and critically
use remote state management.
Use your Terraform State files in a remote
shared location, like an S3 bucket, or
Google storage with locking enabled.
This is crucial for team
collaboration, prevents corruption
and maintain an authoritative
record of your infrastructure.
Configuration.
Always ensure encryption and versioning
are enabled for security and auditability.
This brings us to GitHubs,
which ties everything together.
GitHubs transform our manual.
Deployment processes into fully
automated auditable workflows by making
GI the central hub of our operations.
The key component are simple but powerful.
Git becomes a single source of
truth for both infrastructure
and applications configurations.
We use pull based deployment operators
like Argo CD or Flux that automatically
sync the cluster state with what's defined
in gi and we have continuous verification.
That detects and remedies and
drifts from the desired state.
The enterprise benefits are immense.
We see an 80% reduction in deployment
time and a complete audit trail for
compliance, self-healing architecture
that maintains its desired state
and simplified rollbacks, just
you just revert a get command.
Simple.
So what does this all
mean for your business?
The return on investment is tangible
and significant organizations
adopting these patterns have seen
an 85% reduction in deployment time.
For complex AI workloads moving from weeks
to hours, they have experienced 73% fewer
production incidents due to environment,
consistency and automated testing.
We have achieved 40% infrastructure
cost saving through better resource
utilization and auto scaling.
And perhaps most importantly,
they have been able to get three
times more models into production,
dramatically increasing the throughput
and impact of AI delivery pipelines.
I want to leave with a clear, actionable
plan to get started on this one.
Here's a 30 day plan for some quick ones.
Start with by contain rising
one high value AI workload
using multi-stage docker build.
Establish basic Terraform modules for
your key infrastructure components,
and set up GitHub's repository
to manage configurations and
automate your initial deployments.
From there, you can accelerate
towards production readiness
within 90 day transformation plan.
Implement Kubernetes
clusters with GPU support.
Introduce candry deployment
strategies for safer model
updates, and set up comprehensive.
Monitoring and observability solutions
tailored for your AI workloads to ensure
ongoing performance and reliability.
By embracing these principles of
containerization infrastructure as code
and GitHubs, you are truly move from
container kiosk to a production paradise.
You can build AI platforms that
are not just powerful, but also
reliable, scalable, and bulletproof.
Thank you so much for your time, and
happy to answer any questions you have.
Thank you for this.