Hello everyone and thank
you for joining me today.
My name is Manoj Kumar Awa, and
I'm really excited to talk about
something that's shaping the
future of AI platform engineering.
Now when I say that phrase, AI
driven platform engineering, it
might sound very technical, but to
be honest, it's a simple question.
And the question is how do we
make the lives of developer easier
while also making systems more
reliable and cost effective?
So in this session, we are going to
explore how the artificial intelligence
and machine learning are stepping in
to help with the challenge and why
it matters, not just for developers,
but for organization as a whole.
So here's what we will be covering today.
We will be beginning with the
evolution of platform engineering.
A little story of how we got here and why
the old ways just don't scale anymore.
Then we will dive into idea of
intelligence infrastructure,
automation what it means, what it
looks like, and why it's so powerful.
After that, I will share a couple
of real world case studies.
Stories of organizations that put into
practice and saw some excellent results.
Then we will talk about how strategies,
architectural choices, and some of the
challenges you need to watch out for.
And finally, I'll wrap up with future
outlook and some practical next steps.
That you can take if you want to explore
this in your own talk, own context.
So let's get started with the story of
how platform engineering has evolved.
So when Platform engineering first
emerged, the mission was simple.
Give developers a standard set of tools so
they could build and ship software more.
Consistently, things like
pipelines, development scripts,
and monitoring dashboards.
And in the early days this was huge win.
Developers had guardrails.
Teams did not need to reinvent
the wheel in a way every time
they want to deploy something.
But then everything grew.
Infrastructure became massive, and we
moved from monoliths to microservices.
We went from managing a few
servers to managing thousands of
containers across multiple regions.
When the cloud came in and
suddenly scale was unlimited.
We all have experienced this, but
so where, we were moving parts.
So this created four major problems.
One is mental overload.
So basically developers now
juggle dozens of dashboards.
Alerts and tools.
Every change means extra mental effort.
And the second one is maintenance
overhead which is platform engineers
spend more time fixing and patching
the system than actually improving it.
And the third is scaling bottlenecks.
Manual work doesn't scale, so if your
app traffic grows 10 times, you can't
just hire 10 times more engineers.
And the fourth one is rising cost.
Cloud is flexible, but if unmanaged,
the bills grows fast then the business.
You have probably seen
this in your own work.
Maybe developer spends an entire
sprint just dealing with, broken bills.
Maybe the platform team spends nights,
firefighting instead of innovating.
This is reality means, teams, this is
the reality that teams live in, actually.
And here's a big question.
How do we escape this cycle?
This is where AI opens a door.
Instead of treating platforms as
things that need constant human
babysitting, we can start to see
them as a intelligent ecosystem.
Like systems that not only automate, but
also learn, anticipate, and also optimize.
Here's a simple analogy
in my point of view.
Thinking like driving a car, the
old way of platform engineering
is driving a, shift car.
Where, in rush hours you need to
change your shifts constantly watching
every mirror and it's very stressful,
but yeah, driven platforms are like
moving to a car with self-driving
features like adaptive cruise control.
It manages avoid hazards and
even suggest the best route.
You still decide the destination, but
the system takers of the heavy lifting.
That's the transition
we are stepping into.
So what's on the other side of the shift?
What's the promise of AI driven platforms?
There are four big benefits
I want to highlight here.
First is the less mental
overload developers can hand off
repetitive and routine tasks.
Think about things like
selecting which test to run or
ruling back after a failure.
Yeah, you can handle that.
Leaving developers free to focus
on actual problem solving skills.
Second, faster delivery.
With automations moving out,
bottlenecks and deployments move
quicker and with fewer errors
instead of, stressful once a week.
Release, teams can deploy more
times a day with more confidence.
And third is a self-managing
infrastructure.
Imagine a system that notices a service
is slowing down so it adjusts itself
automatically and fixes the problem
without anyone needing to log in.
That's no longer a really a science
fiction, it's becoming real and
fourth, a better developer experience.
Developers don't want
to fight these tools.
They want platforms that are
responsive and even helpful.
AI can create these environments
that really adapt to the way
individuals and teams work best.
And here's a key point.
This isn't just about
efficiency, it's about people.
Happier developers, write better code
teams with less frustration, move faster.
And organizations that their developers.
Gain a real competitive edge.
That's the true promise of AI
driven platform engineering.
Now that we have talked about promise
of AI driven platforms, the natural
question is how does this actually work?
So at a higher level, there
are five building blocks.
First one is smaller, CID
smarter, C-I-D-C-I-C-D pipelines.
Second one is predictive analysis.
Third is automated remediation, and
fourth is dynamic resource optimization
and intelligent observ observability.
So these are the five pillars.
Think of them as the toolkit that
transforms transact a traditional
platform into one of the, that can learn,
adapt, and that can improve over time.
So let's get deeper into each of these.
So traditional p pipelines
are rigid, right?
They treat every build and
deployment the same way.
Whether the change is small or
huge, the pipelines are on the
same long process that wastes time
and also create more problems.
So with AI pipelines becoming
smarter, they can analyze codes
and decide which tests actually
matter and skip irrelevant ones.
They can also predict deployment risks.
So if something looks wrong after release,
they can also roll back automatically
before even customer even notices.
And they can handle dependency
checks and scru scans without
any extra manual effort.
Think of it like a chef in a kitchen.
A traditional pipeline is like
following the same 10 step recipe
every time, no matter what the dishes.
And a smart pipeline is like a
chef who knows which step really
matters for this specific meal.
Saving time reduces mistakes, and also
deliver food faster and more reliability.
So organizations that actually adopt
this are reporting higher success rate
fewer failed deployments and fast cycles.
That's a big win for both
developers and customers.
Now let's talk about predictive
analysis and incident resolution.
The traditional way is reactive.
Something breaks, the pager goes
off, engineer rushes in, and
you, you need to work in a night.
To fix it.
We all know how stressful it is.
So AI allows us to flip that into
a proactive model so it can spot,
usual patterns in system behavior.
It can perform root cause
analysis shifting through logs and
metrics much faster than a human.
And it call, it can also
suggest fixes or even apply them
automatically if they're safe.
And it's a routine task as the perfect
example could be a CP utilization
where a system automatically
identifies it and increases the CPU
code memory to that specific process.
And it can filter alerts, reducing
the noise, and highlighting
only what actually matters.
So for engineers, this means fewer
false alarms and less wasted time.
And for business it means less
downtime and faster recovery.
So to correlate the perfect
example is again, imagine your car.
The traditional approach is driving
until the engine light comes
on, then rushing to a mechanic.
Whereas the predictive analysis is
having sensors that warn you a week
earlier, hey, your oil is running low.
Schedule a quick service that that
early warning prevents a breakdown.
That's the power of ai bringing
to this incident resolution.
Okay.
So one of the biggest hidden
challenges in cloud computing is cost.
We often overprovision resources just
to be safe, which means, we pay for
capacity that we really don't use.
Machine learning helps us tackle this.
How does it do it does it by
analyzing past usage patterns.
Forecasting future demand and
automatically adjusting resources
or down to match the actual needs
and learning from the outcomes
to improve accuracy over time.
These results are really impressive.
Companies have seen 15 to 30% savings
in cloud costs while maintaining
or even improving performance.
So let me give you a simple analogy here.
Imagine if your home
electricity automatically
adjusts based on your habits.
Lights dim.
When you leave a room,
ac adjusts, et cetera.
Appliances run at off peak cars.
You would say money
without even noticing it.
And that's what machine learning
powered resource optimization does at a
scale for this kind of infrastructure.
Now let's see this in action
with with real examples.
So let's assume there is a gl,
a global financial services
company that was struggling.
Their deployments were slow.
Production incidents were
frequent and cost for climbing.
So in a business where every second
of downtime can affect trust and
revenue, that's a very serious issue.
And here's what they need.
They implemented predictive scaling.
They deployed machine learning,
analogy detection, and they built
intelligent deployment pipelines
with safe and staged rollouts.
So the results speak for themselves.
So by implementing these things they
deployment speed increased by 65%.
Production incidents dropped by 42%, and
infrastructure costs went down by 22%.
Even though they were handling
more transactions, this shows
that AI isn't just a buzzword.
It can really deliver concrete, measurable
improvements in speed, reliability, and
cost, even in high stake industries.
I would like to take another example.
Here there is a fast
growing e-commerce platform.
Their main challenge was scaling, so they
need to support hundreds of developers,
but they couldn't just keep, hiring
more people for the platform team.
Their solution was AI driven
self-service platform with AI assisted
configuration so developers could handle.
Set up themselves and smart
observability that not only monitored,
but also, auto troubleshoot common
issues that they see in a, in, in,
in a very frequent daily basis.
And machine learning powered
scaling to handle huge spikes
during shopping seasons.
And the results are the platform team
supported three times more developers
without adding any headcount.
That's the real story of ai.
It scales people's impact.
It lets smaller teams achieve
big results without, burning out.
So we have talked about all this,
next we will be looking into
this implementation strategy.
So how do we start bringing AI
into your own platform engineering?
Here are some of the practical strategies.
The first one is start small.
So don't try to automate
everything at once.
Pick a high value, low risk area like
test optimization or auto scaling.
This way, you know what you're
getting into and get used
to it and build the trust.
So next is build a strong data foundation.
AI is only as good as the data it
sees, so make sure all your logging
metrics and observability are solid.
Without data, AI can't
make any good decisions.
So next is use feedback loops.
In the beginning, let
human review AI decisions.
For example, if the system
recommends scaling down resources,
let an engineer approve it.
As trust builds, you can
always increase the automation.
So increase automation gradually.
Think of it like learning to swim.
At first.
You keep one feet on the ground.
I know as you get more
confidence, you get deeper.
Same with ai.
Start with recommendations,
then semi-automation, and then
followed by the full automation.
And remember, this isn't just
technical, it's cultural.
Teams need to see value, not just change.
Share success stories internally,
highlight time saved, and celebrate
the wins, that helps people
embrace the real journey here.
So when you design AI driven platforms.
Architecture really matters.
Four principles stand out are,
modularity build AI as plugin components.
Don't just rip and replace all
your whole stack, that's gonna burn
your arms and your energy more.
So second one is explainability.
Make sure people can see
why AI made a decision.
Transparency.
Transparency builds a trust.
Fallback mechanisms always have
manual overhead options so human
can step in whenever needed.
Continuous learning.
Let this system improve with every
outcome and a piece of feedback.
Think of it like, hiring a new
team member at first, obviously you
don't give the entire access, they
explain their reasoning, you double
check their work, and over time
you trust them with more autonomy.
That's how.
We should approach AI in in
platform engineering as well.
Of course, like any, in any other
technologies, we do have some of
the challenges and some of the
technical challenge challenges
could be like, data quality issues,
integrity with older systems, keeping
models up to date, and also meeting
security compliance requirements.
And there are also some of
the organizational challenges.
Which most of the organizations
obviously do notice this, we, that is
a skill gap in AI and machine learning.
And and for the existing employees
it is always a resistance to change
and concerns about losing control
and difficulty managing really.
ROI, beyond just cost savings.
So do, how do we actually overcome these
problems is with a balanced approach.
Invest in upskilling like trainings.
Start with small pilots, communicate
clearly about what AI will and
won't do, and always combine
automation with the human oversight.
So if you address both the
technical and cultural sides,
adoption becomes much smoother.
So I just want to key recap in
know a big Tk K key takeaways here.
AI is transforming platform engineering.
It's creating more scalable resilient
and developer friendly systems.
So start small and scale
gradually, begin with pilots
that solve clear pain problems.
Gradually expand measure
impact on developer experience.
Success isn't just about
uptime or dollar sale.
It's about, making developers'
lives better so they can be more
creative, productive, and do
the actual innovative solutions.
That's the lens through which we should
match, measure the progress of the ai.
So some of the recommendations are here.
You should always assess
your current platform.
Where could AI make a quick,
meaningful difference?
So evaluate your observability.
Do you have the data foundation
AI that needs to learn?
And the next one is, build a roadmap.
Plan progressive implementation.
Start with small wins and invest in
people upskilling your platform teams
in AI and ML for infrastructure.
This is very much needed.
For the continue progress improvement.
So if you do thi if you do these
things you will move from theory to
practice in a safe sustainable way.
And thank you.
I really enjoyed, talking about
this and hope you implement in your
environments and see the big difference.
Thank you for joining me today.