Hello everyone.
I'm Rahul Joshi.
Thank you for attending my session.
I'm going to talk about
platform engineering for
modern data infrastructure.
Where we are gonna see how the data
infrastructure has evolved over last 15,
20 years, what all things have emerged
as a new technologies and capabilities
and how the organizations are generating
and consuming data at large scale.
And that has created a need.
For platform engineering, we look
at these systems as not as isolated
platforms or components in the overall
enterprise, but look at it as integrated
platforms, self-service, large scale,
multi-tenant, right access controls to
enable all the business capabilities of
the latest and greatest capabilities.
That these platforms, enable.
So let's take a deep dive and first
we are gonna start with the evolution
of data platform architecture itself.
So as you can see, I'm showing
three key here on timeline
only big data era there around.
2006, 2007 Loop was, emerged
as a, as an outcome of the
Google's HDFS and MAP newspaper.
And a lot of that has triggered, that, had
triggered a lot of new use cases where,
companies started to build big data lakes,
ingest a lot of data into the lakes and
process all that data by maintaining
their own complex clusters, right?
Clusters of commodity hardware.
The principle for Hadoop was.
It used to run commodity hardware and the
platform engineers used to focus primarily
on keeping these systems operational.
So a lot of heavy lifting used to be done
by these enterprise, and ultimately these
teams that are owned by these enterprises.
For platform engineering
later, the cloud has changed.
The infrastructure management part
of it and data platform shifted
towards managed services like WS,
Google and Microsoft Azure Cloud.
There are a lot of software as a service,
conce where emerged Adobe managed services
like Redshift to BigQuery and Snowflake.
That abstracted a lot of
operational complexity, but
it introduced new challenges.
As it comes with any new
technology on cost optimization
and vendor management because.
Once you go on cloud, you have infinite,
compute level access, so you can
use, you have to use it wisely and
cost optimization, that is key role
on how do you be up to speed on all
the computes and activities you need.
But at the same time, how do you
manage your cost efficiently?
Then third is the Lakehouse architectures
where technologies like Delta Lake,
iceberg and Hoodie are enabling
platform engineers to build systems that
support both analytical and operational
workloads on the same platforms.
Unifying storage with strong
consistency and the right governance.
Each architectural phase here has
contributed important lessons and
has influenced how do we design
and operate data platforms today.
So we are gonna focus on the modern
architecture and look at this thing
on that lens of what are some of
the things platform engineers have
to be aware of or consider while
designing these new platforms based
on the new architecture patterns.
So let's look at some of the core
platform engineering principles here.
If you're building a data platform set.
Enterprise scale.
You need abstraction and interface design.
You have different types of personnel.
There are business users.
There are technical users, right?
They're engineers and these platforms,
data platforms today, which at the heart,
heart of the company data is, powering
so many business capability for, so you
need abstract all the complexities that
are, that goes into the implementation
of the platform and make the interface.
And they know easy for all these personas
so that they can come and use this data
platform capabilities, be it engineer or
data scientist or analyst, business user.
We need to balance what capabilities
we enable to these end users as
part of user experience and what
capabilities we, we abstract as
part of complex implementation.
Second is self-service.
So all these data platforms must provision
resources, deploy, pipelines, right?
Ability to create
resources, use them, right?
Exposition them again, and access data.
Use data, access data as it requires
in a self-service fashion because you
are, if you're talking at enterprise
scale, you're talking about thousands
of users and applications, human
users and applications using these
shared multi-tenant data platform.
So service capabilities
plays critical role there.
Where is infrastructure as code?
Because we are in cloud era now, all
these, a lot of different interconnected
components that must work together
seamlessly as part of cohesive solution.
So platform engineers must they, a lot
of people use infrastructure as a code
to deploy and create resources, right?
In instant deploy your applications.
I update it, but this, these
capabilities need to be.
Used at scale.
And you also need observability and
monitoring sophisticated capabilities
there so that you keep your data
platforms healthy and you maintain
the quality of data these platforms.
And at the same time, look at
how the data is flowing through.
If there are any concerns like latency,
freshness, and schema evolution, you are
able to, look at these things and the
data is flowing through at runtime and
detect some of the problems proactively.
Then, and, reacting to it later when
some application fails in production.
So these are some of the core principles
or modern platform engineering actually
look at if you're gonna do build the data
platform or developer self-service, right?
How do you create truly
self-service data platform?
That needs a fundamental shift in how
platform engineers think about user
interface and developer experience.
The goal is to enable data teams work
independently while ensuring their actions
aligned with organization standards.
So first, platform APIs
and developer interfaces.
You need well-defined,
well-defined platform api.
To provide programmatic access
to the platform capabilities.
These APIs could be rest, or
similar standards, which are well
established industry standards.
So you are keeping your applications
later aligned with latest and greatest.
And you, you should have clear
documentation and versioning strategies
of when the schema changes for all these.
APIs or contracts between the
data producers and data consumers
and the platform capabilities,
it shouldn't be an issue.
Second is standardized data processing.
So there are, if you think about
enterprise, there are so many
different applications and personas
and if they, if it's a shared, their
tenant, multi-tenant data platform.
Then, every use case needs to read
data, get data out, all the data that's
required, do some standardization,
do some processing on that data,
and then, create some business.
Related, meaningful insight
out of that data, right?
So there is, we need some if we do
not have standardization, standardized
data processing patterns across
these different use cases, every
use case will do some redundant data
processing in their own, application.
So standardizing these data processing
patterns is the key to avoid.
All the redundant data processing
and joints and, can be joints as
an example, but it can be, reading
some data, maybe flattening it
and things of that nature, right?
So you, the, you don't want to do
all you, you don't want all your.
All your applications to do
some of these redundant things.
So you have to centralize those and
create consistent data processing
patterns, standardize it so everybody
can use, reuse whatever is available
out there, and then build their
own use case specific applications
or implementations as required.
Third is data discovery
and catalog services.
So how are you going to find what
data is available out there for you?
If you're working at enterprise scale,
you might have thousands of applications
and hundreds of systems producing data
every day, and that's a shared tenant.
So you have different lines of
businesses using same data platforms.
So identifying data, it, having a shared
catalog of all these data sets, making
data easy to find for all these different
applications and humans is key for
developing the self-service data platform.
Next key thing is, big thing is
resource management and cost control.
As we discussed earlier, if your platform
is self-service, then users can do.
Whatever they have access
to, they'll create resources.
They'll run queries viewed as they want to
get their results quickly as, as quickly
as possible if they have right access.
So how are we So resource management
becomes key because you, you can
have practically have infinite skill.
Compute and storage when you're on cloud.
So this is, managing your costs and
processing workloads where for processing
workloads, where they consume a lot
of significant resources and compute
our resource management and cost
controls becomes another key dimension
for designing modern data platforms.
It's looking at multi-tenant
architecture and resource isolation.
So multi-tenancy or enterprises
at least, where you have
multiple lines of businesses.
Each lines of business own their own.
Source of system of records have
their own business lifecycle for
their customers or the end customers.
So it generates data.
Produces data, right?
It needs to store data, needs to
ingest data, it needs to process data.
And if you, are they.
They don't want to build, you
don't want to build different data
platforms for each line of businesses.
So for doing the same thing.
So you need, and that's where the
multi-tenancy comes into picture.
So you have to build your data platform
in a way that the capabilities can be
used across different lines of businesses.
IE in tenants in this case.
So each tenant have their own workspace,
have their own right access controls.
Have their own isolation in terms of how
compute resources are allocated to it.
Have the right access control, or
sharing or not sharing data with other
lines of businesses or subsidiaries or.
Country specific geopolitical
restrictions, geographical
restrictions, and so on, so forth.
And at the same time, you need a
storage and performance isolation.
So you need both logical separation
and physical separation, isolation of
dedicated storage systems and compute.
So that had becomes well optimized
and well managed data platform for
a large enterprise where you can use
multi-tenancy to to reuse as much of.
Platform capabilities as spot to
power all these different businesses.
So what are some of the key
cost optimization strategies?
Let's understand some of the cost drivers.
So primary cost usually includes
computer resources for data
processing because when data is at
rest, it is stored on a platform.
So when you run some, query or request
to get it out, the compute is used,
which basically goes and try to read
data out and give it back to you.
So computer resources for data
processing is one of the key factor.
The data is at rest.
Your storage plays another.
Key factor for your raw data
and then the process data.
If you're working on like data products
or in different layers of data, as part
of Alion architecture, you have raw
data, you have refined data, you have,
purpose built use case driven data,
and all this data needs to be stored.
So at rest you're gonna pay a lot of
storage cost and then network cost
at the time of compute, as well as
at the time of data transfer between
these different systems at runtime.
So platform engineers must implement.
Comprehensive tracking,
monitoring, and, attribute these
cost to specific teams, right?
So we need a good
chargeback models, right?
Basically where who is
using this platform, right?
What are they using it for?
What is the cost of their compute?
So chargeback.
Chargeback is usually well known and well
followed model across large enterprises
where if there is a centralized theme,
let's take an example there, there is
a centralized data lake, which is on
cloud, is managed by enterprise data
team, and then different lines of
businesses can use data lake not to ingest
their data, store it there to consume
it, to process it for any use case.
So chargeback model can be actually
used to track all these expenses and
I'll assign it back to the right.
Line of business where they can get
visibility on how much they're spending.
Are they overspending?
Are they, using these
platforms efficiently or not?
What are things they can optimize?
All the thing things teams can do is
they optimize the jobs by looking at
the scheduling on when this data needs
to be processed and ing and scheduling
rightly, all the workloads could optimize.
The usage of the platform can use
autoscaling and descaling as your,
if you are aware of workloads
and if your workloads and the
demand of compute is predictable.
And third, you can use tiered storage.
For example, on S3, you can
use intelligent tiered data
gets moved to the lower.
Lower, frequent, frequently accessed tier
to lower, frequently accessed tiers, low
usage tier, and things of that nature.
So that's gonna save a lot of money
for you that all these cloud vendors
are coming up with capabilities.
S3, for example, has intelligent
tiering, but even if not you, if you
are aware of your data lifecycle.
Data retention policies, you can apply
the right data retention policies and
move your data sets from a tier to another
tier as part of the lifecycle management.
Alright, let's take a look at next slide.
So automation is key.
We talked about infrastructure as
called looking at, again, thinking about
enterprise scale data platforms here,
if you are talking about thousands of
applications where you need to create
the, provisioning these resources, right?
Compute, then infrastructure
automation is required where you
can create these resources, storage
resources, compute resources in a, in
an automated way using configuration
frameworks, security policies,
network rules, and monitoring systems.
Pipeline automation is required for
all these different applications that
are gonna use your platform to deploy
these pipelines on your platform.
Test it out.
No.
Move it all from dev to QA to
UT Uua to production and monitor
the health of these pipeline in
terms of performance and failures.
Third is continuous improvement.
So att refinement of these automation
processes based on operational
feedback and best practices from
the industries could be taken and
implemented back into these automation.
Fourth is configuration management.
So you have to ensure the, there
is a consistency across all these
different environments because then
you have multiple environments,
f, qa, prod, UAT, all the, all
of them should have exactly same.
Consistent configuration so your,
all your users and applications
get the same experience and early
detect all the issues, if any, and
they don't face any discrepancies in
terms of experience of the behavior
of the plaque across different ones.
Alright, so monitoring,
observability and data quality.
Another key dimension, deep
dive on, so observability in
data platforms is monitoring.
Traditional infrastructure monitoring
along with data specific concepts.
So we are talking about
data platform share.
So there is an infrastructure level
monitoring platform level monitoring
whether the platform is an up and running,
it's healthy, how is it performing, how
is the scalability, how is the usage?
How is the compute usage, what's the
throughput and things of that nature.
And then we, because it's a data
platform, there are some data
specific concerns, like data
quality, pipeline performance, right?
Data schema, evolution.
It.
Errors, failures, e rejection
of data processing rates, right?
Thresholds and things of that nature.
So infrastructure and performance
monitoring covers tracking, resource
utilization, system performance
and service availability across
all the platform components.
Cloud will naturally give you
a lot of monitoring out of the
box, but if there are, if you are
building your own capabilities.
For your data platform, you need
to build your own monitoring and
alerting for your applications.
For data quality, you have
to, and pipeline monitoring.
Some of the key things you need to
look at is there any data missing?
Is there any data leak
between your pipeline?
If it's a data pipeline, you
getting duplicate records?
Are you missing any records?
Are there any schema
validation violations?
Are there any statistical anomalies?
You can have your own data quality rules
and have your pipeline and platform
actually run those data quality rules
when you're trying to process data or
when you're trying to, ingest data.
So tiered alerting systems with different
escalation procedures from different
issue types usually is the right way to,
to implement monitoring observability
and data quality at a large scaling.
Let's look at security and compliance.
Many, not just regulatory
industries like finance, right?
Almost all industries and all the
enterprises in today's cloud world facing
a lot of security, concerns, right?
Cybersecurity and compliance, and
really for regulated industries.
So security and compliance
is not is very critical.
For all the enterprises, no
matter if you're regulated or not.
So that becomes a key requirement or
dimension while designing your modern data
platforms data encryption and protection.
So because we are talking about
data platforms here, how are
you going to keep your data?
State, how are you going
to keep data secure?
You can actually implement multi-level
encryption for data at rest as well
as data in transit and in memory
data masking tokenization, right?
How do you protect your
sensitive information?
That becomes a key capability.
You can have different
data platforms, types.
There could be data platform types which
are allowed to save customer, customer
information, sensitive information
with the title access controls, there
are, there could be data platforms
where you tokenize or, anonymize all
your data and then store data there.
So those are not, those platforms do
not have customer sensitive information.
Access controls and
authentication becomes key.
You have to make sure you have
sophisticated systems and access controls.
At multiple granularity level, you
can have role-based access controls.
You can have attribute
based access control.
You can have or screen green and fine
grain access control at a file level or
a table level or at a roll level, but at
the record level and at the column level.
So all these different capabilities
become key or key implementation
techniques to enable right access
controls and authentication mechanism
for your sharing data platforms and
compliance and audit capabilities.
Comprehensive audit, logging, data
governance, automated compliance.
These are the things which are
covered on in this section.
Efficient system capture.
Detailed access and modification logs
while providing query capabilities
for reporting and investigation.
If you're using things like Delta Lake
or Snowflake for example, you have
a table format and you are allowing
your consumers to use SQL based
connection, then you are gonna be fine
because SQL based consumption tracks
what data is being used, who is using
it, what attributes are being used.
But on non SQL patterns, you may
want to build extra capabilities.
File consumption, for example, identify
and track on who's using which data,
which file, which attribute what
they're doing and things of that nature.
So platform engineers must design
security systems and capabilities that
provide comprehensive protection while
maintaining the performance and usability.
You don't want to, you don't want to
have a security capabilities, which
are impacting your performance and
usability of the platform, or limiting
users to actually use the data.
So that becomes a key.
Consideration for platform engineers.
How do you future proof your
data platform architecture?
Because the, as we saw, the data
technologies and capabilities
are emerging so rapidly.
You have to think about how are you gonna,
while designing new platform, you're
gonna think about how you, how do you
want to future proof your data platform?
So one.
You have to design architectures that
can accommodate new tech technologies
without vendor locking, right?
A lot of this cloud.
Services, managed services
Q into vendor locking.
So you have to load your
data into their systems.
For example, Redshift, right?
Snowflake.
Historically, you have to load
data into Snowflake, so you want
to implement abstract layers.
You want to keep your data platform
as open standard as you can.
So you can, and have an
abstraction there on top of it.
So your users and consumers would not
be impacted even if you change your
underlying storage or compute, layering
future from one thing to another.
So managing your vendors correctly
and managing your, architectures
to keep it go with, as much open
formats as you can, becomes the key.
Keep it future for second is scalability
and performance planning as you.
Create multi-tenant shared platforms.
You need an architecture that can scale
for growing data volumes from terabytes,
to petabytes and so on, so forth.
Because the data is keeps growing
only as a lot of businesses
are, enabling data powered AI
capabilities and ai, platforms and,
understanding their customer behavior.
The data is gonna grow.
It's not gonna spend in future.
So you need capabilities that
and sustain these growing data.
Data volumes, increasing usage,
growing data ingestion, data
processing, data transformation.
You need caching strategies, multi-tiered
storage strategies, all inbuilt in your.
Platform architecture so that in future,
when your data grows, your usage grows,
your platform will scale as required.
And third, you need flexible architectures
that can accommodate business growth.
Changing analytical environments
and evolving governance needs.
So organizational, evolution, if you
are, if become, if you add, if your
business adds more capabilities in future,
which might need in governance or some
compliance, your platform should be able
to easily enable it as required in future.
So successful data platform.
Engineering requires balancing multiple
competing priorities that cannot be
achieved through technology alone,
but require helpful consideration.
So some of that is flexibility,
consistency, self-service, governance,
cost optimization performance.
We covered all of these
in our previous slides.
And these are, these become key dimensions
for, platform engineers and architects
to, to basically design the data
platforms in modern data infrastructure.
So the future of data platform
engineering, as the data
technology continues to evolve.
Platform engineer must remain
adaptable while maintaining
focus on core principles.
So four key principles, core
principles that we covered.
One abstraction.
How do you abstract all your capabilities
that how do you abstract the complex
implementations and enable multi-tenant
platforms for your users and applications?
Second, how do you automate?
And second is automation.
First is abstraction.
So automation, how do you.
How do automate your
configuration management?
How do you automate your deployment?
How do you automate your monitoring
and, predictive analysis, all the
issues in there in the pipelines.
Third is observability, which
includes monitoring, alerting, data
quality, data level observability,
and infrastructure observability.
And fourth, last but not the
least, is user experience.
How do you make your data.
Easy to find for your consumers
through the right governments and
right user experience and how it is
made, available for our use for both
human users and application users
across different lines of businesses.
These principles provide a stable
foundation for navigating technologies
change while building platforms
that can grow with the organization
needs some of the emerging areas.
Where a lot of companies are
exploring to have their data
platforms support key, some of the new
capabilities is real time processing.
How do you enable stream
processing in real analytics?
Second is ML integration.
How do how do you avoid seamless
integration of your machine learning and
analytics models with your data platforms?
Or you have your data platforms isolated,
then all your ml. Workloads cannot use
your data as seamlessly as they can.
And how do you, how could
you build cloud native, fully
distributed and containerized
architectures to gain maximum
benefit of your cloud architecture?
These are some of the key areas
that platform engineers need to
consider while defining while
designing new data platforms.
So the platform engineering approach
to data infrastructure offers a path to
manage complexity of these data platforms
while enabling innovation and agility.
But what we looked at there
are three core pillars, right?
Abstraction, automation, and user
experience looked at two key balances,
which is flexibility with governance
and self-service with control.
Ultimate with the ultimate
goal of enabling transformative
business capabilities.
So by applying these principles
thoughtfully and consistently,
organizations can build infrastructure
that serves as a foundation for
data-driven decision making and
business growth powered by AI and ml.
Thank you so much for watching my session.
I hope this was helpful.
Bye.