Good morning, afternoon everyone,
and thank you for being here.
My name is Yan Pra.
Today we are going to talk about a
critical evaluation in artificial
intelligence infrastructure.
Moving from monolithic to micro
mind, we'll explore how building
a t AI platform with Multigenic.
Architecture that can unlock
the unprecedented flexibility
and performance that traditional
system simply cannot match.
Let's deep down
the landscape of AI
platform engineering at an.
Inflection point.
Organizations still lying on
our infrastructure and finding
themself constantly constrained by
the system will be this problem.
The path forward is to
transformational, not just on
technology, but also on the philosophy.
It is about embracing a new
model built on modularity.
Specialization and intelligence
coordination over the
complex and monolithic.
The organization that mastered their shift
will be one that define the next ticket.
AI powered business
performance and operation.
The today's bottleneck about the
monolithic, I will not say crisis, but
it's going to be definitely crisis.
First, we see a significant
development slowdown.
It's core base become a more
complex and simple update.
That one took a week.
Now sketch into month because everyone
want to consume the same architecture
of the place or the resource.
This leads to a heavy testing burden.
A minor feature Edison can trigger
need for extensive regression
testing across completely and on the
related part of the system as well.
And finally, the risk
of catastrophic failure.
When there is a tightly coupled
system failed, then they tend to
fail completely on every area,
and it'll bring down your system.
The technical depth in the system
has become a barrier to innovate
with monolithic architecture.
Let's deep down how its impact the AI and
the organizational impact on because of
this monolithic ai, the technical issues
creates a profound organizational problem.
Different business unit have different AI
need, but centralized, monolithic process
you and slows down your development.
The result of growing
disconnect day by day.
Within the organization also create a
problem on your current architecture and
it create a problem on your delivery.
It's impact your delivery.
It is also difficult to maintain
a centralized AI system while
eliminating their limitation.
So going with the monolithic
ai, every organization is
going to face this problem.
Let's talk about a
multi-agent architecture.
Fundamental and how this could help us.
The biggest answer is yes, and it
lies in multi-agent architecture.
The core idea is simple.
A complex intelligent doesn't
require a single complex system.
Instead, we engineered a multiple
focused as in it optimized for a
specific problem or a data drive.
This approach guided by a key.
Principle specialized through
a, through decomposition
flexible communication protocol.
We can.
Established an NCP protocol, which
is standard for AI for agent and work
together intelligent coordination layer.
We can orchestrate a coordination layer
among the agent and a natural fault
tolerance so that any failure, one
part of the system should not bring
down the whole system and evolutionary
capability and allowing system to
grow and adapt and launch easily.
The poor layer of agent
deployment framework.
So to structure this approach
we can use four different layer
of the multi-agent framework.
The first layer is the prescription layer.
And this is the layer where
responsible for your data ingestion.
Processing and initial interpretation.
Then you have a cognition layer.
Contains agent mostly responsible
for analysis, reasoning, decision
making sentiment analysis, and these
agents are applied and domain specific
intelligence to generate insight
prediction or recommendation anon
layer where translate your insight.
Decision into a concrete
operation, that external system or
business process can be achieved.
Then there is a coordination layer.
It's an orchestration of the multi-agent,
where multiple agent can work across
all of the layer, and it facilitated
the dynamic collaboration pattern, that
optimized system performance based on
the current condition of the system.
So let's talk about the performance
engineering and distributed AI system.
Performance in a multigenic system
is fundamentally different from
a monolithic, while monolithic
focuses on on a centralized.
Efficiency and distributed
architecture, Excela, parallel
processing and adaptive source.
So big parallel processing
agent can handle multiple tasks
simultaneously, a different resource.
Dynamic resource utilization means
the system also can scale based
on the actual demand inactive
agent, the time they don't need.
It can also.
Low power more while other
can work when it's required.
This is all enabled by a optimized
communication using an advanced
messaging queue and compression to
ensure that communication supports
rather than hindrance and performance.
So ability to do everything what
you want with the less resource and.
Less latency and more performance.
The platform reliability and the
pulse tolerance, how the multi-gen
distributed system can help you on
reliability and cultural tolerance.
The reliability is another area where.
This architecture excels by distributing
risk across independent component.
We create a system with a
sophisticated fault tolerance.
We can implement key mechanism, like a
graceful degradation and circuit breaker
pattern to contain a failure, continuous
health monitoring and self feeling
capability to automatically recover.
Unlike in a monolithic, that requires
a full restart up your whole system.
A multi-agent distributed system
can use a granular recovery strategy
and restoring functionality in
incrementally and maintaining downtime.
If you have a multiple agent
distributor across different,
and they're consuming different
resources and they are distributed,
then you will have that ability.
To incrementally and minimizing
the downtime and, even
restart them individually.
The legacy system, integration
strategy, of course a full
transition doesn't happen overnight.
A smooth transition with
legacy system is essential.
There are four strategies
to achieve on this.
Adapter pattern implementation creates
a translation layer so the modern agenda
and legacy systems can communicate.
Then data synchronous mechanism ensure
information flows sim seamlessly
between old and new component.
API Gateway Strategies provided
a centralized point to manage
interaction handling, security
and protocol transition, and
an event driven integration.
You just a messaging to loosely
coupled system, allowing them
to coordinate asynchronously.
Let's talk about the operational
excellency and monitoring of the system.
Monitoring a distributed system requires
definitely more advanced approach.
Instead of a simple logging,
and just disaster recovery
or any kind of mechanism.
We need capability like distributed
pressing to follow a request entire
journey across multiple agent.
This is vital for.
Diagnosing performance issues.
We also use a correlation based alerting
where the system can distinguish
with between a minor problem, it can
handle itself, and a significant issue
that requires a human intervention.
Let's talk about security and governance.
Nothing in this world is possible without
talking about security and governance.
In the current world at least, security
in a distributor network must also
evolve beyond traditional perimeters.
We rely on the modern strategies like
zero trust, security model, where every
interaction between agent is authenticated
and authorized independently.
Identity and access management
is to provide agent.
With the secure identity and dynamic
permission distributed audit trials
for regularly to check compliance.
And the last one is the behavioral based
threat detection, where machine learning
establishes a baseline abnormal activity
to quickly identify the anomalies.
Change management and team adaption?
Yes, of course.
When you moving out of monolithic
architecture into a multi-agent
distributed platform the
change management is a key and.
Without this, nothing is going to work.
The transition is as much as about
people as it also about technology.
It requires a cultural transit
transformation shifting team from
a mindset of centralized control
to a distributed collaboration.
To succeed, we must focus on three thing,
skill development program to engineer.
For designing and managing disorder
system process evaluation to
adapt our development cycle for
interdependency pilot program approaches
to gain expenses and demonstrate
value while limiting the risk.
Let's talk about a future proofing
AI platform architecture by
mastering this architecture today.
We are future proofing our platform.
We position ourself to leverage
emerging technologies like edge
computing, integration to distribute
intelligence closer to data source,
self optimizing architecture.
Where AI agent can lend to automatically
allocate resources and predict bottleneck,
at least like Autoscale Auto, identify.
Further down to the line, quantum
computing integration could be enable
new classes of agent per currently
impossible in computation, sustainable
computing with energy efficient.
Design and carbon error.
Resource location.
Embracing the multi-agent features
in conclusion.
This move from a monolithic
to a multi-agent AI is more
than a technological upgrade.
It's a fundamental REMA imaging
re reimagining of how intelligence
system are bolded evolves.
The evidence is clear.
This architecture delivers a
superior platform performance,
reliability, and adaptability.
The framework and tools
are available today.
The multi-agent avail.
The multi-agent revolution has begun
and organization that act decisively
will save the future of AI business.
Thank you very much.