Good day, everyone.
Thank you for joining the
session on Exploring AI Powered
Chipboards and their Transformative
Role in Platform Engineering.
I'm Nagarajan Malone.
I work for Intuit as a senior staff
engineer, and I work on delivering AI
driven interactions in my long career.
I've looked far.
In front teams and contributed to
developer platforms, shipping tools,
SDKs, and established self-serving kiosks.
I always wondered if there is
some intelligent assistant who can
help me become more productive and
efficient, wide, repetitive tasks.
in this sta in this talk, I'm
excited to talk about an intelligent
assistant in the form of AI chat
bots in platform engineering.
AI powered
chatbots are intelligent
systems that can interact with
users using natural language.
They have the potential to significantly
impact platform engineering, a critical
area in modern software development
that deals with infrastructure,
automation, and DevOps practices.
Today, we will dive into how
these chatbots can revolutionize
platform engineering by automating
tasks, enhancing collaboration,
and improving overall efficiency.
AI powered chatbots are tools that use
natural language, machine learning, and,
generative AI to understand and respond to
user commands in a conversational manner.
These chatbots integrate with various
backend systems, which again is enhanced
by the machine learning or generative
AI to perform complex tasks, making them
powerful tools for platform engineering.
An example is like chatbots.
We already have chatbots, for, from
Slack and from Microsoft Teams, which
are, already being used for DevOps
environments to streamline workflows
and facilitate communications.
And chatbots can be proactive.
It can start the conversation
based on a triggering event
and is available 24 seven.
what is the gaps?
What are the gaps?
the platform engineering, what are the
gaps, that the chatbot can address?
first, they simplify complexity.
Managing complex infrastructural systems
can be overwhelming, but chatbots provide
an intuitive natural language interface
that makes this task more accessible.
Second, they automate repetitive tasks.
Chatbots can handle routine operations
like deployments, monitoring, and
scaling, significantly reducing the
manual workload for the engineers.
And third, they enhance
real time collaboration by
integrating with communication
platforms like Slack or Teams.
AI chatbots enable teams to have actual
real time conversations, which speeds up
decision making and problem resolution.
Last, they empower users.
Chatterbots allow developers and
engineers to perform tasks independently
without needing specialized knowledge
or waiting for central teams to step in.
This self service capability speeds up
workflows and enhances productivity.
Transformative benefits of AI Chatterbots.
Efficiency.
By automating repetitive tasks,
chatbots significantly speed up
operations, leading to quicker
deployments, faster issue resolution,
and overall improved productivity.
Scalability.
AI chatbots can handle increasing
workloads without performance bottlenecks,
allowing platforms operations to
scale efficiently as demand grows.
Proactive operations.
Chatbots can monitor systems in real time.
automatically triggering responses to
potential issues before they escalate,
which helps in maintaining the
health and stability of the platform.
Consistency.
Chatbots can ensure standardized
execution of tasks, reducing
variability and the risk of human error.
This consistency is crucial
in maintaining reliable and
predictable platform performance.
User empowered helps.
One of the most impactful benefits
is how chat bots empower engineers
by providing them with the tools
to manage tasks independently.
This helps help reduces the bot link
speeds up development cycles, and
free out the security team to focus on
more strategic initiatives rather than
repeating, the same, work with different
teams they support and, getting exhausted.
Some of the, practical use cases,
infrastructure provisioning, chatbots can
automate the setup of new environments.
For example, a developer can, instruct
the chatbot to create a testing
environment for two EC2 instances.
And the chatbot will
handle the entire process.
the CNCD pipeline management chatbots.
Can allow the developers to trigger
paints, deployments, and even rollback,
rollbacks via simple chat commands,
making continuous integration and delivery
processes more accessible and efficient.
Monitoring alerts.
Chatbots can integrate with monitoring
tools to send real time alerts
about system performance issues
directly within the chat interface.
Developers can respond immediately,
running diagnostic commands or triggering
recovery procedures right from the chat.
Incident management.
During outages or incidents,
chatbots streamline response
efforts by automating workflows.
They can escalate issues, provide
real time updates, and coordinate the
actions needed to resolve quickly.
Finally, knowledge access.
AI chatbots can instantly retrieve
documentation, facts, or troubleshooting
steps, providing teams with the
information they need to resolve issues
quickly without having to search through
the extensive manuals or databases,
leveraging the power of GDT AI.
An overview of the typical
chatbot architecture.
It has a user interaction layer.
Chatbot interacts with the
users via platforms like Slack,
Teams, or other chat interfaces.
It can also be in the build phase.
Layers include a natural
language processing engine that
interprets the user commands.
The core logic layer is essential.
The, essentially, the
brain of the chatbot.
Here, the dialogue manage,
dialogue management.
task orchestration takes place,
determining the appropriate
action space around users input.
The integration layer connects the
chatbot to various tools and platforms
such as, Jenkins, Kubernetes,
or cloud management systems.
this allows the chatbot to perform complex
tasks like deployment or monitoring
directly through these integrations.
Security layer is essential, To ensure
that all interactions are secure with,
identity and access management controlling
who can execute specific commands,
ensuring only secure, only authorized
users can perform critical operations.
And finally, continuous learning layer
is where the chatbot, AI models are
maintained and improved over time.
This layer allows the chatbot to learn
from past interactions, improving its
accuracy and functionality with each use.
Here is a high level architecture diagram.
There is a natural language, the chat,
we see the chat interface, and then a
natural language understanding component.
And that component extracts the
entities and then there is a
dialogue management component.
And the dialogue management component can
be integrated with the backend systems.
And then there is a, the response
is passed to the general message
generator and message generator sends
the response to the chat thread.
Here's a little more
detailed architecture.
You have a layer, we already saw that,
the messaging layer, and then the NLB.
The NLB receives internet
recognition and entity recognition.
Intent is the intent of the user,
exactly extracting the actual intent.
What is the work that needs to be done?
What is the request coming from the user?
Entity is what is that the work
is going to, or is that, what
is that going to get updated?
Thank you.
And then we have a Co AI layer.
there's a dialogue management,
which is actually retaining
the previous conversations.
And, the context and the memory.
And, the knowledge based integration, the
all the exhaustive stuff, documentations,
the, which really I can scan through
and then give a, give a response.
And integration with a
large language model.
Okay.
And we have the core layer,
the response generation layer.
The response generation
layer can be template based.
It can provide dynamic responses,
or it can also provide a multimedia
response, like it can generate a
report and share it on the chat thread.
Of course, we have a backend
services, which stores the data.
Analytics and monitoring
can be built on top of it.
And, then there's a security.
And throughout all these layers, we want
to ensure that there is compliance to all
the, to all the regulations, regulatory
bodies, and we ensure the privacy
of the end user is also maintained.
Challenges this, there are challenges
that we need to be aware of.
We need to be aware of while
implementing a chat interaction.
the managing the complex commands with
the natural language understanding, it
can be a task that needs to be done to
Avoid any, ambiguous misinterpretation
of the commands coming from the user.
Security is another major concern
since, chatbots can access uncontrolled
sensitive systems, robust security
measures like role based access control
and multi factor authentication are
essential to prevent unauthorized access.
Integration can be challenging,
especially in complex IT environments,
which a chatbot needs to connect
with various tools and systems.
Ensuring compatibility and
a seamless data flow between
these integrations is crucial.
User adoption is another key
success factor for the chatbot.
If it's not user friendly or
trustworthy, it may be, or
it may not be adopted widely.
Intervening its effectiveness,
ensuring the chatbot is intuitive
and providing adequate training
are essential steps to encourage.
Adoption.
Some of the emerging trends in
the, trends in the AI driven
chat bots is multimodality.
So the input may not be
always in the form of text.
It can be a voice based command or it
can be a document, or can be a gesture.
So there are multiple ways base
to encrypt data into the feed,
the data to the h and bot.
And you can also preserve.
in the format expected by the user.
And, deeply integrated integrations
enables users to navigate out
and into the chatbot seamlessly.
For example, chatbot gets the context
of the activities user has done
outside of the chatbot, selection of
a certain component in that selection
of the converted interface, which
is totally outside of the chatbot.
the context about the user activity is
passed to the chatbot and it readily
gets the context and works seamlessly.
In conclusion, AI powered chatbots are
transforming platform engineering by
automating tasks, enhancing efficiency,
and improving overall user experience.
This chatbots bridge critical gaps
in complexity, automation, and real
time responsiveness, making platform
engineering more accessible and effective.
As we move forward, it is worth
considering how AI chatbots can
be integrated into the platform
engineering practices to drive
innovation and operational excellence.
Thank you.
Thanks for your time.
I would like to open the floor
to any questions you might have.