This is ti.
I have a total of 18 plus years of
experience in information technology.
Right now I am working as a
principal software engineer
in Liberty Mutual Insurance.
Today I'm going to show the
presentation about how we can build
a bulletproof error detection, a
middleware fast approach to dramatically
reducing meantime to resolution
when your application crashes at.
2:00 AM every second counts.
This guide shows how a strategic
middleware implementation transformed
error response across multiple
enterprise applications, reducing
alert noise, improving detection
accuracy, and dramatically
cutting mean time to resolution.
Next, we are talking about the
crisis that changed everything.
It Tuesday morning brought
a stark realization.
Our flagship e-commerce platform had
been slightly failing for over two
hours incorrectly, processing orders
and corrupting critical customer data.
Our discovery came not from our extensive
monitoring systems, but from an escalating
flood of support tickets and an endra
call from our largest enterprise client.
Despite significant investments
in infrastructure monitoring,
application performance management,
and synthetic testing, our first
indication of critical issues continue
to be direct to customer compliance.
This incident exposed a fundamental flaw
in our existing error detection strategy.
Next we are talking
about the state of alert.
The average developer received over
40 alerts daily with the vast majority
being false Positives are low priority
issues, sir. More than three quarters
of all alerts required no action
or were duplicate of known issues.
Sir. Operations team
turnover froze as ongoing.
Engineers reported high stress
levels and sleep disruption.
Engineers were becoming
desensitized to alerts, often
ignoring or delaying responses
to what might be critical issues.
Next, we are talking
about the hidden costs.
On the left hand.
On the left hand side, we, I'm showing
that four different categories.
The engineering productivity teams
spent excessive time investigating
false positives and manually correlating
data from multiple monitoring tools.
The customer tasked eroded with
each incident that went undetected
leading to contract renewals at risk.
The support burden teams fee fielded
calls about issues that should
have been detected and resolved
before customers ever ripped.
Notice the business impact
sales provided credits.
Marketing dealt with the negative social
media and the company reputation suffered.
We had dozens of monitoring tools and
hundreds of dashboards, yet lacked
the fundamental capability to detect
when things were actually broken From
the user's perspective, the catalyst,
a database corruption issue went
undetected for nearly three hours
affecting thousands of customers.
Next, we are going to see the rethinking
of error detection at the source.
The breakthrough insight.
Real errors happen in code,
not in infrastructure metrics.
Traditional monitoring approaches place
sensors at the infrastructure level.
Monitoring CPU Memory Network
and database performance.
These are lagging indicators
of user impacting issues.
By moving our detection logic into
the application layer, through
strategic middleware implementation,
we could capture errors.
At the moment, they occur with
full context about what the
user was trying to accomplish.
Our middleware captures rich contextual
information about each error.
The user's sessions need the specific
operation being performed, the input
data, and the complete execution path.
Next, we are talking about
the architecture philosophy.
Here we are representing
four different categories.
The request pipeline.
Every request flows through a chain of
middleware, components for authentication,
validation, business logic, data
persistence, and response formatting.
The error capture middleware
operates with surgical precision
capturing with contextual information
about each error as it occurs.
The next category is the classification
ML algorithm determines and
category of the error in real
time based on historical patterns.
The next category is intelligent routing.
Alerts are sent to appropriate
teams through their preferred
channels with complete context.
The middleware operates
in multiple phases.
Immediate capture with minimal
processing, enrichment with additional
context gathered synchronously
classification with ML algorithms
and routing to appropriate teams.
Sir. Each phase is
designed to fail safely.
If the error reporting system
itself encounters problems, the
original application request
continues processing normally.
Next, we are talking about
machine learning for intelligent
alerting, traditional alerting
systems, relay on static thresholds
and simple rule-based logic.
Our machine learning approach analyzes
per patterns across multiple dimensions.
Temporal patterns that identify unusual
behavior at specific times are days
correlation analysis that identifies
relationships between different
types of errors and system events.
User coherent analysis that
detects when errors affect
particular segments differently.
Continuous learning from historical
incident data and engineering feedback.
Next we are talking about
dynamic priority assignment.
Not all errors are created equal.
A database timeout affecting one
user might be a minor play, but
the same error affecting hundreds
of users simultaneously indicates
a serious infrastructure problem.
Our intelligent classification
system considers multiple factors
when assigning priority levels.
On the right hand side, we are
showing four different factors.
In as a category.
The number one is an error
patterns, frequency distribution,
and correlation with other errors.
The next category is business
context, affected user segments
and their business value.
The next category is historical
data, similar past errors
and their resolution parts.
The next category is system
state, current load performance
metrics and scheduled maintenance.
This dynamic approach transformed our
alert quality high priority Alerts now
consistently represent genuine emergencies
while lower priority issues are
appropriately batched for business hours.
Next, we are talking about
multi-platform notification strategies.
Different teams have diff distinct
communication preferences.
Often varying by role, time of day,
and incident severity developers,
slack channels for team coordination.
GitHub, issues for tracking resolution.
IDE, plugins for immediate visibility
coming to the operations, integration
with runbooks incident management
platforms, PagerDuty escalations
next to the management is executed.
Dashboards, email
summaries, schedule reports.
Our system learns which channels
generate the fastest response
times for different types of alerts
and adjust routing accordingly.
Intelligent noise reduction,
the signs of signal detection.
Our approach combines multiple techniques
to separate signal from noise, baselines
that learn normal behavior patterns
for each application and service.
Temporal patterns.
Accounting for diary, weekly
and seasonal variations.
Load based patterns, understanding
how error rates change with traffic,
contextual awareness of deployments,
maintenance windows, and business events.
These dynamic baselines enable
the system to detect anomalies.
That would be invisible to static
threshold based approaches.
Next, we are talking about cascade
prevention and root cause identification.
When systems fail, they often fail
in cascading patterns where one issue
triggers multiple downstream problems.
Traditional monitoring treats each
symptom as an independent issue,
generating dozens of alerts for what
is fundamentally a single problem.
Let's take a example of as shown
below the database failure.
When connection pool exertion causes
primary alert, it'll cause the service
timeouts related alerts, supposed and
linked to root cause system maintenance
service dependency map in real time.
And it'll cause the UI frontend
exceptions related with backend issue.
Our middleware captures sufficient context
to identify these relationships in real
time, dramatically reducing alert noise
during major incidents, real production
monitoring metrics and lessons learned.
Issues that previously took covers
to identify are now detected
with minutes of occurrence.
The machine learning classification
system has virtually eliminated
false positive alerts.
Customer reported errors decreased as
issues were caught before customer impact.
The key success factors, several
FA factors provided critical to our
medieval wear implementation and success
execute to support through initial
investment period when development
velocity temporarily decreased,
minimal performance overhead, allowing
instrumentation of even performance
sensitive code parts middle weight that
fails safely to ensure monitoring does
not introduce new points of failure.
Cultural shift to treating error detection
as integral to application design.
Not an afterthought.
Implementation roadmap.
During the foundation phase, select a
single well understood application with
moderate complexity and clear success
metrics for your pilot implementation.
Basic error captured with
rich context collection,
comprehensive logging of sense.
Session info and request parameters.
Synchronous processing with manual alert
routing, scaling across applications.
Develop standardized approaches for
rollout across your application portfolio.
Create reusable middleware components.
Establish standards for
classification and routing.
Provide training and documentation.
During advanced futures, after
establishing basic error detection,
focus on advanced capabilities, machine
learning classification, intelligent
notification routing, cascade detection
and suppression, performance optimization.
Next we are talking about the
future of operational excellence
beyond error detection.
Predict two operations.
The Middleweight first approach
represents just the beginning
of a broader transformation
toward predict two operations.
Rich contextual data provides the
foundation for advanced analytics.
That can predict problems
before they occur.
Machine learning algorithms identify
patterns that proceed system failures,
enabling proactive intervention
before customers are affected.
The question is not whether to begin
this transformation, but how quickly
you can start building bulletproof
error detection for your organization.
Start small, measure everything
and prepare to be amazed by the
transformation your future self
and your on-call engineers will.
Thank you for taking the first step
toward operational excellence today.
Thank you.