Hello everyone.
My name is Qatar.
Today I wanna show you how we can
build healthcare AI systems that
are both powerful and private.
My promise to you is that this will
not be just theory or passwords.
By the time we are done, you'll
have a clear picture of how
blockchain federated learning.
And modern privacy engineering can
be combined to make production great
platforms that regulate us trust.
Deploy.
Developers can easily deploy
and patients can rely on.
So I'll walk you through some real
technical issues and give you the
same insights I've developed from
research and independent study.
Think of this, talk less as a
presentation and more as a workshop
where we are looking under the hood to.
Since I mentioned examples,
everything I share in this session
represents my own views and learning.
Nothing here is from any of
my current or past employers.
The slides are based on public references
such as OAS Top 20 open Academic
Research and my IEEE and MIT work.
This is a personal presentation effort
where I share insights and practices I've
developed through study and experience
to compare notes with the community.
All right, so with that, let's
dive deep into slide one.
The healthcare AI privacy paradox,
AI and healthcare is full of promise.
As we all know, whether it's imaging
drug discovery, or personalized
treatments, these models get better
as their training data gets richer.
But here lies the paradox, right?
The richest data sets are locked behind
regulations and competitive boundaries.
HIPAA and GDPR prevent direct
sharing and even anonymization often
fails because modern models can
reconstruct or infer sensitive details.
I've started cases where supposedly
anonymized DICOM scans or clinical notes.
Could still be linked back to
patients through auxiliary data.
Of course centralizing data may look
convenient, but it creates single breach
point and invites inference attacks.
The way forward is not
to move data at all.
Instead, we need to bring computation
and proofs to where the data
lives while guaranteeing to all
stakeholders that their privacy and
compliance obligations remain intact.
Let's look at this problem even further.
I call it the distributed
nature of healthcare data.
So healthcare data is not just
distributed, but it is fragmented
across incompatible systems, EHRs,
or electronic health records.
They sit inside of Epic
or Cerner as an example.
Imaging probably managed by pax.
Genomic data sets live in research silos.
Clinical trials sit with pharma.
Each uses its own schema
vocabulary and security protocols.
I've seen many technical reviews described
this as a data integration problem, but in
reality, to me, it's also a compliance and
trust problem as a security professional.
The mistake is often to build massive
central extractors to normalize
everything, and outcome is brittle
pipelines and exposure risks.
A better pattern is to build thin,
standardized adapters that run locally.
Inside each institution, these
adapters translate into local formats.
The minimal features required for
training enforce local policy and
generate cryptographic groups.
So by tolerating heterogeneity
instead of erasing it, we can
actually create a system resilient
to schema drift, and local governance
differences, right with that, right
with the problem outlined clearly.
Let me bring in blockchain
as a trust foundation.
When I say blockchain, I don't mean
public chains or cryptocurrencies.
A localized version of it, which
most people call it a permission
ledge that acts as a shared source
of truth between institutions.
Okay.
No PHI ever touches this chain.
By the way, since we're talking about
a chain, since we're talking about
institutions with an S you wanna make
sure that no PHI ever touches this chain.
Then what are we gonna use blockchain for?
What goes on the chain are trust
events, which site trained when under
which, the consent policy allows with
what differential privacy budget,
and what model lineage was used.
So when auditors ask me to prove that
a model was never trained on disallowed
cohorts, the ledger provides tamper
evident evidence or tamper proof evidence.
Call it.
The ledger is the bridge where
compliance meets technology.
This requires discipline design.
Only store hashes and references, rotate
keys with hardware backed identities
and ensure that smart contracts encode
regulatory gates like consent versions
or privacy budgets when done correctly.
Blockchain is not a hype.
It is a compliance backbone.
It's not an extra expense,
but a long term saving.
Let's look at.
And the next piece of it,
which is federated learning.
Now, federated learning turns the
traditional model on its head.
What does that mean?
Instead of exporting data to external
model, we export the model to the data.
Hospitals train locally
and send updates back.
But here's the problem.
Knife, federal learning, nicks.
You know what a learning leak is.
Most people call it knife federated.
Learning leaks also is, if that's
the word that you're familiar with.
Raw gradients can reveal
training examples.
Malicious clients can poison
the model or plant factors.
I've seen and I've seen of
course in, in test environments.
Mostly since this is all new I've seen
demonstrations in academic research
where attackers reconstructed sensitive
features just from update streams.
The right implementation requires
secure aggregation, differential
privacy at the edge, and robust
aggregation at the server.
It also means validating and
attesting the training binaries.
So we know each participant
is running the approved code.
So without these measures.
Federated learning is a false
sense of security with them.
It becomes a practical way
to unlock collaboration.
I also talk about the architecture a
little bit and not just stick to theory.
Like we all agreed in
the first slide, right?
Like a real feder federated
platform must honors.
So inside each institution's
boundary okay there, because
it remain there remains PHI.
There remains consent checks
and local computation outside
the boundary or RY orchestration
policies and cryptographic proofs.
I would say abstraction layers
allow each side to connect
despite of different stacks.
So multi-tenancy is crucial because
the same hospital may participate in
several collaborations simultaneously.
Workflow orchestration must
respect real world constraints.
Hospitals have maintenance windows.
Bandwidths and bottlenecks
and competing schedules.
Think of it like an SRE system.
We need retries in the important jobs,
metrics and back pressure controls,
which is an important, this is where a,
proof of concept either scales or fails
by addressing not just algorithms, but
the operational realities of healthcare.
It let's see.
Let's talk about blockchain
infrastructure for healthcare here.
Infrastructure, design
choices matter, right?
And as most of the security professionals
would tell you that security should
always begin at the time of the
design when things are layer up.
Anything that is done during
implementation and not
during design is expensive.
And counterproductive, of course.
So consensus mechanisms
should fit healthcare's needs.
We usually have tens of participants,
so you know, PBFT style consensus
with, strong IL is ideal, right?
We're talking about blockchain
terminologies now, and smart contracts
like should enforce policies.
Such as no model update is accepted.
If a site's differential, privacy
budget is exhausted, block structures
must strike a balance, right?
So enough transparency to support
audits, but not so much metadata
that it can be de anonymized.
So it's always about the balance, right?
You log enough to make sure that
you have a context in place.
To track what is being changed, but
then you also don't start logging
PHI into it, so it's similar.
And blockchain isn't really different
from that perspective, but hospitals
operate with firewalls, intermittent
connections and strict change controls.
I've seen projects
described in research lit.
Literature fail because they always
assumed on connectivity or open
networking, the right topology,
tolerates intermittent links,
encrypts channels, and achieve leisure
state for the long retention cycles
that healthcare regulators demand.
Let's bring in.
Privacy engineering
integration to this equation.
Now, as we saw the problems of blockchain
we also saw how federation would come
into picture and then how all of this
pieces in together in a integration
of sorts, with privacy engineer.
So privacy technology is not.
One silver bullet, but toolbox rather.
Why I say that is because differentially
a private training gives us provable
limits on what leaks from models.
Secure aggregation ensures that the
server never sees individual updates.
And again, a ZTA right, which
also converts in privacy to.
Zero knowledge proofs, if you have
heard, that can demonstrate that
a site respected a consent rule
without revealing raw counts, call
it the homomorphic encryption.
So homo market encryption allows
computations directly on cipher text,
though it is still expensive, right?
But secure multi-party
computation enables collaborative
statistics without input sharing.
So I have a lot of examples and
you can easily find, companies and
vendors that are specializing in this.
And I see that it's not
that expensive with.
The amount of time that is,
that it's being in the market.
The art I think is knowing
when to use which tool.
That keeps your cost down.
For example, I often recommended
starting with a DP plus secure
aggregation for most workflows and
layering in zero knowledge proofs where.
Regulators or the security condition
in itself, or the risk demands higher
assurances, let's say if it is a PHI
workflow versus a payments workflow
versus a regular PII workflow versus
an anonymized data workflow, right?
Where, which control should be applied?
Risk-based control is what I call it.
So what matters is tracking
and enforcing privacy budgets.
Exposing them in dashboards and ensuring
that cryptographically try to training
receipts without these practices, privacy
promises become marketing lines with them.
They just become enforceable guarantees.
And since we touched on that part,
I would like to move straight
into regulatory compliances.
DevOps integration now.
So since we looked at the privacy
integration already, I wanna quickly
move to the complete holistic whole
picture which talks about the DevOps
integration and how regulatory
compliance at such affects it.
So too often compliance is
bottled on at the end, and that
doesn't works in healthcare.
Why?
I say, compliance must be
baked into DevOps, just like.
How we discussed about Secure by Designer.
You input security, right?
When you.
Crafter design, right?
Every code change and every model
training run must be automatically
checked for HIPAA and GDPR safeguards.
So scrubbing is one example.
And it's not the scrubbing that
happens when the data is stored.
It's actually a middleware that has
come into the picture, a new idea
into the architecture that scrubs
data on both sides, even when the
input is captured, as well as when the
output is supposed to be displayed,
whether it's for a service or a human.
Doesn't matter, right?
So the pipeline itself should enforce
differential privacy budgets, generate
documentation, and fail the build if
something is out of bounds, right?
So model cards and lineage should
be produced automatically, not
written months later for operators.
So in my academic and independent
research projects have insisted that
if a training run produces an artifact
that violates policy, the run fails.
Period, right?
This discipline that by the time you're
in front of an auditor, your evidence
package is already generated from
immutable logs and receipts, so this is
what I call about compliance becoming a
byproduct of engineering, not a blocker.
Now this might just work well if
you're just a single hospital Right.
Or a single institution, but
when the scale grows, right?
And when you're talking about
multinational healthcare institutions
or, even like something that is truly.
National which is present throughout the
country or a major part of the country.
Then you face different set of
scaling challenges and I call them
multi-institutional scaling challenges.
When you work up across
multiple hospitals, the hardest
problems are not technical.
They're human and organizational.
So just like any other industry some
institutions have data science teams,
others barely have it staff, right?
Some have GPU clusters, other can
only contribute via managed notes.
Scheduling conflicts,
cultural differences, and data
quality issues are the norm.
So research pilots have collapsed because
smaller hospitals felt excluded, or
because validation threshold weren't
shared transparently, the solution
is to design for unevenness, right?
You can't just expect a perfect response
for a system that is designed right.
What I mean by that is provide turnkey
edge no for resource for sites, right?
Validate schemas per site to catch data
drift and create incentive structure
so every participant sees benefit.
If you don't solve the human and
governance side, no amount of
cryptography will save your rollout.
And with that, of course the emphasis
should be that, how good this is working.
And since I mentioned that.
The next slide is very important.
Platform monitoring and observability.
Observability in this context means
you're seeing enough to ensure safety
without exposing sensitive details.
So you can't log raw patient
patches or stream identifier.
Instead, you need privacy preserving
telemetry, noise metrics, RA
sweeps, aggregate statistics.
At the same time, you must
detect adversarial behavior.
That means monitoring update
magnitudes to catch poisoning
attempts tracking distribution swift
shifts to spot drift and enforcing
consent policies in real time.
So an example would be an alert
must trigger automated quarantine
actions, for example, right?
If isolation of a site that sends.
Am LS updates, right?
Because human triage at
two M isn't enough good.
Monitoring here is both about patient
safety and system integrity, right?
So I think we discussed a lot of things.
We started with, the basic concepts.
We saw the challenges and we saw how.
The three concepts of,
blockchain federation and smart
integration can help things here.
So I just to map it out clearly,
I wanna make sure that we see the
implementation roadmap also, right?
How do we implement it
is always the question.
And since we are not just gonna
do this as an academic study.
Try to turn it into a workshop.
Rolling this out is not a single launch.
I think that's the most important
insight that one needs to understand.
When you're working with a multi scaled
healthcare platform, it's a phase journey.
Phase one establishes the foundation,
which is a permission ledger.
Basic privacy adapters
and pilot integrations.
That's pretty simple, is how
I would set up phase one.
Phase two pilot's, a
non-critical workflow.
You say a readmission
protection with limited risk.
That's when everybody's happy, you've
done all your security checks, your
privacy checks, your compliance check.
Legal's happy.
Phase three expands to more sites
and more robust application.
Then you do your stress testing
with governance and scaling.
And then comes phase four, right where you
move to high stakes clinical applications.
With PHI.
With PII, right with PCI, with full
monitoring and regulatory sign off
at each stage, success means not
just technical performance, but.
Evidences, receipts, compliance
artifacts, or clinical validation.
By treating this as a stage deployment
with clear gates, we build confidence and
reduce the risk of catastrophic failures.
So even though as security you are just
a reviewer, you're just a responder
to something that is given to you.
As I said, you when these initial
meetings happen, when kickoffs happen
for such projects this is exactly.
The success metric or the success
criteria that you should share, that
this needs to be a phased approach.
And that's when security can,
support this project to the maximum.
Finally, like I said, as an industry
again, this is a, an honest attempt that I
want to share some of these best practices
that, again I've learned throughout
the years through my research, through
my study, through my affiliations with
academic institutions and through my.
And the real point of this is to
transform healthcare through privacy.
So privacy is for healthcare, right?
You cannot have the horse
before the card sort of thing.
So the real point is privacy
and progress are not opposites.
Privacy is what unlocks progress.
As they say.
Privacy lets you.
Work and play in a connected
environment, right?
So without trust, institutions
won't share without collaboration.
AI models would stagnate by embedding
serenity proof and compliance
into the fabric of a system.
We create a platform where hospitals,
researchers, and pharma can work together.
We stop asking people to trust
our intentions and start showing
them cryptographic evidence.
And blockchain is definitely the answer.
The result is not.
Better ai but faster breakthroughs,
safer clinical tools, and of
course stronger patient trust.
That is what I mean when
I say privacy first.
AI patient trust is all I mean by that.
Thank you for, spending
this session with me.
If you take away one idea, let it be this.
I would say in healthcare ai, more
computation improves not data.
That simple shift preserves patient
trust, satisfy, satisfies, regulators,
and accelerates medical innovation.
I'd be glad to dive deeper into specific
controls, governance and rollout patterns.
During q and a. First has my
email address and I would love to.
Get comments, feedback questions
from the folks from the industry.
I thank you and have a
good rest of the day.