Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, the
Platform Engineering Edition.
I'm really excited to share our
experiences and journey so far in building
a serverless generative AI platform.
My name is Murali Malina, and I'm
Chief Technology Officer at SoftRAMS.
I've been really lucky to have been
building teams and software solutions
for more than 25 years and the last
seven years at SoftRAMS itself.
I'm also the co founder and CEO
of a five year old nonprofit
organization called Teaching for Good.
This is a very unique editech nonprofit.
It empowers anybody that is interested
to teach, train, mentor, or coach.
At the same time, you can actually
use this platform to raise funds
for a non profit of your choice.
So in other words, we are a non
profit and we support raising funds
for any non profit of your choice by
leveraging your skills and passion.
To teach and mentor others.
I also had a great privilege of
collaborating and working with
exceptional teams, worldwide teams
in Germany, UK, France, India, China,
Russia, and of course, us and have
built mission critical systems.
In telecom supply chain, particularly
auto industry, healthcare,
working with federal agencies.
And my favorite and pretty
close to my heart is Editech.
I'm not that active on Twitter.
Please hit me up on LinkedIn if you
want to connect and chat about pretty
much anything you want to chat about.
I've been working with SoftRAMS for
almost seven and a half years now.
And SoftRAMS is one of the fastest
growing civic digital services firms.
We support a variety of mission critical
loads for our federal agency customers.
We have been working hard to
bring some of these generative AI
experiences and solutions that depend
on the generative AI into our work.
With our federal agencies, and as
these agencies provide a very unique
opportunities and different levels
of constraints and complexity.
That's one of the factors actually that
led us to build this Gen AI platform.
This can be deployed in entirety into
any customer environment, for example.
And go from an experiment to
production in days to weeks, rather
than weeks to months, it used to
take us to build ML experiences,
for instance, and I will definitely
touch a few aspects and these unique
constraints later in the discussion.
just a shameless plug.
If anybody's looking for an
opportunity, take a look at some
of the open positions at SoftRAMS.
It's a great place to work and it's
one of the top workplaces in the U S.
And it has been recognized for
almost fourth year in a row for
innovation and leadership culture.
Given that this is a, an online
virtual conference, instead of
polling you to see where you are and
what you're doing, I will make a few
assumptions and discuss various aspects.
but please LinkedIn if you have any
specific questions or want to take
this conversation to a different level.
I'm sure many of you are using JNI for
fun and Some probably have also started
using a variety of Gen AI tools at work.
Maybe GitHub Copilot or similar, for
example, or automated peer reviews,
or tools to generate documentation,
release notes, just to start with.
And how about building
new Gen AI applications?
I'm pretty sure you're as excited as
me and everybody else in the ecosystem
when Charged GPT got released.
We all wanted to build these new AI
experiences into new applications
as well as bring these Gen AI
experiences to existing applications.
Or, at least, most of you must be
experimenting with various tools
and LLM models, probably some of
the software as a services that are
out there in the ecosystem as well.
As you all know, AI and ML that we all
know and told as in historians, That
there is an AI or ML before ChargeGPT and
there is an AI and ML after the ChargeGPT.
This transformation is pretty
surreal in many ways and this is
now very pervasive as well across
the board, across the world.
The excitement and ease
of building applications,
ChargeGPT is totally profound.
Suddenly the AI or ML, or I would
say especially generative AI,
is on the list of top priorities
across the board around the world.
Shifting the perception of AI and ML
from what used to be like a little
bit more complicated and costly
process, even more important of the
talent like need for data scientists.
Only so many organizations were
able to afford to build those
end to end ML experiences.
And the chart GPT brought this
into something that is now Totally
accessible to pretty much everyone.
and though we have come a long way in
terms of automated automation, tooling
and systems to build amazing EAML
applications before, but charge GPT and
LLM models in general, are taking us to
a completely different level in order of
magnitude in terms of speed of innovation.
One fundamental pivot for that entire
ecosystem is that LLMs made this
natural language as a new programming
language, making it possible for anybody
in the organization, technical, non
technical, business teams, doesn't
matter, to be able to leverage LLMs,
create apps and assistants, Purely
using plain everyday language.
Of course, this still need to learn
a little bit about how to create
those instructions and how to work
with these prompts, but they can
do it pretty quickly and with that
people from all walks of life now can
create exceptional user experiences
without the need for large teams and
large coding exercises or workflows.
to be able to bring these
experience experiences into life
in practice, I definitely believe,
and I have seen it firsthand.
So many of these enterprise applications
can now be developed without writing
a single line of code by specifying
instructions in plain text and
leveraging any kind of relevant knowledge
basis from variety of data sources.
Be it in documents, presentations,
or even databases, for example.
Teams can now create these custom GPTs, if
you will, or chatbots, or assistants, or
agents, tailored to their specific needs.
And another unique aspect that these
LLMs brought, truly, conversational
interfaces to interact with a
variety of software systems.
Even in conventional software
applications, chart is fast becoming the
preferred and primary interaction model.
And to be able to ensure that these
AI experiments, these AI apps become
successful, that's something that
you can rely on and use it in at your
work, in your organizations and teams.
It is really critical that we provide
access to these models in the first place,
create these capabilities in a way that
those are accessible to regular users,
and provide them that safe and secure
environment so they can actually play
around and build these applications.
The most important part of this is that
now that plain language is becoming the
primary interaction, not only to use
applications, but also to create, It's
very important to make these capabilities
accessible to every team member in your
organization, technical, non technical,
doesn't matter at all, and abstract away
some of these complexities with respect
to how to create the infrastructure,
the workflows, all the other backend
infrastructure tasks, if you will.
And of course.
creating a shareable catalog of sample
applications, reusable prompt libraries,
and a little bit of training so that
you can accelerate the adoption of
that platform in your organization.
And precisely in this context, I
would like to share about the Gen AI
platform that we have built, initially
for our internal teams, but now we're
using it for our customers as well.
We have built this generic platform that
allows anybody in our teams, irrespective
of the technical aptitude to be able
to quickly create a conversational
chart board or an assistant.
But that is also grounded on information
that is provided by the author of this
chart board from variety of data sources.
And kind of this is now
possible to do so in about five
minutes once you have an idea.
So once you can get the chart board
up and running in the five minutes,
it'll allow you to iterate faster,
quickly test them, refine the
prompts, refine the knowledge basis.
And once you feel good about the work, the
quality of the work, the way it is able to
process information, present information.
Then you can actually share with
everybody else in the organization.
And as I mentioned, we do support
federal agencies, and we made sure
that this can be deployed in entirety
into any customer environment.
The initial version of this product was
built as a CDK project with everything
needed, including infrastructure,
the databases for, vector stores,
the orchestration, the workflows,
the pipelines, the access control.
Everything is built using CDK
so that we can deploy to AWS.
We have different versions now available
that will make this entire platform
available to be deployed into Azure or,
Google Cloud or onto on premises as long
as you have a Kubernetes infrastructure.
this platform has been set up to
connect to LLM models across the board.
Either they're offered on AWS Bedrock,
OpenAI directly, or Azure OpenAI.
Our models on Google Vertex are pretty
much anywhere as long as you have
access to the API for hosted models.
And if you want to host your
own models, then, of course, it
is very specific to the cloud.
On AWS, for example, you could set them
up into the SalesMaker to be able to
make them available for the platform.
And the platform comes with handy Prebuilt
features, for example, that will take
care of most of the setup so that the end
users can just concentrate on fine tuning
their apps and making sure everything is
up to snuff in terms of security and by
making automation tools more accessible
across the organization, it definitely
sparks that creativity because everybody
is excited about able to use chart GPT
or a tool, something like chart GPT
that they can build for themselves.
That will help in their own work.
And of course it'll
boost their productivity.
If they could use their own work as well.
this means your team can definitely
streamline some of these workflows
in all, all kinds of shapes and
capabilities and present them in
a safe and secure space so that.
Everybody in the team can
experiment with these ideas
and create amazing applications
to be able to streamline and
automate the infrastructure, the
pipelines, the workflows, and the most
importantly, the security aspects.
We have looked at different use
cases and different applications.
and quickly standardized in all
these varieties of applications
and use cases based on a few basic
capabilities into four different groups.
The first and foremost
important one is chatbots.
These are probably the first application
any user try even on our platform.
And this primary use case is that this
will enable users to interact with
applications using natural language.
And you just can ask questions and
receive answers based on the context.
And this is completely grounded in
the private knowledge basis that the
others of the chartboards provide.
And there are connectors
available to load this information
from SharePoint conference.
Or just upload documents directly.
the next set of capabilities are
grouped into what we call as agents.
The agents are like chat bots,
but they're autonomous, that they
can autonomously make decisions to
decide the flow or the number of
iterations, for example, to prepare
appropriate answers or act on behalf
of the user, or just simply navigate
a multi-step processor, a workflow.
These agents will have the ability
to access different tools, APIs,
or functions, and also will have
access to data sources to gather all
relevant information and let them
make, let them make the decisions
to execute that particular workflow.
And they can iterate through
multiple steps to provide a
final response to the user.
And sometimes they can also act on behalf
of the user, like Creating a task list
or placing an order or updating status
in a tool like Jira, for instance.
And the next one is my favorite,
is what we call as AI for BI.
Every business collects tons of data, and
many enterprises have extensive teams and
systems to be able to extract insights,
analysis, and reports every single day.
However, in, in many cases, it
usually takes days to weeks.
to be able to get an answer
when a business team has a
question about something.
Because this typically requires teams
to go back and identify the right
data sources, fetch the data, put it
in a space area or space or a safe
area to be able to process the data
or create alternate views to be made
them accessible, and then extract those
insights and deliver those insights.
And if the business team happens
to have a follow up question,
which happens all the time based on
the information that is provided.
Typically, the next iteration
goes in a very similar
workflow again, days to weeks.
But now, thanks to LLMs, we can let
these business users ask questions
directly in natural language.
The orchestrator that will rely on
these LLMs, first of all, to identify
what data sources are appropriate,
fetch the data, process the data, And
summarize the data to be able to answer
that question and best of best case is
also that it will also provide all the
necessary background, how it arrived,
how did it process pretty much explaining
the process of going through answering
that question itself, along with the
evidence is presented to the user.
And this can happen within a
matter of one, probably 1 to 5
minutes instead of days or weeks.
We noticed our quickest question
on AIBA solutions is about 30,
35 seconds to three minutes.
It will take longer based on your
use case or quicker based on number
of data sources it need to look at.
number of iterations, number of
queries it need to make kind of stuff.
And it is possible with all the new
frameworks coming up, you can do
all these iterations in parallel.
Sorry, the number of queries in parallel
and quickly iterate that so that you
can actually improve that latency
to get the responses even faster.
And these apps can also support
data visualization, not just
presenting a textual summary, but
also data visualization, prepare.
Powerpoint decks, if you want,
generate reports of dashboards
along with the summaries and
insights in natural language.
So when you prepare a report, you're
not only looking at the visual aspect
of the data presented, but also the
textual explanation of what happened
or what is happening with the data.
And.
The key insights in that report itself,
and it's so easy and totally accessible.
Everybody can understand it.
It's textual, it's graphical,
combined, and it's automated.
The most important part is
this can happen in real time.
And the fourth group of.
Applications, and these are probably
the most powerful in this group,
are what we call as agent crews.
An agent crew represents essentially a
team of self organizing agents that can
collaborate with each other to perform
little bit more complicated tasks.
these agents will work together, assume
different roles and responsibilities,
bring their specialization aspect,
and automate and refine those
processes to create that final answer.
And these are particularly valuable
for multi step tasks, preparing
reports, for example, or doing
analysis, automatic security
testing, for instance, and others.
and even preparing comprehensive
documentation, for example, that
will take multiple iterations,
multiple loads and responsibilities.
So these are the four groups of
capabilities, and for each group, we
were able to identify exactly what
is needed to support these use cases,
the infrastructure, the workflows, the
pipelines for Rack stores, for example,
plus the observability aspect of being
able to see every piece of We have a
lot of back end interactions that are
happening to facilitate that response
so that developers and technically savvy
users have all the information that they
need to be able to evaluate, validate
the responses, look at the performance
issues, and go and refine them as needed
by offering a self service platform
team members throughout the organization
now can easily whip up and launch
these apps without long development
cycles that we used to have.
And it also speeds up innovation because
now everybody that has an idea can
easily and quickly create these apps and
everything else is taken care for them.
And in our journey, of course, we also
teamed up with federal agencies to
see what kind of workloads we want to
support, what kind of use cases we want
to support, and make sure that whatever
we build, that solution, it can smoothly
go live in customers environments.
And every team should be able to
try these things out in a safe and
secure space and smoothly move to
production whenever they're ready.
So to make it happen, we come up with a
serverless platform that is super flexible
and includes all the things that are
required, like an all in one platform,
and it plays nice with all the hosted
models as well as your custom models.
For example, if you want to tap into
any models that are hosted on AWS
Bedrock, You can do or if you want to
connect directly to open AI or host
your custom model, you will be able to
do that as well in the safe confines
of that specific cloud provider.
In this case, the initial version
was built with AWS, so you can
run everything in a safe and
secure way in AWS account itself.
And of course it got the power to reach
into a variety of data sources within your
AWS account as well as across different
accounts, guaranteeing that there is
a safe setup and data privacy across
your accounts and your applications.
Nothing is going beyond the security
boundary with respect to the
data or the privacy is concerned.
I would like to quickly show this
simplified platform architecture.
This is I made sure to bring it to the
essential model so that everybody can
see what it takes to build this platform.
And on top of it, of course,
you will be lots of additional
modules and little customizations.
But this will give you a com
a, a good gist of what it takes
to build a platform like this.
Starting with, you need an interface or
you will be using some kind of client
applications that will interact with API,
so I'm not showing the UI piece of it.
You can build it as an SPA using React or
Wrangler or view, for example, that will
serve as an UI layer for your application
that will interact with the APIs.
And this architecture shows what
it takes to build that API behind
the scenes that can provide these
rich capabilities into the platform.
So you have some kind of authorization
and authentication mechanism.
We're just using Cognito in this case and
federated with single as single sign on
if needed to connect to your enterprise
I am controls and an API gateway that
will accept the request that are coming
in to be able to support streaming.
Of course, you have other mechanisms.
I'll touch upon just in a minute and
the crux of the solution is what we
call as an orchestrator, This could be
a container service or a microservice
or a group or a series of microservices
that are, that will work in collaboration
to orchestrate the workflow that you
need to be able to answer that question.
For example, if it is a straightforward
chatbot, it will directly go and hit the
Bedrock API and get the responses back.
Or if the Rack store, it will include
going to the Rack, bring the context.
include that context and go
back to the bedrock model and
then get the response back.
And every interaction with the agents,
AI for BI, or the multi agent crews,
the, all the crux of the interaction
happens inside the orchestrator.
And it will be relying
on LLMs to do everything.
Some of that work, but orchestrators
are the most important pieces
in this specific context.
And that's as simple as that.
Once you have an orchestrator, and once
you have an API accessible to reach out to
an LLM, this will give you everything you
need to be able to build a Gen I platform.
Of course, you need access
to your data sources.
API is functions and whatnot, as
well as workflows and pipelines set
up that will allow you to upload
documents into your rack store.
And convert them into and store
them into rack store for easy access
later on as part of your queries
on top of it, you will be building
lots of other building blocks.
But this is the essential skeletal
architecture that anybody can build
this platform very quickly and
then refine the platform later on.
It's been close to a year now since
we launched the first version of our
platform, and we have come a long
way and want to share a few things.
That'll probably help you out if you're
also thinking or already building
a platform like this on your own.
the secret sauce to crafting this top
notch platform for your organizations
and clients is training and education
because everybody's excited, but they're
also scared a little bit on not to lose
their data, not to create another security
incident and worried about what kind of
information is fed back into these models.
and that somehow their information
doesn't show up in public anywhere.
So it's very super important to train
everyone in the system, not just
technical folks like developers and
testers, but everyone so that they
will have the foundational skins, like
writing a simple prompt, asking the
right question, right way so that LLM
can bring you more relevant answers.
Since a lot of these folks are also
new to Gen A apps, adding and allowing
them to experiment is really key.
Because we cannot allow them to come up
with the right prompt the first time that
experimentation is key and allowing them
to make mistakes is key and giving them
that immediate feedback as part of the
cost is incurred based on their query.
The latency aspects of performance
aspects, the bias aspects, the
efficiency with how it was able
to pull that information from rag.
So provide all that information
as a feedback to the users, but
make sure that let them quickly
experiment in a private space.
And whenever they're ready, let
them say, let them share it with
everybody else in the system.
And if it is developers, DevOps, security
folks, by allowing them to start using
tools like GitHub Copilot, they get
better with asking questions, working with
Copilots, and then that also allow them
to build applications like Copilots by
themselves by using these capabilities.
And organize some fun hackathons in
safe spaces so that Everybody can dive
into examples, get inspired by looking
at what everybody else is doing, and
get the lowdown on how to use it,
how to create these apps like a pro.
And when you are building up your
platform, it is really crucial to organize
these applications and capabilities
based on skills, based on use cases.
And some sample apps as well.
This will help everybody to understand
what is available, get inspired by
looking at what everybody else in
your organization are doing, and then
quickly start their own experiments.
And make sure that whatever you
build, abstract away all the
complexity and show the simple
interface that everybody can use it.
And that is the key for success
of any of the, any platform.
And it's also really important that.
It is, it's going to be a long journey
for you as your team as well that are
building this platform treated like
a product, start with an MVP, gather
some user input, see how they're
using, where they're fumbling, what
is working, what is not working, and
then constantly beep up those features,
and then you can unlock additional
use cases, additional, capabilities
and additional, security aspects.
And, of course, a lot more metrics that
will make sense to your users as well.
as I said, it's a journey,
it's a long journey.
that learning and adaptation is really
important to be able to build any
platform, but Janai specifically as well.
And when we adopt a little bit more
structured approach to giving training
to all kinds of users, giving them those
space spaces for experimentation, and
taking their feedback and iteratively
build it, I think you definitely
will pave the way for building a
really strong platform that caters
to changing needs and evolving use
cases in your organization and, of
course, for your customers as well.
So with that, I will want to quickly
run down a few highlights as a
summary from this conversation.
It is really important to provide a
safe and secure sandbox for your users.
And as I said earlier, try to optimize
your experiences for the non typical
users first because the language or the
lingua franca for generative experience
is a natural language and we want to
empower everybody in your organization to
be able to do So make sure you optimize
your experiences for the non typical
users and also create that environment
where they can learn from each other.
Looking at the catalog of applications,
catalog of capabilities, demos, as
well as shareable prompt libraries,
for example, go a long way.
with that, I would like to take this
moment to thank you very much for joining
this discussion on platform engineering,
especially building a Janai platform.
Feel free to reach out on LinkedIn
if you would like to connect
and continue this conversation.
Thank you very much, and
have a wonderful day.