Hello everyone and thank you for
this opportunity to present at
Con 42 Platform Engineering 2025.
My name Isla, and I've been working as
AWS Cloud engineer for the past seven
years, helping build scalable, secure,
and cost efficient cloud environments.
Today I'll be talking about
platform engineering with AI driven
self-healing AWS infrastructure.
The goal of this session is to show how
organizations can transform from manual.
Reactive cloud operations into
autonomous intelligent systems that
can self-diagnose, self-heal, and
continuously improve reliability.
We'll explore not just the technology,
but also the organizational
and cultural changes needed to
make this journey successful.
By the end, my aim is for you to walk
away with both practical strategies you
can apply and a broader vision of how
platform engineering and AI can help build
smarter and more resilient infrastructure.
Platform engineering has evolved
significantly over the years.
Traditionally, teams relied on manual
interventions, firefighting incidents,
and patching systems reactively.
This approach worked when
systems were small, but today's
multi-cloud and large scale AWS
environments are far too complex.
The modern approach is about intelligent
autonomous systems that can self-diagnose,
self-heal, and continuously optimize.
It's important to note that
AI doesn't replace engineers.
Instead, it amplifies human
judgment by learning from instance,
predicting failures and automatically
implementing remediation strategies.
Now, let's discuss the
core challenges at scale.
Overwhelming volume of alerts and
monitoring data exceeds human capacity.
Speed of modern systems leaves little
room for human interventions rapidly
evolving Security threads require
continuous monitoring complaints.
Requirements add another
layer of operational burden.
Scarcity of platform engineers
expertise and cost optimization at
scale requires intelligent automation.
Traditional approaches to
platform engineering cannot scale
to meet the demands of modern
enterprise entire environment.
Organizations that continue to rely
primarily on manual processes find
themselves at a competitive disadvantage,
struggling with higher operational costs,
increased downtime and reduced agility.
Here we introduced the AI driven
self-healing architecture.
First comes the intelligent
monitoring using Amazon DevOps
Guru to detect anomalies.
Amazon DevOps guru uses ML to analyze
metrics, logs, and traces to identify
anomalous behavior patterns that
might indicate emerging problems.
Next is the security monitoring,
using guard duty to identify
suspicious activities.
Guard duty also uses ml. Models
trained on AWS global threat, inter
intelligence to identify suspicious
activities and security breaches.
Now the issues are detected
and we need more AWS services
to respond to these issues.
Like AWS Lambda functions serve
as the execution engine for a
remediation actions triggered by
the events from the monitoring.
Services, step functions, orchestrate
complex remediation workflows that
require multiple coordinated actions.
The architecture continuously learns and
outcomes of remediations are analyzed so
that the system improves over the time.
This makes operations not just
automated, but adaptive and intelligent.
Let's look at the real world
examples before implementation.
Platform teams spent most
time responding to incidents.
Thousands of monitoring notifications
generated daily critical incidents,
took hours to resolve security incidents
required extensive manual investigation,
but after adapting, AI driven self-healing
systems available, improved significantly.
Meantime to resolution,
decreased dramatically.
Security incident response times improved.
Compliance violations addressed
proactively substantial cost
savings from optimized resources.
The organization's platform team
evolved from reactive problem solvers
to strategic architects of autonomous
systems, improving job satisfaction
and enabling the organizations
to attract and retain top talent.
Now let's look into the
four stage maturity model.
Stage one is the reactive automation,
and next is the predictive monitoring.
And then we'll go with the intelligent
remediation and autonomous operations.
Now let's dive into each of these
stages and see what all we need
to do to implement these stages.
So the first one is reactive automation.
So in this one, automating responses
to understood routine problems
with scripted remediation tasks
and basic monitoring systems.
These include like basic infrastructure
as core practices, standardized
monitoring dashboards, or having
automated runbooks for common scenarios.
And in the stage two, predictive
monitoring ML algorithms analyze system
behavior patterns to identify potential
problems before the impact users here.
AI powered monitoring tools
like DevOps Guru can be used and
sophisticated electing systems.
Can be adapted and expanded
automated remediation scenarios.
In stage three, we implement
intelligent remediation process.
So far it's just automating how we
detect the issues and monitoring them.
So now it comes to the
remediation process.
So AI systems automatically
diagnose and resolve most routine
problems without human intervention.
Like comprehensive event
driven architectures, complex
orchestrated workflows are
learning from remediation outcomes.
And next comes the autonomous operations.
AI systems handle the vast
majority of operational tasks
with minimal human oversight.
Like predictive capabilities prevent
most problems, self-healing mechanisms
resolve issues automatically.
Humans focus on strategy
and exceptional situations.
Progression through these strategies
and stages requires careful
attention to cultural change.
Alongside the technical implementation,
the teams needs to trust the autonomous
systems making decisions which are
previously reserved for human judgment.
Now let's technically deep dive into
some of the AWS service integrations.
So the first one is DevOps group.
It creates operational baselines
by analyzing historical data
patterns, learning normal behavior
for each application component.
It uses cloud wash event to trigger Lambda
functions when anomalies are identified.
And next is the AWS Guard, duty Guard,
duty Analyzes, DNS logs, VPS flow,
VVPC, flow logs and cloud rail events
to identify suspicious activities.
Findings are published to CloudWatch
events, enabling real time integration
with automated response systems.
Next is a S config.
It continuously monitors resource
states against defined policies.
Integration with system manager
enables automated remediation through
predefined playbooks that can correct
common configuration drift scenarios.
And next is step functions.
So step functions orchestrates complex
remediation workflows with sophisticated
logic for error handling, retrain
mechanisms and rollback procedures.
Lambda function serve as the
primary execution environment
for remediation logic.
The event driven arch architecture enables
realtime response while maintaining
loose coupling between the components.
CloudWatch monitoring and events serve
as the tech, as the central nervous
system routing events to appropriate
handlers based on configurable rules.
But transformation isn't just technical.
It requires organizational change.
Roles evolve from
troubleshooting incidents to
designing intelligent systems.
Teams need new skills in ML
operations, even driven architecture
and serverless computing.
Culturally, there must be trust
in automation achieved through
gradual rollout monitoring and
clear escalation protocols.
Leadership commitment proves essential
for successful transformation requiring
sustained investment in technology,
training, and cultural change.
Security and complaints are
also vital in this process.
Guard's ML models continuously
detect malicious activity.
Lambda functions immediately isolate
threats and config ensures continuous
complaints the than waiting for audits.
Compliance violations
are corrected instantly.
Importantly, not all alerts are equal.
The system prioritizes based on severity
and business impact, like critical issues
triggered immediate action and escalation.
While lower level ones are queued
for automated fix later, this balance
ensures both agility and security.
Now let's discuss change
management strategies like training
programs, mentorship, pairing,
experienced engineering with.
Newer team members are cross-training
initiatives, exposing team
members to different aspects of
autonomous operations, external
training programs, providing
specialized knowledge in AI and ml.
Next is the performance measurement.
We should move from traditional
performance measurement strategies
and adapt new metrics, emphasizing
systems reliability and autonomous
remediation success rates based on
contribution to business objectives
and collaboration with ai.
Communication strategies need to have
clear protocols for when and how to
intervene in automated processes.
Procedures for escalating problems
beyond automated capabilities are
must methods for sharing knowledge
about system behavior patterns like
knowledge translations are good.
Next is the risk management governance
frameworks, providing appropriate
oversight and addressing risk.
Regarding automated decision making.
So this transformation timeline
typically spans multiple years,
requiring patience and persistence
from both leadership and team members
do ahead.
Future trends will take this even further.
Generative AI will create remediation
strategies for novel problems.
Making automation more creative.
Explainable AI will increase
transparency, helping teams understand
why certain actions were taken.
Next is AI powered code generation.
This will speed up development time by
improving our, giving them solutions
for developing infrastructure as code.
At the same time, edge computing,
content computing and multi-cloud
orchestration will push
capabilities beyond today's systems.
These trends promise powerful
capabilities, but also require
careful evaluation of readiness
and integration, complexity,
simulation, and digital vents.
These are emerging powerful enablers.
Digital twins allow entire infrastructure
environments to be replicated virtually.
This lets teams simulate failures,
cascading problems, and remediation
responses without risking prediction.
It helps identify weaknesses before
they occur in real environments.
This is especially valuable for industries
like financial services, healthcare,
or any other critical infrastructure
where downtime is unacceptable.
Continuous implement through
simulation will be a cornerstone
of future self-healing systems.
Based on all of this, here
are some recommended steps for
implementation First, as is current
challenges and identify high
impact automation opportunities.
And next, build a strong foundation
in like infrastructure as code, or.
Having monitoring services and dashboards
in place and adapt event driven systems.
Next is implement automation gradually,
like start with the low risk areas and
then go with your, like in the first
step you have, you might have assessed
some of the existing challenges.
Just gradually increase one
take one risk at a time and
implement one solution at a time.
So that this will help
you grow more in future.
Fourth is invest in training
and cultural change.
This is as important as the technical
change like I discussed previously.
Next is establishing governance
frameworks for oversight.
So like when all the systems are automated
and the decisions are automated, you
need to know what is the escalation
process and when and human should.
Intervene or when he shouldn't.
We need to establish the trust
process and escalation process
when something goes wrong.
And finally, continuously
measure and improve.
So all these stages take multi-year
transformation timeline and plan for
su sustained investment in technology
training and organizational support.
This journey requires commitment,
patience, and sustained effort.
But potential benefits make it essential
for organizations seeking to remain.
T.
The future of platform engineering
lies in intelligent partnerships
between humans and ai.
AI handles the bulk of routine operations
while humans focus on strategy,
innovation, and exceptional situation.
This partnership enhances system
resilience, reduces operational
overhead, and allows platform engineers
to deliver more strategic value.
Organizations that embrace this
transformation thoroughly and thoughtfully
will build scalable, resilient, and
competitive capabilities for the future.
Thank you all for listening.
I hope this session helped you
understand not only the technology.
But also the cultural and
organizational shifts required for AI
driven self-healing infrastructure.
This is not just about automation.
It's about enabling platform engineering
teams to deliver higher value, innovate
faster, and create more resilient systems.
Thank you again, con 42
for this great opportunity.