Hey guys, welcome to Con 42.
Thank you for joining this session.
My name is she Reya and I
serve as a senior engineer
engineering manager at Truco.
Over the last several years, I had
the privilege of leading engineering
teams responsible for building and
scaling large distributed systems.
These are the kinds of platforms that
power millions of users and they come
with some unique engineering challenges.
One lesson I've learned is that scaling
isn't just about throwing more servers
at a problem, anyone can provision
more compute or more databases, but
true scale comes from making systems
resilient, adaptive, and importantly
simple for developers to work with.
That's really the heart of today's stock.
We'll explore how caching.
Something often treated as a
minor optimization can actually
be transformed into a self-healing
intelligent infrastructure component.
We'll see how that shift reduces latency,
improves reliability, and enables growth
without overwhelming engineering teams.
So let's begin by looking at the kinds of
challenges that make this shift necessary.
So let's start with the pain points that
almost every large scale system runs into.
As platforms grow, demand
scales faster than most.
Infrastructure can keep up with.
Databases that once seem to rock
solid, begin hitting connection
limits during peak traffic.
APIs that were fast under small
loads suddenly start chiming
out unpredictably and, sure.
Many of you have been in situations
where an engineering team spends days
or even weeks firefighting, rushing to
patch database overloads, or trying to
chase down why latency spikes during a
big traffic event and what's happening.
In those moments, developers
are distracted from building new
features because they're stuck
keeping the lights on tradition.
Traditional caching helps a little.
But it's limited.
They have static tls those
time to leave settings.
Al data either expires too soon leading
to unnecessary re computation, or it stays
around too long serving scale results.
Scaling is usually manually
manual and reactive.
Someone notices load building
up and spins up more nodes
and observable pretty is poor.
Engineers don't have the data
they need until a user complains.
This patterns repeat across companies,
industries, and technologies.
They highlight why we need
caching and infrastructure that
can actually adapt on its own.
So what does a better approach look like?
The vision is to build
systems that are self-healing.
That adapt, recover, and scale
without manual intervention?
There are five guiding
principles I want to highlight.
First one is self-service platforms.
Developers shouldn't need to
be distributed systems experts.
If a product team wants to add
caching to an EPI, it should be
as simple as a config change or a
notation, not VIX of deep engineering.
Second.
Intelligent systems traffic
patterns shift constantly.
Maybe a product launch in Europe
causes traffic to surge at 3:00 AM
Local time systems should notice
adept and rebalance caching strategies
automatically self-healing mechanisms.
Failure happens.
A cash node goes down a replica legs.
A region experiences network issues
instead of engineers waking up at
2:00 AM The system should promote
replicas, reroute traffic, or rebuild
state from logs without human input.
Fourth one is comprehensive observability.
Self-healing doesn't mean blind automation
teams still need reach, visibility
dashboards, metrics and recommendations.
So they understand what's happening.
Fifth one is effortless scaling growth
should not require a proportional
increase in operational effort.
If user traffic doubles, engineers
shouldn't suddenly be working.
Doublers, the system should
handle the growth gracefully.
This vision transforms infrastructure
from something BRI and reactive into
something resilient and adaptive.
Now let's move from
vision into architecture.
How do we actually design a caching
platform that supports this?
A key insight is that caching
works best as a layered strategy.
At the foundation you have database
caches reducing repeated query costs.
About that distributed caches
act as shared key value stores
accessible across services.
So for example, a Redis is an
example of distributed cache.
Then application level caches hold hot
data right where it's needed in memory.
Finally, edge caches deliver
content closest to the user,
improving global performance.
But layering isn't enough by itself.
The design is held together by
four architectural principles.
First one is service mesh integration.
The caching layer integrates with the
service mesh for automatic discovery,
routing, retries, and circuit breaking.
This services degrade
gracefully under stress.
The second is event driven architecture.
Caches are updated by
streams, not polling.
That means a sink, warming,
real time currency, and even
reconstruction state from event log.
Third is directory based ency at a
massive scale invalidating caches.
Cache is reliably is hard.
Directory based currency
protocols help ensures accuracy
across thousands of nodes.
Layered strategy by spreading caching
responsibilities across multiple tiers,
no single layer becomes a bottleneck.
So what's powerful here is that this
principles combine to make caching not
just an optimization layer, but resilient
backbone for platform engineering.
So static rules only go so far.
This is where machine learning steps
in with ML caching becomes adaptive.
So let's look at some of the.
ML techniques.
So first one is predictive cash warming.
Instead of waiting for a request,
ML models anticipate demand base on
historical usage, popularity spikes,
and even time of day patterns.
This reduces cold start delays.
Second is adaptive, TTL management
static expirations brittle, mL
dynamically adjusts TTLs based on
data volatility and excess patterns,
balancing freshness with efficiency.
Third is anomaly detection.
ML identifies the unusual
traffic potential cash poisoning
attempts or performance
degradations before they escalate.
So here the impact is clear.
Caching moves from being
reactive to being proactive.
Predictive and self tuning.
So how do we make this work in practice?
There are three main
implementation patterns.
First is automated pipelines.
Caching infrastructure should
be defined declarative.
Validated through GitHub's workflows
and rolled out with zero downtime.
This ensures consistency and reduces risk.
Second is developer friendly APIs
abstract away the complexity.
Complexity.
Developers should be able to annotate
methods or endpoints and instantly
benefit from caching strategies
without needing to know the internals.
Third is self healing mechanisms.
Systems detect failures within
milliseconds, promote replicas
reroute traffic seamlessly, and
reconstruct lost state from logs.
When these patterns come together,
caching becomes resilient,
consistent, and developer accessible.
Let's talk about
observability and monitoring.
None of this works if we
can't see what's happening.
Observability is what gives
developers confidence.
So if you can build dashboards that
could track cash or cash hit or mh
ratios latency distributions like P
50, P 95, P 99 memory utilization and
eviction rates error rates and timeouts.
But then more than raw metrics,
observability needs insights.
For example detecting that cache hit rates
dropped sharply after the deployment, or
recommending that caching a particular
endpoint could cut latency significantly.
Observability, if you think about
it, observability transforms raw
data into actionable guidance, and
it's what enables true self feeling.
What's the out outcome of all this work?
The impact of self filling
caching is transformative.
It basically provides latency
reduction users experience faster
response times across the board.
Database load reduction query
volume, drop dramatically.
Freeing capacity, third one is high.
Each ratios caches maintain
efficiently even during peak
surges and global consistency.
Geo distributed caches delivered
reliable performance worldwide.
In other words, caching shifts from being
a small optimization to being a strategic
enabler for scale and performance.
So let's zoom in.
How machine learning
actually powers caching.
There are different ML techniques.
And briefly describe
few ml techniques here.
So first one is neural networks.
So neural networks learn patterns in data
access and predict which items to preload.
We could also apply
reinforcement learning.
What it means is it could continuously
refine eviction strategies to
maximize hit ratio, hit ratios.
We could also use
clustering what it means.
So clustering means group workloads
or users for targeted cash warming.
The benefit includes higher hit
ratio than static approaches.
Reduce memory usage via smarter eviction.
Better search prediction during
traffic spikes cost efficiency
through optimized resource use.
Now this refrains, this sort
of, this reframes caching as a
continuous optimization problem
powered by machine learning.
Now let's talk about the edge where
the caching gets even trickier.
Extending caching to the edge
introduces unique challenges.
First one is currency at scale managed.
And this can be managed
with eventual consistency.
Vector locks.
Vector clocks, and read repair mechanisms.
The second challenges limited resources,
edge notes have less capacity.
So dynamic sizing
intelligent eviction and.
Compressions are essential here.
Third one, third challenge that we
have often seen is network partitions.
Edge caches must continue serving
users even when disconnected and
then reconcile when reconnected.
So by solving this caching ensures
performance is strong everywhere,
not just in core data centers.
So technology alone
doesn't guarantee success.
Practices matter.
So best practices include
self-service infrastructure.
What it means is developers can
provision caching resources with
one click run simulations and
configure without deep expertise.
The second is operational excellence.
Automating repetitive work,
applying predictive maintenance
and minimizing to toil.
Together these practices ensure
caching platforms are reliable,
trusted, and developer friendly.
The next slide talks about the
culture cultural transformation.
So culture is the multiplier
that determines success.
Technology alone.
Technology alone won't scale
unless culture evolves with it.
So what does it mean?
First is culture, which empower
developers, give them ownership
of caching strategies with
tools that simplify adoption.
The second is shared responsibility.
Reliability isn't siloed ops task.
It's shared across teams.
The third is data driven culture.
Use metrics and feedback loops
to guide continuous improvement.
The now what is the payoff?
The payoff is faster delivery, lower
cost, and a better user experience.
Culture is what unlocks the
full potential of technology.
So what lessons can we draw
from building systems at scale?
Some of the lessons include
developer experience comes first.
Simplicity and good communication
matter more than feature overload.
Incremental migration is essential.
What it means is support legacy systems
while enabling smooth transitions.
Third is observability is non-negotiable.
Metrics, validate assumptions
and guide decisions.
Third is expect challenges.
Technical hurdles like hotkey.
Technical challenges like hot keys are
solvable, but organizational resistance
and skill gaps require just as much focus.
And these lessons are universal
across large scale systems.
Finally let's look at
where this field is headed.
Near term trends include stronger ML
models, graph ql, caching optimization,
and automated capacity management.
Midterm.
Midterm, we will see innovations
like serverless cache functions.
Realtime cash analytics novel validation
methods and post quantum security
approaches long term, the vision is
AI driven optimization, autonomous
operations and intent base infrastructure
systems that understand what you
want, not just what you configure.
The TRA trajectory is clear.
Caching and infrastructure
are becoming more intelligent,
adaptive, and autonomous.
Let's wrap up with the big picture.
Self hailing caching isn't
just about performance.
It's about reducing latency, lowering
database load, maintaining reliability
globally, and empowering developers.
Caching has evolved from being side
optimization into a strategic foundation
for resilience and scalability.
If there's one takeaway from today, it's
this investing in self-healing cashing.
Unlocks faster systems, happier
developers, and sustainable growth.
Thank you.