My name is K, and I will be
presenting on healthcare.
Im probability.
I would like to start
with a simple question.
What happens when patient arrives
in an emergency room and their
medical history isn't accessible?
Too often doctors have to make decisions
without knowing about prior allergies.
As results or treatments.
This isn't an IT challenge, it's a
human challenge, and this is exactly
what healthcare interoperability is
about, ensuring the right data reaches
the right hands at the right time.
So today I'll walk you through
on how platform engineering
principles can help us solve
these interoperability challenges.
We'll cover the complexity of healthcare
data exchange, the architecture
we use to address the exchange.
How can the new cloud native and
AI powered solution help some
of the real world case studies?
And by the end, I hope to show you how
engineering choices directly translates
into improved patient outcomes.
The healthcare interoperability challenge,
healthcare data is fragmented, spread
across legacy EHRs, lab, imaging
systems, even personal applications.
Traditional point to point
can't keep up the scale.
Data formats vary.
Now, there are certain HL
seven fire custom schemas.
There is a high security and
compliance demand and solution
needs to scale from small clinics
to massive regional networks.
And when systems don't talk to
each other, patients pay the price.
We have.
A lot of challenges with respect
to having an emergency treatment
without any prior history.
There is a fragmented care in
care coordinations that there are
duplicate test because the test and
the priorit test information are
not available for the doctors to
provide the right care at the right.
So in order to address this, we
have a platform architecture for
healthcare data exchange, which is
a multi-layered architecture that
separates the concerns while providing
flexible integration capabilities.
Data ingestion layer handles connections
to diverse healthcare systems.
Through standardized connectors.
Data transformation helps to normalize
formats and also with the increasing AI
capability, this can, the mappings can
be achieved in a short period of time.
Orchestration layer basically will help
with validation of the business rules.
No consent if there are any,
and any conflict resolution.
The last but not least, the
application interface layer is
primarily providing access to this
information using FHIR compliant
APIs that applications can rely on.
This isn't just a technology stack.
It's about making sure that when a
specialist, a family doctor, and an ER
physician, all treat the same patient.
They are not working in silos.
They are looking at the same information
about the patient and providing
the right care that is required.
There are also cloud native
strategies that we can apply,
and this gives us agility in the
healthcare that is desperately needed.
Microservices and Kubernetes basically
can help from a scalability aspect.
Serverless computing
for variable workloads,
container ization, and also infrastructure
as a code for consistency and compliance.
And obviously as we move to cloud,
there are also an AI enhanced data
mapping and transformations, so ai.
In itself can significantly
reduce the complexity and cost of
implementing interoperability solution.
Traditionally, mapping requires a
lot of manual effort to identify
the relationship between different
data schemas and develop rules.
There are a lot of medicine learning
algorithms and NLP that can help with.
The matching semantic matching for the
mapping purposes, and also the NLPs
are widely available to translate the
free text clinical documentation and
providing the ability to search and
provide analytics on the documentation.
Under the notes
in this section I cover.
Briefly about security and compliance
architecture, of course, in
healthcare security isn't optional.
It has to be integrated
part of the solution.
So we implement federal identity and
single sign on there is always fine grain
authorization, which is provided by role
because different types of healthcare
providers require access to different
categories of patient information
based on their role in patient care.
Emergency physicians may need broader
access or specialties, require only
access to the relevant information.
The data has to be encrypted,
end to end in the solution
from transmission and storage.
Even if intermediate systems are
compromised, the data provides
automated rotation and secure
distribution of encryption keys.
That is a comprehensive audit.
Logging capture all data access and
modification activities to support
compliance, reporting, and secure
monitoring Generates detailed
records without manual intervention,
while providing real-time alerts
from suspicious action pattern.
This isn't about compliance,
it's about trust.
Trust between providers,
and most importantly, trust.
With patients.
These are some of the real world
implementation case studies that
I would like to walk through
a regional health information exchange.
Basically, HIEs are the organization
which connect hundreds of providers
now gives ER doctors access
to critical patient histories.
In minutes and seconds, there are
multiple hospital consolidation effort.
Used this approach to migrate system
gradually without disrupting care
and obviously patient facing apps
built on smart using fire APIs
and giving individuals control
over their complete health record.
Obviously while we have all of this that
has to be monitoring and observability
strategies that has to be aligned
with all of the implementation.
So talking through this while we have the
fire APIs, the application performance
monitoring tracks API response time.
Data transformation throughput
and system resource utilization.
Automated alerting ensures
immediate notification when
metrics exceeds threshold.
Data flow monitoring ensures
information moves through
information pipelines as expected.
It tracks messages, processing rates,
success rates, and end 20 de latency.
There's also an error in tracking analysis
which has, which is done comprehensively.
To ensure if there is an anomaly
detected within the data that has
been tracked and resolved in it
while we build the solution.
We also need to ensure that the
deployments are automated and there are
best DevOps practices that are adapt.
So healthcare and interoperable platform
benefits significantly from this
automated deployment practices that
reduce human error and enabling consistent
repeatable deployments across different.
The complexity of healthcare integration
solution makes manual deployment
processes error prone and difficult
to maintain as systems evolve.
Automated deployment pipelines ensures
that changes are deployed consistently
by also providing rollback capabilities
if there are any issues discovered.
So while we talk through.
The deployment, obviously from an
operationalization, what comes as the
performance optimization and scalability,
so as healthcare interpreter platform
handle significant data volumes,
transaction rates, while meeting response
times suitable for clinical workflows.
So we want to make sure the
data processing is optimized.
Efficient.
Transformational algorithms
minimize computational resources
while maintaining accuracy.
There are also able to handle
parallel processing approaches for
the increasing data volume need.
There are also intelligent caching
strategies to ensure that the same or the
similar set of data is cached within the
system and is not processed repetitively.
Database partitioning, indexing strategies
and query optimization enables platforms
to maintain, perform while accommodating
growing data requirement and historical
data that must remain accessible.
Load balancing and auto-scaling
ensures that perform platforms can
handle variable demand pattern while
maintaining cost efficiency, auto-scaling
algorithms, and just computing resources.
Based on demand while ensuring
capacity for traffic spike.
So where are we headed
from a future perspective?
Obviously there are blockchain concepts
that can be used in healthcare to
ensure there's a tamper proof audit
and patient control data sharing.
Through challenges around performance,
scalability, and compliance remain.
There are advanced AI capabilities using
LLMs that show promise of improving
clinical documentation processing,
and I'm enabling more sophisticated
and natural language interfaces.
So while closing, let's remember,
interoperability isn't just about
system talking to each other.
It's about ensuring people, patient,
doctor, nurses, have what they need
to make the best possible decision.
If we as engineers, architects, and
innovators can design platforms that
connect these dots, then we are not
just solving a technical challenge,
we are improving care, reducing cost,
and in some cases even saving lives.
Thank you.
A good.