Hey, hi everyone.
I'm Shiv.
And I'm here to present a very
interesting topic on forecasting
which is platform first forecasting.
And basically we are going to
talk about engineering scalable
machine learning systems that
drive a lot of business value.
And for the next 15 minutes, I want
to discuss fundamentally how to
build a really robust forecasting.
Scalable forecasting systems that
add consistent business value, right?
And it goes beyond just focusing
specifically on accuracy and focuses
on the whole architecture of the whole,
of the forecasting system in general.
A little bit about myself before we
dive into the details is I'm chef.
I have almost 13 years of work experience
across multiple industries in planning
supply chain SNOB, and forecasting.
I've worked with Caterpillar Dell.
And right now with Amazon where I lead
a team for a team of demand planners,
a forecasting team for Amazon, trying
to build something very similar
that I'm going to talk about here.
Highly scalable forecasting, machine
learning based forecasting systems that
are helping support Amazon's growth.
Rapid growth, I would say.
At a high level the agenda that
I would be covering today is
five key agenda items here.
First we'll talk about what Platform
Engineering Revolution means that
is really upcoming right now.
The Accurate Architectural
Foundations on which it is built.
Why?
It goes beyond accuracy as a
metric to you, define the success
criteria for good forecast.
And then implementation strategies
really important on how we put this whole
architecture into use for the business.
And then some really cool real
world success to stories where
this is already being used.
Awesome.
Rethinking the whole machine learning
based forecasting through a platform lens.
It's really important that the machine
learning landscape it's really important
to understand that the machine learning
landscape has undergone a lot of shift.
It has, it is not just about
this science model which is
this machine learning model.
It's about a lot of different elements
that enable this model to be successful.
The tuning, the the platform in which it
is built the architecture that supports
its deployment, that its usability the
pipeline of data that feeds these models.
Hence the platform based platform
First forecasting represents a
very holistic approach to machine
learning system design, and it.
Fundamentally prioritizes
three things, right?
Operational excellence.
Fundamentally how this whole architecture
is put to use scalability of multi-year
vision on building a system that does
not require complete re-engineering
every one or two years, right?
It has a really good
five to 10 year roadmap.
And then of course business alignment.
How the business teams are eventually
going to use it and put it to use.
A key insight I would love to add based
on my personal experiences brilliant
models setting in research notebooks
provide almost zero business value.
While moderately accurate models
deployed well through these scalable
systems, add much more value than
very sophisticated models that.
End up living in research
papers all their life, right?
So it's very important to learn and
understand how we can deploy these
complex models for the business
to use, and then derive a lot
of really good value from them.
Platform engineering revolution
in machine learning has happened
through, in my view, three main steps.
First is abstraction without
over oversimplification.
Of course, abstraction helps a lot
where really good, effective platforms
hide the complexity of the models and
allow the user to interact with the
models using really simple and easy.
Parameters, right?
And I think that is a really
important successful success
criteria for this whole architecture.
Progressive disclosure of complexity.
It's really important that a user of
some of these architecture and models
are not overwhelmed with information.
And complexity because the moment
that happens it really hampers its
deployment and its adoption in general.
So it's very important that anyone who's
going to use it is going to first we have
to assume that they have minimal technical
expertise and then create a really clear
glide path on how we can onboard them
and show them the complexity over time.
And lastly, API first design.
It's really important that
APIs evolve over time.
So clear versioned APIs for all
platform interactions needs to be done.
And it enables loose coupling
between these forecasting systems
and that consumers and it helps
long-term scalability as well.
Critical architectural components.
I think four key components that
enable this vision of platform.
First forecasting ML systems
is first is data, of course.
Data is the brand butter of
and machine learning model.
Being able to build really solid
data pipelines as well as a clean.
Usable data feeds is.
Fundamentally backbone of it.
So that is the very first step of
making this architecture successful.
Having a solid data architecture.
Number two is stream processing.
Of course, technologies like Apache
Kafka enables processing of a lot
of the data that we feed into these
models at a very high velocity.
And being able to have something that
can absorb and understand this data.
Is super, super important.
Security controls, again, a
foundational element, right?
Data privacy and intellectual prop.
Property production are like
foundation of any system that
consumes and manages a ton of data.
And being able to build something
like that is really important.
And a core building block for the
architecture that we are discussing.
Lastly, feature stores.
Every machine learning model every
machine learning system, I should
say, is unique in its own self, right?
Being able to understand, what
features are going to be built for
those specific use cases for those
specific businesses is really important.
And hence, understanding
where the specialization is
needed is very important.
For tracking and for future
service capabilities.
So we know what we need to continuously
evolve and what we need to maintain.
Now talking a bit about
the success metrics, right?
How do we make sure that we
understand the success of a
forecasting system or an architecture?
H how is that fundamentally
understood by the business?
The first thing in my view is
that goes beyond accuracy, right?
The fundamental accuracy may
wave RMC or any of those standard
accuracy measurement, metrics.
The first one being, business alignment.
How does the forecast enable anyone
to make decisions or understand
the risks, the trade offs, the
constraints in the business?
Because a forecast can be a single
number, but having context to
that number is really important.
Is it too high?
What is, what happened last week?
Is it too low versus
what happened last year?
Same time, and having those.
Having that perspective
is really important.
And that is where the business
alignment comes in place,
where the forecast is there.
But does it align to the business's
goals of, is it growing at the rate
at which the business should be
growing on a weekly level or at a,
monthly or a yearly growth rate level?
The second BI item is
operational efficiency.
One of the key things in my personal
experience that I've seen is some really
good models have really bad diplomats
which ends up being perceived by the
business as not a really good model then.
The science might be really
amazing, but guess what?
Being able to deploy it and create
recurring, really solid outputs
every single week or month is
really foundational to the system.
And hence the ability to use to, to
pick the right model and then deploy it
for the business is really important.
Then that is what get encompassed
in this operational efficiency.
How is and lastly of course, is
the model consistently creating an.
Guess what?
One day it created an output.
The second day it did not.
It's just not consistent and reliable, no
matter how good the science behind it is.
And that perfectly draws into the
reliability and consist consistency.
Part of it is not just.
The performance of the model on a
weekly, week to week basis, but does
it perform really well in a highly
stressed and a complex environment?
Businesses go through peaking
periods and non peaking periods.
Can it, can the model and the
architecture handle those periods
consistently week over week, day over day
throughout the year without any issues?
And there can be bottlenecks or
exceptions where it may not do that due.
May not I should say perform at the same
level as a different time of the year, but
being able to understand why and how, and
having, being able to, having, being able
to plan for it ahead of time is a key part
of this whole architecture as a whole.
The user satisfaction in the end,
the customer is the customer's
word is everything, right?
Having that customer
obsession to understand.
Is the forecasting platform
being used on a regular basis?
Is it being deployed?
Is it helping make really good
decisions in the end of the day?
Is the final stamp that confirms
this, whether the forecasting process
is successful or not, in a nutshell?
Next I want to talk a little bit
about asymmetric error handling.
This is a really important topic and
the reason I say that is oftentimes
in businesses and throughout
my experience, I've seen that
businesses index on a single value,
single number as a forecast, right?
The forecast next week is going
to be a hundred thousand let's say
units that are going to be sold but.
That single data point may
not tell the whole story.
Oftentimes businesses have different
risk appetites and over forecasting
might create less of an issue than under
forecasting or vice versa, and that.
Is an equally important data point
or strategy to understand for the
business than just looking at the
single number forecast and its accuracy.
To give really good examples is
the first one I wanted to list
down here is inventory management.
Certain businesses, stockouts are
a much bigger problem than having
excess inventory where inventory
costs might be very low and
stockouts might be very expensive.
And.
Maybe having access inventory is an okay
thing in some situations and making sure
the service level is really high, because
when the service level is low, guess what?
You lose customers.
Or the other way around where
stockouts might be a much bigger sorry.
I should say the other way around.
Excess inventory might be a much bigger
issue than stockouts, where having.
Constrained inventory doesn't really
create as much of business laws.
As we would expect.
So being able to understand
for the business, which one is
more important and which one is
not, is a very important input.
Similarly, infrastructure capacity.
This is a classic example of should we go
and invest more money in building more,
in more capacity to serve our customers?
Guess what?
When we invest, it's really expensive.
And when we invest, and guess
what the de like the utilization
does not come through.
You're sitting on a lot of
depreciation cost Similarly.
If we don't invest, guess what?
There's a service degradation.
Is that okay for our customers?
Being able to quantify and
understand which one is more
important is extremely important.
Sim something similar happens
in financial forecasting.
The regulatory requirements and
the risk of management protocols
should the business go very heavy
on, regulatory compliance, which
requires a lot of, manpower and our
time investment versus moving fast
where, the business can choose.
To be compliant at a bare minimum
and keep moving fast to grow the
business or being excessively indexed
over meeting, the financial goals.
And the punchline being, being, effective.
Asymmetric error handling requires,
a lot of loss function design
that reflects actual business
consequences rather than just.
Something that is for mathematical
convenience and having a platform
architecture that understands and takes
this feedback is really important.
Next microservices
architecture of ML systems.
The decomposition of the, this
monolith of forecasting system
into focused microservices provides
numerous advantages including improved
scalability, enhanced maintainability,
greater deployment flexibility.
And the four big buckets that I
want to talk about with respect
to these microservices is first is
data and ingestion services, right?
Being able to handle diverse
sources varying frequency.
It updates daily, it updates hourly,
and at the same time, having a really
high quality of data, maintaining high
quality of data is really important.
The second one is feature
engineering services.
Again, being able to transform
the raw data into something
that the model can consume.
And understand and interpret,
and then create a final output
is another foundational element.
The model training services every model
requires some training, some assistance in
the short term or even in the long term.
And being able to do that in a
flexible and controllable and a well
understood manner is a key step.
In terms of making the whole model,
the forecasting process and the
whole architecture successful, right?
So it's a very important pillar.
And lastly, prediction.
Serving services like providing
real-time access to model predictions
through scalable load latency interfaces
enables our customers to consume
the data and reduces any friction in
terms of them for them to understand,
Hey, what is a forecasting output?
How do we use it?
Where can it be immediately where
it can be synthesized to be used
for day-to-day decision making?
And that's really important for
the success of our customer.
So being able to have really solid data
pipelines through dashboards, through
ui, ux interfaces for the customer to
consume that information and deploy
that immediately is another key step.
Next I want to talk about containerization
and orchestration strategies.
Again, this is really important.
When we look at, building really complex
systems, because if we don't containerize
and, understand the building blocks of
or I should say being able to design how
these building blocks interact with each
other, the system get really complicated
and of course become a roadblock in the
long term to build scalable solutions.
There, there are some key considerations
that we should consider when a
containerizing, these massive
architectures that we built.
One is fundamentally understanding
how these containers are going
to handle the machine learning
work, machine learning workloads.
Every ML model has a different
workload requirement.
Every architecture or use case has
a different workload requirement,
and being able to understand
and containerize it based on the
requirement is a foundational.
I would say, or more than a foundation,
like I think is one of the first
steps are design steps that needs
to be considered when thinking
through the whole architecture.
Of course there, there are other elements
to it, like horizontal part auto scaling
for demand patents is, has been one
of the latest go-to methodologies.
In the recent times that
I've seen serviceness.
Technologies for network and
security is another use case.
Persistent storage management
for large data sets.
Particularly important when.
If we look at a longer horizon of
an implementation, like four to five
years, the data set is going to grow.
How are we going to handle it?
What are the policies of
keeping and storing data?
How do our customers want to read and
consume this data on a day-to-day basis?
And lastly batch processing
capabilities for periodic tasks.
Like you, you may not want to
query a 20 million to 20 billion.
Row table every single day.
Maybe the customer only needs
the latest and greatest.
Let's say the forecast, the version of the
forecast that we published only yesterday.
Maybe we can do batch processing
to manage the machine the full
workload of this whole architecture,
much better by segmenting and
understanding what is needed by the
customer on a day-to-day basis versus
on lesser frequency and frequency.
In general.
And again, each system has
its unique requirement.
And hence being able to understand
and document and then make sure
that each of those, criteria and
considerations are understood and
is a part of the design process.
It's it becomes really.
Helpful, particularly in the long
term for that system to scale.
Lastly yeah API design best
practices for immune systems.
Really important again restful API design
principles provide a solid foundation,
but must be adapted to handle the unique
characteristics of prediction services,
resource modeling for prediction must.
Balance, simplicity with expressiveness.
Simplicity being really important for
majority of the architecture with a
unique touch of what is the, what is that
complexity that is needed that is bare,
like foundationally needed, that cannot be
that, that not be present fundamentally.
So the second one is request and response.
Schema design must be flexible enough
to accommodate diverse input formats
while providing sufficient structure
for validation and documentation.
Authentication and authorization are
really important that we don't give
all the access to every single user.
It should be based on
every individual profile.
And being able to manage that is
becomes much more easier on the
architecture to manage, multiple users.
Particularly as you scale.
Not all users will have complete access.
While the majority of the users
will have very specific access,
while others will have the.
Higher level access in the hierarchy
so that they can change stuff
and evolve things much better.
A PA version strategies we discussed
about this previously versioning
is really important, particularly
as we scale so that we have, really
good backward compatibility of
a system and we don't get stuck.
In long term scalability.
Now on the fun part, real world
implementation success stories and the
first two, like EI, I'll talk about
three, e-commerce global logistics
and financial service organization.
I think these three other ones that
I have been very close to personally.
And I can really vouch on how platform
based these platform based architectures
have really helped businesses.
The first one, e-commerce.
I think working with Amazon, I
think I've learned, like e-commerce
grows rapidly and the use cases of
forecasting systems is very unique.
Forecasting a pen number of pens that
we would sell throughout the year is
very different than forecasting the
number of phones or, chairs or couches
that will sell in a year throughout the
year and having different and because
it's so different across the things.
Because it is so different across
these specific use cases we deploy
different machine learning methodologies
across each of these SKUs, and which
in the end requires a very high
compute, highly complex architecture.
To manage right In the end, because
the data sources are different, the
ML models are different, the end users
are different, and hence the whole
containerization that I mentioned
above, the microservices I mentioned
above, becomes really important because
we can build these systems like Lego
block, Lego blocks where certain
level blocks may not be important for
one type of a forecasting use case.
It might be very useful for others.
And being able to do that is, has been
one of the most interesting challenges
that we have o overcome, right?
Global logistics similarly like
every leg of a logistics has a
very different customer base.
And a use case, a first mile is different
than a last mile or a middle line.
And being able to meet and fulfill
the, fulfill those specific
use cases of each leg requires.
Platform based forecasting because
it for, it, it builds a really
solid foundation to meet different
requirements using very similar Lego
blocks with a solid architecture
financial service organization.
Again really important
where regulatory compliance.
Is very important in now in any business
and being able to forecast and understand
where risks exist, be it, our credit
risk or market forecasting, the sales
forecasting that we use to understand
the long term cash flows, et cetera.
And having really.
Good.
Interpretability in these models
and bias detection mechanisms
enables a very successful
financial benefits any business.
But because the finance because the
financial systems will tell a much
tour picture of the future state of
the organization than anything else.
Lastly, the future
direction and conclusion.
Conclusion I think.
The key emerging trends that we
have seen from our point of view is
automobile technologies have been,
have started to democratize, right?
Like a lot of the models that we see
today are available in almost any system.
It, majority of them are available
in most Python libraries or even AWS
platforms, which can be leveraged almost.
By anyone at a very low cost.
And hence the being able to the
federated learning piece where
people are collaborating together
to build singular models which are
successful across multiple businesses.
And then real time machine learning
with continuous adaptation where
the model evolves every single day,
every single hour, I would say.
And then, of course,
sustainable computing practices.
And agreeable is another key part of it.
The key takeaway is I think the punchline
being, successful forecasting platforms
balance, technical sophistication
with operational pragmaticism, right?
It's about building a very complex
system while also being able to deploy
it successfully for the business
to make really good decisions.
And it's not just tied to the
accuracy and accuracy should
not be used as a bottleneck.
To deploy complex and stable and
really good systems to enable the
organizations to make solid and really
good decisions in the end of the day.
Yeah.
Awesome.
Thank you.
That's all that I had.
I know I had a very little time to cover
a really complex topic in the end, but if
you have any questions, feel free to reach
out to me on LinkedIn and I would happy
and I would be happy to discuss more with
you guys and share more of what I know.
Thank you.