Good morning everyone, and
thank you for being here.
My name is Sunil and I have an
experience for almost like a f 16
years of experience in the networking
domain and in the security domain
and also in the automation side.
So today we are here to discuss
about the topic called bridging the
layers in the platform engineering
in the modern network stack.
So in the next 15 minutes, I
will take you through why this
topic is so important to us.
The challenges we face in today's
environment, the tools that help
us to improve our security and the
deployment and everything else, right?
And then finally, some real world
strategies and lessons we can apply.
Okay?
Coming to this matter, why this
is so important for us, right?
Why this matters for us.
Let's begin why this matters, because
applications today are no longer
built as chain monoliths, right?
So they are distributed across different
regions and different locations and in
different cloud environments, right?
Some of them might host the applications
in AWS, some of them might host the
applications in Azure, and some of
them might host the applications
in their on-prem data centers.
And there are scenarios where they want
to host the applications in multiple.
Cloud environments and also in the
on-prem depends upon the needs of the
business and all those things, right?
That makes all clear lines
between infrastructure, the
networking and applications,
but to blood together, right?
Because the requirements have been
changing every day and we have to
see how we can make these things.
Align together and make it in a
better way to deploy the things.
Today, the developers are
expecting something different.
They want the platforms that are fast,
secure, and self-service without needing
to worry about the plumbing underneath.
So why they want, they don't
need to worry about how that.
Network is built at the downstream
where they don't have any knowledge on
how the things are deployed and also
the security of the deployments, right?
So the shift is focusing to rethink the
how infrastructure platforms and networks
come together, and that is where the
platform engineering enters the picture.
Okay.
The key challenges, of course,
that is not easy, right?
The first challenge is complexity
with the hybrid deployments, right?
Where we have the the applications
being deployed in multiple clouds.
And I would say deploying
the things in the on-prem.
And, most probably the how the, all the
things are being deployed and they're
very tough to analyze for a developer.
And the second thing is the
challenge of the security.
The world is moving so fast
with the zero trust mindset.
That means that we have to
identify, verify our required
across each and every layer.
We are deploying the things now, not
just at the at the where the is deployed.
We have to.
We deploy the things more securely for the
business owners and for the applications,
and also for the businesses, right?
And also the last, but not least, right?
The performance of the applications
because the applications being deployed
in a multiple cloud environment and also
in a different geographical locations.
So the third thing is very important
is like the performance, right?
And the way we are deploying the modern.
Applications.
They're very sensitive to the
latencies and they want the things
to be very fast because some of the
financial transactions, gaming and
also the apps, everyone is not ready
to wait for a minute also, right?
Today everyone wants the things
to be happening in a millisecond.
So the performance very mad, is
really very important for the
applications to function seamlessly.
Finally the developer's experience, right?
Reducing the friction for
developers is very critical.
Otherwise, they will bypass the
security controls or build shadow
infrastructures just to move faster
because everyone wants the things to be
deployed in in a days now, not in months.
Earlier we used to take years even for
developing an application, but things
have changed so fast and everyone wants
the things to be done very faster, right?
And in order to.
Deploy the things faster and securely.
We have to think about entering into
the platform engineering, right?
This is where the platform engineering
comes into the picture, right?
Things of all, its glue
between infrastructure,
networking, and applications.
Everyone has to understand how the things
are deployed at each and every layer.
And it's very different, difficult for
everyone to understand those, right?
The main objective of the platform
engineering is abstracts, complexity,
automates the repeat to the
operations, and also provide the
secure self-service platforms.
It creates this foundation that
bridges the developers and operations
teams and also security, right?
In other words.
It lets developers move quickly
while keeping, while still
keeping the network and infras
infrastructure stable and secure.
So if they deploy the things
faster without thinking about
the security aspects of the
applications, that's where the real
challenge of issue realize, right?
Like where people will struggle
in deploying the things securely.
And there is a chance of people trying to
use that loopholes and getting into the
networks or exploiting the applications.
So this is where we have to start
thinking about how do we use, actually
enable the platform engineering and
what are the tools which we can use
today in order to use this kind of a
platform engineering where we can think,
deploy the things faster and securely.
There are four key tool sets.
We'll talk today, the service mess
which eng, which manages the service
to service com communication,
observability, and also policies.
And the next one is the API Gateway
is that's where the security
of ingress, authentications and
developer friendly access is needed.
And the next one is the zero trust
models, which makes sure security
is identity driven and continuous.
And also the finally, the
programmable infrastructure.
Things like infrastructure as code
and GI tops, which allow us to
conti consistently deploy and manage
across the environments, right?
Because as I said like earlier
things we are deploying the things in
multiple cloud environments, right?
And they should be a unique way
of deploying the things faster and
within same set of configuration.
I mean to they say at the security
level or whatever that is, right?
So they have to be unique and we have
to see how programmable we can deploy
the things and automate the stuff.
Service mesh practice.
Let's start with the service mesh
examples include sst, o and linkard.
These tools sit inside the cluster and
manages the east west traffic and retries.
And the observability.
I'm not here to advertise for any kind
of a product or anything like that.
So I'm just bringing up a couple
of examples for the people who
can understand the things, right?
So now we have many other, applications
of the tools in the system are in
the environments now where we can
go ahead and pick whichever is
more relevant to the businesses.
They also bring in MTLS encryption, right?
That these tools can bring encryption
things, which critically for securing
the communications between the services.
The key benefit is that developers don't
need to build these features themselves.
The mesh uploads that complexity,
given them a clean, secure
way to connect the services.
And the next thing is the API
Gateway and Developer's experience.
The the examples of the API gateways are
nothing but like an NGINX like an a PGE
Kong, and there are some kind of an open
source API gateways as well which are
very, user friendly applications as well.
Gateways, which are being used now because
everyone wants, don't want to go on with
some kind of an like an tools which are
not ready to be like an open source.
And it's very hard to manipulate
those configurations, right?
Everyone is looking at
some of the open source.
Tools nowadays because that way we
can enhance the tools and deploy
the things on our own, and also
we can increase the security of
that if there is anything on that.
So some of the people are really looking
at some of the open source tools nowadays.
We have to think about all these things
and for the future deployments and
all those things in practice, they
act as this API gateway, us act as a
bridge connecting the external users
to the platform and then to services.
Behind it, right?
For developers, it makes access
simple, controlled, and secure.
Because of these tools, the
a p gateways takes it of that
kind of an ingress security.
And the next thing is
the zero trust security.
What do you mean by zero Trust?
Security has to be everywhere
nowadays, not just as at the perimeter.
That's where zero trust comes in.
So earlier people used to think there
is an firewall, which is sitting in
in the entry of our network is the
one which gonna secure the things.
It's all over now, just.
Securing at the at the entry or
the perimeter level is all gone.
We have to be thinking about more
more ways of securing this stuff.
So this is where the zero
trust comes in, right?
Instead of assuming that once
you are inside the network,
you are not safe everywhere.
It's, every request is
verified continuously.
This is enabled by I identity aware
proxies and policy driven access.
Examples include the pfi S-P-I-R-E for
service identity for and Google Beyond
Corp models for enterprise access, right?
This approach ensures that both
users and services are verified
before they can touch any resources.
Next comes to the
programmable infrastructure.
Now let's talk about the
programmable infrastructure, right?
With tools like Terraform, combined
with GitHubs tools such as Argo CD
and Flux, we can make infrastructure
reproducible and version controlled.
So someone else let's say that you have
a code on your system and someone else
is also having a code on their system.
We don't want them to be pushing the
codes individually and have a different
ways of deploying the things, right?
So there should be an version controlled
way of doing the things with the GitHubs
and all those things where people know.
Like what the changes have been made
by the other developers so that they
can think about it and someone reviews
and approves the changes with this
tops and all those tools so that
they don't make any unwanted changes
into the environment, which is well
structurally built by someone else.
So this version control thinks,
makes the things streamlined and
also lets the developers to do
it in in a well fashioned way.
This is a powerful because it
enables trust self-service because
you don't need to do this repetitive
task again and again with this
infrastructure as a core platforms.
Right now, developers can request
infrastructure and the file system spins
up it automatically in a consistent way.
No more manual tickets, right?
So with these tools, we are
making everything automated.
People doesn't have to go through that
entire process when they're starting
to build the first application.
So now they know the process,
like whatever they wanted, right?
For any application to be built
let's say that you want an IP address
for the other server or a DNS name
and all those things, these are all
incorporated into the code so that they
all can be happen at the same time.
You don't need to, worry about these
repetitive tasks again and again so
that there are chances then when you
go for this kind of and repetitive
task, there are chances, like people
might miss one step in the deployment.
And there is a chance that people when
they go for a production deployment,
they worry about what happened?
Where did I miss?
And what happened over there?
So instead of that these things,
these tools really helps us a lot
in order to automate this stuff.
And make it like avoid doing any kind
of manual mistakes, which people do.
And this repeatable task being
performed by this programmable
staff makes the things faster.
Also in a more secure way might be
some people might forgot to deploy
in firewall configuration or a
security configuration over there.
And it becomes a problem for the
security of that application.
So this repetitive task should be be
performed by some kind of an programmable
infrastructure so that we don't run
into any kind of an issue when the
applications goes into the deployment.
And the next thing is the
design strategies, right?
Of course.
How we design this platform is
really matters because you cannot
just blindly deploy anything.
And then without knowing how the
underlying things are working
and all those things first layer
abstraction without holding too much,
we want to shield developers from
unnecessary complexities, but still
allow them to visibly and control.
Where needed second, consistently
across environments, whether be
running it in on-prem or in the
cloud or at the edge, the platform
should look and feel the same.
They cannot have a different
base of deploying the stuff when
they host it in AWS or when they
host it in Google, or when they
host it in somewhere else, right?
Or even at the on-prem.
So the things has to be very u same
for the user field and also for the
security and all for the other things.
And the third one is a secure by design.
That means that integrating policies
from the start and continuously
measuring so we know that what's
working and what needs the improvement.
Let's jump into the real world examples,
to make this concrete, let me share
a couple of real world scenarios.
One organization was running
a multi-cloud microservice.
They were struggling with both
the performance and security.
They decided to adopt a service mesh for
secure service to service communication,
and a PA gateway for external access and
infrastructure as code for consistency.
The result.
The reduced meantime dis recovery
to 40%, and also perhaps more
importantly, develops adoption to the
platform increased like dramatically.
So that's the power of platform
engineering when applied effectively.
Let me wrap up.
The te the key takeaways from this
one is platform engineering is gonna
bridge the infrastructures, networking
and the developers, the service mesh
gateways, zero trust infrastructure
as a code, as a core enablers.
The balance is always between
the developer's experience,
scalability and security.
And the best way forward is to
start small, automate incrementally
and measure continuously.
And I would like to close it today for
with saying thank you for everyone for
joining this session with me today.
And platform engineering is not
just a technology trend, it's an
shift in how we design, operate,
and secure modern applications.
If there is one thing I would like
to leave with, it's a Bridging.
The layers is about more than tools.
It's about enabling developers,
operations, and security teams
to work together seamlessly
in modern network stack.
Thank you everyone.