Hello everyone, my name is Roman
Shmahelsky and today I'll talk about
business acumen and why it's so
important for software engineers.
To set up the scene,
imagine you're at your desk.
You have some free time, so you open Jira
to figure out what you should do next.
There are two tasks in your backlog.
The first task is a
technologically challenging one.
It's complex, it involves cutting
edge technology, and it will require
you to push your skills to the limit.
Let's call this task Create Your Own LLM.
It's the kind of task that gets you
excited as an engineer, because it's an
opportunity to solve a difficult problem.
However, this task will only
impact a small portion of advanced
users whom might appreciate the
value that you are building.
The second task we can
trust is much simpler.
It's a bit boring to be honest.
It involves streamlining few processes
and improving the user experience
for a basic function that nearly
all of your customers use daily.
Basically, moving buttons in
UI happened with all of us.
It doesn't involve anything groundbreaking
from a technical standpoint, but it
will make the product significantly
easier and more enjoyable to use
for the majority of your customers.
And here's the twist, you know you can't
do both, you need to push back on one.
Now ask yourself, which task
would you pick, and why?
When answering this question, a
lot of developers will think about
technological advancement of the
project each task could bring, or
perhaps some knowledge they could gain.
In simple words, they'll use their
hard skills to assess the situation.
But today, hard skills are not enough.
And let me explain you this.
Throughout my career, I've had the
privilege of working with many software
engineers, and let me tell you, most of
them are exceptionally bright individuals.
I try to stay in touch and
follow their career closely.
There is one engineer in
particular who comes to mind.
He could easily spend hours debating
the merits of React versus Angular, or
intricate methods to optimize database
storage, or diving into the finest
details of JavaScript interpretation.
Honestly, being in the same
room with him sometimes made me
feel like I was out of my depth.
His ability to craft elegant solutions
to complex problems was so remarkable
that I found constantly putting
off my other tasks just to review
his code and learn something new.
But as the years went by, and
despite his impressive technical
achievements, promotion seems to have
passed him by, and he wasn't alone.
I've encouraged many brilliant engineers
who described their technical expertise,
struggled to gain recognition,
and move up in the career ladder.
And even if you decide to explore
opportunities elsewhere, it's
not a secret that today's job
market is highly competitive.
Every job posting attracts hundreds of
applications and dozens of interviews.
All of these engineers were
technically experts, and in today's
environment, that's simply not enough.
To stand out, whether you're seeking
a promotion or a new job, you need
more than just a technical excellence.
You need a soft skills
and a business acumen.
And that's what I want to
talk to you about today.
How leveraging business insights
can be your key to standing
out in this crowded field.
But, who am I to talk on this topic?
nearly a decade ago, I first began
my journey as a JavaScript engineer.
Over these years, I had the opportunity
to work in the wide range of environments
from small startups to corporations,
from product focus companies to
outsourcing companies, and each of these
experiences have shaped my perspective.
And recently, two years ago, I was
promoted to software engineering manager.
So LifeSync Syncs provides
managerial perspective as well as
individual This gives me a good
view of how business acumen plays
a crucial role in our careers.
Alright, before we dive back into
the soft skills, let's briefly review
the key actors in our projects.
In any project there are multiple parties
who shape the outcome, and each of these
groups brings a unique perspective to
the table and their input is crucial
at different stages of the project.
But when it comes to making
decision, whose opinion matter most?
The truth is that all of these
opinions are matter, but not
equally and not in every stage.
When making decisions, it's
important to prioritize these
voices based on the context.
So first and foremost,
we have the customers.
They are the ones who ultimately
bring the revenue, so their
needs and feedback are critical.
Business leaders are also key players.
They are the ones who took the
risks, created the business,
and set the overall direction.
for listening.
Without their vision and leadership, there
simply would be no project to work on.
Project managers comes next, cause
they act as a voice of customers
within our teams, translating
customers needs into actionable tasks.
And finally, we have tech teams.
While our technical expertise is
essential in bringing the project to
life, it's important to remember that our
decisions should align with overarching
business goals and customers needs.
In summary, while it might be tempting
to focus solely on the technical side,
by aligning our decisions with the
priorities of business leaders and project
managers, we can ensure that our work
not only solves the technical challenges,
but also drives the business forward
and meets the customers expectations.
Now, let's talk about how our skills
are perceived in this context.
For most managers and business
leaders, they don't come
from technical backgrounds.
To them, your hard skills and
ability to code and develop
features are like a binary switch.
You either can't develop a feature
in time, or you simply can't.
And once you demonstrated a certain level
of technical proficiency, others might see
you as capable of getting the job done.
However, due to the lack of
understanding of the complexity of the
work, they might not fully appreciate
the excellence in certain skills.
On another hand, soft skills are more like
a flaws, they exist on spectrum and can be
easily assessed by non technical people.
Your ability to communicate effectively,
collaborate with others, and think
critically are all visible and measurable.
This is why once you reach the
certain level in coding abilities,
investing good time in developing
your soft skills became crucial.
These are the skills that will
set you apart and will make your
work visible and appreciated by
everyone, not only technical folks.
And this helps you advance in
your career, when the technical
expertise alone is no longer enough.
This all brings us to the
concept of business acumen.
So what is this business acumen about?
I would define it as a
combination of several soft skills
applied to the right context.
And what soft skills are we talking about?
Think about what's essential for starting
and running a successful business.
Problem solving.
Every business is funded on the need
to solve some specific problems.
Next, we have communication.
To be successful, you need to
be able to deliver your ideas
and solutions effectively.
Next, we have critical thinking.
Critical thinking, we have to understand
the problems that we are trying to
solve, and this is very essential.
Leadership and proactivity.
You need to take action and drive the
initiatives to achieve the success.
These are the same principles that
apply directly to software engineering.
If you think about each feature that you
work on as a small business, you would see
that the problem solving, communication,
critical thinking, and leadership
are just as crucial in our field.
Having business acumen in
software development means more
than just writing a good code.
It means to understand stakeholders
needs, making decisions that
aren't just technically sound,
but also strategically smart, and
anticipating the effect of your work.
It's ability to see beyond the immediate
technical challenge and grasp the
broader implications for the business.
This is what distinguish the good
engineers from the great ones.
Those who not only solve the problems,
but do it so in the way that they can.
that drives the business forward.
And you might be thinking this is all
sound very complicated and boring and I
just want to write some software without
getting caught up in the politics.
But let me break down what business
mastery really means in practical terms
and you'll see it's not so complex.
So at its core business is
all about earning money.
Even non profit organizations
need to generate income not
for profit, but to fund their
operation and achieve their goals.
And to do this, business owners employ us.
That's a sad capitalist reality.
But it's true.
The main reason we have jobs is not
to experiment with new frameworks or
play with cutting edge technology,
but to contribute to the financial
success of our organizations.
And in a software company,
making money means attracting
and retaining more clients.
As simple as that, more
clients, more money.
To achieve this, a few things are crucial.
Understand client's needs.
You need to know what your clients wants
and you need to figure out it fast.
It involves listening to their
feedback, analyzing market trends
and anticipating their future
needs, solving client's problems.
Once you understand what clients need,
the next step is to solve their problems.
And again, speed is of the essence.
The faster you can provide the solution,
the more competitive you become.
And iterating.
Finally, it's not enough to just
release a solution and call it a day.
You need to continuously iterate,
refine, improve, and adapt your
software to changing client
needs and market conditions.
And we need to do it fast to
stay ahead of the competition.
This cycle of understanding,
solving, iterating at the speed
is the essence of how the software
companies succeed in the marketplace.
Now you might wonder, what about
all of these business analysts,
product owners, and project managers?
Isn't this their job?
And you are right.
These roles are specifically designed to
focus on understanding business needs and
translating them into actionable tasks.
They spent years learning
and mastering these skills.
Your job isn't to replace them, but to
act as a bridge between their strategic
vision and your technical execution.
Here is where your technical
expertise becomes invaluable.
While business analysts and product
owners excel in identifying what
needs to be done, They often lack
of the technical knowledge to
understand the best way to solve this.
For example, have you ever been in a
situation when the project manager tells
you that the change is very small because
a similar change was made in another
project, but you realize that in reality
it's not that simple and it might require
significant architectural changes?
This is a perfect example of where your
technical knowledge comes into play.
By understanding both the business
goals and technical constraints,
you can propose a better solution
that meets the business needs.
while also being efficient and
feasible from a technical standpoint.
This is a win situation.
You're helping the business to achieve its
goals while you're ensuring the technical
implementation is sound and sustainable.
This is what business acumen looks like
in practice for a software engineer.
Leveraging your unique position to
connect the dots between business
strategy and technical execution.
Now let's talk the way how you can
develop the business acumen skills.
First step in mastering business
acumen is to truly understand the
industry your company operates in.
This means more than just
knowing the technical details.
You need to learn the language
of your industry, the specific
terminology that is commonly used.
Understanding this glossary will
help you to grasp the requirements
more effectively and communicate more
fluently with non technical colleagues.
Additionally, take the time to learn
about the key aspects and regulations
that apply to your industry.
Every industry has its own set of rules
and standards that can significantly
impact how business is done.
By familiarizing yourself with this,
you not only improve your understanding
of why certain decisions are made,
but also increase your value as
someone who can foresee potential
challenges and opportunities.
One practical approach is to read
industry articles regularly or even
take the course related to your field.
Whether it's through online
platforms, industry publication, or
professional development courses.
Explaining your knowledge beyond,
expanding your knowledge beyond
just software will make you a more
rounded and insightful contributor.
Next, it's crucial to understand the
internal structure of your company, and
most importantly, how it makes money.
This might seem straightforward, but
it can be more complex than it appears.
For instance, the revenue model
might not be immediately obvious,
especially in larger organizations
or those with diverse product lines.
Start by learning who your customers are.
Are they individual consumers,
other businesses, or
perhaps government entities?
Then dive deeper into understanding
how your company earns revenue.
This could involve subscription
models, direct sales, partnership, or
other streams to get the information
and engage with departments within
your company, such as leadership,
project management, and sales.
These teams are often more than
happy to share insights about how the
business operates because they know.
When the tech team understand the
business model, everyone benefits.
One of the simplest yet most effective
ways to develop business acumen is by
listening proactively, especially during
company town halls and other board
meetings, this session often covers
strategic goals, company performance,
and future plans, essential insights
for anyone looking to understand the
business better, instead of just having
these meetings on the background, as
usual, make a point to actively listen.
Take notes, ask follow up questions.
If the opportunity arrives and reflect
on how the information shared might
impact your work, you'll find that
many of your answers to your questions
could be followed in these discussions,
providing you with a cleaner sense of
direction and purpose in your role.
When the new feature I handed over to you,
don't be afraid to ask why initialize.
This might be feel a bit awkward,
but it's a powerful habit to
develop by asking why each feature
is being implemented, you start to
understand the reasoning behind it.
What problem is it solving
and why is it important now?
Over time, you will see the bigger
picture without even needing to ask.
You'll develop an instinct to
understanding the motivation behind
the feature requests, which allows you
to align your technical solution more
closely with the business objectives.
This understanding transforms your
role from simply executing tasks
to contributing strategically.
As you start connecting the dots between
the motivation and the proposed solution,
you might come up with even better ideas.
Perhaps a technologically superior
solution, or a faster approach,
or something that achieved both.
I have to admit that someone who is
a little bit lazy, there is nothing
more satisfying than taking just a
long boring task and proposing a minor
update to existing project that solves
the problem just as well if not better.
And when everyone agrees to
your proposal, it's a win.
Don't hesitate to share your ideas.
It's your opportunity to demonstrate
your expertise and show how deeply
you understand both the technical
and business sides of the equation.
Even if your idea is not as good and
not getting picked up, expressing it
is far better than just staying quiet.
It shows that you're thinking
critically about how to improve
the business, which is exactly what
this business acumen is all about.
Finally, one of the best ways to
accelerate your development in
business acumen is to find a mentor.
But don't limit yourself
to a technical side.
Seek out a mentor from a non
technical department or even
someone outside of the company.
A mentor will, with a different
perspective, can provide invaluable
insights into how the business
decisions are made, how to communicate
with more, more effectively with
non technical colleagues, and
how to position yourself as a key
contributor to the company's success.
This relationship can open up new ways
to thinking, how you can bridge the
gap between technical expertise and
business strategy, making you a more
well rounded and impactful professional.
Alright, at its core, business acumen
is all about ability to understand
the needs of others and deliver
solutions that addresses those needs.
It may take some time while
until you start seeing these
needs of different parties, but
here are some shortcuts for you.
In startups, the focus is often on
innovation, speed, and adaptability.
You need to implement your products
fast, and you need to be willing
to pivot based on the customer
feedback and market shifts.
The need here is for agility, a solution
that can be implemented rapidly,
often with limited resources, to test
ideas and iterate based on what works.
Tech depth is not only
norm, but necessity.
Big companies prioritize stability,
scalability, and optimization.
Their focus is on maintaining
what they already built while
carefully expanding and optimizing.
Here is a need often for robust,
tested solutions that can handle large
scale operations without disruptions.
When working on this or with big
companies, the emphasis should be on
creating reliable, efficient systems
that align with existing processes
and can support future growth.
Product companies focus on building
and maintaining their own products.
The goal is here to create value
through innovation, user experience,
and long term customer satisfaction.
Their needs here is often to
deep understand of the domain of
the project and the strong focus
on quality and user feedback.
When you're working with a product
company, focus on understanding
the product lifecycle, user
needs, and long term vision.
Outsourcing companies, on the other
hand, provide services to businesses,
often working with the projects for a
variety of clients, their primary need
is efficiency and delivery, completing
project in time within budgets and to
the client expectations, the emphasis
on meeting client expectations and
managing resources effectively to maximize
profit margins with outsourcing firms.
The priority is delivering high
quality work efficiently and
managing clients responsibilities.
Relationships carefully.
Okay.
Project managers.
They can take a task by converting
customer's needs into actionable
requirements that could be done
with allocating the smallest
possible resources and time.
As an engineer, one of the best way you
can support your PM is by helping to
find the most effective path to solution.
This means identifying ways to
achieve the desired outcome with the
smallest possible resource allocation
and within the shortest timeframe.
It's about finding the sweet spot
where you meet the customer's
needs without creating unnecessary
complexity or burden on the team.
Business leaders, they focus on
driving company strategic vision
and ensuring profitability and
fostering long term growth.
They make a high level decision that align
with company goals, manage risks, and
allocate resource to maximize returns.
As an engineer, You can support
business leaders by aligning your
work with these strategic objectives.
This means understanding the company
goals and ensuring your technical
decisions help achieve them effectively.
Focus on delivering solutions
that meet both immediate needs
and long term business goals.
Always keeping your eye on how
your work contributes to the
broader success of the company.
Now let's talk what benefits you can get
once you master your business acumen.
Mastering business acumen directly
contributes to your company's success.
When you understand how to align your
work with the business goals, you'll
help increase overall performance.
And boosts of performance can lead
to more revenue of the company,
which often translates into bigger
salaries and bonuses for employees.
In short, when your
company wins, so do you.
Next is when you focus solely on
coding, your impact may only be
recognized within the tech department.
When you are proactive and engaging
with PMs, leaderships, and of even
sales team, you start to build a
broader network of your advocates.
These connections can significantly boost
your credibility even in areas within
your primary expertise like technology.
This positive visibility can lead
to more opportunities for promotion
and make your valuable asset to
the company, improving both of your
retention and advancement prospects.
It's hard to overestimate this as
it boosts your confidence a lot too.
Understanding business arguments also
gives you an edge in job interviews.
Most behavioral and culture fit interviews
are really about assessing how well you
match the business needs of the company.
By understanding these needs, you
can present your achievements as
a solution to their challenges
and address their challenges.
This is not only increase your
chance to landing the job, but
also helps you to determine if
your role is a good fit for you.
Developing business mastery in your
current role offers a risk free
way to practice running a business.
You get to learn the ins and outs
of the business operations, business
strategy, and decision making
without the personal financial risk.
This experience is invaluable.
If you ever decide to start
your own business down the road.
So let's get back to the
story when we started.
You are faced with a choice, tackle the
technologically challenging task that
excites you, but only benefits a small
group of advanced users, or focus on
the simpler, less glamorous task that
would improve the overall experience
for a majority of your customers.
The answer here lies in understanding
the broader impact of your work.
While the complex tasks might be more
personally fulfilling, the simpler tasks
align more closely with the business
goals, enhancing the user experience
for most of the customers, driving
greater satisfaction and ultimately
contributing to the company's success.
The lesson here is clear.
Sometimes, the base choice isn't
about technical excitement, but the
one that delivers the most value
to the business and its users.
As we wrap up, remember that mastering
business acumen is about making decisions
that align with a bigger picture.
It's not just about technical skill.
It's about understanding your
impact and the impact of your
work on the company's success.
To develop this mindset, start by learning
more about your industry, understanding
your company structure and goals.
and being proactive in finding
the most efficient solutions.
Engage with other departments,
ask why for each task, and think
about how the contributions
can drive the business forward.
I would love to continue this
conversation and support you in
developing your business acumen.
Feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn
if you're interested in learning more
about business acumen for engineers.
Thank you for your time today,
let's keep pushing forward both
technologically and strategically and
create the real impact in our work.
Thank you.