Hi, everyone.
My name is Dmitry Tarayev.
I'm currently a Flutter
developer at Quadcode.
today I would like to speak about
Flutter versus native app development.
From a point of view of a former native
mobile app developer, that's me, I used
to develop for iOS, and then I switched
to cross platform framework Flutter.
So today, first, I'll speak
a little about myself.
Then I'll speak about Flutter in general,
the problem, the pros and cons of Flutter.
Then we'll do a quick technical
comparison of Flutter and iOS.
I'll also speak about my practical
experience using Flutter and, then
what alternatives there exists
and summary about my experience.
Okay.
A few words about myself.
My name is Mithut Tarayev.
I used to be an iOS developer.
I took part in one of the biggest music
apps in Russia, which is VK music.
And a few other projects in VK.
And a big part of my career
was also in teaching.
I taught a few courses on app development
in Moscow State Technical University.
I did an iOS development course.
And then when I switched to developing
using Flutter, I also did some
teaching at Moscow State University
and a lecture in Apollos University.
I switched in 2019 and my first
big project was Yandex pro it's
a driving app, for Yandex taxi.
So that's the app used by drivers,
but not only drivers also by
couriers, which bring food like
Uber, Uber eats something like that.
So it's, an app useful used
by drivers and couriers.
and the team was really huge.
I was a part of big team, but
after that I joined a startup.
it's called blush.
The idea was to make a
AI dating, simulator.
So that's what we did.
Here's a few screenshots
and a QR code to the,
so what is Flutter?
Flutter is one of the frameworks
for cross platform mobile app
development, made by Google.
It uses Dart programming language and it,
and these projects made using Flutter can
be built into several major platforms.
major mobile apps, Android and
iOS, as well as web and desktop.
you could ask me, why do
we need cross platform?
There's already iOS, Android,
and there are lots of
developers who are used to them.
But in many cases, it may be more cost
efficient and convenient to develop a
cross platform app because it's faster.
not two times faster because
you're making one app, but still
significantly faster than two separate
apps, developing two separate apps.
Then also, because of that, it's
cheaper, it requires less developers.
It's a bit more difficult to
find developers, but comparing
to the native app development,
but still it's not too difficult.
And considering quality, it
works reliably, but the app might
look a bit different from the
native apps, especially in iOS.
And, it might be important
depending on what app you're doing.
So from the developer point of view,
what do we get when we use Flutter?
We get hot reload and hot restart,
which is super convenient options.
when you're making an app, you have to
rebuild the project many, times when you
make changes, but having hot reload and,
it, it makes almost instantly, you just
save it and it hot reloads and you see
the changes, when you change the color
of widgets or change phones, this type
of thing, or do you change the layout?
For bigger changes, it might require
to do a hot restart, which might
take few minutes, a few seconds,
but it's not too long as well.
So it, reduces the, time
it takes to do the rebuild.
So you don't need to do complete
rebuilds of the projects that often.
So it also, while you lay out, widgets
and flatter, it uses declarative ui.
and it's, it looks quite simple.
It looks very nice and it's much more
easier than doing layout in code in iOS.
At least it used to before,
SwiftUI, came into view.
And from architectural point of
view, it's also quite convenient.
It's very easy to modularize the app.
and make each feature in different
module or different components and you
can reuse them in different parts of
the app or even in different projects.
so from the technical point, you
can see, like the difference between
declarative and imperative approach.
on the left, we have declarative approach.
On the right, we have imperative
approach, which is used, which
was used in iOS before SwiftUI.
And here on the left, it's how it's
done, like the text view, how it's
shown in Flutter, which looks very
nice and clean and, easy to use.
Another big part of Flutter
is that everything is widgets.
You have a huge collection of widgets
using which you can customize them,
you can use them to make your own app.
few other like technical things.
Dart works in a single thread.
But there are ways to make, to execute
code on other threads using isolates.
And also it's very convenient to work
with asynchrony using async await calls.
It's, very well done and
it's very easy to use.
If we look at Flutter pros from a
product owner's point of view from
a product, what we get if we use
Flutter comparing with native apps.
It is faster, as I said before, like
you make only one app, use a single
code base instead of two separate apps.
So it requires less
developers and it's cheaper.
and as I said, we have a single code
base, so that gives us an opportunity to
have releases on both platforms at the
same time, and also the versions would
be the same, which can be a problem
if you have, native apps and Each
native app is developed by a separate
team of iOS and Android developers.
But as always, there are some
drawbacks from using Flutter.
for a developer, one of them is
obvious is that you have to learn
a new framework and a programming
language, but that's just life.
then there is a smaller demand for
Flutter developers on the market.
And it's not enough to only
learn about Flutter development.
You also have to be very familiar
with platforms, ideally both
platforms, at least one iOS or
Android, because sometimes you have
to get deeper into the platform code.
For example, if there's, some SDK
you want to use and SDK only exists
for iOS and Android, and you need
to use it in your Flutter app, you
have to write to the plugin, which.
just, uses that SDK on both platforms.
It is obviously possible and it's
not too difficult, but you have to
understand how the platforms work.
You might experience some strange
bugs, which are associated with a
release of new versions, Android
or iOS, mostly iOS or a new Xcode.
As iOS is decay, and as I said.
You there might be missing the SDKs
you need so you have to make a plug
in yourself, but there is a huge
amount of Already made plugins.
So you might find the one you
need and not make it yourself
from a product point of view The
app It might be a disadvantage that
the app can look different from
the native apps Especially on iOS,
scroll can feel different or some
UI might feel different from the
like typical UI, which is used,
which the users are used to on iOS.
Also, I've experienced some
problems with animation lags, but
there are ways to overcome them.
And, I think this shouldn't
be an issue nowadays.
And also there are not too many
Flutter developers, so it might be
easy, not be so easy for you as a,
for example, for a startup or a big
company to find, good developers.
and some of my views in, for, situations
where you should or shouldn't use Flutter.
I think you, it's ideal for quick MVPs.
Or the app that should look
the same on both platforms.
And also keep in mind that
you have free web with it.
So the app can be built for web 2
or desktop apps if you need them.
And probably a few situations
when you shouldn't use Flutter or
consider it really thoughtfully.
for example, if you
already have a native app.
iOS or Android, and you need to
do an app for the second platform.
And for example, you already
have like native app developers.
So that may, it might be a case
where you don't need to rewrite
all the apps, using Flutter.
but I do have a successful experience
of switching to Flutter in such cases.
And there are two cases I've experienced.
There is a requirement for the
app to look exactly like a native
iOS app, like to follow all the
Apple human interface guidelines.
so it might be very difficult
and maybe even impossible to
make such an app using Flutter.
So about the practical experience
I've had, implementing Flutter.
The first was Yandex Pro, as I said,
that's the app for drivers and queries.
I joined the team in 2019.
Actually, it was the new team Hired
to do the iOS app, but it wasn't
we had like long deadlines and We
decided to try the cross platform.
We tried the React Native first, but we
had some problems, with our security,
department and they said not to use it.
And we decided to try Flutter instead
and all the team really enjoyed using it.
And, eventually the decision was made
that we should use it in this prospect of.
Replacing the former native Android app.
in 2020, we released the app with
the basic functionality for iOS.
And the native app for Android still
existed and still was, developing.
Because we couldn't just stop
development for Android apps.
It was used by, I don't know, like
thousands and thousands of users.
So we couldn't stop it.
so our goal was to catch up with
the native app's functionality.
And at the time there was also new
functionality being developed, so it was
developed simultaneously for the native
Android app and for our Flutter app.
And while doing that we wrote few
plugins for SDKs that we needed,
the map, Yandex Map SDK, which was,
biggest part of the app probably.
And, because it's on the main screen and
there's so many functionality in that map.
Routing, different points,
different layers, everything.
There are so many things there, camera,
audio, Bluetooth, these types of things.
They were, the SDKs that we used and
we had to write plugins for them.
And eventually in 2022, we managed
to switch to a single code base.
So we caught up with the native
apps functionality on Android and.
At one point that Android app was
replaced in, Google play, by the
new Flutter app built for Android.
So for the users, it was just like
update, but for us, it was a huge
change and it was really successful.
my second experience was
with a much smaller project.
We had a smaller team.
It was three people.
And in the previous project, it was
up to, I think about 40 developers.
So it was a huge project.
This was much smaller.
I came, I was the second in the team.
so the situation we had was
opposite to the one we had, I had
before, so we had a native iOS app.
And we had no Android app yet.
And we began writing an
application in Flutter with the
idea to replace the iOS app.
And initially we just built it
only for Android and we were
going and trying to catch up with
the native app functionality.
So in 2023, we released our Android app.
And, after that, we still continue
to develop new features for both
for the native, iOS app and for
the Flutter app built for Android.
And only in the beginning of 2024,
after all the holidays, we came to the
point where we migrated the iOS users
to the new Flutter app built for iOS.
Which wasn't that easy because,
the initial, the, native iOS app
was built using Firebase, database.
And there was a lot of stuff saved
locally and it doesn't, didn't use
any backend, so that was quite a task,
but we finished it and nowadays the,
blush app, if you download it, it's the
same app on iOS and Android built on
Flutter, And it was really successful.
So let's look at the few cross
platform options that we have.
This is quite a recent chart and Flutter
seems to be the most popular nowadays.
the React Native is very close.
and briefly I mentioned
like few other options.
So we have Flutter.
Then there's Cordova and Ionic,
which use HTML, CSS, and JavaScript.
Then there's React Native, which
uses native widgets with wrappers
while Flutter uses Skia engine.
And in React Native, it uses
JavaScript virtual machine, while
in Flutter, we have binary code.
And.
But React Native might be very
useful because, you're writing
JavaScript and there's much more
JavaScript developers than there
are Flutter developers, obviously.
but potentially it might have
a lower performance and some
security issues because it's a
JavaScript virtual machine, right?
Especially on iOS.
then there is also Kotlin multi
platform, which is growing
and it looks very promising.
I just had a brief view
on what they offer.
And then there is Formal Xamarin,
which, now switched to NET MAUI.
It's not very popular yet, but
it also doesn't look too bad.
concluding my speech, I would
say that I've had a very
positive experience with Flutter.
It successfully replaced native apps,
both in a huge project and, with a
huge team of developers, and then
also with a smaller app and a small
team, the, framework, growing, is
growing and, it's being supported
and it's being more and more popular.
and there is a huge market for cross
platform development, using it for
MVPs, for startups, and you can even
use it in huge and very complex apps.
I know this is a recorded speech, but if
you want to, if you have any questions
about my experience, about Flutter in
general, you can text me on Telegram,
and email me, or text me on Twitter.
Oh, there is also a link,
a QR code for my LinkedIn.
So welcome to join, and send me a text.
Thank you for your time.