Hi everyone, this is Han Joseph Raach.
Today I'm going to talk about
building high performance AI
literature processing platforms.
So AI has been a buzzword
for past several years.
And let's talk about how AI can
be utilized with respect to the.
Navigating through the complex ecosystem
of the researchers out there, the
research is happening every day.
There are plenty of researchers happening
and the publications out there are like
thousands and thousands of applications.
The challenge is not about publishing
a research it's about keeping it up.
Without a powered platforms, critical
research discoveries, something which
may be phenomenal or maybe utilized
to build on top of that's a vital
component maybe for another research.
So if you wanted to navigate through
that and find out those things, it may
be buried in the exponentially growing
volume of publications for an instance.
10,000 plus biomedical papers
are published every day.
So let's talk about rag
retrieval, augmented generation
as a foundation pattern.
Where do we need rag?
There are lots of LLM power models like
we have Gemini Claude Engine, grok.
There are lots of things out there.
What is the value addition
being done by the rag?
Let's talk about it through these slides.
But the main idea is rag
prevents hallucinations.
When you talk about the research
discovery, we want accuracy.
We want the correct
details to be rendered.
So rag prevents hallucinations.
It's about grounding LLM reasoning
in authoritative references.
Let's talk about the role of
distributed vector database
in there and its architecture.
So unlike keywords, embeddings capture
the context, distributing indexes,
ensure subsecond retrieval at scale.
So we are not only concerned about.
Navigating through, through the
complex ecosystem of researchers, we
also want it to happen efficiently.
So rack distributed, sorry.
Vector database helps with
semantic understanding.
We also have distributed indexing,
so which means that it's sharding
across nodes enables parallel
processing and fault tolerance.
So now we are talking about the
sub-second retrieval optimized nearest
neighbor search algorithms maintain
speed at scale, so we want to happen
this entire research to be navigated
through and get us the right truth of
information in split second timing.
That's what we are, we care about.
We care about the reliability,
accuracy, and also the response time.
Event driven microservice architecture,
elastic scaling during document
search surges, keeps ingestion and
inference smooth benefits of this
independent scaling of components.
Fault isolation, a technology
flexibility, and we can use
messaging system like Kafka.
Stateless services and
even driven workflows.
Workflows.
So it's not about how we
are going to implement it.
We may use the mix and match of
different tools and technologies, but
we need to have an architecture which
scales and helps us with the, with
respect to the, without being worried
about the volume of the transactions.
Efficient LLM Inference pipelines.
So here we are talking
about the techniques like
batching, reuse, and caching.
They help us to cut cost drastically
while enabling instant answer.
So batching means it's combining multiple
request to maximum GPO utilization.
We have lots of GPO
resource, but it's costly.
We have to use it very wisely.
We have to if it is needed and if it is
efficient, we need to campaign multiple
records to maximize GPO utilization
response caching, which means that storing
common queries and responses to avoid the
computations being done repeatedly, the
same computations being done repeatedly.
Model quantity, quantitation,
optimizing model size without
sacrificing their quality.
We talked about the rag to bring
more avoid hallucination and to bring
more accuracy in while navigating
through the document search.
Getting the truth out of the
research publications out there.
It's not about getting the right
information, getting the right
information with split second timing.
It's all also about keeping
up with the research updates.
Like researchers change
quickly there are more and more
research publications out there.
Something might have changed,
something may be outdated and new
information might be coming in.
So we also need to keep up to
date with the research out there.
So real time knowledge
synchronization help with that.
It's all about in involving
the techniques, like
continuous inte ingestions.
Incremental updates, conflict
resolution and knowledge integration
entity extraction at scale.
So we are going to implement
domain specific models to
extract genes, proteins.
Here I'm talking about, sorry, here
I'm talking about the model specific
to bioinformatics or biomedical.
So domain specific models extract genes,
proteins, and diseases, merging them into
knowledge graphs for deeper insights.
Entity types like such as genes and
proteins may have a relationship
like causes and cost to buy.
So those kind of entity types and
relationship types or stored at scale.
So which means we can navigate
easily through these geo entities
and their relationship and find out
the right information, which we need.
And we also need to understand the
horizontal scaling strategies rather
than bigger machines will scale.
We scale horizontally distributing
embeddings and inferences
across G-P-S-G-P-U pools.
So we need to distribute and horizontally
scaling will help us to avoid cost when
it's not needed, and also help us to
meet the demand when it's really needed.
Caching layers and cost optimization
caching ensures the instant results
without invoking a full pipeline,
keeping latency low and cost sustainable.
So we don't need to update everything
every minute, if it is something
frequently access to query.
And we don't need to update
it every day every however,
every 30 minutes or like that.
So we probably might update with the next
incremental update, but until then, we can
retrieve from the cache to save some cost.
So cash with can be with the embeddings
retrieval cash or response cash.
Monitoring and observability.
End-to-end monitoring captures throughput,
latency, and inference Quality.
Observability ensures issues are caught
before they escalate, so we have to
capture performance metrics, throughput
latency, error rates, and results,
utilization, quality metrics, anomaly
detection, and distributed tracing.
To make sure that whatever we
deploy, they work and meet the
demand and help us to get the right
information and right on time.
Reliability and error handling
failures are inevitable in any systems.
So when we talk about the system
design, we also need to talk
about handling the failures.
What matters is resilience.
Graceful degradation ensures
uninterrupted service.
Resilience patterns means circuit
breakers, retry with back off
fallback, recur, redundant components.
So grace will, degradation may
be simpler models as backup cast
responses when life fails, partial
resistance when complete unavailable.
Clear error communication.
So we need to adapt a technique
which suitable for that particular
instance, and make sure that
it's not a complete failure.
While we work on to rectify that
problem that is happening in the
production infrastructure as code
and CACD, this is a common technique
used in the software engineering.
So infrastructure as a code
ensures reproducibility.
CACD pipelines validate changes
and rollouts, updates safely.
Infrastructure definition like a Terraform
Cloud formation, Kubernetes manifest.
Automated testing, we can ingest
embed the automated testings in
the code file to make sure that's
happening along with the pipeline run.
CACD pipeline runs gradual rollout.
Canary deployments and bluegreen
strategies, performance
fallback, continuous monitoring
of the deployed changes.
Containerization and
deployment strategies.
So when we talk about the environment,
the run environment of any code, we also
need to talk about the containerization.
So microservices run in isolated,
continuous orchestrated for scaling,
resilience and seamless update.
So the benefits of container.
It.
It provides a consistent environment,
isolated dependencies, efficient
resource usage, orchestration
features, autoscaling, self-healing,
rolling updates, load balancing,
so deployment strategies.
When we comes to deployment strategies,
we can adapt blue green deployment,
canary releases, feature flags, et cetera.
So we also need to come up with
the benchmarking and draw a line
and do the performance validation.
So benchmarks, they validate design
goals, testing under load failure
scenarios, guides capacity planning.
So we have to define those matrices.
Like latency, like for an
example, it should be less than 50
milliseconds for typical queries.
Throughput how many queries should be
processed per second accuracy how much
accuracy we expect We have to define those
matrics and constantly monitoring that
those matrics are met and we are on track
and we deliver what we intend to deliver.
And uptime system availability,
that's a very crucial part.
Cross domain applicability.
Though I talked about biomedical
research, the same patterns, ex can be
extended to law, finance, insurance,
or any type of knowledge for legal.
For an instance, we can have case laws,
sta statutes and regulatory documentation,
doc documents, finance market reports,
filings and analysis, technical documents,
specifications, manuals, and standards.
Historical archives like manuscripts,
records and cultural artifacts.
In, in, in certain industry we may
have plenty of documents conclusion.
So high performance platforms.
So like you carefully engineering,
pipe engineered pipelines.
This blueprint accelerates
discovery across science industry.
It's not about deploying
an LLM for our need.
It's about engineering
an ecosystem around it.
That's, that's then only we can
achieve the accuracy, the speed,
and also we keep up to date to avoid
outdated information being transmitted
to the critical science community.
The architecture patterns
we have explored provide.
Foundation for building scalable,
reliable, efficient AI literature
processing platforms that can
handle exponential growth of
obligations across domain.
Thank you for this opportunity.
I hope that this particular presentation
would've helped few audiences.
And thank you for this opportunity.
One second.
Thank you.