Hello everyone, thanks for joining me.
I'm Vitor Norton.
I'm going to tell you about
the code behind collaborative
components, a little bit about design
patterns as well as web sockets.
So let's get this party started, right?
So just a brief introduction about myself.
I'm Brazilian.
So excuse any English, mistakes.
I'm 10 time winner of Microsoft MVP.
I'm also a developer advocate at SuperViz.
and, but this is my professional
background, the real deal for
this talk is that you need to
know is that I'm a In love.
I'm passionate about
connecting people together.
I'm also highly t of my productivity
tools like Notion, Figma,
Google Docs, Microsoft Office.
I really depend on them.
My whole brain is inside Notion right now.
If I lose my account on notion, I'm dead.
and I love the idea of
working anywhere in the world.
I got to travel a lot.
Because of my work and I had the benefit
of doing some code while I'm still on
Rio de Janeiro and hanging out there.
So this is amazing.
but today I'm not talking much about me.
This was just a quick introduction
to myself for you to understand
how this is important thing for
me, that we have collaborative
components, collaboration components.
What is Collaboration Component?
you know the name.
You may have an idea of what it is.
But let's see.
exactly what it is.
So we have four, I bring, four
examples of collaborative components.
A form element that syncs what
you're typing and what other people
are seeing when you're typing.
so you can use this, let's say, in a
customer support that, The support is
helping someone while on the phone or
something like that to fill a form.
The other one is the who is online.
It's a presence indicator that someone
is in the room together with you.
Someone is looking at this
document, is looking at this page
and you can see Who is online?
The.
The other one is the mouse pointer.
Where you can see, where
people are pointed out.
this is really important for
if you're teaching someone,
if you're assisting someone.
and you can also, merge them
together, like use who is aligned
with mouse pointers at the same time.
you can click on.
The Anna, for example, and go
to her or follow her and see
where her mouse pointer is.
Okay, another component that
we have is contextual comments.
So you can add annotations at any
part of your web page or an element
or perhaps even a 3D environment.
But this, of course, you can
have more components like this.
I just bring some of them for you
to see what we are talking about.
Okay, so you have seen this before, right?
You have seen this on Mario, on Figma, on,
companies are building this because if you
don't, if your application is pushed to
the world for everyone to use and you are
not using collaborative components, Then
you are missing something, extraordinary.
today, specifically, we are going to
break down the code of MousePonders.
We are seeing each level, of its code,
so you can build your own, but mostly
to understand what, what is happening.
Of course, there's some codes that I
will bring, it's not the final code,
it's more a magical demonstration code.
It's not something that Google is
using, the source code of Miro or
Figma, but the idea of it, okay?
So let's break it down.
Let's go to definition and break
down what is mouse pointers.
Oh, it's a hacked element.
At least, this is what you
should expect to add in your
environment, in your application.
You can just say, oh, I want to add
these mouse pointers and this to
just be attached to this element.
So every time a mouse moves inside
this element, it shows across everyone.
Okay, this is what you expect to use.
What is behind this component?
let's see.
This is the thing behind it.
and we'll break down this
even more in a little bit.
But let's see this concept of a room.
A room at line 1 is a group of people.
So you have a RealD that can be,
let's say if you are on Google
meets, it's the idea in the your
L or if you are on a Figma file.
It's the idea of the document.
So you can bring, say everyone, it's in
that page, in that URL, in that document.
This is the rule, okay?
So everyone that is logged into
this same ID, in the same developer
key, and stuff like that, You can
have participants and everyone in
there will be together in this room.
But what is going on in this room?
nothing.
Until now we don't have anything.
But we are constructing a mouse pointer
on line 15 and then we add it to the room.
So when I add it to the room,
I can see everybody, everyone's
mouse pointer in there.
Of course, you can have a conditional
here and say like The host doesn't
see the mouse pointer or something
like that But the general idea is
this So let's keep moving and let's
break down the mouse pointer itself
now, because of course I needed to
explain a little bit about the room.
if you're using a react application
or something like that, you mostly
would use this room as a provider and
then a mouse pointer inside of it.
But I'm just, like I said, this is not,
Actually, this code will work, but, this
is not, it's a demonstration purposes.
Okay.
So what is inside this mouse pointer?
it's the logic to see who, when someone
moves their mouse, you need to see
in your front end, you also need to
update your position to everyone.
and you can have, you need to
make it really fast and smooth.
So this is the three key points,
while building mouse pointers.
Okay, so let's break it up.
So when someone moves their mouse,
I use here a little bit about
a little bit of react, but you
should be able to use this with any
framework, any library that you want.
Even in vanilla Javascript, okay?
here in line 1, I have a mouse
position that I'm saying X and Y, 0.
Okay, so it starts on 0.
and then on line six, I have a
channel and I will talk more about
this channel later on, but the most
important thing is the subscribe.
I'm subscribing and I'm listening
to an event called Mouse Moved.
it works a lot like add event
listener to an HTML element.
So I say.
I'm listening to this mouse move
and when I listen to this, when it
happens, please call me, call this
callback function on the mouse move.
On mouse move, we will receive a
message and we'll get this message data.
And set the mouse position at X and Y.
Okay, so this is pretty much it.
You listen, and then you set the
position, and everything was working out.
of course, you may tweak it a little bit.
You may add something else.
You may only show the mouse,
if you have, the first message.
After the first message you
receive, you may tweak a little bit.
But The idea is that counts here, okay?
let's go to the next challenge.
To update your position for everyone.
like I said, the subscribe works
like the add event listener.
And we're pretty much doing this here.
So we listen to the document event.
And we listen to the mouse move event.
Okay.
It's almost the same thing, but instead
of using channel, we are using document,
to see where, when the mouse move.
Okay.
So it goes to the callback
function, all mouse move, go over
here, we have the event, then we
have the client X, the client A.
Y, and then we put this in a simple,
simpler object called position, and
then, this is new, we publish it.
We say, oh, I'm going to tell, So
everyone that's listening, everyone
that's subscribing, everyone that
is observing this mouse move, that
we have a new position for this.
Okay?
So this is how it works.
This is the code.
Let's go to the third challenge.
how can I make it really fast and smooth?
Oh, this is pretty much just to
say that you may want to use.
And native browser API called
request animation frame that would
update it according to your computer
or your browser settings, mostly
30 FPS, 30 frames per second.
so this way you guarantee that you are
not breaking or violating any rate limits.
Of your application, of having much data
transferred than what's needed, okay?
That's pretty much it.
We have only a few more objects and
stuff like that just to make this work.
but you get the point.
Okay, I told you about the channel.
What is this channel?
What's going on there?
what tenure is this?
Okay.
So remember when I told you that we
are adding mouse pointers to the room?
we now add this real time, it's a
real time dating giant that works as
an event broker as our PubSub, I'm
going to tell you more about it later.
And this real time that we
add, we can connect through.
A lot of channels.
You can create your own channels here.
I'm creating this mouse handler
channel so you can have a channel for
listening to the participants that
is typing, a channel for listening
to, let's say, a live location.
Some, something like that.
We can, unleash your
creativity on this one.
Okay.
We add it to the room and
then we have the channel.
so let's see the
definition of the channel.
mostly we have more than this of
course, but the main things that
you need to understand is this.
event static, the
subscribe and the publish.
So we have this empty object that
we'll have a graph, going on here.
And then you have the
subscribe and the publish.
Something just fall off
my desk, but that's okay.
You have the subscribe and this publish,
function that we've seen before.
the subscribe, we have two parameters,
the event that receives a string, a
callback that receives a function,
we'll have data, and then the
publish that we receive a string,
that's the name event, and the data.
That is any object you want.
Okay.
So this is a pub sub.
This is a publish subscriber.
how does this work?
What is this?
I don't, I'm not following you.
I'm not understanding you.
Okay, I'm here with you.
I'll call you back.
what it is?
the PubSub is a design pattern that you
can see and you can see more about it.
I will have links in.
resources for you later on this talk, but
you can watch and learn this on the guru.
I don't remember the
website name right now.
guru, refactor guru, something like that.
You can just type guru pubsub on Google.
It will work.
but the pubsub works mostly
like the observer pattern.
and I will tell you more about this
later, but this is a design pattern
that's commonly used for a lot of
things like React Redux, for example.
how does this work?
What is the subscribe function?
What's the definition?
we have the event name, we have
the callback, what's going on?
it will see, okay, this may be confusing
for now, so let me just break it down
even more and do a hard code event name
to make it easier to understand, okay?
So this is the same code, I'm just
not using the event name as a variable
and using it as A hard coded value.
So it makes it easier to understand.
Okay?
so we have this check, this condition
that we'll see if we have an event
called mouseMoved on our static
events that we had added previously.
If we don't have it, then we
initialize it as an empty array.
Okay?
So we have an empty array.
why?
Because It will, if has, if doesn't
have, it will add and actually it
will push the callback that we want.
It will add this callback that we are
receiving to the list of this event name.
The publish works almost, works
with these events as well.
and I'm doing this hard coded
thing once again to make it.
Looks simpler.
Okay, so I'm here receiving the mouse
move, and I'm receiving the data.
What happens is that I go to the mouse
move, remember this is an array, okay?
the object that this returns
is array, the event is not an
array, the event is a graph.
but the mouse moved, it's already, and
I go for every single callback functions
that, that I have added, added there.
And I go and say, Oh, call the callback
with the data that I'm passing right now.
So this is one, it's going on over that.
So this is the PubSub.
Okay.
Pretty simple, right?
This is it.
Yeah.
it is this, but we're
missing something important.
we're, there is, this works locally.
This works on your instance of your
application, because remember that
when you do the pub sub, you're
not specifically saying for every
device connected into the room.
We skipped the code behind the
room that I showed you before.
so I'm going to tell you the secret for
having this, working with any device
in any IP hardware, anything like this.
We have one more thing to say.
What's going on?
What is making sense on all of this?
it is a WebSocket.
We're using WebSocket to build this
connection between my application running
on my computer and the application
that you are using on your end.
what is WebSocket?
Okay, WebSocket.
Provides a protocol that allows for
a continuous two way communication
channel between a client and a server.
why?
Because let's go into more
specific details about WebSocket.
It persists connections.
So, the difference between between HTTP
requests and WebSocket is that when you
open a request for HTML or HTTP, let's
say, a REST API post on some endpoint,
you open this connection, you receive
this, post, you push this post, you
receive the return, the response, and
you And then the connection is closed.
Okay?
So if you want to get something,
then you push a get, then you
receive the response, and so on.
you need to open, do the request,
pick the response, close the request.
Imagine doing this for every, third
times per second on the frame rate
that we are using for this example.
you can do this, but, it's not the ideal.
You may break the, your
server at some point.
What you need to do is that you
use a connection that stay opens.
For, stay open, for
continuous data exchange.
I open it, I'm sending, I'm
receiving, I'm sending again,
receiving, sending and receiving.
And then, once I'm completely finished,
once I close the browser, once I go
do something else, Then I close it.
This makes it a low latency.
So it's ideal for this real
time applications, especially
for gaming, something with
live updates, stock options.
low latency is really a big deal here.
Also, it works both ways.
For the client and for the server.
Okay?
okay, I told you the
secret behind the room.
I told you what the room does.
I told you the PubSub.
Where can I see this?
Where, what people are doing with this?
I have a, a few slides,
a slide deck for you.
Who's using this, right?
Let's see.
Let's ask Sharjeepti.
okay.
I did not ask Sharjeepti.
I just copy and paste some print
screen, some screenshots from my
mobile device, but that's okay.
So he's using this, Uber is using
these or an application that you
can track, someone, on your mobile.
so WhatsApp also does this for
when you share live locations.
so the person like on Uber example, the
driver pushes and publish the location.
every second, every.
Any seconds or something like that,
then you subscribe to it and you
update it, update your map accordingly.
Okay?
Another place that you may use, that
people use a lot is Microsoft Teams.
Of course, for video conferences,
of course, for chat applications,
I'm going to tell you.
About short applications and video
conference later, but this is something
that is pretty neat about Microsoft Teams
that Tells you a lot that you can receive
related content of the meeting and the
current status of a person has Accepted or
declined, if the person is online, if it
is not, you have a summary of the meeting
right on your hands and you want this to
be updated every time something happens.
because you don't want people
to refresh, the page every time.
Okay.
And this is pretty neat because I'm
really anxious and I'm really nervous on
every meeting that I tend attend that.
At least for me, it's really important
to see who is already on that meeting.
so I'm not the first one to enter
it or to see Oh, I don't know
anyone that's inside this room.
I will wait someone
that I know to be here.
So this information is.
It's pretty important for
people like me, with anxious,
please let me know if you
have some of this too, okay?
Also another use case scenario is
the live chat application and any
other chat applications, that you
publish a message and you receive a
message, something that's pretty, yeah.
It's not that simple, or at least you
would not expect in a glance, but the chat
applications also use this, is that when,
let's say, Brian starts writing, so the
mobile phone, the iOS, the Android, Or
the computer, the browser will listen to
the type event and will publish it to me.
And I do not receive what the person
is typing, I'm only receiving if it is
true or false or some data like this.
And then I say, update the interface
for everyone that it is in this
channel, saying, oh, Brian is typing.
This is not seen in a glance when we talk
about shared applications used by people.
In pub sub and real time
communication data, but it's also
something, that is being used here.
Another application, a lot of applications
actually is the whiteboard collaborative.
so I bring him my role, that I hope that
you have been using this for a while.
that you know this tool at least, but
if you don't know this, it's mostly
like Figma or I'm missing names of
whiteboard collaboration tools right
now, but there's plenty of this.
But the thing is, you look at this and
you understand what it's doing, right?
If, if you move this card to the
left, it's moving to everyone.
If you click on, let's say, Bea,
you click her, in her, and then
you're gonna see, you following,
her mouse pointers, stuff like that.
So this is pretty much easy to
understand, this whiteboard.
Bye.
And you really needed to
have this synced together.
Another one, and this is one of my
favorite ones, is that you can build
your own interactive workspace.
so this GatherTown, if you don't
know this, I love this platform.
they use this concept of Chibia or
maybe a Habu or something like that.
To create a working environment.
So we have, everyone will have a table.
They will have a common space,
room, a conference room, a
meeting room, something like that.
They can style with, but
you'll see who is online.
You have this video conference.
So when you start approaching to
someone like this, again, we can.
walk with your characters around and
When you get closer to someone, you
start seeing their image and listen
to the audio, just like in real life.
So this is pretty much, an amazing
tool for remote work, for engaging
in remote events, for, everything.
I have this with my
friends, I use it a lot.
And this is a lot of these
WebSockets and PubSub.
I think I will just wrap this
thing up by telling you some
resources that I have for you.
the main resource for everything
here is the JavaScript Design
Patterns, the book from Eddie Osmani.
it's an amazing, simple to read book.
I love it.
Also, I use this as reference,
an article by Vibhali Joshi.
I hope I'm saying this right.
I don't know her, but thanks
for your article on how you can
use WebSockets with Flutter.
so this can give you more
data about WebSockets itself.
You don't need the Flutter part, of
course, but I thought the way she
wrote, the About WebSockets put in it.
And then we have this article about
understanding and implementing
event driven communication
front end development by me.
You can find this as well on DevTools.
Just search by my name or search
by the name of the article.
Also on tab two, I have a few
articles about design patterns.
If you want to understand
more about Observer, Pubsub,
even other, design patterns.
This is it.
Thank you so much for being here with me.
Please follow me on my socials.
if you have any questions, if you
want to ping myself or anything,
just follow me and reach out.
Let's connect and stay together.
Thanks so much.
See ya.