Hello and welcome to comp 42.
Today, we've got a really exciting
session for you talking about
breaking down the principles of
platform engineering and talking about
what platform as a service means.
And with that, we've got two Really
cool interactive demos where we're
going to be talking and taking a look
at virtualization, but also AI in the
context of all platform engineering and
discussing how to empower the developer
experience and minimize some of these
complexities that operations and
developers teams are experiencing now.
In this world of cloud native.
So I want to give a big thank you to
the conference organizers and give
a quick introduction to myself and
I'm joined by the lovely Valentina.
Now, a little bit of background
about myself is that I've been very
fortunate to always have worked
with containers and kubernetes.
It's been a big privilege and
my experiences in that container
tooling the projects podman and
podman desktop as an interface,
I've helped, in the past with those.
and I work as a developer
advocate at Red Hat.
So Valentina, I'll pass it to you.
Yes.
I'm so excited about this session.
So thank you so much for including me.
I can't wait to share all the
agenda and demos that we have.
for you today.
So I'm Valentina Rodriguez.
I'm a principal architect at Red Hat.
I focus on everything Kubernetes.
before that, not that long
ago, I was a developer myself.
So I am so excited about this topic and
how we can bring the benefits of platform
engineering and internal development
platforms into developers personas.
So with that, I would like to
cover the agenda for today.
we will go over this.
Personas, the developer, we'll talk
about platform engineering and how they
can work together, but also look into
platform as a product that we know is
a hot topic right now in the industry.
We want to understand how it works
and how we can take advantage of it.
And with that, it really is
connected with the idea of internal
developer portals and platforms.
we will show you, we will talk about it,
but also we will do a couple of demos as.
As Cedric mentioned, we'll go over
at the end with best practices
and also reference architectures.
but then now we're going to start
talking about what Cedric, I know you're
working on an amazing application.
I want to hear everything about it.
So what can you tell me?
Thanks so much, Valentina.
I'm building out a, you might not think
it's exciting, but a very cool internal
tool, and the first step, is, and I told
this is, how it's traditionally worked,
is that all you'd have to do is pull out
your editor and get to coding, right?
Maybe it's VS Code, maybe it's
Eclipse, IntelliJ, and figure out
what framework I'm going to work with.
Is it a Python application?
Is it a Java app?
and it used to be, much more simpler.
But then we have to start thinking
about a couple more complexities.
for example, with being cloud native, we
have to think about, Oh, what container
runtime am I going to use to package
up my application and its dependencies
and actually run it somewhere?
Is it Podman?
Is it Docker?
Where are we going to store
those container images?
What registry do we
have to put them there?
where are we going to
run these containers?
I'm hoping it's on a platform
like Kubernetes, or a
distribution of Kubernetes.
and then it doesn't stop there because
on top of that, we need to start thinking
about the YAML that we need for these
deployments in order to run them.
In order to take advantage of all the
benefits that we have with Kubernetes.
the YAML that I as a developer
don't really understand because I'm
concentrated on writing my application.
Now I have to think
about these complexities.
Where am I going to store the code?
Is it, is it a remote IDE
that I need to start using?
Do I need to think about CI and CD?
Valentina, I don't know.
Does it stop there?
No, it really doesn't, but I
think you are in a great path.
so you've started building locally, right?
And that's been working well for you.
But then as you mentioned, we need to
start looking into other practices and
technologies and tools to really bring
all those capabilities into different
Development environments and all
the different stages, and we want to
make it with best practices security.
So we need to feel like CICD
building the pipeline with Tecton.
We need to look into something
that I really love with Argo.
For example, when you have.
One source of true, so you can have
all those YAML files really there.
But then we'll start looking into, okay,
let's do this use home charts, right?
It's a really nice practice, that you
can use, hunters for your applications
when you can use the values files and
everything in there as a good practice to
scale all those manifests and reuse them.
But then also, how that will look if we
start looking into, It doesn't end there.
As you said, from Grafana, we need
to start looking at observability.
We need to start looking
into, is this a microservices?
How we connect with Istio?
What about Kafka?
If you want to do some
even driving architectures?
there are so many things
that we need to do.
and this is just a start.
Valentina, I must say it sounds, very
exciting and interesting, but I'm
starting to feel a little bit overwhelmed.
and you might feel like this guy
in the photo here, where you're
looking at the CNCF landscape, and
it's just so overwhelming because
it's exploded in the past few years.
there is a specific project
for every specific use case.
that your company might need and it's
great because it's all open source
and we can all contribute to it But
as a developer i'm starting to be
very overwhelmed And I think that
we can all agree that developers are
under this immense amount of pressure.
And with that, we have the consequence
of the productivity slowing down
and the fact that there is more
bureaucracy, there are more processes,
there are more cognitive overload.
items that have taken me away from just
coding to now having to think about a
lot more so from my day to day job of
just having to write application code.
Now I'm having to think about
application modernization.
And how do we actually translate our
application to a cloud native environment?
And of course, learning new
technologies comes with that
cognitive overload as well.
And These are all part of the different,
benefits that we get from those
technologies that you talked about,
Valentina, but now, if I'm just trying
to focus on getting my application
to run, there's a lot of numbers that
we've looked at and learned from papers
in the field and reports that kind
of point to developer productivity
decreasing, and I think this kind of
brings us to this wall of confusion.
Yes, exactly.
I understand.
Yeah, it's a lot, right?
To take in.
And then we start thinking on what
is that you need to do, right?
Do I need to write those YAML files?
Do I need to learn how?
Like, how that will work?
is it operations?
Is it developers?
And it doesn't even end that, right?
So if we go to the next slide, we also
look into DevOps and the culture and we
want to bring that culture together that
we have seen through the different years
and different use cases that's not enough.
There are many things we need
to think of in the next slide.
We look at.
there's many things we need to start
looking into right from operations to
have access into cluster networking to
have access from that application to
ingress rigorous right into different
components inside outside the cluster.
Security is important from the beginning.
So how we can integrate
all the security within.
my application and all the
components that are consuming.
So there is a lot here that
is not only even technology.
We are talking about processes.
We are talking about people and
how everything combines together.
So it's a lot to take in.
I understand that.
So if we go into the next slide,
I want to ask you like right now,
if we start looking into those
complexities and those things, how
you work right now with your platform.
It's so far, this is,
it's working for you and.
What is it?
What are the process that you need to go
through to get access and requirements?
And how is that been working
for you and the team?
That's a great question, Valentina.
so if I think about it, we're
taking a traditional approach
to, working with the platform.
Let's say, if I need a database
spun up, I make that ticket might
take a little while to come back.
And eventually I get that provision.
we're defining our requirements
up front and going from there.
And it's this happens.
And then there's a response and, it's
slow to the changing needs that we,
we have in a cloud native environment.
And I'm wondering, is there
a different way to do things?
Yes, there is.
There is a different way
if we start looking into a
platform as a product, right?
When this is an.
Always evolving product when we take
also the user's needs into consideration
through surveys, receiving feedback and
meetings and try to understand what are
really the needs and the business needs.
we make these into an agile
way, so you don't need to start.
Waiting for something to be fixed,
but rather just that will be
taken into consideration and as a
product with that product mindset.
It really is evolving that
platform really beyond right?
We start looking into how we can
increase platform capabilities.
What are the users doing to do next?
So it really opens up to many
possibilities, not only to
reduce all that friction and
time wasted, but so much more.
Yeah, I think that's a great point.
That sounds great, right?
Yeah, and I think if we take a
step back, I want to look at what
we have in our environment, right?
We've got this really great app platform
that we were talking about before, right?
With whatever operating system
we're running on top of, with
features for developer tools to
increase my productivity, right?
We've got capabilities for observability
with Prometheus and Grafana, tools for
auditing and compliance and security.
And so it's a great place.
To deploy the applications, right?
But on the other side, we've got
application developers like myself,
creating the tools and the services.
We've got front end back end engineers.
We've got data scientists and data
engineers now that we're working
with AI enabled applications.
But I've feel like there's a bit of
a gap between the actual application
platform where we're deploying our
applications and the people who are.
Developing, consuming, and working with
the apps that will be deployed there.
And so I think that we could connect
this in a way with platform engineers.
And this is the way that Red Hat, along
with the community and industry, believes
in a way to connect the gap between the
app platform and the users with all of
the best practices and security in hand.
And I think this has been
picking up quite a bit.
yes.
So platform.
So that's great that you mentioned that
because platform engineering even has
been named by Gartner as one of the top 10
strategic technology trends for this year.
IDC also predicts by like in two
years, let's say, 70 percent of
enterprise will be adopting a
composable internal facing architecture.
Application platform to really
empower those developers, right?
Because we know that developers
are the last line of defense.
So being that value into the
business with their applications.
So removing all that
friction, it really helps.
So having that platform engineering
concept and practices around
companies, it really helps with
innovation, reducing friction and
everything we have discussed before.
as you said, it's not only, as there are
many, research that are proving this,
and companies are taking, advantage
of this platform as a product idea.
And with that, we want to, yeah, talk
about really platform as a product.
as I mentioned, it's this idea of really
bringing those capabilities right into
the end user and thinking in a way that
we can build this in an interactive
and also iteration way that is agile.
And brings all those capabilities
to the end users to really enable
them to build applications.
I have a question.
what is a platform though?
Yeah.
So according to Evan Botcher, digital
platform is a foundation of self
services, APIs, tools, services,
knowledge, and support, which are
arranged as a compelling internal product.
So APIs, tools, services, and knowledge.
Those are the key components that are
critical to build a digital platform.
And what does this kind of look like?
I know there's this kind of
analogy of the iceberg, right?
Yeah.
So if you're familiar with the tip of the
iceberg concept, if you, yeah, advance
one more, that is so much on a platform.
We know how much platform
is capable of, right?
If we start really at the bottom,
What we need is all the configurations
managers in order to enable this
platform and capabilities to have
as much as self service as possible,
but we need networking, we need a
storage, we need authentication,
artifact builder, all of that.
So all of that, we really want to
hear that from that complexity from
the end user and really focus on.
The creating a great experience.
So at the top, we start with
internal developer platform, which is
backstage, which allows to work with.
for development templates and provides
these developer experience that I
can access different environments
and different applications
capabilities, but it really is just.
Given that complexity, but
given the capabilities that the
platform has to the end users.
So it really focused on enable the users
and bring in a fantastic user experience.
I noticed that, you talked about the APIs,
the tools, the services, the knowledge.
So I also saw at the bottom of
the quote, it's arranged as a
compelling internal product.
So what kind of, what do you mean by that?
Yeah.
So There are, has been defined about
internal development platform, right?
And what are the things
that are important?
And this I have seen also
when working with customers.
So first we need to enable those
end users to have a quick and easy
access into the platform so they
can start building faster, and
building faster into the market.
We really want to reduce
that Time to the market.
so having that stream like
process, it's really critical.
I have seen that sometimes, a
customer had sometimes months waiting
just to have access to a cluster.
So they really, the idea is really
how we can, take that, the company
guidelines, best practices, securities
that are required, but do it in a
way that is really more extreme life
for those end users and they can have
quick access so they kind of stuff.
building those applications and
coding, we want to code also
in a fast, reliable in a loop.
And we want to create that consistency
across different environments.
To promote all those applications
into the different development
stages, but also runtime, right?
Thinking on how we can.
Create that in a stable way,
scalable with secure best practices.
And including monitoring and logging,
which are critical to understand,
what's going on with my application.
So having all of that really set
up, it's really a success for having
that internal development platform.
And speaking of internal
development platforms, I heard
there's a project called Backstage.
Yeah, so Backstage is this, open platform,
that allow us to build developer portals.
So it was created by Spotify, it's part
of the Cloud Native Computing Foundation,
and it really allows developers to focus
on what they want, which is cool, right?
You were saying, Hey, I want to
build my app, and right now I
need to learn all these things.
And when it ends, because now what you
need, not only to learn, but keep your
skillset today, what we disordered.
Teams and, request access
to the environment.
So there are many things
that you need to learn.
The idea is to really create in that
single pane of glass when you can
have everything in one place and
giving you that abstraction layer.
So you can just focus
on what you love, right?
Building the applications, it really
unlocks the developer productivity.
So with that.
Yes, there are many backstage adopters
and every day there are more and more.
So it's a really great community.
The next one looks like, but
what really is what backstage
is composed by five components.
So we have the centralized
software catalog.
That is really all the, made a data and
application ownership for all the software
and uses that you can create within
backstage services, website libraries,
pipelines, everything within there.
The plugins is what really enables
all the capabilities from the platform
integrating with backstage to enable like
CS, CP, monitoring, and so much more.
And then software templates.
These are the critical pieces
because that is what it really
defines all the manifests to create
your components within Backstage.
Either it's an application, a virtual
machine, or an AI application.
The idea is to create those
Templates using best practices,
the company guidelines, security,
everything within there.
So it's in a one single source through in
a repository and everyone can reuse that.
So you can ensure that also
you have version control.
Everyone can, can access.
You can, update, templates.
Frequently, you have all the information.
So it's a really nice way to really
adapt all those best practices without
you needed to learn all the complexity
from what we were saying, right?
All the gators, the hunters, the
CICD, the TACDON, all of that.
And tech docs, of course,
is a critical piece.
If we want to have a centralized place to
learn about technical documentation, it's
really important because as the idea of
writing documentation is really great, but
then It's difficult to maintain, right?
And we have many places and documentation.
Sometimes it's duplicated.
So bringing that it within
backstage is really a nice way
to solve all those problems.
and then the search is just, enable
us to search and look for any
option that is within backstage.
Yeah, with that, I'm going
to go to the next one.
We have, amazing community, that has
built more than 190 community plugins.
So the Red Hat, we are, building
fantastic plugins as well.
You will see some of them, But we
do have a lot of different plugins
that you can take advantage of
to increase that capabilities.
As I mentioned from CICD
monitoring security as well.
So there are so many that you can
reuse, with that, yes, next one.
Now we have the demo to show you how
well, but really is backstage and how
that works within our Red Hat products.
So at Red Hat, I will
start sharing my screen.
So now, as you can see, I am here in
Red Hat Developer Hub, which is based
on Backstage, but we have created an
enterprise grade, internal developer
portal for you, integrated with, Red
Hat plugins and also community plugins
to bring you the best experience.
So here, what you can see is the homepage.
In the homepage, I can customize
everything that I'm seeing right now.
And I now I can access like community
tools, developer tools, CICD,
everything, OpenShift, clusters,
everything that I want here from
my internal developer portal.
This is the homepage.
I also have access to the catalog.
So the catalog, remember, is the place
where I can access everything that's
been created within, developer hub.
So here I have applications.
I have also a virtual
machine created already.
I have, I can see who created this,
what type of application is it, What
type of life cycle we are in with that
application and also I can add some tags.
The tags will help me
to, to start, filtering.
I can also filter by type.
I can also filter by different components.
I can filter here with the different tags.
this is a nice way that I can
just see whatever is going on.
you may wondering wait a second,
would I will see everything?
we have an RBAC, functionality
that you can use in order to
filter and decide who see what.
the idea is you probably don't want,
All the teams seeing everything or
accessing everything, so you can
filter directly just to specific teams.
I also have the APIs access.
right now, I don't have anything
created, but if you are a developer,
you want to see what is available
for you to consume, what are the APIs
that are right now being exposed?
It's a nice way.
I know.
So we'll allows you to look
into the APIs contract.
then we have landing pads.
It's a nice thing that I can just,
I want to learn something new.
So this is my favorite place.
I can just go here and click and it will
be sending me to the specific landing pad.
then we have the TIC radar.
This is an industry standard.
So here it's just, an organization
can set up the maturity level
with their applications.
And this is customizable as well.
So with that.
this is the tool, right?
This is, Red Hat Developer Hub, but also
I want to, take a step back and tell
you again about the software template.
So we said that software templates
are this powerful tool that allow us
to really standardize how we create
any components from applications,
AIs, and even business machines.
So I can create one repository And I can
connect that with the developer hub and
that will allows me to see it here and
it will bring to the developer really a
great experience, with just a few clicks.
I can create 1 option.
And what will happen is that option
will be created in my case in, I'm using
open shift, the application platform.
Can, do you want to see
what I have to show you?
Yes.
Okay.
I would love to see it.
Yeah.
Great.
So right now, what I have is here
on the different, I have different
templates that I could use.
I have a Spring Boot
application, a frontend.
A Java gateway, but also I do have,
I have an AI application, but I
also have these virtual machines.
So this is a great solution.
Imagine that you are a developer,
but you also are working on these
applications, legacy applications.
And you need to access a virtual machine.
So how you can do it in,
in a self service approach.
I can just, select really
a built in machine.
I have here a Microsoft
Windows, built in machine.
I have a RHEL VM large,
and then I have the medium.
So I will just choose
this one, the medium size.
and see this is all customizable.
So if you operations are watching
this, platform engineering and you are
wondering, like, how much power I can
give when I, I give this service approach
to developers to build those machines.
It's up to you.
You can define how much
a developer can change.
So in this case, I am setting
up, okay, what is the GitHub
repository that I am doing?
What is the organization from that?
What is the cluster that I am in?
And then I am, setting up my user.
The namespace is given by default.
And then I, the only thing I can really
do here is just, change my, the name,
decide the name of my built in machine.
So I am not deciding the storage.
I am not deciding the size.
I am not deciding anything.
everything is given to me.
So as a developer, I just want to, I
don't know, test, and then I want to
create this, and then I will create it.
Right now, what it's doing is really
building that virtual machine.
what is happening behind the scenes?
we'll show you in a second.
I can build this.
It may take a second to load.
But I am using OpenShift virtualization.
I have it already installed
in my OpenShift cluster.
I already have everything I need
from the infrastructure perspective.
But what I can do, I can build.
Is when we go to, this 1, I have
everything from here that I can
explore from the virtual machine.
I will have accessibility
to the topology view.
So I can explore the virtual
machine, but also I can add.
This is all customizable as well.
I can add a link to the virtual
machine itself within the cluster.
So I can see all the details
from the virtual machine.
I can also.
Click here and I can access the VNC
console from the virtual machine
and this is all customizable.
So I can give as much access as I want.
So this is really a powerful tool
that allows me just to with 1
click to build a virtual machine.
it's amazing, the power of Red
Hat Developer Hub, it's not
only for building applications.
I want to show you, I have
another application here created.
So this is just an application
that is just built.
With a pipeline, right?
So you can do applications.
You can do provision built on machines,
but also you can build, applications.
I know you want to show
us something about that.
Yeah, thanks so much Valentina.
So speaking of that, it's not just
applications or virtual machines.
It's also in the age of AI.
different AI embedded applications
or projects that we want to, to
essentially scaffold out and start
working from, with all the best
practices of our organization.
So I want to show you this reference
architecture, of what you're going to see
here in the demo for in just a second.
Essentially, we've got data
scientists here on the top that have
been working at Jupyter notebooks.
They've done some model fine tuning.
They've tested their model.
And the model is being served on
our Kubernetes cluster with kserv.
so we can monitor that entire MLOps
process with Kubernetes as well.
But when it actually comes to the
applications that are being developed,
that are inferencing this model that's
being served, I think the developer hub,
portal is a great way to scaffold that
out so that I, as a developer, can focus
on the code, and then the applications.
deployment, the pipelines, the GitOps
can all be handled by the backstage
and developer hub portal itself.
So let's go ahead and head over there
and, and check that out as well.
So I'm here at my team's different
Red Hat developer hub instance
and Valentina kind of showed you
a little bit through the platform.
I've got a little bit of a
different environment here.
We've got a lot of different services
that have been stood up by all of the
different members of our organization.
so I can check those out and see
GitHub depend upon and all of these
plugins that we've talked about before.
I've got a couple more installed here
that I'll walk you through on, but
the kind of, golden path template
that I'm going to instantiate is
actually a Python application that's
going to be, essentially inferencing
a model that we have on the cluster.
And I'll show you how this works
in the, in the background is
that we're using a template.
yaml to essentially set up that template
that Valentina walked you through.
We can preset different parameters.
we can show all of the different
steps that will be instantiated,
such as generating the source
code repository from a skeleton.
Publishing that they're, generating,
deployment resources and artifacts
for, for GitOps and publishing that,
and also using pipelines as well.
So all of this is customizable
and walk through this specific
template that we have here.
What I'll show you is one that we've
already set up so that the pipelines
have ran and this has been deployed.
to the cluster itself.
So here I can see a view into
my Kubernetes cluster, view the
different Kubernetes resources here.
So it looks like that our
deployment here is running with the
application that has been included
with the GoldenPath template.
So it looks okay to me.
We can view the different pipelines that
have ran or succeeded when I made changes.
The API, so it looks like I'm consuming
this photo generator API and we can
view the relationship graphing, which
is pretty cool or the swagger UI.
And so it's just so customizable
so that I don't have to worry
about things as a developer.
I get the abstraction, which helps me
to focus on the actual code itself.
So let's go ahead and see that in action.
This application is, as I said before,
a Python flask application, that's
going to make calls to A model that we
have, on the Kubernetes, environment,
or it could be a remote one late chat
GPT or LLAMA, and for this, I will,
generate photos of Teddy on the beach,
and we'll go ahead and, run this.
Give it a little bit of time and
we'll have a couple of different
photos of Teddy here on the beach.
Love it.
That was amazing.
I really love it.
The power of really internal
developer portals and with Red
Hat developer hub is incredible.
But also what about security, right?
We need to, this concept
of shift left, right?
So try to bring security.
Sooner as possible, really
right into the developer.
So the developer can make
changes really quickly and avoid
finding issues into production.
but we do have many open source
brushes that you can take advantage
of to really, manage like key clock.
You can manage the identity access.
So before even access.
Developer have a backstage.
You are looking into those
person really have access or not.
You also can look into the 6th store
to really secure and sign and verify
all the different software artifacts.
With KubeLinter, you can have
static analysis that runs within
the Kubernetes YAML files.
What really allows you to aggregate
all that software security made a
data and to allows you to really
have visibility on what's going on.
We take the chains and conflicts,
of course, is part of the building
process, making it secure.
and with that, you can integrate with
open policy agent as well to include many
policies as you require to ensure that the
policies are that when you are building.
All that, container image application,
and you will be running it after that
clear, of course, allows you to have
the stability as well into the container
image status, stack rocks helps you with,
build and deploy front end container and
doing risk analysis and vulnerability
scanning that are critical before running
that container image in any environment.
project way, of course, allows you to.
Protect the data and
also provides the image.
Vulnerability is scanning.
Argo CD monitors that actual state
versus the desired cell configuration
that if in case there are any
changes with Falco, it's really
streaming that detection at run time.
here we have a really compelling different
open source products, projects that you
can take advantage of in order to secure.
Your applications with the next slide.
What we will see is what are the best
practices of really shifting left and
security as I mentioned, bringing that
security as early as possible fund your
personas fund your champions status small
with tech talks evolve it into software
templates and keep one portal consistency
across your organization is critical.
And then next, thank you
so much for listening.
Please connect with us.
Yes, and we want to point
you to the slides as well.
So if you follow that link.
You can learn about the slides and also
solution patterns of already built out,
essentially reference architectures
like what we've just showed today with
the virtualization and also the AI.
And if you'd like to connect with us
on LinkedIn, please feel free to do
the Red Hat booth is the virtual booth.
It's the website.
So if you have any questions, we
also want to point you to developers.
redhat.
com, where you can learn about
more projects and products that
we work on, learn about platform
engineering, you can try out developer
hub on your, machine for free.
completely cloud hosted.
You can just try it out, completely
free and get your hands on working
with platform as a product.
And, we want to thank you so much
for coming to our presentation,
for sticking around, watching
the demos on behalf of myself.
And, Valentina, we'd like to say thanks
so much and enjoy the rest of your day.
Bye bye.
Thank you.