Platform engineering meets
thought code management systems.
Today's topic is going to be focused
on unified policies, access and
automation across GIT based platforms.
Who am I?
I am, it's called me around here.
I have an MBA and an MS Degrees.
I'm a senior staff IT
engineer manager at Qualcomm.
I lead a global team, spread
across various compo continents.
I manage GI systems or the GI
platforms like GitHub, GitLab, Garrett.
The user base is around
50,000 plus engineers.
If we talk about bot accounts or service
accounts, I'm not surprised if it reaches
around a hundred thousand accounts.
The focus of my team is primarily
about developer first initiatives.
We provide secure, scalable solutions.
End of the day we want accelerated
software delivery on what
we are doing at Qualcomm.
At large, organizations like
Qualcomm we have various systems.
Whether it is SCM systems or
other systems, we have a, we
have, I'm not surprised if there
are around thousands plus, right?
The policies accesses are all fragmented.
How can we unify them
without unifying them?
What is the impact?
As we know, the impact would be developer
friction, time consuming activities.
End of the day, the velocity will be huge.
So let's dig into deeper
how we can fix the problem.
SCM is considered as platform.
It's not a tool if some organization is
considering GitLab or GitHub or Garrett
or any SCM system as a tool, I sincerely
believe that they have a problem at hand.
SCM is the backbone for developers, right?
What developers, what do they do?
They develop code, the write code.
Where do they write code
and where do they push?
It is all around SCM.
So the utmost importance should be
given should be given to that system.
It, if you're considering it as infra, no.
If it is just an application,
no, it, because it is a platform.
It is integrated with lot of
other systems, so we need to treat
it as a platform and build in
governance should be considered.
Now let's talk about develop
initiative or the experience.
In the past, user
management was a struggle.
What do you, what do I mean by that?
Developer starts developing his
code once he gets a license from
one of their CM systems, right?
Say GitHub, right?
You need a license, right?
So if there is a manual process tied
with it, if the user management is
not seamless, if it is not selfer,
then we have a problem at hand, right?
So activation should be seamless
and then comes a deactivation
because the business side of things,
Hey, your activation is seamless.
Everyone is getting a license nowadays,
and it is incurring opex for us, right?
So there should be a deactivation
process, which is also seamless.
Then comes a reactivation.
What do you mean by that?
Hey, now you deactivated my account,
but I'm back into the project.
I need to activate my license.
Show me an automated way to reactivate.
So all these things tied together
brings in the user management.
The most important thing is you should
think about all the cases and automate
the system and make it self serve so that
the productivity of the developer or the
engineer will be increased significantly.
Then comes the required
systems to provide.
A place to develop because we are
talking about GI systems, which
I'll consider a repository to begin
with, Hey, I have the license.
What repository should I interact with?
If that sort of information is
not provided a automatically.
And what sort of hacks do I need?
Hey I need the read read
permissions to read the code.
Now I need the push permissions
to push the code so that,
people can consume my code.
All these things should be
automated so that the onboarding
process is as seamless as possible.
So you need to be when you are
managing the platform, developer
first experience should be back of
your mind so that everything will.
Seamless.
So now I have the repository.
I have the SI can push the code.
What af after that?
What are there ci cd pipelines integrated?
Is there a template which I can leverage?
How is gittel objects are managed?
All these should be either documented
or clearly communicated to the
developer community so that they
won't scramble behind the scenes.
We initiate, we have an initiative
where there are some public repositories
designed so that the pages or the
Read me articles are published
for the end users to consume them.
In that way, we are, we always have
the developer first experience of
the initiative in our perspective
and deliver it in a seamless fashion.
Then comes what?
How the code reviews are happening.
As a developer, I need someone to develop
to review my code that's given, right?
With AI nowadays, is there a
platform which we can build
for automated code reviews?
GitHub has GitHub copilot.
GitLab has dual, but there is
a license associated with it.
Then it goes back to the
license management, how
seamless the activation is.
Are there any other internal AI systems
that you guys developed, which can be
integrated for automated code reviews?
Eventually, when an automated
code review happens it, it helps
the whole developer community.
As a developer, I push the code,
it is automatically code reviewed.
I can address the code review comments,
and once it is ready to go, I can take
that change to the lead for the review.
Everything is automated.
The time to market has
improved a lot, right?
Our end goal should be that.
Now let's talk about unified
accesses and policies.
Yes.
We need the unified accesses
and the policies, right?
How do you achieve that?
So the service providers or the platform
owners should be cross-checking on how,
what is the scheme provisioning going on?
Can I integrate the skin provisioning
across all the systems is self is SSO
enabled so that if I log into one system,
I can easily interact with other system
as well with a click off button, right?
Think in those lines.
Then comes a classification as I'm
working on project A the, what sort of
classification are we talking about?
Is it proprietary?
How complicate how complicated this
project is when compared to project B?
What sort of sensitivity
I need to deal with?
Can I clone the repository locally and
start developing, or they, should I
be interacting with a different system
to interact this piece of software?
All these should be considered and the
information should be given in a seamless
way for addressing the developer needs.
Then comes the external collab, right?
Yeah.
I'm working on project A and project B.
All, everything is internal, so I'm good.
Now, let me I'm working on project C where
I need to interact with external users.
That means Google for
Qualcomm probably, right?
So watch collaboration controls
I need to be enabling, right?
How is the service
provider providing that?
All these should be vetted properly,
is guest collaborated In GitHub
world, there is a pro concept
of guest collaboration, right?
Should I be integrating that so that
the, and the external user won't be
accessing the repositories, which
they're not supposed to, right?
These things should be considered,
and the policies are designed so
that the compliance is achieved.
And any anomalies can be
controlled or detected in a
proactive way than a reactive way.
Automation is the backbone, right?
They said we can streamline the
processes by automating end to end.
I know it's a term where, hey,
I will automate everything.
But what do you really mean by that?
Right now, our focus primarily
is analyzing the logs.
We have a event based listener and we
created some runbooks for each event.
What sort of action we can take this?
The platform is designed so that,
end-to-end everything is automated.
Let me give you an example, right?
A create action for a user
is created on an SCM system.
The event listener, listening to
that event, that means in that
means the user just got created.
What sort of action I can take for him?
Can I send all the required
documentation for the user?
Because he's trying.
He just got created.
Yes.
That's an actionable runbook that we
can create and send it across while,
in another example, I just created a
fork for a repository, which may not
be needed because of X, Y, Z reasons.
So the event based listener,
listen to that event.
Communicating that proactively to the end
user saying, Hey, you created a fork, but
you may not need this fork in this area.
Why don't you consider
the fork in this area?
I'll give you one more example,
which could be interesting because
nowadays with cybersecurity coming
into picture this could be critical.
So this.
In GitHub or a repository in GitHub
is configured to have a low listing.
That means certain section of ips can
only access this particular repository.
The even listener, even basic
listener, listening to that events
and somehow it came to know that, oh,
someone actually changed that allow
list by removing some of these ips.
So the event base listener caught that
and sent a reminder or sent a notification
to the security team or Goor, as well as
service providers so that they understand
that and take an actionable, a could
be an action taking an action, right?
That action could be asking a question,
Hey, why did you make this change?
Why are you removing
this IP yellow listing?
Or if there is integrating another ip,
that's another event for a security
team checking for, why this IP is added.
Now all these things are critical.
So automation is the backbone.
Now comes the enterprise governance.
I'll most likely talking about
MSP primarily MSB is minimum
security baseline, right?
What sort of minimum
security you need to create.
For your application, that is the key.
What sort of I'll give you an example.
So for every org created in GitHub, I do
not want any public repositories under it.
That is a policy that is a
minimum security baseline,
which you could consider.
That means only the
internal repositories and.
Private repositories can be created.
That is a policy change, which
you can enforce why this matters.
Some cases you don't want to expose
your code to non-authentic users.
Public repositories have a
tendency that it can be accessible
by everyone, including guest.
Including the guest, right?
Could be a problem.
So consider that, right?
What sort of minimum security
baselines you need as a platform
owner or a service provider.
You need to work with your security team
to understand what this MSB means and
what sort of policy should be enforced.
Code secret scanning, right?
Nowadays, scanning is becoming the
shift left initiative where when
a developer pushes the change.
Immediately these scanning tools should
get triggered if there is a need for
CICD platform design that, but some of
the CM systems already have a mechanism
out of the box solution where it it
scans the code, which code QL or gas,
which is GitHub, advanced Security.
All these are designed so that, once
the change is pushed, all these scanning
will happen immediately so that it
can be fixed right at the beginning.
The problem in the past was if it is
not fixed at the beginning stage itself,
then these buggy code somehow gets
released and integrated into the product.
It's too late then fixing that.
Product and coming back to the
coming back to the developer
community to fix that bug.
It's very costly.
So addressing all of that with the
shift left initiatives, particularly
on the advanced CM Systems,
is critical audit dashboards.
This is centralizing, the audit
dashboard is critical because there
could be multiple teams in your
enterprise are interested in auditing.
Their needs.
Security team needs one thing, DevOps
community needs another thing, developer
community needs some other thing.
Product management needs
some other thing, right?
All these should be integrated so that
the dashboards are created for the
right use cases and all of them are
centralized, so we don't, it's not
going to be a sprawl across the board.
Balancing dev experience and dev
developer experience and security.
Developer friction is the
highlight here, right?
As we know hey, I'm doing all of these
to make sure our environment is secured.
I'm doing all of this to
make sure the product will be
launched at the right time.
I'm integrating this
because of that reason.
This reason, everything is there
is a reason, but developer all,
most of the developers care about.
Can I develop my software and push it in?
So you have to balance what you're doing.
I'll take you another, I'll take
another example as we are discussing
about AI based code reviews, right?
From the developer community, they believe
that this code is written this way.
It doesn't need a refactor, but the AI
based code review is coming under the
picture and with the policies which we
designed, it is checking for a lot of
things and it is giving left and right.
So many code review comments.
There will be a developer friction, right?
So adapt the policies accordingly.
By embedding the configs in our ci
cd pipeline accordingly for a project
or a repo based, don't make it like
a generalized policy so that every
developer will follow the policy, right?
There will be a friction if you go,
if you design your systems like that.
So always consider the developer
input or the leads input and design
your policies accordingly, if needed.
At the repo level or the org
level or at the enterprise level.
That is most important thing
because we, happy developer, happy
engineering community end of the
day, deliver the best product.
We implemented all of this in Qualcomm.
We have seen best results I would say.
Access sprawl reduced by 46% which
is tied with the user management and
the access controls as we discussed.
There is no more confusion on
where to go to get a license or
where to go to access a repo.
Everything is streamlined in that way.
User onboarding has significant earlier
it took hours and hours, probably
days in some cases where one user,
one operations guy is out of office.
No one has known how to do
the user onboarding process.
All of these evolved to a streamline
approach Nowadays every user should
be onboarded in less than 30 minutes.
Instance response times
has lowered by 73%.
That means, we are resolving the incidents
faster, way faster because this automation
processes with the chat bots, with the AI
based chat bots we know the KB articles.
We are inputting the KB
articles to the AI systems.
And the operations, the support
team knows how to fix the incidents.
So the response rates has, has evolved.
Finally what are we looking ahead?
We're looking at ai ai, right?
How can we improve in every angle possible
for platform engineering through ai?
How can we predict we how can we predict
the user activities upcoming next
activities, what sort of security cons
analytics we can come up with what sort of
user load be it all these are predictive.
We are predicting by analyzing
the logs through the Log
analyzer tools, which we built.
Coming up to the conclusion saying,
oh a BC day x, y, z days from
this geolocation, the number of
hits will be significantly high.
We are predicting that these nowadays
with the AI techniques, which we adapted
which we designed some tools around
it, and we are taking, we are we are
looking at how we can improve it further.
The, we are improving, we are trying, we
are finding ways to improve the developer
productivity with the compliance harmony.
Thank you everyone, your time.