Hello everyone.
My name is Natalia, and today we're
gonna be talking about privacy in
particular, how to build infrastructure
and products, perhaps some company
processes with privacy in mind.
A
couple of words about me.
I'm a software engineer with over
10 years of overall experience.
The last three years of which I've
been working in privacy in big tech.
And what I've noticed is
that privacy is a highly ambiguous and
extensive domain with lots of terms and
abbreviations and people get lost in it.
Therefore, I'm hoping to bring a
little bit of clarity around the topic.
And give a high level overview
of the scope and its relation to
infrastructure and platform engineering.
And hopefully in a way that
doesn't make you fall asleep.
Now a little bit around the motivation.
Why do we want to care about privacy?
First we want to have
high ethical standards.
We also want to build as well as
maintain user trust and therefore
care for our reputation as a company.
And lastly, we don't want to have
any problems with the regulators.
and regulations, talking about which
regulations are taking over the world.
And it's becoming more challenging
to find a country with, without
data protection laws in place.
On this picture, I highlighted
only the main regulations,
something I'm familiar with.
But I'm sure there are a lot more
and the central regulation is GDPR.
I'm sure you've heard of it And most of
other countries get inspired by it when
producing their own data protection laws
Therefore by making sure you are GDPR
compliant, you automatically get compliant
with most of the other regulations.
Not all of them, some countries are a
little bit more special, for example,
the US with its Federal Trade Commission.
But still, GDPR is a good
reference point for compliance.
Now, When I say privacy, most people
usually hear Signal, Secret Shots,
Onion Network, Blockchain, etc.
And even my friends who work in
tech but are out of the privacy
domain, they think I work on end to
end encryption, making sure people
have private means of communication.
And it's funny because I wish they
knew how different my work is.
Actually is.
It's a lot less cool.
But the point I wanted to
make here is that privacy is
so much more than security.
And indeed security and encryption and
2N encryption is an aspect of privacy.
But privacy is a lot more.
And so far, it's probably been the
most ambiguous and multifaceted
domain I've ever worked in due to its
substantial regulatory compliance side.
Now, I want to give an overview
of the main principles to give
you an idea of what the scope is.
And I tried to make it as short as
possible so you guys don't get bored.
But bear with me here, this is important.
The privacy principles.
The user personal data that you collect
has to be protected from unauthorized
access, theft, loss of damage, right?
Now, you also as a company,
organization, you want to be
transparent with the user about what
data you collect, what people collect.
purpose you collected for, who
you perhaps shared with, how long
you're going to retain it for.
Those annoying privacy notices
that you often see, this is
about the transparency principle.
Lots of people find them annoying, but
this is something that is required by law.
Now, the user should have a means to
access their personal data, perhaps
modify it, opt out for some parts.
And delete it all together, which
is the right to be forgotten.
The user has to have a simple
means of deleting all of their
personal data at your system.
Now, this is not all.
I have a couple of more
to you, for you guys.
Data minimization is about Collecting
only the necessary data needed for your
functional functionality to function.
You can't repurpose the data.
So let's say you collected user
emails for registration purposes.
You can't later use it for
analytics, for example, or for
marketing without the user consent.
Yeah, purpose limitation is
about not repurposing the data.
Now, there has to be a defined
period of time you are supposed
to retain the data for.
GDPR, for example, doesn't have
a specific retention period.
You have to come up with it for
yourself, as long as it's defined.
And you shouldn't store
data longer than that.
And finally, accountability as
an organization, you are held
responsible for adhering to the privacy
regulations, and you must be able to
demonstrate compliance upon request.
So these are the main
principles, but not all of them.
I haven't touched on some of the
aspects like data sharing, and
I'm sure there are a few details
I have, I might've missed here.
However, that's the general idea and I
hope the scope is more or less clear.
So now we can talk about infrastructure.
So we want to build
infrastructure with privacy layer.
How do we do that?
So it's helpful to think about it,
visualizing three main components.
We have our regulations and commitments,
which are often translated to policies.
We have our data and we have
infrastructure and product code, and
they interact with one another in such a
way where the data gets associated with.
a set of policies, then your code is
aware of what kind of data it processes.
It recognizes what data is
sensitive and it is aware of
policies and is able to enforce it.
Hopefully it makes sense.
I'll make a little bit of a pause
here to make sure it's digested
and we can talk about each of
these components in more detail.
So regulations and commitments.
We know what a regulation is, right?
Something that is defined, a
rule defined by regulators.
Whereas a commitment is
something a company chooses
to come up with themselves.
For example, WhatsApp positions itself
as an end to end encryption messenger.
So end to end encryption
is not required by law.
But it's a commitment and the law
requires what's up to stick to it.
So we have our regulations, we might
have some additional commitments, and
they are translated into policies.
A policy consists of three things.
It has a scope, meaning the geographical,
Every way it applies, it has its
enforcement logic, and it has a way
to get associated with the data.
Just a couple of examples here
to make sure it's clear what
policy is for example, email
shouldn't be used for marketing.
purposes without consent in the EU.
It has its geographical tag, it's got the
data element site, and it's got logic.
Retention policy is
something I took from the US.
The bank statements can't be
retained for longer than seven years.
It's also a good example of a policy.
Once we have our policies, well
defined and established, we can
talk about data understanding.
So data understanding is crucial.
Usually it consists of
approximately the following steps.
So first would be categorizing your
data and defining what of the data that
you process is sensitive and register
registering it in one and another way.
Usually it gets registered as a set of
annotations centrally or taxonomy and
when you have that you can annotate your
data throughout your infrastructure,
usually at the API levels, your data
transfer objects, data base schemas, any
data sync that you have can be annotated.
So this is quite helpful to
track where the data is stored
and where it travels through.
And an advanced step would be building
something called data lineage.
And data lineage is a way to
track the life cycle of the
data across the infrastructure.
Ideally, we want to pick a data element,
let's say an email in this case, and
we want to see a graph showing how
it travels to our platform, where it
comes in what elements it comes to.
goes through and where does it end up?
This is a powerful tool that helps
you to gain a lot of control over
your data, but also you can build
a lot of things on top of that.
Particularly, you can build a continuous
compliance automated breach detection.
For example, you can continuously verify
that Some of the data parts do not end
up where they're not supposed to end
up, or not retained for longer than
they're supposed to be retained for.
And also you can generate some
evidence for the regulatory compliance.
There are some solutions out there
that you can use for data lineage,
but you can also build it yourself.
Something like production sampling,
dynamic analysis or instrumentation
might be used data probing, and even
static analysis can be used for at least
complementing your data lineage graph.
Okay.
So a little bit on the
infrastructure and code.
So it integrates our policies in a
way where it knows how to associate
sensitive data with a set of policies
often propagating policy context with
your data is really helpful if you
have context propagation in place.
If your policy or set of policies
can travel through the invocation
tree of your code with the data,
that would be really helpful.
And finally, when the data reaches its
destination point or some other points
the policy can be enforced by the code.
All right.
So hopefully that was more or less clear.
And now I want to talk a little bit
about the practices that are out
there that help us to prevent privacy
incidents and protect user data.
So some of the Practices are
relatively straight forward, and you
probably already have them in place.
Something like access control for
security that ensures that our data
is protected from unauthorized access.
Encryption makes sure that our data is
protected in case of unauthorized access.
Some additional practices like
anonymization, sorry, I have
always trouble pronouncing it.
Anonymization, you can modify your
data before sharing it either with
a third party company or with,
let's say, your analytics level.
Lots of other people throughout
the company has access to it.
You can anonymize it.
Delete the purpose, personally
identifiable information.
Let's say, delete or replace
user IDs by a replacement ID.
You can store this map, mappings
between ID and replacement ID, somewhere
separate on the separate security layer.
So the data can't be
tracked back to your user.
Now, data coarsening is about
reducing the granularity of your data.
Let's say you have a geographical location
of a user, and perhaps you don't need
the precise location for analytics.
Maybe you can make it
approximate, and Then analyze it.
So that could also help to reduce
some of the privacy incidents, some
of the organizational measures that
you can have in place for privacy.
As I mentioned before, having
well-defined privacy policies in
your company is really important.
Have them documented
and very well defined.
And once you have that, you
can train your employees.
To make sure they are aware of the privacy
policies they are aware of the privacy
regulations, the principles, and they can
build your product keeping that in mind.
Some of the processes like privacy
reviews, let's say you release a
feature and you want to make sure
double check that it's privacy
compliant, it can be verified by
another team for privacy policies.
And regular risk assessments
and compliance audits.
but also help to maybe identify some
vulnerabilities in your system and also
reduce the risk of a privacy incident.
And I want to also say a couple
of words on continuous compliance.
One thing is to be compliant when you
say you launch a product or release
a feature, but staying compliant is
a little bit of a different thing.
Thank you.
Especially as the company grows bigger,
things tend to get out of control and
having continuous compliance becomes
more and more useful, automated.
Breach detection is about having
a set of processes in place.
Let's say some regular verification jobs
that make sure that the data is still
compliant against your set of policies.
And if there is a breach that is
found, you can raise an incident.
It can be something as simple as
an email or something a little bit
more complicated, like I don't know.
Setting a fire alarm filing a
task, and yeah, as long, it can be
anything as long as it's addressed.
Yeah, so hopefully I still have
your attention guys, and there
are just a couple of slides left.
And now I want to talk about privacy
investments that you can do today
in order to avoid a headache.
So I decided to break
it down by company size.
So there is a scale here.
It goes from a startup to big tech, and
depending where you are on the scale,
you might choose to do different things.
So let's say you're a startup, right?
Early stages of development.
Things are uncertain.
No Time to think about privacy.
Probably the last thing you
want to think about is privacy.
And I totally understand that.
So a couple of foundational things that
you can do that are not necessarily
privacy related, but they can help
you to reduce the privacy headache.
So context propagation, I highly recommend
that it is really useful, not only for
privacy, but for a number of other things
particularly logging and debugging,
but also having a sense of control
around what's going on in your system.
But then on top of that, you
can do privacy propagation too.
So distributed Tracing is making sure
that Your context is propagated from
a service to a service and beyond.
Having distributed tracing, make sure
you have your context propagation
across the whole entire system.
Also, at this point, you can
implement something basic
as constant implementation.
It wouldn't take too much,
so why not doing that?
And having basic security means
encryption, access control,
and perhaps something else.
But also, not hurt, at least.
So let's say you're a growing company
now, you've got more users, more data,
more employees coming in and out, and
things are getting serious at this
point, and inevitably more hectic.
So this is a good time to have your
privacy policies already established.
And again, once you have that, you can
train your employees to make sure they are
aware of what privacy is and how to make
sure the product they built is compliant.
So understanding and categorizing
your data is really helpful.
Here, too, at this point, you
can annotate your data on top
of the context provocation that
we hopefully previously built.
We can do policy propagation and already
start implementing some policy enforcement
logic once the data and the set of
policies reaches a certain point right.
Now, you are a bigger company now.
In fact, you're huge and
you've got even more users.
Tremendous amount of users, more data,
more employees, and things might be even
getting out of control at this point.
And because it's becoming more
difficult to keep track of things.
So at this point, you're also an
easier target to the regulator.
So one day they can, they are more
likely to knock on the door one
day, because you have more impact
on users and society in general.
So data lineage It's probably a good idea.
And it would help you to, sorry,
this is my cat making noise.
It would help you to keep track of things.
Continuous compliance, automated
breach detection and automatic
evidence generation is probably, would
also probably be helpful here too.
And of course, a regular risk
assessments, compliance audits.
audits would also help to reduce
the risks of privacy incidents
to a significant extent.
So this is the end of my slides.
If you take away from you guys, privacy
is something that benefits from investing
early in pretty much like everything else,
but still privacy, especially,
and understanding and categorizing
your data would help, Keeps things
structured and having well defined
established policies would also
provide a significant advantage.
Thank you very much.
I hope that was clear and somewhat
useful, and I hope to see you next time.
Bye.