Hey, hi, everyone.
My name is Amit Taneja.
Thank you so much for
joining me in the conference.
I'll be going through accelerating
pharmaceutical innovation.
Leveraging AI and platform engineering
to revolutionize drug development.
Some of the table contents is,
I'll be going through traditional
drug discovery challenges, how AI
can play a transformative role in
drug discovery, the different AI
methodologies in drug discovery process.
I'll also be going through
a couple of case studies.
What are the different benefits of AI in
drug discovery, the different challenges
and the considerations and how the
future outlook for AI in drug discovery
looks like, and also the conclusion.
let's talk about the traditional
drug discovery challenges.
one of the major thing is high cost.
The average cost to develop
a new drug exceeds over 2.
6 billion.
The long timelines on average,
it takes over 12 years to
develop and approve a new drug.
Okay.
Inefficiency.
Traditional methods rely on
experimental screening, which
is time consuming and costly.
Now, using platform engineering, we
can a lot of, we can do the automation.
We can automate all these workflows.
So by automating workflows using
platform engineering practices, we can
streamline the drug discovery processes,
reduce any manual intervention,
improve operational efficiency.
Automated pipelines ensure data
moves seamlessly from one phase to
another, saving the time and resources.
AI is a transformative
role in drug discovery.
AI provides faster data analysis,
identifying promising drug
candidates with higher efficiency.
AI powered solutions predict
molecular interactions,
reducing drug discovery time.
AI improves accuracy with models
predicting success rates over 80%.
Now, we can scale.
It's a lot scalable, cloud
infrastructure in platform engineering.
Platform engineering enables scalable
cloud infrastructure that supports AI
models in processing large data sets,
optimizing the computer sources, and
reducing time for molecular analysis.
Scalable systems ensure that AI processes
grow dynamically with project needs.
Eliminating any bottlenecks.
Now, different AI methodologies
in drug discovery.
One of them is deep learning.
models like CNNs and RNNs analyze
chemical bioactivity data.
Virtual screening.
AI evaluates large chemical libraries,
identifying high potential compounds.
Molecular docking.
AI simulates molecular interactions,
predicting how the drugs can
actually will bind to the targets.
Generator models.
AI creates novel molecules for
specific therapeutic purposes.
CICD in platform engineering.
So you, we can use, CICD principles.
Platform engineering will automate
the deployment of AI models.
Ensuring that every iteration
or improvement is quickly
tested and integrated.
This will speed up the time between model
training, testing, deployment, reducing
any downtime, and manual intervention.
Case study.
So AI driven molecular discovery.
Essentia and Sumitomo Genepon
Pharma, AI created a molecule
for immuno oncology, reducing the
development time to just eight months.
Enter clinical trials faster
than traditional timelines.
Typically, 4 to 5 years highlights
AI's ability to expedite the
discovery process, faster time to
market with platform engineering.
Platform engineering practices play
a key role in speeding up the time to
market for AI design model by automatic
key processes, handling large data sets
and integrating various research tools.
The entire drug discovery timeline
was significantly shortened.
Let's talk about the
case study number two.
AI discovered antibiotic.
Helician discovery.
AI screened over 6, 000 compounds and
identified helician and antibiotic
effective against drug desistant bacteria.
Helician expedited a novel mechanism
of action targeting ATP synthase.
Demonstrated AI's ability to find
innovative therapeutic solutions.
Data oriented architecture
in the platform engineering.
In the case of helician, Platform
engineering provided a data
oriented architecture that enabled
the AI models to handle, process,
and analyze vast data sets.
By centralizing the data pipelines,
the AI was able to screen compounds
more efficiently and accurately.
The benefits of AI in drug discovery
reduce time, AI dramatically shortens
the drug development pipelines, lower
costs, fewer trials and error reduce the
development expense, higher accuracy,
AI predictions significantly increase
the chances of success for compounds.
Optimizing resources with
platform engineering.
Platform engineering ensures
that resources both computational
and financial are optimized.
It allows for the automatic
scaling of compute power.
And storage based on AI model demands,
ensuring efficient use of resources
without unnecessary cost increases,
challenges and considerations, data
quality, AI relies on large data sets
that must be accurate and comprehensive.
Model interoperability, complex
AI models can be difficult
to understand and interpret.
Experimental validation, AI
predictions must still undergo
rigorous experimental validation.
Observer, observability and
monitoring and platform engineering.
Platform engineering emphasizes
observability and monitoring
tools that help track data
flow and model performance.
These tools make it easier to
detect issues in AI models, ensuring
higher accuracy and quality of data.
Used in drug discovery.
How the future outlook of AI
and drug discovery looks like.
Next generation AI tools.
Advanced models will further
accelerate the drug discovery process.
Collaboration.
Partnerships between AI experts, chemists,
and biologists will drive innovation.
Expansion.
AI will help develop
personalized medicine.
And targeted therapies, collaboration
platforms with platform engineering.
In the future, platform engineering
will facilitate better collaboration
between interdisciplinary teams by
creating integrated environments where
data scientists, biologists, chemists
can work together on drug discovery.
These platforms will streamline
communication and data sharing.
Conclusion.
Artificial intelligence has the potential
to revolutionize the pharmaceutical
industry by accelerating drug discovery
processes, improving accuracy,
and significantly reducing cost.
As AI driven approaches continue to
evolve, they offer new possibilities
for identifying potential threats.
promising drug candidates,
predicting molecular interactions
and optimizing drug formulations.
However, the success of AI in drug
discovery is heavily dependent
on robust platform engineering.
Thank you so much everyone, for joining
the conference and listening to this.
Thank you again.