Uh, my name is Pasupuleti.
And today I'm going to talk about
harnessing micro fringes for building
scalable, reliable and secure application.
In today's fast paced digital
environment building scalable,
reliable, and secure platforms for
complex work applications is crucial.
And as these applications continue to
grow in complexity, traditional monolithic
architectures often struggle to keep up,
leading to slower development cycles.
scalability challenges, and a
higher risk of system wide failures.
Microfrontends, to this topic, offers a
solution to this problem by breaking down
these monolithic applications into spawner
self contained units, with each unit
having its own independent life cycle.
This modular approach not only simplifies
the development and maintenance, but also
enhances the scalability of the system.
Enabling teams to work on more
autonomously and efficiently.
Today we'll deep dive into these micro
frontends, where we'll understand
this core principles, exploring their
advantages, and discovering how they will
empower us to build a scalable, reliable,
and maintainable web applications.
Next slide.
Firstly, let's start about start with
what are the challenges of the existing
web applications with monolithic
architecture that are out there.
If you see on this slide, on the right
hand side, you'll see a monolithic
architecture based application
where you have the frontend layer,
the web application layer, and
the integration layer, which is
typically your GraphQL layer, and the
service layer, typically your Node.
js.
Java, Springboard application
or any Python or Rust based
application that's out there.
In a monolithic application, what
happens is all these three layers
are combined into one particular
application and are distributed
and scaled and deployed across.
at this picture, let's try to
understand the limitations of this
traditional monolithic architecture.
Particularly, as these kind of
applications continue to grow in
complexity, And the challenges that
we highlight below will show why we
need to move towards Microfrontends.
Why is it necessary?
So the first one is tightly coupled code
bases and scaling issues In monolithic
architecture, the front end, back end,
and the integration layers are often
interwoven into one single codebase.
This tight coupling makes it difficult
to scale the individual components.
For example, if the back end API
layer, for example, here, the Node.
js or the Spring Boot application,
if you start to see more application
load towards the back end, because
there are more number of requests, or
there is more complex logic that the
server needs to do, you We'll have to,
what you typically do is you deploy
more instances of this application.
But in this case, you can't deploy just
the backend API layer independently.
You will have to deploy the entire
application because there's no other ways.
This approach is inefficient, not just
inefficient, but it also is risky as
it introduces unnecessary complexity
and the potential points of failure.
During deployment.
The second issue with this monolithic
architecture is the slow development
and the deployment cycles.
For example, imagine this case that you're
onboarding a new team member for him
or her, the understanding of monolithic
system can be daunting because they need
to get a complete grasp of the entire
application before they start contributing
effectively with slow Here, productivity
also breaks down the team's velocity.
Additionally, the complex nature
of the codebase means that changes
in one area, for example, in the UI
layer, often requires comprehensive
testing across the entire application.
For instance, let's say you want
to deploy a small UI update.
You can't do it in isolation.
You'll have to test the entire
application from print and grab the
integration layer in the backend
layer before you go ahead and deploy.
So this delays the time
to market for any feature.
The third main issue with monolithic
architecture is the cascading failures.
For example, in a monolithic
architecture, a small change or a small
bug in one part of the application
can cause unexpected issues elsewhere.
For example, if you If there is a minor
bug in the authentication module, there
is a very good chance it could affect
the user dashboard somewhere else.
So this leads to cascading often gets
very difficult to find out where exactly
is the root cause for this problem.
And the lack of modularity increases
this wide risk of system outages and
makes troubleshooting often difficult.
The next main issue with monolithic
architecture is the lack of
flexibility of technology.
So what happens with monolithic
architecture is you often lock yourself
into this specified technologies or
framework across the application.
And this can be limiting because, for
example, let's say for part of your
application, you want to use a different
technology or a different version of a
given library, that gets very difficult.
Because you are like tied up
to given technology framework
and version across the app.
in this architecture.
The next one more issue that you
tend to see in this architecture
is team coordination challenges.
So as team continues to grow, coordinating
development between different teams,
like within the team, this monolithic
architecture becomes very difficult.
Teams working on different features
usually often step on Each of the
stores leading to much complex
bottlenecks and CICD pipelines,
and then overall a slow progress.
This lack of ownership and modularity
can hinder a team's autonomy and
reduce the developer velocity.
So based on these challenges, it's
clear that we need a more modular
and flexible and scalable approach
to build modern web applications.
Like a for instance, comes to the rescue.
Microfinance address these issues
by enabling teams to develop, test
and deploy independent front end
modules, leading to faster delivery,
reduced risk and enhanced scalability.
On to the next slide, the
power of microfinance.
So microfinance are a game changer.
When it comes to building scalable,
reliable, and maintainable web
applications, their effectiveness lies
in a core set of principles that define
how we approach the modern development.
If you see, for example, in the picture
over there at the right, the same
monolithic application that you have
seen in the previous slide can be broken
down into three different applications.
For example, let's see.
Let's take the example of, say,
Amazon, which is again Amazon.
Uses micro front ends in its
application, so there could be an
independent instead of the entire
Amazon application being built as
one big application and deploying it.
They do is like just the cart experience
that you see is a separate team.
They might use react on the front end
and they might use Java at the back.
Similarly, the main page, the amazon.
com web page that you see.
There could be a different team
that could be working on it.
And similarly, the payment team.
Similarly, search is being, like, that's
another thing that's working out of there.
micro frontends, what happens is this
gives teams to work on different parts
of the application independently and
deploy and make changes over there.
micro frontends, what you get?
You get independent
scalability and deployability.
One of the greatest strengths of micro
frontends is their, like I was saying,
the ability to operate independently.
Wherein, each micro frontend
can be developed, tested,
and deployed separately.
Allow teams to, release new features
without impacting others applications.
It seems how it feels, it seems like
a very well choreographed dance where
each team moves in sync with other
without stepping on each other's toes,
resulting in a faster, smoother, and
more frequent deployments across.
Secondly, one more thing in
microfrontends are smaller
codebases for faster development.
So, to be breaking down of this huge
monolithic application into smaller
manageable pieces, microfrontends reduce
the complexity of the overall codebase.
This approach enables us for faster
development, as teams can focus
only on their specific microfrontend
without team needing to understand
or test the overall system.
for making a deployment.
This means that you can ship newer
features very fast and improve
the significant time to market,
time to sync, eventually improve.
The next thing is the, the
advantage for micro front end is
the resilience and fault tolerance.
One of the core features that micro
front end offers is complete decoupling.
So basically, by decoupling
different parts of the application,
Microfront can inherently build
this resilience and fault tolerance.
If one component fails, let's say your
cart fails or your search fails, it
doesn't bring down the entire Amazon.
com website.
Let's say your payment is having some
issue, you can still browse for the
product, you can still add products
to the cart, whereas you might not
be able to check out, but all the
other functionalities will go through.
And, uh, this reducing the system risk
of the overall total system downtime
and enhances the overall system
robustness technology agnosticism.
Like I'm saying previously, with
Microshinton, the individual teams can
choose the best tool for their job.
like Amazon homepage might think,
oh, there's just too many re renders
and everything that's happening
on my web page, let me use React.
Whereas probably.
The payment team might think, hey, okay,
for my application, what I'm trying
to do, I can, I would rather use Vue.
js.
So this technology agnostic
approach allows teams to leverage
their expertise or even it also
depends on the team composition.
Let's say, most of the team members on the
particular project or the team knows Vue.
js more than React.
js or even Angular.
js and they could go ahead and
build that particular application
in the technology by choice or
they're most comfortable with.
There's no Tying up of like you have
to use only this particular technology,
this particular version, etcetera.
Next thing is finally gives
you scalability at every level.
It's not just at the application.
It gives scalability
across the entire process.
So microfinance does not offer
scalability, not in terms of technology,
but also in terms of team structure.
For example, as your
application team grows.
You can scale your teams, each focusing
on different micro front ends without
risking of creating this monolithic.
What will add?
This distributed approach of development
allows your organization to grow more
organically, accommodating larger teams
and building more complex applications
without sacrificing the performance or
the agility that you get in smaller teams.
Next slide.
So what do we need to keep in mind
when developing this microfrontend?
What are the best practices?
What are the architecture patterns?
And what are the challenges that you
usually see or have to keep in mind when
building such microfrontend applications?
So the first choice you tend to
make is do you want to split your
monolithic application either
vertically or horizontally?
So what I mean by vertically is, for
example, Let's say in the example of,
Amazon itself, let's say breaking it now,
like for example, let's say any e-commerce
website, so for example, maybe it shows
you a list of products that they have.
One page.
One page like allows you to check
out which contains the card, and
the third thing manages the payment.
One way.
Splitting it vertically would mean
that you would, the entire homepage
will be owned by one team the entire.
Card page will be owned by one team,
the entire payment team will open.
So they'll own both their front
end and their back end services.
Horizontal splitting would be,
for example, would be like, a
team will own the entire UI, a
team will own the entire API.
But typically, the vertical
splitting is more common.
you see more often across the industry,
let's say, at IKEA or Spotify, where
individual teams will maintain both their
front end UI layer and the back end layer
for part, part of the functionality.
Amazon.
com, the home page will be on
both the UI and API workability.
The carting UI and API will be
owned by one team and the payment UI
and API will be owned by one team.
So that's like vertical splitting.
That's more, that's an architecture
pattern or how they've chosen it.
Similarly, you also have to like, keep
in mind that you need to establish clear
communication and contract boundaries.
Ensure well defined APIs.
for communication between micro
friend trends and this avoid
state coupling between them.
This also allows to iterate
independently as long as they
adhere to this con contracts.
So one, the challenge that is
there in Micro friend is caused
microfinance communication and status.
So previous need thought, the entire
application is one application.
In monolithic application,
the entire application is one.
So it's easier for components, one
component to talk to each other,
the others, the other and all that.
Now, since with micro frontends,
all of them are separate, are
separated, are different applications.
You need to be careful or be
cognizant of the fact that it's
not pretty straightforward how the
components can talk to each other.
So that's why we need to use well
defined API and use event driven
architectures to manage the interaction
between these microfrontends.
I would say probably look up tools
like, let's say, Event Puzzles,
Global State Managers, or even like
top tier microspack and microservice
to help this communication between
these two, these microfrontends.
Another challenge or thing
to keep in mind is maintain
consistency of user experience.
so because there are different teams
working on different parts of the UI,
you also need to make sure you also want
to make sure that all these experiences
that we are building are cohesive and
they all feel like they belong to the
same web application, the same page.
So an idea how we could solve this
problem is You need to establish a
comprehensive design system and enforce UI
UX guidelines across all the micro front
end applications that you're building,
or even shared library user conference
can also help maintain this consistency.
So it feels to the user that, okay,
although this given web page, like amazon.
com is being powered by, let's say,
10 different micro front ends, but it
feels like one website to the user.
It doesn't feel like, okay.
The search doesn't look different.
The homepage doesn't look different.
The cart based doesn't
look different at all.
Everything together looks like amazon.
com.
It does not feel like each of these pages.
Each page is different or being
built by different, teams.
The last one is security consoles.
So because now all these applications
are being built by different teams
and different developers, Ensuring
consistent security practices across
the entire application is important.
So we need to develop a unified
strategy that includes secure
communication, consistent authentication,
and authorization practices.
And each of these micro frontends should
adhere to the same security standards to
avoid any vulnerability across the slides.
Finally, in summary, what
are these micro frontends?
micro frontends help down, break down
large monolithic web applications into
smaller independent users, allowing
for modularity and scalability.
what are its key benefits?
Main benefits are independent scalability.
Teams can develop, test and deploy
these micro frontends independently,
leading to faster release
cycles and better scalability.
Faster deployment cycles, because now
that you have smaller code base, results
in quicker development and deployment
cycles, enabling rapid future updates.
Reliability.
in one micro frontend, like I was
saying, will not affect the entire
application, enhancing the overall
system reliability and security.
Technology agnosticism.
teams can use different technologies
for different micro frontends,
promoting flexibility and innovation.
Teams can work in technologies
that they're most comfortable
in and they're stronger.
So what are the best practices
and challenges that you need to
keep in mind while designing this
application are, you need to choose
the right architecture pattern.
Like I was saying, you either choose
the vertical splits or the horizontal,
how you, or the horizontal splits.
So how you want to break down your
overall monolithic application into parts.
So you also need to establish this
clear communication, where to define
the CPI contracts and maintain it.
The shared libraries for all the
applications to use ensure consistency.
That's a huge thing because For the
customer or the user, whoever is
coming to our web page, we need to make
sure that they don't get a feed that
they call for the kind of given page.
It looks like four different
web applications are stitched
together on one page and they
feel or look or work differently.
So that should not happen.
Few real world examples of like really
huge companies that have embraced this
methodology and are using as of today, for
example, a few of them could be Spotify,
Amazon, I key, tens of a few examples that
are out there that have been using and
I've been spearheading, this technology.
So what are my final thoughts?
So micro front ends offer a powerful
approach to building scalable.
maintainable web applications, but
require careful planning and execution.
Embrace the modularity, leverage
the best practices, and address the
challenges proactively to maximize
the benefits of microfrontends.
Thank you all.
Thank you so much for taking
the time to join me today to go
over this microfrontend based
architecture based presentation.
Thank you all.