Hello to community.
I'm Anmar Senior Cloud architect at
Unstack, and I have a question for you.
How much time did you or your
developers spend last week fighting
with infrastructures related issues
instead of building core futures
that your customers actually want?
If you said 40% or more, welcome aboard.
You are not alone.
Today I'm going to show you how the
industry leaders like Netflix, Spotify,
and Capital One, have solved this
problem using platform engineering, and
more importantly, how can you implement
these strategies in your organization.
Over the next couple of minutes,
we'll cover the evolution from
DevOps to platform engineering.
Dive deep into internal
developer platform.
And give you a concrete
action plan to get started.
Let's get started.
Before we dive in, let me
beautifully introduce myself.
I am an and over the past two decades, I
have been helping organizations transform
their software delivery practices.
I have worked with major financial
institutions like Wells Fargo,
first Republic Bank, US Bank,
tech, and technology like.
Persistent Systems and Capgemini.
I have personally led the migration of
monolith applications to microservices
architectures that have dramatically
improved deployment efficiency.
I recently published research on
this topic in the world General
of Advanced engineering technology
and sciences, and today I will be
sharing both the academic insights.
And real world implementation strategies.
Okay, let's start with
the uncomfortable truth.
DevOps has been incredibly successful,
but we have hit a scaling ball.
The practices that work beautifully
for the team of 10, ISTs becoming
nightmarish for organizations
with a hundred plus microservices
across multiple cloud environments.
Our research shows that 69% of enterprise
struggle with DevOps scalability,
but here is what's really happening.
Your developers are
drowning in complexity.
They are spending 40% of their time and
efforts rustling with infrastructure
instead of solving business problems.
Think about the last time your
team need a new environment.
Did it take days?
Weeks.
I have seen organizations where spinning
up a test environment requires approval
from six different teams and takes weeks,
such as like an approximately three weeks.
Meanwhile, your competitors are
deploying multiple times per day.
This isn't just a productivity problem,
it's an existential business risk.
When your deployment lead, lead
time is measured in weeks while your
competition measures stays in us, you
are not competing with in the same game.
Platform Engineering isn't
replacing DevOps, it's evolving it.
Instead of expecting every developer
to become an infrastructure expert,
we are rebuilding platforms that
makes infrastructure invisible.
Here is the key insight.
We treat infrastructure as a product.
With the developers as our customers,
this fundamental shift changes everything.
Suddenly, we are optimizing for developers
experience measuring satisfaction,
and iterating based on user feedback.
Here, the users are our developers.
The difference is profound.
In traditional DevOps, if a developer
needs a database, they might
spend two days learning Terraform,
configuring security groups,
and debugging networking issues.
With platform engineering, they
click a button, answer a few
questions, and have a production
release database within minutes.
This isn't theoretical.
Companies like Next, Netflix
deploys thousands of times per day.
Spotify onboards new developers
in ads instead of weeks.
Capital One reduced the time to
production by 40% while actually
improving security and compliance.
An internal developer platform isn't
just a collection of tools, it's just
a COO system with five core components.
Let me share some concrete numbers
from our research configuration
management alone, just standardizing
how applications define their
requirements reduced to configuration
related incidents by over 40%.
That's not a small improvement,
that's a transformational.
Infrastructure provisioning is
a biggest bank for the buck.
Organizations implementing self-service
provisioning reduced enrollment
creation time from weeks to minutes.
Imagine the productivity impact
when developers can spin up a
complete test enrollment faster
than they can get a cup of copy.
Notice that infrastructure
provisioning and deployment
pipelines get the largest focus.
Which is like a, 50% combined.
These are your highest
impacting starting points.
The beauty is you don't need to
build all five components at once.
Start with your biggest pain point.
If your developers are waiting weeks for
enrollments, start with provisioning.
If developers are fragile and slow,
start with pipelines and like that.
Let's look at the concrete
results from industry leaders.
These aren't theoretical case studies.
These are real implementations
with measurable outcomes.
Spotify story is particularly compelling.
They had over a thousand microservices
and developers were spending hours just
figuring out which service did what.
Backstage cut service discovery time in
half, but more importantly, it reduced
developer onboarding from weeks to days.
They were so successful that
they open source of it, and it's
now A-C-C-N-F incubating project
used by hundreds of companies.
Netflix took a different approach focusing
on development deployment sophistication.
Spinnaker enables them to deploy
thousands of times per day across
multiple cloud enrollments with advanced
strategies, including Canary STA releases.
They maintain 99.99% availability while
deploying constantly something that would
be impossible without platform automation.
Capital One's success is especially
relevant for regulated industries.
They achieved 40% faster time
to production while actually
improving security and compliance.
The reduced security
vulnerabilities by 60%.
Do automated scanning and policy
enforcement built into their platform?
The common thread each started with the
biggest pain point see delivered early
values that the expanded the business
based on their developer feedback.
Let's talk about the technology stack.
The good news is that the ecosystem
has matured significantly.
You don't need to build
everything from scratch.
Kubernetes has become
the defacto standard.
78% of elite performing
organizations use it as their
container orchestration platform.
But here is the critical insight.
Do not expose Kubernetes
to your developers.
Abstract it behind simpler interfaces.
This Golden rule guides
all platform decisions.
Abstract the complex,
expose the necessary.
Your developers don't need to understand
Kubernetes networking or storage classes.
They just simply need to say, I
want a scalable web service and
have it provisioned automatically.
GitHubs is your operational backbone.
Everything including infrastructures,
applications, configurations, lifts in it.
This makes everything auditable,
roll backable, and reproducible.
When something breaks, you can
trace exactly what changed and when.
Service meshes handle this
networking complexity that
kills developer productivity.
Instead of each team figuring
out service to service
authentication, circuit breakers and
observability, the mesh provides it
automatically, which is auto box.
The key is composition over creation.
Backstage for developer portals.
Argo City for GitHubs
IST for service mesh.
Focus on your custom development on
the unique aspects of your business
needs, not the infrastructure plumbing.
This is probably the most
common question I get.
Should we build or buy?
The answer depends entirely on your
context, on our con constraints.
If you are a financial institution
with 2000 plus engineers, unique
compliance requirements and
multi-year timeline building
common custom one makes more sense.
You have the scale to justify
the investment and the need
for deep customization.
If you are a mid-sized company
with standard Technologies stack
and 200 plus engineers adopting
executive solutions is best.
Backstage is production ready,
has a thriving community and can
be customized for your needs.
But here is the reality check.
Building a custom platform from
scratch requires at least a 10 to
15 full-time engineers minimum.
I have seen organizations
underestimate this by 50% or more.
Factor the true cost into
your ROA calculations.
Most successful implementations
take a hybrid approach.
Start with backstage for your developer
portal, Argo City for GitHubs and custom
components for your specific needs.
This gives you at least 80% of
the value in 20% of the time.
The key is starting
somewhere and iterating.
Perfect is the enemy of good.
Remember this and good
is the enemy of shit.
Okay, let's make this actionable.
Here is a proven implementation
roadmap that minimizes the risk
while maximizing EV early values.
Phase one is all about quick wins
and building organizational momentum.
Pick your biggest developer's pain
point, usually CSAD, or environment
provisioning and solve it really well.
Your goal is to get one capability
that developers love using.
I cannot overemphasize this, that you
need a product owner, not just engineers.
Successful platforms treat developers
as customers, measure satisfaction,
and it treat based on feedback.
This isn't a technology project,
it's a product development effort.
Phase two is where you build the
platform foundation add observability.
So developers can debug their own issues.
Integrate security so it's
automated rather than a gate.
Create templates.
So new projects start with best practices.
Built in phase three is where
you get advanced AI assisted
development, sophisticated deployment
strategies cloud orchestration.
But do not skip phase one and phase two.
I have seen organizations try to
build the ultimate platform from
day one and fail because they didn't
establish developers trust first.
The key metrics phase one success
is measured in our environment.
Creation is less than a day.
Phase two, successes, adoption, 80%
of applications using your platform.
Phase three's, elite performance
deployment, frequency, lead times.
And reliability matching industry leaders.
I know it's like in a 12 to 18
months, sounds long, but remember,
your competitors are either already
building this or starting now.
The question comes here isn't whether to
start, it's whether to lead or follow.
Let's talk about measuring success,
because what gets measured gets managed,
and what gets managed gets funded.
These aren't vanity metrics.
They directly correlate
with business outcomes.
Elite performance deployment deploys
6,000, finance 70 times more frequently
than low performance, while maintaining
three times lower failure TR rates.
When your competition can deploy
features in us while you take
Wix, that's not technical problem.
It's an existential business threat,
but here is what's really compelling
the infrastructure cost savings.
Organizations with mature
platforms achieve 30 to 50%
lower costs per transaction.
Using the better resource utilization,
automation and standardization.
For a large enterprises, that's
millions of dollars annually.
Developer retention is equally important
in today's competitive talent market.
Developer satisfaction directly
impacts recruiting and retention costs.
We have seen 25% improvements
in satisfaction scores of
the platform implementation.
Start measuring immediately.
Even if your numbers are
terrible, that's still fine.
You need the baseline to
demonstrate improvement.
I have worked with organizations
that reduced deployment time from few
weeks to two hours within 12 months.
The ROI is unbelievable when you
can quantify the transformation.
Let me save you significant
pain by sharing the most common
implementation failures I have observed.
The I trap kills more platforms
than technical issues.
I have seen beautifully architecture
platforms that nobody uses because
they solve theoretical problems
instead of real developer's.
Pain.
Start with user research,
not architecture diagrams.
This is a very important
point to remember.
The perfect platform always
falls equally dangerous.
One organization is worked.
Where I worked with spent 18 months
building the ultimate platform.
When they launched, developers complained
it was too complex to use and went
back to their old developer tools.
They had to start over with A
simpler approach not invented.
Here is syndrome is very expensive.
Do not build a custom
service mesh when exists.
Do not create a deployment pipeline
when Argo CD is proven at scale.
It means and you don't
need to reinvent the wheel.
Focus your custom development on
what makes your business unique.
Governance balance is tricky, too
rigid, and you still innovation
too permissive, and you get chaos.
Start with lightweight guidelines
and tighten based on actual
problems, not theoretical risks.
Most importantly, this
isn't a technology project.
Remember, it's an
organizational transformation.
You need executive sponsorship, change
management, and clear communication about
how roles and responsibilities evolves.
Technical excellence without
organizational alignment leads to
beautiful systems that nobody uses.
Looking ahead.
The next 2, 3, 2 to three
years will bring transformative
changes to platform engineering.
AI integration is the
biggest game changer.
We are already seeing platforms that
generate deployment configurations
from natural language descriptions.
Imagine describing your infrastructure
needs in plain English and having
production ready environments
provisioned automatically
with security best practices.
Built in GitHub copay showed
us, yeah, as a coding.
The next wave is AI assisted
infrastructure management Platforms that
can predict scaling needs, automatically
remediate common issues and suggest
optimizations based on UCS patterns.
Democratization through low code means
your business analyst can build workflow
automation without bothering developers.
This isn't replacing
developers, it's freeing them.
To work on harder and
more valuable problems.
Multi-cloud isn't coming.
It's here.
84% of enterprise uses
multi-cloud providers.
The platforms that when will abstract
those differences seamlessly,
your developers shouldn't need to
know whether their service runs on
AWS Azure, Google Cloud, or IBM.
Or LL Boomi and any of the cloud different
clouds, they don't need to know about it.
Platform engineering is becoming a
special career path with dedicated
training, pro training programs,
and premium compensations.
This is a high demanding
rules.
The demand for platform engineers
has grown 300% in the last two
years, and it's exhilarating.
The organizations that invent
invest in platform capabilities now
will have sustainable competitive
advantages in developer productivity,
operational efficiency, and innovation.
Speed.
Okay, so now we already have
discussed it quite a lot.
Let's make this immediately actionable.
Don't leave this presentation
with your just inspiration.
Live with the concrete plan.
You can start executing this week.
Week one, send a developer
experience survey.
Ask one simple question.
What's the most frustrating
part of getting code from
your laptop to production?
The answers will be given to you
based on the developer's experience
and your platform roadmap, and create
organizational awareness for the
problems your platform team needs.
Someone with product management
skills, not just engineers.
This person will be responsible
for developer satisfaction,
roadmap prioritization, and
stakeholder communication.
This role is very critical for success.
Your MEP should solve one problem
extremely well, not 10 problems poorly.
Pick something you can deliver in six
to eight weeks, maximum enrollment.
Provisioning and CICD standardizations
are usually good starting points.
Success measure starts immediately.
Track time to enrollment creation,
deployment frequency, and
developer satisfaction codes.
These metrics will justify
continued investment and guide you
decisions towards your decisions.
Here is your homework assignment.
Okay.
Start your developer survey this week.
Do not wait for perfect
conditions or complete buy-in.
Create momentum through
small actions and early wins.
The orations that start will now, the
orination who are starting right now
will have 12 to 18 month advantages
over those that are still waiting.
Platform engineering
isn't optional anymore.
It's table stakes.
Table stakes for competitive
software delivery.
Let me leave you with five principles
that separate successful platform
implementations from expensive values.
Fast.
This isn't about collecting more tools.
I have seen organizations with
47 different development tools
who is thinking that they
may need another 40th one.
Platform engineering is about creating
coherent developer experiences.
That high complexity not add to it.
Second, start with problems that your
developers actually have, not problems
you think they should be having it.
The most elegant technical solution is
worthless if it doesn't solve real pain.
The third product mindset is what
separates winners from losers.
Your platform succeeds when
developers choose to use it,
not when they are forced to.
That changes everything about how you
design, build, and evolve your platform.
Fourth measurement isn't optional.
You need data to justify continued
investment, guide roadmap decisions
and prove your business that
impacted start measuring immediately.
Even if your numbers are
embarrassing, that's still fine.
Fifth, think evolution, not revolution.
Small improvements compound over time.
Perfect platforms shipped.
Never beat.
Good platforms improved continuously.
Here is the reality platform.
Engineering is rapidly
becoming table stakes.
Not competitive advantage.
Every major technology company
already has sophisticated platforms.
The question isn't whether you will
be implementing platform engineering.
It's whether you will do it before or
after your competitors gain an advantage.
Okay, let's connect and
continue the conversations.
So here are my details, my personal
id, email id, and my LinkedIn and the
research paper, what I have done on
this topic and the available resources.
What we are going to discuss
further down now the detailed
survey questions are available.
You can ping me, you
can send an email to me.
I can share under this template.
Let me give you a concrete framework
for calculating ROI On the cost side,
calculate developers time waste.
Take your number of developers,
multiply by hours per week spent on
infrastructure issues, multiply by
hourly rate and multiply by 52 weeks.
Add infrastructure inefficiency costs.
Incident response costs and
revenue loss due to the slow
delivery on the investment side.
Plan for 10 to 15 fts for your
platform team over three years,
technology licenses, migration
costs, and ongoing operations.
Most organizations with a hundred
plus developers to see 300
to 500% ROA over three years.
This math is compelling when
you quantify the transformation.
Here is a practical edition metrics
for your technology stack for developer
portals backstage for open source
compost for commercial AWS per proton
for cloud, native for GitHubs, Argo
cd, or flux for open source GitLab.
For commercial.
Choose open source for customization
and large teams commercial for
enterprise support and compliance.
Cloud native for rapid deployment and.
Managed services before you start.
Here is your plea flight, pre-flight.
Check-in checklist.
Organizationally secure
executive sponsorship.
Identify a platform product owner,
document developer pain points, and
create a change management plan.
Technically document your
current architecture, make
technology stack decisions, and
select your pilot application.
For team readiness, high platform
engineers ensure you have product owners,
project, sorry, product management
skills, and establish your support model.
Don't skip these steps, they
determine success or failure.
I have included some extension resources
in the slides, books like team topologies,
industry reports, and community links to
continue our platform engineering journey.
Feel free to search them and Google them
and join them and continue your journey.
And finally, thank you for your
time investing in this presentation.
Platform.
Engineering rep represents one of
the most significant evolutions in
software delivery practices, and
I'm exited to see how you all apply
these concepts in your organizations.
I'm here if you need any help,
feel free to contact me and I'm
ready to share my knowledge and my
experiences for your team success.
And once again, thank you and thanks
for Con 42 providing this opportunity.
Thank you.
Have a great day.