Hi everyone.
Welcome to conference 42,
platform Engineering 2025.
This is LaMi.
I bring over 20 plus years of
experience in building enterprise
data lakes and enterprise data
analytics platforms across both on pre.
Cloud environments.
Today's talk is focusing on beyond
manual firefighting, building,
self feeling data pipelines with
AI for platform engineering.
Platform engineers today face
unprecedented operational
challenges because of exponential.
Growth of data and exponential growth of
data pipelines across the enterprises.
Every transaction or user interaction
generates a lot of data that
has to be ingested, transformed,
validated and provide and available
to data analytics platform.
Even though we have most advancements
in orchestration frameworks and cloud
native platforms, pipeline failures
remains one of the persistent pain point
across all the production environments.
In the next slide, we talk
about current challenges.
Engineers spend mata of the
time debugging the failures.
Fixing the broken data pipelines
manually restoring service continuity.
This talk explores transformative to
potential of VA A driven self-healing
data pipelines by leveraging
anomaly detection, root cause
analysis, autonomous remediation.
So that enterprises can move from
react to firefighting, to ProAct
to eventually autonomous operation.
In this talk, we'll be focusing on three
use cases across retail sector and health,
healthcare domain, as well as financial.
Domain and also we talk practical
implementation strategies.
What are the factors to be considered
for governance, and what would be
the measurable written investment?
Adapting, yay a in platform engineering.
The introduction, we talk here.
The modern enterprises all defined by
data, every strategic decision, customer
experience, complaints reports all depends
upon seamless data flow from source system
to analytical platforms and dashboards.
To handle this demand platform, engineers
has to design complex data pipelines
that operates with high reliability due
to the complexity of these pipelines.
Say small schema mismatch, our network
outage configuration transformation,
breaking the enter downstream
workflow, which impacts losing the
revenues, opportunities, compliance
violation, and violation, and delayed
insights of the decision making.
In this slide, we are going to
talk how the current traditional
monitoring is working.
The traditional monitoring system
notifies users when something fails
and remediation is almost manual.
As of today, 60% of platform engineers
operational bandwidth will go.
Troubleshooting and recovering the
job and the amount of jobs or data
pipelines or interconnected jobs.
The probability of at least one
failure daily is near certain, so by.
Seeing all these failures, utilization
of Yaya power, self-healing data
pipelines makes a paradigm shift.
Instead, engineers reacting to the
failures, pipelines can autonomously
detect the anomalies, diagnose the root
cause, and take the character action.
By doing that, the role
of engineers now become.
Firefighters to supervisor focusing on
the governance, auditing, and improving
intelligence of these autonomous systems.
So the current, what is
the burden of this manual?
Troubleshooting is for the, any
enterprise is cost association because any
downtime of critical pipeline in retail
organization delay the inventory updates.
Across the thousands of stores, whereas
in the case of financial services,
broken fraud detection pipeline can lose
millions of dollars for that institute.
In this slide, we are going to
talk about the key challenges
of manual pipeline management.
The manual process has
highly failure frequency.
Because of hundreds of interconnected
jobs interconnected jobs and also failure
of one job can impact downstreams and
difficult to stress the root cause
and locks are often augmented across
the systems, requires engineers to
stitch together and close manually.
This, the, this situation is not
sustainable for data ecosystems.
So the promise of AA in self
filling data pipelines decides on
these following four capabilities.
One is anomaly detection.
This indicates algorithms
continuously analyze the matrix logs.
Data quality checks do
detect any abnormal behavior.
You by using trans
transformer based models.
That demonstrated exceeding 90%
in identifying the anomalies.
The second one, root, the second
capability, root cause analysis.
With the utilization of natural language
models, GPT-4, we can analyze the logs,
trace the dependency graphs, identify the.
Most probable root cause with
the minimal human impact.
The third capability, autonomous
remediation once the cause is identified.
Reinforcement learning
agents are rule-based.
Automation trigger can
take the character actions.
Continuous learning is by learning
from previous spoilers, successful
remediation and human feedback.
This is one of the case study in the
retail sector where the global retail
sector, our company managing two
terabytes of data ingesting from source
to target is facing frequent data
pipeline failures because of s screamer
changes or high volume traffic spikes.
The manual process often took
covers leading avail, leading
to delayed product availability
on e-commerce platform with ai.
The k 99% of time across critical
data pipelines are achieved and
anomaly detection with 94% accuracy
is identifying schema mismatches, ude,
and automated recovery of workflows
from two hours to five minutes.
As achieved, as well as operational
cost, estimated from a million
dollars to reduced downtime.
In the healthcare, another case study
in the healthcare sector, the IT uses
GPT-4 to automatically pass the locks.
Identify the failure, authentication,
or misconfiguration policies
with autonomous remediation.
We can isolate the failing notes,
rerouting the data, and hand over it to
the engineers to review the EA actions
to take care of high risk scenarios.
So the results were for profound.
The recovery times are dropped by 70%.
Complaints, audits conformed, all a
driven actions were logged and auditable.
Another case study that conducted
was in the FinTech company.
In the FinTech sector, real
time fraud detection demands
subsecond responsiveness.
The leading tech form faces the
challenges when even where even shortages
could explore platform to fraudulent
transaction with AA data driven.
Self feeling.
Data pipelines are reinforcement
learning agents, dynamic resource
allocation as and when the volume is
more immediately allocating more compute
resources to fraud detection models.
So that it's automatically
identifying frauds in subsecond,
responsiveness and automated failure.
One is automatically all the automated
failures to backup pipelines without
human intervention and recovery
times are dropped from subsecond
levels ensuring uninterrupted.
Fraud detection.
So the adoption of self-healing pipelines
will help not only reducing the fraud
risk and also reassuring regulators and
customers of the platforms reliability.
So the whole technical foundation
of the self filling pipelines
relies on detect, analyze, optimize.
So the transform transformer based
anomaly detection, identifies
time series matrix log anomaly
detection natural language models,
identifies the root cause analysis.
Reinforcement learning agents
will use resource optimization
agent continuously learn.
Optimal policies for scaling
routing resource allocation, the
how the enterprises can implement
these self filling data pipelines.
The architecture patterns
will be three ways.
One is centralized a layer, other
one is decentralized embedded agents.
Third one is hybrid models.
So the governance and trust plays
a critical role whenever any
organization enterprise adapts ai.
So the, so if.
The that the self feeling data
pipelines, make sure it is compatible
for editability, which means every
variation has logged with explanation
and industry specific regulations as
followed in the compliance framework.
Human AI collaboration engineers
should remain supervisory roles,
reviewing high impact remediation.
These autonomous systems operate within
guardrails of gain trust, so building this
trust in self-healing system any requires
transparency, continuous monitoring and
cultural change within organization.
So the role, the information business
impact when any organization implements
the self filling data pipelines, what we
saw here is the downtime reduction was
approximately a. Very reduced on term
reduction was 99% are achievable and
there is huge number of dollars are saved
in terms of handling the volume spikes
as well as routing the failure data to
different node and avail and making sure
platform is available for all the time.
And the team got a productivity
gain of 70% because of.
Automatically rev running the
data pipelines for any failures.
So the benefit of self-healing
pipelines extends beyond technical
resilience, customer satisfaction
with faster, more reliable services.
The retina investment often calculated,
comparing the avoided downtime,
cost, reducing fraud exposure, and
engineering hours saved the, so the
future of self-healing pipelines.
As the data grows, enterprise
data pipelines grows.
With the utilizing this a power cell
feeling pipelines, it'll be battle
tested solution, and that is already
transforming in retail healthcare finance.
So by adapting anomaly detection,
natural language return, root
cause analysis, reinforcement
learning, our continuous learning
organizations can achieve unprecedented
reliability, compliance efficiency.
That's all for that today's talk.
Thank you.
I.