Hey everyone.
I'm, and I'm excited to be
here to discuss a topic that's
transforming our business operate.
The topic is modern ERP as the platform
backbone for AI driven supply chain.
So we are living in an era where supply
chains are no longer linear their dynamic.
Interconnected ecosystems driven
by data, AI promises to revolution,
revolutionize, supply chain planning,
execution, and responsiveness.
But there's a catch.
Most enterprises are still running
on outdated ERP systems that
were not built for the future.
Today's enterprises phase a
critical inflection point.
On one side we have exponential
growth in ai, machine learning,
IOT, and predictive analytics.
On the other hand, we have legacy
RP systems, which are rigid, siloed
and are not designed for real
time AI power decision making.
This mismatch creates inefficiencies
like data silos, delayed
visibility, and an inability to
respond to disruptions quickly.
The traditional ERP systems were
built for transaction processing
and not for intelligence.
They're like Ivy built for
cars, but now we are trying
to run I speed trains on them.
Without modern ERP platforms that
integrate AI natively, businesses risk
falling beyond competitors who can
sense, predict, and respond much faster.
In this session I will share why modern
ERP must serve as backbone for AI driven
supply chains and how organizations can
transform from reactive, siloed operations
to truly intelligent, connected networks.
We'll also explore what makes an
ERP already with real world use
cases and how companies can future
proof the supply chain platforms.
All right.
So now that we've set the stage
for why AI driven supply chains are
critical let's address the elephant
in the room which is our existing
ERP systems are holding us back.
The promise of AI can only be realized if
the foundational systems can support it.
And legacy ERP systems simply
were not built for this new world.
First.
Legacy RP implementations
are highly fragmented.
Over years of customization and
bolt on solutions, enterprises have
ended up with disconnected processes
across planning, logistics, asset
management, hr, finance, and sourcing.
And this fragmentation creates data silos.
Where critical information is
locked in isolated systems leading
to delays in decision making,
duplicated efforts, and an inability
to respond quickly to disruptions.
Second data, which is the life
blood of AI, is often not ai.
Already in this systems ERPs may
hold vast amount of structured and
unstructured data, but much of it is
incomplete, inconsistent, and siloed.
AI models thrive on clean, standardized,
and integrated data across functions
like supply chain finance, hr, et cetera.
Without this, AI initiatives fail
to deliver meaningful insights.
The third reason is the rigid
architecture of legacy ERP, which
makes it extremely challenging to
integrate with modern technologies be it
cloud-based platforms, machine learning
framework, or emerging capabilities
like digital twins and generative ai.
This lack of flexibility means
every integration becomes a
costly, time consuming project
rather than a seamless capability.
This limitations of fragmentation,
poor data readiness rigidity are why
companies struggle to unlock the full
potential of AI in the supply chains.
The good news, paradigm is emerging
ERP modernization, guided by
platform engineering principle,
and that's what we'll explore next.
So how do we how do we
overcome the limitation of
legacy ERP we just discussed?
The answer lies in rethinking ERP
not as a monolithic application, but
as platform engineer for agility,
scalability, and intelligence.
This is where platform
engineering principles.
Come into play transforming ERP
into flexible foundation, capable of
supporting AI driven supply chain.
Platform engineering focuses on
building scalable and maintainable
technology ecosystems by treating
systems as a set of interoperable
services rather than one rigid block.
When applied to the enterprise resource
planning applications, it allows us to
break down the traditional structure
into modular composable pieces.
That can evolve independently
and integrate seamlessly
with emerging technologies.
The key tenants of platform
engineering approach are microservice
architecture, A PFS design, even
driven architecture microservice
architecture instead of a single
tightly coupled system, functionality
is de delivered through microservices.
Self-contained modules, for
example, finance, procurement,
planning, logistics, et cetera.
This gives organizations unprecedented
flexibility to scale specific
capability rollout updates faster,
and adopt innovations without
disrupting the entire system.
Second is the a p first design.
API APIs are the glue that ensures
all ERP functionality is easily
accessible and integrate with other
company or other enterprise systems,
be it external partners or internal
partners and also AI solutions.
A well documented version,
API strategy, future proofs
the ERP and enables continuous
integration of new capabilities.
Last but not least, the event driven
architecture which moving away from
Batch Pro, batch based processes
to even driven architecture.
Which means real time responsiveness
inventory update, demand
signals disruption are processed
instantly enabling predictive and
adaptive supply chain operations.
By adapting this platform, engineering
principles, microservices, APIs,
and even driven architecture, we
create an ERP foundation that.
That is no longer a barrier
to innovation but a launchpad
for AI driven transformation.
Okay, let's move to the next slide.
Awesome.
So we've seen our platform's energy
platform engineering transforms ERP
into a flexible modern platform.
But flexibility alone is not enough to
truly enable AI driven supply chain.
We need unity.
A unified ERP architecture that
breaks down silos across enterprise.
Legacy ERP systems operate
as isolated modules.
Whereas modern Unified ERP
architecture treats every part
of the business like planning,
logistics, sourcing finance, asset
management as intercon interconnected
components of a single ecosystem.
This shift lays the foundation
for AI because AI needs holistic
real time data to be effective.
End-to-end visibility with unified
ERP gain real time access to
data across the value chain.
This means decisions are informed by
what's happening right now, not by
outdated reports or delayed updates.
Processes processes no
longer operate in isolation.
For example, maintenance scheduling
can automatically factor in
production plans, inventory levels and
transportation constraints, enabling
crew optimized operations unified ERP
enforces consistent end-to-end process
across the enterprise where it's.
Planning, sourcing, or asset management.
Everyone follows the same best
practices guidelines removing
inefficiencies and inconsistencies.
Finally, unified, ERP establishes
common data model and governance
policies across the enterprise with
thereby reducing the data quality
issues that undermine AI initiatives.
Clean, standardized data, as we know, is
the bedrock of trustworthy AI insights.
Breaking down silos through
unified ERP architecture
doesn't just improve efficiency.
It what it is what makes AI in
supply chain truly positive.
And so next we'll see how this unified
platform enables for intelligent,
autonomous, and decision making at scale.
Okay, next slide.
Alright, so as we saw that unified ERP
architecture breaks down silos internally
but it truly unlocks air driven value air.
Now for that ERP must also
integrate seamlessly with the
broader enterprise ecosystem.
This is where in, integration excellence
becomes the key differentiator.
Modern ERP can no longer operate
in silos or as an island.
AI thrives on compressive.
Connected data flow from
shop floor operations to
strategic financial planning.
This means moving beyond simple point to
point connections to a deeply integrated,
intelligent operational network.
The core integration pillars
in any, in a new era, ERP, like
S four is the core backbone.
Then on top of that, you have advanced
modules like Ariba, extended warehouse
management, transportation management,
integrated business planning, the
financial supply chain management,
which use the end-to-end visibility.
To the entire supply chain and beyond.
And then you have systems like Teamcenter,
which are used for product lifecycle
management MES systems like camstar or
LIMS systems like Lab Vantage, which play
a pivotal role in each of their specific
areas, but come together in terms of
a comprehensive connected data flow.
When ERP becomes this deep, deeply
integrated up, it transforms from a system
of record into a system of intelligence
powering predictive analy analytics,
automated decision making and AI driven
optimization across the enterprise.
So the key here is the integration
excellence and how do we achieve that.
Great.
Go to the next slide.
Alright, so let's look at some of the
examples of of how we can leverage ai.
So far we have talked about building the
foundation of AI driven supply chain.
Now let's look at one of the most
powerful real world applications of this
approach which is predictive maintenance.
This is where the modern ERP IO
OT and AI converge to deliver
a tangible business value.
As you, as you all know, equipment
failures are costly unplanned downtime
can all production, can dealer shipments
and essentially erode customer trust.
Predictive maintenance flips the script.
Instead of reacting to breakdowns,
companies can actually predict
and prevent them using AI
driven insights and algorithms.
IOT sensors IOT sensor
network embedded in machines.
Feed, continuous stream of data
about the equipment be it the
temperature, vibration, pressure,
and, and many more attributes.
Modern ERP systems aggregate and.
Con contextualize this data, making
it actionable across the enterprise.
On top of that, the machine learning
algorithm are able to detect
subtle patterns and anomalies
early signs of way or failure
that human operators might miss.
These insights are not just descriptive,
they're predictive, anticipating
problems even before they occur.
With AI generated early
warnings, maintenance.
Maintenance teams can schedule
repair during planned downtime.
Order parts spare parts in advance
and eliminate costly surprises.
This moves organizations
from reactive fighting.
Two proactive.
I think the results are very compelling.
Reduced downtime, lower maintenance
cost, improved asset longevity.
And I have customer satisfaction.
This is just one example of a modern
ERP As an AI enabled platform backbone
delivers real competitive advantage.
Okay, let's look at another example.
As predictive maintenance showed
us how AI and RP transformation
operations on the supply side.
Now let's look at the demand side.
AI driven demand forecasting one
of the most impactful applications
of AI and supply chain management.
Accurate demand forecasting has
always been the holy grail for
supply chain practitioners and AI
is finally making it a reality.
Traditional forecasting methods
struggle with volatility, limited
data inputs, and the need and the
need for constant manual adjustments.
Ai can overcome these limitations
by leveraging massive data sets,
self learning algorithms and
advanced scenario modeling all
enabled by modern EIP foundation.
The modern AI algorithm tap into vast
data sets for multiple sources be it
sales history market trends, social
sentiments, weather patterns even IOT
data to uncover even patterns that
traditional methods cannot detect.
Unlike static models
that degrade over time.
Yeah.
Algorithm learn continuously.
They are just dynamically as data flows
in ensuring forecasting remain accurate
without constant human intervention.
AI also empowers organization
with what if capabilities.
It can generate multiple forecast
scenarios, helping business plan for
uncertainties like demand, surge,
supply, disruptions, and market share.
The result it's it's reduced
stockouts, lower inventory costs
fast, faster response to market
changes, and a significant competitive
advantage edge over others.
This is our modern ERP enables
business to move from guess from
guesswork to precision forecasting
fueling resilience and profitability.
Okay, let's move to the next slide.
Alright, so we saw at AWA Transforms
operations and forecasting, let's.
Now let's address another critical
area where modern E-L-P-N-A AI converge
contracts management and risk mitigation.
This is the area where natural
language processing or NLP.
Is making a real impact.
Contracts are the backbone
of business relationships.
We all know that covering everything
from supplier agreement to customer
agreement, to compliance requirements.
But in many enterprises, many
companies, contracts are still
unstructured, manual and very
disconnected from operations and NLP.
Changes that by turning contracts into
actionable intelligence NLP capabilities
can can automatically extract and
analyze key details from every contract.
Like payment terms, what
are my delivery obligations?
What are the compliance clause
and many more items like that.
Essentially eliminating manual
reviews and reducing errors.
Machine learning algorithms.
Can scan thousands of contracts to
identify hidden risks, such as unfavorable
terms concentration of exposures or
patterns that could lead to disputes.
This proactive insight allows
companies to mitigate risk before
it becomes expensive and costly.
When integrated with ERP systems, this
contract intelligence don't just sit.
In the legal side or the legal
department, it treats directly
into operational decisions.
One of the examples that I've seen
is a supplier, when they miss a
critical delivery obligation, ERP
can automatically adjust production
plans or trigger alternative sourcing.
By inputing, NLP, forward contract
intelligence into ERP organizations
gain better compliance, reduced risk,
and faster smarter decision making.
This is another step towards making
ERP not just a system of record,
but a system of intelligence, right?
So let's move to the next one.
Okay.
Forward looking vision.
So we've explored our modern ERP supports,
today's AI driven supply chain needs.
But what's next?
Where is this journey heading?
The future of ERP is not
just a transactional system.
It's becoming the launch path for
enterprise wide AI innovation.
The shift from traditional
back office ERP to AI enabled
platform is more than an upgrade.
It's a paradigm shift.
ERP will be the no center of the
no center for AI driven decision
making across the enterprise.
LA large language ma models.
The n the LLMs will enhance nearly
every happy process from customer
service chat bots that under understand
complex inquiries to air driven
procurement to autonomous planning.
This brings intelligence to every
interaction that we know of digital twin.
The digital twins of entire supply
chains will provide real time virtual
models of operations powered by the
data foundation, ERP System Delivery.
This allows company to simulate
and optimize operations before
making decision in the real world.
ERP systems will increase.
Will increasingly annual routine
decisions automatically like inventory
replenishment your supply selection,
your production scheduling which
will free human experts to focus on
strategy and more on the innovation
side of things with edge computing.
ERP.
Connected systems will process and execute
decisions at the point of action while
staying synchronized with the core ERP
enabling instant distributed intelligence.
The evolution of ERP into an AI platform
backbone is not a distant intuition.
It's happening now.
Organizations that embrace the
shift will lead in resilience,
inefficiency, and innovation.
The, probably the question for all
of us is are we ready to make ERP
the foundation of our AI future?
Alright, so let's look at
implementation strategies.
So we, we've seen the vision
of ERP as an AI launch pack.
But how do we actually get there?
This transformation requires
disciplined strategic approach,
and that's where the implement
implementation strategies come in.
Implementing an AI Ready ERP platform
isn't just a technology project, it's a,
it is a business transformation success
depends on aligning data architecture
people, and the business value.
Everything starts with clean,
consistent consistent and governed data.
Without a trusted data foundation, AI
will fail to deliver accurate insights.
First thing, first, establish data
quality standards, ownership and
governance policy from the outset.
Avoid the trap of trying
to boil the ocean.
Focusing on specific business
domains like planning, logistics, or
maintenance when made modernization
will have the highest impact.
This approach delivers quick
win while bundling and building
momentum for broader transformation.
Balance innovation with stability,
use cutting edge technologies like
microservices and APIs, but ensure they
instantly and and seamlessly integrate
with proven enterprise grade systems.
Last technology won't succeed.
Without people invest in skill
development have a stakeholder
buy-in and be ready for the cultural
readiness for AI enabled operations.
And finally deliver tangible
business value early and of and often
identify use cases that generate
measurable return on investments.
This builds the, this builds the executive
support and funds further innovation.
Let's move to the next slide.
Alright.
Now that we have covered
implementation strategies,
let's look at the architectural
foundation that makes modern ERP.
Truly adaptive composable architecture
with the API first design.
This is the shift from rigid
monolithic ERP system to flexible,
more modular platform that can
evolve as business need changes in
today's dynamic environment business.
Requirements change now very rapidly.
Traditional ERP upgrades can keep up.
They're too slow, they're too expensive,
too costly, and too disruptive.
A composable architecture enables
companies to build, to evolve
and integrate capabilities on
demand without being constrained
by a single inflexible system.
The core principle of the composable
ERPR, the modular component,
the microservices, a PF first
design, even driven architecture.
We, which we briefly discussed about this
architecture turns into leaving evolving
system one that can integrate with future
innovations without major overalls.
And it's the backbone for AI
ready intelligent supply chains.
Let's go to the next slide.
Alright.
As we embrace AI driven ERP platforms,
there's another critical dimension we
cannot overlook which is the security,
the governance, and the compliance.
AI brings immense power, but it
also introduces new risks that,
that demand robust strategies with.
AI embedded into ERP.
We are not just processing business
transactions, we are making
autonomous decisions, managing
very sensitive data and relying
on the machine learning models.
This raises the stakes for.
Trust, accountability and resilience.
And the key focus area here
is the data governance.
We must ensure data lineage,
quality and transparency.
This includes managing training.
For training data for AI models,
detecting bias and making algorithms
explainable to stakeholders.
Model, the lifecycle management
AI models can't be set and forget.
We need to, we need structured
processes for worsening, for performance
monitoring and automated retraining.
To keep models accurate and reliable.
Then there is, privacy production.
Protecting personal and sensitive
data is, is absolutely non-negotiable.
Techniques like differential privacy and
federated learning allow us to preserve
privacy while leveraging AI at scale.
Last but not the least is the AI security.
We must defend against advers
attacks data poisoning, model
extraction attempt, et cetera.
Without robust security, even the
most advanced AI can be compromised.
And building strong security
governance and compliance framework
ensures that AI enabled ERP systems
are not only innovative, but
also trustworthy and resilient.
This is how we create platform.
That businesses and
regulators can rely on.
Let's move to the next slide.
Alright, so we discussed the technology,
architecture, and the governance.
But here's the truth.
Technology alone doesn't
transform business.
People and processes do, so to
fully leverage AI enabled ERP
platforms, we must prepare the
organization itself for change.
AI enabled ERP is not just a new
system, it's a new way of operating.
Success requires rethinking
processes, upskilling of
teams, and evolving leadership.
To thrive in this environment
we must strategically redefine
workflows, integrating human
expertise with intelligent automation.
And this is not.
About replacing people.
It's about enhancing collaboration
between humans and AI driven systems.
That's about the process
redesign the skills development.
Essentially building the
right technical and business
competencies is very essential.
Team needs to understand data.
AI and process automation to
fully harness this new capability.
Then there's the leadership evolution
where leaders play a pivotal role.
They must adapt to overseeing hybrid
teams, balancing automated decision
making with human judgment and fostering
a culture of innovation and adaptability.
The organizational readiness is.
Not a one-time checklist.
It's an ongoing commitment to change.
Companies that embrace this
mindset will lead no while those
who resist risk falling behind.
That's a very simple fact
about organizational read.
With technology, governance and
people all aligned enterprises can
truly unlock the power of ERP as the
backbone for AI driven supply chain.
Let's bring this all together
in our final thoughts.
Okay.
Going to the next slide.
So we explore the technology, the
architecture, the governance and
the people side of transformation.
Now let's bring it all
together with the big picture.
ERP modernization isn't just a IT
project, it's a strategic imperative.
The world we operate in is increasingly
complex, very fast moving, unpredictable.
Traditionally, ERP
systems ti cannot keep up.
They were built for stability
but not for adaptability.
Modern ERP infused with AI becomes
the foundation of intelligent,
responsive, and adaptive enterprise.
Organizations that embrace this
transformation will gain sustainable
advantage that go beyond cost saving.
They'll be able to anticipate customer
needs rather than just re react to them.
Optimize resources across the value.
Respond proactively to market
shifts and disruptions.
The urgency of action is very important.
The window to establish leadership
in this transformation is narrow.
Those who act decisively now
will create advantage that
competitors will struggle to match.
Those who do delay risk being left
behind in a marketplace that rewards
agility, intelligence, and innovation.
The future belongs to the
enterprise that make ERP the
backbone of AI driven operation.
The question isn't if this transformation
is coming, it's whether you will lead.
The transformation or be forced
to catch up, now is the time to
modernize, innovate, and take the lead.
So with that.
Thank you for your time
and engagement today.
I appreciate the opportunity to share
insights on how modern ERP can serve as a
backbone for AI three one supply chains.
We have covered a lot of ground
from the challenges of legacy ERP to
platform engineering, to integration
excellence, AI powered applications,
governance and organizational
readiness required to succeed.
The key takeaway is clear.
ERP modernization isn't optional.
It's the, it's a foundation of
competitive advantage in the ai.
I'd be happy to continue this
conversation, explore your specific
challenges or discuss practical steps to
accelerate your EIP MODERNATION journey.
As you go back to your organizations,
I encourage you to ask are we ready
to make the platform that drive
intelligence across our enterprise?
Those act now will define the
future for their industries.
Thank you once again.
It's been pleasure speaking with you and
I look forward to the exciting future.
We can build together.
Thank you.