Good morning, and good evening everyone.
Depends on where you're joining from.
Thanks for joining the session.
My name is MuTu Shandra Mohan,
and I have more than 20 years of
experience in data engineering domain.
And today I'm gonna be talking about
building real time graph database
that can be leveraged for both real
time and analytical capabilities.
And I'm gonna be talking about
the architectural patterns that
can be followed and the key design
considerations that need to be accounted
in building the graph database.
I wanted to start with the putting
the question of why we need to
adopt graph database, right?
What is the problem statement
in building a graph database?
The key thing comes from
handling the relationship data.
In today's scenario, the data.
It's very complex.
And getting analytical information out
of it getting information out of the data
is crucial and especially in handling
complex data patterns like social network
data handling supply chain information
and how to identify fraud from a given
data set and building knowledge graph
from a given data data set that can.
Provide information out of the data is
very complex mainly because of the la
last volume of data, large volume of data
that that we handle on a on a daily basis.
The, that, that brings in the
need for graph database in a
traditional relationship database.
Identifying this complex multi
hop analysis is very difficult and
considering scalability is even more
challenging and that is one of the main
reasons that we adopt graph database.
We will get into more details
as we go through the session.
So as I move along.
When we decide to build a graph
database, what are the challenges?
We as as a platform engineers now
either in the data engineers or in the
platform engineers, what are the common
challenges that we face on a database?
Or in, in building the
lifecycle of the database.
I wanted to cover these three
bullet points that's listed here.
One is when we build the graph
database that we are going to use
it for real time analysis, right?
The often the expectation is
to handle customer calls that
can be addressed in subsecond.
The query response times this is this
is a very a common case when it comes to
fraud and cybersecurity use cases that the
response times need to be fairly quick.
And how do we adopt seamless
integration with the different.
Different applications or systems, for
example, it can be a microservices,
API based systems, or it can be a batch
oriented data integration platform.
Or it can be even with any
of the packaged applications.
So how do we integrate with different
applications and systems that can bring in
heterogeneous data to the graph database?
How do we integrate it?
And then the third thing is how do
we address the scalability concerns?
We can do vertical scalability, but
that has a limitation at some point.
So one of the one of the more,
most common adopted architecture
is the horizontal scalability.
So that it, there is no limitation in
terms of the amount of scale that we can.
We can grow into, right?
So how do we how do we adopt horizontal
scalability for an ever-growing
demand on the data side, and
especially with graph database, right?
So how do we handle
these three challenges?
Is what we are going
to be discussing about.
And these are some of the key
challenges that comes into when we
start implementing graph databases.
And  and there are very few technologies
that kind of  stands out to handle.
These critical, important challenges
when it comes to graph database.
Moving on what are the limitations
of the traditional approaches.
Or in other words like the current
databases that are available.
And when we look at the current database,
I think one of the key thing that
comes out is the relational database.
So what are the challenges
in a relational database?
For a use case that we adopt
with graph database often comes
with a lot of interconnected
relationship among the data.
The key thing is how do we build
build a system that can inherently
provide the ability to for the users
to analyze the data and provide
the information out of it, right?
So that is where the relational database
kind of struggles in terms of building
the relationship within the data.
When we say relationship at a high level,
yes, there is a relational database
that provides one-to-one or one to many
relationship, but what we are talking
about is complex relationship with
that are that are not direct, right?
So that is where the
relational database struggle.
And it is more often realized when
it comes to running the queries to
understand the relationship, right?
For example, one of the use cases like
who is a friend of friend or find all the
friend of friend who share at least three
interest with a particular user, right?
This doesn't come with a
direct  query analysis.
On a relational database when
you want to address this problem,
that's where the second point comes.
It's an exponential com complexity
because often we don't know how many
levels of analysis that we wanted
to perform and how many joints
that we wanted to perform, right?
So in most of the cases in relational
database, this often comes at a point
of making an assumption that how many
levels that you wanted to perform.
That's where the limitation of the
relational database comes into play,
where graph database scores out.
And that multi hop analysis in a end
number of hops that we wanted to perform
graph databases handled so easily.
And the way how it graph database,
addresses this problem is that the
way it stores the data the the graph
database stores the relationship as
a first class citizen rather than
as a data as a property, right?
So relationship is being stored.
And that's how the data is being is
being sorted or stored so that the
traversal queries can be handled
so easily and any sort of indirect
relationships and multi hopp analysis
that, that needs traversal based on
the dynamic results that are fetched
at the previous step can be achieved
using the graph database solution.
And that's how it differentiates itself
from any of the relational database or
document database or any sort of search
database and graph stands out separately.
Moving on what is the core
architectural pattern?
So we are gonna be talking about
different things, but the first
one that I wanted to talk about
is an event driven architecture.
I picked up the event driven architecture
because this is one of the in, this
is a common use case that comes
to different graph implementations
because often the times the graph
implementation, the expectation is that.
How do I handle fraud use cases
and it comes to financial or even
sometimes non-financial institutions
how do I address the fraud and
cybersecurity use cases, which
requires faster response time, right?
And that is where the event driven
architectural comes in when we talk
about event driven architecture.
It often the handles the ability
of implementing or integrating
with an event event based system,
something like Apache, Kafka or any
of the streaming platforms, right?
There are good amount of graph
database that inherently supports.
Integrations with even based systems.
They have connectors with Apache Kafka
or any of the other streaming systems.
And and any sort of even driven
updates that comes from from these
systems can be handled using a
distributed database that kind of.
Routes the calls to a specific partition
within the database that that is driven
based on the relationship that is that is
identified while building the data model.
So it's a hand in hand process that
you identify how you are going to model
your data and that gets a specific.
Storage unit, which is
partitions in a graph database.
And that can be easily retrieved
at the time of handling real time
updates that any sort of event driven
architecture that feeds data in a
real time manner can get easily routed
to the specific graph partitions.
And what it brings us brings the
capability is that it can handle
it, it can it can handle if there
are any outages, it can replay the
data from the streaming platform.
We can quickly replay from
where where we left over.
And multiple consumers can consume from
the same event for different purposes.
Even in terms of a graph database, you
can have a different graph instances that
handle different customer expectations.
That can be one for fraud related use
cases, and that can be one for marketing.
Use case.
Both can be fetching the data
from the same Kafka instance
or the streaming platforms.
So that is one key
consideration to look look into.
Because at the time of defining
your data model you also want to
consideration what sort of systems
that you wanted to integrate with.
And what sort of given driven
architecture that you wanted to adapt to?
There can be instances
where we don't need it.
It can be a pure batch processing systems.
But often it's the case that that
you wanted to have even driven
realtime architecture and and event
driven architecture is a very fairly.
Robust system compared to
other API based integrations.
It depends on the situation, but
even driven architecture is a
much more reliable architectural
pattern that can be looked up to.
Moving on.
What are the different horizontal
scaling strategies that we can adopt?
So we talked about the
the growing needs of data.
When it comes from different sources,
like it can be an iot system or it,
it can be from a these days there
are large volume applications that
generates data in a real time manner.
So how do we handle.
Data that's coming from these systems.
How do we make sure that
we handle them correctly?
So one of the key thing is handling it
through horizontal scaling so that you are
not hitting a limitation at some point.
And horizontal scaling handling
it through distributed systems
is the, is the way to go forward.
And within horizontal scaling
approach what are the different
strategies that you can use?
One is a graph partitioning.
Where the graph database, as we know
is defined from how it has been defined
in the mathematical, the statistical
models vertex and edge based and
how they are connected by each other
and how they comprehend each other.
When it comes to graph partitioning.
This is also at the time of graph data
model modeling and that you define
how you want, what is the key thing
behind your your data partition, right?
Whether it is driven through
vertex partitioning, or it
is through each parting.
It is largely driven by
your your query pattern.
How you are going to be doing it is not
in terms of your data characteristics.
It is going to be how you are going
to be consuming your data from your
querying patterns going to look like.
So depends on that.
You might want to choose between
a vertex based partitioning
or edge based partitioning.
There are different graph
database that supports it.
There are.
Some databases that doesn't support it.
So this is one of the key consideration
when you wanted to adopt a graph database
to see which partition, which type
of graph database that you wanted to
choose, and whether that can support
a ver, a vertex cut partitioning
or a h cut partitioning, right?
That is one.
And the second thing is what kind
of replication strategy, right?
Often when we talk about
distributed databases, there are
different it follows the cap, the.
There are different replication
methodologies that are being adopted.
One is full consistency.
There is there is the other one that's
the eventual consistency model, right?
The eventual consistency model
is that you write to a quorum and
then you read it from a quorum.
So that way you are fairly confident
that you are reading the latest data.
So that is eventually consistent model
is one strongly recommended approach
when it comes to graph database because
it's not gonna be a system of source
it's just a system of reference.
So eventual model is fairly reasonable
to go with and a master slave
replication where you write it down
to one and then you read it from
the replicas, that's another one.
And there are things like consensus
protocol, which is a different.
Approach of eventual, but
it follows a raft protocol.
That's another replication strategy.
So all these are some of the key
aspects to look into when you are
looking for horizontal scaling.
Graph database that support horizontal
scalability and which is essentially one
of the key characteristics of distributed.
Computing or distributed data storage.
I have put it into two different groups.
One is like how you are
going to store your data.
That's your graph partitioning part,
and then what kind of replication
strategy that you wanted to adopt to.
That's more from a computing and
data data storage eventually.
And, 1, 1, 1 key thing to look
into is like graph is again
it's not a stateless system.
It is a, it's a stateful system.
So you wanted to consider about
the storage what kind of storage
that you wanted to, so that your
travels again is fairly easy, right?
So that, that's something to look into.
But.
Distributed database is
the way to go forward.
That's what we wanted
to cover on this one.
The next one is we talked about
this the kind of storage that
we wanted to adopt into, right?
So you decided that you wanted to go
for a distributed database, but if you
are not sure about what kind of, storage
that you wanted to adopt into this is
where your next design aspect or the
architectural aspect comes into play.
What is going to be your use case
that you are going to handle?
Is your use case going to be like
a sub subsecond or a sub Yeah.
Subsecond queries that you
wanted to address in a fraud
or cybersecurity use case.
Or is it is it gonna be a system that
heavily relies on how you are going
to store the data but may not be
needing a sub-second response time?
There, there are use cases like that
often times that you look at to a data
store where you are okay to wait for two,
three seconds or even up to 10 seconds.
But you wanted to be more towards
storing the data in a persistent manner
that you are able to rely upon the
data and faster recovery time, right?
So if you have a use case like
that, and then there are specialized
storages, like document stores or key
value paths columnar databases, right?
Those are again a flavor of
your distributed databases.
May not be truly graph, but it probably
doesn't need a high amount of data.
So you can fairly run better
than a relational database.
That's another specialized storage
that you can look up to, right?
So these are the different flavors in
which you can adopt to a hybrid storage.
Like things like in memory when you
are looking for subsecond, then you
can go for Redis graph or Apache graph.
As as an option.
And when it comes to persistent storage,
like Neo four J Amazon, Neptune,
that's another thing to look at.
And there are specialist storage.
There are tons of things.
And in the market oftentimes
when you have a NoSQL database
it comes with a graph database.
There are cases that
we, we often look up to.
Using the same NoSQL storage with
a graph layer on top of it because
you don't have to adopt multiple
technologies to, to support your use case.
So that's another area to look into and
query query optimization techniques.
This is like post your graph database.
You have adopted a graph database
and then you have you have fed
in a good amount of data into it.
Like how do you.
Optimize your query, right?
So this is where you you put the hat
of a developer and then see what is the
best way in which I can I can define
my query or design my query, right?
So you can look at the option of early
termination that is once you reach a part.
A query result point, then you
don't have to continue the query.
That's an advantage with
the graph database that you
can terminate the query as.
And when you you have reached
the result point, right?
And then there are bidirectional search.
What I mean is that you can
start from multiple points
depends on the query criteria.
And this is where a graph database plays
a critical role that if you wanted to
start with a country, and if you start
with a particular age group, right?
So you can have these two search points
and you convene towards or converge
towards a singular result site, right?
So you can start from bidirectional point.
So that way your query
run times would be faster.
And this is this is something
different from our relate
traditional databases, right?
And and then there is cost base
optimization that you can do.
What it means is that you can find
out what is the degree distribution
for that means when you are on a
particular vertex, you can see how many.
It just are connected to it, right?
So that way you know what is the
criticality of that particular vertex,
and you can do cost-based optimization.
If there are high degree,
then probably you don't want
to run your query from there.
You wanted to start from a much lower.
Vertex, so that way
your results are faster.
So that is one way of cost based
optimization that you can adopt in
with the query optimization technique.
So these are some of the trivial ones,
but can yield the high results when
it comes to query optimization and
then memory management strategies.
This is go hand in hand with
your query optimization.
You can adopt things like
your vertex edge pooling.
So basically you can fragment your memory
and see what graph elements that you
wanted to store in memory, so that way
your garbage collection, GC collection.
Often times that you you will find
these databases use Java heavily,
so the garbage collection, once you
address garbage collection, your
query response times are faster.
So that is the main intention behind it.
And then compress direct
presentations, each graph database
will have its own compression logic.
One of the key thing to look after
is something like CSR which kind of
uses a bit backed adjacent list that,
that helps in compressing the data.
And that kind of helps in
getting the runtime faster.
And then you have the hot cold
separation that this kind of goes in
relation with your monitoring your
database that you identify, what are
the key vertexes or key partitions
that, that are hot and cold which
are like often used versus less used.
You can separate or not separate.
Identify them and try to split
the hard partitions into multiple
different chunks of give more compute
power and more storage so that
the queries can run faster, right?
So these are different areas that
you can look into from a memory
management sta standpoint that
can help lead higher results.
And moving on the integrations pattern.
So this is where we started with when
you want to implement graph database
you wanted to implement in an area
and fashion that's one of the more
often use cases that we have seen.
But it is not limited to that, right?
But even within a near real time
there are multiple different
methodologies that we can opt into.
One of the key thing is the change
data capture which is the logs that are
retrieved from a traditional databases.
Or you can have a custom connector that
kind of reads from a traditional database
and then start pumping in data using a
streaming platform in the form of a CDC.
So you can have data integration.
Pipelines that you can connect to graph
databases or even connectors that are
available using streaming platforms that
you can use as an integration pattern.
This is one of the most common
thing that that often that we
see with graph implementations.
And the second thing is
the graph QL integration.
So this is where you see graph as a
database kind of retrieve the results.
Identify the relationship.
So often we get the question
that you have a graph database,
and why do you need a graph ql?
So this is where we see the heavy
lifting is done by the graph.
That means identifying the unknown
relationship, multi hop analysis scanning
through a large volume of data and
bringing those information out of it.
Is done through graph database, but
then you often need to integrate
through a schematic layer, right?
And where we expose the data to Y
end consumers in the form of a UI
or any other integrations, right?
That is where Graph QL comes into play.
That if you wanted to if you
wanted to match the data between
a customer platform with.
With the cybersecurity or a fraud analysis
data, that is where graph brings these
two data together, stitch them together
in the form of a schematic layer and
present it in the graph QL integration.
So that is another integration
pattern to look into.
It depends again on the use case how
you are going to consume the data.
And then and very own use case
that is the analytical integration
that integrates with warehouses
or from big data platforms.
That often we go with Apache
Spark connectors that kind of
does the heavy lifting with
large data of large data volume.
And you can have connectors like press two
or Tryo if you wanted to run SQL queries.
Because these connectors provide a
schematic layer and you can run and you
can some of these graph database provides.
The ability to run a direct SQL queries
that you translate under the hood to,
to convert them into graph queries.
Moving on monitoring and observability.
This is monitoring and observability
is standard across different
systems, but what is the thing to
look after in the graph database?
The key things to look after is the
query complexity metrics, right?
So you have tons of queries that
that, that are being run, right?
But often you wanted to see what
are the queries that perform bad?
And what is the traversal path
that these queries are taking?
And what are the queries that
often use high memory, right?
How do we how do we improvise them?
So this is the bottleneck
identification layer.
Whether it some of the strategies
that we looked at, whether it needs
partitioning, whether it is a hot, cold
part hot cold partition that, that needs
to be addressed or whether it can be
handled through some compression logic.
Identifying this complexity
metrics is one thing to look after.
And the heat maps again, the
heart VAEs and heart edges.
Often that if you have a customer base
and that is very kind of centric towards
a particular region those are things to
look after from this heat maps, right?
And distributed tracing.
This is a fine grain analysis to
find out when you have a query that
probably doesn't perform good, you
break it down into individual layers.
There are you can achieve it using
any of the logging platforms and
often it is it can be done through
the native graph logs itself.
You can break down the different
layers of the query to find out
which layer is performing back or
or needs to be improvised so you
can get the idea what can be done.
The next bullet points we cover about,
providing a custom dashboard that kind of
captures these these use cases, but what
different metrics that need to be adopted.
Things like cluster coefficient
trends, degree distribution changes,
and component size distribution.
The, so these are some of the metrics
that, that, that needs to be looked into.
And yeah.
Moving on.
So you have a graph
database up and running.
How are we going to back
up and recover the data?
Because you have customers who
rely upon this data, so you need
to have a reliability score on it.
So how do we do backup and recovery?
So one of the most common things
that people recommend is to go
for a full graph backup because.
What that means is that you don't want
to do an incremental backup because
this is not a traditional database that
you get the logs the incremental logs
out of it, and then and then store it.
Because these are all
interconnected graph data.
So often we try to use, to the extent
possible, we try to adopt full graph
backup that is the most reliable one.
But when you when you start implementing
real time solutions that those are
not often directly possible so there
are even sourced incremental backups
that are available that are largely
supported by all these databases.
You just.
Take the running event logs and you
are able to build the snapshots out
of this and that's the next level of
reliable backups that you can get.
But it, there are some trade
offs that need to be looked at.
What is the RTO and what is
RT objective for the for this
particular strategy that you wanted
to set as in business expectation?
Finally there are some advanced techniques
that are that are being used in some
cases which are like multi version
concurrency control that basically.
Takes backup in a real time
manner without blocking, right?
But again, these are things that are
new in the market and that needs that's
being explored in different use cases.
When it comes to some of the
critical use cases, I think those
are still in the experimentation
stage as I would like to point.
Yeah, so this is capacity planning.
So you are ready to
build a graph database.
What are the key things to look up
to when it comes to capacity planning
as a, as UD the architect hat.
What are the out of the box
strategies that are available when
you wanted to do capacity planning?
There are some proven methodologies and
proven tools or accelerators available.
For example, the synthetic
graph generator, that is
a tool that you can use.
So you feed in some of
the informations about.
What, how many tis, how many edges
that you wanted to build, and what is
the data size that you are expecting?
You feed in that information and
it gives you approximate figure
of what you should be looking at.
So that is a great tool to start with.
And one of the most reliable
thing that I would say is the
comprehensive load testing.
That is to actually start a POC.
But you run different scenarios
that, that, like things like
the burst scenarios, right?
You a COOs testing, right?
You test it and find out, because
often with graph database the data is
unpredictable because you often find new.
Patterns of data, because that's the thing
that the graph database, that is, that
you find out different pattern patterns
of data that's something unknown to you.
So the load testing is a great way
in, in my view, but it takes maturity
time and then memory modeling.
This is similar to load testing,
but you you try to build a complex
scenario that you try to query at
least one percentage of your graph
that has a large set of edges and s
that are being connected to, and you
try to query at least one percentage
of the graph data from that, right?
So that is basically you try to
put your system under stress.
And find out how your system performs.
So you are basically planned
for the worst in that case.
This is true when you wanted to
use for your analytical use cases
this memory modeling stresses.
So that, that's from a capacity planning.
Certainly the tools is
the good starting point.
And once you are into some level of
maturity from the implementation,
then you can go for the load
testing or the stress testing.
So the, then that comes the
architectural trade off, right?
So what do you want, how do you want your
system to look like, from a consistency
versus performance standpoint, right?
So often, like we, we talked about
horizontal and distributed systems, right?
How do you want your system to be?
Like, whether you wanted a full
consistency or eventual consistency,
or you wanted handle the performance
as the major thing, right?
So this is where you will have to find
out what is the targets target users
that you wanted to address whether or
use case also that you wanted to address,
whether you wanted to handle the.
A real time use case or you wanted
to handle an analytical use case, so
that kind of drives the cap there.
Whether you wanted to put
consistency first or you wanted
to handle performance first.
So that that, that's
one thing to look after.
So that, that is purely based on what
user base that you wanted to handle.
So oftentimes that I would like to
point out is that even though you have
the same set of data, you might want to
consider multiple graph instances because
your target audience could vary, right?
And that is where it is.
And then flexibility.
This is more in terms of choosing your
graph database, whether you wanted to go
for a typed or a property graph, or it
is an adaptive indexing graph database.
So the way this is different in the
way that the graph stores the data
whether it is like a vertex and edge
based schema, which is a type graph.
And then whether you wanted to handle
the property graph, which is more towards
knowledge, graph building, or whether you
wanted to do an adaptive indexing that you
build an index, run the query, and then
the indexes gets dropped at the end of it.
So it, it's more in terms of
choosing what type of draft database
that you wanted to choose, right?
So these are things to to address at
the time of choosing the database.
At the time of implementing a
particular graph use case, and at the
time of finding out which target user
that you wanted to address, right?
So those are the key things that
will drive this particular strategy.
So we talked about graph database
that, that's being used across and how.
What is the current state
that that it is right now?
What are the future
directions for graph database?
So it, it has its own limitations.
Things that, that needs to be looked
up is that graph often requires
high computing because of the way
it handles com complex queries.
So there are there are work that,
that are being adopted to see how to
improve the hardware acceleration,
to implement things like GPU and
handling graph algorithms natively.
So those are things that are
being in, in, in work right now.
And the machine learning I would say
it is, it has already been into a good.
State right now, because often the
graph has worked along with machine
learning integration, but it is being
expanded largely that both graph
and machine learning comprehend each
other to build complex use cases.
And even in, in some cases, I have
seen AI based implementation users.
Graph to a watched extent, right?
So that that's a major work area
that's currently in in progress.
And then serverless graph databases
are, excuse me like cases where there
are a lot of graph providers that they
provide their offerings in, in the cloud.
There, you don't have to worry
about the hardware behind it.
And that's coming as
a serverless offering.
So that's also another growing area that
I wanted to quickly touch upon where
graph is heading towards graph databases.
Yeah.
At last I wanted to give a quick.
Overview what are the different
areas that we talked about?
Graph being a real time implementation,
near real time implementation that often
follows distributed implementation.
And mainly for addressing the large
amount of data that it handles.
And when it comes to integration, it
indicates with event driven architecture.
To handle use cases on a ML or
fraud or cybersecurity use cases.
And from a storage standpoint we kind of
balance it out between the cost versus
performance the three different scenarios
that we talked about in memory, hybrid
and in memory, hybrid are some of the
key areas that we talked about, and
the persistent storage is another one.
So those are key areas.
I, at the same time too, when
I want to conclude, I wanted to
make sure that, not every case use
case gets implemented with graph.
So we need to be very clear about
what use case that we wanted to
implement and what is the target
audience that we wanted to address.
And the kind of strategy that
we wanted to implement when we
in, when we do data integration.
And so that will eventually
drive us to success.
I hope this session was
very useful and informative.
And I really look forward you in, in,
in any of the future implementations
that, that you implement these strategies
and, I wish you a great day and success.
Thank you.