Hello friends, this is Santos.
I'll be presenting on scaling medical
imaging infrastructure for life
critical healthcare applications.
We describe how advanced flexible
endoscopy uses this architecture.
The agenda platform
architecture, fundamentals.
What is the core infrastructure?
Real time video processing pipelines.
What are the storage?
Arctic architecture design principles.
Then performance engineering
and availability.
What are the scaling strategies,
optimization techniques,
and how do you recover?
From disaster during a procedure.
What are the data management
and integration tools we use?
How are they connected to the cloud?
What is the security and
compliance we are following?
Then we end with case studies
and future directions.
See when the medical platform fail,
patients are directly impacted.
The momentary system.
Lag in bronchoscopy could mean
missing a critical airway lesion
that could be even cancerous.
A storage failure might result
in lost or lost diagnostic
imagery that cannot be recreated.
So more what are the technical challenges?
So the stream bandwidth, the
single procedure produces massive
amount of uncompressed data sets.
The latency, the end-to-end photon latency
should be less than 200 milliseconds
in best case scenarios, we have systems
with 90 to one 20 millisecond latency.
The uptime is 99.99%.
We have multiple imaging modalities,
RGB, near I fluorescence.
Each have distinct data streams
with unique processing requirements.
Most of the modern endoscopes are at
least HD requiring robust infrastructure.
Core infrastructure, architecture,
compute requirements.
We need clusters with hundreds of
CPU cores and multiple high-end
GPUs for real time processing.
Dedicated resources for video encoding
transcoding Andys enhancement operations,
separate compute pools for real time
versus batch processing workloads.
What is the network architecture?
10 gigabits per second.
Backbone capacity, quality of service
mechanism, prioritizing endoscopic
traffic, multiple edge ingestion points
with automatic fail, fail or capability.
Specialized low latency parts
for real time clinical workflows.
The real time video processing pipeline,
data integration, image enhancement.
Apply advanced image processing
algorithms for noise reduction,
enhancement, color correction, et
cetera, encoding compression H 26 5
to reduce bandwidth while maintaining
quality distribution, multi-protocol
streaming to viewing stations and
adaptive bitrate capabilities.
Tired storage, architecture.
Hot tire, N-V-M-E-R-A active
recent examinations with sub
millisecond access latency.
Warm tire is SSD storage.
Recent procedures up to 30 days.
Cold tire is historical procedures
with adaptive or intelligent
compression algorithms.
For cost effective long-term retention,
horizontal scaling and
performance optimization.
Stateless microservice design,
enabling linear capacity expansion,
Kubernetes based or orchestration
with automatic port scaling based.
Intelligent load balancing, considering
data, locality, and network topology.
Session affinity, ensuring consistent
processing for procedure streams.
Performance optimization.
GPU Acceleration for compute intensive
video processing zero copy buffer
management, minimizing memory transfers.
ADD caching for frequently accessed
content time series databases,
optimized for procedure metrics, high
availability and disaster recovery.
What is the redundancy architecture?
Eliminate single points of failure
through redundant power network.
Automated failover, continuous health
monitoring with sub sub millisecond
detection of component failures.
Geographic resilience, comprehensive
chaos engineering, and regular
failover testing are essential.
Partial failure test, partial
failure modes, network partitions
and cascading failures.
Scenarios under control, conditions
to validate performance, resilience,
data management, analytics,
infrastructure, realtime
ingestion, processing framework
analytics platform BV.
Propose using a Kafka buffering
base, high batch, high bandwidth
video feeds, stream processing for
initial validation and enrichment.
For the processing framework, it
is lamb architecture, combining
stream and batch processing, GPU
acceleration for computationally
intensive tasks analytics platform.
It's self-service analytics
for quality improvement.
Feature stores for consistent
model training, security and
compliance framework, HIPAA
compliance, a S 2 56 encryption.
For data addressed hardware security
modules, role based attribute control
systems, tamper proof audit, logging
with cryptographic signatures, data
privacy protection, end to end encryption
from capture through Archer, through
archive hierarchical key management
with perfect forward secrecy.
Data classification.
Classification, driving
automated protection policies,
access control systems.
Context aware authorization, multifactor
authentication with single sign-on
integration, behavioral intering,
suspicious access patterns, healthcare
system integration, single sign on.
Federated architecture as reference
pointers, PACS connectivity, DICOM
interfaces converting video to
multi frame objects, intelligent
routing, balancing immediate
availability with source storage.
DICOM web WA interface for restful access.
XT XTS frameworks enabling
cross enterprise sharing.
Cloud and hybrid deployment strategies.
Cloud native architecture kubernetes
authorization, enabling sophisticated
deployment patterns, hybrid
implementation, edge computing within
the hospital networks for latency
sensor operations, multi-cloud
resilience, abstraction layers, enabling
portable deployment across providers.
Case study, academic medical
center implementation.
The, we had a deployment profile of 1200
bed academic medical center performing
50,000 endoscopic procedures requirements,
99.99% uptime, subsecond latency, a
Kubernetes ization enabling dynamic
scaling during peak procedure times.
The key results were reduced latency to
under 200 milliseconds while providing
virtually unlimited storage EMR
integration with federated architecture,
preserving video quality, successful
handling of 200 plus concurrent
procedures during peak time, about
40% reduction in op operational cost
through performance optimization.
Future directions, AI and ML integration,
edge computing advanced imaging for
high definition, ultra high definition
eight K 3D reconstruction from
endoscopic video enabled enhanced
visualization navigation assistance.
Thank you.