I am Alexander Kolubov, and today
I am going to talk on high load
systems and the challenges they bring.
My presentation will be based on my
extensive experience in social network
development and product management.
If you are interested, fasten
the seatbelts and join the ride.
First, let me introduce myself and
share some light on my experience.
I worked as a team lead at one
of the biggest social networks,
where I led teams up to 10 members,
including sales specialists, and
analysts, and project managers.
As a developer, I designed, developed,
and maintained various features for the
desktop and mobile web versions of a
social network across backend, frontend,
I have redesigned the social network
interface for multiple user sections,
completely rewrote network widgets
for external sites, maintained privacy
settings for closed profiles and content
archiving function, overhauled the backend
and frontend for the mail notification
system, handling millions of emails daily.
And finally, I have created a system
for conducting NPS and CSI surveys
that covered the two largest Russian
social networks and some of their users.
Today, I want to touch upon the
following aspects of the topic.
We'll briefly discuss how to define
if the system is high load or not.
Then we'll talk about the way high
loads change the system requirements.
And based on my expertise, I'll highlight
what approaches and technologies can
help overcome high load challenges.
Let's begin with definition.
What system can we call high load?
A system is considered high load
if it meets several criteria.
First of all, high request volume.
The system must hold
millions of requests daily.
Second is a large user base.
Support millions of concurrent users.
Next is extensive data management.
Manage terabytes or
even petabytes of data.
Performance and scalability maintains
responsiveness under increasing loads.
Complex operations performs resource
intensive calculations or data processing.
High reliability requires 99.
9 percent or higher time.
Geographical distribution
serves users across multiple
locations with low latency.
Concrete processing handles
numerous concurrent operations
and finally load balancing.
Distributes traffic effectively
to avoid bottlenecks.
Basically, this is what we
already can call High Load.
One more thing I want to mention is
that if I were to give a one sentence
definition of what High Load system is,
I would say that High Load is it when
usual methods for processing requests,
storing data, and managing infrastructure
are no longer enough, and there is
a need to create custom solutions.
Let's take a look at VK
social network loads.
Here is what the system had to
process already a couple of years ago.
100 million users per month.
100 million posts and content creations
per day, and 9 billion post views per day.
The numbers you've seen on the
previous slide results in these
performance metrics, so we can
definitely call VK loads are high.
Now that we have defined that our system
is high load, we can take a step further
and take a look at the difficulties
the management of such systems entails.
First of all, it's performance over
maintaining fast response times and
processing under high load conditions.
Besides, we need to store, retrieve and
process large volumes of data effectively.
Then we'll have to provide that
scalability is possible at any stage.
Ensuring the system remains
operational and available despite
high traffic and potential failures.
And definitely we need to build
systems that can recover from failures
and continue to operate smoothly.
Apart from challenges, high load
systems bring certain risks, and
that is why we have to question
some of the traditional tools.
The main issue with external solutions
is that they are not highly specialized.
Instead, they are designed for broad
market applicability, and it often
comes at the expense of performance.
There is also an issue with security.
On one hand, external solutions are
usually well tested due to their
large user base, But on the other
hand, fixing identified issues
quickly and precisely is challenging.
Moreover, updating to a fixed version
might lead to compatibility problems.
External solutions also require
ongoing tweaking and fixing, which
is very difficult, unless you're
a committer of that solution.
And finally, they may
not scale effectively.
Naturally, with the growing loads,
reliability, data management,
scaling requirements are increasing.
For example, in the past, downtime
for maintenance was acceptable.
Users had lower expectations
and fewer alternatives.
Today, with the vast availability
of online services and the high
competition among them, even short
periods of downtime can lead to
significant user dissatisfaction and
negatively affect net promoter score.
Quick recovery used to mean a
service was never considered down.
Today, according to the five
nines standard, it's mean 99.
999 percent uptime, which is often
referenced in the tech industry,
only about five minutes of downtime
per year are considered acceptable.
Also users previously kept
backups, but now cloud services
must ensure zero data loss.
While systems were once planned in
advance, there is now a need for them
to scale linearly at any moment due
to possible explosive audience growth.
And convenience and time to market.
In a competitive environment,
it's essential to launch
features quickly and efficiently.
Further on, we'll discuss some possible
ways on how to overcome these challenges
and meet the highly lowered requirements.
Here you can see how VK social
network grew and gradually transformed
its architecture and adapted or
created technologies that suited
the scale and new requirements.
Here is what happened.
As long as platform growth
attracted a large audience,
numerous bottlenecks appeared and
optimizations became a necessity.
Databases could no longer keep up, project
code base became too large and too slow.
The volume of user generated content
also increased, creating new bottlenecks.
In normal sized projects, traditional
databases like MySQL and PostgreSQL,
etc., can meet all your needs.
However, in high load projects,
each need often requires a
separate data storage solution.
As the load increased, it became
crucial to switch to custom, highly
specialized databases with data stored
in simple, fast, low level structures.
In 2009, when relational databases
couldn't be effectively, couldn't
effectively handle the growing
load, the team started developing
their own data storage engines.
This engine functions as microservices
with embedded databases written in C
or C Currently, there are about 800
engine clusters, each responsible
for its own logic, such as messages,
recommendations, photos, hints,
letters, lists, logs, news, etc.
For each task needing a specific
data structure or unusual queries,
the FC team creates a new engine.
The custom engines proved
to be much more efficient.
Engines use simple data
structures, as I said.
In some cases, they store data
as nearly bare indexes leading to
minimal structuring and processing
and at the reading stage.
This approach increased data
access and processing speed.
We also get more efficient
data replication and sharding.
Reliance on master slave replication
and strict data level sharding enables
horizontal scaling without any issues.
Also, all data is heavily cached.
often pre computed and in advance.
Caches are sharded with custom
wrappers for automatic keys
count calculation on code level.
In large systems like ours, caching moves
from merely improving performance as main
goal to reducing load on the backend.
The next challenge was optimizing
the application code itself.
It was written in PHP and became too slow,
but changing the language was impossible.
The with millions of lines
of code in the project.
So the goal of QPHP compiler is
to transform PHP code into C This
approach boosts performance without
the extensive problems associated
with rewriting the entire code base.
The team started improving the
system from bottlenecks and
for them it was the language.
Not the code itself.
Finally, in real production environments,
KPHP proved to be from seven to
10 times faster than the standard.
Just simple PHP.
KPHP was adopted as a backend of VK.
By now it's supports PHP 7 and
8 features, making it compatible
with modern PHP standards.
KPHP allows fast compilation and
efficient development cycles.
It enforces strict typing to reduce
bugs and improve code quality, and uses
shared memory for efficient management.
The system supports parallelization
and coroutines so multiple
processes can run simultaneously,
and optimizes code flow in line.
It enhances performance on systems
with non uniform memory access.
Then, with the NullVerify linter, the team
enhanced code quality and reliability.
NullVerify is designed for large
codebases and focuses on analyzing
git divs before they are pushed.
It indexes around 1 million lines
of code per second and analyzes
about 100, 000 lines per second.
Besides, it can run on
standard PHP projects.
Application was also partly transitioned
to a microservices architecture
to accelerate time to market.
This shift allowed to develop services
in various programming languages.
It also provided.
greater flexibility in
the development process.
By breaking down the system into smaller
independent services, it became possible
to deploy updates more rapidly and ensure
that each component can be optimized
with the most suitable technology.
As I have said, after optimizing database
and code, the team began breaking the
project into optimized microservices,
and the focus shifted to addressing
the most significant bottlenecks
in content, storage, and delivery.
Images emerged as a critical
bottleneck in the social network.
So the problem is that the same image
needs to be displayed in multiple
sizes due to interface issues.
requirements and different
platforms, mobile with retina,
non retina, web, and so on.
Before the resized images
before this, before changes to
the resized images, occupied a
significant amount of storage space.
But now the team eliminated breakout sizes
and instead implemented Dynamic Resetting.
They introduced another microservice
called Image Processor that
generates required sizes on the fly.
Additionally, they transitioned
to serving images in WP format.
This change was very cost effective.
The optimizations led to significant
improvements as highlighted on the slide.
So it's always worth identifying
and optimizing the biggest
bottlenecks for better performance.
While the choice of technologies is
unique for each high load company,
many approaches overlap and demonstrate
effectiveness across the board.
We've discussed some of the VK's
strategies, and it's worth noting
that many of other tech giants
also employ similar approaches
to tackle high load challenges.
For example, Netflix used a
combination of micro services
and distributed architecture
to deliver content efficiently.
They implemented caching
strategies using EV cache.
and have developed their
own data storage solutions.
As one of the Russian's largest tech
companies, Yandex uses a variety
of in house databases and caching
solutions to manage its search engines.
and other services.
I cannot but mention Clickhouse here,
a highly specialized database developed
by Yandex to meet its specific needs.
This solution proved to be so
fast and efficient that it's
now widely used by others.
Yandex created an open source database
management system that stores and process
data by columns rather than rows and
its highly performance query processing
makes it ideal for handling large
volumes of data and real time analytics.
VK also uses.
LinkedIn implements a distributed
storage system called Espresso
for its real time data needs and
leverages caching with Apache Kafka
to manage high throughput messaging.
Tweeter employs a custom built
storage solution called Manhattan
designed to handle large
volumes of tweets and user data.
Same decisions in all companies.
Wrapping up, let's us quickly
revise that we discussed today.
First of all, high load systems are
applications built to support a large
number of users and transactions
at the same time, and they require
excellent performance and reliability.
Second, the challenges of high load
systems includes limits of scalability,
reliability issues, performance
slowdowns, and complicated integrations.
Then we've mentioned that high
load systems have specific
requirements, preventing data loss,
allowing fast feature updates,
and keeping downtime to a minimum.
Next, using external
solutions can become risky.
Under high load, so often there is a
need to go for some custom solution.
Where to begin?
You need to identify the key bottlenecks
and then find a way to approach them.
So this is where the optimizations begin.
Among other technologies, high load
systems usually rely on effective
scalable data storage with good
caching, compiled languages, distributed
architecture, and good tooling.
And still, there are no fixed rules
for creating high load applications.
It's always an experimental process.
Thank you for your time.
If you have any questions on the
topic, I will be glad to answer them.
Feel free to message me in Telegram.
Bye.