Hello everyone and thank you for joining.
Today I will be talking about platform
engineering for data science at scale.
Over the past decade, data
science has evolved dramatically.
What started as individuals
analyzing spreadsheets has now
become enterprise wide AI projects.
These projects need sophisticated
and infrastructure and scalable
computing and reliable deployment pipe.
But here is the challenge.
Many organizations invest heavily
in tools and talent, yet still
struggle to move machine learning from
experiments into real business systems.
That's where platform engineering
plays a critical role.
Slide two.
The problem isn't usually the algorithms
or the data, it's the infrastructure.
Traditional approaches often
create three main issues.
First, fragmented tool genes.
Different team use different tools,
which makes integration very difficult.
Second inconsistent environments.
The classic works on my machine
problem where models fail
once moved into production.
Third, deployment bottlenecks.
Data scientists build models,
but engineering teams struggle
to operationalize them.
Platform engineering solves this by
providing a centralized, scalable, and a
standardized foundation so data scientists
can focus on innovation, not firefighting.
Moving on, let's look closer at the main
challenges environment, inconsistency.
Models behave differently in
development versus in production.
Tool fragmentation.
Too many tools lead to silos
and maintenance, headaches,
resource inefficiency.
Sometimes too much
computing power is wasted.
Sometimes not enough is available.
Fourth, deployment complexity.
Putting a model into production
takes too much manual work.
Fifth, security and compliance
risk Patchwork solutions make
it hard to stay compliant.
These challenges slow down
progress and raise costs.
So how does platform engineering help?
It follows a few key principles.
Obstruction, hide the messy infrastructure
details, so data scientists can
focus on their work self service.
Let teams provision environments and
deploy models without waiting for it.
Standardization, ensure everyone
follows the same patterns and tools.
Observability, monitor model
behaviors, data quality, and
performance at all times.
Scalability, make sure the
system grows and demands grows.
Security by design.
Build security into the platform from
the start, not after the thought.
Most of the most important foundation
is containerization, containerizations.
Make sure models run consistently
across environments, avoid conflicts
and even allow multiple versions
of a model to run at the same time.
Then comes microservices.
Breaking big monolithic systems into
smaller focus services like data
integration, model training or monitoring.
Each can be scaled independently
together with or orchestration
and service mesh technologies.
This makes platforms more
flexible and easier to manage
in cloud environment.
Certain design patterns make
platform reliable and efficient.
12 factor methodology, a framework for
scalable maintainable applications.
Even driven architecture
triggers training or scalable
automatically when new data arrives.
Immutable infrastructure, every change
creates a new version making rollbacks
very safe, circuit breakers and bulk.
Protect against cascading failures
and keep workloads isolated.
Autoscaling expand or shrink resources
based on demand saving costs.
Machine learning pipelines are the most
likely to assemble line of data science.
They like raw data, transform it, train
models, validate them, and deploy results.
A strong pipeline provides
orchestration to manage dependencies
and scheduling data, lineage and
versioning to track every step and
ensure reproducibility fault tolerance
to recover gracefully from failures.
Good pipelines also integrates
smoothly with enterprise
systems and optimized resource.
A data science platform
must serve many groups.
Data scientists need quick
experimentation and easy access to data.
ML engineers, they need reliable
deployment and monitoring tools.
Platform engineers need visibility
into performance, cost, and compliance.
Security team needs strong control
without slowing others down.
Business stakeholders need to see results.
Metrics like performance speed and ROI.
Balancing all of these needs is what
makes a platform truly successful.
Monitoring is the heartbeat of platform
engineering, the monitor infrastructure,
server storage, networking application.
They monitor latency,
throughput, error rates, data.
In that we monitor freshness,
quality schema, compliance models.
What is monitored is
accuracy, drift and anomalies.
With this data, we optimize performance
and set up alerts so issues are
fixed before they impact users.
The future of platforms is exciting.
Edge computing brings model
closers to where data is generated.
Automated ML reduces manual
work in model building.
Federated learning trains models
across different data sources
without moving sensitive data.
Multi-cloud strategies improves
resilience and flexibility.
Sustainability is becoming essential.
Building platforms that are efficient
and environmentally friendly.
Platform engineering changes the game.
It can triple productivity.
Since data scientists are no
longer required to deal with
infrastructure headaches, it can
cut deployment time in half, moving
models faster into production.
It can double the innovation because
teams share knowledge more easily and it
can reduce infrastructure costs by 40%.
Through efficient resources, it's a
real shift from fragmented systems
to a streamlined, scalable platform.
The key benefits, the benefits
are both technical and strategic.
Democratization making advanced
tools available to more people.
Reliability, reducing risk in production.
ML system.
Collaboration, helping teams share models
and insights instead of duplicating
work cost optimization, using resources
more wisely, future ready, being able
to adapt quickly to new technologies.
The implementation roadmap.
So how do we actually build this?
Here is the roadmap.
Assessment.
Identify pain points and a plan.
Foundation, build core components
like containers and orchestration,
platform development, create
workflows and self-service
tools, operational excellence,
add monitoring and optimization.
Continuous evolution keep improving
with feedback and new technology.
To wrap up platform engineering
is more than a technical fix.
It's a strategic investment.
Yes, it takes planning and commitment,
but the payoff is huge, scalable,
reliable, and efficient platforms that
give companies a real competitive edge.
In an AI driven world, the organizations
that embrace this will move faster,
adapt better, and ultimately win.
Thank you for listening.
I would be happy to answer any
other questions that anyone has.