Hello, everyone.
Super happy to join COM32.
This is Lone from
Electrolux Group in Sweden.
Today, my colleague Vladimir and
I are going to share our work in
the field of platform engineering.
Including infrastructure,
orchestration and cost engineering.
So today's talk will be
divided into four parts.
First, I will briefly introduce
the context of the whole work.
Secondly, Vladimir will share more about
infrastructure orchestration with the
help of our internal developer platform.
Then I will talk more about
cost engineering and also
our open source projects.
Let's start from the context.
At Electrolux, there are many
categories of appliances.
In our organization, we mainly
work on the home appliances,
including three categories.
Taste, an oven, for example, care,
a washing machine, and well being,
an air purifier, for example.
These are connected appliances.
Imagine this lady bought our oven,
made it connected to the internet
via our mobile application.
She places some food in it, and
the camera recognizes the food.
And the suggests the cooking
mode, temperature and duration.
Then the lady can interact with
the oven using voice assistant in
the mobile application and the sets
up everything with several clicks.
Finally, the oven cooks the food and keeps
sending updates to the mobile application.
To support this magical experience.
There are many different developer
teams, and from our side, we work as a
platform engineering team, and we want
to empower our developers to focus on
innovation and reduce the complexity.
That's why we build our own
internal developer platform.
Which is the core of our
developer experience.
In this way, we provide nice support
by adding features to the platform
instead of repeating the work.
Our platform today covers different
domains, like infrastructure,
provisioning, service management, etc.
And we keep adding new domains.
One new domain that we added
recently is cloud cost, which I
will share more during this talk.
However, I have to say that
IDP is not the silver bullet to
address all the complex scenarios.
We will share the whole journey
with you in the next 20 minutes.
So let's take a further look at our
techniques deck, which is very diverse.
Many different coding languages
are used by our developer teams.
We also have a set of CICD tools
like CircleCI, Jenkins, AgileCD, etc.
As appliances are connected from
different places all over the world,
we need to run various of services
globally on different cloud providers
like AWS, Azure, and Google Cloud.
However, at the same time,
this diverse tech stack also
brings us extra challenges.
So feel free to leave a comment if your
developers or you have faced or have been
facing some issues from the left column.
For example, too many different
tools, multi cloud setup, etc.
Or drop another comment if you
work as an SRE and are facing some
challenges in the right column, like
too many direct messages, not enough
time for development, and so on.
If you have challenges in both
columns, we feel you very much because
we were in a similar situation.
Now I would love to invite Vladimir
to share the journey of addressing
these issues with the help of IDP.
Vladimir, welcome to the stage.
I can explain how it was in the past.
Hello everyone, my name is Vladimir,
I am a senior SRE at platform
engineering team at Electrolux.
And about three years ago, SRE team
handled bunch of support requests daily.
Such routine requests as access
control, infrastructure issues, getting
data from prod databases, and etc.
It feels every day that you are the
most important person in the world.
If you work in this direction,
developers are blocked by us and waiting
for our response for a long time.
We decided to automate
as much as possible.
We started with the Python script that
did automation for a Terraform code.
So at least we could do this thing
faster, but it didn't solve the challenge.
We did brainstorming what we should
provide to developers, so they don't
need to ask us for the support and
manage infrastructure by themselves.
When I joined the organization,
there were around 20 developers.
Now there are more than 300, and
our organization is still growing.
Unfortunately, the size of our
platform team is not growing that much.
So we decided to provide
a platform instead.
Our first solution was
a self made platform.
The next, as many in the
industry, we moved to backstage.
When it was released in the beginning,
we used only UI from backstage, but
later we took back in part two, most
of the site features as authentication
catalog, to avoid extra work from our
side, developer journey starts from
getting all necessary access for work.
We launched a user onboarding
plugin for new joiners to replace
the manual steps we did before.
For now, engineering leads
can grant every access that is
required and never reach out to us.
From this slide, you can see different
vendors that are covered by this plugin.
After they got all the necessary
accesses, it comes to infrastructure.
You wouldn't expect developers to be
able to create all resources, even
if they have access to everything.
Somehow, we need to control it and
it's complicated task for them to do
it without knowing the infrastructure
and best practices of setting it up.
So we looked into two types of
use cases, developer usually
come to us for the support.
They want to create a resource like
AWS Kafka, radius, and et cetera.
And second one is, create some new
resources that are not supported by IDP.
For example, for some POC, because
they need to investigate new
technologies to use it in IOT.
We created for them UI, where they can
define and provision their infrastructure.
Here is an example.
Our backend runs in Kubernetes.
So very frequently dev team need to
provision or destroy new EKS clusters.
Developers can go to IDP, select
EKS template and IDP will provision
different resources for them.
For example, it creates
VPC and EKS cluster.
Then it installs autoscaler,
ingress controller, datadoc
agent, and our own cost exporter.
Developers don't need to know how to
configure the cluster to publish logs or
metrics into our observability platform.
Cause data will be displayed
in IDP automatically as well.
Sometimes developers need something
that is not supported by IDP.
They create their own Terraform
modules for provisioning.
The resources, for example, we
don't use DNS configuration so
frequent, and there is no need to
develop IDP, IDP component for that.
Any Terraform code still go via
IDP and we keep managing and
tracking everything in one place.
We already have a bunch of
different infrastructure templates
that defined by our team.
Developers teams can use the
template to provision the
infrastructure they need in the cloud.
Thank you.
How it works?
it has a few layers.
First one is a backend API,
that's serving our developers
and providing interface for them.
Second one is a Terraform modules
that are ready for production usage.
And, third one is a cloud APIs we use for
getting data from cloud, like metadata, or
even using for creating resources there.
We have a versioning of the templates,
and if we make some improvements with a
new version, the running infrastructure
will be updated automatically.
Another is very important part
of the platform is a service.
Developers are deploying it every
day and they need some tool to
see the current status of it.
We added services to the platform as well.
Now they can use different features
like CICD status, secret lists,
images in Docker registry and manage
services in Kubernetes by restarting,
killing the posts and et cetera.
And everything is available
in one page, no need to have
a direct access to clusters.
If they need to roll out change or some
specific version of their service, we
have manual deployment feature for that
by using IDP.
You are getting not only provisioned
infrastructure, but also getting more
information of how your infra works
and, for developer it was a big change.
Once one backend developer shared
with me, that before infrastructure
was a, like a black box.
For him, something abstractive,
scary, and hard to understand.
Starting using IDP, he
learned much more simply.
Because we visualized it,
ensure that it's, tested and
safe for developers to use.
And he was able to start
doing things on his own.
Internally and externally, because of, the
public talks like that one, we started to
receive feedbacks that it would be great
to have same solution in their companies,
since everyone facing the same challenges.
Meanwhile, we were not already that
happy with the support we can provide
because we built IDP very customized.
And, it supported only AWS cloud, while
people in our organization started to
request the Google and Azure clouds.
We did another brainstorming and ended up
with building the open source version that
is going to soon replace our current IDP.
How it looks like you
can see from the video.
The first version of our open source
project is going to be focused
on infrastructure management.
How I showed today and, We will add
much more features for services,
cost, and et cetera, a bit later on.
In summary, we have automated a lot of
daily routine tasks and got the time to
focus more on developing, new features
that will be very helpful for everyone.
In the next part, my friend
Lonk will explain how we
are going to open source it.
Lonk, the stage is yours.
Okay.
Thank you, Vladimir, for
the nice presentation.
Next, I would like to share
more about cost engineering
and our open source projects.
Before going into the details, let's
take a look at an example first.
Or maybe a question to you.
Does your infrastructure
or service burn money?
In our case, Electrolux sells
appliances to consumers with a
fixed price, as shown in the slide.
After buying the appliance, the
consumer can onboard it to cloud
and interact with the appliance
using our mobile application.
This means both the mobile application
And the appliance communicates with our
cloud infrastructure, which constantly
cost some money for consumers, they only
pay for the fixed price of an appliance.
However, for Electrolux is crucial
to keep track of the cloud cost.
In order to better control the
cloud cost, we start from collecting
the needs from different teams.
From the management team, they usually
ask the following questions, like
what is the total cost of Project X?
What is the cost chain?
How to optimize cloud cost?
These questions are usually higher
level questions and require cost
aggregation from multiple clouds.
Then, from developers, they care more
about the cost of their own services.
Thank you for your time, For
example, what is the correlation
between the service usage and cost?
And there's also the same kinds
of needs in your organization?
In many cases, it's true
at our organization.
However, we also received
different feedback from developers.
And their answer is, they just
don't care about cloud cost.
I think I pretty understand this
because developers want to focus more
on writing code and delivering features.
The problem here is that when there is
a spike in cloud cost, the management
team usually asks to analyze the
reason and about how to fix it.
Our platform engineering team can take
the investigation at the beginning, but
we don't know the actual usage of the
related cloud resources by developers.
Then we have to kick the
ball back to developer teams.
And at that time, they have to
care about cloud cost and take
proper actions to control the cost.
In order to address these
issues, there are two directions.
One is multi cloud cost
aggregation, which is helpful for
answering high level questions.
For existing solutions,
there are some limitations.
For example, users might be
overwhelmed by the features, and the
subscription might not ship, even if
you only need several key features.
And direction, another direction focuses
more on developers requirements and is
related to fine grained cost breakdown.
Each cloud provider usually provides nice
tools for analyzing tool, analyzing cost.
But the limitation is one provider can
only support checking its own cloud cost.
Users have to switch among different
tools when they have multiple cloud costs.
So in our organization, we have
implemented two different products
for addressing these limitations.
One is called InfoWallet, an open
sourced multi cloud cost aggregation
solution, which I will introduce later.
And another one is a set of cost
metric exporters, which I will
introduce in the next slide.
So a cost metric exporter is a
service That fetches cost information
from a cloud provider and transform
them into promising as metrics.
For example, we have AWS cost exporter.
It uses AWS cost exporter APIs to get the,
sorry, AWS cost explorer APIs to get the
cost data from an AWS account regularly.
Then expose the data as a premises metric.
Then it becomes available for
different observability platforms
like Grafana and Datadog.
There are several benefits
of having cost exporters.
First, the architecture is vendor
neutral because the costs, cloud
costs from different cloud providers
are finally exposed as metrics.
It's extensible as well because
you can implement your own cost
exporter by following the same steps.
These exporters can be deployed
into different clusters to
make it scalable as well.
Furthermore, The ultimate benefit of
having cost exporters is now we can
have cost metrics displayed on the same
dashboard where service metrics are.
This is very helpful for developers
to understand the correlations.
Between the usage of cloud resources
by a service and its total cost, our
cost exporters have been listed on the
premises official documentation page.
You can find more information where
the link on the slack on the slide.
As mentioned just now, we implemented
another product called InfoWallet,
which is a backstage plug in for
multi cloud cost aggregations.
To use InfoWallet, site admins
only need to configure a set of
integrations, for example, some
credentials for their Azure cloud
subscriptions and AWS cloud accounts.
Then InfoWallet retrieves all the
cost data from different cloud
providers and aggregates the
cost based on the user's needs.
This answers the previously mentioned
questions, like what is Project X
cost in category cloud computing?
for listening.
I hope you become interested in it.
I will show you more about using
it, using our demo website later on.
So before the demo, I would
like to mention that we recently
released a new feature called
Business Metrics on InfoWallet.
Why we need such a feature?
Because without a context, it is
hard to answer whether an increase
of your cloud cost is good or not.
For example, if the number of active users
on your platform has doubled, the increase
of the related cloud cost is not very
high, then it may make sense because the
unit cost of one active user might drop.
That's why unit economics is
a crucial metric to understand
the business efficiency.
InfoWallet enables users to fetch metrics
from different observability platforms
and display them on the same cost graph.
Here I have a real story to share.
Around one month ago, we observed
that the daily cost of the
IoT category increased a lot.
However, the number of connected
appliances did not increase that much.
So we shared the findings
with our IoT team, and they
quickly located the problematic
environment thanks to InfoWallet.
The reason is that some of the air
conditioners are misconfigured to
send unnecessary messages to AWS.
IOT.
In summary, without having related
business metrics for cloud costs,
it becomes difficult to justify
the increase of cloud cost.
I'm proud to say that both.
Cloud cost, cost exporters and
InfoWallet have been open sourced
and our GitHub organization.
InfoWallet also provides you a demo
website to easily try its features.
So now let's take a look together.
So this is our GitHub organization,
Electrolux open source software.
And there is a replica of InfoWallet,
you can find all the documentations,
source code and the related issues
here, and you can also visit our
demo website using this link.
So here is a sandbox environment,
on backstage, and we have installed
the latest version of InfoWallet.
Though the cost data and
metric data are faked.
But I think it's easy to get
the idea off having info wallet.
So here you can see we fetch info
wallet fetches different cloud cost.
And by default, it aggregates
everything for you.
So at the first site, you
are able to check the total
cost of your cloud resources.
And then you can select
different time ranges.
It sends another API to, another set
of APIs to fetch cloud cost and also
caches the data so that you don't need
to fetch cost from cloud every time.
And then, all the cost data
can be analyzed and can be
grouped by different dimensions.
For example, by the name of account,
like here we have several AWS accounts,
actual account, and also Google account.
And then it shows you the summary of each,
account's, cost, the portions, and also
the increase or decrease of each account.
Then you can also check like
the total cost of different
providers and also cost category.
So these are the categories
defined by focus.
And actually, InfoWallet aggregates
costs from different cloud providers
into these standard categories.
For example, compute category can contain
AWS EC2 costs plus Azure Functions costs.
Of course, you can also, twitch between
monthly cost and daily cost, and you
can also use filters to focus more
on, for example, a specific category
of cost or a specific wonders cost.
And here you can also switch to show
or hide business metrics and, to check
the details of each category's cost.
So feel free to give it a try and
leave your comments on GitHub.
We will be super happy
to hear your feedback.
All right, back to the slides.
The tools are nice, but I have to say
that it's only a good starting point.
The goal is to optimize the cloud
cost, while it is fundamental to
have sufficient cost observability.
With the help of these tools,
developers are able to check a service's
abnormal behavior regarding cost.
Here is an example of fixing
misconfigurations of logging and
saving unnecessary cloud cost.
We also organized cost optimization
programs regularly in our organization.
It sounds like a competition and is quite
interesting for developers to participate.
We provide cost observability tools
where our IDP and then developers
analyze their cloud costs and
propose actions for saving cost.
In the last round of this program,
we are happy to see that developers
made many good optimizations
from different directions, and we
saved more than 30, 000 per month.
To summarize for developers.
It's very important to achieve
cost efficiency from cost
awareness for platform engineers.
When you design your cost management
solutions, it is recommended to
follow FOCUS, which is a vendor
neutral, open source specification for
consistent cost and usage data sets.
And for everyone, cost engineering
is not only about techniques.
But also about culture.
For example, cost optimization
programs can be very helpful for your
organization to build such a culture.
Till now, we have shared our
recent work in infrastructure
orchestration and cost engineering.
To summarize today's talk, we started
from discussing various challenges
and then Vamir shared more about
infrastructure orchestration and
service management using IDP at last.
I also shared the work about cost
engineering and open source projects.
You can find all the related
open source projects here.
Feel free to give it a try and
drop your comment on GitHub.
Thank you so much for
listening to our talk.
We hope you enjoyed it
and let's connect it.
If you have any questions,
see you next time at Com 42.
Cheers.