Hello and welcome to con
42 platform engineer 24.
I'm Haral and I'm going to talk
about developing and creating.
Telephone providers.
We'll talk a bit about an IEC refresher.
What's infrastructure as code?
Where do I start when I want to create a
provider and how do I go about creating
a provider including a live demo?
First of all, I'm Harald Safra, Data
Platform Engineering Team Lead at RISC V.
Macam manages all the online databases,
everything that has to do with online
systems and access either to end
customers or to analytical systems.
Infrastructure as code is a programmatic
definition of infrastructure elements.
It allows repeatable, documented
processes, you don't have to
click through UIs or do the same
manual task again and again.
And there are two general approaches to
how you go about infrastructure as code.
The first of them is declarative.
The user defines what they want
to achieve, and then the platform
framework does the work for them
and provides the infrastructure.
The other one is imperative.
The user defines how
they want to create it.
They iterate over loops, they create the
code or code like structures that go ahead
and create infrastructure elements, and
we can contrast Terraform and Pulumi.
On either side,
different providers are the plugins
that interface with the infrastructure.
A P.
I.
Terraform core is a framework that
knows how to create a object and
infrastructure element, but doesn't
have any idea about how it how the
infrastructure is created and managed.
To increase over that to create from
providers interface between core
and the infrastructure API and core
interfaces with a provider over RPC
as of today, there are 4400 plus
providers and the list goes on and
on and the main thing to remember is
that anyone can create more providers.
You don't have to be any first to go.
You don't have to be part
of the infrastructure team.
You don't have to be part of the
product or the company at all.
When I need to create a
provider for external databases
that can be used in my team.
But I didn't, I was not part
of the database development.
So anyone can create one.
As long as there's a public API
that allows you to interface.
So where do I start when I
create, want to create a provider?
The first is to understand a bit
about the architecture of the process.
So we have Terraform
Core on the left side.
And Terraform Core is the executable
that you run and manages the operations.
It knows how to rate infrastructure, it
knows how to route infrastructure, and
it knows how to calculate deltas between
the needed state and the current state.
Thank you.
It interfaces over RPC
with a Terraform provider.
That's a, that's the plugin
that you will develop.
And that Terraform provider that's
sitting in Golang specific, specifically
interfaces with a client library.
And that client library interfaces over
native protocol with the infrastructure.
The native protocol could be HTTP
calls, gRPC, SQL system calls.
REST API, anything that infrastructures
knows how to understand and implement
the API.
You need for the API, you need
to find the correct API to
interface with the infrastructure.
There could be old versions, new
versions that are easier to work with.
But, if there's a version that
has an existing Golang client for
it, I would advise to go for it
because it will be easier for you
to create the plugin with that.
Obviously, as I mentioned.
The provider is written in Go, so
you need to know Go, understand?
Go is a compiled and high
level programming language.
You need to understand and
get first thing though.
You don't need to have a specific
deep understanding of it.
You can use the Google
Chat GPTX to go along.
But you need to understand the
constructs, control structures,
and everything like that.
There's a good step by
step tutorial that I used.
Under go dot dev slash tour, it
will help you go step by step
learning, go from basic primitive
types, controls, infrastructure,
interfaces, things like that.
I found the simple language to understand
to learn, especially if you have
knowledge under the programming languages.
It's compiled, which I like because the
compiler now finds errors that you don't
have, you don't bump into during runtime.
One gotcha that I found that there
are no exceptions, meaning you
need to explicitly check for error
conditions for function calls.
Otherwise, your code will just panic out.
Remember that check, check
return values, the underscore
ERR, return value is a friend.
HashiCorp's documentation.
Is the thing that the commission used
in school recommended it's located in
their development portal within the
link here and you can also scan the QR
and find that read the docs again, and
they will give you a basic understanding
on how strings plug into one another.
After you've learned Go, you've
read the documentation from the
HashiCorp documentation, you can
go ahead and create a provider.
And I will be using a demo
to make this a bit more real.
This demo is a plugin, plugin that
creates managed lines in a text file.
Simple lines and simple text files.
All files are managed in a single path.
There's a file resource that has
file name and the lines array.
The file API was provided
for you by me and is limited.
It doesn't have a lot of primitives.
You could read line, you could write,
and you can count the number of lines.
In the file, but not a lot more than that.
And you can see that the resource
definition on the left, which has a file
or one and two lines like one line two
maps into a file that has two text lines.
You can grab the code under my GitHub.
Repo, Terraform provider file that
you can also scan the QR to get
the different plugins framework in the
recommended way to create a providers
that have virus, 2 or 3 different ways
and do an API specification change.
The new way is the plugin framework.
It allows.
Need to manage your business logic
and focus on your business logic and
have the plugin framework do the hard
nesting of connecting to core over RPC
and you start working on that by cloning
the telephone provider scaffolding firm
repo and to your private repository and
then you can customize it from there.
When working with Terraform,
there are four basic operations
that Terraform core needs to be
able to run over infrastructure,
they provision infrastructure and
they amend the Terraform state
accordingly to create operation
of the creates the resource.
It could create a file in our case,
but we also create an EC2 server.
It could also create a user
in a managed, SAS database.
The read operation reads the
current infrastructure state.
The update operation changes attributes
that can be changed according to the API.
Obviously, not all
attributes can be changed.
If you want, if you go back to
the EC2 example, if you want to
recreate the EC2 server, some things
can be updated, like the SSH key.
To destroy and create it, but
some attributes can be updated
and update API does that.
The last operation is delete, which
removes the regions and Terraform Core
also uses that for recreate operations.
In case a user wants to change attributes
that can be changed without destroying,
Terraform Core will go ahead and delete.
And recreate resource by
using Destroy and Create.
Again,
if you look over the code, you can see
that, this is the clone, and there are
a few things that I mentioned earlier.
The file, API that I provided for
you has a few basic operations.
Read dry, count the lines, remove files,
and remove lines from whatever files.
That's something that I add
that the ation and examples and.
If you look the quicker resource here,
file resource, you can see that each of
the primitives that I mentioned earlier
has, a method associated with that.
So we have a delete method and an
update method and a read method
and a create method and a few
others that covered, bit later on.
And if we expand the create method,
for example, we can see that it has.
A code that has to do with interface
interfacing with their phone call.
It basically gets the copies
of the request from there from
core into a local variable.
Then there is logic that does the
operation and the infrastructure
in this case, creating a file
and writing lines into it.
And then it returns return value back.
To tell from court to allow
it to know what happened and
allow it to amend the state.
Accordingly,
each of the resources and data
has schemas and attributes.
Schemas and attributes are the
mapping between configuration
blocks to provide the code.
And they define what parameters
are needed to create a
structure to change its values.
Some of them can be mandatory, some
of them can be the option, but these
are the parameters that are needed
to create the infrastructure itself.
Schemas have attributes that define
data, specific data elements,
and each attribute has a type.
The type could be a primitive, an instance
before, a string, or it could be a complex
data type like a map, an object, a list.
Each of the attributes also has
properties, a description, it's optional,
sensitive, and other properties.
And it can also have optional validators,
The check that the user supply values
match what the infrastructure provider.
If you take a look at the code,
you can see that this is all
implemented in a schema function.
And the file has two attributes.
First of all, the file itself.
has a description, file data
resource, and it has two attributes.
One of them is a file name, which should
have this, description of file name.
It's required
and has a validator that map that,
forces the file to have a specific, to
match a specific regular expression.
It also has an additional attribute
called lines, which is a list attribute.
And each one of those It's a string value,
so it's a list of elements of TypeString.
And in this specific case, it also has
a validator that enforces the line to
have at least two lives, as an example.
You should note that descriptions
under the attributes and under the
filename do use them because they
are then copied over to the document,
automatically created their documentation.
That, that creates that basically
copies the description and
filing and, an element type here.
And then you can see this combination
later on copied into publishing to
terraform registry for your end users.
Types.
The plug types are not
native go nine types.
They have additional methods
and in, functionality to handle
null values and unknown values.
For example, in N 64 and other
primitive have a is null method that
returns if it's null or not, and
primitives are actually using the value.
Type method, for example, the
N64 has a method called value N64
that returns a native Golang N64.
Collections are converted into
Golang types with the as method.
for example, list, you can grab
the list, the elements of a list
as the native Golang type with
elements as, and then cast them
into a slice or array of strings.
You
should go back to the code,
you can see and go back to, for
example, the create function.
You can see that the full name of the
file is created by appending the base
path for the provider with the file name,
which is, which is, framework string
type, but we grabbed the value, the
goal and value with various string that
returns it into a native string that we
can use to, to append into other values.
After he created the provider.
You're quite happy that you want to run
it, but you want to see that it works.
first of all, you don't have
to publish the provider into
there from registry to run it.
You can use to run it locally.
You can use that, do that
by using the dev overrides.
Is stanza inside the Xena configuration
file and then send the TFC like a
shake file to that's fine for in
this example, you can see that the
C like on shake file has develop
rise and maps that the registry
address into a local path on my Mac.
You can use log based debugging for
simple cases, but you can also use
debugger based debugging, which is
far more powerful for complex 1.
So you do that by running the main.
Method of your provider with
my dash debug equals three.
It will output an inbound driver.
You copy it to wherever you want to run,
and then you run terraform action and
that the action will break the debugger.
Let's see how that works.
First of all, I have my code here.
Let's look at the run configuration and
see that everything works correctly.
So we have a debug and you
can see there's a program.
Agreements have dash debug equals true.
I said the break point, for example, let's
say I want to debug the read operation.
So I set the break point here
and then I run the program.
If we compile and then output an
environment variable, which I copy
and then based here
as it is.
Now, this directory has a
configuration for Terraform.
So it has a provider block, a provider
file that defines the base path,
which is This is that directory.
It also has a resources file that defines
2 file resources, file 1 and file 2.
You can see that each
file has a few lines.
And if we cap the file 1, for
example, you can see that it
has 2 lines that are defined.
As I mentioned earlier, I exported the
TF3 attached providers, and now if I run
Terraform plan, it will start, and then
it will pop up the debugger, and you
can see that the Terraform run itself
is waiting for the debugger output.
You can use the debugger to
just basically scroll through.
Code your code like everything else.
And you can see, for example, that
the full name here that is created
is a read operation for file 2.
If we want, we do the program again,
it will continue running and then
it will end and refresh the state.
If you don't need that, and
you can see that it's just the
state and the real equation.
And in this case, there's
no change in the file.
So there are no changes infrastructure.
When you're done with that, obviously
you want to stop the debugger.
And then we can go back
to the presentation
after you debug the code, you're happy
with your test and automatic test
and accepting this for your resources
and data sources and to allow you
both to check the code is working
correctly and what to be later on
interface into the GitHub actions.
The state is already checked in basically
in this test suite, and if you want
to create a test operation by yourself
on the infrastructure itself, you need
to add them to the acceptance test.
You can run the test
manually with make test, and
the way it happens is to
create a resource on the score.
Test dot go fight in the same
directory and the make will grab them.
So if we go back to the code, close
the menu, you can see that, for
example, the fighter sauce has a
file resource test underscore go.
And this has function.
Each function is a test that has
pre check steps for the test.
And as I said, the test, the
state of the check in place.
For example, in this case, it configs
with a function that we'll see a
bit later, and then it will need
to create, create a file, like if I
want, it has 2 lines, 1 and 2, and it
checks the attribute, just checks the
attribute that the file name is file 1.
The second step in this step is to
actually update file one with lines two
and three instead of one and two and check
that the lines and the first and the zero
place in the first line is equal to two.
Both of these functions
use a set of function.
Test X, but it could be whatever
you want, just returns and a term
from configuration file, basically.
So we have a provider stanza
and a resource stanza.
And you can see that the values
are pending into here just to
make creating configuration files
easier instead of just writing them
here explicitly again and again.
When we're done with that, you can,
you can run the acceptance test, and in
this case, they passed, which is nice.
You created your code, you debugged
it, you created the acceptance
test, you created the commutation,
you are all fine and happy.
You want to publish it
and therefore register.
The first is create a GPG key.
You'll use for and definitely registry
will use to validate code is indeed yours.
Send the GitHub secrets
GPG private key and pass.
Raise accordingly.
Create a Git tag named V.
The V version would be V 0.1, 0.0 V 2.3.
Make sure that the funnel
sematic versioning, and.
This tag is what drives the GitHub action
that's included with a telephone provider
by the framework and that action builds.
Both, both all the executables and
also pushes a WebBook to read to
Terraform registry to allow you
to grab new, the new resource.
So you need the tag, really.
The next thing is you log into
Terraform Registry and add the repo.
once you've done that, you
authenticate back to GitHub.
it'll create a WebEx hook that
will, push in new updates.
That are tagged into Terraform
Registry and you wait a bit.
It takes a few minutes and for Terraform
Registry to grab the changes from GitHub.
And then you can see your
provider published into Terraform
for other people to use.
Every published into
Terraform for the public.
So be aware not to publish any kind
of proprietary code or anything
that's, Let's discuss the secret
that we can't really divulge
to wrap it up.
Me and my team started from manual
management of this specific database.
we have used Terraform extensively for
other cases, but in this specific database
that we need to manage, we had the
manual management script and confluence.
I had to let go and learn
Terraform framework.
I created a provider and
release a few more features.
It's a free conversion, zero dot format,
and I published a provider and my team
is it, and I hope that other people
around the world use it too, because
it makes managing databases easy.
Thank you all for your time.
I'm Haral Safra.
You can find my contact details LinkedIn
and get up, get a profile below.
I would be more than welcome.
Any questions.
If you have anything, reach
out to me and we got to help
with anything that you need.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you for being here with me.