Hi everyone,
a recent CatPoint survey identified
that 66 percent of organizations use
2 5 monitoring hubs or build tools.
And it also identified that 24 percent
of organizations have breached a
contractual service level agreement
obligation during last 12 months.
Those are two very important numbers.
Having more than two to three or more
than two observable dual is a little
problematic because you will struggle to
identify a unified, a single truth state.
And the 24 percent number about
contractual failures are alarming as well.
What it shows is even with multiple
tools, the organizations are struggling.
My name is Indic Vimalasuriyath.
Welcome to Platform Engineering 2024.
My presentation is based out
of AWS observability as code.
And I'll focus on leveraging Datadog to
enable advanced platform engineering.
As part of my presentation, I will
provide you a quick overview of challenges
faced in the modern day observability
platforms due to distributed nature.
And we will quickly discuss about role
of observability in platform engineering.
And we will touch about Datadog,
which I will be using to
enable observability as code.
in AWS based infrastructures.
And we will look at how we can enable
or implement observability as solutions,
real world implementation details.
And we will wrap it up with
some of the best practices and
pitfalls you may need to avoid.
So quick intro about myself.
I, my name is Sindik Vimalsuri.
I'm based out of Colombo.
I live with my daughter and wife.
I'm coming from a very strong
reliability engineering and
solution architect background.
My specialties are site reliability
engineering, observability,
AIOps, and generative AI.
I'm currently employed at Virtus.
R.
I oversee technical delivery
and capability development.
I'm a very passionate technical trainer
and an energetic technical blogger.
I am, AWS Community Builder,
part of Cloud Operations and also
Ambassador at DevOps Institute.
So to start, the distributed systems
and modern day systems are evolving
fast and with that it's also
increasing the complexities
we need to manage.
The traditional monolith systems have
already moved into microservices.
And on from my data centers, which
we use to host our applications,
we now move into cloud and some
instance we move it from cloud to
the serverless architecture as well.
So what this has done is there's
an expansion of data sources,
surging data volume and exponential
rising failure scenarios.
So while it's good and while it add
lot of value in modern day systems.
it has bringing in certain level of,
increased failure scenarios as well.
So which, which resulted in difficulties
in managing these environments and also it
has increased the role of observability.
So the traditional monitoring, which was
mainly rule based, predefined approach of
looking at systems are no longer enough.
We have moved into observability,
and that's mainly due to
distributed systems complexities,
dynamic nature, and elasticity.
And most of our systems
are now container based.
We have CI, CD deployments,
integrations, we are connecting
to API gateways, and there's a
increased, in cloud service providers.
Some of the systems are in poly
cloud, multi cloud, leveraging
multi welder solutions.
And our systems have scalability
challenges, which sometimes we are using
these cloud service providers solutions
to, resolute, to, rectify and this require
observability into this as scalability
triggers and we would like to detect
things much faster, resolve things much
faster and we want to have end to end
visibility of our, the user journeys.
So these are some of the key things
which is, increasing or which
result, the need for observability.
So if I quickly touch upon
observability about logs are
the, what is your code is doing.
We typically use logs to, for
our root cause understanding.
And we have metrics.
Metrics are nothing but numbers, a point
in time performance of your application.
And metrics are generally used for
alerting because it's a number,
it's a good way of allowing
us to generate our alerts.
Thank you very much.
And we have tracing.
Tracing is what is your code
is doing at a snap point.
You can see what that code is doing,
method level, the time taken, and
even you can trace a request from a
front end request to middleware to
the backend, which is database calls.
So tracing is very important.
It's allowing us to understand what to
time taken in our code, and it's allowing
us to see what is our code is doing.
And on top of that, we are building
alarms, which are our monitors.
We are developing a lot of dashboards.
We are coming up with synthetic monitors.
We are looking at real user monitoring,
which is trying to understand what
is your actual end users are doing.
We are looking at the infrastructure,
we are looking at the network, we are
looking at the security aspects of
our ecosystem, and obviously we are
looking at how we can optimize cost,
the infrastructure cost, AWS or the
cloud provider and other cost as well.
So pretty much these are the key
fundamentals when it comes to
observability which you want to achieve.
So when it comes to platform engineering,
I would like to take a one example.
Let's say you have one organization
which is having around three
departments or line of businesses
and each department have multiple
applications or engagements running.
And sometimes what can happen is that
these engagements or the application
teams may find their own comfortable
observability tool based solutions and
observability tools, alerting tools,
log management tools, security aspects.
So they will leveraging
things they prefer.
So what this happened is, over a
period of time, we are losing the
unification, the unified approach.
It's very difficult to
enable consistencies.
It's very difficult to build
consistencies across these systems.
And it difficult to, whenever
new applications and new
services are coming in.
We are having trouble and challenges.
So as part of platform engineering, what
we are trying to do into this specific
area of observability is we want to build
a unified observability strategy, which
is about, which is to make observability
consistent across teams and ensure that
there's a centralized observability.
And we want to build efficient
troubleshooting and incident response
framework, leveraging cross team
collaborations, which will derive fast
and efficient root cause analysis.
And we also want to ensure we have
scalability and reliability, leveraging
proactive monitoring, predictive
capabilities, and other advanced
features, and things like capacity plan.
And we will also develop, enhance
developer experience because developers
are important and they had to have the
end to end visibility observability
into our production systems.
So this allows us to, there's
a need of us to build like self
service observability solution.
Access and dashboards is
specific to developers as well.
And we will.
Figuring, enable some services
related to security and compliance
and cost official and cost
tracking and those things as well.
So those are the key aspects or
the key part of, observability
in platform engineering, and that
will enable us to get the true.
value of platform engineering
in observability area.
And let me talk about Datadog because
here we are trying to use Datadog
on top of that AWS and trying to
see what And what, capabilities of,
observability and, observability as
code solutions which we can enable.
So here, if you look at it,
we have multiple data sources,
like Datadog supports around
750 plus, source integrations.
It supports logs, traces, metrics,
and metadata sessions as well.
So it also provides a lot of dashboards.
alerts, collaboration, mobile,
monitoring workflows, what dog, which
is the, it's on AI platform and also
integration into open telemetry.
So some of the use cases, observable
use cases, data dog is providing our
infrastructure, monitoring applications,
performance, monitoring, unified,
universal monitoring, log management.
The continuous integration visibility,
continuous profiling, real user
monitoring, network monitoring,
synthetic monitoring, cloud
security, application security,
observability pipeline, and many more.
So all of this allowed our, the key
partners or the teams like development
teams, IT operations teams, Security
team, support team and business to
have a full view of our ecosystem.
So when you are building a AWS
base, observability driven platform
engineering solution, there are a
few things we need to be, focused.
So one is our centralized
Datadog integration.
So if it is the sim standard.
workloads.
We might have to integrate, example
for EC2s, the agents as well.
And if it is containers, then we'll
have to do the integration as well.
If it is, less like AWS Lambdas, we
might have to intercept the Lambda
the libraries and then enable this
AWS integration, especially for ACM.
And then with this, what we are trying
to do is enable, the key, aspects or
the elements of observability, which
is about enabling the standard matrix
and the dashboards and, locks, which
we want to make sure it's consistent.
And also the traces, the spans and
those things so that we can troubleshoot
and identify what's happening at.
microservices hosted in
AWS or in the containers.
Or even AWS Lambda as well.
So on top of that, Datadog allows us to
develop alerting and incident workloads.
And also there are other services
like looking at the performance and
scalability, resource management, cost
management, and other CI, CD integrations.
And looking at things like automated
setup and looking at the governance,
how we can build different access
controls and how we can enable
compliance control and other developer
related services such as developer
access, documentations and trainings.
So those will allow us to develop a
comprehensive observability platform
engineering framework for AWS.
so moving on.
So when you look at observability
as code, so there are key elements.
One is, treat your observability
configuration as codes, which
is about agent integrations or
integration with Datadog in AWS.
Looking at metrics, logs and traces
and how you can set up, them with AWS
based ecosystem and how we can leverage
Datadog to achieve those things.
And next one is about
versioning and management.
We want to do versioning control.
We can reuse the components like Git.
So which is allowing us to do version
control and tracking our, changes
and increased the collaborations.
Of course, this, the observability as code
solutions, we will have to enable with a
CI, CD related deployments, automations.
So that way we can, while the
development teams are developing these.
solutions.
They can push all these, the
observability as code solutions into
a multiple pre live environments.
From there, we can start deploying
and until we deployed into production.
So this we can enable consistency
and standardization, implement
standardized templates, come up with
some quality gates, and we can come
up with modules for observability
configuration, and apply some consistent
settings across multiple environments.
And this will enable us to do
a comprehensive observability
monitoring and maintenance.
conduct reviews, validations of our
configuration, implementing test
frameworks and, and to ensure that
we have a proper quality gauge as
when we are moving from our pre
life to the production environment.
And also we can have a
standardization in documentation.
And this will allow a lot of
collaborations in multiple teams.
And the whole idea is that we will not
that data doc, but we will develop our
solutions as observability as code.
And this code has, can be moved from
one environment, one environment until.
We move into production and different
teams can contribute this we can do
the version tracking we can enable
Configure the collaboration and
we can have better quality as well
So moving on some of the benefits
of observability as code solution
when you are thinking of aws It
will improve accuracy, there's
enhanced visibility because, you are
working as code and because of that
visibility drives a lot of accuracy.
So it's code, you can do a lot of, a
lot of validations and a lot of, and
even a lot of collaborations as well.
While we enable a lot of corroborations,
we can build a lot of quality gates on
top of our code and it's much faster.
So we can have much
faster turnaround time.
It can be consistent
across the environment.
So that's one of our challenges.
We may lack Observability, when it comes
to the consistency in environments,
example, you may have some sort of,
some degree of observability in your
production environment, but it might not
be, identical in your lower environment.
And what that happens,
developers will have a challenge.
And even there can be misunderstanding,
misinterpretations, and there can
be some challenges in, achieving
what we're trying to achieve.
And obviously observability as code
Promote better collaboration and
it's allow us to do a continuous
improvements in our systems.
So moving on.
with AWS there are a lot of observability
called, tools, which we can use
things like Terraform, Ansible, j
pmi, or AWS code formation as well.
And this systems we are going to
leverage Terraform, which is widely
being used, across the board.
And what we are trying to
achieve is we want to ride entire
observability as code solutions using.
Terraform and then ship push into Datadog.
And what we are trying to achieve
is we want to create things like,
enable the Datadog integration.
So we can completely automate AWS and
Datadog integration using Terraform.
And we want to ship this logs into
AWS based logs into Terraform,
either it's your EC2s, the workloads,
or the container based workloads,
or your serverless framework.
So all of those things
we can ship to Datadog.
And we can streamline that using Terraform
and enabling APM in your containers
or the EC2 based workloads or even
in your serverless based frameworks.
We can leverage observability
as code solutions.
And then we want to build common
metrics and enable common metrics and
develop common dashboards So this is
very important because generally the
developers and the devops teams srs
They will refer some of these standard
dashboards And what we can do is it's
not just these standard dashboards
are available in your production, but
you can enable those in different to
your pre live environments as well.
Example, test and development environment,
test environment into an integration
environments, staging environment.
So this way you can have unification and
developers are able to look at things.
And before they are trying to see
how their code is going to behave
in production, they have the
ability of trying to understand
how things are behaving in the
pre live environments as well.
And then we can automate the.
synthetic monitoring creation,
the synthetic monitors,
this is very important.
This about creating production end user
and mimicking them and what actual end
users are doing so that way we have
more control of trying to see how our
application is behaving and we can of
course generate a lot of alerts on top of
these synthetic monitors or the metrics
or some of these log events as well.
And we can automate the entire
account creation, the access
control in as observable as code.
We can enable the CI CD pipeline
integrations, and in some instances, the
distributed insulating setup as well.
And one of the important aspects when it
comes to site reliability engineering is
define your service level indicators and
define your service level objectives.
DataDog as an observability tool is
providing a very good capability of
defining service level objectives.
You can either create with your good
events divided by total, or you can
create SLOs based on your synthetic
pointers based on to monitor uptime and
things like that, or you can have SLOs
based on different time slices as well.
So all of these options which DataDog is
providing, you can automate, you can write
your, we can get our developers to write.
SLOs and write it using observability
as code solutions and that can
be navigated through multiple
product pre production environments
until it moves into production.
So that way we can enable consistency
across the Service level objectives
from pre live environment to
the production environment.
We are obviously able to use automated
incident management workflows, enable that
using our observability as code solutions.
And finally, our compliance
and governance control as well.
So what we will do is we will look at
some of the cost snippets of how we can
do some of the terraform code snippets.
So that will give you some
idea about these integrations.
So if I take a step back, so if I want
to Define or develop the observability
as a code solution leveraging datadog for
aws So what we will do is the step one
is we have to define our observability
configuration What we'll generally do is
we'll identify and create configuration
files Covering the key observability
components such as metrics logs and
traces dashboards Events and most of
the things I have covered part of the
previous slide and we will look at version
control We can have our the observability
as code our code in git And then we can
manage the versioning, we can enable
collaboration, we can enable branching,
and we can follow merging strategies.
So that way that we can have more
comprehensive control of our observability
And we can build a lot of test solution
as well, the unit testing and other
form of validations such as syntax.
And other validations as well.
And we can have to then the fourth step
is to enable this with the continuous
integration, integrate with the CI
pipelines, enable it automatically
run test on to ensure these things
go through multiple environments
before we move into production.
So we can have multiple quality gates
and part of before CI, you can do
the automated deployments as well.
And then we'll have to build
the monitoring and validation.
Monitor the automated deployments
moving across multiple, instances,
and then validation process.
We can ignore multiple teams who
are owning these pre live anonymous,
like the developers, the testers,
the integrate into end-to-end teams
and into an integration teams and,
even the DevOps and SRA teams.
So they can go through this,
observability as called solutions.
Those outputs in multiple
environments, pre-live environments.
for continuous review and validations.
So this will typically enable your
meters and compliance as well.
So if you look at, because this, we
are trying to focus on Terraform.
So this is a typical
Terraform folder structure.
So you will have your observability
as code, the folder, and then
we'll have the deployments.
You will have main A TF and your providers
for the, which will enable you to, do the
provider configuration with data talks.
You can define your variables and you
can version your Terraform as well.
And then we can have a set of your,
the YAML files, which are looking
at your creating monitors, service
level objectives, dashboards,
creating maintenance windows,
or other integrations other.
the form of automations,
which you want to enable.
So if you look at typically, if you
want to integrate, the data dog, what
we'll do is we'll have to enable data
dog agent running in your workloads,
or, we can do a direct, integration
with our serverless framework as well.
So here we can use data form.
to do this configuration.
So you can see we are using
Datadog, APS and other keys.
So you don't have to actually, what
you can do is we can use AWS secret
manager, and then we can read these
keys part of a reading secret manager
so that we have a better mechanism
of handling secret keys as well.
And we are able to, Some of our
logs in AWS, which is typically
reside in cloud work, and then we
can ship these logs into data dog.
And while doing that, we can do
a lot of, regular expression.
We can level at them to
split our knocks and then.
Some of those important locks and we
can filter locks based on the lock type,
like it's on the error or the warnings
or likewise, so we can identify extract
some of these different lock exceptions
and said, so we have a lot of exceptions.
So we had to be mindful that data dog is
a paid solution and it can be sometimes
a little expensive when we are using.
Lot of, log related, when you are trying
to ship the entire log into Datadog.
So what you can do is you
can use a lot of filtering.
So that way that you can save
some of the cost when it comes to
using Datadog for log management.
moving on, so one of the other important
things which I personally like is lot
develop lot of synthetic monitors.
So we can develop a lot of synthetic
monitors to test, different pages
or some of user journeys and we can
provide some, the failure, the retries.
And here again, those are
very important things.
So this will, the synthetic
monitors will actually try to mimic.
end user in our production systems,
so it has a lot of value and, so we
can again use, Terraform to get this.
And one thing I, personal of
my favorite is creating alerts.
So we'll have to create alerts
based on, we, first it's about
service level objective based
alerts based on your caching layer.
you have to create a list based
on your, the middleware, the
logic layer, the service layer.
and you have to create some of
these alerts based on your other
end to end journeys as well.
So it's, so what you had to do is
your alert has to be more or less
correlated with service level objectives.
So it's level objectives will correlate
with end user experience, and you
can, of course, have a lot of triggers
when it related to infrastructure
monitoring, network monitoring and
other anomaly monitoring as well.
Alert can be standard is that,
the metric driven alerts.
Or you can enable some of the alerts
like, AI capabilities like anomaly
related alerts or forecasting.
And then alerts, you can define what
are the thresholds, or you can let,
in case of anomaly detection and
forecast anomaly detection, especially
let Datadog handle those things,
the thresholds, diamond thresholds.
Based on baseline.
So you can configure what are the teams
these alerts has to go through and
you can come up with a lot of tagging.
So the using observability as code
solution in AWS in this area that
will provide you a lot of options,
a lot of standardizations and that
will add a lot of value in a large
organization managing multiple teams.
And then, most of the teams assuming
they use some workloads like EC2.
So the containers.
Or, yeah, they are using serverless
based solutions, like Lambdas.
And, pretty much, sometimes your,
what you monitor might be same,
if your caching metrics, if your,
the service layer related metrics,
which are your, the backend related
metrics, frontend related metrics,
if you, Enable real user monitoring.
So there can be a lot of common metrics.
And on top of that, we can even absorb a
lot of common dashboards as well, which
can be aligned, which can be even Carter
into multiple different end user journeys.
Because the technology is same, the
what's happening at the background
is same, so we can create some of
these very standard dashboards.
So those these dashboards can be
using observability as code solution.
We can move in different environments
in AWS like your pre live.
The staging of production.
So that way you have a lot of consistence.
You enable, you allow your developers
to go and, look at, how the
application is behaving in multiple
environments, not only in production.
So this is a very value added
thing and with this we can make
it lot of, standardization.
So when the same
capabilities we can, allow.
Other engagements,
other teams use as well.
So whenever new applications, new
engagements are getting onboarded,
things will be very straightforward.
They can just simply plug into the
Git, look at these Terraform scripts,
observability as code solutions, and then
integrate these in their AWS environment.
So moving on, one of the
other thing is enabling APM,
application performance monitoring.
Here again, if it's like the workload
based, Or using open telemetry or
serverless blade integrating apm
with your serverless frameworks.
We can leverage there are observability
as code solutions in aws as well And
finally, some of these, the platform
engineering typical use cases are
account creation, access control, and we
can use observability as code solution
here in AWS, but we can do is we can
have a different access layers for your
dashboards to the monitors, your logs.
synthetic ability to recreate
the admin users, read write
privileges, account creations, cost
views, and all of those things.
So we can leverage Terraform and
which mean your observability as
code solutions with AWS, leveraging
Datadog to achieve these capabilities.
And finally, of course, like we can
use this to streamline our CI CD
pipeline integrations using Terraform.
So this will be very, beneficial
because we want to ensure this
observability as code solution
goes through multiple environments
so that we can take this benefit.
And, in case if required, there's
a specific customization needed
for your distributed tracing setup,
we can leverage this as well.
And as I said, one of the other important
thing is defining service level objectives
and sometimes we have seen there's a
common framework, common aspects when
we are defining because in a typical
organizations we are using some of these,
the AWS based workloads, the containers
and serverless frameworks and that
enable us to leverage some of these,
standardizations and the common factors.
So using SLO as code, what we want
is instead of defining SLOs at
last, or developing SLOs as once the
application goes live, we want our
developer community to think about
SLOs, service level objectives, when
they're designing, developing, testing,
and try deploying these, the code into
multiple environments, so they can
write the SLO as part of your code.
Okay.
And then ship and let it go through
multiple environments until production
even to add production so that way that we
can monitor our service level objectives
and even example in one of our pre
live environment we can do performance
testing we can do soft testing we can
do security testing we can do other
form of stress testing and we can see
how our SLOs are behaving we can mimic
some of the high peak traffic the high
concurrent traffic and simulate some of
or, spike, or the flood of traffics and
different type of user behaviors, and we
can see our, how our SLOs are behaving.
So this is a very powerful feature.
So typically what happened was people
define SLOs in Datadog ecosystems
at large state for production.
But this way, from the very
beginning in multiple environments,
from the start, we can do that so
that there's a lot of visibility.
Okay.
Consistence and we can achieve a
lot of good things by doing this.
And obviously Datadog provides whenever
there are, events created, we can invoke
some webhooks and from there we can,
invoke some remediation engines running
in our AWS workloads or serverless
framework like lambdas with that we
can do a lot of, self healing, we can
build a lot of self healing solutions.
We can do a lot of automation solutions.
So observability as code is
providing those capabilities as well.
And then we can, of course, build
our compliance and governance
control based out of this
observability as code solution.
And finally, in case, when,
whenever we have any scheduled
deployment, scheduled downtimes.
or downtime related to back
end teams, which will have an
impact on some of our monitors.
We can enable maintenance windows, or
whenever there are CI CD deployment,
unless if you are using a very
sophisticated deployment strategy, you
are calling out a certain level of outage.
You can create your maintenance
windows as observability as code,
and then you can suppress your traps.
So you can integrate that part of
your the release the CACD pipelines so
that way you can test it as well and
whenever you are doing this production
deployment automatically pipeline will.
enable the maintenance window, which is
suppressing your relevant traps during
that particular deployment window.
And after that you can enable
it and do a testing as well.
So this whole aspect, instead of
doing manually, you can leverage
the observability as code solutions
in AWS to achieve this thing.
So moving on, so those are some of
the things which we can do as part
of observability as code, which will
support our ultimate goal of developing
a comprehensive observability related
components, services, things when
it comes to platform engineering.
So while you're doing this, I think
it's very important for you to
be mindful of typical, issues and
ensure that you are ready for that.
And one of the key issue is whatever we
do these days, we had to ensure that we
have a way to measure progress and how,
whether what we have done is actually
allowing business to see some benefits.
So we had to look at your mean time for
detection, mean time for resolution,
mean time for between failures.
So we had to ensure that there
is a way for we can extract these
metrics so that we can measure
this when we are going through our
observability as called journey in AWS.
And we had look at how, whether this
is helping us to improve reliability,
availability and how this is, helping
us to enhance the customer experience.
So this can be tagged into your service
level objectives, can improve your service
level objectives, in a periodic fashion.
So those are some of these
values we have to bring in part
of these kinds of solutions.
And also, can you improve
your developer velocity?
Can this have more, positive impact
on your DORA metrics, which is like
lead time for change and reduce
increasing the change, Frequency, make
your production volatile while you
manage your customer experience using
service level objectives and reduce the
deployment failure rate and those things.
So you had to think about those things
and capturing those metrics and some
aspects of this, you can of course use
observability as code solutions as well.
So this, you can, instead of letting
teams is coming up, up with Their own
solutions you can make this standard make
it also observability as code solution.
So That way this can be tracked properly
as well And finally before we wrap up
so observability as code has a lot of
advantages, but there are some best
practices You have to be mindful.
So number one I would suggest is managing
your secure api keys So when it comes to
Datadog integration using AWS, you will
have to look at, there can be your Datadog
API keys and AWS based credentials.
So those you will have to leverage,
and access in a very, secure way.
And you will have to definitely use
version control because that's one
of the key advantage, key elements
bringing in observability as code.
So think about ensure you don't miss
out and you do the version control.
Keep your cord in the gig and those are
best practices and you obviously will
have to do a modularization instead
of you know going a big band way.
Modularize it to your agent data
dog integrations, APM enable, Real
User Monitoring enables, Metric
enablement, Dashboard creation,
Monitors, Synthetic monitors, Log
pipelines, Governance, Access controls.
So that way there's modularization
so that you can take those advantage.
And this observability as code
solution has to be plugging
with your deployment pipelines.
It has to go through multiple environments
and until you move into production.
So that this way you can take the
True potential of this observability
being written as code for AWS.
And you'll have to look at, role
based access controls, enable
them, based on your user community.
You'll have to look at
how you do that as well.
And this has to be a centralized solution.
So it has, this should provide
centralized output, centralized
dashboard, centralized architecture.
the alerting mechanisms,
centralized logging systems,
standardization across everything.
That is very important.
So this has to reside in standardization.
So every engagement, every line of
business, every team in your organizations
are pretty much following a defined
and standardization with quality
gates and with, the ability to review.
Thank you.
So this should come up with a lot
of documentations, reviews, so
that will enable collaboration.
And Datadog has a lot of integrations,
sometimes leveraging those direct
integrations will save you time
when it comes to AWS like serverless
integration, container integration,
and with other different AWS
service integrations as well.
So all of this is driving collaboration.
So you have to ensure that these,
taken and taken into your, multiple
teams and work with them to enable this
collaboration so that you can get this
value out of this, enabling observability
as code for your AWS ecosystems.
With that, I would like to
take a close my presentation.
I hope you enjoy it and we'll see
you in another future presentation.
So thank you very much
for taking your time.
And there are great.
amount of presentations done by different
presenters, part of platform engineering
2022 and 24 by organized by con 42.
I'm requesting everyone to look
at these presentations as well.
So thanks for taking time.
Take care.
Bye.