Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the streaming plane,
the plane that brings all
other data planes together.
I'm Hubert Dulay, developer advocate
at StarTree, the company that provides
Apache a real time OLAP database.
I'm really happy to be presenting among
many other data experts here at COMP42.
About me, I'm the primary author
of two O'Reilly books, Streaming
Data Mesh and Streaming Databases.
And in this presentation, you'll get
to see some ideas from both books.
In this session, you'll learn
about a few concepts that are
shaping the future of data.
First, we'll explore the data divide,
what it is and why it's becoming a
critical challenge in data management.
Next, we'll discuss data gravity
and how it influences where
and how data is processed.
We'll also introduce the
streaming plane, a crucial layer
for handling real time data.
And finally, we'll cover how to
effectively consume real time analytics.
Enabling you to make data
driven decisions instantly.
The data divide describes data
movement within a business and
is crucial for understanding how
data drives business decisions.
In summary, The data divide
distinguishes between two main
data planes, the operational
and the analytical data planes.
The operational data plane consists
of data stores that support the
application's powering a business,
while the analytical data plane is
focused on data analysis and insights.
The idea is that the insights derive
from the Analysis are fed back to
the operational plane in hopes of
generating more revenue or, more
importantly, preventing revenue loss.
As data moves through a typical
pipeline, it doesn't just get copied.
It undergoes transformations, cleansing,
and security processes like encryption.
The data is secure and reliable
by the time it reaches the end.
However, getting this refined data
out of analytical systems is tough
because these systems often reformatted
into formats like Parquet, which
are great for analysis, but make it
hard to access complete data sets.
This is where ETL, Extract Transform
Load, and ELT, Extract Load
Transform, processes come into play.
While there's debate on which
is better, the lines between
them are starting to blur.
Each plane has its own type of database.
On the operational plane, you get
OLTP databases that are optimized for
operational workloads like Insert,
Update, Delete, and Single Row Lookups.
These databases are usually row based.
On the analytical plane, databases
are optimized for analytical
workloads like aggregations and joins.
These are called OLAP databases, or
Online Analytical Processing databases.
What makes them special is that they store
data in columnar formats, which is more
efficient for running complex analyses.
OLAP systems keep a history of
all the data that originated
from the operational side.
That's really useful for tracking changes
over time and seeing how things evolve.
In the operational plane,
you'll see microservices
supporting various applications.
And on the analytical side,
you'll find data lakes, data
warehouses, and lake houses.
But here's the thing, since the data on
the analytical side is already clean and
transformed, why should transformations?
Moving data from analytical
to operational is hard.
It's an upstream path.
OLAPs don't like to return
all rows and columns.
That's not what they are optimized to do.
Remember that these databases are
intended for analytical workloads.
Selecting all the raw records from a
table in an OLAP is expensive and slow.
Solutions like we're Reverse ETL and data
activation are designed to help bring this
polished data back into your applications.
Data gravity is a concept that compares
data to a planet, where accumulated data
attracts services and applications, much
like a planet's mass pulls in moons.
In traditional data architectures,
data flows from operational systems,
moons to an analytical system, the
planet, leading to potential overload
and latency as the analytical system
becomes burdened with historical data.
However, with a streaming plane, data
can be processed closer to its source,
acting like satellites that alleviate
the gravitational pull, enabling smoother
data flow and real time analytics.
Data gravity Highlights the challenges
of managing growing data, while the
streaming plane offers a solution for more
effective data movement and processing.
In the streaming plane, you'll typically
find several key systems working together.
First, There are connectors, which
enable seamless data flow between
various sources and destinations.
Then, we have streaming databases that
store and manage real time data streams.
Real time OLAP data stores provide
the ability to perform fast
analytical queries on streaming data.
Streaming platforms like Kafka, Red
Panda, and Pulsar are the backbone.
Handling the distribution,
and routing of data streams.
And finally, stream processing
frameworks, which allow you to
process and analyze data in motion,
ensuring timely insights and actions.
There are two ways to serve streams of
data, synchronously and asynchronously.
Synchronous serving is handled by
databases that consume directly
from the stream, such as streaming
databases and real time OLAP databases.
Real time OLAP databases are specifically
optimized for analytical queries,
allowing you to query real time data
with low latency and high concurrency.
High concurrency means these
systems can efficiently serve
many end users simultaneously.
On the other hand, asynchronous
serving of processed data
streams is managed by Kafka.
In the diagram, the two Kafka
icons represent either the same
Kafka cluster or different clusters
replicating data across them.
The key difference between synchronous
and asynchronous serving lies in
how data is consumed and delivered.
In synchronous serving, the client
requests data and waits for an immediate
response, which can lead to delays
if the data is large or complex.
Conversely, Asynchronous serving allows
clients to subscribe to data changes
and receive updates in real time without
waiting for a request response cycle.
This approach is more efficient
for handling continuous streams
of data as it enables clients to
react to changes as they occur.
Ensuring that no updates are missed.
Asynchronous systems, like those
utilizing Kafka, can handle high volumes
of data and provide a more scalable
solution for real time data processing.
Data locality and replication are
crucial concepts in the streaming plane.
For example, if your operational
data is in EMEA but you need to serve
it in APAC, you wouldn't want your
APAC systems to constantly reach
out to EMEA for real time data.
This would create latency
and potential bottlenecks.
Instead, you replicate that
data between regions, and tools
like Kafka make this easy.
By creating replicas of your
data in other regions, you ensure
that applications local to those
regions can consume streaming
data efficiently and in real time.
And keep in mind, because
this data is still within a
Kafka topic, it's streaming.
In real time, operating within
the physical limits of speed,
like the speed of light.
A materialized view is a database
object that contains the results of a
query, storing them as a physical table.
Unlike traditional views, which execute
the underlying SQL statement at query time
and do not store results, materialized
views pre compute and cache the results,
allowing for faster data retrieval.
They can be refreshed periodically or
on demand to keep the data up to date.
But in the context of stream processing,
materialized views are continuously and
incrementally updated as new data arrives.
This capability makes them particularly
valuable for improving query performance,
reducing data duplication, and simplifying
analytics, especially in environments
where real time data access is crucial.
Balancing between push and pull queries is
essential for optimizing performance and
meeting specific use case requirements.
One effective approach is to utilize
materialized views, which can act as
a bridge between the two query types.
By submitting a push query to create a
materialized view, clients can benefit
from the heavy lifting done by the push
query, while simultaneously subscribing
to changes in the materialized view.
The balance between push and
pull queries can be adjusted
based on the application's needs.
For instance, if low latency is paramount,
a greater reliance on push queries may
be warranted, while scenarios requiring
more complex queries might benefit
from the flexibility of pull queries.
Ultimately, the choice depends
on the specific requirements of
the application and the nature
of the data being processed.
The diagram that models how to
balance push and pull queries
illustrates the tradeoff between
query flexibility and latency.
It features a box in the middle
representing a materialized
view, which serves as a bridge
between the two types of queries.
As you move down the diagram, The
materialized view provides less
flexible queries but offers better
performance, meaning that the
queries execute with lower latency.
This is ideal for scenarios where
immediate data availability is critical,
such as user facing applications
that require real time updates.
Conversely, as you move up the
diagram, the queries become more
flexible, allowing for deeper
insights and more complex queries.
However, This increased flexibility
comes at the cost of higher latencies,
as a serving engine has to perform
more work to fulfill these requests.
The overall concept is that
push and pull queries can work
together to find the right balance
between latency and flexibility.
Push queries are preferred for low
latency requirements, while pull
queries offer the flexibility needed
for more complex analytical tasks.
The materialized view acts as
a compromise, allowing users
to benefit from both approaches
depending on their specific use case.
This balance is crucial for optimizing
real time analytics, as it enables
systems to react to events while
also providing the capability to
perform ad hoc queries when necessary.
Global replication and local
consumption are vital in the
streaming plane for optimizing
performance and reducing latency.
Global replication duplicates data across
multiple nodes, ensuring consistency and
enabling efficient workload distribution,
while local consumption allows for faster
access to data at its source, enhancing
performance and resource optimization.
Together, we They create a robust
framework for efficient data processing
and scalability in streaming environments,
supporting federated governance
and tailored security measures.
The streaming plane enables the
creation of virtual data products that
can be consumed locally, even if the
source of the data resides remotely.
This is achieved through a
streaming platform like Kafka.
Users can query and interact with
data locally while it is incrementally
replicated from different global regions.
A streaming data catalog is
essential to managing these
virtual data products effectively.
It serves as an inventory of data and
its metadata, enabling users to discover
and subscribe to streaming data products.
The catalog provides crucial
metadata, including table definitions,
validation rules, data types,
and lineage information, which
helps consumers understand the
data's provenance and processing.
In summary, the streaming plane
facilitates the consumption of virtual
data products that may exist remotely,
while a robust streaming data catalog
ensures effective governance and
understanding of these data products.
The Venn diagram of the
operational, analytical, and
streaming planes illustrates how
these areas of data processing
are distinct yet interconnected.
The operational plane focuses on
transaction processing and generating
real time data, while the analytical
plane is dedicated to complex tasks.