Hi everyone.
My name is P Juan from Ocean Based Global.
In the next 15 minutes, I will show
you how platform teams can run rack
semantic search analytics along a
single database platform, S code
plus vector running on Kubernetes.
The goal is simple, fewer moving parts,
lower latency, and easier governance.
For both structured and unstructured
data, all with multi-tenants
and strong consistency.
Here is today's journey.
First, I will share why AI will
close the challenge platform teams,
things like fragmented texts, high
latency, and the governance issues.
Then we will move from
real world challenges to.
To one platform solution.
Looking at how a unified
approach can simplify operations.
Next, I'll introduce Ocean based
as a unified database for modern
AI apps showing how SQL and vector
workloads ran together on Kubernetes.
Finally, we'll ramp up with some
closing source and cater with that
you can bring back to your team.
According to IDC, over 92% of global
data is now in an unstructured format.
This exactly is this data drives AI
workloads like React and semantic
search executives and IT leaders
are also recognizing this shift.
41% say rack as essential, and
over 80% believe that gene AI
models using their own enterprise
data will be K competitive edge.
And this isn't just theory.
Clo recent research shows
enterprises are moving fast.
Two thirds are already using enterprise
AI infrastructure platforms, and the
60% are embedding agent AI directly
into their core applications.
So AI workloads are no
longer experimental.
They're becoming mainstream
enterprise critical workloads and
that creates new challenges for
platform and the database team.
Which we will dive into next.
Now, if AI workloads are becoming
mainstream, the next question is, what
does this mean for our technology stack?
The real, the reality is different.
Different workloads requires very
different capability for intelligent
question and answer, charitables.
They need low latency access,
thematic search and context
awareness for log analytics.
Normally detection, it
needs high ingestion, right?
Ax search and metric aggregation for the
core business systems, it's comparing,
it needs strong consistency is a ID and
S. And because of this, organizations end
up teaching together multiple specialized
databases a transactional database,
a data warehouse, a vector database,
sometimes in a graph or NoSQL engine.
The result, the stack is getting
complicated, more system to
upgrade more ETL pipelines.
Higher cost and more risk when
workloads span across them.
From my conversation with many
platform engineers and from our
own experiences, this is what most
teams, which they had one platform
for all data workloads and a strong
consistency and a high availability.
Seamless integration with AI
pipelines, elastic scaling on
Kubernetes and UN unified access and
multi-tenants with resource isolation.
But here is the reality is they
face every day just like fragment.
Augmented the data system trade off
between performance and consistency.
Complex data movement between services,
difficult scaling across data flow
workloads, inconsistent query models
and APIs, talent interference and noise.
Neighbors.
Let me make this more concrete
with with the user case that many
enterprises are building today.
AI powered Knowledge
retrieval for internal Teams.
This is a conventional architecture
you will note, you will notice
it looks quite complicated.
There is a transactional
database for metadata.
And a vector to store.
A vector store for embedding
maybe a, maybe an elastic search
cluster for full text search.
And all of this need to be
synchronized with ETL drops.
Now, what does this mean in
practice, you'll end up maintaining
multiple databases, synchronizing,
synchronization, introduce.
Latency and inconsistency.
Each additional component adds
to the cost and operational risk.
And if one part goes down,
the whole pipeline can break.
This is exactly the kind of fragmented
stack we described earlier, how to operate
costly to scale and fragile in production.
Now here is how the team
approaches the problem.
Instead of stitching together
multiple specialized systems,
they build on ocean-based as
a unified database platform.
This allowed them to reimburse structure
and vector search in the same engine,
deploy elastically in on Kubernetes and
removes the heavy integration burden.
And as the results speak for themselves,
correl latency dropped by over 70%.
That is, that used to take offers to
refresh is now available in minutes
as the amount of integration code to
maintain has been reduced by over 40%.
So by moving to a unified data platform
engineers gen, both similarity,
simplicity, and the performance, something
that was very hard to achieve in a
conventional multi database data set up.
Let's look at a topical conventional
architecture for AI powered.
Knowledge retrieval.
When a user when a user issu issues
a query, the system needs to interact
with multiple backend systems.
First, it queries MySQL
four structured data.
Then it queries the vector
database for and embed, so
IES is involved for catching.
In total a single request
incur at least the four.
Network run trips and the end to
end latency extend 170 milliseconds.
On top of that, the platform must
maintain data consistency across
all their systems, which adds
additional complexity and overhead.
This is exactly where Commissional
architecture, Chicago multiple systems.
High latency and complex integration.
In the next slide, we will say how
we use Ocean Base simplifies their
stack and just, and reduce latency
with Ocean Base.
A user query no longer needs to
touch multiple backend systems.
Instead, the query is handled
within a single platform.
Combining both structured
and unstructured data.
As a result, the entire request only
involves one query, not multiple
round trips, end to end latency
drops to just the 50 millisecond.
Data consistency is strongly maintained
across the system at all times.
This, it treats how consolidate
consolidating your data and the
search capability into a single SQL
compatible platform can dramatically
reduce latency and simplify operations.
Here is the practical example of
what we mean by hybrid queries.
Imagine a user asking.
Recommended distance
within five 500 meters.
Average consumption below five
doors, rating about 4.4 0.5.
No queries for no queues
for the coffee shop.
Now this requires, this request
involves multiple data types, GIS
data for location and distance.
Relational data for price and rating
web, the search for thematic relevance.
In most systems, you would need to stage
together different engines to handle this.
This means multiple queries, complex
integration and added latency.
But with Ocean Base, this
entire request can be answered
within with just one SQL state.
That's the power housing of having
structured special and vector data
all unified in a single database.
It makes life much simpler for
developers and enables faster,
smarter application for users.
Let's, let me quickly walk you
through the ocean based architecture.
First data is distributed across multiple
availability zone, which means we can
scaler horizontally as workloads grow.
Onis.
Ocean base is fully containerized
supports operator based mag management
and aurora's elastic scaling
for both computer and storage.
This, mix it very cloud native
and easy to operate at scale.
Second, let's talk about
availability and consistency.
Ocean base is built on the axus
consensus algorithm with the trip
with the triple replica mechanism
across availability zones.
So even a note or zone fails.
We also have automatic failover.
And the system always
guarantees strong consistency.
In short, the architecture is designed
for elastic elasticity and resilience
and the trust trust thinners, which are
critical for AI vehicles in production.
Another important reason for
choosing ocean base is multi
tennis compat compatibility.
This means that different workloads can
run on the same ocean-based clusters while
being isolated into separated tenants.
Each talent has its own dedicated
resources, so this is so there is
no interference across workloads.
With this, you truly get one
platform for all data workloads.
The STEM engine supports O-L-O-T-P
transactions, log analysis, semantics
retrieval, and even AI applications
without needing multiple databases.
And with the unified unified access
layer, developers can use a single
SQL engine to query both structured
data and unstructured data, including
full text search and vector search.
This makes the developer and its parents
much simpler and it helps platform
teams consolidate their database tech.
As we ramp up, I'd like to
leave you with the fail case.
Takeaways.
First one, platform.
All workloads be for the next decade.
Dedicate.
With Ocean Base, you can significantly
reduce the number of systems
in your stack and cut down the
integration complexity that platform
engineers often struggle with.
Second, the same platforms just supports
both structured and unstructured data.
That means OLTP analytics.
Photo has search and even vector search
for AI workloads all in one place.
Third, ocean-based offers elastic
scaling and runs natively on es, so
it fits naturally in naturally into
modern coordinative environments.
And finally, with the fuel
systems to integrate and maintain.
Platform engineers can focus more on
delivering value to the business instead
of spending time staging system together.
That's the vision we are driving
with Ocean Base, a single unified
database platform for the next
generation of applications.
One platform, all workloads,
less complexity, more innovation.
That's the ocean-based promise.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time.
Okay.