Hello all welcome.
This is Sharon ING Hora.
I'm going to talk on Platform First.
Mobile Automation.
I have around 20 plus years of experience.
I'm working with Cognizant Technology
Solution, and I am in two 10 plus years
with mobile automation with on different
cloud platforms like cts, perfecto.
And browser stack and mobile device.
I'm available on LinkedIn for any
if we want to discuss more on this.
So I'm working with, mobile
Cloud plus AI as well.
So I thought of, presenting this PPT.
So yes, let's get started.
Platform first, mobile automation
engineering, t testing infrastructure
across enterprise ecosystem.
A technical exploration of how platform
engineering principle transform
mobile automation from isolated
QA process into integrated cell
service infrastructure that scales
across multiple cloud environments
and diverse development teams.
As we as per the first slide platform,
first mobile automation, we are talking
about the t testing infrastructure across
the various, enterprise ecosystems.
The platform engineering revolution.
So modern enterprise face complex
mobile testing challenges nowadays.
We are doing mobile automation, but
we are very complex infrastructure,
multiple device ecosystems, diverse
operating systems, versions,
varying network conditions, and
continuous delivery at a scale.
So basically, we have various
ecosystems of, available right now.
And we have diverse operating
systems like in iOS and Android.
If you see every month we have new
releases, we have new devices different
type of versions, upgrades, right?
And there are various network
conditions also associated with it.
A lot of complexity right now testing
with mobile devices and we have, native
apps or reactive web based we have
to validate test in mobile devices.
It's very complex nowadays.
And continuous delivery at a scale.
Traditional approaches with, siloed
QA teams manual infrastructure
management can't keep pace
with these demands right now.
Yes, it is very difficult.
You cannot buy each and every device.
You need some type of solution.
Where devices are available on
demand as and when need is there.
For this platform engineering reemergence,
mobile automations product, platform
engineering, obviously, they think,
this is just not a mobile automation.
It's a mobile, it's a product
rather than a service.
Okay?
It's altogether different product
because it's a big elephant nowadays
because everybody's using smart
phones, mobile devices, iOS or Android.
So it's creating a self-service, API
driven system that empower development
teams while maintaining enterprise
grade reliability and governance.
So basically, it is API driven
and it maintains enterprise
grade reliability and governance.
It is secured by government is
monitoring all those, policies,
compliance, and all those things.
Organizations implementing platform
first, mobile automation report.
Dramatic improvement in deployment,
confidence reduced time to market, enhance
ability to response to market changes.
So yes, as you see it has dramatic
improvements in deployment,
confi aggressions, reduced time
to market, and all those factors
which are associated with this.
Now we talk about
architectural foundations.
So what are these
architectural foundations like?
It is infrastructure S code.
GI tops driven deployments
like CICD, vvc, right?
We have GitLab, GitHubs multi-tenant
architecture as such, right?
So what is infrastructure as code?
It is a modern platform engineering
trade mobile testing, infrastructure
code, eliminating environment drift, and
ensuring reproducible test conditions.
So like we have Terraform Polo
or AWS, we have Azure also.
Google Cloud also, right?
This defines environment spanning
multiple cloud providers.
We, this use YML adjacent
configuration files automatically
provides appropriate resources.
Kubernetes provides runtime foundation,
which isolated secure containers.
So yes, we have Kubernetes which works
on, secure containers containerized
approach using Kubernetes.
So we have now we will talk
about GitHub's driven deployment.
Like we have testing configurations,
automation scripts and infrastructure
definitions resides in gate repositories,
enabling version control, peer review,
and automated deployment workflows.
This will change follow same rigorous
process as application code staging
environments to receive updates.
First for validation, progressive
delivery patterns, roll out new
testing capabilities gradually.
Then we are multi-tenant architecture,
enterprise platform support, multi
development teams while maintaining
strict security boundaries through
isolated testing environments.
Network segmentation ensures sensitive
testing data remains isolated.
Each tenant receives dedicated namespace
resource quotas and access controls.
And also it has role-based
access controls, integrates with
enterprise direct directories.
So basically, we are multi-tenant
architecture where we are using,
cloud-based infrastructure.
Might be A-W-S-G-C-P,
Google Cloud, or Azure.
So it is very secured and network segment
is, segmentation basically, which ensures
your data is secured enough, right?
And it has role-based access
controls by default, it is denied.
So if you have a role, it will be
given the access, like that in cloud.
This is how it works.
Now we'll talk about AI
enhance resource orchestration.
So we have modern platform engineering
incorporates artificial intelligence
to optimize mobile testing, resource
allocation, machine learning algorithms,
analyze historical testing patterns.
Predictive models consider application
release schedules, test execution
times seasonal traffic patterns
and team productivity cycles.
Intelligent test selection algorithms
identify minimum test suit required
to validate specific changes.
So basically what we are trying to
say here is AI is basically machine
learning algorithms are there, which
will analyze historical testing patterns.
So we have a lot of data from the
past, which is getting analyzed by, AI
LLMs or machine learning algorithms,
which will, which is a key for the
pattern testing and predictive model.
Consider application releases schedule.
So basically all the LLMs, ai, lms,
or, predictive models are there.
Which are based on heavy data from the
past years which will predict, which will
release the schedules, execution times,
and team productivity cycles as well.
Now we'll talk about intelligent
test selection algorithms.
Identify minimum tests suit required
to validate specific changes as such.
Because of this, machine learning, we have
intelligent test selection algorithms are.
Built in over the years which will
help us to minimize the test suit
required to validate specific changes.
So all the critical flows are
tested using, these intelligent
test selection algorithms.
These proactive approach eliminates
resource contention while minimizing
cloud computing costs, ensuring adequate
testing capacity during peak demand,
while avoiding over provisioning during.
Quite periods, yes.
So this will very cost effective
because this is on demand cloud and
resources we are using on demand.
This is a proactive approach.
So that is why, AI and Cloud helps a
lot for cost reduction for the company.
Now we will talk about some,
cross-platform compatibility, automation.
What is this comprehensive
device mattresses.
And beyond functional testing
and global device forms, what is
comprehensive device mattresses?
It is a sophisticated platform
maintain which maintains devices,
mattresses, spanning iOS, android,
and imaging platforms automatically
executing test suits across
representative device combinations.
So basically it's a mechanism which
will have the mattresses which will span
across the platforms like iOS, Android.
And which will execute test suits
across represented device combinations
on various device combinations.
It is going to, execute all
the test suits, excuse me.
And it'll also beyond functional
testing, compatibility testing,
access to performance accessibility.
So basically we are talking about
not only functional testing, we are
talking about performance accessibility.
And user experience
consistency testing as well.
It is automated with visual regression
which detects UI in across devices.
Devices are of, various
sizes and shapes, right?
We can easily, if they're UI
insistency, which we can identify
very easily using regress.
Across the devices, across the platforms.
We have, global device forms
cloud platforms are available,
like c test, which, have multiple
physical devices, perfecto.
Or we can talk about mobile
device labs or browser stack.
This will be having real devices
as well as emulators, which will
enable testing across various network
condition and regional configurations.
So based on regions, we
can select these devices.
Suppose I'm in us, I want to select,
devices in Australia because I
have a customer in Australia.
I want to see the latency,
network speed and everything.
So using these, cloud provider
providers, I can select the region
and we can test accordingly.
And that will let us know what is
going on with that region, devices,
or are we facing any issues.
So this platform orchestration,
manage device allocations, test
scheduling result aggregation.
Presenting unified compatibility
reports to development teams as such.
So this is the platform orchestration
teams, which manages all these,
devices, allocations test scheduling.
This is on the orchestration
layer of the platform, basically.
Now we'll talk about progressive
delivery integration.
So what is it?
It's a feature flag integration,
candidate deployment testing
automated roll back triggers.
What is feature flag integration
like to suppose, example.
You are going to deliver
new code in production.
And it's a very.
New functionality.
So now what you will do is you'll
slowly throttle that in production in
Android or iOS platforms, like 1%, 2%
in first few days based on the feedback.
Then you will enable that feature
flag for, 15%, 20%, and within
couple of months you will be a
hundred percent throttling that.
So that is called
feature flag integration.
Then we have candid
deployment testing, right?
What is it?
It's automatically compares mattresses
between control and experimental groups.
Detecting performance regression
crash rates, increase our
user experience degradation.
So basically what it is
doing, it just perform.
It's, it provides the mattresses ex on
the experiments detecting performance
regression crash rate, increase or
user experience degradations as well.
Now we'll talk about
automated rollback triggers.
As such, respond to testing
failures or metrics.
Degradation instantly reverting
problematic changes to protect
user experience while enabling
aggregative innovation cycles.
So we are talking about
automated rollbacks.
Say for example, if I am deploying
some new code in productions
something happens, right?
Something network problem, some code is
not working or something fails, right?
So there should be automated
rollback mechanism, right?
Which we say disaster recovery, right?
So we can make sure, we are on the
original state, previous, original state.
This is how this automated
rollback triggers.
Basically, this is for the
progressive delivery integration.
Three factors are there, as we discussed.
So these systems basically, balance
the risk and velocity in mobile
application development, providing
confidence data that informs
rollout decision at each stage.
Yes, this will, make sure every
stage we are getting the correct
information based on these flags,
deployments, or rollback triggers.
Now we talk about, industry applications
financial services, what is it?
Compliance driven automation.
So in financial sector, a data, PCI
compliance data is very important.
You cannot share data like that.
It should be compliant, mask, and,
otherwise company or financial
organization might face a lot of issues.
Or people can sue if financial data
is shared or there are some losses.
So what we are saying is financial
service organizations face unique mobile
testing challenges due to stick regulatory
requirements and security constraints.
Platform engineering
addresses these through.
So basically, financial organization
has to be PCI compliant.
It should not share the data like that.
It's a very secured industry, we can say.
So how platform engineering
address these issues through
automated compliance testing.
So yes, P-C-I-D-S-S, SOCs and Regional
Banking regulations are there, right?
Which is automated.
So that, manual you might.
Fail on something, but if processes
are automated, vetted accordingly and
this, there's less chances of failures.
And then policy as code framework, right?
That defines compliance rules
in machine readable format.
Then security testing automation
that detects vulnerable value.
It's encryption.
Ensure secure data handling.
So basically security testing is
must, and if it is automated that's
really saves a lot of time in leakages
vulnerabilities across the financial
organization with that product.
This approach transforms compliance
from a manual gatekeeper process into
an automated quality gate, dramatically
reducing regulatory review cycles by
maintaining strict security standards.
Automated reporting generates
compliance documentation.
Required for regulatory audits,
streaming government process without
sacrifice, government velocity.
So yes this is really, approach
transforms compliance from manual
gatekeeper to automated where you can
have less chances of, leakages security
issues because is automated and it's
a role-based process, basically.
Now we'll talk about industry application,
e-commerce performance at scale.
So traffic simulation engines, right?
What is performance?
So like we see traffic simulation engines.
So here, what is their model complex
Using journey including browsing,
searching, card managing, and checkout.
Process across represented
device configurations.
Realistic load patterns include
geographic distribution, device
diversity, temporal, variations that
my mirror actual shopping behavior.
So what this traffic simulation
engines is basically, let's say you
are navigating to one website, right?
So this will, simulate the traffic
patterns, load patterns, at what
time, people are visiting these sites.
What.
It's a holidays or, weekends or
what days, basically, so this
simulation engines will scale all
this automated performance monitoring.
So what it'll do is detects degradation
in real time triggering scaling actions.
So alerting operations teams to
prevent performance related incident
during peak shopping events, right?
Like we have Thanksgiving or holidays,
it's a peak shopping day, right?
Integration with content delivery
networks, edge computing platforms, and
show optimal performance well, right?
So basically in a cloud world, we
can say edge computing platforms
are platforms which are near to
that geographic locations like
we have Australia, US, or Europe.
We will be having edge
locations near to that.
Where performance, basically is more, if
I'm accessing a website from Australia,
it has a same website as more performance.
If I'm pointing that website to us,
and if I'm accessing Australia, it'll
be low latency performance, very slow.
So that is the concept of edge computing.
Now we'll talk about performance budgets.
So enforce accessible response
times, preventing performance
regressions from reaching production
and maintaining optimal user.
Experience across diverse
device ecosystems?
Yes.
So basically enforcing the
acceptable response diamonds per
preventing performance regression.
So automatically the scale
testing environments to match
production load patterns.
So basically performance budgets.
We can try to automatically
scaling testing environments.
Basically we are putting the same budget,
whatever we are doing in production, which
will scale the environment automatically.
Testing environment so that, we can
match the actual production load patterns
that is very important key feature.
Now we'll talk about, self-service,
API and developer experience.
So a successful mobile automation
patterns, prioritize developer
experience through restful
APIs, enabling programmatic
access to testing capabilities.
Okay, restful APIs they will
enable programmer technical
excel to testing capabilities.
Like we have, restful APIs where we can
directly call API services and check, we
can get the response, whether it's get or
post and accordingly validate the data.
Then graph will interface is
providing flexible queries.
We can have graph queries to
precise testing data, real time
subscription, delivering test results
and infrastructure status updates.
So real time, we can get the test results
and infrastructure status updates as well.
So we have comprehensive as d
liabilities, as well as simplifying
platform integration across
popular programming languages.
So yes, we have, these SDK libraries
available which we can integrate
to our, programming languages
across might be, Java, see whatever
language we want to integrate it.
Code generators are there creating a
boilerplate testing confi configurators.
Nowadays we have, copilot
and all those things.
We can just instruct it and
we can get the codes also.
And there are various other
code generators as well.
Interactive documentation with executable
example, demonstrate platform so we can
give interactive documentation as such.
We can have a PowerPoint interactive,
documentation, which will be show us
exactly how codes are getting executed
and how we can have those executables.
Now we'll talk about observ
observability and operational excellence.
First is comprehensive
monitoring in this section.
Then we have distributed tracing.
Then we have service level,
objective, then error budget.
So what is comprehensive monitoring?
So we are talking about, this
covers the infrastructure,
health, text execution metrics.
Developer productivity indicates
enabling productivity should
resolve capacity planning.
So basically this is overall, you can
say budgeting, monitoring of execution.
Everything comes into comprehensive
monitoring as such, right?
All the capacity planning all
type of, indicators are there.
Distributed tracing means provides
visibility into complex testing
workflows, identifying bottlenecks
and optimizing execution path
across the testing infrastructure.
What we are saying here is it'll
provide the visibility into testing
workflows, identifying bottlenecks,
if we have any bottlenecks, right?
That will optimize execution
parts as well across the testing
infrastructure, service level objectives.
Here we are talking about, defined
platform reliability expectation,
driving continuous improvements
efforts through objective criteria
for infrastructure changes.
So basically we are talking about
platform reliability, driving
continuous improvements efforts.
So this is ongoing process.
In the infrastructure for changes.
Then error budgeting.
So we should, balance innovation,
velocity, stability requirements,
providing objective criteria, managing
the pace of pattern evolution.
So here we are talking about, how
patterns are getting evaluated, right?
Accordingly, we are budgeting,
providing objective criteria.
So it should be like some
criteria driven, right?
It should not be like, we have to do
something for doing it, but it should
be business driven, criteria driven.
So now we are talking about go
governance and policy enforcement.
So here we are talking about,
enterprise platform requires governance
framework that balance developer
authority with organization control.
Here we are talking policy engines and
for security requirements, resource
limits and compliance standard.
Automated policy validation prevent
non-compliant congregations from breaching
production integration with admission
controls and validation web books and
force policies at the intersection level.
Here we are talking about cost
management policies, prevent runway
resource consumption while enabling bus
capacity for critical testing needs.
We are talking about resource quota.
Establish clear boundaries.
Budget alert, provide early
warning for potential over.
Automatic scaling policies, balance cost,
testing of effectiveness, regular policy
reviews, ensure governance framework
evolve with changing organizational needs.
So basically what we are talking about
is a government policies we should
be up to date and we have to make
sure we are reviewing our policy on
daily basis so that we are compliant
with the GO governance framework.
And government policies as such.
Now we'll talk about future directions,
where we have to go from here.
So we are talking about edge
computing and 5G integrations.
So edge, a native testing, validation,
application performance under the
i low latency conditions while
ensuring compatibility across
diverse edge computing environments.
Like we have spoken about, edge locations.
What is edge location?
Edge locations means, if I am in
Australia, I'm accessing some website
or from mobile devices, right?
So I will be hitting a
nearby edge locations where
performance is good, right?
Although that website is hosted in
us, but through Azure locations,
it performance is very fast.
Then we are talking 5G network
Simulation EN enables testing of
advanced mobile capability, including
augmented realtime ion IOT integration.
So we are talking about
here 5G integration.
Sustainable testing practices, carbon
aware testing schedule, shift resource
intense operations to periods when
renewable energy availability is
highest reducing environmental impact.
Green software engineering principle
guide platform development,
ensuring environmental constitution
influence architectural decisions.
So basically we have to be, make sure
it's environmental and, engineering
principles are implemented accordingly.
So we should follow good practices always.
Now we'll talk about
implementation strategy.
So first is build a strong foundation.
Yes.
We have to focus on infrastructure,
comprehensive observability, developer
centric design for building a strong
foundation enable self services.
So we have to make sure
every developer is self ent.
We have proper documentation, SD,
SDKs intuitive APIs, libraries,
so that, it should be integrated
testing into their workflows.
Developers should integrate the same.
Implement governance.
So we should, balance developer
autonom organization control through
policy engine that enforce security
compliance and resource manage
management, which is very important here.
It evolve continuously.
So we have to learn and
evolve continuously.
We have to add whatever the new data
we are reading new testing techniques
it's evolving process basically.
A data drive iterative
improvement, scaling platform
capabilities as they matured and
adopting emerging technologies.
These elements enable iterative
improvement, scaling as platform
capabilities mature, creating
the foundation for sustainable
growth and continuous innovation.
Now we'll talk about the
strategic, imperative.
So platform first, mobile automation
represents a fundamental shift in
how enterprise approach testing
infrastructure by treating
testing capabilities as product.
Yes, rather than sources.
So this mobile infrastructure
testing, all this is like a product.
Okay.
We should read all together
as a different product.
Mobile testing.
It should not be treated to the services
organization, achieve unprecedented scale
reliability and developer productivity.
Team, the transformation extends beyond
operational efficiency to strategic
advantage, enabling what this will enable.
Faster time to market, enhanced
competitive positioning,
improved deployment confidence,
a reduced operational overhead.
Organizations that master these
capabilities will define the future of
mobile application development, setting
new standards for quality, velocity
and scale in the digital economy.
So mobile is the future, right?
We have a smartphone and Android, iOS.
So we have to make sure, all the
organization understand that these
capabilities and it should be treated
as a product, not as in service.
Oh, okay.
So we come to the last slide.
Thank you very much for
listening me and watching me.
And in case of any questions,
KU as I told in beginning right,
I am available on LinkedIn.
You can search by chair and
preaching who, and we can connect
there and discuss more over there.
Thank you very much.
Good day.
Bye.