Hello everyone.
This is Uluru.
Today's focus is on building a resilient,
automated monitoring platform for voice or
IT systems and how this approach reflects
a broader shift in platform engineering.
Clear, reliable voice calls matter,
whether from business or personal chats.
Keeping those systems humming
is no small fe, and this
presentation shows how it's done.
The platform predicts issues
before they disrupt calls.
Streamlining work for developers.
Let's start with the big picture.
Platform engineering has evolved
from reactor maintenance to
intelligent predictive operations.
Modern infrastructure demands, monitoring
systems that detect and resolve
issues before end users are affected.
The resolution presented here.
The solution presented here
is a centralized platform that
emphasizes automation, scalability,
and seamless integration with
the development workflows.
This is not just another dashboard
producing endless alerts.
It is an intelligent system capable
of rapidly identifying genuine
issues, minimizing operational
burden on reducing costs.
The emphasis on secure
service interrupt disruptions.
Faster innovation.
Picture, a monitoring system that
doesn't just flag problems, it
stops them before they start.
First, let's explore the
challenges this platform tackles
monitoring distributed system often feels
like chaos, disconnected tools, also
alarms and time consuming manual fixes.
IP Systems introduce complex heterogeneous
environments with fragmented visibility.
Traditional monitoring causes alert
fatigue due to false positives while
manual remediation, slow recovery.
The platform was designed to address all
these problems simultaneously providing
accuracy, speed, and self-op optimization.
This platform uses machine learning
to solve real issues, predict trends
and learns from past patterns, all
the while cutting through the marks.
How does this happen?
It starts with platform
engineering principles.
A strong platform should be
invisible, meaning, reliable,
stable, and low maintenance.
Platform engineering
builds infrastructure.
The developers' log monitoring
infrastructure must be treated as
a product with user experience,
reliability, and continuous improvement
as core priorities In real time
communications such as voice or ip,
there is no tolerance for delays.
Reliability must be absolute.
The platform hangs routine tasks.
Screening developers to focus on
creating with clear insights when needed.
And let's look at
architecture that powers this.
Imagine a system built for
flexibility, speed, and handling
any challenging thrown at it.
Microservices provide modularity
and independent scaling.
Apache Kafka forms the backbone
enabling high throughput fault
tolerance telemetry streaming.
A plugin based ingestion layer
collects data from diverse
voiceover IT and environment.
Prometheus and Elastic Stack deliver
deeper metrics, logging and visualization.
These tools are selected because they
are proven and they're highly scalable.
They're open source.
The architecture ensures scalability
and fault tolerance without redesign.
It is like a toolbox for voiceover.
IP monitoring works with
any setup, no hassle.
Let's zoom in on how these
pieces come together.
Data flows from call quality metrics.
Network indicators and system
performance that will diverse
data into realtime pipelines.
Machine learning, analyzes telemetry,
continuously dashboards, alerts,
and automated remediation are
produced from this unified flow.
This is not just data collection, it
is continuous learning and adaptation.
This diagram maps the journey from raw
wise or IP data to actionable insights.
Solve metrics, network stacks, flow
through Kafka, get processes instantly
with fine tuned machine learning
models, and appear as dashboards
or alerts or automatic fixes.
Developers access these insights, writing
their tools, APIs ID plugins, and so on.
Machine learning plays a huge role here.
Let's dive into that.
Machine learning algorithms, establish
baseline performance patterns and
detect subtle degradations early.
False positives are reduced by
distinguishing normal variation
from real issues, quality prediction
models, forecast feature performance
trends, enabling proactive
intervention before users are affected.
This represents a shift from reactive
monitoring to intelligent production.
If call quality drops, the system knows.
If it's a blip or a problem,
avoiding pointless alert, your
false alarms and proactive fixes
keep users happy without the chaos.
This predicts, this predictive power
needs a fast processing system.
Let's check that out.
Using a Lambda architecture,
the system combines.
Millisecond level streaming
and it's alerts with batch
analytics for deeper insights.
This platform uses a dual approach,
instant alerts for argent tissue,
and deeper analysis for print builtin
back pressure mechanism prove prevent
overload during the traffic spikes event
Correlation identifies root causes.
Minimizing cascading failures
and unnecessary alerts.
Features like circuit breakers
and event correlation keeps
things steady even during traffic
spikes and pinpoint root causes.
Parting issues is one thing.
Fixing them automatically
is where the magic happens.
Issue detection, trigger
automated response.
Validated remediation actions are selected
based on severity and historical success.
When a glitch appears, the platform
doesn't just send an alert.
It takes the best fix checks
if it's safe, and replace it.
Procedures execute safely with
the drive canary deployments
and rollback mechanisms.
Every action improves feature responses.
The system continuously learns from
outcomes, delivering self-healing
infrastructure with guardrails.
This automation lets teams focus on
building rather than firefighting.
Developers benefit big
time from this setup.
Let's see how.
Monitoring must enhance, not
hinder developer workflows.
The platform is designed
to make developers' lives
easier, not add complexity.
And API first designs offers programmatic
access to the configuration and data.
CICD integration deploys monitoring
upgrades alongside application code.
Issues can be caught locally
before code ever hits production.
Local monitoring and ID plugins provide
realtime insights without extra overhead,
and it's not just user-friendly.
It saves money too.
There's no point in developing
intelligent monitoring systems if the
benefits do not outweigh the costs.
It is important to keep the cost low.
Smart data management and streamlined
workflows deliver top tier
monitoring without a hefty price tag.
Intelligent data lifecycle management
reduces storage costs by 65%.
Stream processing optimization
delivers 40% higher efficiency.
Right sizing and workload elimination
achieve 30% reduce resource savings.
This makes the monitoring both
comprehensive and cost efficient.
This platform doesn't just save costs.
It's built to grow
the platform processes, massive telemetry
volumes with millisecond alerting latency.
Oriental Scaling supports future
growth while predictive scaling.
Anticipates.
Demand reliability is validated through
load testing, chaos engineering, and the
meta monitoring of the platform itself.
Sophisticated caching and
benchmarking maintain exceptional
performance under stress.
So how does this get rolled out?
Let's talk best practices.
Key success factors include
infrastructure as code for
repeatable, auditable deployments.
Comprehensive integration testing for
realistic validation, team training
and knowledge transfer for operational
independence, incremental adoption to
deliver quick wins and build confidence.
Start small, see quick wins, and
scale up as confidence works.
This platform is not standing stake.
Let's look at what's next.
Plan enhancements include
advanced AI models with a deeper
understanding and exploding smarter
AI for trickier predictions to
keep the number of false possible.
Insignificant Native Cloud integration
with service measures, serverless and eeb.
P. S observability, edge computing
support for constrained and environments
immersive visualization in Q2 navigation
for complex systems, the future of
monitoring is about staying ahead, and
this platform is leading the charge.
Let's wrap up with what
this means for everyone.
This monitoring platform demonstrates
how modern platform engineering
can transform operations.
This platform transforms monitoring into
something smart, scalably and developer
friendly spliting infrastructure as a
product enables continuous improvement,
scalability, and reliability.
It's more than tech.
It's a way to build infrastructure
that teams love, balancing
reliability and innovation.
Intelligent automation turns
reactive monitoring into predictive
self-optimizing infrastructure.
Consider how this approach can
elevate systems and drive progress.
Thank you.