Hello and welcome to Con Session.
My name is Pu and the topic of my
presentation is Beyond Native Automation,
how RPS Superchargers Salesforce.
In this session we'll be discussing
how robotic process automation can be
integrated with Salesforce to achieve
seamless end-to-end process automation.
We will examine the challenges enterprise
has faced in connecting diverse
systems, legacy systems, analyze the
strengths and limitations of Salesforce
native automation tools, study.
And demonstrate how RPA Bridges
critical integration gaps, especially
these gaps will occur while we are
using any kind of legacy systems.
This session will provide you with
a complete understanding of where
RPA adds value, how it works in
conjunction with Salesforce, and the
measurable business benefits that
results from this combined approach.
So for today's agenda, we'll be discussing
about the integration challenges.
Where we will outline the complexity of
modern enterprise technology ecosystem.
Second, we'll discuss about the
native Salesforce limitations.
We'll also discuss about what Salesforce
provides us and its limitations
identifying the specific scenarios
where data tools are not enough.
Next, we'll be discussing about how
RPA can act as a bridge, which will
explain how RPA can overcome these
limitations that the Salesforce has.
Fourth, we'll be discussing some
real world integration scenarios,
which which many of us might
have overcome in our experience.
And we'll also discuss some
practical examples from
different industries as well.
And finally, we'll also look at benefits
and future outlook where we will summarize
the advantages of this approach and
look ahead to emerging opportunities.
Let us begin by exploring the integration
challenge that exists in nearly.
Almost most of the enterprises
that we have that we have.
So in today, in almost every
organization today, the technology
landscape is a mixture of different
generation and types of systems.
There are more than SaaS platforms,
longstanding ERP systems, custom built
applications, industry specific tools,
and in many cases legacy systems
that have been in place for decades.
Salesforce has become the leading CRM,
also customer relationship management
platform, and is often at the center
of digital transformation initiatives.
It is, its automation capabilities are
strong and its ecosystem is extensive.
However, even with these trends,
Salesforce cannot on its own, achieve
complete frictionless automation
across every system in the enterprise.
This is not a shortcoming
of Salesforce as a platform.
Rather, it's a reflection of the
reality in which enterprises operate.
Not all systems have modern APIs.
Some processes still depends on physical
documentation or offline workflows.
Others require human interaction
with outdated interfaces.
These realities create integration
challenges that cannot be solved
with NATO sales post tools alone.
Next we'll talk about the en
the enterprise integration gap.
Integration gaps typically occur in
four main areas, modern APIs that
still require middleware and careful
orchestration, middleware and connectors
that introduce complexity and cost.
External portals that require
manual data transfer and file
based processes involving Excel
CSV PDFs and similar formats.
And finally, legacy systems with
proprietary or terminal based interfaces.
These gaps result in manual work,
increase cycle times and higher costs.
Enterprises that implement RPA
alongside Salesforce often.
Report measurable predictive gains as
manual processing time per employee
per week is significant, significantly
reduced, and also in many cases,
we might not find the right or the
best resource that can still work on
legacy systems or even any developers
that still work on legacy systems.
Now let's discuss about native
Salesforce automation tools.
Salesforce provides several
native automation capabilities.
The first one of which Salesforce
have improved a lot is flows.
Visual workflow builder that
allows administrators to create
complex logic without writing code.
Enterprise grade developments can,
processes, can process hundreds
of transactions per second.
We, we have the standard APEX programming,
which is a proprietary programming
language, enabling developers to
build custom logic and sophisticated
integrations covering most business
use cases when properly architected.
We have the standard web services
that Salesforce provides as well,
including rest and soap APIs to expose.
Salesforce functionality.
Externally, I'm the bulk API for high
volume of synchronous data processing.
We have platform events which enable
event driven real time integrations
between Salesforce and external systems.
While these tools are really powerful,
we might still have difficulties
communicating with some of the
systems that we have discussed,
like Excel or legacy systems.
It all, it also depends on what
the target system provides, right?
Next, let's discuss where
Natto tools falls out.
As I was saying, so natto Salesforce
automation tools, face limitations in four
key areas, legacy system integrations.
Systems without APIs require manual
data entry or specialized connectors.
File-based processes such as handling
Excel spreadsheets, PDF PDFs, or scan
forms that require human processing,
external web portals where data
must be transferred manually between
applications, cross system orchestration.
When workflows span multiple systems
with varied integration capabilities,
making end-to-end automation difficult,
these scenarios require an alternate
approach to achieve full automation,
RPA, the bridge between Salesforce
and the enterprise Robotic Process
automation represents a shift in how
integration can be achieved instead of
relying only on the APIs and middleware.
RPA operates at the user interface level.
Just as a human user word, but faster,
more accurately, and without fat fatigue.
RPA can be used to replace tedious manual
work that has to be done on a daily
basis, where the system can handle all the
clicks and the automation that the u the
manual automation that a person can do.
RPA can take over all
of those capabilities.
So performance assessments should
show that RPA bots deliver exceptional
accuracy in UI interactions.
And can reduce processing
times dramatically.
This approach allows integration
with systems that otherwise cannot
be connected natively extending
Salesforce automation capabilities
across the entire enterprise ecosystem.
Now, let's discuss how RPA complements
Salesforce RPA enhances Salesforce
automation in four distinct ways.
Navigate any interface.
RPA bots can work with web browsers,
desktop applications, terminal
emulators, and even Citrix environments.
This reduces integration development
time compared to API based approaches
process unstructured data when
combined with AI capabilities like
OCR and Natural Language Processing.
RPA can extract data from documents.
Emails and images with high accuracy.
Maintain audit trail,
every bot action is logged.
Providing visibility for compliance
and troubleshooting and improving
incident detection rates.
Scale on demand.
Bots can be scaled instantly to
match workload demands, handling
complex workflows without
additional administrative overhead.
These trends make RPA and Salesforce
together a powerful combination
for enterprise automation.
Now let's discuss some real
world integration scenarios.
So first, let's go with order processing.
In an automated order processing workflow,
a board moer Salesforce for new orders.
Let's say, oh, here we
are integrating with SAP.
It logs into the SAP interface, navigates
to the correct screens and enters.
The bot itself can type
in the order details.
It captures the confirmation number
and updates Salesforce automatically
any exceptions are flagged for human
review, and these exceptions can
be reported in Salesforce as well.
This automation achieves substantial
annual savings and reduce both cycle
times and error rates to minimal level.
As I was saying, when we combine RPA and
Salesforce, it uses more powerful tool
than Salesforce, working by itself with
the standard or native APIs that we have.
Next, let's discuss about real world
integration scenario Invoice processing.
Invoice processing often involves multiple
formats and manual validation steps.
The RPS solution is as follows,
OCR technology extracts
data from scanned invoices.
The bot validates this data against
purchase orders in Salesforce.
Approved invoices are entered into
the accounting system, discrepancies
generate Salesforce cases for review.
This reduces handling time from
minutes to seconds per documents.
And improves accuracy significantly.
With this, it helps us read the document.
RPA itself can help us read the document
and also if there's any data that has
to be stored that is in the document
back into Salesforce as on a particular
record that is possible as well.
Now for next scenario, let's
discuss real world integration
scenario compliance data collection.
Manual compliance checks require
staff to visit numerous websites,
search for providers, and copy
credential information into Salesforce.
With the help of RPA, bots accesses
licensing websites on a schedule, this
search for providers listed in Salesforce.
They capture license status,
expiration dates, and other details.
Salesforce records are updated
automatically, as we saw in our
previous example where RPA can read
a document and update Salesforce back
with the data that's in the document.
Similarly, in this example, RPA can
still go to go through different
websites, gather information from their
store it in rp, and at the final step
we can update it back to Salesforce.
Organizations benefit from
lower audit preparation costs
fewer compliance, penalities,
and substantial annual savings.
Let's discuss.
Let's go through a basic
technical architecture of RPS
Salesforce integration it.
The technical architecture includes
four pillars, monitoring and
governance, centralized observability,
dashboards, alerting, and SLA
management integration patterns.
Clear separation of bot initiative versus
Salesforce initiative flows aligned to
system constraints and latency needs.
Security framework least privilege
access, credential, valuing auditability
and compliance control, development and
environment, standardized pipelines,
version control environments.
For Dow Test and PRO and repeated
developments, organizations are
adopting tightly integrated.
API first designs in concert with
RPA typically achieve higher through
throughput and lower latency than
traditional middleware only solutions.
Next, let's discuss some
integration patterns.
There are two primary patterns,
bot initiated actions.
Bots call Salesforce, REST APIs
to trigger workflows and update
records achieving significant
latency reduction for certain steps.
Bot bots can interact directly
with Salesforce UI when needed.
Bots can publish platform events
to initiate real time processing
with strong data consistency.
Next is gonna be Salesforce initiated
automation outbound messages from
Salesforce Notify RPA Orchestrators
to Start Bots Platform events
are consumed by RPA listeners
to launch tasks in real time.
Custom Epic scholars can invoke bot
endpoint supporting higher stride.
Through processing rates.
Selecting the pattern depends on
the system of record, transaction
volume, latency requirements,
and operational controls.
Now let's discuss some benefits of
native RP integration in Salesforce.
Some of the key benefits include single
vendor, red, reduced procurement and
contract management overhead, consistent
user experience, lower integration related
incidents within a unified architecture.
Integrated governance where we can
have faster security administration
and audit preparation, simplified
licensing and training where it
helps us lower enablement costs.
These advantages translate directly into
lower operational costs and strong ROI.
Let's discuss some
implementation best practices.
Effective implementation
follows three best practices.
Start with process discovery.
Document current manual steps.
Identify systems without APIs and
calculate RI to prioritize use cases.
It's always start small.
We don't have to build a complicated
process where we want to replace
RPA, so we gotta start small.
Understand how RPA works better for,
again, for every individual company.
Design for resilience, implement rigorous
error handling, fallback parts for
system downtime, proactive notifications
and plan maintenance windows.
Maintain human oversight, configure
exception workflows with high first time
resolution, provide performance dashboards
and institute approvals where appropriate.
We also want, we also need to make
sure that when RPA as, when the bot is
interacting with a particular website,
or if it's interacting with a particular
screen, whenever there's any kind of
upgrade done to the website we have to
make sure that same kind of maintenance
is done to the bots as well, so that
the click that, that the bot does.
Still works as expected these
approaches and ensure reliability
while preserving control.
Next, let's discuss some successes,
some KPIs and metrics here.
And average 80% reduction in processing
time because it's gonna reduce
manual, manual effort, drastically
95% improvement in error rates.
Again, that's a very high chance of, it's
a manual process for there to be errors
and three times increase in volume handle.
Qualitative benefits include higher
employee satisfaction, faster
customer delivery times fewer
compliance penalities, and improved
scalability for high volume scenarios.
Next, let's discuss some industry
specific applications and ROI.
In healthcare, automated
credentialing reduces audit costs
and integrate legacy systems.
There are still a lot of companies
where there are legacy systems which
do not have proper APIs, where that
is where RPA can come in and help
integrate with those legacy systems
and also speed up the process.
In manufacturing, all
cycle times are reduced.
Customer satisfaction improves
and repeat business' increases in
financial services, document processing
costs, job and accuracy for standard
documents remains near perfect.
Some of this, some of the main, one of
the main benefit, as we discussed was
where RPA can help read through the
document and scan through it completely,
process the data and update it back to
Salesforce, where the data that's in the
document can be reported in Salesforce.
Future outlook, the evolution
of enterprise automation.
The next phase is the convergence of
RPA, AI and CRM, intelligent processing
automation, AI driven decision
making, NLP and predictive analytics,
hyper automation, orchestrating
millions of transactions daily.
And finally, digital twins maintaining
real time process models for optimization.
These capabilities will accelerate
digital transformation and reduce
technical resource requirements.
Embracing the automation imperative.
The integration of Salesforce CRM and RPA
represents more than a technical upgrade.
It is the strategic
imperative by leveraging CRM.
Integration and RPA Legacy connectors.
Together organizations create
end-to-end automation without
replacing existing infrastructure.
Research across hundreds of enterprises
shows that tightly integrated R-P-S-C-R-M
strategies correlate with higher rates
of digital transformation success, and
substantial higher return on investment.
And some of the key takeaways that we
have that we discussed are RPA bridges the
gap between Salesforce and Legacy systems
enabling full end-to-end automation.
The measurable benefits span
industries and includes significant
R-O-I-R-P-A enhances rather
than replaces human potential.
With RPA human error
can be reduced to none.
Basically none.
The time to implement is now to
maintain competitive advantage.
Thank you for attending this session.
The integration of RPA with Salesforce
is not simply a technical improvement.
It is a strategic imperative
for organizations seeking to
lead in a digital first world.
Again, Thank you for
attending this session.
Take care.