I'm excited to share with you today
at COM 42 platform engineering 2024 as
we discuss enhancing cloud computing
security, multi layer protection
and advanced threat detection.
As organizations increasingly rely on
cloud technologies, ensuring robust
security has never been more critical.
Today, I'll guide you through the key
strategies and technologies that can
help protect your cloud environments.
Let's start by looking at what
we'll cover in this presentation.
First, we start with an introduction
to cloud computing and security,
where we will set the stage by
discussing the fundamentals of
cloud computing and why security
is so crucial in this environment.
we'll dive into the cloud computing
security challenges that our organizations
face today, exploring the various
risks and vulnerabilities that are
inherent in cloud environments.
Following that, we'll move on to
a multi layer protection approach,
where I'll explain how implementing
security at various levels within cloud
can help mitigate these challenges.
Then we'll discuss advanced threat
detection techniques, focusing on
the tools and technologies that
can identify and utilize threats
before they can cause any harm.
After that, we'll look at proactive
measures you can take into, to reduce
breach times, helping to minimize
the impact of any security incidents.
To ground our discussion in
real world application, we'll
review some case studies as well.
Finally, we'll conclude by
summarizing the key takeaways.
and exploring future trends in cloud
security, which will provide insights
into how the security landscape is going
to evolve and what organizations can
do to stay ahead before we dive deeper.
Let's take a closer look at
the security landscape of cloud
computing has an integral part of
how organizations operate today, and
its growth is nothing remarkable.
First, cloud computing is rapidly growing
spending expected to reach a staggering 1.
2 trillion by 2025.
This quote reflects how essential cloud
services have become for businesses
of all sizes, enabling them to scale,
innovate, and operate more efficiently.
However, as more organizations migrate
to the cloud, securing these environments
is becoming a critical challenge.
Unlike traditional IT infrastructure,
cloud environments are dynamic
and distributed, which introduces
unique security complexities.
Cloud computing has revolutionized the
way organizations manage and store data,
instead of relying on premise servers.
Companies can now leverage the
flexibility and scalability of the
cloud to store vast amounts of data and
access it from anywhere in the world.
This revolution in data management
has led to significant advancements
in how businesses operate, making
them more agile and responsive.
But with these advancements
come new challenges.
The dynamic nature of cloud
environments means that security
measures must constantly evolve
to keep up with the new threats.
Traditional security models
are often not enough to protect
cloud resources, requiring a more
sophisticated multilayered approach.
This bar chart illustrates the increasing
rate of cloud adoption from 2018 to 2023.
The adoption rate shows a steady growth,
emphasizing the rising importance of cloud
services and consequently cloud security.
The rapid growth in cloud adoption
highlights the need for robust
cloud security measures as more
organizations rely on cloud services.
Given this trend, let's discuss why
security is so crucial in cloud computing.
As businesses increasingly rely on
cloud services, the potential for
data breaches, unauthorized access,
and other security incidents grow.
Protecting sensitive information, ensuring
compliance with regulatory requirements,
and maintaining trust with customers
are just a few reasons why robust
cloud security measures are essential.
By implementing comprehensive
security strategies, organizations
can mitigate risks and protect
their assets in the cloud.
Now let's explore some of the specific
challenges that cloud security presents.
Cloud computing a range of security
challenges that organizations must
address to protect their data and
maintain trust with customers.
As cloud environments grow in complexity,
these challenges become more pronounced
and require innovative solutions.
This includes the risk of data
breaches, insecure APIs, insider
threats, compliance and legal
issues, and a lack of feasibility.
Addressing these challenges
effectively requires a multi
layer approach to security.
Let's tell you into what that involves.
Multilayer protection, in cloud
computing involves, implementing
security measures at various levels
within the cloud environment.
This approach ensures that even if
one layer is compromised, others
remain intact to protect the system.
This importance of a multilayer security
strategy lies in, in its ability
to, to address diverse threats and
vulnerabilities, providing a robust
defense against potential attacks.
we look at what are the different
layers of protection are and also how
data flows through these different
security layers in a cloud environment.
This diagram illustrates the multi
layer protection approach in cloud
security, which involves implementing
security measures across various
levels of the cloud environment.
Each layer serves a specific purpose,
from network security at the base, to
identify and access management at the top.
This ensures comprehensive protection
against a wide area of threats.
By integrating multiple layers of
security, organizations can create
a comprehensive framework that's
difficult for attackers to penetrate.
Each layer reinforces the others,
providing a strong defensive mechanism
against a wide array of cyber threats.
flowchart represents how data
moves through a different security
layers in a cloud environment.
This includes network security,
application security, data encryption,
IAM, and endpoint security.
Each layer of security plays a critical
role in protecting data as it moves
through the cloud infrastructure, ensuring
comprehensive coverage against threats.
Let's now move on to the step by step
implementation of multi layered security.
Multi layered security approach is
essential for ensuring that each
layer of your cloud environment is
protected, providing comprehensive
defense against a wide array of threats.
We begin by securing the
network infrastructure.
This includes implementing
firewalls to filter traffic.
deploying intuition and detection
and prevention system, which
monitors and block malicious
activities and ensures that secure
network protocols are in place.
security serves as first line of
defense preventing unauthorized access
and safeguarding the communication
channels within your cloud environment.
Once the network is secure, the next step
is to focus on application level security.
This involves implementing secure coding
practices to reduce vulnerabilities
during the development process, conducting
regular vulnerability assessments, To
identify this and potential weaknesses
and managing patches to keep all
applications up to date within
the security latest security fixes
application security ensures
that the software running in your
environment is resilient to attacks.
Next, we need to protect the data
needs to be protected at when it is
stored and also when it is transmitted
encrypting sensitive data using strong
up to date encryption algorithms ensures.
That even if an attacker gains access
to the data, they won't be able to read
or use it without the encryption key.
Encryption acts as a vital safeguard
against data breaches and loss.
Next, managing who has access
to the cloud resources is a
critical aspect of security.
Deploying IAM solutions to control and
monitoring access, ensuring that only
authorized users can reach sensitive
data and systems, implementing role
based access controls, PCM is permissions
according to the user's roles, and
uses multi factor authentication,
adds an additional layer of security.
IAM and ensures that users only
have access to the data they need.
Finally, we secure all endpoints that
connect to the cloud environment.
This includes mobile devices,
laptops, and all servers.
Deploying antivirus software and
endpoint detection response solutions
to monitor and protect these devices
from malware and other threats.
Endpoint security is the
last line of defense.
Next, we'll discuss some
common pitfalls to avoid, when
implementing these measures.
The common pitfalls include
overlooking endpoint security,
inadequate employee training, and not
regularly updating security protocols.
These oversights can
create vulnerabilities in
your security frameworks.
To effectively implement multi layer
protection, organizations should follow
best practices, such as regular security
assessments, employee training, and
the use of advanced security tools.
Continuous monitoring and updating of
security protocols are also crucial
in adapting to evolving threats.
Collaboration with cloud service providers
to understand shared responsibility models
is essential to ensure that security
measures are aligned and effective.
Next, encryption plays a
vital role in cloud security.
So let's explore some techniques
used in cloud environments.
is a fundamental aspect of cloud
security, which ensures that data is
protected both at rest and in transit.
By converting data into a secure
format, which is unremovable without
the correct decryption key, encryption
techniques in cloud security
include asymmetric encryption,
symmetric encryption, symmetric
encryption, homomorphic encryption.
Each technique has its strength, and the
choice depends on the specific security
needs and the type of data being put in.
Let's look at how these encryption
techniques are utilized in practice with
a focus on the most commonly used ones.
This pie chart shows the distribution
of encryption techniques used
in cloud environments with
AES 256 leading its usage.
The popularity of it indicates
it effectiveness and reliability
in securing data, making it a
perfect choice in cloud security.
We also have DLS, and
used apart from a S two.
Encryption is crucial, but
advanced state requires more
sophisticated, detection methods.
Let's now explore the stages
of an advanced persistence.
The chart here shows the stages
of an advanced persistence threat
from initial recognizance to
the completion of the mission.
Understanding these stages is crucial for
implementing timely and effective threat
detection and responsive strategies.
Early detection is key to mitigating the
impact of these sophisticated threats.
To address these threats,
organizations need advanced
threat detection technologies.
Let's discuss some of
these technologies next.
Advanced threats in cloud computing
are sophisticated attacks that often
bypass traditional security measures.
These threats may include advanced
persistence threats, zero day
exploits, and targeted attacks.
To combat these, organizations need to
deploy state of the art technologies
that can detect and respond to
malicious activities in real time.
Technologies such as Intuition Detection
Systems, Behavioral Analytics, Machine
Learning Algorithms, and Threat
Intelligent Platforms are essential.
Several case studies highlight the
effective, effectiveness of these
technologies in real world scenarios.
Now let's move on to the importance
of say regular security updates and
audits in maintaining cloud security.
Regular security updates and audits
are essential components of a
comprehensive cloud security strategy.
By keeping security systems up
to date and conducting thorough
audits, organizations can identify
vulnerabilities, ensure compliance, and
mitigate risks before they are exploited.
Automated update mechanisms and batch
management systems are critical to
this process, which ensures consistency
and prominence across all systems.
Let's visualize the impact of
regular updates and audits on
reducing vulnerabilities that
are with a comparison chart.
This bar chart compares the number
of vulnerabilities before and
after implementing regular separate
security updates and audits.
There is a significant reduction in
vulnerabilities post updates, if you see.
Highlighting the effectiveness of these
practices in enhancing the overall
security posture of an organization.
Proactive measures coupled
with real world insights can
significantly reduce breach times.
Let's explore some proactive
measures and case studies.
Proactive security measures
have often proven effective in
various real world scenarios.
These measures include regular
vulnerability assessments,
penetration testing, security audits.
These height organizations
identify and address weaknesses
before they can be exploited.
Additionally, implementing secure
security automation and orchestration
tools allow for faster response times
and reduces the risk of human error.
One of the key benefits of proactive
security measures is the reduction in
breach detection and response time.
Let's dive deeper into the
importance of reducing breach
times and the strategies involved.
Reducing the time it takes to detect and
respond to security breaches is critical.
This can be achieved through
rapid detection using advanced
threat detection techniques.
Continuous monitoring and
automated response mechanisms
such as security orchestration
automation and response tools.
Integrating security tools and platforms
streamlines the incident response
and developing incident response
playbooks ensures swift and effective
responses to To illustrate the impact,
let's look at how proactive security
measures can significantly reduce
breach detection and response times.
This line graph shows how breach
detection and response times decrease
over a year after implementing
proactive security measures.
What detection and response times
show a significant reduction.
Underscoring the importance of
continuous monitoring and automation in
maintaining a secure cloud environment.
Now let's take a look at some security,
specific security tools, starting
with tech intelligence platforms.
Intelligence platform or in short
PIP is designed to help organizations
aggregate, analyze, and act upon threat
data to improve their security posture.
Firstly, PIPs gather data
from multiple sources.
This source includes open source
feeds, commercial vendors, and
internal threat intelligence.
By pulling data from various data
streams, Tips provide a comprehensive
view of potential threats.
Next, the platform processes
the aggregated data.
Through advanced analysis, tips identify
potential threats, turning raw data into
actionable insights for security teams.
Now let's discuss how tips
can actively prevent breaches.
Tips collect data from various sources.
including, like I said, open source
feeds, commercial threat intelligence
providers, internet, internal
security logs, and much more.
This step ensures that the
platform has a wide and detailed
view of the threat landscape.
Next, we have threat analysis
using advanced algorithms, machine
learning, and correlation engines.
TIPS analyze this data to identify
patterns and potential threats.
This capability allows tips
to detect anomalies that might
indicate malicious activities.
Finally, tips generate actionable
intelligence that can be used to update
security policies, configure intelligent
detective detection systems, and
automate responses to detected threats.
This process enables organizations
to respond swiftly and
effectively to potential threats.
By integrating TIPS into your security
infrastructure, you enhance your ability
to detect, analyze, respond to threats
in real time, providing a significant
boost to your overall security position.
Now let's look at some of the key
benefits of Threat Intelligence Platform.
TIPS centralizes threat data and applies
sophisticated analysis techniques,
which significantly improves both the
accuracy and speed of threat detection.
This capability is crucial for
identifying potential threats
before they can cause harm.
TIPS empower organizations to
stay ahead of emerging threats
by continuously monitoring and
analyzing global threat landscapes.
This proactive approach helps
you anticipate and mitigate
attacks before they happen.
insights provided by TIPS are
enabled quicker, more informed
responses to security incidents.
By reducing response times, TIPs
help minimize the damage caused
by breaches, protecting your
organization's critical assets.
In summary, TIPs play a vital role
in modern cybersecurity strategies,
enhancing threat detection,
enabling proactive defense, and
stimulating incident response.
This diagram visually represents the flow
and, integration of a threat intelligence
platform within your security framework.
We have threat intelligence platform,
which has aggregated aggregation of data.
and then, using aggregation data, we
have, data analysis and actionable
intelligence, generated by the TIP.
This integration ensures a dynamic
and responsive, security framework.
Each component works in concert
to protecting your organizations
from a wide array of threats.
Now let's dive into Intuition Detection
System, and IDS in short, monitors
network traffic from suspicious
activity and potential threats.
This helps in alerting security
teams to any anomalies that
could indicate a security breach.
Ideas can be classified into two
types, one being network based ideas
and the other being host based ideas.
Network based ideas monitors
network traffic across the entire
infrastructure, detecting threats
that move through the network.
Host based ideas focuses on individual
devices, monitoring for suspicious
activity at the endpoint level, making
it ideal for detecting insider threats.
or attacks on specific assets.
Both network and host based
IDAs are critical components in
identifying and mitigating threats
within a cloud environment.
detection systems utilize different
detection methods, which help in
identifying potential threats.
We have signature based detection.
This method encompasses network
traffic against a database
of known threat signatures.
It's effective for detecting
known threats, but may miss novel,
previously identified attacks.
We have next anomaly based detection.
This approach uses machine learning
and statistic models to detect
deviations from normal network.
It's more adept at identifying
new or unknown threats
that can generate more false positives.
In terms of response capabilities,
passive ideas is the type of ideas
which allows the security team but
doesn't take action against or detect
a threat Leading the response to human
intervention, we have next active ideas,
also known as inclusion prevention system.
These systems can automatically
block or mitigate detected threats,
providing real, real time protection.
I solutions can, integrate with the.
Threat intelligence platforms for
enriched threat data and automated
response mechanisms, enhancing
their overall effectiveness.
They are also compatible with
other security platforms like
firewalls, security information,
and event management systems,
ensuring comprehensive protection.
Finally, when considering IDRS
implementation, it's important to
evaluate their performance impact.
This includes ensuring that they can
handle high volumes of network traffic.
without introducing significant
latency, which is critical for
maintaining operational efficiency.
This slide presents a comparison
table of different AIR intelligence
detection systems based on their
detection methods, response
capabilities, and integration options.
We have three solutions here
which you can compare, one
being signature based detection.
This method relies on comparing network
traffic against a database of known
threat signatures, which is effective
for identifying well known threats.
However, it may miss novel attacks.
this offers a passive ideas approach,
meaning it allows the security
team to such special activities,
but takes on automated action.
It takes no automated action.
It integrates with TIPS and firewalls,
providing a basic layer of protection.
We have an IDEAS B, for an example,
which employs anomaly based detection,
which uses machine learning and
sophisticated statistical models to
detect deviations from network behavior.
This data is more adept
and can identify new or unknown threats,
but can generate more false positives.
It is based on active ideas capable of
automatically responding to threats, but
blocking or mitigating them in real time.
It integrates with SIEMs.
and tips, making it ideal for more
dynamic and complex environments.
We have mixed IDS C.
This solution offers a hybrid
detection method that combines
both signature and anomaly based
approaches, providing a balanced and
comprehensive detection mechanism.
Like IDS B, IDS C is also an active IDS
with automated response capabilities.
It offers the broadest integration
options, working seamlessly
with TIPS, FIEMs, and firewalls.
So we have a holistic security framework.
Understanding these differences can
help you choose the right idea solution
that's that best fits your organizational
specific needs and security posture.
Now let's visualize how these ideas tools
fit into broader security infrastructure.
We have this diagram which illustrates
how ideas integrate with a broader
security infrastructure including threat
intelligence platform and security
information and event management systems.
At the core of this diagram, we
have IDS, which plays a central
role in monitoring network traffic
and identifying potential threats.
It feeds information to TIPS, which
enhance threat detection by aggregating
and analyzing data from multiple sources.
TIP then processes this information,
generates actionable intelligence
that can be fed back to, the ideas
for, for real time threat prevention.
Then we have SRM systems, which are also
integrated into this ecosystem, serving
as a hub for collecting, analyzing,
and storing log data for various, from
various sources, including ideas and tips.
This diagram also shows, security
organization, orchestration, and
automation response tools and tools.
which can be integrated further automating
the incident response processes by
triggering predefined actions based on
insights provided by TIPS and SIM systems.
This holistic approach to security
ensures that your organization
has multiple layers of defense.
With each component reinforcing
the others to create a robust
and dynamic security posture.
Next, we'll explore some real world
case studies that demonstrates
the effectiveness of these
integrated security solutions.
Firstly, we talk about
Capital One Data Breach.
In 2019, Capital One experienced a major
data breach that exposed the security,
like sensitive personal information
of more than 100 million customers.
Bye.
This breach was caused by a misconfigured
firewall on a cloud based storage system,
which allows, unauthorized access.
The security gap was, the attack
exploited weak, weak access controls.
And a misconfigured web
application firewall.
The attacker used a vulnerability in this
infrastructure to gain access to sensitive
data stored in Amazon S3 buckets.
this breach resulted in a significant
financial loss for Capital One, including
an 80 million fine by the Office of the
Controller of the Currency, which is OCC.
It also damaged the company's, The
learned being, this emphasize the
importance of, properly configuring cloud
security settings, regularly auditing
and updating security configurations.
Also employing stronger access
control to protect sensitive data.
Another notable case is Netflix approach
to security automation and orchestration.
Netflix, as a leading streaming service
provider, operates entirely on cloud using
AWS to manage its infrastructure as well.
Given its massive scale, Netflix faced
potential threats from large scale
cyberattacks, including DDoS attacks.
inside our threats and data breaches.
To counter these threats, Netflix
implemented a multi layered security
strategy that includes advanced threat
detection systems, continuous monitoring,
and the development of internal security
tools such as Security Monkey and
Limo to automate security processes.
Netflix also adopted a chaos engineering
approach, regularly simulating
failures and security breaches to
test the robustness of its systems.
Netflix's proactive approach has
significantly reduced security incidents,
enhancing its ability to quickly detect
and respond to threats, and it also
improved its overall security policy.
Similarly, Sony PlayStation Network Breach
offers some important lessons as well.
So let's talk about that.
it was a while back, in 2011, Sony's
PlayStation network was hacked.
which led to a theft of personal
information from, 77 million
user accounts, including
credit card details as well.
The attack was facilitated by
inadequate security measures, including
outdated software and insufficient
encryption of sensitive data.
The breach forced Sony to
shut down the PSN for 23 days.
resulting in a significant
loss of revenue.
Sony also faced numerous lawsuits and
had to invest heavily in improving
its security infrastructure.
This case underscores the need for
regularly updating software, encrypting
sensitive data, and implementing
strong incident response protocols to
mitigate the effects of a data breach.
Dropbox's multi layered security
approach provides another
instructive example as well.
So let's talk about that.
Dropbox, as is a cloud based
file storage service used by
millions of users worldwide,
like including enterprises
that store sensitive data.
As a cloud service provider, Dropbox
faced threats from data breaches and
unauthorized access and data leaks, which
could compromise the privacy of its users.
So Dropbox adopted a multi layered
security approach as well, including
two factor authentication, encryption of
data at rest, and I'm in transit as well.
security audits.
Dropbox also engages in regular
penetration testing and has
a robust boundary program to
identify vulnerabilities as well.
Because of this comprehensive
security strategy, Dropbox maintains
a strong security record with
minimal incidents of data breaches.
The proactive measures taken
by Dropbox have significantly
enhanced its operation as a secure
cloud storage provider as well.
Looking ahead, what are the
emerging threats in cloud security?
So let's explore some of the future
trends as computing continues to
evolve or shape or does the threats
and challenges associated with it.
Let's explore some of the emerging threats
that organizations need to be aware of.
Firstly, container security issues,
containers, which efficient, while
efficient can introduce vulnerabilities
if not properly secured, especially
when using shared resources.
This can lead to privilege escalation
or container escapes where an
attacker breaks out of a container
to gain access to other host systems.
You have serverless
architecture vulnerabilities.
Serverless environments reduce
the attack surface, but can.
Still be vulnerable to issues
like insecure configurations,
mismanaged permissions, etc.
You have supply chain attacks.
As organizations more rely more on
third party vendors, supply chain
attacks, where attackers compromise the
security provided to infiltrate their
customers are becoming more common.
So some of the strategies for these, for
mitigating some of these threats, right?
If we, if we talk about that, we have
adopting zero trust architecture, which
means implementing a zero trust model
where no entity inside or outside,
outside of the network is trusted by
default, continuously verifying users
and devices before granting access.
Ensuring that even those within
the network are monitored
and authenticated regularly.
We have regular security audits.
Basically conducting frequent
security audits to identify
and address vulnerabilities.
And then we have vendor risk management,
which strengthens supply chain security
by carefully vetting vendors, requiring
them to adhere to security standards, etc.
Let's look at the future trends as well
in cloud security that are shaping up.
As we look into the future, cloud
security will increasingly rely on
advanced technologies to protect
or against involving threats.
Two key trends, trends are at forefront,
which are AI driven threat detection
and quantum resistant encryption.
Yeah, AI driven, or artificial
intelligence and machine learned driven
are becoming, are becoming integral to
detect, This technology can identify
vast amounts of data at very incredible
speeds, enabling us to detect anomalies
and potential threats that might be
missed by traditional creativity measures.
We have quantum resistant
encryption,
which is being developed to protect
data against potential future threats.
quantum computing.
Quantum computers could potentially
break traditional encryption methods
such as RSA and ECC by solving complex
mathematical problems exponentially
faster than classic computers.
To counter this threat, new encryption
algorithms are being developed.
Together, these environments represent
the cutting edge of cloud security,
providing robust defenses against
both current and future threats.
Organizations that adopt these
technologies will be better equipped to
protect their data in an increasingly
complex and dangerous cyber landscape.
Let's look at this encryption,
quantum resistant encryption, and
AI driven encryption, and why it's
crucial for the future as well.
Quantum computing poses a significant
threat to encryption methods, as we rely
on the vulnerability of current encryption
and quantum resistance algorithms.
Quantum computers have the potential to
break widely used encryption methods,
because they solve mathematical
problems exponentially faster
than classical computers.
This capability would encryption
techniques ineffective.
Exposing sensitive data
to potential breaches.
To counter this threat, new encryption
algorithms are being developed that are
resistant to quantum attacks as well.
As we prepare for the advent of quantum
computing, organizations must begin
assessing their current encryption
methods and planning for the transition
to quantum resistant encryption as well.
How do we prepare for these, right?
Organizations should assess their
current encryption methods, like I said.
And then, also transition like planning,
begin like planning for the transition
to quantum register and encryption
techniques, including, new algorithms
and updating key management practices.
And also, organizations need to be
stay informed, on what, encryption
techniques are being built, and then,
necessity of, adopting them as a.
In summary, let's review the key points
we have covered today and look at how
our missions can stay ahead to mitigate
any emerging and existing threats.
In summary, we have explored the
critical aspects of cloud computing
security, including the importance of
multi layer protection strategy and
the role of advanced threat detection.
By understanding the various
levels, layers of protection and
employing cutting edge technologies
to detect and mitigate threats.
Organizations can significantly
enhance their cloud security posture.
As cloud computing continues to evolve,
staying informed about future trends and
adapting security strategies will be key
to maintaining robust cloud security.
The integration of AI driven threat
detection systems and the adoption of
quantum resistance, resistance encryption
are just two examples of how the
industry is preparing for the future.
By being proactive and forward thinking,
organizations can protect their data and
maintain the trust of their customers.
Finally, thank you for the
opportunity and hope you for I hope
you find the information valuable.
Thank you again.