Hi everyone.
My name is Satish Manna and I'm very happy
to be part of K 42 Platform Engineering
2025 session, and I'm here to talk about
compliance aware platform engineering.
Just a little bit about me
before we go into the session.
I have over 25 years of experience
across multiple continents.
I was in Asia Pacific
for the first initial.
Career about 14 years, and in the last
11 years in the USCA, in my overall
experience, 20 plus years are very
focused on financial organizations.
When I begin this presentation,
I like to immediately acknowledge
that most platform engineers
already understand how to automate
infrastructure, the harder parties
doing it in regulated environments.
What I have learned over the years.
Is that compliance isn't something that
can be added on at the end of the build.
Just like we architect our.
For high availability or performance,
we need to architect specifically for
provability, meaning that we cannot only
apply controls, but also demonstrate
how and when they were applied.
That's the central idea behind
compliance aware platform engineering.
In my experience, the cultural
mindset is just as important as the.
Technical approach.
Rather than thinking compliance teams as
blockers, we need to engage them early
as stakeholders In platform design, that
means mapping the regulatory controls
to practical, testable assertions
that can be implemented in core.
Once the collaboration is in
place, the platform team becomes
an enabler by providing a clean.
Reusable way for application teams
to consume compliant infrastructure
the moment they need it.
The stock is therefore structured
around real world experience from
financial institutions that operate
in multiple regulatory zones.
You will see that we.
Moved away from siloed manual tasks
and towards a model where compliance
is embedded directly in automation
pipelines delivered as part of the
platform and continuously validated.
Let's start by outlining today's agenda.
To make this concrete, I will start
through the regulatory landscape.
We have had to go through and design based
on the regulatory landscape requirements.
It's important to understand this first.
Because tooling decisions and
architectural patterns only make sense
when you look at the type of evidence
regulators expect us to produce.
For example, under MiFi two, which is
one of the regulators in Europe, like
so in the U-S-A-A-R-B and India, a Mass
in Singapore, we are required to log.
All tax timestamped transactions
and pro synchronization of the
time source for those locks.
That has very real design
implications when you're starting
to develop this solution.
Design or think of this solution
once the context is set.
I will take you step by step through
the evolution of our delivery
model from ad hoc DevOps pipelines
into a scalable platform model.
I'll spend most of the time on
four concrete building blocks and
show how each one contributes to.
Compliance by design.
The number one is provisioning frameworks.
Number two is hard and golden images.
Number three, CICD, gate integration,
and the last one is policy as core.
Right after that, I will show how
we exposed all of these to the
wider organization via self-service
because it's not just enough
to build a compliant pipeline.
If people aren't consuming
them easy, right?
Then I'll share what
worked and what didn't.
In case study format and finally
walk through a practical roadmap
that others can use to get
started in their own environment.
Even though the examples and use
cases are predominantly from financial
organizations, this can be applied in any
regulated industries, like in healthcare,
retail insurances, you name it, right?
So wherever there are some
regulations applied by some
external auditors or regulated
organizations, so this can be applied.
So what does the compliance challenge
look like in the financial services?
Let's look into that in this next slide.
Let me drill you into the
landscape a bit deeper.
Financial services organizations operate
under multiple overlapping regulations.
Reason being, they operate in various
continents from various countries.
SOX governs internal controls
over financial reporting in us,
whereas GDPR governs personal data.
As I mentioned earlier, one of the
European regulators MiFi two mandates,
granular record keeping of order and trade
events, and Dora introduces operational
requirements across hybrid infrastructure.
What's key here is that each regulation
not only tells you what must be
protected, but often how and when
that protection must be verified,
those requirements become technical.
For example, mafi to explicitly
states about the timestamps to
a millisecond accuracy for the.
Financial transactions that are performed.
That means a simple NTP is running isn't
a good answer for a regulator, right?
You must implement timestamp, lag,
logging, regular validation of NTP
drift and retain those logs for.
Audit review, this is where
manual process breaks down.
Nobody can manually verify under
that level of details across
hundreds of thousands of servers
on a daily or on a regular cadence.
So what we discussed early
on is that compliance is
fundamentally a data problem.
It's about having the right telemetry
stored in the right way at the right time.
Proves you enforced your policies,
which means the only scalable solution
is to automate all of it, including the
evidence of compliance and make it part
of the platform to manage this platform.
Engineering itself had to evolve.
Let's see how the platform engineering
did evolve over the period of time.
When I reflect on my own
journey, we started in very
traditional infrastructure silos.
Like many other organizations across
the globe, at that point in time,
operations and security had their own
tools, processes, and approval workflows.
Application teams were.
Often frustrated with the delays.
So they built shadow scripts, a
PowerShell script here, an Ansible
role there just to bypass bottlenecks.
That approach gave us speed in isolated
pockets, but didn't give us consist worse.
It created zero shared
accountability for compliance.
Every team was doing their own automation,
but no two teams did it the same way
and the results weren't reusable.
Shareable traceable, the shift to DevOps
helped at that point in time, right?
So because it broke down the
wall between dev and ops and
gave us automation pipelines, but
again, each pipeline was custom.
One team integrated in Jenkins, another
used GitLab, some applied straight into
public cloud, someone to the hybrid,
like into AWS and VMware as an example.
While that gave velocity
it also created dozens of.
Fragmented delivery patterns.
None of them fully aligned with
regulatory policies at audit.
Regulatory policy policies at audit
time, we had no easy way to prove
compliance across environments
because there were no single baseline.
So platform engineering was that logical.
Next step, instead of every team
reinventing the V, we began packaging
proven practices into reusable version
infrastructure services that the
whole organization could consume.
This is where the big change
for compliance happen once the
platform teams owns the baseline.
Exposes it as a service.
Every team that uses the
platform automatically
inherits the correct controls.
Developers don't have to waste
time interpreting, say, for
example, number of multiple pages.
Policy documents are waiting
for manual risk approvals.
The compliance rules are built
into the self-service itself,
right into the service itself.
That's also where the
cultural shift happened.
We started being just operators,
running servers, and became
product owners of a platform.
Internally, we started
calling the platform.
Compliance aware product, and when the
teams consume that product, they get
both velocity and compliance by default.
So compliance is no longer a
checkpoint at the end of a pipeline.
It's baked into the pipeline itself, into
the images, into the provisioning glass,
and into the self-service experience.
So how do we actually build
system with compliance back?
So let's look into see how do we build
secure hybrid IAS provisioning frameworks
in your next type in our next slide.
So when we implemented our
provisioning framework, the
first objective was very clear.
No resource should ever
be deployed outside of.
A policy enforced path.
In other words, if someone wants
to spin up a VM or a database or a
storage bucket, they can't just create
it directly in the cloud console.
Everything must be declared
as infrastructure as code.
Typically, with Terraform in Azure, we
use bicep and arm templates, and every
Terraform request is passed through a
policy engine that validates it against
centrally defined before anything is.
So we have centrally defined rules
before anything that's going to
be built using this ISE code.
To make this real, let me
give you some examples.
If encryption address is disabled,
the deployment is rejected.
Or if someone tries to attach a
public IP address to a subnet that
designated for a regulated workplace
workloads, the request fails.
So the policy engine blocks it.
So the, these are very simple
controls, but when they enforced
automatically, they set enormous
amount of remediation effort later.
The second major capability we
added was predefined landing zones.
These aren't just empty networks.
They're blueprints that already contain
our overlap network topology identity
and access management model, monitoring
hooks and logging configuration.
So when a workload is deployed into
a public cloud or onto the private
cloud, it automatically lands in a
secure, pre-approved environment.
So teams don't even have to think about
whether logging is enabled, whether
backup preferences are attached.
They just inherited it.
One of the most important lessons we have
learned the way along the way is that.
Policy engine needs to remain
independent from the IAC engine.
So policies evolve faster than
infrastructure code as code, right?
So for example, if regulators update
encryption requirements, I don't want
to go back and rewrite Terraform modules
across doesn't suffer repositories.
So by separating policy into its
own repository and enforcing it
as an admission control layer,
we can update controls globally.
Immediately without breaking
infrastructure code.
So the end result is a framework
that gives developers what they
need, the ability to provision
infrastructure quickly, but
only through a compliant path.
What I have observed is that.
It doesn't reduce flexibility at all.
In fact, it increases the
confidence teams know what the
provision is already compliant.
Operation teams know they are not
going to be chasing exceptions later,
and because of this framework works
consistently across both cloud and
on-prem, and we have been able to unify
governance in a way that scales globally.
So we, we learned a lot about,
alongside applying compliance on the
provisioning process, we also need to
ensure the new workloads themselves
start with a compliant baseline, right?
So what does that mean?
That drives us, that takes us
into the golden image creation
with compliance, right?
Golden images are often treated
as convenient, something to,
quickly provision because
everything is embedded into it.
But in a regulator environment,
their foundation of compliance,
our pipeline starts with a
vendor ISO, for example, say.
Windows server, IORL image and immediately
applies our hard hardening baselines
from CIS level one, as an example,
internal account and lockout policies
and configurations for audit and logging
for a centralized lock forwarding
right once the base hardening is done.
We embed operational agents and malware
file integrity monitoring, like time
synchronization settings, backup
configuration, and endpoint protection,
and the next phase of the pipeline runs
any vulnerability related scannings
and checks the image against all
known high severity vulnerabilities.
So only if the images passes these
checks does it it does get version
and published into the catalog, right?
So every release is signed
and timestamped, giving us an
immutable audit record of exactly
what was approved and when.
So another key point is that.
The golden image lifecycle is automated,
so we rebuild on fixed account,
so every two weeks, for example.
There are certain exceptions in
situations like WannaCry or an emergence
of a critical CDE, so it means we
never massively patch live workloads.
We just replaced them using
new trusted base image.
That's how we have eliminated drift and
provided consistent audit reports for.
Every server in the estate.
So configuration drift, we have used power
DSC, Azure, DSC, right configuration for
windows and civil playbooks for Linux.
But compliance shouldn't
just stop at provisioning.
As I mentioned earlier, it must be
extended into CICD pipelines, right?
So let's see how the CICD automated
compliance can be baked into
The entire process of compliance
are platform engineering.
So we have code commits, building
the pipelines, having an approval
blades, and then a deployment, eh.
Doing a monitoring at around time, so
once team started using the provisioning
framework and golden images, the next
logical step was to move compliance
checks directly into the CICD pipeline.
That means we embed policy testing
just like we embed unit tests.
If someone proposes a changes to an
ISE module, the pipeline will run a
policy test suit that validates things
like I am principles, whether it has a
tags, is it compliant with respect to
the tags, or does it have a mandatory
logging, encryption, and network rules?
These are just examples.
If anything fails.
The policy test, the pipeline stops
and gives the engineer a precise
feedback on which policy failed and why.
So that not only prevents
non-complaint changes, it also
educates the engineers over time.
They start to understand the
regulatory intent behind the policy.
We have also extended this
into runtime validation.
For example, once a workload is
deployed, we run periodic complaint
scanning using the same policies.
That allows us to detect and
alert if anything drifts from the
up road and standard baseline.
The key point is that compliance
becomes a continuous activity,
not a pointing time audit.
So next, let's look into policy as code.
This is a cornerstone of
compliance ops, right?
So policy as code is really what
binds everything together, right?
Rather than storing governance
in documents, we translate them
into machine readable policy.
A simple example is storage buckets
must have server side encryption
and block public access, right?
So we spoke about this earlier
example, so I'm continuing with the
same example here as well, right?
In the policy scope.
So we write we write that in the bicep
on templates and committee to the Git.
So when a developer attempts to
provision a bucket, the provisioning
engine queries the policy runtime
evaluates the request and returns allow.
RI, explanation because those
policies live in get, we can apply
the same software development like
Lifecycle to them, and we have pool
request, peer reviews, automated test
and approvals before a particular
pool request is signed off.
And we have a traceability
around what changed, right?
So this also gives us the ability to wash
policies and roll them back if we need to.
When the regulator asks us.
When a particular rule was
implemented, our RY it changed.
We have full audit trailing git.
So one of the added benefits is
that policy as code allows the
platform team the compliance team to
collaborate with a shared artifact.
The risk team doesn't need to read
Terraform, and the engineering team
doesn't need to read those documents
that contain multiple policies.
They both look at the policy escort
repository that's shared across.
The source of the truth changed the
entire dynamic between those schemes.
In a nutshell.
So for example, like if I have to come
into talking about what technologies we
use, Corp Sentinel, OPA AWS, configures
and Azure policy for IAC, right?
The process involves creating a
policy registry map to regulations
version controlling them.
Test logic embedded in it.
We also automate remediation and evidence
generation policy as code makes compliance
verifiable and scalable transforming
rules into enforceable and testable code.
So now that we have made
everything compliant with all the
frameworks, how can we make this
a balanced self-service model?
Fadi.
Customers are the developers to use it.
So let's dwell into our next slide.
Enabling self-service while
preserving compliance, right?
I think we have very strong base
so far, building the framework,
building the golden images, adding
the compliance, putting them into CICD
gate so that, it can be validated.
Look, now engineers just don't want.
Autonomy, right?
So engineers want autonomy, right?
While compliance teams need
governance, the sweet spot is at
the intersection of automation
and self-service and governance.
Embedding compliance into self-service
platforms enable speed without
sacrificing regulatory alignment.
At this point, once the building
docks were in place, we focused on.
How to make them consumable, right?
So if they cannot be consumed,
there's no point in having
infrastructure as code at some point.
So we built a self-service catalog where
development teams can select from a
set of pre-approved environment types.
So for example, windows
service with sql and start.
Linux server with app stack
installed containers with runtimes
and other stuff in stock, right?
Each of those catalog entries is
simply a wrapper around the approved
provisioning modules, right?
The golden image and the policy runtime.
From a developer perspective,
it's just a click.
If they're using a UI or an API
call, if they're running through
some programming language and they
get the environment within minutes.
From a compliance perspective, they're
forced through the compliant provisioning
path, which triggers the compliant
gates and applies the golden image.
The beauty of this model is that
the faster we make the self-service
experience, the less incentive
there is for teams to bypass it.
In fact, they prefer the platform
because it saves the time.
We also track consumption and attach
metadata to every provisioned resource.
That means we can answer auditors
like, who requested this workload?
What policy version was enforced, and
what controls were applied immediately
without digging through the old
emails or, change tickets, et cetera.
So that's how we did the
enabling self-service while
preserving the compliance.
Let's look at case study in a
leading financial organization,
what challenges we had, what, how,
what approach we have taken, how
the results enhance the reduction in
the compliance exception, et cetera.
And our, the biggest pain point for the
financial organization was that they
didn't know the how these regulations.
Translate into technical requirements.
It was that every region and
every business unit integrated
them slightly differently.
That meant the same type of server
could be built at least six different
ways depending on where it was applied.
It created massive headache to at
audit time because each region had
to justify why its configuration
is different from the others.
So by consolidating.
Hardening into a single golden image
pipeline and enforcing provisioning
through a central policy engine.
We unified all those regional
variations into a one global standard.
The result was not only a
faster provisioning from down,
from days to under, few hours
or less than an hour, right?
But also a reduction in audit findings
because these were finally a, they
were single source of truth con
for configuration and compliance.
Another important outcome was improved
collaboration with the risk function.
Once they saw that the policies were
implemented in code and enforced
consistently, they were much more
comfortable delegating control to
the engineering firm teams that in
turn sped up project delivery and
reduced the policy debate cycles
during large platform rollouts.
So now how can you take
this into your organization?
Let's look at the roadmap,
the implementation roadmap.
So if you're trying to get
started, start with a small pilot
project through the concept.
Next, assess your current
compliance requirements and
automated automation opportunities.
Define a compliance ops strategy,
roadmap, tools, processes,
and any required art changes.
And then implement the foundation, say
using Golden images policy as code.
And then scale across environments
and integrate with existing workflows.
Use CACD policy gates, right?
Finally, measure compliance
metrics and continuously improve.
So this is what could be implementation
roadmap for in any organizations that you
want to implement this whole framework.
So before we close, let me
leave you with some key.
Takeaways.
So key takeaways.
First, compliance must be design
principle, not an afterthought, right?
Second, automation is essential because
manual processes cannot keep up.
Third, compliance ops is the natural
next effort regulated environments.
Finally, self-service and compliance can
coexist if platforms are designed well.
So that concludes the key takeaways
in the entire presentation.
I would like to Thanks.
Thank you for your time.
I hope this session gave you a clear
roadmap to scaling compliance of
automation in your respective industries.
Even though I have specifically
focused on financial services.
Thank you very much for this opportunity.
Looking forward for more sessions in.