Hi everyone.
My name is Mohammad Nja.
I work as a solutions architect
at Amazon Web Services.
So thank you for joining
for today's session.
So today I will be talking about
Amazon Queue Developer and how is
it integrated with GitLab to create
a next level developer experience.
So before diving into the D details,
I wanted to share a report from
GitLab Global DevSecOps which was
shared last year, which says that 74
percentage of organization using AI
for software development reports the
desire to consolidate their tool chain.
So we have seen the AI tools have been
part of our personal life as well as.
Our work life for many months
and couple of years now.
So what we have seen from customers
is a strong requirement or a need to
consolidate, some of the tools so they can
perform their tasks related to software
development in a single tool rather than,
using multiple tasks, which increases the
complexity as well as causing confusion.
That has been a need that customers
have been, sharing with us.
So how can we help the people who have
been using KIT Lab, so that, that's
the main part of our today's session.
So that's where GitLab Duo
with Amazon Q mbs, right?
So we know that GitLab is a very
popular DevSecOps platform that has
been used by software developers and
IT professionals all across the globe.
Now with integration with Amazon Queue
you have the ability to accelerate
your overall software development
lifecycle, whether it's transforming
your legacy code or in order to, you
have an idea and you wanted to create
code and all the way to, raising a
merge request in GitLab, that all can
be accelerated, using Amazon Queue.
And also you, if you want to
conduct security code reviews.
For your code, Amazon queue
can also help with that.
So the aim of using Amazon
Queue is to accelerate your
software development lifecycle.
So we will talk about some
of this in the coming slides.
We also have like few demo videos that
can help you in better understanding
of the features of Amazon Queue.
And one more important thing is that
as of today, the Amazon queue is for
GitLab customers is only available for
GitLab self-managed ultimate customers.
So I also wanted to talk about some
of the core features of Amazon Queue
when using it along with GitLab Duo.
So the first one is streamlining
software development, right?
As I said before, if you have an idea,
so you have a, code triple which you
have in GitLab and say there is a new.
Issue that you have created an idea,
and with the use of Amazon Q can.
Look at that issue, see the descriptions
and create a code, for you, which
you can then review yourself and,
add or remove anything that you
don't, you want to update and then
send all the way to, MER request.
So we will see again then
in a demo video coming up.
And the second one is
optimizing your code, right?
You can use Amazon queue to generate
unit test from a merge request.
Another important thing is like
maximizing the code quality and security.
So with Amazon Queue you can perform,
high quality security code reviews.
And lastly, you can modernize your
code, you can transform your legacy
Java applications that are using
eight or 11 version, and then.
Transfer me to Channel 17 in minutes.
And earlier we know that it can
take up to weeks or in some cases,
depending upon the size of the
code, it can take up to months.
But we'll see, shortly how Amazon
Q working along with Kit Lab can
accelerate that transformation.
So coming to the first feature
is idea to merge request, right?
So what are the benefits?
And it is quite clear, right?
It's faster feature implementation cycles.
So if your business requirement
needs a particular new feature that
you want to deliver it, quickly
with the help of Amazon, QU can
deliver it much faster now and.
Core quality, right?
It gives you and another perspective
from the A R AI code AI tools such
as Amazon Queue to ensure that the
quality of the code is high and it
doesn't contain any, vulnerabilities,
which it can detect through the unit
security code code scanning, et cetera.
And.
And lastly, it improves the
developer productivity, right?
And thus the overall aim
of using such tools, right?
So for the demo, we have a sample.
GitLab page where we have a sample
project with types script, files.
So now what we are going to do is
we will be creating an issue, which
is essentially an idea that we want
to integrate into this project.
So what we'll be doing is
we'll be creating an issue
on the top left and we can.
Title.
So in this case it's an adding
a new signup flow to the
website, as you can see here.
And and you create an account for
the user that takes an email and
password and username add a flow
for existing users to sign in.
And this should be linked
from the whole page, right?
So those are the few descriptions that we
have added into our the new issue, right?
Now what we are going to do is like once
we created it, the issue will be invoking
Amazon Q using forward slash q and Dev.
And once we enter that, we will
see anime a message from Amazon
Queue Service saying, I am working
on generating code for this issue.
I'll update this comment at Open
Emerge, request when I am done.
So in the background, it's going
to look at the title, it's going to
look at the description that you have
entered, and then it's generating.
Quote on behalf of you, and
after a few seconds you will see
an open merch request, right?
So let's take a look.
So you can see that it has finished
generating the proposed code
changes and opened a merge request.
So we can go to that merge request now,
and you can see it, it documents or
it updates all those comments in the
relevant, issues or merge requests.
So it's easier for us to understand
what's happening in the background on what
exactly Amazon Queue service is doing.
So you can see that the
code has been implemented.
So the other important step is to
review the code changes, right?
So you go through the code and see
what are the additional code that
it has been degraded, and see if
there is anything that's missing.
And basically doing a quick check
of the quality of the code, right?
So in this case, what we are
what we're seeing is like we, we
are trying to include one more
small feature into the code.
So in this code there is no logging.
So this, in this term you can see
we are adding a comment again,
saying at logging and when we.
After we add the comment and then we again
invoke the Amazon Q Service slash Q Dev.
What it does is the same thing.
It reviews the code, it reviews
your comment, and then it creates
a code, based on your requirement.
Right?
So again, going back to the changes,
you can see there is now a new
file called Log at or ts, which is.
Very recently created for you and
you can review that code and if
you're satisfied with it, you can
basically upload the moist request.
So this is one of the features of
FAM using Amazon Q with kit Lab.
So the next one is J
application Modernization.
Let's say in your current in organization,
you have your applications that are
using Java eight or Java 11 applications.
So if you're looking to modernize
or transform the versions to
Java 17 quickly, then Amazon Q
is a tool that you want to use.
The specialty of using this tool is, it's
not just transform your code, but it does
that in a well-documented way, right?
It creates an upgrade plan and it
generates, the ready to review MER request
while maintaining full traceability.
So you have that full clear
documentation of what happened.
What are the dependencies
that he it removed?
that are, it has upgraded.
All sort of information that you would
need will be documented along with
the actual transformation of the code.
So now let's take a look at that demo.
All right, so now again, we have a
new issue which we have given a title
called Upgrade Project to Java 17.
And then what we are going to
do is give a in the dis in the
description, we will be invoking.
Amazon q in this case will
be invoking transform.
Earlier we used dev, DEV in order
to generate code, but in this one
we are transforming the code, right?
So that's why we are using transform.
And then when we create
the issue you will see.
What are the different steps
that Amazon Queue will perform?
So the first one is I'm running
the GitLab CSAD job required.
Transform your code and then it'll upload
your code, generate a transformation plan.
It'll transform your code and then
generate a merge request, right?
So we'll see.
What are the, what's the
accreditation plan and the
documentation that Amazon Q provides?
So you can see that it has started giving
output and very quickly you can see
that it, it analyzes the source code.
It says the lines of code in your
application, dependencies that needs to
be replaced, a file should be changed,
and the plan transformation changes
all those steps by different steps
that it'll take in order to upgrade.
And once it's created the cre
transformation plan, the next step
is actually transforming the code.
And you will see that, yeah.
It has finally created that.
Merge request for the upgraded
upgrading to the Java 17.
And as you can see in the screen
it details all those additional
details that you'll recur like the
additional code that has been replaced.
What are the files that has been changed
and what are the next steps that it'll do?
Asks you to do right?
You should always review the
code and see the change that
it has made to the application.
And again, but most of the times
you might have to make your small
changes in some of the files.
But the aim of using Amazon Q is
to accelerate your overall software
lifecycle development, right?
And that's what we are seeing now.
You can see that it has paused
the, different stages of
your pipeline and it yeah.
So this is one of the other demo that I
wanted to show you how you can utilize
Amazon Q to upgrade your Java legacy
applications to two, which have a 17.
So moving on to the next and
final feature is the code reviews.
So we know that when we develop
the code, we do the, peer
reviewing, and other measures.
But with the, gen ai we can.
Do much better, right?
That's basically using Amazon queue
services such like that to review
your existing code and it'll suggest
are there any vulnerabilities?
Are there any scope fori optimizing
your code, to make it more
resilient, more secure in nature.
So for the demo, what we are going to
see is we have emerge requests, right?
And we, with all the code that we have
written down or generated by Amazon queue.
And then what we are going to do
is like review that code to check
for quality or, security issues.
So for that purpose, we'll be
using forward slash q review.
And when you comment
that behind the screen.
It scans the code and it gives you
a detailed information on the the
vulnerabilities it has detected.
And it also highlight the piece of
code in your actual code base to see.
This is where you have that vulnerability.
So in this use case, you can see
that it has, it is seeing that
is a possibility of SQL injection
attacks because of this code.
And what you can do is like you
can review the findings and then.
You can fix it then and there, right?
And for that we use the fixed command.
And when you add that command, it'll
generate the updated code and you
can review the code changes again
and ensure that it's all good.
And then, apply the suggestion.
So this is one of the ways you can.
Utilize Amazon queue to, basically
review your code for, quality checks
and other security vulnerabilities.
So that's all what I wanted to talk to
you about, just highlighting the main
core features of Amazon Queue and if
you're using GitLab in your organization.
And if you're using AWS, what I would
suggest is, give it, try with Amazon Queue
and see how, if it helps in your, software
development for your organization.
So feel free to scan the Q QR code
to learn more about this integration.
And as I said before, as of
today, it's only available for
self-managed ultimate customers.
But yeah, thank you.
Thank you so much for
taking part in this session.
I hope it has been helpful and I hope
you have a good rest of the day in
the platform engineering conference.
Thank you.