Hello, everybody.
How you doing?
My name is Victor.
And today in this particular
course today, I'll be teaching
you about, a course, a topic.
I'm talking about a topic called
beyond the code, building cyber
security awareness in your
platform development team.
So if you are looking to inculcate
the best practices into your platform
development teams, this particular
talk, you would actually find useful.
By the end of this talk, you should
be able to understand some modern
threats that your team actually
faces as a platform development
team and how to elevate your
security mindset in your team.
So it's important for us to
understand that, the cybersecurity
landscape is evolving just to where.
We with more, improvement in technology,
there's also going to be improvements
in security threats, so there's a
rise of sophisticated threats and
the attack vectors, improving attack
vectors here simply means, the
means through the channels through
which you can actually be attacked.
So for instance, things like IOT systems,
for instance, You can actually be hacked
through your cameras or maybe your fridge
because fridge freezers and fridges today
have I have like I like IoT devices too.
They can actually be.
Connected to via the Internet,
and there's also an increasing
reliance on technology today.
Lots of organizations, almost
everybody in the world CrowdStrike
event where because of there was a
downtime with the CrowdStrike system,
airports were shut, airports could
not, their operations were affected.
In the world today, technology
is like the backbone of most
of the business processes.
yeah, so the first thing to actually
look at when you're talking about
integration security into your
platform development lifecycle is
to have a secure by design mindset.
What it means here for the shift approach
means the fact that, you Make sure that
whatever you do when you arrive with
your designs, maybe you are designing
a cloud application or a software.
For instance, you want to make sure
that it is secure by design, meaning
that you consider security first.
It doesn't matter how fancy
whatever your building is.
If it's not secure, it can actually
be an attack vector through which
your system is going to be attacked.
There should also be a secure
testing and analysis piece.
What this means is that you should have
a very good quality assurance process in
place in your platform development team.
you shouldn't be in a hurry to
move a product into a, an app or a
software into the production system.
Without adequately testing it, you
should have a very good quality
assurance system or methodology.
And there are also automated
security tools you can
actually use to achieve this.
And there are also
different methodologies.
You can actually also make sure
you do penetration testing.
Penetration testing means that you
actually get maybe a hacker to, you
get a hacker to actually target your
system to see how, where and where
your system could be vulnerable.
I could also.
Do things around statistics, code and
statistics, static code analysis where
you can actually review the source code
or what you do to actually see whether
there are any bugs where, for instance,
if there are any bugs that could actually
make you prone to being attacked via SQL
injection attack, for instance, those will
be identified with a static code analysis.
Process.
it's also very important to you.
That's what you're looking to
have a security conscious culture.
They should be regular awareness
trainings held in your organization, and
they should openness and transparency.
What this actually means is the
fact that your team should be people
should be encouraged to, speak up
when they feel something is wrong.
Okay, you should encourage an
atmosphere of people speaking up,
people not keeping to themselves
when they feel something is wrong.
It could be the difference
between you being cyber safe
and you being cyber attacked.
Okay, so it's very important to
encourage a community and ambience of.
Open transparency is very important
for you to maintain security
conscious culture within your team.
incentives could also be provided to
members of your team when a member of
your team, actually does an achievement
or is actually like a cyberspace champion
in the sense that he or she encourages,
The team needs to be more cyber a lot.
you could actually sign our words for
those kind of people and give them
our words or maybe monetary gift of
our chance to encourage them so that
all the members of the team see that
good behavior is actually encouraged.
Going back to the secrecy
awareness training.
This is a lot actually been
found that most companies are
not doing a lot to, train.
They're not doing a lot to actually train,
their staffs regularly around, Cyber
security trainings and cyber security
trains, so it's not just enough for you
to organize a cyber security training.
When you're onboarding your
staff, you should also make sure
that it's a question of process.
They should understand the importance of
things around not having a cladex policy.
they should have a cladex policy, things
around changing their passwords regularly,
things around not sharing, things
Sensitive, office things when they're
personal social media, things like that.
Those are reminders, nudging your staffs
to make sure that they don't become
like an attack vector themselves with
moving towards social engineering.
And so in social engineering concepts,
your staffs may actually be an attack
vector that you could be hacked from.
So you have to be very careful, You
should also look at implementing secure
coding practice on the technical area.
We talk about things
around form validation.
For instance, I spoke about
password for the previous slide.
when it comes to things around input
validation, you should say, if you have
some sensitive files, For instance, you
could also secure it to the way that
the password to access those files would
have certain rules and requirements.
For instance, it could be that the
password must be maybe 15 characters long.
where you must have a capital letter,
small letter symbols and all that.
So there must be, good input
validation built into your system.
There should also be secure authentication
and authorization systems, things
around MFA, multi factor authentication,
to make sure that the person who
is logging in or having access to
sensitive documents, Is supposed to
be the person having access to them.
Okay.
So this is very important to know.
Then also encryption, it goes without
saying, it cannot be overemphasized
and it cannot be understated that
you need to encrypt sensitive files.
Oh, look at the CIA triad.
Things around your confidentiality, your
integrity of your files is so important.
So sensitive details like passwords
or, system like systems in your,
In your disposals, you should make
sure that you also inculcate things
around the least privileged access
methodologies where anyone who shouldn't
have any business having access to a
system should not have access to it.
It should be encrypted from them.
It's only individuals who would have,
who, who, Authorized to have access
to the information who, you can use,
you can say something like around a
need to know basis, something around
a need to know basis where it is only
when they have to know that it would
actually have access to actually decrypt
that file and have access to the file.
So encryption is very important.
The number four would be
secure logging and monitoring.
This is so important, very important.
You need to have a secure logging
system that shows who actually logged,
who actually accessed the resource.
And when did they access the resource?
It cannot be overemphasized.
When you have a cyber attack and you
are doing a post incident recovery, you
want to go back and check, actually,
let's be cyber attack who accesses
file who was killing through this file.
It will help you investigate.
So there's a need to have a secure logging
system that shows that tracks the time
and whatever anybody did in a system.
Some organizational systems around
them use different softwares
to actually track this down.
So you need to check for a software
that actually works for you to project.
Then if your physical security of
your platforms, things around your,
network security and segmentation,
implementing a firewall is non negotiable.
You will need to have interaction systems,
your QALYs, QBM IRADAR, QALYs, DACTRACE.
Different options for you to
use from Microsoft Defender.
you should also implement
firewalls outside and inside
your network if need be.
You can also, for some
organizations, I know some , your
staff probably work remote.
You probably want get a VAN establish
a site end to in v you secure v and VPN
system to ensure that there's enough,
there's a very good segmentation.
That helps your remote workers
connect securely to your network,
in such a way that it does not
affect your main usnc files.
Okay.
So that is what's network security
and segmentation will help you do.
Then best practices.
You need to have best practices.
I've spoken about that
in the previous slide.
You even must have a good access,
I didn't say an access management
system that talks about your
authorization, access and authorization.
people who are logging into
your systems must have the right
login credentials to do Okay.
If you log in, if your login process
is broken, you might as well know
that your systems are not safe.
Okay.
And you should also have to do
regular scanning so that where
and where you are actually weak.
It's a good practice to have penetration
testers come to test your systems
regularly to know where you are weak.
So you can do that maybe every three
months to check, okay, get a penetration
test that will actually test your system.
Physical security measures since around
Creating barriers to your systems.
you should have guts
in your data sentence.
if you have data centers, if you're
filed on August 10 on the cloud and
you have some offline files stored in
data centers, you should have fiscal
gaps, fiscal barriers, surveillance
systems, cameras, to protect access
to your, your critical infrastructure.
Very important to have all those in
place, and of course you should have an
adequate backup, adequate backup measure
in place just in case maybe there's a
fire, so that your systems are not lost.
Make sure you back up
your systems properly.
Incident response planning
cannot be overemphasized.
you should have In your security
policy organization, there should
be, a comprehensive incidents
response plan as regards, the
procedures for containing any security
incidents you might actually have.
You should have a dedicated team, maybe
outsource dedicated team that would be,
Taxed with the responsibility of handling
any incident you might probably encounter
in the course of your day to day work.
Okay.
And of course, there are software
that could actually help you with
threat intelligence and analysis.
I've mentioned some like
DuckTrace and IBM Curator.
There are lots of them, but you need to
work with what works for your budget.
Okay.
So incident resource plan, you
should have an incident resource
plan in your security policy.
that shows the appropriate response,
how you are going to actually deal
with the incident, how you are going
to do it during the incident and
after the incident, what steps will
be taken so that you don't fall to
that same server attack next time.
Very important.
yes.
So There's a need for continuous
monitoring, you have to continuously
monitor your systems, you have to
continue to monitor them because the
cyber attackers are not actually sleeping,
so you have to continuously check.
Though some systems will give you
false positives, some softwares
like, I know Qualys and some other
systems, sometimes they may throw
what they call false positives.
which might not actually
be a cyber threat.
you want to make sure that you check very
well, you investigate for that, you check
the logs and check that, okay, this system
is actually, this is actually not actually
a false policy, but if you see anything
unusual in your monitoring and your
vulnerability assessment, you raise it
up to your line manager to let them know
what to do so that they can take it up
and actually neutralize any cyber threat.
lastly, I would, I want to talk
about Empowering your team.
It's so important for you to take
security awareness training seriously.
it is very important to work
on a mindset of your team.
They need to understand that cyber
security is everybody's business, not
just the security team's business.
Everybody should be cyber aware.
Very important.
That's why I mentioned
you need to train them.
You need to train your staff.
Regularly around security because
he has different security threats
coming up every day and your system,
your staffs need to be aware.
They should also be.
you can also have things
around threat modeling in the
interactive security simulations.
You can actually do security simulation
where you check You know, you mimic real
world scenarios to help people at it.
So that would help you identify how
you're going to respond to a threat.
You can also, when it comes to security
awareness and training, you can also
conduct fun games, security games,
that can actually, you can give me
five security scenarios, true quizzes,
interactive games, challenges, and
why your staffs are having fun.
They'll be learning things about security.
Okay.
Just to make them have fun and they will
have that mindset, within them that.
Okay.
We have actually, we need to be actually
be cyber secure and we need to have
informed, actually learning something.
And with that, you are improving, you
are empowering, the security mindset.
And in conclusion, I just want to say that
it is very possible for you to actually
cultivate a security conscious culture
within your platform development team and
protect your platform development team
from modern threats so that you can have a
resilient cyber posture in your platform.
in your organization.
So you need to take this seriously.
And if you aren't doing any of the
things listed in this presentation
before, please take out time.
You can speak to a cybersecurity
consultant about it.
And I actually hope and believe
that, you will find you have
found this presentation useful.
And, yes, so it is very, I find I,
I counted the privilege to actually
present in conf platform and the conf.
42 plus from engineering 2024 program.
And I'm sure that you would, you've
actually found this pretty useful and yes.
So I guess I'll catch up with you another
time and wherever you are in the world,
I want to say, have an amazing time.
Thank you very much for listening.