Hi, everyone.
I'm very glad to be here.
I'm Amir, the CEO and
co founder at Sensor.
Sensor is an AIOps company,
bridging together advanced,
observability elements using, EVTF.
And machine learning stacks, which uses
data in order to look for deficiencies
and service degradation, which we
came to speak about here today is
essentially a very interesting concept
of bridging the gap, both technically,
but also from an operational point of
view and how to utilize the advances.
In the forms of, the use of
an internal, developer portal.
and it's how essentially use, the
real time topology or the dynamics
of the environment as a connected
issue between the platform engineering
part and the DevOps and SREs.
So going through the journey that we will
cover today, we will speak about an IDP in
general and what's missing from the IDP.
We'll verify that it's not the first
use case that suffered from the exact
same phenomenas and what we can learn
from cybersecurity in that aspect.
We'll go in deep dive at how real time
topology could be used as a shared
language of how to bridge between
the IDP operation on what I want
to do, what is the configuration.
or the configuring state of the services
or system, and how to correlate and
bridge that with the runtime topology.
and that is an important part
of, essentially connecting
between these two worlds.
we'll speak about what you can do
with a closed loop, mechanism, what's
happened if you force feed data from
the observability mechanism, the
real time topology back into the IDP.
And we'll, cover or we'll finish this,
session with a little bit of pointers
about how to get started, which are, the
most important parts to pay attention to.
So I hope you'll, I
hope you'll enjoy it on.
Let's start, IDPs or internal developer
portals, as being your businesses are
very incredible tools for bridging
between the development parts in
the DevOps part, essentially, the
ability for an organization to create.
Both the schema, but also the rules of
what is going to be running to production,
what type of artifacts needed to be
collected about them, configured about
them and expose that, expose that to
the developers as means to save time.
for our platform engineering
teams and DevOps team.
but pay attention that they're very
focused about what I'm trying to do,
what I'm trying to achieve, what is the
configuration state that I want to be
applied in the production environment.
And with that, we will see elements.
In this case, we're looking at, we're
looking at the Kubernetes environment
or Kubernetes topology, in which we
have the physical resources like the
nodes, And we have the logical resources
like the Kubernetes clusters, the
namespaces, the workloads, and the pods.
And we can see the schema element on
top of them, the elements which we're
trying to bring into configuration by
the IDP and all the way to the developer.
On their own.
One half of the equation, because
they're sometimes missing or
lacking in some critical context.
And that context, comes or stems
from the difference between what's
happening on design time to what will
happen on the runtime environment.
Resources will behave differently.
If not, if we're looking at the pods
environment or workload environment,
of course, what I'm trying to do
from configuration part, things like
allocates or request and limit their.
Elements or artifacts, which I'm
configuring, but the behavior in the
runtime is going to be different.
It'll be different because the
node has different resources to
give, and so on and so forth.
The interaction between the
different elements are also
sometimes hard to, encompass.
If you're looking at things like
ATIs, which are crucial, for the
interaction between the element,
there are parts which are much harder
to model, in a static environment.
Towards what they're really doing
in production and how they're
manifesting themselves in production.
Another good example would
be the use of third parties.
Sometimes it's very hard to
conceptualize even the schema layer.
I'm using a certain third party service,
which is an important part of the
service that I'm trying to deploy.
How am I learning about that exposure?
I'm learning about that
dependencies, which are, of
course, very important in the.
Complete life cycle or software
life cycle, deployment life cycle
that we're trying to achieve.
And of course, runtime configuration.
What eventually happened, what was
allocated, what was configured on the
different physical and logical layers
and misconfigs, of course, that some
of them can happen only at runtime.
For example, someone going through not
the IDP or doing a configuration directly.
On the cloud environment could lead
to a lot of interesting things, with
regard to what the IDP is seeing
versus what is the real situation.
the important part or
the important aspect to.
Understand here is that we're
not the only domain which facing
this exact same challenge.
A very good analogy could be
the world of cyber security.
And more precisely for taking the,
taking the platform engineering
in SRE, as a comparison, the world
between the application security,
the AppSecOps and the DevSecOps.
The one which are responsible for
what I'm doing from application
security and production to the one
who actually serve and maintain
it on the runtime environment.
and we could see that throughout
the short history, but meaningful
history of cybersecurity, that gap or
bridging that gap between the static
analysis and the runtime to create
an environment which is tailored
toward the shift left movement was an
important part of making that a reality.
Moving between the static catalog in
which the artifact would be things like
vulnerabilities and, OS, components,
the authentication and encryption,
keys, configuration, different
framework, the secret, an analogy
to an IDP, they will be part of the
schema, which I'm trying to config.
But the runtime environment yields
a lot of important dynamics in
order to tie the knot between them.
elements which I'm trying to
do in production would be,
is something really deployed?
Where it is deployed?
It is internet exposed in
terms of the surface of attack.
Is it behind some sort of a firewall
or, or, or filtering mechanism?
Are there runtime mix configuration?
Are there, do they have
any relevancy to something?
which is on the static catalog part,
that bridging, was very important in
order to one, get an accurate view
of what is an actual attack surface,
focusing or prioritizing the real risk,
not just vulnerabilities, which of
course would collapse the entire team
because we'll just try to fix everything.
but that formal formalization of what
is important, what is the priority?
it's, it's crucial for these teams to,
predicting the function, efficiently.
and of course, the embedding of
policies and guardrail earlier on the
SDLC, making sure that the things and
the elements which I'm putting in the
Configuration time, which I'm putting
in an earlier stages of, the software
development, the software deployment,
pipeline are going to really appear
in the runtime environment, which is a
very strong analogy to what's actually
happening on, on an IDP, on an IDP world.
So for platform engineering,
these are some contexts.
comes from essentially having a very
nice grasp or a very deep view about
the real time topology of the services.
What is actually going on in production.
The benefits of using or being able
to feed force this type of element
back into the IDP are numerous.
I will just mention a few.
The ability to get full
and closed loop visibility.
What I try to do.
What I meant for things, to be
looking like, and what actually
came about in reality, having
more efficient troubleshooting.
Of course, there is a lot of
vague line between where, one's
responsibility like a platform
engineer is going to land and when.
Another responsibility like
the SRE is going to start.
There's a lot of, there's a
lot of back and forth between
them and going way back to the
developers which are fed by the IDP.
Therefore, this type of
information is super crucial.
and eventually less IDP maintenance
required from various reasons.
One, being able to Actually be actuary on
the status of the production environment
being left cold or think about things
which are runtime related and not
IDP related and so on and so forth.
white heart that we understand
it's not a trivial move.
We understand that people
would have done it.
There are some sort of runtime
integration towards the IDP, like getting
observability streams from your APM.
We're infrastructure monitoring
tools, but it's still hard.
It's hard because the runtime
dynamics are much more complex
than the static dynamics.
The static dynamics could be.
Somewhat, somewhat compared
to a configuration file or a
configuration tree, something
that I could traverse easily.
That's not the nature of
the runtime environment.
The runtime environment is a live,
moving, changing graph, which has a lot
of inputs coming from things that happen
on the infrastructure layer, things
that happen on the application layer.
And just changes coming from the
software deployment pipeline.
All of these together make these
dynamics very, active, very,
very, very time, sensitive.
so this type of, this type of bridging
becomes, harder to get than you
might think about, at the beginning.
So topology enriches the IDP with
runtime concept on multiple layers.
So we're speaking here not only about
how a production environment is looking,
but also with the context of the running
environment, with the context of the
running application, infrastructure.
The network layer and the APIs will
give a little bit of examples when
we're going through the following
slide, what you can see here coming
from our system that could be achieved.
I would assume by our system as well is
1st of all, the ability to automatically
get the important information coming
from the observability layers, which
parts were deployed, what type of
APIs are now being run, and that as
a beginning, Gives a very nice glance
to what was deployed in production
moving forward.
Now, if we look at the IDP hierarchy
of the IDP schema, we'll most likely be
faced with looking at specific services.
so the deployments, run, status, the
runtime configuration, which will, appear
as runtime label, so on and so forth, and
the performance of strategic services.
If we look again here, and if we look
at one of the services, now within
that context, we can see things like
the health behavior, the important,
the important metrics, which are
crucial to understand the health and
performance of that specific service,
the ability to track the deployment,
what's meant to be happening, and how it
behaves in runtime, and of course, the
events, things which are accompanying
or are the operational status of the
service in the production environment.
Moving forward with, the left element
or trying to combine what we spoke
about earlier, to the left level, this
would be, the third party resources,
the internal resources with regards to
their actual properties, things like
availability, latency, And the status of
the third party resources could be public
APIs, payment gateways, for example.
If we look here again, and now we're
looking at the real time Kubernetes
topology, here are the third parties
being used, things like the databases
or queues, runtime caches and APIs.
And also, if we'll open the, if
we'll open the internal deployment,
now we can see the runtime dynamic.
Each and everything here is accompanied
by a lot of different layers.
but the importance is you
can really see the flow.
You can really see how it's all tied
in, tied into the bigger picture.
And all this information is essentially
very complementary, and very important,
very important when, being given with,
being given with the IDP data or the
what we're trying to achieve data.
Okay, so let's, let's try to
recap and, understand at the high
level the real time topology.
It allows us to enrich the service
catalog with what we put in
our schema, what we try to do.
And what was actually happening or
represented in the runtime environment
with all the different contexts.
This would be the
configuration of dependencies.
and that's a very important goal
that we're trying to achieve.
It also provides a common language.
The IDP tries to encompass the
platform engineering way of thinking
about What is the right abstraction
level of the production environment?
That's something which is clearly need to
be explained and used by the developers.
But on the other hand, this will
implicate the runtime environment.
So the common language here
cannot go on a single way.
It's not only IDP up toward developers,
but it also, if you will, looking at the
IDP down toward the runtime environment.
And with that, the production environment
Personnel which is responsible for
maintaining that runtime environment.
SREs and DevOps would be a good example.
You have to close that loop.
And if not, then an IDP as a function
would be always a center of attention
because you need to comply with both these
layers in order for it to work in reality.
It also furnishes very crucial
context for decision making.
If I'm looking at something at the
IDP that would be exposed to my
developers, that's not the only
knowledge in the world which is crucial
in decision making throughout the
software development lifecycle and the
operational or maintenance lifecycle.
There needs to be more data
there exposed to the developers
and exposed to decision makers.
So throughout things like issues,
procuring or maintenance or
analyzing what should be done.
the entirety of the needed
information would be there, for
right decision making and to have
a clear view of what's going on.
So let's look at three
real world use cases.
anticipating a reliability impact.
one of the holy grails or trying to, or
the most wanted things to achieve is to
understand when I'm going to do something.
What is going to be the eventual
implication and how can I close that
loop as fast as we can in order to
verify that it's working indeed.
And what we anticipated is the performance
hit or is an implication on the runtime
environment could be realized very early.
of course, with that topology can enrich.
The tribal knowledge.
That's what people are thinking.
That's what people are
knowing from past experience.
what they already encountered
with past incidents.
but that with the topology becomes not
a tribal knowledge, but the actual set
of data points, which could be verified.
Understanding which are
the affected services.
If there is a runtime, implication,
is there any implication on
the service level objectives or
the service level agreements,
which I comply with to my user?
and eventually it helps us answering
real world important questions.
Example, what does the service
really cost from resource?
point of view, where there are changes
in the CPU consumption envelope, memory
consumption envelope, what is eventually
the spin off cost of a service.
The benefits are, of course, being able
to define, store stronger guardrails
within the IDP based on real world data,
based on data driven checklists, and not
based only on what we call the tribal
knowledge or based only on experience,
which is, of course, bound to be true.
are bound to be broken.
people are making a lot
of software changes.
People are making a lot
of infrastructure changes.
And new deployments will fail.
Even existing deployments
with updates will fail.
And that is something which has to be
as dynamic as the runtime environment.
real world example for something like that
could be a service which is deployed in
a high volume transaction environment.
during peak hours, we would assume to
see a lot of mechanism coming into play.
Things like auto scaling or being, being,
consuming much more, Resources, and
that often lead to incident by itself,
incidents which are related to memory
overload or any, chain events like
impacting, downstream services, things
like dashboards or front end or any, any
transaction, transactional environment.
So being able to, foresee, do a loopback
from the runtime environment towards
what's being presented in the IDP
can eventually both in a real time
environment give you the right data,
but also the process of improvement
allowed that to be, allowed that
to be incorporated within the IDP.
So the guardrails really, identify and
the guardrail, really represent what's
happening in the production environment,
and they're there for, much more,
comforting or much more, much more, real.
to what should be the, what
should be the guardrail in
the, in the actual deployment.
Another element is how we use that to
verify deployments in, in real time.
as we said, IDPs often, the, often,
offer a developer guardrail, things like,
limited memory usage, CPU usage, latency.
budget or bandwidth budget, to ensure
eventually, the efficient running
and reliable running of deployment.
These are there to make sure that
even a faulty deployment won't bring
down the entire system, but it will
be localized in a way so it doesn't,
doesn't affect the rest of the services.
but these are really in, in a lot
of times are set, during development
phase and much more, sometimes they're
based on assumptions or they based on
intuition, which is essentially the
message that we're trying to convey here.
This is a lot of times the
source of many failures.
This cannot be based on intuition, but
has to be, foreseen from the runtime
environment, which will feedback,
which will values, and pushed into
the IDP or integrated into the IDP.
So that represents what's
really happening there.
Could be two directions.
It could be that I'm thinking
something which is too low,
for the runtime environment.
Could be too high for
the runtime environment.
And that would be another aspect
of how efficient I want to be.
In the runtime environment, as a
topology can provide this runtime
monitoring of performance of deviations
from means or from any other metric,
it could accelerate the remediation by
having enough data for the developer
who is now trying to understand what's
going wrong or the platform team,
which is trying to understand what.
going on, and as we said, as the
continuous process of improvement also
allowed these guardrails to go and
eventually converge towards reality.
and when that's something which becomes
that, when that's something which becomes,
a continuous process on the platform
engineering part on the development parts,
eventually create a better methodology.
to make sure that these things
which run, smoother and smoother.
a real world example here, when
a new service is consuming more
resources, example here could be
excessive CPU, but it could be memory
or any other consumable resource.
the real time topology with regards
to, the metrics, with regards to the
log, with regards to other, evidences.
can flag that immediately and can flag
that with the content of who's speaking
to who or what's going on within the
dynamics, which is a valuable and
crucial piece of information, which are
needed by, needed by the developers.
Investigating and responding to issues.
So we understand that I did.
I did these support a lot of the time.
The notions of incident.
They support a lot of the time
the integration with observability
tools, either on the infrastructure
layer or the observability layers.
They're supporting integration
with third party or higher layer
incident management platforms.
So the data is.
contextualized.
The data is already meant to be there.
the service catalog is a very valuable
asset for root cause analysis.
It's essentially the building
blocks which I'm trying to look at.
And the root cause or the source
of an issue is going to be most
likely something within the catalog.
There are caveats to that.
the example that we gave about third
parties, but most likely if it's a,
an issue and internal issue, it's
going to be an element, which is
part of the catalog, the problem
or the element, which is missing.
It's only extending through.
Again, what I'm trying to configure,
what is my schema, what I'm trying to
orchestrate into the runtime environment.
If we bring in the information from
the runtime environment, now we have
essentially the matching between the
catalog and the runtime catalog, if
you will, and those crosses between
them are essentially a very important
part in the root code analysis or.
issue analysis that any engineering team
is going to run through, essentially
trying to mark off elements which
are not relevant until they converge
on the element which is faulty.
So that is a very natural and
native behavior for teams to act
with and the tools like the IDP has
to support it and has to bring in
the data in order to enable that.
A real world example here, I team needs to
identify whether a service, which is now
a faulty, degrading toward the customer or
towards the internal customer, is related
to issues with third party resource.
That would be something which is
really hard to do just based on.
Orchestration or just based on the
configuration part, we have to have
more data in order to understand
the health of that service to
understand the dynamic and use of that
service with 3rd party or external.
Dependencies and that should be again.
Presented towards the platform
engineering team towards the
development to understand.
We're not only where to look at, but
put, to put a focus or, to pinpoint the
exact location of where it can start.
And that's something which cannot be
achieved just by looking, just by looking
at static schema or just looking at,
just looking at the service catalog.
It has to come from somewhere else,
but it's very important to look at
that with, with regards and with the
context of the elements in the system.
Thank you.
Common pitfalls and, how to avoid them.
the maintenance, it's essentially,
true for a lot of things.
but closing the loop between the service
catalog and runtime is only a first step.
don't put, don't overlook the
resourcing or don't think it would
be, a minor or a, a very small
engineering effort, to keep it properly
maintained, to audit it, to service it.
There's a lot of, there's
a lot of commitment.
Which is needed here to make the
thing, to make these things run
smoothly, to operate smoothly.
But that is for sure an investment,
an investment, worthwhile of, doing.
Incomplete runtime context.
In order to do what we're speaking
about, you need enough context.
And depending on the complexity of the
system, depending on the amount of,
if you will, free variables, in the
system, which includes the resources,
the APIs, the third party services.
this thing is sometimes hard to bring,
not only in terms of actually having
the data, but from the configuration
of the runtime tool set, from, the
aspect of how much Investment is
needed from not only time perspective,
but also tool price perspective to
having all the different connectors
to the different layers in the runtime
environment and bring it all to the IDP.
It's worth mentioning here that
technologies like EVPF technology
can enable auto discovery of
the runtime environment, which
can better and ease the toil.
of exposing that data, without manually
going and configure a million type of
dashboard, a million type of connection
point, could be very helpful here.
static snapshot.
so to be useful, the runtime
topology need to be continuously and
automatically discovered and updated.
Not only is a way to.
Collect this data, analyze these data,
able to not use a lot of documentation,
which is most of the time irrelevant
on the, on the day of writing it.
so being able to actually get that,
as a continuous process, is super
important and saves a lot of time
of trying to do it in any other way.
Tips for getting started.
building your topology.
of course, observability tools can help.
A lot of them has elements like, a lot of
them has elements like, runtime topology,
usually based on things like, DNS.
Or basic modes of, networking,
but they often require a lot of
configuration around them to.
Explore all the different, layers.
there are platforms that offer auto
discovery, in real time or real mapping,
if you will, of the environment.
This is, as we said earlier, often with
the help of technologies like eBPF,
which are exposing, the dynamics, not
only from a configuration point of
view, Or, or not only from the tendency
point of view, but stemming from real
networking elements, real interaction
between the different services.
the integration of your, the integration
of the topology with the IDP.
the IDP, already most of them offer
integration with observability
and incident response platform.
It would be very native, it would be very
native to integrate, the topology part.
With the caveat we said, we spoke
about earlier, as good as the good.
It'll only be as good as the topology,
exposed from, from the observability tool.
but that is as a first step, even
bringing it front facing, towards the
user of the IDP, is very important
to put all the needed data in one
place, and have, and have this data
reachable, by the u by the users of
the, IDP, prioritization of use cases.
Prioritization is, naturally important, in
any engineering, in any engineering venue.
but being able to identify the quick wins.
Where are the hotspots?
Where are the services which are more
tailored toward failure, which makes
more, problems or makes more challenges?
In the production
environment, focus on them.
You don't need to solve the entire system.
You won't be able to solve an entire
system, especially if the scalable,
scalable one, but the ability to.
minimize that look at the important
part, the important building blocks,
whether they're internal, whether
they're a platform or infrastructure
part or service elements or third
party elements, which are super
important priorities based on them.
And eventually, when the relevant
team is looking at the IDP or the
relevant thing is using the IDP.
If we can put this quick win to
where that specific team on the
grand scheme of things, it's not only
net positive, largely net positive,
because from the beginning, these
are the elements which are most, most
likely to require that and use that.
and the last element would
be to scale and expand.
Very, very common if we're speaking
about the concept of quick wins, but you
need to prove to the users of the IDP.
This is a valuable tool.
So using this early win and being able
to go step by step, building more or
additional opportunities to weave in
or to put in the runtime context into
the IDP are Not only valuable, but as a
process of internal con conveying, whereas
the process of proving internally that.
Winning mechanism are super important
and using this, strategy to build it in
step, prove it in step and eventually
using it in step, are going to eventually
affect the software development life
cycle, the deployment life cycle.
All of that would be achieved,
improving in, in ways that,
people can cope with that.
I really hope that you enjoyed
that as much as we did.
we think there's, A very
large room for collaboration.
We're in large collaboration between
what's being done on the observability
world between advances in, in,
the abilities in the observability
world and how real time topologies
could be auto discovered, exposed,
maintained by the tools themselves, and
integrating this data toward the IDP.
eventually it becomes, only logical
that we're speaking about things like
a continuous integration, continuous
development, and thinking about the
software development lifecycle, deployment
lifecycle, those tools has to work
in, have to work in, have to work in
conjunction, to water, to one another,
they're complimenting one another.
And each and every one of them is
depending on the other one from things
like the IDP, which encompass the
organizational knowledge about what should
be defined, how it should be orchestrated,
where it should be orchestrated.
And eventually doing, the deployment,
doing the deployment or commanding the
deployment, to the production environment.
And of course, all the way through the
outer hand, which is the deployment
environment or the runtime environment,
in reality, and those won't leave
this cannot to cannot live in void.
Eventually, they're dependent not
only with the teams which need to work
together in order to solve issues or
to add capabilities to the system.
But also, from technical perspective,
there is going to be a lot of
convergence between the abilities of
those two on integration here is native.
I really hope that you enjoyed it.
we will be happy to answer any
question by email or by, by coming
to us through, through the website.
And I wish you very happy,
very, very productive day.
Thank you.