Hi, my name is Omer Farooq, and today I'll
talk about how to secure applications that
are built around Gen AI or integrate Gen
AI capability into existing applications.
But before we get started, I'd
like to talk about a little bit
about myself and introduce myself.
I am a founder and security engineer
at Oxford Security based in Maryland.
We've been around since 2018 and we've
been able, we have been able to help over
50 different customers build out their
digital transformation general journey
from on-prem to hybrid to multi-cloud.
We've been able to help them integrate
DevSecOps, including DAST, SAST,
and interactive testing and security
validation of the networks, and then
their phishing attacks as part of
their large scale security initiatives.
We are experts and we take a lot of
pride in presenting data as technically
close to as, with engineering
rigor and engineering practices.
We make sure that our data is
transparently available to not
only our customers, but when
possible to our larger audience.
That's why we take a lot of our time
and we make sure that we present
and give back to the community.
So today, in that spirit, we'll talk
about how to secure Gen AI applications
or applications that exist and
are integrating Gen AI capability.
And what that mean and how to do that
rapidly and do it in a way that scales up.
So we will start off by a little
bit of short introductions
about LLM applications.
We'll go into how LLM applications
are built and what are the challenges.
This will include application
frameworks and include an
application development methodology.
And then we'll dive into more into how
to automate LLM application deployment.
either as part of existing tooling's
tool set or to build new tool sets.
And finally, we'll cover LLM
security, how to make sure that you
be strategically built LLM application
secure, and how do we tactically do
things to make sure that they are
actually built securely by engineers.
One of the key underlying themes we would
like to make sure that we follow along
with this Is that we understand that
LLAMP applications are no different from
existing applications, but the trick is
to make sure that we do not increase the
OpEx or the operating costs to expand the
application sets or the functionality.
We should be able to integrate these
new function exciting technology into
our existing applications without having
to redesign or reengineer our delivery,
our integration and our security.
So let's get started and go
and talk about LM applications.
So the talk title is LM SecOps.
And I like to type to put that
together and used and put that
together to a, to the Venn diagram
that we have on the screen.
LLM applications usually
are on the form of chatbots.
That do summarization to translation.
Basically, there are things that are
either used by machines or users.
that are based on the principle
of a question or query.
And there is a response.
But there's much more than that.
LLM applications usually have
built in semantic search.
They have built in complicated
data rights management platforms.
They have a lot of data life cycles.
So we'll talk about that
as part of our LLM Ops.
So when we are integrating and we are
building out applications with LLM
capability, we need to understand how to
make sure the data life cycle policies The
data ownership and classification policies
are extended for the current existing
applications into LLM applications.
And this overlaps with the security.
As it, as the organizations shift left,
we need to make sure the LLM security
Shift left at the same time, and thus,
we'll talk about how to secure the
models, how to secure data, how to
ensure data privacy, how to build the
data rights management, how to ensure
the data is only in granularly available
to the right set of people when they're
asking a question on a large data sets.
So once again, LLM SecOps is a
combination of LLM applications,
LLM CI CD automation, LLM security.
I'd like to, I'd like to start
out with a high level picture.
This is a one view of the world,
but it's not, and it should not be
considered all reference models.
But one common reference
model for LM applications is
the model around how to build
a chat bot or a machine to machine
interface that essentially has a
query and then gets back a response.
And essentially, usually a query
is translated to our embedding.
Those embeddings are looked up in a
vector database to find the closest
data set that is related to that.
Sometimes this is also used, AI is
used to build the right level of query
by something called semantic index.
the data itself is injected
into initial data prompt.
and the data prompt is optimized by
either building a bigger context or
using L-M-A-P-I to ensure the prompt
itself is functional and optimized,
and then the you, the prompt is
routed through the LM ap, LME, through
the l to the LM through the API or
sometimes you have LM caching the data.
The response is content filtered.
And the content filter response is
provided back to the user of the machine.
This high level architecture presents,
is not super difficult to understand.
But one of the things that I like
to point out at this point is that
it is important to maybe possibly
build a reference application or
build LM applications in two ways.
One, keep the front end, the
UI or the machine interface
separate from the back end.
And this can help organizations
in multiple different fashions.
From OPEX point of view, building a
single large multi tenant LLM backend
can help you build out one, one, one,
one backend that has a detailed rights
management for data and assets that
can be front to multiple different
application types, either bots, Other
translation services, data summarization
services, middleware that use the
LAI, or even other AI services.
This segregate, this decoupling of
the frontend to the backend will
help also with security and the
development and deployment of it.
We'll show that how decoupling of this
application at the backend and the
frontend is critical in actually making
sure security scales up at the same time.
Not all frontend applications are going
to be equally complex, but they will
have their own set of requirements.
It makes sense to secure the frontend
applications using current existing non
LM security models, and then ensure that
all the new future LM security provisions
only have to be done once in the large
one singular backend that could be
frontend for multiple different frontends.
what are some of the high level
challenges that are usually part
of LM applications development?
One, there's a lot of integrations.
LM applications are data routing
applications where a certain
amount of data is pulled, a certain
amount of data is acquired from
sometimes real applications.
Near real time systems.
It could be coming from OT equipment.
It could come from IOT.
It could come from Bing search.
It could come from search engines
from the, from specific catalogs.
It, the data could cut, the data
could be egressed and ingress
from all types of data sources.
That's what makes LM
applications very powerful.
Being able to build and, Chains of events
or change of data interactions that makes
the query and the response very powerful.
Data integrations represents
few critical security issues.
All integrations require you to have
secure network, all require you to
ensure that you have delegated access.
And furthermore, it ensures that
you, the data that's being accessed
on the base, based on the initial
request user has entitlement to that
data that's going to be used for his
semantic search is going to be used
for his AI search or his AI query.
Furthermore, as the data is being
embedded and pulled into the embedding
databases, the LM applications,
that data needs to be equally.
Part of your data lifecycle
process, but the retention policy,
the classification policies and
data catalog and tags and labels.
This becomes a difficult challenge
when you're dealing with a lot of data.
But at scale for different
front end systems.
We'll talk about how to use
specific tools and technologies
and concepts to build that out.
That's part of our LM Ops.
And finally, if not equally
important is the AI services.
It is possible an AI application or
AI back end that is LM application
back end will interact with
multiple models, if not one or more.
We need to be very careful about how
those model integrations and models
APIs are protected, not just for cost.
But also for availability, ensuring
those meter services are logged, making
sure that those model communications
are protected over the public
Internet with at least with some
level of data encryption at rest.
The data itself, when you're inquiring
from the user to all the way to the
model, can potentially include a lot
of proprietary, if not sensitive data.
including personal information, including
things that could be considered privilege.
Thus, AI API model security is equally
important and needs to be considered
as part of the LM application security.
We'll cover this and we'll talk
about how that can be secured as part
of our LM SecOps, which is in the
latter part of this conversation.
So before we get into a little
bit of how and what LM application
look like, I like to start out with
saying, let's put a developer hat on.
And how do you build an LM application or
how do you actually add an LM application
capability into existing application?
you have two major components.
You have the actual logic and of data
integration, and then you have the model.
And Understanding the use of the
right model is very important.
That also is equally important because
not all models offer the same type
of security and responsible ethical
AI capability as other models.
Pulling an open source model from public
internet versus a model that's managed
and curated has different set of side
effects and different consequences.
Be careful when you
choose the right model.
Also, like as we mentioned prior.
Keep the front end of the application,
the bot, the user, or the machine to
machine interfaces separate and try
not to consider those as part of the
LM applications as much because those
could be factored out and developed
using existing application interfaces
or with low code, no code solutions and
keep a focus on building one time an LM
backend that could be secured with data
rights management and other features.
And does not have to be redeveloped.
Another feature of LLM applications,
this is very important to cover because
this dictates how security and how
development works is the fact that LLM
applications are cloud native artifact.
They were built in the cloud.
They've come from most of the
development is in the cloud.
And that means is that a lot of
the components, part of the rapid
prototype and fast results methodology
for LM application required to use
a lot of open source data router
frameworks like slang chain, a
semantics kernel, and llama index.
You will have a lot of
components of all resource.
If not, the entire model
could be open source.
You will be using a lot of low
code, no code for your front end.
You will be using, leveraging a
lot of cloud services, including
serverless and managed services for
AI and AI related compute and storage.
And most of the times, if not all,
you will be utilizing some kind of a
vector database that will be sitting
in the cloud or could be on prem
that needs to be protected equally,
just like the way we traditionally
protect traditional databases.
Though the purpose of the vector
database is an It's a bit different,
and the capability is different,
and the data context is different.
We still need to protect the vector
database equally as the data, how
we protect traditional relational
and non relational databases.
before we get further, I'd like to point
out three large principles for data
application security for LM applications.
One, decouple the architecture.
Applications should be cloud
native whenever possible.
Applications should be managed services
as much as possible and vector databases
should be, should, per storage and
performance should be considered.
Now, these principles are not entirely for
LLM application development for security
development, but they're part of a general
principles that you should consider.
Decoupled architecture will provide
you better return on your investment.
Applications in cloud native will allow
you to do rapid prototype, which is part
of what all applications are built like.
And vector databases that have higher
performance of storage functionality
will allow you to make sure that you have
the data rights management at scale, so
you can build a decoupled architecture
that we want to build for security.
So the next concept that we want
to talk about is now that we know
what the, what LM applications look
like, and we understand the design
principles and how the methodology for
LM application is, which means fast
prototypes, build fast, fail fast.
How do we do that?
And the one and that is basically, and
how do we do that with existing tools?
And how do we do that?
with, without learning new tricks
and how do we make sure that we do it
quickly in a way that we don't slow
down the prototypes and the development.
going from Jupyter Notebook, for
example, to an application can be done
quite literally over, over a few hours.
But when you do it at a scale and do it
from an organizational point of view, how
do you bring all those teams together?
you can use your existing pipelines.
The good news is if the additional of a
few stages and steps in your cloud native
or your on prem automation, you should
be able to support LLM application.
How do we do that?
let's start with
automation and deployment.
The backend applications that are part
of the LM applications are no different.
There are still cloud native, but
yet, but the minute differences are
about the configurations of the model,
how to integrate the keys and how to
integrate this, the service accounts.
All of those should be
deployed and automated in the
similar fashions we do today.
Integrations of secrets, integrations
of tokens should be done in a similar
fashion as we do today, except with
the caveat that, remember, a lot of the
applications for LM are meter services.
In that scenario, we do suggest to pick
up the speed and use delegated access.
Whenever possible, make sure that you
build LM apps within your application.
To utilize the end users credentials
and users, identity for meter service
past that responsibility out of
the model and don't manage it at a
large level manager, the user, the
organizational department level.
Build new indexes and new detections
and new threat detections for you
in your SecOp tooling for LLM ops.
There, there won't be that different
for your existing, but they will require
to have separate LLM For example, for
prompt injection and data and prompt
poisoning, you will need to build
that in your, in the threat detection.
For example, if you see a user.
Continuously trying to do prop injection.
you need to build out new threat detection
scenarios in your same tool or your threat
intelligence, threat planning tool, keep
it, you need to pull in the fees for the
threat intelligence to make sure that
they include the LLM application types.
And if not the last and the most
informed data management, you do
need to enable encryption at rest.
Encryption in transit, encryption in use,
we need to make sure the embeddings, the
question and the answer, the responses
that are logged into the applicant,
that are logging the data, the questions
that are asked by the users of services
are considered privileged information.
One of the key things we need to make
sure the part of the LMOPS is that you
need to make sure there are column, if
not in column encryption to protect.
The response and the requests
that the application will see.
This can be considered equally
privileged as two people's conversation.
Because people and users will ask
and inquire things that are either
very personal or PII, include PII,
or do include company private,
company sensitive, or general
sensitive data in their queries.
Thank you for listening.
the queries have to be protected, have
to be only available to a certain users.
The honor trail and the investigative
and the forensic investigation should
only be available to a certain users.
The data rights management of the
log data is a critical component.
And we suggest that, we suggest
using column encryption.
We use suggesting using double encryption
to make sure those columns with the data
requests and data prompts are protected.
Before we get into LMSecOps, security
ops, we need to cover the Some of the what
left high level privilege and what are
we really protecting and work and trying
to gear towards with an LM application?
And how is that different for
from a traditional application?
Traditional applications are also equally
worried about data leakage, but they
are less worried about prompt rejection.
They're less worried about what model
poisoning to some extent because
sometimes there are no models.
adversarial attacks against LLM
applications are different than from
the nature of the attacks that are
for existing non LLM applications.
For example, adversarial attacks
on LLM application could be to
introduce LLM hallucination.
And finally, the ethical concerns are
our primary part of the LLM SecOps and
how do we make sure we manage those.
So let's start with ethical concerns.
Ethical concerns are something that you,
that we should think about when we're
building out applications, and those
could be tuned using content filtering.
Data leakage can be addressed using
data rights management and double
encryption or column encryption.
Adversarial attacks can be protected
and detected using SecOps and threat
detection and threat intelligence.
Model poisoning and prompt injection
can be protected using the traditional
input validation, metered throttle
responses, content filtering, and
those type of built in cloud resources
for making sure that the model stays
protected and inputs are checked.
Next, but finally, we get to the
point where we can actually do things
today to protect our LLM applications.
I filed them under the Tactical LLM
SecOps and essentially these are the
few steps at high level that we can
take today using existing tooling
to protect our LLM applications.
Number one, use your existing tooling for
DAST and SAST to ensure that all LLM open
source components that include SCA, that
includes using SCA tools or using SAS
tools, Make sure you all the code that
is written for your LM application is
equally goes through your secure coding
practices as your other code, even though
it might be cloud native, even though
it might be more configuration heavy,
even though it might be something that
looks as an, as a serverless function.
All of this code needs to
be protected and reviewed.
we suggest using tools for.
as existing pipeline steps to run
scans of this code, making sure that
these particular code snippets of the
code libraries are able to protect
against prompt injection are able
to protect against model poisoning.
There are certain different
tools out there that are able to
look for these kind of patterns
within the LM based type of code.
So if you already have code that is able
to do build semantic index or is able to
do response or input query caching, you
can build out and scan this particular
piece of code with these scanners to
ensure you are focused and hyper focused
on finding those vulnerabilities.
Ensure that content filtering, ensure
that content filtering is both ways,
that the input and the output, ensure
the model does not, is not, does not,
is not able to accept PII, or is not
able to, or is able to accept PII if
needed, but to a certain limitations.
Make sure the data that gets
ingressed, ingressed into the model
is classified, is labeled, is tagged.
Those are the things that at the
code level you can check today.
You can make sure that the rights
management with your back end
logic is tested and using DAST
and other validation tools.
And last if not least, ensure
all your logs for all your
applications are end to end.
And they're able to capture data capture
from user to machine and back to the user.
In case you need to go back and
trace out LLM interactions to
either find detection of abuse, or
detection of illegal data usage, or
model hallucination, or model prompt
injection, those ones will be critical.
Thank you for joining me today for this
conversation about LLM Security Ops.
I hope you had, I hope you had enjoyed
this conversation and took away the
key points about how to keep the data
front end and the back end separate,
how to build up the automation
and the security from a shift left
perspective from day one in your LLM
applications or adding the capability
of LLM into existing applications.
If you have any further questions
or you would like to have a dialogue
or if you'd like to have questions,
feedback, feel free to contact us at www.
auxin.
io.
My email is omarfarouq at auxin.
io and I'm always happy to respond
back to constructive feedback.
Thank you and have a great day.