Hi everyone, I'm Rishabh Mehra and today
I'll be talking about on device large
language models, which I believe is a path
to safer and more efficient AI systems.
Let me start by describing who I am
and why I'm talking about this topic.
So I studied computer science at Stanford
where I was researching on computer
vision systems under Professor Fei Li.
We worked on publishing
papers in MLHC and NeurIPS.
in the computer vision
and healthcare field.
From there, I went to Apple, where I
worked on device machine learning models
to make iOS smarter as a system, as
well as prototyping efforts for Apple
Intelligence, which was a large language
modeling system Apple launched recently.
Now I'm working on Pinnacle, which
is a startup in the intersection
of all three of those fields.
Also, as a fun fact, I have, an
interest in rock climbing and that's
why it shows up in the pie chart there.
Alright, now let's look at the table of
contents for today and what we'll cover.
We'll start with why on device LLMs
matter, why we're talking about these.
We'll talk about state of the art,
what's out there, and we'll see
some examples of how they perform.
We'll go through some real world use
cases which are already deployed.
Then we'll talk about what MVP
is and what the path to this
MVP would be in my opinion.
And we'll conclude with where I see
these models in the next five years
and the applications they'll enable.
All right, let's start with the first
topic, why on device LLMs matter.
Let's start by first understanding
what large language models are.
The way I like to define large language
models, of course at a very high level,
is through a three word game I used to
play with my sister when I was young.
I would say three words, my sister
would follow up with the three most
likely words she think would be best,
and then I would say three words, and
so on until we formed a full story.
Interestingly, large language models
are trying to do the same thing.
You give them a bunch of words, And
they reply with a bunch of words
which they think make the most
logical sense, given what you said.
Of course, this is a very high
level definition, but that's the
task they're trying to perform.
Now let's talk about three
major problems I believe there
are with large language models.
The first is privacy evasion, invasion.
Privacy invasion occurs because the
types of applications that use large
language models need personal data.
They're often you telling it
information or providing it
information through your computer
screen, et cetera, which they process.
This raises major privacy concerns
because you might be sharing your data
with an LLM provider like OpenAI, but
also an intermediary like a startup.
So you need to trust both those companies.
Large language models also have
a massive carbon footprint.
For example, just training GPT 4 in
an article was shown to have emissions
equivalent to driving 18 million
miles in a gasoline car and a single
inference call to GPT 4, again in an
article, was shown to be equivalent of
charging a mobile phone 60 times over.
Then also another problem
with large language models is
their ability to mimic humans.
This is because large language
models are essentially producing
language similar to humans and this
leads to problems such as deepfakes.
The internet is flooded with
deepfakes, but also the possibility
of fraud increasing a lot.
For example, imagine getting a call in the
voice of your mother and your mother tells
you she's hurt and she needs some money.
You'll probably transfer the money,
but later you'll realize that this
was just a large language model
talking in your mother's voice.
This is a very big concern, but
we won't talk about this today
because this is a whole other talk.
We'll cover the first and
the second points today.
So moving these large language
models from the internet to on
device solves the first two problems.
This is because on device
models are off the grid.
They don't need internet.
They don't need any external connection.
There is no middleman.
Everything is on your device.
So there's no privacy risk anymore.
And as a result of these models having
to run on device, they're automatically
smaller, and smaller means that they're
greener, and they essentially have,
will have a lesser carbon footprint.
And this is again, just by
design that you have to make them
smaller to run on the computer.
All right, now let's talk
about state of the art LLMs.
Where is this technology today?
What does it look like?
And we'll do this through two demos.
So for the first demo, I'll give
the following prompt to the LLM.
Hello, I'll be giving a presentation
with the topic on device LLMs, a path to
a safer and more efficient AI systems.
Can you give me a one line opener,
make it engaging and thought provoking?
So I take this prompt and I will
Copy the prompt and then I'll use
OLAMA, which is a way to essentially
run large language models on device.
The model I'm running is LAMA 3.
1.
This is a model by Meta and
it has 8 billion parameters.
This is now loading into
the memory of my computer.
I paste the prompt and run it and
it gives me a reasonable response.
Let's read the first one.
As we increasingly rely on AI, Can
we afford not to rethink the way
we build models from edges of our
networks to edges of our devices?
Makes sense.
It's nice.
It's not perfect, but it's a good start.
All right.
Now just to get a baseline, sorry,
before we get the baseline, we try
to run this on Lama billion, which
is a much bigger model by Facebook.
And this is now loading into memory.
But as I'll soon realize this
doesn't actually load into
the memory of my computer.
I open activity monitor and I see
this model is taking tons of memory.
It's already taking 32 gigs, which
is more than what this computer has.
So this model essentially
cannot run on my device.
so we've seen that the model
size on device is seven to 10
billion, somewhere around there.
now just to get a baseline, we
run the same prompt in GPD 4.
0.
So I paste the prompt, run it.
And I get the response, which is,
imagine smartphone is not just smart,
but a powerhouse of intelligent privacy.
Welcome to the new frontier
with on device LLMs.
So perfect opening, exactly what I wanted.
And that's what we have
come to expect from GPD 4.
0.
But of course, this is
still running in the cloud.
And as we saw, Lama 8, we produced
a response, which made sense, but
it's not at the level of GPD 4.
0 yet.
All right, now for the second test,
we'll do a coding challenge where
we'll get these models to create
Minesweeper, a popular game, and
we'll see how the different models do.
So let's start by copying this
prompt I created to write, make
the models write Minesweeper.
And we'll again start with
Llama8B, the tiny model by Meta
that runs fully on my device.
As you can see, it produces
code which makes sense.
It's calling the init function,
print board, create mines,
count adjacent mines, reveal.
All of this makes sense for
a typical minesweeper game.
So now, it's, Finishing producing
this code, it's written the play
function, which is a while loop
to play this game indefinitely
until you hit a mine, of course.
now I can go ahead and copy the code.
I'll paste the code into a Python
file called minesweeper llama8b.
py.
And then I'll go ahead and run the code.
Unfortunately for Llama, it doesn't run.
it only took me 15 to 20 minutes to
correct it so it wasn't too off and
other iterations produce slightly better
code which sometimes even compiled.
okay now to get a baseline
let's go to GPT 4.
0, paste the prompt and as you can see
it very quickly generates the code.
Of course this is again running
on the server and we expect this
to be great but just to get a
baseline let's see what it does.
The code looks similar to what
was produced by Lama, but of
course, as we know, the quality
is expected to be a lot better.
So I do the same thing.
I copy the code, go back to the terminal,
create a file called minesweeper gpt40.
py, paste the code, and now I run it.
And here we get a perfectly
working version of Minesweeper.
I type 3 4, hit a mine,
and lose in the first turn.
So let's go ahead and play once more.
And here I can essentially run through the
entire game of Minesweeper where I'm going
through different options I've chosen.
This is fast forwarded and
then eventually I write 3 3.
hit a mine and the game ends.
All right, now the interesting part.
We're going to paste the same prompt,
but in a very different model.
This model is called CodeQuin.
This is by the Alibaba group in China.
this model is only a 7
billion parameter model.
So it's a much smaller model than even,
or not much smaller, but a smaller model
than the Lama model we saw earlier.
So it's able to run fully on device.
But the interesting thing about
this model is it's customized and
tuned to do well on coding tasks.
So its strength is coding and it
outperforms LLAMA as we'll see soon.
So right now it's writing code,
it creates the board, counts the
mines, reveals a similar structure
to what LLAMA was producing.
It's a bit slower running on memory, even
though it's a smaller parameter model.
Presumably it's not as
optimized as Llama for MacBooks.
so I'll give it a second
to just finish coding.
Almost there.
Alright.
There we go.
It's finished the setup.
code given some description.
I will go ahead, copy the code and follow
the same procedure where I'll create,
I'll copy the code, create a Python
file called Minesweeper code or q7b.
py, paste the code
and then I run it.
Interestingly, it shows me the locations
of the mines visibly, which is a bit
weird, but it at least runs the code.
Then we write the location of a mine
03, but it doesn't end the game.
Then I write 00, which is not the location
of the mine, and that, that works well.
So essentially it's playing Minesweeper
correctly, except that it shows the
mines at the beginning and hitting
the mines do not end the game.
I played around with this code after
the demo and it took me less than five
minutes to make it fully functional.
So it was definitely higher quality
than what Llama8B had created for me.
All right, we have looked at,
these models qualitatively,
but let's look at some numbers.
sorry, the bottom right number is
hidden because of my video, but it's 78.
So let's start from the top left, LAMA 3.
1, the 8 billion parameter model.
let's look at the chat reasoning
task, so how well it performs
on chat tasks and coding tasks.
So for LAMA 3.
1, The 8 billion parameter model got a
73 on chat and about the same on coding.
The 70 billion got 86 on chats,
an amazing score for such a small
model and the same on coding.
GPT 4.
0 got 86.
7 on chat and 87.
8 on coding.
So again, close to each other.
But CodeGrend, the tiny model
by the Alibaba group, got
78 on the coding challenge.
So much higher than the 8 billion
parameter Lama model like we saw earlier.
And this shows us the importance of having
task specific models, which we'll talk
about more in the coming slides as well.
Next, let's explore the current
real world use cases for on
device large language models.
So these are use cases
already out there in the wild.
Here's a list of these use cases.
Some of these are large language
models and some of these are related
technologies, which use similar
tech to large language models.
So style transfer, this
is already out there.
If you want to convert your
email to a more friendly email
or a more professional email.
This is already possible today
with large language models.
Speech to text.
Converting, your audio to text is a very
important task and this actually works
really well fully on device today already.
probably almost as good as the
server side model to be honest.
Summarization.
summarization does work on device today.
It's not as good as server
side, but it's pretty good.
You can get 80 percent of the
value you'll want out of it.
And finally, translation, same as
summarization, works really well
on device, slightly worse than
server side, but it's almost there.
Now let's actually look at some of these
use cases in action through a demo.
All right, so let's go through the
use cases which we saw before through
the eyes of Apple Intelligence.
Apple Intelligence is a suite of
features Apple launched in iOS 18.
1.
Some of the features in this
demo also came before that.
As you can see, the phone is on
airplane mode, so there's no internet.
This is fully on device, not running
a model on the server or anything.
So what I'm doing here is I'm in the
notes app, and I'm typing an email.
Hi Alex, reached this site.
Good to meet you, but I don't think
now is the right time to collaborate.
While I love your vision
question mark, the product
isn't the right fit, right now.
Hope to collaborate, someday.
RISH.
So not great English, but it's a start.
So I can go ahead and select this.
I can go to writing tools, which
is one of the new features Apple
launched, and I can click on proofread.
So here Apple suggests me
change a couple of words.
RISH comma this side, good
to meet, and then some days
combined into a single word.
Not super helpful, but it's okay.
So let's try some other writing tool.
this time I select writing
tools and I click rewrite.
So rewrite is now going to
rewrite the message as expected.
So it says, Rish, it's great
to meet you on this side.
So I think Rish is the other person
instead of me, which is incorrect,
but let's look at the second sentence.
However, I don't believe this is
the appropriate time to collaborate.
So this sentence and the rest of the
email is a lot better than before.
So it's getting there.
It's actually improving it the way I want.
Let's just remove RISC to make
the job simpler for the LLM.
And this time when I select the
email, I'll go to writing tools, but
I'll just change it to a friendly
tone, so style transfer this time.
And I get the response, Hi Alex.
It's great to meet you.
I think we're both on the same page about
wanting to collaborate in the future.
I just don't think now is the
right time to work together
on this particular project.
I hope we can still find a way to
work with each other in the future.
So work flawlessly.
Next let's test dictation.
Dictation is essentially, speech to text.
I'm seeing the sentence.
You can't hear it.
Hi, this is a test for seeing
how the dictation works.
And it again worked flawlessly, fully
on device, airplane mode is still on.
Next, let's try selecting
this entire email.
And we'll try to create
a summary of this email.
I don't want to go
through this whole email.
So I'll go to writing
tools and click on summary.
Unfortunately, that does not
work without the internet.
So just to make sure it works
with the internet, let's turn
on the internet, writing tools.
And I click on Summary.
And I got a summary telling me the events
with Uber, Bloomberg, Citadel, etc.
And RSVPs are required
for all these events.
So I got all the information
I needed perfectly there.
Next, let's look at Spotlight.
Meet Alex at 10 a.
m.
Airplane mode is on again,
and I got a meeting invite.
So there's NLP matching going
on here, even if it may not be
fully large language models.
That's unknown.
Next, let's look at Translate.
So I try to translate hello.
It doesn't work without the internet.
So I turn on the internet and what I can
do now is I can click the three dots and
click on download languages, scroll down,
And I can simply download Spanish onto my,
iPhone, so now it should work on device.
It also downloads English.
So now I go back into airplane mode
and I write, can I get the churros?
And it translates to Spanish without the
internet because airplane mode is on.
And presumably this is correct.
And I write thank you and it says
gracias, which I know is correct.
Next I have all these
lists of notifications.
I can click show less airplane mode is on
And I get a summary of the notifications.
So summary in this context seems to
work without the internet as well
All right, that's just a rapid fire
of a bunch of features in apple
intelligence that work without the
internet hence running fully on device
Next, let's talk about the path to MVP.
MVP, in my opinion, if we can reach GPD 4.
0 level performance being the accuracy
on device, that would be game changing.
That would be a product that will actually
be extremely valuable in everyday life.
To reach this target, I believe we'll
have to improve the hardware to be able
to run 30 billion parameters on device.
I think these 8 to 10 billion parameter
models are still too small to have enough
information, but we see promising results
from 60, 70 billion parameter models.
I'm sure we can make them smaller,
perhaps to the size of around 30 billion.
Models need to be more specialized.
So like we saw CodeGwent
absolutely outperformed, Lama 3.
18 billion, despite having
similar number of parameters, just
because it was coding specific.
You can go one level deeper.
You can make it Python specific
instead of coding in general,
and that might be even better.
Next, we need to improve adapters.
So adapters are things like
LoRa adapters, which can.
Which again, I can't go into details,
that would be a whole other talk,
but essentially can add a layer
of specialization without having
to recreate a whole new model.
So let's say you have a Python
specialized model, you can then use
a LoRa adapter to make it a model
for creating games using Python.
So we've become even more
specialized using adapters.
So in terms of software innovations,
we already talked about, the second
and third point, which is adapter
mechanisms and specializations.
But one more thing that needs
to be innovated is enhanced
compression techniques.
so not only on the hardware side
can we reduce the parameters, but
we can start compressing these
models into smaller and smaller
models, pulling out the parameters.
by using better compression techniques.
And then on the hardware side, we
need optimized processing units
to run bigger and bigger models.
Instead of 10 billion models, we should be
able to run 30 billion or higher models.
But also we need an enhanced
memory architecture.
This would be the RAM system.
because these models need to be
extremely quick, so they need a
really solid memory architecture.
I'm not a hardware expert, so I can't
go into details about these topics,
but at a high level with, in what I've
discussed with hardware experts, these are
the two main frontiers we need to push.
All right, and then finally,
let's say all of this happens.
We have 30 billion parameters.
These models are running fully on
devices, specialized, have adapters.
What's the outcome?
Let's talk about the real world
use cases these models will enable.
So the first is augmented workflows.
These models will become deeply
integrated into everyone's work life.
You'll be able to share your entire work
context with these models because they're
not sending any data to the server and
they'll streamline every single task
in your life, whether it's emails, data
analysis, presentations, or even like
filling out Excel sheets or writing code.
The next is On Device Therapy.
On Device Therapy will become better
with these models because you'll be
able to share more and you'll have
advice available at all times, in
your pocket or on your computer.
Legal assistance.
This will help both lawyers,
because they'll be able to share
client data with these models,
at any time to get information.
And they can trust these models because
they're running fully on device,
but they can also help the layman
to get legal assistance quickly,
without having to engage a lawyer.
And again, they can trust this model
because it's fully on their device.
So they can have that same,
lawyer client, relationship.
with this model where they know the
model will not breach their trust.
And then finally medical diagnosis.
Medical diagnosis will again be empowered
by these models because you'll again
be more willing to share your personal
data and you'll be willing to share
your entire medical history with these
models because they're fully on your
device so you don't have to worry about
where your data goes and you can get
really accessible healthcare diagnosis.
and potentially even
treatment using these models.
That's all I have for today.
Thank you for coming to the talk.
If you have any questions or
follow ups, please feel free to
email me at rish at pinnacle.
co.
Thank you so much.
Bye.