Hello, everyone.
My name is Vijay Kumar Balabhoju, and
welcome to CON42 Prompt Engineering 2024.
I'll walk you through the reinforcement
learning in AI driven assessments and
how this actually helps in enhancing
continuous learning and accessibility.
These are the topics that
I am going to cover today.
introduction to reinforcement
learning, and then, Theoretical
framework for, reinforcement learning.
Reinforcement learning, I will
sometimes substitute it for RL.
So, and, what are
personalized learning paths?
And then a real time adaptive assessments.
Accessibility and flexibility.
Continuous feedback and learning loop.
Gamification in learning.
Predictive learning and assessments.
And we will end with the
conclusion and future directions.
introduction to reinforcement
learning, right?
And what is reinforcement learning?
The definition is, it's a branch
of machine learning focused on how
agents should take actions in an
environment to maximize cumulative
rewards through trial and error method.
And what's the importance of this
is, with the increasing demand
for personalized education,
reinforcement learning offers adaptive
solutions, that cater to individual
learning preferences and styles.
And the primary goal for this one is,
the primary objective is to create
intelligent systems that adaptively
optimize for learning experiences,
enabling continuous skill development
and improving educational outcomes.
Right.
theoretical framework of
learning reinforcement.
Reinforcement learning.
we have, agent.
Basically, these are the key
components I'm going to cover.
we have an agent.
An agent represents the learner.
Or an adaptive learning system.
And then we have an environment,
which refers to the context in
which the learning takes place,
including content and assessments.
And then we have a state action reward.
These are the core elements where a state
represents the learner's knowledge level.
Actions are the choices made by the agent.
And the rewards, are like
providing feedback on performance.
Now let's cover the, personalized
learning paths, right?
Basically, a learning path,
is an essential concept which
provides a direction, and, with a
definitive goal for a learner on
what they are trying to achieve.
And, with a learning path, it
actually enables the learner to take
a certain path to reach the goal.
basically, what are the things that the
person need to learn through the journey
of learning to achieve the end goal.
And when it comes to a
personalized learning paths,
I've divided it into two things.
Basically, one is a dynamic curriculum
adjustment, and another one is the
performance based learning optimization.
What is a dynamic curriculum adjustment?
It is actually an RL based system
analyzing learners performance
in real time, allowing them to
modify the curricula instantly.
For example, if a learner excels
in math, the system can introduce
more advanced topics without
a traditional waiting period.
Now, when it comes to performance based,
in this case, by monitoring metrics such
as accuracy and response time, the system
ensures that the learner face appropriate
challenges which promotes effective
learning and prevents frustration.
Real time adaptive assessments, right?
what it means is, basically, this
RL algorithm continuously assesses
learners performance, making real time
adjustments to question Difficulty
to keep, to question difficulty
to keep learners engaged and
accurately measure their knowledge.
Basically, it's all about the
engagement and stuff, right?
as the learner makes a process,
progress, with their assessments, these,
RL algorithms, they assess in real
time and then adjust the difficulty
level as per the, the responses
that is provided by the learner.
Take for an example, a
case study here, right?
A software developer preparing for a
cloud computing certification, right?
Now this case, in this case, this
RL algorithms, they benefit this
learner, from targeted questions based
on their strengths and weaknesses.
And now what this ensures is a well
rounded preparation strategy for
the person to achieve their end
goal, which in this case is a cloud
computing certification, right?
Now, when it comes to accessibility
and flexibility, right?
we're talking about, reinforcement
learning, AI driven assessments, right?
basically, these assessments
can be taken care taken, by the
learner anytime, anywhere, right?
Meaning, a learner can access the
assessment at their convenience,
accommodating various schedule and
the lifestyle, which is particularly
beneficial for, working professional
and remote learners, right?
So that's, anytime, anywhere, it's at
the convenience of the learner, right?
And then, across device learning
continuity, basically, we deal
with many devices these days.
Laptops, computer, like the phones, and,
even a smartwatch and things like that.
Now, this Reinforcement learning
powered platform allows learner to
switch seamlessly between devices,
such as from a laptop to a smartphone.
Now that ensures the continuity
in their learning experience.
Now, implications for remote learning.
These systems, these systems, they provide
personalized feedback that enhances
the quality of the distance education.
Promoting a more engaged learning
experience for the remote learners.
Alright, now, continuous feedback
and learning loop, right?
So immediate personalized feedback.
This is very important, right?
it's not like a traditional way of
simple correctness evaluation, right?
I go give an assessment and I
get assessed on that particular
thing and then I get a score.
This is the traditional
way of doing things, right?
Now we are moving away from
that traditional concept of
simple correctness evaluation.
In this case, the system
provides a detailed insights.
helping learners understand
their mistakes and then correct
from their misconceptions.
This is immediate, and this is more
personalized for this particular learner,
whoever is taking these assessments.
And now integration of feedback.
feedback dynamically adjust
the learning pathway.
So that way, we are introducing new
content where learners show readiness or
revisiting foundational topics as needed.
Now, feedback is dynamic.
Okay?
Now, feedback is, and, the, basically
the, the feedback is dynamically
adjusted for the learning pathway.
Okay?
And that when a new content is
introduced, the engagement from the
learners is actually improved as well.
Now, how this is going to impact?
Now, this approach fosters a greater
sense of ownership in learners.
This increases the motivation and
retention rates by, by ensuring they
are actively involved and in the
learning, the enhanced learning process
is actually presented to the user.
What gamification, an important
concept in learning, gamification
improves motivation and then increases
the engagement, in learning any
new concepts for a learner, right?
And how does this work, for an RL based
reward system is dynamic reward mechanism.
They adapt to individual
learner preferences.
Utilizing badges, points, or
a virtual currency, for that
matter, to enhance the engagement.
Now, motivation through
achievement unlocking.
How does this work?
The reinforcement learning system
generates achievements tailored to
skill levels, ensuring that learners
remain challenged but not overwhelmed.
Promoting a sustained engagement.
Usually, it's things go ahead, it, things
could be overwhelming for the learners
when, a more complex scenario is produced
when they are, is presented to them.
when the learner is not even
ready to actually take up
that more complex scenario.
But in this case, this is a sustained
engagement wherein the progression
happens as per the learner's
involvement and as per the engagement
and the way they are actually, the
learning process is progressing.
So let's take a case study, right?
for example, In a language learning
platform, the reinforcement learning
system identifies high engagement with
speaking exercises and then combines
and incentivizes writing tasks to create
a balanced skill, between, for the
speaking and the writing tasks, right?
Moving on, predictive learning
and assessments, right?
Anticipatory skill development.
analyzing the historical data and
industry trends, RL systems can
predict what skills are necessary for
the future success of this learner.
Now, RL systems, they
become the guiding factor.
They guide the learners to
proactive skill acquisition, right?
Basically, it's a, it's adapting.
The new learning paths and enhancing
that learning path to make it better,
to make the learner successful
for the future engagements.
And then proactive curriculum planning.
In this case, the system
modifies learning paths.
to introduce relevant topics in alignments
with predicted future needs, right?
this ensures the learners are well
equipped for evolving job markets.
And then, we have long term
trajectory optimization, right?
RL algorithms model complex interactions
between different skills and facilitating
pathways that promote comprehensive
competency development over time.
With this, we come to the
conclusion and future directions.
To summarize it, the integration of
reinforcement learning in AI driven
assessments is going to reshape
the educational landscape, offering
personalized and adaptive learning
experiences that significantly
enhance engagement and outcomes.
challenges ahead.
We need to address the algorithm bias
is, addressing the algorithm bias is
crucial for the fairness and transparency
in educational technologies, and
understanding the complexities of human
learning processes remains a challenge.
future research.
We need to continue the exploration
of, reinforcement learning capabilities
improvements in algorithm interpretability
and integrating reinforcement learning
with other AI technologies like
natural language processing will
further enhance educational system.
that concludes, this session.
Thank you so much.