Welcome all for conference 42,
prompt Engineering, 2025 online.
I'm Swami Viro, working Vice President
of Intelligence and Mission Learning
at JP Morgan and Co, where I led in the
intersection of advanced AI technology and
financial systems with deep automation.
I am dedicated to modernizing investment
banking process, driving innovation,
and ensuring data driven mission making.
Today I'll be speaking about transf
role of VE augmented generation
agents in finance, and how
intelligent prompt automation is.
By streamlining workflows,
enhancing data quality, and
enabling smarter, faster operations.
Let us discuss about
critical infection points.
So like mainly we have
three infection points.
One, data fellows and manual
process and real time risks.
Let us dive deep into these three things.
The financial services industry faces
unprecedented challenges in maintaining
data consistency, regulatory complaints,
and operational efficiency across
increasingly fragmented systems.
Traditional data management approaches
can no longer sustain the velocity,
volume, and complexity of modern markets.
The IM of retrieval Augmenting
generation system combined with MultiGen
architectures represents a fundamental
shift in how financial institution
process information make decisions.
These systems demonstrate measurably
improvement across critical
operational dimensions while addressing
core challenges that help plant
investment banking for decades.
Okay, now let us talk about
the data consistency crisis.
So today, like we know.
10 million plus daily transactions,
70 and hundred plans and continuous
operation of system 24 by seven.
Investment banking operations sell evolved
into extraordinarily complex ecosystem
where data flows through numerous
systems, platforms, and jurisdictions.
Simultaneously, major investment
banks process tens of millions
of transactions daily with peak
periods reaching exponential higher
volumes during market volatility.
Take daily transactions processed across
multiple systems, requiring perfect
consistency, integration points between
front, middle, and back office platforms.
We need perfect integration,
continuous operations, global markets
demand around the clock process.
Each transaction generates multiple
data points that must remain consistent
across front office trading systems,
middle office risk platforms, and
back office settlement infrastructure.
Traditional batch processing
introduces latency.
That creates windows of inconsistency
while real time interaction attempts
struggle with computational demands.
Okay, now let us start, like in
existing system, what are the
complications with human cost?
So mainly with the.
Mainly data quality issues,
manual reconciliation process,
and regulatory requirements.
That is dive deep data quality issues,
combine integration challenges,
information originates from driver
sources, live internal trading
systems, external market data vendors,
regulatory reporting platforms,
and counterparty communications.
Each with different formats, update
frequencies and quality standards.
Highly scale provisionals spend
significant time identifying
discrepancies, researching root
causes, and implementing corrections.
What that adds limited strategy
value, but remains essential
for operational integrity.
Manual reconciliation process cannot
scale to vinyl modern transaction volumes
while maintaining competitive speed.
Even small discrepancies cascaded
into significant problem when
undetected across multiple systems.
Regulatory requirements are another
layer demanding detail, audit trails,
data lineage, proof, and complaints
across multiple jurisdictions.
Okay, now let's discuss about what
is the architectural foundational
and how multi-agent system works.
In this diagram.
So query means like any trade, maybe
it is in the different formats and it
interacts with lm and before interacting
LM it going to get its context from
Vector database and after that and going
to work with different agents there.
State processing agent
risk assessment, compliance
monitoring, or settlement de can.
So let us dive deep.
So in framework, enhance language
model capabilities by connecting
them into authority to data sources
rather than relaying solely and
embedded training knowledge.
When process inquiries about trade
settlement status, the system reduces
relevant information from transaction
databases, settlement platforms,
and counterparty communications
before generating responses.
This approach ensures
accuracy, provides a trails.
And allow system to work
with up to date information.
Extending beyond model training data.
Multi-agent architecture, intelligent
distributes across specialized components
rather than monolithic systems.
Individual agents focus on
specific domains, trade processing.
Monitoring or settlement reconciliation.
Developing the expertise while
coordinating to solve complex problems.
Agent coordination protocol enables
sophisticated workflows through well
defined interfaces that maintain
modularity while handling complex
negotiations and optimizations.
So all with the LMEs, like after that.
So it's gonna mainly focus on
semantic search and vector databases.
So in this like in semantic search
and vector database, we mainly
have this components like document,
organization, vector emits.
Seman and contextual understanding.
So for this document, organization,
regulatory frameworks, trading policies,
market data, and historical transaction,
organized for such while reserving
relationships second vector embeddings.
Content transformed into mathematical
representation that captures semantic
meaning and context semantic criteria,
contextual relevant information
even without exact keyword matches.
Finally, contextual understanding
system handles financial
terminology, variations across.
Causes and time periods.
This semantic understanding was
crucial when dealing with financial
technology that varies significantly
across different contexts.
Enabling the system to find
relevant information regardless
of how queries are phrased.
Okay, now let's talk about the
microservice architecture of lys.
So we use microservice architecture
everywhere, but it is pretty much similar.
What we use some orchestration
like a p, a gateway and different
A components interactive here.
So mainly the microservice architecture
supporting AA capabilities provide
the scalability, reliability, and
flexibility demanded by production,
financial systems, individual services,
and specific functions, and scale
independently based on demand, independent
scaling services, scale based on demand.
Massive transaction volumes during
peak period while maintaining
cost efficiency during normal
operations system resilience.
Service isolation ensures
issues in one component do not
cascade into systemwide failure.
Next, security by design.
Access control logging built the
foundation with comprehensive.
Okay, so next important topic is.
So like we have data engineering.
So first one, data source.
Like for every brand, we need data source.
Here in this investment banking, we
use market data, internal reports,
or regulatory documents, and we can
use this as a context and prompt
prepares the templates and intent
classification and prompt optimization.
So every year, lamp just need this prompt.
Process the engineering prompts and
gives the output in different format,
automated compliance, monitoring,
recommendation, and customer reports.
So what are the core
benefits with this brand?
Engineering, mainly enhanced accuracy.
Engineered prompts reduce hallucination
and ensure domain specification.
Second, decision making data
interpretation and report
generation Third, regulatory
consistency, embeds complaints,
both operational efficiency.
Three professionals high value
to us with scalable intelligence
exchange, AI insights across this
and client operational securely.
Okay, now let us see how the realtime
trade process works in the ai.
Okay.
So from execution to
settlement in milliseconds.
So we know that like in the current
world, like so based on the trade
type, it may take three plus one, or
three plus three or three plus seven
or three plus 15, or even sometimes
it goes to plus 30 to settle.
So in that way now it is
reducing to millisecond.
So it's a data achievement
actually, when you trade executes
a complex structured product.
Intelligent agents automate
workflows that previously required
extensive manual intervention.
The system immediately
validates state economics.
Checks, credit limits,
regulatory complaints, and
in shared settlement process.
All within milliseconds
of trade execution.
Trade execution.
Structured product is executed by trader
and instant validation, close economics,
credit limits, and complaints Verified.
Finally, auto settlement
process initiated automatically.
Realtime reconciliation performs
continuous comparation of trade details
across systems, immediately flagging
discrepancies for investigation.
This immediate detection prevents small
issues from combining into larger problems
and dramatically reduces the operational
burden of reconciliation teams.
Okay, now let us discuss about
intelligent reconciliation.
So in Reconci
we mainly talk about the traditional
approach and a based approach.
There is a lag to load this presentation.
So mainly
batch crossing overnight in the
traditional approach and also,
undetected discrepancies, numerous
false positive from format variations,
manual investigations of every PLA
and delayed problem resolution.
So all these things happen
with the traditional approach.
So with the a enhanced approach,
we can achieve continuous severe
time reconciliation, India
discrepancy detection, contextual
understanding of equivalence.
Of false and prevention, so Amm
system understands contextual,
recognizing that various property
names, settlement dates adjusted
for already are minor price
differences within tolerance for sure.
Don't represent two discrepancies.
This intelligent reduces false
positives substantially allowing
reconciliation teams to focus on
genuine issues requiring investigation.
Okay, what are the
advanced risk assessments?
Okay, advanced risk assessment,
like mainly we're categorized into
historical analysis position, Mandarin
correlation detection and emerging risks.
Okay.
Risk assessment capabilities, benefit
and LY from a system that rails and
across vast amounts of historical data,
current position, and market conditions.
Risk manage systems that apply
Redfin to current positions, AI
and systems, identifying emerging
patterns, correlations across seemingly
unrelated positions and potential
risks that don't fit standard models.
Okay, next, historical analysis.
Across of market data.
Second position wondering realtime
exposure assessment across portfolios,
relation detection, identifying hidden
relationship between positions, emerging
risk, identification of non debt.
The system continuously monitors
market conditions, analyzes historical
and assist portfolio exposure across
multiple risks dimensions, simultaneously
enabling more aggressive risk taking
within appropriately limits, while
maintaining prudent risk management.
Where do complaints monitoring?
Okay, here we have four different ways
of complex monitoring, one regulatory
tracking, pattern analysis, impact
assessment, and proactive prevention.
Complaints monitor, react to risk
management rather than simply flagging
transaction that violates explicit rules.
A systems identifi patterns that
suggest potential complaints
issues before violations occur.
Regulatory tracking.
Monitoring of regular changes
across jurisdiction, pattern
analysis, identifying behaviors
that suggest potential issues,
impact assessment, evaluating how
changes affect current strategies.
Prior to prevention addressing
issues before they became violations.
The system understands
regulatory requirements
across multiple jurisdictions.
Facts changes, and assesses how
those changes impact current
creating strategies and positions.
This proactive approach allows
compliance teams to orders potential
issues before they become violations
significantly reducing regulatory risk.
Okay, now let us talk
about performance at scale.
So production system characteristics
are like transactions per second
peak processing capacity during
market volatility should be like
1 million plus transactions per
second, and system availability.
Finance up time with automated failover.
Is subsequent performance for
interactive operations, the microservice
architectural individual components
to scale independently directing
resources to bottlenecks services during
peak periods while maintaining cost
efficiency during normal operations.
A. Continuous health monitoring ensures
finance availability that financial
operations demand trade validations
occur within milliseconds of execution.
This calculation complete quickly after
support real time position, monitoring
compliance, checks operated, trading
speed without becoming bottlenecks.
These aggress seal latency
requirements demand careful
optimization of every system component.
Okay, let us talk about security
and compliance implementations.
We have mainly six topics here, like
data protection, explainability,
access control, model validation.
Logging incident response data
protection number one, comprehensive
encryption covering data
addressed in transit and in use.
Sensitive financial information, protected
external threats and unauthorized internal
access control pipeline permissions with
role based and tribute based controls.
Dynamic authorization conditions
based on context and risk level
audit logging, comprehensive trail
captures every system interaction.
Secure logging infrastructure
prevents tampering with audit
regards, explainability.
Here rationally for every a edition
that human reviewers can understand and
validates transparent edition making
at mission speed model validation.
Ongoing monitoring ensures a
components continue operating
correctly as markets evolve.
Maintain system effectiveness.
Finally, in general response, detection
of ous behavior, automated containment
and response to prevent escalation.
Okay, now let's talk about
miserable business impact.
Here we will talk about four different
things like cost reduction, efficiency
gains, and error, and steady flexibility.
Cost reduction, automation reduces
manual effort for road in operations.
Annual growing transaction volumes
without proportional staff increases
efficiency gains complete in minutes.
In short of hours.
Faster confirmation and settlement.
Improve client service and
comp to advantage error.
Pure operational errors means less
correction time, reduce settlement
failures, and improve regular standing.
Next, strategic flexibility content to
portion new opportunities and new markets
and launches products with operational
infrastructure that supports growth.
Financial institutions implementing
these technologies report
substantial operational improvements.
The efficiency gains allows handling
of growing transactional volume,
minimal managing cost, transforming the
economics of expansion, and enabling
opportunities that would be economically
unviable with traditional approaches.
What is the path forward?
So fundamental transformation
of financial operations.
Rad, enhance multi agent A.
Systems are funda, transforming
investment banking operations.
This goes beyond automation enabling
system that handle complexity.
And speed The traditional approaches.
Current state miserable through cost
reduction, efficiency and risk management.
Near firm evaluation, cost
implementation, reduce risk, and
expected capabilities, future potential.
Autonomous operations advance
reasoning and risk prevention.
As a becomes essential financial
institution must prioritize systematic.
A adoption organizations committed
to this transformation will thrive
in increasingly competitive and
technologically sophisticated industry.
Thank you for joining us Agents in
Finance, transforming Investment
Banking through intelligent
automation using prompts.
I appreciate your engagement and
thoughtful questions, and I'm grateful
for the unity to share this exiting
advancement with you in this conference.
24 2025. Feel free to reach out
me in my LinkedIn Swami video.
Thanks again.