Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining my talk.
My name is Maximi Chatow.
I work at Perlin in Munich
as a technical consultant.
And today I would like to present to
you a short result of investigations
that we did at our clients with
regards to semantic retrievers or
basically what is coming beyond it.
Namely how we can not only
leverage embedding models.
Keyword based methods, but also
LLMs that we prompt in order
to get more satisfying results.
With regards to retrievers, let's
first look at the challenges of
conventional retrieval setups.
So what usually happens is that
a user of a retrieval system, in
order to get a set of documents
out of a corpus forward, a query.
That they want to query
documents about to a retriever.
This retriever then goes through a
corpus with the help of a, some kind of
search or embedding model and retrieves
documents that fit to this query best.
So in case of an embedding
model, that would be with regards
to semantic relatedness with
keyword based models like BM 25.
That would be.
Kind of the congruency of of keywords
between the query and documents.
And then people end up with retrieve,
with a set of retrieve documents
with the amount that they like.
And either they can use it with LLMs, but
they can also, and this is the important
case here for us not use it with LLMs,
but for example, present it to the user.
Use it with some downstream
data application.
The challenges that come with this
setup are that you always need to
take into account the entire query
when you do the retrieval process.
So you cannot focus on certain
aspects or add in certain, like
a certain focus on some part.
It's always a black box that
you cannot really control.
With this conventional retriever setup.
And also there's no reasoning
process behind this.
So that means that the order of the
documents, or the one that is favored
the most by the whole setup cannot
be influenced by a reasoning process.
And this might be of interest if you
have some very specialized domain.
Where either semantic models or keyword
based models break down because stuff
is too similar for these models.
And then you would need a reasoning
process to yeah, to find minute details in
the differences between the documents and
then use that as a basis for reordering.
And we, at Perlin, were
confronted with such a case that
one of our clients recently.
And we saw in the quality, the
quantitative quality of the
retrieval results that we cannot
just make do with this kind of setup.
We would need to use an LLM in the
retrieval process to make it more fine
grained and have more fine grain control.
So what we did is that we used the
setup that I just presented, so
feeding a query to a retriever.
Equipped with corpus and embedding
model to only get preliminary documents.
So with a classic retrieval process, you
would get a preliminary set of documents,
but then you would leverage an LLM to
refine the set and refine the order and
then end up with the retrieve documents
that you're actually looking for.
The nice thing about this is that
it offers an additional text input
dimension where you can refine aspects,
you can add metadata to your documents
at this stage that you want to be
leveraged or that you want to be
considered during the re-ranking process.
So this enables us then
to now use reasoning.
So you can either use a normal
LM or even a reasoning LLM.
To reorder your documents and
you can inject other aspects
like metadata rules, for example.
Also, that could not be captured by
a classic non LM retrieval model.
And now looking at, into the detail of how
we actually did this we actually used the
LLM not just as a one off re ranker, so
putting all the documents into the prompt
and then having it select from them.
But we used the LLM as a
binary document operator.
So what we did is we put two documents
into a prompt and a query, and then.
Ask the LLM.
This is the domain.
Look at the following two documents.
Look at the query.
Which one did do you find more
suitable to answering this query?
Please give me an answer, either A or
B, or left or right, or up or down.
And what we end up with by doing this
for all combinations of documents is a
matrix that compares all the documents.
By verdicts of the LLM.
And then you can see, for
example, that document two is
more suited than document one.
And document three is then
less suited than document one.
And with this you can establish
an order of documents in the end.
Especially if you use the LLM multiple
times at a non-zero temperature,
you can get some statistics to
ground this ordering on, and then
you can basically count the verdicts
and order the documents by that.
And we found in our project research
that this is more reliable than a one
of invocation, especially if you're
dealing with many preliminary documents
because you would end up potentially
with a needle in the haystack problem.
And documents would get
lost in the LLM processing.
And this way you have more control
of this re-ranking process.
But, and that is to be considered as well.
Runtime and costs are of
course, an issue here.
So this takes way longer than
just a one-off LLM comparison or
even a classic retriever set up.
Alone.
And yeah, the incurring costs
are of course also higher than if
you just use an embedding model
or even a keyword based model.
Because you have to do many basically
on the order of the square of the
number of documents, LLM calls.
So what is our take home message
from this anecdotal anecdotal talk
about one of our projects is that.
We have seen that conventional
retriever setups do have difficulties,
especially with specialized corpora
and retrieval tasks with special
needs like certain aspects, certain
focuses to to pay attention to.
And we recommend LLMs as re-ran in this
case in a binary comparison setup as
I've just explained, because we have seen
that with just comparing two documents.
The results are quantitatively.
Better than with one
off LLM ranking setups.
So thank you for listening and
looking forward to the other talks.
I.