Hey everyone, my name is Razelle Scarlett
and today I'm going to be talking
to you about prompting AI to build
a pregnancy app that I could trust.
All right, so let me just give
you a little bit of background.
For me, in my opinion, I don't
think we talk about pregnancy
in the workplace enough.
It's a taboo topic.
It's also a very sensitive
subject for many pregnant women,
of course, are birthing people.
But I also think, because of the
lack of discussion, this also leads
to poor maternity leave policies
because a lot of our industries
like tech are so male dominated.
And then that leads to overworked
expecting moms and also I think we've
ended up developing a lot of pregnancy
invasive app or privacy invasive
pregnancy apps try saying that three
times but basically I think we a lot
of the tech industry will be like
oh let's get into this area in the
2020s or 2015s or whatever like let's
get into this area where it seems
underserved let's make these apps
for, feminine personal health data.
And then they figure out, Ooh, like we
don't care that much, or at least as a
user, you figure out, Whoa, they don't
really care that much for my privacy.
this is nice to track, but it's
also sharing my data with a
ton of different, platforms.
before I go any further,
my name is Rizal Scarlett.
I'm a staff developer advocate at Block.
I'm very passionate
about open source and AI.
And I'm passionate about the data
privacy as well, which almost
seems opposite of each other.
And one of the reasons I'm
interested in this particular topic
today is I'm 35 weeks pregnant.
And with that, I will tell
you the agenda as well.
So we're going to talk about lack of
data privacy online, something I found
called the centralized web nodes.
AI agents tips and tricks
for using AI agents.
We'll do a bit of a demo and
I'll show you all some resources.
So it's going to be lots of fun.
So I'm already used to, and you
all are probably as well, apps
that just collect massive amounts
of personal data about you.
And really we just
accept it for what it is.
and oftentimes we accept it for
what it is because that's just
how the internet has been, but.
That shouldn't be how it always is, right?
I started thinking this is really weird
when I downloaded A app when I decided
oh, I think I want to start a family and
tiktok instagram reels facebook target
Everyone youtube every commercial had
to do with becoming a mom And i'm like
dang, how do you guys already know?
I just downloaded the app And nothing
else has occurred besides downloading
the app and I figured this can be also
annoying and very invasive if someone has
experienced a miscarriage and now they're
being constantly reminded by this, by
different applications about motherhood.
So the question that I pose to you all
is who should really own your data?
And from my perspective, it should be you.
You should own your own data.
so one thing I looked into it is
called DWNs or decentralized web nodes.
They're open source.
They are, basically a personal
data storage mechanism.
So you can think of it like a Dropbox,
but it's encrypted and you as the user
have ownership over it and you can control
who has access to different types of
data in it and how that's made possible
is with something called protocols.
These are javascript objects or json
objects where here you can see you
can define who can do certain things,
who can read, who can write, who
can query your data and all of that.
So in this particular situation
they're saying for this web app.
Anyone can create a chat,
but only the author and the
recipient can read that chat.
And you can, if you've made a pregnancy
app or anything like that, you can
say, Oh, I only want the provider to
be able to read this, or I only want
my partner, my, parents or just myself
to be able to have access to this data
So I thought of like a wild kooky idea.
Can I use ai to help me build this app?
that uses decentralized web nodes
partially i'm a little lazy.
So let's see what we could
do and I decided to look into
different types of ai tools.
I've used github copilot heavily I
wanted to try something new so i'm
trying out goose today and goose is a
developer So Agent local to your machine.
It's available in your terminal.
Also available in your ideas like
Visual Studio Code or IntelliJ.
And like I said, it's open
source and it ends up having
full context of your project.
Now I do want to emphasize it's not an
LLM and we're used to LLMs, which are
Known as large language models, they're
trained on large amounts of data and
use prediction algorithms to generate,
summarize, translate, and analyze Content
so that content can be anything images
video code or just text and we probably
most used to using like GPTs from OpenAI
like GPT 3, GPT 4, Sonnet, Gemini.
Maybe you don't even realize you're
using it because sometimes it's
abstracted away with a user interface
such as ChatGPT or Cloud or GitHub
Copilot or Midjourney or Google or
Dolly or all these different things.
But we're interacting with
LLMs behind the scenes.
Instead, as I mentioned, Goose is an
And now, the AI world, we're having a
tough time with definitions right now.
So people are struggling with
figuring out what exactly is an
agent, but the way I've defined it,
at least in the context of boost is
that it's software that can execute
operations without human intervention.
Or what little human intervention, and
basically their agents are given a goal.
They decide on what actions need
to be made to reach that goal.
And they take that
action to reach the goal.
So in my personal opinion, I think
Goose is more of a semi autonomous agent
because it can do everything for you.
But it does take some time to
pause and check in if you're
okay with some of the commands.
And I like that because I know that
AI hallucinates like I recognize
that I know that it makes mistakes
so I feel safer knowing that I'm
maintaining some level of control.
so I also wanted to know just for
my personal gain is like agents
The way it sounds, it's just
automation, but what's the difference?
So agents are more given goals to
achieve, and then they learn, adapt, and
make decisions to achieve those goals.
Whereas with automation, it's
given a situation, response to
the predetermined action, if the
situation matches one of its recipes.
The way that Goose works in
particular is you bring your own
LLM, whatever you prefer to use.
Do you like OpenAI's GPT's or do you like
to use Sonnet by Claude or whatever it is?
You bring the one that you think
is good for your situation and
the one that you like to use.
Then you prompt Goose and you say
something like, hey, I want to create
some unit tests and Goose It goes to
the LLM and it's yo, LLM, yo GPT-4 row,
Brazil wants to create some unit test.
How do I do that?
I need you to make a plan for me and
then the LL m's, okay, first you're
gonna install React testing library.
Then you're going to look at this
first method and you're going
to write a unit test for this
and that and so on and so forth.
Goose comes back to you, it communicates
the plan to you, and then it executes
the plan through shell commands.
Now we know sometimes
shell commands fail, right?
Maybe sometimes it didn't
type in the right thing.
Or your environment's weird or whatever.
So we have some different options
or goose has different options for
what it does when a command fails, it
might ask the LLM for an updated plan.
It might be like, yo, when I installed
react, test and library didn't work.
And then it might be like the LLM might
be like, Oh, I forgot to specifically
tell you which version to install.
Sometimes the command might be
running too long and it'll stop
and tell you, Hey, can you.
Tell me what command I need to run
or can you run the command yourself?
It might be a little bit faster
or sometimes the command might
need elevated permissions like
your password and it might be
like yo It asks for your password.
I don't know it.
Can you run it on your end
and tell me when you're done?
So just letting you know this demo,
the demos I'll be doing will not be
perfect because AI is non deterministic,
meaning it's unpredictable, likely
to have a different result each time.
So no matter how much I practiced
before, it might show me something crazy.
So we're going to switch over to that
in a quick second, and start the demo.
Okay.
So I switched back over to my terminal.
because this is where I'm
going to interact with Goose.
and I made a directory and everything.
So what I'm going to go ahead
and do is instead of necessarily,
so to start a session, I'm going
to say Goose session start.
And instead of me deciding to create
a pregnancy web app, we're like,
More relatable first, then we're
going to do the pregnancy web app
just to see how Boost acts, right?
So it started up a session for me and I'm
going to say, let's create a collaborative
real time drawing web app using Next.
js.
So right now when it's responding it's
going chatting with that llm coming
up with a plan for me And it's going
to be able to print that plan out and
show and communicate that with me.
So we'll see
it's taking a bit probably because I
have a whole bunch of stuff running.
Oh, perfect So it came up with a plan.
It's it's going to do some basic setup.
It's going to set up canvas.
It's going to, implement a
web socket in the backend.
And then it starts creating the
project, with these files and all of
that for me, which is super exciting.
And it's okay, just go
ahead and run the project.
for me.
Oh my God.
Perfect.
for the sake of time, I actually
just, had, my own on the side running
or I already used goose to do this.
This is you watch a cooking show and
they're like, we made some cupcakes.
But we already made some cupcakes.
So I did use goose to create this
beforehand, just for the sake
of time, since this is supposed
to be a 15 to 20 minute talk.
And here we have a
collaborative drawing app.
It's nothing too crazy, simple.
We can always go back and say,
Hey, add color, add buttons for
toggling erasers and stuff like that.
But we have something that we see works.
All right.
Next thing I want to show y'all is
the actual creation of the pregnancy
web app, but I want to Do something a
little bit more like it's a little bit
different here and what i'm gonna do is
I recognize that decentralized web nodes.
They're not like this common technology
They're new, not a lot of people are
using them yet, and so therefore the
LLM and Goose may not have information
about decentralized web nodes like that.
So what I did instead is I created
what is called a Goose hints file.
So I'm going to go ahead and recreate
that with you guys and let's see,
we're going to do touch Goose hints.
And I'm going to open this up in Vim.
All right, so in my Goosens file, you
can give context to your, to Goose, so
it can know how to operate on things.
What I did is I went to the documentation
for DWNs, and I'm like, I copied
and pasted all the relevant parts.
So I'm going to go ahead and do that.
And let's exit this drawing web app.
I'm going to go ahead and copy
and paste this so it knows
what to do and when to do it.
All right, cool.
So now we've inserted it
and I'm going to do right.
Okay, awesome.
So we have our goose hints while giving
goose a bit of context, but we also want
to, or at least I want to make a plan.
So we saw goose make its own plan,
but you can also make your own
plan for goose if you wanted to.
and I think of this as the, Oh, I know
what to do, but I'm just lazy to manually
do it and I want Goose to do this for me.
So I'm going to create
another, file called a plan.
yaml.
And, alrighty.
And we're going to open it up.
We're going to say touch plan.
yaml.
And, Oh, I already did that.
let me see if I have made two.
I'm gonna do vi.
I'm gonna open it up and
say vi plan not yaml.
All right now in my plan, I made
this ahead of time just for the sake
of time We have a kickoff message
telling it what we're going to
do We're going to create a next.
js web app that acts as a pregnancy due
date calculator and I gave it tasks I'm
like first create a directory install
this project or dependency create a ui
where users can input their The first day
of their last cycle, all of that stuff.
And then we're going to say, quit already.
Now we can start a square, a
goo session, an SQ goo session.
We can say SQ goo session, star dash plan.
And then we can say plan.
yaml.
So we're saying, started
with this particular plan.
and it's supposed to see what I did wrong.
Oh, okay.
Let's put you in that yammer with
a because that's how I spelled
the end of the extension So now
it's going to go ahead and follow
what I told it to do, right?
It's making that directory it's cd'ing
into the directory and it is going
to install all the things I told it
to install, like Next and React and
Web5 API for the DWN and all of that.
Now, for the sake of time, again,
like I said, these run pretty long.
I've already Done this again and we
see the code that it wrote for it.
I've already done this on the side Just
to make things a little bit faster.
It says run npm run dev.
I'm already doing that So
we can see what it made.
I'm gonna bring it over here.
It's pretty plain It's pretty plain, but
let's say if Your last cycle the first day
of your last cycle was I don't know Oh,
let's pick a random date April 4, 2024.
When you calculate the date, that would
say that you're 30 weeks pregnant.
your due date will be
Wednesday, January 8, 2025.
But the thing we care about is,
okay, it's been written into
our decentralized web node.
How do we know that for sure?
I told it to print out.
If it worked, or to print out
the data that it printed to the
decentralized web node, and it did.
So we have a record here, and this
is something I would expect, what my,
experience with decentralized web nodes
is where it has all the stuff in here,
all the encoded data and the record ID.
So it was successful,
which is really exciting.
And actually, I have some time to show you
all the web app that I actually had made.
So I'm going to cancel all of this
Exit so that was just a demo one,
but I made a more flourishing one
so localhost 3002 A little bit more
detailed and we have time to show this.
I'm so glad that we do.
So this web app, it's not the
cutest, but I thought it was
cool that I made this with AI.
It took time to be a
little bit more detailed.
And so I'm like, all right, if I
get started, click here to log in.
And then I put in what would be
my username and I want to be.
I'm signing in as self,
not provider, not partner.
Set my username.
And then here is where I
can like, track my cycle.
if I wanted to.
So I could say, oh, Monday, October 28.
And then maybe the end date.
Was Wednesday the 30th and then I can
put The flow types maybe started heavy
Medium light or something like that.
It shows the colors for it or not the
colors But the indicators for it and
we know it was saved in my personal
decentralized web node because it gets
printed out here I'm saying that it was
it was Added successfully and we can see
that same object that I expect to see
from a decentralized web node so That
was like something I did on the side with
ai it would take way too long for me to
show you or with goose in particular,
and for the designs, I actually used vo.
dev So i'll show you all that vo.
dev.
This is owned by verselle and
you can think of oh How would I?
how would I like prototype or
design like a little web app?
This is pretty nice and fun to use.
and I want to go back and just
show you all if you wanted to
get into a goose or try out.
AI agents a little bit.
I would encourage you to go to
github.com/block/goose to check
out the repo and install it.
And then we have
documentation@block.github.io slash goose.
thank you so much and I hope this
was an interesting talk for you.
Bye.