Securing multiple income streams
is something that has always
been on the rise in South Africa.
We even have a very scientific
name for it, side hustles.
Students, corporate employees, and even
those who have retired have side hustles.
According to the 2021 Brand Map Consumer
Insights Survey, 30 percent of middle
class adults have side hustles such
as running small businesses, home
industries, and jobs that are completely
different from their main employment.
While side hustles allow one the
opportunity to financial freedom and
creativity, they can lead to burnout
due to the demands on time and energy.
This can lead to some people
feeling discouraged from having side
hustles or even performing poorly at
their main jobs due to the growing
demands of their side businesses.
Now, the traditional approach
to solving this has always
been to turn to labor leverage.
That is hiring people to do some
of the work so you can focus
on the more important stuff.
The issue with this approach is
that not everyone can afford it.
This can also lead to financial
stress when the business is not
doing so well in, in revenue.
Now, we as the current generation of young
people are rather blessed because just
recently The side hustle community or gig
economy has come to realize the potential
of AI in solving this problem for us.
With AI, we can multiply our
efforts as if we have hired people.
We can scale our businesses to 150
people and only have one that is human.
today we are going to talk about
a topic that has a lot of people
rethinking how they do side hustles.
AI
Now, as many of you might know,
my name is Matandwa, and I'm a
junior software engineer at BBD.
Throughout my life, I've always been
fascinated with the integration between
business, people, and technology.
So much that, last year, I graduated
with a BSc in Computer Science
and Business Computing degree
from the University of Cape Town.
Most importantly, I believe that
technology is about people, and that
LLMs are the closest we have ever
come As a civilization to getting the
machine to speak the human language.
Now, an LLM, as it is a black box that
we can feed a prompt in the form of text
and have it cough out an answer for us.
And sometimes media like images and audio.
This is your chat GPT, your Gemini,
your cloudy llama, et cetera.
We, we can take the output of one LLM
and feed it as input into another.
This will create what we call chaining or.
Layering, it also turns out that
we can take a chain of layers and
encapsulate them under an identity,
which can include a name and contact
details like email and phone number
to create what we call an agent.
This is what will be your
employee in your business.
Now, because agents have names and contact
details, they can communicate with,
the external world and with each other.
Now, when this happens,
you have an orchestration.
AI agents working together
to achieve a mission.
And this mission could be anything from
marketing and consumer service to product
recommendations and financial management.
The possibilities are endless.
What's important to note here is
that we have delegated work to
something you don't even pay a salary.
So you can focus on the more
strategic decisions for your
business and personal commitments.
Now, before we get to the
demos, there are a few ways we
can think about orchestration.
On an agent level, since you have
multiple layers, you really want to
be clear as to what each layer does.
An agent is an AI being.
It needs rules to make decisions by.
It needs to know what is
allowed and what is not allowed.
We also need to recognize that
overloading it with instructions and
rules in a single prompt could lead
to confusion and hallucinations.
Hence the need for layers.
One way we can implement layering
is to go from abstract to concrete.
That is, the layer at the top does
not necessarily need to know, about
or how to pull data from the database.
It just needs to know, which database
to pull from and whether or not that
database has the information it needs.
The actual query or SQL query
generation can be delegated to
the more concrete layers below.
Layering also allows us to
add security middleware.
For example, we can add a middle
layer between the top layer and the
layer below that looks at a case in
isolation and decides whether or not
to allow the request to proceed to the
layer below, which in our case will
be the one connected to our database.
Now this is powerful because we can
implement morality, ethics, and ensure the
agent does not deviate from the mission.
Which in our case is, again, to
make the business owner more money.
to demonstrate this, or to
demonstrate the idea of layering,
I will show two examples.
One example will be a simple
agent with just a single layer,
and the second example will be an
agent with three layers, where the
second layer is the security layer.
but before we get to that, just to
give you an idea as to what you need
to create agents, the first thing you
need is an orchestration platform.
I'll be using something I built for
my own ideas, which is OAI, but you
can also use LearnGraph, you can use
Streamlit, or you can just go with
plain Python and VS Code and just
write your agents from scratch, right?
It's all up to you.
The second thing you need is like
an idea of what agents you need and
what each agent is supposed to do.
and lastly, you need patience.
That is, patience to test.
going to the demo, just going
to open my first example here.
DevFest 2024.
if I come to, sorry, Is it the single
layer example, which is this one here.
And, so what you're going to see here
is just a simple, agent that, if you
look at the prompt, It's name is Andy,
and it's a nice salesperson for a small
apple farm based in South Africa, yada.
And it's supposed to reply to all
customer queries with a bit of humor.
So it tries to be funny, right?
the model I'm using for that, or the LLM
I'm using for that is just ChatGPT 3.
5.
And, oh, and I also added the voice
service to get the agent to talk to me.
So services, or at least in the context of
OAI, are tools that the agent has access
to, that it can use to go about completing
whatever task you want to give it.
In our case, I gave it access to the
voice service, so it can just speak to me.
So now, obviously this is a simple prompt,
there's nothing special about this, it's
like ChatGPT prompting and all of that.
So if I open that, I can say,
Hello, what is your name?
Sorry, there we go.
Hello.
My name is Andy, the friendliest
apple aficionado at our farm.
How can I help you today?
Okay, hello, my name is Andy,
the friendliest apple, whatever
that word is, at our farm.
How can I help you today?
I just realized I'm not sharing my
audio, so you can't really hear,
but this text that is written
here, it actually reads out to me.
but that's fine.
Um, that's just a simple prompt or
a single agent with a single layer.
so the second example that I want
to look at is the important one.
So let's close this.
it's not this one.
It's customer queries, security layer.
Let's see.
So this is the agent
with the security layer.
So I go to layers.
And like I mentioned earlier, you
have, again, from abstract to concrete.
So that is, you have the layer at
the top, then you have the middle
layer that implements security,
and then you have the data layer.
So how this agent is supposed to work is
that the data layer has access to a SQL
database, as you can see, OAI SQL Server.
So this allows it to
connect to a SQL database.
and that database has information
about customers and sales, right?
So we can ask this layer.
information about let's say, for
example, how many customers did we have
for the year 2024 or how many of our
customers, bought from us, last year,
December or something like that, right?
It's all up to you.
And for that time, I'm using chat GPT 4.
0 and yeah, that's that.
So that's the data layer.
But now the data layer needs to be
protected because we don't want anyone to
have access to this information, right?
So what I did here, I added a second
layer called security, like I mentioned
earlier, that, We'll take in a request
from the top layer and it will look at
the email that request is coming from.
And currently it's connected to Gmail.
I'll show you how that works, but
actually I can't show you, but we'll see.
So how that works is that you
have a request coming from the
layer at the top or the top layer.
And this one will look at the
email and compare it to what
we have here in the allow list.
So that if that email is coming in, is
in the allow list, then we want that
request to proceed to the layer below.
If it's not in the allow list,
then obviously we want to block
that person from having access to
this kind of information, right?
Which only makes sense.
And then here, I'm also using GPT 4.
0 just to show you, you can use
any model you want, actually.
I haven't loaded my Anthropic,
API keys, so I don't have the,
your Cloudy or those models.
And then, here at the top, now you
have the top layer, which takes, the
information, or which receives the
emails, and it takes those emails and
forwards them to the layers below,
which in our case would be, where
is it, the security layer, right?
And then obviously the security
layer applies its security stuff,
and then the request can proceed
if it's in the allow list or not.
really nothing special
here, just another prompt.
And again, Chachapiti 4.
0 so how this is supposed to work is that
so you, I'm sorry, so you have This agent
is connected to an email Um, to, to an
email account on Gmail So it, it's using
OAI mail So I can actually go to my Gmail
and send it an email But the issue with
that is that it's going to take at least
15 minutes for The service I'm using
to, you know Get that email to my agent.
So what you're going to do since we don't
have that much time We're going to fake
emails coming into the agent so what I'm
going to do I'm going to chat to the agent
and I'm going to say new email from me
and Sorry, just to make this bigger.
Let's say Who are our customers?
Who are our customers?
And then I run that So what's supposed
to happen is that I'm supposed to get
a list of all our customers because
this email is in the allow list, right?
Here is the information on our customers.
One Green Valley Grocers.
Two Sunny Acres Market.
So there we go.
Three Hilltop Organics.
that's our customers.
And it's the customers that are
coming directly from the database.
It's not just made up names, right?
which is really cool.
it's just really, it's
a really cool thing.
But now, let's say that the
same email came from, just gonna
modify this, copy it, say the same
email came from, what's the most
fraudulent email you can think of?
Um, the same it came from, what's, I
can't think of a name, abc, mandy, right?
Or let's say it came from mandy at gmail.
com.
And.
Mandy wants information, wants the
same information that I asked for.
And let's see if it's going to
allow Mandy to get that information.
I'm sorry, but I cannot provide access to
customer information because your email
is not on the list of authorized users.
If you have any other questions or need
further assistance, please let me know.
Okay, so as you can see, it did not
allow that request to go through because
Mandy is not on the authorized list
of users, which is super, super cool.
so basically that's how you would go
about, implementing security with using
layers or using layers rather, right?
So back to the presentation.
Of course, like I mentioned earlier,
agents communicate with each other.
And by breaking down a complex problem
or task into multiple agents, we
apply the divide and conquer strategy
often used in computer science.
This means that no matter how complicated
the task, we can decompose it into
smaller, manageable tasks, continuing
this process until we reach a level
where each part is straightforward.
Each smaller task can then be
assigned to an individual agent.
And once the agents have completed
their tasks, they can bring their
solutions together, gradually building
up to solve the larger problem.
An example of this is what I call the
proxy to expert approach, where you have
a main agent that receives requests and
forwards these requests to agents that
are better suited to provide responses.
Now, the beautiful thing about,
proxy to experts is that we can
provide one interface to the user.
The main agent and have a hundred
or even a thousand experts that
it can refer to for advice.
So the next demo that I want to show
you is an example of this where we
have Just going back to the demo
Get out of here come back here
Proxy demo And yeah, so this is the
orchestration with three agents.
So one of the agents is a customer expert.
So this agent knows
everything about customers.
again, oh, sorry, actually, you, we
can pull this information from the
database, but here I just hard coded
it into the prompt just for simplicity.
so that's, this is the customer
expert, it's, it's a customer
expert for a small apple farm.
and it answers questions
relating to customers, and
these are all our customers.
And then we also have a sales expert,
also for the small apple farm, actually
they're all for the small apple farm.
And the sales expert stores
information about, the orders that
customers made with the date and the
number of units that they bought.
And By units, we mean apples, right?
Again, we could have, taken this
from the database using the SQL
service, but I'm sorry, I'm hard
coding it here for simplicity.
So that's that.
And then the last agent to the,
yeah, the important agent we
have here is the proxy agent.
So the proxy agent basically has,
it knows all it knows about, the
customer expert and the sales expert.
And what it does, when it receives
requests about sales, it forwards them
to the sales agent, or sales expert.
And when it receives, requests
about, customers, it forwards
them to the customer expert.
I can show this to you
with, who am I chatting to?
I'm chatting to the main agent.
So if, let's close this one.
I'm going to say.
Tell me about, or who are our customers.
Who are our customers.
So what's going to happen here is that,
it's going to reach out to the customer
agent, ask it for the list of customers,
and then reach that list out to me.
this is cool.
So what, another thing that we can
try, is say for example, this is cool.
Three.
Asterisk, cast risk, fresh apples.
Limited.
Asterisk.
How many customer id?
Three.
What is JJ stores?
If you need more details
about their purchases or
interactions, just let me know.
Have, for the year 2024.
So how many orders did JJ
stores have for the year 2024?
So what's going to happen here?
I'm sorry, but I don't have any
information on orders or customer activity
for the year 2024, as my training only
includes data up to October, 2023.
Please contact the sales department
or check your current Customer
Relationship Management, CRM, system
for the most updated order information.
Okay, I think it hallucinated there.
but basically what it's supposed
to do is basically reach out to the
sales agent, sorry, and ask it about,
sales for JJ Stores for the year 2024.
And I think it's because of the year
that it actually gave that answer.
Let's say, how many orders, let's say
sales orders, how many sales orders,
Orders do we have for JJ stores?
Okay, let's try that.
We have a total of four
sales orders for JJ stores.
Okay, there we go.
So it gave us the answer the correct
answer for all sales orders for JJ stores.
I think here what took
it off was the year 2024.
And it was only trained for after
October, so I could have maybe modified
my prompt a little just to be clear as
to how to handle years, for example.
but yeah, that's an example
of hallucinations, eh?
cool example.
But yeah, we have four sales orders for
JJ Stores, and if we actually go to the
sales expert and we count the orders for
2024 for JJ Stores, that's the first one.
So that's one, that's two, that's,
sorry, that's three, and this is four.
So it's correct.
We have four orders for JJ
stores for the year 2024.
So that's how you would go about
implementing, proxy to experts and
which allows you to have, a main agent
that can refer to as many experts as
it can possibly refer to, to give you
the information that, that you need.
You just need to be clear, in your
prompting to, to make sure that you
really want to reduce hallucinations.
Which is like the next
part of my talk, actually.
a conversation about AI running a business
does, of course, come with a few concerns.
And one of which is hallucinations.
As we saw earlier.
how can we trust our agents
are doing the right thing?
When we can see, for example,
with chatGPT, that it can
sometimes give the wrong answer.
Now, LLMs hallucinate due to
the nature of their training.
The data they were trained on can contain
biases, inaccuracies, and misinformation,
which can be amplified during prompting,
especially when there is not enough
context to drive the LLM to a more
accurate response, like we saw earlier.
there are a few things we can
try to reduce hallucinations.
One of which is to choose the right model.
That is, if you're going to be, if you
have a problem that involves coding,
for example, you really want to choose a
model that is good at understanding code.
If you have a problem where the agent
needs to analyze pictures, you want to
choose a model that is better suited
to deal with, pictures and media, etc.
So choosing the right model is
important because you don't want to
use a model for something that it's
not really supposed to be good at.
Because now you're just going to be
wasting resources and money, right?
So that's the first thing you
can try to reduce hallucinations,
choose the right model.
Secondly, we need to learn
good prompting techniques.
Thanks.
And there are two things we can try here.
The first one being the
chain of thought method.
That is, you have, or when you
prompt your, when you write your
prompts, you also ask the agent to
break down, the steps it's going
to take to get to the solution.
Now this works really well,
even with humans actually.
The minute you have to think
about how you're going to get to a
solution is the minute you tend to
think deeper about the solution.
Which in our case, in the
case of LLMs actually, it can
drastically reduce hallucinations.
And secondly, we can look
at few short prompting.
That is, you prompt the LLM with examples.
so basically, you ask it for
green apples, but also you tell
it what green apples look like.
so what's going to happen here is that
it's going to take the framework that
you give and combine it with the facts
that it has for that particular moment.
particular problem to give you
a response that is closer to,
to, to the true response, right?
And the third thing we can try, the second
last thing we can try is reg models.
So that is every time we prompt a
model, we also give it access to
documents that it can refer to for
more information about this specific
task that we're asking it to do.
For example, if we are, if we prompt
in the model around refund policies,
we can give it access to, to our
website or the page on our website
that speaks about refund policies.
So now when it tries to answer or provide
a response for us, it can look up stuff
on, on, on our website to make sure
that it's actually giving information
that is relevant to our problem.
So that's basically regmod models.
You prompt with documents, right?
retrieval augmented generation.
Beautiful thing.
The last thing that you can
try is to fine tune the model.
as we know, actually, with every machine
learning model out there, there's
parameters that you can change that can
make the model better suited for the
kind of task that you want to use it for.
One of the parameters that LLMs have
is temperature, at least in Langtrain.
temperature allows you to control
the creativity of the model.
I think in Langtrain it's
a value between 0 and 1.
So the closer it is to one,
the more creative the agent is.
And the closer it is to zero,
the less creative the agent is.
So that's one parameter, but there's
a, there's more parameters that
you can change to fine tune your
models to reduce hallucinations.
Now, as you all might know, hallucinations
are a risk and like any other risk,
we can reduce the likelihood of it
happening, but we can never be a hundred
percent sure it will never happen.
another approach we can take is
to reduce the consequences or the
impact for when the risk happens.
This will answer the question,
if my agent does hallucinate,
how much could they lose?
Now, there are a few ways
we can go about this.
I'll only mention two.
The first one is to adopt hybrid models.
That is, you have the human and you have
the agent working alongside each other.
So the human will, or the agents
will handle the routine tasks
and the human will handle the
more high stakes decisions.
So an example of this is let's say
an online store, a customer wants a
refund and the agents are going to
be the ones handling the process of
refunding the customer just up until
we send the money to the customer.
And now when we have to send the
money to the customer, the human is
going to come in and be the one to log
into their bank accounts and Do the
clicking to send money to the customer.
So that's hybrid models, So if
our agents do hallucinate and they
want to refund a customer that is
not supposed to be refunded, then
obviously the human is going to catch
that and say, no, we can't do that.
Right.
secondly, you want to add monitoring
and observability systems like
Langsmith to catch hallucinations
before they spread through, through our
orchestration or even worse to customers.
The beautiful thing
about such tools is that.
They also allow us, they also
allow for continuous learning and
improvement of our agents to meet
the evolving needs of our business.
that's the solicitations.
And obviously there, there are, a few
more concerns around, LLMs, especially
in the context of putting an LLM to
work to handle part of you, running
your business, And because of time, we
can't really talk about all of them.
But, through, through my interactions
with people, in the field of AI
and machine learning, I've come
to learn that hallucinations
are the biggest one of them.
That's why I really spoke about
hallucinations, but if there are
more issues, we can always chat.
I don't know where, but yeah, I
think there's going to be on, on,
on the, on the YouTube thing, there
should be something below there that
could, that can allow us to chat.
yeah, so just to close off, I'd like
to say, as we stand at the threshold of
a new era in business management, the
opportunity to leverage AI has never
been more accessible or more impactful.
Imagine a world where you're able to
scale your side hustle without sacrificing
precious time, where you can focus
on creativity and strategy while your
AI driven systems handle the routine.
This.
This isn't a vision for large
corporations, it's a reality
you can start building today.
AI is here to amplify your
efforts, not replace them.
By thoughtfully embracing these tools,
you're reclaiming the hours and energy
that were once lost to the daily grind.
You're not only growing a business,
you're creating a more balanced life.
One that allows you to
focus on what matters most.
let's embrace this future together.
Start exploring.
Take the small steps and watch how
AI can help you multiply your impact.
Magnify your success and give
you the freedom to thrive.
Thank you.