Hello, everyone.
Welcome to Prompt Engineering 2024.
My name is Pawan Bhavati.
Today, we are going to discuss
on balancing functionality and
security, a framework for IoT
software integration with third
party services in critical sectors.
Before I go there, I
have a disclaimer to say.
The views and opinions expressed in
this presentation are my own and do not
represent the views or official position
of my current and previous employers.
The content is based on
general industry knowledge and
publicly available information.
No proprietary or confidential information
will be shared during this talk.
Thank you.
So a little bit background of myself.
I'm a technology professional with over
15 years of experience in SDLC, the
software development lifecycle, various
stages, application development, API
management, across diverse industries.
Academically, I hold a master's
degree in computer science from
Staffordshire University, UK.
My, my expertise lies in blending
robust security measures with
cutting edge development practices.
10 years of focused
experience in security.
I've been last 10 years in security,
API audit, cybersecurity related
initiatives, working, as a, as an
architect or principal engineer.
Thank you.
Let's talk about the introduction to
IOT integrations, the importance of
third party integrations, key security
challenges, securing IOT integrations
by authentication and authorization.
Securing communications in IoT
ecosystems, data privacy and
security across the life cycle.
Mitigation strategies and best practices.
One case study, if you have
time, and then conclusion.
So introduction to IoT and
third party integrations.
What is IoT?
So IoT refers to the interconnection
of devices, enabling data exchange
and automation across various domains.
What are the key stacks in iot?
The cellular iot connections reach
3.4 billion and are projected
to reach 75 billion by 2025.
Highlighting the massive scale of iot,
what are the challenges By, in Ivo t
with a rapid, growth and development.
Integrating third party services
is main challenge and for the
functionality, but introduces
security vulnerabilities, mainly.
Accessing the data, data
privacy, must manage carefully.
These are the main challenges.
Let's talk about the benefits of third
party integration, the importance
of third party integrations.
What are the benefits?
The third party integrations unlock.
enhanced features, reduce costs
and increase efficiency so that we
don't need to reinvent the wheel.
We can utilize the already existing
software application available
in the market, the best optimized
frameworks which are available.
We can utilize that by integrating
the third party integrations.
The specialized services help solve
complex problems such as real time
data analysis and directive maintenance
applications across sectors.
Smart cities integrate traffic
management, public safety, and
resource optimization systems.
Mainly healthcare use remote monitoring,
wearable health devices, and predictive
analytics for patient monitoring systems.
Mobility implement smart traffic
solutions, optimize public transit
routes, and improve fleet management.
What are the key security
challenges in IoT integrations?
Scalability is the main challenge.
Microsoft As IOT ecosystems grow,
managing billions of connected
devices becomes increasingly complex.
The security vulnerabilities.
Integrating third party services
expands the attack surface.
We don't know what software they use,
what is the open source softwares
or what are the libraries they use.
So that increases when we integrate the
third party services into our ecosystem.
That increases the security vulnerability.
Risks include data breaches, unauthorized
access, and There are scenarios
where a third party application is
integrated into our databases or the
servers where the breach happened
into the third party service, which
eventually attacked our data servers
through the third party application.
Data privacy concerns, IoT platforms
handle sensitive data, making data
protection critical to maintaining
trust and compliance with regulations.
Securing iot integrations.
So how are we going to secure
these IO OT integrations,
authentication and authorization?
How are we going to achieve these
authentication and authorization
authentication mechanisms?
Mainly multi-factor authentication
requires multiple forms of verification.
Adding an extra layer of security so we
can enable a multi-factor or two-factor
authentication to authenticate any user.
to come into our ecosystem,
our software application.
Token based authentication is main,
one of the, one of the prominent
way of authentication, for the user
to authenticate, JSON web tokens,
which are JWT provide a stateless
scalable solution for authentication.
What are the authorization
protocols available?
OAuth2, OpenID Connect.
These are the widely used secure
authorization role based access controls
Attribute based access controls and
there are relation based access controls
as well securing communications in iot
ecosystems how are we going to secure?
communication in between the channels
or in between the systems or in between
the third party systems and other vendor
systems encryption methods What are the
encryption methods available to ensure
data confidentiality with the robot?
So Aus 2 56 encryption
end-to-end encryption, which
protects data from device to the
cloud throughout its journey.
Secure protocols is one of the, is
one of the method by using the HGT p.
S Mandatory for secure web communications
for any API APIs communication.
We can use the HGT PS.
And MQTT over TLS, a lightweight secure
communication protocol for IoT devices.
And COAP over DTLS used for
resource constrained devices.
So how are we going to
prevent the data manipulation?
Use VPNs to secure communications
and prevent data interception.
Implement digital signatures, digital
certs, and message authentication codes,
which are MACs for data integrating.
what are the data privacy and
security across the lifecycle?
the data lifecycle, the data
security lifecycle, mainly
consists of seven stages, which
are capture, store, analysis, use,
and then publish, archive, punch.
The lifecycle stage is
mainly on collection.
the collection use secure boot
mechanisms and authenticate APIs.
The transmission, Encrypt all data using
industry standard methods, storage, store
data in encrypted databases with strict
access controls, deletion, use secure
deletion methods such as crypto shredding
to ensure data cannot be recovered.
What are the mitigation strategies
and best practices available?
The API security, like we talked
about the API communication
by using the JSON web tokens.
OAuth2, OpenID, multi factor
authentication by using these
implements by implementing these strong
authentication and authorization and rate
limiting and monitoring API activity.
So what is the rate limiting?
So any API to API connected
communication happening to any gateway.
We can configure at gateway level, the
rate limit, how many transactions per
second, the backend API is allowed,
or we can configure, the max number so
that we can monitor the API activity.
If that max number is increases,
we can set up the alerts, warnings,
and, and the, configuration at
greater than 5 percent of my max.
Thanks.
Give us a warning or distributed email so
that products production operations team
members are, tier one people can go and
monitor why it is happening, what made,
what is the main factor, the root cause
of these all of a sudden peak activity
for this API traffic, the access controls
enforce the principle of least privilege
and review access rights regularly.
Okay.
The case study, the smart standard
overview, there is a smart city project
in Spain involving 20, 000 IoT devices.
What are the key integrations they did?
They did environmental monitoring,
sensors measure air quality and noise
levels, smart parking sensors of
mobile operators, traffic condition,
traffic management, adaptive control
systems, optimized traffic flow.
The results.
20 percent reduction in pollution
levels, 25 percent decrease
in parking related congestion.
The challenges solutions for this city
project, scalability, hierarchical network
architecture, interoperability, support
for multiple protocols and standards.
Security and privacy, end
to end encryption, and data
anonymization they achieved.
So the conclusion.
The future of IoT integration promises
to be transformative, driven by
emerging technologies such as 5G, edge
intelligence, and quantum safe encryption.
So organizations must be proactive,
embracing a balance between innovation
and security, while adhering to
stringent data protection laws.
So there is a balance the balance between
the functionality Versus the security
that's the main goal of this talk.
Thank you for listening to
me I hope this will help.
Thank you.
See you again