Okay, good.
Good morning.
Good evening everybody.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Kasi, and today I want
to talk about a fundamental shift in
how we build and deploy artificial
intelligence in the enterprise softwares.
We are moving beyond simple, isolated
AI tools, and we are entering
into an era of orchestration.
The presentation is about the.
Designing multi-agent AI systems that
can intelligently navigate our most
complex environments, which is our
ERPs and how our hybrid IT systems.
For the last few years, the
enterprise AI has often looked
like this, a series of silent.
Pilots.
For example, a marketing chart
bot here and a finance tool there,
an onboarding tool elsewhere.
They're all totally disconnected,
fragmented, and it requires
a ton of manual overhead to
make them talk to each other.
The model is.
Often broken and it
doesn't scale the future.
And what we are building today
is an adaptive ecosystem.
This is a move from isolated experiments
to coordinated networks of AI agents that
provide enterprise wide intelligence.
The they orchestrate data.
And most importantly, they
can autonomously optimize
enterprise workflows.
This is the challenge and
opportunity we will be exploring.
So exactly what is exact, what
exactly is a multi-agent system.
It is a helpful, it is helpful to
stop thinking about one single ai
instead, think of a team of specialized
experts, autonomous agents, coordinated
actions, and a goal directed steps.
Autonomous agency, the agent is
an AI entity with a specific role.
You might have a data analyst agent,
you might have a compliance agent,
and you might have an inventory agent.
Your data analyst agent, again,
can be subdivided into specialized
in bioinformatics, for example,
genetics, for example, and whatnot.
When it comes to coordinated action, these
agents don't just have to work alone.
They must be able to communicate,
collaborate, and delegate tasks
to solve problems that are far
too complex for any single agent.
And they do this with a purpose.
The system is given a high level
enterprise objective, reduce
procurement cost by 10%, and the
agents work together to achieve it
with minimal human intervention.
So next, what are the main four
main pillars for this enterprise?
AA orchestration.
There are four pillars
for this orchestration.
The first one is a goal directed planning.
Always planning is the most important one.
The system must be able to take a big
complex goal and break it down into small
and executable tasks for each agent.
Second, dynamic reflection.
This is crucial.
The system must be able to
look at its own performance.
Learn from its successes and
failures and get smarter over time.
Third, tool orchestration.
The agents are useless if they
can't interact with the real world.
The pillar is about giving them
access to your existing tools, your
APIs, your database, and your ERPs.
And finally, collaborative
problem solving.
This is the multi-agent.
Magic agents share insights and
coordinate actions to tackle challenges
that cross departmental silos.
This isn't just theory.
These are powerful frameworks
available right now that allow
us to build these systems.
Auto Gen is coming from Microsoft Graph is
a graph based structure, which is perfect
for complex cyclical workflows where
agents might need to rethink a problem,
what we call a cyclical reasoning.
When it comes to auto gen, it
is very excellent for creating
conversational agents that can
solve task together and crew ai.
Provides a role-based framework.
You literally define your agents
like a team, a senior researcher,
a writer, a manager, and they
collaborate based on the hierarchy.
Okay, let's make this real.
Where is this being applied
or is it just theory?
These things are getting applied
in procurement applications, in
procurement business in finance,
in hr, and in document management.
For example, when it comes to
procurement, I'm seeing automated
supplier evaluation, contract compliance
monitoring, running 24 class seven.
Across global supply chains.
When it comes to finance,
this is a game changer.
Think automated invoice processing,
real time expense reconciliation, an
anoma anomaly deduction that not only
finds fraud, but also generates the
audit trial in hr, we are automating
the entire onboarding workflows
using conventional interfaces to
resolve employee queries instantly.
And when it comes to document management,
agents can classify, extract, structure,
data, and route documents to the right
person, eliminating massive bottlenecks.
How?
How are the business impact measures
and the business impact is not trivial.
These are real measured results
from multi-agent deployments.
We are seeing an average of 65, 60
8% reduction in processing time in
workflows like procurement and finance,
and 92% improvement in accuracy
for tasks like data extraction and
a 45% gain in cost efficiency by
optimizing workflows and removing.
Manual, repetitive work.
This isn't just incremental increment.
It's a step change in
operational efficiency.
Next comes the integration between Hi
between different EA agents in ER within
ERP and also in hybrid IT landscapes.
Now for everyone in this room who manages
enterprise it, the first question is,
this sounds great, but I have a massive
complex SAP system and Oracle system.
How does this possibly integrate?
This is the most important
part we don't rip and replace.
The beauty of multi-agent framework
is its modular architecture.
You can adapt it incrementally.
The agents connect to your existing
systems, both cloud and on-prem
through standard APIs and middleware.
The you can start by automating
one small part of the process.
This approach massively reduces
risk, accelerates your time to
value, and lets you modernize without
breaking the bank or your business.
Next is about the critical
implementation challenges.
Of course, this is not without challenges.
You have to go into this
with your open eyes.
There are three critical hurdles,
security, data, privacy, scalability,
governance, and compliance.
We are giving agents
access to sensitive data.
This demands, I'm sorry,
this demands robust.
Authentication and governance,
and it comes to scalability.
As you grow from 10 to 1000
agents, how do you manage
computational resources and cost?
When it comes to governance and
compliance, this is a big one.
If an agent makes a decision on behalf of
somebody you must have an audit trial on.
What does it think?
Why does it make a decision?
And you must be able to satisfy
the regulators and build the
trust based on your audit logs.
Next is what are the
strategies for safe adoption?
So we spoke about challenges.
We spoke, we got excited,
we spoke about challenges.
Now it's time for us to know how
do we address these challenges.
First is comprehensive audit logging.
Second is bounded autonomy.
And finally, incremental deployment.
So we briefly spoke about audit, logging.
Every decision, every action, every piece
of data and agent touches must be logged
for transparency, bounded autonomy.
This is a key concept.
Agents are not given free reign.
We define clear operational boundaries,
and most importantly, we program
escalation path for human oversight.
A human is always in the
loop for critical decisions.
Finally, incremental deployment.
Don't try to boil the ocean.
Start with a low risk,
high value use case.
Validate this results, then expand.
Next is building your
multi-agent roadmap, right?
Your path to adoption must look like this.
First is foundation, followed by piloting.
Next is scaling and finally optimizing it
again to summarize this right all what we
are saying is don't try to boil the ocean.
Access your current state, and
find that the first high value use
case is going to be implemented.
Pilot it.
Define your first agents in
a re controlled environment.
Measure everything.
Scale, expand the successful
partners across other departments.
Now optimizing.
This is where you truly
orchestration, orchestrate.
You enable autonomous agent collaboration
and create self-learning capabilities.
Next is the end goal is here.
End goal.
Here is a fundamental shift in thinking.
We are not just building tactical
projects, we are building a self
optimizing digital ecosystem.
One where agents learn, adapt to changing
business conditions and coate autonomously
creating enterprise wide intelligence.
Okay, next is our playbook.
First is Playbook is a very clean one.
First is you have a design.
Second is integrate and then Scale.
And what is our key takeaways?
The key takeaways from the last 10
minutes are Multi-Agent systems are next.
Evolution of Enterprise ai, moving us from
isolated tools to coordinated systems.
Practical frameworks like Auto
Gen, land Graph, and Crew AI
are available to build today.
Today, success demands a balance.
You must balance between innovation
and governance and security.
And finally, the path to
success is to start small, think
big and more incrementally.
Thank you so much.
Again, my name is Kasi Pal.
Thank you for this opportunity.
You can see my LinkedIn
LinkedIn, URL here.
Thank you so much.