Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining this
session on prompt engineering.
As AI systems become more integrated
into our workflows, understanding
how to communicate effectively with
them becomes increasingly important.
Today, we will dive into the
challenges, key considerations, and
best practices for crafting prompts
that yield effective AI responses.
Prompt engineering is the practice
of designing and optimizing inputs
to AI systems to get desired outputs.
Think of it as learning to
speak the language that bridges
human intent and AI capability.
Just as we adapt our communication
style when speaking to different people,
we need to adapt how we communicate
with AI to get the best results.
Why should we care about
prompt engineering?
First, better prompt leads
to more accurate and relevant
responses, crafted prompts save
time and computational resources.
When using commercial AI
services, efficient prompts
can significantly reduce costs.
And finally, a good prompt
engineering helps minimize risks
like bias and hallucinations.
We can safely say that it is the art
and science of creating effective
prompts that guide AI to provide
relevant and accurate answers.
In any AI application, especially
in conversational AI and generative
tools, a well crafted prompt can be the
difference between a useful response
and one that misses the mark completely.
One of the primary challenges in
prompt engineering is ambiguity.
An unclear prompt can lead AI to respond
in the ways that may not meet our needs.
Another challenge is bias.
At certain prompts may inadvertently
guide the AI toward biased responses,
depending on the data it was trained on.
Context dependency means that slight
change in phrasing can alter responses.
Character limits can restrict
amount of context we provide.
And finally, without proper
structure, we might get inconsistent
responses across similar queries.
Before writing any prompt,
consider these key factors.
What's your ultimate goal?
We need to consider the
audience and purpose.
A prompt intended for technical
users will differ from the one
aimed at general consumers.
Then what does the AI, what
context does the AI need?
What are the constraints
you are working within?
It's essential to recognize the
limitations of the AI, understanding
what it can and cannot do.
What format should the response take?
And importantly, what safety
considerations should you keep in mind?
Here are some best practices
for prompt engineering.
First, use clear instructions.
The more direct you are, the more
likely the AI will respond accurately.
Next, refine your prompts iteratively.
Test and experiment with different
versions to find out what works best.
Testing and monitoring for bias
and sensitivity is critical to
ensure fair and balanced responses.
And provide context whenever possible to
narrow down the scope of the response.
Let's look at the best
practices for structure.
While you're structuring your
prompt, start with relevant context.
Clearly state the task and then
specify the desired format.
Whenever helpful, provide
examples and then outline any
constraints or limitations.
Following this structure helps ensure
clear communication with the AI.
Now let's go over an example of what
a poor prompt is and what a prompt
that follows the best practices
I mentioned earlier looks like.
Here, the user wants to know
how can I improve customer
satisfaction in my online store.
While it's clear that the focus is on
customer satisfaction, it doesn't specify
areas of, what areas are of concern,
which leaves the response too broad.
The prompt doesn't specify how many
suggestions are needed or what kind of
suggestions are needed, such as whether
they are looking for quick tips or they
are looking for in depth strategies.
It also doesn't indicate the
type or size of the online store.
Which leaves the AI to guess
what might be relevant.
Now, what on the right hand
side is the improved prompt.
Let's get into the details of how
that prompt becomes effective.
By following the best practices.
This prompt specifies that the
recommendations should focus on
customer service, website usability,
and post purchase follow up.
It helps the AI target these key areas.
It also clarifies that it's for a small
online retail business, which allows
the AI to tailor suggestions for a
smaller team with limited resources.
Requests five concise and
actionable strategies.
By setting expectations for a focused
and structured response, that is
manageable for the intended audience.
Now let's look at another example and
compare the responses from the AI.
This is a prompt for creating
emergency evacuation instructions.
The initial prompt is straightforward.
But it lacks the specificity needed
for a complex setting like a concert
venue, which is a detail which has
been provided in the effective prompt.
Write emergency evacuation instructions
is a vague request that doesn't provide
any context, format requirements,
or audience considerations.
As a result, the response is too
generic, not tailored for the unique
needs of a large venue, and failed to
account for specific emergency types,
languages, and accessibility needs.
In contrast, the improved prompt is
a great example of how incorporating
the best practices can lead to
a much more effective response.
This prompt specifies the type of venue.
A 1000 seat concert hall with multiple
floors and exits, and outlines particular
scenarios such as fires, medical
emergencies, and security threats.
It also includes special instructions
for disabled patrons, staff roles, and
event for even format requirements, like
bullet points and universal emergency
symbols to ensure clarity and usability.
With this detailed prompt, the
AI generated result is much more
comprehensive and practical.
For example, each emergency type, fire,
medical, and security has clear and
concise instructions with universal
symbols and multilingual indicators.
Specific assembly points and special
instructions for mobility assistance
and a breakdown of staff roles are all
provided, ensuring that the instructions
are easily understood and actionable.
This comparison shows the
power of a well crafted prompt.
When we are specific about our
requirements, structure, tone,
and context, we guide the AI to
produce a response that is detailed,
organized, and ready for use.
The improved prompt's clarity, structure,
and relevance show how best practices
in prompt engineering lead to much
more accurate and usable outputs.
Prompt engineering is
an iterative process.
So start with a basic prompt, evaluate
the response, identify issues,
refine your prompt and repeat.
Each iteration helps you understand
what works and what doesn't, which
leads to better results over time.
Use of advanced techniques
can enhance your results.
In chain of thought prompting, we
guide the AI through multi step
reasoning to enhance its accuracy.
It helps AI break down complex problems.
Role assignment can help set the tone
and perspective, such as asking the AI
to respond as if it were a historian.
It provides helpful context.
Few shot learning uses
examples to guide responses.
By allowing us to give specific
examples within the prompt and
setting a standard for responses.
System instructions help
overall behavior parameters.
Using conditional prompts with
if and then conditions can help
clarify nuanced instructions.
Adjusting the temperature of the model
controls and the randomness of responses,
allowing us to define, to fine tune
between creative or factual outputs.
Now let's look at some common
pitfalls to be mindful of.
Even after applying best
practices, we need to keep these
common pitfalls in our mind.
First, overcomplication.
Sometimes, in an effort to be thorough,
we add too much detail, which can
overwhelm the AI, causing it to miss
the main point and diluting the focus.
So aim to keep the
prompts clear and direct.
Assumption of knowledge is another trap.
Never assume the AI has background
information or specific knowledge
without explicitly providing context.
Lack of specificity is
a frequent issue too.
Without clear direction, the AI may
provide broad or irrelevant answers.
Unintentional bias can also slip in.
Based on the wording we choose.
So it's essential to carefully
phrase prompts to avoid the AI
going in a biased direction.
Ignored constraints.
Whether character limits, formatting
requirements, or ethical boundaries,
it can affect the quality and
suitability of the response.
for listening.
So by keeping these pitfalls in
mind, you will be more prepared to
create prompts that consistently
lead accurate and relevant results.
Now that we have followed all the
instructions for prompt creation, it
is important to validate its quality.
We start with an accuracy check.
Does the AI response directly address
what you are asking for in the prompt?
Task completion check is for
verifying that the AI successfully
accomplishes the intended task.
Relevance checks that the output
is focused and appropriate.
Bias evaluation involves reviewing the
responses to catch any unintended biases,
which may require adjusting the prompt.
Consistency testing ensures
that reports are accurate.
Repeating the prompt yields
consistent quality answers.
And finally, user testing is invaluable.
Gathering feedback from actual users
can reveal if the prompt is achieving
its intended clarity and effectiveness.
As AI systems evolve,
prompt engineering will too.
We will see new capabilities, better
tools, and evolving best practices.
The key is to stay adaptable and
keep learning as the field develops.
Thank you so much for
paying attention today.
I'm Aditi Godbole.
Please feel free to connect
with me on LinkedIn for further
discussions or any questions.
Thank you.