Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining this talk.
My name is Vladimir.
I'm a software engineer at Wales Corp.
In this session, I will be talking
about how to turn AI into APIs.
Big disclaimer, this talk is
from my perspective as a software
engineer, not a data scientist.
I will be demonstrating how software
engineers can use OCR and LLMs
to build their own applications.
Before we dive into the demo, let me first
give you a quick introduction to OCR.
OCR stands for Optical Character
Recognition, which is the process
of converting images of typed
text into machine readable text.
For example, if you have a scanned
document or any other image with
text, OCR can extract that text for
further use in your application.
Of course, there are many
options that provide OCR.
As a service that is Amazon Textract
or Google Cloud Vision API, for
example, but OCR is not enough.
there is a problem.
OCR usually convert images
into unstructured text.
But actually we need structured
data to work with it to build a
good interface for our clients.
Most APIs usually represent data as JSON
or any other serializable structure.
So it will be nice to extract text from
images, find the available data from this
text and represent it as a JSON, right?
And in 2024, we can actually do this.
this is where LLMs can really help us.
Many of them offer API for developers.
For example, OpenAI provides
many features through their API.
And one of the most interesting
and useful feature, in my
opinion, is function calling.
Function calling is extremely useful
for a large number of use cases.
It also has JSON mode.
The model's output is guaranteed to be
valid JSON when JSON mode is enabled.
This is exactly what we need, right?
how can we use it?
I will show you.
Let's go ahead to the demo.
And now I'm going to get my
hands dirty and write some code.
I'll be using TypeScript for this demo.
First, we have to set up an application
to handle HTTP requests from our clients.
I will be using Deno, which is
a modern JavaScript runtime.
Think of it like Node.
js, but better.
let's open my terminal.
Okay.
I'm gonna use dynainit to create a,
the basic structure of our application.
We have to give it a name.
I'm gonna call it receipt scanner API.
Why not?
All right, Dina has executed this command.
Now let's follow the instructions.
We, I will navigate to the project
folder and as you can see here,
there are three files here.
The first file is dna.
json, which is just a configuration file.
The second file is main.
ts, where we will write our code.
The third file is just a file
for tests, but I don't need tests
on this talk, I will delete it.
Okay.
Good.
Now let's open . I will use Vem for that.
we are seeing a few lines of an example
here, but I'm going to delete them.
So now I will be using Dina Surf.
What is Dina Surf?
Gina has actually a built in HTTP server,
and this function just runs that server.
If we check the definition of
this function, we can see that
it accepts a handler function.
This handler needs a accept
request from clients and return
the appropriate responses.
All right, now let's go ahead and code
a simple echo server to get started.
I'll just show you how it works.
Okay.
We can run it like this.
I'm going to use QRL to test this server.
All right.
It works.
so now let me explain again what
exactly we're going to create now.
let me open my browser.
Um, here is a overview, of how it'll work.
I will be using this direct jets for OCR.
Because it's free and open source.
I could use Amazon Textract for example,
but in this case it doesn't really matter.
Let's go through the flow
quickly, step by step.
First of all, the client sends a
request with URL of the receipt.
Then Textract extracts
text from this receipt.
The extracted test is passed to chat
dpt, along with a well structured prompt.
chat dpt does some magic and applies our
custom function to put data into a JSON.
And that JSON is sent back
to the client as a response.
Quite simple.
So now I'm going to use Tesseract.
js.
First, let's take a look at documentation,
which includes a brief example.
how to use it.
example of how to use it.
the first thing is, we, need
to create a worker and then
pass URL to recognize function.
the worker will automatically download
an image and extract the text from that.
Okay.
For this demo, I have a receipt
that I will be working with.
This one.
I just want to extract a description.
unit price and amount, for each item.
Additionally, I want to
capture total and total.
we'll use chat dpt for that.
Okay.
Let's go back to my terminal.
I'm going to import this
direct from my, from npm
and then i will use i will create a worker
and then use this worker on every request
good let's test it i'm gonna use
qrel and good okay, for now, our
application can extract text from images.
However, this text is unstructured and
contains a lot of irrelevant information.
We will use chart2BT to extract for,
to extract only the key information
and put in, put it in to JSON.
Okay, to use OpenAI
API, we need an API key.
You can easily create your own
API key on official website.
yeah,
yeah.
It's called OpenAI developer platform.
that is also an API reference here.
Okay, I'm gonna use the official
JavaScript library for OpenAI.
This one.
okay, let's open my editor.
And
I'm gonna import, I'm gonna
import OpenAI from npm.
Um, we have to put a P key here.
I'm going to load my IP key
from my system environment.
okay, let's create a chat GPT completion.
We will use, GPT 3.
5.
Access.
I will provide two messages, each
message has a specific role, but I
will not discuss it, in this talk,
the first message, which has a system
role, establish the main chat context.
the GPT model will understand
that it should act like a
helpful receipt analysis tool.
In the second message,
I will put the prompt.
so we need to come up with a
good prompt here for chat GPT.
For example, like this.
note that I concatenate my prompt
into a disrect result here.
you can come up with your own
prompt based on your use cases.
This my, this most creative part actually.
Yeah, I need only One choice,
so I'm gonna put one here, and
also I'm gonna turn on JSON mode.
now we need to ask ChatDept to map the
data into specific JSON format, and
for that we will use the function tool.
Let me show, let me show how.
I will copy and paste
a piece of code here.
I
can use it here.
the most important thing
here is a JSON schema.
this part.
we here define receipt
items as a JSON schema.
Every item has description.
unit, price, and amount,
which is a number.
all these properties are required, and it
has also subtotal and total as a number.
Once we get the completion here, we
can grab the first choice from it
like this, I'm going to remove it.
I take first choice here and I look
for a tool call that has this name.
If we can find, we will send a
internal server Otherwise, we
will take the arguments and send
back them to our client here.
And that's it.
I'm skipping important things like
argument validation and, token
optimization, because it's a just a demo.
okay, let's test it.
I'm going to run it here
and use QRL.
Wow.
it works.
Unbelievable.
Let's compare this JSON
with the original image.
Let me open the browser.
I'm going to have to open this, yeah.
It get a little bit wrong amount,
but everything, but, but it extracts
everything we need as you can see.
And that's it.
That's all you need to get started
using OCR and ChatGPT in your project.
If you run into any issues during
this talk or would you like to discuss
it, just reach me out on Twitter.
And thank you so much for your time.
I really appreciate it and enjoy
the rest of the conference.
Bye bye.