Hi, everyone.
Welcome to this Conf42 Prompt
Engineering Conference.
And even more welcome to my session
topic on exploring co pilot capabilities.
Now, for today, we have, about 45 minutes
presentation time, where I'm going
to try and show you quite some demos
to keep it a little bit entertaining.
Now, in short, although the main
topic of the conference is prompt
engineering, I actually wanted to take
it one step further and talking about
how to actually use prompt engineering
using Microsoft Copilot and not only
in like web or work like M365, but
actually giving you a walkthrough
of what it different co pilots, are
available today within Microsoft.
Now I'm going to start with a quick
overview, what generative AI is about.
Next to that, I'm going to zoom in a
little bit on, obviously, the prompt
engineering, and then from there,
walking you through a couple of
scenarios, where you already know, or
should know, that the ones I'm going to
walk you through are not the only ones
available in, the Microsoft world today.
Now, before we're going to jump
into the technical details,
I'll share a bit about myself.
So Peter De Tender, originally from
Belgium, but moved to Microsoft
Redmond close to three years ago.
I've been working for Microsoft a bit
more than five years as a Microsoft
Technical Trainer, which means I'm
basically providing full day sessions,
sometimes full week sessions, workshops
on the Azure platform where my main
technology focus has always been Azure
architecting DevOps and in meantime,
app modernization using developing
on Azure as well as co pilot and AI.
If you should have any questions during
the conference, feel free to reach out.
If you're watching this later on
as a recording, nothing should
stop you from reaching out.
I got my LinkedIn details up here.
You can reach me on Twitter.
You can send me an email.
So now let's jump in and talk a
little bit about Generative AI.
So these are just a couple
of headlines from, a bit more
than a year ago, actually.
Where everything was around,
revolutionizing AI using the chat
GPT generative AI capabilities.
And there's a lot of headlines here,
but the main goal is that it's here.
Yes, a bit more than a year
ago, it was totally new.
Nobody really talked about it.
And I would say the
capabilities are crazy amazing.
And it's also a big part of
what I want to share today.
Now, giving you one easy example, this
is where, for example, I started using.
A prompt to generate my bio picture,
like when I'm starting training, like
every morning basically, or sometimes
like Monday morning in a multi day
class, then I need to talk a little
bit about my background, like building
up credibility for the training.
And that's where now I start playing
a little bit with prompt engineering.
To generate my bio picture.
Now, the thing is, how do
you get from your image into
a prompt engineer component?
So I'll walk you through the basics
where it should not be as harder as
what I'm going to try and show you.
If you look a little bit at this
picture, you're going to see that
there are a few different elements.
And I would say for me,
just as an example here.
What I would highlight
is, for example, Seattle.
Now you know my roots, it's Belgium.
So you can see the Belgium flag up here.
If we look at Peter himself, you can
detect a little bit of spiky hair.
You can detect glasses.
You can detect the hoodie
which I like to wear.
You can detect the Microsoft logo
and some sort of a laptop.
Just looking at that picture and
recognizing the key components,
that's all you need to build up.
Your prompts, why?
Because if I move all this into some
few sample prompts actually used for
generating those images, the first
one was cartoon man, Pixar style.
So you can use, some already
existing, artistry, you could say.
But now the rest of my prompt across all
three is basically the same with a big
smile wearing glasses, thin beard, dark
brown, short hair, gray hoodie, Microsoft
logo, Surface laptop in the background,
show the Seattle skyline and the Belgian
flag on top of it and just reusing
like 99 percent of the same prompt, but
then only making some minor changes.
Flipping from Pixar style to
Simpsons style to Marvel comic style.
That's how you're going to end up
with pretty cool and sometimes even
remarkable, impressive, outcomes of that.
Now that's the setting the
scene on prompt engineering.
Now in short, what is prompt engineering?
It's where, again, about a year
ago, The world was going crazy.
So again, just a few headlines here
from, reputable magazines and news,
papers where I picked up like,
it's actually a pretty cool thing.
So a lot of them literally talk about like
the first one here, rising significance
in prompt engineering, or the other
one, the number one thing CEOs are
investing in right now is, guess what?
Generative AI.
And then the last one here,
obviously the one that I like most
is that thanks to generative AI.
The AI job paying more than
300, 000 without having a
computer engineering background.
quite impressive, but is it all
really that important and that easy?
in short, what is prompt engineering?
The first part in engineering is,
prompt engineering is the prompt.
a prompt can be described as,
involving instructions, providing
details, providing a context, Passing
it on to a large language model
and then achieving a desired task.
The second part is engineering.
When our engineering here
refers to developing, optimizing
prompts to efficiently again,
use that large language model.
Now, by the way, if you want to learn
more prompt engineering, I'm going
to give you another easy example.
Now, I would say prompt engineering
sounds a little bit wrong.
Now, why?
Because engineering sounds hard.
It sounds difficult.
And since not all of us are engineers,
it almost seems I'm not even able to
use that generative AI technology.
So that's why within Microsoft, we
actually like to use the term the
art of the prompt, or as I like
to describe it, prompt artistry.
Now, what does it mean?
You could grab like a tool of brushes,
you could grab some colors, you could
have a canvas, but that's no guarantee
to actually come up with a nice painting.
On the other side, prompt artistry
should not be all that hard, since in
the end, we have the natural language
concept, allowing us to assist with,
creating our prompts, but also using it.
And in the end, you're
basically switching.
And that's the part that I like about it.
You're switching from
searching into finding.
And the way to do that is basically
asking a series of questions.
So moving this into a business context
that later on, I'll show you in
one of the demos, you'll see that.
A scenario could be something like this.
We have a goal in mind, which means
what do you want Copilot to do?
Next, it had the context,
like why do you need it?
who's going to be involved?
Apart from that, we have the source, where
later on we'll talk about web and work,
and eventually what are the expectations.
So the example here could be, I
need to review, come up with details
about Microsoft Financial Report.
The context, I need it for a
meeting that I have next week with
Microsoft executives, for example.
The source could be web or work, which
means I'm going to use the trained
language model information, like
public data that it's been trained
on, Or, and that's specific to Copilot
in M365 that I'll share about, a lot
more later on, using your corporate,
Microsoft 365 backend data like
OneDrive, email, Teams, and SharePoint.
And from there, my expectation
is I don't need all the details,
but I want you to give me like a
summary in seven bullet points.
It's almost identical to approaching
Your colleague approaching the CFO,
maybe in this case, oh, could you
provide me like the Microsoft report?
But instead of giving you all the
details, you're gonna fine tune it,
you're gonna summarize it, and then the
actual prompt could be something like
this, where everything is now nicely
coming together in one larger prompt,
where the prompt, again, is technically
almost identical to just asking a question
in the, I dunno, human world without
using copilot to help you with that.
Now enough talking about it, I'm going
to switch to, my first demo here.
So what I'm using right now is copilot.
microsoft.
com.
So you open up your browser.
You connect to copilot.
microsoft.
com and it's going to ask you like,
Hey, how do you want to authenticate?
Do you want to use work?
So that's the difference web and work.
Or do you want to use a personal account?
Now I'm going to switch
to my other window.
And actually trying to show you,
there we go, what it looks
like in the personal space.
Now, this is what we
describe as unlicensed.
So I'm authenticated with my
Peter at Google account, and I
could ask basically any prompt.
There's a few sample prompts on screen,
and I could do something like this.
What, Oh, I already have it here.
So I'm, my roots, I'm from
Belgium, which means I like food.
I like beer and preferably food
that has some sort of beer in
it, which means, beef stew.
So to come up with some
new ideas, I literally.
Went for a prompt.
I'll show you in a second.
I got beef stew meat.
Like I went to the store,
got me some beef stew meat.
And can you just come up with
some ideas, share a few recipes.
So without doing anything
specific or spectacular, it's
now coming up with a recipe.
a couple of different recipes.
It shows me the ingredients and it also
provides me the actual instructions,
how to, start creating this.
Next to that, I could also do
something like, can you create an image
showing a delicious beef stew meal?
And that's what I could
maybe, for example.
Show to my wife later tonight
when she's back from work.
Back to our corporate environment.
So the entry point is the same.
I'm using copilot.
microsoft.
com.
We're now instead of using personal, I'm
going to switch to my work environment.
What this is going to do is shifting
to what we now call biz chat.
So what is biz chat?
There's actually a short link.
M365.
cloud.
Microsoft, but that's a little bit
new, I would say because before
we all had to go to copilot.
microsoft.
com.
I'm in my trusted M365 environment, where
now it means I can actually start finding
information, using information, and then
later on maybe editing my environment.
Now, before that, I'm going to switch
back to the presentation for a little bit.
And talking about
all the other cool stuff inside Copilot.
Now, in short, what is Copilot?
Copilot is like a collection, you
could say, of different AI assistants.
Powered by the generative AI to help
you with what we call cognitive tasks.
Copilots are often driven
by natural language.
The large language model
that I already talked about.
Copilots are also embodied by a chatbot.
So that's what I showed you
in one of my first demos.
Humans are still in control.
That's one of the amazing things
I like about the term co pilot
is that you're still the pilot.
You're in charge.
You need to validate the answers and
you're going to decide eventually what
part of it that you're going to use.
Now, the main value I would also say
is really depending on what kind of
tasks are you performing and I'll walk
you through a couple of demos on that.
that later on.
Now we describe it as
the era of co pilots.
Now what does it mean?
Think of co pilot as that well trained,
well aware, up to date, real time
collaborator for basically anything.
So it allows you to generate content.
It allows you to literally put
Become that assistant if you
want one of the building blocks.
By the way, I didn't
mention in that overview.
what is a good prompt is a persona
and I'll show you that in a demo
later on where you could now
go Hey, co pilot, you're acting
as an Azure technical trainer.
And you can only answer
Azure technical questions.
If there's any question coming up
about, how to prepare beef stew, you
won't be able to, answer that prompt.
Or, obviously, flipping it around,
like your, I don't know, 15 year
experienced, I don't know, high quality
Michelin star alike restaurant chef.
You've been managing the kitchen for
15 years and I want you to come up with
a delicious meal, recipe and so on.
But you do not know anything
outside of the kitchen.
Something like that.
So that's another cool thing.
So it's again back to our co pilots.
So it's going to allow
you to generate content.
It's going to allow you to
optimize your productivity.
It's going to allow you to automate
your cognitive tasks and then
eventually, helping you completing
your tasks in a more fun way.
Now, although I called my topic copilot
capabilities, it's actually not even
possible anymore to describe even the
basics of copilot or all different
Microsoft copilots we have in meantime.
I'm going to try and zoom in a
little bit on my screen here,
but if we look at like the
capabilities, Peter is big over there,
so I would say we have co pilot.
We have capability integrations for
developers for business applications.
That would now be our dynamics
environment, and then we have, Modern
work, so everything around Microsoft 365,
data and AI, that's the core of our AI
solutions, still integrating with machine,
machine learning using the Azure platform.
In the browser, a little bit,
whoops, what I already showed you.
And the main message here is,
there's a copilot for pretty much
anything, for pretty much any user.
And that's what this slide is actually
trying to jump in every now and then.
Maybe something wrong with the animations,
but this is a slide that I, a slide,
sorry, that I personally like a lot.
Why I call it the rooms of the house.
This could be your private environment,
obviously your apartment, your home,
where you could talk to your wife, your
partner, your kids, and stimulating them
to use Copilot for pretty much anything.
Now, obviously this is a little
bit more in the business context.
And what it means is again that we do
have copilots for pretty much any user.
If you store corporate data inside
SharePoint, Teams, Outlook, which I
think everyone is pretty much doing
in the Microsoft world, you're going
to rely on copilot for Microsoft 365.
If we look at the business part
of it, like where you're going to
store business data, it might be.
Co pilot for Dynamics, where
we're now covering solutions for
HR sales teams, marketing teams.
That's the idea.
If you're a sysadmin, if you're
a data engineer, you're going
to look into managing co pilot
integration using co pilot for Azure.
You have co pilot for security, co
pilot for Azure, where it's going
to help you looking into your Azure
subscriptions, your Azure environments,
and providing you feedback like how are.
My service doing, can you help me creating
a new Azure template to do something?
That's the idea.
If you're a developer, you're
going to focus on co pilot
for GitHub or now, I think the
official term is GitHub co pilot.
I'll walk you through that a little
bit later on, and then eventually
co pilot for anyone else where you
might go for power apps or co pilot
studio, allowing basically any user.
to create their own custom copilots
outside of what's already available
here on screen as a capability.
So from here, I'm going to walk you
through a few different examples.
I'm going to start with Copilot 365, later
on GitHub Copilot, and then eventually
showing you apart from the capabilities,
I'm going to walk you of Copilot in M365,
Copilot in GitHub, how you can actually
create your own Copilots, whether you're
a developer or just a traditional user.
And hopefully that's
going to become clear.
So the first piece is adopting Copilot.
So imagine the story that I like
to use in this presentation is,
we started with generative AI.
Maybe you looked into ChatGPT or
maybe, You're still using it today,
where now I'm going to try and
convince you that there are some
additional benefits in using M365.
So my first wave here is adopting Copilot.
We talked about the private space, the
unlicensed space, but I would say for
corporate use, preferably you're going
to pay for that Copilot M365 license.
I think roughly, but
not all that important.
Check with your Microsoft
account team, I would say.
But I think on average, it's
around 30 per user per month.
Now you might think okay, Peter,
that's a quite a big investment
for a larger organization.
So what's the gain?
First of all, you have access
to the large language model.
In web and work.
I showed you a super basic prompt,
give me some recipes, around beef stew
in the private space, and I'm going
to show you the same prompt that, or
similar prompt that I'm going to use
in the corporate space next to that.
It's going to allow you to use
generative content creation.
You can use Copilot in M365
in all Office applications.
In Word, in Excel, in PowerPoint,
in OneNote, Copilot pages,
one of the newer capabilities.
You can use it to find information,
you can use it to brainstorm an
idea, and again, basically using
it as that well trained colleague.
And then in the end,
optimizing productivity.
So in short, how does it
work a little bit from like a
helicopter architect perspective?
You have the large language models.
Copilot in 365 is using the GPT 4 model.
So one of the most up
to date trained models.
It's going to hook into Microsoft
Graph, where Graph is the API
integration that we're using to
present you data from Office 365.
One drive, one machine.
SharePoint, emails, and Teams.
Now, the other nice thing is that
although Copilot runs as a service,
it's embedded in almost each and every
Office product in the meantime, but
it's also respecting your security.
Which means that it's going to
run in your usual account mode.
So your data is your data.
We're not using it to train where
some other generative AI solutions are
actually using your prompts to train the
models and they're using metadata from
your content to again train the model.
Within Copilot we're not doing that.
So your data remains your data and it's
also respecting security boundaries.
It's already mentioned integrated
in M365 applications, and you
can also use it in the web what
I showed you in my previous demo.
So that let's shift to, the next
demo here, where I'm going to
go back to what we now describe
as the Co Pilot M365 BizChat.
And that's over here.
So I landed in copilot.
microsoft.
com.
Do you want to use personal?
Do you want to use work?
And we land here.
A lot of different options you
can do, or you can use from here.
So it's going to try and help
you a bit with, sample prompts.
The sample prompts here are actually,
coming and I'll show you that later on.
From what we call co pilot lab.
So if you do aka.
ms forward slash co pilot lab, it's
going to show you how, you can come
up with what I call sample prompts.
They've been created by the product
teams vetted by, the first wave of users
and feedback from customers as well.
So for example, within the
corporate space, you might need
help with preparing for a meeting.
You might be looking for a file
type, or a document name that you
remember from like a customer, but
you don't really know where to find
that document because it's somewhere
in your SharePoint, it's somewhere.
In your OneDrive, you know that
it's there, but you don't really
know exactly where to find it.
And that's where your
copilot is going to help you.
So I'm going to go back to,
another sample idea here.
Let's say in preparation
for my meeting, can you.
I'm going to go ahead and list up the
latest Microsoft financial report.
Now, before
I'm going to run this, let me
talk a second about work and web.
So thinking back about the previous
slide, I talked about the large language
model using public trained data.
That would be the web.
We're now, if we switch to work, that's
where it's using your corporate M365.
So depending on the task,
remember you're in control.
You need to think about where.
Am I going to find the
information that I need?
So if I use the web tab, for example, and
I'm going to run this prompt, what it's
going to do is pulling up information.
Again, this is not a hundred percent
real time, internet search, but it's
providing me feedback based on what the
large language model has been trained on.
Now it's going to provide me
here, some input, all good.
And it's going to show me
the actual annual report.
So that's another nice thing with Copilots
that it's going to show you not only
the prompt feedback, the response, but
it actually also comes up with, the
source where that information came from.
So I could use.
Like the web page here, and
that's going to show me all the
details and I can download it.
And that's what I'll reuse later on.
Now, the nice thing is here.
Like the sources are public web,
sorry, public internet pages.
now, if I switch to work, what it
actually means now is that I'm going to
use the same prompt, but this time it's
going to use internal corporate sources.
SharePoint, OneDrive, Teams meetings,
for example, and it's typically also
providing more insights, more details
because it's closer to the employees.
Now, the baseline scenario
is still the same.
So it's going to give me the
details, but it's also pointing
to files that I have access to.
I can shift to Copilot in Word,
for example, where now this idea
is I downloaded that Microsoft
Financial Report and I can have
Another integration with Copilot.
There's actually two
different ways to use this.
So one example is what
we call Copilot drafting.
So whenever you're in a Word document,
in PowerPoint, in Excel, in OneNote,
you're going to see this little
Copilot icon showing up over here.
What it allows me to do is now using
Copilot generative AI capabilities
to help me with my document creation,
my document research, my Business
idea, compilation and whatnot.
So I could do something like writing a
prompt back to the basics, where now I
could do transform this into a table.
The use case here is that maybe I
don't know how to do this in Word,
but I like to find that information,
reuse it and move it into a table.
That's what, again, what we call drafting.
Why?
Because.
It's still a draft.
I need to confirm keeping it or
I could go back to the prompt
and actually updating my prompt.
I'm going to keep this change for now.
That's all fine.
Now, another use case is using Copilot
to help me with my document, but
this time I'm not really changing
anything in the document, but I'm
going to take some other actions.
Again, we do have our Copilot lab
based, sample prompts to get started.
And if you want more.
You can actually use this view prompt,
and it's going to show you the copilot
lab vetted prompts from here based
on the task that you want to perform.
The prompt scenarios are different
in Word, in PowerPoint, in Excel.
That's the idea.
So there is a prompt here.
Summarize this document
in X amount of points.
Now, again, showing you that it's
understanding your natural language.
You could do something
like, can you provide.
Need, key takeaways from this document.
I don't need to add from this document
because I'm already inside the document.
Now, I like this one.
Key takeaways because it might
have a different connotation for
basically, any different user.
If I'm in a financial report
and I would ask my CFO, can you
provide me the key takeaways?
The answer will be totally different
than if you would ask, one of your
HR people, or if you would ask, like
in my case, a technical trainer.
Can you talk about
Microsoft Financial Report?
The answer will probably
be slightly different.
But even then, the core
concept remains the same.
It's going to provide me the prompt
input, it's going to provide the response,
and it's also providing me the source.
This time, no source on the
Internet, but it's a source within
the Word document, and then jumping
across different paragraphs.
Another cool example,
is inside PowerPoint.
One of the things that we all have
to do, like creating PowerPoint
decks for our presentations, right?
Where I'm going to start from a
new presentation, where again, you
can see up here, we do have Copilot
and here on the side again as well.
The use case is again, slightly
different depending on again,
the task you want to perform.
So I'm going to start the upper
one here, and it's going to offer
me what we now call the CoPilot
PowerPoint Narrative Builder.
Imagine my scenario here.
If you paid attention to the pitch
at the start of the session, it's
like making users more productive.
So the flow would typically be, doing
research, going to the internet,
finding information, go to SharePoint,
OneDrive, anywhere on the planet.
To find your information, you're
typically going to move that into a
Word document and building up your flow,
or your story of your presentation.
And then eventually you're going to
move all that into PowerPoint slides.
All that can now be optimized
with one easy prompt.
So I'm going to reuse the same prompt,
create a presentation about, and so on.
I'm using the exact same
prompt, copy pasting.
And again, it's going
to use generative AI.
To build up the layout of my
presentation based on the content,
the actual headlines, the chapters,
if you want, within my financial
report, based on the same generative
AI prompt that I used before.
I still have.
Co pilot integration, I could add
something at a topic about Azure AI.
I could move my outline components
around, so I could move it up and
down, and then eventually asking
to generate the actual content.
What it's going to do here is starting
with the base outline, it's going
to create the different slides.
Next to that, it's going to add It's
going to add all the different chapters
and the last it's going to add content
where it's not just some minimal text,
but it's actually providing full details,
adding images, adding bullet points.
And on top of that, adding
speaker notes as well.
And all this in, again,
just a couple of minutes.
I did not edit this piece
of the presentation for
the recording, by the way.
If I open up one of these slides.
You can see that everything is there.
The information is coming from
the prompt response and it's
also providing the speaker notes.
The other nice thing is from here,
if I go to co pilot on the site,
remember I briefly talked about graph.
So what I can do is add information
from forward slash and that's going
to allow me to browse for files.
Now here, if I want to add information
from Let's say a customer, or at least
I know the topic of the presentation.
I could do something like Contoso learn,
it's a sample customer I'm using here
and adding some information from a
Word document from another PowerPoint,
and it's getting nicely integrated.
So that's, in short, what
our Copilot M365 is about.
Next example is targeting, a little bit
more, what I would call the developer.
Team within your organization, you have
GitHub copilot based on all the same
concepts that I already talked about,
allowing you to not only document
code, analyzing code, writing code, but
also overall making your developers.
more productive, similar
to traditional M365 users.
So in short, what is Copilot for
GitHub or yes, I know GitHub Copilot,
I think is the more common name.
Now, you still have the large
language models on one end.
In the middle, that's the integration
with your trusted developer environment.
Visual Studio Code extensions, Visual
Studio JetBrains, and a few other
environments, and then ultimately your
developer velocity, reducing technical
depth, integrating better code, reusing,
GitHub copilots to, for example, create
documentation, something that typically
developers not always like to do,
or why not, having a scenario where.
You might be the new
developer on the team.
You need to jump into an already
existing project and you want to
learn, what's actually happening there.
So that's, a few examples that
I'm going to try and show you
in my next GitHub Copilot demo.
So I'm using Visual Studio Code.
This is a little sample app where it's
integrating some OpenAI services in Azure.
And allowing me to transform, a
summary of a YouTube video into
three to five bullet points.
If you want to get access to this
app, by the way, it's a bit off
topic, but I actually have it on my
GitHub, Repo, if you go to github.
com slash P E tender, you're going to
find it as the YouTube, summarizer.
It's not about the app, but just
showing you some capabilities
that we have with Copilot.
So the first example is
I'm jumping into this app.
Maybe this is an app that like,
why not you clone from my GitHub
repo and you go what's Peter doing?
from the language perspective.
So I could go into my copilot extension.
I'm going to open it up and this is
from the previous run testing your
demos is always a good thing, right?
Where I'm literally using add workspace,
which means, Hey, get up copilot.
I want you to look into this specific
application, not just this file, but
everything around it, and provide an
explanation for the active selection.
So I selected, a certain part of my
app code and asking for an explanation.
What it's doing here is providing a pretty
detailed, pretty extensive, Description
pointing to the different files.
So the same concept that I talked
about and showed you in web, in work,
in my PowerPoint and Word documents,
is now the same for GitHub Copilot.
Using language pro large language
model, translating, recognizing your
super basic prompts, but you can
actually make it more powerful, and it's
going to provide you an explanation.
Another example that I have is, can
you add necessary code to integrate
this app with Azure Key Vault?
So it's again providing a description.
It's going to explain like I need these
nugget packages, and from there it's
going to show you the new lines of code.
But again, it's still a draft.
So you need to decide okay, this
all looks good, and I'm going to
insert it inside my application.
I could go into my app settings.
I'm going to show you this live,
where now I could go back to my chat
window and document this code snippet.
And again, there are quite some pre built
keywords that you could use, like the
ad workspace that I showed you before.
But on the other side, you
don't really have to use it.
because again, it's relying on
your, traditional natural language.
Now you could go okay, Peter.
I recognize this as JSON.
I recognize your previous code,
which is like NET C sharp.
But what if I'm a Java developer?
What if I'm a Python developer?
So I could go back.
I could select everything in here,
where now I could do something.
Can you rewrite the C
sharp code into Python?
And then in just a couple of seconds, it's
actually going to help you recognizing the
exact same syntax from your code pages.
And from there translating it into Python.
I'm not going to apply it from here
because obviously it's just one
easy example, but that's really
the power of GitHub Copilot.
Using it to explain existing code, using
it to document code, using it to rewrite
code and then maybe even using it to
find, optimizations to maybe rewrite full
snippets of code and actually, or even
allowing you to maybe even migrating your,
existing legacy code into newer language.
But
what if M365, what if web, what if.
GitHub Copilot, I would say,
is still not good enough.
That's where now you also have
the option to extend your own
Git, extend your own Copilot.
Two different scenarios.
The first one I'm going to zoom in for
a couple of minutes is Copilot Studio.
Using Copilot Studio, it's going to
allow you to, what we describe as a no
code or low code, like injecting the
minimal experience as a developer, to
actually create your custom co pilots.
Everything I talked about
up to now is still valid.
So it's allowing you to
customize co pilot in M365.
An easy example, you want to add,
additional Teams integration.
You want to add integration with
other corporate applications
where you're going to read out
information from your corporate users.
find me emails from my manager
where you don't have to specify
the name, Of the manager based
on your organizational chart.
It actually knows, who
your manager will be.
That's the scenario.
Second one is integrating
specifically building from scratch.
So not using extensions to M365, but
actually building your own custom copilot
from scratch using copilot studio.
You can imagine I got a
little demo coming up.
How to use Copilot Studio.
So the idea is that you
connect to copilotstudio.
microsoft.
com.
You're going to authenticate, you
need the license, and from there
you can start building, creating,
composing your app, although you don't
really need to think as a developer.
And there's a lot of examples
available, like a safe travel chat
function app, a website Q& A where
you can build up the flow of the
prompts, that's the nice thing.
store operations like optimizing,
retail, creating an IT helpdesk scenario,
allowing your employees to find not
only answers, but actually helping
them fixing issues, resolving issues,
and also helping in, in creating,
but also reducing support tickets.
There's links to documentation
and anything else from here.
So let's say I switched to Copilots and I
already reused my, Safe Travels template.
So what it's going to give me
here is a pretty step by step drag
and drop, if you want, scenario.
Allowing me to come up with my own
co pilot, defining the data backend.
Like you can use information from our
corporate backend, or you can literally
provide the actual data set yourself.
And then also helping the
users who start using the chat
capabilities into your own scenario.
I'm going to try and refresh
because it's not coming up.
That's what happens when you do live
demos during recordings, But that's fine,
I could show you how to create a new one
so you could build your own new co pilot.
Let's say we're going to do IT Helpdesk.
Oh, bad example.
Let's see what we already have.
So that's the other thing where it's
not just about your M365 because
then you would use that extension.
But now you can interact with
third party applications.
Imagine you have this step by step
flow where you want to use data from
Google Drive, you want integration
with DocuSign, you want to send
Slack update messages and whatnot.
Think of it as building your own solution
using the same large language model
concepts, having that look and feel co
pilot experience, but now connecting
to your specific corporate data.
And then the last piece here is Still
creating your own custom co pilots,
but instead of relying on the power
apps based integration or the co pilot
low code no code scenario is now we
actually do have a team of developers
and we want to build our own extensions.
So what can we do there?
The answer there would be Azure AI Studio.
So what is Azure AI Studio?
It's gonna, it's running on
top of the Azure platform.
You deploy Azure AI service.
And a little differentiator here
is that it's not only relying on
the chat GPT like GPT 4 models.
But also allowing you to integrate
other language models besides OpenAI.
So you can integrate Lama from Meta.
You can integrate, Phi from Microsoft.
You can integrate Mistral
and a few other as well.
Apart from deciding which language
models you're going to use.
You can have an integration
with the chat playground.
You would typically use chat
playground to validate the outcome
of different large language models.
And then from there, that's where
the actual development work comes in.
You're going to use it
to fine tune the model.
Maybe you're going to use Azure
AI Studio for custom development.
So integrating a little bit what I showed
you in my YouTube summarizer example.
I'm going to build a little
app, little web interface.
I'm going to rely on AI Studio.
And the Azure AI services to provide
me interaction with the AI APIs.
And then maybe even going all
the way to the machine learning,
starting point of AI eventually and
using it to train your own models.
So with that, I'm going to switch to
my last demo and showing you a little
bit what AI Studio could look like.
So I deployed my AI service.
So basically in the Azure portal,
you look for AI, Azure AI service.
It takes a couple of minutes, and
from there, it's going to tell
you to navigate to AI Studio.
And that's where I would say the
creation, the validation actually starts.
I deployed two different models,
but I can show you a little bit
what the model catalog looks like.
So again, we have.
Models from Cohere, Mistral, Meta, so the
LLAMA options are in here, GPT, so the
OpenAI, and you can start mixing matching.
Obviously, depending on the use
case, the recommendation would be
to use the specific model that you
want to use for your environment.
Once your models have been deployed,
I have an example here with 3.
5 Turbo and 4.
The main difference, I would say,
is the lifespan of the data that
has been used to train the model.
An easy example to show you what I
mean by that is if we have a default
prompt, who's the prime minister
of the UK?
Where based on GPT 3.
5, as you can see here, it's going to
tell me, as of September 2021, that's
basically the last up to date this 3.
5 model has been trained on,
it's going to provide the answer.
But now if I switch to GPT 4.
0, that got published like earlier this
year, and using the same prompt, who
is the Prime Minister of the UK, you're
going to see that based on the exact
same prompt, the answer is different.
Because now GPT 4 has been trained
up to October 2023, give or take.
So that's how it could impact the
answers in your business model.
Another thing, since, the conference
overall talks about prompt
engineering, remember that you can
use your own system prompt as well.
AI assistant and so on.
But what if we turn this into URI?
Microsoft technical trainer, why not?
Let's translate Peter or replace, why not?
Peter, the technical trainer
with a co pilot scenario.
You are a Microsoft technical
trainer and expert on Azure platform.
You can only answer Azure questions.
If any other domains come up.
In the question, apologize and offer
the user a Belgian beer suggestion.
Why not?
So this is what we call fine
tuning your co pilots if you want.
And again, this is mainly fitting
in the custom co pilot scenario.
So if I try this.
And I'm going to use the exact same
prompt, who is the prime minister of
the UK as a Microsoft technical trainer?
You probably cannot really
answer that question.
Now, what it does, and that's the other
cool thing, it's still using generative
AI, Because now, actually, by the way, if
you're watching this, this is actually a
perfect suggestion, recommending Chimay
Blue, which is, one of the nicer, best,
fine, classic Trappist beers we have.
That's in short, how you could start with.
integrating this into your own developing.
If you want to learn, there's
obviously a lot more we can move
all the way into PromptFlow.
We could talk about Symantec kernel.
We could talk about integrating other
development scenarios, using Python,
using C sharp, using Java, all that is
basically developing your own custom
copilots where the baseline is using.
Azure AI Studio.
So with that, we're at the
end of my presentation.
I hope you enjoyed it.
I hope you learned some new things about
prompt engineering, the building blocks,
what composes like a good prompt, and
then from there a quick walkthrough
of some highlights in the different
Microsoft Copilots that we have.
I hope you enjoyed the rest of
Conf42 Prompt Engineering Conference.
If you should have any questions
after participating, after watching
this session, I'd Don't hesitate
reaching out pe tender at Microsoft.
com for email or Teams.
I'm on LinkedIn as PDTIT and you
can find my personal blog on aka.
ms slash PDTIT as well.
Thank you for now and enjoy
the rest of the conference.