Hello everyone.
I'm Balraj Kraj, QA architect
and IT specialist expert.
Today I'd like to explore how
codeless automation and AI
prompts empower manual testers.
I'm gonna take like around like 20
minutes and I will get discussing about
the challenges, the automation barriers,
and a new how to democratize automation.
The frameworks that we follow to
implement those automation, codeless
automation and the benefits.
And we will also discuss about
the common concerns and the
takeaways at the end before we see.
Okay.
Let's get started from manual
testing to prompt mastery.
How this can be achievable.
Yes, this is achievable.
This is very beneficiary, I would
say, but the first challenging facing
we need discuss about the challenges
for the manual testers today.
There is a widening gap job posting, now
demand automation and E screens, creating
a shop divided QEA, manual testers.
The reach in product knowledge and
domain expertise face growing pressure
as roles evolve faster than ever.
Script based tools like Selenium and Cirus
remain out of reach for many non coders.
Widening gaps in pay
progression and job security.
The rising stakes, yes.
EA driven development and
rapid CACD cycles have raised
the bar for quality assurance.
Teams are more expert to deliver faster
feedback, broader coverage, and continuous
integration of test into every bill.
The risk.
Cease and detest us with invaluable
insight into user journeys or
being sidelined by technical
automation rules, even though their
intuition remains irreplaceable.
The traditional automation barriers,
coding prerequisites, automation
rules, demand coding skills
like Java, Python, Java, screen.
That many experienced manual testers
lack with this technical barrier
creates an artificial debate between
technical and non-technical testers and
understanding the complex frameworks.
Now, the complex frameworks shift focus
from what to test to how to code the test.
This distracting from core quality
insight and another burden is
maintenance script based automation
requests constant updates for all UHA.
Creating significant technical debt
that worries team in maintenance
work rather than innovation.
A new parum democratizing
the test automation.
The convergence of codeless automation
platforms and prompt engineering
techniques offers a transformation
solution by combining intuitive to
interfaces with well craft DA props.
Organizations can empower manual
testers to translate their domain
expertise into executable test
without writing a single line of code.
We show simplicity.
Codeless platform use drag and wrap
interfaces that mirror testers,
mental models, making automation
accessible and entity from day one.
And next one is ary.
That unlocks sophisticated
test generation, still feeling
locators, intelligent assertions
through natural language commands.
If you are able to handle these two,
we can able to preserve the domain
expertises test is leverage their
replaceable product knowledge while
seamlessly adopting modern automation
practices on contributing immediately
four PACE transformation framework.
Platform evolution, knowledge transfer,
standardization, the process, and scaling
the process In Platform evolution.
Initially, we need to access codeless
tools based off organization needs,
tech stacks compatibility, and
a prompting comp capabilities.
Look for the platforms that
truly democratize the automation.
This is very important to take it
off and once we have a curated.
Platforms that were set Then
knowledge transfer train manual
testers on visual automation and
the problem engineering techniques.
Avoiding technical complexity
while building confidence
through hands-on practices.
That way testers will be ready to work
on the day one standardization process.
Establish the reusable prompt libraries.
Test templates and the best
practices for consistency.
Create a foundation for scalable
maintainable automation,
then scaling up the process.
Integrate the automated test into CACD
pipelines, expand coverage systematically
and measure impact on release
velocity and defect detection rates.
Little detail about Pace One
evaluating the codeless platforms.
There are critical selection criteria
that we need to take care of that we rest.
All of four three pieces
will be in the smooth place.
First thing is a native futures.
The tools that should support prompt
engineering capabilities and intelligent
test generation, visual workflow design.
The tool that should intuitive
builders that mirror testing.
Thought processes.
Then seamless integration
connects to Jira, CACD tools.
Test management tools now is all the
tools support this, so I think we should
be good in this self feeling capabilities
adopts automatically to UA changes
dramatically reducing maintenance product.
That's upcoming even for the code.
We were expecting the self fielding
capabilities to reduce the maintenance.
Then why not?
It is with codeless automation,
collaboration tools, version control
team, libraries, and shared resource.
These things we should tools that
support all these activities.
We need to avoid platforms
that merely hide code behind
abstractions or record extensive
scripting for advanced scenarios.
Codeless solution should enable
productivity in days, not months.
Some of the example I like to explain
about the pace one that we discussed
about a financial service QA team used.
Testing autonomous mode to auto generate
one 20 login and a dashboard test
from plain English prompts in a week.
The key takeaways, A driven test
creation saves manuscripting time.
And uncovers missed edge
cases nearly yearly.
Second example, the visual workflows that
I'm talking I was talking about earlier.
A telecom tester adopted test are
recorded to build a regression
flows by clicking through the ua.
No export editing needed.
Key takeaway visual builders mirror a
test mental model, allowing manual testers
to contribute automation immediately.
Phase two, knowledge
transfer and upskilling.
Reframe the automation concepts.
Introduce usual workflows as a natural
extension of manual test cases rather
than fundamentally different disciplines.
Map a familiar testing technology
to automation constructs.
Introduce prompt engineering basics.
Teach testers to write effective
prompts that generate accurate locators.
Assertions test logic.
Start with simple examples
before progressing to complex
scenarios here, leaving, right?
That makes us to feel better
on contributing each thing.
Hands-on practice provide a sandbox.
Environments where test can environment
safely without fear of breaking
production systems, encourage
iterative refinement and peer learning.
Now all the software system have
their own dedicated test environment.
That is the best place to practice
whatever they like, because beyond that,
there are stage UAT performance platforms.
Everything is different.
So nowadays, all application
have a standard standard test
environments to practice with.
Celebrate the year livings.
Recognize initial automation,
success, publicity to build momentum.
Showcase how quickly manual testers can
contribute meaningful automated coverage.
That makes feel better
even for other testers.
Okay.
That's something they feel, that's
something that is doable and they're
able to move forward with it.
It's a special mention about
the prompt engineering that is
a, the bridge to automation.
Prompt engineering bridges the gap
to AI powered automation letting
use testers use natural language
to articulate testing intent.
The skill they have already
hone from years of writing
test cases and bug reports.
For example, natural language test.
Navigate to checkout, verify
total matches, card complete
payment, valid card details.
It's a pure natural language,
but it's a prompt for the com.
One trigger or one command intel.
How to locate the locate
with the natural language.
Simple.
In a simple word.
Find the summit button in the login form.
Even if it is ID or class
name changes between releases.
That way it automatically detects.
Submit button, even if it
is an ID form or class form.
This will take care of it and how to
implement the assertions in the command.
Confirm error message appears
when email format is inval
and includes helpful guidance.
This is a simple language that gives
act as a command for the assess.
Navigation effective prompts reduce
complexity dramatically allowing testers
to focus on what needs testing rather
than wrestling with how to coding.
This leverages existing domain expertise
instead of requiring entirely new
technical skills because new technical
skill paper lack on the domain knowledge,
so that's sometimes it is risky.
Some of the examples I like to describe
about it reframing automation concepts.
A government QA team converted 50
manual UI flows into visual workflows
using test and chat GT prompts.
Instead of saying, click here,
validate there, tested, started
saying, verify user registration.
Email triggers after
successful form submission.
This is the natural
language Act as a command.
These plain language tips.
Autogenerated, codeless, automation
scripts, the key benefits
testers finally saw automation
as historically, not the coding.
Take prompt writing one example on it.
During a two week workshop, test
practice transforming acceptance
criteria into yay prompts, such
as log in with valid credentials.
Check the dashboard
loads within two seconds.
This is the command test.
That will evolve it.
Tools like BLE and testing
converted those into maintainable.
Automated test key benefits
builds confidence that
language is equal to logic.
Nothing to think more about it.
Once test realized their own words can
power automation, confidence skyrockets,
and your transformation takes off
Phase two, phase three.
That is very important.
Standardizing and storing
all the best practices first.
Initially, prompt libraries curate
the proven prompts for common
testing patterns like login flows.
Form validation, data verification,
enabling quick reuse and
adoption across projects.
And also standardize the
templates like test templates.
Develop standardized frameworks for
different tissue types like regression
smoke integration, ensuring consistency
while maintaining flexibility.
Quality guidelines.
Establish clear criteria for maintainable
automation, naming conventions,
documentation standards, and review
process that prevent technical data
standardization, accelerates onboarding
for new team members, improves cross
team collaboration, and protects
institutional knowledge from being lost
to turnover or organizational changes
where co-host turns into
clarity in the space.
Three.
Prompt libraries.
A state level curating created
a centralized to prompt
library inside Confluence.
It included reusable prompts
for our login payment and a data
validation across 12 microservices
when any prompt was improved.
All related issues all to updated
via are linked references, key
benefits, every tester contributes
once and every benefits.
Everyone benefits, right?
Ones test everywhere That is possible.
Tested templates.
Some of the example teams
in different business units.
Build the standard templates for
regression smoke and EAP test where
tester could drone a base, a PH, check,
health check template, customize a few
prompts and be up and running in minutes.
Key benefits, maintenance.
Consistent coverage and structure across
products while saving, setup time,
pace for scaling and
the ca CD integration.
Pretty much.
Yeah.
Scaling of the process is important.
Part of the all the.
All the four pieces like CACD
integration, embed codeless automation
into continuous integration pipelines,
configure automated test, execution
on code, commits full request and
scheduled intervals for continuous
quality feedback, progressive coverage.
Expansion.
Start with critical user journeys,
then systematically expand to edge
cases and integration scenarios.
Measure coverage growth alongside
defect reduction rates to demonstrate
the value performance, monetary.
Track key metrics, test, execution,
time ness rates, maintenance
effort and time to feedback.
Use data-driven insights to refine
the approaches and demonstrate
clear ROI to stakeholders.
Some of the example of it.
In CACD integration in one of the
insurance modernization project,
automated pursuits were triggered
directly from GitHub actions
and assured DevOps pipeline.
After every code commit within three
sprints, 80 percentage of the regressions
checks ran automatically before ing.
Key benefits QA become continuous dev
defects are caught in hours, not in
days for progress coverage expansion.
The QA team began with FI
critical business flow, like
registration, payments, and reports.
Over time.
They used prompt based test
generation to expand coverage
to 45 plus edges scenarios.
Using dashboards, they dragged
automation coverage growth
alongside defect reduction threats.
Key benefits builds measurable momentum,
expanding impact without overloading tips.
The transformation
becomes self-sustaining.
We stop treating QA as a project base.
It becomes part of the organization's DNA.
Every release, every commit, every
prompt adds intelligence to the system.
Key takeaways, empowering manual
testers, transforms manual testers into
automation enablers by executing them with
codeless platforms and AI driven tools.
Leveraging their invaluable
domain expertise.
Structured transformation, a four
piece framework, guides, organizations
through platform evolution, skill
development, standardization, and scaling.
Faster enable automation success.
A prompt for prompt engineering,
prompt engineer access the critical
bridge, allowing testers to use natural
language to define complex test logic
and accelerate automation adoption.
Enhanced to quality and efficiency.
This approach delivers faster release
cycles, higher software quality, and
employees, QA teams, ensuring they remain
central to the development process,
transforming QA into a
human centered discipline.
Human plus EA equal to smart quality.
This framework doesn't
replace human testers.
It imps them by blending codeless
automation with AI driven prompts,
testers amplify their impact without
losing the creative and critical
thinking that define real quality.
The future of QA isn't just
faster, it's more human, more
insightful and more collaborative.
Measurable benefits of the transformation.
These improvements translate
directly to accelerate release
cycles reduced to production
defects, and announced team morale.
Quality becomes shared responsibility
rather than the bottleneck.
Faster test creation codeless approaches
grammatically reduce time from
test design to execution coverage.
Increase the com democratized
automation enables broader test
coverage across futures and platforms.
Maintenance reduction,
self-healing test, and yay.
Driver updates.
Minimize ongoing overhead
tester engagement.
Manual testers report
higher job certification.
When with automation skills,
safeguarding institutional knowledge.
This is the key thing that we
were introducing this framework.
One of the greatest risk in
traditional automation transformations
is the loss of domain expertise.
When manual testers are sidelined
organizations, four feet years of
accumulative product knowledge, user
behavior, insights, and H case awareness.
So we capture the expertise.
Testers encode domain knowledge into
reusable prompts and visual workflows,
and share widely codeless platforms.
Make automation assets transparent
and accessible to entire teams.
Evolve, test, refine, and expand
automation based on production
insights and emerging scenarios.
This virtuous cycle transform
institutional knowledge from tribal
wisdom into living documentation,
re silent to team turnover and
scalable across the organization.
Some of the common concerns that
I'm like to address pretty much
everywhere in the social media, but
I like to give the answer for that.
A replace test entirely.
No.
A arguments human judgment, but cannot
replicate the critical thinking,
empathy, and contextual understanding
that experienced test is bring.
Codeless automation
makes test more valuable.
Not observ or codeless tools are
robust enough for complex scenarios.
Modern platforms handle sophisticated
workflows including EP testing, database
validation, and conditional logic prompt.
Prompt engineering unlocks advanced
capabilities without coding requirements.
What about vendor locking?
Choose platforms with export
capabilities and open integrations.
Prioritize tool that announced rather
than replace existing process, allowing
gradual adoption and flexibility.
Key takeaways, democratize
automation with Codeless platform
and follow the four PACE framework.
Leverage the prompt engineering
as a bridge skill, then amplify
the institutional knowledge.
Thank you everyone for listening
this, I hope this was very helpful
for all the organizations that who
are undergoing all the EA upgrades.
Thank you.