Today I'm going to talk about
generative AI in development
processes and dev tools for this.
My name is Bogdan Snisar, 14 years
of software engineering experience,
had different roles, software lead,
engineer, CTO, remarkable companies.
It's a Revolut, Wix,
currently partner at Overview.
It's consulting for LLM and
machine learning research.
And development of products, co
founder and CTO for RedRay Space.
Fashion search and discovery
platform for finding clothes.
Here is my links, feel free to follow.
Okay, let's start.
Before diving into the details, I want to
just highlight what actually, highlight
and group projects into several areas.
it's a taxonomy of usage of
AI for system operation and
software development lifecycle.
there is a four groups that
I find out reasonable here.
Conventional systems
with conventional SDLC.
This is where most current software lives.
Standard systems, like traditional
inventory management systems
using standard development
processes without any AI.
Some legacy.
Conventional systems
with AI augmented as DLC.
Emerging area where tools like
GitHub Copilot or something
similar, used by developers.
Could be just any project and
this is the area where I want to
concentrate further during this talk.
another area, it's actually some
products where people developed products.
Exactly, AI systems itself, yeah,
augmented systems with conventional
SDLC kind of idea of having, ML
based product in production, but
using the same as DLC as usually, and
just the combination of everything.
When we develop in AI product and
using AI tools for SDLC, as we see
as DLC, it's a part It's common for
everything and where AI development's
really interesting for me.
And I want to share my experience
from what I used and what looks
reasonable at this current moment.
What's SDLC itself?
It's a process that contains
from different phases.
It's not only coding.
It starts from requirement analysis.
Just, we need to plan what we do.
going to implement, then development
process, then testing, integration
testing of it, deployment into the
production, and maintenance of it.
This is the SDLC overall.
interesting to see what actual
researchers are trying to solve.
Where are the current
trends and what's happening?
There is an interesting paper that
Summarize, it's pretty, pretty fresh,
that summarize the whole number of
white papers and researchers that
happening across the whole internet.
They find out that majority
of things concentrated on
software development itself.
Different angles of it, I will
cover a couple of them, but there
is a developments in software
maintenance requirements,
engineering, software design.
Software management looks
like in the SDLC process.
There is a two emerging parts.
It's a coding and maintenance.
However, in the proportion, I believe
maintenance, it's a bigger because
we have a lot of already written
software that requires maintenance.
And it's interesting that problems
mostly concentrated on generation.
Not problems, but tasks that develop,
tasks that researchers try to achieve.
It's a generation of code, generation
of different things, recommendation
and some classification things.
Let's think about what EDL product or
what's actually some people envision
as a dream about software development.
It's a fully automated SDLC.
That's a set of AI agents
that's responsible for.
operating independently and
make the SDLC autonomous.
Starting from role assignments,
requirements engineering,
development, testing, deployments,
and all another things.
Currently looks like we can use
LLMs during SDLC as a helpful tools.
To reduce human errors on, or
make our work easier in some way.
moreover, there is some, of
course, rumors about autonomous
software engineer as a service.
For example, Divine or
open sourced SWE agent.
This is a set of AI agents that
can reflect software engineer.
Or they try to do that and according
to the test, it's not works so well.
in reality, this agent is
just a dream right now.
However, we see that this
chance will continue.
And who knows what happens in 2030s.
instead of trying to replicate the whole
software engineer as an agent, there's a
reasonable to have it splitted on several
functions and maybe to automate or create
helpful tools for part of the SDLC.
First thing that comes
to me, it's a planning.
There is a requirements engineering
phase where we need to gather
requirements and understand.
There's an interesting quote.
If my job was coding solutions to
problems with rigorously defined
requirements, it would be concerning.
It's about that people are pretty
bad in expressing what they
want and like developers say.
I think opposite.
LLMs are really good in understanding
of some unstructured requirements
into some structured way.
this is really good thing
for requirements engineering.
It can be used to interpret unstructured
requirements into the text specifications
or even user stories in reality.
LLMs can help requirement
engineering to highlight unknowns.
It's actually an important thing.
It can navigate to some gaps
into the requirements that
actually are not so visible.
Or it's hard to understand that these
gaps exist just because LLMs has some
generic knowledge and it could be used
to fulfill those gaps or identify them
and use this as a knowledge for follow up
questions during the requirement phase.
And another interesting point is to
classify functional and non functional
requirements from different sources.
From, for example, user reviews.
On the platforms.
It's actually interesting thing
that LLMs can be used to identify
requirements based on the user feedback.
And just create already fully refined or
halfly refined tickets that already ready
for grooming phase or planning phase.
Or at least to create them
into the developers pipeline.
So requirements engineering,
it's an interesting thing.
Another, of course, part is
the development, how LLMs
used in software development.
There is a lot of directions where
research happening right now.
It's a code completion, summarization,
search, content, code understanding,
actually pretty important program
synthesis, API recommendations, API
kind of generation, also interesting
and I guess here it's emerging.
problem exists, method
name generation, et cetera.
That's nice.
Moreover, there's only two hard things in
computer science, according to the quote,
caching validation and naming things.
And naming things already not a
big problem, according to the LLMs.
What tools I'm personally
find out interesting?
It's a replit, for example.
in reality, it's reflect of AI
agents that It tries to build
some ready to use solution.
it works only for Python and JavaScript.
Majority of LLMs are well
trained on these things.
And it's really bad actually for some rare
languages or complex languages like Rust.
What is this tool good for?
It's for prototyping for something
to show as an idea, as a concept.
It has a lot of nice features.
Standard use cases like authorization,
authentication, access to the database.
And it's time saving for fast prototyping.
And it's pretty crappy
for specific use cases.
When you try to do something non
specific, it's a bit problematic.
Cursor.
It's actually not a platform, it's a tool.
It's a kind of a VS Code fork that
had a lot of recent developments.
With code completion, assistance for
code, we can refine and ask it to do
something, to modify code at different
angles, and it's pretty nice, actually.
However, it's not so good in working
with big projects, so my current
activity, when I copy paste something
to the cursor, work with it, and then
copy paste back to the IDE or VS Code.
The reason, because I can do the same with
chat gpt, but with chat gpt I need to all
every time write some specific prompts.
Here it's a tool that likes
design to work with code.
So in some way useful.
that's mostly my main usages of
LLMs in software development.
There is a GitHub co pilot, but
I cover it in the next phase.
What about maintenance?
There is actually a
really good fit for LLMs.
Program Repair, Detection, Review,
Debugging, Bug Reproduction,
it's an interesting direction.
Hope there will be some
interesting products there.
Logging, another interesting idea
that we can automatically augment
software code with logging.
Because usually software
developers put logging randomly,
without any kind of a system.
Either it's some problematic place or
there was a bug or something like this
If the LLM can make it automatically
and put it with the understanding of the
context, it's really nice time saving
for maintenance especially BugJar, also
a nice thing Actually good fit for LLMs
another interesting thing for maintenance.
It's a search how to find Something across
the whole part of the project, it's gives
ability right now to merge and join a
lot of piece of information together and
make it as a useful information to make,
to help, to actually, to solve something.
It could be specs, Jira code, test cases,
bug reports, documentation, et cetera.
Just something can give you
the answers based on it.
There is a couple of products
that working with this.
I actually work on the GitHub Copilot
workspace, but there is Atlassian
Aroma, not used, but it's interesting
to see, Naboo AI, and GitHub Copilot.
In some way it's interesting, right
now it's mostly good for finding,
however, GitHub Copilot tries even
to give you ability to add something.
For example, U Express, you have
a specification, then you want to
add some specific details, and this
thing can generate code based on it.
This part works, let's
say, extremely well.
Okay with small classes
for specific cases.
It's a bit problematic.
It's problematic Yes, because it can
lose the context or don't understand
the whole context of the problem clearly
But the ability to merge information
really nice Another thing of maintenance,
it's working with pull requests.
Actually, this is a nice thing It's
a GitHub marketplace, CodeRabbit,
AI, it's nice, actually, it helps
to analyze code and makes pull
requests review really good.
Because sometimes it can find
what I missed, sometimes I find
what this tool missed, and this
is a good combo in reality.
Just because it's just a
real feeling of Copilot.
Another part of maintenance,
it's working with issues.
There is a, just example,
GitHub Marketplace 2, dosu bot.
It can work with issue requests
and it tries to resolve this issue
as answering to the question.
sometimes it makes a good job, in getting
answers, especially with analyzing the
code base and resolving some issues.
issues without human interaction Pretty
nice actually the idea good Another real
direction where it works for maintenance.
It's a documentation Usually
developers dislike write documentation
because they becomes outdated
pretty easily However, with LLAMPs,
I guess it's a good direction.
I just don't use any tools except chat
gpt, but it's nice thing, especially
for code comments and reflecting
readme and documentation with code.
So we just changing the code and
documentation reflects it without
our interaction, interactions, maybe
just only with some supervisory.
However, no tools here.
Another really nice thing, it's tests.
That's a really important part of SDLC,
and here the LLMs are really powerful.
And see a really big value of them.
it's a test generation, verification,
test automation, a lot of things actually.
why it's so good?
Because, edge cases, That's what
I think, and edge cases that LLM
can generate is quite bigger.
So it's really nice that it can generate
more edge cases than I usually do.
And that's really helpful in
this case, because it also helps
navigate some gaps in understanding.
Proven clear value.
Works not only for unit tests,
but works for Selenium tests.
It can be used, especially right
now, as I can understand, a visual
part, so it can be used for writing
some Selenium specifications that
gives you ability to test application
end to end and to reflect it.
Someone can be called that's TDD not
so aligned with his developments,
but I would say even It's current
capabilities, this LLM tools can at
least cover and increase test coverage
for code that make it more maintainable.
It can detect changes and
improve overall code quality.
Another good example, it's a paper
by Meta about automated unit test
improvement using large language model.
They create the pipeline that's
responsible to improve test coverage.
Just as we discussed previous slide, the
idea is that it generate test case test
cases, not the unit test, but actually try
to understand what to test to fulfill the
ideas or like specifications for tests.
Then it's doing some prep testing of it.
Then generate tests.
Runs builds, and when this build
passes, means this is already
successful number of tests.
Then post processing is
improving of code coverage.
And here we are, we have a ready
to create the pull request.
Really nice paper that says that
Meta itself internally tries to
use it, uses for different cases.
what we can summarize here.
It's interesting that for
code writing, it's not so bad.
It really helps for boilerplate
and repetitive code tasks.
it's good for changes to
end user code, actually.
When it's not about complex things.
When it's just for some small part of
it, for some class, it can be useful.
It's really nice for test and especially
for test data generation, because
sometimes it's really hard to generate
some test data or come up with it.
You need to think about it.
here is really proven value.
It's nice for assistance
in unfamiliar tasks.
It's another interesting
part when LLMs can be used.
For example, this CSS for HTML generated.
Even though that you don't know CSS,
like CSS for back end developers.
that's nice.
I tried even with ChatGPT.
It works really, it works.
After some number of iterations, I
can manage to write some specific
cases that I am not familiar with.
And it's really good for
integrated search over a data lake.
It's a really emerging thing, especially
for big projects, because In big
projects, the issue of complexity
between different parts is really big.
It's not good for changing a complex code.
Yeah.
And it's not good for refactoring.
Because refactoring requires changing
with understanding of the big context.
for maintainability of complex
legacy code, it's not so workable.
And of course it's not good for
generating a complex code or like code
for multiple cases or even multiple
classes when they're involved in this.
In a nutshell, it works great right now
for unit tests, for testing, let's say.
It works great for some prototyping.
And it's not so good for maintenance
of the legacy or big projects.
Yes, we heard about recent talks that,
for example, Amazon just save a lot of
hours for migrating from one version
Java to another, but in reality, I
think it's just minor code changes
because migrating from one version
Java to another, not so complex.
Just the language really famous
for their backward compatibility.
So this is a kind of a summary
that I see reasonable right now.
What else?
What interesting side
effects this thing creates?
One side effect I see
it's code churn by years.
There is a article that, yeah, this
article will use some extrapolation,
but in reality it says that code
churn increases after the LLM cycle.
boom started, there is a couple
of comments and, the idea is that,
practical consequence of LLMs, that, it
works well for experienced developers,
but for newcomers, it becomes a bit
problematic because, LLMs generate
some code, but you need to understand,
is it okay or not, how to modify it.
And it requires experience
to work with it.
And usually it generates something that's
not really nice, or it's nice, but partly.
and it means if we really follow
the LLMs without any supervisory,
It creates a legacy code
quicker than people usually do.
this legacy code will be problematic
for next maintainability,
the maintenance of it.
Debugging and fixing this code.
it means LLAMP is good for
generating code, but this code has
a higher effort on maintainability.
And this is a problem that
actually could be solved.
And where I guess some researchers
will try to solve because new code
generation, it's nice, but maintainability
of it, it's another important part
because, it's a really big part of
overall lifecycle of the project.
This is an interesting outcome
that I see even with my code.
that's, here is the emerging thing.
However, it's all my story right now about
the usage of LLMs and things for DevTools.
So thank you for your time and I
hope it was interesting to listen.