Hey guys.
Thanks for joining me.
This is ULA and I have around two
decades of IT experience and most
of my experience is providing
healthcare solutions in cloud and ai.
Today I would like to talk about a
solution we recently implemented for a
federal or CMS mandate where we support.
More than 2 million Medicare member,
and this mandate is about how do
we ensure our Medicare members
utilize their supplemental benefits?
They are entitled, and even though
they have enrolled and entitled,
but most of them, they don't
proactively leverage or utilize them.
The goal of this federal mandate was to.
Ensure organizations or Medicare
organizations reach proactively these
members asking them to understand
what they are entitled for, what are
pending supplemental benefits they
can utilize, and what is the duration?
So this is a mandate which was supposed
to be implemented in 2024 December.
So let's deep dive into it.
So this initiative represents a pioneering
case study in leveraging AI within the
healthcare compliance setting, a new
benchmark for efficiency and accuracy.
Its successful implementation is
POed to deliver transformative
impact, reshaping industry standards
and ensuring equitable benefit
distributions for millions of members.
So the challenge we had is the
unprecedented data demands in 2024,
as this was mandated, where our
organization is supposed to understand
more than a hundred supplemental
benefits we support today, but currently.
More than 10 different vendors,
source systems are providing the
services to the organizations.
So how do we ensure that we gather
all the information, we filter through
the different benefits as these
are complex benefits to understand
they have their own structures.
So the challenge is the data.
How do we play around with the data?
Understand different
structures for these 200 plus.
2 million plus members.
So this is the highlight of like in
this project, what we have faced,
where we had around 102 supplemental
benefit, different benefits.
Each has a distinct demand and istic
categorized and standardized, and
there are 10 different source systems.
Integration of these systems and
understanding each system to see what
benefit they provide, how they are
different from other source systems,
maybe overlap between different systems.
So that's another challenge we had.
And we had two, two plus million
members were supported using
the Medicare organizations.
Who are involved in medical as
well as PDP or pharmacy benefits.
So how the AI prompt help
to solve our project.
So our strategic eruption of
prompt engineering and AI assisted
development revolutionized the entire
development life cycle, enabling.
Unprecedented acceleration in solution
delivery while rigorously upholding
compliance and ensuring absolute
accuracy across all the operations.
Accelerated prototyping where
harnessing large language models, we
swiftly prototyped complex ll logic.
Significantly compressing development,
timely timelines and enabling
rapid adoption to evolve healthcare
data transformations optimized.
SQL generations AI driven SQL
Generation streamlined the dimensional
modeling of our health event Data
mart, ensuring superior performance,
robust scalability, and imp
impeccable data integrity for critical
analytics enhanced test scenarios.
Leverage AI leveraging AI v meticulously
crafted comprehensive test cases,
covering integrated edge cases in
benefit utilization patterns to guarantee
unpowered solution reliability and
unwavering laboratory compliance.
How the prompt engineering helped
in being in HIPAA compliant,
unlocking unparalleled security and
regulatory, our prompt engineering.
Expertise was pivotal navigating
the landscape of HIPAA compliance
through meticulously crafted prompts.
We translated dense federal
guidelines into a CRI crystal clear,
actionable technical specifications.
This accelerated the dynamic generation
of robust audit logging frameworks and
ENT data governance protocols, ensuring
steadfast utterance to federal security
standards from concept to deployment.
This AI powered method methodology
not only guaranteed unwavering
patient data protection, but also
significantly enhanced operations
agility and drastically mitigated.
Compliance risks solidify our,
solidifying our commitment to secure
responsible AI innovation in healthcare.
So this is a high level like
technical architecture or basically
the background on, apart from
the ai, what AWS services we use.
We used EC2 instances and Lambda.
These are serverless and scalable
computing resources to efficiently
process vast data sets, ensuring
rapid data transformation and seamless
integration for complex works.
We leveraged s St S3 storage to
establish a highly secure compliant
data lake for comprehensive storage
of raw and processed healthcare
information optimized for accessibility,
integrity, and long-term retention.
RDS was leveraged, which is a highly
reliable and high performance relational
database to manage critical structured
benefits and member data, enabling
accurate reporting and insightful
analytics for informed decision
making beyond just a federal mandate.
Our AWS based AI solution delivered.
Unmatched scalability, iron Cloud,
security, and unwavering reliability.
Established in the Future Proof
Foundation for critical data
operations and driving innovations
in patient care and compliance.
This particular solutions set a benchmark
being on percent or 10% on time.
The success of this delivery
across the industry demonstrated
a new paradigm for operational
rigor, accountability, inspiring
others to elevate their standards.
Furthermore, this Unpowered track
record grant us strategic or
significant computer advantage.
Opening doors for strategic partnership
and fostering sustained growth in
rapidly evolving healthcare landscape.
Unleashing the power of prompt
engineering, how prompt engineering
help in accelerated development cycles.
Achieved a remarkable 40% reduction
in overall development time by
strategically implementing advanced
prompt engineering techniques.
Fostering agile and highly efficient
project execution, ensure a proper
hundred percent on time delivery rate
for all federal reporting requirement,
demonstrating our capability to streamline
complex compliance process through
innovative, prompt driven automation.
Our prompt engineering framework
empowered our team to pivot from
tedious repeated coding task to a
high value strategic initiative.
This not only dramatically accelerated our
delivery timelines, but also solidified
our commitment to maintain the regard
risk quality standards our client expects
transforming compliance
into strategic advantage.
Unified Data Foundation where
streamlined the operations and
ensure the data integrated by
establishing a single authority
source of truth, eliminating redundant
processing, and fostering accuracy.
This helped in proactive member
engagement, engagement and also
future regulatory framework and in
empowering strategic decisions where.
Leveraging the newly enriched compliance
data to provide a critical insights,
empowering leaders to optimize benefits
offerings, refined planning, and drive
superior outcomes across the organization.
Unlocking AI potentials critical
in insights from our journey.
So I would like to share how AI has
helped in our journey and what can help
others mastering prompt engineering.
Tailored for healthcare AI crafting
prompts that expertly blend deep
healthcare domain knowledge with
precise technical specifications
proved essential, dramatically
accelerating the generation of accurate,
robust, and immediately usable code.
Achieving around cloud security
and stringent HIPAA compliance
for AI generated code demanded the
meticulous iterate to refinement,
transforming raw output into the
production ready, regulatory approved
solutions, LLM as a strategic
connectors unifying diverse teams.
The LLM emerged as a powerful catalyst.
Seamless bridging communication
divides between clinical experts.
Technical developers and
business strategies fostering
unprecedented alignment and
accelerating project execution.
Strategic prompt engineering,
ensuring compliance healthcare, ai,
applying AI responsibilities in highly
regulated healthcare environments.
Integrate HIPAA and industry specific
regulation directly into prompt design,
leverage precise legal and clinical
terminology for clarity and accuracy.
Demand comprehensive adult audit
trails and documentation for
traceability and accountability.
Rigorously validate AI outputs
against established security
framework like NIST and ISO.
Continuously refined prompts with
clinical and legal experts to ensure
patient safety and regulatory adherence.
So this is a flow where, how
the transformative AI helped our
project or any generic project.
So in the discovery phase.
How it helped in the design
phase, what we utilize.
So in the discovery phase, harnessing
AI powered LLMs to de deeply analyze
the existing risk systems, revealing
critical integration points and hidden
dependencies to establish a robust
architectural foundation employee to
rapidly generate in issue architecture.
Options in implementation,
accelerate deployment.
Cycles by AI driven prototyping.
Prototyping of ETL pipelines and
complex data transformations.
Ensuring efficient, reliable deployment,
leverage AI to ultimately generate
comprehensive test scenarios, meticulously
covering all edge cases to guarantee
system stability and performance.
Automate the generation of precise
technical document and compliance report.
Significantly reducing manual effort
and ensuring audit readiness and clarity
beyond compliance, driving value.
Through strategic transformation, we
didn't just meet a federal mandate.
We leverage it as a catalyst to
unlock significant value, dramatically
boosting member engagement and achieving
unparalleled operational efficiency.
Unlocking tomorrow's health,
AI's transformative power.
We saw beyond many regulatory compliance
harnessing advanced AI to not only
meet the mandate, but fundamentally
fundamental redefine how we deliver care.
This isn't just a technology, it's about
pioneering a smarter, more empathetic.
Healthcare experience for every member.
This initiative also created
a broader impact on healthcare
innovation, fostering culture of
continuous implement and technological
advancement across the organization.
Furthermore, we established a
scalable framework ready for future AI
implementations, ensuring our ability
to adopt and lead in the evolving
landscape of medical technology.
I would like to call some key
takeaways from our implementation,
how prompt engineering in AI help
drive rapid innovation, leveraging
prompt engineering slash development
cycles up to 40%, and helped in
high quality solutions and meeting.
Project timelines or
federal mandate on time.
Master regulatory challenges utilize AI
driven development to seamless translate
regulatory requirements into robust
cutting edge technical implementations.
Unlock new growth revenues by
redefining compliance from a burden
to a strategic asset Fostering.
Deeper member engagement and
significant operational advancement.
Equip yourself with advanced prompt
engineering strategies designed
for regulated industries, ensuring
unparalleled security, precision, and
adherence to all compliance standards
for a future ready healthcare system.
I hope this was helpful.
Thank you.