Hello all and good afternoon.
My name is Al. I work for Gensar
Technologies as a delivery manager at this
conference of Prompt Engineering 2025.
We are going to share our experiences
on the supply chain residency model,
what we faced during the pandemic.
In this particular session, we are gonna
talk about some key challenges, what
automation was done, how it was done.
What are the key takeaways?
So let's dive in.
We all know that the COVID-19
pandemic gave us a very different
world what we are hearing today.
All those unprecedented disruptions made
it very difficult to operate the way it
was over the regular non activities which
were physically allowed were restricted.
Restrictions, workforce
limitations and everything
became very difficult to manage.
That was a wake up call to
initiate a digital transformation.
When I say digital transform
transformation, I'm talking about how do
we make sure that the manual processes
and physical dependencies are managed in
such a way that you get an accelerated
digital experience, all those activities.
Are required for the survival in
this crisis world, and that basically
emerges you as a stronger, more
resilient partner in the industry.
Let's see.
What are the things that
we took as action today?
In this journey, we are gonna talk
about some of the crisis management,
some automation solutions, the
resiliency framework that we built.
How the residency framework helped
us in the digital acceleration and as
part of the digital acceleration, what
strategic advantages were achieved.
We also examined the lessons from Gensa
technology, supply chain transformation,
and provide some actionable takeaways
for strengthening the resilience
against future disrupts, while
unlocking sustained efficiency gains.
Looking at the deep vulner.
The pandemic exposed to us.
First of all, what used to work in
the office environment is disrupted.
That is not going to work.
All those paper based order processing,
email coordinations, spreadsheet
tracking, that is a bottleneck
when it comes to remote working.
The physical presence requirements in
terms of field operations, equipment
installation, partner training,
all those because of the lockdown.
Were not able to process.
It was everything was at fault.
At the same time, in terms of supply
chain, inventory is the key, as you
all know, inventory had a limited
visibility and limited visibility,
meaning delayed information leads to
delayed decisions, which basically
amplifies the impact of this disruptions.
And then coming to our infrastructure,
which is the networking piece.
The centralized and inflexible
network basically means it's
a single point of failure.
If one note goes down, your
environment is collapsed.
There was no plan B because Plan
A always worked, but that was
not the case during the pandemic.
So what is the operation lifeline
of Partners and Field Automation?
Let's take a look at that.
Will build the threat here.
So patent field automation emerge
as an essential capability for
organizations navigating the pandemic.
Other than doing incremental
improvements, those technologies
provided transformation capabilities
that enable business continuity.
Under the extraordinary constraints.
Through automation of order
processing, digital partner
enablement and remote field operations
organizations maintain a critical
function while competitors struggle.
At Gensar, we implemented these
technologies strategies and have shown
that how the world has changed and how it
is important to recover from the crisis.
In terms of taking a top bottom
approach, we basically divided
the work in three areas.
First is order capture second processing.
Third is fulfillment.
So automated intake from the
partners through API integration
eliminated manual data entry.
That was the first step that was taken.
Second is about processing and
validation of the particular order
in our new middleware system, which
had checked the inventory, checked
the routing options, everything was
done without a human intervention.
And third, and lastly is the fulfillment.
Which is basically about triggering
the shipping, updating the systems
in terms of if the shipment has
received or not, and receiving and
creating notifications in real time.
And as an impact, the transition
latency dropped dramatically.
Orders that used to take days
previously now are taking hours.
Remote teams maintain full
operational capability without
physical presence in the office.
That enabled continuity.
When lockdown was actually in focus,
going further down, we had also
enabled direct partner equipment
shipping and digital tracking.
That means we have real-time visibility.
We have streamline distribution
and automated notifications.
In terms of real time visibility,
GPS and IOT sensors were used
extensively to eliminate any
uncertainty during the shipping status.
Enabling proactive exception management
in terms of distribution rather than
going, rather than taking the equipment
and shipping it to the centralized
warehouse, we bypass that and directly
ship to the customer's partners location.
That basically accelerated
the delivery times.
And in terms of tracking.
The automated notifications were
enabled in terms of every milestone in
terms of dispatch, transit shipment,
and that was all done through emails.
This particular approach transformed
distribution from liability
into a competitive advantage.
Partner received equipment faster
with full transparency, while internal
team focused on strategy activities
rather than tracking shipments only.
Going into remote configuration,
virtual training to add up to
what we did in the past, right?
In terms of order management
validation, milestone, and
creating the real time tracking.
We also enabled a remote configuration
and virtual training platforms.
It was added up in terms of giving
a more further partner satisfaction.
Remote configuration was enabled in such
a way that technicians could remotely
configure equipment, eliminate Tinder
travel needs automated configuration
templates, ensure consistency and
digital audits had a compliance
documentation without any paperwork.
To enhance that further, we created
a virtual training platforms,
which had interactive modules
enabling partner training.
On demand access and automated
assessment, which was basically
checking the competency and identify
any knowledge gaps as a business.
Impact operations.
Team operations that previously
require expensive site visit
that was not required anymore.
Part development, accelerated expanding
capacity while travel budgets were
still frozen because of the pandemic.
The shift to remote operations
became permanent delivering sustained
cost savings beyond the crisis.
Coming to the resilient design framework,
building for the Insanity, we took
a modular architecture approach.
We broke it down.
The architecture has to be modular
in such a way that component based
system allowed a rapid configuration
and modular replacement, significantly
reducing irr irrigated times.
We had automated monitoring installed.
That way we can check the real time
health of the systems creating any issues.
In addition to that, there were
simulation testing scenarios created
to make sure that everything is running
as robust during the crisis management.
And to back up, we had a comprehensive
documentation in place to have
insured, which had rapid onboarding.
Proper knowledge transfer
continuity management during
the staff ordinary times.
As a result, we could see that if
you look at the chart from fully
automated to traditional approaches,
operation organizations, which
were working in the automated mode,
can see a 15 times faster recovery
rate in terms of traditional peers.
And that is what we achieved
during this automation phase.
So the key insight is that
recovery speed directly correlated
with the digital maturity.
Automation provided the agility
needed to pivot the operations quickly
while manual processes had frictions.
So this was the recovery rate that we
see and that had augmented everything
in terms of how we move from manual
processes to automated processes.
Now how do we get into a digital
adoption mode and act as an accelerator?
So the digital piece is done, but now
it needs to be adapted by partners
and also the vendor management.
So there was an adoption speed that
was put into place, activities that
used to take years, but done in months.
We had remote monitoring
to for organizations, which
enabled real time monitoring.
We did investment in terms of post
pandemic budget ion for supply chain
automation compared to pre COVID
levels, and as we know that the
ion era is going to be sustained.
So we, there was a need for,
to have a permanent operational
improvement done on all these areas.
So what are the key capabilities
for long-term efficiency?
The first, as I mentioned,
remote monitoring.
Without a physical presence,
how do I make sure that my
equipment's health is maintained?
There is a self-healing into place.
How does the supply chain status keeps,
continues to operate functionally?
And I get the statuses of those supply
chain module as and when we move
the equipment from one the store.
Second is about real time
inventory visibility.
Automated tracking across the
entire supply chain, enabling
data driven decisions, and
reducing the stockouts by 60%.
That's a big number in terms of,
because when it comes to supply
chain, inventory is your key.
If you run out of stock, that means
your entire pipeline is stuck, and we
want to make sure that never happens.
Contactless fulfillment.
Automated, picking, shipping,
packing, all those key things are
done, contracted contactless because
the systems are, put 'em in such
a way that they work seamlessly.
What are the practical approaches
that we took during the automation?
So embedding automation
into a supply chain.
We started with a pain point.
We identified the high friction processes
causing the most operational pain.
That was the first thing
on the drawing board.
From there, we understood that
we have to make sure that our
architecture is modular in nature.
That way whenever changes have
to be done, they are rapid,
faster, and easier to maintain.
After the modulation of the
infrastructure, we worked towards the
integration of the partner ecosystem.
We want to make sure that
the two residency requires.
Coordination across the entire supply
chain network, including partners
ecosystem and event ecosystem.
We invested in training, making sure
that everybody understands what are
the areas that needs to be done to
for effective supply chain management.
And at the last we did test and iterate.
Regular solution testing
varies residency, so continuous
improvement ensures systems evolve.
While changing needs.
So these approaches aren't just
theoretical, they are practical
lessons from the organization that
successfully navigated the pandemic.
So basically you start small, prove a
value, and then scale systematically,
as in when you move towards your goal.
What are the strategic advantages
and why digital maturity matters?
As we know that the enhanced agility
basically means that your rapid
response to market change allowing
organizations to quickly pivot operations,
reconfigure supply networks, and
uncertainty becomes an opportunity.
Second is our partner enablement.
Automated tools and real time
collaboration strengths, ecosystem
relationship partners amplify
capacity without signifying
significant cost increase.
Third and during competitive advantage,
automation provides permanent
benefits, lower cost, faster cycles,
and superior customer experience.
This creates a sustainable
market differentiation.
Coming to the final key takeaways, what
are what we did in terms of building
a resilient supply chain network?
So automation is non-negotiable.
In today's world of ai, that
is how it's going to be.
And pandemic proved that the manual
processes are just not going to sustain.
Partners and field automation are
an option, but they are essential
capabilities for the modern supply chain.
Operating in uncertain environments,
agency requires in additional design.
It this particular activity did not
just happen over as an accident.
They implement the
resolution design framework.
You have to have a architecture approach,
automated monitoring, simulation,
testing, complex documentation, so
all were deliberate actions for the
choices of the architecture that we
took that gave us a digital maturity
and drive competition advantage.
Organizations with mature automation
capabilities recover 15 times faster.
We know that based on the
chart, at the same time, the
stockout options was 60% less.
That this is a big number that gives
digital maturity, agility, and enables
partner ecosystems and delivers
sustained efficiency beyond the crisis.
And so final point is start now and you
have to build incrementally, begin with
a high impact pain point, build modular.
Integrate partners, test them regularly
because next disruptions is inevitable.
But the question is,
are you ready for that?
That's my last slide.
Thank you so much for this opportunity
in terms of giving me into this
session and I had a great time.
Hope you had some great,
lovely, thank you so much.