Hello everyone.
I'm Nagarjuna Malladi.
And today we are exploring how Site
Reliability Engineering or SRE has became
a transformative force in enhancing
system reliability across industries.
Developed by Google, SRE began as
a framework for balancing system
operations and software engineering.
Aiming to maintain system
reliability and manage scalability.
Today, as nearly Every industry is
undergoing a digital transformation
from retail to healthcare.
SRE principles have moved beyond
tech companies to become critical for
managing reliability and efficiency in
sectors where even minor disruptions
can have substantial impacts.
By undergoing these principles,
industries can improve both user
satisfaction and operational resilience.
Let's go to our table of content.
We'll review a little bit, introduction
of site reliability engineering.
And then, go through a couple of,
industries, e commerce, financial,
health industry, gaming industry,
and cross industry applications
like telecommunication, media, and
entertainment, and transportation.
And we go through key
performance metrics and industry
benchmarks, and then we conclude.
Let's go to introduction.
SRE stands for site reliability
engineering, and it's essential, the
application of software engineering
to infrastructure and operations.
Google pioneered this approach
to ensure it's complex systems
were available and scalable.
Today, as digital systems became
the backbone of multiple industries,
SRE helps to manage and optimize.
These infrastructures, for example,
in healthcare, reliability translates
to continuous access to patient data.
In e commerce, it ensures
websites stay fast and responsive
even under high traffic.
With SRE, industries can handle these
critical demands systematically.
Let's go to the core principles of SRE.
SRE's three main principles, or I
can tell pillars, are reliability,
scalability, and security.
Each serving a distinct but overlapping
role in ensuring smooth operations.
Reliability is about system
uptime and availability.
Ensuring users can access
services without interruption.
Scalability.
On the other hand, means the system
can handle increased load seamlessly,
which is essential during times like
Black Friday in retail or during the
trading peaks in finance security.
The third principle is crucial for data
production and compilers, particularly
in highly regulated industries like
healthcare and financial service.
Where a breach could mean not only loss
of trust, but also regulatory penalties.
Examples.
Reliability.
Redundant infrastructure in cloud systems
that automatically redirects traffic to
functioning servers during an outage.
Scalability, load balancers that
distribute traffic efficiently,
allowing systems to add or reduce
servers in response to demand.
Security, encrypted data
flows that protects sensitive
information from unauthorized
access and meet legal requirements.
Let's go to, let's analyze
a couple of industries.
In this presentation, I covered a
couple of industries, how SRE is used, e
commerce, financial service, healthcare,
gaming, telecommunications, media and
entertainment, and transportation.
Each industry brings unique challenges.
E commerce is vulnerable
to sudden traffic spikes.
Healthcare needs absolute data privacy
and gaming demands ultra low latency.
At these industries share a common
need for reliable, secure, and
scalable systems that can handle
industry specific challenges.
Today's discussion will focus on And each
sector's distinct needs and explore how
SRE principles are tailored to meet them.
Let's see the unique
requirements by the industry.
Each industry requirements are shaped
by the specific demands and expectations
of its users and regulatory environment.
For example, in the e commerce.
Every millisecond counts.
And studies show that a one second delay
can reduce conversions by seven percent.
Financial services operate under
rigorous standards such as PCI DSS
for card transactions as need systems
with guaranteed uptime in healthcare
strict compiling standards like HIPAA
mandate security and logging and
downtime could endanger patient safety.
This is very critical.
Understanding these needs allows SRE
to adapt its principles effectively,
ensuring systems meet the unique
requirements of each industry.
All industries prioritize the reliability
and security of their digital operations,
although implementation varies based on
specific needs and regulatory standards.
E commerce face two primary challenges,
maintaining the site performance under
high demand and reducing the cart
aboundment due to slow paged loads.
SRE solutions like auto scaling enable e
commerce platforms to automatically add
or remove resources as traffic fluctuates,
while CDN content delivery networks.
speed up the content delivery by
bringing data closer to the users.
Improving the load times.
Kavos engineering is also increasingly
common by simulating potential failures.
It tests system resilience.
Together, the solutions help e
commerce sites stay fast and reliable.
Increasing user engagement and revenue.
Let's go to some examples.
Autoscaling.
Automatically increasing server
resources during the flash sales.
CDNS.
Enhances website speed by distributing
content and balancing traffic loads.
As it's regional data centers
to speed up the side load
times for international users.
Kavos engineering, testing what would
happen if a server fails during the peak
shopping hours and impact, optimized
load times, reduced cot abatement
and enhanced user experience lead
to increased revenue and obviously,
it's a customer satisfaction.
Let's go to
Yeah challenges of sre solutions
challenges and sre solutions in
financial services have stringent
compilance requirements such as GDPR
in Europe and PCI DSS for payment
processing, making SRE solutions crucial.
Data encryption and access controls
secure sensitive transactions, while
continuous monitoring identifies
potential threats in real time.
Disaster recovery plans are Very critical.
Establishing backup systems
that can immediately take over
if a primary system fails.
By implementing these SRE practices,
financial services reduce downtime
risks and maintain regulatory
compellence, protecting both customer
trust and financial stability.
Let's dive into a couple of examples.
Data encryption.
Encrypting user data end to
prevent unauthorized access.
Continuous monitoring, using monitoring
systems that immediately flag suspicious
activity, reducing fraud risks.
Disaster recovery, regularly testing
backup systems to ensure they function
seamlessly in the event of failure.
Impact.
Reduce downtime, enhance security,
and maintain regulatory compliance.
Help prevent financial
and reputational loss.
Let's go through the healthcare.
In healthcare, SRE solutions are crucial
to secure patient data and provide
uninterrupted access to critical records.
End to end encryption safeguards
sensitive data while redundant systems
keep electronic health records, EHRs,
accessible even if primary system fails.
Compliance management for HIPAA in the U.
S.
include secure data sharing
mechanism and logging all across,
all access to sensitive information.
The solutions enable healthcare providers
to offer consistent, secure patient care
as data privacy and system availability
are literally matters of life and death.
And a lot of healthcare
companies, they want, almost 99.
9 percent uptime, for
their testing trials.
Also, let's go with a couple of examples,
redundant systems, backup systems in place
that keep patient records accessible.
For example, if primary system
goes down, HIPAA compilers.
Secure mechanisms to share patient
data between doctors while logging all
access for the, for accountability.
Real time replication, ensuring patient
data is up to date across multiple systems
to prevent errors in critical situations.
Let's go some challenges
and SRE solutions in gaming.
Online gaming demands.
Ultra low latency for smooth.
Real time gaming experience, especially
during events or game launches.
Network optimization and edge
computing help minimize latency by
processing data close to the user.
Auto scaling infrastructure
accommodates Some spikes in traffic
while continuous monitoring identifies
security threats, like DDoS attacks.
By implementing these practices,
gaming companies provide players
with a responsive, secure
experience that keeps them engaged.
Let's go to a couple of examples.
Network optimization.
Reducing lag by optimizing data
flow between servers and users.
Edge computing.
Bringing game data processing
closer to players, especially
for real time multiplayer games.
Continuous monitoring.
Monitoring for DDoS attacks and other
threats that can interrupt gameplay.
Low latency, what's impact?
Low latency and secure scaling
games, environment, keep players
engaged and protect both player,
both data and gameplay quality.
Let's go with, cross industry
applications, telecom,
media, and transportation.
In telecommunications, SRE practices
optimize network reliability and
automate network provisioning, while
self healing protocols address outages
swiftly to improve customer experience,
media and entertainment rely on
CDNS, and streaming optimizations
to deliver high quality content.
Transportation benefits from predictive
maintenance and real time tracking.
Improving efficiency
and minimizing delays.
Each of these sectors uses SRE to
maintain operational reliability,
underscoring SRE's impact.
Adaptability and value.
Let's dive into some examples.
Telecom.
Self healing.
Automatically rerouting traffic
during outages to prevent call drops.
And, streaming optimization,
enhancing video quality across devices
by optimizing content delivery.
Mainly it focuses on high quality
content delivery using CDNs,
optimizing streaming protocols and
supporting device compatibility
for enhanced user experience.
Transportation SRE facilitates route
optimization, real time tracking and
predictive maintenance, which are
critical for efficient transportation
and infrastructure reliability.
It uses IoT data to predict when vehicles
need service, minimizing the downtime.
Let's go to a couple of metrics
for success by industry.
Each industry has metrics
that measure SRE success.
For e commerce, page load times under
three seconds are crucial to prevent
a 40 percent user abatement rate.
Financial service requires 99.
99 percent of time as mandated
by entities like the FCA in UK.
In gaming, latency needs to
be under 100 milliseconds to
maintain player engagement.
For transportation, metrics include
optimized ride sharing routes and reduced
wait times through predictive maintenance,
while media and entertainment focus on
high streaming quality to reduce churn.
Let's go to a couple of examples.
E commerce.
Targeting load times to reduce
aboundment and boost conversion.
Finance.
Achieving near perfect uptime to meet
regulatory requirements and build trust.
Gaming.
Minimizing latency to prevent
users from leaving the platform.
Let's conclude in conclusion.
In conclusion, SRA principles
offer adaptable powerful solutions
across diverse industries,
ensuring reliability, security, and
scalability As we, we have seen.
SRE adapt to sector specific challenges,
whether supporting real time transactions
in finance or ensuring healthcare
compliance, emerging trends, including
automation and predictive analysis, will
continue to advance SRE practices, making
systems proactive and self healing.
Embracing SRE principles is
essential for organizations.
To gain a competitive edge, secure data,
and maintain operational resilience.
As digital transformation continues
to accelerate, the role of SRE
will become more and more pivotal.
Emerging trends suggest a move towards
even greater automation, predictive
analysis, and machine learning to
support SRE efforts, making systems
more proactive and self healing.
For organizations across all sectors,
embracing SRE principles will be
essential for maintaining SRE.
competitive advantage by reducing
downtime, securing data, and
delivering seamless user experiences.
Looking to the future, SRE will remain
a cornerstone of a reliable digital
operations, shaping a way industries
handle the complexities of a motor
infrastructure and the user demands.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time, for
listening, the presentation and
thank you for your attention.
I hope this session has provided a
clear view of how SRE practices enhance
reliability across different industries.
I would be happy to discuss further
or answer any questions you have.
This enhanced script adds depth and
provides relevant examples To help
convey each concept effectively Let me
know if you would Like to meet me or you
know if you have any further questions,
you know I have we can meet in my
linkedin or You know any social media
platforms and then we can discuss more
about sre concepts Thank you very much