Hi there, folks.
Welcome to my little presentation
on prompt engineering.
My name is Charlie Reynolds.
I'm a fractional CTO.
a big fan of AI, and very
keen on prompt engineering.
So let's dive into a little presentation
just by way of introduction then.
So just like in life,
you get what you ask for.
So if you ask good questions,
you'll get good answers.
And if you don't, then the saying follows.
and for me, I think asking
clear and imaginative questions
leads to some interesting
results and some useful results.
And that unlocks a lot of
good capability from AI.
There's also, beyond that,
you've also got AI orchestration,
which you're going to touch on.
And that's where you use multiple
specialized AIs to work together.
to do various jobs in concert.
this is a quote that I
quite like by Einstein.
imagination is more
important than knowledge.
there's a little bit more context to
this, but I think, the gist of it for
what we're looking at right now is
that by not just giving very specific
instructions where you're looking for
very specific results, but using a
little bit of creativity can actually
get you to some innovative outcomes.
so with artificial intelligence, I
think this is now particularly poignant.
so the technical knowledge and skills
are obviously crucial in order to
build AI, and evolve it and so forth.
But I think a little bit
of human, imagination and
ingenuity can go a long way.
so when it comes to prompt
engineering, asking the right
questions in the right way.
we'll get you to some very useful
and valuable outcomes on, as I say,
a bit of imagination goes a long way.
in terms of what we mean by prompt
engineering, in simple terms, it's
about designing effective instructions
that get you effective results.
so asking the right questions,
thereby unlocking value.
and, it supports effective interaction.
So in terms of some key concepts,
as I say, it's not just about
the technical skill set.
It's also about some creativity
as well as precision.
and rather than just talking to AI
about what we already know about,
It's also asking ourselves, to use our
imagination, look at what is possible.
and that therefore means that by the
two of you combining those skills of
using human ingenuity with the vast
amounts of knowledge that AI can
tap into, you can get to some new
possibilities and new innovations.
So by way of examples, then, instead of
asking AI very short, simple questions
like what's the weather, which is
obviously very vague, you should be much
more specific and ask questions along
the lines of, what's the weather in Paris
next Tuesday morning for my business trip?
and you'll get a vastly
different response.
quite often, there'll be a little, there
can often be a bit of embellishment
as well, where you'll find that,
by adding in little details about
the nature of what you're doing and
why you're doing it and so forth.
the AI can take those cues and actually
give you more than you bargained for.
it might not just tell you what the
weather's doing, it might also tell
you that, As it's a business trip
in Paris, actually these are some
good activities considering what
the weather's likely to be doing.
Or again, you can feed that
in to refine your prompt.
and again, that's just a very short,
simple example, but you get into, you
can get into much more complex examples.
with the kind of work that I
do, for example, I often find
that using several different AIs
together can be very effective.
so you can get much more complex tasks.
and that's where what's called
AI orchestration comes into play,
where you can find specialized
AIs that you can string together.
we'll dig into some examples
of that in a moment.
so things like a system
that generates, text.
So chat GPT is prime example of that.
another that would analyze
sentiment and then another that
can actually summarize the results.
By putting different prompts into each
of those and taking the results from
each of those and feeding them into
the next AI, you can actually get to
quite a powerful solution that way.
How does that work then?
How are we crafting effective prompts?
there are many different ways to do
this, and this is just my take on it.
there are some, tried and tested
methodologies out there and some,
mnemonics that you all may be familiar
with, but I'm coming at it from
the angle of using your imagination
and striving for innovation.
There's three parts that I've used in
this, which is clarity and imagination.
clarity is key.
Absolutely.
But using imagination can
get you a long way as well.
so if you think of yourself
like a director and you're
guiding a bunch of actors.
And you're envisioning and,
imagining the final performance
and then crafting prompts that
lead the AI in that direction.
so again, if we look at AI used for
content generation, for example, instead
of saying generate an article about AI,
you might say something more write a 500
word article on AI's impact on healthcare
using statistics from the last five years.
And that is obviously much more specific.
the next part is context
and orchestration.
as I say, in more complex tasks,
you might be using multiple AIs that
have each got their specialisms.
and you have to have real clarity around
what it is you're trying to do and
exactly what it is that you're expecting
from each of those AIs, for example,
and therefore they will fit together
neatly and give you what you need.
as I much mentioned earlier, you can
have, an AI that can provide summaries
of articles so you can take vast
amounts of information and knowledge,
and turn those into succinct summaries.
you could then use another AI that
is more specialized around things
like bias, and then you could pass
that over to another AI that can
actually pull all that together.
So having taken a vast
amount of knowledge.
summarized it, checked it for bias,
and then converted it into a final
output, which is, free from bias.
and you would use different
prompts for each of those in
order to get to that outcome.
and then lastly, iteration and refinement.
just as many of you are probably used
to in the world of software development.
iteration is key.
and each time that you put that prompt
through and refine it, then you'll
get closer to the desired output.
So again, an example around that
could be that you're using a, chat
bot in the customer service context.
And again, you've got, chatbots that
will happily interact with customers,
but at the same time, you'll have
a much more specialized AI that is
finely tuned for sentiment analysis,
and we'll be looking to see if that
customer is getting frustrated.
And therefore, in some cases, it might
decide that actually this is where
human intervention would be optimal.
so you orchestrate those models together
so that you have, much more, enjoyable
experience for the customer and you
have a much slicker AI solution.
So
why is prompt engineering important?
why does it matter?
Given that AI is going through
this massive growth spurt, and
it's now becoming quite ubiquitous.
the ability to ask the right questions
is becoming more and more important.
So prompt engineering enables
us to transform AI from a
simple tool into a collaborator.
and again, this is where I go back
to the idea that Einstein put forward
around imagination being so important.
and, it's not just about what the A.
I can do, but it's about what
we can imagine it doing, in
fields like health care, finance,
customer service and many others.
prompt engineering, as we've touched
on briefly, allows us to orchestrate
many different systems together with
that AI capability, and therefore
you get seamless and intelligent
workflows off the back of that.
in healthcare, for example, AI systems
can be used to orchestrate patient data,
predict outcomes and assist in diagnoses.
and obviously the success of those systems
depends on how well they're guided with
the prompts, but also, it's critical
that they've got high quality data.
being fed into them as well.
So moving on to conclusions.
as I say, asking AI about things that
we already know about isn't really
getting the best value out of it.
it's challenging yourself and
challenging the AI to think differently.
and to explore new possibilities, and
asking the right question in the right
way, and that therefore opens doors,
orchestrates systems together harmoniously
and leads to innovative solutions.
what I would say is the next time you
interact with AI, don't just ask it for
an answer, imagine the possibilities.
asking the right questions and thinking
about how you might orchestrate different
AI models together to create something
greater than the sum of its parts.
you could even ask AI to help you
with refining those prompts, and
say, how can I make this better?
what's suboptimal about this?
give me a crash course in
how to refine my prompts.
there are many possibilities,
around how you can interact.
With the AI, which will enhance your
prompts, but it will also enrich the
AI and it becomes a virtuous circle.
So that's all for me.
It's just a short, sharp
taste of presentation.
there are many different levels
and aspects to this, but I just
wanted to provide a bit of challenge
around using your imagination.
that's all for me, Charlie
Reynolds of CTR Consulting.
and I hope that I will speak to
some of you in the near future.
Thank you.
Take care.
Bye bye.