Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, prompt
Engineering, another session.
My name is Jamis Akia.
I'm a solution architect at Snowflake.
Today I'm going to cover the topic for
prompt engineering for data engineering
how we can unlock the natural language
access to cloud data platform.
I have been working in data and
analytics field for almost 12 years now.
I have lots of experience working
with lots of different clients on
different data engineering projects.
Also lots of implementation on
cloud, on-prem, cloud data platform.
Also have done lots of migrations.
From on-prem to cloud data
platform and then worked with all
across different domains also.
And I can definitely see here the
impact of how the prompt engineering
can play in data engineering.
So to start with how the evaluation
of data access was and now how
it's getting evolved over the time.
Data engineering is always, and
as of now also is more of attack.
We consider that we need a people,
data engineers or data developers
to do some of these things.
They have to either write a very
complex SQL views or they have to create
lots of different store procedures.
They also have to do lots of scripting
and then also have to manually manage lots
of pipelines that are coming from source.
And then we are transforming the data.
And then also we have to do lots
of monitoring, lots of security
concerns, lots of data governance.
So all of that goes into
the traditional approach.
What we are seeing now with LRM
that there will be a revolution
of this data engineering by using
large language models, which will
change the paradigm using lots of
different things that can be enabled.
And reduce some of the time
complexity and make it easy for
everyone to use and implement data
engineering and data ecosystem
less technical trainings required.
And we can also de democratize the data
across the enterprise very quickly.
So LLMs are definitely beyond chatbots.
When initially when we
heard about chat, GPT.
Everyone was like, okay, it looks
like this is what LLM looks like.
If you prompt for something,
either you get a output.
So you converse con, like it's a
conversational AI where you can talk
with the chat bots and you can get
your answers, question questions
answered, stuff like that very quickly.
And also you can, content generation
is a very big application right
now where everyone is using that.
There is so many different things you
can do with chat, GPT and all the other
tools that are coming in the market.
But there is a potential for LLMs in data
engineering for making our transformations
on how we consume our data from cloud data
platform and LLM can definitely breach
some gap between the business users and
the technical data infrastructure that
we always face, challenge with how fast
we can turn around things, how fast the
data can be accessible for everyone.
So some of the applications
that we can definitely think of.
With LLMs in data engineering
number one is query generation.
We can definitely convert the natural
language, respond to get a optimized sql.
This can be done on a cloud data
platform like Snowflake using some of
the technologies that they are offering
already, like Cortex Analyst, snowflake
Intelligence, and we can definitely see
some of the other companies are also using
some of this LLM data engineering tools.
Like E-T-L-E-L-T, tools like DBT is also
already using that pipeline orchestration,
triggering workflows through conversation.
I want to run something that was
run last night just to fix something
that is updated in the source side.
I can just say run the last run last
night runs and it'll run for you.
And that's one of the advantage you can
take from the LLM Prompt engineering.
And definitely real time analytics.
I want to find something about my data.
I want to learn about where the
sales are, high orders are getting
less, what region is impacted,
if I have any company wide issue.
Those are the things I
can definitely talk to.
Data on the fly with my real time
analytics using natural language.
To implement this LRM, prompt
Engineering there are core
components that we have to focus.
When it comes to data engineering
number one is context optimization.
We have to provide LLMs enough
information, business information,
and also the relationship between the
data to ensure that the query that
are getting generated are accurate
and we are getting the quality output.
There are lots of different
ways you can do that.
You can make sure that all
your data quality is good.
You create a business
layer using semantic.
Views or semantic models that has more
information that business users also
have relation between different terms,
different law logics, how you calculate
things, what is, what those type of
information can be stored in a layer.
And it helps with the
context optimization.
The more context you provide
to RLM more accurate and more
fast, you get the output.
Prompt design pattern.
You can talk to LLMs, you can get the
answers, but if you write a particular
thing or write questions in a particular
manner, you get a particular answers.
So if we know that what are the
different templates that we need to
follow, we can actually create reusable
templates, which guides the business
users to successfully interact and also.
Get the consistent output if
there is requirement of that.
And then there is a doc access,
which is always there, but we
want to make sure that there are
standardizations across, if there is
requirement of doing that for business.
We also have to make sure validation is
done on a data integrity and data quality.
We have to implement lots of
implement safeguards to verify that
the output that we are generating.
From the existing model is as expected.
There needs to be a rigorous testing and
lots of different validation that needs
to happen before we allow it to get used
by the business users in production.
And then last but not least, we have
to also have feedback loops, which is a
human interaction, that we continuously
refine the prompts based on the user
interaction and model con performance
to improve the accuracy over the time.
A model can learn from itself once it
starts generating the quality outputs.
So it's very important
to have a feedback loops.
Now, what is the biggest advantage that
we will get with this prompt engineering?
In data engineering?
The most powerful outcome we can see here
is deep democratization of data access.
Business users can ask
questions in plain language.
They don't have to go to the IT teams
or technical experts every time.
For some of the things that
they want to get answers from.
They also have something that we can
build, which allows them to transfer the
technical operations, if any, that can
be handled through the LLM interface.
Now this can be a little complex depending
on the business requirements, like what
type of interface that you want to build,
but you normally want to build something
that allows technical users to also
monitor, but also business users to run.
On the fly.
If they have to do something, if they
need to do a data refresh, if they
need to get additional data source,
those type of things can still be
handled through the LLM interface.
And then last but not list, we can have
the cloud data platform like Snowflake,
which allows business users to execute
and return results very quickly.
There are so many different things
you can do in the cloud data
platform with AI enabled with
lots of features that are coming.
That can allow business
users to feel empowered.
It's a less it's a less work
for the analytics engineer,
engineers to enable users and
also get things created very fast.
The value for the data can be
get very fast, and it can be
created and built for scalability.
What are some of the real world examples?
We already talked about ad aocc querying.
We dis users can basically ask
questions on what they want to see
from the data, if the data is created
with the high level of semantics.
The example here we can see,
show me the customer retention
rates by region for quarter four.
Now, if the prompt and prompt engineering
will go back to the model, and if
we have all the schema and data.
Relationship define in a way.
And then the answers we will get
either, we can ask that it creates
a SQL query and you copy paste the
SQL query and run the SQL query or
verify the SQL query before it runs.
And then once it's run,
it gives you the output.
And then output can be either in the
tabular format, chart, format, whatever
the preference that users have.
So you can do some of those things
where you want to add a validation
point, and then also create the charts.
Or sometimes if you don't want
people who are not technical.
We can directly give them the
output pipeline management.
This is more for the developer team
or the monitoring team or the admin
team that can trigger things like ETL
processes, schedule jobs, monitor data
flows through the conventional command.
Like they can just def if I want to
run a particular nightly customer
aggregation pipeline, I don't have
to go in the scheduling tool and
search for the job that does that.
I can just run the prompt and say, run
the nightly customer aggregation pipeline.
And it should run the right job for me.
And then data exploration, which is
a very, I will say, broad application
right now that we can have, which allows
you to understand what's going on.
You can run the hypothesis you
can run the marketing campaigns,
you can run the analysis of what
type of products you can launch.
It can give you lots of different things.
It can be a a predictive engineering
or it can be a. Prescriptive
engineering, whatever data that you
want to try and get the output for.
So it's very application.
You can see the example on the right
hand side, something like that.
You have a natural language search on
the top, and then the things that you
have built already can change according
to the search that you're doing.
So it can be a very different ways of
doing prompt engineering embedded within
BI or within your data exploration tools.
There are challenges obviously,
to address because we do all know
it's been lots of different topics
that people are talking about.
One of them is accuracy and vaccination.
How we can make sure that the accuracy
is at best, so that's one of the
thing that we can avoid is by doing
rigorous validation and testing
frameworks to prevent the data to be
giving anything that is not right.
We have to also do some of the data
quality things, but also once the
data quality checks are done and
model is using the data, we still
need to do some of the testing.
And then we have to define some
guide rails to avoid hallucinations
because sometimes the LMS can think
that they are right and then they
just go into the loop of doing the
things, which once they start doing.
And if it's incorrect, then it always
going to give you the incorrect
on output or incorrect answers.
So to make sure that the guidelines
are there to say, okay, some looks
like something is going wrong with
the model, and someone is able to make
sure that the model is always running
in a way that it should run with the
high accuracy and no hallucinations.
The second big challenge is
data governance, security.
This is independent of lms.
We all know data governance and
security is always the critical
part of the data ecosystem.
We have to make sure.
That we have all the possible data privacy
regulations, compilation compliance
requirements, and then obviously make sure
that the permissions to models that are
either reviewed from the security team or
we also want to make sure that the data
that we want to pass onto these models are
gar guarded by not sharing anything that
need, doesn't need to share to the model.
Like any PII information,
any personal information.
Any company data that is not,
does not qualify for using for
ai as per the policies that are
defined at the organization level.
You have to make sure that you
have the right data governance,
security built on top of the
infrastructure that you're building.
For LLMs model fine tuning, we have to
have fine tuning on the domain specific
schemas and business terminologies.
To improve the performance significantly.
There are so many different
things you can do.
You can define a layer, as I mentioned
before, which is a very good quality
layer, which is basically business layer
that allows you to create semantics
about what is what, how that, how
things happen, what is the business
logic, what happens and what scenario.
All those type of information,
other than the actual structure
and unstructured data, helps the
context to get the model to tune.
Much better.
And if you want to get the model, give
more accurate answers, you can give more
and more useful context that allows model
to tune itself or fine tune itself to
get better output performance at scale.
The one of the things that we
always heard about is that once
we start using these models and
complex queries and large databases.
The performance can be impacted
and how you can make sure of that.
You want to make sure that you have
enough compute resources, but not always
using all the resources, and you are
trying to do the things to make sure
the performance is always responsive
and user experience is always better.
And you can do that by doing optimization
strategies that can be used to make
sure the performance is always better
when you're performing at the scale.
As I said, governance is
the foundation of trust.
If we can use any.
To deploy the successful LLM, we have
to make sure we have a very robust
governance frameworks, access control.
We have security column masking
and force automatically.
You can define data masking policies.
You can have role-based access control.
Audit trails, you want to make sure
that you have a complete logging of all
the m generated queries and operations.
And then you also want to make
sure that you have human before the
execution, wherever it is required.
So from my experience working with
so many different clients, and from
my understanding of how things are
always going in a way that it's
successful, is that you need to
make sure that you have a roadmap.
You have a. You have a really good
understanding of how things are going
to be created and used over the time
for a particular use cases or for all
the use cases that you have for prompt
engineering in your organization,
especially for data engineering.
You should start with the limited scope.
Try with one particular date, business
domain or business unit, or a particular
data engineering process, and then
work on it and see if it works
fine, and then go for the next one.
Rather than trying to use everything
at once, try to minimize the scope.
That will always help you
to define the quality and
consistency of what you're doing.
You can also collaborate across the team.
We have to make sure everyone from the
business side, data engineers, security
team, compliance team, all of them are
involved to make sure that whatever we are
doing has covered from all the aspects.
Is there anything we are missing?
We have to make sure that we
are doing everything that we can
to make sure that all the data
governance, security, business logic
is used to implement the LLM Prompt
Engineering project text extensively.
Again, we are coming back to the
validation because we want to make sure
that the data quality or the results
quality or the accuracy of the model that
is giving the output is at as the best.
And then we are getting the
right and in and correct value
information that is really important.
And then we have to scale incrementally
because that also allows you to
get feedback every time you have
something small that is implemented.
And then gradually you are expanding your
capabilities, which also connects back to
the performance at scalability that you
are able to scale, but also make sure that
your performance is consistent and your
feedback that you're getting is also used.
To do the changes for the
work that has been done before
moving to the next project.
So what future of data
interaction looks like?
We all know the LLM is going to evolve.
We are going to see lots of
different new technology every day.
There is something new
that we are hearing.
The models are growing, the
companies are building new things.
The companies are coming.
With new things.
So there will be lots of different
things that will happen, especially
from the data engineering perspective.
The boundary between the business users
and the data platform will blur further.
We will see lots of power users, lots
of business users are also doing lots
of things which are much more technical.
By just doing the natural language
commands and prompt engineering
will represent a fundamental shift.
And how organizations think about data
accessibility and technical expertise,
it will allow them to do the faster
decision making because they have
basically eliminated the time between
the data team or the support team because
business users are directly talking to
the data and accelerating the decision
cycles by getting the input and getting
the output and using that information
to make the decisions very fast.
And there will be a smarter
data practices across.
How data means for getting more insights.
I think there is a culture shift that we
have seen when we are, when there was a
pi wave, when self-service analytics came.
Now it's again the LLM wave with
prompt engineering that will make
the data driven culture much more
mature and it'll be tech savvy.
Environment where people will learn
about this new stuff and interact
with LMS and use prompt engineering
to do most of their things.
So what are some key takeaways
from today's session?
Prompt engineering accents
far beyond chat bots.
We all heard about chatbots.
We are all about content generation,
but it is powerful tool that
will democratize the access to
complex cloud data ecosystem.
Success requires careful attention to
accuracy, governance, and fan tuning.
We already saw and discussed like what
all we need to make sure that we have
a proper framework and collaboration
across the organization to make the
success out of this prompt engineering
applications, smart small test,
rigorously and scale incrementally.
That's the mantra there, which
will allow any organization.
To build this infrastructure.
Use LLMs, use prompt engineering
in a way that is always scaling
and performing at it best.
The future of data
interaction is conversational.
It's going to be like you're
just talking with data.
You're not really doing any
data analytics, but you're just
trying to understand, and the
prompt engineering will allow you
to have sort of an interaction
that will empower and accelerate
innovation across the organizations.
Thank you very much for listening me.
I hope this session was useful.
And you are learning something
new about prompt engineering, the
application in data engineering,
which is going to grow very fast.
And looking forward to much
more exciting times for data
engineering and prompt engineering.
Thank you.