Hello, everyone.
My name is Chetan Nepatak.
I am currently working as a
Chief Producting Technology
Officer for Analytica Data Labs.
In today's session, I intend to spend
25 to 30 minutes talking through some
of the Gen AI abilities that we've been
building in our product LEAPS, which is
essentially a low code, no code platform.
and I'll give a bit more context
about that in, in just a few minutes.
but before I get started, a little bit of,
background and introduction about myself.
I have been, working in the
space of, AI, ML deep learning
for the last, 12 years now.
by, By education, I'm,
I've done two masters.
I'm a MBA from me and PC Paris,
and also, master's in advanced
computer science with focus on, AI.
I started off with computer vision,
and, went on to build, a deal models in,
predicting, in price prediction engines.
and then a few other models around, in the
fintech space, which were really about,
doing, evaluations using machine learning
models for, both insurance and loans.
and then the last, one and a half,
two years, been working on the
product to build in, generative
abilities, and that's been the
focus for the last 18 months or so.
and my today's discussion will
revolve around one of the products
that we have built and rolled out,
which is both stable and it's scaling
rapidly, and one of the abilities.
and I will talk through some of
our experiences there, and some
of the best practices that we have
seen that has worked for us as we
moved along from POC to production.
which is, a very apt, topic
for, for discussion, today.
So moving on, four essential
talking points today.
I'll start off by giving the context
of the app, and then I'll move on to,
talk about the various components that
go into, the, the app architecture
or the abilities architecture.
and then a little bit of, discussion on
prompts and rank, rank, and then finally,
quick note on what's coming next and what
the things that we're working on next.
so that's, the agenda, for this
discussion, Coming to the context of
the app, like I mentioned earlier,
the, the app really is built
grounded for, that they're a citizen
for people who are non technical.
This is a low code, no code platform
which does end to end data science, and,
it, you can not only build models, so
it has abilities which are pre modeling,
abilities, it has the modeling abilities,
and of course, the post modeling abilities
which is deploying and serving the models.
and we are continuously enhancing
that as we integrate with the
larger ecosystem in this space.
the, The app that I'm talking
about today in this session is
the RAG based inference engine.
In fact, these are multiple RAG pipelines.
So there is a parent RAG pipeline which
integrates into child pipelines and
the parent RAG pipelines really is the
orchestration this inference engine, is
akin to a copilot, and this, tries to
take the user through, various aspects
of bringing down, the barriers to
learning and the barriers to, working
with the, with the platform as large.
we are trying to address three, broad
umbrella questions, or abilities
with this copilot, the first one
being, what, can I do next, which
is, nothing but the recommendation
engine, again, a RAC pipeline, the
second one being, what else can I do?
This is, this is basically the
scenarios engine where, the LLM
model, and the associated RAC pipeline
come to an agreement in a assisted
mode with the user, as to what the
intent is in terms of the scenario
and then the back, backend workflow,
build those scenarios for the user.
and then lastly is the, do it for
me, which is our processing engine.
again, abilities, different
abilities in, product coming
together in a rack pipeline.
the processing engine
essentially, helps the user.
give a very few inputs and, generate
or either generate models, do,
any kind of pre processing and
even build, charts and dashboards.
So these are the three broad
abilities of the copilot.
And then there are some abilities,
which again, are part of this larger
three, So that's the context of the
app and it is this app that we've been
focused on the last one year and we've
been evolving our RAG architectures
to enable this co pilot abilities.
How did we get started?
Obviously we got started like
everybody else did, building simple
RAG architectures or pipeline.
we obviously had to move on to,
making sure that, whatever that we are
building is, is relevant, to, to the
user and has the, the right, responses.
so we had to quickly move to a
more evaluation driven, development
or metric driven development.
and then gradually, we build our
evaluation landscape, which is
again growing, as there are more
and more tools available and more
and more metrics, become available
for, every component that is there
as part of the entire RAC pipeline.
we are, gradually adopting to that.
But as of now, I think it's time today.
These are three key, moving parts,
to our matrix driven development,
to our entire evaluation landscape.
we are, in terms of approach,
very, reference based, which
means that, everything that we're
doing based on ground truth.
And to do that, obviously,
you need a very, you need rock
solid, gold standard eval data.
We, we are continuously building that.
Again, completely labeled
and annotated by humans.
in terms of, the scope of
evaluation, we do end to end,
and of course, component based.
When it comes to component based, we right
now focus, again, more on, On the, the
retrieval and the generative components,
but we are moving towards, building
more evaluation metrics, including unit
testing as we bring in more complexity and
more components in our, in our pipeline.
so generative, and, retrieval metrics
are, Build using the Raga framework
and we using the standard matrix there
of F1 score which is basically a good
balance between precision and recall as
far as retrieval is concerned and for
generative we are basing our evaluation
on faithfulness and, answer relevancy.
the other element, important element
of our, matrix treatment development
is, is the design consideration.
this is, this is key, Point or guiding
principle rather which helps us figure
out what are the kind of matrix we need
to bring in and Also, what are the kind
of components which we need to either
enhance or what additional layers are
needed In terms of design consideration
we I use three, deterministic versus
non deterministic, which basically means
that whether, how much of large language
models are we going to be using for each
of our components, we are currently using
at two, two, two of our components, use
large language models, and we gradually,
evaluate that, and based on, how much
of, deterministic and non deterministic
components we have, that will drive
our evaluation landscape as well.
and then next, of course,
is, turns, very important.
Now, when we started off, we were
very boundaried, we were, we did
not allow an open conversation.
but now gradually from a single
term conversations, we have
moved on to multiple turns.
and then we will, open up, make
it, a very free flow, text.
we are still a little boundary, but, we
are multi term conversational co pilot.
that's, what the current state is, and
we are, continuously testing that, and
the third important, design consideration
is the prompt flow, based on, again,
whether a single turn, multiple turn, the
complexity, the use case, of the copilot,
and as we build in more and more abilities
in copilot, I've spoken about the three
umbrella, but then within that, there are
a lot of those smaller abilities, that
determines what is the kind of prompt
engineering and prompt flow that will be
needed, whether these are complex queries
which needs decomposition, or they, need
any other query enhancement treatment.
based on, that we decided, what
kind of enhancement or component
we will be needing, and what
metrics we will be needing.
So this is really our, evaluation
landscape and how we go about, bring,
taking these three pillars to drive
our metrics driven development.
in terms of how we progressed on this, we
started off with eyeballing, at the POC
stage, and throughout the POC stage, all
that the teams were doing was eyeballing.
and as we were doing eyeballing,
we had our experts, which is, our,
analytical team, which, started to
use the eyeballing outputs, and the
pairs of query, query context and
responses, to build in the eval data.
so we started building the eval
data right from our, POC stage.
we also use certain synthetic data
generators, to build those pairs.
and then, we moved on to doing, as we
developed more, larger eval data set.
we moved on to doing, structured,
supervised, evaluation.
and now, of course, we're
trying to move to LM as a judge.
this, of course, needs very
sophisticated prompt engineering.
and once we achieve this, we'll
have a full instrumentation or
automation of our evaluation.
these are the three, these are
the three, prominent stages,
in our evaluation journey.
we are, just about starting
to use LLM, as a judge.
but our, we continue to use, eyeballing
and our supervised, ground truth,
evaluation model, is working well for us.
so that was around, around evaluation,
which is really the big piece
and that takes a lot of our time.
and then the next, important element
or pillar, is the data pre processing.
we started off with, various
chunking, methodologies or strategies,
fixed chunk, preprocessing.
Fizz chunking, content based chunking,
but we settled on to semantic chunking
because, when we, did our comparisons,
the semantic chunking was working
best for us, but then, it depends on
the kind of use case and the, source
data, data that you have, you could
potentially, be using a hybrid chunking
strategy, which might just work better.
parsing is of course the
most fundamental thing.
That's where everything starts,
depending on what kind of documents
you have, whether those are code
files, those are, webpages or PDFs,
Word documents or even images.
Depending on that, you would be using
different parsing algorithms or tools.
we've tried many, we've, and our current
tech stack is, inclined more on the,
parser variable from, the Lama landscape.
sparse and dense retrievers, we, we
are starting to feel that we would
be needing dense retrievers, now,
although, sparse retrievers have
worked, for us, the DF, IDF, and
BM25 is what we have used, so far.
but we started to get some vocabulary
mismatch problems, and, our teams
have now started the next POC
of, putting, the Dense Retriever
components, in our RAC pipeline.
we have been focusing on
metadata from day one.
a lot of our, abilities are
driven by this metadata.
and when we say metadata, metadata,
in context of rank obviously is the
metadata of the documents and the,
metadata of the chunks and also the,
potential metadata around, even prompts
if you're doing good prompt versioning,
but we also do metadata around the
context of, the user, and that context
is built in, what we refer to as the, the
organizational business map, and the KPI.
So we captured that metadata too.
And all of this is in our metadata
database, from where we, pull in
the context, which, then gets fed
into, which I earlier mentioned
into our orchestration layer.
and then from where we do the routing
for, the various, RAC pipeline.
so these are the four, Essential elements
of our data pre processing that, we
currently engaged in and, now, starting
to experiment, and bringing the dense,
retrieval capabilities, in a platform.
Query Enhancement, we didn't do
much of it initially, but we, we
wanted to ensure that we have the
best practices in place to make sure
that the intent is fully understood.
and as the, as we opened up and as
things became more conversational and the
conversation boundaries were loosened up,
it was, it became clear that enhancements
would be needed to, break down complex,
Queries, to decompose them to ensure
that the intent becomes very clear.
so we do a query decomposition, and
we use, a large language model there.
the other thing that we started to
do now is to, do, is to do hide.
Which is, again using, which will
be using a large language model.
It really goes a little further
than using a supervised encoder.
and it, builds, theoretical documents.
and those documents can then be, It is
classified as part of one, classification
of documents from where we then
generate, pairs of queries which are
very relevant to that particular chunk.
So chunk classification, is s something
that we intend to build by, not only
using the, document chunks that we
have through our semantic chunking,
but also by, using, the hide technique.
Routing, we've been using this, since day
one because we have different databases.
So we have a routing layer and
this routing layer based, on,
which, which database we need to
send the query to, does its job.
so the routing layer is responsible
to understand the query.
And, again, it's basically, decomposing
as the queries become more complex,
understanding the intent of the query.
and then routing it to the correct place
now as we do all of these things, it is,
it is, one of our challenge is to ensure,
that the complexities that we're building
in, they don't impact the latency.
and so our DevOps team, our infrastructure
team, are all a very integral part of,
doing everything, on the rack pipeline,
and, building the rack abilities.
And what kind of deployment architectures
and infrastructure we can use.
We currently are on AWS.
The product is on AWS.
And we are increasingly evaluating
every service in the JNI ability
on AWS, including the serverless
abilities that AWS has to offer.
To ensure that we offer good latency.
we, in terms of our, in terms of our go
to market, we are, very B2B, a high touch
model, but our abilities are low touch.
while we don't do a hundred
percent SAS, SAS based model.
So it, it is, sometimes
behind the firewalls.
The application is sometimes behind
the firewalls of the customer.
So we have to be very clear in terms
of the various, architectures that are
needed based on the usage and concurrency,
and also the, associated cost.
our trade offs, is very important and
we spend a lot of time understanding
that and building the infrastructure
architecture around that.
so that's the, that's the other,
important piece and element, of our,
of our, larger pipeline, which is,
continuous enhancement of the queries.
Thanks.
the next, the obvious candidate, after
query enhancement, that we worked on,
significantly on and we continue to
work, is, the retriever and re ranking.
we, didn't have time, We had re ranking
from very early days, but, more retriever
abilities, are gradually being built.
we generally classify these
abilities in three broad categories,
is the, is retriever, post
retriever, and, and generation.
and while there are a lot more, techniques
here, I've only, mentioned on the slide.
Thank you.
The ones that we either are using or we
intend to start building, immediately.
iBead Retriever, is, we've had this
since day one, the filter vector search.
which is simply a filter on
top of your vector search.
That's, that, is standard now
in most rank, architectures and,
we, we continue to use that.
re ranking, we, we've tried
both bi coder and cross encoder.
I was settled on, a cross encoder and
we, we found that the cross encoder works
better, in our use cases, simply because
it compares, two sentences and payers.
So as long as you have a
good, training data of payers,
cross and code is a way to go.
and, we currently use the coherent reran,
which is, which works on, cross encoder.
But we do have certain, by, by, by
encoders still working, but I think,
gradually we're going to phase them out.
Hierarchical indexing again,
seems like this has been adopted
well and has become a standard.
this is, this significantly enhances
the precision of the rank application,
You simply, in a hierarchical,
indexing, you, we organize the data in
a hierarchical structure as the name
suggests, and you have categories and
subcategories based on, on relevance and
relationships, and the retrieval process
focuses on those relationships and the
relevance, and the, and they process
the retrieval, by, doing, what we call
as a parent and teacher relationship.
and channel nodes.
hierarchy indexing is we use
extensively, so that's, working for us.
C RAC, CRAC, whichever way you pronounce
it, which is corrective, corrective
RAC, this is, a new technique.
We've started to use this, or experiment
with this, so we have current POCs, which
are running in this, C RAC is, is It, it
brings in another component, which is a
lightweight retriever, and this retriever
really self evaluates the, the quality of
the documents retrieved, and it provides a
confidence index, so we are, we're hopeful
that, this particular component is again,
going to, LLMS as a charge, help us,
instrument, do the full instrumentation
of, of a evaluation, landscape.
like I said that we want to move
towards as much of automated
evaluation as possible.
why we will still be, focused on, making
sure that our, eval datasets are robust.
but having produced those, eval datasets,
we want the rest of the pieces to
be really as automated as possible.
fine tuning, again, very helpful.
this is the, generation, we keep the
LLMs that we use fine tuned, based on
whatever the context of that LLM is, is,
whether it's for generation or whether
it is for query composition or even
some of the other, abilities that we're
building that would require, use of LLMs.
so we, that's a standard practice,
wherever we have data, we fine tune it.
Wherever we don't, we, generate
synthetic data and we fine tune it.
So that's the retrieval and re
ranking, abilities that we have,
and that we're currently using and,
the one, I spoke about C Rank that
we intend to use, going forward.
So that was about the various
principal components that we
have, in, in a RAC pipeline.
A RAC pipeline, at a very high level,
has, looks like, the, The pipeline that
I have on the deck, we have the queries.
Then we have query transformation.
we are routing across
three, different databases.
We have the product docs database.
We have the user history and
what we have the context TV.
The context TV is, is, is really
the context of the business
where we have the business maps,
the processes, the features.
all of which is used to
develop, analytical models.
we're currently using, like I said,
two places, large limit models.
One for query decomposition,
where we're using chain of, chain
of thought, prompt engineering.
and, we're using, prompting
for augmentation process.
so the key takeaway really is
that, prompt engineering and
drag are really tied together.
obviously we don't hope, we don't
want to over engineer, prompt
engineering, wherever it's not required.
But the key takeaway is that, wherever
we use, whichever component uses a
large language model, That is where
we will be using sophisticated prompt
engineering and that is how these
two are really married to each other.
A simple rank probably uses prompt
engineering only in the augmentation
process, but as you bring in more and more
LLMs for different components, as I spoke
about, sophisticated prompt engineering
is absolutely bedrock for, doing, relevant
and, a more, a correct, RAC pipeline.
in terms of our next steps, We are trying
to move to a modular RAC architecture.
This is also the need and, from our
customers, wherein, we are going to
be doing subscription based pricing.
So there are different abilities and
these abilities need to be dockerized and,
deployed, in a microservices architecture.
So making sure that we are ready for that.
And as are each of these components and
these services grow, not in terms of the
usage, but also in terms of, the data
that they're handling and the kind of,
responses that they need to generate.
so as that grows and it becomes more
sophisticated, We, these services need
to, take a life on its own, of their own.
And, we would need to move towards
a modular RAG architecture.
we are, one of our challenges
has been, versioning of prompts.
so we are, evaluating different products
where we can have end to end versioning of
prompts also because like I said, we are
putting in more and more LLMs in different
components of the RAG architecture.
we are almost ready, with the, with the
unit testing, and, we're using ProudFu
for that, and that's something which
has become part of our, development
lifecycle, that is currently, running.
it's almost a practice now, and then
lastly, we're looking at, agentic
abilities wherever they are needed.
like I said, earlier when I was
describing about, the application,
there is, the parent, orchestration,
engine, inference engine, and, right
now it's built on, custom rules.
but we intend to bring in, use of other
tools as well to make sure that, context
is brought in from other data sources.
and we have agenting abilities there.
so those are the, some of the
next steps that we intend to take.
and that's, that was a high level view of.
What our application does, what is,
the current, architecture of our, RAC
pipelines, and some of the, learnings
that we have had, on working on these
abilities, for the last one year.
so I think I'm back on time.
I hope, I hope this, session was
useful and, the audience got, some
important, pointers from this.
I will be very happy to take questions
whenever the opportunity arises.
thank you so much, for,
being there, and listening.