Hi, everyone.
Welcome to my session.
I am super excited to be the speaker
at Con42 Prom Engineering Conference.
In this talk, you will learn what are the
generative feedback loops and how to use
them to create personalized recommendation
solutions and generate targeted
ads based on real time information.
This session can be specifically useful
for Python developers, data engineers.
or, super base or we relate users looking
for solutions for detecting changes on
primary database like, a super base or
PostgreSQL and streaming these changes and
continuously updating vector databases.
For ai powered applications, let me babur.
I'm developer advocate at glass flow.
I'm also microsoft's mvp For azure ai
services if you have any questions,
please scan the qr code and connect
me on linkedin I will be more than
happy to address all of your questions
Here's what we will be covering today
We'll start with an introduction.
What is a generative feedback loop and
followed by the real world use cases
and real time GFL pipeline architecture.
I'm going to explain and show you, the
components, how to detect changes on
your primary database and streaming these
changes, continuously updating all your,
as a destination vector database, when
you are building AI powered applications.
And you will see also demo of building
a typical pipeline with, technologies
like Glassflow, Superbase, and Vue 8 for
our simple, ERBNB, listing application.
To optimize and personalize these
property listings for a Airbnb, this
will be a live demo of running the
production ready pipeline in 15 minutes.
By the end of this, my session,
you will be able to process
a simple Airbnb listing data.
which is in the super base and enrich it
with AI and store it vector database like
we wait, and you can also search through
all these, and Richard listings in the way
we're using, we weights, graph console.
I'm incredibly happy to have the,
such a knowledgeable, audience
in this session and this webinar.
So let's me start with, by
understanding was a feedback loop.
feedback loop actually relates
to the use of, current, outputs,
to optimize the future, results.
It involves, as you can see in
diagram, utilizing outputs, to
generate better, inputs in the next
stage and feedback loops are critical
components also in, training AI models.
Like when you are give, some AI model
data, a model you can train, but in
real time also user input can impact
on the AI model responses in real time.
Generative feedback loops or
shortly GFL, takes also approach
of a generative AI model.
but it takes a step further by
introducing continuous improvement cycle.
As you can see in the diagram in GFL,
the output generated by the AI, when you
do from engineering, is not just a final
product is a part of ongoing process.
Usually GFL, takes the
results generated from the.
Gen AI or from your language models
like GPT vectorizes them and saves
the result back to the vector database
and you can use this generated
data for future AI processing.
And this output is used to also improve
the future results from the AI models.
In other words, the outputs become
the inputs for the loop cycle.
And AI outputs are analyzed to
optimize training data for the
AI or algorithms, parameters.
The goal.
It's to improve the quality of
the future content generation.
Let's think about AI can generate
a code snippets based on the users
requirements and create a feedback loop
with tests to improve the code over time.
some people always confuses, GFL with GNI.
GNI, we know that it primarily
operates, in a one way direction.
It generates a content based on
the input data you provide for AI.
however, GFL on the other side,
incorporates the feedback loop where AI
solution continues to learn and improves
from the outputs as it's generated.
And GNI, we know that it's typically
used for creating new content or new
data, summarizing existing data, but
GFL is focused on improving AI outputs
So over and over time, so the cycle of
feedback loop learning and GFL solutions
are more complex than the standard GNI
models because they require mechanism
for collecting feedback from the users
or from the human, analyzing it and
adjusting the AI models accordingly.
Let me bring a couple of examples.
A good example of GFL in action can
be the personalized recommendations.
There are AI might
suggest products to user.
Based on the browsing history
or clicks or purchases on an
online store, like a website.
The users further can interact with these
recommendations to provide the feedback
to AI to refine the future suggestions.
In the real estate, another example, in
the real estate industry, for example,
property listings are often updated.
if you want to buy or rent the apartment
with the new information, such as the
price always changes, availability
also changes, and additional features
like, you can add sofa, you can
remove the refrigerator and so on.
And GFL pipeline can automatically
update these descriptions of, let's say,
real estate, listings or information.
By making do, making sure that
they always, car currently
optimized for social engines.
If you open a Google and then search
for, specific apartment, if the apartment
data is changes in real time, you can see
also, this, also reflected on your search.
Other examples, you can apply the GFL
and these two other industries like
a real time job listing optimization.
For example, the platforms
like LinkedIn can use this TFL.
if the AI detects, let's say, someone
searching for remote work or flexible
hours, it can update the relevant
job listings to emphasize these,
expectations or aspects, thereby
like increasing, the visibility of
your job posting to the candidate.
to make it more attractive, for them,
or you can use the same solution GFL,
like to customize travel itineraries.
This is one, this example, I really,
I like, let's say if you use your
frequently search for some new
trips online or cultural experience
in different countries and AI.
Can, create, generate some itineraries to
include, some activities that perfectly
aligned with the preference of the user
and other exams, like a TV shows, you
can like a Netflix can use to create
a personalized viewing experience.
the red Netflix.
You can always see the quite relevant,
movies, based on your, historical,
watch it, like the movies always,
it will find something relevant
to your emotional, experience.
if you want to learn more about the GFL,
I found this article by the author Connor.
He explains very nicely the concept of
Generative Feedback Loops with large
language models like LLMs, how you can
retrieve the information from a vector
database such as WeWeight to prompt
vector databases generative model and then
vectorize and save the results of the AI
generated content back to the database.
let's focus on now GFL
with real time data.
for listening.
as you can see in the diagram, real
time data transformation, and this
transformation are the backbone of
a very effective GFL automation.
it's about detecting, real time data
changes and continuously updating
vector storage on the right side.
In the context of, ERBNB listings, this
means as soon as like new room is listed.
you, the description of, for the
room can be, created by the AI and
vectorizes for a better search.
And then, you can store the data.
It's a vectorized result
in a vector database.
Let's say user searching for a cozy
apartment in Paris using Airbnb, and
he can see all up to date options
for him in the same location.
And the real time transformation also
here, what it does, As you can see,
if you see the yellow square is sort
of pipeline, we are detecting some
changes from APIs, files, databases,
where exactly Airbnb listings, located,
and then say, if new Airbnb listing is
added, we are generating, description
based on the Airbnb listing attributes.
we are calling the open AI or other
models, such as compilations and point.
And then B for the generated
content from the AI, we are
calculating vector embeddings.
And then we are sending a vector embedding
to store somewhere in the vector database.
Why we are storing in the vector
database, because we would like to
build, in the next step, like simple.
And the application, to give the booking.
com experience to the users,
where they can search for.
some, apartments, by, using the human
language and then this human language
can be also converted to the vector
embeddings and we can compare our data
corpus we created in the vector database.
To find the matching the
apartments for the user query.
This is a, everything is happening
in real time, as you can see, in
the previous slide, I showed you.
Data, can change here, maybe
every minute or every five minute.
And this data is captured and in
milliseconds, data will be visible.
In the vector databases.
This is the concept of real
time GFL, how that works.
And now let's focus on, the, some
of the technologies, to build,
how we can build these pipelines.
One of those technologies I'm working
with also, helps you to build real
time data pipelines for, AI use cases.
Like you can build a pipeline
such as a real time GFL using
Glassflow and Glassflow simplifies
also creation process of your real
time data processing pipeline.
As we have seen previously, you may spend
up to 15 minutes to setting up everything.
And your new pipeline is, ready to
run in a production, environment.
and also with Glassware, you can
integrate, with various data sources
such as PostgreSQL, MongoDB, or some
message brokers like a Google PubSub,
message queues like Amazon SQS, and you
can apply transformation in the middle.
Then you can store the results to
the databases or BI analytics tools
or vector storages like Vue Vid.
So this is, how the works, the Glassflow,
why we, decided to build this solution,
especially for Python developers.
we are trying to offer all in one
platform, for, that focuses on the
creation of, easy creation of your
data pipelines for data engineers
and data teams, especially for data
scientists, you don't have to worry
about the infrastructure under the hood.
In other words, it removes the
complexity of the, real time for data
processing pipelines, be it Kafka
plus Flink, you can do everything in
a single serverless infrastructure.
let me explain how that works,
building a pipeline with Glasswell.
let's say you, start with connecting
to your live data sources like
Airbnb listings using built in
integrations, or you can build your
own integration using Python SDK.
Then you start to build your pipeline,
within the local environment like a Gospel
web app, or Using the CLI, if you prefer,
like CLI option, then you implement your
transformation function, which is a very
heart of the transformation in Python.
And you can, after your transformation
function is ready, you can deploy to
serverless execution engine, where
your transformation can scale up to
processing like billions of records.
And you don't have to worry
about the scaling and manually.
And then when the transformation
is ready, you can send the
output event to the transcript.
Internet destinations using the same
integrations or building integrations.
this is, some of the use cases
you can achieve with Glassflow.
You can build your pipeline, for
example, to enrich your data with
predicted future prices, using
AI, and to detect some changes.
In your database and also
sending this data changes by
transforming to their destinations.
You can also build some let's say
realtime clickstream analytics
dashboard to analyze clickstreams
data from your website and sends them
to other downstream applications.
If you want to know more about
Glassflow and Glassflow use cases,
You can scan this QR code, it will
bring you to the GitHub repository.
Where you can try some of our
real world examples and run them
just right from Jupyter notebook.
Now let's come back, switch to our real
time genetic feedback loop automation.
We're going to build as a part of
the session sample pipeline for GFL
to make a feedback loop pipelines,
as you can see, here in the diagram.
We have data source, let's assume
that ERB data always stored to
the SuperBase because while using
SuperBase, SuperBase is open source.
First of all, then, it is another
alternative to Google Firebase, which
works quite nice, especially when
you have a real time data and your
data always changing your database.
Let's say whenever new, ERB listings
added, or you updated existing one.
and Superbase can trigger an event,
to send this change directly to
the Glassflow pipeline, using it is
a webhook, data source connector.
Every change happening, Airbnb listings
can be, actually, send it to the
automatically to the Glassflow pipeline.
And then when you, It reads
the glass of pipeline.
You can do where AI and vectorization
and you can write transformation
function to apply some, AI driven,
solution in a driven insight in Python.
In this case, let's say, AI model.
can call the open AI to enrich
listing and descriptions by
generating, more descriptive,
description for the Airbnb listing.
you can summarize it and then
transform it, all the descriptions.
and then at the same stage will
be vectorize it and converted to
the vectors, format, and it'll be
sent to the vector database like
a , as you can see in diagram.
I will show you, why this approach
and why we are calculating
your vector, embeddings.
And again, like we are
storing a vector database.
you will see in the next slides, I will
give you some of the example queries.
It will give the, more, cleared,
querying option for users.
They don't have to use SQL, if data runs
in the Vector database, they can use
query data using their human language.
let me, explain what
is our sample data set.
To train our AI or the build a pipeline
and we can use like a simple CSV data set.
And we're like, is there some room
listings that say New York city
from Airbnb last year in 2023.
And this dataset includes every, Airbnb
listing attributes, such as a listing
name, host name, location, details, room
type, price, availability, and so on.
once a dataset we have.
Here we can, what we can do by
running this pipeline and saving to
the data to the way with, we can run
typical queries, like we can fetch,
let's say, top five most reviewed
listings in New York or in Brooklyn.
this could be quite useful to identify
popular listings in this area.
Or you can find the listings, in Brooklyn
that, a budget friendly, let's say,
less than 100 US dollars and have a
positive reviews, something like that.
Or you can also search for the queries,
may user might be looking for listings
that are described, like I want have
a, the apartment with a great view.
This query would return the most relevant
results based on the user queries.
And this conversion, from the human
language to the, vector query operation
will be handled automatically by
the vector database, like Vue Wait.
Once you understand the pipeline
and, GFL, let's build this pipeline.
step by step.
Here, how we build our pipeline, like
we start with setting up our vector
storage, which is our final destination.
we create a pipeline with
Glassflow and we set up the super
base with a simple, Airbnb data.
Then, we run the pipeline.
Once data already In Vuelo GraphQL, I
will show you how you can query, Vuelo
weight using it is GraphQL console.
Let me bring your
attention to the demo here.
As you can see the demo, in place.
I will start by, analyzing,
creating first, setting up the Vuelo
weight cloud, you can create, the
first cluster, on Vuelo weight.
Then, once the cluster is up and
running, you can, start to create a
new collection, inside your cluster.
It is called, let's call it Airbnb,
NYC, which is we did in New York.
Then, you choose a vectorized type, like
in my case, I'm using Text two Vector
from the open ai, and you choose a model
like text embedding three small or large.
for me, it's a three small is
enough, and you can keep the rest
of the configuration by default.
So as a next step, and now once I have
the, Vuex site is ready, I'm going to
create the pipeline with Glassflow.
You can sign up for it for free.
You can get a free account.
And when you can create
your first pipeline easily,
let's create a new pipeline.
And then, choose a data
source as a webhook.
Because we are getting data from
Superbase, as the events, sends
events through the webhook.
The third step is defining
your transformation function.
You can define by writing the Python code.
As you can see, I have created already
one simple transformation function.
it, simply, receives, from SuperBase
Airbnb listing data, and, using
the OpenAI, it generates, the
description from the Airbnb attributes.
Then, after AI response, with a generated,
Airbnb listing, description, we're gonna
create, create the vector embeddings.
As you can see, it has a handler
function, which is important
function for, GlassFlow.
It automatically detects, whatever inside
the Lua logic under the handler function.
And then, our transformation
function is more or less ready.
So next step, yes, also we don't
forget to include your, dependencies,
like OpenAI dependency for my
transformation function or Py file.
And next day, we, I'm going to
define data sync operation, where my
transformer data will be send it again.
I'm going to choose a webhook
because out the data I will send
to, we wait, collection that we,
created with you in the before.
So I'm gonna, find first, we
wait cloud, API key, in the URL.
I need a URL for the, my cluster and
just copy past the URL for the cluster.
And then I will bring
the admin key for that.
let me find the admin key
from Vue with console.
and I can give me the define also
content type and like application JSON.
Then.
it's a mandatory to define also,
the API key to make sure that we are
securely connected to V Wave cluster.
Then, we send our data.
from the Glasslow Pipeline.
here we go.
I have the Bureau token
and authentication is done.
I will click on the next step.
And you can see the
overview of your Pipeline.
And when you press to click
Pipeline, your Pipeline is ready
to run in a serverless environment.
The last step is setting up a Superbase.
Make sure that you have
a Superbase account.
Assume that I have, my already
created a simple database, called
it Airbnb, NYC, in super base.
You can see, from I had
some different data sets.
This one is from, 2019 and has some
attributes, to map the Airbnb listings,
like host name, location, room type price.
then, once I have, this data in place.
I can go and navigate to, the
table editor to see, sample data.
As you can see, I have now, existing
sample data, five, listings in place
to give your understanding, like
this is how the data is looks like.
and I'm, I will create a webhook
trigger on Superbase because
Superbase, triggers using the webhook
or the Glassdoor pipeline, right?
let's create our webhook.
Okay.
Like you can call it, you can give it
any name, in my case, maybe ERBMB, a
listing, or ERBMB data change capture,
because it changes, detects, the changes
and sends to the Glasgow pipeline.
And you're reading in the next
step, create, choose a data type.
database, table, which database table
we are, choosing and events like
in sort, we have frequent entries,
should trigger in sort or so on.
this, and also next step is we need
to also define, Glassflow Pipeline
Access Token in the webhook URL,
because when the SIPL base calls the
Glassflow, we need to securely make
this connection using the access token.
I put it in the header of the,
view, triple base web hook,
access token for the glass flow.
Now, as you can see, is our, the
pipeline, for the web hook is ready.
And make sure you need to enable
real time for your database because
it should get real time updates.
Now everything is set up.
Next step I'm gonna.
send, some more sample data to
SuperBase because you remember we
had the only, like five listings.
Let's add maybe 10 or
20 more for, my listing.
As you can see, I have a bunch of them
in the sample data set, and I have also
one Python script called, to populate
the, SuperBase with sample data.
And, I have one Python script called, to
populate the, SuperBase with sample data.
And, I have also one Python
script called, to populate the,
SuperBase with sample data.
it just inserts, rows of
data, in bunch, in batch mode.
We are just, three, simulating, some
incoming or registering your listings.
but in reality, this, service, any service
can call these, to, insert some more data.
And let's run this Python script
and generate some input data.
I'm going to create 20 more rows
for the super base listings.
There we go.
I added 20 more.
Everything's successful.
and now I can switch back to
the super base and check if,
this data already in place.
Yes.
As you can see, the data
is in place and now.
we can go to Glassflow and check, if the
data received by the Glassflow after we
did the insort on SuperBase side, right?
at the real time what's happening.
Yes.
Here we go.
As we insorted, every insort,
detected by SuperBase and sent
to the Glassflow pipeline, which
is where our magic is happening.
And Glassflow is already, in
milliseconds, and sent to the SuperBase.
after this transformation and
I can now, ready to query, and
search for Airbnb listings.
And, the view with the GraphQL console.
I did one query, like to find, five
most reviewed listings in Brooklyn.
Yes.
Here we go.
Here are some listings.
And now let's try, some, query
using, the human language.
For that, you need also, the OpenAI key.
Because, we need to, it's going to use AI
to, use like human interactive searching.
I'm going to pass my open AI API key.
let's say when user, might be asking
like luxury apartment with a nice view,
and as you can see, it found, based
on the human language, relevant, data.
in our, database and the summary is
actually generated, from the summary
generated from the AI generated this
summary, but we had in the beginning,
only the data, about the Airbnb
listings and this generated data
summary can be always, change it and
reach it, in based on the property,
something that's on the property side.
if I change now and find any
property and change the price.
For the property, it will be reflected
immediately on the view weight.
This is how the, real time, continuous
vector embeddings generation.
And, with the database, dating works.
So that was my, demo in summary.
we have, so far presented, concept
of the generative feedback loops.
And this describes, let's say, not only
using the results from the database to
answer, the user's queries, but, we can
also save the result and, once, we create,
save the results, back to the vector
database again for future references.
So this is called, we call it GFL and
real time GFLs, uses real time data, to
receive, like user input and change the AI
output based on the user's interactivity.
So you can always get most relevant and
updated content using a real time GFLs.
So I hope you find the
session interesting.
If you have any questions.
and now we can jump on a current session
or give you questions in a comment,
and, scan score code to find the,
the use case I showed you with GFL.
Also other use cases, do you
want to try out, you can try
out some of other use cases.
Thanks for your attention.
and have a nice day.