Hello everyone.
My name is Raje.
I'm principal engineer at Synopsis.
My presentation is about how ultra
ethernet and UL link accelerate
token to token performance.
In my presentation, I'll be covering
on AI infrastructure bottleneck
need for enhanced interconnect
technology, UL link Ultra ethernet,
and finally the conclusion.
AI infrastructure bottleneck in
the present AI infrastructure.
There is exponential growth
in the compute demand.
Despite parallelization, the training time
of model have rise from week to months.
If you look into the picture on the
right hand side, model parameters are
doubling every three to four months.
Multi-dimensional systems are getting
stretched, like network bandwidth,
network latency, memory, bandwidth,
memory capacity, and then compute.
Also the design complexities
are increasing memory bandwidth,
interconnect bandwidth.
Now if you look into the extreme right
side, we have a DDR standard, HBM
standard PCA standard and DD day to day
standard are exponentially increasing.
Therefore, we need AI infrastructure
with enhanced interconnect technology
to meet current and future demand.
Need for enhanced interconnect technology.
In this slide, let try to understand
why GPU performance is important.
If you consider AI ML lifecycle in the
picture, to build a model, we need to
prep the data first, we need to prep
the data, build a model, train it,
test it, and then fine tune the model.
So there is a continuous feedback
provided to fine tune the model,
and this loop continues during
which data is split and fed.
To multiple GPUs and sometimes
multiple machines at larger scale.
Therefore, GPU performance influences
the timeline of deep learning.
UL Link Scale Up UL Link is
an open source interconnect
technology developed to scale up.
Accelerators for AI workload.
If you look into the
picture here, we have a pod.
This is also called as a cluster.
We have a racks in them
stacked vertically.
Each rack will have a GPU.
All these GPUs are interconnected
to get together through a UL link.
So what are we trying to achieve here
is we are trying to connect all the GPUs
together to create one big giant GPU.
To enable memory sharing and
synchronization between the
accelerators so that there is a direct
load store and automat operations
enabling between the accelerators.
UL Link can connect up to a
hundred to thousands of GPUs
together ultra ethernet scale out.
So Ultra Ethernet is an open source,
high performance networking technology
developed by ultra ethernet consortium
to offload AI workload and HPC.
If you look into the picture on the
right hand side, we all, we have
already discussed about UL Link
now talking about ultra ethernet,
which is highlighted in the local.
These are.
Connecting all the clusters
together, which is called scale out.
This establishes a high bandwidth,
multi-path open, standard,
highly configurable interface.
This is very much important for AI
clustering and also ALTA ethernet
stack introduces new transport layer
with enhanced congestion control
and then enhanced RDMA capabilities.
Here we are talking about interconnecting
millions of GPUs together.
Conclusion Token to token performance.
UL Link is used to connect two aspirators
together so that there is a memory
synchronization happening between them.
This scenario is optimized for AI
workload because of rapid token passing.
Ultra ethernet establishes low
latency, high throughput for rapid
token exchange and scalability.
Thank you for taking time
and watching my presentation.