Good morning everyone.
Today I'm gonna talk about the most
exciting developments in software
engineering, how we are using artificial
intelligence to transform code at massive
scale, far beyond simple auto complete
suggestions to intelligent repository.
By transformation, we are
living in a pivotal moment.
Developers have traditionally relied
on like line by line tools and
manual refactoring for large changes.
But what if we could use AI for
doing entire package migrations,
build and buck fixing, which
involves automated error resolutions?
COVID refactoring structural improvements,
maintaining a specific behavior, fixing
code style issues, enforcing a standards
automatically static analysis based
repair, fixing link, or analyzer phonic.
Static analysis annotations, such as
adding type hints or documentations.
Let me show you how we are
actually using AI powered large
scale code transformations.
Before we talk about solution,
let's understand the core
problems we are trying to solve.
There are three fundamental challenges
that prevent Standard L LMS from handling
large scale transformations effectively.
First context window limitations.
Here's the variety.
Most code bases are massive.
You can't fit an entire repository
in a single L-L-M-A-P-I call.
We need to break the code base
into intelligent chunks and
orchestrate multiple LLM calls
each with the right context.
This requires sophisticated
mechanism that understand software
structure, not just splitting code
randomly at character boundaries.
Problem two, knowledge cutoff.
LLM are trained up to a certain date.
If a code basis use a library
that was updated yesterday, the
model wouldn't know about it.
This is especially critical in
programming where API changes happen
frequently and outdated knowledge
can lead to incorrect solutions.
Problem three, hallucinations ELs are
fantastic at generating code that looks.
Good syntactically correct, but they're
also prone to making things up using
APIs that don't exist and ignoring
edge cases or implementing logic that
reasonable, that seems reasonable,
but it is fundamentally flawed.
For critical transformations,
this is unacceptable.
These three challenges mean that LMS
alone, even powerful ones, simply
cannot reliably handle repository
scale core transmissions without
human interventions at every step.
Your Enters code plan.
Code Plan is basically a symbolic
framework that combines the creative
power of large language models with
the rigor and precision of traditional
symbolic reasoning and static analysis.
What does code plan do?
It automates large
independent code changes.
Think package migrations across your
code base, multiple file refactorings
of modernizing legacy code.
The key innovation here is treating
repository level coding as a planning
problem, not just a generation problem.
Code plan integrates LLM
with intelligent planning.
It doesn't just generate code, it
reasons about what needs to happen,
breaks it into steps, validates those
steps, and orchestrates the execution.
Some real use cases are C
sharp package migrations across
your entire code repository.
Python dependency updates that touch
multiple services, static analysis
driven repairs when you're fixing
violations, or compliance issues.
Adding type annotations
to UN type code at scale.
Code Plan is extensible.
It's built on modules and
transformations, actions and prompts
that you can customize for your
specific in software engineering tasks.
Code plan at a high level, is a symbolic
framework for building AI powered software
development workflows for inner and
outer loops for software engineering.
It in the power of LMS with intelligent
planning for tackling complex coding tasks
that cannot be solved using LLM alones
it basically combines the power of LLM
and symbolic static analysis approaches.
Okay.
Let's, lemme walk you through
what, how code plan actually works.
The architecture has majorly
three competence, input, code,
plan, engine, and output.
The input basically consists of your code
repository or directory knowledge based
repositories with precise transformation
instructions and examples, static analysis
reports and logs that identify issues.
The code plan engine consists of four
major aspects, prompt contests, the first
prompts contextualization before we pass.
Before we ask anything to the
lm, we carefully prepare prompts
with most relevant context.
This is crucial.
Bad context can lead to bad outputs.
Second planning and orchestration.
Complex transformations are in one
short operations code plan, breaks them
into structured steps and coordinates
the execution, making decisions about
which tools to use and in what order.
Dependency analysis.
Using a ST, we pass your code using
abstracts and text trees, a representation
that captures the actual structure
of your code, not just a text.
This lets us understand the relationship
between the different components.
Static analysis.
We validate the transformations and
use static analysis to guide them.
Is this the, is this
transformation correct?
Did we break any builds or did you test?
Will it break any downstream
downstream dependencies stack
analysis gives us the confidence.
And finally the output is
basically the transfer generated
code ready to be integrated.
Here's a walkthrough of the
architecture diagram on the left side.
As you can see, the inputs consist
of the code repository, the knowledge
based repo, or the instructions.
The static analysis allows for
verifying or for performing static
analytics based transformations.
The main engine consists of from
contextualization planning, orchestration.
Dependency analysis, which uses
abstract syn tax trees, static
analysis, validation, and the LLM.
And on the right side, the generated code
is the output code which gets generated
transforming your repository at a high
level the technical magic which happens.
And code plan majorly consists of three
techniques, LLM planning instead of asking
an LLM to solve a problem in one shot.
We ask it to plan.
Break the complex task
into structured steps.
Choose which tools and techniques to
use decide the order of oxy execution.
This enables the goal directed
execution rather than hoping on a
general purpose model gets it right.
Ad based chunking.
We don't split the code at
arbitrary character positions.
We use a ST to, which is abstract syn
to identify meaningful boundaries.
Function classes, loops.
Each chunk remains
syntactically valid on its own.
This produces better embeddings,
better retrieval, and more accurate
LLM responses RAG the retrieval.
Augmented generation and RAG basically
consists of a retrieval and a generator.
The retrieval finds relevant
chunks from your knowledge base
and instructions and the code base.
The LLM generator basically integrates
the context into its responses.
This combination basically reduces
the hallucinations, overcomes the
context length eliminations, and
incorporates, incorporates fresh
knowledge into the training data.
Together, these techniques create
a powerful system for handling
repository scale transformations.
Okay, now let's go
deeper into the abstract.
Synex trees as well as the rank.
Okay.
Let's walk through an a SD
con concrete with an example.
So here's a simple python code,
a function that greets someone.
When we pass this a SD with our a SD
pass, we get a hierarchical restructure.
At the top is a function deaf node.
Under that, we have the
function name, greet.
The argument's name and
the return statement.
The return statement contains a
binary operation string court,
which is string contact conation.
Combining Hello with the variable name.
Name.
Now this might seem like a minor
detail, but it's transformative
when an LLM sees the structure
representation instead of raw text.
It understands the code
at a much deeper level.
It knows these are distinct
Symantec components.
It can reason about how changing
one part affects the others.
This structure enables meaningful
code chunking file, LM, processing,
and accurate relationship
between the different components,
LLMC code as plain text.
It's just a sequence of characters
they don't inherently understand.
The function is different from a
loop that a variable declaration
is different from a function call.
They make educated guesses
based on statistical patterns.
This leads to generate generic, inaccurate
responses and potential hallucinations.
The A ST solution breaks the code into
organized hierarchical representation.
Now, the LLM can understand
methods, properties, arguments,
data types, and logic flow.
It sees the skeleton of your program.
This makes the AI responses far
more accurate and insightful.
When you feed an LLM and a
ST in text, you're given a
semantic understanding layer.
That's the major difference between a
generic tool and a specialized tool.
Okay.
Next chunking.
Now we are gonna look at the
two approaches for breaking
the code into chunks.
The first one is traditional and
the next one is ESD based chunking.
Traditional character based
trunking treats code like any
other text you might split at 500
characters or a thousand characters.
Here's what happens.
You end up cutting through
middle of functions.
A function definition
gets split across chunks.
An inclusive statement sits alone.
The semicolon statement that closes a
statement might be in the next chunk.
The core structure is disregarded.
You get malformed, syntactically
invalid fragments, statements
lack proper syntax closure.
The semantic meaning is
completely destroyed.
And LLM asked to process this fragments
would get completely confused.
It's like asking a, someone, asking
someone to understand a sequence
broken randomly across lines.
Next.
Now let's see how ad-based chunking.
Significantly improves our use case.
Each chunk represents a code boundary.
The pre-processor
include is its own chunk.
The using declaration is its own chunk.
The complete functions are
preserved as a single chunk.
This.
Which makes more sense and provides
better understanding to the LLM.
The code is split and meaningful.
Boundaries, functions, control structures,
usings, declarations, et cetera.
Each chunk is syntactically
valid and complete.
Semantic integration is
completely preserved.
When an LLM receives syntactically valid
code that represents semantic boundaries,
it can generate better confirmation.
There's no guessing about
context that was cut off.
The model understands the
complete picture of that chunk.
This is a foundation technique
which we use for enabling
repository scale transformation.
The planning, along with the A ST
analysis, helps us split the task into
meaningful sections and loop our irate
over the LLM calls providing meaningful
chunks of the A SDU back again and again.
Next, we are gonna look at rack
retrieval, augmented generation.
We use RAG majorly for two
major aspects, knowledge cutoff
and high restoration problems.
RAG has two simple components.
The retriever searches through your
knowledge space, documentation examples,
existing core best practices majorly
trying to understand what is the
transformation you're trying to achieve.
It uses the retrieval.
It uses a retrieved documentation,
combines it with the a SD based chunking
and provides it to the generator.
The generator takes whatever the retrieval
found and process it through an LLM.
The model integrates this fresh
up-to-date context into its.
The beauty of this approach is that the
LLM has current information about your
specific APIs, frameworks and patterns.
It's not operating on the general
knowledge from its training data.
It's operating on the actual code
base and the knowledge base of
instructions, which we provided to it.
This combination dramatically reduces
hallucinations, overcomes context,
length limitations, and ensures your
transforms use latest frameworks and the
best practice from your organization.
Okay.
Let's talk about real world impact
First time savings organization doing
mainframe migrations have seen 70%
reduction in modernization timelines.
Tasks that used to take three to
five years are completely automated
quality improvements code plan
because it integrates with a
feedback loop with static analysis.
The transformations are.
Completely valid and preserves
the original behavior.
There are fewer manual errors
in large scale transformations,
higher confidence in the results.
Developer productivity developers
are free from repetitive error
prone task allows focus on high
value architecture and design work
enables non-experts to perform.
Code transformation as well.
Enterprise applications, packet
transformations across hundreds of
files, hundreds of repositories,
legacy code modernization, compliance,
and security updates at scale.
These are real use cases delivering
real business value today.
Future and challenges we need to be
honest about the current limitations.
Context, length still limits
extremely large code bases.
Some code bases are simply anonymous.
Model Ations is not
completely disappeared.
Their reduce, but validation
is still essential.
Repository scale analysis
is computationally heavy.
It's not free.
Complexity in handling dynamic
languages such as Python and JavaScript
is higher as we struggle with this
traditional tactic analysis with them.
Emerging trends.
One of the biggest emerging trends
is multi-agent systems where
multiple specialized agents have the
different parts of transformation.
Continuously learning from
developer feedback as to how
developers modify its output.
Integration with actual development
tools such as your id, CICD pipelines,
not just standalone processing.
I would like to conclude
with some key takeaways.
First, we are all, we are moving from a
line by line auto complete to a repository
wide reasoning from simple text generation
to structured planning with validation.
Neural approaches are pure LLM based on
neural approaches are being integrated
and made neuros symbolic hybrid systems
that combine the best of both words.
Planning frameworks that decompose complex
tasks, ad based understanding MULTICONTEXT
integration are some of the main aspects
which are enabling this transformation.
Line, AI powered large core
transformations are no longer a
theoretical or distant future.
They are achieving production ready
results on real world repositories.
Right now, this technology is transforming
what's possible in software engineering.
We are not replacing software developers.
We're amplifying or enabling
them to achieve more.
We are automatically.
We are automating what's repetitive
and error prone so that they can
focus on what's creative and strategy.
The future of software engineering
is at repository scale, intelligent
planning and powered by ar.
Thank you.
I.