Hi, my name is Hema and I work
as a release train engineer
in Tyler Technologies.
So my role is all around how
Agile works, scrum works.
So I am even like agile coach,
so I know in the real world how
Agile works and what problems we
face, what team problems will be.
I felt like AI can be useful in this area.
That's where I'm here with AI as your
agile, copilot, predictability, risk
aware, and human-centric delivery
in the age of prompt engineering.
So what are the problems
that right now Agile has?
Has like challenges, the
real, the reality gap.
Enterprise agile teams frequently
encount significant gaps between
strategic plan and actual delivery
outcomes leading to missed
deadlines and resource misalignment.
And the common pain points are sprint
overruns and missed commitments,
inaccurate effort estimate,
hidden dependencies, surface late.
Resource allocation will be insufficient.
AI beyond task automation, it can be
a strategic CoLab pilot, intelligent
planning and proactive risk detection,
how a strategic co-pilot works.
AI transforms from simple automation
to intelligent partnership, augmented
human development decision making
across the delivery life cycles.
Intelligent planning, so how this works.
Machine learning models analyze
historic patterns to enhance
backlog, refinement, and capacity
forecasting, proactive risk detection.
So how can AI help in this area?
Real time monitoring identifies
collaboration issues and burn
down signals and delivers blockers
before they get escalated.
So there are some AI driven capacity
models like skill alignment analysis,
seasonal productive patterns, historic
velocity data, productive success
rates, so we can better use them.
So it, it also helps in enhancing
sprint success, how the opportunities by
integrating AI powered capacity modeling
with traditional agile planning teams
can significantly improve their sprint
completion rates and estimate accuracy.
The key lies in combining machine
intelligence with human expertise
to create more realistic,
achievable sprint commitments.
How is that going to be helpful?
Predictive ANA analytics for agile
velocity forecasting where predictive
sprint capacity on team composition,
complexity patterns, and historical
performance trends can be delivered,
so can be derived multi-dimensional
prioritization, BA balance, business
values, technical dependencies, risk
factors, and resource availability
for optimal backlog sequencing.
And shortened planning cycles reduce
planning overhead while whitelist
improving accuracy through AI assisted
estimations and dependency mapping.
We are good that we have
the all predictability.
So how does it works actually?
Graph paste, backlog,
intelligence dependency mapping.
AI analyzes relation between user
stories, identify hidden dependencies
and cross team coordination needs
that traditional planning might miss.
If there is a human who is planning, they
might miss some parts of our dependencies
between cross-functional teams, but AI
helps us in that area and technical depth.
Visibility.
So the common problem that today's
Agile team mostly fails is they realize
there is a technical depth which is
hidden after too many sprints pattern.
So in this space, even AI can help us with
identifying the technical depths upfront.
So real time risk protection.
So NLP, power Insights, natural language
crossing analysis, standup notes,
comments and communications to detect
sentiment shifts and collaboration issues.
So in Agile, there is a most
common dysfunction that we observe.
The team don't communicate, so we can
have an AI as a spy or a help or a
coordinator, which can help us with that.
Then velocity tracking monitors,
sprint over sprint trends to identify
declining performance pattern before
they impact delivery commitments.
Then behavioral signals, track meeting
participation and collaboration patterns.
In a, as I there are too many
meetings and we don't know how
many of them are effective.
So AI can be can give us some
important notes out of that
meeting, which will help the team.
Then burnout prevention.
We might tend to overload a
particular person with lots of loads.
So AI help us identify this particular
person has so much load in the
current sprint, and he's expected
to work the same in the next sprint.
Then there's a chance of burnout.
So AI help us even to identify
the moods of the team.
In that case, cross-functional resource
optimization, intelligent as assignment.
So AI assisted resource allocation
enhances throughput by mapping team
member performance availability
and skill development goals
to optimal work assignments.
The system considers individual growth
objectives alongside delivery needs,
creating a balance between project
success and professional development.
So it helps with the core
functional resources as well.
Responsibility, AI adoption, transparency
frameworks, clear documentation of
ai decision making processes, ensures
steam understand how recommendations are
generated and can challenge assumptions.
Ethical guardrails, establish
boundaries around AI usage particularly.
Regarding team monitoring to
maintain trust and respect individual
privacy explainability models.
So AI must provide some clear reasoning
for their suggestions only that there
will be trust built with the team while
they take the suggestions of from ai.
Keeping humans in the loop
argument, not replacement.
So AI serves as a decision support
system, providing insights and
recommendations while reserving
human judgment and team anatomy.
Final decision still remains with humans.
We are not trying to
replace any human with ai.
We are just trying it to
be a helpful model for us.
Preserving team dynamics.
Successful AI integration strengthens
rather than undermines collaboration,
moral and psychological safety
within agile teams, the technology
supports the human elements that
make agile effective communication,
trust, and continuous improvement.
See your practical playbook.
Assess current state.
Start with pilot projects,
train and enable teams.
Iterate and improve.
The future of Agile delivery.
AI powered Agile isn't about
replacing human expertise.
It's about amplifying it By
combining machine intelligence
with human creativity, empathy,
and judgment, we create delivery
systems that are more predictable,
more resonant, and more humane.
I would like to thank each one of
you for giving me this opportunity.
As I say, AI is a helpful model, not
seriously replacing any humans, so we can
best use AI in our agile world as well.