Hello.
Welcome to this talk about how a large
language model took me on vacation.
My name is Erik Lijsma and I'm a senior
front end engineer at Soap Rasteria.
Today, I'm going to
take you on this story.
This is a story of my own, all of some
core insights I had working with AI.
Yeah, we're going to see what I've
learned from this interaction,
how it improved, my AI usage.
So it all started over a year ago,
when I started to use, JetGPT to plan
a holiday, a holiday trip for me.
it was not much travel
experience I had at that moment.
So I started to collaborate with
Chachipiti and tell me about some options.
And in the end, we went
to Porto in Portugal.
I always see this trip as the
start of my personal life with AI.
It has some impact there.
I had one of the best
holidays I've had so far.
And like I said, it was very nice because
we didn't have much travel experience.
And this Chachipiti collaboration really
took a lot out of my hands figuring
stuff out and giving us a carefree trip.
And I started to realize that AI
can really make a big impact on
the non digital world as well.
And not only for me, but
for every person's life as
well, if they want it or not.
During this trip planning, I found
out some, steps and realizations,
which I'm going to share with you.
So the first thing is about
understanding the technique.
while planning this holiday, this
trip, you start to notice that on
the trip, things work differently.
First of all, we were going to a country
with a different language, but also how
you approach getting your dinner, go over
your activities or your daily schedule.
These things work different
than they work at home.
they can be so fundamentally different
that you have to adapt to that.
If you do the things how you do them
at home, it's not going to work.
this is one of the understanding
parts for me that AI you should
also use, how it was meant to be.
How does an actual large
language model work?
And for me to understand how a large
language model worked really did a
big benefit on my, quality of output.
and we have already so many
times, but it's a language model.
And I don't think we
can emphasize it enough.
It's even in a name, a large language
model, but we are so easily deceived
by the power that AI has, that our
conscious filters, are easily bypassed.
First in the beginning.
And we probably all know and
remember this, the situation.
And.
We started to be very polite
to our interactions with AI
and with large language models.
Mainly because somewhere in the
back of our minds, we thought they
might gotta take over the world.
I rather be nice to them.
So hopefully they.
Be nice to me as well.
Then the other way around where
we would be direct and not as
nice, but getting good results.
But AI is still a language model
and context can change, but we
are easily deceived by that.
we often got the feeling that I, that
large language models have a more, have
more understanding, more knowledge,
but it has no absolute knowledge.
As an example where.
When we ask an, a JGPT who is the son
of Marilee Pfeiffer, it's going to
give us a pretty convincing answer.
Only it's not true.
Knowledge wise, this isn't correct.
It's no, it's not a fact.
It's the other way around, where,
Daniel Baldwin, this is him, is
not the son of Marilee Pfeiffer.
And by changing the context, because,
Marilee Pfeiffer is not that famous,
but her son is, and when we ask her
who is the mother of Tom Cruise, which
is the actual son of Marilee Pfeiffer,
it's telling us the right answer.
So this change in context already,
determined the knowledge it like the
AI has and how easily we are deceived.
We had the same with image and with image.
We have a natural filter.
When we see something,
we are eased more easily.
I'm noticing things are off.
So with images, it started to
use, very, weird and non logical
ways of showing fingers and hands.
And that's not nice.
So we started trading on those,
on those, things to make it look
wet better and have a nicer.
representation of a hands.
and we got better at it or the AI got
better in it and it got to understand it.
But in the meanwhile, for example,
roller coasters don't nearly get as
much, attention as hands and fingers, do.
So you see these images look very
natural, like very realistic.
only to see that they are not real
or possible or, based in reality.
And we see that and we feel that more
naturally that this is not reality.
And with text and it's harder
to get that context to see how
true to, to, to reality, this is.
And it's a particular
problem for text models.
And that's different than image,
video, or sound, sound models,
because this text is not natural.
image and the other things,
we naturally perceive them.
But text is something we had to learn.
and this is why this is
so big of a difference.
So in my preparation, I asked AI
to help me prepare a packing list.
here I got a reply that
had some formatting in it.
And this is one, learning for me that
understanding, to use formatting to,
give context or emphasize certain parts
of an text are, is really helpful.
It gives the model some structure to work
with and understand what's being asked.
And we can use this building blocks,
to give context to formatting.
Let me show you a couple of them.
to distinguish certain sections
of your prompt, we can use
different formatting tools.
For example, backticks to
highlight snippets of code,
triple quotes to distinguish
certain parts from other parts.
this is, an attachment or like the text,
I'm talking about a line separator to,
to distinguishing sections between your
prompt and heading with a column to show.
the next thing has some, is
related to this heading and list.
If there are unor or ordered.
They also give some
context to, to a section.
And this also goes for inline,
context and syntax context.
So here we're using a couple of the
same, items in a more inline, version.
So b can emphasize a path
or a certain variable.
quotes can highlight certain
sections of a sentence.
We can use placeholders like a name.
We can later on.
I fill in with the real person's name
or capitalization to really emphasize
that word or even special characters
to, to maybe get some comments or
clarification on certain parts, like
giving a key value relationship.
and XML text.
These are really, nice, especially in
Cloud AI by, by Anthropic XML text can
really emphasize what different sections
are about and label those accordingly.
Next to the formatting and, the way of
writing, you can also give some context
to, The certain approaches or prompt
engineering techniques you can add to
this, you can use to communicate with AI.
And here are some well proven prompting
techniques that, at this moment, during
that phase where I started to, go
on this trip, got to learn and, know
what they meant and how they work.
and let's go for a couple of them.
You're probably familiar
with the role prompt.
It's maybe one of the most
famous prompting techniques.
this is where you tell the AI to act in a
certain way by imitating a certain role.
And it looks like this, where you say,
Act as a fill in the blank and then ask
for a task that this, role would, fulfill.
I think it's a really nice,
prompt, but I think there can
be some improvements on this.
I will show that late later on.
Another prompting technique
is the unfinished chat prompt.
this really interesting, fun
and can be surprisingly useful.
I even got it by accident.
Some, sometimes.
this prompt focuses on building towards
a question and then by simulating
a chat with another person and then
stopping right at the moment where the
answer from the other person would be.
And then have the ai, continue
your, your chat message, with,
with the ex, with the answer.
So the next example here you can see
is, me wanting to, know how to change
my, dark and light mode on my phone.
And I'm submitting this chat with
an Apple support employee stopping
at the moment where the employee
is going to give me an answer.
and here it provides a clear answer
on, it has the context of a chat.
And in this context, it will
give me the right answer.
Another known one is syrup shot prompting.
This technique is just handing
over question without any examples.
For example, translate this into that.
and then it just go goes along.
but here, it's.
pretty obvious that with zero
shot prompting, you will also
have a few shot prompting.
And this technique, you'll have a
little bit more control over the
output by showing some examples.
So it continues that, that feel
and aesthetic of those examples.
but it can also be more fixed on too much
stuck on the examples that were given.
So at one of the mornings of our trip,
we wanted to get some pastries and we
asked the employee of the, of the hotel
to guide us to a local bakery, which
where we could get the local, pastries.
And he told us to go to the boulevard and
we went there on the sunny, summer day.
there was some music playing outside
and we entered the shop and the shop
was full with all kinds of pies,
cakes, and these different, pastries.
behind the counter was a bakery
and we started to pick like
which pie do we want to get?
And they all looked very tasteful.
this bakery was looking at
me often What do you want?
which pie do you like?
and then I ask him, give me the
recipe of your best apple pie.
And this feels weird, right?
Because if I ask a baker to act like
something, it's a different context.
and this context is for
us very understandable.
It's not suitable in this bakery.
It is not fitting, but in
language, it doesn't show that.
and this is what I like to
call implicit conversations.
So this sentence, give me lyrics
for a road trip song in the summer.
It is not as clear.
What is the context?
I can ask this to a child of 11 years
old and don't get really good results.
Or I can ask this to a big,
artist, a music artist.
Who can give me a really good lyrics.
so this sentence doesn't
convey that context.
Now, when I have this sentence,
the music you make is amazing, for
listening to while being on a road trip.
After five number one hits, what will
the lyrics of your new road trip song be?
And this will get a different result
of, lyrics and probably more high
quality result because this has way
more context inside this sentence.
so this is what I like to, do is to have
the context be part of the conversation
instead of always mentioning the
context or mentioning in context that
you maybe do not want like an actor.
it's not as good in the end result
is that the actual, profession he
is acting about, would do that.
And I hope this talk made you aware
of how important that context is
and some guidelines to use that
context to, engineer your prompt.
I'd like to thank you for your
attention and hope to see you next time.