Hello everyone.
It's a pleasure to be here to talk about
a topic that I'm very excited about,
prompt engineering for e-commerce ai.
Today I will be exploring how strategic
prompt design can harness the power
of AI to transform the tools we
provide to online sellers, and in
turn, enhance the customer experience
across the e-commerce industry.
By 2030, we envision a landscape
where a driven assistance are embedded
in every aspect of online retail,
and effective, prompt design will
be a key to making that happen.
For a AI to really drive this benefit,
we need to give it the right guidance.
And that's where prompt
engineering comes in.
What do I mean by prompt engineering?
Essentially, it's the practice of
grafting clear strategic instruction
or questions for an AA model so
that it produce the output we want.
Instead of treating the AI like
a block box, we guided step by
step with well-written prompts.
In e-commerce, AI isn't
just a nice to have anymore.
It's becoming a, it's becoming
a competitive necessity.
Companies are using AI across the board to
personalize the customer experiences, to
forecast the demand, to automate marketing
and logistic and more and much more.
And with the emergence of powerful
generative AI tools like Open As GBT
or like RO Cloud, even smaller sellers
can tap into AI for things like content
generation, answering customer questions
and making product recommendation.
But the effectiveness of all these
application hinges on how we prompt them.
If you give an AI a poorly word or vague
prompt, you will get a sub power result.
Conversely, your well designed prompt
can unlock incredibly useful responses.
In short, prompt engineering is essential
to leverage as power in e-commerce and
drive the real business value from it.
To structure our discussion today,
here is a overview of our agenda.
We'll start by looking at why prompt
engineering matters in this contexts.
Essentially, how good prompts
amplify the impact of e-commerce ai.
I will then start some prompt
strategies and best practices.
For example, a framework called CoStar.
To answer your prompts are effective.
We will dive into personalization
showing how prompt driven AI can
tailor product recommendation and
experiences for individual softwares,
and we will cover how AI can help with
inventory forecasting and dynamic price
optimization to improve operations.
There is lot to cover, so
let's drive in after that.
We will circle back to how AI can
generate content, things like product
listings and description and what kind
of issue o benefits that brings in.
Then we'll discuss conversational
commerce, which covers chat bots
and wise assistant, and how prompt
design guides those interactions.
Next, I also some of
the RIY and advantages.
And finally we will look into the future
outlook toward 2030, things like that.
Let's dive in.
Why does prompt engineering
matter so much in e-commerce?
AI put simply and a's output depends
directly on prompt guiding it, the
quality and relevance of what AI
produce are tied to how we ask for it.
If our instructions are vague
or poorly thought about, we
will likely get suboptimal.
S conversely, a clear, grafted
prompt, yield more useful outputs.
Prompt engineering also
allows us to inject our domain
knowledge into the as process.
We can incorporate our company's
specific expertise, our brand wise,
and context of our customers, right
into the prompt that makes the a
response more relevant and on brand.
Without that, the A might give
generic answers and don't quite
fit our business or audience.
We should also recognize that generative
AI is already transforming e-commerce.
New AA tools like GPT and Cloud are
enabling wide range of capabilities
from personalization, product
recommendation to automated content
generation and customer service.
Every major e-commerce player is
exploring these technologies because
they can dramatically enhance customer
experience and streamline operations.
By mastering prompt engineering
companies can truly harness
this generative AI revolution.
It lets you to take these
powerful AI models and aim them
precisely at your business.
Problems they pay off is better
customer experience, higher sales,
and more efficient operations.
In soft prompt engineering turns a generic
AI into tailored AI for your e-commerce
needs, which is why it is so crucial.
So how can we craft gra great prompts?
There are few best practices
and even frameworks to guide us.
One useful checklist goes
by an acronym, CoStar.
Which I will explain in a moment,
but let's start with simple general
principles First, it's important to set
constraints and be ready to iterate.
When I, when you write a prompt,
include any necessary limits or
requirements right in the text.
For example, if you need the a's
response to be under a hundred words,
or you wanted to avoid certain content.
Say that upfront.
Then treat prompting as
an iterative process.
Review a's output, and
refine your prompt if needed.
You might not get the perfect
answer on the first try,
but try tweaking the prompt.
You can hone in on a great result.
Next, consider using a
structured framework like CoStar.
To cover all key element of a prompt.
CoStar stands for context, objective
style tone, audience and response format.
It is basically a prompt
writing checklist.
Ensure your prompt addresses.
Each of these element can lead
to more on target results.
For example, context means
providing background information.
The AA should know objective means
stating clearly what outcome you are
looking for, style and tone referred
to the manner or voice you want.
The answer audience reminds you to
indicate who is the answer is for,
and response format means telling ai.
If you want a list, a narrative
bullet point or JSON format.
By covering all these bases, you
give the AI your well-defined job,
which usually means a better output.
Another best practice is to always
provide enough context and clarity.
If you are prompt is too short or
too vague, the A might fill in the
blanks in the way you don't intend.
So include relevant details.
For instance, rather than asking what
product should I recommend, you might
say you are a virtual assistant helping
a customer who likes outdoor activities
based on their browsing history.
What product would you recommend and why?
The second prompt use the ai, a role, a
background, and a specific task, and you
are more likely to get a useful answer.
This type.
This ties into defining the A's
role tone and style explicitly.
As I hinted, you can start a
prompt by setting a persona.
Finally, use examples and format
guidelines to steer the ai.
If you can show the
ai, what do you expect?
Even in a small way, it helps.
This could be as simple as providing
a sample output or explicitly saying,
please respond in three blood point.
For instance, you might
include in your prompt.
Here is an example of good answer, our
answer with a sort paragraph followed
by a bullet list of three key features.
Supplying these cues and prompts helps
the AI follow your content closely.
Remember, the AI can only do what we
ask it to do, so the more precisely
we ask, the better the results.
Now let's switch into some concrete use
cases, starting with personalization.
A powered personalization is indeed
changing the game in e-commerce.
With the latest generative models, we
can build very rich customer profiles
and deliver highly tailored product
recommendation and shopping experiences.
It's, it is as if each shopper
has their own personal assistant
guiding them through your store.
Here is how it works.
Sellers can incorporate
specific customer contacts.
And preferences us into
their prompt given to the ai.
For example, I could prompt an AI
with something like the customer
recently bought Running source and
has been browsing trial running gear.
Give that context, suggest three
other products that this customer
is likely to be interested in.
With a one sentence rationally for each.
By guiding the AI with kind of a detailed
contracts, it'll generate recommendation
that truly resonate with that
individual saw person's need and taste.
Each customer in effect gets suggestions
that feel handpicked for them.
This level of personalization increases.
Engagement and the likelihood
that the customer finds exactly
what they're looking for.
So what kind of impact
can personalization have?
The numbers are pretty impressive.
Retailers who excel at personalization
product recommendation have seen up to
40% higher revenue compared to those
who don't leverage personalization.
Customer loyalty and retention
are also a huge boost.
Some business report or 50% higher
customer retention rates when they get
personalization right, and personalized
suggestions often lead to bigger BA sizes.
Isis, for instance, one study
found roughly 10% increase in
average order value from the
effective product recommendation.
In short, personalization
isn't just nice to have.
It's a significant driver of business
results when customers feels like so
shopping experience is tailored to them.
They tend to buy more, stick
around longer and stay more loyal.
These data points underscore why investing
in a driven personalization is important.
Next, let's look at inventory
and demand forecasting.
Another area where AI combined with the
right prompts is making huge difference.
Traditionally forecasting demand was often
only about 60% accurate, but companies
that have adopted a driven forecasting
have significantly improved in that.
With accuracy rising to 80%, that's
a big jump, meaning you are predict
your prediction of what stock is
needed are much closer to reality.
As a result, you can align stock
levels much better with actual
customer demand, and when you
have a better handle on demand.
You avoid those detailed dreaded
stock stockouts, the situations
where a product runs out.
In fact, a driven forecasting has been
able to cut down stockouts by up to 65%.
In some cases, think about 65%
fewer out of stock messages.
That means customers are far more li, far
more likely to find the item they want
is available, which of course translated
to more sales, happier customer.
It is also worth noting that a
forecasting was in a much wider
range of data than traditional
methods, a human or legacy system.
Might look only at past sales trends, but
AI can factor in unstructured data like
social media, bus weather forecast, or
news events that could influence demand.
By analyzing these additional signals
alongside the historical sales, the
AI builds a more holistic view of
what might drive demand up or down.
This often leads to
more accurate forecast.
For example, you could prompt AI
given last year sales data and the
recent virtual, so social media
maintenance of our product predict
next month's demand for each category.
A well-designed a system will
consider both the past results
and the current social media trend
to produce a nuanced forecast.
It might catch, say that a surgeon
online interest will likely to
translate into higher sales next month.
Something a traditional
model would easily miss.
This kind of smarter context of
our forecasting is becoming a real
competitive advantage in retail
alongside the forecasting.
AI can help optimize pricing in real time.
Dynamic pricing means adjusting
prices on the fly based on various
factors, and AI can juggle all those
factors for better than a person can.
For example, an AI driven pricing model
will consider current inventory levels.
If a product is overstocked,
it might suggest a slight
discount to move it faster.
Whereas if the inventory is low
and demand is high, it could
recommend holding the price steady
or even nudging it up slightly.
It'll look at market trends.
If there is a surge demand for a
category or a seasoned seasonal
uptake, then AI reacts accordingly.
It'll monitor competitor pricing.
If competitive drops their price, a
can quickly advise a price adjustment
to stay competitive, and it can
even factor in customer sentiment
from reviews or social media.
For instance, if a product is getting
rave reviews and a lot of bus, the
AI might recognize that people are
willing to pay a premium for it.
Whereas the negative sentiment
might trigger a price drop
or a promotional offer.
By synthesizing all these inputs,
inventory, demand, competitor pricing,
sentiment, et cetera, a can suggest
an optimal price at any given moment
to maximize revenue or profit.
This level of tiny, big pricing
responds much faster to market changes.
Than any manual pricing team could.
It helps since you are not leaving
the money on the table during the
high demand and not stuck with
unsold stock during low demand.
In start.
AI driven dynamic pricing can
protect margins while also keeping
customer satisfied that prices
are far responsive to the market.
All these improvements in
forecasting and pricing ultimately
source up on the bottom line.
In fact, a study by Zi Company
found that companies using
companies using AI in their supply chain
and operations saw striking results.
They managed to reduce.
Inventory levels by 20 to 30% on
average, which means less capital tied
up in stock and lower storage costs.
They also cut warehousing
costs by about 15 to 20%.
Since with linear inventory,
you need to less space and you
can operate more effectively.
Logistic expense fell by a similar 15
to 20% as well due to a smarter routing.
And fewer last minute urgent shipments.
Perhaps more impressively, these companies
decrease stockout incidents by up to 65%.
This aligns with what
we discussed earlier.
Better demand forecasting means self
stay stocked with what customer wants, so
you capture more sales instead of losing
customer to an out of stock message.
They also reported improvements in.
Sell through rates.
All of these metrics
add up to a major ROI.
From A Driven Operations, you
are cutting cost in inventory
and logistic and simultaneously
increasing revenue by selling more
of what you are, what you stock.
It's great illustration that investing in
AI and pro engineering isn't just about.
Cool tech.
It has tangible business benefits from
efficiency guide to revenue growth.
Now sift our focus to content creation,
specifically how AI can generate
product listing and description
and what that means for ses.
As many of writing good
product copy for every item.
The titles, the description, the bullet
point features can be very time consuming.
Generative AI has gotten surprisingly good
at producing this kind of content today.
Instead of writing each description
from scratch, a seller can provide
an AI with a few key details, say
a list of feature, some keywords.
Or even an image and the AI
will draft a complete engaging
product listing for them.
It's like having a junior copywriter
working 24 by seven on your catalog.
The efficiency gains here are huge.
One small business reported that a cut
their product listing creation time from
60 minutes per item to just 15 minutes.
Imagine going from an hour of
human work to a quarter of an
hour with the AI assistant.
That's a 75% time saving, multiplied
across hundreds of thousands of product.
This is a MA massive boost in
productivity, and if it is not just
about speed, the AI content often
produce an Siva boost as well.
The AI naturally weaves in relevant
keyword to product copy, which helps those
listing rank higher in search results.
In one case, after switching to age and
listing, a retailer saw a 20% increase in
our kind of tracker to organic traffic and
about 15% higher sales for those products.
So the AI was effectively doing some
EO optimization on top of saving time.
AI can also enhance the shopping
experience in another base.
One example is summarizing
customer reviews.
Popular products might have hundreds
or thousands of reviews, far too
many for any shopper to read through.
A can help by reading all those
reviews and generating a concise
summary of common points.
Essentially, I produce a high highlight
reel of pros, cons, and recurring
themes that customers mention.
Another frontier of e-commerce
AI is conversational commerce.
Using chatbots and wise
assistance to engage customer.
This is all about making the
online shopping experience more
interactive and human-like.
Human-like through conversation for a
chat bot or a wise assistant To be truly
effective, it needs two things well
grafted prompts, driving its dialogue and
access to the right data in real time.
In other words, behind every helpful
chat bot response, there is a carefully
designed prompt or script and a connection
to UpToDate information like product
details, order statuses, or customer
profiles to ground that response.
When done right, the result is a
bot that responds in a very natural.
Helpful manner and can retrieve the
information it needs on the fly.
Retailers today are using
chatbots for more than basic FAQs.
These bots are starting to handle
fairly sophisticated tasks.
For example, a customer might
tell a chatbot, I am looking for
a gift for my 10-year-old niece.
She loves science kits.
The chat bot can ask a few smarter
follow up questions and then
recommend a suitable product.
It is not just about answering questions,
it's guiding product discovery.
These chat bots can also handle
upselling and cross-selling.
For instance, out helping you to find
a laptop for a graphic design, the bot
might suggest a compatible monitor.
Or a productive case, much like an
in-store sales assistant might do.
Analysts predict that by 2027,
a significant chunk of customer
service interaction will
be handled by AI chat bots.
As companies embrace their capabilities,
we are also seeing a shift from a
chat bot being used only for support.
Into being used as sales assistance.
Modern a h Bots powered by advanced
language models can maintain context over
multiple back and forth interactions.
They remember what the customer said
earlier in the conversation, which
shows the interaction to flow naturally
just like a human conversation.
These bots are getting
quite good at understanding.
Nuanced inquiries and
providing personalized advice.
It is not hard to imagine that soon
when you are on an e-commerce site.
The chat bot might feel as capable
as a well-trained human salesperson
who knows all the products.
In fact, some online retailers
have already moved beyond
basic customer service bots to
deeply sophisticated a agent.
That can handle anything from product
recommendation to closing a sale.
The common thread with both chat bots
and voice assistant is that their
effectiveness comes down to the prompt and
their design of their conversational flows
the better we design this interaction,
giving the AI clear instruction plenty
of context and access to the data.
The more helpful and natural the
experience become for the customer.
Now, to make these conversational
agent really effective, we have to
be smart about how we set them up.
In other words, how we engineer the
prompts and incorporate customer
data, one key strategy is to inject.
Relevant data into the prompt.
We also make use of system
roles and personas when
configuring these assistance.
This means we explicitly tell AI
what its role is on how to behave.
Another important topic is guiding the
a's action through the conversation.
We don't just let the bot.
Wing it entirely.
We provide a sort of conversational
blueprint, and we definitely want
the AI to maintain context and
reasoning throughout the conversation.
In practical terms, this means
as conversation goes on, we keep
giving the AI the relevant history.
When companies implement these
sophisticated AI assistance, they
are seeing measurable improvement
in customer related metrics.
For instance, a large set of
customer inquiries can now be handled
automatically by chat bots, especially
the routine repetitive questions.
On average, about 70% of.
Routine customer inquiries
can be handled or solved by AI
without needing a human agent.
Customer can get instant answer at any
time, and your support team is freed up.
Toggle the more complex issues.
There is also evidence that
having immediate AI assistance
during the shopping experience.
Process or reduces court amendment.
Some retailers have been roughly, yeah,
12% reduction in court amendment rates.
After introducing AA system
and more importantly, customer
satisfaction, CSAT tends to go up.
Softwares appreciate getting
quick, helpful services.
In fact, companies have reported that.
Their CSAT scores improving significantly
with a assisted support, in some cases
raging around 90 per 95% satisfaction.
Let's step back and talk
big picture for a moment.
Specifically, competitive advantage.
Adopting AI and prompt engineering
early can give your company a mood.
That late adapters will struggle
to cross being a first mover in
developing a strong AI and prompting
strategies yield compounding benefits.
You get to lean early IT rate
and refine what works over time.
You build up a library of
effective prompts and process that
are tailored to your business.
If a competitor waits a few years to
start, they will not only be playing
catch up on technology, but they will
miss all those hard earned lessons.
You have a accumulated.
In other words, the gap wides
and early adopters can pull
further and further ahead.
This dynamic is why we see so much
urgency among execution about ai.
In fact, roughly 80% of executives
expect AI to sign significantly,
transform their business in next few
years, and there are investing heavily
to make sure they are not left behind.
Those who integrate AI deeply into
their operations now will develop
expertise and data advantage
that become very hard to match.
The competitive gap will become, will
widen between companies building their
AI and data playbooks today, and those
sitting on the sites, the A model
themselves, are available to everyone.
But how you can use them can start you
to can set you apart your proprietary
customer data, plus your unique prompt
engineering know how, essentially form
a secret recipe that others can copy.
So embarrassing prompt engineering
early isn't just about short term wins.
It's about securing your
piece as a leader long term.
With AI capabilities that
become a true competitive mode.
Now let's look at to the future.
What might e-commerce a
tools look like by 2030?
A lot of experts predict that the
way we interact with technology in
retail will evolve dramatically,
and a will be the center of it.
One big change will be.
The rise of natural language interfaces.
We have touched on this idea.
Instead of using complex dashboard
or forms, we will interact with
our business systems by simply
talking or typing in plain language.
We also expect digital domains
of customers to become a key
digital domain is like a virtual
model of a customer built.
From all their data by 2030, companies
might maintain a digital twin for
each shopper, an a representation that
predicts their preference and behavior.
This would enable hyper-personalization.
Another concept is autonomous workflows.
This means end-to-end process in your
business that an AI handles automatically.
We already see.
Pieces of this yeah, auto recording stock.
So when inventory is low, but in the
future, entire multi-step workflows
might run with minimum human oversight.
We can't forget AI Coates for employees.
Think of an AI coate as a smart agent
working alongside your team or even.
Taking a certain task for operation
managers, omnichannel orchestration
will likely be powered by ai.
As the line blurs between online
and offline shopping, AI will help
ensure a seamless customer journey.
And finally, we'll see AI
providing perspective insights.
Routinely today, a lot of
analytics are descriptive.
A also will help very good at prescriptive
analytics telling us what we should do.
It would say, you are sales
are down 5% this week.
It'll add and I recommend
you to X to fix it.
This turns AI into not just an analyst,
but strategic advisor for business.
To make this future a bit more concrete,
let's zoom in on the idea of natural
language interfaces replacing dashboard.
Today, if a manager wants a specific
report or insight, they type,
they typically have to navigate
a dashboard or a run inquiry.
In some analytics tool, it's doable,
but often only those with some
training can get the data they need.
In the future, the manager might ask
an AA assistant in plain English or
whatever their preferred language.
And get answer with an explanation.
Begin the screens.
It might pull up last week sale data.
Identify the top sell list, and then
analyze various factors to answer why.
Maybe it finds that one of
the top products sold well,
because there was a promotion.
Another because of social media
posts went viral and so on.
All of that would come as a conversational
answer in second with no one having
to manually compile a report.
This kind of interfaces could
really democratize data access
within the organization.
So how do we get from today's capabilities
to that 2030 vision it requires.
Investing few key areas right now.
First, build prompt engineering
expertise on your team.
Upskill your people so they know how to
work with a tools craft effective prompts.
This might involve training programs or
work have focused on AI and prompt design.
Second, strengthen your data foundation.
A is only as good as the data its feed.
Take a hard look at ev, your
e-commerce data, product data,
customer data, sales, analytics.
All of it is it well organized?
Is it accessible to the AI when needed?
Are we capturing the right information?
Investing in clean and structuring
your data, perhaps integrating
your data system across will pay.
Huge dividend the third, adopt an AI
first culture within your organization.
Encourage your teams to ask how can
we use AI to dackle this problem?
Finally, start pilot project
and build a playbook.
By focusing on people skills, data
culture, and pilot project, you
will prepare your organization
to fully leverage prompt.
Prompt guided AI in coming years.
To wrap up, I would like to leave
you this thought By embracing prompt
engineering and weaving AI into
fabric of your operation, e-commerce
business can unlock unprecedented
gains in effective efficiency,
personalization, and competitiveness.
Thank you.