Hi guys, my name is Han.
Today we are gonna talk
about the prompt engineering.
This is one of the most
demanding skills for this ticket.
So let's start what we have today.
Okay, so today we are gonna talk about
what is the prompt, what is the prompt
engineering, how to write a good prompt
what is the technique we can use?
How to, how this prompt is evolved
and where what is a trend for
emerging trend for the prompt?
Okay?
And we'll see some of the cases,
studies as well as ethics and
responsibility of AI practice.
We are going to cover everything
in this today's presentation.
So let's start guys.
What is the prompt engineering?
So prompt engineering, basically I
use user give the inputs provided the
requirement, prompt, document that or
structure that instructions and provide
this detail to the a, a l process,
the data and generate the output based
on the instruction of provided by the
prompt and you will get the result.
Based on the instruction you've given.
So that is in simple way we can
say it's a prompt engineering Now.
What, let's understand more
about the prompt engineering.
Prompt engineering is not only
the art, it's art and science to
generate your desired results.
Why we call art, because it give you
the desired results and why we call
it science, because if you have to
have, provide the clear cut instruction
structure and context of background
behind that, we have to remember one thing
better, the input and better the quality.
Otherwise you'll not get a good
response if do not have the good.
Prompt.
Can be, prompt, can be for in any form,
text, visual and audios can be provided.
The input can be provided in any form.
Okay.
Visual, audio and codes.
So let's see how this
prompt engineering works.
So we have to understand the
concept for the prompt engineering.
But before we go and talk about
more about the prompt engineering,
we need to understand what is the
LLM Large language model, which is.
The heart and key of the this one.
So next couple of slides, we are going
to see how this prompt has evolved and
we're gonna talk about the LLM as well.
So let's see how the
prompt has evolved in 2020.
There was a keyword prompt.
There, is there, sorry,
there is a keyword prompt.
We just give the inputs
through the prompts and just
hope for the best results.
Okay.
Then we see the then we see the 20,
21, 22, a few short examples or come.
So it means like you provided some
of the example template to the.
To the AI or prom based on that example.
In template, it'll generate the response.
Then the role based or chain of thoughts
has been evolved in 20 23, 20 24.
So AI can be act as a role act, act
as a plays a role or persona act as
a analyst, act as a manager, and and
can provide the response accordingly.
Then it's further announcement has
happened, the chain of thought,
thinking about the logical
step-by-step process, and it'll
provide you the, provide the outputs.
And then multimodal prompts where we talk
about the the text, audio and different
types of, can be considered as an input.
This oral, we are gonna discuss
in next couple of, next couple
of slides where we are gonna talk
more in detail about that one.
This is the, just a history
of how the prompt is evolved.
Okay, now let's go and talk about
LLL as we discussed earlier.
Large language model, it's basically,
basically the data which can be provided
in any form, text, images, speech.
The large set of data has been pointed.
Provided, and it's been
trained, this clean data will be
stored in the vector database.
This is typically is the function
of the large language model.
So large language model is the source
for your AI to generate the data.
This is what the this is, this is the
feature of the ai, which can be develop,
developed through the deep learning
method we are using to develop the AI
and develop this large language model.
And which, if we are going,
which is used frequently used
by for the prompt engineering.
For the prompt, let's
seek couple of examples.
Are there, okay.
Like we all knows about, or most of
the works are using the chat g, pt, and
other AI based prompt engineering tools.
So chat, GPT is also used.
The LLM large language model.
It is a 2.5 trillion parameter,
used two huge dataset to perform the
different multiple types of functions.
Similarly, the bot, it's
another one LLM model.
For prompt engineering, it used
the three 40 millions of parameter
to provide the desired results.
So Google, Germany is another one example,
which is developed by the Google mine.
This all are the.
All of the example of the state
of the art will provide you the
very good, accurate results based
on the LLM has been developed.
So now let's go further.
There was one case study was AI
powered Financial Reporting Chatbot.
So have author one of the article AI
Reporting Financial Chatbot, which you
can find out on as per the below link.
So we have implemented this
for our clients or customers.
So after implementing, we see
the 65% productivity key in 94.
94% of reporting accuracy and the
significant faster performance we saw.
When you have time, let's go
through this article and read it.
You will get more insight
about the article.
Now, what is a prompt?
We need to understand the prompt before
we talk about the prompt engineering more.
The prompt is nothing but
it just a call of action.
Call to action.
What is a call to action is you tell to
the AI how what to do, how to do, and
sometimes we need, say what to avoid.
To get the desired output,
that is called a prompt.
So prompt engineering, why
the prompt engineer matters.
The nowadays the AI is used by or
prompt ai, use AI and prompt and
used by almost in all the sectors,
especially the, when you have to write
a good detail or documents or research,
paper, law, healthcare, business, or.
Significantly using this one.
But we have to remember, in order to
get to write a good good documents
and document, we should have, the
good LLM or large language model
has to be developed accordingly.
So good data input will
give you the good results.
Okay, so better input
is the better output.
Not only the, so we have to
see the quality of the prompt.
Good quality prompt will
give the good results.
Bad quality prompt will
not give the good results.
It'll give you the give the bias
information and it'll waste your time.
This one, so we have to focus we'll see
some of the examples in the see how the
good and back prompt will impact the work.
Okay, so this is what you have to
remember this to talking to when you're
talking about the prompt engineering.
You have to remember when you
like how to talk to the ai.
So the language is, it is
called a prompt engineering.
It is the prompt, the language
which you're using effectively
communicating to the ai.
So let's see.
Why effective prompts are important.
Effective prompts is important because
if without the effective prompt
there is it'll directly influence
your quality with the AI response.
If you do not have the good prompt,
you're not get good response.
Crafted prompt will give you the
desired results what you're looking for.
That one, that is why the
importance of the prompt is there.
Now, let's see some of the examples.
Good versus bad prompt.
You can see here if you go and
just give the instruction, explain
the ai, help ai, so it is a very
weak the scope is very high.
You'll not get the results,
you'll get a very generic
results or output of this one.
But in order to give us a good
instruction to the prompt, okay, you,
if you mention explain AI in a hundred
words using the simple language, it is
a, it'll give you the desired results
and with the specific limitation.
So this is one of the
example and another example.
If you say, tell me
about the cybersecurity.
This is again, a little bit weak.
You're not talking, you're not specific
because cybersecurity could be the
plenty of information available.
What you're looking is not very clear.
But if you want to make it the good
prompt, you can say, list of three, common
cybersecurity threat, or explain how this
micro Microsoft defender mitigate them.
Similarly, you can ask like.
Prompt, if I can you
write the email for me.
It's very generic.
But if you ask them to play the
role or act as a project manager and
draft the email repetitive response
based on the highlighted uncertain
points, you'll get a better results.
So these are the example purpose of
this example to show to all of you.
Prompt see how you will give the
input or instruction based on that.
You'll get the response.
So we have to learn about how do
you need to provide the provide the
the prompt or details to the ai.
So in order to get the good results.
So let's check it.
See.
So the best way to to give the input
to this one, you should remember this.
Four points.
Okay.
So we should provide the context or
the background of the work, of work,
what background, what you're doing
context to the ai, and then the provide
the task information, what you want.
AI or prompt has to respond back to you
and then provide the constant what are
the limitations are there If you have
limitations so that you should provide.
And similarly, to provide any additional
information which you want to do.
See here the, one of the
example is highlighted here.
The marketing manager like suppose, okay,
so you are the marketing manager for the
few new product launch in FMCG sector.
This example is talking about
you are providing the background
about the marketing manager
belongs to the certain sector.
So this will give us a will help
us move to get a good results.
Similarly, we.
To perform that good ta we AI to
perform the task more efficiently.
So now the example is written here,
the right is short paragraph that
describe the target audience for the
product and the key marketing messages
that will be resonate with them.
So this is the task, what
you've given after providing.
The background and the task.
You give it with the example, and then
you're putting the constant on that one.
The response should not be more than one
50 character and should be focused on
the most important marketing messages.
So now you're limiting and
providing the constant one 50 words
and focus on the certain areas.
And then additional information like
the product is washing liquid for
the washing machine, targeted for
the urban and semi-urban households.
So with the help of this type of
structure once you provide to the prompt,
you'll get a very accurate answer.
So keep in mind this formula, the
context towers, constant extend function.
This is very helpful to provide
the structure, form detail to get
a better results from the prompt.
Okay.
You can remember a few of the works for
the prompt engineer, which will help
us to give us a more accurate results.
Like Act S you can, this
is a persona pattern, okay?
So where you can ask LLM or ask AI to be,
act as a manager, analyst, specialist.
So we'll give you the better result.
When you say ask for the analysis,
he'll provide you the more
detailed analysis of the certain.
Certain detail which you're looking
for, this specific field summarize
when you asked to summarize
today, I use this word summarize.
So then here to summarize for
you in the way you're looking for
multiple information in in the
summary statement, the way you want.
So use this word, this
words are very helpful.
Generate.
So it'll generate the output, the
way you're looking, the based on
the ideas or the details it's given.
So it generate the new ideas as,
as well as the concept for you.
So use this so it'll help you predict.
So based on the current place,
the data level, he will predict.
Or train for you.
So you can use this word, this, these
are the words which will help you to give
a more record results, elaborate more.
So you can have asked to AI to
elaborate more in simple language.
So on particular topic, on particular
point, on a specific specific area.
So it'll help you to give
us a desired results simply.
And the last one is nothing but
more than like simply simplify.
So it can provide the result
in the simple language so
everyone can understand easily.
So these are the power works.
Along with what we saw, how to write
a prompt along with this power box, if
you can use that will be very helpful
for you to get the good results.
So now let's go to the next one.
So there are core, prompt techniques.
There, there are many techniques which
can be used to get the better results.
There are a few techniques are
listed here, like role prompting
as we already talked about.
We can ask AI to be act as a pm
act as a lawyer, act as analyst.
So these are the few examples there.
Role-based prompting.
So can we play the role and give
the good results chain of thought.
It's a step by step process
the way human think.
You can provide the instruction and
you can expect that result as per the.
As per the instruction given, so it
can solve your complex problem, I
think with the step by step process.
So you should know how to
instruct to the prompt.
So this is the chain of thought.
We can use the technique to get the better
results You could have multiple time.
You need to give the instruction
like step by step process.
First time you give certain instruction
based on the output, you will go
the second set of instruction.
Then third set of mention.
I will give you the good
results based on that one.
All together come by few short is just
another one case where you can provide
the example based on the example, AI or
prompt will return you the the response.
Zero short nothing but just a
straightforward just to provide the
instruction based on the instruction
able will like a response back to you.
So these are the core pro technique.
Which you can use for to get
a, get the better results.
So we see so far the three way.
Okay.
You can use the provide the
context, background information,
more details to them, okay?
And we can use the the power ws
as well as we can use this prompt
technique to get the good results Now.
The prompt quality.
Okay.
When we are talking about the prompt
quality, we have to remember one
thing garbage in, garbage out.
So good prompt will give the good results.
Bad prompt will give the bad results.
Before, before we like what, for
what is the best way to provide
the details to the prompt.
Keep in mind the goal and audience first.
Okay?
Keep it.
And then accordingly, you can provide the
information, provide the more background
and data point as much as possible as
a part of the format, what we talked
about, background context, this one,
and to how to mention very specifically,
you need the desire in which format.
You need the bullet points
summary, PPT or Word document.
They, the AI will be
generate all this for you.
Add the restriction because
you're not adding the restriction.
It'll be the open in it.
Either the length.
Okay.
Tone, perspective or any other thing,
which you are looking a specific
thing from as a part of your response.
So these are some of the points
which you need to be which you
want to make sure you are using.
This, keep in mind this
point for using the prompt.
Okay.
For accuracy to avoid any biasness.
No.
We talked about prompt.
We see how to write the prompt, but if
you, we see some of the good example, good
and bad example, how to write the prompt.
So there is success story based
on the prompt engineering after
evolving of the prompt engineering.
There are a few example,
I'm, we are gonna talk today.
There are plenty of them
are available if you to.
Go and search through the AI
or go in Google, you'll find
so many examples as there.
One of the, one of the examples of most
of the customer support or fortune fin
aid companies using the AI assistance
or chat bot for chat bot and a other AI
for ticket resolution, we see the 14%
increase on their average resolution.
Similarly, the MIT able to with the
help of structure form, they're able
to produce the better research articles
and documents, so the quality is
significantly improved and save the time.
Also.
Similarly the PCG has like b, c, G
mentioned, like even the non-technical
people can solve the complex
problem with, because of the prompt
engineering is available because of
the prompt, good prompt is available.
So this is another one cases there.
Okay.
And we see the McKensey has developed the
product library, which can help us to go
code receptor and identify the root cause.
It saves significant time
as well as money for them.
So these are the few
success stories out there.
Many more could be there.
This is the like, how to use the prompt.
So you will, you really get
a good results of the prompt.
Now let's review some
of the story, which is.
The failure cases.
So as I mentioned earlier, okay,
the garbage in, garbage out.
If you do not have the good LLM okay,
and you do not have the the good LLM,
then you'll not get a disaster if
you don't know how to use the prompt.
Also, in that case also the, it
could be the case of failure.
So one of the airline, chatbot,
give the example like, give the
misleading information to the customer
and the lawsuit has been filed and
the airline paid the huge penalty.
This is one of the information
we are using the the chat bot,
because might be the chat bot
given the misleading information.
It's not trained properly.
With the LLM, this is one of the example.
The another one, the sensitive data leak
example is happened where someone is.
Accidentally share the code
to code confidential code with
the, with open AI or with the
with the prompting engineering.
Okay.
So that become the issue.
And then later on the organization, block
the chat GP within their own organization.
One of the, one of the very, very
interesting case with the terms
of service agreement has been,
updated by by by automated ai
and they have mentioned on that.
The the chatting and other information,
customer information can be used to
train to the AI without their concern.
Consent.
So this has, again, become a big issue.
It was came in the news also.
Article.
So then later on they have
automation corrected, that problem.
The one, another one thing
the, if you're using the AI to,
for like example for hiring.
Okay.
So one of the case, what happen
in hiring the the AI will.
Was a bias and providing the
information based on the age insects.
Okay?
And that could create the issue.
So later on, this has been blocked
by the Ian who are using that ai.
So this one, so you to remember
when we are getting the.
The benefit of the AI that we
could have the issues, also the ai.
So how to use, what
process we need to use.
What is the ethical way of working?
How to write the prompt
to get the good results.
We have to make sure every time
we need to validate that results.
Since you see some of the cases of failure
and success, and we earlier saw some
of his example of good and bad prompt.
This could be the cause of
the success and failure.
Now let's go and see.
So we so far we talked about lots of
things about the prompt, how to write
now, how to write the prompt and now
see looks, how, where the trend is going
now, future trend we are talking about.
So ums.
Like we need to, like in the next,
next 24, next three, four year,
you will see the more governance
will be coming to the picture.
Talking about the more about the
standard audit more audit is going
to happen because it, AI can be used.
According to governance and audit
has to be happened to make sure the
accuracy of the AI to avoid any issues.
AI going to further going to use,
like that's a multi-agent going
to closely going to work with the
copilot that is q See it's in, it's.
It's, we'll see in the next 20.
You only going to see in the next four
to five year it's going to more, you'll
see the progress on that one multi-model.
We already using text, images, and audio.
Now you'll see the started combination
of that one be it's coming in the future.
Ai so.
Can be given the instruction on multiple
modes together and get the response in
a different way, the way you're looking
and the most important dynamic learning.
So it can be, AI can be learned as
on the fly adoption that you see
this changes is going to happen
in the next three to four years.
This is the trend.
Now let's take a pause here and
because we talked a lot about the
prompt, so what we covered so far.
Okay.
We talked about what is
a prompt engineering.
We talked about what is a prompt,
how to write the quality prompt.
We talked about provide the good
detailed background context.
This one.
Pick the pick.
We can.
Use a different technique.
We talked about like chain of thoughts,
prompt and other techniques can be
used for writing the good prompt, what
tool and framework we need to use.
And and most important thing about
this one, the ethical part, which we're
going to cover in the next couple of
slides, like how to, what could be the
how do we need to work and how do we
human need to validate all these ones?
So these were the, so
far, the key takeaway.
Let's go forward.
So ethical, we are working,
so we have to remember.
AI will give you the lots of input.
So you should be transparent
with your client customer or
anyone whom you're working.
If it is if it is ai, AI contributed
work, you need to mention
clearly it is AI generated work.
It could be edited by
you after generation.
Taking the help from the AI is
not a bad thing, but you should
be transparent about that one.
Communicate accordingly.
Avoid claiming the AI genetic
content belongs to you.
Clear.
Please make it big.
Be clear.
Okay.
And to your client, customer, or anyone?
Like it is the age united contract.
So you can, you, it should be good
for everyone if you mention this one.
So we talked about this one and.
We should not use the unbiased
wording while writing to the prompt,
because that's very important.
This is the basic ethics we have to
follow while using the prompt for for ai.
So we should, we all are responsible
for following the ethics and develop
the good community to how to use the ai.
Okay.
Now let's see.
Governance and safety.
We already talked a little bit about
in the previous slide about the
government governance and safety.
We have to be very clear
about how to handle the data.
So some or and retention policy that has
to be defined very clearly within the
organization as well as outside work.
So we should have rules
and regulations should win.
Place to avoid the misses of the policy.
Train your team or train
your peers colleague.
On other members who is using
this one ethical way of working.
Okay.
And make them responsible for the
good, using the prompt accordingly.
So output, AI generated output,
it's, and make sure you are verifying
that AI generated output it.
Can be a bias based on the LLM is there.
If you not human need
to verify that output.
Otherwise it'll be, so we have
to make sure all the AI generated
content has to be verified by human.
So you have to crosscheck with this one.
So this is what the most
important thing for the governance
and safety point of view.
Now, the, all the data presented in this.
Presentation are you can see the reference
and data sources are available here.
So it's all the data we are presented from
the certified places we pull the data.
So it's talking about that.
Now I want like when to talk
more about what, how the prompt
engineering impacting your work.
Okay.
Or your current workflow.
How your what is your experience
about the prompt engineering?
We'll talk about some time and we'll take
some of the question about HL policy and
what should be the perfect prompt for you
and how is your experience about this one?
So let's talk sometime during our meeting.
We'll more deep dive about this one.
So look like I have covered
most of the stuff here.
I think so.
We are good for now.
If you have any question,
please post the message to me.
We'll try to answer that question.
Thanks for joining.
Thanks everyone.
Thank you guys.