Welcome, everyone, and thank you
for joining this session on ethical
considerations in educational technology.
I'm Santosh Kumar Pulijala, a senior
NET developer in HCL Global Systems.
Today, we will explore the
exciting innovations in
edtech and discuss the ethical
responsibilities that come with them.
In this session, we are going
to look into the introduction
to educational technology.
Key technological innovations, the promise
of edtech, and all the concerns that
we have, like ethical concerns, privacy
and data protection concerns, equity and
access, transparency and accountability,
digital being and screen time concerns.
And we are going to dive deep into
responsible implementation strategies.
First, let's look into the
introduction to educational technology.
Educational technology, or edtech,
rapidly transforms classrooms and opens
up opportunities for more accessible,
tailored, and engaging learning.
It has become a powerful
tool in the modern classroom.
As of 2020, this sector was
valued at nearly 90 billion.
And is protected and is projected
to grow almost 285 billion by 2027.
This significant growth reflects a
global shift towards digital learning
driven in part by the COVID 19 pandemic,
which made remote education a necessity.
Over 94 percent of countries implemented
remote learning solutions with About
60 percent adopting online platforms
at various educational levels.
The result is a more accessible
learning experience and a promise
of improved educational outcomes.
However, these advancements
also pose challenges.
Questions about how to protect students
data, ensure equitable access, and
uphold the quality of education.
across diverse communities.
As we advance, establishing ethical
guidelines and governance in edtech
becomes essential to protect the
rights and well being of students,
parents, and educators alike.
With this in mind, let's examine the
key technological innovations in EdTech
Innovations are transforming how we
approach education with artificial
intelligence, virtual reality, and
data analytics at the forefront.
AI and machine learning have introduced
adaptive learning platforms, intelligent
tutoring systems, and automating
automated grading, all of which
personalize learning experiences.
For instance, adaptive
learning has shown a 2.
5 times increase in students math skills
by tailoring content to individual needs.
Virtual and augmented reality, which
is VR and AR, have opened immersive
learning avenues, making abstract
concepts tangible, which improves
engagement and retention by as
much as 7 percent data analytics.
Often integrated into learning
management systems, enable real
time tracking of student progress,
Allowing educators to respond
swiftly to individual learning needs.
These advancements are powerful, but
we must implement them thoughtfully
to avoid potential pitfalls.
For example, AI driven systems
should be transparent and unbiased,
while VR tools must be accessible
and not overly intrusive.
Now let's look at the broad
promise EdTech holds for learners.
The promise of EdTech.
The promise of educational
technology is immense.
By leveraging ed tech,
we are moving towards.
More personalized learning where AI
and machine learning tailor lessons to
individual student progress, allowing
them to learn at their own pace.
Immersive experiences made possible
by virtual reality and artificial
reality help bring complex ideas to
life, making learning not only more
engaging, but also more effective.
Data analytics are transforming teaching.
Providing a real time insights that
enable educators to adapt their lessons
and support each student's unique needs.
The statistics back this up.
Adaptive platforms can increase math
skills by almost 250 percent and
immersive VR experiences have been
shown to improve test scores by 7%.
Despite these benefits, the ethical
challenges we face cannot be overlooked.
We must work to ensure this technology
is accessible, safe, and fair.
Let's take a closer look at some
of the ethical concerns, beginning
with privacy and data protection.
Ethical concerns in education technology.
While the benefits of edtech
are clear, We must also address
the ethical concerns it brings.
First and foremost, privacy and data
protection are significant concerns.
As edtech tools collect vast
amounts of data, the risk
associated with unauthorized
data access and breaches grow.
Equity and access are
another critical issue.
Many students, especially in low
income or rural areas, face a
digital divide that limits their
ability to benefit from these tools.
Transparency and accountability
are essential as well, especially
when it comes to AI driven systems
that impact students as well.
Especially when it comes to AI driven
systems that impact students evaluations.
and learning paths.
We also need to consider digital
well being as excessive screen
time can have negative effects on
students mental and physical health.
As we dive into each of these
topics, we'll discuss ways to
address these challenges and create
an edtech environment That is both
innovative and ethically responsible.
Now let's look into privacy
and data protection.
Privacy and data protection are
vital components of ethical ed tech.
Educational institutions must
comply with data protection
regulations, such as FERPA.
Full Form is the Family Educational
Rights and Privacy Act in the U.
S.
and GDPR in Europe, General Data
Protection Regulation, which
outlines standards for managing and
safeguarding student information.
However, compliance alone isn't enough.
EdTech tools gather a significant
amount of sensitive data, such
as academic records, attendance,
and even behavioral information.
This creates vulnerabilities,
especially in low income countries
where data protection laws may
be insufficient or non existent.
Cyber security threats are on the rise.
408 cyber incidents were reported in U.
S.
schools in 2020 alone, making an 18
percent increase from the previous year.
To combat these risks, schools must
invest in robust security measures
and provide clear privacy policies.
Protecting students data
isn't just about compliance.
It's about creating a safe digital
environment for all students.
Where students parents and educators
can trust the technology they rely
on now Let's look into equity and
access Ensuring equitable access to
technology is essential in net tech.
The digital divide remains significant
challenge with only 25 percent of
students in low income countries have
access to digital resources, compared
to 96 percent in high income countries.
This gap means that millions
of students are left out of
digital learning revolution.
Accessibility extends beyond income level.
Students with disabilities also
face barriers when a tech platform
lack necessary accommodations.
Furthermore, biases in AI algorithms
can reinforce existing inequalities,
necessitating careful oversight.
For instance, in the U.
S., around 43 percent of households with
incomes under 30, 000 lack home broadband,
limiting their access to digital learning.
Bridging these gaps requires a
collective effort from policymakers,
educators, and developers.
We must invest in infrastructure,
develop inclusive technologies and adopt
policies that make digital learning
resources available to every student.
Now, let's look into
transparency and accountability.
Transparency and accountability.
In AI systems, as AI systems become more
embedded in education, transparency and
accountability must be top priorities.
For AI to be a trusted tool in education,
its decision making process need to be
explainable, especially in high stakes
scenarios like student evaluations.
A recent study showed that 63 percent
of parents are concerned about
algorithmic decisions in impacting
their children's academic assessments.
The black box nature of AI, where complex
algorithms make decisions without clear
reasoning can be a problematic leading to
issues with fairness and accountability.
Ensuring human oversight is critical.
In fact, 86 percent of teachers believe
AI systems need a human element to
guide decisions and address any biases.
For example, the controversial algorithm
used in the UK for A level grading
disproportionately downgraded students
from disadvantaged backgrounds.
Establishing clear guidelines
for human oversight.
And algorithmic transparency is crucial
to build trust and safeguard the
integrate, integrity of AI in education.
Now, let's look into digital
well being and screen time.
Digital being is an often overlooked
yet vital aspect of a tech.
With increased screen time, it's essential
to balance digital and traditional
learning to protect students cognitive
development and physical health.
Studies show that children who spend over
two hours a day on screens tend to score
lower on language and thinking tests.
Additionally, prolonged screen use
can lead to issues such as eye strain,
poor posture, and mental fatigue.
Schools that promote digital literacy
and educate students on managing
screen time see tangible results,
including a 40 percent reduction
in cyber bullying incidents.
To support students well being, schools
should offer mental health resources,
limit unnecessary screen time, and
incorporate digital citizenship programs.
Ultimately, digital literacy skills
help students navigate online risks and
misinformation, promoting a healthier
and more balanced approach to technology
use in their educational journey.
And now let's look into responsible
implementation strategies.
A responsible approach to ed
tech implementation involves
several key strategies.
Data governance is fundamental.
Clear data policies, regular audits,
and dedicated privacy staff help
safeguard student information.
Equity and inclusivity should guide
every decision, with investments in
infrastructure to close the digital
divide and ensure that digital resources
are accessible to all students.
Transparency in AI is also very crucial,
requiring explainable algorithms and
regular bias audits to uphold fairness.
Lastly, promoting digital well being
calls for balanced screen time,
mental health support, and digital
literacy training for students.
Each stakeholder has a role.
Policymakers must prioritize
comprehensive data privacy laws.
Educators need ongoing tech training
and an ethical approach to tool
evaluation, and developers must
adopt privacy by design principles.
By working together, we can ensure
edtech support students learning while
upholding their rights and well being.
Okay, let me conclude this topic.
In closing, the integration of
technology in education offers
incredible possibilities from
personalized learning and immersive
experiences to real time data insights.
However, that benefits come with ethical
responsibilities that cannot be ignored.
Protecting student privacy, bridging
the digital divide, ensuring transparent
AI, and promoting digital well being
are all essential steps to create
a responsible EdTech environment.
As we continue to innovate, let's commit
to these principles, ensuring that
technology not only enhances learning,
but does so in a way that is fair,
safe, and accessible for all students.
By taking a proactive, ethical approach,
we can make a positive, lasting
impact on the educational landscape.
Creating a future where technology
and human values work hand in
hand to benefit every learner.
I really want to thank you for
your attention to this topic.
And if you have any questions, or
concerns, you can always reach me on
LinkedIn at Santosh Kumar, space Pulijala.
Thank you so much.