Hello, everyone.
I'm Modi and I'm excited to talk
with you today about how we can
improve AI and network security using
technologies like Kafka, secure proxies.
and modern software architecture.
As we depend more on data and connected
systems, making sure they are secure and
reliable becomes even more important.
Today I'll go over some of the topics
here and we'll understand more about
AI and Kafka's presence in the AI.
So introduction to AI and Kafka
for real time data processing.
And we'll go through the key features
of Apache Kafka for AI workloads, the
real time AI use case powered by Kafka,
securing AI data pipelines with secure
proxies, and how to integrate AI workloads
with Kafka Connect, and how to implement
zero trust architecture with Kafka.
Before going this, we'll understand
what is zero trust architecture.
And a case study on AI and Kafka in
action and we'll go through some best
practices, industry best practices for
building secure, scalable AI pipelines.
Okay, let's start.
So and again by the end of this
talk, you'll see how these tools
work together to create a strong
foundation for AI and secure networking.
Okay, let's get started.
So the growing need for real time AI So
as technology advances, there is a rising
need for AI that operates in real time.
If you notice, we are no longer
just storing and processing
data in large batches.
Now, industries like finance, healthcare,
manufacturing, and e commerce rely on
AI to make instant decisions, anomaly
detection, and natural processing
language based on the live data.
So think of fraud detection banking
where AI systems need to flag unusual
transactions as they happen or in
a healthcare where real time AI
can support doctors in making quick
informed decisions during surgeries.
When it comes to Kafka role, Apache
Kafka is a powerful tool for handling
high speed data streams in real time.
Essentially, it acts as a central hub
that gathers, stores, and distributes data
continuously with high throughput, which
is crucial for real time AI applications.
In a real time AI, data needs to move
from multiple sources, sensors, using
user interactions, and internal systems.
to the AI models instantly.
Kafka allows this by processing
data as it's created,
enabling real time decisions.
For example, in an e commerce application,
Kafka can track every click and
purchase in real time, so AI models can
instantly recommend real time decisions.
products or spot potential fraud and
Kafka also supports secure and reliable
data handling with features like
data replication and fault tolerance.
Kafka makes sure data flows
smoothly, even when issues arise.
And, there are like challenges in
the traditional systems, right?
So traditional systems are often
built around batch processing,
where data is collected, stored,
and then processed at set intervals.
So this approach for certain use
cases But it's a, yeah, it's good
for certain use cases, but it's a
big limitation for the applications
that need real time insights, right?
for example, in fields like finance and
healthcare, Delays in data processing
can mean missed opportunities or
even risk to security and safety.
Another major challenge
is scalability, right?
So traditional systems can struggle
to keep up as data volumes increase.
often becoming slow and requiring
costly hardware upgrades.
This makes it hard to scale applications
that rely on constant data flow, like
live monitoring or, predictive analysis.
Kafka addresses these challenges
by using a distributed and
scalable architecture that allows
for real time event processing.
talk about the key features of
Apache Kafka for AI workloads.
Apache Kafka is an ideal
choice for AI applications.
To support real time AI and advanced
analytics, We need tools that can
process and analyze data as it
flows and without any delays, right?
So that's where Kafka Stream
Processing API and ksql come into play.
Both are designed to handle real time data
streams effectively, enabling instant data
transformation, filtering, and analysis.
So Stream Processing API and ksql.
So let's.
discuss more about this.
So this feature Allows developers to
create sophisticated data pipelines
for AI tasks such as a real time
sentimental analysis anomaly detection and
predictive maintenance So when it comes
to stream processing API, particularly,
and this is a powerful API within
Kafka that allows us to build custom
applications that process data streams.
With this API, we can perform
complex operations like joining
streams, aggregating data, or even
transforming messages as they're mixed.
For example, in a real time fraud
detection system, The stream processing.
A PA could be used to continuously
analyze transaction patterns and detect
anomalies as soon as they're occur.
That's pretty much it.
Pretty important, right?
yeah.
When it comes to K sql, K sql, which is
a calf of query language, is a SQL like
language, built for, Kafka that allows us
to write streaming queries on live data.
Case QL makes it easier.
To work, streaming data since we don't
have to write complex code Just like
this straightforward sql commands
to filter transform or join data
for instance If you wanted to filter
specific type of transactions in a
financial application We could use
ksql to pull only the data we need in
real time without heavy processing.
So together The Stream Processing API and
ksql offers flexibility and simplicity
for working with streaming data.
They enable us to perform real time data
transformations and analyze directly
on Kafka, which is essential for us.
for supporting real time AI
applications that need, fast
and fast accurate data insights.
When it comes to integration with,
data systems, Kafka Connect is a tool
that is a part of cap Kafka ecosystem,
which is pretty much designed to
simplify and automate the process of
streamlining data between Kafka and
other data systems, like simplifying
the data flow of AI applications.
and, the big advantage of, using, the
Kafka's approach in AI is, so it gives
you a high throughput and low latency.
Like Kafka itself is designed to
handle large scale, data ingestion,
like a millions of, messages.
And it'll process.
in a lightning time and slow latency
enabling its enables real time processing
latencies within below 10 milliseconds.
So these are pretty good, the kafkas.
Let's discuss about a real
time AI use case, Kafka.
as we earlier discussed about
the anomaly detection, right?
this time we'll go a little bit deeper.
A little bit deeper about what
this anomaly detection is and how
this will be useful for our end
to end, day to day lives by AI.
anomaly detection is essential in
today's AI driven systems, especially
for applications in security, finance,
and operations, where spotting
unusual patterns is critical, right?
Anomaly detection helps identify
unexpected or abnormal events in data.
Think like unusual login items,
irregular financial transactions,
or system performance issues.
In a real time, AI, anomaly
detection takes on even greater
importance because it allows
organizations to respond instantly.
For example, in the cyber security,
detecting an anomaly might mean
identifying a potential attack.
As it's happening, allowing for immediate
action to mitigate threats or the
financial services, real time anomaly
detection can help flag fraudulent
transactions before they're processed.
So one of the, the other, real
time use case Is, natural language
processing, which is aka NLP.
Kafka facilitates this, the
real time processing of language
data for applications such as,
chatbots or voice assistants.
on the social media platforms, right?
So using this, natural language
processing, integrating this lab, having
this natural language processing with
Kafka, it enables real time analysis
and processing of text data streams.
Open it's open up the possibilities for
applications like, sentiment analysis.
Contact, content link, content
filterings, chatbots, and
more in dynamic environments.
By combining NLP models with Kafka's
powerful data streaming capabilities,
organizations can create scalable
responsive systems that analyze test
data as it flows through various sources.
So the other, another important
thing is a predictive maintenance.
So AI models leverages its real time
streaming capabilities to prevent when
a failure occurs, thereby reducing
the downtime and maintenance cost.
Decision Supporting Systems aka DSS
with Kafka, which enables organizations
to make real time data driven
decisions by processing, Analyzing and
integrating information from various
sources by utilizing Kafka's robust
data streaming capabilities, decision
support systems can gather and process
information in a real time that helps.
in a critical decision making
across various domains like finance,
healthcare, e commerce, and operations.
for example, in a healthcare, real
time AI processing can provide
doctors with insights based on the
patient data, assisting in diagnostic
and treatment planning, right?
this is very important, like
additional support systems.
With Kafka, we can create
wonders using the help of AI.
Let's talk about, the security, securing
AI data pipelines with secure proxies.
securing AI data pipelines with secure
proxies is critical for, protecting
sensitive information as it moves between
different components in a distributed
real time processing environment.
It acts as intermediaries.
It acts as an intermediary that
enforces security policies, monitoring
traffic, and masks underlying system
details, ensuring that AI data
pipelines are robust against attacks,
unauthorized access, and data leaks.
There are many examples of using secure
proxies for securing AI data pipelines.
And we can discuss some of them here.
For instance, like compliance
with data regulations.
This helps organizations meet
their private, meet privacy laws.
For example, GDPR, General
Data Privacy Regulation.
And, CCPA California Consumer Privacy
Act, then ensuring the sensitivity,
the sensitive data is not, is handled
securely throughout the pipeline.
And one other example
is the risk mitigation.
while incorporating secure proxies,
in a Kafka based CA system, it
reduces the risk of data breaches.
Nowadays, the big financial institutions
and, other companies, they're
focusing main on the data breach.
We have seen many instances,
the data got leaked.
So considering that you using
Kafka, we can avoid the situation.
performance considerations, right?
When it comes to performance, Like
despite adding all these layers of
security, secure proxies are optimized
to ensure that there is no significant
impact on data processing latency.
Let's talk about integrating AI
workloads with Kafka Connect.
integrating AI workloads with
Kafka Connect creates a powerful
scalable solution for, streaming
data into machine learning models
and AI systems in real time.
Kafka Connect as a.
Character framework allows for seamless
data movement between Apache Kafka
and other data systems like databases.
file storage and cloud services.
This integration enables AI
applications to leverage real time
data flows, providing insights
and actions based on the latest
data without manual data movement.
So by scaling these AI pipelines
with Kafka Connect, we can
achieve seamless AI pipelines,
sorry, seamless data integration.
So it allows organizations to easily
connect AI workloads with external data
systems, such as cloud data warehouses,
data lakes, and, on prem databases.
and one, one other, thing using AI
pipelines with Kafka Connect we can
achieve is the scaling improvements.
Kafka Connect can deliver up to a 50
percent improvement in data scalability.
and optimization, accommodating
growing data volumes, pre
built and custom connectors.
So we can utilize a wide range of pre
built connectors for a proper data sources
or develop customer, custom connectors
tailored for our specific use case.
one real world example is that, a retail
company integrated its machine learning
models with Kafka Connect to enable.
real time inventory management,
which leads to significant
reductions in stockouts and their,
and the excessive inventory.
Let's talk about implementing a
zero, trust architecture with Kafka.
So implementing zero trust architecture
with Kafka is essential for securing,
data flows in real time applications.
and distributed systems.
Zero trust assumes that every
user, device, and application
inside or outside the organization
should not be trusted by default.
So this approach enforces strict
identity verification and continuous
validation, ensuring that data
integrity and privacy are maintained
across Kafka based architectures.
We can, enhance, security
with zero trust architecture.
Let's talk about some key items, zero
trust security principles, primarily
zero trust security principles.
So employ a never trust
always verify approach.
So this approach, where every data access
request is authenticated and encrypted.
Okay.
Like a continuous authentication, Kafka
integrates with zero trust frameworks
to ensure the data is continuously
protected at every point in the pipeline.
So middleman attacks, right?
so enforcing by enforcing this
encryption and secure authentication
protocols, we can help, preventing
the middle, middle man in the middle
attacks and other security threats.
Some of the, yep, some of the best
practices, for building, secure
scalable AI pipelines are listed here.
So this guy, we can have different
items listed here, which is
like design recommendations.
So using event driven and microservice
architecture to manage the complexities
of real time data processing, security
considerations, incorporating,
encryption, secure policies, and
zero trust principles to protect
the data throughout the pipeline.
And as we already discussed about
the performance optimization tips,
so we can use, we can optimize the
Kafka configurations, such as, topic
partitioning and replication factors.
To make sure it has a high
throughput and low latency.
That's pretty much important So when it
comes to monitoring and alerting by while
setting up the continuous monitoring and
alerting for Pipelines performance and
security event to detect and in response
to issues promptly So the moment when
when we set this proper alerting in
case of any issues It will alert you
on time and we can mitigate the risk.
So
on to conclude this, so integrating
Apache Kafka with EA systems.
secure proxies and zero trust
principles, which creates a secure
high performance data pipeline.
So this combination allows real time
data processing while ensuring only
trusted users and devices access the
data, protecting sensitive information
and enabling AI applications to
act on up to date available data.
It's a powerful way to make
data more secure, scalable,
and responsive across systems.
By adopting these modern architectures,
organizations can enhance the accuracy
and reliability of AI systems while
maintaining robust data protection.
Thank you so much.