Hello, everyone.
Welcome to COM 42 I'm the DevOps
HR engineer at Landover E.
In this session, I'll be talking
about integrating cloud technologies
for enhanced healthcare system, a
comprehensive approach to transforming
healthcare infrastructure.
To begin with, I'll be talking about
integration to cloud integration in
healthcare, CICD automation, driving
and Productivity in healthcare.
Kubernetes for scalable and cost
effective healthcare infrastructure.
Documentum for advanced
healthcare content management.
Leveraging AI and neural network
for advanced healthcare workflow.
Integrated Documentum and Neural
Network for workflow automation.
Creating a unified cloud
platform for healthcare.
Future readiness and adaptability
of the integrated system.
One of the countries.
Introduction to Cloud Integration
in Healthcare Problem Statement Data
management is challenging in healthcare
due to the increasing volume and
complexity of medical information.
Traditional systems are often
fragmented, leading to inefficiencies and
difficulties in scaling up operations.
Regulatory compliance, e.
g.
HIPAA, imposes stringent
requirements on data handling,
making robust solutions essential.
Thank you for your time.
Solution overview.
Cloud technologies enable integration
of different healthcare processes,
ensuring seamless flow of information
by leveraging modern tools like
CICD, Kubernetes, Documentum, and AI.
Healthcare organizations can
create a unified platform that is
efficient, scalable, and secure.
The aim is to improve patient
outcome while reducing operation
cost and enhancing confidence.
CI CD automation driving
productivity in health care.
Continuous integration,
continuous deployment.
CI CD in health care.
Key feature.
Tools like GitHub Actions automate
the software lifecycle from
development to deployment, ensuring
rapid integration and feedback.
Docker containers maintain consistent
environment across all stages, Reducing.
Discrepancies between development
and production benefits.
The automation of build and deployment
process allows healthcare IT teams to
release updates more frequently, ensuring
application meet evolving medical needs.
Reducing manual intervention in deployment
minimizes human error leading to 50
percent drop in deployment issue.
Kubernetes for scalable and cost
effective healthcare infrastructure.
Scalable cloud infrastructure with
Kubernetes Dynamic Resource Allocation.
Kubernetes auto scaling capability
allows for resource adjustment based
on current demand, ensuring optimal
application performance, especially
beneficial during high period workloads.
During a period of high demand, such
as public healthcare emergencies or
large scale data processing tasks, high
availability, Kubernetes orchestrates
workloads across multiple nodes,
providing failover capabilities
to prevent service interruption.
This ensures that healthcare applications
remain accessible, reducing the risk of
downtime that could impact patient safety.
Documentum for advanced
healthcare content management.
Efficient management of
medical data using Documentum.
Data organization.
Efficient.
Effectively manages various types
of data from patient demographics to
clinical notes and medical imaging.
Facilitates unified storage for both
structured and unstructured data.
Simplifying information retrieval
and enhancing interoperability.
Compliance and security designed
to meet stringent regulations such
as HIPAA, ensuring data privacy and
security at all time, provides a robust
system for tracking document access
and modification, enabling detailed
audit trails for compliance purpose.
Input efficiency reduces the
time required to locate critical
document and patient records.
Thank you.
allowing healthcare professional to
dedicate more time to patient care.
Leveraging AI and neural network
for advanced healthcare workflow.
AI powered healthcare with neural network
pattern recognition, deep learning models
such as convolutional neural network
can detect complex pattern in radiology
images, potentially diagnosis conditions
more accurate than human radiologists.
Predictive decision making.
Any algorithm can predict patient
outcome by analyzing historical data,
enabling personalized treatment plan
and early intervention for conditions
like diabetes or heart diseases.
Workflow automation.
Automates repetitive tasks such
as sorting medical records, or
prioritizing patient for treatment.
Streamlining administrative workflows.
Integrating Documentum and Neural
Network for Workflow Automation.
Intelligent Workflow Automation
in Healthcare Automated Document
Workflows uses metadata which triggers
initial processes automatically, such
as updating patient EHRS when new
information is added or generating
alerts for missing information.
AI enhanced recommendation.
Suggest diagnostic tests or
treatment based on pattern
identified on the patient data.
Improving critical
clinical decision making.
Recommendation workflow optimization
based on historical data.
Enabling better resource utilization.
Creating a unified cloud
platform for healthcare.
Seamlessly integration
of cloud technologies for
healthcare transformation.
Unified approach.
Centralizes various healthcare
applications and processes on
a single platform, ensuring all
components work together efficiently.
Integrates tools for development,
CI, CD, deployment, governance,
data management, documenting, and
AI to create a holistic solution.
Workflow automation automates and
streamlines operations such as updating
records, processing Managing patient
appointment eliminates information
silos by making data accessible
across departments, improving
collaboration and patient care.
Featured readiness and
adaptability of integrated system.
Preparing healthcare system
for future challenges.
Scalability.
Easily expands to handle increased patient
volume, new healthcare application,
and more complex data processing needs.
Flexibility.
Support the integration of new
technologies such as wearable
devices for remote patient
monitoring genomic data analysis.
Sustainability provides a foundation
for long term innovations in
healthcare including precision medical
medicine and AI enhanced diagnostics.
Ensures that the system evolves
with illicit and without the need
of Frequent large scale upgrade.
Conclusion.
Cloud integration offers pathway to
more efficient data driven healthcare
system capable of reducing cost
and improving patient outcome.
The combined benefits of CICD, Kubernetes,
Documentum, and AIP today future
proof our healthcare infrastructure.
And this concludes my session and
thank you very much for giving
this opportunity and Please enjoy
your next conf42 talks and thanks.
Thank you very much.
Bye.