Hi, first of all, thank you for
Con Fortitude team for providing an
opportunity to present a topic on
optimizing SQL server infrastructure
for LLM workloads in hybrid environment.
Thanks for joining.
My name is Siva.
I'm working as a principal
database administrator in Paycor,
which is now a Paychex company.
In this talk, I will present about how
SQL Server get ready for LLM workloads.
Let's start the presentation.
Yeah.
The agenda of this talk is the LLM
infrastructure challenges and legacy SQL
server limitations, Azure SQL managed
instance, and I link for real time
replication, performance optimization,
and global architecture patterns.
Security, governance and real
world implementation of EMI, future
proofing your data infrastructure.
This is the agenda for this presentation.
Okay.
The, what are the challenges we have
right now for LLM infrastructure,
that traditional SQL server.
He's having a limitations, like a
high latency data, access patterns,
limited scalability for concurrent
EA workloads, complex replication
across environments, performance
bottlenecks in real time scenarios.
So the modern LLM requirements are
subsecond response times per prompts,
continuous data synchronization,
elastic scaling per variable demand.
Enterprise creates
security and governance.
So why legacy SQL
architecture struggle with ai?
In legacy deployments, we haven't designed
for a unique demand of LLM workloads.
Prompt engineering requires instant
access to synchronized and courage
should be optimized for data access
across the distributed systems.
So the gap between yay application
velocity and database respond
times create a critical bottleneck
that impacts the user experience
and limits of AI capabilities.
To address these solutions, Microsoft
provides a managed instance that is the.
Built for hybrid AI in this hybrid
cloud integration it helps to
synchronize the data from on-premises
to Azure without any latency.
And this is all also have
the built in governance and
compliance and data protections.
So this helps you.
Increase your performance
based on requirements or need.
So to set up manage instance, the
communication between your on-prem
server to manage instance will be
taken care through MI link that
is called Managed Instance Link.
This link.
Take care of synchronization between
Uber, Azure, and on-prem environment.
The synchronization will happen
based on log based synchronization,
which is similar to Uber,
always on ayc configuration.
The latency would be near zero.
So with this less latency, your
Azure environment MI instance, is
ready for your LLM access because it
helps current and consistent data.
So the advantage of MI it is
have a performance optimization.
You can have utilize query store
insights that leverage historical query
performance data to identify patterns,
optimize execution plans, and eliminate
bottlenecks before the impact of A
LLM response times the other benefit
memory control workload classification.
So am I intelligently allocate resources
based on workload, priority, ensuring
prompts, serving queries, receive a
dedicated memory and compute resources.
The other benefit is
concurrency optimization.
Fine tune connection, polling parallelism
settings and isolation levels to handle.
Hundreds of simultaneous
requests without degradation.
So architecture pattern
for a global prompt.
Data sourcing organizations with
a global operations need prompt
data available across regions
with consistent performance.
To fulfill this requirement, the am I
link enables multi-region replication
to apology, where on premises SQL server
feeds regional ministry instances.
This architecture reduces cross
regional latency while maintaining data
consistency, allowing LLMs to serve.
Users from the nearest data source,
regardless of where the personal data
resides, in simplest terms, you can set
up multiple MI links across multiple
regions from one source database.
Key performance metrics for LLM
workloads, target correl latency.
The response time, concurrent
request, it'll support multiple
queries on the same time.
And the availability.
Microsoft will take care of
H-E-A-D-R per Azure manager
instance, and there is a less minimum
delay to synchronize the data.
These are the key performance
metrics for LLM workloads.
The other advantage with the manager
instances is you can utilize it
as a per hybrid data disaster
recovery, as well as AI continuity.
For example, your primary SQL server.
That is your production environment.
You have a setup for MI link with the
MI instance so that the MI instance
will help to synchronize the data and
it act as a read access for your LLM
workloads and as well as works as a d.
Environment.
So in, in case of disaster, you can
utilize and you can fail over your
right loads from on premises to Azure.
So it acts as a both rules
A, a access as well as Dr.
The other advantage of MI is.
It'll a hundred percent integrates
with Azure synapse integration.
So with this, you no need
to have traditional ETLs.
The integration analytics with
Azure Synapse Link enables advanced
augment generation scenarios.
Pre aggregated and index frequently
accessed the prompt context in
synapse producing query complexity
and improving response times.
This separation of concerns allow
transactional SQL workloads and
analytical prompt preparation to
operate independently, preventing
resource contention, and optimizing
each of its specific purpose.
This is one of the example for
a real world implementation.
For example, you assume that there
is a global bank presence across the
world and they want to set up a LLM
chat bot with the their customers.
And the major data is an
on-premises environment.
In this case, you can use MI link and
set up a managed instances across the
regions so that the bot can access the
local MI instance instead of everything
hitting too, you source on premises data.
So this helps the response
times and reduces the latency.
With this solution, you can reduce
the prompts, prompt response latency,
and it is compliance with the
regular standards and it
supports concurrent AA sessions,
security and governance in a pipeline.
This helps data classification you.
You can use automated discovery
labeling of since two data elements
used in prom access control, role
level and column level security
and force across the replication.
Each targets audit trials.
You can set up a
comprehensive logging all.
AI driven data access for
compliance and reporting encryption,
always encrypted columns and TDE
protected data in transit at rest.
So these are the features you
can use in your MI instance
based on your requirements.
So to tune over LLM, these are the
things we need to follow first.
Enable query store.
This allows to capture all, all over
queries, so it helps to fine tune
if any queries taking longer time.
Configure Resource
Governor for AI workloads.
So if you configure this one, you
can separate ever prompt queries
and other queries so that users
can get a quick response, implement
connection, polling best practices.
You can size over buffer polls
based on every requirement.
Optimize index for read heavy
patterns, like create a proper
index based on your query.
Which improves the response times.
Monitor your MI link logs to ensure
that everything is working in sync.
So future programing, your
AI data infrastructure.
So the implementation first
phase, you have to assess.
Evaluate current SQL workload and
identify yay integration points.
Phase to optimize, implement
MI replication and tune for
low latency access scale.
Expand multi-region architecture
with integrated analytics.
Phase four, innovate leverage
hybrid infrastructure for the
next generation AI applications.
So the key takeaways is
modernize without disruptions.
MI link brings like CQL and
modern AI requirements without
requiring full migration.
Optimize for real time courage,
store and workload classification and
tuning eliminates LLM bottlenecks.
Scale intelligently.
Hybrid architecture supports
global workloads while
maintaining enterprise governance.
Thank you.
Thank you for providing this opportunity.