Hello everyone.
I'm Victor Gabriel, a season supply
chain consultant from GP Worldwide.
I'm thrilled to be here speaking at
Prompt Engineering 2025 conference.
Today I'll be sharing a success story
on how we have helped a global food
manufacturer to uncover about $30 million
in cost savings using a Power BI tool with
the embedded prompt engineering framework.
In the next few minutes, I'll walk you
through the challenge that we had on
hand and the approach we've taken and the
solution framework we have developed, and
perhaps we will learn how the solution
can be used to implement, to solve similar
business problems across other industries.
Now with that, looking at the
challenge, this particular client
is a $15 billion food manufacturer
with a huge number of contact
manufacturers across North Americas.
So like many large organizations
today, they do struggled with scattered
data across multiple systems, limited
visibility into real-time cost
information, slow identification of
margin, leakages, and difficulty turning
data into meaningful de decisions.
Now, for them, Excel
dashboards weren't enough.
They needed something faster, smarter,
and easier to use for their employees.
Now what we've done was, as part
of the solution, we have developed
a hybrid analytics approach.
Now, this framework was built using a
power BI for structure and Microsoft
copilot for intelligent prompts.
Now, while Power BI gave reliable
real-time dashboards, explaining or
conveying the data, co-pilot added a
prompt driven layer where users could
simply ask questions with quick answers.
This made analysis, instant
decisions that once took hours.
Now it just take few minutes or seconds.
Diving a little bit into
the platform architecture.
The architecture rests on three
key pillars, power BI Foundation.
That's where the realtime
dashboards are developed.
Presenting the data facts,
prompt engineering layer.
This is where the scenario modeling
is done through the Microsoft copilot.
The integration engine, this is where
connecting the data connects happens with
a multiple across multiple manufacturing
systems, supply portals, finance data
to form a single source of truth.
Now, together with all three pillars,
it gives us a single source of growth
and a rapid insight generation.
Yeah, looking into the
prompt engineering in action.
So what it actually means.
Analysts could talk directly to data.
That's what it means.
They can ask any question they
may want, they can ask a question.
Hey, you know why my scrap rate went
down in scrap rates were high in Q3.
Why?
What factors have I actually contributed
to the most to the scrap varis and Q3?
And the system responds with
visuals without within no
time, and summarizes instantly.
No manual analysis is needed.
Prompt engineering made advanced
analytics accessible to everyone,
not just the data scientists.
Now the approach, talking about the
approach now that we have the framework
here, is the approach for execution.
The focus was was what was the focus
was kept on two major levers, the margin
performance and the cost optimization.
Margin performance.
That's where, the focus
was on conversion cost.
The overall yield profitability per
product, and the cost optimization.
That's where the supplier
cost benchmarking was done.
Packaging efficiencies the metrics
were looked at and the production
process improvement initiatives.
Now, by targeting these, we could quickly
see where the money was being lost and
where the improvements can be made.
Now talking about the timing
now, usually for projects like
this, timing is everything.
This solution was launched during
a major corporate restructuring,
key insights, guided leadership
decisions telling them which applies
to consolidate, which to grow, with
which to shift production, directly
supported company's new operating model.
And these are the results,
the transformative impact.
The impact was pretty clear.
30 million was achieved in savings
across scrap and conversion costs.
When I mentioned scrap it's coming
from the raw material and packaging
scrap from the pro, from the from the
products and the conversion costs.
Now that's number one.
And faster decisions were made
with more transparency and the
supply performance were improved.
And it also helped us with
the real time tracking.
And the platform paid for
itself several times over.
It, it was almost a good number
of written over written on
investment as one of the results.
Now here is the real world application.
Now, one of the major findings that we
saw as the outcomes were the scrap rates
were 15% above the industry benchmarks.
That have contributed to losing
a lot of money wasting millions.
Now using the prompt driven
insights, we found consistent
product recipes across suppliers.
Now remember we are talking
about the food manufacturer
and the product is a is a food.
You can say it can be a candy or
it can be an energy bar, or it
can be any food I, any food item.
So now think about.
The product recipe now, making it
streamlining the product recipes
would help now, and that is not easy.
So one of the things we were able to
fix it by standardizing the formulas
food formulas the renegotiating the
supply contracts, adding the live
performance alerts supply performance
alerts, and within 18 months,
the food scrap raw material and
packaging scrap was at the industry.
Best levels now that has given the the
client about $30 million in savings.
Now, what lessons have we learned?
Just in general?
In general, from executing this project?
Always start the business questions.
Start with the business
questions, not with tools.
What what the tools are important.
But starting off with the business
questions is primary is most important.
And ensuring the data quality
early on is important too.
Poor data just, kills the good analytics.
Work across work cross-functionally.
When we say the data, the the, one
of the pillars of the framework
was the integration engine.
It is important that we.
We weed the data.
We are able to integrate the data,
transform the data that comes
from it, that comes from finance,
that comes from operations,
that comes from supply portals.
Now, working cross-functional with
the cross-functional teams is quite
important now, and using the AI
wisely now it should enhance and
not replace the human judgment.
As we are using the copilot to
support web, making some of the
decisions, data driven decisions,
it is not to replace entirely.
But it just arguments
enhances the human judgment.
Those were the, some of the lessons we
have learned from executing this project.
From insight to action, what
was the overall decision
cycle that we have observed?
Now, a quick reminder that, how
insights are turned into action.
First is the data integration.
This is where the real time updates
from all the sources are aggregated now.
Then the visual discovery, visualize
and spot trends in the dashboards.
Then the prompt driven analysis, asking
the questions, testing the scenarios
with ai in this case, the co-pilot,
but you can also use the L lms.
Synthesizing the copilot generates
the summaries for executives so that
the data-driven decisions can help
make some of the meaningful business
decisions and the implementers
obviously making the decisions and
acting on them, launching the project.
And launching the initiatives,
the team are acting on it
and monitoring those results.
And we go back in the cycle to refine it.
So this loops keep kept on the keep the
continuously, it kept, it needs to be
kept continuously improving from data
to decision and decision to action.
So that's it's a virtuous cycle now.
The practical Brooklyn, if we have
to get started on similar projects
way to get started in your projects.
If you are looking at how can
we implement a kind of a similar
framework to realize cost savings
using a similar solution framework.
First, identify three to five
high impact areas, then build a
simple power BI dashboard, then
layer in a copilot gradually.
So first is a Power BI dashboard.
Make sure that you know the data you have
the data and you're able to spot trends.
Then on top of it goes of the
co-pilot or any LLN and then track
the insights that leads into actions.
And the fifth one is the
scale and standardize.
Once it is proven, it's all
about proving the value early
and then expanding it fast.
So that can be a successful blueprint in
order to execute for similar projects.
Now talking about the future,
this is just the beginning of ai,
augmented supply chain intelligence.
Now next comes the predictive analytics.
We just have the prompt engineering
layer, and next comes the predictive
analytics, automated recommendations
and risk forecasting all blended.
Blending the structured
data with adaptive ai.
So whether you are tracking the margins,
erosion, or supplier optimization or
network complexity, remember Power bi,
it just gives a structure and prompt
engineering, it gives us the agility.
It just gives us that speed.
Now together it'll give us a
clarity of thought clarity of the
business performance with the speed
at the, at a good rate of speed.
Now I really appreciate, again for
this opportunity that was given
to me to present this to all of
you now, feel free to reach out to
me in case you have any questions
or to share simply your thoughts.
Now, with that, I would like to
say thank you for the opportunity
once again to be a speaker here at
Prompt Engineering 2025 conference.
Thank you all.