Optimizing AI interactions.
So techniques in prompt engineering
for enhanced model performance.
So in coming to introduction to
prompt engineering is a new area
where we should know how to ask
questions, how to instruct an AI model.
So it is called prompting.
Prompting is an art.
So to get a best response,
we should prompt effectively.
The more focused we are into prompting,
the more effective we get out.
Practicing prompt engineering will enhance
the AI model performance and usability.
It will improve the response
that we are supposed to get.
There are different AI
models, in market right now.
The OpenAI, started with GPT 3.
Now it is with GPT 4.
And we do have image generation
model called Dell, E.
We are using multiple generative AI
models like Meta, Chad GPT, Microsoft
Copilot, et cetera, and everyone has
started using now these AI models.
So how to use these AI models effectively?
So we need to know about prompting, which
will get the response from the AI models.
Every AI model generates outputs
based on patterns in the data.
They have been trained on prompt quality,
directly provide the user quality results.
Roles of prompt engineering
in working with AI models.
So basically, a prompt is an input or
query that a user asks an AI model.
Say for example, what is
the temperature today?
What is the temperature
in California today?
More specific query if you want.
it should have variable prompts
which will give us various results
even if the question is same.
So the prompt should be clear,
specific, it should have a context.
Then we will get the best response.
Structured prompts produce best results.
Now, how to structure a prompt for
getting a best result from an AI model?
Let us see.
For that, we should know about different
prompts, different types of prompts.
There are instructional prompts.
Instructional prompts, we can request AI
to produce a specific format of style.
Say, for example, we can, ask to write a
poem with 10 lines or write a poem on this
context, write a poem on about flowers.
Some instruction we can give to AI.
AI will respond us.
As we need, it can write stories, it can
write essays, it can write poems, it can
write cover letters, resumes, depends
upon the input we are giving, that are
all the instructions we are giving.
In some cases, we might
need to give a context.
Say for example, some strategies
of business growth based on current
economic trend, the context we are
setting as current economic trend.
So the contextual prompts basically
provide the background information,
So that AI can, shape its
response according to the context.
Next one coming is the interactive prompt.
So to generate various
perspectives interactively.
We can talk to AI like a
human in a discussion mode.
For example, about the current election.
What do you think of the current election?
Who will win?
What is the possibility of winning?
We can keep asking questions.
They can keep answering.
So they will give multiple responses.
So there are, these are the
three different type of prompts.
Instructional prompts, contextual
prompts, and interactive prompts.
Now we come to know
about different prompts.
Next question is, What are all
the techniques for optimizing
this, prompt more effectively?
The first thing is, it should
be more specific, be specific.
More details in your prompts will
provide you more accurate results.
For example, asking for a diet plan
to change the PT Generate UI model.
What is the best diet plan for, for a day?
That is a general question.
If you are asking for an adult, for 36
years of age, or for a kid, or, South
Indian, or, American dishes, likewise,
if we give more specific, items,
we will get more specific answers.
Apart from that, we
can give examples also.
I will be coming to the example section
so that I can explain them in detail.
So after that, the next step for
effective, Prompt is setting context.
We have to ask prompt, say for
example, about the election in
the current election context.
If we are asking, chat GPT or any AI model
about what do you think about election?
They will give general answer only.
But if you are asking a query, what
do you think about election, current
American election, then we will get the
exact response which we are looking into.
And also same like tone, set
the tone level of formality.
Let us validate some examples, some case
studies, how prompt engineering works.
I'm asking a query, give me
a balanced diet for a day.
what is the response?
See, the response looks like a
balanced diet, given some explanation
about the balanced diet, and they
are giving breakfast, multiple
options, mid morning snacks.
and multiple options they are giving.
That's a big response.
Now I'm planning to give more
clear and specific prompt.
Give me a balanced diet for a day
for a six year old girl child.
Now the prompt answer is different because
I really want a six year old, girl child
diet, but I'm asking a balanced diet.
It's a general question.
It will be common for everyone.
Now, if the question is more specific
with six year old child, It is giving
about, the, the kid's explanation and
the breakfast option with morning style.
The option got changed.
The option is more specific
to a six year old child.
let us give more context also.
Say, for example, the same,
give me a balanced diet.
For a 10-year-old boy
with an issue in eyesight.
So issue in eyesight can, can be
with, nutritional deficiencies also.
the GPT model, the AI model, has taken
the eyesight issue as a context, and it
is considering the 10-year-old boy and
also after calculating all the, details
from internet, it's, giving a, response.
specific to the context which we need.
as we discussed, in the previous slides,
there are different type of prompts,
instructional prompts, interactive
prompts, setting examples in prompts, etc.
Let us see how instructional prompt works.
Now I'm asking, the AI model to
give me the response in bullet
points with maximum 10 lines.
I already have a, response
in the previous slide.
If you see in the previous slide,
I already have some response with
some explanations, tip, et cetera,
but I want the response in lists.
I'm giving the response and
I am setting a limit of 10.
and I want everything
to be in bullet points.
So what happens?
It has reduced, the explanation
description, but all the points
it has given in bullet points.
And if you count, it will not go
beyond 10 lines because I have
limited them to responding 10 lines.
Same way.
They say, let us try with
interactive prompt option.
So now I have a, a diet plan for a
10 year old, boy with eyesight issue.
Now I am thinking whether the eyesight
is only because of the nutritional
issue or any other issues are there.
I don't know.
I just want to interact with someone.
So I'm interacting with the AI model.
I'm asking him, what do you
think that causes issues in
eyesight of 10 year old boy?
Now I'm giving some instruction also here.
Give me the response in a
paragraph of five sentences.
Now the AI with all the possible issues.
Excessive screen time, genetic
factors, nutrition, lack of proper
nutrition, bright light exposure,
UV rays, smoking, all the list,
all the possible list it is giving.
And also it is limiting to a
paragraph of five sentences.
Now I can ask again on top of this.
On top of this, like what
about the genetic factor?
What about excessive screen time?
How should be the excessive screen time?
It will give, keep giving the answer.
So in advanced prompt
engineering, techniques also.
Now this interactive prompting,
we, it can be done iteratively.
For example, what are all the genetic
factors can be, the cause of eyesight,
a model can respond with all the
genetic factors and the user can
compare it with their own, requirements.
Accordingly, it will,
ask again the questions.
And also for lack of proper nutrition,
if we can ask on top of this interactive
prompt, if we can ask about lack of
nutrition, then it will explain more
about the, what are all the nutrients like
vitamin A, B, what are all the nutrients
which are required for a proper nutrition.
Then we can think about, the diet plan.
Okay.
So this kid is having a
vitamin A carats every day.
So we don't need a vitamin
A, again on this plan.
or we can ask how much
vitamin A is required.
So that, how this iterative
process will go on.
It's like we can interact
with the normal human beings.
And for the further questions, we
don't need to ask the same question
again, we just need to ask about
what are all the vitamins required.
That's it.
If we ask what are all the vitamins
required, the AI model will understand
the context from the previous.
Prompt it will set the context that this
user is asking about a 10 year old boy
and the issue is eyesight and they are
thinking about improving the nutrition.
So this what are all the victims this
question is related to that context.
It will automatically assume that is the
beauty of this AI generative AI models.
We can set examples also in the
prompt so that GPT will, GPT model
will understand that example.
and give the result in the same way.
Give me the same response.
I'm asking.
I already have a response.
But I, it doesn't look good for me.
Now I'm asking.
Give me the same response
in different way.
For example, I'm giving an example.
For example, genetic factors
need to be a heading.
Give an explanation.
Excessive screen time
need to be a heading.
Give an explanation.
Now, see the surprise.
The breakdown.
They are giving genetic
factors and given all the list.
excessive screen time,
given all the descriptions.
The same way they are responding.
This is how we will set
the examples in the prompt.
Apart from that one, there are multiple
advanced prompting techniques also called
few short learning, chain of thought
prompting, tree of thought prompting, etc.
In few short learning, we can give
few, we already saw in that, context
setting example in the previous,
slide, setting examples in the prompt,
setting examples in the prompt.
This example I have given only one item.
If we are able to give more and more
examples, AI will understand the context.
And gives the more and more specific
response, which exactly we need To
provide a few more examples for desired
outcome to help the model generalize
And also show in chat gpt how they will
arrange output in list bullet point, etc.
This is just an example and What
about chain of thought prompting?
Chain of thought prompting will be
encouraging the model to explain
its reasoning step by step.
So for example, they're telling genetic
factors, the, they're mentioning some
reason like if the, if there is a family
history of vision problems such as
myopia and astigmatism, child is more
likely to in inherit these conditions.
This is what they mentioned in the genetic
factors and the genetics play more role
in determining child's psych health.
Now, we are thinking, so whether
any family member is having myopia,
whether the kid also will get it.
we are thinking about
the, AI models reasoning.
We can question it, we can question
it, why are you thinking if a
family, history of a vision problem
is there with myopia, the kid also
should, what is the possibility,
what is the percentage of myopia?
getting that one for the kids.
we can ask for more reasoning.
If we ask for more reasoning, they
will get more specific, we will
get more specific answers of that.
model will be encouraged to
explain the reasoning step by step.
They will give more examples.
So there are this much population in
such a place and in that place this
much people had myopia and their
kids has been identified with myopia.
So this is a reason why they
are telling the family history
will impact their eyesight.
Likewise, model can explain
it like a human being, like
a doctor, like a, advisor.
And, this AI models can act as
our supervisor, our juniors.
We can ask them to write coding.
We can ask them to write a
program, develop an application.
This text, it's amazing.
It's amazing.
Ask question again from the
response, which is already given.
It is possible.
This interaction can go for hours.
It will, they will never get tired.
They will, we will get more
and more specific answers.
To get an AI model in its maximum
effective way, the only possibility
is to send an effective prompting
like chain of thought prompting.
Now the next advanced technique is tree
of thoughts interacting the model to share
a different perspective of the response.
in a single response, you'll be having
different, ways of approaching it.
So that one, a response, AI models
can give different perspective of the
response and are from those perspectives.
A user can read and identify which
perspective they are looking into it and
that perspective we can ask them again.
this, GPT models, they are, AI models can
help us help our, help us for, writing
codes, any code, like we can, writing
codes reviewing and, and trouble shooting
issues, possible trouble shooting issues.
We can, it's.
It's covered.
It depends upon how much data set they
have covered in their AI model, that much
coverage if we can get from them instead
of, searching in Google, the same data is
getting trained by the AI model means what
we are asking effectively in the prompt
we will get in the most effective way.
Now, we got a response.
Can we believe it?
100 percent right.
Of course, we cannot believe it.
Why?
Only because.
Every AI model is trained
for a set of data.
how far, how vast is that data?
How see if it is, from like
Google covered the details.
The same VA model covered the entire,
Wikipedia or entire Google and entire
internet depends upon the coverage
of the data, which they have done.
They will, get us the response
and also from their training data,
they will get us the response.
we, it is our responsibility not to
relay the response 100%, instead validate
the response whether it is matching.
Whether it is relevant.
If we are asking about election and
is it is relevant to what I am asking
instead of considering the result as such.
Is it is relevant?
Is the response relevant to the problem?
Whether the response is
logically structured and is it
understandable for the user?
Whether it is easy to follow?
And A double confirmation is
required, whether it is accurate.
This, if we are asking for some financial
figures of the growth of a company,
then the model will give a result.
And if we are searching it in
the latest result in internet, we
might be getting different results.
Why?
Because sometimes, say for example, if
model is trained for the data until 2023,
Then 2024 details model will never fetch.
In that case for getting
the latest result, we might
rely on the other sources.
So accuracy need to be validated.
We need to know about the model, how
they are trained on what set of data
they are trained, but still we have all
these apart from this, all these pros and
cons, we can use this as a, guideline.
Even though the accuracy, we need
to validate coherence, relevance,
everything we need to validate and we
need to do the , we need to test the
same, prompt, the different versions
and validate and compare the output
because, the MA model should be able
to provide the, same relevant answer
if you are asking the same prompt with
different, wordings or different versions.
We can try adjusting the phrases
context and examples based on the
feedback so that and finally we can
get the, refined model performance.
coming to conclusion and best practices.
Prompt engineering is essential for
maximizing AI model performance.
Prompt engineering is one of the future
items which all technology people and
every common man will be looking into.
Specificity, context, And clear
instructions will drive better
results from an AI model.
Experimentation and iteration
are key to optimize the outputs.
Of course, we need to try multiple prompts
instead of relying on the single response.
We have to provide more
and more experiments.
examples and context on what we are
thinking in my mind because the magic
behind here is they will understand,
AI models will understand the context
and examples whatever we are setting.
Continuous evaluation and refining
the prompts is required for
more and more accurate results.
So this is coming to a conclusion.
And what are the best practices
required to, have an advanced prompting
to get a, best AI performance.
So happy prompting, get the
response effectively, keep looking
into, but kindly reach out to me
for any further clarifications.
Thank you.
Thank you for, today's session.