Good morning everyone.
I'm Nina Villa.
I'm a program manager
at three Code Solution.
Today I will walk you through on
how Enterprise can drive successful
large scale migration using the
process automation and AI innovation.
So over the next few minutes, we
will explore how automation transform
migration from one-time project
into a continuous capabilities
that fuel digital transformations.
I.
So first we will see the
evolution of enterprise migration.
In the past, migrations were simple lift
and shift activities, just moving the
workloads from one place to another.
Today, they have become far more
complex involving multiple teams,
tools, and compliance framework.
But the future is different.
It is about treating the migration
as a strategical capacity, so
continuous automated transitions where
system evolved dynamically without
disrupting the business operations.
So in today's world, automation
is no longer an optional.
It is a strategical necessity
for any organization.
So with respect to migration, manual
migration comes with a real pain points,
long project timeline, unpredictable
result, and a high risk of errors.
So automation directly addresses these
issues by shortening the delivery
timelines, improving the predictability.
Enhancing the data quality and freezing
the specialized team for innovation
instead of repetitive migration work.
So automation is not just about
speed, it's about reliability,
consistency, and governance.
Now we will see how migration can be
done in a scalable and a repeatable way.
So each organization should anchor
them around the below four pillars.
Number one, discovery automation.
Number two is a transformation engine
three is the orchestration platform, and
number four is the automated testing.
So each pillars complement
the other together.
They ensure every step from analysis to
execution is efficient and auditable.
So now we will move on with the
first step, which is nothing but
the discovery automation here.
The process will automatically
discover all the dependencies.
Data lineages and also the
system interconnection.
So in traditional method, documenting
this relationship to take weeks or months.
Now with this automated discovery, we can
visualize the entire ecosystem, understand
how every data source and the services
impact each other, and allowing the team
to plan the migration intelligently.
So once we know what to migrate,
automation help us to handle
the transformation at scale.
This includes automated schema,
conversion code, refactoring,
and bulk data migration.
For instance, tools can now convert
the Oracle schema to Postgres,
SQL rewrites store procedures,
and migrate the terabytes of
data with built-in validation.
The goal is accuracy, speed,
and minimal manual touch points.
So here we see the three most
common migration pattern.
Number one is the cloud migration, like
moving the workloads to AWS Azure or GCP.
The second one is the big data
modernization, like transitioning
from Hadoop to modern cloud platform.
And third one is the data
warehouse evolution modernizing
to a platform like Snowflake.
With automated schemas
and query translation.
So each pattern benefits largely from
automation, reducing the cost and
time while improving the confidence.
So now we move on with the
intelligent orchestration.
So even with automation,
orchestration is critical, like how
we sequence and monitor every step.
So intelligent orchestration
defines workflows.
Executes them automatically adapts
to condition in real time and
validate each stage continuously.
It's like having an air traffic controller
ensuring every migration activity runs
smoothly without collision or downtime.
So now we have come to the
last pillar, which is nothing
but the automation testing.
So automation testing ensures
quality and reliability across
every stages of migration.
It systematically validates each component
against the functional and the performance
benchmark, achieving a coverage that
manual testing can't even match.
So differential testing automatically
the source and the target systems
to catch the hidden logic or any
data issues early with real-time
monitoring and automated rollback.
Teams gain instant visibility and
can recover rapidly if problem arise.
So making migration faster, safer,
and far more predictable is the main
goal for this automation testing.
So now we are moving towards how AI had
exponential values to these migrations.
So mission learnings can
analyze previous migrations to
predict effort, cost, and risk.
And then the AI driven automation
process are just workflows dynamically
to resolve issues in real time.
And then the last one is
the predictive analytics.
Forecasting the potential
bottlenecks before they happens.
So these things allow the team to
act proactively rather than reactive.
So zero time migration strategies plays
a key role in all the organizations.
Business continuity is non-negotiable.
So modern strategies like continuous
replication, intelligent routing, and
instant rollback allows us to migrate
system without user even noticing.
This means that no weekend cut over, no
loss, productivity, and all migration
happens while the business keep running.
So the ultimate goal is to move beyond
project-based thinking and to make
migration and enterprise capability.
That means investing in automation
platform, nourishing skilled teams,
building repeatable frameworks, and
making a solid technology foundation
enterprise that do this can adapt quickly
to new technology and gain a competitive
edge through an agility and speed.
So here is a simple roadmap to start.
Assess your current migration process.
Define your target automation vision,
then implement gradually beginning
with the high impact use cases.
Then measure and optimize continuously.
It's about building momentum.
Start small, learn, and then
expand every success compounds
into a long-term transformation.
Thank you all for joining.
I hope the session gave you a new
perspective on how automation and AI
are redefining the enterprise migration.
So let's go and explore how we can
create more migration excellence
within our organizations.
Thank you.