Hi everyone.
I'm bna.
Thanks for joining me for the session.
Today I'm going to talk
about how to accelerate your
career via experimentation.
Think of the session as a field guide.
We'll hit experiment design patterns
that work in the wild, the platform
pieces that make experimentation fast
and trustworthy, and the career moves
that turn your work into impact.
My goal is that you leave with a playbook.
You can start using this week.
Before we jump into the session let
me take a minute and talk about myself
and why this topic matters to me.
I've spent over a decade helping teams
design and scale experimentation using
data to build products and solve business
problems, not just report on them.
My core craft is experimentation and
casual inference, choosing right design
for the constraint, measuring impact,
credibility, and translating results into
decisions On systems side, I design and
operationalize experimentation platforms.
So the tests are reproducible,
observable, and cheap to run.
And strategically, I'm obsessed with
connecting insights to outcomes,
turning analysis into decisions
leaders can trust, and building a
culture where data informed is default.
That combination, methodology,
platform, and business impact is
what I'll share with you today.
Let's quickly look at the agenda.
For today, we'll start with why
AB testing matters for your career
where experimentation experiments
create value, and how to choose
the right experiment design.
And we'll dive into some basic
statistical concepts and understand
some of the techniques that you can
use to speed up your experimentation
and then pivot to talking about how can
you build experimentation portfolio.
What are some of the tips for
interview success strategies And, we
will end this with an action plan.
Now let's start the session by
talking about why expertise in
the experimentation matters.
Now this is a high demand skill.
It's sought, highly sought after.
It's a combination of data science,
experiment design, and business
strategy in a measurable way.
Companies across all the industries
are desperately seeking for
professionals who can design,
implement, and interpret experiments
that drive real business outcomes.
And additionally, with advancements
in the large language models LMS are
being used in every part of the life.
It becomes crucial to validate the
results through experimentation.
Experimentation helps evaluate
prompts effectiveness, measure
change in the response quality,
detect biases, understand the
overall model behavior at scale.
Professionals who have
this are indispensable.
And the value of understanding core
principles of AB testing benefits
everyone, not just data analyst.
Engineers can build smarter
experiment ready systems.
Product managers can make evidence ba
based features and roadmap decisions.
It also has strategic impact through
cross functional collaboration
experimentation, bridges.
Data engineering decision design and
product teams helping you communicate
insights effectively and influencing
decision making across the organization.
The skill makes you indispensable
as the translator between technical
complexity and the business value.
Okay.
Now let's see where the
experiment creates value.
The answer is every department
in the modern organization can
leverage experimentation to
make data-driven decisions.
You can see some of the
examples here on the slide.
These are only a few examples, but
the key here is understanding which
experiment approach work best for
each use case and business context.
And now how do we choose
the right experiment design?
And let's look at what all.
Experiment designs are
available right now.
The start.
The first one is AB
testing, which is a classic.
This compares variance simultaneously
grade for feature releases and UI changes.
And the multivariate and factorial
is used to test multiple elements
and learn interaction effects.
Holdout studies are used.
To measure long term and network
effects that ac that accrue over
weeks, months, and sometimes a year.
Business constraints should pick
the design not the other way around.
When the traffic patterns and the
platform complicate things, switch
designs switchback experiments are used
to rotate by the time so that the same
unit cycles through both the variants.
Idle for marketplaces
and two-sided platforms.
Geo experiments randomized
by the region when user level
randomizations risk spillovers.
Useful for location-based
features and marketing.
If true randomization is not possible, use
credible alternatives such as difference
indifference interrupted time series,
synthetic controls difference indifference
compares before and after changes in
the treated group against a similar
control group that didn't get the change.
Interrupted time series looks at
the structural break, right when
the in intervention happened,
if the level or the slope jumps
at that point and nowhere else.
That's the signal synthetic control.
When you change something in one
big unit, say state or city build
a weighted virtual control from
the other units that didn't change.
So the pre-print matches yours.
Expert judgment matters.
Choose designs based on constraint.
Technical capability and interventions
nature, know when to deviate
from the pure randomization.
Okay, now let's jump and take a
look at the statistical concepts.
I wanna take a different direction here.
In talking about basic statistical
concepts, there are a lot of excellent
resources online that can teach you
about what exactly this concept is.
But today I wanna spend some time.
Talking about tying these concepts
to the business and why it's
important for business, how
can you think in those lines?
First hypothesis testing.
This drives clarity.
Knowing how to form good hypothesis
teaches structure, thinking.
It's not about is it better,
but what outcomes and why.
The mindset helps align experiments with
business strategy and ensures test has
clear success criteria before the launch.
Second one is the
confidence and uncertainty.
This builds trust.
Communicating uncertainty transparently
builds stakeholder confidence.
Leaders don't expect perfection.
They expect honest ranges and risk.
A this skill separates strategic
thinkers from report generators,
effect size and power.
This helps you prioritize what matters.
Understanding these concepts help
you focus on impactful changes,
not statistically trivial ones.
The multiple testing disciplines
today, we run hundreds and thousands
of experiments every month with number
of experiments and variance we test.
There comes a need to control
the false positive rate.
This protects business from
false wins and bad rollouts.
The last, not, but not the least.
The fifth one is sequential and thinking.
In today's world, we see a need
for faster experimentation.
To improve velocity of experimentation
and get continuous learnings, we
need modern techniques like SQL
Ambition to support adaptive learning.
We've look, now that we have looked
at sequential ambition, which
drives experimentation velocity,
let's also look at other techniques
in traditional experiment setup.
We have to wait for the larger samples.
This delay is experiment time, insight,
and thereby product development.
If you look at sample size formula
here the sample size is directly
proportional to the variance.
Thereby if you reduce the variance
by half, you'll reduce the sample
size by half by implementing.
Variance reduction techniques,
you can achieve statistical
significance faster with fewer users.
This translates to quicker decision
making, accelerated product iteration
and more experiments run overall
driving rapid innovation and growth.
Now that we have looked at the concept
of the variance reduction, let's look
at some variance reduction techniques.
So the first one, which is regression
adjustment with three period covariate.
This is an umbrella for Cupid and co-op.
Pre-post we pick one or
two strong pre-treatment
predictors at just the outcome.
This will help lower the variance.
We will look at cupid in
detail in the next slide.
Now let's go to the second
one, which is balance.
Assignment at launch is
blocking or stratification.
While you're randomizing.
So treatment and controls start
equal on the stuff that matters.
Third one is metric engineering.
Noise enumerators and denominators
and heavy tails blow up variance
instead of aggregating per user or
in aggregated per user cluster level
wind rise, extreme outliers, and lock,
transform the right skew metrics.
Cluster aware estimations
for geos or switchback tests.
Analyze cluster, block level or
use cluster robot robust standard
errors, exposure and eligibility
hygiene count only truly eligible
and actually expose users.
Freezing events definitions
prior to the experiment.
These are some, a few
variance reduction techniques.
Now let's look at Cupid in detail.
Cupid is one of the vastly used
variance reduction techniques in Cupid,
we reduce the variance by using the
pre-ex experiment data that can help
explain variance post experiment.
Let's look at an example.
Say we want to run a test to see if people
run slower with weights attached to them.
The experiment.
Mile time is a metric we get
when we run the experiment.
And corresponding row will tell you if
the weight were, the weights were added.
By looking at the data on the
right, you can already see that the
experiment, mile time is influenced
by how fast the runners already were
which is a baseline baseline my time.
In this case, we can leverage the
average baseline mile time to help
explain the difference in the variance
and use the change column, which is
a difference between the baseline
mile time and experiment mile time to
understand the impact of adding weights.
What we are doing here is using pre-ex
experiment data to reduce the variance.
That was explainable.
Some of the best practices are
using the variable that has high
correlation to the variable of interest.
When we are applying cupid there is no
need to stick with just one variable
from the pre-ex experiment period.
We can use multiple variables if
you believe that could reduce the
variance, effectively use baselines
that reflect the normal behavior.
Make sure the data only is from the prior
to the experiment period, not from the
period where the experiment is running.
You can handle missing data
by imputing the values.
A call out for people who are interested.
There are.
Some advancements, toin methodology called
qac, where in place of using regression
model and single or multiple covariates
from the pre-ex experiment period.
QAC uses machine learning models
to predict the baseline metrics
by leveraging multiple variables
from the pre-ex experiment period.
For those interested, I have
attached a link to this at
the end of the presentation.
Please feel free to take a look.
Now in this new era, we are,
it's also essential to master the
experimentation with experimentation
on LMS and prompt engineering.
So let's take a look at a couple
of use cases where we can leverage
experimentation to optimize large language
models and optimize the prompts that we
are giving the la large language models.
So the first one is prompt optimization
systematically comparing templates
few short examples and system
instructions to achieve superior
outcome, quality, and relevance.
The second use case for
experimentation is model benchmarking.
Evaluating performance across different
LLM architectures or fine tuned
versions of some effective models.
And third one is RA pipeline enhancements.
Optimizing RA by testing
retrieval strategies, chunking
methods, and ranking algorithms.
Fourth one is personalization
and contextualization.
Assessing how dynamic content
windows and user specific data define
models and boost user engagement.
The last one is proactively identifying
and mitigating harmful outputs,
biases and hallucinations through
comprehensive and systematic testing.
So there are a lot of use cases,
even within large language
models and prompt optimization.
And thinking about which
kind of experimentation
methodologies can you apply?
You can leverage normal AB testing,
multivariate testing, or contextual
bandwidths, depending upon the
requirement and the evaluation that you
wanna perform for offline evaluation,
you can use automated frameworks.
Syn synthetic data can be leveraged
and we can use the LLM as a judge
method to to for the faster iterations.
Okay.
Now that we have an idea of what
experimentation is, basics of the
experimentation and how to improve the
speed of the experimentation, let's
look at some of the common pitfalls.
If it seems too good to
be true, it probably is.
Whenever you find results that
are extreme, it's always good to
check against common pitfalls.
Now we can think of common
footfalls in four broad categories.
The first one is technical
implementation issues.
That is sample ratio,
mismatch logging gaps.
When a unit of randomization
is different from the unit of
analysis, it inflates variance.
The second one is experiment, design,
floss interference and contamination.
Because the units in the control
and treatment have impact on one
other statistical analysis errors,
if you have a need to peak at just
the false positive rate so that
there is no room for p hacking.
Fourth one is contextual challenges
and some additional challenges like
metric grift, seasonality et cetera.
Now we have covered, oh.
Common pitfalls and e testing.
Let's look at how to use this
to accelerate your career.
Understanding and partic practicing
these concepts will enhance your
analytical maturity, your shift,
your mindset from reactive to
proactive experimentation strategy.
This will also help you challenge.
Opinions of leaders with evidence
and guide strategic decisions,
you will become a person.
Bridging the gap between
cross-functional teams, translating
stats into business impact.
All this will differentiate you in
the market and make you invaluable.
Now let's look at how to build
the experimentation portfolio.
If you're just starting out there
are three key steps to building
experimentation portfolio.
Working and documenting
realistic scenarios.
Document the process, showing problem
identification, hypothesis development,
experimental design choices, statistical
methods with the CRE business rational.
Start by contributing to o open
source contribute to experimentation,
frameworks and statistical libraries
like a stats model, PMC, cetera.
Show business impact.
Think about end-to-end demonstration.
Develop a mindset to I trade
an idea instead of one and
done kind of experiments.
I also wanna share some success
strategies for interviews.
Interview Success in the
experimentation field requires
not only technical expertise.
But also mastery of concepts
and being able to explain it in
simple terms to stakeholders.
Prepare specific examples where
your experimentation work drove
measurable business outcomes.
End-to-end experimentation
knowledge on how experimentation
fits into larger ecosystem and
how to run experiments at scale.
A combination of these three would
help you be successful in interviews.
For anybody who is starting out you
must be curious on how the trajectory
of an IC looks in their science field
specializing in experimentation.
So here is an outlook.
This is a broad, I broad view of
how the TRA trajectory would look.
An entry level candidate would be
expected to have rock solid AB testing
fundamentals, clean hypothesis,
reproducible analysis, and clear writing.
When you think about the mid-level,
it's, the person in this role will
be leading multiple experiments,
mentoring analysts diving into
sequential and standardizing guardrails.
A senior would set experimentation
strategy partner with engineering to.
Drive the platform experimentation
platform drive cross function.
Cross org decisions with quantified impact
principal or staff would shape the system.
Pla develop roadmaps, contribute to
open sources, conference talks teach
the organization on how to learn faster.
So this is a general idea of
how the trajectory would look.
Now to summarize everything that we
have looked at till now there are
three key takeaways and the first one
is develop deep technical expertise.
The second one is pair it
with strong business acumen.
Last but not the least, is master
end-to-end experimentation ecosystem.
Together, these three form
foundation of successful career.
I will end my talk with the action plan.
I would highly encourage for the people
exploring data science carriers to
specialize in experimentation to start
today, engage with community, share the
learnings, and learn from the community.
Stay current with emerging
trends in experimentation.
The experimentation field evolves
rapidly with new statistical methods.
Staying current would
differentiate you from others.
And with that I'll end the presentation.
Thanks for being here.
Thanks for taking time.
Please reach out to me on LinkedIn if you
have any questions or simply wanna chat
about experimentation or career, or if
you wanna, I'll talk about anything else.
I'll be happy to.
Connect.
Thanks for the time.
Thank.
Thanks everyone.