Hello everyone.
I am RA principal, Salesforce engineer
and platform architect at ON 24.
I'm excited to be speaking
at Con 42 Prompt in day 2025.
It's a space where we explore
how to make AI systems more
reliable and human aligned.
My talk today is titled
Prompting for Trust.
It's about how we as builders can design
prompts that make large language morals
not just accurate, but trustworthy.
In enterprise AI trust is the
real adoption barrier, and it
starts long before deployment.
Here's what we'll walk through today.
First we'll look at the trust
challenge in enter enterprise ai.
Then we will talk about why
trust starts right at the prompt.
We will move into five core principles
for trust building prompts, some real
world case studies, and we'll finish
with the roadmap and key takeaways
that can apply in own ecosystems.
The trust challenge in enterprise ai.
In many organizations, LMS are
already running chatbots, co-pilots,
and decision supporting tools, but
performance alone doesn't create
adoption if users can't explain how
or why an LLM reached its answer.
They won't act on it.
That's the trust gap.
An invisible friction
that slows AI rollout.
You'll see systems technically capable
but unused because people don't
feel confident in their reasoning.
So the challenge isn't about model
capability, it's about human confidence.
Trust begins at the prompt layer.
That's why we instruct the model,
determine the way we instruct.
The model determines how it behaves.
Three areas matter most.
Prompt design where we control
how the model frames its answers,
sites information and expresses
uncertainty, context, scaffolding
where we give structured content.
So outputs used enterprise language,
and comply with regulations and output
performing where we make reasoning
visible and easy to validate downstream.
So prompt engineering isn't
about better responses.
It's about designing comprehension,
accountability, and alignment into
every interaction, core principles
of trust building prompts.
Now let's talk about the five principles
that make prompts trustworthy.
Confidence tagging, ask
the model to label outputs.
As act now needs review
and seek expert input.
Source of attribution, make the model side
documents or reasoning sources directly.
Adaptive clarification.
Let the model ask for more information
when the user's intent is unclear.
Progressive disclosure show high
level insights first and then
deeper details only when requested.
Audit trail integration embed metadata
into outputs so every decision
can be placed and audited later.
Together.
These principles make the system
transparent, accountable, and
easier to trust confidence.
Drug tagging in action.
Here's what it looks like in practice.
Instead of just outputting data, the model
says defect rate, moderate coined action,
inspect the proportion of the batch.
Now the user instantly understands the
level of certainty and the next step.
It's no longer an answer.
It's guided contextual response.
Conference tagging gives users permission
to act or to validate further with clarity
lining outputs with enterprise context.
One major reason why trust
breakstone is context mismatch.
Gmic elements don't understand
your organization's vocabulary,
regulatory boundaries or thresholds.
So the solution is structured.
We inject domain vocabulary like.
Qualified or material risk.
We embed regulatory S like GDPR
or SOC compliant requirements,
and then we define thresholds.
Specifying, specifying where to
escalate, approve, or send for human.
This ensures that model outputs
are consistent with enterprise
policies and human judgment building.
Building feedback loops into prompts.
Trust isn't something you design once.
It's something you maintain.
That's why Facebook
feedback loops are critical.
When users correct an error response,
that signal can be captured right
into that chat or orchestration layer.
Then we refine prompts, identify
failure models, and then we fine
tune models based on real feedback.
A trustworthy system doesn't just
doesn't just answer it like, here's a
case study lead qualification assistant.
Here's a real example.
Sales reps are ignoring
AI generated lead scores.
The issue wasn't accuracy,
it was explanation.
So we redesigned the prompts
to incur confidence tags.
Source citations and structuring
the reasoning change.
The result is 71% more follow up actions
and 34% improvement in conversations.
Nothing changed in the model.
Only the prompts.
That's the power of trust centered design.
One more case study
summarization pipeline.
It's a legal documentation summary.
Teams refuse to trust AI
Aries without every clause.
We updated prompts to add section
level attribution and highly.
Ambiguous losses or deviations
with standard templates.
Suddenly the review time
dropped drastically and the
user conference rose near 90%.
Once people could see where each statement
came from, trust followed naturally.
This is one more yesterday,
decision support chat bot.
When asked, should we
approve this vendor contract?
The older version answered immediately.
The improved version asked, is
this a new vendor or a renewal?
What's the contract value when it checks?
Spend thresholds and compliance
before recommending approval?
That small shift gathering, missing
context first dramatically increased
user reliability and trust.
Structured prompting techniques
to make this scalable.
We used structured prompting patterns.
Schema driven outputs force
the model to respond in JSON
or it, so systems can validate
automatically, chain automatically.
Chain of thought prompting makes
the models show its reasoning
before giving the final.
And conditional instructions
handle edge cases.
For example, if data is missing,
it'll ask for clarification.
These design patterns create
transparency by default.
This slide shows the transformation
clearly before black box outputs.
No, no visibility.
No confidence signals.
Low user engagement After transparent
designing chains, source attribution,
confidence tagging, and context awareness.
When you treat prompt layer.
As a design service, not a technical
input, you turn alarms from opaque
responders into trusted collaborators.
Now looking at the implementation
roadmap, here's how to get
started in your own environment.
Step one or current prompts, find where
ambiguity or opacity creates trust gaps.
Redesign for transparency, add
tags and verification triggers.
Test with real users, validate
comp comprehension and usability.
And I trade based on feedback.
Keep refining instructions
to close landing lobes.
Trust is not a feature,
it's a continuous process.
So the key takeaways, trust is
designed, you can architect.
Transparency, accountability and
alignment through intentional
prompt design context is critical.
Structured prompting users.
Reflect your enterprise
vocabulary and policies.
Feedback drives improvement the most
trusted systems evolve with user input.
And finally, users trust
what they understand.
When we combine confidence tagging,
attribution, and progressive
disclosure, your AI stocks being a
mystery, becomes a reliable partner.
Thank you for your time and attention
to this Con 42 prompting 3 20 25.
I'm Raku and I hope these ideas
help you design prompt strategies
that earn trust, not just s Feel
free to connect and continue the
discussion on building transparent,
human aligned element systems.
Thank you very much.