My name is Harpreet Singh.
I'm going to talk about how do we
leverage the sales data analytics to
optimize the pharmaceutical drug launches.
So I'm going to talk about some of the
typical challenges we have, when we
are talking about the drug launches,
how data analytics, work as a solution.
I'll also cover some of the aspects
of the predictive modeling AI
machine learning, in the scenarios.
also we'll look at, some of
the, cases where the real time
analysis help with the insights.
Also, we will, we'll cover some of
the KPIs and then we talk about some
of the advanced data architecture in
the industry and then some of the best
practices, for these analytics deployment.
So I think to start with, I think
the very first thing about when
you think about any drug launch
in the pharmaceutical industry.
It takes a lot of time and efforts
and resources if you think about
an average one, Development
of one product costs around 2.
6 billion dollars It provides you an
exclusivity of few years So then I think
the market timing and entry is critical
also as a first product It gives you
a competitive advantage in the in that
therapeutic area Also, I think the the
initial months are very critical because
that's where 60 percent of the revenue is
generated in like just first six months of
the launch so For the companies it is very
important then they optimize these launch
strategies To make sure that they are in
their highest revenue potential right and
helping a lot of patients at the same time
so now Let's talk about, we understand the
challenges, but how do the data analytics,
from the sales side help with that?
So I think the sales data analytics,
in the launch phase, for the product
provide real time data insights,
which help you to optimize in
every step of the cycle, right?
So for example, if you
think about a forecasting.
different predictive models can be
used, to forecast of the product
revenue and which are typically
in a very good accuracy range.
also, there's a lot of element
of the real time data processing.
There's a lot of rich
data on the pharma side.
So processing of those data also
provide you a quick insights
to react on the market events.
Also based on this, We are able
to penetrate a market potential
or market share at a higher rate.
So all these different elements of
the analytics and data addresses these
challenges and then we'll talk some of
those in details in the next few slides.
I think the very first thing is about when
you think about the advanced analytics,
predictive modeling, AI, machine
learning, we do have a lot of data, right?
So if you think about the data
from the prescriber, from the
doctors, patient level data, medical
claims, hospitals buying product.
So there's a lot of rich data.
That's where a lot of, AI
algorithm can be used to provide
those insights and insights.
Some of the capabilities of the
predictive models can be related
to how do you target the physician.
So if you want to look at which doctors
you need to target for the pre launch
and the post launch phase, a lot of
AI driven segmentation we created,
then you can look at who are the high
potential prescriber and then you
can optimize the engagement for that.
Also from the pricing point of
view, there are different models
available where you can use.
multiple inputs and have Provide what
should be the right price for the
product and providing the competitive
advantage at the same time I think
when you think about these models, they
have evolved a lot in last few years
right now We are talking about 80 to
90 percent accuracy in these models.
So we are getting a really good accuracy
from these predictive models when you
think about the insights Also, a lot of
these models can also be used for the
territory deployment and that provide
an efficiency of at least 30 percent
efficiency with the, with deploying
those territories for the launches.
I think the other important thing, when we
think about a lot of data, you think about
there's like millions of data points,
also because that launch is so crucial.
There's limited time frame when we
have to react a company has to react
on the market events So real time data
processing definitely helps a lot.
And then if you think about the real
time processing Reduce the market
response time from 15 days to like few
days and like maybe three days, right?
So these Definitely improved
accuracy in forecasting.
you can you are able to predict things
more accurately also at the same time You
Any kind of adjustment you need to make,
in, in, in that launch strategy, you can
do it like as less as like in 72 hours.
so these are very critical things
and timely things during the
first six months of the launch.
And then, before the launch and
after the launch, there are a lot
of KPIs which play a critical role,
in understanding if the product is
on a right path for the success.
these KPIs are derived by different
data analytics, pieces around it.
So when you think about, I think we
have some of the examples here, think
about the conversion rate, right?
So when you launch a product,
how many doctors have actually
prescribing this product?
So definitely, I think the, if you can
achieve 15, 20 percent conversion in
first three months, that kind of correlate
with 85 percent of the probability of you
would achieve, your first year target.
Also, when you think about the patients,
the persistency on adherence to the
product is also important, right?
So how long a patient is staying on
therapy for 3 months, 6 months, right?
So if you have a good persistency, good
adherency, you have a very high chances
of product is getting a successful launch.
So these early conversion rate, provides
a momentum for the launch, for the
commercial success and higher persistency
definitely build that brand loyalty
and market leadership at the end.
so these benchmarks, these KPIs, you
can track them on a weekly basis.
You can track them on the monthly
basis based on the objective
of their brand launches.
So now I think, There are
different pieces, right?
I think we talk about the AI, predictive
models and then the real time, generation.
also we talk about this plethora of data
across doctors, hospitals, patients.
The other important thing with
that much of data, you also need, a
very high processing speed, right?
So we are talking about
like petabytes of data.
So now a lot of pharma companies
are spending A lot of money on their
infrastructure around the data warehouse
right on the aws cloud based system.
So to process this kind of data, right?
So there's definitely a lot of cloud based
warehouse that can handle like millions
of transaction per second Once you set up
these infrastructure on top of that We are
implementing like python or r kind of a
language which Provides you these models
and these high accuracy Also hundreds
of dashboards are built on top of that.
So you have your data structure then
your python and r and then you have a
lot of dash dashboard tableau dashboard.
You think about Power bi dashboard that
also helps you to see how What's happening
in the market and then these dashboard
create like I would say hundreds of report
for different customers based on their
need like sales marketing finance etc I
think with all of these things in place.
and helping a successful launch.
I think there are some best
practices right across the
industry, which we have seen.
I think the first thing we just touched
about, the data quality has to be there.
It's garbage in, garbage out, right?
If your data quality is not
good, you will not have that
highest, higher accuracy, right?
And there, there are definitely a
dedicated team in, in, in the pharma
companies, which are working on the
lot of validation process, right?
To make sure that the millions of
records what we are having has a higher
accuracy and it's a good quality data
they have a lot of different Framework
on data governance, which provides you
like continuous audit of this humongous
data Also the other thing when you
think about the best practices, there
are a lot of different models Which
requires resources and An effort to
implement that so one of the Approaches
maybe apply a pilot product, right?
So for example, you want to have a
prediction model which predict how many
new patient will come into the market
So instead of doing like a full fledged
national level implementation, which
would require millions of dollar You
can start with a small territory, right?
You start with one territory and
test that model and Get that feedback
from the sales and marketing and
do you see a value out of it?
So This phase approach definitely help
you so you start with territory and then
based on that You can apply that fine
tune the model and apply throughout the
nation so these Scalable implementation,
definitely give you a lot of confidence
and at the same time these models are
built based on feedback, during the pilot
phase The kpis we talk about so they're
like at least 50 kpis pre launch and
post launch With a higher accuracy that
also provide a critical insights right
throughout that and then if you have to
do a course correction You can do it do
that during that launch phase Also, I
think that the model updates and then is
are there any biases and the consistent
performance tracking is also a critical
piece I think with that maybe I think
just A conclude all of these thing is
that the integration of the sales state
analytics and in pharmaceutical industry
has proven to be transformative right
and providing a substantial improvement
in terms of the market penetration
the resource optimization a successful
launch so so definitely is solving a very
complex challenge, right and then We talk
about the development cost and then how
compressing the launch window and then the
traditional methods like previous methods
were, I think it's helping we, it's
helping us to overcome those challenges.
And then advanced predictive modeling,
AI, machine learning, these are,
even accelerating these insights
for the company and making sure
that the launches are successful.
So results, and I think
the approaches are clear.
The pharmaceutical companies are
implementing these data driven
strategies on an average of 30 23
percent improvement on launch trajectory.
And then they see a higher market
penetration and significantly
reduced response time.
with that, that's all from my side.
Thank you.