My name is Hari Ramshetty
and I'm a software engineer
on the infrastructure team.
today I'll be talking about cloud
cost optimizations and how you can
use FinOps and FinOps practices
to reduce your AWS cloud costs.
Today I'll also touch briefly
on how you can use AI powered
tools like ChargerBT, cloud.
Gemini and Llama to help
you reduce the cloud cost.
I'll also touch briefly on the AI
agentic approach using the Lang chain
and crew AI where you can build your
own agents that will help you with
the cloud cost optimization process.
I'm excited for this talk.
So let's just get started.
some introductions.
I'll be going through, introducing what
is a cloud native cost optimization.
What are some of the cost drivers
in cloud native platforms?
What are some of the resource
management techniques?
some container and serverless
optimization, some storage and
data management, monitoring
and cost observability.
what is finops?
A cultural approach to
what cost optimization.
And then I'll deep dive into
leveraging prompt engineering and
finops to drive cloud efficiency.
So let's get started.
So the first thing is.
Like what is a cloud native platform?
The cloud native platform
is a platform that lets you
build and deploy applications
seamlessly on the public cloud.
It can be on any container orchestration
platform like Kubernetes, ECS or EKS.
You have AKS for Azure
Community Service or GCP.
So whatever the public cloud may be.
So those are called as
cloud related platforms.
So this is where you
deploy your applications.
And these environments tend to be dynamic
and complex in nature because setting up
requires like you need to set up a VPC,
you need to set up a security groups, you
need to set up a whole bunch of virtual
networking, and also you need to deploy
the deploy and maintain the virtual
machines, which we call EC2 instances.
so each cloud providers
have their own terminology.
At the end of the day, it's
just like virtual machines.
so some of the statistics show that,
30 percent of the cloud spending is
basically due to resource mismanagement.
And this tends to be true, because
you often have engineering teams, who
spin up these instances, spin up the
new databases for testing purposes.
they tend to build new features, which are
sometimes abandoned because the business
doesn't require them and they're never
turned off or decommissioned properly.
this is the source of the problem.
Like increasing cloud cost and, the
objective of this presentation covers
strategies for optimizing costs in
cloud entity setups and also enabling
financial responsibility without
compromising on agility or scalability.
So let's get started.
So what are some of the cost
drivers in cloud native platforms?
The first thing that comes to our
mind is virtual machines, compute.
So compute comes in
various different forms.
It can be like easy to virtual machines
that are managed by us or it can be
like a lambda, like function as a
service that can be, managed by AWS.
AWS.
So for the virtual machines that are
managed by us, like the cloud providers
give us a variety of virtual machines.
They're like the smaller virtual
machines and some are like a very
resource intensive, CPU intensive or
memory intensive virtual machines.
Now each have their own pricing model
and, Data like they tend to be more
expensive, as they scale vertically.
Now, the serverless executions are
a tricky bit because it lets you
execute a function as a service.
But if you call that function like 100,
000 times, it tends to get expensive.
So there's no benefit of
using function as a service.
when you're calling it frequently.
So the next type of, the
cost driver is storage.
Storage comes in three forms.
You have block storage, you have object
storage, and you have RDS, databases.
Now the object storage is S3.
So S3 is pretty scalable.
So we tend to fill up our
S3 buckets with S3 buckets.
We have a bucket sprawl, where we
store tons, like terabytes of data.
Sometimes this data is used,
sometimes it's not used.
we tend to ship most of our logs
into these buckets, and these
are put in sanity arguments.
And if we forget to put a lifecycle
policy on this, it tends to get expensive.
That is one of the cost drivers
and it applies the same for AWS
block store like EBS volumes.
So every virtual machine has a
block store, like EBS volumes.
You delete the virtual machine,
but you don't delete the volumes.
The volume is still available, but it's
detached from the eStroke machine, but you
are still being charged for the storage.
The next one is RDS databases.
the databases are like Aurora PostgreSQL
or like similar such databases.
sometimes these databases are over
provisioned with much higher IOPS.
like you don't need that scale
of RDS databases because you
don't have that much volume.
We tend to over provision things because
we expect the volume to grow someday.
But that is a problem for the another day.
The next cost driver is data transfer.
So Data transfer charges are
often overlooked because they
Creep up in your AWS cloud.
So think of this as in an organization
It's not just like one single account
you have 10 different accounts.
Some are broad.
Some are non prod.
You have one account per team You And
they have their own VPC and they want to
connect to another VPC in another account.
You have the NAT gateways, you have
the transfer gateways, you do VPC
peering, you do cross AZ transfers.
there are multiple different
layers of networking abstractions
that is, that really blends this.
Data transfer, charges you don't
expect these charges to be like, simple
There's okay cut here so the next one is
data transfer charges So the data transfer
charges are the cost from network egress
charges, which is if you have multiple,
AWS accounts in an organization and
each account has its own VPC and you're
trying to connect these VPCs using net
gateways or VPC pairings and you have
applications in multiple different VPCs
trying to continues to talk to each other.
There's a charge for that, and these, if
not control, these charges tend to be.
increasing if there's, for
example, there's a spike in a
traffic, from one VPC to another,
you see a data transfer charges.
The next one, the most probably
is a third party services.
So all the cloud providers,
provide, third party APIs.
Through their portal and basically they
have their own subscription models.
For example, you have red hat licenses
for the ec2 machines That are provisioned
through aws account now these Sometimes
these licenses are managed through
your cloud provider but if not managed
properly these tend to Add additional
burden to your AWS cloud build.
So what are the common challenges?
So these challenges are pretty much
common over entire cloud architectures.
One is over provisioning.
So over provisioning means you're
over provisioning, compute for the
application that it doesn't require.
So you are giving excessive resources
To the applications and this
causes so for example, you have an
application that uses like only 10
percent of the CPU and you are And the
remaining 90 percent of the cpu time
is under that is over provisioning.
The second one is lack of visibility so
Resource usage is not often clear because
It's easy for, in the cloud providers
make it easy for you to provision
resources and you don't see the impact of
provisioning these resources immediately.
Until you get a bill at the end of the
month, so There is not an instant alert
that lets you know that okay this action
that I have taken Is increasing the
cloud cost so the lack of visibility
is often one of the common challenges
There's multi cloud complexity.
So Most of the organizations are on
single, cloud provider, but there are
other, organizations that do multi cloud,
where some of those resources are on AWS
and some of the resources are on GCP.
we had an instance where, some of the
engineers were working on a hackathon
project, and, This was like three
years ago and they forgot to turn
off the instances in like the google
cloud account because most of our Work
goes in one single cloud provider.
It's hard to keep track of all the
resources in a multi cloud environment
so resource managing techniques Right
sizing so right sizing ensures that
the allocation matches the workload.
So You There are multiple
tools that help us do this.
There's And this works on
various different levels.
So for example, you have AWS tools
like AWS trusted advisor Which lets you
know, okay, these are the databases that
haven't had connections in the past few
days or These are the idle instances
that are not getting any traffic.
These are the idle EBS volumes Which
are not attached to any EC2 instances.
So The AWS Trusted Advisor is such
a tool that's really helpful for
you to know which resources are
not used anymore so that you can
deprovision them appropriately.
And also the right sizing, I would,
and when it comes to containers,
so the right sizing, like for
example, you have Kubernetes.
And kubernetes has limits and requests
so requests make sure that you have
certain amount of cpu and memory And
there's a limit so, understanding how
much your application needs Because you
have the observability tools in the mix.
So once you have these observability
tools you can Say, Hey, how much,
this is the amount of CPU that I need.
I don't need one gig, memory
and five virtual CPUs.
I can just get by one virtual CPU.
And like 4.
5 gigs of RAM.
Now this, so understanding what
your application requires and
appropriately setting those
configurations is rightsizing.
Autoscaling.
So autoscaling is dynamically adjusting
your resources based on real time demand.
And this is much more impractical scenario
applied on various levels of abstraction.
So AWS provides what's called as
an auto scaling group where like
you can provision more nodes in
the cluster Like automatically
based on a certain threshold.
So for example, let's just say you have 10
ec2 instances In an auto scaling loop and
you have a spike in traffic because you
are running some thanksgiving Promotion
and you're expecting these traffic
to go up and you need more instances.
Now setting an autoscaling group and
letting it expand, let the autoscaling
group add more nodes to deploy
applications like, horizontal scalability
is called autoscaling and basically you
need to be aggressive with autoscaling.
You have to set up proper thresholds
because once It's not just scale up.
You should also scale down
once the peak is over.
The next one is instance types.
So one of the instance types that all
the cloud provider I think all the cloud
providers provide is like spot instances.
So spot instances are like much cheaper
than the regular instances, but they
don't Guarantee the availability they
come at much lesser cost but They can
be terminated at any point of time by
your cloud provider Now these, spot
instances are pretty much useful for
various different tasks like CICD,
you have like batch processing, where
you have the one off job where you
want to process a bunch of records
and you spin up these spot instances.
The next one is reserved instances.
So reserved instances are ones you know
that you need a minimum number of records.
instances in your autoscaling group
or your cluster and instead of like
dynamically provisioning it you said,
Hey, I need this number of cbus at all
time And that's when you go to your cloud
provider and say hey, I need this compute
365 days 24 hours a day And that's when
you go to the reserved instances to make
sure like you get a long term discount
and of course Like that's the best for the
applications that run 365 days 24 hours
And the second one is on demand instances.
So the on demand instances are
used for short term variable needs.
As you all know, this is the most common
type of the easy to use instances that
we use, in our cloud architectures.
So one more thing I want to talk about
here is the density optimization.
so in containers and serverless,
Models, you have a container
that runs your application.
You have a bunch of various small tiny
containers that run on a single node.
So thanks to docker and kubernetes
Building and deploying containers has
become pretty much easy, for everyone
and also like Integrating kubernetes
has proven to be a substantial
feature cost savings, for the cloud.
one such thing is the
density optimization.
density optimization means you include
more number of containers per node.
you provision, one big node and basically,
deploy multiple small containers or,
configure your Kubernetes, to deploy
these applications on like a single node.
So that is density optimization like
More number of, pods on a single node.
So this helps you like use less
nodes, but also like you have
like more number of containers.
There's no idle CPU time or idle
memory that gets wasted here.
So the next one is node autoscaling.
So the node autoscaling, as we talked
before, it's similar to, auto scaling
group you as you get more and more
demand, you add different nodes.
So in the Kubernetes, environments,
we use, carpenter, one of the
cluster, and also there is a cluster
auto scaler, which adds the nodes.
To kubernetes
and also There are some of
the optimizations that you
can do is execution times.
So One other thing is we want to see like
for example, if there is a job kubernetes
job that's running in a pod and Basically
that part is stuck in a flashback loop.
Now.
We need to keep track of these
Restarts And make sure that this
don't occur because Oftentimes,
this is a wastage of resource.
So a single kubernetes job is
supposed to perform a job and then
Just complete it the part should die.
and the other one is reducing idle
times so implement efficient cold
start strategies to minimize idle
costs, so Whenever there's a new part
spins up you have the application
inside it running You The application
needs to spin up whatever the JVM or
other, software that it needs to run.
so we, we can do some strategies at the
application layer to reduce the idle time.
Next one is code optimization.
So minimum minimize dependencies and
optimize code for better memory and
cpu usage you can take a look at the
flame graphs Like see if there's any
like potential memory leaks in your
application and fix those there's
These are the smaller optimizations,
but overall they compound to,
significant cost optimizations.
The storage and data management.
So one of the things that we can
do for cloud cost optimization is
implement policies, to move data across
storage tiers based on expertise.
For example, you have, Like a doc that
you want to store for the compliance
reasons, but it's not Accessed frequently.
So what do you do?
You store it in a like less accessed
year, which is lesser cost and basically
you implement a lifecycle policy where
An object you can it might be a document
or any other it's a log file like it's
goes through a different phases of
tiers And it's stored in archived, and
this helps you reduce like the storage
cost for S3 or other object storage.
The other thing that we can do is
data compression and deduplication.
So techniques like data deep compression,
And the application reduced storage needs.
basically because you have a hundred
DB file, you can just compress
it aggressively to make sure like
you have 10 GB or 20 GB file.
the regular audits.
So routine audits also help identify
and remove unnecessary data.
sometimes you only want to
store seven years worth of data.
Data and the data that's
more than seven years.
You don't need it.
So Performing regular audits on the
data helps you Like access like reduce
your cloud costs monitoring and cost
visibility, so Continuous monitoring.
So continuous monitoring is
essential for identifying
unexpected usage spikes and tracking
resources like utilization trends.
So this means that we need to always
expect that if there is a spike,
There's actually a bug somewhere that's
causing the spike and we need to set
up appropriate monitoring and alerting
to let know to let us know that, hey,
there's a spike that means something or
there's a bug and production or other
environments that's causing the spike.
There's AWS Cost Visibility Tools.
AWS Cost Explorer is one such tool
that helps us deep dive into what
resources are we using, like what are
the cost patterns, like how much we
are going to be spending, in particular
month based on the current usage.
And this gives us a visibility into
how much the change in configuration
can lead to the increase in cloud
costs So and also we can set up budgets
and alerts so we can do spending
thresholds On a particular aws account.
Let's just say we have a thousand dollars
Maximum budget on an AWS account running
as example application now We can set up
alerts when basically there is a spike or
when the forecast is more than The current
budget and we can set up alerts And we
can fix what's causing what resources were
provisioned That's causing this alerts to
get fired up There's cost allocation tags,
the so the cost allocation tags is one of
the crucial parts of Cloud cost management
because it lets you know which team which
project or which department you this
resource belongs to and how much it costs
because It's all about unit economics.
So how much so for example, if you're
doing a transaction of hundred dollars
How much you're actually spending
for the cloud is what matters?
so if you're making a hundred dollars
in a transaction and you're spending
eighty dollars on a cloud cost
That's not a viable business model
finops.
So finops is a cultural approach to
cost Optimization So finops provides
a framework for cost management that
integrates financial accountability into
cloud spending it just means that It's
a culture shift where finance teams are
more involved, with the engineering teams
like we Like it's a shared responsibility
between all the teams to make sure that
we are operating the cloud effectively
and basically, like at a low at a
lower cost and this also One of the
principles of the FinOps is that the,
the engineering teams should be able
to know, what are the repercussions of
their actions of provisioning resources.
And it should be near instant, or at
least it should be like, the predicted
cost should be like, visible to the
team so that they can take active, steps
to like, to not cross their budgets.
Thanks.
Etc.
And so this helps, developers and
the engineering teams know that, hey,
I want to make a design decision,
but cost is also one of them.
So these are all the principles
of FinOps and implementing FinOps,
will help like organizations
make like cloud use much easier.
leveraging AI and FinOps
to drive cloud efficiency.
AI powered tools can continuously monitor
cloud usage and expenses in real time.
for example, you have all this data
about billing and cloud usage, like
how much cloud we are using, how
much idle time, how much busy time.
Now, we can train some AI models,
Based on the data that we collect
and based on that, we can design the
tools that can say, Hey, at this point
in time, you, like you are going to
have a spike in load and that way.
So you can predict that you might need
resources at certain point of time.
And this helps team prepare for
if they need any resources at
certain point anomaly detection.
So AI algorithms can also analyze
historical spending data to detect cost
anomalies and irregularities allowing
businesses to address these issues from
So there's always anomalies in the data
so It might be like as I said before it
might be some bug that's causing a spike
at one point of time Another for example
There is if you are, the NAT gateway cost.
So the data transfer cost, there's
a spike There's a huge bunch
of requests that's going out.
There's data that's coming in There's
ingress data and basically that's there.
That's an anomaly because some
there's a misconfiguration on the
Network side that's caused this spike.
Now AI algorithms can Detect this
cost anomalies and attributed to hey
this change has cost this much to the
organization eliminating inefficient
resource use so ai can help eliminate
idle cloud resources and unused resources
by automatically shutting down or
resizing them Reducing wasteful spending.
I'll talk more about this in the ai
agentic approach yeah, let's move forward.
Demand forecasting and autoscaling.
As I already said, AI can predict
the future demand for the cloud
resources, enabling better planning and
deployment, and dynamically adjusting
resources to avoid over provisioning.
using prompt engineering for
achieving cloud efficiency.
This is what we have been waiting for.
As you guys already know, the
prompt engineering is how you
talk to AI models to get the job.
And one of the key things about the
prompt engineering is role prompting.
So what is role prompting?
So role prompting is a
technique in prompt engineering.
to control the output generated
by the model by assigning a
specific role to the AI model.
This can be any model.
I just used shared GPT example
here, but it can be cloud, it
can be llama, it can be Gemini
or any AI model that's GPT based.
So we can make use of rules like
FinOps Expert and craft prompts by
providing more context to the prompt.
Let's see a couple of examples.
So some of the prompts using
the FinOps Expert rule.
So here what I did try was, as a
FinOps Expert, can you please help
deep dive into our AWS Cloud Build?
Please explain what is different
unplanted costs And I'm an amortized cost.
So as someone who is coming
to like cloud billing Like
specifically it was cloud billing.
There are multiple different types
of costs like you have like unplanned
costs You have amortized costs and
there are multiple different costs.
So to get you Understand, AMRLs can
definitely help you to do that and you
can use roles like FinOps Expert to help
you guide how to implement the FinOps
best practices in your organization.
This is one of the experiments that I did.
So you can also use as a FinOps Expert.
Can you analyze our AWS invoice
and let us know why our AWS
bill was higher than usual?
Can you please provide details,
detailed report on how could
we reduce our AWS spend?
Now, this is a very specific prompt
and I'm also giving some context
to the AI model so that it knows.
I've also gave the invoice and let the
AI Like why was the spend like, you
know increased in the previous month so
Since we are talking on the same page.
so one of the things that is popular
is Like most people are trying to
get now is ai agentic approach.
So ai agentic approach is Like we
build ai agents to get the job done.
So for example You can build
an ai agent That would monitor
The usage of a resource.
Let's just say there is a
resource that says hey this
Resource is been idle for a while.
It's not even taking connections.
Let me you know, shut down that
server I will let the infrastructure
institute know that this is happening
and I will let them and i'll shut
down the like the database temporarily
Now this is what an ai is Agentic.
AI approaches so we can build
like simple ai agents So
there's two amazing resources.
One is lang chain.
One is crew ai They use prompts under
the hood the prompt engineering so they
can act as a part of automation And they
can talk to any of the ai models that are
currently available like chat gpt cloud
or any other open source models, and
basically, like you build an AI agent that
will help you, implement these actions,
for cost optimization on your behalf.
let's get to the conclusion.
so cost optimization in cloud platforms
requires a comprehensive approach.
that balances technical strategies
with organization shifts.
it's not always easy.
the cloud native platforms
are, like, increasing.
there's a need for the
cloud platforms that operate
efficiently and at a lower cost.
By understanding the primary cost drivers
such as compute resources, storage,
data transfer, third party service
organizations, we can implement like
tailored techniques to reduce expenses
without compromising performance.
more resources, is not equal
to like more performance.
That's true that you can run like, a
big instance and throw an application
on it, but that's not how it works.
resource management practices like right
sizing auto scaling and diversified
instance types from the backbone of
effective cost optimization at the
end of the day at the end of the day
These are the core principles like use
how much you need Auto scale whenever
you need and use the right resources.
That's it.
And additionally, when it comes to
container and serverless, make sure
you use like limits and requests
appropriately, coupled with when it
comes to databases and block storage,
use data lifecycle management,
lifecycle policies, and to make sure
that the data is stored, securely.
And also in a cost efficient way
and, and also like I want to put a
strong emphasis on monitoring and
cost visibility framework is really
important because, without adequate
monitoring, you don't even know what
resources you have, what are the spikes.
So having a strong monitoring
foundation, having a budget alerts,
having a proper utilization alerts
will help you track resources even
before the AWS cloud lands at you.
So FinOps principles bring a
cultural dimension to this strategy,
encouraging cross functional
collaboration and fostering cost
awareness within development teams.
I would reiterate that FinOps will help
business teams Finance teams understand
the cloud expenditure, with the help
of the engineering teams and also The
engineering teams would be responsible
For the cloud costs and the actions
that they take for provisioning new
cloud resources So this financial
accountability in every stage of cloud
management Organizations can align
spending with business goals creating
a culture of continuous improvement.
Thank you That was my talk
for today hope you liked it.
There's a great future for cloud
cost optimizations Using agentic AI
approach, which i'm truly excited about.
thank you everyone have
a good rest of your day