Hi everyone, my name is Hilik
Paz and I'm the CTO at Arato AI.
Arato provides an end to end Gen AI
application delivery platform for AI
builders that integrates AI technologies
like LLMs into enterprise applications.
Today we are going to talk about a
critical security challenge that has
emerged as LLM became part of modern
applications, prompt injection attacks.
I'll introduce a new model based input
validation approach designed to mitigate
such risks Drawing some parallels with
SQL injection prevention techniques
from traditional security models.
First of all, what is prompt injection?
Prompt injection is a form of attack
where an adversary manipulates the
input to a large language model in such
a way it causes the model to behave
unexpectedly or output unintended results.
To better understand this, let's look
at an analogy with SQL injection,
a well known attack vector in
traditional web applications.
SQL Injection With SQL injection,
an attacker inserts malicious SQL
queries as part of a user input field.
Which the system later incorrectly
treats as part of a valid query.
This input is mixed with the coded
SQL instructions, forcing the system
to treat it as a part of the SQL.
It can then later lead to an
unauthorized access to a database.
Notable SQL injection vulnerabilities
were found in major corporates
like Cisco, Tesla, Fortnite that
recently had vulnerability that
let attackers access user accounts.
Similarly, in prompt injection,
user input is mixed with the coded
instructions intended for the LLM.
An attacker might insert hidden
instructions in the user input
field that overrides your intended
output, leading to harmful behavior
or leaking sensitive information.
As LLMs are integrated into more
applications, especially critical
ones like customer service and
automation, Preventing these attacks
becomes increasingly important.
Let's look at a short demo.
In this demo, I'll show you
a simple but effective prompt
injection attack on my demo app.
The app is a travel planner app
that takes user input and uses
an LLM to provide trip plans.
Watch what happens when a user
inputs contains hidden LLM follows,
resulting in unexpected responses.
So this is our Trip Planner demo app.
Let's see what happens when the user plans
a trip to Paris, let's say for three days.
We're using here Cloud 3 Haiku,
so it should take a few seconds
until we'll see the trip plan.
And we've got ourselves a nice trip
plan for our next visit to Paris.
Let's see what happens when the
user inserts harmful content.
I've already prepared a
data set of some examples.
We'll pick this one.
And we'll enter it instead
of the location field.
As you can see, we got
an unexpected result.
But prompt injection can be much more
harmful than just outputting LOL.
The user can get access to
our internal configuration.
In this example, the model outputted
the entire internal prompt that we have.
Now that we've seen how easily an
LLM can be manipulated, let's talk
about some prevention techniques.
One common approach is context filtering,
where the input is pre processed and
potentially harmful segments are removed.
Another technique is static prompt
design, where we hard code responses
and maybe even inputs that reduces
the flexibility for dynamic inputs,
but that limits LLM usefulness.
These techniques often fail in complex
or adaptive scenarios, which is why we
propose a more sophisticated approach,
a model based input validation.
It's based on a prompt that will
be sent to an LLM, hence the model
part, and it will focus on specific
input validity based on a set of
parameters you will see in a minute.
Let's start by introducing the core
of this approach, the meta prompt.
This prompt acts as a filter
between the user input and the LLM.
The metaprompt is designed to
examine inputs for specific context.
In this example, the parameters for
location input might be a type location,
samples that include city names,
country names, maybe other definitions
of locations, and the user intent for
a specific location one can visit.
Let's see another demo once
we've implemented our metaprompt.
Back to our demo app,
let's activate validation.
Validation will make sure our metaprompt
runs on each input prior to the actual
invocation of the triplen request.
Let's start by running the metaprompt
validation on a good input.
And as expected, we got our triplen.
Let's go ahead and run it
on the malicious input.
This time our metaprompt
worked and blocked that input
from continuing to the LLM.
Let's take a closer look at the
different components of our prompt.
You will probably notice that
we're using a system message
for the general instructions.
and a user message to hold
the actual user input.
The system message determines what
role the AI should play and how it
should behave generally, and at least
theoretically should play a stronger
role in following these instructions.
rather than giving the same set of
instructions as part of the user message.
The actual difference of having
these messages in a separate system
prompt rather than the being part of
a single user message depends on many
factors including the model and the
parameters you choose, but that's a
topic for a whole different session.
The first section is a set of general
instructions we give to the AI.
We set the tone, the purpose of our
prompt, and make sure that it focuses
on the sole purpose of validating input.
For example, We give him the task
of classifying that user input.
We define the format it should
expect to get the user input.
And by doing that, we are trying to
prevent interpreting the user input as
instructions the model should follow.
There's a very basic anti
jailbreaking message here.
Of course, in a real production
use case, this message will
be much more comprehensive.
And we also tell the model never to expose
its role capabilities or limitations.
Next is the section where we
define how the output looks like.
We perform two operations here.
The first one is we specify the
format, which is a JSON object with
two keys that we expect to get.
One key will be the actual
result, pass or fail.
And the second key, as you can see here,
is a new variable that we introduce.
called secret, and it will contain
a randomly generated value for each
interaction that we will call this prompt.
This secret doesn't have any direct role
in the actual prompt formal function.
It doesn't serve as assisting the AI in
any way, in understanding if the input
it is now assessing is valid or not.
But it does act as a kind of an internal
mechanism for our own metaprompt.
Because, as like any other prompt,
we might also be exposed to prompt
injection attacks on our metaprompt.
By introducing a secret value that the
prompt must return in a valid response,
We give our code the ability to analyze
if that response has been tampered or not.
The third section is where we introduce
the dynamic part of the metaprompt.
It includes type, category,
intent, and example.
The type and category are the most
basic aspects of the input that we
expect the prompt to validate against.
For example, it can be a string
that represents a location.
Or a numeric value that
represents a budget dollar amount.
The intent is where we explain what
level of flexibility we allow in
choosing these kinds of variables
from the relevant category.
For example, we can have a very
strict intent for a location.
Saying must be a specific city or state
name, or we can allow a very flexible
location choosing by saying any form or
any description that suggests a location.
It can be abstract, it can be
even fictional, as long as you
can interpret it as a location for
the purpose of planning a trip.
And lastly, we provide a set of
examples that will help the model
analyze the actual user input.
Maybe match it to similar examples
and understand if it is indeed a
valid and relevant input or not.
And lastly, the user message that includes
the actual user input we should validate.
In this example, using a JSON object will
also assist the model in understanding
it's an input rather than a set
of instructions it should follow.
Let's take a look under the
hood and view the monitored
LLM calls we've just performed.
Note that the variable type,
category, examples, and actually
the metadata that we provide to our
metaprompt in both cases is identical.
The only difference is the user input.
When the user enters
Paris, validation passes.
But when the user enters harmful content,
it fails as expected, and our code knows
not to continue to the next step of
passing the entire prompt to the LLM.
As we've seen, validating the input
before it reaches the LLM is crucial.
But beyond just running individual tests
like we just did, it's important to test
the meta prompt like any other prompt on a
diverse set of data, to ensure it works as
expected in a wide variety of scenarios.
Why is that so critical?
Because user input can be highly variable,
ranging from simple, formed inputs
to very complex and malicious ones.
A good metaprompt needs to be
consistently distinguishing between
valid inputs like New Jersey and harmful
or nonsense input like ignore all
instructions across the entire range.
Testing against a diverse dataset helps us
simulate real world usage and uncover edge
cases where the metaprompt might fail.
So we should test different input
types, location, language, duration,
or any other field type that our
business application requires.
Different user intents, we might sometimes
allow for a more flexible user intent, and
might sometimes be very strict or rigid.
And various structures, for example,
what happens when a user enters,
the initials of a city he wants
to visit in a location field.
We can assess how well the metaprompt
handles these variations and
make improvements accordingly.
This testing is essential to ensuring
that the prompt validation mechanism
is both robust and adaptable,
able to catch injection attempts
while allowing valid inputs.
When we introduce a new category, for
example, we should also experiment
with various category parameters, like
relevant examples, different user intents.
This comprehensive and iterative approach
ensures that the metaprompt is not
just effective in controlled cases that
we've just tested, but also can handle
unpredictable nature of real world data.
So let's take a short demo on the
concept of a dataset and how we can
validate our metaprompt against it.
First, let's take a look at our datasets.
Okay.
Depending on the use case we're
developing or optimizing for, we
will build the relevant test data
that we want to experiment against.
Let's assume we're optimizing
for location input fields.
We provided several data sets, for
example, a list of valid locations,
We can see the different user
inputs, and of course, the expected
response, which is passed in this
example, as they are all valid.
If we drill down to a specific line,
we can see the entire metadata that we
pass to the meta prompt, including the
category, the intent, and the examples.
Similarly, we've prepared a dataset
with malicious content or malicious
user input, used as a location field.
that we will want to experiment against,
and of course, in this case, the
expected result is always a failure.
Now let's see how we can use these
datasets in a real experiment in Arata.
Let's create a new experiment.
We will select our dataset,
and for our initial run, we
might keep the prompt as is.
And let's see how it behaves against
our data set, and this time we chose
GPT 40mini, we'll click save and run,
and we'll let the experiment execute.
And let's view the results.
So you can see we got a very high
score matching the similarity.
of our expected results from the
data set, although not perfect.
Let's see the details inside.
Here, for example, we got exactly the same
response that we expected in our data set.
But in other cases, for example, in
this line, our data set expected a pass
result, but the actual status we got using
our prompt with 40mini was a failure.
Let's try to understand why.
The user input was a romantic location.
While the model might have been right
saying that this is not a real place or
specific location, as we explicitly added
an intent saying it can be abstract,
we would have expected it to pass.
So let's try to change one of the
parameters of our experiment and
see if we can reach better results.
We will first try another model.
Let's take a different vendor.
And we will run exactly the
same experiment with the same
prompt and data against Clode3IQ.
Let's view the results.
This is much better.
We get exactly the expected results
on each one of the individual lines
that we run the experiment with.
At this point, we can decide if that's
good enough and we want to continue with
the model and parameters we've just had,
Or we want to go back to the previous
model and try to improve our prompts,
maybe play with the parameters, etc.
Let's run another experiment with invalid
location data that we've uploaded.
In this experiment, we will also
add an additional validation.
to see if we can detect harmful content.
We will select the relevant
dataset and create the experiment.
Again, at our first run, we will
not change any parameters in the
prompt and we'll run it against 4.
0 Mini.
We can run in parallel against
a different model as well.
And let's view the results.
First, we will look at
the results against 4.
0 Mini,
and we got very close to
100 percent similarity.
We can see there's a slight difference
in the output format, but the
content itself is what we expected.
And looking at Claude's
results, we see very similar,
successful run against our data.
So we've seen how you can
experiment multiple versions of your
prompts, models, configurations.
and data to achieve your business
goal and to optimize your prompt.
When experimenting, it's
important to have a baseline.
In the recent examples we've just did,
the baseline was the data set that we've
uploaded with the expected results.
But of course, we can also
experiment against data we've
collected from production and
verify it is correct and experiment
with our next version of prompt.
To conclude, we've seen how prompt
injection poses a significant threat
in LLM applications, much like
SQL injection did for databases.
While traditional techniques like static
prompting or filtering might mitigate some
risks, they often have many limitations.
Our model based input validation approach
offers a more adaptable solution by
leveraging LLMs to validate inputs.
Unlike deny listing approaches,
where the LLM is asked for the entire
input if it is malicious or harmful,
our method uses an allow listing
approach, where we explicitly define
what inputs are valid and expected.
This provides a stronger defense
by limiting the range of acceptable
inputs on one hand, but enhancing
the flexibility of the final prompt
that we can use on the other hand.
By focusing on allowListing, we create
a controlled environment where the
LLM processes only valid inputs.
This approach significantly reduces
the risk for prompt injection while
still offering the flexibility
needed in complex data inputs.
Thank you all for your time today.
I hope this session has been insightful.
If you have any questions, comments,
or would just like to keep in touch.
Please email me, follow us on
LinkedIn or visit our website.
Thank you very much.