Hello everyone.
Today we'll talk about my favorite
topic, anti fraud platform.
We'll mainly talk about the FinTech
case study, but we'll also talk about
other industry examples and philosophies
about generalized frameworks.
Would be not excessive to say that
I've been working on anti fraud
for more than four years in a
variety of B2C product companies.
I also successfully applied the exact
math that I studied at university
and, Build, effective ML anti fraud
pipelines in Yandex advertisement,
working with the cheaters in
Playrix and fraudsters in Axios.
So the plan for today to begin with,
we look at the example of what fraud
is and why anti fraud is needed.
We're going to analyze payment
fraud in the FinTech industry
and the cheaters in game.
Next, we'll go from simple to complex.
As any ML engineer would think in solving
the problem of anti fraud, what would be
the pitfalls and how to overcome them?
We'll talk about ML system design,
real time processing, and even about
other step in pipeline development
in anti fraud process, except ML.
In the beginning, let's delve
into the concept of anti fraud.
Let's figure out why a
company can benefit from it.
To understand what anti fraud is, first
you need to define the fraud, of course.
Let's say these are customer sections that
are not intended by the company, which
result in deterioration of k metrics.
If the client uses internal inefficiency
of the company's mechanisms, fraud
calls, endogeneous, otherwise exogeneous.
Accordingly, we call anti fraud
mechanism and process that
prevent this malicious action.
I'd say that the fight against fraud can
be fully automated where the decisions
are made based on data and understanding
of the product, but without manual
work, it is almost impossible to leave
the anti fraud platform completely.
The definition though, the
metric was not chosen by chance.
It's convenient for us to formalize
fraud at the set of complex action of
an agent with our internal system, when
eventually has an effect on our metric.
So for a unique user ID, for
our fraudster, we can, compare
the corresponding drop in
money retention and so on.
let's start with a simple example
of fraud in mobile game dev.
usually free to play games are built
with paywalls, a difficult place
where only a very skilled player can
pass through, or they must pay in a
in game stop for additional benefits.
A froster can use some software
to break the game and, bypass
the most difficult levels.
at the same time, if the game has
an online competition with other
participants, they Same player can latch
huge advantage over others, which spoils
impression for the rest people for sure.
Here the key metric of detection
will be number of attempts per level.
How quickly a person
passed a difficult level?
Did it happen on the
first time, for example?
If yes, it's worth to think about it.
Now it's getting a bit harder.
why does any fintech, company
have, so of course the place where
customers money is stored, which
means they're only mechanism.
Also a mechanism for how
this money gets there.
We'll discuss, the study in payments,
a transactional fraud linked to
foreign exchange conversion rates.
Let's imagine that, a techie from
Europe used a, Payment system
to place Euro into USD account.
at the time of submitting the application,
the billing system generate a document
with a fixed price of Euro USD.
However, the person actually
had the right to pay it or not.
Therefore, he has time to see
where the Euro USD rate will move.
if the Euro becomes cheaper, then
a person can make a transaction.
If it becomes more expensive,
then, do not send money at all.
Don't do transaction.
Those, the payment billing creates an
option for the client to buy dollars,
sell errors when, the insurance of
this option costs zero for client.
Actually, all that remains for
the client is just to monitor
the fixed rate and create a fraud
with a positive math expectation.
Okay, let's build an,
automatic anti fraud.
Assume that, we have a.
payment cost metric that takes
into account the money that comes
to us, like in one currency in
Euro or Indian rupee or whatever.
And, which goes to the payment, in
another currency commissions, measure
and, normalizes anality somehow, and many
other indicators, complex, big metric.
We will draw a time series for this
metric with a blue line in time.
Let's take the classic gradient boot
boosting, train the prediction of the
value, train, and predict variance
of time series by autoregression.
And, look at the segments
and people in particular.
draw orange line for a specific segment.
let's call it India by country,
segment, already at that stage, if we
made a good, classical ML prediction
of time series, we can identify
the pitfalls, segment in detail.
now we have a hypothesis that payment
fraud may occurred rupee and dollar.
a few words about ML.
What about ML?
I will be blunt here and, suggest that you
don't waste, your time trying to optimize
neural networks to catch anti fraud.
there is a very simple and,
understandable reason why.
as theory of probability and ML algorithms
in particular work when the same event can
happen many times in similar conditions.
If this is done, then we can create
prop function, build statistic
and make hypothesis, whatever.
Obviously, it is quite difficult
and long to train neural network.
But, it's even harder to make it stable.
And, here I can compare Antifraud
with, crazy gladiatorian arena
in which you never know what
will happen in the next moment.
So the same fraud can have many
different complex variation.
It is very quickly adapt to anti
fraud and therefore neural networks
go bad faster than you set it up.
So better to forget about it here.
At first glance, it's more or less simple.
The model is trained
offline on a data lake.
Kubernetes launch a model
in the persistent pod that
lists the data from Kafka.
this data is a user data.
why is it so easy?
if we don't have heavily loaded
services and, we need only client data.
Technically any ML engineer can
adjust it nowadays, but it's not easy.
In a realistic situation, usually
predicting sometimes is quite a
difficult task, and we need a lot of
different representative data to increase
accuracy, reduce variance also and so on.
In our case, market data is generally
necessary by definition of our fraud.
What then?
then we need a hire of team C
developers who will design an
effective reader of market quotations.
You can imagine how can, How much the
load on services will increase, the
complexity of data security and so on.
it is already worth thinking
about the infrastructure.
So the antifraud system doesn't slow
down the load on the product itself and
the customer do not experience delays.
Therefore, we'll have a market provider
and the aggregator block in our ML design.
In fact, this is an extremely
simplified scheme since
aggregation itself includes many.
processes start from data qualities,
checks and, and a fair architecture
of microservices that allows you to
combine data in convenient tabular
form with the correct timestamp.
What other problem could be,
it's too generalized, isn't it?
Of course, we are trying
to come up with a function.
that, will well reflect the bad
action of customers, but often
an ensemble of model is needed.
You need to clearly understand that
in order to achieve high accuracy in
anti fraud with a decent recall, it's
not enough just to train model well.
It's necessary to study very careful what
kind of fraud you have and associate a
separate set of metrics for each fraud.
accordingly.
So in our example, the generalized
payment cost can be divided into
commission costs, market arbitration,
different platforms, arbitration time,
cost, for, interaction with the payment
system, counterparties and so on.
this, our infrastructure is, expanding
and requires an individual analyst,
data scientist, approach to identify
clusters of metric models that will
give the best accuracy of forecasts.
On the top of answer in the model, you
need to choose the ideal algorithmic
solution that will match your risk
appetite, namely to answer the question,
how often we can make a mistake.
it's time to talk, how to make,
this ensemble perform often.
in the beginning, the SMPU Spark
was, used as a default solution,
but it was, sorely lacking.
Now Trina is used for, modeling and,
computing in my current company,
which shows itself much better due
to, completed work with, memory.
Another option here would be, GPU
Spark calculation, but it's not
trivial to run properly sometimes.
A huge problem, especially in,
transactional and market data is
an uneven load on infrastructure.
So our news, Yeah, we have a,
periods with a high load in our case,
it's in use, but in your company,
it may be a different period.
this period, period with a high priority
at this moments, all prioritization
with all resources is given to the vital
function of, of the product, making
transaction or, Transcription sponsored
by RenaissanceRe Traits, whatever, while
the model, politely receives information,
actually, it's just not efficient
and, we can't calculate it properly.
From this point of view of ML, a
specialist, we have, two solution either
to, intelligently adjust the model.
to the high load intervals, or to make
a separate model, not in real time
that is looking for fraud on the high
load, the second wall of calculation.
In total, we'll have, fast, efficient,
and accurate collection almost always.
But in the most difficult moments of
product, we reduce amount of resources
allocated to anti fraud block and,
either perform in a simple version
without the wasting time and, catching
the big, biggest frauders, the most
painful in terms of metric or recalculate
this entire block into the past a
few minutes after load stabilize.
So a flying support team.
in fact, in fact we come to a very
important part of today's story and, what
about the before and after ML model part?
These are people, analyst and
anti fraud officer standing there.
look at the probability formula, please.
If we.
competently built a pipeline for filtering
good users from frauders from, fraudsters
while, filters will be independent is
just the, with the right processes, we'll
make a huge improvement in accuracy of
the entirely anti fraud platform because
our filters of analytical ML and the
operational team will go independent way.
All different teams have a,
they're all researchers and
thoughts how to capture fraudsters.
let's look at the full
pipeline using an example.
The analytical department signal,
signal that a strange activity was
happening in India, for example,
dropping a little deeper our metric.
and, they noticed that the
people associated with the one
particular payment system had
dropped it significant on average.
Okay.
Now email engineers step into the game.
look at the metric, study data,
predict this metric, and, catch
quantiles from people, with a
particular strange behavior.
After the correct validation of the
model, it became obvious that some
of them can blocked immediately.
These are, molecular fraudsters.
But, in the same part where the
accuracy is, close to average,
ML engineers are not sure.
And, they give, these cases
to the operational team.
they sort out the, borderline cases,
they're digging into the deepest essence
of why the fraud occurred and, making
decision with their heads and hands.
what next?
Monitoring.
Also very important part.
Monitoring both online and offline
metric is crucial to ensure the
system operates efficiently.
One of the most important online
metrics should reflect the
potential business cost of fraud.
such costs related to the
payment system, may help us to
prevent it or calculate, uh.
it an efficient way, in particular
tracking, not just the value, but
also the behavior of the cost.
it can provide the early detection
mechanism for fraud, helping business
to balance fraud prevention, with
the operational team as well.
Offline metric provide a deeper
relation of the model security over
time, given the class imbalance.
Often present in the fraud
detection, metrics like peer oak
and, particularly useful for,
assembling the model's performance.
Additionally, monitoring the
false positive rate is crucial.
as, because we want to minimize false
positives and, we need to maintain.
A positive user experience while,
effectively, fighting against fraud.
And, visualization of this metric
allows to team, analyst on or,
operational team identify, emerging
fraud patterns and, spike activities.
Therefore, as you can see, online metrics.
using visualization and the special tools
go directly to rapid response people
to check complex edge cases, either
when the model is uncertain or where
metrics are contradictory and they need
to, detailed analysis, offline metrics
as usual will help us to determine the
degree of degradation of the model.
And, over time we'll retrain it.
Once we need it.
so thank you for your attention and,
thanks, to, Conf42 for the opportunity
to talk about ML in antifraud.
The main conclusion from my story
can be drawn that, don't need to over
complicate places with the mathematics
that you do not require it while the
proper process approach allows you
to improve the quality of the model.
Multiple times.
Thank you.