Hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk titled Sisyphean
struggle navigating performance
issues in modern IT landscapes.
My name is Ravitej Uveeramachaneni.
I work as a principal software engineer
for a software services based company.
And the main reason, or the main,
topic that I'll be discussing today is
how performance issues plague the IT
industry today, why it's a challenge,
why it's a tough challenge and a
challenge that may never be solved.
you'll all agree, if you've, if any, if
you have, IT experience, you'll all agree.
Performance issues are an ongoing thing.
There's no such thing as, as users being
completely satisfied with performance.
Even if they're satisfied today, they
won't be, in a year from now with the
same systems and the same performance.
so the idea of the talk is just
how performance varies, the
challenges it, it brings up.
And.
And how to overcome them.
so let's get started.
Excuse me.
just a review of the contents
that we were discussing.
So again, like I said, we'll be discussing
why IT performance remains a challenge.
any business line, even if it's a
software company, even one of the
high performing tech ones, why IT
Performance, remains a challenge.
You cannot rest easy on your laurels,
thinking your product is working fine.
Today, you'll have to, you'll have to
account for many unforeseen things.
and so that, so basically why it
performance remains a challenge.
The next thing is the complexity
conundrum in IT systems.
So how complexity of multiple systems
working together impacts performance.
so that's an area of discussion.
Also, we'll be discussing the
rising expectations and of users
when it comes to performance.
Like I said at the beginning, even
if users are happy today, they will
not be a year from now or six months
from now with the same system,
and with the same performance.
Users expectations keep increasing and
with advancements in technology, you
will have you, you will have, even if
your system is performing at the same as
it was performing a year ago, you might
see competitors, come in and perform
at a, a better, level than your product
is performing or, things like that.
So with advancements in technology,
you will always want to be at the
top when it comes to performance.
And then there's the human elephant,
element and, performance challenges.
Things like, how, skilled
labor impacts performance.
And then we'll talk about the
resource constraints and optimization.
the cost algorithm.
There's always, you can always spend a
lot of money to improve performance, but
it comes, obviously it comes at a cost.
So how do you go about, balancing the two?
we'll also talk about advanced
solutions and performance management.
What are the advanced techniques
to monitor performance and so on?
and challenges to definitive solutions.
There might be solutions today as
to how to tackle performance issues.
But what the challenges
are with those solutions.
and what the implications for I.
T.
professionals are, and future research and
directions, when it comes to performance.
And I finally, conclude, the
paper with, why performance
will always be an ongoing thing.
so again, an introduction, as to why I.
T.
performance remains a challenge.
Performance issues in I.
T.
systems continue to
challenge professionals.
Despite major advancements in technology,
think of it, we should always, we should
have put performance issues behind us
with all the technological advancements
today, but that's not what I find,
no matter which, which, the company
I work for, you're always debugging,
something related to performance.
It could be network.
it could be your, data load.
It could be a database.
it could be your UI and so on.
So performance is one of the most
complex challenges to solve because
of so many systems being involved.
You have to, let's say, something
that was working fine yesterday,
suddenly stops working today.
It is hard to pinpoint.
A reason as to why you
restart your system.
Things are back working fine.
Maybe they are Back to working as normal,
but you cannot you cannot, you can look
at the logs, you can do all the debugging,
but because of so many systems being
involved, you cannot, you sometimes
cannot pinpoint as to why there was a
lag in performance at a certain time,
at a certain time with a certain system.
So it's just a difficult thing.
to pinpoint and it's, it's like I
said, it is an evolving challenge.
It is, it will always be a challenge, 10
years from now, 20 years from now, impacts
and the impact performance issues have on
business, obviously, as any industry, if
their IT systems are not performing well,
it will have a business, impact even more.
So if, Your, company is a software
services provider or, or you live in
the, technology space, take Google,
X or any social media platform.
If you, if your site, or if your,
website goes down for a few minutes,
it costs you millions of dollars.
so it does have performance
has an impact, on the business.
What the key causes are, Performance
challenges mainly arise from,
increasing system complexity.
So as you integrate more systems, if
you're a developer, you, you understand
there is a DevOps side, you, there's
a deployment, side, to your code, then
there is the aspect of writing good code.
so because of complex systems
being involved, those could,
lead to performance, challenges.
So the, again, the purpose of this
presentation is to explore the complex
factors causing persistent IT performance
issues, evaluate the solutions that we
have today, and suggest strategies for
navigating these challenges effectively.
so let's discuss the complexity
conundrum in IT systems.
complex interconnected environments.
They are one of the reasons
for, performance issues.
Modern IT landscapes consist of diverse
interconnected components, including
cloud infrastructure, microservices,
and lots of, Internet of thing devices.
With these, interconnected environments
and conflict, integrations, those,
introduce new bottlenecks, bottlenecks
multiply with complexity, increase
distribution and interdependency,
amplify the risk of performance,
bottlenecks across systems.
like I said a few minutes ago, it's
a challenge to, isolate what the
root cause was for performance.
Because most of the times what
ends up happening is, let's say
you're having a database issue.
You restart the database and
the performance issue is gone.
so the issue is gone, but we still cannot
pinpoint as to why there was a issue
in, in, in the first place because it's
hard to reproduce, performance issues.
So it's a challenge.
It's a challenge of root cause isolation
with each component introducing its
own set of performance characteristics.
isolating and troubleshooting root
causes becomes a demanding task.
An example of that would be a delay in
data processing within a microservice can
cascade through an entire application.
As I'm sure, another good example would
be, again, like I said, our database, if
it slows down, it, the data that is being
fetched, that, it slows down and then it
has an impact on your reports or whatever
the database is fetching, or whatever
you're fetching from the database.
So, also let's talk about the ever
moving target, which is rising
expectations and advancements.
user expectations are always
changing, that's why we call
it an ever moving target.
As consumer technology advances, so
do user expectations for system speed,
responsiveness, and reliability.
Again, just think back to 10 years
ago, the cell phones that we had, the
phones that we had, they were a major
advancement compared to 20 years ago.
But, we cannot use those devices today
just because we demand more, speed.
so technological advancements
also introduce new demands.
Again, the classic example
would be your, cell phones.
your mobile phones with
advancements in chip design and
with advancements in CPU and GPU.
Thank you.
The phones always perform better
than the previous generations.
The performance might be marginally
better year over year, but when you
compare it to 10 years ago, you would
see a drastic performance improvement.
So put in other words, you cannot
take a phone that was launched 10
years ago and use it in today's world.
the applications designed for
phones today, and so on wouldn't
work on hardware of, 10 years ago.
Changing standards is another
moving target, which is what was
once considered acceptable is now
deemed subpar as expectations rise.
to keep pace with technological progress.
Um, another example, deviating
from the mobile phone would be AI
applications like real time video
processing, demand high computing power.
you have, you get access to 4K, 8K, and,
we don't know what else in the future.
but as you, as you
unlock more, resolutions.
that will put more processing, that will,
that will demand more processing power.
And so you need more, more
resources to solve that challenge.
and then there's the human element
and performance challenges.
things like, things pertaining
to a human element would be
impact of code and configuration.
So inefficient coding practices obviously
could lead to, subpar performance.
or, suboptimal performance.
and if you use suboptimal, algorithms
and misconfigurations, you would
all in those cases too, you
would, obviously see performance
issues, variability and skills.
Not everyone, is, has the
same level of skillset.
So that's why, the top engineers
going to only a few companies, and
and so with variability in skills.
comes, variability in product
that is being, put out there.
so the skill levels and practices of
developers vary, which can lead to
inconsistent performance within systems.
another, human element would
be uncreditable user behavior.
A good example of that would
be sudden spikes in traffic.
let's say a new product was launched,
Or, everyone is, or YouTube suddenly,
lets all users, download, videos,
in, in, in the highest resolution.
So if everyone tried to download
the same video, it would obviously
put a, put, a strain on the system.
just certain spikes in traffic
or unexpected data growth.
can create an unforeseen system strain
like, unexpected data growth would be,
you haven't, really, accounted for, a
good example again would be YouTube,
where, at one point, the maximum number
of views, or the displayed view count
on YouTube was, a certain range and
then, with that, with some videos
exceeding that, they had to change that.
So things like that, even though in that
example, it's not a performance issue.
you could see why, sudden,
unforeseen systems train could
lead to performance issues.
again, example of that would be a
sudden increase in user activity
during a promotional event can overload
systems not designed for such spikes.
So, and so then let's discuss
about resource constraints and,
and the optimization cost element.
Good examples of that would
be limited IT resources.
Organizations often operate
under constraints with limited
access to hardware, software,
licenses, and skilled personnel.
and so with limited resources, you have
to work within your budgets, and if
you're not ready to pay, for the newest
chip, or if you're not ready to pay for
the best talent that will show in your,
that will show in the performance of
the products that you put out there.
So it's always a balancing act.
IT teams must prioritize between
optimizing performance, meeting
security and compliance requirements
and staying within budget.
Cost performance trade offs, upgrading
systems for optimal performance
can be costly, requiring careful
consideration to avoid overspending.
An example of resource constraints would
be deciding between upgrading server
capacity or allocating funds to other
critical IP needs like cyber security.
So let's discuss some advanced
solutions and performance management.
Some of the advanced solutions are
enhanced monitoring techniques.
You can have the best in
class monitoring techniques,
advanced monitoring techniques.
Tools now use machine learning for
real time anomaly detection, providing
insights that allow proactive response.
So instead of reacting to an issue, AI
insights can tell you beforehand if you
are going to have a performance issue.
And that way you can, do what is
necessary to prevent it from, happening.
You also have sophisticated
troubleshooting, options
available in today's world.
some of them are AI driven,
root cause analysis.
Distributed tracing and chaos engineering.
All of these help to proactively
detect and address potential issues.
Holistic optimizations strategies,
those include auto scaling.
These are mostly on the infrastructure
side where you configure your load
balancers for auto scaling and DevOps.
DevOps practices allow more
efficient resource use.
and a smoother user experience.
An example for advanced solutions would
be implementing auto scaling during
peak usage to ensure that systems can
handle increased traffic smoothly.
now let's discuss the challenges
to, the definitive solutions.
some of the, excuse me.
So unintended consequences, optimizing
one area can inadvertently cause
issues in another, especially
in tight integrated systems.
I've seen this a lot where.
You fix one area of the code
and break something else.
So it involves, good communication.
solving performance issues, involves
communication between other teams.
also you being aware of not just
your, area of expertise, but what
could be the potential impact of
you changing something within the
system to make performance better.
If it impacts someone else, maybe.
Maybe, you have upgraded to a
new database connector and that
database connector is not supported
to one of the integrated systems.
now suddenly you have, your
integrations failing and so on.
So unintended consequences,
are one challenge.
Then you have the trade off
conundrum, which means improvements
in aspect of performance often
require sacrifices in another, such
as speed versus data consistency.
so that's pretty self explanatory
where you are looking for speed,
but, you're missing your data is
missing or, you're not getting
the cleanest of data and so on.
Then you have the innovation paradox, the
rapid technological advancements introduce
new performance challenges, just as
solutions for older challenges, emerge.
So again, like I said, uh,
what you were satisfied with.
10 years ago, you're no
longer satisfied with today.
So rapid technological advancements,
they always, keep the user, wanting more.
again, a good example would be increasing
security measure, measures may add
layers of authentication, potentially
impacting system response, time.
So what does this imply
for IT professionals?
it means you have to keep Evolving
your skill set, professionals need to
shift from reactive troubleshooting
to proactive predictive performance
management technique techniques.
You also need to have
cross functional skills.
You no longer can just be an expert
in your area, like a developer
should know about the DevOps side.
Similarly, a DevOps engineer
should know about, should be able
to read code and say, what is a.
What is a bad code versus
what is good code and so on.
understanding system architecture,
data analytics, and emerging
technologies is essential for
modern performance management.
Importance of, communication,
like I touched on earlier.
Effectively conveying technical issues and
solutions to non technical stakeholders is
critical to gaining support and resources.
Now, for many businesses, IT
is not their main, business.
Maybe for an oil and gas company.
If they want to spend more on IT to
improve performance, and so on, they
need to first be able to understand
as to how it impacts their business.
And so you being able to effectively
communicate, maybe they don't understand
that a breach in, an IT system could
negatively impact, the business.
So explaining things like that
to them, explaining things
like how performance could.
Could cause a loss in
business is really important.
The role of IT teams is no longer just
maintenance, but also to align their
work closely with business objectives
for better overall performance.
So what does future research
state and where are we headed?
So there are advanced technologies.
predictive models that are coming up,
developing more context aware predictive
models using big data analytics to
anticipate potential performance issues.
We also have, another area of
future research could be autonomous
optimization, that is researching
into self adjusting systems.
We don't have that.
today, that can automatically configure
and allocate resources in real time.
Human AI collaboration,
exploring effective ways to
combine AI driven insights.
with human expertise to enhance
troubleshooting and optimization,
where, an example would be you have
AI techniques to notice trends where
it could alert you to potential
performance issues and you proactively,
jump on and, and see what's going on.
Standardization of metrics,
creating standardized performance
benchmarks to allow comparison
across diverse IT environments.
That could also help with, future
research could be targeted to towards
that where, you do have benchmarks today,
but they're not the same benchmarks do
not apply to, all the systems and so on.
an example would be industry wide
standards for system latency or
data consistency would enable better
benchmarking and performance evaluations.
So in conclusion, the paper talks about,
it acknowledges persistent challenges.
Performance issues are challenging,
but drive innovation and IT.
It's because users are never
satisfied with performance
that you always see innovation.
You have opportunities
for proactive strategies.
Embracing proactive management, leveraging
emerging technologies, and fostering a
performance oriented culture are crucial.
What lies in the road ahead?
Continued research into predictive
analytics, autonomous optimization,
and standardization of metrics
will pave the way forward.
And as a final note, Although a
final solution may be elusive, even
with all of these advancements at
some point will become the norm.
and then you'll, there will always
be, challenges as of that date and
years from now, which will mean the
quest never ends and you keep, you
keep trying to, improve performance.
so although a final solution may
be elusive, the pursuit of optimal
performance will continue to
inspire advancements in IT, pushing
professionals to innovate and excel.
Thank you.