Hello everyone and thank you for joining.
I Am pri, and today we'll explore how
cloud-based telematics is reshaping
the way we manage commercial fleets,
driving efficiency, sustainability,
and deep operational insights.
Fleet management used to be about
keeping vehicles on the road.
Now it's about connecting every
vehicle driver and route into
a single intelligent ecosystem.
I'll walk you through the technologies
real world resolve and where the
future of connected fleets is heading.
And I'm pleased to talk about it in the
com 42 Prompt Engineering 2025 conference.
But before that, let me introduce myself.
I am a senior technical program
manager at Ford Motor Company at Ford.
I lead initiatives that combine
cloud infrastructure, IOT,
and analytics to transform.
How we manage mobility systems, my focus
is mostly to build scalable, secure,
and intelligent telematics platforms
that enables proactive decision making
and measurable return on interest.
This work touches everything from
predictive maintenance to sustainability
tracking, bringing together data
technology and human behavior
to create more efficient fleets.
And it's clear that the
commercial telematics market
is becoming a cornerstone.
Of transportation innovation, you can see
that the global fleet telematics market is
projected to reach $214 billion by 2030.
That's a massive
transformation opportunity.
Telematics enables measurable value.
Predictive maintenance can reduce
maintenance cost by 25%, and
intelligent route optimization
can save around 20% in fuel.
These savings will compound
across thousands of vehicles,
improving profitability while
also lowering emissions.
In short, cloud telematics isn't just
a technical upgrade, it's a strategic
business decision that drives both
sustainability and competitiveness.
To understand why this shift
matters, we need to look at how
fleet management has evolved.
In traditional fleets, everything
was reactive, scheduled maintenance,
manual inspections, and paper reports.
This meant issues were often discovered
only after breakdowns occurred,
which was costly and inefficient.
Now, cloud-based telematics
flips that model.
Vehicles now transmit real-time
data about performance,
location, and driver behavior.
Fleet managers can now monitor
everything remotely, and they
can also automate insights.
We have gone from reactive management
to predictive intelligence by
creating a safer, leaner, and
a more sustainable operation.
Now let's look at the technical foundation
that makes all of this possible.
The cloud telematics architecture.
Each vehicle becomes a data source
through iot modules that track
performance GPS and environmental data.
This data is protected.
By through multiple
multiple layer security.
Which is encrypted, authenticated,
and verified from end-to-end.
Now, hybrid connectivity, as you can
see, is combining cellular and satellite.
This ensures that data is transmitted
reliably from anywhere, whether it's
a density or a remote mining site.
Once in the cloud, this data is
processed by scalable analytics.
Engines that apply machine learning
to detect anomalies optimize
operations, and even generate insights.
In short, this architecture connects
vehicles, drivers and managers through
a secure, intelligent digital backbone.
Of course, none of this would be effective
without reliable, always on connectivity.
Now fleet operations are only as
effective as their connectivity.
So in urban environments, cellular
networks provide fast, low
latency data transmission for
real time tracking and updates.
But fleets, they can operate beyond
coverage zones, rural highways,
deserts, or construction sites.
That's where the satellite backup
step steps in it's seamless switching
ensures that no vehicle ever goes dark.
Intelligent algorithms select the
best network automatically based
on signal, strength and cost.
The result is a hybrid communication
layer that guarantees uninterrupted
data flow, operational safety, and full
fleet visibility anywhere on the planet.
Continuous connectivity enables one of the
biggest breakthroughs in fleet management.
Predictive maintenance.
In a connected fleet, every
component from engines to break
becomes a monitored asset.
Sensors collect this real-time
performance data while cloud-based AI
models learn what normal operation looks
like and flag deviations very early.
Instead of waiting for breakdowns,
we can predict and prevent them.
This approach reduces emergency payers.
Cut maintenance cost by 25%, up to 25%,
let's say, and extends vehicle lifespan.
Downtime drops, reliability increases, and
fleet utilization improves dramatically.
Predictive maintenance represents a
cultural shift from fixing to foreseen.
Once the vehicles are healthy
and connected, the next challenge
is optimizing how they move.
That's where intelligent routing comes.
Every route a fleet takes impacts,
cost time, and carbon footprint.
Cloud-based telematics
uses real-time traffic.
They look at the weather data and
the load parameters to compute
the most efficient routes.
Automatically, the system adapts to the.
Rerouting vehicles around congestion or
storms, balancing loads for efficiency and
reducing fuel consumption by up to 20%.
This not only saves money, but
also reduces emissions supporting
sustainability, coal, it's dynamic.
Data-driven navigation that
thinks ahead, not just reacts.
Driver behavior is another critical
factor in achieving these gains.
It influences safety,
fuel use, and asset life.
Telematics tracks driving patterns,
speeding, braking, idling, and uses
this data to provide real time feedback.
The results are striking.
30% fewer harsh driving incidents,
40% improvement in safety scores
and 15% longer vehicle life.
Gamification and coaching
makes it engaging Drivers
get performance dashboards,
recognition, and even incentives.
For safe and efficient behavior, it
creates a positive feedback loop between
technology and human performance.
Now imagine seeing all of these
insights, vehicle drivers and
performance metrics in one place.
The operations dashboard is the
command center for the entire fleet.
Managers can see every vehicle's
live location, health status,
and estimated arrival time.
Alerts notify teams instantly if
maintenance is due, or if a vehicle
deviates from expected performance.
Performance metrics like fuel
consumption, utilization rates, idle
time, they're all tracked automatically.
Automated reporting saves hours
of manual work and provides
executives with a clear data-driven
insight for strategic planning.
And when organizations
implement this technology.
The results are transformative companies
using cloud telematics see measurable
results, 15% total cost savings, 20%
better utilization, and significantly
reduced emissions, optimized routing,
predictive maintenance, and safer driving.
Directly improve return on investment
while advancing sustainability goals.
This is in theory, it's happening
today across logistics, delivery
and public sector fleets.
The more data we collect, the smarter and
cleaner our transportation systems become,
and the next generation of connected
fleets will take this even further.
Let's say the future will be defined
by ai, edge computing V two X
and digital twins edge computing
processes, data directly in vehicle.
Cutting latency and
improving response times.
AI will autonomously make decision
making, continuously learning from
millions of data points V two X,
which is vehicle to everything.
Communication enables safer, more
coordinated traffic flow, and digital
twins will create replicas of entire
fleets, letting us simulate routes.
Maintenance strategies and even energy
usage before implementing them in reality.
So let's recap the key
lessons from this evolution.
Cloud telematics transforms operations.
Shifting from reactive management
to predictive intelligence.
Hybrid connectivity ensures reliability
fleets stay visible anywhere in the world.
Data drives sustainability, route
optimization, and driver insights
reduce both costs and emission.
And the future is
intelligent and connected.
AI and vehicle to everything.
Communication will define the
next chapter in fleet management.
These are the four key takeaways
from what we have learned today.
With that, I would like to say thank
you all for joining this session.
Cloud telematics is more than a tool.
It's an enabler for smarter, safer,
and more sustainable transportation.
By connecting data, people and
technology altogether, we can
unlock new levels of efficiency
and environmental responsibility.
I look forward to continuing this
conversation and exploring how
we can bring this innovations
to our own fleet operations.
And I'm thoroughly honored to be
speaking at the Comp 42 Prompt
Engineering 2025 conference.
Thank you very much.