Hi everyone.
I'm Rich Solinki.
I'm a manager, data
Management in Ally Bank.
Thank you for joining me
today for this presentation.
I will be talking about how we can
transform enterprise data management
using Lakehouse architecture.
A model that combines the best of
both data warehouses and data lakes.
Over the next few minutes, I will
walk you through why this approach
matters, what core principle make
it work, and how it is delivering
the real business impact at scale.
Data explosion, A growing challenge.
As we all know, data is
growing at an incredible pace.
By 2025, global data volumes are expected
to reach 175 terabytes, and almost
one third of that will require real
time processing For enterprises, this
means we are no longer just dealing.
With relational data in clean rows
and columns, we now handle structured,
semi-structured, and unstructured
data coming from countless systems.
These fragmented environments
create serious challenges in
governance, security, and operational
efficiency, making it harder to
deliver timely and trusted insights.
Four years, organizations have
relied on two main approaches, data
warehouses and data lake, and both
have their strengths and weaknesses.
D one on one hand, data
warehouse offers reliability,
consistency, and strong governance.
But they are expensive and rigid.
They struggle with
scalability and flexibility.
Data lakes, on the other hand, are
cheap and highly scalable, but they
often turn into a data swamps with
little governance, unclear ownership,
and no transactional consistency.
So enterprises have been forced to
choose between structure and flexibility,
and that's where the Lakehouse
concept really changes the game.
Lake house architecture.
Bridges the gap.
It combines the reliability and governance
of data warehouses with the scalability
and cost efficiency of data lakes.
With Lakehouse, we can handle diverse
workloads from batch analytics to
realtime streaming and even machine
learning on a single unified platform.
This approach eliminates a trade off.
That used to exist.
It allows us to build one
govern centrally and serve many
different use cases efficiently.
So what are the core capabilities
of like house architecture?
There are four major pillars
that defines the Lakehouse model.
First asset transactions ensure that
we maintain full data integrity even
as we scale to billion of records.
Second schema enforcement
gives us flexibility.
We can support both schema on
read and schema on right models
adopting to evolving business data.
Third is real time Analytics
allows teams to query batch and
streaming data instantly without
building complex ETL pipelines.
And finally, unified Governance provides
a single place for metadata line
tracking and compliance, something that
is critical for enterprise adoption.
Multi zone structure model.
To manage data systematically, we
structure the lakehouse into three
zones, raw, refined, and curated.
The raw zone stores data exactly as
it arrives, preserves the original
format for auditability purpose.
The refined is where
cleansing, validation, and the
standardization of data happens.
Business rules are applied here
and the curated zone contains high
quality analytics ready data sets
for reporting and machine learning.
So basically we are preserving the
data as it is coming in the row.
And then any massaging transformation,
any business rule application will
be taken care as part of refined and
users can use for business analytics.
Curated zone.
This layered design ensures
traceability and promotes data
trust across the enterprise.
So within the lake house, we often
use data vault modeling because it
provides both flexibility and historical
traceability with both of which are
very important thing in modern world.
It is designed for change so we can
involve a schema without breaking
downstream systems In this model.
Hub captures the core business
entities and their unique identifiers.
Link represent the relationship
between those entities and satellite
store descriptive attributes
and full historical context.
So this structure allows us to track
how data changes over time, which is
key for governance and audit compliance.
Scalability means nothing if
performance does not keep up.
So optimization is crucial.
We use column file formats like PERQUE
and ORC, which compress efficiently
and read only the necessary columns.
During a query, we implement
intelligent caching.
For frequently access databases, cutting
down response time for repeated queries.
And through dynamic partitioning,
we organize data by time, geography,
or other dimension, allowing faster
pruning and parallel processing.
Together these techniques give performance
high while maintaining cost efficiency.
Traditional architecture depend
on multiple ETL pipelines.
Data is extracted, transform, and
loaded across several systems.
This creates latency,
complexities and multiple points
of failure in a lake house.
We adopt an ELT approach Instead,
extract and load first, then
transform directly in place.
This means fewer copies, less
maintenance, and faster time to insight.
So by reducing redundant data movement,
teams can focus more on analysis
and less on fixing the pipelines.
Let's talk about automated
governance practices as we scale
governance can't be manual.
It has to be automated.
We use data quality automation to
validate incoming data and flag
anomalies before they affect analytics.
We maintain completely lineage and
audit trails to track how data moves
and transform across the system.
Which simplifies compliance
and troubleshooting.
And with role based access control and
encryption, we ensure that sensitive
data remains protected, which is
still accessible to authorized users.
The proactive governance makes the
system both secure and self-healing.
When organization implement the Lakehouse
model, the results are significant.
Maintenance effort dropped by 60% because
fewer pipelines and tools are needed.
ETL workflows run around 45%.
Faster thanks to in-place.
Transformation and overall
cost of ownership goes down by
roughly 40% beyond the numbers.
The biggest gain is agility.
Teams can deliver insights
faster and respond to business
needs in near real time fashion.
So how does this all come together
in a real world environment?
The architecture usually
has four key layers.
First data ingestion layer that
brings in both batch and streaming
data from different sources.
Second is storage and compute are
decoupled, allowing each to scale
independently based on workload.
Governance and catalog layer maintains
metadata access policies and data lineage.
And finally, the analytics
and conjunction layer.
It provides flexibility for users from
BI tools to data science notebooks.
This end-to-end design gives both
control and freedom to data teams, and
we can use data as a strategic asset.
So in this slide we'll talk about
the implementation considerations.
So for those who are starting
their Lakehouse journey,
a few practical lessons.
First, choose platforms that
support OpenTable formats like data
Lake Apache Iceberg, or Hoodie.
This prevents vendor lock-in.
And future proofed our design.
Second adopter phase migration strategy
begin with known critical workload
to build expertise and confidence.
And third, invest in team training.
Success requires engineers and
analysts to understand both
warehouse and like principles.
It is much about people and
process as it is about technology.
So to wrap up, the lake house architecture
eliminates the longstanding trade off
between data warehouses and data lake.
It provides the governance and reliability
enterprises need, which offering the
flexibility and scalability required
for modern analytics by simplifying
pipelines through multi-zone.
Storage and ELT workflows.
We achieve faster insights
and reduce operational costs.
So ultimately it is about
delivering the measurable business
value, better performance, lower
cost, and trusted data at scale.
Thank you for listening
to this presentation.
Please reach out to me if
you have any questions.
Thank you very much.