Good morning everyone.
I'm from Microsoft and I'm
thrilled to be here at Comp 42.
Network engineering, as many of has
traditionally been about cables, routers,
and keeping systems online, but today
that world is being completely redefined.
We're entering an era where
AI isn't supporting just the
network, it's actively running it.
Optimizing performance, predicting
failures and adapting on the fly.
In this talk, I'll explore how AI is
reshaping network engineering, what new
skills we need and how we can design
scalable, reliable, and intelligent
networks for this AI driven future.
Let's start with how our
field have has evolved.
A traditional approach
was straightforward.
Manually configured devices,
monitor up time and react to
problems when something broke.
If a router failed at 2:00
AM someone got a call.
Today, we have shifted to a modern
paradigm where intelligent systems
can predict issues before they
occur, optimize themselves and
make decisions based on data.
For instance, modern data centers can
now automatically reconfigure traffic
patterns or, and the paths basically
when latency is noticed on a particular
path with no human in the loop.
So the role of network engineer
has changed from being an operator
to becoming a systems architect
and a data driven strategist.
Network engineers must span three
worlds, enterprise networks, cloud
providers, and telecom operators.
Enterprises care most about
compliance of time and security.
Think of a global bank that
must follow strict regulations
that keep trading systems live.
24 7. Cloud providers and put
emphasize automation and elasticity.
Companies like Microsoft Azure
or AWS need networks that scale
across continents automatically.
Telephone operators handle massive
traffic and cardiac great reliability.
Imagine managing billions of
iot connections simultaneously.
Each network is unique, yet
they are deeply interconnected.
The future engineer must pay
fuel fluent in all these three.
In enterprise environments, the challenge
is balancing reliability and regulation.
Networks must meet audit data
sovereignty and zero trust
requirements while staying efficient.
For example, a healthcare company
integrating patient data across multiple
clouds must ensure HIPAA complaints
without slowing access to doctors.
Engineers have to design architectures
that maintain redundancy, security
and performance, all while supporting
legacy systems that were never meant
to talk to modern cloud services.
It is like renovating an old
house while keeping the lights on.
You can't afford downtime
in cloud and service provider spaces.
Speed and scale is everything.
Four imperatives that define this
environment first is automation.
Tools like Terraform or Ansible
replace manual configuration.
You can deploy hundreds of routers with
a single script orchestration and scale.
Managing thousands of network nodes
require systems like Kubernetes
for networking to maintain
consistency and reliability,
performance optimization Subsequent.
Latency can be made or can be
make or break applications like
online gaming or stock trading.
Elastic scaling networks must
expand and contract based on demand.
Think of video streaming traffic
spiking during a major sports event.
AI ties these together, helping us
make real time data driven adjustments.
Now let's ground ourselves in the
core skills that still matter.
AI can optimize configurations, but
it can't replace deep understanding of
writing protocols like BGP or SPF and
MBLS, for example, when AI recommends
the route change, engineers must
interpret, why is it improving latency
or masking and underlying topology issue?
Likewise, IPV six.
Security and observability are becoming
fundamental with billions of iot devices.
Joining networks IIPV
four is simply not enough.
So while AI helps automate
and enhance our foundational
knowledge remains our compass,
the network engineer of
tomorrow is a hybrid.
Part network architect, part software
developer, part data analyst.
Beyond Protocol Mastery, we need
programming, fluency, AI literacy,
and data interpretation skills.
For instance, when AI models suggests
optimizing bandwidth based on telemetry
data, you should understand how
that model learned, what features it
used, and what biases might exist.
The more we understand ai, the
better we can collaborate with it.
Turning the engineer into an
AI co-pilot, not a spectator.
The toolbox of a motor
engineer looks very different.
Now we are seeing tools like Ansible,
Terraform, net, and Napalm, all
focused on automating repetitive tasks.
If you add Python, yaml, js O and
jet this is now the new command line.
Picture this, instead of configuring one
switch at a time, you push a GI commit
and the change deploy across hundreds of
devices, which validation checks built in.
That's why the new
baseline is clear Python.
Get Ansible APIs.
SGN controllers, these are the keys to
building intelligence scalable systems.
AI is already deeply embedded
in network operations.
It helps with the anomaly detection,
spotting unusual spikes in traffic
that might signal an attack.
Predictive maintenance, identifying
ports or links likely to fail soon.
Root cause analysis, correlating thousands
of logs in seconds to find the issue.
Without ai these tasks will become
humongous and take a lot of time.
But with the help of AI, we are
able to scale up much better and
root cause it much more efficiently.
A real world example is a global
Telco used an AI to detect
wifi degradation across regions
before customers ever noticed.
Serving millions in support calls
these capabilities transform
operations from reactive to proactive,
from firefighting to forecasting.
The shift AI drinks is not incremental.
It's transformational tasks that took
hours like sifting through telemetry data
now happen continuously and automatically.
AI systems analyze traffic behavior,
link health and security patterns to
adjust configurations in real time.
Imagine a network that knows
peak hours for your app.
Reallocate bandwidth and tunes,
quality of service parameters
before condition actually happens.
That's the power of moving from monitor
and react to anticipate and adapt.
Self optimizing networks
are where AI truly shines.
These are systems that can self-diagnose.
Radar out traffic around failures, and
even heal themselves automatically.
For instance, if a link in Singapore
fails and the network could re out through
Tokyo in milliseconds without anyone
touching a console, the impact is massive.
Reduce downtime, faster
resolution, and lower costs.
But autonomy must come with guardrails.
Engineers must define safety limits.
Like what an AI can change to
avoid any unintended consequences.
So this definition of guardrails
and how you put safety checks
in place is pretty important.
And this brings us to
a cri critical truth.
AI can enhance, but not
replace human expertise.
A lacks context.
It doesn't understand business goals,
regulations, or organization culture.
For example, an AI might flag a large data
transfer as security threat, but a human
knows it's a sanctioned quarterly backup.
The best networks come from
AI plus human collaboration.
AI accelerates analysis.
Humans provide judgment,
strategy and ethical oversight.
As engineers, we remain the interpreters
and architects behind the intelligence
feature.
Ready networks are modular, API,
driven and observable by design.
A PA first design allows systems
to integrate and automate easily.
Microservices architecture
ensures scalability.
You can upgrade one service without
taking the entire system down.
Declarative configuration lets
you describe the desired state.
Instead of typing imperative comments,
the system figures out how to get there.
Observability by default, gives AI the
data it needs to learn and improve.
Think of it as moving from a static
machine to a living evolving organism.
Scalability and resiliency aren't add-ons.
They must be baked into the architecture.
Horizontal scaling adds
more nodes, not bigger ones.
Stateless design reduces dependencies.
Graceful degradation.
If one part fails, the system
still runs, even if partially.
Chaos engineering deliberately
breaking things and testing to
build confidence and recovery.
Netflix popularized this idea.
Their Chaos Monkey tool randomly
shuts down systems to test resiliency.
Networks need the same philosophy.
Plan for failure and design for recovery.
So how do we get there?
Here's a five step roadmap.
Assess current state, identify where AI
can help, and what skills your team lacks.
Build the foundation, automate
repetitive tasks and collect telemetry.
Pilot AI solutions.
Try AI in low risk areas
like anomaly detection.
Scale intelligently, which
is like bringing successful
pilots into production.
Monitor results and refine
them, iterate over them.
Foster innovation, encourage learning
hackathons, and crossed in collaboration.
This journey is iterative.
Each phase strengthens the next.
It's evaluation, not revolution.
To wrap up, master the fundamentals.
Deep protocol knowledge
never goes out of style.
Embrace continuous learning.
AI and automation evolve quickly.
Stay curious, think architecturally.
Design for adaptability and scale.
From day one, collaborate
across disciplines.
The best results come from networking
software and data teams working together.
The future of network engineering
isn't about replacing people with ai.
It's about augmenting our intelligence,
creating systems that learn,
adapt, and evolve alongside us.
Thank you all and I hope this
inspires you to start building
tomorrow's networks today.
Thank you.