Cyber defense used to be written
in codes, playbooks, policies.
Now it is written or spoken in prompts.
A sentence can now accelerate a threat.
Configure a policy, configure
policies, and even expose secrets.
What an honor to be here at the
Prompt Engineering 2025 conference.
My name is Cynthia Kyo to a cybersecurity
architect with years of experience in
managing identity and assess management.
As data security.
Today I'm going to be discussing about how
security co-pilot reinvent cyber defense
using prompts from prompts to protection.
Let's face reality with the.
Evolving landscape.
We have about 7,000 password
attacks per second, not minutes.
This is like having 7,000 doors open.
Ling, while you are still thinking
about how to close the last one.
83% of organizations, we have more
than one breach in their lifetime.
This is not a scare or a threat, and this
is not a probability of if it's when and
how often this breach is going to happen.
80% of executives are living in
fair due to AI leaked risk Employees
partners are now putting prompts,
inputting sensitive information into ai.
This is a big challenge and I like
to call it the pressure cooker.
We are currently facing the pressure that
organizations are facing, the pressure as
an enterprise that we are facing, and the
pressure as security analysts and security
defenders that we are facing present.
It's becoming very overwhelming
for defenders, for analysts.
AI is moving at the speed of light, so
also attackers are making use of ai.
AI can now draft.
Phishing male emails even better
than humans, difficult to track.
Analysts are drowned, are flooded
with alerts, both false positive, both
those that are critical with fatigue.
Even the best team cannot
manage the flood of alerts.
Or manage or check security
loopholes within the organization.
The issue or the challenge is in that
security professionals are not skilled
or the threat landscape and attackers
are now moving at the speed of light.
It becomes difficult.
Analysts to follow through.
Because this era requires managing a lot
and managing context, defenders need to
operationalize ai Since attackers are
now weaponizing artificial intelligence.
I said earlier that those that the
previous slide shows the pressure
organizations are facing, this is
showing the current pain point of
security professionals facing this.
It requires analysts to be able to
manage the security landscape at
scale and also at machine speed.
To be able to combat the speed
in which attackers are exploiting
loopholes in our organization with
the use of artificial intelligence.
Since ai, the same force that can be
used to weaponize, our organization can
also be used to amplify our organization.
To manage our security posture.
As a Microsoft certified Information
Security administrator, I make use
of Microsoft security copilot, and
I taught it to share, use it as a
case study to see how AI can become
our teammate and a force multiplier
with artificial intelligence.
Prompts can now be turned to policies,
some risk to strategies, and even
recommendation and response to resolution.
Imagine the frustration that analysts
are facing with the landscape changing.
Attackers becoming so fast.
Leveraging artificial intelligence
to exploit our organization, it now
becomes very important and critical
for security analysts, security
professionals, to leverage the use
of artificial intelligence as a
force multiplier in our organization.
Instead of checking or
searching for alerts manually.
With the use of artificial intelligence
and leveraging prompts, a security analyst
can decide to type in natural language
to assess the security posterior office
organization, or the environment like
asking what, who are the most suspicious
or high risk users in the organization.
This now becomes a way to manage gaps.
This is not automation.
I call it argumentation.
Helping security professionals to
leverage artificial intelligence
in order to be able to manage our
landscape at machine speed and at scale,
leveraging the use of intelligence
in a smarter way because attackers.
Weaponizing using artificial intelligence
and defenders, we need to operationalize
as well using artificial intelligence.
This requires us to be able to
understand context, to be proactive
and to utilize intelligence market.
With Microsoft Security copilot, you
can integrate it across your endpoint
from Defender Purview, Microsoft into
a lot more to assess your identity and
assess management, to assess your data
posture, to assess weak points and
vulnerability within your ecosystem.
Then.
One of the silent, I call it the
silent and most dangerous drifts.
All loopholes that organizations
have is conditional assets drifts.
Imagine you are in a large
enterprise, users are onboarded.
They change rules and sometimes even
exit the organizations users in the
course of changing rules are acquiring
different rights, admin rights.
What about application drift in
your organization where you have
applications deployed into the
organization and they are not covered
with conditional access policies All.
We have redundant policies, duplicate
policies, all these are quiet ways
in which attackers can leverage these
loopholes to assess our organization.
When users are not covered
with proper policies like multi
default authentication, attackers
can easily compromise those.
The identity of those users
to assess our environment.
What's about having different
policies that are obsolete, duplicate
policies, conflicting policies.
It becomes very difficult
and messy to manage.
And as a security analyst and
professional, I can tell you that it.
It is also very difficult for the human
eye to detect such loopholes, and that
is why Conditional Access Optimization
agents basically manages these drifts.
User drifts, application drifts
and manages policies to ensure that
these policies are consolidated.
And all this do not create
loopholes and vulnerability.
Within our organization, it creates
that awareness, that context, to
understand the ecosystem, to see gaps
immediately and respond to it before
it becomes a breach or an access
point for attackers to leverage now.
Let's go straight to the demo
to see how conditional access
optimization agent works.
Right now I'm going to show basically.
The use of conditional
access optimization agent.
I'm in the Microsoft intra tenant, and
here you can see users at high risk.
In my tenant, I have 54 user
detection with high risk level.
So now I'm going to go straight to agents.
I click on this, go to agents.
It takes me straight to the conditional
access optimization agent where I can
check for user drift to see users that
are not covered by conditional access
policies, like multi authentication to see
applications deployed in the organization
that are not covered with this proper
policies and even check for policy Mer.
So here.
With conditional access optimization,
it shows me the performance highlights.
Right here I can see I have one
20 unprotected users discovered.
This is AI.
At work,
I can also see activities that have
been carrying out by the agent.
Extent of the where you see a security
analyst drowned with a lot, drowned with
managing floods of configuration and
policy with the agent on guard 24 hours.
The security analyst can
also take a break as well.
So here I can view the
activities of the agents.
So basically this shows me
the activity of the agents.
From seeing what it did from the
conditional access optimization engine,
seeing the policy user drift, you can see
it scanned users within the last 24 hours.
You can see these activities, so
let's go straight into subjections.
That is where I like to show more.
These suggestions basically
scans your environment.
And tells you where there are gaps, and
also give you recommendations on how you
can apply policies to cover these gaps.
So now I have here there's a
recommendation or a subjection saying
how two users to existing policy
require MFA for financial apps.
For high, medium, and
low risk signing user.
So there is a financial application
used in the organization and before
users should assess that application.
The condition access optimization is
suggesting that two users currently have
not been added to those PO to that policy.
So that is a gap.
So with this, I can now
apply the subjection.
So it basically even gives me an
explanation that the policy requires users
to complete multi-part authentication.
All I have to do is to click this and
apply the subjection, and it shows
that the subjection has been applied.
So now those two users are now covered
by multi authentication while assessing.
This financial application, so basically
conditional assets optimization, it covers
across user drifts, your application
drifts, and even consolidates policies.
That is the beauty of AI
when used in cyber defense.
Next I want to talk about is
going straight to our data.
Now that we've seen how to manage
identity and assess management,
managing gaps within our loop
organization, from application drift
to policy drift, and to policy.
Loopholes to even user drift data
move across like our organization
from your SharePoint to your teams,
to your Outlook data move across, and
that is where Microsoft purview and
the security copilot comes into play.
Basically managing the data
governance and data security.
Of our organization leveraging data
loss prevention to ensure that there
is no expiration or data oversharing
of sensitive information so that
executive wound fear AI leakage risk,
or managing insider risk across ano
loss activities of users checking
for intentional or unintentional.
Activities carried out by users and
tracking it in real time with security.
Copilot prompts can then be leverage to
even assess users that are not covered by
data loss prevention policies or assess
the sequence of activities that users have
carried out or a nice insider has done.
In seconds, you can see what they've done.
Either they downloaded documents.
If they send sensitive documents
to their personal emails.
So that is the beauty of where we
use data governance, leveraging
artificial intelligence and making
it conversational in real time.
Let's look at the demo
of how this is done.
Now I'm taking you to
the Microsoft Power View.
I'm going to click on Solutions, and here
you can see copilot is right here for us.
I'll click on Solutions right away
and click on data loss prevention.
So basically data loss
prevention is checking for.
Data exposure to see information that
has sent out of your organization
or even within your organization.
Sensitive information gives you that
real time, a lot for you to check it,
and you can also create policies when you
notice these gaps in your organization.
First, I'll click on policies.
Now with copilot, all I have to do, I
can get insight on the existing policies
I have deployed in my organization.
I don't have to go
around searching around.
All I have to do is just click
this, get insight on policies.
I'm going to click get insight
on policies in my organization.
I've done that and I can
leverage either getting insight.
Based on location, based on
the classification of data.
So if I want to get insights
on my location, lemme check by
endpoint, for example, I click
this and it generates this for me.
It says, it gives me
information around the policies.
So what I can say here is.
Your policies are looking for data
in location, in the location of
endpoint devices with a total of 16
policies applied to the location.
So I already know the number of
policies applied to that location.
It shows me the type of information
from financial data, privacy and person.
So I have details of the
classification and all.
I can also go ahead and get insight
based on another location, maybe
exchange teams and all that.
Then let me click on alerts
here is easy, so easily
get information on alerts.
For example, if our policy has
triggered something, it can, I can
easily get that information here.
So I click on this and
let's check this first one.
DSE policy.
DLP Policy match for a document,
POS lever, I click this.
So this is a document.
Apparently a user was trying
to, or an employee was trying to
download this document on a device.
And is a sensitive document,
the POS lever document.
So all I have to do is to
come in here, go straight down
and summarize the alert.
So all I click this, summarize.
Summarize a lot or
summarize user activity.
So I want to see a summary of the alert.
It's already telling me that this
is a high severity DLP alert, and
the next thing I can also do is give
me details of the policy as well.
Data match for the document.
So with prompts, you can easily get
this information within me seconds.
So something that will take us
as you get it within seconds.
I can summarize user activity.
So see what the user has been up to.
So here.
This shows that this a,
this like a insider risk.
The user is found to be involved
in inspiration activities on that.
On the same day, the user sent emails
with attachment outside the organization.
The user uploaded files to cloud storage,
which included files that were sensitive.
So it gives me the sequence of activities.
Collection of unusual
volume of sensitive files.
They also engaged in deleting files.
So it was a sequence of activity of where
the user uploaded information, sensitive
information into the cloud, sent that
attachment outside the organization and
then went ahead to delete those documents.
So this is more oh, maybe I
disgruntled the employee who
is exiting the organization.
And is not happy.
So with this prompt it has been,
I was able to get this information
in real time just using words.
So security co-pilots and prompts are
changing the way in which we manage
our security landscape, making it
easier for security professionals.
Security analysts to move faster
and at the pace in which attackers
are exploiting our ecosystem.
Just like I have talked about prompts,
prompt is also like a new perimeter.
Now, we also need to safeguard
this prompts and audit
every activities or prompts.
Done by security analysts to ensure
that it is not compromised, ensuring
that there is auditability of every
process and treating security copilot
as a privileged assess surface because
security copilot is now is our teammates.
So we need to track every
activities and ensure it is
covered with the proper policies.
As well.
There should be need with critical pilots.
Visibility and speed must co exist.
There should not be in isolation so that
while we are leveraging prompts to combat
security challenges and work at the speed
of light, we can also ensure that our
security copilot is protected as well.
AI isn't here to replace us.
It is here to reveal where we
must evolve because attackers
already speak AI fluently.
It's time for defenders security
professionals to also do from
prompts to protection, from noise to
insight, from reaction to resilience.
If we can't out cold attackers,
we should outthink them.
And the new language is our words.
Leveraging prompts to combat
security challenges to combat the
trade landscape, leveraging prompts.
As our weapons defenders
don't fail from lack of skill.
They fail from lack of skill, lack
of context, because they can't
manage the speed in which these
floods and alerts are coming in.
So encourage everyone to leverage the
user's prompts in mitigating security.
In managing our security posture as it'll
save us a lot of time and ensure that we
become proactive rather than reactive.
Thank you very much.
Feel free to connect with me on
LinkedIn, and it's been a great
pleasure to be part of the Prompt
Engineering 2025 conference by.