Hey everyone.
How's it going?
My name is Dan Cleary.
I'm the co founder of PromptHub
and today we will be talking
all about prompt engineering.
We'll talk about why prompt
engineering, is it dead?
system message versus prompt or
user message, how different models
require different types of prompt
and prompting methods, a variety of
different ways that you can try to
get better outputs through prompt
engineering methods, best practices.
Does persona prompting even work?
Meta prompting and a whole bunch of
templates and takeaways throughout.
So I like to start with this question
of like, why prompt engineering?
this was a pretty popular opinion.
I'd say early on that prompt engineering
wasn't really a thing, but I think Over
the months and years since ChatGPT came
out, I think people have found that
it actually can be quite hard to get
the type of output that you're looking
to get from a model consistently.
and that's where kind of prompt
engineering comes into play.
And small changes just end up making
a big difference here, because
of how models latent space works.
So if you say, write a
code to render this image.
write secure code as if you
were John Carmack, which is
like a famous software engineer.
You'll get drastically different
outputs just by those small tweaks.
And I think that will always
be there in some capacity.
you maybe have to do less of the
engineering and method type work
in the future, potentially, but I
think there's always going to be
a small place for this, at least.
Another reason why it's important
is that it's one of the three major
ways to get Better outputs from LLMs.
and it's the starting point.
So you do a bunch of prompt engineering,
you see where you're at, what problems
you're running into and whether
you need to turn to other methods
to solve those remaining problems.
It's just a starting point for a lot
of teams and it's very accessible.
You can be technical, you can
be non technical, and you can
get your, up and running very
quickly with prompt engineering.
And so lastly, you really can't avoid it.
And so for all those reasons, that's
why I believe it's important, at
least for the time being, and I
think into the near future here.
And lastly, in the same way that
having good UI UX product experience
is a competitive advantage.
Having prompts that work
well is a similarly important
competitive advantage for AI teams.
So now we'll talk about the different
types of messages that models can
support, namely system versus user.
So system message, as you can see
here, you are helpful assistant.
Then we have a user message, which
is like the prompt where you're
sending to the model to get an output.
So on and so forth.
System message is optional.
Like when you're doing
these things via the API.
so this is the stuff that you are, is
behind chat GPT's interface in terms
of what open AI has programmed, the.
Chatbot to sound like and
think and so it's optional when
you're sending it via the API.
It's used to set context and rules,
so just the higher level things
versus low level instructions.
So setting the role, context, guiding
the model behavior, controlling
format, things like that, versus
the prompt is where you get more
specific, more of the contextual info.
The focus, so on and so forth.
And we have a couple of examples in the
wild here from companies like OpenAI.
Anthropic also published
theirs, on their documentation.
So you could see the system messages
that power their Claude, chatbots.
And so now we'll talk about how different
models require different prompts.
So if you're interchanging between
providers and even models within the
same provider, you've probably run
into this experience where each of
them has their own differences in
the way they handle tasks and the
way that they sound and respond.
so for example, we'll
take a chain of thought.
so this is thinking step by step,
prompting the model to do some
reasoning before giving an output.
There's an experiment ran where they found
that chain of thought actually reduced
the performance of Palm two, which is, an
older Google model at this point, but just
goes to show that doing what is considered
a best practice didn't help performance.
In this case, it actually
made things worse.
And That just goes to show that one size
is really not going to fit all, which is
the second paper we'll talk about, which
is from VMware, where they basically
tested a wide variety of different prompt
openers, descriptions, and closers.
They put all these prompts together
using all of these different parts here.
Here are a couple examples
of a math dataset with the
various system messages here.
Some have a role, some
don't, so on and so forth.
And what they did was they had the
model generate the best prompt.
for that specific task.
And so they, they let the model decide
and do its own metaprompting based
on the task and the outputs that it
was receiving and so on and so forth.
This was what Llama 2 created and
you could see, it's including kind
of some Star Trek language here.
So this is after running hundreds of
prompts, doing hundreds of metaprompting
in like an experimental way.
setting where there is, a high
degree of statistical significance.
Versus Llama 2, 13b, so same
family, same provider, doesn't know
mention of any Star Trek things,
like it's all very cut and dry.
And then this was pretty popular last
year, this kind of take a deep breath
and work on this problem step by step.
This was a similar experiment where they
had the model figure out a top instruction
for itself, and they ran a bunch of tests
to see which one goes to the top here.
And so they were, this is the
top instruction for the A variety
of different models here, and we
can see GPT's fours is You know,
five times larger than palm twos.
And so it just goes to show that
everything is going to be a little
bit different depending on the model.
And that's why it's important
to test these things.
And if you're looking for more
information on models like max tokens,
context, windows, costs, features, and
functionalities, we have a, directory
that we just launched that has all the
information for basically all the model
providers that are the most popular.
All right So moving on to My two favorite
prompt engineering practices and the
one that we tell the teams that we work
with to focus on is you know giving the
model room to think this is a popular
one and kind of relays into Chain of
thought to a degree you want to let the
model think you don't want to force it
to give an answer Or overly constrain it.
You want it to go through some
sort of reasoning process and
come to an answer on its own.
And then using delimiters or some
way to better structure your prompt.
I can't tell you how many times
I've had a team say, Hey, we're
struggling with this prompt.
Can you look at it?
I look at it and I can't even.
See what's going on.
And so that's a good litmus test
is have someone else look at your
prompts, see if they can organize
it or understand your organization.
And if not start to provide some
of that via, delimiters, backticks,
quotes, whatever is going to
help structure the prompt better.
Now we'll look at a few.
So just to set the stage, a zero
shot prompt is just a normal prompt.
So if you hear that ever referenced, it's
basically just a typical prompt like this.
A few shot prompt is when you include
examples inside of your prompt.
So this would be all one prompt
sent, but we're going to say,
show It's examples in line.
So we're classifying the
sentiment of this feedback.
So this person's positive,
then negative, then positive.
And then we're going to let the model
kind of fill in the, the blank here.
And you could do this
via multiple messages.
So like sending an array
of messages from the API.
And that's typically, I think, technically
what few shop really is rather than
having it all be in one message.
Because the model will handle it
different if it has it in its history
versus reading it all in a prompt.
Both ways are effective.
Both ways are worth testing.
SureShot Prompting is really
helpful in a variety of domains.
It can help with structure.
format, content, style, and tone,
and those are really the really big
areas that I've seen it be helpful.
How many examples?
The great benefit here is that
you get a lot of the gains from
just having one or two examples.
And then it plateaus and can even
degrade in a lot of situations.
we say, hey, start with, Anywhere from
two to five examples, if you're still
not getting the performance you're
looking for, you might need to look
elsewhere because you have the chance of
it starting to degrade, the performance.
A couple of other important,
best practices here.
Use diverse examples.
So if you're doing a sentiment
analysis, don't use only positive ones.
Use a combination.
Have them cover a wide range
of what you are going to be
expecting in your application.
So cover those edge cases.
Random, randomly order them so you
wouldn't have all the positives in one
section and then all the negatives.
And then make sure they follow
a common format so the model can
better learn, in context there.
And we have a whole guide on this as
well, with lots of examples and templates.
Alright, next up is according
to prompting, which is basically
just trying to ground the model
in a specific set of information.
so you can see in this original prompt,
it's asking a question, and then it just
has, adds in according to Wikipedia.
So it's trying to guide the model to the
type of answer that you are looking for.
are looking to.
And this can be helpful, especially
if you've done like some fine tuning.
And here's an example of that.
Again, all the templates are
available in PromptTab under
the templates tab for free too.
And then last one I believe
is called step back prompting.
So this is a very similar kind of, I say,
variant of chain of thought prompting,
where you send a question, you have
the model kind of think step by step
in first kind of abstract concepts, and
then Use those abstractions to reason
through the question or the task.
And so you prompted to do this thinking
first, and this is what you see with a
one preview and a one mini where it thinks
about the step that reasons about them.
And then it solves the problem.
So again, yeah, these are
all linked in prompt up.
So app dot prompt dot U S slash templates.
Last up.
And my favorite one is persona prompting.
So this is like very
popular for a long time now.
so this is like giving the.
the model, a persona to
solve a certain task.
And there are a lot of papers
on both sides of this in
terms of how effective it is.
I have come out to the other side
to thinking it's actually not that
effective in certain use cases.
And the main reason comes
from a learn prompting.
org paper, which is linked here.
I had this intuition that it wasn't
great for doing accuracy based tasks,
and this really reinforced that.
So basically they set up an experiment.
They ran 2000 prompts, and it was a MMLU
case, so like a knowledge based, task, and
they gave a bunch of different roles here.
And really the kind of long
and short of it is that.
The genius when they were told
the model, it was a genius.
It got a lower percentage than
when it told it, it was like an
idiot or something like that.
Yeah.
The genius was actually the
worst performing one here.
And so how can you reconcile that and
still think that role prompting works?
I don't know.
we have to look at other data, but this
seems just pretty strong to rule out
that conclusion and everything else.
I would say it may just be anecdotal,
but it is helpful in terms of,
I would say, Tone and style.
So if you're doing content generation,
things like that, but not for increasing
accuracy, last up, we'll talk a
little bit about meta prompting.
So what's meta prompting.
It's a prompt engineering method that uses
the LLM to help you write your prompt.
So using chat GPT to
help write your prompt.
And we are big proponents of this.
We think this is how prompt engineering
should really be done alongside
the model that you're working with.
And the same way they use, AI and LLMs
for writing and coding, you should
do it for prompt engineering as well.
work together to form a good prompt
for your use case, and then go and test
that, and continue that iterative loop.
And there's a bunch of
tools out there to do this.
We have one that we launched, and
specifically, we will run a different,
Prompt to generate your prompt.
So that meta prompt based on whatever
provider you're using, because as we
saw before, every provider is different.
So we've baked in those
differences into the meta prompt
for each one of the providers.
Leverages best practices.
It's free.
You can use it in our
app without any account.
so that's good to go.
Anthropic was one of the first ones to do
this, and I think they have a really great
grasp on prompt engineering in general.
So you can use this in
the Anthropic console.
A bunch of best practices built in.
It's open source.
it does charge.
that's nominal.
And then OPI actually just
released one, past month or so.
You can use it in the playground and
it generates system messages only.
but it's still usable and fun.
And we did a little bit of prompt
injections to get the prompt behind
that because it wasn't open source.
And so that was really cool to see.
It's always interesting to see how The
model providers are writing prompts.
So that's available in prompt as well.
Wrapping up four things you can do today,
structuring your prompts with headers,
delimiters, that's going to be a big help.
The more specific you are
in your instructions, the
better your prompt will be.
You can throw out all the other methods.
if you can just nail
that part, that's great.
And if you don't nail it, all the other
stuff really isn't going to help you.
Examples of VFU shop
prompting is a great way.
I think metaprompting plus a few shot
plus chain of thought is like really going
to be the winning formula going forward.
and then don't overly constrain the model.
And thank you.
I hope you enjoy this.
If you want to talk about
this, feel free to reach out.
we're active on LinkedIn, and yeah,
have a great rest of your day.