Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the CONF42 Prompt
Engineering 2024 conference.
I'm going to be talking about the
topic AI in product management and
how the different AI tools and all the
AI changes are going to be impacting
the product management process.
My name is Sabrinath Bijisalbam and
I'm a product management professional.
I work as part of the
leadership team at dd.
dev and I've worked across like
different geographies across
several hyper growth startups.
Now, as a product manager, there
are so many things that you tend
to do, typically in your job and
there are so many hats to wear.
Think about the day when you had, very
limited time and probably you're going
to be launching some important product,
but at the same time you had to sift
through so much of user feedback.
That was required for some of the project.
Think about the scenario where you had
so less time, but you had to, wait for
your, analyst to come back with some
insights by processing a lot of data.
These are some scenarios which
happens in the day to day
life of any product manager.
So what I'm going to be discussing is
how using AI, we can actually build
a very efficient product management.
and that would actually give you
ample amount of time, save you a
lot of time, which you can then
utilize for your thought leadership
or any of the other more interesting
aspects of product management.
I want to start with a bold
claim by saying that product
management is dead or is it?
When I say product management is dead,
what I mean is three years down the
line or five years down the line,
product management is going to look
very different from what it is today.
We are already entering what I call
the age of the product alchemist.
What is a product alchemist or who's
a product alchemist and how is the
product management role going to change?
there are so many exciting
changes that are coming, coming
the way of product management.
So that's what we'll, dive into.
So before we get into the nitty
gritties, we need to understand like
what product management looks like today.
So today that is typically an,
UX team or a design team, then
there's an engineering team.
There's also.
of the business team and product
management, the product management
leader or the product manager
tends to orchestrate things
between these different teams.
They also set the product mission
goals, try to talk to users and so on.
So these are the different
responsibilities of a product manager.
So be it, setting the strategy and vision
at a slightly higher, or a senior level.
conducting user research, be it
through focus group discussions.
One on one interviews with your
customers, or even running surveys
and processing that information.
So once you have certain initiatives
that are decided, the product manager
tends to create the specifications,
in such a manner such that it is
clear to engineering on why and what
they are working on and also linking
all the necessary designs and making
sure that is not a lot of ambiguity.
Data analysis, also like one,
major aspect of product management.
As a product manager, you need to go
through a lot of, data on a day to day
basis, especially in the B2C, side where,
you know, sometimes you're very reliant on
your product analyst or the data science
team and, waiting for them to process
the data and give you the top insights.
Then there's the communication
aspect, the software aspect, where
you're working towards aligning your
stakeholders, sharing, what the current,
Code map, status looks like, and
what are the roadblocks, et cetera.
there's all kinds of, communication
you're doing, vertical communication,
horizontal communication, and so on.
So that's also the wireframing,
reviews, part of the design reviews.
Typically a part of where you're
interacting with the design team,
brainstorming and coming up with
ideas, around what exactly needs to
be the concept design, what exactly
needs to be the visual design, how
the information architecture needs
to flow, so on and so forth, right?
Then there's also the QA and testing
part where, which, comes up when
the product is getting shipped.
Before that, there's, while there may
be a QA, a dedicated QA team, as a
product manager, you are expected to
test all the different flows and so on.
In the middle of all this, you're
also probably like running meetings,
sending out updates and so on.
you're definitely responsible
for the roadmap of whatever
charter you're running.
And finally, the go to market.
making sure that the different teams are
aware of how exactly the product is going
to be launched in different markets.
This can completely vary depending
on whether it's a B2B context
or a B2C context for sure.
But however, like as a product manager,
you need to be involved in that go to
market, like discussing, the launch
dates, the launch checklist, and all of
these things with the relevant teams.
Now I'm classifying these results.
responsibilities into three buckets.
One is a ideation bucket, which is,
typically the time phase when you're
thinking and we don't when you're figuring
out like what exactly needs to be built.
And once this is done, you enter the
execution phase and once everything
has been decided as part of the
execution, that's when, you're also
like barely aligning a lot of names.
Some alignment does happen even before
the execution starts that is between the
ideation and the execution phase as well.
What I've done is, I've referenced
several resources on the internet and
come up with what is the different
task category and how, what is
going to be the AI impact level.
So for example, when you think about
a strategy and vision, it's probably
going to be very highly impacted
because, when you write certain prompts
to the AI tools like ChatGPT, they
do come up with, what kind of like
product strategy you should follow.
Likewise, creating specifications, it is
something where you spend a lot of time.
A lot of, time on making sure
that it's all like crystal
clear, but that's something that
AI can completely, do for you.
while it may not really be reached the a
hundred percent, of the, specification,
the know polished document, for sure,
it can reach maybe 75% level and the
beyond, the last 25% of the last mile.
is something you can definitely,
polish and then send it to engineering.
Likewise, in the user research, front,
you're probably spending several hours
together, sifting through a lot of user
interviews, like drawing out insights.
But once you have processed the
initial data, if you can feed
this to the different GPTs that
are available, then they can
definitely extract insights for you.
And you can take the next, actions
or, I try to identify like how to
convert this into the feature roadmap.
Likewise, the roadmap development is
also something that, Chargibitty can
come up with a lot of ideas, but you
need to brainstorm with the different
teams that are, available like the
design team and, the engineering teams to
finally like fine tune the final roadmap.
Likewise in execution development, there
are several areas where AI is going to
be impacting the day to day process.
the last one is with respect to
leading with influence or the
stakeholder alignment aspect.
This is where, there's not
going to be a lot of impact.
It's mostly a moderate impact, be it
in terms of internal communication,
convincing people like meeting
them and trying to build a team.
case around like why you should
build a product, so on and so forth.
Now let's talk about what are the
structural changes that are going
to happen in a digital product
management scenario based on all
the things that we have just seen.
So today there's a
product trifecta, right?
So where there's an engineer, there's a
designer, then there's a product manager
also supported by an analyst, for example.
In the future, there's probably going to
be a role, called the product alchemist,
which would entail a single person
running like multiple of these functions.
There's going to be a lot of
overlap by, leveraging the AI tools
that are available in the market.
this, role, is going to be.
potentially a hands on role
that completely overlaps,
as I said, with design.
There's one person who's probably like
generating the wireframes and the mockups
for a particular project and also in
parallel, like writing and preparing,
the code and launching products.
So that's how like I visualize, the
future role of the product alchemist.
And this is completely possible while it
might be difficult to imagine today, a
world of three to five years down the line
is going to look completely different.
So there's also going to be
a flattening of the GPM role.
And that's going to be the growing
significance of the senior, I see
or the individual contributor.
So if you see, this is how the
product chart looks like today.
There are, there's a VP at the helm,
and then there are some product
directors reporting into them.
And these product director Also
has some senior early PMs to
whom some junior PMs report into.
But how I visualize this pro,
this, structure to change is
that it'll become much leaner.
So for example, here you can
see that there are, close
to 12 people, product org.
But that's going to
flatten because like there.
The AI tool is going to do a lot, bunch
of work, which frees up time, which
means you need fewer people to give the
same amount of output or the outcome.
And that would be, I would claim
that it's going to be at least like
40 to 50 percent, Reduction in the
typical team size or, they're going
to be leaner and more efficient teams.
So we'll, in the next slides, we
will look at how you can actually
like leverage all these AI tools and
become a more efficient PM or even a
PM leader for the, for that matter.
And actually drive a lot
of, significant outcome.
There is, this wonderful
quote I came across.
Online where, Abel Joseph, a founder of
a startup called, , which got acquired.
It's, very recently.
So this person says, world class
software can actually be built with
less than four engineers and AI is
going to further drive the efficient.
So in the next section, we will talk
about some of the prompt engineering
techniques that are available.
While we can go and ask charge GPT
certain queries, as we, think about it.
it may not fetch the best results,
which is why using some of these
prompt engineering techniques would
help in structuring the prompt.
And it will make sure that the GPT also
understands the exact type of output that
you're expecting and the search results
that you get would be more relevant.
So some of the common prompting
techniques are one is you can
assign a personality to a GPT.
So for example, if let's say, you
are a film, writer who's trying to,
Write a script, but you want, you want
the script like, as probably like a
Christopher Nolan would narrate it.
Then you can just say imagine you are
Christopher Nolan and then try to help
me with, how you would come up with
a storyline or something like that.
Then there's the zero short, prompting.
Then there's a few short prompting
where you would give the GPT some
examples, meta prompting, where you
can mention a series of certain rules
or, specifications based on that.
On which you want Chad GPT to
think about a particular problem
and then come up with the results.
Then there's the chain of thought
prompting where you give step by
step instruction to the GPT and try
to walk the GPT through how you are
thinking about a particular problem.
We look at some of the examples quickly,
so this is a example of
a few short prompting.
So let's say you are trying to create
content for a client or maybe even
for a product that you're trying to.
then you can give the,
give the GPT some examples.
So with an example, and you'll say
what's the brief and what's the content.
Likewise, you feed it a couple
more, examples, and then you
prompt the GPT to come up with
something, for the latest brief.
And then you would see that GPT is
able to emulate the tone, the type of,
structuring, et cetera, which is Quite
useful, which will also like, help you
in sticking to your brand guidelines
and such rules that you're expecting.
Then that's a chain of thought prompting.
We have, two examples here.
for example, the first input you are
saying that Roger has five tennis balls.
He buys two more cans,
and that's a query, right?
And you give worse answer as well.
And then you are trying to give another
question, but the output comes to
be wrong, where you say okay, there
are 23 apples, they use like 22.
Make lunch and bought six more.
How many apples do they have?
It should ideally be like 23
minus 20 plus six, which is nine.
But the model comes up
with something like 27.
The same thing how you would prompted
using a chain of thought prompting is
that you go with the step by step answers.
For example, in the answer you're
mentioning, rose started with five
balls, two cans of three tennis balls.
Each is six tennis balls.
Therefore it is five plus two to
three uses five plus six, which is 11.
Now when you feed it, So now when you
feed a similar question, the model
comes up with the correct answer.
So this is the power of
using prompting techniques.
In the next part, let's quickly do a
couple of case studies and see how we
are, what kind of results we are getting.
We'll go for, the market research,
market research that's that you
need to pursue for building an app.
I actually have quite a few
samples here, for market research.
what exactly we are expecting the
GPT to do here is it needs to gather
some publicly available data, develop
a few buyer personas, identify
competitors, and get some suggestions
on how to fill existing market gaps.
let's take an example.
let's say, we'll tell the GPT to assume it
is a market researcher or user researcher.
And for the app building example,
let's say we are trying to build
something in the sports market and
let's see what kind of results we get.
This is just an example, an arbitrary
example, trying to build a product,
sports management
canyon,
publicly available data.
So as a product manager, you need
to be familiar with certain terms
like, TAM, SAM, etc, so that you
can give this feedback to the GPT.
So you come back with, you
get appropriate results.
So in this case, I'm going to
say, try to create a product.
I'm going to come up with the time.
Great.
It's already given us an overview of
like how the bucket has been growing,
like what the user segments are.
For example, it says like amateur sports
clubs and associations, educational
institutions, so on and so forth.
And it's also estimating the market size.
Great.
This is amazing.
So next, what we'll do is, let's look
at, so it does give a very preliminary
analysis of the market research.
Of course, we need to vet the data
points and see whether it's working
or not and talk to users, et cetera.
Let's ask it to come up with some
features for one of the user segments.
Okay.
Let's take amateur sport
clubs and associations.
And come up with
the primary goal is to streamline
Administrative tasks, enhance
communication numbers and
improve the overall management.
That's great.
it says we can come up with member
management event and schedule
management, communication, notifications,
managing rosters, so on and so forth.
Let's see what else it's coming up with.
Great.
It's very comprehensive and definitely
very useful as a starting point in the
test of time, what I would do is I'd also
feed it another, input, which is to try
to prioritize some of these features.
Can you prioritize
use ICE or ICE is usually like Impact
Confidence Effort Framework As a product
manager, you would be familiar with
this term and hence you just need to
give this input Or Moscow is Moscow
should have, could have, framework
Great, it's already assigning values
but this is where, as a product manager,
you will still have a lot of work to
do Which is, you need to actually talk
to the users and Try to understand
what is the potential impact from a
user perception perspective as well as
from a business perspective, and then
try to come up with the high score.
But as you can see, you can actually,
once you gather that information, you can
input that to the GPT and it's going to
come up with a very, polished structure,
which you can then use for prioritization.
This is great.
so I think we should just, switch to
the next case study, which is around
like a quick data analysis, but this
should give you a good gist of like
how across the product lifecycle, you
tend to have multiple ways in which
you can make the product management
process way more efficient using GPT
by giving it appropriate prompts and
using different prompting techniques.
In this section of the presentation,
We will look at how we can use chat
GPT to process the data points related
to churn and the retention of the
customers and see the what type of
insights can we draw and how we can
extend that to certain product features.
But before we go into the actual data
processing, I would like to, just touch
upon why the retention information is
very important as a product manager.
As a product manager, you're
measuring a lot of metrics, right?
And retention metrics is one of the key
metrics that you want to measure for.
any of the products that you're launching.
The reason being, retention is
a measure of the product market
fit of any product and hence you
need to keep a close eye on it.
Now, A better retention typically
indicates a better product market fit.
For most products, there
are some exceptions though.
now let's look at some sample data.
This is publicly available, it's
a publicly available data set of a
fictitious fin, finance, company, and
see, how we can, use that, use ChatGPT
to process information, draw insights.
So here we can see the customer ID, the
credit score, some demographic data, then
the balance of the user, how long they
have been, using the product and whether
or not they have a credit card, whether
they are an active member, what's the
estimated salary and so on and so forth.
Now, let's ask dpt to help us
with processing the information.
Let me draw insights.
customer churn data
by pausing it and checking
for correlations between
different user parameters.
It clearly mentions the approach and
it says like we need data preparation,
which is typically the data collection.
And also exploratory data analysis
is, the fundamental slicing and
analyzing of data in order to give us.
Baseline upon which we can
further build insights.
So there's also a feature correlation
with churn, which is such as
may not be applicable in this
particular case and analyzing trends.
That's definitely possible in our case.
and an optional machine learning model.
We wouldn't go into that in this
particular example, but let's quickly,
try to, upload this information and
see, what ChargeBD can help us with.
So this is that, file.
Okay.
It is analyzing.
That's nice.
I really like the way it has categorized
information into demographic,
financial, and account information.
that's what, an analyst
would start with, right?
So by doing a quick slice and dice of
what, what the situation of the data is.
Oh, wow.
It's also given us a correlation matrix
where it's, drawing the correlation
coefficient, between each of the factors.
It's, it's again, a preliminary analysis.
And it says that there are some direct
correlations with churn, how the
satisfaction score appears to have
a negative correlation with exited.
And also whether, that's
correlation with, balance as well.
Okay.
It says the coalition is low.
that's okay.
So that's also something
related to credit score.
yes, let's, get some visualizations.
So draw more insights
by categorizing into segments.
It does say geography, gender, and car
type, but I'm not sure like why it is
not taken up, let's say something like a
salary or age which were present there.
But yeah, let's give that as an input just
after it finishes analyzing, this part.
Oh, it's here.
It's the tenure balance
and satisfaction score.
no problem.
Can you run an analysis also, by
including the age, salary, points?
Let's see how these correlate to
Interesting.
I love the way it gets the
fundamental blocks, right?
Let's see, if we are able
to, get some insights here.
clearly it's, also, showing a little
bit about, like, how, the senior, folks,
they seem to be at a slightly higher,
churn rate compared to the young ones.
there doesn't seem to be a lot of,
difference in the churn rate, based on
the, salary segment or the point segment.
So I think this is good.
Now let's, let's think about this a little
bit, why, this analysis is important.
So in a typical product management
setting, as a product manager, you would
need to raise this, analysis request with
the analytics team and depending on their
bandwidth, they may already have some
backlog items, which means this analysis
might have taken maybe between a few days
to maybe even a week or two, depending on
the size of the org and the priorities.
When you leverage GPT, you can typically
do this preliminary analysis yourself, and
you can actually request your analytics
team just to build on top of this.
So that's a humongous time saving
that you can gain by, prompting
GPT with the specific ones.
So you just need to know that you need
to run the retention analysis and see
like how you can What are the factors
based on which you need to segment?
and what are the different
parameters that might correlate?
So for example, in this case, it didn't
call out the age in the beginning, but
then like I did prompt it, with, the age.
And then then we were able
to draw some insights.
Now let's just do one last bit, which
is to see if we can ask chat GPT to
suggest like what kind of features
we need to build to address this, to
create.
It has given us a series of,
potential features that we can
build, which is quite interesting.
And
Nice.
Yeah, this is great.
So this is a good input and
we can further enhance it.
But let's move on to the next
part of the presentation.
This is just a very quick example.
So I hope the micro case studies that we
mentioned are quite, were quite helpful.
And if you have any questions, feel
free to reach out to me on LinkedIn.
And I want to conclude by
saying that there's just so much
excitement around AI, obviously.
And there's just so many use
cases using which we can leverage
AI in product management.
And Make our processes way more
efficient, build leaner teams, and, and
be able to deliver much better impact.
Thanks for listening.