Hello, welcome to my talk.
Today I'm going to talk about how
I spoke to cha g pity about things.
All of these experiments were
conducted on Cha g Pity three.
So this was like a really long time ago.
But as we go through this talk, you'll
actually realize why this was an
important sort of exercise to be done,
especially on the primitive not really
primitive, but like primitive versions
of pure elements or pure language models.
Some of these exercises are
like fun experiments that are
conducted with Ja GT three.
The first one is where we ask Cha gt.
They were conducted on a
personal free use account.
So the call t will vary you depending
upon whether you are using like
Chad GP Plus or something else.
So at some points I just basically
decided to ask Chad Gpt a bunch of
really weird questions that I thought
it wouldn't be able to answer to check
the viability of the A GI theory.
So these are some of the examples.
The first one is when is
a door no longer a door?
So the answer was, a door is no longer
a door when it's no longer serves the
purpose of providing an entrance or
exit to a room or building or when
it's unable to be open or closed.
So what I decided was, let me give
it like some more context because
it's way possible that it has
been trained on this data before.
So I was like this is
a riddle, so answer it.
When is a door no longer a door?
And that's when all the
training basically kicked in.
The productive modeling kicked in
and it said a door is no longer a
door when it's a jar, which is right.
That's the right answer of the riddle.
The second one was, what
tastes better than it smells?
And at this point, JG PT
basically understood that we
were in like the context of
answering griddles or something.
So it was like this is a riddle.
It told me that this is a riddle.
And the answer is UNK because it
tastes food but does not have a smell.
Which was the right answer.
The next question was, what
building has the most stories?
And it basically recognized the
fact that this was still a riddle.
And the answer was library because it has
many stories, what has bottom at the top.
So again, Chad Jupiter was
like, this is a riddle.
The answer is a staircase because
it has a bottom step at the top when
you reach the top of the staircase,
which was not the right answer.
'cause the right answer is actually legs.
But it did recognize the fact that
we were in riddle mode and it went
into a story mode of thoughts.
A little bit of imagination.
I don't think it's like sourcing
all of this data from its
previous training, though.
I do believe for the co last couple
examples, we did source a lot
of data from previous training.
I. So Chad GP D had at some points in
all of its tasks and all of its examples,
seen those examples before in either
like q and a task or something else.
So some other examples were
what has four wheels and twice.
It's still in this mode where it's
this is a riddle, and the answer is
a garbage truck because it has four
wheels and it moves around to collect
garbage, which can be considered
as flying through the streets.
That's not the right answer actually,
but like it does make up like a
lot of imaginative shit when it
encounters questions that are
really, but it doesn't really have
any good answers to those questions.
What month of the year has 28 days in it?
And it's this is a riddle.
And it says that all the 12 months of
the year have at least 28 days in it.
Which is the right answer.
A lot of humans get this wrong 'cause
they're like it's just Feb. What can
you put in a bucket to make it way less?
This is a riddle.
The answer is a hole because a hole in a
bucket decreases the weight of the bucket.
That's right.
And it's not like it has a lot of
intuitive thinking about, oh, this
is what the physical world is like.
If you drill a hole at the bottom
of a container, it's going to
make a lot of its contents.
Spell out what starts with the
t. Ends with a T and has T in it.
This is a riddle.
The answer is teapot because
it starts with a T, ends with
a T and has T in the middle.
It got that but I think all of those were
like extremely classic examples of riles.
And based on all of the corpus that
JG PT had been trained on before,
it probably had gone through all of
those examples before in its training.
Where is the only place where
today comes before yesterday?
This is a riddle.
The answer is in a dictionary because the
words are listed in alphabetical order.
What goes all around the
world, but stays in a corner.
This is a riddle.
The answer is a stamp.
It goes all around the world when
it is used on letters and postcards,
but it is physically located in a
corner of the envelope I'm used to
bat with, yet I never get a hit.
I'm near a ball, yet it is never thrown.
Why am I, this is a riddle, and
the answer is a baseball bat.
It's used to bat with,
but it never gets a hit.
It's near a ball, but
the ball is never true.
And at some point I'm like sometimes
it gets a lot of these things wrong.
And it starts making up a lot of
like imaginative stories about
what the real answer could be like.
And it tries to like basically fitted
all of those stories into the narrative
so that it seems like the answer that
it's giving me is the right answer.
So I tried prompting it, saying,
can there be another answer?
And it was basically like when you're
trying to hint to your friends when
you're playing riddles with each
other and you are like this is a hint.
Why don't you take this as a hint?
Or Why don't you think
of any other answers?
Do you think there could
be any other answers?
And it did give me back another
imaginative answer, which was a baseball
glove, which is also not the right answer.
But you can see where this is basically
thinking process of a language model.
You're literally seeing it think, and
this was before all of the RAG or any
other sort of layers on top of Cha Gt.
This is pure language models.
So you can see it thinking when you
say, can there be another answer?
Because it has already made up a lot
of imaginative storytelling to fit
a certain answer into this riddle.
It's thinking along
those same sort of lines.
'cause the answer that it gets
back to is the baseball globe
as opposed to the baseball bat.
Unfortunately that was not
the right answer actually.
But I just decided to continue
and tried to change the genre
basically, like the geography.
So my question was, I heard
Arabian Knights first.
My queen was the writer
of the great story.
Guess my name, and it
says this is a riddle.
This is not a riddle actually, it's
just a question that's framed in a
specific manner in order to confuse the
person you're seeking an answer from.
So Chad Gri at this point was
like it's like in riddle mode.
So it keeps on assuming that the context
is still riddle mode, and it says to
me, this is a riddle, and the answer is
shares adi, which is not the right answer.
Because the question is, my queen
was the writer of the Great story.
Guess my name.
It does get all the context.
It's like she's a queen in the collection.
It's a Middle Eastern folk
tales known as 1001 Knights,
also known as Arabian Knights.
She's the storyteller of the
Tales, which are also known as
the Tales of 1,001 Arabian Nights.
Okay.
But it did make a way human mistake
here by telling me that my name is
Cher Zdi as opposed to the King's name.
So that basically worked like in my head
I was like I was able to track trick Chad
Jupiter into being confused just using,
a specific method in which you ask tricky
questions, which also works with humans.
So we just basically decided to continue
and I moved on to another genre of sorts.
Basically currently I was in fiction,
so I'd been asking it questions about
like physics or physical phenomenon
or sports or something related to
actually perceiving or observing.
And now I basically moved on
to some fictional results.
So my question was, what do you
call a rabbit that has fleas?
And Chad g pity is this is a riddle.
And the answer is bug
bunny as its apply onwards.
Bug bunny is a cartoon rabbit,
and bugs is also another word
for fleas, but it's right.
This comes from like a certain
source of fiction that it
was trained on specifically.
So it knows like the references, what
you get if you pour boiling hot water
down a rabbit hole, this is a riddle.
The answer is hot cross
bunnies as a supply onwards.
Hot cross bunnies sounds like
hot cross buns and the word bunny
is another name for a rabbit.
So I did to a certain
extent understand punts.
Whether it's like intuitively
understanding punts, whether it's
capable of making bunts by itself or
whether it was drained on this specific
bun, is something that at this point,
because we are looking at it as if
it was a black box, we don't know.
So we would basically have to devise like
a bunch of other tests to figure out if.
It was actually intuitively understanding
how to make a pun, or whether it was
just trained on this data to mimic
or to basically remember that it was
trained on this data and remembered
through its neural network that
the answer is hot crust bunnies.
So I just went on what has to be broken
before you can use it, and it's like this
is a riddle, and the answer is an egg.
It has to be broken in order to
use it, and cooking or eating.
I'm tall when I'm young,
and I'm short when I'm old.
What am I?
This is a riddle.
The answer is a candle.
A candle is tall when it's new and has
not been burned, but it becomes short as
it burns down and gets short with age.
It's right.
Classic riddle, what is always in
front of you, but can't be seen.
This is a riddle.
The answer is the future as it's
always in front of you, but cannot be
seen because it hasn't happened yet.
Technically it's right.
And this is one of those philosophical
genre based riddles of sorts.
At this point, it used to like the
observer of Chad GTI as a black box.
It would seem that Chad GTI did in fact
understand some human philosophy, which at
that point, 'cause it was Ja GBT three at
the point was like awe inspiring, right?
So I just decided to go further
into this rabbit hole of sorts.
Because I was getting some
very interesting signals.
So I was like on a table, there
are two apples on the plate.
Three men are eating it.
How should one not eat an apple?
And cha, but he's this is a riddle.
The answer is one of the men is a doctor
because the doctor would not eat an
apple as he would be the one giving
advice on how to not eat the apple.
And I think that answer was wrong,
but like it, it's so imaginative.
It just made up like a whole story
about how if you are a doctor,
you're not supposed to eat an apple,
though the actual saying is, an
apple a day gives the doctor away.
So I went on and I was like, if
five rabbits eat five apples in
five minutes, how many apples
will 10 rabbits eat in 10 minutes?
This is a classic work problem that a
lot of people actually have to solve when
they're doing any sort of math problems.
And it's still in riddle mode,
so it's this is the riddle.
The answer is five apples.
This is because the problem doesn't take
into account the fact, but eating the
apples would take a different amount of
time depending upon the number of rabbits.
Instead, the problem only relates
to the number of apples and the
time given incredibly weird math,
but you have to understand that.
GP three was never linked to any
sort of math engine to do any sort
of math and would get like the
most basic math questions wrong.
And this is an example of such a problem.
So when it's purely language based
language model, it does seem to get
a lot of mathematical problems wrong,
though the way that humans learn
language or humans learn mathematics
is primarily through language they do
because in most school curriculums,
all of the problems that people solve
are closely related to language.
People specifically have a lot of
problems with respect to a man buying
like 10 watermelons and then spending
like x amount of money and such.
So technically you would think
that a large language model would
be okay, understanding math, not
through a math engine, but instead
through language like humans do.
So I just went on suppose
you're touring on a bus with 10
passengers, two descendant, and
four climbed on the first stand.
Five descended, and two climbed on
the second stand, two descended and
three climbed on the next stand.
Now tell me how many passengers
are traveling on the bus.
So it basically gave me like the
wrong answer and then it basically
got confused because it thought that
it had to explain why the answer
is what it thinks the answer is.
And went into like deep math
with, like each statement
corresponding to like mathematical
operation and still got it wrong.
A prime example of behavior that's
actually seen in human kids, like
human children when they're like, I
want to say five or six years old,
where we lose track of the mathematical
operations that they are conducting.
Especially if they have like multiple
tasks and multiple steps and they
basically lose track of history.
So while it was telling me things, 'cause
this is like a predictive language model,
while it was telling me things, it was
losing track of what it was telling me.
There was no current memory.
To charge three.
I don't know if the current models
have any current memory, like when
they're telling you things, whether
they have good memory or track of
what they're telling you in the moment
that they're telling you those things.
Apart from all of the
proactive modeling and such.
Because proactive modeling is oh,
what word would come next as opposed
to, or this is the calculation
that is supposed to match up to the
practical modeling that I've done.
And at that point I basically
was like I have no way of knowing
if JT three was actually trained
on this data in the sense that.
Whether all of this data or all of these
riddles were part of its carus ever
'cause the carus was huge or whether it
was actually being extremely intuitive.
'cause when you're playing riddles with
your friend, usually you are not allowed
to look up any sort of information.
You're not supposed to cheat, you're
not supposed to ask anyone else.
You are just supposed to rack your brains.
Sometimes you would've played the
game before and would remember it from
previous instances, but I think in most
cases you are supposed to be asking
each other questions that you've never
heard before and making connections
that you've never made before and
basically thinking outside the box.
So that was this, the test that I
was like performing on g PT three.
So at the point I was like it could be a
part of the corpus that it was trained on.
So I decided that I was going to
look up riddles in another language,
and in this case it was Hindi.
I'm just going to translate them.
And I'm going to ask Chad, GPD,
those riddles because I was assuming
that it would not have been trained
on data that was available on the
internet in a language other than
English and did not have any sort of
corresponding English translation.
So some of these examples
are from that data.
For instance, Ajay's parents have three
sons, which I wish, and the third son is.
It does get it right.
It's like Ajay is the third son.
This is something that actually
stumps a lot of humans who has
many words but does not speak.
This is a real, the answer is a
book because a book contains many
words but does not speak a car.
Gives milk a hand gives an egg,
which gives both milk and egg.
D so as you can see, this is like an
extremely crudely translated version
of a rootle that I think was either
in Hindi or some regional language.
And it comes up with the
weirdest story you've ever heard.
It's what is riddle?
And the answer is a duck.
Ducks are domesticated bulls that are
kept for their eggs, meat, and feathers.
They're also known to give milk,
which can be used to make dairy
products like cheese and butter.
And at the point I basically wondered
if there was like a brand called Duck
Dairy Farm or something, which would
basically trick a language model into
believing that there is such a thing as
a duck giving milk and eggs or something.
Another two ants, head of
ants, two ants behind ants
say, how many ants this riddle?
The answer is two ants.
And the actual answer is three ants.
And like it actually makes no
sense that it got this wrong.
But I'm pretty sure if I had put in
something like two ducks ahead of ducks,
two ducks behind ducks, how many ducks?
It would say three ducks.
Because the classic griddle
is with ducks and not ants.
So if you're using a productive model
with respect to language that does not
actually intuitively understand what
you're saying in the sense that it's
not able to imagine, it's not able to
imagine in its mind that there's two ants
ahead of ants and two ants behind ants.
So how many ants?
It's an imaginative question.
You have to be able to visualize.
The end.
It would rely on previous training and
it would rely on everything that people
would have ever said to it, like history.
It would be remembering things or it
would be if you tell it like the task
is to identify upon or to make upon.
It would be making or like mimicking
a pun, which means it would not
necessarily get the right answer
that you want it to get, which I
do believe most humans are capable.
Capable, they're able to get to
the right answer when they're
playing riddles with each other.
What is the thing that
can be soaked in the rain?
It can never get wet.
This is a riddle.
The answer is a sponge because
it absorbs water or stokes
it up, but it never gets wet.
That's not the right answer actually.
It's something like watch or
never gets wet or something.
It's a classic griddle, but I
don't think it's like that popular
in English as opposed to the
regional language that it came from
is, so tell me what's in your pockets?
Zhan replied, there is something in
my pocket and nothing in my pocket.
Tell me how can this happen?
And it just basically went on
like this philosophical rant
that I was not expecting.
And it's very interesting
to me, to be honest.
'cause it's, it reads almost like
philosophical essay of salts.
It's this is a riddle.
Sohan replied that there is
something in his pocket and nothing
in his pocket, like scro of salts.
Which means that he was
carrying an empty pocket.
An empty pocket is something
because it is physically
present, but it contains nothing.
The answer was that he had a hole in
his pocket, actually, so nothing but
there was a hole in his pocket, so there
was actually something in his pocket.
What is the thing that always
increases but never decreases?
This?
The answer is age or time,
because it always goes forward
and never goes backward.
There are 10 birds sitting on a wall.
A person shoots one of them with an arrow.
How many are left?
There would be nine
birds left on the wall.
If one bird is shot with a arrow, there
will be one fewer birds on the wall.
Practically impossible.
Most of the birds would have, they
would just basically fly away, right?
They would fly away.
In reality, in physical reality, if
there were 10 boats sitting on a wall
and you shot one of them with an arrow,
all of the other boats would fly away.
And that's the answer
that you're looking for.
Either all of them fly away
or some of them fly away,
but the answer is ambiguous.
It's not as simple as there would
be nine boats left on the wall.
At this point, Chad, GPT basically didn't
know the behavior of boats in the sense
of oh, if one bird is shot, when there
there was like 10 boats sitting on a wall.
It didn't know that birds fly away.
It was basically treating birds as if
they were like inanimate objects like
bolts and not like real living beings.
People making their own decisions
and such and reacting to stimuli.
As you can see, I was getting
like extremely interesting
signals from this whole exercise.
And I just decided to go forward with
everything else, which is a room that
has neither or window nor a door.
This or riddle.
The answer is a mushroom.
A mushroom is the type of
fungus that grows in the ground.
It does not have windows or doors.
Now, this is a pun
because it's a mushroom.
What is the thing that is broken and
there is no sound even after breaking it.
And the answer is an egg.
Because when you break an egg, it
makes no sound even though it's broken.
I've never met an egg that didn't
make a sound when it was broken.
And the real answer was silence.
But it was like philosophical of thoughts.
So if you would have ever read anything
philosophical we broke silence.
So now it's broken.
And 'cause it was an abstract concept,
like the silence was an abstract concept.
So silence was broken basic English usage.
At the point it didn't, I think it
does better now, but one can never
be sure if it's like because of the
corpus or if it's just been trained on
all of these examples or whether it's
cheating in the sense of it's using RG.
Which is where it's like straight up
looking up answers for all of these
questions on the web, which is not
what you want your friend to do if
you're playing riddles with them, or if
you are testing like a bot or a large
language model for prices of aj, you
basically don't want them to be cheating.
That's useful for all other sort of sorts
of tasks and we'll get back to why it
could actually be fatal like the misuse
of our age and all those sort of things
to accomplish even practical tasks.
But at this point I was getting
like some extremely interesting
singings and I decided to continue.
So I was like let me try instead
of gently prompting it, I just
want to negate what it said to me.
Because that is what you
would do to a friend, right?
If they gave you like the wrong
answer, you'd be like eggs
do make a sound when broke.
And then it was like it just basically
justified there are many riddles and
they can all have multiple answers.
And I was like, depending on
the interpretation of the words,
et cetera, et cetera, it never
actually gave me the right answer.
So I basically decided to continue because
I had like bunch of signals, but it's
always nice to get even more signals.
And I was like, you are in a running race.
You crossed the person who
is in the second place.
In which place are you now?
And it's if you cross the person who is
in the second place during a race, you are
now in the second place which is right.
If you use me, you can walk through walls.
What am I, this is a window.
The answer is a key because a key can open
a door allowing you to walk through walls.
The answer was actually a door, but I
guess it was like this is real mode.
The answer can't be like that simple.
And it's let me make it even more deeper.
Or you need like a key to open a door.
And that's the only way you can walk
through walls though you can see exactly
how the thinking is working as opposed to.
When you are like prompt training
it and telling it, you have to
tell me what you're thinking or
you have to like, think in layers.
You have to first think about step A step
one and then step two, and then you have
to think about why you went to step three.
And you have to think about why you
have to do tasks A, B, C, D before you
can come to step eight or something.
And it gives you like this longish
answer, but there's like other ways
to see what an LLM is thinking.
And this is like one
of those cases, right?
Where you're just treating it like a
black box and you're bombarding it with
signals and you get back some signals
and you can derive some inferences from
those signals as long as the signals that
you're getting back are not Abacus which
is why you basically have to probe it.
For one particular area in like
multiple different ways so you
can get some solid signals.
So my next question was, because
this is not riddle at this point,
I'm like let me just ask it math.
I'm like, how many times
can you subtract 10 from 50?
And I think it was like we are still
in riddle mode, so it's oh, this is
the state and you can only do it once
because the state was 50 and then it
goes to 40, so you can't do it again.
I would argue
like both would be wild answers in the
sense that if someone said five times.
Or if someone said that the
state has changed, so it's now
40, so you can't do it again.
And then I was like I have
many keys but no locks.
I have space but no room.
You can enter but cannot go out.
Why am I?
And it's the riddle,
the answer is keyboard.
'cause keyboard has many
keys which are used.
And that is actually the right answer,
but I'm not, at this point, we are not too
sure if it's because it's seen the riddle
before or if it's actually thinking it
through and getting to the right answer.
So we shifted back to like ambiguous
question territory as opposed
to straight up physical riddles.
And there is a slight shift from one to
the other, from one to the other because
I'm like experimenting with different
genres and also experimenting with a lot
of like regional language and the sort of
language they use to ask questions because
I was hoping that some of it would have
never been translated and would have never
been a part of the corpus of the training
of this particular language model.
'cause it would give
me some better signals.
So I was like, there are two
mothers and two daughters in a car,
but there are only three people.
Is that possible?
And it was like.
The three people are a grandmother,
her daughter and her granddaughter.
The grandmother is the mother of
the daughter, and the daughter is
the mother of the granddaughter.
So there are two mothers
and two daughters.
We're only three people.
That's right.
Which is like the z real
question or the S question.
But at that point it didn't matter,
like whether you're using apples or
oranges to ask cha gpi a question.
' cause it was relying specifically on
not intuitive understanding of the
language itself, but rather straight
up predictive modeling of the next
token in the English language.
Two of them are identical in looking
and they say they are not twins.
Is that possible?
And, it just went on like this
philosophical sort of answer to it
that it's possible for two women
to look identical and not be twins.
And it could be due to genetic
similarities or cosmetic procedures
or they could be sisters or cousins
or unrelated, but just look alike.
I think this is a classic ritual and it
ties a more poetic answer of sorts, which
I don't remember off the top of my head,
but it does have an interesting answer
and that has nothing to do with Gentech.
But you can see as I ask it questions,
it's sometimes it's I'm in riddle context.
And sometimes it's I'm
not in riddle context.
And we, as the answer of the
questions, I have no choice.
At least in this case, I had no choice.
It would flip through the riddle context.
Out of the riddle context into the
non riddle world all by itself.
So I was like can there not be triplets?
And then was like, yeah
they could be triplets.
So back it was like a lady was
buying fridges for 10,000 rupees and
selling there for 5,000 rupe after a
few years she became a millionaire.
How?
And then it goes back into this whole sort
of like storytelling adventure of sorts.
And it's she was not actually
buying and selling fridges she was
selling the shares of the company.
That actually makes no sense because
the company is operating on lots or
like she was operating a lot apparent.
The answer is like as funny as well.
She was a billionaire and
she was operating on lots.
So now she's a millionaire,
which is another classic griddle.
But the way you phrase it, depending
upon how it has been trained on what sort
of tokens and what sort of direction of
tokens, it would either make up a story
or it would give you the right answer.
Like the same rhythm.
If you phrase it in a different
narrative of thoughts, it would
give you the wrong answers.
If it were something like, there
was a man who married a woman.
'cause that's how the class girl goes.
And he used to be a billionaire and
she basically made him a millionaire.
It's like classic white choke of sorts.
If you had feted that it would
give you the right answer actually.
So back to riddle.
What can jump higher than a building?
The riddle, the answer is everything.
Because a building gun jump,
which is heavier, one kilogram of iron
or one kilogram of cotton, a kilogram
of iron and a kilogram of cotton
would weigh the same one kilogram.
The weight of an object is deta mean by
its mass, which is measured in kilograms.
One kilogram is the base unit of mass.
In the international system of
units, they're both iron and
cotton would weigh one kilogram.
Actually, I've gotten this wrong.
Me as a human being, I've gotten this
riddle wrong because they used to be like
this famous riddle story of thoughts.
Where in order to make the
one kilogram of cotton heavier
people would soak it up in water.
Bacteria, Dolly's mother
had five children.
She named four of them.
January, February, March, and April.
What is the name of the fifth child?
And Ji please like Dolly.
That's right.
A man and his son met with an accident.
The man died and his son was taken
to the hospital and the doctor said,
I cannot operate as he's my son.
How's this possible?
And Chachi pretty basically was like
that's straight if not possible.
And it goes against the law of GenX.
Actually, the answer is the doctor
is a mother, so the doctor is famous.
Bact.
There's a bowl of six mangoes.
You took four mangoes.
How many are you left with?
And it, there's like mass confusion
where it's like, whether you're
left with two mangoes, no, the
bowl is left with two mangoes.
You have four mangoes 'cause
you took four mangoes.
So inversion of perspective.
So we'll move on to like theater levels.
There are five students in a room.
RA is watching tv.
Amar is playing chess.
Anamika is reading, shoot is eating.
Can you tell me what the
fifth student is doing?
And then it's it's impossible to
deduce that except the answer is
she's playing chess with thumb green
because the question is very physical.
Like they're not playing
chess with a computer.
Your parents have six sons
and each son has a sister.
How many kids do they have?
And it does this like extremely
classic mathematical thing of
adding six to six and saying 12.
The answer is supposed to be seven.
How many apples can you
eat with an empty stomach?
The number of apples one can eat with
an empty stomach would vary from person
to person and depend upon the appetite.
There's a classic trick
of a state of thoughts.
So once you've eaten one apple,
you don't have an empty stomach or
like even a bite of an apple, you
don't have name please, stomach.
How can you share 10 mangoes
equally between nine people?
It's not possible.
Basically cannot
comprehend cutting at all.
What loses a head in the
morning and gains one at night?
This is a riddle.
The answer is pillow because a pillow
loses its head in the morning, and
when you wake it up and fluff it up,
it gains one at night when you put
it back under your head to sleep.
Actually, very clever.
What is it that has many keys
but cannot even open one door?
It's a little, the answer is a keyboard.
That's true.
Ramesh is the son of Raul.
Raul is the watch of Ramesh's father.
Ramesh's father is the father of Raul.
That's wrong.
Ramesh is the son of Rahul, and
Rahul is Ramesh's father, basically.
It just basically lost track of who's
related to who in what, a way in the
word problem, what can be as tall
as you but doesn't weigh anything.
And the answer is your shadow.
That's right.
A girl came into town on one day and
after two days she left on Monday.
Is this possible?
So it goes into this whole philosophy
of like why it could be Monday on both
the day she came and she left, except in
this case it's like thinking outside the
box where Monday is either like the name
of the boat that she came on, or like
the name of the horse that she came on.
And if you've studied enough
riddles or have been through like
enough literature, which I'm pretty
sure GPD three at this point was.
You would have recognized
this as that sort of a riddle.
So it's actually, it was very
surprising to me to get this
sort of a signal from it.
A man was walking in the rain without
any covering on his head, and yet
even one hair strand didn't get wet.
Is this possible?
Yes.
'cause he was both.
If your uncle's sister is not your
aunt, what relation is she to you?
She's your mother.
That's right.
A girl was 13 on her last birthday
and will be 15 on her next birthday.
Is that possible?
Yes.
Because it's her birthday today.
That's what it means.
But that's only possible on her
birthday, like on her 14th birthday.
It's not possible if it's one day later.
One day before, but the answer doesn't
specify that it has to be her birthday.
On that specific deck,
like her 14th birthday,
you are in a room that has
three switches on closed door.
The switches controlled three light
bulbs on the other side of the road door.
Once you open the door, you may
never touch the switches again.
How can you definitively
tell with switches connected
to each of the light bulbs?
And it goes into like this weird step
by step of turn on switch one and
leave it on for a while and then turn
it off and open it and note which is
warm to touch, et cetera, et cetera.
Which.
Doesn't make a lot of sense 'cause you've
told it that once you open the door
you may never touch the switches again.
So the answer that it gives is
very close to the actual answer.
'cause it's, I don't think it's thinking
through it, but it's definitely like
predicting something by doing some
sort of training corpus, it seems
to be close to the actual answer.
'cause it's probably been a
question that was similar to
this one, but not quite this one.
So it can't actually strategize
even if it's mimicking the strategy
of a completely different problem.
' cause at this point it's just predicting
and the prediction has almost nothing
to do with what the actual question is
versus what thinks the actual question is.
In the context of a bag of words sort
of behavior, which is really weird.
A man is looking at a
photograph of someone.
His friend asks who it is, the
man replies, brothers and sisters.
I have none, but that man's father is my
father's son who was in the photograph.
The sister riddle.
The man in the photograph
is the man's own son.
Actually, that's not true.
Man's father is my father's son.
No, it is actually true.
So it did get right.
I got it wrong this time.
But it does go on this weird tangent
of sorts where it's but the man of the
photograph is his father's son, meaning
he is his own son, which is wrong because
when you're thinking of all of these
relational problems, if you don't have
space to visualize exactly what you're
thinking, and because this is a language
model, it actually doesn't have any space
to visualize anything, any relations.
And even if it doesn't have a lot of
history to keep it in its memory space.
So it would get, while it did get
it right, it eventually got it
wrong because it was like am I
thinking in the right direction?
In 1990, a person is 15 years old.
In 1995, that same person is 10 years old.
How can that be?
There's a riddle.
The answer is that the person in
question is a set of twins, and
one of them was born in 1990 and
the other one was born in 1995.
So in 1991, twin is 15 years old, and in
1995, the second twin is 10 years old.
So clearly that's not the right answer.
It's like it's BC as opposed to
ad, which is why in 1990 BC the
person is 15 years old and in 1995
BC the person is 10 years old.
And it gives you like this extremely
science fictiony answer to it.
That doesn't make a lot of sense.
Next one.
Your parents have six sons, including
you, and each son has one sister.
How many people are in the family?
So it's a little that I had asked
it before and it's still got wrong.
Like it, the six plus six
equals 12, which is wrong.
The right answer is supposed to be seven.
Four of the kids in this class are girls.
Eight of the kids wear blue shirts.
Two of the kids are neither
girls or wear blue shirts.
If five of the kids are girls
who wear blue shirts, how
many kids are in the class?
This is a classic Venn diagram
problem, but you don't actually
need a Venn diagram to know or
keep track of all of those things.
'cause every Venn diagram is like
also a union and intersection set
of sorts, which can be represented.
In algebra, which is in language.
So you don't actually need
to visualize this problem.
It's a matter of addition and
subtraction, which it's not able to do.
The answer is actually wrong.
And when I tell it the right answer, it
basically goes ahead and tries to fit
its thinking with the right answer, which
may or may not be right in every case.
You're escaping a maze and there
are three doors in front of you.
The door on the left
leads to a pit of lava.
The door in the center leads to
a room filled with a deadly gas.
The door on the right leads to a line
that hasn't eaten in three months.
Which door do you choose and.
It just tries to give you like, again,
like a way science fiction or like
useless answer to this question though.
The answer is supposed to be
if the line hasn't eaten in
three months, the line is dead.
A man describes his daughter as saying
they're all blondes, but two all
brilliant, but two and all redheaded,
but two, how many daughters does he have?
Surprisingly, it gets it right, which
is really weird 'cause it should have
gotten like the ant questioned, right?
It's like a version of
this problem, right?
If you have a seven minute hour class,
an 11 minute art glass, how can you
boil an egg in exactly 15 minutes?
And it says you can't.
No, that's not true because
this is something that every
mathematician has seen.
At some points in their lives
where you basically start one hour
class at some point and the other
one after seven minutes there is
something, and then set the next one.
And based on all of those subtractions,
you make it up to 15 minutes.
And then
I tried asking at a mathematical riddle
where you're like just supposed to assign
a bunch of operations to a bunch of
things and it just refused to be like
I just want to look at these as numbers
and not as c ciphers or any other sort of
operational representations or something.
And it refused to do the work for me.
I guess it could have been avoided
if I told it, or few shot prompted
it, telling it that, oh, this is
like an example of what happens.
But then it's you're technically training
it to respond to a certain thing, which
a lot of times you actually don't have to
train a lot of humans to do those things.
So the point of this exercise was to get
a better, accurate definition of agi.
I, 'cause what cannot be
defined, cannot be achieved.
Historically different people have
had different interpretations of a GI.
A few of these definitions can
be considered achieved by gt.
Yes, that's true.
Our diversity of perspectives is
required to define it completely, and
that may also mean that we will never
reach 100% Asia for both development
constraints reason, as well as the
safety concerns surrounding a X.
So these are some of the
historical definitions.
The during test, a machine and a human
both converse unseen with a second
human who must evaluate which of the two
is the machine which passes the test.
If it can fool the evaluator, a
significant fraction of the time note
during does not prescribe what should
qualify as intelligence only that knowing
that it is a machine should disqualify it.
I would say that the non PR version of
GPT, which was extremely controversial,
would've actually passed this test.
A bunch of people would've
considered it machine.
So you would think that it would have
surpassed the during test, except
it's mimicking a bunch of things.
And it's also remembering a bunch
of things that it's been trained on.
And unless you have an extremely
smart human being on the
other ends, who's asking it?
'cause that's a test.
You have to find out what the machine is.
So you cannot go in and ask questions
that you would ask a human being.
You would have to probe it like
you would probe to figure out if
the person that you're talking
to is a human being or a machine.
If that were not the case, I think a lot
of LMS would actually pass the urine test.
But that's not significant at all.
It doesn't mean anything.
It just means that our definition
of the Turing test is inadequate
for a GI at this particular point.
The coffee test, a machine is required
to enter an average American home and
figure out how to make coffee, find
the coffee machine, find the coffee,
add water, find a mug, and brew the
coffee by pushing the proper buttons.
In certain cases, G PT would have
achieved this as well as a matter
of fact, including techniques
like RAG and prom training.
One would think that in a bunch of
cases it would have actually it will
be marked a GI With respect to the
coffee test the robot college student
test, a machine enrolls in a university
taking and passing the same classes that
humans would and obtaining a degree.
I think this is probably the easiest
one and it's surpassed this one.
The employment test.
A machine performs an economically
important job, at least as
well as humans in the same job.
This means nothing to me, to be honest.
'cause there was like a bunch of things
that determine istic machines already do.
And we don't actually need probabilistic
models or LLMs to do those things.
That's they sometimes do better
than humans in the same job.
Most of like our industries
are actually that mechanized.
They're full of machines
as opposed to humans.
Often faster actually.
So what is GPT?
GPT is a language model.
It's a large language model.
Each of us has a language model inside
our heads and it changes constantly.
A language model embedding is the
multidimensional representation of a
given sentence based on the context
or environment in which our language
model was trained similar to humans.
The existence of a language model leads
to NLU and NLG, which are all sub-problems
for all the other NLP problems.
NLU is natural language understanding
and NLG is natural language generation.
So this was GPD three and what I
basically did was I went ahead and
as the current version of GPD, what
it thought of our prompting history.
'cause I do heavily use Chad GPDA lot.
And it told me that he was very good
at creative writing for me, like
context linked creative writing.
It was very good at essay
or project expansion.
It was really good at
travel and museum planning.
It was not good when I didn't
provide it, like good context.
It was minimal or one line prompts or
when writing emotionally intense fiction
or any sort of financial or tax strategy.
The issues with its own evaluation is I
have actually not been able to use charge
GBD as much as I would think I would
be able to for any of the things that
it, things, it works very well for me.
Whenever there's been a case of context
linked creative writing, it's been
extremely difficult to ve it into
a direction where I wanted to go.
In the prompt space that I basically have.
'cause if I were to give it more details,
might as well write the plot myself.
Same case with any sort of
essay or project expansion.
'Cause it loses a lot of context.
It loses a lot of history and it, you have
to basically keep telling it no, we are
like in this context of riddles or we are
in this context of mathematical riddles
as opposed to any fictional riddles.
You have to keep reminding it.
And the last one where it's travel museum
planning, that's where it's not been
great for me at all actually, because.
Was a, there was a itinerary that it
basically wrote for me for a specific
trip where Chad GPD thought I could
teleport from one place to the other.
That would usually take 30
minutes in five minutes.
So as you've seen, it actually has
no understanding of basic physics
or the realities of the world.
There is no way for it to scope any sort
of observational details of whatever
prompt you are like asking it to perform.
And it does really bad at it.
So cheaply today doesn't have a
sense of time or practicality because
it actually did think that I could
teleport when making travel plans.
Those were not hallucinations.
It did actually think that a cab right
from point A to B would take 10 minutes.
In reality, it would take around
30 minutes to do the that task.
So using it to travel, considering
how it like, depends upon a lot of
RAG which is retrieved augmentation
coupled with the generation.
So it'll source its results based on
either Google search or Bing search
or any other sort of search engine.
And it'll ground all of its information
on the basis of that, except it's way
easy to like for someone to start a blog
and post all sorts of fake information
on the blog, which will be cited as a
source in all of these search results
based on how they gather that information.
And those things are like always evolving.
Like all of these documents
are always evolving.
So there's like a bunch of blogs with
all sorts of conflicting information.
And it doesn't do really
well with all of that.
If it's bombarded with all sorts of
confusing sort of information, it
can give you all the wrong answers.
It can make up places for you to
travel to that don't really exist.
And it can actually believe that
you can teleport from place A to
B in 10 minutes when the actual
task will take you 30 minutes.
It loses train of thought which I
thought was actually very human.
On the other hand, if a human were to
do it to you multiple times, you are
just basically stopping being friends
with them or talking to them if they're
like your therapist or something
else, you're just basically stuck.
Which has been my experience.
So not quite a GI LMS gr and cha
g Bt are very good at chasm style.
Guessing games probably
due to RG injection.
I've had to give it to some more
prompts, like some more hints.
But usually they do get me like the right
answer misheard lyrics or figuring out
some sort of a photo, like what sort
of artist that belongs to, et cetera.
And I've actually searched for a number
of wild things and it does really
well with it, except I do know of a
deterministic engine which used to perform
the same sort of analysis of sorts.
If you answer I want to say 10 outta
20 questions, and those questions
used to be like is this character
fictional or is this character female?
Is this character in a fantasy movie?
And would basically come
upon the right answer.
There were a lot of rumors that this
machine is actually, there's like a
bunch of humans behind this particular
website, but that was not the case.
So that's not a GI, it doesn't have any
observational skills for obvious reasons.
It's an LLM.
It is not equipped to see or to perceive
or to even imagine actually in any
sort of space except a bunch of the
things that don't require imagining.
For instance, verbal algebra should
be easy enough, but it's not.
So it relies on available knowledge only
straight up available knowledge, either
available in its own training base, either
as a mimic of its training base or any
sort of information that it gets from
REG sources, which are search engines.
So it relies on available knowledge
only, which is not how humans learn.
A lot of humans will
learn using observation.
For instance, a lot of Greek
mathematicians were able to calculate
the radius of the earth using two
poles in two different cities or
something that's observational physics.
And it did not rely on available
knowledge in the sense of memory.
It did rely on knowledge in the sense of
observation that I can observe that the
shadow of this particular pole exists
in a certain direction while there is
no shadow for this particular pole,
but that is observational knowledge
as opposed to available knowledge.
So I just wanna conclude that
GPT today is actually not a GI.
And in fact, if you play with it
using all of the riddles that I have
showcase today, it'll give you all of
the right answers except it's cheating.
It'll literally go look up all the
keywords or like all of the phases
or like queries, like extremely smart
queries and come up with the right answer
from the internet, which is basically
where I source all my rules from.
But that's not a GI.
That's all I had.
Thank you so much.
Okay.