Hello everyone.
I'm pre Patil from Equinix.
I build multi-cloud infrastructure
and interconnection for
high performance AI needs.
Thank you for joining me to
explore my talk for reactive
prompts to autonomous agents, LLMs
for multi-cloud infrastructure.
Over this past year, I have spent a lot
of time on exploring the next stage of
cloud deployment in the world of ai.
We have seen Terraform and cross.
Planes facilitate cloud deployment
and maintain the desired state
using reconciliation loop.
That worked well for many years, but now
is the time to advance it even further.
In this talk, we will see how large
language models LLMs are exploring
and evolving and not just answering
our questions to actively managing
complex cloud infrastructures.
This shift from manually reactive prompts
to autonomous agent behavior is poised
to revolutionize cloud infrastructure.
Gartner has said the agentic
AI is a top trend of 2025.
We don't need Gartner to say that.
We all know that by now.
In this talk, we'll talk about how
multicloud can leverage agent tech ai,
talking about AWS Azure GCP even on-prem.
A full hybrid mix, if you will.
We will discuss on how LLM can move
beyond merely splitting the config
snippets to actually orchestrating the
tasks across multi-cloud, all while
balancing the exciting opportunities
with very real risks, the hallucinations,
misconfigurations, and the cost.
Most enterprises run at least two
public clouds plus co-location on-prem.
Facilitated by S like Equinix.
They all have different IMS
network models, APIs and billing.
Billing knobs.
The result is a config sprawl, policy
divergence and reconciliation drift.
Old fix was write a glue script or a
terraform and have PR reviews at scale.
The glue on the Terraforms and the cross
planes became second platform to maintain.
Sometimes if people don't maintain
the GitHubs model, then we would end
up having them as tribal knowledges.
What we want instead is a continuous
awareness of state across the providers.
Policy driven orchestration and autonomic
reconciliation that respects the change.
Window approvals and budget.
Think treating cloud boundaries like
availability zones with explicit
control, our cost, and other risks.
And what most teams
today use LMS reactive.
Ask cha g pity for a Terraform script.
Tell me how to connect
a LB to my target group.
And the VPCs, if it does generate
good scripts, no doubt about that.
But you end up with a lot of on off
scripts without full validation and with
full confidence, we don't docs anymore.
Neither does cha G PT or any
LMS would just end up giving us
information that it best knows it.
So for one good.
And is we wrote a chat assistant and
asked to write a clean VPC module.
And it did in minutes, but all it did
was apart from building a VPC module,
it also had a place where it would
open up all the traffic and all that
because we forgot to mention a bion host
restriction, nice code, wrong outcome.
The lesson without.
Context and checks, you are accelerating
both right and wrong changes.
So what should be the vision of having
an autonomous agent of this sort?
It should have continuous awareness.
Take snapshots of multi-cloud
states, drifts and quotas.
It should have proactive de
detections for misconfigurations,
security vulnerabilities, cost
anomalies, and a autonomous.
Resolution, propose and execute
fixes with approvals and rollbacks.
Think of this agent as a junior, SRE
with excellent documentation recall
wrapped under strict guardrails.
It suggests and even allowed to
execute and then explains what it did.
The core of this architecture is Ritual
Augmented Generation, also known as rag.
The difference here with RAG is between
confident fiction and grounded action.
The retrievals will be that of.
Current desired state.
Think terraform Terraform
states, terraform documentations
scripts cloud formation.
It'll will also will look into
actual states through cloud APIs.
It'll look into change histories,
think logs, prs, run books
policies like security policies,
FinTech policies provider docs.
Not only a p aspects,
but also best practices.
Amazon always provides well architected
writeups and they are very resourceful
model plans With this in context and not
just the blank state example can think
of before touching a security group, the
agent reduce the intent port for IAC.
Our infrastructure as code pulls
all the current rules from AWS that
already in is presenting your infras
policies that you have set up ahead of
time telling for bidding, opening all
the poor for admin VPCs for example,
and any change tickets over the time.
The output of this is a proposed diff.
Plus the rationale on why
we are doing certain things.
The next piece of the architecture
is where you get your confidence
with the verification pipeline.
It.
Start off with syntax validation.
Yamo, JSO, Terraform.
Do the linting, do the formatting,
then is the semantic analysis.
Logically thinking what it
is doing is right or wrong.
Think of reasoning models here.
Then the guard rails for all your
policy, compliances, budgets,
tax encryption, geo residency.
GDPR kind of compliances whatnot, right?
And then finally, your dry run
testing, Terraform Plan cube
cut diff your smoke test on your
staging environment, et cetera.
I also recommend.
Doing a dual model verification
where the second model of a rules
engine would critique the plan,
ask why is it doing a certain way?
Is it required?
What can go wrong?
Think of red teaming the real
value of these autonomous agents.
It's not just during the deployment,
but between the deployments.
The agents will continuously
monitor across the clouds for
any changes like I am Devs.
Route table changes health of your
load, balance, quotas pricing.
It detects the drift automatically
and tries to correct it.
Alert with context.
Which is more significant than
we all think, and once it.
Identifies any of these changes, it then
runs its reconciliation using, either
by opening a PR and having somebody
approve it, or if it is pre-approved,
it could just proceed with deployment.
A practical example, right?
This is anecdotal happened to me.
One of the members who had access
to the, to an AWS account made
modifications to a security group.
Now we all in the team had to go all over
the place, try to see what happened, when
things were not working without clarity on
where to reach and what to do to fix this.
If the agent and autonomous agent was
there, it already has complete context
of the desired state and it can run
its reconciliation rule and propose
the solution and also propose what
went wrong on a certain scenarios.
While all of this sounds great,
there are problems starting with
hallucinated configurations.
We have seen that LMS as we know it today.
Can end up hallucinating and getting
to the same rabbit hole of trying to
solve a problem that doesn't even exist.
Then security exposure, we might end
up over giving overprivileged to agent
and that can cause a huge problem.
Cost escalations of if there is no.
Proper guardrails, we might end up
overspending on certain resources we
might even end up overspending on.
Additional cost medication
is very straightforward.
Always validate your resources and
deployments unit tests and automated
tests to verify that agents are
behaving as they're expected.
Most importantly, least, and on
demand privileges always provide
privilege only to the resources
that the agent needs at the time.
It needs then cost control, not
just for the cloud resources, but
also for the agent's inference.
But trust doesn't come automatically.
Trust comes with transparency,
reversibility, and learning.
We need to log all the LLMs
decisions and reasoning.
Bring human in the loop.
Have a tiered approval time
boxed change windows so that you
are in control of the change.
Not in the middle of the night or
at 2:00 AM have rollback mechanism.
Every agent action must map to a version
artifact for instant rollbacks, and
then the continuous learning to fine
tune your agents meeting your needs.
Based on all the learnings that
you have had and the agents
have had based on all the logs.
While this framework is very
encouraging and exciting, it can also
be very overwhelming in terms of its
implementation in your environment.
So I recommend to start off simple,
start with reactive announcement.
When I say that, think about
keeping your current flow as it is.
Just add retrievals and validation
around LLM generated artifacts.
Next stage is integrate, rag rag can
start off with your documentation,
your infrastructure as code, some
run books some well architected or
best practices from the providers.
Then start off with continuous monitoring.
Have your agents start detecting
drifts and reporting them.
And the final stage when all the
confidence is in place, start
with deployment and autonomous
actions with human in the loop and
with the change window in mind.
So the key takeaways here is to use
AI like it was always meant to be,
not just for copy pasting code, but to
leverage its reasoning and its knowledge.
Start off very simple.
Take small steps and have
an incremental adoption.
Build a robust architecture around
rag and multi-stage verification.
Know your risks and manage your risks.
With that, I want to thank Con 42.