By the end of today's session, hopefully
you'll have a working understanding
of how AI is changing the hiring
landscape, particularly in technology.
And then we'll learn some techniques to
battle hard and people centric processes
such as talent acquisition using AI.
Now just understand, I chose
talent acquisition because of this
personal mission that I was on, but
it could also be useful for other
human centered processes as well.
Alright, so today's agenda is going
to look a little bit like this.
First, I'm going to start
with some anchoring bias.
I'm going to talk about the
circumstances that kind of led
me to take on this experiment.
And then we're going to talk about my
personal mission a little bit here.
Because if you're going to risk it all,
you might as well make it personal.
We'll talk about the
process that was followed.
Now, because of the magnitude of research
that was required for this exercise,
we're only going to cover a couple data
points associated with this experiment.
And then finally, we'll
talk about the outcomes.
Alright, so first of all, I need
to anchor you guys in some bias.
You guys need some context,
because this wasn't just
initiated out of nowhere, right?
There was a reason why
I started this process.
So we're gonna start with a little
bit about me, and I know it's a
little cliche, but it's important
to understand my context and the
things that I want to solve for and
how it relates to this exercise.
So my name is Daniel Preece.
I'm an engineering manager
of digital experience teams
for a super regional bank.
Now, I'm an engineer first with
20 plus years of experience
across various industries, ranging
from bare metal computer chips
to cloud native architecture.
And everything in between.
I'm currently on a personal
mission to improve the developer
experience for the teams that I
oversee, and I love growing others.
I like to watch the light bulb turn
on as people learn new skills and help
people through their soft skills and
as they navigate their career journey.
So when I started this experiment,
there was a hiring climate
that predicated all of it.
I was hired at my current
organization in 2020, in July 2020.
Now, prior to that, there was this
thing going on, in the 2019 into
2020 called the great resignation.
And this is where people decided
that they wanted to do something
about their quality of life.
A lot more people wanted
to work from home.
They wanted to be with their families.
They were tired of commuting in every day.
Many people quit their careers.
They were experiencing burnout
and decided, you know what?
It's time to move on.
To something else, and we
can see that in the data.
when we look at February,
2019 is February 2020.
There was a 47 percent reduction of
applications across all industries.
Now, some of you may think, we also had
this thing called the coven 19 pandemic.
Not sure if you heard of it.
actually.
When the United States shut
down that was March of 2020.
So this is a year prior to
any of this even occurring.
We're starting to see a significant
reduction in the number of applicants
and people in the job market because
they're looking for something
more in that quality of life.
So the talent pool itself
is electively decreasing.
Now, while that's going on, while
the talent pool is electively
decreasing, we also have big
tech going on a hiring spree.
And we're also seeing that in the data.
Now, first, I want to acknowledge here
that this data covers a period from 2019
through 2022, that 20 to 19 to 2020 period
is that period of the great resignation.
And then beyond that is when we
get into the COVID 19 years, right?
We're all separating, social
distancing together and big tech
is actively hiring like crazy.
The other piece of data I want to
acknowledge here just because of
its bias a little bit is Amazon.
They are part of the supply chain
and the COVID 19 pandemic, right?
They are part of the
improvement of the supply chain.
And so they did ramp up
significantly in that process.
But the rest of big tech like
Microsoft, Apple, Alphabet, they
grew by thousands, if not tens of
thousands from 2019 through 2022.
This is very frustrating because, again,
we have this great resignation going on,
people are electively not wanting to work
anymore, and also Big Tech is drinking
our milkshake, because at the end of
the day, the talent pool is only so big.
Pulling in talent from the same
talent pool around the globe and
prior to that, there was a big push
for digitization and recruitment as
a solution for talent acquisition.
so as part of, the way that talent
acquisition is working, they want
to move from very manual toil based
processes into automation so that it can.
Focus on better set of
behaviors and better outcomes.
So what does that mean?
What does the digitization
of talent acquisition mean?
we really want to automate those data
heavy tasks that are highly repetitive.
In the SRE world, this would be analogous
to things that we would call toil, right?
So we want to automate
those processes away.
They're also a little error prone.
we also want to take things like resume
screening, any of the scheduling.
So if you've ever done any scheduling,
we select your own schedule with
Talent acquisition, or maybe an
HR representative or a conference
speaker or whatnot, they're
scheduling tools that are out there.
Technology screening right to
understand as a person understand
a particular technology set, or
does a resume actually satisfy a
particular technology needs, chat
box, which are used for relationships.
And this is prior to generative AI.
When we were working more with
natural language processing,
just a small segment of.
What we now use as part of generative
AI and RPA is a robotic process
automation to manage those leads.
Now, all this automation was really
there with this promise that it
would free up the recruiter's time
for more strategic tasks, right?
building out your talent network,
as well as building those
relationships with the candidates.
All right, so let's talk a little
bit about a hiring process, right?
Because we now understand,
we've got this great resignation
going on, talent pool shrinking.
We've got big tech drinking our milkshake.
We've got a lot of
automation in the process.
But what is the process?
for most organizations,
it looks like this.
We have talent acquisition and HR deciding
that they're going to have a strategy.
They're going to do either open up
roles as needed, or there's going
to be some sort of recruitment
effort to build a talent pool.
They might reach out to career
fairs or job fairs, right?
They really want to build up a network
where people can source candidates.
It may also include external sourcers
as well, whose job is just to collect
these networks for you, for these
organizations and set HR up for
success in terms of their hirings.
Then we may take a candidate through
a technical interview, right?
Which is like a technical screen.
if you're in technology, you've
gone through this is where you're
going to ask them simple questions.
They make it harder and harder
over time, but they're really
trying to understand what your
tech technical acumen looks like.
It's really hard to do in
a short period of time.
So it tends to be pretty quick
though, like 30 minutes to
an hour at most, to get, to
understand your technical literacy.
And then to offset that a little bit, what
you can do in practice, more organizations
are starting to use automated tests.
Now this is a thing that I
had a personal gripe with.
The automated testing thing is
part of my personal mission.
Because while they're useful
in most contexts, in some
contexts they can be used poorly.
And so I had some concerns, so
I really wanted to address that.
Then there's also a
manager meet and greet.
And this might not be somebody who's
directly invested in the process.
Maybe a senior, more senior person
or a person outside the process.
They're really just looking
for red flags, right?
Cause you can have a great candidate
and you're like, Hey, this person
did great on the interview.
They did great in the technology
screen, but, you may have missed the
red flags and all of your excitement.
So this person is really there to help.
sell the organization, maybe sell
the geography where they're going
to need to move to if they need to
relocate, sell the culture of the
organization and really look, just
look for red flags and the candidate.
but if everything's great, then we
move on into the next piece, which
is the competency based interview.
And we'll cover that shortly, but we
really just want to understand not the
technology itself that you know, but.
and there's a lot of great questions
and competency based interviews that
really help you understand a person
and if they're the right team member
for the job, not just do they have
the right skill set, but do they have
the right behaviors within that skill
set to be able to do their job and
execute and bring the right kind of
values and culture to the organization.
And then lastly, we
compare the notes, right?
We take all of these things and
we say, okay, does the person,
is there skilled enough, right?
Okay.
Do they seem to solve
the problems well enough?
Do they have no red flags?
Do they really want to be
part of this organization?
Do they match our values?
Do they solve problems in a way that
is meaningful to the organization?
If everything is great, we give that
candidate a thumbs up, we make an offer.
And that's typically how most
organizations work, at least the
organizations that I've worked
with, as part of the hiring process.
So anyway, that's a background about the
hiring process we want to work through.
So at this point, I need to tell
you a little bit of a story, right?
So I'm getting a little frustrated with
different pieces of the hiring process.
And at one point I was
doing a lot of interviews.
I think over a course
of, Three or four years.
I was doing hundreds of interviews a year,
and I wasn't just doing them for my teams.
I was doing them for other
teams in the organization.
I work for a large organization,
and so I got a kind of got a
reputation for being good at them.
I like doing them.
I think it's fun.
I like picking apart people's brains.
And so I was doing an interview.
First of all, there's this
person on your screen, right?
Kind of looks like the
Lorax, big bushy mustache.
you frowned upon to talk about
somebody's physical features, especially
as it relates to an interview.
But this is important.
I was talking to a candidate and I
was doing a technical screen and I
think I was asking a simple set of
questions, something like, what is SOLID?
And SOLID is an acronym, it means
like Single Responsibility, Open
Closed Principle, Live Scoss
Substitution Principle, Interface
Segregation, and Dependency Inversion.
Now, most candidates, they will
say, something like dependency
injections, set a dependency inversion.
and we'll navigate that a little bit.
So I'm a few minutes into this
conversation and as the conversation is
evolving, then the facial features aren't
really lining up with the mouth at all.
Like the movements aren't quite there.
Now, I wasn't sure if it was just the
auto audio buffering issues or if it was
like, just The latency over the network
or whatnot, but it didn't seem right.
Something was off.
And so I get to this question, right?
what's the difference between dependency
injection and dependency inversion, right?
And really the answer there is
dependency injection is a way
to perform dependency inversion.
It's not the only way, but it is
the most common way, typically
the way we do things today.
So I get to this question
in the audio cuts.
I'm like, okay.
Okay.
This is not abnormal, right?
Sometimes the audio cuts, right?
And screens cut, whatever.
So the candidate starts
typing on the screen.
I can't hear you.
I have an audio issues.
Okay, it's great.
And but then something
registered in my head.
You see the candidate as they were typing.
I could hear their keyboard
clicks in the microphone.
So that's when it registered.
The person that I was talking
to in audio was not the person
on the other side of the screen.
The person on the other side of the
screen was mouthing the words because
their microphone was working just fine.
Oh my goodness.
This is crazy, right?
So they said, Hey, look, I'm going
to call back in a few minutes.
I'm going to rejoin the line.
okay, that's fine.
And while that's
happening, I start texting.
I am in the, the HR department,
our recruiter and say,
Hey, what's going on here?
I think our candidate might be
fraudulent and they say, stay in
the line, start asking questions.
And so went ahead and continued
the rest of the interview.
Five minutes later, the person shows
up again, they're on the visual, their
audio comes through and they asked
where we were on their questions.
And so we regroup again and they
give me a, not a great answer, but
we continue through the interview.
But the voice.
was completely different.
The accent was completely different.
The tone was completely different.
And the person on the other end was
still mouthing the words and things
weren't lining up, but they were
using their bushy mustaches to cover
so that you really couldn't tell
that it was necessarily the mouth.
But I'm a musician and I could pick
up on these audio cues from the
way the lips are moving and the way
it's supposed to be interacting.
I knew something was off here.
So after everything said and
done, we talked to our recruiters.
we really came back and said, hey, we
were, we think there might be an issue,
particularly with the sourcing agency and,
we might need to do something about it.
But it was providing some evidence
that, hey, there was some fraudulent
activity that was going on in the system.
Now, if you're in a hiring
role, there's some questions.
have you ever experienced.
fraud and hiring, whether it's,
the person's audio is different.
They won't go on video.
I've had situations where people
are typing in the questions.
I can see them on video typing the
questions and they're reading it.
it's great that they're resourceful.
I think it's important software
engineering, but it's also important.
You have a good foundations
and you're able to express
the answers pretty readily.
as a person who showed up on day one, not
been the person you even interviewed with.
That's another thing that we commonly see.
So it's very interesting.
So I'm getting frustrated because while
we got, talent pools are decreasing
because of the great resignation, right?
We got the big tech, trying to
get everybody they possibly can.
We've also got to deal with fraud and
this is a really challenging climate
to work through, which the reality
is with the situation is if you're
not cheating, you're not trying.
And for a lot of people who are
looking for jobs at this time,
they are cheating like crazy.
All right, so now we got to get into
our personal mission a little bit.
So I had some concerns about the
automated testing that we were using.
Some of the questions seemed simple,
some of them were ridiculously hard.
And they weren't testing whether you
knew the language or not, they were
testing could you solve the puzzle.
Which on some level was not great
because these were like Mensa
level puzzles that you could solve
with any language using for loops.
And I thought that was really not
the right way to solve the problem.
yes, you could screen out certain things,
but I'm looking for things like code
quality, maintainability, cyclomatic
complexity, cognitive complexity.
All sorts of things that are important
in the maintenance of software over
time, not just did you solve a problem.
And so I had some concerns and I started
elevating them to the organization.
So in spring of 2022, I started
voicing the concern about the
automated code assessments.
I didn't like the way that they were
being used as a blanket utility.
I wanted to make sure that we're
using them in the right context,
maybe with more junior engineers who
didn't have a professional background
because it really didn't make sense.
If you had somebody who wrote clean code,
To write it in this way, when I took this
test, I wrote clean code, and I honestly
just needed a for loop, but that's just
how I write, and that's just, it wasn't,
didn't seem like the right set of problems
that we were solving for, because it
really wasn't solving for engineering,
it was solving for the puzzle.
So in summer 2022, I was asked to
be part of a panel that reviewed
questions for fit and application.
We wanted to improve our questions because
we thought that might be a problem.
just, again, we didn't want super
hard questions, but we wanted
them to be enough where you had
to, understand the sequencing.
And so after that, I started
to ask if, has anybody tried
to run these through copilot?
Because it was in beta and chat GPT,
which I think was in an early beta.
It was crickets.
Everybody said that the process was fine.
Like, why would we ever
be concerned about AI?
It was, it was new, and I don't
think a lot of people really cared,
and it was part of our strategy.
So in fall of 2022, ChatGPT 3.
5 is released to the general public.
And this, at this point is when I
started taking these questions and
bringing them through ChatGPT to see
which ones could be easily figured out.
And as it turns out, a bunch of them, not
all of them, could be easily figured out.
And that kind of signaled the ones
that we needed to start retiring.
We need to not use them anymore.
But the challenge is when you
retire something, you create new
work because you now have to Create
new questions and those also that
also have to go through the system.
And so it's a little bit
challenging to deal with.
Now, when I started to present
some of these findings, just
about the questions themselves.
Now, this is just technical questions
like solving the code puzzle.
that's just one lens of this.
And I was getting frustrated that I
wasn't getting enough attention around it.
So in winter of 2022 into, January
2023, the plot starts to thicken as
I'm spreading this knowledge around.
All right.
So let's break the context before we get
into the thickening of the plot, right?
So we got like the great resignation.
We got big tech, drinking our milkshake.
We got these fraudulent candidates.
We got some automated testing
that's really not so great.
it's good, but it really could be better.
And then we got this challenge
of also being on prem, right?
we as an organization that one
I work for really want people
in the locality that we're in.
and that's important to us to build up
the community that we're operating in.
And so these things are just filtering
out really good candidates and it's
really becoming problematic to find
the right people for the organization.
So now it's time for some creative
problem solving like I'm expressing the
frustration and I happen to be speaking
at a conference in the middle of Ohio
in the winter, middle of nowhere, right?
Snow all around and we're at
this convention and it's a
big technology conference.
four day conference and on one end is
the conference hall and the other end
is like a resort side of hotel rooms and
in between is a bunch of restaurants.
And so I'm walking from the
conference center to my bedroom.
It's late at night.
It's 10 something at
night and I'm just done.
We have an early day the next day.
And so one of my, one of my buddies
who actually, is part of this,
he was a speaker and he said,
Hey Dan, I want to talk to you.
And I'm like, no buddy, like I'm tired.
I'm ready to go to bed.
And he's Hey, I'll buy you a drink.
I'm like, okay, fine.
So let's go ahead and have a talk.
And so he was talking about my
frustrations and he said, look,
Dan, I've got a proposition.
I think you've done an amazing thing with
this test, and I think we need to build
some content on this and start talking
about this more and help bring better
awareness about fraud as a vector and
how or how generative AI can be a vector
and fraudulent candidate hiring and
how we can improve the overall process.
He's a man of science
and I'm a man of science.
He said, look, let's create a process
and let's talk about this candidate.
And so we started figuring
out names for his candidate.
And we called him Chet Gupta,
which is a play on ChatGPT.
And that was the name, Chet.
It's like a Texas chat, and so
we were like, we like that name.
And then, couldn't figure out a
whole name for GPT, so we got Gupta.
And we, we started plotting
this out over a napkin.
At a conference, and we figured
we chop this around and figure
out what is this worth doing.
And as it turns out, this turns
out to be a really good set of
materials over the long term.
A lot of people have had interest in this.
I've spoken this particular talk
at multiple conferences nationally,
and it's been a great talk to bring
awareness, but with that, we wanted
to find a process that's repeatable.
So you can bring it to your
organization and try it.
for different human centered processes,
not just talent acquisition, but
we wanted to create a persona.
Now, when we initially started
this, we looked at using, LinkedIn
and creating a fake profile.
It turns out it's frowned upon.
So we didn't do that.
We did, generate some AI bio pictures
that we wanted to be a part of that
persona as we were pregaming before we
made that decision to not use LinkedIn.
So we're going to go through
that in a little bit.
We want to run the test problem.
So I hadn't done a lot of this research.
I wanted to run some more problems
through, through, chat TPT, as
well as co pilot that was the new
hotness at the time, See if it
can solve the problems for us.
And then I want to prompt some of
the technical screen questions.
These are the things like your, your data
structures, your algorithms, what do how
do you apply a particular object oriented
pattern versus a functional pattern?
What not right.
At this point, we're, we're, it's
getting late and we're talking through
the process and we said, Hey, look,
maybe we want to start bringing
talent acquisition along for the ride.
Now, as it turns out, somebody from our
talent acquisition department was there.
And so we're able to pull them in,
collude with them a little bit on how
we're going to go about this process.
And we, we wanted to have the shock
and awe with a larger group, but
we really wanted to understand the
process a little bit more and bring
them to our side of the table.
Because we didn't want to
attack talent acquisition.
We just want to make sure that
we're addressing a conflict in the
process and how to manage that.
And then we were we decided after
that we would perform the competency
based interviews questions,
which is Are a little different
than our technology questions.
They're more situational.
They're less technical.
And we wanted to see how chat
TPT would respond to that.
And then ultimately, we wanted to
do is bundle this up together as a
nice little package and present it
to our talent acquisition department
to see if we can make meaningful
change in the organization.
All right.
So these are the chats.
So all of these were generated,
I believe, using Dolly, just
like the Lorax picture before.
and so the prompt here was, Create
using dramatic lighting, create a
LinkedIn profile bio picture for a
software engineer named Chet Gupta.
That was it.
Now, when that happened, we
got 300 gentlemen who are
represented on the screen.
And I said, Hey, look, at some
point during these conferences.
I started to realize that Gupta
introduced some bias into the
system, and so I removed the word
Gupta, and then I got, these two
Caucasian gentlemen here as well.
now if you notice, again, there's
still bias in the system because
all of the pictures that here
that are generated all have.
Assume that software engineers have
shallow stubble and, and glasses
and they pick white people and
Indian people based on the names,
but, as a Hispanic man, right?
I could be a chat too, right?
So why not have a Hispanic chat?
Anyway, there's bias in the system.
It's there.
It's something we need to
acknowledge at some point.
But this is a system
that we're operating in.
So we started to select the pictures here.
And, so if we go from like
the top, like in the middle
there, we said, Hey, this chat.
This Chet Gupta, he looks like he's
a musician, like he plays jazz,
music only drinks IPAs, maybe a
little pretentious, maybe he's not
the person you want to deal with.
so what about the guy on the far right?
he looks like he runs, like
he's the CEO of a company.
So we said, no, maybe we don't want to
use him because I'm inspired by him.
He doesn't look like an employee.
So what about the guy in the bottom left?
as it turns out, he looks like a lot of
our other engineers as part of our group
and it'd be too stereotypical there, but
he does, and it looks like just a guy we
would hang out with on an everyday basis.
Now, these were the three
candidates we had when we
initially started this process.
The two Caucasian gentlemen were just
an afterthought as we were given this.
So we're really focused
on these three people.
And so ultimately we selected
the guy in the bottom left.
He's going to be Archette.
And again, these pictures
are all generated.
And When I first gave this talk,
we also had synthesized audio and
now they're synthesized video.
So the way that you can present this is
interesting because you don't need to
have video that's rendered over time.
It can be rendered in real time
and that's very interesting.
You can have profile pictures that are
generated and send in LinkedIn profiles
or even send in on resumes, right?
They aren't the real candidate themselves.
Also very interesting.
But the bot guy in the bottom
left is the one we chose.
Now the competency based interview.
I want to talk about this one for a second
because we talked about the technology
screen and technical assessments, but a
competency based interview is one where
we're following a star shaped pattern.
So we're looking for things
like your situation, your task,
your action, and your result.
We're not necessarily looking for how you,
for what technology you used, although
it is important, but how you used it.
Or maybe how you dealt with a difficult
situation or maybe challenging individuals
on teams or maybe if you're late for a
project, but those kind of situations
and how you overcame them, we want
to make sure you clearly define the
problem set in the situation, the
task and the action and the result.
So the framing is really important
because communication is very
important when we're hiring people.
All right.
So we asked chat or chat GPT.
when were you on a team
that face challenges?
And so the response that we got
back was, one of the main challenges
we faced was communication.
We had a feature that involved
multiple components and the
interactions between them.
And it requires close collaboration
between the team members to ensure
that everyone is on the same page.
However, due to different work schedules,
time zones and communication styles,
Some team members found it challenging to
keep up with updates and changes, leading
to confusion and misunderstandings.
Another challenge we faced was technical.
The feature requires integrating
with a third party API that's poorly
documented and difficult to use.
And some of those team members
lacked experience with the API and
struggled to understand its nuances,
leading to delays and errors.
To overcome these challenges, I, Chet
Gupta, decided to take several steps.
First, I organized daily stand up
meetings to ensure that everyone is
aligned on the process and any blockers.
Second, I introduced task management
tools like JIRA or Trello to track
progress and maintain transparency.
And third, I paired up team members
with varying levels of expertise with
the API to ensure that everyone has a
solid understanding of how it works.
And then by taking these steps,
we successfully overcame the
challenges and helped the team
achieve its goal of delivering
the new feature By the deadline.
Now, some of you are going to have
two different answers to this, right?
Some of you are going to
say, this is a great answer.
Wow.
This is well thought
through and it's amazing.
And actually it really is.
This is a really great situation.
Task action result of this.
This question is prompting.
The other ones may say, Hey,
look, this person invented agile.
It's already been invented,
which is also true.
But believe it or not, we get this a lot.
A lot of candidates come in and we'll say.
They're not familiar with Agile, they're
working with organizations that have
only used parts of it, or parts of
maybe a larger framework, and, so they
don't have maybe a total experience or
a total lens on the things that we're
necessarily looking for, and That's okay.
And it's okay to have that
background just because Agile
is supposed to be appropriate
for the context that you're in.
And so it's okay to not have like
maybe a larger understanding of it
or maybe a different set of tools.
Not everybody uses Jira or Trello.
So it's totally okay.
So let's ask maybe a technical question.
Right now, technical interviews are, what
we want to understand is the breadth of
experience across relevant technology.
So this is how T shaped you are.
And so for a full stack engineer who
needs to understand like front end,
back end, maybe networking and gateways
and whatnot, databases, this is
important, but they're very T shaped.
they're wide in their acumen, but
they might not be super deep, but we
do want to understand that as well.
So we're looking for the depth of any
experience in any one technology, because
we want to really understand, how deep or
why they are in a particular area relevant
to the role that we're trying to hire for.
And then we want to make sure that they're
exposed to various patterns and practices.
We're going to cover concepts, like object
oriented patterns or design patterns.
And we really want to figure out, what
is their total acumen, which is very
hard to do in 45 minutes to an hour.
And then the way that we do that
is through adaptive testing.
So we start in an area, like maybe, like
a language like Java or C sharp, which
the questions will get harder and harder
or design pattern or something like,
solid, single responsibility and whatnot.
We'll go through those into harder
concepts, like into like domain
driven design, general responsibility,
assignment principles and whatnot.
But the goal of that technical interviews
to understand against the rubric, how
this candidate sits, how deep and why
they are, because, it's very challenging
to do, and we have to move quickly.
So the adaptive testing
model works well for us.
So one of the, one of the questions
we have here is an algorithm.
This is actually a retired question,
which is, In Java, write a function that
determines if a given string is balanced.
Basically, you want to determine
On it, if a string has, open parens
and closed parens that there's,
if you send eight open parens,
do you have eight closed parens?
And the chat GPT response or the chat
Gupta response was the one that's
posted here, which uses a stack.
It's an algorithm, sorry, it's
a design, data structure that
allows an object to come in first.
and as you add more things, the top
most thing on that stack comes out as
opposed to the first item coming out.
And so a queue is the opposite of a stack.
And that's first in, first out.
Stacks are last in, first out.
And so this is measuring the open paren.
So every time an open paren comes
in, it adds something to the stack.
And every time a closed paren
comes in, it removes something.
And if you're at the end,
then the stack is empty.
Now, is it a perfect answer?
Probably not.
Is it a good answer?
Yeah, it's not bad.
it solved the problem.
And I think this is pretty fantastic in
terms of the response that we're getting.
When we look at our rubric answer,
the answer is pretty similar,
except we're using an integer based
accumulator to do that, calculation.
So instead of maybe a more memory
intensive object like a stack, we're
actually just using an accumulator to
say, every time an open parent comes in,
we add something, and every time a closed
parent comes in, we remove something.
And if we're at zero by the time
we're done, instead of negative or
positive, then everything's fine.
Effectively chasing the
same results, right?
And so these are good answers are good
enough answers, especially if you're
dealing with more junior engineer.
So this starting to look like chat
GPT is not a bad candidate, right?
We got our questions that
we're asking about competency.
We got our algorithm question
that's being asked very well.
All right, maybe let's ask some
slightly harder questions or maybe
some data structure questions
that are a little different.
So one of the things that we wanted
to ask for was, could you explain
what a concurrent hash map is?
And this is a Java centric, data
structure, for the most part.
And a concurrent HashMap.
As he responds, it's a data structure
that allows multiple threads to read
and write key value pairs simultaneously
without inconsistency or race conditions.
In a typical hash map, when two threads
try to access and modify the same
key value pair concurrently, a race
condition occurs, leading to data
inconsistency or even program crashes.
However, a concurrent hash map
uses a mechanism called locking
or synchronization to ensure that
multiple threads can access and modify
different parts of the hash map at
the same time without conflicts.
And in a concurrent hash map,
The data is divided into buckets.
Each bucket has its own lock.
And when a thread wants to read or
write a key value pair, within that,
it first locks the corresponding
bucket so that no other thread
can access it at the same time.
And then once one thread is done,
it unlocks the bucket so that
another thread can access it.
And this mechanism allows multiple
threads to access and modify different
parts of the HashMap concurrently.
So this is a great explanation so far.
Very wordy, and I'm sorry for the
wall of text, but that's how it is.
What's interesting is
what's happening next.
So Now it starts negotiating trade off.
So it also responds.
However, it is important to note that
locking and synchronization mechanisms
can introduce some overhead and decrease
the performance of the data structure,
especially when the number of threads
and the size of the hash map is large.
Now, when you're dealing with the
software engineer, like this is important
because we want to understand, can
they look at the design, Patterns of
the way that they're going through
the creational process and say, is
this the right tool for the job?
And so the ability to evaluate a data
structure and say, it's the right
tool for the job is super important.
And it's growing more and more important
as we look at the kinds of algorithms
and structures that we would use for
AI and maybe a B tree for one kind
of problem or a KNN, algorithm for
another and how we want to manage
our grouping and our correlation.
So there's a lot of different, just
because you know an algorithm doesn't mean
that it's the right algorithm for the job.
There's a lot of different ways to
apply them, so it's important to
understand how they sit in context.
ChatGPT is providing a contextual based
evaluation of a particular data structure.
This is valuable as an engineer.
It's valuable for a
candidate to understand.
as I got into this, there were
some things that started to
get pretty stinkin interesting.
So if we look at the results that
we're getting, so the one on the
right is the organization's kind of
rubric response that we're looking for
something along this lines and the one
on the left is the one that chat GPT
gave us and as I'm starting to evaluate
this, I'm looking for common themes.
So I've color coded them, like for
to say, these are the common themes
where we have something going on.
So in our answer, we segment or
internal data structure for locking
where they use the word buckets.
And I think it's analogous, right?
but what gets interesting
is how, what happens next.
So as I started to dive into this, We can
see the last piece that we were looking
for is that their answer says it locks
a corresponding bucket and in ours it
says it does it without locking at all.
So I decided to go ahead
and do some research.
Which answer is right?
I need to know, right?
I'm not necessarily a Java guy.
I really focus on different languages.
So I needed to go do a little
research to figure this out.
And as it turns out, chat GPT, check
Gupta was more right than we were.
This was starting to turn out
to be a very interesting thing.
Our candidates were better at
development and being a better
gatekeeper than we were for engineers.
So some concerns and we started to
make some changes as a result of that.
So cool.
We've got this candidate now who's
answering questions very well.
He's answering situational based
questions for teams very well.
there was a lot of research about this.
some of a lot of the questions when
they were being asked, they were It
took longer to write the question than
it did for ChatGPT to respond to them.
And that's crazy because now it creates
these opportunities where a person can
read over it, gloss over it, provide
some human interjections, maybe some
ums, or let me think for a second and
just natural inflection so it doesn't
sound like a robot's reading it.
And that's interesting.
Now, when we think about prompting,
right at the time of this writing, it
was a lot of it was based on just text
input, but you can also take audio
input, do some transcription, live
transcription, which drops it into an
API and does the same thing as well.
So you don't need to have somebody
actually handwriting these promptings
to give you the results of the
feedback that you're looking for.
So let's talk through
some of these outcomes.
All right.
So first of all, we just,
this we're presented and
bundled all this information.
We decided that, we really need to have
a better awareness about, cheating that's
occurring during our technical screens
and our competency based interviews.
And we wanted to provide some education
and uplift to the organization to
make sure that they were equipped with
the tools necessary to be able to do
constructive interviews and root out
maybe toxic candidates who weren't
be valuable for the organization.
We also started looking at Ongro
and scrutiny of the vendors
and how things were used.
We had a sourcing vendor as a part of
this like conversations, particularly
the one with the Lorax picture where
that candidate, that or that the sourcing
agency, was actually we had suspicions
that they were providing candidates that
weren't the right candidates for the job.
ultimately, we ended up changing
our relationship with them because
we realized that they were sending
us candidates that were fraudulent.
And so it closed the gap there.
That was a significant vector.
And then we also looked at our candidates.
Our testing tool to say,
is this the right tool?
And so one of the interesting parts
about the testing tool was that we
started asking questions about the test.
I said, Hey, look, I don't think
these answers are the right answers.
And and they said, I
said, everything's fine.
The people who write the
test say everything's fine.
It's not going to be an issue.
So I said, okay, that's great.
I'm not really sure it's
a good enough answer.
Who writes the test?
They said the vendor does.
So I was screaming in font
ligatures at this point, right?
And I said, okay, so the people
we pay to do their job are telling
us there's nothing to see here.
There's nothing to worry about.
oh!
Snap, we need to do something about this.
So we met with the vendor, we
started talking through the tool,
and we said, hey, look, what do
you guys think about generative AI?
How are you guys navigating?
And they were letting us know that they
love it, and they think it's great, and
it's a powerful tool, and, it's hard to
test for, because it's non deterministic,
which basically means that it's not going
to give you the same answer every time,
and the facts play into the facts, so it
can give you new answers based on previous
facts, and that's all very interesting.
Except we pay for a tool that can
now be broken with generative AI.
And this is a problem.
So are we going to continue
to pay for this tool?
So I said, what do you guys think
we should do with your tool if it's
not satisfying the problems for
these cases that we have today?
And they said, look, don't
use it as a complete stopgap.
Why don't you go ahead
and proctor your tests?
Now I told you we're interviewing
a lot of people, right?
So I can't take my best engineers all day.
Take them away from valuable work.
They're contributing to the organization
to sit down and make sure if somebody
is actually taking a test correctly,
so it becomes a big problem in terms
of how we use our best people to
solve problems for the organization.
So really take an extra scrutiny to
say this is the right tool for the job.
And how are we going
to approach this tool?
And so we had to look at changes to our
technical testing and we're still in
evaluation for using things like public
facing repositories and we're leaving
certain things up to the hiring managers
to say hey, if this test isn't appropriate
for you, we might not introduce.
This tested result as a way to bias
against a particular candidate.
Maybe you want to use a different
mechanic or vehicle to make that happen.
And the reality is our tools,
they're just not good enough, right?
So tools in isolation, such as
our automated co testing tool,
it's an ineffective stopgap.
But that aside, there's also
other challenges, right?
Our adaptive testing is no longer
an effective litmus because you're
just one prompt away from being
able to get a well reasoned answer.
And this is going to start to
require more social interaction
to improve the feedback loop.
So we can start getting better cues
about whether a person is, a bot or
whether they're actually, a different
person in the audio or, there's somebody
who's manipulating in some way, right?
To get hired for whatever reason, right?
So some things like, after giving
this conference a few times, I've
heard certain different talent
acquisition folks say, I've seen this.
This is crazy.
And so what I've started doing
is using instructions on a post
it note and having the candidate.
Read the instruction on the Post it note
and provide the same response or just
give a response to the note or provide a
visual cue on the Post it note or maybe
some sort of like a notepad to say,
I want you to do this and then maybe
look to the left or to the right, just
to see if they were the person who was
actually seeing the content on the screen.
And so that was very valuable feedback.
And I think, we've started to
consider what it means to have.
Better social interaction is cameras
on visual cues and whatnot in our
feedback loop, but the tools themselves
in isolation are not good enough And so
we're gonna have to get more creative
about the way we you know, we validate
the legitimacy of a candidate We
have to consider that competency bit
interviews at this point to as well.
They can be framed with some light
prompting It doesn't take much For
a candidate to drive contacts or
create some context behind the scenes.
And as we were creating these competency
based questions, I think we went through
for the CBI, probably 7 to 10 questions.
and each one was pretty stinking good, to
be honest with you and, very long winded
responses, which is, CBI typically only
has, It's an hour long conversation,
typically has three to four questions.
You want them to be long essay
kind of questions, and so you're
getting a lot of rich, deep context.
With light prompting, and that's really
challenging to navigate and quite frankly,
we have seen the automated code test
can be easily solved with plenty of lead
time to introduce those human elements.
making mistakes or doing things
that kind of look close enough.
these code tests typically will run and
they'll run with a bunch of unit tests
and you'll find that some of these tests,
maybe 99 percent test coverage because
they introduce a human element by design.
Because they add the time to that
would allow them to be able to.
To look human.
They're not perfect solutions
or close enough solutions,
and that's very interesting.
And the text screens again
are just a prompt away from
providing well reasoned examples.
So what it would look like
if you wanted to try this.
I think the first thing you need
to do is assume positive intent.
hiring talent is not a
frictionless process.
There's plenty of opportunities
to reduce the friction, but some
of that friction is important.
But just because it can be automated
doesn't mean it should be automated.
And that's something we need to figure
out as we navigate a gen AI world.
I once heard that AI in general
should be the best thing that
happens for humans, not the worst
thing that happens to humans.
And so I think it's important to just
be, pragmatic and appropriate when
we apply automation and artificial
intelligence to our process.
The next thing to do is
to lead with empathy.
it can take months or years to
bring in tools that will help reduce
this friction or things like toil.
And in our case, it took a very long
time to bring this automated testing
tool, which at the crest of its
mature implementation became highly
exploitable using generative AI.
And lastly, you are a second.
Thirdly, you want to be able to
bring talent acquisition with you.
It's better to work together to
address concerns than to attack a
process or people group who created
that process such as a department.
You really want to bring them along
for the ride and say, Hey, look, I
think we might have an exploit vector.
I want to suss this out with you.
Can you help me understand
where your context is?
And I'm going to show you where my
research is and we're going to work
together to create a better process.
And lastly, seek win outcomes.
ultimately, you're looking
for an effective process.
The person that you're going to hire,
especially if you're dealing with the
talent acquisition process, the person
you're going to hire is going to spend
about 1, 800 hours a year with you.
That's the average amount of time a U.
S.
candidate will spend in office
or working with somebody, hybrid,
remote, whatever, with your peers.
And so if you're building a team, you
want to make sure you protect your team.
That's a lot of time that
they're going to spend with them.
You want to make sure that they're
the right candidate for the job.
So if you do have any questions,
you're want to look at some of
the research that we've done.
I would, feel free to reach out to me.
You can reach out to me by
email at DanielMprese at gmail.
com or you can reach out to me on
LinkedIn at in slash Daniel Mprese.
Thank you for taking the time today to sit
through this conversation and learn some
more and hopefully you had a great time.
Thank you again and have a great day.