hello everyone!
Let's talk about prompt engineering.
What is it?
Art or science or maybe
your next job title?
I'm Maxim Selnikov.
I'm based in Oslo, Norway, where
I work in Microsoft, where I help
developers to succeed with our cloud
technologies, tools for developers.
And, everything related AI.
I personally, a developer
myself, and I build applications
since, late 90s of last century.
And I'm big fan of the
developer communities.
In Oslo, where I based, I founded a couple
of conferences and, run a few meetups.
My favorite topics to present about
are web development, all kinds of
cloud development, and of course, AI.
Everything related to generative
AI, including prompt engineering.
I found multiple estimations
on, the number of people who
use generative AI on our planet.
And, the most conservative ones say
that it's well over 1 billion people.
That's a number, right?
What do these people
use generative AI for?
just for us to start the discussion.
I identified three
large application areas.
First of all, everything related
to productivity, your personal
productivity, your business productivity,
everything related to usage of
generative AI in education and science,
and many other areas where we can
really get super powered by gen AI.
Next creativity.
After all, it's called
generative AI, right?
So it can generate for us
many, very interesting things.
so we can really feel ourselves super
creative, but, there should be someone
who is building these applications for us.
Someone who is, actually, Constructing
this UIs that we can use both
for productivity and creativity.
And yeah, here I'm talking about people
who are actually building these AI
infused or intelligent applications.
And I'll do my best to make this
particular session the most useful
for exactly this category of people.
people, but at the same time, I'm sure
that even if you don't have any intention
to build your, application, you can
still get lots of useful information from
this session because, it contains some,
general recommendations, some general,
practices for your improved Prompting.
And, after this session, when you
open any kind of generative AI powered
service like ChatGPT or similar, you
will know better how to communicate.
what is common thing
in all these scenarios?
Let's look how we, for example, ask Meet
Journey to create a new image for us, or
how we start conversation with Microsoft
365 Word, on, creating some very smart
and solid template for our document.
Or let's look how we communicate
with a GitHub copilot for improving
our code, not even saying about
the chat GPT as a service itself,
where we literally chat with this.
Of course, one common thing
is the way we interact.
And, the fact that it all starts with
the prompt with, some text that we write.
And, even though model landscape is
emerging and there is, next amazing
model is, released while I speak, while
you watch this session, and there are
already, multiple models available.
And, It's becoming more and more complex.
There are large language models.
There is new generation of small language
models also multi modality is really
available now even though There are
different kinds and types of models.
Some of them are general some
of them specialized Still
we all go back to prompts
This is why I consider prompt engineering
as a separate discipline or at least as
an essential skill of many people, not
only developers, but, many technical
people, many people on business positions.
and, what is this after all,
this is a process of, designing
prompts of, tuning these prompts.
And the further optimization, while
we keep satisfaction on a satisfaction
level on the results that we get
back from the large language models.
And of course, it's also important to,
to follow cost efficiency, because in
many cases, we talk about some paid
services when we talk specifically about
like high and large language models.
Let's look closer at the prompt components
or if you wish we can call it prompt
anatomy in many cases Again, at least
when we are the users who chat with
chat GPT We don't really think too
much about How we structure our prompt.
We just communicate and as long
as we are happy with the results.
We don't want to Dive deeper into all
these nitty gritty details That's fine.
But when you build your AI infused
application It's really good idea
for you to know how that works from
inside and again the same ideas and
the techniques are still applicable
to your like day to day conversations
with any generative AI powered service.
So yeah, let me, introduce how that works.
in many cases we have very clear and,
concise and straightforward instruction.
What we want to get from this
particular call to our, generative AI
service or, more technically precise.
The two large language model
exposed by one of these services.
and yeah, let me illustrate it by
this example what on the screen.
Let's imagine that we are building
applications for marketing automation
that gives us Nice, at least drafts,
maybe, or maybe ready to go emails
that, share details on some new
products that we either produce or sell,
or, it's again, it's not obligatory
as in role of developers, you can,
use the same, ideas and techniques
when you just, use ready to ready
products, with, some prompts available.
Instruction.
Of course, we have to also provide some
primary data about this product itself.
Also, we can provide some context
or we can call it secondary
data about tone we expect.
In this particular situation, we want
to be friendly and exciting, but for
different scenarios, there could be
different ways of, exact, narrative
that we expect from the model.
Also, we, identify, we set the
format, we define the format,
we want to get, answer back.
And in this particular situation, it's
definitely something that, that is
in the middle of, overall, developer
chain of, of this product, because
you see that we expect not just text,
but, Jason, definitely this will
be somehow processed by the next
steps of, our, for example, backend.
So we say that we want to get back.
Not just subject and the body,
but JSON object with these fields.
Also, we provide an example and
in this particular situation,
it plays at least two roles.
First of all, yeah, it demonstrates the
model, that kind of text, maybe length
of the text and again tone and old
structure That might be a good fit for us.
And also we double down on the format.
So this is why, we, put example
exactly in the format that we
described on the line above.
Why do we need this duplication?
Stay tuned.
I will explain why that might be useful.
So this is how we, human or
developers look at the prompt.
And this is how large language
model or LLM understands
the same prompt on its end.
And that it's split into tokens.
And actually, tokenization
is the first step.
procedure that happens when
you send prompt to LLM.
So large language model understands
your, your prompt in form of tokens.
And, when time has come to generate
answer for you, it also generates
this recursively token by token.
On this example, that, many words.
are equal to one token, right?
One word equals one token.
But of course, the real situation
is much more, complex, right?
So you see that, some words, take.
Multiple tokens and exact
implementation of how that split
is up to implementation of a large
language model, or it's a tokenizer.
There is no any kind of strict rule how
many, Words equals to how many tokens
or how many characters equals to how
many tokens we can very Approximately
say that at least for this generation
of LLMs and for English texts 100 tokens
is Approximately, equal to 75 words.
so that means like one token is maybe
around four characters in English text.
For different languages, the
ratio is completely different.
You might ask me, why do we ever need
to have this knowledge about tokens?
Because Definitely when we are
in user role, this is hidden
completely under the hood for us.
We communicate with
sentences in, sentences back.
when we are in developer role, Also,
this is not that visible at the
beginning of, when you start building
your AI application, but very soon as
a developer, you will understand super
important meaning of tokenization.
And this is why, because number
of tokens in your input and
expected output, first of
Cost of, this particular call,
if we talk about some hosted,
LLMs hosted by some vendors.
And also there is technical limitation on
number of tokens you can send and receive.
on this slide, there is some
screenshot from, pricing for
Azure OpenAI, services for GPT 4.
0 model and 0.
1 preview model.
And for legacy purposes, I
also listed price for GPT 4.
And, that, we are in good situation
as developers because prices.
are going down.
And first of all, yeah, that
it's priced by 1 million tokens.
So every single token for a few
number of calls, maybe this is
not something really crucial.
The price becomes really different when
we talk about some scale usage, but, Yeah.
Yeah.
Still very important to keep eye on it.
And that in GPT 4 it started for
60 per million and suddenly GPT 4.
0 that is more capable,
more performant model.
It's many times more Cheaper
and this is general trend.
there is newer and newer technologies from
outside of providers of LLM services and
yeah, so it's it's very good, especially
for example startups they have to
recalculate their economy and recalculate
in a positive way and next column I want
to emphasize on this screenshot is context
and this is exactly the Number of tokens
we can send in one particular request.
So we see it's not number of characters
or number of words or bytes or whatever.
No, it's calculated in tokens.
This is why it's very important to
understand, at least roughly estimate
number of tokens in your request.
prompts.
as you see, modern models are quite
capable and we talk about a hundred
plus thousands of, of the token.
So we are not talking about every single,
word or white space or, not even about
sentences, not even about paragraphs.
Maybe you can, currently send.
Pages of text as a prompt for these
models and again trend is work
good for us models are Capable to
accept more and more tokens, but
still there is a limitation, right?
So you cannot send maybe full book at
least currently at least at this moment
So this is why, again, tokenization
concept is extremely important and, we'll,
have a few more slides on this topic.
And of course, different providers
of, these LLM services provide
different ways for you to save on,
on this usage, all kinds of, caching.
All kinds of, batch calculations when
you don't need output, here now, but
you can wait a bit and then, price for
this call will be cheaper than regular.
All kinds of, some dedicated, capacities,
that really depends vendor from vendor.
And you also noticed that, model
selection makes real difference.
First of all on capabilities, on quality
of the output, and second on the price.
And, I offer you to use this
simple strategy on model selection.
First of all, try with the most
capable, the most performant,
and, in many cases also the most
expensive model on the market.
maybe you can, try different providers.
And, Identify your best prompt that
gives you the best possible results
Then you can try to downgrade to the
next cheapest one Next cheapest model
in some cases you might to might need
to fine tune the prompt slightly but
check the results if Result or completion
in technical terms when we talk about
prompt engineering is the same or better.
Maybe you can Do next step in
this downgrade and try even
cheaper model Maybe again results
will be the same or even better.
Sometimes that's also possible and it
will give you a chance to save Some
dollars if no Then you just go up to the
previous step where you downgraded from.
It's a simple and efficient
model selection strategy.
Also, you can use multiple models and in
many cases, if we talk about, not hello
world AI infused application, this is not
just one call to the, LLM, it's a chain
of the calls, maybe to multiple models,
maybe to even to multiple providers, maybe
it's mix between, some hosted services,
model hosted by external vendor, model
hosted by yourself, and maybe even a
model that is running straight on your
device or on your customer device.
So that, really depends
on business scenario.
So if you have a chance to use multiple
models in this particular feature
of your AI infused application,
you can follow a simple rule.
for.
Let's say, complex tasks like
generation, you can use expensive ones.
This is, where they really shine.
And, yeah, every new generation
of the model provides better and
better results in generation.
While summarization,
classification, categorization.
This is, again, our days, not
that complex tasks anymore, at
least for a large language models.
And the cheap ones do them pretty good.
another strategy.
is chaining.
for example, you want to send to a large,
expensive model some large amount of text.
This is how your prompt works, right?
but you can leverage cheaper and maybe,
Like very fast one, maybe your, your
own fine tuned model to summarize this,
large amount of text you are going to
send to expensive one also might work
good for you with a minimal performance,
decrease, you will save a lot of time.
some, some budget,
let's go back to talking conversation.
So I hope that I convinced you that,
keeping eye on number of tokens
you send is crucial for, economy
of your application, not only for
economy, but also you remember that,
there was just technical limitation
of a number of tokens you send.
And after all the shorter prompt,
normally the faster you get completion.
So it's, like multiple reasons
why you want to, minimize your
prompts and how to do this exactly.
First of all, very simple rule.
have a closer look at.
White spaces in your prompt.
this is something that we can
easily overlook because this is not
something that is very visible, right?
A couple of extra white spaces.
We can just, okay, ignore this.
But in reality, Some large
language models treat every single
whitespace as one extra token.
Not a big deal.
If you talk about one short request, but
if we talk about, I don't know, hundreds,
thousands, millions of requests that
might bring some, some difference to
your final bill and the end of the month.
Next for, different data formats,
try different, different ways
to like, implement this data.
What I mean exactly can be easily
illustrated by example of, how
we supply, Date in our prompts.
I'm technical mind and my first impression
was okay The shorter string with the
date the better chance that it will take
fewer tokens In reality, not at all.
So you see on the bottom line, short
format of the date takes six tokens, while
on the top line, it only three tokens.
So sometimes it's counter intuitive.
Again, this is example for one
particular large language model.
I don't even remember which one
different models can do it differently.
experimentation is the only way to really
identify what's your optimal format
for this or that type of, your data.
if you talk about tabular data, this,
straightforward tabular format is,
pretty much, space efficient, and what's
very important, understood by LLM.
no need for you to, always reproduce
JSON like format where you supply
caption for every piece of the data.
No, just provide some table headers,
separated by pipes, or type, tabs, or
you'll find your Personal separator and
then rows with the data in vast majority
of situations LLM will understand what you
mean also Language makes real difference.
I already mentioned that English is
the most straightforward ways for way
for Prompt engineering because it's
the most efficient while we talk about
tokenization at least again for the
mainstream Large language models I
suggest this because vast amount of
data, all this, Wikipedia, public books,
et cetera, et cetera, data that was
used for LLM training was in English.
it still understands other languages
perfectly well, but if we talk about
tokenization, the same, let's say,
Concept same sentence in different
language might take more tokens than
the one in English i'm not saying
that you have to translate everything
all single time But again experiment
and I want to start introducing some
tools and yeah in On next slides, you
will see more and more very useful
tools frameworks libraries that can
simplify your life as a prompt engineer.
the first one called LLM Lingua, and
this is nothing by but prompt compressor.
It's created by my colleagues from
Microsoft, and it's open source.
So you can take this tool and host
it locally or on your own server.
And yeah, as the description says,
it takes your prompt and compresses,
but it does it in a very smart way.
of course We can try to
do it ourselves, right?
But, we do not, not always understand
which parts of our prompt are crucial
for, LLM to really understand what
we mean and which parts we can skip.
who can help us?
Of course, another large
language model, right?
And in this particular case,
this is compact one, maybe we can
call it a small language model.
And yeah, so this one is used
to identify and remove non
essential tokens in your prompt.
And with some playing, some fine tuning,
you can get up to 20 times compression
with either zero or minimum performance.
loss because definitely, of course, some
time is needed for this, first step,
LLM or SLM to compress your prompt.
But on the other hand, prompt will be
shorter and, it might happen that you save
some milliseconds just because of that.
if we take prompt from our
first example about, email.
about, new headphones and run
it through this LLM Lingua.
I did it without any
fine tuning, just as it.
So it took literally a couple of
minutes for me to set everything
up locally on my machine.
I immediately got 17% Compression
of this prompt and you see a prompt
looks approximately the same, right?
but definitely Something is removed,
but the devil is in the details.
LLM lingua knows exactly what is
non essential for like other LLMs
Yeah, so I really encourage you
to try this tool Now, some general
recommendations about prompts.
Be specific and clear.
The more concrete your order, your
request, your ask to the prompt, the
better chance you get nice results.
At the same time, be descriptive
and if possible, use examples.
Again, you might need to educate LLM a
bit on what, you expect as a completion.
Order of the components.
Of your prompt matters.
There is no any kind of,
strict rule or rules on that.
only some recommendations,
and it's on the next slide.
Sometimes you need to double down.
Sometimes you need to repeat
either instruction or format, or
any other component of the prompt.
again, this is not a.
Mandatory, absolutely, but if
you are unhappy with, the results
you get back, try it, experiment.
And for the cases when we talk about
classification and categorization, you
better explain in your prompt explicitly.
Like this.
If you don't know which category to
put this text in, you better say,
I don't know, rather than force put
it into the, one or another bucket
that you provided in the prompt.
It will save you time on,
validation of the results.
Based on this general recommendation
some a bit more technical
ones or more concrete ones.
We can say like this Back to order
matters Normally for your optimal
prompt you start with clear instructions
in some cases You might want to
repeat instructions at the end.
Again, this is not a requirement.
You just need to experiment Don't be
shy to provide very clear instructions
Syntax, in your prompt, just, provide some
separators between different, sections.
You can even call these sections.
the better chance you explain
LLM what is what in your prompt,
the better result you get back.
Don't try to multitask.
One prompt for one task, you
better organize set of, the calls,
like chain the calls if you need
to, perform something complex.
And also, many providers of the models
and many models are capable to accept,
some extra parameters, not only prompt
itself, but some, parameters for,
for C in case of GPD family these two
parameters called temperature and Top
probabilities and they both affect how
creative this model is, how deterministic,
you can, you want your answers to be.
Of course, Models, model output
are, non deterministic, right?
but if you, for example, put temperature
to zero and top probabilities, to zero,
the better chance that you will get
the same result for, the same prompt.
Otherwise, if you put everything
to the maximum, it will be
as creative as possible.
possible.
Let me list a couple of techniques that
is widely used in prompt engineering.
And again, it might be very useful in
your, in career of prompt engineer or
AI engineer, or just a developer and,
zero shot versus few short prompts by
saying, short, we mean example here.
and let's.
Let's imagine that we are building,
some automation tool for insurance
company for first line of support.
And we gather it, question from,
Our customer via email automation or
maybe a transcribed phone conversation
and we want to pass it to this or
that department of our company.
It's either auto insurance
or flat insurance.
the prompt is pretty straightforward.
We ask to categorize one, two, three,
and this prompt illustrates one of the
techniques I mentioned giving model and
So if the question is not relevant, you
better, say it's not relevant, just,
mark it as three in this particular
case, rather than force push it to
either auto or home flood insurance.
Again, we'll save some time
on validation of the results.
This prompt might work good.
If it still fails in some, situations,
you can educate this a bit.
Use the same prompt, but somewhere in
the middle, inject a couple of examples,
maybe examples that use specific words
from this specific, field, maybe it's
like from your specific geo area, or
I don't know, something that is from
a real use cases, and, where a model,
for example, failed last time, you
can supply this as an example and
you'll get definitely better results.
Also, you have to find the balance.
your prompt becomes a bit.
Longer, right?
That means a bit more expensive,
maybe, slightly, longer time to
process completion, but, content or
like result is the king after all.
We want, perfect, output.
Another super powerful technique
called chain of output.
this particular example
is solving math problem.
First of all, maybe, I'd say that LLMs
are not perfect mathematicians at all.
and, normally you don't use this for
solving any kind of, math problems.
But, I really want to illustrate
this technique, by its, simpler
of all to illustrate it by
exactly this math problem.
story.
So just imagine that we, want to ask, for
an answer on some simple math operation.
So in the white, prompt in the
light blue, there is, output or
completion, more technical, term
result is here and it's wrong.
So 8 million liters per year
is completely incorrect.
I don't want to dive too deep.
Why that happens in
very simple words, LLMs.
are trying to find the lowest
hanging fruit in, in all
this, kind of calculations.
Of course, it's not real calculations.
but I want to explain to you how to
fix this and, possibly many other
situations, not all, not, limited to any
kind of, math or If we add one simple
sentence, let's think step by step
and explain calculations step by step.
As a result, our completion will
be a bit longer, that's fine.
But the most important thing is the time.
The answer is correct.
And, also, by the way,
this is not, exact wording.
You have to use all the time.
This let's think step by step.
No, you can experiment with a longer,
shorter description, something like
customized description, but you have
to, force model to literally think step
by step or provide reasoning behind
every step and results will be better.
you will clearly see this.
Another technique is not exactly about
prompting itself, but how we construct
overall communication with LLMs.
And in many cases, we need
to send multiple calls to
complete one particular task.
I already told you that.
Not good idea to multitask one prompt
for one operation, but, you can easily
organize prompt chaining by orchestrating
some your, some, backend tooling.
And, you can use again, multiple
models for multiple tasks, hosted
model from one provider, another
provider, your own model, local model,
fine tuned model, general model.
you decide, right?
What works.
Best for yourself.
And the whole idea is very simple.
You can use output of a previous call
to the model or part of this output as
a part of the input for your next call.
So this way you achieve a very good,
situation when you, literally, get
what you want with, minimal efforts.
Now I want to introduce Cambridge
dictionary word of the year 2023.
2023.
And this is hallucination.
Hallucination in context
of our interactions with
the large language models.
And this is something that is really
annoying in all kinds of AI engineering,
in all kinds of prompt engineering, all
kinds of building AI infused applications.
So this is again, outcome
of, how LMS were, designed,
invented, and how they work.
in, in summary, they are very
good in making up facts and,
making this in a very trusty way.
So it's very, complex sometimes to
identify what is, correct in this
output and what is wrong if we talk
about some, as some facts we requested.
Fortunately, there are multiple ways
for, if not removing completely,
but reducing hallucination,
mitigating its consequences.
For example, you can explain model not
only what you want, but also what you
don't want to receive back from this.
So you can limit number of use cases.
Also, this is a recommendation that I
already introduced, give, model and out.
If you're not sure, say, I don't know.
This is, this could, this simple statement
could be your part of the prompt.
As well as this one, sometimes it's, of
course, it's super naive technique, right?
But sometimes that, that works.
Don't make up facts.
As a part of your prompt, if there's
a chance for you to organize, multiple
short conversation with, your LLM, like
chat, like maybe you can, ask every
time, are you sure that you have all
information to answer this question?
If not, you better
request some extra months.
step by step reasoning and asking
model to explain along with the answer.
Basically, this is a chain of
thoughts technique also helps,
but all these points, what on the
picture are nothing compared to this.
You can dynamically find and inject
relevant context in information
straight into your prompt.
And you can say, Use only
this information for answer.
I mean forget all your knowledge
from wikipedia and the public books
Discard this we only need you to use
this data in its trade in the prompt.
I can illustrate this by Example
of us in the role of developers who
build internal application for Say our
employees to investigate what's possible
in medical insurance coverage for them.
And let's imagine that we got a question
from employee, via chat bot, or again,
via some automated email engine.
Does my health plan
cover annual eye exams?
And at the top of the prompt, that
we explain all the, prerequisites.
We are intelligent assistant and, yeah,
you can answer, questions about health
care and use Only sources below for the
answer and we also directly inject into
this prompt These three sources that are
relevant for answering this question.
Sounds very simple, right?
But of course we have to and
yeah completion in that case
will be nice and 100% Correct.
But how do we exactly
identify these sources?
How do we find these sources?
These few sentences in, for example,
dozens of, PDFs or documents
or somewhere in, in database.
How we identify these sources?
How we, shorten these sources?
How we rank them after all
to provide top 3 or 5 or 10,
depending on your use case, items.
And Answer to this question is Retrieval
Augmented Generation Pattern or REG.
as name says, it's about retrieve these
sources, these data sources, augment
them and, augment your promptery
and after all generate completion.
Generate completion is trivial.
This is after, about, sending
your final, Call to, final prompt
to LLM augment is even simpler.
This is just a string operation.
This is, literally inserting sources
of information into your prompt.
Like we've seen on this previous
example, retrieve is the real magic.
How?
based on this particular question or on,
question plus previous conversation, we
really identify data we need from, again,
back to, use case with, dozens of PDFs
with all this insurance, information,
and of course, here we can leverage.
one more large language model, this
one, say one that we use for the final
call, or most likely in vast majority
of situations, this will be completely
different one, specialized, and also,
you might want to, vectorize your
request and, those you have to send
this request to vectorize database.
Unfortunately, it's all,
out of our today's schedule.
Scope this could be your homework to
learn more about retrieve component of
rag and in the real world It's even more
complex because it could be multiple
sources of this information, right?
So before Constructing your final prompt
that contains everything you might
want to send requests to your Internal
database to some external API and who
knows where else so maybe you might
Want to have some orchestration support.
Surprise, surprise.
In real world, it's even more complex
than just, this orchestration.
and if you talk not about this
particular call to or chain of
calls to, LLM, but also about.
Full life cycle of our AI
infused application or like
a generative AI part of this.
we want to get some tools, some,
frameworks for ideation, for
building, for making everything,
real, how we deploy, how we, monitor.
it's, let's say very specialized
part, DevOps, but specifically
for your LLM interactions.
We can call this LLMOps.
So let me introduce more tools
that can help us both with, this,
orchestration of our calls and the
operationalization of all flow.
First couple of tools I want to mention
is LangChain and Semantic Kernel.
And these are amazing orchestrators
of everything you need to
interact with any kind of LLM.
So these two libraries or frameworks,
you name it, are very similar.
They support slightly different,
Set of programming language slightly
different set of Platforms but in a
nutshell they are helping you to Get
very nice abstraction over all your
interactions with LLMs so you don't
need to write all these calls all this
ping pong from scratch also There are
many more very interesting features
included in both of the framework.
So When you start your new AI
infused application, don't ever
start, like your, low level,
communication with LLM from scratch.
Find your perfect, level of abstraction,
in these two or any other frameworks.
And for overall orchestration or
personalization of your LLM application,
I recommend you to have a look at
PromptFlow, another open source tool.
this one also created by my colleagues
from Microsoft that in code first
way can help you again to keep a full
control over full cycle of your LLM,
development starting from experimentation.
Up to monitoring
from flow.
You I could look like this.
This particular short video
is from, the hosted version.
There is one on Azure, but you
can get the same UI straight in
your, VS code ID, via respective.
extension called PromptFlow.
basically it reproduces your interaction
with LLMs as a graph where some
nodes are pieces of Python code.
Some nodes are calling of LLMs.
Some nodes represent prompts where you
can iterate through multiple variants,
for example, to identify what is the best.
And after all, you can host everything
on the cloud of your choice.
There are many learning resources
available about prompt engineering,
and, I hope that you will get PDF of,
this session with all active links.
What is the future of prompt engineering?
I have set up the questions.
I will not give you answers on.
I encourage you, yourself find the answer.
For example.
Will it be a separate job
title or just essential skill?
Will it become simpler with tools like
Longchain, Semantic Kernel, PromptFlow?
Or they become more complex because
there is multi modality, you
have to closely work with vectors
if you talk about React, etc.
Doos, will it be democratized and pretty
much everyone who ever sent a request
to ChatGPT will call themselves Doos?
Prompt engineer those, there'll be title
inflation or it will be more gated,
discipline and who will benefit the most
people who understand how our language
constructed linguists or people who
understand how code works technologies.
Or maybe people who know everything
about this particular domain,
where this application comes from
and able to formulate the problem.
And do we survive competition
with LLM based prompt engineers?
Because LLMs are also
perfect in creating prompts.
I invite you all to the Prompt Engineering
Conference I organize, in November
and this will be second edition.
First of edition was,
last year, super popular.
and, if you watch this session
before November 20, just go
and register your ticket.
If you watch this after,
still go to the same URL.
You will find all sessions
recorded straight there.
And it's online, it's free.
It's free, open for everyone.
Thank you very much for watching this
session and my last prompt for everyone.
Let's stay in touch.
This is my LinkedIn profile.
Find me, just scan this QR code or find
Maxim Salnikov Microsoft on LinkedIn.
And it's my great pleasure
to stay connected with you.
Ask me about, prompt engineering,
AI engineering, any questions
or, any questions about web
development and cloud in general.
Thank you very much.