Hi, everyone.
My name is Marina Goplacheva.
I am a product manager.
I've been working on a few AI products
for several years now, specifically
enterprise applications in HR tech domain.
And today I'm going to share with
you my professional experience and
what I've learned from building
conversational AI experiences in HR tech.
First of all, just briefly, I would
like to say a few words on what
exactly I mean by conversational AI.
I think it is important
because the terminology in
this space is somewhat fuzzy.
Although, it's not that new.
Some years ago, it was mostly chatbots.
It is the application of machine learning
that enables people to communicate
with mobile apps, interfaces, devices,
et cetera, using your own words.
It's written off spoken.
The focus is also on producing
natural and seamless conversations
between people and computers.
And usually those interactions
are designed as human as possible.
And voice has become a very
common modality in this
space for several years now.
And I think the reason that in this space
we do love voice so much is because how
we perceive something that can speak.
as somewhat human and intelligent.
That's why I love this quote by Judith
Shulevitz about our minds respond
to speech as if it were human no
matter what device it comes out of.
But I'll talk later of, about how
it's sometimes difficult to live
up to these expectations when you
design conversational AI experiences.
I think conversational AI.
is one of the best ways to
deliver value in HR tech.
I've been working in this space since
2019 and at that time it was not something
common to use conversational AI in HR.
And I do think at that time that
was quite progressive thing to do.
If you look now at biggest vendors in HR
tech, you'll see companies like Oracle,
Workday, SAP SuccessFactors, ADP, all
trying to move into this direction
of conversational interfaces as well.
why do I think conversational AI is
the best way to deliver value in HR?
first of all, the ability to use your
own words make a huge difference.
Employees do not need to remember a
specific term or the name of a service or
a specific app to get to what they need.
And it usually is the
case with HR services.
As someone who worked in HR tech for
years, and I love HR, I always saw
this gap of understanding between HR
and employees in terms of terminology.
So removing this obstacle by giving
employees Ways to get to what they
need using their own words and
understanding is, I think, a great thing.
The other thing is the one interface,
which is no interface in case of
conversational AI, and how we usually
say that it's an interface less UI
or in case of conversational AI.
And I think it's another big thing
if you work in any big enterprise.
I'm sure you know the mess most
companies have in terms of, how
many tools they have, systems, apps.
and that makes it very difficult
to mitigate for employees.
So removing this mess and giving them
to use something that has one interface.
That's one.
Interfaceless UI is also,
I think, a great thing.
The other thing is the ease
of use in terms of UX compared
to traditional HR platforms.
You usually have to invest time and effort
to teach employees to use these systems.
Also, if you've ever been a part of
any HR transformation, Associated
with new implementation of a new HR
platform, you will know that a lot
of change management is required.
Conversational AI takes a
lot of the change management
hassle out of the equation.
You also can build conversational
AI experiences on top of what
you have without re-engineering
existing systems and.
Finally, these ability of what
we call meeting users where they
are so that they don't need to
interrupt their usual workflows.
We call those, systems, apps, messaging
apps where employees, which employees
use in their everyday work surfaces.
So integrating conversational AI.
on all those surfaces seamlessly
is another great thing,
that makes Condensational AI
great to use in HR domain.
I've designed Condensational AI skills
for nearly every aspect of HR, whether
it was onboarding, lead management,
compensation, performance management.
I'd say not every single aspect of
HR processes can be easily designed
in a conversational interface.
There are some things that are
still maybe better done in a
full UI content rich interface.
But even those can be incorporated
and I'll talk about it as well.
So how do you build
conversational AI experiences?
First of all, I think no matter
how great your tech stack is, good
design practices are essential.
In my view, it is foundational
for designing any kind of tech
product which is used by humans.
And the experience of interacting with the
AI product can be fundamentally different
than with traditional software products.
Hence, you have to design for that.
If the design is not up to the level of
the technology, that itself is a barrier
for making the most out of these products.
It is a barrier for adoption and
overall results in poor experience.
And also I think part of this problem with
design practices for AI is that there is
a large knowledge gap and perhaps cultural
gap between people of a UX background and
people of a machine learning background.
So we need to think of
ways to minimize this gap.
Try to find ways for UX designers and
ML experts to collaborate effectively.
I'm certain that UX designers nowadays
have to understand a lot better what's
happening in the backend of ML products.
You also have to design conversational
experiences with an understanding
of how conversation works.
There are some scientific foundations
of how human conversation works.
We also need to remember things like
models tend to degrade and the performance
of the algorithm goes down with it.
So how do we design for that
into the product itself?
To make sure that we are still delivering
the performance there over time.
Researching and understanding your
users is also still necessary.
I remember when I was designing
voice skills for AI voice
assistant for internal employees.
For I was biased towards asking
questions within a voice flow as
if it was a logic flow within the
UI app equivalent of that flow.
And there were users who were
experienced at using assistants
like Amazon Alexa a lot at home.
So those users interacted with voice
skills as they were talking to a human.
But those two are hugely
different mental models.
And it's a huge difference in
how you could, you would go about
designing that AI product for
two different groups of users.
So you have to research how
people use your products or
use AI products in general.
Just having great technology does
not mean it doesn't need to be
designed and applied properly.
In order to build personalized.
conversational AI experiences
at scale, you need to leverage
the context of the users.
To do that, you have to
invest in fixing your data.
And I'm not just talking
about data quality, but in
building an additional layer.
That is, you have to have a high quality
codified descriptions and dictionaries
of the data of your employees.
because your LLMs have
to query that context.
Another thing I would suggest is to
maybe supervise the process of AI
development, not just the outcomes,
especially when you are designing complex
compound conversational experiences.
and in cases when you are not, Using
public models, but starting from scratch.
Think whether it makes sense and it's
feasible to set up experiments involving
people in the development process.
It makes perfect sense to do
that when trying to AI, apply
AI to complex decision making.
It will give you invaluable
insights into what expert human
does and what is the ideal process.
And the more granular your
understanding is, the better.
My next point is on the
levels of anthropomorphism.
When I started working in conversational
AI space back in 2019, I quickly realized
that a lot of time and effort in that
space was spent on trying to find ways
to make people feel comfortable with this
technology by putting a human face on it.
I think I spent hours every week in
conversations about how to design
the conversational interfaces,
trying to mimic how humans speak.
And it sounds logical, because when
you introduce language or speech into
the equation, you immediately have this
perception of these things as intelligent.
The question for me is, that level
of anthropomorphism is needed.
Is it?
necessary?
Is it going to speed adoption
or make for a safer adoption?
Or is it just setting bad
expectations right away?
And for me, the answer is, it depends
on what you're trying to achieve.
When, for example, I analyzed how
people used the AI assistant we
developed for our internal employees.
We realized from the data that
people generally use conversational
AIs for utilitarian goals.
And their wording and
language is reflected in that.
AIs are tools for them.
So they cannot be more than
that, because humans cannot make
emotional connections with them.
And frankly, I don't think people should
make emotional connections with things.
Moving to my next point.
I think you do not have to limit yourself
with modalities and concepts like AI
thirst, voice thirst, anything thirst.
Yes, conversational AI is about
natural language, but it does not
have to be pure natural language.
Later in my career as conversational
AI product owner, my team and I
did a great job Incorporating micro
UIs into conversational AI skills.
And so combining natural language
models with graphical UIs, you
can have the best of both worlds.
Especially in HR, it just makes sense
for main things to be able to have both.
Again, meeting employees where they are.
On devices, platforms, systems
where they work without the need
to break their usual workflows.
I think it's essential.
For many years, people like me in HR tech
space struggled with this one big thing.
That people do not spend their
time on HR, in HR systems.
They primarily spend their time in other
systems, in case of knowledge workers.
Or in case of blue collar
workers, they don't spend that
much time in any system at all.
this context in which interactions
occur shapes the perceived utility
of success of that experience.
there was this one example of an
experience, we developed for some
of our employees some time ago.
And I won't go into specifics, but
it failed miserably just because we
were so focused on the problem itself.
And we missed the most important thing,
that in order to use that conversational
AI skill we developed to solve one
of the pieces of work they were
doing, and it was some tedious stuff.
We didn't know, we did know
they didn't like to do.
But, we ended up with people not using
it because it required these people
to interrupt their usual workflow.
To go to open the assistant on some other
device, and it was just not worth it.
This interruption just
made no sense to them.
I think this thing of meeting employees
where they are is also crucial.
And the last thing I wanted to mention
is that the important thing to remember
is having AI doesn't mean we need
to ram it end to end AI everything.
We still need to recognize what is good
for and what is good for and use it to
power the most effective experience.
Especially in a regulated domain
like HR, there may be cases where
it may be better to leverage rigid
or more traditional technology.
For example, with issues around payroll,
you may need direct controls there.
So there will be cases that will
live outside of the AI components.
And you can do a lot by how you design
the things that you do and how you create
the user buttons and the mental model
for the person using conversational AI.
So I think the AI first craze should
not get in the way in cases where we
have to put security controls in place.
In conclusion, and to wrap it
up, I think yes, as I said.
Design practices are crucial
and they are key no matter how
powerful the technology is.
And you have to remember that
conversational AI or any AI is a
tool that should be aligned against
a specific business objective of
what you are trying to achieve.
And it's critical to consider
the state of your AI.
HR data, tech stack and risk
tolerance when it comes to
implementing conversational AI.
That's all from me today.
I hope you found something helpful
and useful in what I've talked about.
And thank you for listening.
If you're interested in maybe talking or
reaching out to Just find me on LinkedIn.
I'm always happy to talk all
things conversational AI or
anything you want to talk about.
thank you.
Bye bye.