Hello, everyone.
I'm Monika.
Thank you for joining me.
Today's talk is about enhancing
embedded device security,
a cost effective approach.
Embedded devices are essential
in our day to day life.
We are very much dependent
on them in every aspect.
they are in home automation.
Transportation and medical devices,
education there everywhere.
However, these devices often like
the, the robo security measures, which
puts them, at risk, due to the cost
power and performance trade offs.
So in this talk, we are going to
discuss about some of the applications.
we can use to improve the
security of these devices.
Cyber criminals often target
the embedded devices which are
in critical infrastructures, or
industrial systems or AOT systems.
for example, you can think of flight
controls or it can be, A healthcare
system, or it can be a gas pipeline, or it
can be any other which are very critical.
So often they try to exploit
the weaknesses through a for
example, they may try like this
default password, the password.
Passwords, or they may exploit the
outdated firmware where they know that
this buffer overflows or stack overflows
or any other kind of issues are already
exist and they try to exploit those first.
a study shows that, 83 percent
of the embedded systems actually,
lack the security features.
so the breaches, which incur due to this,
lack of security features is very costly.
Often organizations pay millions of
dollars because of the damages and
as well as to recover, these systems.
So to improve the security of the
embedded devices, it is crucial
to, consider addressing the
known vulnerabilities as well.
so secure core practicing, eliminates
the potential, vulnerabilities like a
buffer overflows and memory corruptions.
secure boot mechanisms, helps to
enhance the security by blocking the
unauthorized access to the software.
and also, they, they validate the
authenticity of the firmware that is
being executed, and this is very important
because otherwise, otherwise anyone
can inject the malicious code, during
the boot up, and then they corrupt the
boot software or they can take control
of the device after the OS comes up.
secure boot mechanisms can also
helps to mitigate, some of the,
some of the attacks, along with this
intrusion detection also helps to
improve the network security where
it can detect the any suspicious
activities or possible attacks.
It can alert the administrator
or even we can take automated
actions to prevent any attacks.
obfuscation also helps.
to enhance the security of the devices
by, randomizing the symbol names
and the function calls in the code.
this, this, makes, harder for the
attacker to reverse engineer the
code to create, targeted attacks.
To improve the robustness of the embedded
devices, it is important to consider
other advanced security measures as well.
for example, control flow integrity,
encryption of the code or, address space
randomization, or we can, insert the stack
and erase or authenticate any dynamic,
modules that are, dynamically loaded.
Control flow integrity, helps with, helps
with, security because, It doesn't let the
attacker to execute any part of the code.
control flow integrity makes sure
that only the validated execution
paths are actually executed.
other than that, like any
other paths won't be executed.
attacker won't be jumped from one
part of the code to any part of
the code, because it's prohibited
to do address space randomization.
Helps, also helps because every time
the device is, boot up, every time
the device boot up, the image kind of
loads it a different place in the ram.
So it, it, it helps with the mitigating
certain kinds of attacks as well
as it also makes the, it also makes
it harder for the, attacker to.
To create any targeted, attacks.
Authenticating any, dynamically
loaded models is also very
important, because otherwise,
attacker might include a malicious
code as part of the dynamic models.
also strictly controlling the
access to the parts of the
memory by different models.
When, there are like a multiple
system on trips is very.
Important as well, because there are
sometimes if one of the component is
actually a compromise, it is highly
possible that through that attacker
might compromise the other component,
other devices on that chip as well.
So instead of that, if we can strictly
access the control, we can mitigate
some of the security attacks as well.
The other proactive measure to
improve the security, includes,
regularly updating the software.
for example, patching the software
regularly is, crucial, either to fix the
bugs or to fix any known security issues.
most of the time, cybercriminals
tries to exploit these unknown issues.
So it's very important to,
close, those, known issues.
other techniques are like, address
sanitization and undefined behaviors,
like sanitization at runtime, or also,
helps to mitigate some of the attacks.
For example, sometimes attackers,
can craft, can craft The system to
run into undefined behavior and then
corrupt the memory so that they can
take control over it by enabling
these in the devices, we can make sure
that we are these any attacks which
are related to this are mitigated.
as discussed in the beginning,
the security of the embedded
devices is often trade off with
the performance and the cost.
however, we can still prioritize the
security on these devices by conducting
the threat models to identify the
critical vulnerabilities and by, only
considering the restricted risk profiles,
which are actually, suitable for the,
for these, embedded for the given
embedded device and as well as for a
given, constraint, we can also consider
like improving the performance of
these, secure algorithms or introducing
the, hardware, dedicated, hardware
accelerators, for the cryptography related
things, or we can, Use the lightweight
algorithms to reduce the load on the
embedded core and, uh, and also we
can, utilize like existing environments
if there are any security issues.
we can, use them or if there are
any trusted, trusted, trusted
execution environments, we can use
them to maximize the protection, but
without affecting the performance.
Here are the list of different,
techniques that we have discussed,
and these, techniques can be, rolled
out to the existing, embedded devices
to reduce the attacking surfaces.
so with all these, different kinds
of method, it makes it, harder for
the attacker to craft the cases,
specific to a, given device and
then, exploit those vulnerabilities.
So these methods, these methods helps
to reduce the number of attacks.
By collaboratively considering to,
considering the security by design, by
using the industry standard frameworks
and then using the scanning tools to
detect the vulnerabilities and also
threat modeling to detect any known,
known threats ahead of the time and
then, improve the code accordingly.
And also by designing the
layered architecture to integrate
the defense in, principles.
And then by implementing the
secure protocols, we can reduce
the, we can reduce the attacks
on this embedded systems.
study shows that 80 percent of the
critical vulnerabilities are reduced
by regular updates and, scanning.
90 percent of the, attempted breaches were
blocked because of the enhanced protocols.
now we can see that, these security
measures are, really important
by incorporating at least, some
of these measures will really
ensure that, embedded devices are
protected at least to some extent.
we can provide the confidence to
the users, by following this core
principle where we can provide
the, robo security frameworks.
to protect the critical operations,
we can monitor the, systems in real
time to, for the, and provide the
security status and also provide
the visibility into the systems.
we can also make sure that the mission
critical, environments are always,
performed, have a consistent performance.
this way we can, we can, Not only
just show that, security is going
to be, add on future, but it's
a foundation of everything that
we do with the embedded systems.
In conclusion, with the adoption of
security measures which are discussed
in this talk, we can transform the
embedded systems from the vulnerabilities
into resilient technologies.
We can enable a secure, intelligent,
and interconnected digital systems which
are ready for the future challenges.
The key takeaways from this talk are,
we can implement the robo security
measures from the beginning of the
project itself, and, we can continuously
monitor for regular, updates, for the,
security patches or implementing the
security protocols or, updating, any
known, issues or, And also optimizing
the security, without compromising
the functionality, all, functionality.
we can also build a trust, with the user
by fostering the conference, through
the transparency and the reliability.
So the next actions that we would
need to take is assess our systems
and then implement the best practices.
Practices that suits the needs and without
impacting the performance of the systems.
And also it is very important to stay up
to date on the current security trends
and as well as the emerging threats.
I hope you like my talk.
Thank you for giving me this
opportunity and have a very good day.