Good morning.
Good afternoon.
Good evening, everyone.
Thank you for being here.
My name is Vinodupaturi.
I do have 11 years of experience
in the financial industry.
Currently, I am working as
a senior software engineer.
Today, I am thrilled to talk about the
subject that's not just critical for
financial institutions, but for everyone.
AI powered fraud.
detection.
Did you know the financial fraud
cost the global economy over 5.
4 trillion dollars annually?
This is a staggering number emphasize
the urgent need of innovation.
Today I'll be discussing how artificial
intelligence and machine learning
are transforming the fraud detection
into high efficient, proactive,
and customer friendly process.
Let's dive into the fundamentals
of AI powered fraud detection and
understand why it's such a revolutionary
force in financial security.
Billions of transactions
are processed every day.
Within these transactions,
fraudsters are hiding, adopting,
and exploiting the loopholes.
How do we oversmart them?
Using artificial intelligence.
There are three major
approaches for fraud detection.
Supervised learning, unsupervised
learning, and deep learning.
Supervised learning.
AI will always thrives on
learning from the past.
Using billions of label transactions,
supervised learning algorithms
refine themselves over time
to achieve a staggering 99.
9 percent accuracy in the fraud detection.
For an instance, think of
how your email filters spam.
AI applies a similar concept to
transactions, but with precision sharp
enough to spot even the most complex
patterns of fraud in milliseconds.
Unsupervised learning.
Fraud isn't always static.
It evolves.
Unsupervised learning steps in
where the pattern isn't clear.
It identifies hidden threats,
the anomalies we don't know
exist, and improves early
fraud detection by 42%, 42%.
Imagine a AI system spot unusual
behavior in the transaction from
a new system or a new location.
Even if it doesn't match
previous fraud patterns, AI
flags it for a deeper analysis.
Deep learning.
This is the powerhouse for
of modern fraud detection.
Deep learning network process thousands of
data points for transaction in real time.
This means they don't
just identify a fraud.
They stop it as it
doesn't, as it's happening.
Deep learning has slashed cardinal present
fraud by 76%, a major achievement in
the fraud against, fight against digital
fraud, real time fraud prevention.
Let's move from detection to the
prevention in the real world,
area where AI truly shines.
Imagine a fraudster attempt to
use a stolen credit card online.
Before the transactions can be
processed, the system flags it as
suspicious, blocks it, and notifies
the rightful account holder.
All this is happening in
a fraction of a second.
Prevention can be done
in three major ways.
Real time transaction analysis, behavioral
biometrics, synthetic identity detection.
Real time transaction analysis.
AI system analyzes 100k
transactions per second.
Scanning for anomalies
within a few seconds.
is 50 milliseconds response time.
For an instance, consider a user,
in New York whose card is currently
used for purchases in London.
EA immediately flags this as a potential
threat based upon the patterns like
unusual location and transaction size.
This level of speed ensures the
fraud in, fraud is intercepted
before it can be used.
can cause damage, protecting
customers and saving billions.
Behavioral biometrics.
AI studies how users
interact with their devices.
Their typing rhythms, swipe gestures, even
the pressure they apply on a touch screen.
This creates a digital fingerprint
unique to each user, which is incredibly
hard for a fraudster to replicate.
Behavioral biometrics have reduced
the account overtake attempt by
impressive of 89 percent accuracy.
Synthetic identity detection.
Fraudsters create fake identities
by combining the stolen data
from multiple individuals.
These synthetic identities often
go unnoticed in the transaction.
Traditional systems.
AI maps and analyzes fabricated identities
with 94 percent precision, intercepting
fraudulent activities before it can occur.
Use cases.
We have explored the power of AI,
how it prevents fraud in real time.
Now let's zoom in on
real world applications.
Real time transaction monitoring.
AI analyzes thousands of data points for
transactions like location, time, device,
and spending patterns within milliseconds.
Suspicious transactions are flagged
and blocked immediately, preventing
the fraud before it cause damage.
Let's imagine a customer card is
suddenly used to buy high value
items from unfamiliar locations.
AI detects this anomaly and stops the
transaction instantly, saving the customer
and institution from significant loss.
Account takeover protection.
Fraudsters often gain unauthorized
access to accounts using the stolen
credit cards and stolen credentials
or by brute force attacks.
Behavioral biometrics
and machine learning 5.
Deviations in the user behavior
such as login patterns, device
usage, and to identify and
stop these unauthorized access.
AI neutralizes account takeover
attempts and protects both customers
data and institutional trust.
Synthetic identity fraud mitigation.
Synthetic, synthetic fraud is one
of the fastest growing threat where
fraudsters create fake identities using
the mix of the real and fabricated data.
AI cross reference the data
patterns across multiple systems,
identifying inconsistencies that
human investigators might miss.
AI prevents 87 percent of synthetic
fraud attempts saving institutions
billions of dollars annually.
For an instance, if the loan
application is flagged as a suspicious
due to the mismatched identity
details, AI can block the process
before any funds are dispersed.
Phishing detection and prevention.
Phishing is one of the most common
and, common entry point for the fraud.
Natural language processing scans
communications like emails, messages, and
calls, for phishing keywords and patterns
and the links blocking them in real time.
Impact.
Institutions intercept phishing
attacks before they reach customers
and ensuring their safety.
AI protects every aspect of the
financial ecosystem, from individual
transactions to large scale operations.
This solution doesn't just respond to
fraud, they anticipate and prevent it.
By safeguarding accounts and transactions,
AI strengthens the bond between
institutions and their customers.
Implementation roadmap.
To realize the future, organizations
need a clear and actionable roadmap.
Let's discuss the steps to
simplify the implementation
and AI powered fraud detection.
Building a robust AI fraud
detection system isn't just
about deploying algorithms.
It's about the strategy, alignment,
and continuous improvement.
Define objectives.
Conduct a comprehensive internal
assessment to map out a plan.
fraud detection goals and align
them with overall risk assessment
and risk management strategies.
For an instance, if your goal is
to reduce a fraud by 50 percent and
ensure the customer's trust, define
it clearly to guide your approach.
Data assessment.
Data Audit your existing
data infrastructure to
ensure quality diversity.
Poor quality data leads to
biased and ineffective AI models.
For an instance, if an organization may
discover gaps in the data collection, like
missing behavioral insights and address
them before training their AI systems.
Model selection and training.
Experiments, experiment with multiple
models leveraging advanced machine
learning techniques like supervised,
unsupervised, and deep learning.
Choosing the model that adapts to evolve
the threads and provide explainability.
Deployment and monitoring.
Rolling out the AI in phases.
with continuous performance
tracking and the feedback loops to
refine defect detection mechanism.
Fraud detection is not like
a fight and forgot effort.
It requires a real time adaptability.
For an instance, if an organization
deploys AI for online payment first,
refine it accurately before expanding
to the other regions or demographics
or maybe other type of transactions.
Benefits of AI powered fraud detection.
We have seen how AI detects and prevents
fraud while enhancing customer experience.
Now let's focus on the game
changing benefits that makes AI must
have for financial institutions.
Fraud isn't just a cost, it's a threat.
to trust, efficiency,
and customer loyalty.
With AI, we are not just fighting
fraud, we are transforming the way
business operates, protects, and grows.
Let's break this down for you.
Reduce fraud loss.
Every fraudulent transaction costs
not only money but reputation.
By intercepting the fraud at a source,
AI prevents the loss before they occur.
Enhance security.
Traditional security systems
rely on static rules.
Can't keep up with evolving threats.
Adapt to algorithm.
Continuously learn and
adjust to the new threat.
New fraud tactics create creating
an intelligent and evolving shield.
Customers and business.
Feel confident knowing their data
and transactions are safeguarded.
24. 24 by seven.
Improved efficiency.
Manual fraud investigators
are labor intensive and slow.
By automating fraud detection workflow,
AI reduces the investigation times by 73%.
For an instance, if a finance, for a
financial institutions receiving hundreds
of fraud alerts daily, AI prioritize
the most critical cases and provide
investigators with actionable insights to
reduce them in minutes rather than days.
Enhance the customer experience.
Customers want security that
doesn't disrupt their experience.
Frictionless fraud Prevention operates
behind the scenes, allowing the
customers to use the transactions
confidently without interruption.
This approach has driven 90 percent
customer satisfaction rate, turning the
security into competitive advantage.
Data driven insights.
Fraud detection isn't just
about stopping threats, it's
also about learning from them.
Sophisticated analytics decodes, complex,
fraud patterns, providing actionable
intelligence to provide strategies.
AI identifies a recurring fraud
pattern tied to a specific geography,
allowing institutions to proactively
strengthen defenses in that area.
Challenges and considerations.
We have explored the incredible power and
benefits of AI in the fraud detection.
However, No transformative technology
comes without its challenges.
To maximize its potential, we must
recognize and address these hurdles.
Data quality and bias.
AI systems are only as good as
the data they are trained on.
Poor quality or biased data can
lead to inaccurate predictions.
A biased model might incorrectly
flag legitimate transactions from
certain demographics, creating
frustration and loss of trust.
Model explainability.
AI systems are often seen as a
black box, making it difficult to
explain how decisions are made.
Transparency is essential
for a stakeholder's trust,
from regulators to customers.
For an example, if a customer asks
why their transaction was flagged as
fraudulent, provide a clear explanation
building confidence in the system.
Moreover, incorporate explainable
AI techniques that provide clear
and understandable insights
into how decisions are made.
Regular Rhetoric Compliance As AI adoption
grows, so does the regulatory scrutiny.
Laws surrounding adoption Data
analytics, data privacy, ethics, and
algorithm fairness are evolving rapidly.
Noncompliance can lead to hefty
fines, reputational damage,
and operational setbacks.
Continuous learning and adaptability.
Fraud.
Fraud detection evolves constantly.
Static models quickly become absolute
in the face of emerging threats.
A system trained on past fraud patterns
may miss a new type of phishing,
scam, or synthetic detection attacks.
By leveraging continuous learning,
AI models stay agile, updating
themselves with real time data
to identify new fraud techniques.
Institutions must invest in ongoing
training and monitoring to ensure AI
remains effective and future proof.
Future of AI powered fraud detection
It looks, let's look ahead and explore
how AI will evolve to meet the growing
challenges of financial security.
The future is bright with
endless possibilities.
Imagine a world where fraud is intercepted
before it even reaches its customer,
where AI systems don't just reach,
react to the threats, but predicts and
prevent them with unparalleled precision.
This is The feature where we are building
advanced analytics.
The next wave of AI will harness the
quantum computing and deep learning
to develop hyper intelligent models
with unmatched predictive accuracy.
This means fraud will be spotted not just
in milliseconds, but even anticipated
before it occurs based on dynamic
patterns across millions of transactions.
Real time risk assessment.
AI driven risk, risk engines will
evaluate threats in real time, enabling
proactive decisions within milliseconds.
Reactive security will transform
into proactive defense systems,
reducing vulnerabilities and
losses to near zero levels.
Personalized security measures.
AI will craft in individual security
protocols tailored to each Customer's
unique behavioral patterns and
with their transactional history.
These dynamic measures will
enhance the trust and significantly
reduce the false positive.
Collaborative fraud prevention.
AI platforms will enable the secure and
decentralized network for institutions
to share their threat intelligence.
This collective effort will create a
powerful and adaptive defense ecosystem
that benefits the entire financial sector.
For an instance, a new type of
fraud detection in one institution
is immediately shared across the
network, preventing its spread.
Conclusion.
Let's bring everything together.
AI powered fraud detection
is not just a technique.
It's a transformation,
a way of doing things.
To build trust, protect assets, and
stay ahead of ever evolving threats.
With all this approach, there is a
97 percent accuracy rate in the real
time threat detection, 63 percent
reduction in the false positive,
and saving time and resources, and
73 percent faster investigation,
enabling quicker resolutions.
With AI Financial institutions can
move from reactive to proactive,
from static to dynamic, and from
traditional to transformative.
The result, a world where fraud
is no longer a growing threat,
but a manageable challenge.
Thank you all for your attention.
I hope you are excited about
the possibilities of AI powered
fraud detection as I am.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.