Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining me today.
I'm Aditya Singh, and I'm excited to
present a framework that's transforming
how we evaluate search and recommendation
systems in the next 15 to 20 minutes.
I'll show you why traditional
metrics are failing us, how we can do
better and the dramatic improvements
that we achieved in practice.
The challenge.
So let's start with the
fundamental question.
Why do we need to evolve
beyond traditional metrics?
Traditional metrics, engagement
metrics like CTR, conversion rate,
while valuable, fail to capture three
critical aspects of modern user behavior.
First, the position bias significantly
distorts our understanding.
Research shows that it can inflate CTR.
think about it, an item placed at the top
of page usually gets more attention, but
does that truly reflect its relevance?
Second, the users interact with
content in increasingly complex ways,
scrolling, hovering, partial views,
scrolling past and then coming back.
and these things are simply
missed by click measurements.
Third, with the rise of multimodal
content, videos, interactive elements,
rich media, we need metrics that
understand how different types of content
influence user attention and engagement.
Let's move next.
so let's look at why
traditional metrics fall short.
Take CTR as an example, while it provides
a baseline engagement metric, it fails to
account for three crucial context factors.
First, Algorithmic Ranking
Bias, where our own system's
decisions influence user behavior.
Second, Complex Interaction Patterns, how
users naturally navigate through content.
And third, the interplay between item
positioning and user selection behavior.
Our data shows these distortion
factors have significant impact.
Position based attention
decays varies by up to 30%.
Context item influence affects
engagement by 25 to 40%.
Temporal patterns cause metric
fluctuations by up to 42%,
and device context requires
adjustments of approximately 25%.
And these are just academic concerns.
they directly affect our ability
to optimize for user experience.
to address these challenges, We have,
developed three core mathematical models.
don't worry if you're not a math
person, I'll break this down to you
in, mathematical to practical terms.
But before we go there, traditional
metrics, as I was talking about,
if you just look at raw CTR, just
because something is in top position,
it will have a higher raw CTR.
But when used and conversion, actually.
But when you normalize that conversion,
given the fact that this thing was
shown at the top position, you find
out that the click through rates,
or engagement rates rather, aren't
too different from the baseline.
You can see the blue bar here,
the red bar being the raw CTR.
If of something on the left most
histogram, a bunch, you can see that the
red bar is basically the raw CTR observed
for something in the top position.
And because that thing was at the top
position, it's expected it will get some
engagement, but is that engagement coming
because it's a really engaging content or
because it was placed in that position?
So this type of, gap, which
exists in, the engagement metrics.
That we collect on our platforms can
lead us, can lead to skewed behavior
and also feedback loops in our system.
if something just directly shows up on
position one, it directly gets a boost.
And because of that boost, the model or
the systems or the feedback mechanism
that has been built, a learned mechanism
or a mind mechanism, whatever it is,
It can be confused as though why was
this popular and these systems help
us identify that the popularity or the
engagement is coming either from position
or from the context or due to the type
of content that we have, whether it
is because of the platform and so on.
So this is what we are dealing with.
As I said, we do have mathematical
models, that we can talk about.
and these, models basically
handle three different things,
three different independent
dimensions that we have identified.
first of all, it's our
position bias model.
And, it can be described as a very simple,
what do you call it, a probability model
in which we define the probability of a
click given at position i is defined as
by this relation where you can think of
beta i as an attention discount factor.
It tells how much we need to
adjust for an item's position.
So if something is in the top and if
it is relevant, then, give whatever
its relevance be, we discount its,
relevance by an attention discount
factor to truly know how relevant,
how engaging that content will be.
For instance, we found that position
five needs about 3x adjustment to
reflect the true engagement rate.
Second, the temporal decay function.
In this, we, in this formulation, we
capture how users attention diminishes
over time, but with an interesting twist.
Attention doesn't decay linearly.
We found that users have bursts of
renewed interest, especially when they
encounter highly relevant content.
then third, we come to our
cross item influence model.
this relation gives us or helps
us rather understand how an items
affect each other's performance.
For example, a compelling video
can boost engagement with related
text content by up to 40%.
But if that text didn't was not
accompanied by a video, an engaging video,
then it would hardly get any attention.
here we can look at the, user
attention decay analysis, something
that we have modeled and something
that is actually observed in data.
And you can see a lot of idiosyncrasies
or peculiarities rather that are observed
or that exists rather in a platform.
For example, if it's a mobile device and,
There are only, when it loads up, there
are only, three content views or three
things that you can display to the user.
the engagement rates or the impression
rates, rather impression count and
engagement rates further on for the
fourth item will be very different
from the engagement rates and metrics
observed for the first three items.
this is one sub system where the
fourth position was a little bit
different compared to the first three,
and you can see it repeats again
when it you go to position eight.
So these, idiosyncrasies or
peculiarities differ within a platform.
So for example, you can prick show
the same content on web in which
you have a larger real estate.
So you can show multiple
pieces of content.
on mobile device, the
real estate is limited.
You only show a few.
So even these presentation
differences, UI differences or
platform differences can affect how
the user interacts with your content.
Here, just to give a overview, the
relative attention score that you
see on the y axis is a normalized
measure, and it's combined by using the
viewport timing, that is how long was
the item visible, active engagements,
that is how many clicks and hovers
did the user do, and then, scroll
velocity near the time, near the item.
you can see, that the attention is
higher in the top three positions.
then there is some variance after that,
and then it stabilizes at some rate.
and you can see that it, if we
just predicted by our theoretical
model, there is some differences
in actual observed user behavior.
And this is what, essentially,
what we want to measure.
Ahem.
as we talked about, again, going, and
talking about a more comprehensive
framework for contextualized evaluation.
position bias needs to be corrected.
There are multiple ways of correcting it.
these are correction mechanisms.
The other one were modeling, mechanisms.
One more important thing that I would
like to talk about that we didn't cover
earlier was the viewport tracking method.
So things like, scrolled, depth
tracking, time for which the content
was visible and the attention score are
some things which are very crucial in
figuring out how users and are, spending
their attention currency, I would say.
for example, scroll depth tracking,
we measure just depth of how deep
the user engaged by just figuring
out, the viewport bottom and then
normalizing it by the page height.
Similarly, for visibility time,
we figured that time out just
by summing up the start time.
the difference in the end and
start time, and then summing up
over all the pieces of content.
And then the attention score is just
simply, active time, viewed time in
active time divided by the total time.
usual stuff, but these, go a long way,
for, measuring, what we are looking for.
the, what do you call it?
User attention analysis.
the, That's a good question.
So now let's dive into what we have
learned about user attention patterns and
the image that you see, displays how, and
what is this fascinating phenomena and
which challenges the conventional wisdom.
So for example, you would
expect something to be on.
that is ranked fourth to be more
engaging by default than rank five.
But if you have a presentation, a matrix,
like a tile like presentation, and if the
fourth item that you recommended, which
you think is more relevant than compared
to the fifth item, shows up all the way
to the right and to the top, compared
to the fifth item, which shows up just
below, the top ranked, content, you'll
see that the, in default engagement
rate, just because of the position
is higher for content, which is on
position five compared to, position four.
So observations are pretty evident.
the top positions receive three
to five times more attention.
there exists a left side
bias in horizontal layout.
Maybe it differs in places where content
or the language is read, or the script
is rather read from right to left.
In cases where the script is
read from left to right, there
might exist a left side bias.
If in the other cases, there
might be a right side bias.
then there is a significant drop in,
engagement, a drop off points in the UI.
So elements where, there are folds or
changes, then we see significant drop.
And also, there is huge difference
as I have talked earlier between,
attention patterns, for users,
using, mobile devices or desktops.
Desktops have a larger real estate.
mobile devices on the hand have
completely different interface and so on.
um, again, content quality and user
intent act as powerful moderating factors.
but still, position
bias can overpower them.
we, then there exists something called
a tension cliff where you can see, as
we have noted earlier, there is a drop
in, Attention or engagement at certain
positions, which is very peculiar to how
the content was presented to the users.
and also there exists some sort
of psychological threshold after
which users switch from, systematic
to an exploratory browsing mode.
that psychological threshold can
show up in something where a user
says, I've scrolled enough pages.
So that page itself becomes a unit of
attention, unit that got an attention, but
the other sub, subsequent pages do not.
For example, you might have seen that
the, Google searches also, they usually
almost no one navigates to position two.
if the content is getting engaged
on second page, and almost no one
definitely goes to page 3 or page
4, unless they're really looking
for something very specific.
that page, the Google result page 1, is
one such, or switching from one page to
another, can be one such attention cliff.
if the content is getting engaged on
second page, That attention or that
engagement could have, the rate could have
been much higher had that content been
shown at a relevant position in page one.
So there, there are these things that,
very peculiar to how the whole system is
orchestrated, how the platform exists,
why and how do users interact with it.
And it also depends between each user.
different users, different, interact
with things very differently.
different generations, interact
with content differently.
Min and deal generation, Gen
Z and all those, there are
very, significant differences.
Sounds good.
then, before we go, I just want to
figure, say that, you know, all this
starts with a data collection layer.
And it's our foundation.
All of these observations are founded
by an excellent data collection
layer, which is able to give us
things like, the viewport tracking.
A lot of people don't have it.
I would highly suggest that you have
very sophisticated viewport tracking
and you capture as many events as
possible within on your platform.
viewport tracking for precise
visibility measurement, interaction
events that show how users engage,
capture as many events as possible.
user data for contextual understanding.
So are we, saving the user journey, as
they are interacting with the content,
as they logged in their session, what
happened in their session, and so on.
And then content data to classify
different types of formats.
So for example, they logged in.
Your platform provides different types of
content that the user can interact with.
Let's say they interacted with, a video
content and then after that, two positions
after that, there is a text content.
So there are correlations, that
is, or rather observations that the
Engagement rates after an engaging
content has been shown, they can change
the engagement rates on subsequent
content, which gets shown to the
user depending on what format it is.
that's one thing.
then, I would say, let's dive deep
into, user attention analysis.
so we already talked about it.
but.
Before we go to format level
analysis, let me also talk about
how do we mitigate position bias.
There are multiple ways to do it.
We have already talked about
some models and metrics to
figure out the position bias.
now some other ones are, viewport
visibility patterns are analyzed, to
identify area of high user attention.
We already talked about it.
It requires, sophisticated,
what do you call it?
The logging, of all the
events happening on the UI.
Then scroll, rep, distribution
data is used to adjust item scores
based on relative likelihood.
these can be done, up, away from what
your traditional ranking does, or this
can be built into your ranking model.
that is how deep did the user interact
with your content or your platform and
all these models we have seen were done
when they can be done in very different
approaches, but when they are applied in
whatever format they are applied, they
do reduce position bias up to, up to 30%.
It can even be higher.
At least we have seen 30 percent and,
this can lead to an accurate measurement
of item relevance and performance.
removing the position bias.
let's go to, the next, type of
interaction, which can happen.
this interaction is
cross format interaction.
So moving to content format interactions,
our format interaction matrix
reveals some surprising patterns.
On the left hand side, you have, the
content which was shown first and on the
on the top most is the content that was
subsequently shown to the user and the
numbers aren't exactly what we have, what
I mean, I have seen on different platforms
because I, some things cannot be exactly
shared, but it looks something like this.
where, the, format of an item that has
been, shown to the user affects how the
user interacts with subsequent content.
videos emerge as the strongest
influence drivers, actually.
And now we have observed that the
video length, if it's a short form
video, Reels and TikTok and all
that stuff, that, creates, what
we call a tension halo effect.
They boost engagement with
neighboring content by 70 to 80
percent, but the timing is crucial.
the effect decays by about,
three or four positions.
So, people can use this sort of
information to build models in which,
we are, repeatedly, spiking the,
engagement that we get out of the user.
So interactive elements now,
elements in which user can
click, tap, zoom in or whatever.
these things, create what
we call engagement momentum.
So users who interact with one
interactive element are 75 percent
more likely to engage with others.
And this creates opportunity
for strategic content placement.
So think about it.
So if you're coming up with an ad
creative, then, strategically placed
and intelligently made, interactive
elements can just do wonders.
And perhaps the most surprisingly,
we discovered that complementary
format players like an infographic
showed by detailed text can boost
mutual engagement rate by up to 40%.
this isn't about just variety.
It's about creative, cognitive
synergies, by figuring out what
the user behavior, is doing.
let's look at the
implementation guidelines.
let's look at, concrete results.
our viewport aware scoring system has
transformed how we measure engagement
and delivered three CRE improvements.
First, precision in Attention measurement
are tracking systems capture micro second
level visibility data, revealing users
making crucial engagement decisions
as in as little as 300 milliseconds.
Second, we also account for what we
call engagement windows, optimal periods
when the users are most repetitive
to create, to certain content types.
For example, video content performs
35 percent better when presented
after text based engagement.
And third, by combining these insights
into our mathematical models, we have,
achieved a 28 percent increase in
optimization success, in optimizing
for success rates across different
platforms and content types.
The, I mean, the accounting for
creative formats, the cross format
interaction strength is really strong.
repeating what I just said earlier, but
the framework that we have estimates
how would the strength, what is the
actual strength and then based on that,
we can optimize of how to use that
strength and create these synergies
that I was referring to earlier.
temporal retention decay is modeled
to capture diminishing effects of user
attention over time, particularly in the
long term, and these insights inform the
evaluation process leading to significant
improvement in optimization decisions.
Thank you.
As I just, defined, and this is also
something that we, I just covered.
we need viewport tracking and precise
tracking, session level dynamics
of how users are interacting with
the platform within each session.
And then, we, the metric that we figure
out that, we are measuring how accurate
is that measurement and where is that
measurement actually coming from.
all of this depends on
good data collection.
as I said, capturing real world viewport
visibility data, spatial temporal
interaction mapping, and finally
controlled experiments in which users
are exposed to certain combinations,
certain UI elements or, certain, content,
types or pairs or combinations are some
things, how through which we can learn
more and then optimize our system better.
real world impact of this
framework has been substantial.
Let me share three key metrics
that demonstrate its value.
The prediction reliability
has now improved.
By 35%.
In practical terms, this means we are
significantly better at forecasting which
content will resonate with the user.
For content team, it translates to
more efficient resource allocation
and better editorial decisions.
Our optimization success
rate has increased by 28%.
Teams using this framework are more
informed, at decision making about
content placement and format selection.
One team introduced A B testing, reduced
their A B testing cycle time by 40
percent by achieving better results.
More importantly, these aren't
just metric improvements.
We are seeing tangible user experience
enhancements and with 15 percent increase
in session depth and a 23 percent
improvement in content discovery.
let's go to the next slide.
So looking ahead, we are exploring
four exciting directions that we'll
be, further enhance this framework.
I see I have only listed three
here, but, let me go through them.
First is, we use advanced ML models.
then, so that sort of works for us
by doing personalized normalization,
because we are going to learn a user
profile and how that user particularly
interacts with our, platform.
Then we do multi modal evaluation.
We are expanding our framework to handle
emerging formats like in augmented
reality and interactive visualizations.
this includes development of
new metrics specifically for
immersive content experiences.
And, the other thing is a real
time adaptation of framework
by evolving user behavior.
And this, is, done by the next generation
of models, which will adjust by it with
online training that is happening all
the time, based on how the users are
now interacting with the, platform.
And think of it as adaptive
normalization system.
I think, there can be another
thing in which we are doing
privacy first analytics.
whatever we are learning, we, can
do it in a federated way such that
the user privacy is preserved.
we do learn how the user
interacts, but we do it in a way
that is very privacy preserving.
key takeaways.
Okay.
as we conclude, I want to
emphasize three critical points.
First, the context matters more than ever.
Traditional metrics alone
cannot capture the complexity
of modern user interactions.
Our frameworks provide necessary context
to make meaningful optimization decisions.
Second, normalization and correction
aren't just technical necessities.
They are fundamental to understanding
true content performance in today's
multi format, multi device world.
Finally, data driven insights,
when properly contextualized,
lead to significantly better
optimization decisions.
We have seen this across
different platforms, content
types, and user segments.
So these three takeaways, these are
some advanced metric components.
You guys can take a look.
I have added them to the slides.
feel free.
ping me with any questions.
This is the implementation architecture.
pretty standard.
you guys can go through it and,
it, it's, it has everything
that I've already talked about.
Um, The slide is attached in the
future ML directions, I would say, the
future direction is advanced ML models.
As I said, we went through real time
adaptation, multimodal enhancement,
and privacy first analytics.
with this, I would say thank you.
Thank you for your attention.
I look forward to your questions and
discussing how these approaches might
benefit you in your specific use cases.
Thank you.