Good morning team and good morning all.
Hello, this is Gopi and today we are
discussing about and I'm going to
give a presentation on SAP BW system
to migrate to AWS cloud and that
AWS cloud, the transformation with
enhanced performance and scalability.
So basically this presentation
outlines a comprehensive strategy
for migrating SAP BW system to AWS.
Leveraging data driven insight
and proven best practices to
achieve enhanced performance,
scalability, and cost efficiency.
This session offers actionable insights,
including a real world example and
data driven results, empowering
organizations to confidently embark
on their cloud migration journey.
So what is the understanding our last A
PBW landscape data volume and complexity,
as well as dependencies and integration?
First, we are going to talk about conduct
a comprehensive assessment of our SAP
data ecosystem and S-A-P-B-W ecosystem.
Evaluating inate data volumes that
frequently span for terabyte two petabyte
and critical analysis helps identify the
precise cloud infrastructure requirements.
To support our organization's
complex data management needs.
The second option is
dependencies and integration.
Meticulously document and analyze
dependencies across our SAP BW system.
Include, including interstate connections
with ERP platforms, diverse data
sources, and enterprise reporting tools.
This holistic mapping ensures a
static, strategic, frictionless
migration and integration within
the AWS Cloud environment.
So leveraging AWS for a seamless
migration, AWS Migration Hub,
and second option is AWS Server
Migration Service, that is AWS SMS,
and the third option is AWS Database
Migration Service, like AWS DMS.
So first, when we, so we are, if we
are going to first option or just
rush our entire migration strategy
through AWS Migration Hub, offering a
unified platform that provide a real
time visibility, tracks, progress
and enable cross team collaboration
for a streamlined transformation.
If I go with AWS Server Managed Migration
Service, Automatic and accelerate your
server migrate with AWS Server Migration
Service, reducing a manual intervention,
minimizing potential downtime, and
ensuring a smooth risk migrated
transition to the cloud infrastructure.
The third one is AWS Data
Migration Service, AWS DMS.
Execute a precision driven database
migration using AWS Database
Migration Service, enabling zero
downtime replication, data integrity
presentation, and seamless transformation
of our SAP database ecosystem.
optimizing the data transfer
for a large data sets.
If you're using image
and S3 for data storage.
Or AWS data direct connect
high speed transfers.
So if I go with the S3 data storage
utilize image and S3 advanced object
storage architecture to securely host SAP
BW data sets Providing petabyte two scale,
scale storage with 99.9999% of durability,
automating data replication, and storage
options for optimal cost management.
If you go with AWS Direct connect
for it, high speed transformation.
Implement AWS Direct Connect to
establish a private dedicated network
connection with a consistent 1 2 10 gb.
BS bandwidth, enabling encrypted low
latency data migration and reducing
network complexity compared to
traditional internet based transfers.
enhancing performance
in the AWS environment.
Imagine EWS.
leveraging, leverage provisional IOPS
EBS volumes to deliver high performance
and low latency BW workloads, ensuring
constant IO performance and rapid data
retrieval for complex analytical process.
Optimized EC2 instance.
Strategically select a memory optimized
or computer optimized EC2 instance
that align precisely with our SAP VW
concept, computationally complexity,
enabling scalable performance and
cost efficient resource allocation.
Ensuring scalability and reliability.
What is the high performance
infrastructure or dynamic
resource optimization?
What is a high performance infrastructure?
Generally, if big systems like SAP
VW systems, we are going to use X
large EC2 instance strategically
designated to accelerate complex SAP
VW analytical workloads, delivering
a robust processing capabilities
and expensive memory resources.
for sophisticated data queries.
If we go with the dynamic resource
optimization, deploy AWS autoscaling to
intelligently and automatically modulate
EC2 instance capacity in real time,
dynamically reporting to fluctuating
workloads demand while maintaining
peak performance and cost efficiency.
Optimizing SAP BW for cloud performance,
cloud specific configuration,
tune your SAP BW parameters.
For cloud specific configurations,
taking advantage of AWS services
for features to enhance performance
and reduce resource consumption.
Second one is query optimization.
Optimize our query SAP BW queries to
minimize processing time and improve
response times, ensuring efficient
data retrieval and analysis purpose.
Cost reduction.
Optimize our AWS resource.
the first one is, performance testing,
the second one is, utilization to
reduce overall cost, leveraging
cost effective EC2 instance, and
storage option to minimize expense.
Regardless, post migration testing.
Once the migration is complete,
then we are going to do that
different type of testing.
The first one is functional testing,
second one is performance testing,
third one is, Security testing.
Generally, the functional testing
functional team will validate the core
functionalities such as a data loading,
reporting and data analysis operated
as expected in the AWS environment.
Also, once the functional testing
completed, we are going to
deal with performance testing.
Generally, the performance,
like the SAP BW system, in any
organization, it's a high system,
high volume, high resources system.
Once the migrating completely, we are
going to do that performance testing
in AWS environment, perform performance
tester under various load scenarios
to ensure That the migrating system
can handle with anticipated workload
demands the final security testing.
So generally SAP BW system and
ERP system, any ERP system is
going for audit for that purpose.
Various security of our migrated SAP BW
system in the AWS environment and ensuring
data integrity and confidentiality.
Embracing the power of AWS for SAP BW,
enhance its scalability, leverage us.
AWS elastic infrastructure to scale
our S-A-P-B-W system up and down,
based on our changing analytical needs.
Ensure optimal resource allocation,
increased performance, utilize
the AWS High Performance Computing
resources and optimize slower
resolution to significantly improve
the performance of S-A-P-B-W system.
Register the cost benefit from AWS.
Cost effective price models and
optimized resource utilization to
achieve significant cost saving
compared to on premises environment.
Sorry, key takeaways
and actionable insights.
The first one is strategic planning.
The second one is leverage
AWS services, and the third
one is focused on performance.
If you go with first one, the
strategic performance, a well
defined migrating strategy is
crucial for success, encompassing
through assessment, data transfer,
optimization, and performance tuning.
Leverage of AWS services.
Embrace AWS services like Migration Hub,
DMS, and S3 to streamline the migration
process and ensure data integrity.
This leverage AWS service we already
discussed in the previous slides.
Focus on performance like optimize
SAP BW system for cloud performance
by implementing cloud specific
configurations and leveraging
high performance EC2 instance.
The next step, embarking
on our cloud journey.
This presentation has provided a
comprehensive overview of the next
gen SAP BW migrating strategies.
To take in the next steps, schedule
a consultation with our team to
discuss your specific requirements
and develop customized plans for
smooth and successful transactions.
Thank you for your time.
Thank you.
Have a nice day.