Hello everyone, my name is Vamsi Upaduri
and I work as a senior statistical
programmer at Gilead Science.
Today I'll talk about the role of
statistical programming in accelerating
clinical drug development process.
Did you know that it can take
anywhere between 5 to 10 years and
millions of dollars to bring a drug
from discovery stage to market?
Today I'll discuss how statistical
programming Place a critical role in
accelerating this process, transforming
the raw data into actionable insights to
evaluate the drug safety and efficacy.
With growing complexities in clinical
trial designs, increased data
volumes, and stringent regulatory
requirements from agencies like FDA
and EMEA, The robust statistical
programming has become essential.
We'll explore its impact at every stage,
from managing and analyzing data, to
ensuring regulatory compliance, ultimately
leading to faster and more effective
treatments to improve patient outcomes.
Let's explore the evolution of
tools in statistical programming
and how they have transformed
clinical data analysis over time.
SAS laid the foundation as a gold standard
with validated procedures, robust audit
trials, and comprehensive documentation
to ensure regulatory compliance.
R introduced flexibility and innovation,
providing advanced statistical modeling,
high quality data visualizations,
and collaborative ecosystem of user
contributed packages, making it
ideal for an exploratory analysis.
Python revolutionized the field
with its integration of machine
learning, automated workflows, and
powerful data processing tools.
to support the real
world evidence analysis.
Together, these tools help
programmers to address the increasing
complexity of clinical trials
with precision and adaptability.
Clinical programming plays a key role.
critical role in providing data analysis
across all phases of clinical trials.
In phase one, it analyzes the
safety data, identifies any
adverse events, and determines
the dose tolerability of a drug.
Phase two, focus on assessing the
safety and preliminary efficiency,
efficacy in a small population.
While phase 3 evaluates the
safety and confirms the efficacy
in large patient groups.
In phase 4, statistical programming
team monitors long term safety
and real world effectiveness.
by integrating real world data
and detecting any safety signals.
Comprehensive statistical data analysis
ensures reliable trial outcomes by
evaluating the safety and efficacy.
And furthermore, The regulatory
standards are upheld by developing the
STDM and ADaM datasets based on the
CD standards and generating TLFs as
per the Statistical Analysis Plan to
ensure the data traceability, integrity,
and seamless regulatory submissions.
Statistical programming often bridges
the gap between the protocol and data
analysis by converting the complex
protocol into precise programming
specifications, ensuring the accurate
implementation of study endpoints.
and analysis methods.
Adaptive trial design leverage advanced
algorithms for dynamic sample size
calculations and treatment allocations
enabling responsive trial modifications
based on the accumulated data.
Automated systems for safety monitoring
enables continuous surveillance tracking
adverse events and conducting risk
benefit assessments with statistical
outputs by data monitoring committee.
Finally, a predefined interim analysis
will be performed to review the validated
outputs generated by a statistical
programmer to make evidence based
decisions to make sure the trial,
continuation or modification or a
decision to early terminate the study.
Regulatory compliance is the cornerstone
of any clinical data submissions,
and standardized datasets play
a critical role in this process.
STDM and ADaM datasets are developed
and validated to meet the stringent
FDA and EMA requirements by following
the CD standards, implementation
guidelines, and therapeutic area
specific guidance documents.
For example, the requirements can
vary between significantly between
the oncology and virology studies.
Adhering to these guidelines
ensure alignment with
evolving industry standards.
Comprehensive submission
documents such as DEFINE.
XML, STDM Data Reviewer's Guide, Analysis
Data Reviewer's Guide, facilitates a
thorough submission regulatory assessment.
Additionally, leveraging validation tools
like PNaCl 21 enables conformance checks.
And ensure data integrity,
minimize risk and delays
throughout the submission process.
As clinical trial grows more complex,
leveraging innovative technologies is
essential for efficiency and accuracy.
AI and machine learning revolutionized
trials by automating the data
cleaning process, reducing manual
errors, and using its predictive
models to optimize the outcomes like
forecasting patient enrollment and
identifying any patient reports.
Cloud based platforms enables seamless
global collaboration with secure, scalable
infrastructure, supporting the real time
data processing and integrated version
control systems to prevent delays.
Additionally, an interactive
and dynamic visualization tools.
create dashboards for data safety
monitoring reviews, DSMB, to improve the
regulatory submissions with graphs, which
enhances stakeholders communication.
Together, these advancements
streamline the trial processes.
and enable faster and more
informed decision making.
Let's look at two
contrasting case studies.
One demonstrating the success of
statistical programming during the
rapid development of COVID 19 vaccines.
And the other highlighting the
challenges in the regulatory compliance
phase during an oncology trial.
Together, these examples show the
critical, the statistical programming
role place in the clinical trials.
The COVID 19 vaccine development
showcased how advanced statistical
programming can transform the clinical
trials using sophisticated adaptive trial
designs and real time data analysis.
researchers were able to reduce the
development timelines by significantly
80 percent enabling simultaneous
phase 2 and phase 3 trials.
Rolling regulatory submissions
further accelerated this process,
submitting a new, setting a new
benchmark for its efficiency.
On the other hand, a pharmaceutical
company faced a significant
challenge with its oncology trial.
A six month submission delay
occurred due to clinical CDISC
failures, CDISC compliance failures.
including inconsistencies in derived
variables and missing documentations.
This highlights the critical importance
of robust statistical programming
and stringent quality control to
ensure smooth regulatory submissions.
As clinical trials grow more complex,
Adopting best practices in statistical
programming is essential to ensure
efficiency, accuracy, and compliance.
Successful programming involves
integration of expertise from protocol
development all the way to the submission,
establishing series compliance templates,
And automated workflows for process
standardization, performing systematic
data validations at every milestone to
maintain quality assurance and investing
in continuous training to stay up to
date with the regulatory standards and
leveraging cutting edge tools like AI
to enhance the efficiency and accuracy.
Together, these practices.
form a comprehensive framework that drives
the success in drug development process.
The future of statistical programming
is defined by four key directions.
First, integrating real world evidence
data using AI powered analytics
enables the seamless inclusion of
data from electronic health records,
insurance claims, and patient
registries, providing deep insights
into clinical treatment outcomes.
Thank you.
Second, the decentralized trials are
becoming increasingly important, relying
on robust systems to validate and analyze
real time patient reported outcomes from
its wearable device data, making clinical
research more accessible and flexible.
Third, adopting open source tools like.
R and Python fosters collaboration and
innovation while maintaining strict
regulatory compliance and validation
standards to ensure high quality outputs.
Finally, traceability is critical with
automated documentation and versioned
environments ensuring that all the
analyses are transparent, replicable,
and ready for regulatory review.
As the landscape of clinical trials
evolves, regulatory bodies like FDA are
modernizing clinical trial processes by
introducing innovative frameworks for
complex trial design and master protocols.
They are also developing comprehensive
guidelines to integrate real world
evidence with a focus of deep quality
and validation and to establish standards
for validating AI and machine learning
algorithms to ensure transparency,
reproducibility, and support for
advanced analytics in clinical research.
As we look ahead to the future of
clinical drug development, statistical
programming remains a driving force
for innovation and efficiency.
By continually evolving to meet new
challenges and adopting advanced
technologies, the field ensures
faster, more cost effective trials.
Collaboration between programmers,
researchers and regulators will be
essential to overcome the complexities
paving the way for improved patient
outcomes and the need to deliver the
life saving treatments worldwide.
Thank you for attending the talk.