Hello, everyone.
My name is Lourduma Reddy,
Tirmala Reddy, and I'm a senior
SAP consultant specializing in
SAP basis and HANA administration
with over 17 years of experience.
I'm excited to welcome
you all to this session.
Today, I will be talking about how
to achieve zero downtime SAP HANA
database using high availability
with pacemaker cluster setup.
In today's digital economy, where
system outages can cost enterprises
millions of dollars per hour.
Implementing robust high availability and
disaster recovery solutions for SAP HANA
in database has become mission critical.
This presentation delivers an in
depth exploration of architecting zero
downtime SAP HANA environments using
pacemaker cluster with a specific
focus on performance optimized
scale up and scale out systems
replication configurations that achieve
Subminute recovery time objectives.
In this side, we'll see, about three
pillars of SAP HANA high availability.
The first one is fault tolerance.
Guaranteeing continuous operations through
system replication and seamless failover.
Minimizing downtime and
preventing data integrity.
Second one is disaster recovery,
protecting against catastrophic
events with geographically dispersed
data centers and rapid recovery
strategies for business continuity.
The third one is tenant duplication.
Managing multiple SAP HANA tenants,
also called instances, with independent
failover capabilities, enabling targeted
recovery and resource optimization.
Here we can see how to achieve
uptime up to 99 percent with advanced
features like the first one is system
replication, ensuring high availability
by maintaining a synchronized secondary
instance ready to take over in
case of a primary instance failure.
This technique guarantees minimal
downtime and maintains data consistency.
Second one is active configurations.
Maximizing system utilization by allowing
read only access to the second instance.
This approach provides a performance
boost and improves resource allocation
while maintaining high availability.
Third one is time travel capabilities.
Recovering from data corruption or
accidental changes by leveraging SAP
HANA's time travel functionality.
This powerful feature enables rollback
to previous point in time, protecting
time integrity and ensuring resilience.
Here we see some real
world success stories.
And the testing frameworks
prevented data loss.
Discover how rigorous testing of
HA cluster identified and mitigated
potential data loss incidents during plan
maintenance, ensuring business continuity
and protecting critical information.
Next one is comprehensive
testing framework.
Learn about the comprehensive
testing framework covering various
scenarios including graceful failover,
primary secondary node rashes.
and maintenance windows,
ensuring the robustness and
reliability of your HA solution.
Here we see how to achieve maximum
performance using strategy,
scale up and scale out system
replication architectures.
First one is intelligent resource
allocation, leverage advanced SAP HANA
configurations that dynamically allocate
up to 90 percent of no resources.
like CPU or memory, optimizing
computational efficiency and eliminating
potential performance bottlenecks.
The second one is seamless
failover strategies.
Implement preloaded secondary instances
with sophisticated synchronization
mechanisms, achieving sub minute
failover times and guaranteeing
near zero operational interruption
during critical system events.
Here we will see how can we leverage
active read enabled configurations.
Dynamic read distribution.
Intelligently distribute read only
transactions across synchronized
HANA instances, minimizing
primary stress load and improving
overall system responsiveness.
Next one is linear performance scaling.
Unlock up to 100 percent additional
computational capacity by enabling
parallel read workloads across
primary and secondary nodes without
compromising data consistency.
Here we'll see how to implement
foolproof takeover decision frameworks.
The first one is conduct comprehensive
node health assessments using
multidimensional metrics Such as
analyze system performance, memory
utilization, network connectivity, and
real time response times to create a
holistic view of cluster node status.
The second one is implement SAP
note 2063657 best practices.
Integrate SAP's official guidance for
configuring precise failover thresholds,
defining weighted decision metrics and
establishing automatic recovery protocols.
The last one is design adaptive
failover strategies with
intelligent resource management.
Create dynamic decision frameworks.
that prioritizes workload continuity,
minimizes potential data loss, and
optimizes computational resource
allocation during node transitions.
Here we see how can you architect
for scalability and future growth
of high availability solution.
The first one is predictive scaling.
Anticipate future growth and design your
HA solution with scalability in mind,
ensuring seamless expansion and adoption
as your business demands increase.
The second one is modular design.
Build a modular architecture allowing for
incremental scaling and easy adoption of
new components as your system expands.
Maintaining flexibility and adaptability.
The third one is automated provisioning.
Embrace automated provisioning
tools to simplify infrastructure
management and enable rapid scaling.
Ensuring agility and responsiveness
in a constantly evolving environment.
Here, these are one of the
most important recommendations.
How to secure your high
availability architecture.
The first one is access control.
Implement strict access control
measurements to restrict unauthorized
access to your HA infrastructure.
Protecting critical
systems and sensitive data.
Next one is data encryption.
Ensure data confidentiality and
integrity through encryption,
at rest and in transit.
Safeguarding sensitive information
from potential breaches.
The third one is regular security audits.
Conduct regular security audits
to identify vulnerabilities.
And implement necessary security
updates, ensuring the ongoing
protection of your HA architecture.
Here we see, how to monitor and maintain
the HA solution for optimal performance.
Real time monitoring.
Deploy advanced monitoring solutions like
Prometheus and Gafana to continuously
track critical performance metrics.
Such as CP, utilization, memory
consumption, network latency,
and system response times.
The next one is proactive maintenance.
Develop your comprehensive risk
based maintenance strategy.
That includes automated patch management,
require system health assessments,
performance tuning, and schedule
infrastructure reviews Here, we'll go
through some key takeaways and next steps.
By leveraging pacemaker cluster and
implementing best practices for system
replication, active configurations,
and robust failover mechanism, you
can achieve a true zero downtime
SAP HANA environment, maximizing
system availability and resilience.
Remember to prioritize testing,
security, and ongoing monitoring
to maintain optimal performance
And ensure the long term success
of your high availability solution.
Thank you again for joining this session.
Have a great day.