Hello.
So today I will go with AI
healthcare in transforming patient
care through predictive analytics.
The global healthcare AI market
valuation has reached to 15.
1 billion.
This presentation explored the
integration of artificial intelligence
in healthcare systems, focusing
on implementing the strategies and
outcomes, specifically across diagnostic
enhancements and treatment optimization.
We will delve into the technical
architecture, data management,
and predictive health capabilities
of AI in healthcare, while also
addressing critical implementation
challenges and ethical considerations.
AI driven diagnosis enhancements have,
we can categorize into two parts,
increased accuracy and reduced cost.
Advanced machine learning algorithms
have demonstrated exceptional diagnostic
precision with AI power system achieving
sensitivity rates between 87 to 98.
3 percent across the diverse medical
specialties, significantly outperforming
the traditional diagnostic methodologies.
The other category is reduced cost.
Natural language processing and AI
technologies have proven transformative
in healthcare administration,
enabling hospitals to streamline
operational Process and reduce
administrative expenditures by up to 3.
8 million annually, while
simultaneously enhancing overall
healthcare delivery and efficiency.
The predictive analytics have the
main another goal is identifying
the high risk patients in advance.
we can categorize these into two parts.
The first one is predictive modeling.
In the predictive modeling, advanced
predictive analytics model leverages
machine learning to precisely
identify the high risk patients with
an impressive of almost close to 90
percent of accuracy, enabling healthcare
providers to implement the targeted
and preemptive care strategies.
Next slide, please.
The other category falls under this
year is reduced readmissions by
intelligently analyzing the patient data.
These innovations models have
successfully reduced hospitalized
readmission rates by 28%.
Significantly improve the patient
outcomes and streamline the
healthcare resource allocation.
The next category is we're talking
about processing medical data.
So we can While processing the data
we can how we are how the data volume
and how the data is accurate Once
while coming to the data volume the
contemporary healthcare infrastructure
process and Intra 200 structured and
unstructured medical data points per
patient, generating a massive of 1.
5 petabytes of comprehensive
medical information annually.
Sustaining a rigorous 99.
2 percent data accuracy rate, mission
critical of ensuring the reliability of AI
algorithms and safeguarding the patient's
safety in an aesthetic, sophisticated,
multi layered data management system.
The another important thing is for
the while generating these models
that AI algorithms are processing
the medical images predictions is the
one of the very important category.
This is the revolution category.
One of the revolution categories,
image processing, conventional neural
networks analyzes 400, 000 medical
images, leveraging advanced deep
learning techniques to detect the Subtle
pathological abnormalities with 95.
8 percent diagnostic accuracy.
Dramatically accelerating
the clinical assessment and
early disease identification.
Outcome prediction.
Sophisticated gradient boosting.
assembles models, integrate
complex patient data to predict
clinical outcomes up to 93.
4 percent precision, enabling clinical
clinics to develop the personalized
treatment strategies and practically
manage their potential health risks.
Implementation of challenges.
So for this category, I would
like to say around Two categories
I can say one is the data breach
and AI protocol vulnerabilities.
So coming to the data breach,
healthcare data breaches have escalated
dramatically with a struggling 37.
2 percent annual increase, exposing
critical patient information and
undermining trust in digital health.
At the same time, AI protocol
vulnerabilities are Alarmingly, 74
percent of healthcare organizations face
significant of AI protocol weakness,
demanding urgent implementation of
comprehensive security framework and
strengthening the ethical safeguard.
Ethical implementation of accuracy,
disparity, and transparency is one of the,
categories in the ethical implications.
The first one is, we'll go
with the accuracy disparities.
AI diagnostic algorithm demonstrates
significant demographic Variability
with accuracy rates flanging up
to 34 percent across the different
population segments, revealing critical
system biases that could compromise
equitability healthcare delivery.
Transparency and trust.
A mere 38 percent of healthcare
providers report feeling adequately
prepared to articulate the reasoning
behind aid driven medical decisions.
Understanding the urgent need for an
interpretable and accountable artificial
intelligence system in clinical settings.
So we can divide the whole, future
of healthcare into two parts.
So we can go with precision medicine
and predictive analytics and patienting.
These three topics we have already
discussed in the previous slide.
So we just categorized
in a pyramid of triangle.
While we go with the precision of
medicine, so trial ring treatment
to individual genetic profile
and clinical data or targeted
therapeutic interventions.
Predictive analytics, leveraging
machine learning to forecast disease
progression, potential health
risk, and unprecedented accuracy.
The last one is the patient engagement.
Empowering the patients through
personalized health insights,
real time monitoring, and
proactive wellness strategy.
The future of AI healthcare transcends
traditional medical paradigms Promising
hyper personalized care plans, predictive
early disease detection, and dynamically
optimized treatment outcomes as AI
technologies continuously evolve.
Key takeaways.
I would like to consider that these,
I consider into three parts like
Potential A, Potential Implementation
Challenge and Collaborative Approaches.
While we go with the A, Potential
A represents a transformative
force in healthcare capable of
dramatically enhancing diagnostic
patient, personalizing treatment
protocols and significantly improving
the patient care outcomes through
advanced predictive analysis.
Successfully integrated AI requires
comprehensive strategies, addressing
complex data security risks, resolving
ethical dilemmas, and ensuring
algorithm transparency to maintain
patient trust and healthcare integrity.
The final one is like
collaborative approach.
Full potential demand strategy
collaboration among the healthcare
professionals, technological
innovators, and regulatory experts
to develop responsible, adaptive,
and patient centric ecosystems.
Next steps of embracing
AI and better future.
Develop strategic AI infrastructure
by allocating dedicated resource and
recruiting specialized talent to design,
implement, and continuously improve
the AI driven healthcare solution.
Create comprehensive software security and
ethical framework that ensure the patient
data protection, algorithms, algorithmic
transparency, and adherence to the highest
standards of medical AI governance.
Foster AI driven healthcare.
Interdisciplinary collaborations through
structured knowledge sharing platforms,
connecting to healthcare providers,
AI researchers and technologists, and
policy makers accelerate innovative
and responsible AI integration.
The last one is launch comprehensive
patient education initiatives that
demystify AI technologies, demonstrate
tangible benefits, and build trust
through transparent communication and
interactive engagement strategies.
Embracing AI transformative healthcare
future, all transcend mere two
technologies innovation its revolutionary
approach to the patient care.
By strategically deploying predictive
analytics and intelligent treatment
protocols, we are reimagining
healthcare as a proactive personalized
and ecosystem that anticipate in
this individual health trajectories.
Mitigates diagnostic.
Uncertainty, uncertainties and
deliver precision medicine tailored
and unique genetic landscapes and
comprehensive health narratives.
Our mission is harness as an empowering
collaborative tool that amplifies
healthcare professional capabilities.
Dramatically improves the patient
outcomes and construct a more
equitable, intelligent and
compensate the medical future.
This is all about the today demonstration.
Thank you very much.