Hello everyone.
Welcome and thank you
for joining me today.
I'm excited to take you through
how Python and AI can enhance
test automation and security for
quality driven DevSecOps approach.
Before we dive in, let me give a
quick introduction about myself.
I'm Sriman Yaram, senior software
engineering manager in test at
Coupa Software with over 19 plus
years of experience in distributed
systems, microservices, and
quality engineering practices.
I have worked across industries
like FinTech, SaaS, and enterprise
products, delivering high scalable
and resilient products used by Fortune
500 companies, with several products
recognized as industry leaders and
best in its class by research firms
like Forster, Gartner, and IDC.
Outside the work, I enjoy mentoring
and sharing knowledge with a
tech community, staying ahead
in evolving software landscape.
I explore AI, AI's impact on the ever
changing, software industry, landscape.
Before we dive in, here is a disclaimer.
I would like to clarify that views
and contents shared today are
entirely my own and does not reflect
those of my employers or, employer.
or any, affiliated organization.
The code samples provided are
demonstration purpose only and may
not be fully functional serving to
illustrate, concepts rather than, rather
than being a production ready code.
Okay, before we dive in, again,
quick agenda, introduction
to, Dev, DevOps and DevSecOps.
in this one, we'll try to focus on
understanding DevSecOps, its importance
and differences from Dev, DevOps.
Then we'll go into role
of Python in Dev, DevOps.
Python automates security tasks and
integrates into CI, CD pipelines.
then we will roll into leveraging
AI in DevSecOps, AI enhanced
security with automated threat
detection and proactive insights.
Then we'll go into tool based approach.
And I tried mapping, this, tools,
in a DevSecOps, phase, right
from the, development phase.
So we divide the tools into dev phase.
What are the tools that we can use,
code review phase, build phase,
deployment phase, production ready phase.
And how these tools can be
effectively implemented as well.
Then we will, go into some of
the best practices, practical
tips, for gradual adoption and
focusing on high impact areas.
While I mentioned many times in the
slides that CICD very frequently,
in, in, in upcoming slides.
But for this demo, our focus is on
showing the key open source tool.
These tools can be seamlessly integrated
into CICD pipelines for GitHub actions
or for automated security testing.
Interaction.
So DevOps.
DevOps transforms software
development by focusing on speed,
collaboration, and automation.
However, security often takes
backseat, leading to vulnerabilities.
Now, that's where, this, what, DevOps,
DevSecOps comes into the picture.
DevSecOps builds on DevOps by
embedding security from day one.
Right from the development phase itself,
making it as a continuous, development.
And it's a shared responsibility across
development operations and security team.
Why shift to DevSecOps?
Cyber, attacks are becoming, more
sophisticated and very frequent.
Compliances like GDPR, SOC, HIPAA
requires proactive security measures.
A breach can, result in, several
financial and, reputational damage.
DevSecOps helps us to detect
the vulnerabilities right in the
development phase itself and prevent
security gaps before they escalate.
On this slide, my key takeaways
are DevOps focused on speed.
DevSecOps ensures speed with
security, preventing costly
mistakes and costly mistakes to
be avoided as early as possible.
While we are ensuring the
compliances from the start as well.
Let's quickly see the role
of Python in DevSecOps.
As we know, Python is
one powerful language.
Python is a game changer in DevSecOps.
Python is a top choice for security
automation because of its simplicity,
flexibility, rich echo system.
Rich echo library systems, while
other languages can do similar, tasks,
Python stands out of it's easy of use
and fast deployment, making security
automation accessible to everyone.
I would like to highlight where Python,
really helps vulnerability scanners.
Detecting flaws early with
the tools like Safety, Bandit,
Dependabot, Trufflehawk, GitLinks.
There are a lot of tools
which are available.
AI based security solutions.
Python strengthens in AI, ML. Helps
to build smarter threat detection and
more models faster than any other.
Another, good thing, threat detection.
it analyzes the logs, real time
logs to catch suspicious activities
before they became bigger issues.
While, the other things which I
would like to highlight in Python
as well, it's easy to learn and use.
for even for non security
professionals or for any other
programming language experts as well.
Works well with popular
security and DevOps tools.
Large community support.
We have large community support
and ready to use libraries with,
which makes automation much easier.
Again, key takeaway.
Python makes DevSecOps practical and
efficient by simplifying security
automations and enabling teams to
focus on building secure applications
without extra complexities.
Now comes why role of AI
in security and DevSecOps.
Why AI in security?
It's a provoking question, right?
What are the key benefits we are getting?
How does it contributes to DevSecOps?
Yeah, security techs are
getting smarter and faster.
AI help us to stay ahead by Predicting,
predicting potential risk by analyzing
the patterns, just assume just like
a weather app forecast, be forecast
storms and weather conditions based
on the day, based on the past data.
Detecting suspicious
activity in real time.
Think like of a home security
system that alerts you when
it detects unusual moments.
respond, instantly stop threats
from spreading like an automatic
sprinkler system that puts out
a fire before it gets worse.
Again, if we go back to the second
question, the second provoking
question, what are the key
benefits that we are going to get?
Automated Threat Scanning.
AI can scan a huge amount of data quickly.
Like a spam filter that sorts through
emails to catch phishing attempts.
Intelligent Code Analysis.
It not only spots security flaws,
but also suggests fixes just
like a grammar checker, right?
That corrects your mistakes as you write.
Continuous security improvement.
AI keeps learning and adapting.
It's like your fitness tracker
that adjusts goals based
on your activity patterns.
Now the third question I would
try to address is how does
AI contribute to DevSecOps?
Smarter test pipelines.
AI creates better test cases.
Oh, assume like it's like
GP, it's like your GPS.
or maps suggesting the best route
and, based on the real time, traffic.
Real time anomaly detection.
AI monitors, logs, and system, logs.
It's like a surveillance
camera and that notifies you an
unexpected visitor is coming.
Automated complaincy checks.
AI ensures policies are followed.
Think of it's like a tax software that
helps to stay you complaint without manual
effort to just to conclude the slide.
my key takeaway here is AI
is not here to replace us.
It's there to make security smarter,
faster and easier to manage.
before we get into deep dive into
the tools, here is, what I have
divided the tools into six phases,
considering the development life cycle.
one is the static analysis,
phase where I, dev phase, and we
use, tools like static analysis.
the, again, the security, Security
is not just about having the tools
again, it's about making them smarter
with AI to catch issues early and
automate responses effectively.
AI helps to optimize security
tools to work better and faster.
So again, as I mentioned, at dev phase,
we are going to use static analysis tools.
at code review phase, we would
be, using secret detection tools
like Git Lake, TruffleHawk.
there are, if you take the
landscape of these tools, there
are Hundreds of tools available.
but for this demo I just picked
for each phase two tools.
Some of them would be
common, but just to, for this
demonstration purpose, I took two.
There are, commercial tools as well.
There are open source tools as well.
There are lot of tools as well.
the idea is to just how we can integrate
these tools into our pipeline using.
And then leveraging the AI to make
sure the threats are attempted
as early as they are detected.
Now, static analysis tools, we are
going to use PYLint and CodeQL.
AI, here we'll leverage
the AI help as well.
AI does not just point out issues.
It suggests fixes and
predicts risks as well.
another example like is like a smart
assistant that helps you to write
better, more, better code and more,
secure code and a quality code.
Another, one, again, we are speaking
about code review phase, secret detection,
git leaks or truffle hawk, right?
AI helps cut down, false alarms
and provides guidance on,
storing sec, secret securely.
Think of, it's like an experienced
auditor who knows exactly what to look to.
Then we'll go into dependency
scan on the build phase.
tools like safety, safety
or dependabot, helps.
And if you are leveraging AI, AI
can analyze the trends and warns
about potential vulnerabilities
before they become serious.
Similar to how a health app predicts
potential issues based on the trends.
Now then comes to functional phase
or we can, sorry, deployment phase
where we will do functional testing.
Tools like Postman, Helinium, can be
used here and leveraging AI creates
and adapt to a test case, generation
automatically test case generation fixed,
fixing broken, issues or fix, reducing
the flakiness in the test execution.
Assume as we spoke, it's like
a GPS rerouting when you hit a
roadblock and, we will use then
next comes as the security testing.
That's where post deployment.
this is where, DAST,
comes into the picture.
We call it as DAST.
DAST tools, OSAP, ZAP is one tool.
Yeah, and leveraging AI can help
you pre authorize vulnerabilities
based on the real, impact.
in other words, it's like a
doctor telling you which health,
issues needs an urgent attention.
Then comes, finally, post deployment.
it's not just, sitting
and relaxing, right?
We have to do, the product, production
phase as well to see if there are
any anomalies in our, production.
It's monitoring, right?
when again, we are trying to
leverage AI, continuously, it, it,
it watches the logs and detects
anomalies before they escalate.
And an example could be just
like a home security system that
learns and adapts to new patterns.
Again, to just to see what would
be the key takeaway from here.
AI makes security smarter by
improving, detection, reducing
manual effort and helping team to
focus on what matters the most.
Now, we'll try to look into some of the
tools that we discussed in the past slide.
So in the dev phase, we are
focusing on, Two tools, uh,
that is PY Linked and, CodeQL.
if you see, the line number, before we
go into the code demonstration, let me
help you to understand what is PY Linked.
Think of PYLint is like a spell
checker for your Python code.
It enforces coding standards, detects
issues like unused variables, for
example, unused variables, and ensures,
ensures compliances with best practice,
ensures compliances and, best practices.
For example, practices like PEP8
and all those things can help you.
with the AI, integrating with the
AI, it offers smart suggestions.
Thanks.
auto fixes and better
issue pre authorization.
Then comes to, the other tool
that we were talking about, right?
CodeQL.
What CodeQL is?
CodeQL acts like a security
detective, scanning to identify
vulnerabilities in your code itself.
could be such as like SQL injections, XSS
and all things right at the development
phase, analyzing the code itself.
Now, integrating with AI, if you
take, an example of, we are taking
here as a Salesforce code, TFI base.
that's one of the model,
that's developed by Salesforce.
what it does is it has past
vulnerabilities, databases, and provides
deeper insights, for better prevention.
we, it's that model is being,
basically, it's trained on
analyzed, generated code insights.
It helps summarizing, and,
provides actionable, fixes.
boosting your development, productivity
by automating tedious tasks.
another, thing that I want to highlight
here is why we are taking a local model.
Okay.
There are models, there
are different models.
We can either use GPT or
BERT or any other models.
But here is the thing, right?
So I'm taking a local model.
So it's running on the local,
your machine where your pipelines
are, where this code is running.
That's where the model
will be run as well.
please remember here, see
certain things, right?
Privacy comes into the picture.
Some companies won't allow to share
our findings to, external system.
GDPR compliances comes into the pictures.
That's where I took a model here,
which is running in Salesforce.
Salesforce model, which is running
on local, but, there is one
advantage and disadvantage as well.
Let's talk about that running model
locally ensures privacy, without
sending data to external servers.
However, these models
may not be up to date.
That's a cons because
it's running in local.
It has might learn from the past,
data, but not one of which is
going on the, currently, right?
So that needs to be updated.
So this model needs to be frequently
updated to have, the good,
vulnerability database with you.
Again, there are possible other possible,
models as well, which can run, locally is
code, but, great for coding understanding.
GPT codecs, provides intelligency
code suggestions, tab 9,
polycoder, and, other things.
Now, when you're making a decision, just
look into privacy versus updates, right?
Local mode ensures privacy.
But may miss the latest security
trends that we discussed.
Performance boost.
AI helps developers focus on real
issues, saving time and effort.
Again, before we go, let's
go into co, co, deep dive.
So if you see, line number five to eight,
if you focus, there is a function which
is trying to do a run pylint, which is
trying to run the lint, linting process.
And, here we took a sample, Python file.
You can run it in the entire repository.
And then you get everything in,
standard out, in the results.
standardout file.
And then we are also running,
codeql, and, Code ql.
Again, there is a process.
You can, you can go and check
the documentation, how it runs.
We create a database with fi,
python code scanning, Q Ls file.
That's, latest, security vulnerabilities
that can, it can understand.
So it'll check based on that.
So the new ones keeps updating.
So again, this needs to be updated
as well to have new, newer one.
And then again, this is also, we
are trying to store it in a result
data, in a result, variable.
And then, I'm trying to extract, based
on the line numbers because I'm trying
to remove all the junk, from this one.
And then finally, what I'm trying to do
is per line number that I'm retrieving,
I'm passing it to the, my model.
Okay.
My model is now trying to understand
and finally, gives me an output.
let's see the output first.
Okay.
This is how the output looks.
If you see PY linked,
before, AI integrated.
If you see, it says PY
linked analysis report.
Just focus on line number seven,
constant name, secret key does not
confirm to uppercase naming style,
which just says that, secret key is
not in a, does not confirm to uppercase
naming style and all those things.
It's just PY links is, Checking on,
naming cases and all those things
like camel cases and all those things.
Okay.
Now line number 15, again, combined
injections are detected via os.
py open and end of line, end of py lines.
But I'm just for a demonstration,
I'm taking these two lines.
And if I, if you give the same thing
to, AI before and after, if you see,
It's not only suggesting to, use, the
naming conventions and all those things.
However, AI is also suggesting to use hard
coded secret with secret key, using this.
So it's a suggestion it is also giving.
it's not only detecting your
coding standards, but it also
suggesting, the things as well.
because we pass that, report to AI and
the model that Salesforce model, and
it's just trying to suggest those things.
And similarly for line 15.
It says, subprocess that run,
versus instead of, os p, po open.
So what it is trying to do is
it's trying to speed up our work.
It's trying to supercharge the developer,
to start looking in this direction.
It's a suggestion which is trying to
give versus what we have with PY link.
That's where the flexibility, that's
where the real usage of the tools is
coming into the picture, where it,
we are trying to fasten up our work.
Now, similarly, if you take a code ql.
Security analysis report.
Before AI integration, if you
see line number 22, SQL injection
vulnerability detected in raw query.
However, we know that there is a SQL
injection could be possible at line
number 22, but how do we fix that?
No, we don't know that.
or an expert developer could know
it, but as soon as we see this
particular execution, we would
not be able to justify that what
could be the possible SQL engine.
Injection attack.
On line number 30, cross site
scripting, is possible as well.
Now, AI suggested fixes, if you see, it
says replace raw query with parameterized
SQL query, and it is suggesting as well.
So that's the power of
AI we are leveraging.
That's the power of AI, the model we
are trying to take, which will help
us to fasten up, not only detecting,
it is also providing the solution.
These kinds of things are
available in commercial tools.
However, with open source also,
we can achieve this, where we are
taking the AI help to get solutions
as well for the problems we have.
Line number 30, use escape name to
sanitize user input in HTML rendering.
So this is the end of AI fixes.
That's what it is suggesting.
So tools like, there are a bunch
of tools that we can use it, but
if you are trying to leverage AI
help, you are getting supercharged.
that's where it helps.
Now let's talk about a review phase.
secret detections, while we,
while many good coders also
tries to, hard code a secret.
So it could be in a test file or it could
be anything or, any other, tokens as well.
So we need, a tool which
can help us in review phase.
It's very hard if a developer,
tries to review it, there is
a chances that it'll mess.
That's where these tools
comes into the picture.
secrets made, secrets, detection
made simple with, GitLab
Git Lake and Truffle Hawk.
and again, AI is power by
Salesforce code, TFI base.
Again, you can use any of the models,
which are, can be run locally.
But here for our demonstration, I'm using
this, again, secrets like API, keys.
passwords and tokens can be
unintentionally end up in code, right?
So posing a serious security
risk, manually finding them is a
difficult, but tools like Git leaks
and Truffle Hawks can help them
or directly find them efficiently.
we'll talk before, we go in before
detail and the demo of the code,
we'll see, what is Git leaks, Git
leaks, basically, GitLinks tries
to scan the entire repositories
and finds, predefined patterns of
secrets and entropy checks as well.
it can be worked with any CACD
pipeline, to catch serious,
issues before, deployment.
That means your PR cannot be merged
until, unless you address this.
you can integrate that with,
pipelines or even in GitHub
actions, you can integrate this.
Trufflehawk again, dives
deeper into commit history.
to uncover high entropy strings that could
be, that could be posing the credentials
and all other sort of security issues.
Ideal for post commit reviews
to catch overlooked secrets.
Then now, if you are integrating
with AI, How it can help us.
So AI, again, we have seen in the,
in the, in the past example, smarter
detection, Code T5 improves accuracy
by learning from the past findings
and reducing false positives.
Sometimes it could be a
false positive as well.
That also will be helping us as well.
Context awareness, it
understands the code context.
to different, real secrets from a noise,
and also provides automatic remediation,
provides actionable, recommendations
such as moving secrets to secret values.
Continuous learning adapts to
evolving patterns, identifying
new risks as they emerge.
Okay.
overall it's enhancing productivity, helps
developers quickly address identified
Issues with all with without manual
intervention again, before we go deeper
into the code Here is my key takeaway from
this with ai power tools like salesforce
Codify secrets detections becomes smarter
faster and more reliable Ensuring better
security without extra manual effort.
Now if you see the code
line number six to, 13.
If you see what we are trying to do is we
are trying to run, the tools basically.
So the two tools we, you can
either use TruffleHog or GitLex.
See, refer line number 24 and 25.
which where we are trying to call first
TruffleHog and then later GitLinks
and we are calling the method runScan.
Again, if you see we are trying to
run this and then we are trying to
get the output and then again we are
passing that both TruffleHog output
and GI Lake's output into our model
and model is trying to passe it and
then it is trying to suggest the fixes.
Let's see how the fixes looks like,
what before and after, how it looks.
So if you see Truffle hog
before it is adjacent file,
it's very hard to understand.
at least, as a developers, we would be
able to understand how we were, you know.
this is very, vague strings found AWS
key password and all sorts of things.
So AI integration after
AI, this is how it looks.
Let's focus directly on
the AI suggested fix.
Move the keys to AWS secret manager.
This is your friend, your buddy, who is
trying, it's acting like your buddy who
is trying to help you to understand that,
hey, move this, things to a secret manager
and reference it via environment variable.
That's a very good, suggestion.
And, GitLeaks, again, if you see
GitLeaks, it is trying to say
secrets are found in so and so
file method and all sort of things.
And now if you see the things,
use the environment variables
for, or a secret manager.
Instead of storing
credential in this file.
So these are the suggestions we are
getting not only suggesting it is try
to help us our code and it will try
to Say that there is a problem here
and then you can fix it this way.
So that's the Power that we are
getting from integrating now.
let's see a build phase.
uh, in the build phase we will try to
find out the hidden vulnerabilities
in our third party libraries that we
are using You However, finding the
tools like safety dependable will
help us to find out the libraries.
However, the problem, comes
into the picture is, challenges
and dependency management.
Okay.
Manage, managing software
dependency is a complex and
challenging, challenging as well.
Developer often time face,
faces several key challenges.
Like such as like security risk, right?
Dependency may contain
vulnerabilities that expose
application to potential threats.
That's what we are discussing.
Tracking and resolving these
vulnerabilities manually
is very time consuming.
Okay.
it's very frustrating as well because
one library you change, it may not be
compatible because of multiple things.
Okay.
deprecated code issues.
An example could be a
Upgrading dependencies can
introduce breaking changes.
Okay.
to the deprecated functions, I
didn't identifying affected code.
manually, fixing, requests a significant
of effort of the time, again,
high cost of, regression as well.
now, because you have to test
the entire application, whether
it's working fine or not.
Every dependencies, upgrade,
this is time consuming.
and overall, it's a problem.
So what we can do is, using ai.
The solution could be, use AI, so
which would, help us to, help us
in, dependency management, how AI
can, help us in enhancing dependent
management by automatically, detecting
the vulnerabilities, compatibility
analysis, and, risk predictions.
These are the things, which could help us.
And here is what my approach is.
I'll explain the code in detail.
But, it's a multi step process,
which I would say, first one
is where we are trying to find
automated, vulnerability scanning.
So we are using a tool like safety here.
And I took an example of a safety or you
can use depend on what as well, or another
tool, to detect known vulnerabilities.
First, it is trying to scan and it
is trying to find out what are the
vulnerabilities coming by our third
party libraries that we are using.
Okay, then we will try to analyze
the code for deprecations.
Say, let's say, there is a library
we found and we want to use
that, but is there any deprecated
method or any code issues?
So I use a technique called AST based
parsing to identify outdated functions.
Then I'm using, dependency visualization.
That's not coming, that code
is not showing up in the slide.
We'll see in the next slide.
graph based mapping to
understand the relationships.
So we are using JNN networks to
understand the code relationships.
And then finally, we are going
with AI powered risk production.
This is where the AI is, where
we are using, GCN models.
We are using GCN models to pre authorize
updates and minimize the failures.
again, We can use real time
security again, which will, which
we can integrate with the GitHub
advisories to stay updated.
So another tool which we can also
use is GitHub advisories, which
will have the updated, libraries
information and all sort of things.
if you go into, detail of the code,
from line one, line number one, to PHI
as where we are now focusing where, the
function, what it does is it scans the.
project dependencies using safety
tool, to know, to find the,
identify, known vulnerabilities.
The output is passed into a JSON
format for further processing.
so that's where the JSON format is.
Now, we will see in the next two slides
how AI can help us, but, I'll just try
to help you to understand here as, it pre
authorized the detected vulnerabilities
based on severity and expo.
and, possible, noise.
then, let's focus on the next, method.
next code block, refer here nine
to, 16, code block nine to 16.
What it basically does the functions,
scans and gives, gi gives a python
to detect the deprecated function.
As I mentioned, we are
using a SD technique here.
Try to find out the deprecated
functions, to analyze the code structure.
how AI can help here?
AI can suggest alternative
functions and estimate the impact
of replacing the deprecate methods.
that's automatically analyzing.
Now let's go to the
next block of the code.
here if you see, step number three, we
are trying to visualize the dependency
vulnerabilities using network.
What it basically does,
build a dependencies graph.
To visualize the relation between
dependencies and their vulnerabilities.
Highlights risks dependencies visually.
So I haven't executed this code,
but if you take an example here,
you will see the dependency graph.
now if you are leveraging AI, AI
can detect complex relationships
and predict that the impact
of change before they happen.
Okay.
Now, fourth one, if you refer the block
from 30 to 40, Two, where I would say,
utilizes graph neural network GNN to
predict risk scores for dependencies.
AI learn pattern from
historical vulnerabilities
and dependency relationships.
Now, provide AI can, AI helps to
understand, the PID provides actionable
risk to prioritize upgrades efficiently.
whichever the library you want to
upgrade, it will help you to understand
that and reduce unnecessary updates by
focusing on high risk, dependencies.
Okay.
this is my approach.
There are multiple approaches
that you can, take.
And finally, the fifth one,
fetch real time security update
updates from advisory from GitHub.
You can have your GitHub token and
all sort of things and find out, the
security advisory from Git as well.
Now, let's see how this
code looks like before AI.
the, it is a manual process.
It shows dependencies.
NumPy has a high risk here.
and then dependency request
has high, high risk.
One as well.
Sorry, medium as well.
Potentially deprecated old
function in examplecode.
py at line number 15.
So again, as I mentioned, I'm not sharing
the live code outputs because I'm just
trying to show you how this code is.
it's written by me.
Example.
code.
py has an all deprecated method
so that I, for demonstration
purpose, I just captured here.
Again, After AI automated the process
looks like this dependency MPI cv
security high and risk score is 0.85.
So we got, 0.85 as the
highest one recommended action
upgrade to MPI to this one.
Impact analysis deprecated
function detected.
In example, code Dopy rep replace this
old function with the new function.
that's a beauty of the AI coming into
the picture So here again, I haven't
taken the real time example, just a
mocked up example here again dependency
requests, for this library as well.
We are trying to find out the score is
zero zero point six five Recommendation
is review api usage and apply patches.
No breaking changes detected.
So there is no breaking changes,
which would be detected so
Challenges, dependencies are
listed without a pre authorization.
If we, if you see the before AI,
developers must manually assess
impact and compatibility issues.
extensive manual effort is required.
With the, improvements of AI,
Pre authorization of risk scores.
You could see the risk scores as 0.
85 for NumPy.
And automated code analysis AI can help
you to identify the potential breaking
changes and suggest the fixes as well.
So overall, it reduces the testing
effort, and, saves your time.
Overall, on this particular one, my
key takeaways, AI empowers developers
to handle dependency management very
effectively, with a confident, with
a very confidence by automating the
analysis and prioritizing the risk and
overall reducing the time, and effort.
Now, let's talk about functional testing.
again, here we are taking, functional
testing Postman, Neumann, and, Hellenium.
the goal here is to ensure the
correctiveness and reliability,
by validating the business
flows, workflows end to end.
it could be the APIs or it could be, UI
and also identify, the whole goal, right?
So we want to identify the security as
well as the functional, issues as well.
to reduce the production issues, which
will in turn saves the cost and effort.
Here the tools, as I mentioned,
Postman and Newman, just to give a
quick overview for those who doesn't
know what is Postman and Newman.
Simplifies API testing, and automates
workflows and enables continuous
validation in CI CD pipeline.
Hellenium, again, AI powered self
healing tool that adapts to UI changes
by tracking elements, locators,
reducing flaky test failures.
Let's say flaky, there is
a flaky test case which has
changed because of a locator.
Hellenium can help us to bypass
that and helps to move forward.
And which is very much
required, in, testing.
with the AI integration here, what we
can do is smart test pre authorization,
focus on high risk areas by analyzing
test history and failure trends.
we can say, ensure resource are used
efficiently, and, again, with the
self healing automation in coming
into the picture, as I mentioned.
If there is a flakiness, we are
reducing or minimizing the flakiness
and, which will help us to overall
maintain the test cases and focus on
new future testing, and other things.
And, AI can also help us providing
actionable insights, provides root
cause analysis and recommendations
for improving test coverage.
Again, my key takeaway here
is AI driver functional test
cases, reduces the flakiness.
It accelerates debugging and
improves reliability, making
tests smarter and faster.
Okay, now let's focus on security testing.
Why security testing is still needed?
Even with the security coding practices,
security testing is essential to detect
runtime vulnerabilities, evolving
threats, and configuration issues that
might arise post deployment as well.
It ensures compliances, protects
against emerging attacking, vectors and
provides an additional layer of defense.
So that's where security
testing is very important.
So we are using here two tools, OSAP,
ZAP, and Nikito, both will enhance
the security testing with DAST.
And, SAST.
So what is DAST?
Dynamically Application, Security Testing.
The ones which we have seen so far
is, SAST tools, which is Static
Application Security, Testing.
now we are seeing the DAST tool here.
OSAP, ZAP is one of the famous, tool,
which is also called a Z Attack Proxy.
very popular tool that simulates real
world, attacks which are, To see how the
application will behave at a run time.
Okay, The attacks could be different
the vulnerabilities that could be
different sql injections cross site
scripting security misconfigurations in
our live applications, so it basically
analyzes the web application without
access to the source code mimicking,
attacking as a behavior, attacking
as a, customer or attacker behavior.
Okay.
While DAST focuses on runtime security,
as I mentioned, SAST focuses on source
and binaries to detect vulnerables
at the code level before deployment.
So that's why we need, testing,
security testing at, DAST level
as it's a runtime application.
how AI can enhance our security testing.
AI can enhance security testing by
automating scans, prioritizing critical
vulnerabilities, and reducing false
positives, allowing team to focus on
real threats and faster remediation
before it goes into the production.
So we are marking up the cases.
And then trying to test our application.
Okay.
AI enhanced security
testing, code overview.
If you see how I am
using this application.
So generally people use, scripts to run.
but however, I have coded everything here.
So if you see a step one, we are
running Ozap, and Nikito scans.
so we first, we are triggering, Nikito
at line number three and then, Zap.
And then, we, once that is done, we are
scanning the results and then we are pre
authorizing which one we want to fix it.
And then we are finally,
reducing the false, positive.
to go back again, line number one to
seven, which will help you to perform
the automated scans on the application,
and then we are going, line number, 14,
to 20, if we see we are pre authorizing
the findings AI ranks vulnerabilities
based on severity and risk factors.
And then we are going
with, false positives.
We want to reduce the false positives.
So we are using the filter basically.
So from line number 23 to 31, it
refines, results, ensuring, accuracy
by filtering the irrelevant alerts.
So if we have, we need that, we want
to focus on the right ones, right?
And then step five is
where the suggest fixes.
So we are trying to, take AI help
on providing actionable security
fixes, that could help us the
acceleration of the development.
Again, and then, line block number six.
If you see, we are just
atti running the, script.
And I used my stream tech here.
and, the key takeaway from this particular
script is security testing with ai.
Ensure proactive protection, by
detecting active, actual evolving
threats, and then we can automate,
automation of the pre authorization
and accelerating the remediations.
So now, if we go back, how, basically
it looks before and after, let's
go back before AI integration.
If you see, Before AI, challenges we
see is manual security testing required
constant oversight, large volumes of false
positives overwhelmed with security teams.
Lack of prioritization
led to delayed responses.
And again, fixing vulnerabilities
requires extensive research and effort.
However, after the ai, if you see
now, if you see it's very neatly
done, based on the prioritization
it is giving, it's taking the
risk score, risk factors as well.
If you see, predictive risk
score is 0.92, critical.
That means we need to address immediately.
Automated scans, run some schedules
without, manual, manual interventions.
AI filters out the noises and
focus on critical vulnerabilities.
Now, if you see it's pre authorized
and then also, suggest a fixed,
fixes, how you can fix it.
So if you take an SQL injection
attack, again, here it's example.
login, use parameterized
queries and input validation.
Then again, suggested fixes,
line number two, if you see,
implement a proper input sanitize,
sanitization using security library.
so it detects and it pre authorize.
So increased, the advantages that we
get, again, is increased efficiency.
security can focus on real threats
without wasting time on false positives.
again, improved, accuracy.
AI reduces the chances of human error in
manual pre authorization and response.
And overall, again, faster
reduction, faster, fixes.
And overall, my key takeaway again,
integrating AI into security, testing
transforms a reactive approach
then, transforms a reactive approach
into a proactive and efficient
processes, reducing exposures
and ensuring faster, resolutions.
Okay.
Now let's see, with the, AI
integration, how the logs looks like.
So in traditional, security,
the challenges, right?
So if you see.
if you take back the same scenario
like detecting threats like brute
force attacks and unauthorized
access could lead inefficiencies
because slow detection, reactive
approach, false positives, manual,
contaminations, which all creates time.
Okay.
If you take example before the
logs, before, AI integration,
if you see User login attempted
it from so and so IP address.
Multiple logins fails detected.
Potential brute force attacks detected.
Now, with the, without AI action, right?
So security teams again has to
go manually analyze the logs and
block the IP after detection.
In meanwhile, there could be a
serious threats which could happen.
All, all what is happening is response
delays and further unauthorized
possible, access attempts.
With the AI, we are trying to enhance
the security monitoring improvements
with AI automated detection with, AI
identifies suspicious patterns instantly
proactive responses, reduce false
positives, automated contamination,
that's a beautiful immediately
blocking of threats and enforcement
of security, security measures.
Now, if you see example here, we have
detected an alert on our login page.
So the risk is very critical.
The scoring is also, we have done with
our previous algorithm, 9.5 and what,
contamination we are, try, trying to
take IP address is blocked because we
don't want to more number of, threats
to come up or, request to come up.
And we also enable, we have
also identified what are the
customers who has been, affected.
And immediately we have enabled, MFA, we
have, revoked the, session tokens as well.
then we are also suggesting the developer
to implement rate limiting and capture.
So all this will help us, to
immediately take an action, using, ai.
so the key take, key takeaway again here.
AI driven monitoring enables
faster, detection, faster
resolution, automate automation of
contamination smarter, remediation.
Reducing overall risks very effectively.
With that saying, let's talk
about some of the best practices.
Okay.
So best practices for AI
driven DevOps, DevSecOps.
Okay.
Practically, let's see this.
Start with small and grow smart.
AI can be overwhelming.
So it is because to start, it's
recommended to start with small
manageable projects instead of trying
to implement everything at one place.
One place.
Pick specific area and then try to fix it.
preauthorize what matters most.
Some of the internal services are there
which may not be, that, important.
Customer facing, right?
So take examples of customer
facing applications.
so focus, like, where there is a lot of
customer facing security enhancements
are required automation automate as much
as repeated to tasks and then slowly
move into what is the most required.
These areas could help us you
to provide a quick wins and help
establish trust in the AI capabilities.
Keep it transparent.
Okay.
once the biggest concern with AI is
trust, ensure that AI driven decisions
are clear and easy to understand.
Okay.
Transparency helps teams feel
confident in AI recommendations.
Make it easier and adopt, and
act on AI driven insights.
If possible, if people don't
trust it, then it may not
be, it won't be that useful.
Always improve.
A is not a one time setup.
It needs continuous
learning and improvement.
We discussed, about, the local models
versus, the frequently upgraded model.
So again, regular updates
are required, fine tuning,
feedbacks, feedback loopholes.
Help maintains, the accuracy
and effectiveness of our models.
And over time, the system would
be predictable and trustable.
As your time evolves, your
AI model should also evolve.
Integrate it smoothly.
AI should fit into your
existing DevSecOps workflows.
Seamlessly, don't enable
everything at once, start with
smaller steps as we discussed.
It should not feel like an overwhelming
response to developer and also,
should not be a burden rather than
enhancement, to the current process.
Choose AI solutions that, that
compliment your tools and workflows,
to make it a transition effortlessly.
initially, you will see some, hiccups
and some back, back, back steps.
But slowly, you have to educate
the developers and get things done.
not developers, every engineering team.
Okay.
Now the future of AI in DevSecOps.
Let's take a look at how AI is
shaping the future of DevSecOps and
why it is becoming as an essential
part of modern security practices.
AI enhances speed, accuracy and
efficiency, proactive security and
automation, scaling without human bias.
enables a smarter, decisions
making through insights, continuous
improvement with feedback loops.
So overall, what I want to say is AI,
as it continues to evolve, it will also
play in a bigger role in DevSecOps,
driving efficiencies, automations, and
smarter security strategies and smarter
remediations, smarter contaminations
that helps organizations to build
safer and more resilient applications.