Hi, everyone.
My name is Anna.
I'm a data scientist working
in developer advocacy at IBM.
I'm super excited to talk to you today
a bit about AI agents and how they're
reshaping the future of AI as we speak.
So it goes without saying, over the
last few years, AI has transcended
across almost every industry.
From customer service, healthcare, and
even agriculture, AI is reshaping the way
we work and the way we think about work.
I'm sure many of us have used
a large language model and been
disappointed by its responses.
So why is it that some large language
models are able to successfully complete
complex tasks like writing JavaScript
code, for example, but can't answer simple
questions like, what is today's date?
The answer to filling these
information gaps lies in AI agents.
So what exactly is an AI agent?
An AI agent refers to a system or
program that's capable of autonomously
performing tasks on behalf of a user
or another system by designing its
workflow and using available tools.
So what makes them any different
than a traditional AI assistant
like we've used in the past?
traditional LLMs, like IBM's Granite
models, Meta's Llama models, or
Google's Gemma models, just to name
a few, produce their responses based
on the data used to train them.
And they're bounded by knowledge
and reasoning limitations.
Hence, why an LLM is unable to
provide us with today's date.
It can't access information
it wasn't trained on.
In contrast, Agentech technology
is modular, and it's easier to
adapt to personalized tasks.
Without the need for human intervention,
tool calling is used on the backend
to obtain up to date information,
optimize workflow, and create subtasks
autonomously to achieve complex goals.
In this process, the autonomous
agent learns to adapt to
user expectations over time.
And the agent's ability to store past
interactions in memory and plan future
actions encourages a personalized
experience and comprehensive responses.
This process can be broken
down into three stages.
First there's goal
initialization and planning.
This is where the agent takes in
a user query, extracts the main
goal, and creates a plan of subtasks
in order to reach that goal.
Next, there's tool calling.
In which the AI agent uses its available
tools to fill any information gaps
in the LLM's pre trained knowledge.
These tools can include external datasets,
web searches, APIs, and even other agents.
After the missing information is
retrieved from these tools, the
agent can update its knowledge base.
This means that each step of the
way, The agent reassesses its
plan of action and self corrects.
We have the flexibility to either
create custom tools for our AI agents,
Or use pre built tools like the ones
already available through LangChain.
For anyone unfamiliar with
LangChain, it's an open source
LLM orchestration framework.
Additionally, LangGraph is built on
top of LangChain, and it's a framework
specific to agentic workflows.
It's a specialized library
within the LangChain ecosystem.
And we'll be using both
in the upcoming demo.
The tools available through LangChain
are vast and they include functionality
for search, web browsing, code
interpretation, productivity, database
management, and much, much more.
Lastly, the final stage is
learning and reflection.
This is where an AI agent uses
feedback mechanisms such as other
AI agents or a human in the loop to
improve the accuracy of its responses.
Feedback mechanisms improve the
AI agent's reasoning and accuracy,
and this is commonly referred
to as iterative refinement.
To avoid repeating the same mistakes, AI
agents can also store data about solutions
to previous obstacles in a knowledge base.
Alright, now let's bring
in some real world data.
As seen by a recent survey of
AI developers, a whopping 99
percent of them are exploring and
developing use cases for AI agents.
Clearly, this is a major topic
with lots of growth potential.
Now let's apply this preliminary AI
agent knowledge to an example that
is applicable to many of us today.
Let's say we want to plan a vacation
and we're unsure about the number of
our remaining vacation days at work.
If I were to ask an LLM this user query,
How many vacation days do I have left?
The LLM would either hallucinate or
simply return a response that indicates
it can't provide me with this information.
Not only does the LLM not know who I am
and where I work, but it also doesn't
have the ability to figure that out.
Whereas, if we were to provide the LLM
with a tool that searches a database of
vacation days for each employee, along
with the same user query, an AI agent
would be able to provide us with exactly
the information that we're looking for.
This is a simple example of the
significance of agentic systems.
Of course, as with most things in
AI, we can make this more convoluted
through the use of reasoning paradigms.
There are several reasoning paradigms out
there, but the one most commonly used is
React, short for reasoning and action.
And it's not to be confused with the JS
framework, as I've learned once before.
Essentially, with React, we're
controlling the logic of a compound AI
system by putting the LLM in charge.
In other words, we're designing
the system to think slow, readjust,
As seen in this diagram, the agent
begins with a user query from which it
extracts the main goal, as well as any
subtasks that goal is dependent on.
Then, the agent checks its
tools and determines the
appropriate ones for each subtask.
It then executes the subtasks
and finally provides an output.
The process doesn't end there, however.
Instead, the agent determines
whether the output is satisfactory.
If not, the agent adjusts
and the process is repeated.
Otherwise, the agent returns the
synthesized response to the user.
And so this encapsulates the end
to end process an AI agent goes
through to produce responses
to user queries using React.
don't AI agents seem great?
what if I told you that they're
more powerful when working together?
That's right, multi agent systems
tend to outperform singular agents.
There is strength in numbers due to
the larger pool of shared resources,
optimization, and automation.
Instead of multiple agents learning
the same policies, one agent can
share its learned experiences
with the rest to optimize both
time complexity and efficiency.
In a multi agent system, agents remain
autonomous, but they also cooperate
and coordinate in agent structures.
And each agent within a multi agent
system has individual properties, but
all agents behave collaboratively to
lead to desired global properties.
Multi agent systems are particularly
valuable in completing large scale,
complex tasks that can encompass
hundreds if not thousands of agents.
Multi agent systems can operate
under various architectures.
In centralized networks, a central unit
contains the global knowledge base.
It also connects the agents
and oversees their information.
Some strengths of the structure are
the ease of communication between
agents and uniform knowledge, and
a weakness of the centrality is
the dependence on the central unit.
If it fails, the entire
system of agents fails.
Whereas in decentralized networks, agents
share information with their neighboring
agents instead of a global knowledge base.
And so some benefits of this
are robustness and modularity.
The failure of one agent doesn't
cause the overall system to fail
since there's no central unit.
And one challenge of decentralized agents.
is coordinating agent behavior to
benefit other cooperating agents.
Multi agent systems also
come with their pros and cons
regardless of system structure.
Firstly, they're quite flexible.
We can adjust the system by removing
and adding agents as needed,
which ties into their scalability.
As we can tackle much more complex
goals than a singular agent could.
And each agent comes with its
own domain specialization.
So agents are not relearning
the same information.
Instead, they're collaborating
by sharing information.
In turn, the greater the number
of agents, the greater the chances
are of an agent malfunction.
And the harder it can be to
coordinate each agent to benefit
other cooperating agents.
Since multi agent systems involve
dependencies between agents for
accomplishing subtasks, this means we may
also encounter unpredictable behavior.
This behavior can be due to
infinite feedback loops, changes
in access to certain tools, or
malfunctioning due to design flaws.
And we can mitigate this risk
by incorporating means of
system interruption, human
supervision, and feedback.
This is especially important
when working with sensitive data.
Okay, so given all of this information,
you may still be wondering, why should
I care, and how does this apply to me?
here are just a few of the incredible
ways in which AI agents and multi agent
systems can help us as humans to allocate
our time to more nuanced and critical
tasks that can't be easily automated.
Probably the most common use case of
AI agents today is the integration
into websites and apps to enhance
the customer experience, whether
it's serving as virtual assistants,
providing mental health support,
simulating interviews, and much more.
In healthcare, AI agents have the
potential to alleviate the workload of
medical professionals by overseeing drug
processes and drafting treatment plans.
For Thus allowing their time to be
spent on urgent, hands on tasks.
Additionally, AI agents can
also optimize rescue operations,
in times of natural disasters.
They can do this, by locating
those in need of rescue,
using tools like social media!
Lastly, multi agent system can be a
powerful tool for managing complex
transportation systems, like railroad
systems, truck assignments, or marine
vessels visiting the same ports.
Now having said this, by no means
am I saying AI agents in their
current state can be 100 percent
trusted with these listed use cases.
Agents applied to these use cases
should be under significant supervision
and should undergo thorough testing
before being fully implemented.
Regardless of this, I think we're
at such a pivotal time, of agentic
AI that it's important to put
its capabilities in perspective.
If we look at the current trends of how
enterprise AI developers are using AI
agents, we see that about half of them
are using them for customer service and
support, followed by project management,
serving as a personal assistant, And
content creation, HR, transportation,
healthcare, and only 1 percent of
developers in AI are not currently
exploring or developing AI AJA use cases.
Now that we've established the
foundational understanding of AI agents
and we've seen some real world data
about their significance, let's demo how
to build an AI agent using LangGraph.
We'll use pre built Lang chain
tools for a React agent to showcase
its ability to differentiate
appropriate applications of each tool.
The code that I will share with you is
available on GitHub, as well as on IBM.
com, and I'll include the links to
both at the end of this presentation
if you'd like to run the project on
your own time and experiment with it.
so okay, let's jump right into it.
Alrighty, so since we've covered the
basics of what an AI agent is and how tool
calling works, we can go ahead and take a
look at our prerequisites for this demo.
So there is one, you will need an
IBM cloud account, and keep in mind
there are hyperlinks throughout this
entire demo, so you can go into either
the github repository or the ibm.
com page and, follow along there.
So once you have created an IBM Cloud
account, you can then log in to watsonx.
ai.
Which is in step one.
There you can create a watsonx.
ai project and Make a note of your project
id which we'll need for this demo And
finally you can either create a jupyter
notebook from scratch Or you can import
an already existing Jupyter notebook.
So if you want to go ahead and
download this one from the GitHub
it, directly to what's next.
ai, that is also an option.
Moving along to step number two,
we will set up a what's next.
ai runtime instance and API key.
So you can create a free
instance, choosing the light blue.
plan of WatsonX.
ai runtime.
There you can generate an API key.
And finally, you can associate the
runtime instance to the project
that you just created in step one.
Once we have all these preliminary
steps completed, we can go ahead and
install and import relevant libraries,
as well as set up our credentials.
I've already installed these libraries.
I won't rerun this cell, but I just
want you to see that we've imported
all of the necessary libraries and
modules that we'll need, as well as, we
have loaded our environment variables.
there are several ways of setting
up your environment variables.
My personal preference is
to use a separate env file.
that is what I have done here, using OS.
Here we can also set up our
credentials for the What's Next API,
so that is our API key, our project
ID, as well as the API endpoint.
Your endpoint will be specific to
your region, so please reference the
documentation to make sure you're
using the correct endpoint, otherwise
you will have a hard time connecting.
We can also set up our open weather
API key, Which you can generate by
creating an OpenWeather account,
and all of this is free to create.
We will be using this API in a
later step for a link chain tool.
In step four, we can go
ahead and initialize our LLM.
So in this tutorial, we'll
be using the IBM Granite 3.
1 8B Instruct model.
And I will be setting it up
using the chat Watson X wrapper
available through lang chain.
And this wrapper is pretty neat.
It allows us to integrate
tool calling and chaining.
And to initialize the LLM, I'll set
the model parameters here as well.
One thing to point out here is I
set the temperature to zero to limit
the amount of agent hallucinations
and overall LLM creativity.
Moving right along, we can
establish the built in tools.
So to do we will use the tool
class available through LangChain.
And the first tool that we'll set
up is the OpenWeatherMap tool.
So this uses that API key that
we set up in an earlier step.
And when I set up these tools, I provide
a name for the tool, a description,
and overall, the function that is
meant to be run when calling each tool.
The next tool we'll set up
is the YouTube search tool.
Pretty self explanatory.
It'll return YouTube links to
videos relevant to the user query.
And finally, we can set up a password.
a online shopping tool which uses Ionic.
This is also available through LangChain.
And this is essentially an e commerce
marketplace tool that returns search
results relevant to your user query.
I'll explain a bit more about the
search parameters in a later step.
So now that we have our tools
defined, we can put them into a
list and simply call the list tools.
And here we see how the tool is loaded.
We see their names, their descriptions,
the functions, as well as any API keys.
So now for step six, we will actually
get to implement some tool calling.
And before we jump into creating
an AI agent, I first want to see
how the LLM performs, simply being
provided a user query and its tools.
So we will use the bind tools method
available through link chain, and we
will invoke a user query asking what
are some YouTube videos about Greece?
Okay.
Just to print the response,
additional arguments.
so just to see a little
better what's going on here.
We can see that the function YouTube
search was appropriately selected from
the tool base, and that the argument
of Greece was also successfully
extracted from the user query.
But as you can see here, the actual
tool response is not returned.
That's because we're not
creating an agentic system.
This is simply the LLM with its tools.
moving right along, we can actually create
the React agent using the createReactAgent
method available through LangGraph.
And so as we've discussed, I
won't go too into depth again.
But just to refresh our memory, the
user provides a user query to the LLM.
In our case, this will be a React agent.
The agent then assesses its tool base
and determines the appropriate tools for
each subtask within its broader goal.
Finally, once it collects all of
the tool messages, it formulates a
synthesized response to the user, and
if successful, the process ends there.
If the user is not satisfied with
the results, the process repeats.
So let's go ahead and
initialize our React agent.
Super simple, super clean method.
Okay, so now that we've set up our
agent, let's ask the same user query.
What are some YouTube videos about Greece?
Awesome.
So as you can see, we have the
human message, which contains
our initial user query.
We also have the AI message, which is
The one that you previously saw with
the LLM and the buying tools method.
But the interesting part here is that
our AI agent actually calls the tool,
as you can see by the tool message.
And so once it receives that
tool response, it's able to
formulate a synthesized response.
So here it is within the AI message.
We see the message says, here are
some YouTube videos about grace.
We have the YouTube video title.
Along with the URL.
And here we have two URLs.
Wonderful.
Okay, so now we can move on to testing
whether the AI agent will know when to
use tools for non YouTube related queries.
So let's ask a weather related question.
What is the weather in Athens, Greece?
Okay, let's see what we have here.
In the human message, we
see our initial user input.
In the AI message, we see that the weather
search tool was selected appropriately,
and that the argument of Athens And
Greece was also extracted correctly.
Then in the tool message, we see a
thorough description of the weather
in Athens, Greece, retrieved from the
weather tool, and finally in the AI
message, we see a synthesized response
that lets us know the temperature, as
well as the wind speed and humidity.
And whether there's any rain and
the cloud cover in Athens, Greece.
Okay, so finally, let's test whether
the agent will know to use the e
commerce marketplace search tool
when provided with this user query.
We will ask the agent to find some
suitcases for less than 10, 000 cents.
You might be wondering why I'm
using US cents instead of dollars.
So that's one thing to keep in mind
when using the Ionic search tool.
It actually uses cents and not dollars.
And so the equivalent of
10, 000 cents would be 100.
So just keep that in mind when
running your user queries.
And we can go ahead and run this now.
We have our human message.
We then have our AI message where
we see that the Ionic commerce
shopping tool was correctly selected
and that the argument of suitcases
under 10, 000 cents, those arguments
were also successfully extracted.
So then within our tool message,
we should see suitcases under.
100.
And we can verify this within
our synthesized AI message.
So we see here are some
suitcases under 10, 000 cents.
The first response is a
suitcase at the price of 80.
The next one is a suitcase that costs 34.
So as you can see, these
suitcases fit our criteria.
We have the synthesized
response that we're looking for.
So there's definitely a lot of room here
for creativity and to have fun with this.
So feel free to test out different
user queries on your own time.
And.
Yes, this is it!
This is how you create an AI agent
using LangChain and LangGraph.
So to recap, we created a React
agent in Python using the WatsonX
API, and we used the Granite 3.
1 8 bit instruct model.
We also use the YouTube weather and online
shopping tools available through link
chain and we were able to successfully
receive the output we were looking for.
So I hope that this was fruitful
and I hope you enjoy running your
own user queries on your own time.
Thank you for joining me today.