Hi, everyone.
I'm Shashank Reddy Pirevelli, currently
working in Walmart as a software engineer.
I'm excited to be here to explore
a topic that has a tremendous value
for business across industries.
How AI improves data quality
for better business insights.
In today's data driven world, accurate
and reliable data is the backbone
of any successful business decision.
However, as we know, data is often
unstructured, incomplete, or inaccurate.
These data quality issues can result
in poor decision making, missed
opportunities, and inefficiencies.
In this session, we'll explore
how artificial intelligence is
transforming data quality management
by offering advanced solutions.
We'll also dive into real world challenges
as well as how AI approaches in sectors
like financial services and manufacturing.
Today, we are facing a number of
challenges across data quality.
Let me highlight a few key issues.
Data team often spend about 40
percent of their time dealing with
quality issues, which can consume up
to 25 percent of operation budget.
This result in substantial
loss of productivity.
Next, we have the issue
of critical data gaps.
Many enterprise systems functions at
only 75 to 80 percent completeness,
leaving important insights hidden
due to missing or incomplete data.
Another challenge is the
issue with duplicate records.
Around 25 to 30% of customer and vendor
record contain duplicates resulting
in waste resources and leading to
inconsistent customer interaction.
Lastly, corporate data become outdated
at a rate of approximately 23% per
year, and B2B data is even more
volatile, degrading by 36% annually.
This rapid rate of data decay makes
it increasing difficult to rely on
information for accurate decision making.
These challenges not only affect
productivity, but also hinder overall
business performance and growth.
Now let's talk about how AI
power solutions are transforming
data quality management.
With advanced AI algorithms,
we can automatically detect
and fix data inconsistencies.
This reduces error rate by an impressive
67 percent and process data 50 times
faster than the traditional methods.
Moreover, natural language processing
models are now being used to
standardize data across multiple
languages, achieving 94 percent
accuracy and ensuring consistent
data quality and on a global scale.
Additionally, using advanced
machine learning models, AI can
intelligently fill data gaps with
91 percent accuracy, eliminating
the need for manual data entry.
In real time, AI validation systems
can process up to 850k records per
minute, maintaining an impressive 99.
5 percent accuracy.
This ensures errors are detected
and corrected before, and after.
The impact critical business decisions.
These AI solutions are drastically
improving both the speed and accurate
of data management, making it easier to
ensure high quality data across the board.
Let's now look at the impact of AI
powered solutions in financial services.
Thanks to machine learning algorithms.
We can accelerate transaction validation
and fraud detection by 250 times.
This significantly speeds up the
processing and validation of transactions,
allowing business to respond to potential
issues much faster and more effectively.
Next, we observe 35
percent reduction in cost.
By leveraging smart automation and
predictive maintenance, operational
expenses are cut down by 35%.
At the same time, service
quality is enhanced.
Resulting in more efficient
and cost effective operation.
Then there is a 92 percent reduction
in errors Advanced pattern recognition
significantly reduces complaints
related data error by 92 percent.
Minimizing the risk of cost,
regulatory mistakes and penalties.
Lastly, we save 66 percent of time.
Automated data collection and
validation process reduce regulatory
report time by 66 percent.
Allowing staff to focus more on
strategic task and significantly
boosting overall productivity.
These improvements not only boost
operational efficiencies, but also
mitigate risk, lower cost, and
enable more efficient decision
making in financial sectors.
Next, let's explore how AI is
transforming supply chain data
optimization in manufacturing.
AI powered validation systems
continuously monitor production data
in real time, catching defects before
they can impact product quality.
This ensures we maintain a 99.
7 percent accuracy rate.
Automated data harmonization ensures 98.
5 percent consistency across
global suppliers, eliminating
discrepancies and achieving
seamless data alignment worldwide.
Smart algorithms automate supplier data
matching and verification, reducing
weeks of manual work to minutes and
significantly boosting efficiency.
76 percent greater accuracy,
enabling better planning and
minimizing supply chain delays.
AI 34.
5 million annual savings and
significantly enhancing the bottom line.
These AI solutions streamline
operations, improve accuracy, and
save significant time and money,
making supply chain management
more efficient and cost effective.
Now let's take a look at some key
implementation best practices for ensuring
the success of data quality initiative.
Start by conducting a comprehensive
baseline assessment to understand
where your data currently stands.
From there, establish clear quantifiable
objective focusing on customer
financial and operational data.
This will give you a solid
foundation and clear goal to aim for.
When choosing the right technology, plan
for 42 percent annual data volume growth.
Look for a platform that can handle
processing data volume up to 2.
5 petabytes annually, with
the capacity to scale up to 5
petabytes within the next 3 years.
This ensures your system is future proof
and can handle increasing data demand.
Adopt a phased approach with 10 to 14
week pilot project to test and refine
before full scale implementation.
Conduct multi layer validation
including automated testing, business
process validation and user acceptance
testing to ensure the system
meets all business requirements.
By following these best practices,
you can ensure smooth, scalable
and successful development.
implementation of data quality solutions.
Let's now explore how AI driven
data quality management is
enhancing business intelligence.
By leveraging AI organizations have
reduced forecast error rate by 64
percent leading to far more reliable
business planning and decision making.
This helps companies make smarter
and more confident decisions.
AI driven solutions deliver
92 to 96 percent accuracy in
demand prediction, surpassing
traditional methods at 75 to 80%.
This precision transforming inventory
planning and enhancing customer
satisfaction by enabling business to
respond effectively to market needs.
AI has improved forecasting
accuracy by 37%, reducing
working capital needs by 28%.
This frees up resources
for strategy investments.
while maintaining optimal stock levels
and minimizing excess inventory.
These improvements have a
significant financial impact, with
organizations saving an average up
to 32 million annually throughout
precise resource allocation.
In short, AI powered data quality
management is transforming
forecasting, inventory management,
and financial performance, making
organizations more agile and effective.
Now let's take a look at how AI
is enhancing customer intelligence
to drive better marketing
outcomes and customer engagement.
A has led to 73 percent improvement
in customer segmentation precision,
allowing business to create hyper
target market strategies across more
than 12 distinct customer personas.
AI driven personalization and real
time response optimization has led to
42 percent increase in campaign ROI.
Leveraging predictive analytics and
proactive engagement strategies,
organizations have achieved 35 percent
higher customer retention rate.
AI has increased customer
lifetime value by 2.
1 times through enhanced engagement and
data driven relationship management,
ensuring customers to stay longer
and spend more over that course.
In summary, AI is significantly
improving how customers segment,
engage, and retain customers, leading
to high marketing effectiveness and
greater customer lifetime value.
Let's now focus on how AI is
driving operational performance
optimization across key areas.
Advanced AI 76 percent faster with 99.
9 percent accuracy in
validation and cleansing.
This ensures faster processing and
higher data quality driving better
business insights and decisions.
AI improves resource utilization
accuracy by 41%, optimizing
workforce and asset deployment.
This ensures Resources are
allocated effectively, reducing
waste and maximizing value.
AI driven improvements have
cut data management overhead
by 34%, resulting in 2.
8 million in annual savings.
This reduction frees resources
for strategic investments and
enhances operational efficiencies.
In short, AI enhances speed,
decision making, resource allocation,
and cost efficiency, driving
operational optimization, and
boosting bottom line performance.
To wrap up, here are the key
takeaways from today's discussion.
AI powered data quality solutions have a
transformative impact on organizations.
This significantly improves operational
performance, customer satisfaction,
and strategic decision making
capabilities, empowering businesses to
perform better and stay competitive.
AI has delivered exceptional
results in financial services and
manufacturing, driving significant
efficiency, accuracy, and cost saving.
These sectors leverage AI to streamline
operations, improve forecasting,
and enhance customer experience.
A successful implementation strategy
follows a phased approach with clear
objectives and comprehensive validations.
This ensures smooth adoption
and maximizing the impact
of AI driven solutions.
Looking ahead, AI driven data quality
management is poised to become even more
crucial in shaping business intelligence
and driving operational excellence.
As data continue to grow in volume
and complexity, these solutions
will play an increasingly vital
role in helping business grow.
Stay agile and make data driven decision.
Thank you all so much for
being part of this session.
I truly appreciate your
time and attention today.
It's been a pleasure sharing insights
into how AI enhance data quality
for better business decisions.