Hello, everyone.
My name is Karthik
Medhavi Benagamori Sriram.
I'm excited here today to discuss
about a topic that is fundamentally
reshaping software development,
that is, AI assisted development.
The way we write, review and
maintain code has been transformed
by artificial intelligence.
enabling developers to work more
efficiently, reduce errors, and
innovate faster than ever before.
AI coding assistance is no
longer a futuristic concept.
It is already an integral part of
the modern development workflows.
From intelligent coding suggestions
to automated testing and even real
time debugging, AI is accelerating
every aspect of software engineering.
Companies that adopt AI driven
development practices are seeing
drastic improvements in productivity.
code quality and deployment efficiency.
In this talk, I will walk you
through the real world applications
of the AI in software development,
examining how leading organizations
are leveraging AI and discuss the
essential skills developers need to
thrive in this AI augmented future.
Whether you are a software engineer,
an engineering manager, or a
technology leader, understanding
AI's role in development, Is crucial
to stay ahead in the industry.
Let's dive in
the state of art today.
AI is not just assisting developers
It is fundamentally reshaping
the way how software is built.
Let's start with one of the biggest
transformations AI coding assistants
like GitHub Copilot study show that
these tools can accelerate development
cycles by up to 55 percent and 96 percent
of AI suggested code is accepted by
developers in production environments.
That's a staggering level of
adaption, but AI's impact goes
beyond just generating the code.
AI powered tools now understand complex
code bases and architectural patterns.
providing developers contextually relevant
suggestions across 20 plus programming
languages and hundreds of frameworks.
This level of sophistication
allows AI to assist in debugging,
optimizing performance, and even
automating mundane coding tasks.
Additionally, AI is
reducing bug rates by 40%.
automating 80 percent of test
writing and drastically improving
code documentation quality.
The result development time
is effectively cut in half.
These statistics highlight why companies
that embrace AI driven development gain
a significant competitive advantage
in speed, quality, and innovation.
For developers, this means A shift in
focus from writing repetitive code to
strategic thinking, problem solving, and
leveraging AI to enhance their workflows.
The more we understand and
integrate these tools, the more
productive and efficient we become.
Smart package management.
Managing dependencies in large
scale applications has always
been a challenging task.
AI powered package managers are
now revolutionizing this space by
intelligently resolving complex dependency
conflicts and versioning issues.
These smart resolution systems
reduce build errors by 60%, ensures
that developers spend less time
debugging compatibility problems.
Security is another critical
factor in software development.
Signatures, real time vulnerability
detection, and automated security
patches ensure that applications
remain secure from evolving threats.
Beyond security and dependency
management, AI is also enhancing developer
productivity by offering context aware
coding suggestions that align with
specific frameworks and libraries.
This means that developers
receive hyper relevant suggestions
based on their projects.
exact requirements and their
package dependencies cutting
development time by 40 percentage.
Ultimately, AI powered package
management ensures seamless software
integrations, reducing downtime,
improving security, and making
development smoother and more efficient.
Quality assurance and deployment
pipelines have traditionally been
resource intensive, but AI is transforming
these areas by automating testing,
optimizing CICD workflows, and predicting
software failures before they occur.
One major breakthrough is Testing,
which uses machine learning to
detect complex edge cases and
automatically generate test suits.
This technology reduces testing
cycles by 60 percent while
significantly improving test
coverage, leading to high performance.
high reliability and fewer
defects in the production.
Similarly, AI driven CICD integration
is reshaping how software is deployed
by analyzing historical build patterns
and systems performance metrics.
AI can optimize deployment strategies and
anticipate failures before they occur.
Smart rollback systems use predictive
modeling to prevent outages, ensuring 99.
9 percent system uptime.
AI is also bringing predictive
analytics into software development.
By analyzing historical data, AI can
provide precise timeline forecasting
with 85 percent accuracy Proactively
identifying bottlenecks and recommending
optimized resource allocation strategies.
These tools are helping teams to
reduce project delays by 40 percent
making AI an essential asset
in modern software engineering.
The full potential of AI in
software development is realized.
when it is seamlessly integrating
to DevOps, automation, and
infrastructure management.
First, AI powered DevOps
practices are cutting development
and deployment times by 40%.
Thanks to automated infrastructure
orchestration and real time anomaly
detection, AI driven monitoring
tools continuously scan system logs
and performance metrics, identifying
potential issues before they escalate.
Second, End to end automation
of development workflows ensures
consistency and efficiency.
AI driven decision making in CI
CD pipelines, security scans, and
code reviews enhances software
reliability and minimizes human errors.
The results speak for themselves.
Companies implementing AI in
development workflows achieve 99.
9 percent system reliability through
automated testing and validation.
75 percent faster deployment cycles
and better team performance through
data driven accountability metrics.
AI is not just an add on
to software development.
It is now a core component of efficient,
secure, and scalable software delivery.
To fully harness AI's capabilities,
developers must understand how AI
models function and how to integrate
them effectively into their workflows.
The first step is AI literacy,
understanding fundamental concepts like
prompt engineering, retrieval augmented
generation, called RAG, neural networks,
training data, and AI model capabilities.
Without this knowledge, developers may
struggle to use AI tools optimally.
Second, structured learning
is essential for AI adoption.
Companies that invest in hands on
workshops, AI documentation review,
and real world exercises enable
their teams to quickly adapt to AI
powered development environments.
Finally, informed decision
making is the key.
With a deeper understanding of AI
strengths and limitations, developers
can strategically tools, sorry, choose
the right tools, fine tune models,
and optimize AI driven workflows.
The result in up to 40 percent of faster
deployment and development cycles.
and a more seamless AI adoption process.
AI powered code embeddings are
revolutionized how developers
interact with large scale code bases.
Traditionally, searching for relevant code
snippets or understanding architectural
patterns required manual efforts.
Relying on keyword based searches
and static analysis tools.
Now, AI driven vector embeddings
transform source code into high
dimensional numeric representations,
enabling AI models to comprehend
code semantics at near human level.
This transformation provides
three major benefits.
Large codebase navigation.
Developers working on million
line codebases often struggle
to locate relevant functions,
dependencies, or patterns.
AI powered semantic search.
Allows us to retrieve code base on
meaning rather than just keywords.
Reducing search time by 60
percent compared to traditional
graph based searches.
Pattern recognition.
AI embeddings detect recurring
architectural patterns, identify
redundant code, and even suggest
refactoring opportunities by analyzing
semantic similarities across multiple
repositories and code versions.
Advanced code comprehension.
These embeddings help AI models understand
syntax, functional relationships,
and context, making AI assisted
development more accurate and intuitive.
By leveraging AI powered embeddings,
developers can write, refactor,
and maintain codebases more
efficiently than ever before.
Retrieval Augmented Generation, RAG, is an
exciting AI development that bridges the
gap between AI driven coding assistance
and real world context integration.
Unlike traditional AI models that generate
code in isolation, RAG enhances AI outputs
by dynamically incorporating relevant
documentation, previous code history,
and organizational best practices.
Let's break down how RAG is
transforming software development.
Context integration.
Traditional AI generated code suggestions
often lack project specific relevance.
RAG improves accuracy by
integrating knowledge from existing
documentation, past commits, and data.
and team wide coding standards,
ensuring generated code is highly
tailored to the project at hand.
Adaptability.
RAC dynamically learns from
a team's architecture, naming
conventions, and design patterns.
This ensures that AI driven generated
code aligns with organizational standards
and requires fewer manual revisions.
Comprehensive capability.
RAG is not just about writing new code.
It can assist in refactoring legacy
systems, scaffolding new features,
and generating test cases, providing
end to end AI support throughout
the software development lifecycle.
By leveraging RAG, teams can
streamline code generation, improve
consistency, and reduce errors,
ultimately making AI powered development
more robust and production ready.
AI tools are powerful, but
their efficiency depends on how
strategically they are implemented
within a development team.
Here we will explore three key strategies
to maximize AI tool efficiency.
Organizations that adapt a systematic
approach to AI tool optimization
achieves faster development
cycles and reduce code defects.
This involves structured
integration practices, feedback
loops, and continuous learning to
refine AI's role in development.
Prompt engineering.
The AI matters.
Advanced prompt engineering techniques can
increase first attempt accuracy by 75%,
reducing the need for manual revisions.
Developers who craft contextual domain
specific prompts get more reliable
and relevant AI generated code.
AI tools offer features
beyond basic code suggestions.
Organizations that fully leverage
debugging, refactoring, and testing
capabilities report a significant
decrease in technical debt and greater
improvement in system performance.
By focusing on these strategies,
teams can unlock AI's full potential
and transform their development
workflows for maximum efficiency.
The impact of AI driven development
goes beyond just software engineering.
It extends into global innovation
and societal transformation.
AI is accelerating breakthroughs in
multiple industries, reducing time to
market by 60 percent and enabling teams to
solve complex, challenging tasks faster.
Here are the three key areas where
AI is making a significant impact.
AI Power Tools enables developers
to tackle large scale, intricate
challenges with greater confidence.
By automating repetitive tasks and
enhancing problem solving capabilities,
AI allows developers to focus on
creative, innovative solutions.
AI assisted development is shaping
industries beyond software engineering.
In healthcare, AI driven development
is helping researchers to build
predictive models for disease detection.
In sustainable energy, AI is optimizing
resource allocation for smart grids.
These advancements show how AI powered
development is transforming the
world across different industries.
With greater power comes responsibility.
As AI takes on a larger role in software
development and other industries,
teams must prioritize fairness,
transparency, and accountability.
Regular bias audits Explainable AI models
and inclusive design principles must
be in place to ensure ethical AI usage.
The future of AI in development is
bright, but it requires a balanced
approach that considers both
innovation and responsible deployment.
As AI continues to evolve, ethical
considerations must remain at the
forefront of AI assisted development.
Without proper governance, AI
systems can amplify biases, introduce
security risks, or lack transparency.
To mitigate these concerns, organizations
must focus on three key areas.
Implementing bias detection systems.
AI models are trained on
vast data sets and biases can
unknowingly creep into the system.
By deploying robust bias
detection frameworks, and scan
for gender, ethnicity, and
programming paradigm biases.
Organizations can ensure that AI driven
development remains fair and equitable.
AI models should not
operate as black boxes.
Developers need audit trails
that tracks every AI decision.
model training data and deployment
details, maintaining comprehensive
documentation and enhances trust,
traceability, and accountability
in AI driven development.
Ethical development requires
cross functional collaboration.
Companies should establish AI ethics
board, conduct quarterly audits, and train
engineering teams on ethical AI practices.
Clear governance structures ensures
that AI driven decision making
aligns with organizational values.
And societal norms by embedding
these ethical foundations into AI
assisted development Organizations
can maximize AI's benefits while
ensuring fairness security and security
As AI transforms software development,
the role of developers is evolving.
Mastery of traditional programming
alone is no longer sufficient.
Developers must now blend AI enhanced
capabilities with fundamental
software engineering skills.
Here are three crucial skill
areas for modern developers.
Developers must become proficient
in leveraging large language
models, understanding prompt
engineering techniques, and
integrating AI, large language model
APIs into development workflows.
These skills allows teams to
harness AI for automated coding,
debugging, and testing, and
integrating AI into their own apps.
Managing AI models in
production requires expertise.
in data pipeline optimization, model
versioning, and performance monitoring.
Developers or researchers experienced
in these areas can ensure that AI driven
applications remain reliable and scalable.
As AI takes on a bigger role in
development, architects must first design
AI first systems that balance scalability,
security, and ethical considerations.
AI driven software solutions must be
resilient, interpretable, and reliable.
and adaptable.
As AI powered development tools
continue to advance, they're
fundamentally transforming
the way how we build software.
From automating repetitive coding tasks
to enhancing debugging and optimizing
software performance, AI is accelerating
innovation and redefining developer roles.
AI is helping developers write, review,
and debug code faster than ever before.
AI driven tools automate tasks like code
generation, error detection, predictive
maintenance, allowing developers to
focus on high level problem solving
them and architectural decisions.
Rapid prototyping is now possible
in days rather than weeks, cutting
development cycles significantly.
The role of developers is shifting
from manual coders to AI orchestrators.
Instead of focusing on low
level syntax, developers are now
responsible for integrating AI tools,
managing AI automation workflows,
and optimizing AI generated code.
This shift means developers must adapt
to new skills like AI integration, model
tuning, and ethical AI implementation.
AI is powerful, but it cannot
replace human intuition,
creativity, and critical thinking.
The future of software development
lies in collaboration between AI and
developers, where AI automates repetitive
tasks, while humans focus on innovation,
strategy, and complex decision making.
AI is no longer just an assistant.
It's an integral part
of software development.
Developers and organizations
that embrace AI driven workflows
will gain a competitive edge,
accelerating innovation while ensuring
responsible and ethical AI adoption.
The future is not about
AI replacing developers.
It's about AI enhancing and empowering
human expertise in building the
next generation of software.
Thank you for the opportunity.
I hope this talk was
helpful and insightful.