Hello, everyone.
Welcome to my talk on transforming
workflow automation, leveraging AI
and machine learning for enhanced
efficiency and digital decision making.
In this talk, we are going to explore
how these technologies are driving
efficiency, intelligent decision making
and adaptive process across the industry.
Let's get into it.
The evolution of workflow automation
from task to intelligence.
we have the traditional automation,
and the now AI power automation.
So the traditional automation, centered
on mechanically automating repeatability
tasks through the rigid and script
driven process, where, people, used
to write Java, NET, the typical
software development, characterized
by, manual configuration, predefined
workflows, and limited flexibilities.
This system operate on static
rule-based logic with minimal
contextual understanding.
So once it is set, every time there is, as
a change happens or a new, SOP, comes into
the picture, somebody have to open the
code and then, change the configuration
or rewrite the, the workflow, stages,
and then how to redeploy release the
late, the next version of the software.
Which is the type consuming
and expensive on the long run.
coming to the AI powered automation.
so the transcending, basic task execution,
AI driven, driven workflows leverage
advanced machine learning algorithms
to dynamically analyze the complex
data set, generate the intelligent
insight and, autonomously adopt to
evolving operational environments.
This sophisticated approach
enables continuous learning,
predictive optimization and
unprecedented operational efficiency.
So in, in the, the world of, BPM and
C-M-N-D-M-N, the workflow stages are
going to be driven by the data, and
create the task or create the approvals.
based on, based on the data and the, the
ever changing, the business processes.
So what is the benefit of the
AI driven, automation, approach,
unlocking the efficiency and insight
through, AI and ML? 50 percent of
intelligent, task optimization,
AI driven workflows dramatically
minimize the manual intervention.
empowering teams to redirect human
creativity to towards the strategic
high value organizational objectives.
And 90 percent of operative intelligence,
advanced machine learning algorithms
transform historical data into
precise predictive models, enabling
organizations to anticipate the train,
mitigate the risk, and make data driven
decision with unprecedented accuracy.
AAML in action, the real world
applications, it is across all the,
sectors, in finance, advanced AI algorithm
detect fraudulent transactions with 95
percent accuracy, proactively safeguarding
financial institutions, reducing
potential losses by millions annually.
The healthcare industry, the machine
learning models in the predictive
diagnostic, and identify the potential
health risk up to 18 months in advance.
transforming the healthcare from reactive
treatment to proactive prevention.
The manufacturing, AI driven predictive
maintenance reduces the unexpected
equipment failures up to 70 percent
minimizing the production downtime
and generating substantial cost
saving across industry operations.
The power of national, language
processing, in a couple of use cases
here, automated email management,
leveraging the advanced NLP algorithms.
Organizations can now, automatically
parse, prioritize, and respond
to the email with unprecedented
accuracy, dramatically reducing
the administrative overhead and
accelerating the communication workflow.
in the case of intelligent chatbots,
our next generation age and was powered
by sophisticated NLP technology can
comprehend context, intent and nuances,
delivering the personalized real
time support that seamlessly mimics
human interaction and dramatically
enhances the customer engagement.
So adapting to the change, the
reinforcement learning for dynamic
workflow the first step, the reinforcement
learning algorithm leverage the
sophisticated reward based mechanism to
enable the workflow that, autonomously
adapt and optimize performance in
complex and rapid changing environment.
Through the advanced computational models,
this intelligence system iteratively
learn from each interaction, progressively
refining the decisions, making strategies,
and minimizing, performance errors.
In critical domains like supply chain
management, reinforcement learning
can dynamically recalibrate routing,
inventory, and logistic protocols,
delivering a significant operational
efficiencies and cost reductions.
The future of workflow automation,
is, starts with, the bottom level,
with the robotics where advanced
robotic system that, intelligently
collaborates with the human teams.
Thank you Automating complex,
physical tasks with the precision,
adaptability, and expanding the
boundaries of human productivity.
As an next upper layer, cloud
computing, where the elastic, globally
distributed infrastructure provides
scalable computational power, enabling
seamless integration of advanced
technologies and support complex
intelligent workflow architecture.
Going higher, IOT, hyper connected
sensor network, that captures real
time granular data across physical
and digital environment, providing
rich insights for predictive and
proactive strategic planning.
And at the top, AIML transformative
intelligence that, dynamically
learns, predicts, and autonomously
optimizes the workflows.
enabling unprecedented adaptive
decision making and continuous
organizational evolution.
The actionable strategies for
implementing AIML in the workflow.
The first step is a strategic
process assessment, conduct a
comprehensive audit to pinpoint the
specific workflow bottlenecks and
opportunities where AIML can deliver
transformative operational improvements.
and the next is the robust, data
infrastructure, develop a strategic
data management, framework that
ensures high quality, clean and diverse
datasets necessary for training,
accurate and reliable AI models.
And as a next step, iterative
implementation approach, deploy
the targeted pilot project with a
clear metrics, enabling controlled
experiments, learning, progressive
scaling of AI model solution.
across organizational functions.
So the benefits of AI driven workflow
automation are enhanced efficiency,
where, streamline the operation,
reduce the manual effort and free
up valuable resources and, the
improved decision making, leverage
the data driven insight to make more
informal and strategic decisions.
Increased agility, adapt quickly to
changing the conditions and market demand.
improving the responsiveness
and the competitive advantage on
gain a competitive advantage by
optimizing the process and deliver
exceptional customer experiences.
Reimagining the work on the
powerful synergy of human
creativity and AI intelligence.
A ML driven workflow automation
represents a transformative
partnership where intelligent
technologies amplify human potential.
By automating the routine task and
providing advanced insights AIM powers
professionals To elevate their work
enabling deeper, strategic thinking
Unleashing creative problem solving
and fostering more meaningful customer
connections that derive genuine innovation
So the key takeaways and next steps are
from this talk are AIML power workflow
automation is transforming the way we work
offering the unprecedented opportunities
for efficiency, intelligence, and agility.
Embrace this advancement, explore
the potential of AI, and prepare
your organization for a future where
human and AI collaboration derives,
rise to innovation and success.
Thank you for joining my talk.
See you next time.