My name is Dileesh, welcome to my talk
on optimizing network performance,
and automation using Apache
Airflow, Python and data science.
So let's get started.
So I'll cover this PPT in brief, and
then I'll go through, how Apache Airflow
works and give a short demo of it.
I've have it installed on my
local machine, so I'll just
give a quick demo of it later.
So let's get started
with the presentation.
So introduction to network performance
automation, So there are several modern
challenges, that networks face, right now,
which is due to the increase in complexity
and, scale of, the devices and the
new, technologies that come into place.
So everything needs to
have network, right?
So all of these challenges, some of
them can be solved by automation.
And the main driver for that automation
is Python and the orchestrated
platform that's best built for running
Python workflows is Apache Airflow.
So for network challenges, so there
are several components, right?
So coming to complexity.
So there are several multi
layered architectures, with, a
mix of, legacy and modern systems.
So there are different devices
that we connect to and different
protocols that they follow.
And there are different technologies that
exist within a single network as well.
And the network has to support all
of these technologies in tandem.
So coming to scale, so now due to
the proliferation of the internet,
so right now the connected devices
that we use, have exploded in scale.
So for example, from your watch
to phone, headphones, laptop
devices, any IOT devices that
you do and it's growing actually.
The prediction is within
billions, within 20.
2030. and, due to the
increase in, density as well.
So if you take a grid of, certain,
areas and compare the devices
that's that exists right now with
previous version of the devices.
So right now, the density,
has increased a lot.
and if you want to have a smart city or an
industrial IOT city, that it puts really
pressure on the current infrastructure,
and it tests the limits of it.
and, there are other challenges such
as resource allocation, where you
have to distribute all the bandwidth
to all these devices and the compute
power and storage, to avoid bottlenecks
for the devices and latency as well.
So coming to latency, you would
need a network to perform in a very
optimized way for these devices to.
stream whatever content that
you are streaming, right?
So for example, if you have an AR VR
device, that streaming data, so you don't
want to have any lag in the network.
So all of these are challenges that
are faced by, networks currently.
So a role of automation in improving
network performance, right?
So automation is one of the
cornerstones for, scaling and
optimizing network performance.
it can do productive fault management
where it can detect, any issues with the
network, reroute the traffic through,
devices and conditions and, outages.
So you can have some automated scripts
run the network and, resolve that issue.
And there are several Python
powered automation tools.
So Python has Played a big role previously
and plays a big role right now, with
within the networks to proactively
fault manage, for these networks.
So you can use Ansible, Netmeco, Napalm.
So these are all, packages
within Python, right?
So these are powered by Python.
And coming to dynamic scaling
and self healing networks.
So whenever we talk about dynamic
scaling and self healing networks,
there are software defined networks,
SDNs, and you have your network
functional, virtualization.
So it uses Python as well.
And Python scripts.
Drive a lot of, network
and network performance.
So it, interacts with different devices,
different frameworks, routers, which
is, any network device that you have.
and these controllers, the devices have
controllers that are support Python.
So you can use Python to interact with the
device directly, and they have the built
in libraries that are built, that you can
leverage to interact with these devices.
So coming to some, real
world examples, right?
Apache Airflow, you can use it
to, optimize your, orchestrate
your network workflows, including
provisioning, monitoring, and scaling,
suggesting provisioning, network speed
testing, and semantic similarity.
So these are some of the
examples that we've used in the
past, for some of my clients.
and it's proven to be very good.
and very optimized version of,
provisioning, monitoring, and scaling, and
improving that for network performance.
So coming to Apache Airflow.
So what is Apache Airflow?
So it's an open source framework.
it's an orchestration tool, basically
whatever Python scripts that you have,
you define those scripts in a way it's
there orchestrated in a way that you
can run all of your tasks within Python.
and, the core component of Apache
Airflow is scheduler, where it schedules
your Python workflows, the way that
you mentioned, how you want to run it.
So it's built in Python itself.
So it's built on top of Python.
it uses something called, DAGs.
So directed acyclic graphs,
where you can schedule.
All your components in an acyclic manner.
for example, if you want to run
three functions, you can define which
function to run first, second and
third, and so on and so forth, right?
So you want to run third, first,
second, and then first, you can
define it that way, making them
dynamic and reusable and scalable.
coming to the key features, right?
Dynamic workflow authoring.
So you can use Python code to
define tasks, the dependencies
and schedules for that.
in the configuration section, you
can mention how often do you want to
run it, just like a cron job, right?
So you can, write the cron expression
for it to run, to your liking every
once in a while, once in a day.
or a however you like, right?
So extensibility.
it can integrate with other systems.
you can have custom operators, hooks.
So there are already several
built within Apache Airflow.
and everything is written in Python as
well, where you have custom operators,
that can interface with, Azure or AWS
or any other cloud provider on any other
system that you would like, scalability.
So it supports distributed
systems execution as well.
So it has components like celery,
Kubernetes or local executor that can
perform tasks in a scalable manner.
So you basically start
out with a local executor.
So these are backend
functionalities, right?
So executor is nothing but something
that's behind, an Apache Airflow
framework that runs, your workflows.
you can, so initially started with a
local executor where you execute these
tasks and the, if you don't care about
the, scalability part, you can start
with local and then scale out basically.
So that's how you make the
systems distributed, right?
So basically you start out with,
vertical scaling, where you have a
single device, single machine, and
increase the resources in that machine.
And then you scale up to multiple systems,
as you, as your scale and increases.
So monitoring and alert.
So it has integration with, different,
Platforms such as Slack, email, Microsoft
Teams, or, discord, anything, right?
So all of the things are built in so you
can use that to alert you, and web UI.
So I'll get to and get into this
later, but it has a really intuitive
and a really great way to visualize,
manage and debug workflows.
coming to the benefits of it, right?
So it simplifies your Python code a lot.
So if you have, let's say a thousand
lines of code, it's really hard for
you to, manage and maintain that code.
What went wrong, where it went wrong.
Of course you can do some logging
statements and find out what's going on.
But, Apache Airflow gives you a
really intuitive web UI where you can.
Log in and check the, check the, how your
DAG performs and see where it went wrong.
Exactly.
So it enhances the transparency.
logs and visualizations so you can
visualize what's going on with your
workflow and reduce manual interventions.
So use cases of Apache Airflow
in network operations, right?
So you can have Apache
Airflow run some provisioning.
So it automated tasks like, provisioning
physical sims or virtual sims,
managing IMSI ranges and updating
systems like SRP, and others.
And, once I've implemented this,
it turns turned out to be a very
fast, execution of SIM provisioning
rather than the legacy systems.
So Apache Airflow gave us a platform where
we can leverage Python and, different.
Parameters of provisioning process to
really improve the speeds for first net
HSS, it's first net is nothing but first
responder communication network where, all
of the communication for first responders
have happened through that first net HSS.
And it turned out to be,
really great for that use case.
Network speed testing.
So gathering telemetry data,
analyzing, key performance indicators,
triggers, anomalies in network.
So it turned out to be a great use
case for speed testing as well.
Coming to configuration management,
deploying configuration to router
switches, and other servers and services.
it, it makes it very easy to
configure all of your devices.
Thank you within your network
and predictive analytics as well.
So the way that you can write
Apache Airflow workflow.
You can have all of your ETL tasks
performed within the pipelines itself,
and you can have your machine learning
models or semantic search models as well.
So how Apache Airflow, helps
automate workflows, enhance
efficiency and optimize resource use.
So coming to automation, right?
So Airflow eliminates
manual interventions.
that's like how automation
works basically, right?
So you trigger your workflow based
on scheduler or the external events.
It runs all the tasks that you define
it to run and then picks up all
the, things that you want it to do.
Efficiency.
So if you run Celery as an executor in
the backend, it can parallelize tasks,
to how many cores you have in the system.
you can have multiple requests process
at once and try to use execution time.
It restructures the failed
tasks intelligently.
So there is already a built in
mechanism where you can handle re
tries, failed, processes and ensure
that, the workflow is reliable.
the resources automation, right?
So there is some concept called task
queues, where you can manage the balance
and work workloads within multiple, VMs.
where you can use kubernetes executor
to scale out all the pods and,
containerized workflow execution.
So you can have your
resource allocation as well.
So automation workflows,
for large sim provisioning
projects, you can use Airflow.
That we've discussed earlier.
So why use Python for Airflow, right?
So Airflow is built on top of a
Python itself, but within Airflow,
you can code Python again.
it's the, for the intuition for
using Python is basically easy to
learn syntax, extensive libraries.
So it has a really good open source
and all of the machine learning
and, Data related stuff happens
in Python in nowadays, right?
if you want to talk about Spark, so there
is libraries for PySpark, within Python
itself, where you can use Spark modules
and Spark frameworks within Python.
There are several libraries and
frameworks that lets you manage, all your
network automation needs within Python.
So netmiko or paramiko, if you heard
about SSH communication, these are,
frameworks that help you with, SSH based
communication to configure, network
devices and interface with those.
So you can automate tasks like, device
configuration, backup troubleshooting.
So you have napalm, pi, SNMB.
You can check this out later.
I'll just give a brief overview of
network X is a really good thing
where you can analyze and visualize
network graphs and topology and
mapping and simulation of the networks.
pandas and embryos for network telemetry
and logs, trends, and anomaly detection.
Basically, pandas, you can create data
frames and process objects within Python.
So predictive analytics for
network optimization, right?
role of data science in
network optimization.
You can identify trends and
anomalies in network, performance.
You can predict failures before they
occur, reduce the downtime, and you
can optimize the resource allocation,
such as bandwidth, processing
power, use for network automation.
So machine learning, right?
So there are several libraries built
on in Python for machine learning.
So if you're trying to build
a machine learning model, you
don't need to do it from scratch.
Python probably has a library
that already does that.
So scikit learn.
So there are several scikit learn.
There are several libraries within
Python for machine learning.
You have TensorFlow, PyTorch, Pandas,
NumPys, for your data processing.
And, these are, you can use these,
libraries for some use cases, such as
failure prediction or anomaly detection.
and automation, use predictions
with Apache Airflow, right?
So you can use Python integrates
basically with everything, right?
So any device, any network device,
any models, any third party
systems that has support for APIs.
it probably have a built in
library that it can leverage.
it, enables real time decision making
through, trigger events, right?
So, so let's take an example
of a workflow tag, right?
So you collect elementary data,
you run a machine learning model
for prediction and some kind of,
automated action you can trigger with.
So automation of network
configuration and provisioning, right?
So using Apache Airplane Python, you
can, do some complex stuff, such as
by same provisioning network setups.
You can set up, a script that
does provision to systems like
HSS, FirstNet, Gport, HLRmind, and
range allocation for SIMs and MCs.
coming to benefits, right?
So it's efficient, accurate, scalable,
and monitoring, wise for, Apache
Airflow, everything that I mentioned
right now, those are the beneficial
benefits that for using, Apache Airflow.
If you take an example for SIM
provisioning, within Apache Airflow,
you collect all the user requests, SIM
types, MC ranges, and you execute the
provisioning tasks with different systems.
So each system has one component
where it uses either RTELnet, LDAP,
or whatever, communication, way of
communication that you do either SSH.
Now to that system and origin, all
the sims, you validate those, you
present the log status and, you can
have a workflow that step that can,
notify, someone of the completion.
So that's basically,
it for how to optimize.
So let's dive right in to, how
Apache Airflow works, right?
Airflow is an open source tool, right?
So there is really good documentation
on how this basically works.
what, providers, these are
all the active providers that,
Airflow supports right now.
So you can have a Cassandra
connection to Cassandra, Amazon,
AWS, a lot of stuff, basically.
So if you take Amazon, for
example, using Apache Airflow.
they provide all the versions
related to, they're within
their, server itself service.
So installing it in your local, right?
So I've installed, my
version using, Docker.
So there is really good
documentation on how to do it.
So you can play around with it as well.
But first let's make sure our Docker.
Instances running right now.
So Docker engine is paused.
So let's resume that.
So I already have a Docker installed.
Let's go to a terminal.
Let's check.
It's already running.
No.
Yes.
So I've installed earlier.
let's check.
So I have the Docker compose file.
So let's do Docker, Docker compose up.
So it creates all the containers.
and it starts up all the services that
are required for So one of the good
thing is all of the containers are built
in, using Docker, so you don't need
to create each instance separately.
if you're planning to run a
parallelized version of Airflow.
So it's starting up.
Let's see.
So it's started all the Airflow stuff.
Docker, reduce.
Postgres.
Postgres 13 is a database that Airflow
backend uses for storing metadata.
So web server.
It looks like all the service is
running except for Docker Airflow.
Let's see what's going on.
There you go.
I think it started now.
Let's go to localhost and
check if it's running.
So I see the instance is running.
So this is a UI that you get to, you
get to log in screen, but default
or airflow and airflow credentials.
so here you have your dags, dags are the
workflows that you can schedule, to run in
Python and it shows all the dags, right?
And there are two sections
here called active and Post.
So you can have your workflow and
you can either have it run or, in
a pause state or an unpause state.
If you want to run it, you
can click on this button.
It will make it active.
So there are two, active
workflows right now.
If you want to turn it off, you can
just turn it off using this button.
So it gives a really good user interface.
You can manage everything here.
So coming to security, it
has users, roles, actions,
everything, permissions too, right?
So you can manage user permissions.
if you go to users, you can find all the
users here, you can create users, you can
drill down into how you want to manage the
RBAC for users, and you have admin section
as well, where you have all your variables
and you can basically create connections
to different, Services where it can see
it has all the stuff related to, Amazon,
AWS, Azure, Docker or anything, right?
So it has a lot of built in libraries.
You can interface with
SQLite database as well.
If you select SQLite, it should
give you a connection to a SQLite.
So you give it a host login, password.
It should be able to connect to and
there is an option to test as well.
So you can create a connection and
test it out coming to workflows, right?
So this is an example
workflow that I ran earlier.
So it gives you a really good interface.
So it took 20 seconds to run.
The run type is manual
because the schedule is none.
So there is no schedule set up for this.
So, if I run this again, so it should
automatically trigger a new Where, if you
check the graph of it, how this looks,
so this is how the graph looks right?
So first it goes here.
The logical output is run this.
And you basically, once this
is run, you go to this step.
And after this executes,
you run all of these steps.
So now this is done, right?
So let's drill down into each of this.
So this is nothing but Python code base.
So, basically you define
all of your functions here.
these are just examples
that airflow provided.
So this is a. way that you can
specify what the DAG is about.
And this is a function
basically, print context, right?
So it, this is a task.
This is an operator where you
can print the context of what's
going on within this function.
So here there are other functions as well.
Let's see what sleep three does.
So
sleep for three.
So this is task sleep for three.
and you can drill down into event
log what happened within the events.
details of this, and you can
go into each individual log and
check what happened there as well.
So if you check the logs, so this is
nothing but, the log for this task.
So all of the quarks here,
you have context, variables.
We have what happened within
the log, within the operator.
And if you click on here, you can
check out what's going on here as well.
So that is it for Apache Airflow.
so there is, interactive APIs as well.
So it, everything is built in within here.
So let's open Swagger.
So it automatically, it takes,
basic code, Airflow and Airflow.
And you can use this
APIs externally as well.
If you have Postman, if you want
to test it out, you can basically,
8080 and, run the DAG ID.
So it asks for basically.
Few things, right?
DAG ID.
So you can select any DAG ID from here.
Let's check what the DAG ID is for this.
DAG ID is example Python operator, right?
So let's copy this
and paste it here.
Oh, let's do get.
So it gives you all the
information about this, right?
So what the DAG is about the file token.
Where it is and what's
going on with the, DAG.
So there is a lot of stuff that I
want to go out, but I don't think
I can cover it in one session.
But, yeah, you can go to the documentation
and, find out, about Apache Airflow mode.
So you can run, so this is
basically what I told, right?
You can run your workflows as code.
And security is built within Airflow as
well, where you can, there is something
called fernet key, that encrypts all your,
passwords, usernames, everything, right?
So basically security is
baked in to Apache Airflow.
And this is how we set
up a diagram, right?
So this is basically how a
diagram, so you define a task.
You'll give an operator and you'll
ask Airflow to run the operator.
so that is pretty much it for
Apache Airflow, Python and network
automation, and data science.
So if you have any more questions,
you can certainly reach out to me.
Thanks for joining me in this session.