Hi everyone.
thanks for joining the
Python 2025 conference call.
So today I'll be talking about designing
a robust architecture for seamless
and efficient migration from on
premise infrastructure to Azure Cloud.
So in this presentation we will delve
Into the best practices for creating an
efficient architecture that facilitates
Seamless migration from on premise to
club the talk covers everything from
planning automation to leveraging azure
services for scalability and cost savings.
You will live with practical
tips to guide your cloud journey.
let me, go for an introduction
to cloud migration and Azure.
overview of Cloud Adoption Azure role.
let's start with an,
overview of Cloud Adoption.
Why it has become essential
for modern businesses?
Cloud migration refers to the
process of moving data application
and other business elements from on
premise infrastructure to the cloud.
So Azure as a cloud platform plays a
pivotal role in this transformation.
Its flexibility, scalability, and
security capabilities make it a preferred
choice for enterprise across industries.
So by adopting Azure,
organizations can access.
A wide range of services that
ensures their, operations remain
agile, cost effective, and secure.
So benefit of migrating to Azure.
So migration, migrating to
Azure offers numerous benefits.
First, scalability, which provides like a
virtually unlimited computing resources,
allowing businesses to grow without
worrying about infrastructure cost.
It also enhances flexibility by
enabling companies to shift from
Capital expenses to operational cost
security is another strong point.
Azure is equipped with advanced
security measures, ensuring that
your data is always protected.
Additionally, Azure global presence
enables high availability and disaster
recovery across different regions.
Azure services over for overview of
cloud migration is like Azure provides
a comprehensive suite of services
designed to facilitate cloud migration.
Key services like Azure Assist with
planning and executing the migration.
Is your site recovery ensures business
continuity, while tools like a zoo storage
and networking help optimize performance
and connectivity, whether it's for virtual
missions, database or entire workloads.
I should has dedicated services for
every aspect of migration journey.
Let's jump to next slide.
So here we will talk about pre
migration consideration as a
saying like existing on premise
infrastructure for Azure readiness.
So before embarking on migration,
it is crucial to assess.
how do you optimize your
critical infrastructure?
This includes understanding the
state of your hardware, software,
network, setup, and the application.
Are they optimized for cloud migration?
Conducting a thorough assessment helps
identifying potential roadblocks, such
as outdated systems or applications
that may require re platforming or re
architecting your cloud compatibility.
setting clear migration objectives.
Defining clear objectives is
essential to successful migration.
Do you want to reduce cost or
enhance performance, improve
scalability or reliability?
Whatever your goals are, it's important
to align them with your business needs.
For example, if your goal is to disaster
recovery, you might prioritize Azure
Site Recovery feature to ensure minimal
downtime during the migration process.
key factors for workload, SAP
workload migrations are like
migrating SAP workloads, particularly
systems like SAP HANA or S4 HANA
requires special considerations.
SAP HANA are often highly complex
and ensuring that they run
smoothly on Azure requires in depth
understanding of Azure capabilities.
So factors like HA, High Availability,
Performance Optimization, and
Storage Management are essential when
migrating SAP workloads to clouds.
Let's dive into next session.
next slide.
So core principles of cloud architecture.
We will talk about that.
when designing a cloud architecture, key
principles includes Scalability, security,
resilience, and cost optimization.
These four are the main key principles.
Scalability ensures that your
architecture can grow your business.
Security is critical, ensuring the
sensitive data is protected both at
rest or in transit and in transit.
Resilience ensures minimal downtime
with automatic failover and
cost option optimization helps
ensure that you don't overspend
on unnecessary resources.
Azure well architecture framework
provides That helps the success
of your cloud architecture.
So this tool, what we have in
Azure, it includes key P five
pillars, cost optimization,
operation, excellence, performance,
efficiency, reliable, and security.
Each pillar is designed to ensure that
you are building a robust, efficient,
and secure cloud infrastructure.
Ensuring smooth operations
in the long run.
SAP specific cloud architecture
design is somewhat like, it's not
different, but similar to that.
For SAP specific workloads, what we
do is that ensuring high availability
is critical first for them.
Azure provides options like AV zones,
that means availability zones, and
load balancing to maintain uptime.
Additionally, migrating SAP HANA database
requires specialized configurations.
Such as high performance storage
options and ensuring data integrity
during the migration process.
Let's go to next slide here.
We'll talk about Azure Migration Approach.
So what are the approach we follow?
There are many type of migrations
approach we can follow.
So when migrating to Azure,
we follow like lift and shift
that is Rehost they call it as.
This is the simplest approach.
where you move as they are to
Azure with minimal charges to suit
different type of work requirements.
Re platforming, that is called,
we call this a repackage.
In this approach, you might need
to modify certain components to be
more Azure friendly, but don't make
drastic changes to the architecture.
re architecting for Azure Cloud Native
solutions, this is most comprehensive
approach, where you redesign your
application to fully leverage Azure
Cloud Native services Such as using Azure
Kubernetes service for containerizations,
tools and services for migrations.
What we use here when we do the
migration to streamline migration,
we use Azure Migrate is a central
centralized hub to access and also
move your on premise workload to Azure.
And Azure Site Recruit as we have
discussed, as we discussed in our previous
slides where it ensures disaster recovery
and smooth failover during migration.
Azure automation simplifies and
automates repetitive tasks and making
the migration process more efficient.
So data migration and synchronization,
let's talk about that, why we need that.
So tools like Azure Database Migration
Service allows you to transfer your
database to Azure with minimal downtime.
For larger databases, You can go for
Azure Data Bots, offers a physical
appliance for secure fast data transfers.
Azure Data Factory is one more
tool which helps synchronization,
synchronize data across environments,
ensuring that data is consistent and
available during the migration process.
Let's get on to another slide.
Next slide is this is the also.
Post migration optimization
management will talk about here.
So SAP post migration
optimization, what does it mean?
So once the whole migration
is complete, optimizing SAP
workloads on Azure is crucial.
So this includes.
Performance tuning to ensure that SAP
application runs smoothly as well as
storage optimization for SAP HANA,
which can be resource intensive.
Azure provides various tools to help
monitor and fine tune these workloads.
And let's talk about a continuous
monitoring and maintenance.
So Azure, we have a lot of tools like
Azure Monitor, Azure Automation and
Azure Center, Security Center helps in
countries monitoring and how does like
so with this comprehensive monitoring
tools like Azure Monitor where you can
monitor real time insights into your
workloads and then Azure Automation
helps maintain consistency across
environments while Azure Security
Center ensures your system remains That
is the main important, tool we have.
Regular maintenance is vital to avoid
issues and optimize performance.
Let's talk about ongoing backup and
disaster recovery, which is a critical
part after post migration of SAP systems
or any application you take it up.
So even post migration, backup and
disaster recovery are essential.
Azure Backup ensures your critical
workloads are safe and While high
availability and disaster recovery plans
ensures that your application can quickly
recover in case of any system failure.
Let's dive to next session.
Let's talk about leveraging
automation for migration.
So automation is a key
part of cloud migration.
So here, why I said automation is a
key part of learning because Automation
Azure Automate helps streamline the
migration process by automating tasks
like deployment and patch management.
Azure DevOps allows you to done
define, sorry, infrastructure
as a core, enabling repeatable
deployment and ensuring continuous
across environment environments.
Azure Logic apps can automate workflows.
And integrate various systems
without manual intervention.
That is the best part here
we have in automation.
So we do have Cloud Adoption
Framework for migration.
When we do migration, the Cloud
Adoption Framework, what we have is
helps guides your migrations, SAP
migration through several phases.
How does it guide?
Like strategy phase.
We're aligning cloud adoption
codes with our overall business
strategies and planning phase.
This phase conducts readiness assessments
to ensure that your infrastructure and
the processes are prepared for migration.
And ready phase is there, setting up
governance models and security framework
to ensure compliance during migration.
Adopt phase, this is the phase
where, executing the migration plan.
While ensuring minimal disruption
to ongoing business process,
governance phase they will say
that ongoing compliance, cost
optimization and operation governance.
Manage phase here we do continuous
monitoring optimization and
scaling post migrations.
So these are all like, part of like
cloud adoption framework phases,
which we follow to ensure that smooth
migration of your, landscape to cloud.
Let's get into the next
slide where we'll talk about
Conclusion and future directions.
So we'll talk about something like,
so whatever we have learned cloud
journey migration journey so far,
we'll make it as a wrapping up.
So here, cloud migration is a
complex but rewarding journey
that involves careful planning,
execution, and ongoing optimization.
Once you have successfully
migrated, you will see significant
improvement in scalability, cost,
efficiency, and performance.
The future of cloud and SAP
in digital transformation era.
How does it look?
As a digital transformation
accelerates, the future of
cloud and SAP is intertwined.
With emerging technologies like AI,
machine learning, and IOT, SAP's role in
the cloud continues to grow and companies
are leveraging these capabilities
to drive innovation and business
Innovations in cloud migration, AI, ML,
and edge computing are part of this.
Technologies like AI, ML, edge
computing are revolutionizing
the cloud migration process.
These innovations help automate tasks,
predict issues before they occur.
And optimize workloads in real time,
making cloud adoptions even more seamless.
The earlier we talked about
about HA, high availability.
So to failover from Azure side,
we have different tools like,
AV zones with the SLAs of 99.
99%, AV set with 99.
95%. So those are the
SLAs for, from Azure side.
Whereas from SAP side, for HA, we have
clustering tools, like Pacemaker, SIOS
Cluster tool, and Veritas InfoScale tool
is also available, where we can make
the failover, automation of failover,
in case of any disruption to the primary
region or primary system, primary HANA
database, or SAP EACS server or SAP
Enquiry Application Server will be there.
So with those tools, we'll do the
failover, automation of failover.
So at any point of time, the
user will not see any disruptions
during their working session.
So let's talk about my last point,
like emerging trends in SAP and
cloud, how that future will be.
The future of SAP in the cloud is
increasing, increasingly cloud native.
As SAP continues to evolve and
organizations are adopting cloud
native solutions, leveraging
microservices and containerization.
To create more flexible and
scalable architecture on Azure.
That's how I conclude.
I work for Microsoft.
Thank you all.
Thanks for listening to my session.
Thank you all once again.
Bye.
Take care.