Hello, welcome to con 42 Python 2025.
My name is Ashok Chonlakata.
I'm going to, I'm going to discuss about
revolutionizing data center operations.
It is a quantitative analysis
of AI driven optimization.
Let's, without any delay, let's
get into the topic, coming to
the predictive maintenance.
it is about reducing equipment failures.
coming to the AI powered early warning
system, our machine learning algorithm
process real time sensors, achieving a
47 percent reduction in unexpected The
system provide critical alerts up to
72 hours before potential issues arise
and enabling proactive maintenance
coming to the continuous performance
monitoring with a 96 percent prediction
accuracy through advanced monitoring of
temperature, vibration and power patterns.
We prevent an average of
127 hours of downtime.
Per quarter, maximizing operational
efficiency and coming to the resource
optimization in terms of maximizing
efficiency, improved resources
utilization, AI power system achieved
a 31 percent improvement in resource
utilization by dynamically allocating
computing resources based on real time
workload analysis and automated capacity
management latency, advanced machine
learning algorithm, Reduced server
latency by 38 percent through intelligent
load balancing and a predictive traffic
management resulting in 42 percent
faster application response time.
coming to the energy management
in terms of optimizing cooling
systems, enhanced cooling efficiency,
advanced deep learning model.
Achieved a 42 percent improvement
in cooling efficiency through
real time temperature optimization
and smart airflow management.
This resulted in annual
energy savings of 3.
2 million kilowatt hours
across our facilities.
reduced PUI, PUE.
Through AI driven thermal mapping
and intelligent load distribution, we
reduced power usage effectiveness, PUE.
from 1.
6, 1. 7 to below 1.
25 within six months.
This 23 percent reduction in
cooling costs translate to 2.
8 millions of savings.
security, advanced threat
detection and response.
So 98.
5, 5 percent accuracy,
detecting a security incident.
Uh, our airport security
framework issued 98.
5. in identifying potential threats,
analyzing over 1 million security
events per second while maintaining
a false positive rate below 0.
1, 0.
01%. coming to the reduced response
times, critical security incidents
are now addressed within 45 seconds.
An 85 percent improvement
in security incidents.
Over manual intervention.
This rapid response
capability has been prevented.
99.9% of attempted reaches across
our global infrastructure network.
coming to the capacity planning,
the predictive future demand.
in this, the model, we use these
neural network model, our advanced
deep landing framework leverage.
ISTM neural network to achieve 96
percent accuracy in demand, forecasting,
processing fires of historical data
across 2000 performance metric to predict
capacity needs up to 18 months in advance.
proactive scaling by analyzing workload
patterns and resource utilization trends.
Our prediction system automatically
initiate scaling operation 72 hours
before demand spikes, resulting
in finance service availability.
And a 42 percent reduction in all
provisioning cost while maintaining
optimal performance across all systems.
cost savings and return on
investment, ROI, annual savings.
These AI implementations have
collected, collectively resulted
in average annual savings of 2.
4, 2. 4 million for
enterprise scale deployments.
Increased efficiency by automating.
Automatically process and
optimization resources.
AI solution reduce operation cost
and improve overall efficiency.
Enhanced competitive advantage.
AI driven data center operations deliver
a competitive edge by enabling business
to adapt, change engineering needs, and
deliver Superior performance coming to
the intelligent coming to the integration
challenges and, practical insights.
in terms of data quality, implementing
a robust data validation protocol
and a cleansing pipelines to ensure
consistent, accurate and a properly
labeled data sets for a training,
coming to the model training, balancing
computational cost with the model.
Flexicity while maintaining extensive
training data set across diverse
operational scenarios, coming to the
deployment and monitoring, establishing
a continuous integration pipelines,
performance metrics and automated
monitoring system to ensure reliable model
performance in production environments.
case studies, the real world
implementations, in terms of small data
centers, a regional cloud provider with,
800 kilowatt facility implemented a
driven cooling optimization resulting
in 35 percent energy savings, which
in terms of, around 450 K annually.
while improving equipment
reliability by 25, 28 percent and
reducing carbon emission by 420
tons per year, which is beautiful.
And then coming to the large scale data
centers, a fortune 500 company, more
than six megawatt data center deployment,
deployed AI based predictive maintenance,
cutting equipment failures by 40%,
achieving finance uptime and saving 2.
5, 2. 1 million annually.
Roadmap for future AI adoption.
we can, achieve this in three steps.
step one, expand AI applications
and then improve AI model accuracy.
And number three is foster collaborations.
conclusion, embracing AI
for data center excellence.
AI driven.
Optimization offers significant benefits
for data center operations, including
increased efficiency, reduced cost,
and enhanced reliability by embracing
AI data center can achieve a new
level of excellence and unlock the
full potential of the infrastructure.
And then, let me know any questions.
Thank you.
And thank you for giving
me this opportunity.