Hey everyone, I'm Amar.
I'm thrilled to welcome
you to the session.
As a senior manager of software
engineering at Lowe's, I have had
the privilege of leading the teams
that design and deliver platforms
capable of supporting millions of
users and millions of transactions.
Today we are here to learn some of it
and then deep dive into how real time
data is transforming customer experience
at a scale, discover how millions of
interactions are being processed in near
real time or every second, and then how
do we build ML powered recommendation
engines and then how Python helps
create fast, efficient data systems.
just think about this, right?
if you could process over a million
records or million transactions every
second, while, maintaining a near,
uptime, a near perfect uptime, and
provide actionable insights quickly.
Right.
Imagine the competitive advantage that,
brings whether it is delivering lightning
fast personalization recommendations
or enabling, real time decision making
or proactively addressing customer
needs, before they even arise.
In this session, we will uncover
the architectures required, and
strategies that companies are
using to achieve these goals.
I'll share, the real, world examples,
walk you through, the architectures,
technical designs, and probably, the
challenges and how do we overcome that.
whether you are here to supercharge your
technical expertise, gather actionable
insights, to tackle, the current
challenges that you are, your team is
facing, or probably like, just simply
exploring the incredible possibilities
of, the real time analytics, you're
in the right place, let's get, going.
So let's understand, the
customer expectations.
What are the customers expecting, lately?
so in today's hyperconnected digital
landscape, I think, a, a survey
indication, says that 82 percent of
the customers now expect real time.
personalized experiences that instantly,
adapt to their individual preference
and then probably immediate need, right?
so the companies who have
strategically deployed and try to
solve these, real time personalized,
situation, have seen a remarkable,
26 percent boost in the customer
satisfaction and an extraordinary,
a customer, lifetime value of 3.
2, X.
So let's get, to, how do we, deal
with, dealing with, These, scenarios
to unlock the customer insights, right?
in today's competitive, digital space,
I think, primarily the industry leaders,
Amazon could be Amazon or could be
Netflix or in the, in the, in the
space that they are leading are ha,
harnessing, the power of, like advanced
algorithms, and probably mission
learning models to process and analyze,
massive streams of data in real time.
By managing over 1 million, customer
transactions every second, these companies
are able to extract immediate or valuable
insights instantly to understand what
is the guest or customer is expecting.
Right.
Just try to understand how does
this algorithms work or what is
this real time data about it.
I am going to deep dive much into
the technical aspects pretty soon.
But imagine how does this algorithms
work and then how do we get to
a state of talking through these
real time monitoring or predictive
analysis or sentiment analysis.
So the first step in the
process is the data collection.
So in this particular, scenario, it
talks about, the data that is being
collected from various sources like
web activity, IoT devices, and the
transactions that are happening.
And then the data is in the raw format,
so it has to be processed, cleansed.
so some, some examples could be
removing duplicates or handling missing
values or maybe, adding synthetic data
in case the data is not available.
All these steps are being done during
the pre processing step, right?
And this data is being fed to,
the, pre trained, models, to,
pre trained ML models, right?
at this point of time, what do we
certainly look around is we understand,
or analyze the behavior, patterns
such as like collaborative filter for
recommendations, and then probably
predict the outcome, say in, in, in
the case of retail, situation, right?
is the, what is the guest looking to buy?
What is the guest looking to buy?
What item are probably, is the guest
going to make the transaction, right?
And then, we could be also able to
segment customers dynamically based on
some of these real time interactions.
So, So, one biggest, I think, so these
models will, enable the decision, a
decision engine, wherein algorithms, that
trigger actions, these algorithms trigger
actions such as, personalized offers
or product recommendations or alerts.
Say probably like, say, once this
particular, event is being triggered, but
we also wanted to have a feedback loop.
which talks about, the user responses,
are fed back into the system to improve,
the models through continuous learning.
So if I'm just trying to jot down, the
things that we just talked about, so
there's a data collection system, there's
a data processing system, and you have
an ML model, which, the model will be
pre trying to determine, Behavioral
pattern, predict outcomes, and then
probably do the segmentations as required.
And then the outcome of that is a decision
engine, which will be, the, say some
examples could be like, in the case
of retail, it could be a personalized
offers, or it could be, a personalized
pricing or a dynamic, personalization,
is something that would be done.
And then the data would also be
retrained with the feedback loop, right?
So let us dive into, how, the,
industry retailers are using or
how, some of the success stories
that we wanted to talk about, right?
So here I have put down like
two examples, like, so, probably
like in, in, in a retail industry
and then the dynamic pricing.
So I wanted to take a minute and
understand, help you out or, talk through,
you know, What are all the use cases
that are possible, by using it, right?
Some of the use cases possible.
So let's assume that, let's take
an example of Amazon, where, it
recommends products dynamically
based on browsing, probably purchase
history and similar user data.
So the outcome of this is obviously higher
conversion and then it also gives us
the customer, it enhances the loyalty.
So when it comes to banking and finance,
the fraud detection algorithms, flag
unusual activity or a transaction in,
real time prevents, so the outcome result
is to prevent losses and improve trust.
Say, I think some of us, who might have
been shopping in a different state or
shopping in a different place where the
system did not detect the, transaction
in the past street, it tries to block it.
So, in a near real time, it helps
to avoid, the fraud transactions or
probably if our cards are being lost,
it helps in detecting that information
and try to, stop the wrong transactions.
So when it comes to, healthcare, I think
probably, monitoring, the patient vitals
through, IOT devices and, and alerting
doctors, about anomalies, instantly.
so this will help with the faster
response and, probably like the
better patient outcome, right?
and when it comes to the media, so I
think, the Netflix plays a bigger role,
in a day to day, life of an person.
So Netflix, Netflix,
probably like personalizes.
content recommendation,
based on the viewing history.
And then, so probably like a time
based pattern, like it derives a mood,
the mood of a person, and then tries
to detect the time based pattern.
And then probably based on
the demographics, right?
so this will give increased viewer
engagement and retention, right?
when it comes to retail, so some of
these Personalized discount offers to
in store customers based on their mobile
app, using and browsing data, right?
It turns out to be improved sales
and then in store experiences.
When it comes to airlines, airlines can
dynamically, airlines do dynamically,
adjust the pricing, or suggest add
ons based on user search behavior.
it's an, again, optimized revenue
and better customer targeting.
So this directly, empowers, the
customer, And this directly, empowers,
enhanced customer experience and it
also helps in the customer revenue.
So, it's, it's a win win situation
in, the cases where the real time,
analytics are being, deployed.
So let's move on to the next, slide.
So let's try to understand, I have
just, gone through, talking about,
a quick rundown of, what is, what
are the components of building
a real time, framework, right?
So let's try to understand,
a little, detail.
So, It's primarily, five
to six, six step process.
So, it's a data ingestion,
where, millions of transactions
per second, is being handled.
I'm going to talk through what
are all the, design in detail.
but, in this particular case, there
are various, sources of, data ingestion
and then these data ingestion helps
to handle millions of transactions
to get from diverse, sources like
web, IoT devices, transaction
systems, payment systems, et cetera.
so, and then the next step in the
process is, you call it as a stream
processing, you want this to be,
processed as a stream, not as a batch.
so, during this layer, we process
the data, cleanse the data, and
then, like remove duplicates, and
then take actionable, insights to
get into the actionable insights.
You, like, this is a critical
layer through which, where the
data cleansing happens, right?
And, then, we will have the data storage,
obviously, when it comes to the real
time analytics in order to take some,
insights into it, the, the data will be
stored, in, like says, either, NoSQL or
SQL or, depends on the data sometimes we
wanted to store in time series databases.
And here come, and next the
mission learning engine.
in this case, we, we will
try to generate the real time
recommendations, predictions, and
provide the customer insights.
And then, the insights has to be, sent to,
the, like, for the consumers to consume.
and, like we, we will.
Empower this data through
APIs or through service layer.
so at this phase you have a two mechanisms
where we call it as a push delivery and
pull delivery where, the model is emitting
the data so someone can consume it.
Or, in another case where we, have
a pull delivery where we keep it
open and the consumers will start
listening to us and start getting it.
So, depends on, the use case situation,
the teams, will choose the option.
And when it all comes down to, as
we implement the great, framework,
we also wanted to ensure that.
There's monitoring and observability
pieces has been covered, right?
so, just to ensure that the application
runs stable, accurate and scalable.
so let's try to dive, deep into,
the, data ingestion pipeline, right?
So I'm going to take one, one
of the technology as an example.
And then, probably I'll say,
maybe what are all the tools
available, to do some of this work.
Thank you.
so I'm taking Kafka as an example,
as a streaming platform where, so
from various sources of, the, systems
are the data, emitting systems.
we will start sending the data to a Kafka.
and then, we will start, having a
processing layer read from the Kafka.
If you are imagining a
web, a web application.
web or IOT devices or mobile
apps or could be social media or
could be transactional system.
All these will start
emitting the data to Kafka.
So we provide an API layer or the system
provides an API layer or, through other
mechanisms, it starts emitting Kafka.
When we create a af, when we,
consider Kafka, for our data ion
aspect, some things to consider,
for an better performing Kafka.
So probably segmenting, the.
Kafka, by the customer
partition, or probably like
I'll put in a different word.
Partitioned, by, the customer or
event type is required to maintain
the sequencing if required.
and probably like, obviously Kafka
comes up with the compression.
It has, I believe, three of them, Snap,
EasyZip, and, and I forgot the other one,
but I think depends on, the need basis.
I think using one of these algorithm will
help for the faster throughput, right?
when, when we are reading or
when we are, writing into it.
So I, I personally like to use Snappy
for faster throughput, but I think all
the other, compressions would work great.
When it comes to, streaming, I think
the popular things in the market
is like Apache Spark and Flink.
so one thing to consider when we are
thinking about, one of these, streaming
processing system is to enrich, data
by, joining, the customer, profiles,
either in a, Redis or DynamoDB.
so aggregate metrics such as clicks,
probably like purchase or, session
duration and then probably like,
filter out, like, the invalid data or
probably like we just, in a simpler
words, filter out the noisy enables
or noisy records, using, some of
these Python rule, based, engines.
Thanks.
So, when it comes to storage, I think
there are multiple variations of storage.
We have an hot storage probably
for the real time data.
So, DynamoDB or Elasticsearch and
then probably if you wanted to do
some historical analysis and create.
year on year comparison or
month on month comparison.
So storing the data in, S3 or HDFS or
GCS buckets, will play a bigger, role.
when it comes to, the, a critical
portion of it to get the insights,
out of it, like feeding the
data to mission learning, model.
So it's training and, inference where
we wanted to train, models, offline.
so that you're using some customer
interaction, probably like from the data
lakes and then, use, frameworks like
say PyTorch, to, do some of this work.
And then probably, one thing is that it's
always better to store in, store these
models in a centralized model registry.
And then, some models, using this,
one of these fast API based REST
service or probably model serving
framework like TensorFlow, serving.
and, absolutely use Feature Store, like
Feast, to handle, the real time features.
when it comes to API layer, I think,
just to, integrate close with the
API can be written in many languages
and many, frameworks, but just to
integrate closely and, continue to use
the same libraries across the board.
it is better to expose RESTAR,
gRPC APIs to solve this real time
recommendations and then probably insight.
So certainly we can use FAST and FLASK
APIs to derive some of this information.
when it comes to Now the monitoring
aspects of it, I think, we wanted to use
Prometheus, to monitor this Kafka metrics,
like, is there a consumer lag, or is the
data flowing through, properly, et cetera.
And then we wanted to use Grafana
dashboards for, pipeline performance.
And then, you know, We wanted to use
Elk Stack to see and write the errors.
so in order to achieve, the high,
performance patterns, certainly
consider, parallel processing is one
thing to consider something like, use,
Python's multiprocessing or tools like
Ray or CPU based tasks or ensure that
Thread safe, data processing, right?
and, see, the places where the
caching can be enabled, right?
Caching frequently used data
like user profiles in Redis or,
to reduce, database queries.
And then, back pressured, handling
like, so use Kafka consumer groups
to dynamically scale consumers.
and autoscale compute resources
in a cloud, like using
Kubernetes or AWS Lambda, etc.
Right.
So when it comes to the tech stack,
as I was just talking about, like data
ingestion, we can use, Kafka, AWX,
Kinesis, Stream Processing, Apache Spark,
and then probably like Apache Flink.
And when it comes to the storage,
DynamoDB, S3, Cassandra, Influx,
Druid, a lot many variations in
that when it comes to ML training
or inference, TensorFlow, PyTorch.
and then, I call as a data delivery
or a serving layer where we can use
FastAPI, Flask, TensorFlow, Serving,
or when it comes to a monitoring
and observability, Elk Stack, right?
So, as we talk about, millions of
transactions, how do we want it to ensure
that the scalability considerations
are being, in picture, right?
So, as we just talked about, ensure
that, the Kafka is being partitioned,
enough, and then it is being partitioned
by consumer region or a customer region
to handle, the load distribution, right?
sharding, use sharded Redis
cluster for low latency lookups.
And then when it comes to horizontal
scaling, scale, stream processing,
by adding more work on outside.
So some of the challenges, when it comes
to delivering, the, high performance or
high scalable near real time with 99.
9 percent uptime, systems include say,
how do we handle high data ingestion rate?
Use Kafka with, probably
like multiple partitions.
And then, if you want low
latency predictions, deploy the
ML edge or close to the, edge.
consumer, or customer as much as possible
when it comes to data consistency.
like during the stream processing
use exactly once, processing in
Flink or Spark, for fault tolerance
use Retrace and then probably like,
the dead letter queues in Kafka.
So, , this framework, ensures that, we
are, we are building a scalable system
for real time customer analytics.
and at the same time, we also
ensure that it po powers, the,
actionable insights, immediately.
So, like what is the, ROI by
implementing in the real world, right?
So, obviously, as we just, understand,
it's an increased revenue where,
we boost sales by 30 to 35 percent
to 50 percent through, data driven
personalization and, targeting,
targeted market strategies, right?
And then, improved customer
loyalty, reduced customer churn by
up to 25 percent with predictive
insights and tailored engagement.
H U, higher customer satisfaction
through, personalization and,
like proactive support, right?
obviously, it all boils down to how do we
operate efficiently, cutting down support
and marketing expenses, by 20 to 30%.
so what's the future
of, customer experience?
so when we talk about, the customer
experience, it, it is not an, It used
to be the case where the customer
experience used to be the same for,
all the customers that are entering
a store or all the customers that
are trying to get a service, right?
So, the future of customer
experience is hyper personalized,
predictive experiences per customer.
So, say if Amar wants to, Go
to, say target, and then he gets
to see what he wants to see.
and then, so it helps with intelligent
AI driven customer support where,
the, Answers to some of these customer
queries can be, quicker, no wait times,
and then better customer, interactions.
so, and like using this, we will
have the real time omni channel
interactions, a customer moving from a
web to mobile app to a store and vice
versa, or, coming from a marketing
channel, coming from a marketing app.
So this empowers to have like a
seamless integration across the board.
And then, using this adaptive analytics,
we can be able to derive some of
these strategic insights, right?
advanced real time data analytics
is, revolutionizing the complete
customer experience and then,
delivering, intelligent insights.
And then, like customizing or deeply
personalized interactions, between
the customer and the customer
reps, across every touch point.
So what are the key takeaways, from
this, real time data analytics?
So, I think enhanced customer expect,
expectation, Enhanced customer
satisfaction and this both boils
down to increasing the ROI, right?
So what are the next
steps in this journey?
so like understand, what is the, what
is, what data is available and then
probably understand the critical touch
points and then identifying, the high
potential, analytical opportunities.
Not every data can be, used.
the data that is continuous and
the data that is required for the
business and the data that enhances
the business, operations, enhances
the customer experience, enhances the
ROI is where we wanted to set some
time and then understand, the customer
interactions, and the data available
and probably start with the next step.
And then, depends on the technology
stack that is already existing
and then depending on the data
volumes that is available.
we will start deploying, advanced
real time analytics platform, ensuring
that, there's a seamless technological
adoption and then probably ensure that
it is cross functional, adaptability.
so.
In all the cases, we
don't need to use Kafka.
If you are getting like say 10
transactions every one hour,
probably like they might directly
emit to some of these, databases.
We don't need to have Kafka.
example I was just talking about, right?
So as I just called out earlier,
in every case, we don't need to
have the same set of technology
or same set of streams, right?
I was just talking to you about how do
we handle and high performance things.
There might be cases where.
The data volume is low and the insights
that we are taking might not be immediate.
It could be a batch processing, right?
So understand the business acumen
and understand the business use
case and start deriving, the
architecture around those patterns.
So, as, we are almost end of our,
session, let's embrace, the real
time, evaluation, right, revolution.
So when it comes to real time data
analytics, as, we talked multiple times,
it is transforming how the customer
experience, should look like, right?
and probably, businesses start gaining the
competitive advantage and then probably
building the customer, relation and, drive
a sustainable growth, in this journey.
So as, we come to the end, thank you for
taking, time in, attending this session.
if you would like to learn more or if you
have any questions, feel free to reach out
to me, on my LinkedIn, and you can reach
out to my LinkedIn at amarnathimmadisetti.
thank you again and, have a good day.