Hello, everyone, and welcome
to the implementing agentic AI
solutions in Python from scratch.
Here is the repo, and you
have full access to it.
We have all the code samples.
I'm using my notes here, which
I'll have access to, as well as an
HTML version, if you so need it.
So who am I?
I'm one of us, a regular Pythonista.
I was in tech in the early 2000s
as a business information architect
and certified Microsoft SQL
Server DBA for about four years.
And then I returned in 2017
via WordPress and JavaScript.
Frameworks.
Moving to Python and
machine learning in 2021.
Currently, I'm working on a project,
AI powered knowledge systems, building
a book framework similar to my Python.
test full stack, which is
here at pytestcookbook.
com.
I've also got some useful notes on
Django full stack testing, and here
is my main project at the moment.
I'm based in Brighton in the
UK, down on the south coast,
and here is our lovely beach.
And I'm a volunteer coach at Cobar.
io, which I find very rewarding.
We meet every two weeks.
And I've just got myself a
new Red Fox Labrador pup, Leo,
much earlier than planned.
And locally, we have a red fox that
is quite tame, and seems to check
Leo out, and they both stare at
each other, wondering who's who.
My first computer was in 1979, and
it was a paper tape reader, with
a teletype printer for output, and
cut and paste was cut and paste.
So what are AI agents?
The word agent is a subject of much
discussion in academic circles, but
if we're looking at AI agents, we can
see that Pydantic has its version, a
primary interface for interacting with
LLMs, and an Anthropic also defines
workflow and agents, and Hugging Face
says AI agents are programs where
LLM outputs control to workflow.
What we're going to do is we're going
to look at examples of code to see what
AI agents are and what they can do.
Now, for example, if we look at this
link here, we will see The range of
AI agents that are being created.
There's 46 character categories, 825, all
different versions in different areas,
so it can be quite overwhelming to know
which framework to use and what they are.
What's the aim of my talk?
Well, my talk is to a chain to
achieve that, to demystify AI agents
and AI programming because it can
seem like it's another different
world of development for us, ISTs.
And what I'd like to propose is what if AI
agents adjust Python code with a REST API
call, admittedly to a very magical API?
Then we could use day to day Python
design patterns to handle the
responses we get back from these
API calls to the AI, to the LLMs.
And so the main focus of this talk is
to demystify and simplify, and not to
focus on actual real world applications.
And with that in mind, we don't need to
fully graph the code this time round.
It may take a few minutes.
iterations to fully grasp it, so
perhaps to look at the high level view
and to see how it is different from
just regular Python and to realize
that actually AI agents are Python
code with REST API calls to an LLM,
admittedly a very magical REST API.
In fact, what I'd like to propose
is that actually there's no real
difference between doing our regular
day to day Python and Python code.
It is very much like a mouse
that we turn around 180 degrees.
It's still the same actions, up,
down, left, right, but in a different
way, in a different paradigm.
And that can be a little bit tricky
to get to grips with initially.
And in this regard, there are three areas
that I consider to be part of agentic AI.
First, it seems that we can almost
create on the client side the
endpoint, the roots, that we would
normally build on the server side.
We also use natural and human
language, in my case English, to
create code, very much like pseudocode.
And thirdly, we give a sense of
autonomy, in a sense that the LLM
can direct the flow of the app.
And that could be within
bounds that we have created.
But basically, the next step
can be determined by the
LLM, which our app will take.
So before we go into some code examples,
why don't we just refresh ourselves
on what a REST API is before we start
using any library implementations by
using just the requests library so that
we can see that how we actually do a
POST request to our LLM rather than
using, say, an OpenAI library that hides
the implementation of the requests.
So we have our model, we have our
endpoint, and it's worth noting that we
only have one endpoint, one root, and
we'll see why this is apparent later on.
And we will need to send our
token, our API key, in the headers.
We will send our payload, for example,
our model, a list of messages, whether
we're streaming, the temperature.
And here, with requests,
what we can do is send POST.
With all these details to get a JSON
response and to bear in mind, the
request is a string of characters and
doesn't contain any objects or other
data types, and basically it's a JSON
dumps or if we were in JavaScript,
it would be a JSON stringify.
Where all that information
is created as a string.
So what we'll do now is we'll look
at our very first file, 01, to
see this in action and to see the
basics of an agent application.
We're now in our very first file, 01, and
the first thing we're just going to do is
load in our imports of OS JSON requests,
and to read our keys from the env file.
I'm going to keep mine secret here,
but you have a copy here as env.
sample.
Just paste your Open AI key here.
If we come back, what we can
then do is load in our AI key.
And just check that we have
it, which we see we have here.
We're going to select our model,
which in this case is GPT 40mini.
And we just check that it's here.
And for the demonstration, we're going
to create our own class to show how
we can do a request to the endpoint.
Later on, we'll use one of
the libraries from OpenAI.
But we're just going to see in
a very raw form actually how
we would create our own class.
request to an LLM
directly to its endpoint.
So we're going to be making a
POST request to this endpoint.
And what we're going to do in this
class is use this one single endpoint,
and there's only ever one endpoint.
It's not that we have different routes
for different tasks that we want to do.
We have the temperature, which
is a hyperparameter that kind of
takes into account the probability.
Zero means it's very strict and
is as deterministic as possible.
If we want to be more creative in
generating text or images, we would
vary the temperature to, say, 0.
5, 1, etc. The range is between 0 and 2.
We have our system prompt.
We'll get into that.
Our API key.
And here we have our headers
so that we get authentication.
Giving it the content type.
This is our request.
And when we want to generate some text, we
pass in a prompt, our query, our request.
We pass in the payload of the model, the
messages, the system prompt, our prompt.
We'll get into that.
Whether we're streaming, in this
case false, the temperature.
And here, we make our requests
to that endpoint with headers
and also with the payload.
And we can put in here for
future reference, URL equals.
So that's a little bit clearer.
So now that we've got that
class, let's create an instance.
We pass in the model we want.
We pass in the system prompt,
which is like, gives the character
or the personality or the role.
of our agent.
And we're saying in this case, you
give concise answers to questions
with no more than 100 characters.
We can get into more complex
system prompts later, and that's
the sort of prompt engineering.
And we can then make a request
to say what is Pydantic.
And if we print the response that we get
back originally, it is a JSON, stringified
JSON object of all this information.
But if we drill down through
choices, message, and content,
we will end up with the Pydantic.
response that we want by Dantic
is a data validation and settings
management library from Python.
And you can see how it's
respecting the 100 characters.
So this is our base and we can see
that if we were not using any of the AI
libraries but merely using our Python
library of requests and env, that this is
how we would send a POST request to the
LLM with all the details that it needs.
what we would get back.
And what we can do is we can just
hide this and then show the response.
We can see it's quite complicated
in quite detail, but it's choices
is where the answers come back.
We want the very first one.
And as we work through, we see message.
We want to look for the content
where the answer to our query lies.
So this is our base template.
We're going to replace it with
OpenAI library for our calls.
Let's now move on to
the second file, O2 API.
And what we're going to do is we're
going to get a joke back, but we're
also going to make a little bit of
prompt engineering to get the LLM to
rate the joke and give us the next step.
So let's go into that to
see an example of that.
So if we go into O2 API, We
again load in our usual imports.
I'm using rich to colorize
the console output.
And we know we can make a
request to some random joke API.
To get a joke here, using the
request library, and we get the joke.
We won't go into that.
We will load in our open API key.
We'll get our model as usual.
And what we'll do is we'll then
set up a more elaborate, system.
We're going to start with
our basic system message.
You are an assistant that
is great at telling jokes.
But we want to get something
a little bit more advanced.
And it's almost as if we were sending to
the endpoint a new endpoint that would
do something totally different for us.
But what we will find is actually that
we will do this on the client side.
So.
Let's just add this extra prompt here,
and I'm just going to call it prompt
engineering because it's separate from
the system message, totally customizable,
doesn't have to be prompt engineering.
And we're giving it a set of
instructions, and we could almost
consider this to be pseudocode.
A joke worthy of publishing is
a joke that has a rating of 8.
5 or 10 or above.
If the joke is worthy of
publishing, also includes the
next step, whether to publish it.
Otherwise, tell us what the next
step would be, which we should retry.
We give it an example.
of what we're going to get.
So this is called, one shot prompting
or multi shot prompting where
you give one or more examples.
And basically we're giving it an example
of what we would like to get back.
Please supply the response
in the following format.
It's in JSON format here.
And to actually help it, let's actually,
although it works, to be more specific,
we'll say the following JSON format.
Because we want to have
clear instructions.
And here we see we get the setup, the
punchline, we ask it to give us a rating,
and we also then tell us that based
on the rating and whether it deems it
worthy of publishing, to either send the
next step, that we pass on higher up in
the app chain to publish or to retry.
We're also giving it some further
instructions to remove all backticks,
any unnecessary characters.
Once again, I did say JSON format here,
and using capitals can be a useful
way to emphasize things for the LLM.
And also we're saying that if we
do a retry, do not repeat the joke,
and we can even say thank you.
So this is our pseudocode.
This is almost a new endpoint that
we would like to have where we
could send a request and it will
process something different rather
than just returning us a joke.
But what we do is on the client side, we
send that code up to that one endpoint.
And that's the mouse being
at 180 degrees different.
It's like we are now
creating our own code.
REST endpoint R route here.
So we just add those two together
so that it's now the system message.
And we also have our user prompt,
which is going to tell a light hearted
joke for an audience of Pythonistas.
And when we send up to the ALM, we want
to send a list of all these messages,
and the convention is we have prompts.
We have a role for system, and
its content is the system message.
We have a role for user, and
the content is the user prompt.
We can also have role of the AI
assistant, because we may want
to filter out the messages.
And this is the practice with these
LLMs, is that we have a system message,
user message, and an AI message, which
is the response back from the LLM.
So we complete as before, but
this time we are using the OpenAI.
If we scroll up to the top, we're using
from OpenAI, one of its libraries.
So we can just create the client
here, An instance of OpenAI.
And therefore, when we send the request,
we don't need to be as detailed.
We can use a convenience method.
Client.
chat.
completions.
create.
We send the model we want.
We send all our messages
in, which is these prompts.
And when we get it back,
we will get a response.
Again, it's in the choices, it's
in the message, in the content,
and we can display it here.
So we now get a JSON object here,
where it has the setup, the punchline,
The rating and what it advises
to do next in the flow, which
we publish as opposed to retry.
Now, in our app, we might have a
state object that holds all of this
information because this is we've
made the REST API call to the LLM.
But what we do next is day to day Python.
It's any system design, PubSub,
ActorModel, FiniteStateMachine.
We've now been given
exactly what to do next.
Now we can pass that over to another
agent, or we can act upon it ourselves.
And what I'm going to
do here is I run it out.
I've extracted it out nicely.
JSON data.
And when I look at it, I can then
basically see that if the result next
equals publish, for example, I can
load it into our state object, and
I could then go on to publish it,
to send a message to another part
of our program or to another agent.
The main thing is we're kind of
getting almost like an event driven
application, but we've been asking
the LLM to decide the next step.
And that's the autonomy, because
it could have come back with retry.
And in which case, the flow of the
program would go in a different direction.
And so what I've just done
here, I've extracted out the
next step, which is publish.
So this is how our app would have its
flow and its direction directed by the
LLM, as opposed to us imperatively.
So to recap with this, the
main thing is we're structuring
what we would like to get back.
Rather than just getting a joke,
we're setting back an endpoint.
We're setting back instructions.
This is our pseudocode.
This is our REST endpoint that we
send from the client up to the server
along with our payload, and then we
get the response back as we want.
And we're going to see various
different forms of these prompts.
They could be more advanced and
more structured as we go along.
So when we get that back, we can then
basically decide what we want to do next.
If we're having many agents, we
may keep track where each agent is.
So this was O2 API.
An initial start into prompt engineering
and how we use the client side REST API
coding in natural language, enabling
autonomy to take place in our AI agent.
We've seen the two out of the three
steps of the AI reverse process,
where we kind of created on the
client side our route, our endpoint,
and the use of natural language.
And we briefly looked at autonomy.
So how do we handle this
autonomy of the flow of an API?
AI agent app.
Well, we asked in our LLM to
give us not just a rating,
but to give us that next step.
And in this case, it was published.
So what we'd like to do now is to begin
to see how we can handle this in our app.
And we're going to go on to our next
example, which is a sort of an idea is
leading into the idea of an FAQ or sort
of the router pattern, a sort of if else.
And what I like about the FAQ pattern,
which we're going to see now, is
the fact that we can introduce
a little bit of AI into our app.
So let's have a look at
this example of OA03FAQ.
We're going to see an example of sort
of retrieval augmented generation.
Now, we're not querying documents,
but RAG is basically supplementing our
query with additional information that
we haven't fine tuned our model with
or that's important for our LLM query.
So what we're going to do is
we're going to give it a list of
frequently asked questions and
have a little chatbot experience.
So And this is going to pave way
for the next file, which will
be a sort of a router pattern.
So once again, we load in our imports, we
get our key, we get a utility client from
the OpenAI library to ease our connection
to the LLM, which is picking our model.
And we're going to create now a function
that has some history, that has all
the previous messages, that has the
system message and the user prompt.
And the history is important because it
gives us a record of what went on before,
because every request is stateless.
It's like the LLM is seeing
it for the first time.
So we need to pass the history
back with it so it has context
and a certain degree of memory.
So in our function chat, We're
having our role, our system.
We're adding in the history of all
the previous messages that we have
in our chatbot and our user message.
We can print out the history,
print out the messages.
We're using the stream option
for our chatbot, which we'll see
in a minute, and we're going to
then chunk out our responses.
So this is where we start to build
more context into our chatbot.
agent.
We're saying it's a helpful
assistant for a shoe store.
And if a user asks a question, please
be as helpful as possible and as
courteous and professional manner.
You are provided with the
following facts to help you.
Please be verbose and suggestive.
So now I'm changing like the
character and the nature of the
prompt, adding in a little bit
more verbosity and suggestiveness.
So here is a list of just some
basic facts about our shop.
And bear in mind that this could
be retrieved from the database.
This could be a result of
selecting from the Options from
a form for further information.
But we can see here is if we
just pass some extra content,
some retrieved content.
Admittedly, it's already in the file,
but it could have been retrieved from
a database or from some other source,
and we join it onto the system message.
We can now use Gradio to set up a little
chatbot interface to see how this works.
And if we look at the code while this
is working, it hasn't taken a lot to
introduce a fairly sophisticated little
chatbot based on very limited information.
We could very much increase
this greatly in our app.
So as that runs through.
Almost there.
Come back down.
We have our Gradio interface,
and let's just open that up.
In fact, I'll put it in.
There we go.
Here's our chatbot.
Type message.
Now, it's quite simple.
I could just say Sunday, and if we
look at that, it's coming through.
Thank you for your inquiry.
Our store is picked up.
It's about time.
It's Monday to Friday 9 to 5.
Unfortunately, we're closed on Sundays.
Notice how it's quite
verbose and suggestive.
We look forward to welcoming you soon.
If we come back to our code, we
can see that here are the facts.
We don't have very many.
This could be a much
more complex document.
It could be an MD markdown file.
It could be driven from the database.
So if we come back and
let's have another example.
I can say green belts.
Thank you for reaching out.
We don't do that.
Gives us the address.
It says that basically
exclusively in shoes.
So this little example here of basically
having an agentic AI with a minimum
amount of rag, a minimum amount of extra
context can produce a nice small little
app in your, small little AI app in your
Python app without having to be fully AI.
This is what I call a
bit of AI programming.
Now, this is quite an interesting
pattern, because in the next one, it's
the agent router, and it's something
that happened when I was at CodeBar.
somebody asked that they
would like to get a job in AI.
They were doing Python.
And I said to them, Do they have
an AI department where they work?
And they said, No.
And I said, What do they do?
They said they were insurance.
I said, What do you do?
And they said they they don't write
the reports that they're there to go
to person that when somebody wants
a report, they know which one it
is, and they can run it for them.
I thought, Brilliant.
You can do that.
And there were concerns.
They said, put me out of a job.
I said, yes, but you'll then be
the head of the AI department.
And so what we're going to
do is we're going to have a
little variation on this FAQ.
It's a similar type of thing.
We're loading in all the usual imports and
setting ourself up the same chat message.
And a useful tip is caps and italics
and even markdown in one's prompts
actually have an impact with the LLM.
It's being trained on so many
of these that it begins to
recognize the importance.
And I'm just basically
setting up a report agent.
I'm saying you're a
report selection agent.
You're very good at returning the best
report to answer a user's question.
For example, if a user wants a joke,
you reply with, and I'm just using
this format for demonstration purposes.
This will make it nice and bold.
The tool they need is the get joke report.
If they want total sales, the tool
or report they need will be the
get sales would be the best report.
So I made a list of reports here for
whether use the get weather for hotel,
the hotel booking, very much like we
did in the last FAQ, adding them all in.
And if I run all of that, we
will see now that we can actually
have a report selection agent
that will get the right report.
And if we combine that with
information like the date range or
any other properties, we could even
run the report for them and send it.
All through agents.
So let's check.
We've got this one working.
Lovely.
Okay.
So say I want to take a plane and
notice I didn't use the word plane.
I use flight.
Plane to Rome.
What report should I get?
Get the flight.
Plane to Rome and Auto, let's
just check the typos there,
to Rome, and auto to Paris.
It comes back with those two reports.
So straight away, with that, if we had
the information, shall we say, sent
along with it through a form selection,
we could then get the right report.
And so this is an example of a
sort of router that actually,
what do we want to do next?
Through a very simple addition of
some context to our system message,
I'm going to return to this slide a
number of times because it's easy when
we're going through these different
patterns and function callings to lose
sight of what is the essence of an A.
I. agent and A. I. agents are python
code with A. P. I. request to L.
L. M. s. We can only pass a string
in the A. P. I. request and in that
string we create a job description.
And this could be what the role is, what
they do, these are the tools you have,
here is the data to work on, this is what
we want returned, and in what format.
This is prompt or flow engineering.
How we make use of this in terms of
design patterns is then day to day Python.
Fundamentally, it is a function with
inputs, LLM magic, and some output
returned in the form that we want.
And we'll return to this slide
as we proceed through some of
the more involved examples.
Now we've seen how an
agent can make decisions.
About the next step, the autonomy,
how we've created our sort of
client side API, and we use natural
language, but an agent may need tools.
It may need to do anything.
It may need to make a
request to the Internet.
It may need to call upon a function
that we have in our code base to
calculate something and use that it.
as part of its response.
So what we're going to do in O5 is
we're going to look at not how we
just define tools, but also how an
agent can decide which one to use.
Now, usually it's better to have an
agent to just one single thing, but
sometimes we might have an agent that
might need to make a decision for a
particular task, which tool to use.
So we may need to determine Which
tool to use in the agent and
basically, what happens is we're
constantly adding new messages.
Now, where does those functions run?
What's going to happen is when
we've given the prompt, which we're
going to have a look at now in 05.
What we're going to do
is do the standard setup.
But now when we come to our tool
prompt, we're saying you're in a system
that is very good at determining what
tool to use to solve a certain query.
And our AI programming is we give
it in descriptive form, which
is saying we're using Markdown
here to emphasize this is tools.
We have two tools.
We're describing our calculator
tool that does basic arithmetic.
And it responds in JSON.
And we give it an example of the JSON
format, of that, when we pick the
particular tool called Calculator,
the next signal will be to use the
doCalculation function, and, for
example, what argument should be passed.
This is an example of one scenario.
We have a second tool, which
is a joke tool, something
totally different, JSON format.
And this is what the result
the tool would look like.
So, for example, we can ask it a question.
What is 10 times 9?
And what we're going to do is when
we send that out, it will actually
determine that the tool it needs, the
response it's sending back to us is
the calculator, the do calculation,
and the arguments that are needed.
We can strip all of that out and
basically then say if the do next was do
calculation, we can run those functions.
If it was perhaps, for example,
to do the joke, we might do an
internet request to get a joke.
So let's just go back
to the flow of messages.
We're doing all the usual messages.
But when the API, when the LLM
decides that it needs a particular
tool, what it does is it sends back
the tool signature and the arguments
that it's extracted from the query.
We then on our own computer box, not the
LLM, run that function, get the result.
And add that back to the list of
messages and send it to the LLM that
does the next step, for example.
Now, that particular example is one
where we're going to see later where
we're going to use planning, where it's
thinking, making an action, getting a
result, putting it back in the loop.
This particular example here in 05 tool
is just the first step of showing how
it can determine which tool to use.
So I'm just going to run everything.
And as you see, we load in
our imports, we get our key.
We get our messages.
It's added into the system
message at the very end here.
Our code.
This is our endpoint.
On the client side, in
natural human language.
And it's like a very clear description you
give to somebody when they join a company.
This is how you do your job.
The more detail, the clearer
you can be, the better.
So, for example, we
asked, what is 10 times 9?
We've added the messages in.
We've got back this response
that it's determined the tool
it needs is the calculator tool.
It knows what to do next.
It's the do calculation,
and it knows the arguments.
10 and 2, 10 and 9, and the
operation is multiplication.
What is 10 times 9?
Notice how it's picked up
times and multiplication.
What we can then do is strip that all
out, and if we come back down here, in
this particular agent, we can actually
run some code, or we could pass this on
to another agent, or run it through a
loop again, which we'll see later on.
So in this example, because it knows that
doNext says doCalculation, it extracts all
the information, the tool, the arguments,
and then basically just carries out these
functions to produce the answer back.
So if we do that again, but with
some different numbers, 102 times 3,
and we run it all, and we see
it going back through to clear.
It's now picked out arguments
102 and 3, operation multiply.
Let's do add.
What is 102's plus 3?
Let's run that.
We can see that it's
picking out the arguments.
It's knowing which tool it needs.
1 0 2 3 and addition.
And when we come back down to the
answer, it produces the answer 1 0 5.
Let's see if it picks up if
it needs the different tool.
So, for example, here, I'll do that.
Tell me a joke.
I'm doing this at a builders conference.
Let's run it all.
So now it should determine
that what is the right tool.
It's the do joke tool.
It's a different tool.
There it are.
The joke, do joke.
The audience has picked
up one of the arguments.
It doesn't run here.
Because the do next is do joke, it
just goes off to the internet and gets
a joke, and then we see the answer.
So you may be thinking they all seem
a little bit the same, the router,
the tool use, the basic query.
And I suppose they are because
they're just function calls.
At the end of the day, we're just
doing Python functions, getting
a response back from an API, then
doing something with that response.
The difference now is that we create
our endpoint, we create our route on the
client side, ship up that pseudocode.
ship up the kind of query,
and we get the answer back.
And we also enable a certain level
of autonomy because we can ask the
LLM what it should do next based
on the prompt that we sent it.
So this is what is called tool
use, or it's just function calling.
And it's just a mechanism of
how we do the function calling.
And once again, the function
takes place on our box.
We don't run it on the LLM's box.
And when we get the result of that
information, we pass it back to the LLM.
And we're going to see that when we come
on to the what's called the reason act
react type pattern for planning agent.
So we've seen a few little pieces of
how we can create simple AI agents,
and some can be quite powerful.
Your utilities, like we saw in the
frequently asked questions or the report
selector and What we're going to do now is
actually look at the four main patterns.
Andrew Ng, in his lecture, listed here,
talked about the four main patterns.
Reflection, where the LLM kind
of re examines its own work.
It sends it back to itself, but
with a critique to say, make a
critique of what I've just sent you.
Tool use, we've seen an example of that.
planning, where it comes up with a
plan to execute a multi step goal,
and also multi agent collaboration.
So we've seen a number of these
examples, and what we're going to
do now is we're going to look at the
reflection pattern, the tool pattern,
planning, and the multi agent pattern.
So let's go into the code to look at
the reflection pattern to start with.
We're now going to look
at the reflection pattern.
And let us not forget in
essence what we're doing.
We're just creating a big string
job description that we send.
We get some response.
We may append that to a new request
or start a new request from fresh.
But in this reflection pattern, what we
do is we generate a response with our
first query, then add this content to
the request in a second query where we've
asked it to do something, and in this case
to have a critique and further refinement.
So in some sense, the first
request, it can be considered
as actually almost like RAG.
That we're generating some
content to add to a new query,
augmenting it with a new set of
instructions and getting a response.
And what we're going to do in this one
is we're going to ask it to generate
some Python code, and then we're going to
ask for it to critique it and make some
adjustments to produce a final response.
So we use our usual standard opening,
getting the key, setting the models.
And we can see here that we're
setting the very first system
message, first role, as a Python
program tasked with generating code.
And we're generating our chat history.
We append our system content,
the job description, as it were.
We then add to that, list, the
user query, which in this case is
generate a Python implementation of
requesting an API with request library.
And we then send that to the LLM
to get our response back.
And here we get our response.
And before we do that in for the next
step, we also add what we got back.
So we can see we get the
response from the LLM.
It's giving us some sample
code with an explanation.
Now we want to reflect on that.
We want to send it back again and
have a little critique or refinement.
So in our chat history, we add
in now another system message,
and we're saying you're an
experienced and talented Pythonista.
You're tasked with generating critique
and recommendations for the user's code.
All of these messages are attached
together and sent, because we
must remember that the request is
stateless, so it needs to know what
went on before, so we must parse in
that history of the conversation.
And we then get our critique
back and display it.
And here is the output.
Your code demonstrates a solid
approach going through it all, all
the way down.
And then we add this again, this
critique to our chat history, send it
all in again to get a final summary.
And here's our final
summary in form of an essay.
You scroll down, and here is
our final output as requested.
Now, of course, what we do and how many
times we go through it is up to us, but
the pattern is literally just Making
requests, getting a response, taking that
response, adding it back into our chat
history, adding in a new prompt to do
something with that and get a response.
It's one function after another
with inputs producing outputs get
put into the next function as an
input that produces an output.
So this is a reflection pattern.
And as we scroll down,
we see the final answer.
Key improvements.
And, of course, we can make this a
class and make the input come through a
certain form field or through a chat bot.
And once again, if we go up to the
very top, we can remember, in essence,
this is really what we're doing.
We're making a function.
We're passing in inputs, getting
an output and really chaining it
from one request to the other.
In this particular reflection pattern,
we're going to look at using planning
or using reflection and tool calling.
Once again, let us remind ourselves
that we're looking in this talk to see
what AI agents are in terms of their
simplicity before we move into frameworks.
And what we're going to do now is use a
sort of pattern of react, reason and act.
And essentially, we pass the output of
each step as an input to the next request
to an LLM, like we did in Reflection.
But we're going to add in some tool
calling, and we're also going to be adding
in some effectively routing, because the
agent will determine which tool to use.
And how to use it.
We'll do this with the 20 planning agent
with loop dot py But we will also do it
with the notebook where we will do this
Looping manually so we can see how it
works So let's just go to the python file
and we can see that we run in everything
As usual and we're creating an agent class
where we're setting the client the system
role We're using the under core method.
We're using an execute function where we
can just invoke the llm to get a response
You And what we want to do in this example
is calculate the total price for an item.
And the two tools we have
are calculate the total that
given a price adds on the VAT.
We also have another tool, function,
get product price, that for a given
argument gets the price of the product.
And if we scroll down, we will
see these two functions here.
CalculateTotal, GetProductPrice.
So let's look at our system prompt, and
we're telling it how we want it to work.
We want it to think, take an action,
get an observation, and repeat the loop.
So we give examples of what the tools are.
What the kind of response we'd like
to get back for both the calculate
price, total and get product price.
And we're also given an example session.
So what's going to happen is a user
is going to say, what is the total
cost of a bike, including that?
We want the AI response
to be in this format.
Thought, I need to find
the cost of a bike.
We're pipe delimbing it so we can
get the function name and the price.
arguments, but it's going to be an
action type as opposed to an answer.
We're going to get the tool call
and we're going to get the argument.
We will get the response back of an
observation of the actual return of
that function, which we will then
use as an input to the next query
where it now needs to calculate
the total price including the VAT.
It's an action.
It knows to use the calculate total,
and it has an argument passed into it.
This is just a sample example so it
can see the format of what it needs
to do, and that we will always be
passing in the result of our LLM
course as observation pipe 240.
That's what it can expect.
Then we tell it that if you
have the answer, print out an
answer for us in this form.
So let's just run this just to see
what it will actually look like.
And if we scroll down.
We can see we've got a loop.
We're not going to get into each
line of the code, but basically
it's going to be looping around.
If it's an action, it
will run that function.
Get a value and pass it back
through to be used again.
If it determines it has an answer, it'll
print the answer and exit the loop.
So, for example, we've got three here.
One is the cost of a
bike, a TV, and a laptop.
So, let's run that and see what happens.
It's starting the loop.
It has a thought.
It has an observation.
It gets passed in.
And each time we get the result here,
but we can see the summary answers.
But if we look at a particular loop
starting the loop, it has the thought,
I need to find the cost of a TV.
We've extracted out the action.
We've extracted out that the
function call is going to be get
product price and the parameter.
We get an observation of 200.
That now gets VAT back in, and it
now knows it needs to calculate
the total, including the VAT.
It's going to use a calculateTotal
with the 200 that we passed in.
The observation is returned back as 240.
That gets put into the
loop to get the answer.
Now, if you notice, we've missed one
here, and we have the answer here.
And that's the nature sometimes of
LLMs, that things do actually go
wrong because it's probabilistic.
But we get the first one,
the price of the bike is 120.
We do get the result, 240, but we
don't get it printed out in the answer.
And if we were to run this again, come
back in here and open this up,
and if we run it again, we'll
probably see a different answer.
Starting the loop, 120, answer
found, the price of the bike is 120.
Starting again, we found
the price of the TV is 240.
And now we've got the price of the
laptop, 360, and we get all three answers.
So it can show that we can't
take things for granted because
the Things will be missed out.
It is not 100 percent deterministic.
So we need to put in some checks and
balances if we were using these results.
But this is an example of
actually how we can loop through.
So what we're going to do now is
actually go to the notebook version
and see how would we do this manually.
What's actually going on?
So We use the same setup, use the
same system prompt, same functions.
But what we do now is we call an
instance of this planning agent with
the client and the system prompt.
We set up an instance of it and we
pass through the first question.
What is the cost of a
laptop, including the VAT?
When we run that, we get back
the result, which is thought.
That we can now extract out by
splitting on the pipe exactly whether
it's an action, what the function
name is, and what the parameter
name is, what the argument is.
And as you can see, when we do
that, we get the function, we
need to run the getProductPrice,
and we need to do it on a laptop.
So manually, this is what we would do.
We'd say, if the next function is, which
we've just determined here by extracting
out this item here in the output.
If it's get product price, run
get product price with that value.
The argument that we got is
the third, fourth item here.
So we get 300, and we said in our prompt
that we would send it back in in the form
of observation, pipe, and the result.
So this is what we're going
to send as the next prompt.
So we run it with our agent.
Next prompt, the result.
It now determines it still needs
another action, but it's the calculate
total and it needs the price of
300 to be calculated with VAT.
So once again, we strip out
the function and the parameter.
We need to do calculate total
and the argument of 300.
And once again, we run this manually.
You know, it's to calculate total.
And the next arc, there are
different ways that we could
run that using, an eval method.
But for simplicity, we're just going
to run it manually is calculate total.
We get the answer 360.
Once again, we're going to send that back
in, in the form of observation result.
That's what we specified
in the system prompt.
So we're sending this
back in as the next query.
That's the next prompt.
Pass it in to the agent, the
next prompt of observation 360.
Print the result.
Now that it's determined it
has an answer, it prints it
out in the format that we want.
Answer.
The price of the laptop,
including that, is 360.
So if we go back up again and
basically change it, and now let's
work out for the price of the TV
and see exactly the same again.
We're going running through.
We
now know the action is get
product price, but it's for a TV.
It runs the function.
It gets the price that it's 200.
We send it back in and
saying the observation from
the previous action is 200.
It then extracts what it needs, and now
it's starting to calculate the total
with the VAT, 200, extracts again, runs.
We then run the function with the
extracted argument, we get 240.
We now send this observation
back in the form that we said we
would, observation pipe result.
You send this into the next query, goes
into here, you print the result, answer
the price of the TV, including VAT is 240.
Now, there are many ways you can
refactor this and use eval without
actually having to specify in a
step the actual function name.
That's effectively what
we do when we do our loop.
We basically extract all that information
and execute appropriately in our loop.
So I hope this kind of shows that although
we can have many different patterns,
Essentially, it's basically involving
reflection, sending back a previous output
as an input, use of tool call, and also
the use of planning of breaking up a task
into separate steps that it executes.
So they all sort of overlap
and are interconnected.
And I hope that this actually explains how
AI agents work and how if we look at where
is the AI in all of this, literally it is
just in the execute function to the LLM.
The rest of the AI part is just
where we invoke the instance of
the agent with the next prompt
that produces all these results.
The rest is we're just stripping
with day to day Python, sending
it back in to the loop, and then
running again another AI API request.
Well, we've just been
through quite a lot of code.
It's something really to digest offline.
As I've said before, it's taken me quite
a while just to kind of work through
and really get it clear in my own mind
to be able to explain it to people.
So if you don't feel it's kind of
sunk in, that's not a problem at all.
That's probably to be expected.
And that's why I've given you the repo
and all the code examples here so you
can work through them, chop it up,
change them around to get understand it.
So we saw the sort of four main,
we've seen sort of reflection, we've
seen tool use, we've seen a sort
of planning where we're sort of
basically having to break a problem
down into steps and work through them.
We haven't really seen
multi agent collaboration.
And the reason for this is basically
it's a design pattern of how one
wants to use what one gets back
from each agent with another agent.
Is it the active pattern, the
pub sub, finite state machine, as
in, for example, like Landgraf?
And what I'd like to talk about
in closing is the libraries and
frameworks that are available.
And I like to think of libraries
as sort of frameworks without
the framework, as it were.
Lots of convenience, tools,
simplicity, that we can build
the overall design pattern.
And Pydantic AI is a new one that's
come towards the end of 2024.
Pydantic is well known
in the Python community.
And as you can see, structured output.
It's very important because we want to
pass structured output from one agent
or from one part of our app to the next.
HuggingFace SmallAgents is another
very small, lightweight framework
library that they implement so that
one can create one's own overall
framework or design pattern.
Then we see many different
crews and swarms and frameworks.
And these are basically design patterns
for, essentially, intercommunication
between bits of code, our AI agents.
And we saw before in the AI agents
directory, how many different
frameworks there are around there.
As you can see, if we start with the
simplicity as we have been doing, we
might refactor it, build our own library.
And then realize actually other people
could benefit from them, customize
it to make it more easy to use.
And then we add another framework to
the AI agents directory, for example.
So in terms of frameworks, there's
LLAMA Index, LLANG Chain, LLANG Graph,
AutoGen, Crew AI, and then very many more.
All very good, all very useful.
And hopefully, having gone through
the simplicity of these AI agents,
not only could you maybe just design
your own mini framework, But when
you come to use these frameworks, you
will actually understand what it is
they're doing and how they're doing it.
So, in summary, I hope AI agents have
been demystified and helped us understand
what they can do, enabling us either
to build our own frameworks or use
existing ones, with a deeper appreciation
and understanding of how they work.
And Anthropic has, in their
blog, has come up with this,
when and when not to use agents.
And I'll just read it out loud because
it sums it up better than I could.
When building applications with
LLMs, we recommend finding the
simplest solution possible, and only
increasing complexity when needed.
This might mean not building
agentic systems at all.
Agentic systems often trade
latency and cost for better task
performance, and you should consider
when this trade off makes sense.
When more complexity is warranted,
workflows offer predictability and
consistency for well defined tasks,
whereas agents are the better options
when flexibility and model driven
decision making are needed at scale.
For many applications, however, optimizing
single LLM calls with retrieval and
in context examples is usually enough.
Thank you very much for letting me
present this topic on AI agents,
their simplicity and their power.
My name is Craig West.
Thank you very much.