Hi, I'm Justin Deering.
Welcome to my talk on setting
up Docker on a Windows desktop,
without a, without Docker desktop,
and without a Docker license.
So basically, the problem here, in many
situations, if you are a corporation
of a certain size, I believe it,
certain money or certain number of
employees, you cannot, use Docker
desktop without paying for a license.
Now, my company, my employer, Nudesic,
does happen to provide us with Docker
licenses, but we are also consultants,
and sometimes we get, sent off and
have to use a laptop of one of our
clients, or a virtual desktop of one
of our clients, and they don't have
Docker licenses on their machines.
so anyway, we're going to go
through the setup over here.
just some prerequisites, you want
to have a Windows machine, you want
You need to have WSL set up on this
laptop so you can do Linux containers.
You need to have Hyper V support.
and container support, as
well, set up on the lab.
So you need those features
set up as part of Windows.
If you're not a local admin,
you need those features set up.
Containers, local containers,
and you need WSL set up.
once, an unprivileged user can install
all the WSL distributions they want.
so let's start off with
the basic situation here.
Okay, I'm a Python developer.
I'm in Visual Studio Code.
I have this blank
project over here, right?
And I want to start developing
Python stuff, but I want to do
it inside a container, right?
honestly, the easiest way to do
that is, make sure you have the
DevContainer feature installed.
Okay, so install this feature and
just go and build a DevContainer.
Okay, so we're going to say 3, hold on,
let's say zsh, we want it
in, let's say we want zsh.
Keep defaults.
I depend a lot.
Okay, and what this is going to do is
this is going to create the DevContainer.
Now, here's the thing.
If you don't have Docker installed
the first time, and actually that's
how I got Docker installed in this
is going to set up your default.
WSL distribution, and if it, if you don't
have a WSL distribution set up, it's
going to sit there and say, hey, do you
want to install WSL, WSL distribution,
and it will install Ubuntu, and it will
install Docker in Ubuntu, and, basically
your Visual Studio code will be set up
to, to use those for dev containers.
And if you ever want to access those
dev containers over here, you can just
go, here, and we can go into Ubuntu.
Okay,
okay And boom, there's our
there are the containers.
I have some wordpress containers
running with how I do this, right?
so it's going to go inside of here
Anyway, like I said when you did
this the first time you did this
and restarted the container it
would just set that up for you.
Okay, so that's your first That's
your first setup over here.
just very simple.
Just go in visual studio code Create a
dev container any dev container you want.
It will set up linux for you now You
cannot access this You Without doing any
other, without doing a bunch of other
socket files and configuration, you're not
going to access this docker from outside
of W, outside of your WSL distribution.
but this is, good enough.
if you want to play with containers,
just go into Ubuntu and just do
it that way, plain and simple.
that's the, that's the
best way to do this, right?
Now what about Windows containers?
Now I have it set up,
actually, on my machine.
As you can see, I have it set up
for Windows containers, and my
Docker over there is over there.
you can install the, what's called
Docker Community Edition and it's
free, and it's available for free.
On the Docker website, they hide it a
little bit, but if you just Google or
Bing or whatever, use your favorite search
engine, look for Docker Community Edition,
you can find your way to get a zip file
that has just two binaries, docker.
exe and dockerd.
exe.
Now, how do we install this, right?
we just unzip the file over here,
and I'm going to show you how to
do that from the command line.
And I'm not even going to, actually,
I'm going to show you the website.
So you end up on that, you're going to
end up, if you search for Docker Community
Edition, you'll end up over here.
and you'll end up going to this link,
you'll go download the last, you'll go all
the way to the bottom, you'll download the
latest zip file of the day, now it's 27.
5. 1, and then you can run
these PowerShell commands.
I'm gonna do it old school.
I'm gonna do it, I'm gonna do it,
from, the command shell, okay?
because you can unzip files in the
command shell because Windows ships with
two Unix utilities, curl and tar, but
it's not Linux tar, it's BSD tar, which
for whatever reason can unzip a zip
file, which is why they went with that.
it's BSD tar.
Anyway,
so xvf, I already downloaded it, so okay.
And we're gonna, oh,
third time recording this demo.
Okay, now,
and then you can go add that to the path.
So to add it to the path, we already have
it set up in the path, as you can see.
But you can just go in the registry.
You can do this via PowerShell,
you can do this via reg.
exe, but I'm just going to show you
the registry version, and you want
to go to, You can either go to HKEY
current user slash environment, which
is the path just for your user, or if
you want to add it to all the users.
HKEY current, HKEY local machines,
current control set, control
session management environment,
and it has all these variables,
including this one path over here.
And there's a million ways, and you'll
see SQL and Docker in the path over there.
And that's the way to permanently
add it to the path, right?
and it's in the path, right?
So then we're going to go C colon
slash docker three slash docker D.
Oh, it's actually going to
make that folder for me.
Okay, so it actually made
that in a separate folder.
Anyway.
and you can say dash register service,
that will register the service.
And you can see this
docker runs the service.
Okay, it's running as a service.
you can go, in the service list
over there, and this is a service
you can start or stop just like
IIS or any other Windows service.
you can also just run Docker D by
itself, and where the configuration
for this store, the configuration for
this is stored in, and we'll actually
program data slash docker, and
this is, you need to be local
admin to get these files over here.
And so just, so basically, to install
this, you're going to definitely need
local admin, To install the docker,
but if you want to just, if you just
want, if you have WSL in your system
already, you can install docker on your
WSL system for your Linux containers.
And we need UAC activation
to activate this.
And we're going to show you how to,
basically we're going to show you
how to configure this from here.
So this is a few configuration
options which are rather
important for Windows containers.
Config daemon.
json, right?
Okay.
Now the important thing is here you
make a group called dockerusers.
Okay, now this group called dockerusers
are the users of the, are the users.
So basically if you have UACs set up in
your machine like I do, so even an admin
user, doesn't by default have privileged
access, they can't run the docker command.
So you have to sit there.
And go and make this file and
add this to the docker theaters.
there's another setting you might
want to set in here that you might
want to look into if you want to run.
2019 Windows containers on a 2025,
on server 2025, or basically like
Windows, Windows 11 Insider Edition,
basically, to get to that version.
you're going to have to set
up, Hyper V isolation as
opposed to process activation.
There's another setting you want to set
in here, but there's a better setting.
The main setting you're going to want
to set in here, you're going to want to
set a group called Docker Users, right?
And then you're going to want to
type, local group docker users add.
Over here to add the user, it's
going to say at the very end, user.
And then you're gonna, so
that's gonna make the group.
And that can be any group name you want,
but I want it to tag with convention.
and you can say group name, and
then you can say, and then you
can say, local group over there.
Okay, and that's gonna sit there.
And obviously you have to run that at the
admin over here, so you're gonna have to,
you'll have to go do that command
over here, By the way, that weird
thing I'm pasting on the keyboard is
actually, OBS Studio, how to install OBS
Studio, wouldn't get it, the Microsoft
Store thing, it's not a password.
don't worry, not sharing
my password over there.
Okay, no such user group, some user,
so anyway, you type that command,
you set that up, and then, you would
register that service, and then you
would type, Ultimately, after you
register that service, you would
type start service to start that up,
and then you have Docker running.
So that's how you get in Windows, so
that's how you get the Docker daemon, so
you're, the Docker daemon on Windows, to
do Windows containers, the Docker daemon
on, Linux via WSL, those is, and those are
the two things you're going to want to do.
You have some other options here
I'm going to show you, and one
of them is called Podman, okay?
And
I have this set up, It's not running now.
It's going to tell me the
Podman is not running.
But basically, to install Podman,
and once again, you can go use Winget
or something to install this more
easily, but you can go install Podman.
So Podman is a open source
re implementation of Docker.
It's a daemon less re
implementation of Docker.
It is sponsored by IBM.
I'm not part of the
group that sponsored it.
I'm part of a new death hit company
that, is owned by IBM, but I don't
know the Podman people at all.
or anything like that, we tend not to, my,
my group tends not to deal with Podman,
but I think it's a perfectly fine tool
to use, but anyway, Podman is if you live
in Red Hat, that's what, is your guided
towards, using, Podman is daemonless.
Podman does not support
Windows containers.
Podman only supports Linux containers.
Okay, but you can go
install, this UI here.
And, you can also install Podman on Linux.
it seems to work just fine.
My main, caution against using Podman
is, if you want to use dev containers
and you want to use Visual Studio with
dev containers, and you're using Podman,
you're going to have some trouble.
You can go and sit there and, rename the
Podman executable to Docker and then, it
should mostly work except when it doesn't.
But, you're probably better off just
installing docker personally if you
if your main thing is I want to run
dev containers and, do that, right?
but anyway, Podman does give you a,
desktop edition, like a GUI version
as well as CLI version over here.
so anyway, we're going to do Podman.
Let's see if we can do
Podman machine start.
and just Podman will run inside of the,
there's a concept, Podman has a concept
of running these containers rootless,
which is, gives you some more security
and it generally works just fine.
And by the way, for running containers,
they work, I run a Minecraft server.
on Podman, and it works just fine,
and it's as close to production, I've
never used, I've never used Podman
for a work related thing, but it
runs my kid's Minecraft server, so
that's pretty close to production.
Anyway, you go set that up, and you do,
and the Podman command is completely
compatible with the Docker command,
so I can go to, just to show you,
Let's go, pull Azure right
down here, or, Podman, and
it's going to pull that down,
right, so here we go.
we've got, that works just fine.
So that's another way to do it.
The final way I'm going to show you,
actually the second final way, is
there is Rancher Desktop by SUSE.
this is a GUI that, that, that wraps
around, some other options over here.
Rancher is a, basically, so Rancher is
a nice, another alternative to using the
Podman Desktop if you want to try this.
I've used this before, it works just fine.
I'm not going to.
Demo it, because you're just
gonna install the Gooeys.
this gives you, some more options with
Kubernetes, and nerd control that, which
finally brings us to our final option.
So if you want another, open source,
container, solution, you can use
container D and Nerd Control.
ner Container D is a container,
Damon and Nerd Control is a docker.
Reimplementation of the docker
CLI, basically, to do that, right?
So you can install these options.
there's some support
for windows containers.
Not the most, the Windows container
support is not the most mature here.
I don't see much of an advantage of
doing this, locally in your dev machine,
unless you're already dealing with Neural
Control and Container D, and then that
part of your whole Kubernetes setup.
If that's the case, then
totally go for this.
Ben, you probably know more
about this, than I can show
you inside of Lightning Talk.
But those are your options over here.
you can go here and you can
download, This, this has some,
certainly some advantages to
doing this on Windows Server.
Maybe if you want to go with,
Container D inert controls
as opposed to Docker server.
but anyway, that's about it.
thanks for coming to my talk.
Thanks for watching.
And enjoy the rest of the, conference.
Check out some of the many other talks.