Welcome to my session on
accelerating AI lifecycle.
Today, I will talk about how we at Meta
work towards making AI lifecycle and
essentially the research to prod cycle
faster for scientists and engineers
to iterate and deliver their work.
But first, who am I?
I'm Pari Gupta, and I'm a Senior
Production Engineer at Meta.
I work on Python Language Foundation
team, which manages the entire
Python ecosystem within the company.
For the longest time, I worked
in the interactive computing team
focused on Bento, Meta's internal
Jupyter notebook distribution.
Outside of Meta, I like
to paint and dance.
Before diving into all the exciting
and creative improvements that
we've made so far, Let's go back to
basics and start with AI lifecycle.
AI is an iterative process.
When I first started out,
I thought it was linear.
You collect the data, you train a
fancy AI model, and do the testing.
Then you deploy that model in production,
and then you're magically done to
reap the fruits of the AI system.
Easy and dreamy, right?
What a noob I was.
It was very soon that I realized that AR
lifecycle is more of a cycle with a lot
of back and forth than a linear graph.
Here's an oversimplified version
of what an AR lifecycle looks like.
It contains different stages such as
product scoping, data engineering,
actual model development, deployment
of that developed model, and so on.
monitoring of how it,
on how it is performing.
And finally, business
analysis and insights.
You'll notice a lot of back and forth
arrows between different stages.
These indicate that lifecycle
is not a steady loop, but
involves a lot of revisions and
iterations for better results.
Out of all of these stages, the data
engineering and model development
components is called ML prototyping.
Thank you This phase is very core to the
cycle and its effectiveness can really
speed up the overall delivery of AI.
The most commonly used ML
prototyping tools are Jupyter
Notebooks and Kana environments.
Let's dive into them.
Jupyter Notebooks is an open source, web
based, interactive computing platform.
They allow you to create and
share documents that contain live
code, equations, visualizations,
And narrative text and images.
It's widely used in
academia and industry alike.
One of its main benefits can be seen
in data science and engineering.
Notebooks can help you massage
the data into the format that's
expected by your model, develop
data features, do scientific
computations, and even visualize
your data to derive insights from it.
Another is ML modeling and testing.
To prove a hypothesis, a scientist would
develop an experiment, code a hacky
prototype, and run it on their notebook
iteratively to train and test their model.
Jupyter notebooks have
several other benefits.
They're language agnostics, which
means that you can easily not just
run Python, but any other language
such as R, Hack, JavaScript, etc.
Lastly, it is back end agnostic.
This means that you can run your code
locally or on a remote server or a
GPU or a CPU cluster fairly easily.
Conda.
Conda is a popular package manager
used for managing software environments
and dependencies in data science
and scientific computing world.
It was developed as part of Anaconda
distribution and includes Python
and other programming languages for
major scientific computing tooling.
Conva allows its users to create isolated
environments where different versions
of packages can be installed and used
without interfering with one another
or with the base system environment.
This makes it very easy to manage
dependencies and avoid conflicts
between different packages and versions.
Now I want to share some of the
ideas on how we at Meta have explored
and executed to make ML prototyping
faster within the company so that our
researchers can deploy their models.
and make them work for the fast growing
world of artificial intelligence.
Bento.
Bento is the internal
distribution of Jupyter notebooks.
It is particularly optimized for
Meta's needs to make it compatible
with the internal codebase.
It allows users to execute their code
on different servers within Meta.
Now, let's see how we've improved
this interactive platform.
Have you ever exe Have you ever
wanted to rerun and visualize
data on a regular basis?
Maybe make reports or see how the model
is performing to make informed decisions?
Inspired by Pet Paper Mill's
approach, Pento introduced powerful
tooling to schedule notebooks to
run code at any cadence on any
server in a privacy aware manner.
This helps us ensure that all the
permissions are intact for user's ease.
Next is persistent sessions.
Ever come across a situation where
you wanted to run code remotely
and lost internet or wifi got
disconnected or something as simple
as a laptop went to sleep, you lose
all the long running executions and
you have to start all over again.
It's sad, right?
We implemented persistent sessions
and sophisticated notebook recovery
mechanisms where users can access
their data computations on, any Jupyter
session across different servers.
You can simply execute a long running in
your notebook and come back to Jupyter
session at a later point in time,
essentially resuming the session with all
the data computations already available.
Another idea that made a difference
in developer productivity and improved
ML prototyping was cross platform
debugging between We are scored at
Meta and Bento here, one click on
any Python file would push you into
a debugging session or a note or a
notebook to iterate on your code with
all the dependencies that you may need.
Not only this, we also introduced
notebooks within VS code itself.
which makes it very easy to import and
export in and out of IDE at any time.
There are several other innovations
that we've made so far and influenced
the ML development and really
made some quantifiable speed ups.
Integrations to enable data privacy and
security reviews, support for serverless
servers, enhanced SQL cell support,
ability to use multi language kernels,
auto suggestions using internally
developed Gen AI agents, and so much more.
Kotlin is relatively a newer
introduction to our developer tooling.
We want to bring most of the
open source experience internally
in a controlled manner.
This enables faster onboarding of
researchers to the ML development cycle,
which will Lowering the learning curve and
hence making the product delivery faster.
Researchers can play with their GitHub
projects more freely while they are
experimenting with their ML models.
One thing to note here is
that Meta is a large monorepo.
This means that there is one
version across all the projects
that exist within Meta.
This introduces a lot of
difficulties when it comes to quicker
experimentation and version switching.
Conda, on the other end of the
spectrum, provides full version
control of dependencies that a user
may want to experiment with before
marring to one specific version.
Conda meta is packaged into a portable
virtual self contained environment.
which can be accessed from
anywhere the user desires.
And finally, as we plug Conda environments
for specific MLE use cases, we also
enable better telemetry, accountability,
and tracking in terms of errors,
package usages, and vulnerability checks
to ensure that researchers can work
without worrying about any breaches.
The last interesting idea that I
want to share today is the power
of combining these two tools.
Basically, I mean that Runconda
as a Jupyter kernel in the
back end of a notebook.
This in particular has accelerated
the development of AI models and
experimentation bringing research
and production development
much closer to one another.
It has actually reduced the cost.
Thank you.
Here's the link to my LinkedIn profile.
I'll make the slides public in case anyone
wants to go through these resources.
Thank you.