Hello, everyone.
I'm Shavan Kumar Nendrambakar.
I'm a seasoned SAP Cloud and S4
HANA software developer consultant
with over 15 years of experience in
information technology, specializing
in SAP technologies and implementation
across healthcare, retail, oil and
gas, and manufacturing industries.
This presentation explores the
recent advancement and integration
strategies in SAP S4 on our cloud
and SAP Business Technology Platform,
examining their combined impact on
enterprise digital transformation.
We will dive into the architectural
evaluation, integration strategies, and
deployment flexibility across on premises.
Cloud and hybrid environments and industry
specific implementations across retail,
healthcare, and manufacturing sectors.
Our journey will cover the technical
infrastructure of SAP BTP, including
its platform as a service capabilities,
development environments, and
artificial intelligence integration.
We will also evaluate the business
intelligence and analytical capabilities
that enable real time decision making.
Thank you.
Let's talk about the evolution
of SAP Enterprise Solutions.
It has been marked by significant
technological advancement and
changing business requirements.
SAP journey from its initial R3 system to
the current S4 HANA platform represents
a fundamental shift in the enterprise
resource planning architecture.
The traditional SAP R3 system introduced
in 1990s established the foundation
for client server enterprise computing.
But it was limited by its
rigid data structures and
batch processing capabilities.
With the advent of in memory computing
technology, SAP introduced HANA in
2010, making a pivotal transition
toward real time data processing
and analytics capabilities.
The subsequent development of S4 HANA
represented a complete reimagining of
the core ERP system, optimized for cloud
development and digital operations.
Let's look at SAP S4 HANA architecture.
The architecture foundation of SAP
S4 HANA represents a significant
evolution in the enterprise software
design, built upon sophisticated
in memory database structures that
enable real time data processing and
advanced analytical capabilities.
The core architectural components
comprise three primary layers,
the database layer, powered by SAP
HANA column storage technology, the
application layer, which hosts the
business logic and processing engines.
and the presentation layer, which
delivers the SAP user experience.
This architecture facilitates the
streamlined data processing by
eliminating the traditional aggregates
and redundant data storages, resulting
in significantly reduced data footprints
and enhanced system performance.
The simplified data model reduces the
storage requirements by up to 80%.
With the embedded analytical
seamlessly integrated into
operational process, Organizational
gain instant insights for informed
decision making, driving operational
efficiency, and business agility.
Let's talk about integration framework.
The integration framework between SAP S4
HANA and BTP established a confidential
connectivity layer that enables
seamless communication between various
enterprise applications and services.
This framework utilizes the cloud
integration suite, API management,
and integration advisory to
orchestrate complex business
process across hybrid landscapes.
The integration architecture supports
both synchronous and asynchronous
communication patterns, enabling real
time data exchange while maintaining
the system reliability and scalability.
Key integration patterns include
application to application integration,
and business to business integration,
and API based scenarios, all secured
through robust authentication
and authorization mechanisms.
Let's talk about deployment flexibility.
SAP S4 HANA offers organizations
multiple implementation options to
align with their specific business
requirements and IT strategies.
The on premises deployment model provides
maximum control over the infrastructure
and customization capabilities,
particularly beneficial for organizations
with complex legacy system integrations.
The cloud deployment options delivered
through SAP S4 HANA Cloud offers
a rapid implementation, automatic
updates, reduced maintenance overhead
while maintaining the comprehensive
functionality and the security standards.
The hybrid deployment model combines
elements of both approaches, allowing
organization to maintain certain
components on premises while leveraging
the cloud capability for others.
This model is particularly valuable during
phased cloud migration strategies Enabling
organization to transition gradually
while maintaining the business continuity
and leveraging existing investments.
Let's talk about SAP BTP
technical infrastructure.
The technical infrastructure is built on
a robust platform as a service foundation
that supports multi cloud deployment
strategies across major cloud providers.
The platform infrastructure is
designed with a microservices
architecture that ensures high
availability, scalability, and security.
The PaaS capabilities encompasses
I'm going to show you how you can
use conference services for database
management, application runtime,
connectivity, and security, enabling
organizations to develop and deploy
enterprise applications efficiently.
The development environment within
SAP BTP offers a diverse ecosystem
of tools catering to different skill
levels and development approaches.
The low code, no code solutions primarily
delivered through SAP Build Apps enable
business users to create applications
through visual development interface.
and pre built components.
Professional developers benefit from
sophisticated development tools,
including SAP Business Application
Studio, which provides a cloud based
integrated development environment,
supporting multiple programming languages.
The AI and machine learning integration
capabilities of SAP BTP represent A
significant advancement in enterprise
automation and intelligent processing.
SAP AI business services provide pre
trained machine learning models and
APIs for common business scenarios,
such as document information
extraction, conversational AI, and
intelligent robotic process automation.
The platform support for generative
applications has expanded to include
capabilities for natural language
processing, code generation, and
automated testing, significantly
accelerating deployment cycles and
improving the software quality.
This framework integrates with
the popular data science tools
and supports both structured and
unstructured data processing.
Enabling organization to implement
sophisticated AI solutions
while maintaining enterprise
grade security and compliance.
Let's talk about industry
specific applications.
The implementation of SAP S4 in
the retail sector has transformed
traditional retail operations by
enabling real time inventory management.
Personalized customer experiences
and predictive demand planning.
Retailers leverage the solution to
create unified commerce experiences
across physical and digital channels.
With the capabilities for intelligent
store operations, dynamic pricing, and
automated supply chain optimization.
The platform ability to process massive
volume of point of sale data in real
time enables retailers to make data
driven decisions about merchandising,
promotions, and inventory allocations.
Advanced analytical capability supports
sophisticated customer segmentation.
The platform's ability to process massive
volumes of point of sale data in real
time enables retailers to make a data
driven decision about merchandising,
promotions, and inventory allocation,
advanced analytical capability,
support sophisticated customer
segmentation, and personalization
initiatives, while integrated machine
learning models help predict consumer
behavior and optimize stock levels
across complex distribution networks.
In the life science and healthcare
sectors, SAP solution address
critical requirements for regulatory
compliances, patient data management,
and research development process.
The platform provides validated
system that meet the GXP requirements
and support FDA compliance while
enabling advanced analytics for
critical trials and research data.
Healthcare provides utilize these
solutions for enhanced patient care
coordination, medical supply chain
management, and healthcare analytics.
The integration capabilities allows
seamless connection with medical
devices, healthcare information systems,
and other regulatory requirements.
The manufacturing industries demonstrates
SAP capability to support industry 4.
0 initiative through integrated
smart factory operations.
Thank you The platform enables
real time production monitoring,
predictive maintenance, and intelligent
asset management through IoT
integration and advanced analytics.
Manufacturing leverages these capabilities
to optimize production schedules, reduce
downtime, and optimize quality control.
Manufacturers leverage these
capabilities to optimize production
schedule, reduce downtime, and improve
quality control through automated
inspection and testing process.
The solution ability to integrate with
the shop floor systems and automation
equipment creates a comprehensive digital
trade throughout the manufacturing process
from design to production and maintenance.
Let's talk about business intelligence
and analytical capabilities.
The business intelligence and
analytics capabilities of SAP S4 HANA
and BTP represents a comprehensive
framework that transforms raw data
into actionable business insights.
SAP The predictive analytical framework
integrates advanced statistical algorithm
and mission learning models to forecast
business trends, identify patterns,
and anticipate future scenarios.
This capability is enhanced by SAP
Analytical Cloud Embedded Intelligence,
which provides sophisticated predictive
modeling tools that can be applied across
various business functions from financial
forecasting to supply chain optimization.
Data integration and management
within the platform provides a
unified approach to handling the
diverse data sources and types.
The architecture supports real time
data replication, ETL processes,
and seamless integration with
both SAP and non SAP systems.
This unified data management approach
ensures that data consistency and
reliability across the enterprise
while maintaining the data governance
and compliance requirements.
The real time analytics and reporting
capabilities leverage the power of in
memory computing to deliver instant
insights and interactive visualizations.
Users can access live business data
through customizable dashboards, embedded
analytics, self service reporting tools.
The platform supports natural
language query processing, allowing
users to ask business questions
in the plain language and receives
instant visualizations and insights.
Advanced features such as storytelling
capabilities, collaboration
tools, and models analytics ensure
that insights are accessible and
actionable across the organization.
Let's look at commercial models.
SAP's commercial framework for BTP
and S4 HANA demonstrates a flexible
approach to pricing and licensing that
accommodates diverse organizational needs.
The consumption based pricing model
implemented through the Cloud Platform
Enterprise Agreement scalable enables
our nation to optimize cost by paying
only for service actually consumed.
The model provides access to the
full range of platform services
while allowing organization to
scale usage based on demand.
The pay as you go model offers even
greater flexibility, particularly
beneficial for organizations
exploring new capabilities or
managing variable workloads.
Subscription based service provides
Predictable costs and comprehensive
access to specific service
bundles, making budgeting more
straightforward for organizations
with their stable usage patents.
These strategic pricing models
deliver measurable business value
with the customer reporting 30 to 40
percent in reduction in total cost.
These strategic pricing models Deliver
measurable business value with the
customer reporting 30 to 40 percent
reduction in total cost of ownership.
Organizations typically achieve
ROI within 12 to 18 months through
the reduced infrastructure cost.
Average 25 percent savings.
Improved operational efficiency and
accelerated innovation capabilities.
The flexibility to choose and
combine models enables organization
to optimize spending based on
their growth and performance.
Usage patterns, future
trends and developments.
SAP's future innovation will
transform enterprise computing
through groundbreaking technologies.
Quantum computing integration
will drastically accelerate
complex calculations.
Solutions will enable real time IoT
data processing at unprecedented scales.
The next generation of AAML capabilities.
will deliver intelligent
automation and predictive
insights with remarkable accuracy.
These developments are complemented
by industry specific solutions that
address vertical challenges, enhanced
natural languages interfaces that
transforms the user interactions,
and a comprehensive sustainability
feature that helps organizations
meet their environment goals.
Together, these advancements
positions SAP at the forefront of
digital transformation, enabling
business to thrive in an increasingly
connected and sustainable future.
Conclusion, the integration of SAP
S4 HANA Cloud and BTP represents a
significant milestone in the evaluation
of enterprise software solutions.
demonstrating the transformative
potential of cloud native architectures
combined with the advanced analytics and
artificial intelligence capabilities.
This platform ability to support diverse
deployment models, industry specific
solutions, and flexible commercial
frameworks provides organizations
with the adaptability required in
today's dynamic business environment.
The extensive integration
capabilities Sophisticated
development tools and AI services.
Enable our nation to accelerate their
digital transformative initiatives.
As emerging technologies continue
to evolve and business requirements
become increasingly complex,
SAP's commitment to innovation and
industry specialization positions the
platform well for future challenges.
The success of implementations across
retail, healthcare, and manufacturing
sectors validates the platform's
adaptability and effectiveness in
delivering the tangible business value.
Organizations leveraging SAP S4 HANA
and BTP as a foundational element
of their digital infrastructures are
well positioned for success in the
rapidly evolving business landscape.
Thank you for joining me today.