Hi, everyone, and welcome.
I'm really excited to be here today
to talk to you about vector search.
It's a fascinating technology
that's transforming the way we find
information in the age of semantic
understanding, where we're not just
looking for keywords, but actual meaning.
this comprehensive review.
we'll give you an idea of the
architectural foundations of vector
search and its implementation
across multiple domains.
my name is Siddharth Pratap Singh.
All right.
to fully appreciate vector
search, let's take a quick look
back at how search has evolved.
Remember when we used to rely on typing in
exact keywords and crossing our fingers?
That was token based search,
using simple word matching.
It was fine for basic searches, but it
often struggled with the complexities
and ambiguities of human language.
Then came semantic search, a
step in the right direction.
The idea was to understand the
intent and context behind our
words, but the technology at the
time just wasn't up to the task.
Fast forward to today and we have
vector search, powered by incredible
advances in machine learning and NLP.
It's like semantic search on a whole
new level, able to truly understand
what we mean and find relevant results
even in massive, messy data sets.
Okay, let's dive into the
mechanics of vector search.
At its core, it's about transforming
text into high dimensionality vectors.
These vectors are like numerical
representations that capture
the meaning of words and their
relationships to one another.
Think of it as converting language
into a format that computers can
really grasp, a way to map words and
concepts in a multi dimensional space.
This transformation is made
possible by neural networks,
sophisticated algorithms that can
process complex data relationships.
They can handle all the nuances of human
language, like synonyms, ambiguity, and
context, while maintaining efficiency.
Different types of neural
networks are used in the process.
each with its own strengths.
Some popular ones include RNNs, Recurrent
Neural Networks, Convolutional Neural
Networks, and Transformer Networks.
RNNs are practically good at processing
sequential data like text, while CNNs
excel at capturing local patterns.
Transformers have revolutionized
NLP with their ability to handle
long range dependencies in text.
And to find the information we
need amongst a sea of data, we
use specialized index structures.
these index structures are designed
to enable rapid similarity searches
in high dimensional spaces.
They allow us to quickly sift through
millions of vectors and pinpoint the
ones that are most similar to our search
queries, all while balancing search
speed, memory efficiency, and accuracy.
Some common index structures used in
embedding based search or vector search
include KD trees, bird trees, locality
sensitive hashing, which is LSH.
Okay, so let's go with the
implementation architecture.
We'll take a closer look at how a vector
search system is actually implemented.
There are a few key components
that work together seamlessly.
First, we have the document
processing pipeline.
This pipeline takes raw text data.
And transforms it into a machine readable
vectors we were just, referring to.
This involves several steps, including
cleaning the text, breaking it into
meaningful chunks, like sentences or
paragraphs, and then creating those rich
numerical representations into, through
our chosen embedding model into vectors.
This process can also include
things like stemming, lemmatization,
and stop word removal to further
optimize the search performance.
Then, when you type in a search query,
the system actually converts it into
the same vector format as the documents.
The dimensionality of the search, the
vectors from the search queries as
well as the documents are the same.
It's like translating your query
into the language of the data,
enabling true semantic matching.
Finally, the index.
The search index comes into play.
It uses efficient nearest neighbor
algorithms to quickly find the documents
that are most similar to your query
based on their vector representations.
how, what we mean by similar is that in
that dimensional space, the documents
that are most relevant or, answer the
question that your query has, they
lie closer in that dimensional space.
The system then intelligently
ranks the results.
taking into account not only the semantic
relevance, but also the factors like
quality of the document, the historical
behavioral popularity of the document,
amongst the users on your platforms,
and then some user preferences.
Okay, so we'll go over some
domain specific applications.
We'll take up e commerce and health care.
So embedding base search or vector
search isn't just a theoretical concept.
It's already having a real
world impact in various fields.
In e commerce, it's revolutionizing
the way we shop online.
It helps us find the perfect product, the
most relevant product, even if we can't
quite articulate what we are looking for.
It can understand the intent
behind vague searches.
For example, something like, birthday
gift for a 10 year old who likes
science and suggests relevant products.
on the business side, it helps
companies detect fraud and
ensure secure transactions.
for queries like this, for example,
the one I mentioned, birthday gift
for a 10 year old who likes science.
Most of the products that
an e commerce catalog has.
It does not contain keywords
that go along with it, right?
People will put in science kits,
astronomy kits, or computer kits as a
product, but they wouldn't necessarily
mention 10 year olds who like science.
So these queries are
very well represented.
And the products, are that are retrieved
using vector search are relevant
that you wouldn't find in the legacy
token based retrieval in health care.
It's helping doctors and researchers
across critical access, critical
information faster and more accurately
imagine being able to instantly
find relevant medical records or
research papers, even if they use
slightly different terminologies.
an example in e commerce, like I just
mentioned, this can be life saving
in emergency situations are crucial
for groundbreaking medical research.
And of course, all this is done
while maintaining strict compliance
with privacy regulations.
VectorSearch is also a
game changer for academia.
It can analyze complex relationships
between research papers, help us
uncover hidden connections, and
accelerate scientific discovery.
For example, it can identify papers
that are semantically similar.
Even if they don't share any
common citations, leading to
new insights and collaborations.
In the business world, it's
breaking down information silos and
making knowledge sharing a breeze.
You don't need to dig through
endless files and folders to
find the right information.
However, or regardless of how the
information is stored or organized,
the vector based indexes can provide a
critical infrastructure or a critical
system that can get you all these files
and folders that you're looking for.
This can lead to improved decision
making, increased productivity,
and a more connected workforce.
Let's come to how this is implemented and
being used in media and legal departments.
In the media industry, VectorSearch
is powering the next generation
of content recommendation systems.
It's like having a personal assistant who
knows your taste in movies and TV shows
better than you do, because it understands
your intent, maps them into embeddings.
It's helpful in suggesting content
that you'll actually enjoy.
It can analyze your viewing history,
genre preferences, and even your
emotional responses to content to provide
highly personalized recommendations.
For legal professionals,
it's revolutionizing how
they research case laws.
Imagine being able to instantly
find relevant precedents based on
the nuances of legal arguments.
even if they use different wording or
address slightly different circumstances.
this takes countless hours of research and
leads to more efficient legal strategies.
but how do we know if,
it is actually better?
the numbers across the industry from the
research papers speak for themselves.
We've seen significant improvements
in search accuracy, user
satisfaction across the board.
In many cases, vector search has
been shown to outperform traditional
keyword searches by a significant
margin, leading to more relevant
results and a better user experience.
The best part, this field is
actively being worked upon.
all the researchers across the industry
are constantly refining this technology,
making it even smarter and more efficient.
There are technical challenges.
as we deal with the ever growing
amounts of data, we need to ensure
our systems can handle the load.
That means finding innovative
ways to manage data and optimize
performances, especially in
distributed computing environments.
things need to be fetched fast.
performance optimization is another one.
the model improvements are also happening.
better and better models that can be used
to create these embedding representations
or semantic representations.
They are continually being
researched and innovated upon.
These challenges actually also
present exciting opportunities.
Imagine combining vector search
with cutting edge technologies
like distributed learning.
We could improve model performances
while keeping data privacy in mind.
Going on to the next slide.
the future is bright.
We're seeing a convergence with
privacy preserving technologies,
allowing us to search across
decentralized databases without
compromising sensitive information.
there are applications in blockchains.
There are applications in.
um, privacy preserving medical databases
that do not compromise sensitive
information and are still able to find
relevant information for your queries.
We're also seeing integration with
distributed computing, enabling
robust search architectures that
can handle massive amounts of data.
With the rise of more sophisticated
NLP, we can expect even deeper
semantic understanding, leading to more
accurate and relevant search results.
Vector search is, more than
just an incremental improvement.
It's a paradigm shift in
how we find information.
It's about moving beyond simple keyword
matching and truly understanding the
meaning and context behind our searches.
As we continue to refine the technology
and explore new applications, it will
definitely play a crucial role in
unlocking the power and information and
driving innovation across industries.
Thank you, all for listening.
I hope you're as excited about the
future of vector search as I am.
thank you so much for taking your
time and hearing what I have to say.
Thank you.