Hello, everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
Today I'll be talking about a data
frame library named fire ducks that
we are working at the research lab.
So we will explore, the motivation
behind developing the fighters by stating
some of the key challenges with pandas.
And of course we'll be talking about
the tips and tricks and the best
practices when dealing with large
scale data processing in pandas What
fireducks is and what it is offering
the optimization strategy available
with it With some live demo and the
resources available on fireducks
so Let's have a quick introduction.
My name is Saurav.
I'm currently doing in the I'm
currently working as a resource
engineer at NSE Corporation.
So I have been associated with
NSE over the last 11 years where
I'm doing different work in
the field of high performance
computing, distributed processing,
AI machine learning and desktop.
So we have a long history of working
with the vector supercomputer.
where we start with S6 series of
supercomputers and, work with various
legacy applications from tsunami
prediction to earthquake simulations
on this vector architecture.
my leader at my team, Stacy Sarkar, first
thought that we including our expertise in
the field of HPC and the compiler and this
kind of distributed processing related
tasks, How about creating something
that will use the compiler technology
because we have a keen interest in
compiler And at the same time do something
with the python for the data science
community So that is the time when you
thought okay data scientist often face
challenges With the pandas computation.
So let's create some library That will
look completely same as pandas But
internally it will have a compiler
and do a lot of magic kind of stuff
Such that a programmer, a pandas
programmer can experience much faster,
data processing when using firetrucks.
So please stay with me till the end of
this presentation where I'll be talking
about various best practices I will give
you walkthrough with the finders the
offering the motivation the Comparison
with other data frame libraries that is
available and of course the end of the end
I'll have some frequently asked questions
because this is something online.
So and Of course if you have any
questions, you can get in touch with
me over the linkedin or other social
media i'll be happy to collaborate
and help you in whatever matter I can.
Yes So this is the flow.
I believe all of you can relate
what we do as a data scientist, we
collect data from various resources
and the data in the raw format is
not resilient digestible by the AI
algorithm, AI machine learning algorithm.
So what we do is we clean the data,
make it more meaningful so that we
can get a better features out of
it and we can do a better model.
So better the data is
the better the model.
That is some kind of old story
that we have been learned about.
But the important thing for this entire
cycle to understand that, although
AI machine learning is taking time
and deploying model is also taking
time, but the most time consuming
part is the creation of the data as
per the research from the anaconda.
It says that the data loading, cleaning,
and the visualization is something
that occupies almost 75 percent
of the effort of a data scientist.
So if you have a lot of questions in
mind, if you want to extract a lot of
many features, You need to spend a lot
of time in during the first a few months.
I would say for doing the efficient
data exploration So that is why
various researches has been happening
in this field Because this is one of
the most important areas where we need
optimization Now with these ladies,
let me have something about pandas.
I believe all of you are from
the data science background So
you must have Work with pandas.
So it is one of the most popular
libraries even today It is having the
second most download after numpy But
it comes with some kind of problems.
The very common one is it's not
multi threaded So if you have a good
system with many core available,
you cannot be able to leverage
that so Your program will be slow.
You have to wait for a longer time
to get your result if you are working
with large data So So longer waiting
times, slow execution, if you're running
this on the cloud side, a higher cloud
cost, and of course, longer execution
will activate a lot of carbon dioxide.
So these is, these are something
that is associated with bundles.
So it is ideally not
ideal for the large scale.
scale exhibition, right?
So now Although these are the challenges
related with pandas But the key challenge
is like there are various way of writing
the same programming pandas So if we
ourselves can identify the best approaches
the best practices and take care of that
when writing our program It's fine enough
because by default pandas doesn't offer
you optimization as it is eager in nature
so whatever you Ask it to do it will do it
for you So if you have written a good code
unoptimized one yet, you are at good stage
But if your program has performance issue
You may need to pay a lot of performance
cost when your data goes in size or
your program goes in complexity So we're
talking about some crucial performance
issue that involves in a pandas program
and how to take care of that And what
are the automation possibility for those
cases using fireducks and other library?
So to going forward let us understand
one by one the best practices and
challenges associated with data
large scale data analysis program So
with that let us have a first quiz.
can you identify?
Which one is a better code whether
the left one or the right one?
yeah since i'm doing this online, so
definitely cannot take the response
from you But when I asked this kind of
question in one of the event last time,
so I believe I had Mostly around 90
percent of them answered the rightmost
one is the best performing query Because
of many reasons so as you can see this
is written in chain and that is ideally
the best way of writing This kind of
query in pandas or pandas like library.
Why Let's have let's understand
that with some kind of Illustration.
So let's say this is the data that I have
loaded from file Of course, you can see
there are some duplicates once I remove
the duplicate This will be the data my
data might be reduced to its half Then
I will shorting the result by b column
selecting, the top two of the result and
that's it Now, let's assume some kind of
memory footprint associated with the data.
Let's say my data is 16 gb You After
the removing duplicate it will be
8gb, 8gb and some other gb, so at
the end of the thing it will be 32gb.
But till the time the foo is alive
all these references like df2 t3 are
alive because pandas not pandas python
cannot Make them ready for the garbage
collection because they have the
reference alive in them alive, right?
So that is the challenge with not
writing zend expression what happens
when you go for the zend expression
It will be like, the data is loaded.
We remove the duplicates But now when
we'll be applying the shorting at that
moment, I only need the input from the
drop duplicate side So I don't need
this data anymore So this data will be
out of reference and python can make it
garbage collected based on It's neat.
So the same way when I will perform
the top two, I don't need the
duplicated result drop duplicates
result I only need the shorter result.
So this way at the end of my program I
can remove the intermediate data that
is there that is generated during my
query of the long expression So and that
is definitely going to help you when
you'll be dealing with large scale data.
I'll be showing this kind of thing
with example in my upcoming slides.
So that is one of the best practices
that write your expression in chained
expression and it is possible in
pandas, of course it's possible.
So as much as possible try to go
for the chained expression such
that you can avoid this kind of
memory and performance issues.
Now let's consider the second one.
So here is a quiz.
Where it is trying to solve the same
problem it is trying to find the
top five of a value based on the
shorting from the b column, right?
Now, can you guess which one is a
better code if you give the if you're
about to write the code whether you'll
go for the top one or you'll go for
the bottom one yeah, so when I asked
this kind of question in a recent
event, so almost I have mixed answer
So 40 to 50 percent answer that the
top one is the good one And 50 to 60
percent answer that the bottom one is
the good one So with the majority the
answer is of course the bottom one.
So if you yourself, thought it is
the bottom one Give a pat on your
back Now, let's understand why it is.
So what happens ideally your data may
have many columns in relative, right?
Not only a and b if you are going to
perform the shorting on the entire
data, what will happen, not only the
target columns A and B, rest of the
columns like C to J will get shorted.
And that will never be used in your final
result because you're only interested
To have the shorted value from the a
column after the result is shorted by
b So the c to g column will get shorted
based on the b columns It will occupy the
memory, but it will no longer be needed.
So it is waste of competition time and
memory So what you can do you can create
a view of the data of my interest that
i'm interested in a and b column only So
why not just create a view of that data?
You Perform the same steps do the
same thing and this will definitely
going to reduce a lot of competition
calls because it doesn't matter How
many column you will data may have?
Because you also understand.
I am interested in a and b so let's
not bother about rest of the column
Let's create a view and work on that
This kind of optimization is something
called projection pushdown and it is very
important that we should take care when
dealing with large scale data analysis
Now, let's consider another example You
So before going to the quiz, let me show
what it is trying to do For example, I am
an, I have an employee table in a country
table and I want to perform some kind
of merging to have a larger joint result
and see who are the employee, who are the
male employees from which country, like
how many, like country wise count of the
male employee is something of my problem.
So how it can be done, one thing that
I can just join these two tables.
Then I can filter all the male category
from the result in data and I can
perform a group by count So by looking
at this illustration, can you identify
what is the performance bottleneck?
Yes The issue is with the expensive
merge operation So although we are
only interested in the male category
employee What we did is we performed the
merging on the entire employee table.
We could instead do what?
We could first filter only the male
category from my employee table and
then we can do the merging operation.
Followed by the group by count It will
do a lot of benefit when you have like
kind of 50 50 percent of the employee
ratio Or you have very less amount of mail
Like employees because it can reduce your
data by to a great extent and the merge
will not take much time in that case So
this is something called predicate push
down In terms of compiler technology.
So again, this is one of the very
important optimization strategy We
should ideally take care of that And
we'll see with some demo that how
this kind of strategy is important
when dealing with large scale
data analysis in upcoming slides.
So now let's put these two in,
some kind of, like rule of thumb.
So again, in order to understand
that the importance of such execution
order, let's take this example where
it is trying to perform shorting
by the E column, do the filtration
based on some conditional B column.
Select the E column and get the top two.
Now, in order to illustrate that,
let's consider this is my data and
if I short the data with this color
code, I will have the shorted result
from the yellow, red, green, and blue.
this is my data after I shorted,
something like yellow, red, green,
and blue will be the result.
Let's consider b equals to 1 for
the darker shade and b equals
to 1, 2 for the lighter shade.
if I filter, I'll only have the lighter
shaded part, then I will select the
only E column and find the top two.
Now, if we carefully notice this
entire data flow, can you identify
what is wrong in this journey?
Of course you can, right?
you can say that although I am
interested in only A, B and E columns.
I have already involved rest of the
columns like c and d that is there
in my data that have been used But
never referenced so that is ideally
a waste of membrane competition time
So instead what we can do is we can
first identify that for this query.
I only did a b and e column so why
not just create a view of a b e column
such that we can reduce my scope of the
data first in the Horizontal direction
by applying pushdown projection Okay.
projection poster.
Then I can see that, okay, this
is my data and, but instead,
why to short this entire data?
Because I'm only interested in
the lighter shaded part, right?
So what I can do, I can, for, before
going to do shorting, I can reduce the
data further by applying the filter.
Once the filtration is done, I can have
my further reduced data and this data
is ready for the shorting because that
is ideally part of the data that I'm
interested to perform the shorting on.
Now apply the shorting, find the
E column and find the top two.
This is the way by applying kind of
projection pushdown You can ideally
optimize the data flow and this is
a very important execution order.
Following that in your large
scale data analysis, you can
definitely make sure a lot of it.
Benefit from the execution
time and the memory.
So we'll understand this with some Demo
with some example real example in upcoming
slides Now with that, let's understand
what fire ducks is and why to explore this
library So the first thing, the fireducks
is a DataFrame library, high performance
compiler accelerated DataFrame library.
why it is called so?
Basically, the ducks is, it's just a name
of the animal because all the DataFrame
libraries, they're like the pandas,
boulders, they are named after an animal.
So we just thought of, first
of all, we thought of DAX.
Some data frame accelerator, but
dx is already a name that time.
So we thought of naming it as a ducks
So it doesn't have any link with the
duck db for information But the fire
has a meaning fire is from the flexible
ir engine What is ir is something
called intermediary representation.
That is the backbone of the fire dogs
jit compilation So what fire does do is?
It's lazy execution not like pandas like
you ask and it do instead you ask and
it creates some instruction for example
you ask it to do shorting instead of
shorting it will just create okay you
ask me to do short on this data on this
column perfect then you ask it to do
please filter based on this condition
it will just create an instruction
Without any calculation or, like
computations, just create an instruction
followed by a projection instruction
and followed by a slicing instruction.
Just some instruction will be generated.
So if you measure the execution time
for this part, you will see that it's
executed blink of the eyes because it does
nothing in, but creating the instruction.
Now you can tell me like when
this instruction will be executed.
these are the instruction that
will be automatically triggered by
some of your action on the result.
For example, when you want the result
to be printed, when you want the
result to be dumped in a file by two
csv2 parquet kind of operation, when
you apply some kind of aggregation on
this result, for example, finding some
maximum minimum value or something.
So that is the time by when these kind
of expression will be automatically
triggered and it will be executed.
With some compilation related optimization
now, let's say like I want to print
the result So that is the time the
compiler will be activated and it
will try to figure out the instruction
associated with the result And what are
the instruction it will say that okay.
I want to find the top two based
on e column So it based on the
filtration b column based on the
shorting on the a column This
is how the compiler understand.
Okay, I have this data, but I'm only
interested in a b and e column So it will
add a new instruction To project only
the target columns of a b and e before
doing the further operation Such that
it can reduce the data in the horizontal
iteration first Then it will figure okay.
You want to do short then you want
to do filter That means you're only
interested to perform shorting on a
selective set of rows it can do some
interchanges of the instruction.
It can do the filter first, then
it can do the short and rest of
the operation will remain as it is.
This way the compiler will
optimize the generated IR.
Once the optimized IR is generated, it can
be translated to another pandas version.
For example, if you consider it's a
pandas program, it can be something like.
Project a b e filter based on this
condition perform the shorting
project the column and take the top
two Now this can be a pandas program.
This can be a c Api call this can be
any other library call of your interest
because this ir is quite flexible It
can be translated to any other data
frame library or any other method call
for your reference I just ported it
to pandas to understand it better.
So that is why write one query You
Use this design and it can execute
anywhere of your target choice So we
have developed this multi core kernel
in c where we use the multi threaded
and other high performance related stuff
like effective utilization of the caches
the vectorization and other related
stuff such that not only, the results,
but also it can do much faster when
just comparing the kernel operations,
like the only filter, only join, only
group by itself will be faster because
of the careful optimization, careful
implementation of the algorithm.
So again, I'll be talking about these
in details in the benchmarking slides.
So now why you should be understanding
or you should be interested in exploring
this library because the first thing
Pandas doesn't offer you optimization, but
firetax is lazy So because of the lazy it
can do just in time optimization for you
If you have a good system with multiple
core available it can distribute it can
parallelize the workload not distribute
parallelize the workload among the
multiple threads So that will result much
faster data analysis If you work in the
cloud you will experience less cloud, cost
and of course, it will run much faster So
it will attribute to less carbon dioxide,
but the most important thing is if pandas,
that's fine You don't need to understand.
You don't need to learn a new library
new data frame library So when the
technology like ai and these kind
of llm things is progressing so far
It's better to learn a new technology
than to learn a new library, right?
So just you know pandas because we
all of us usually start from pandas So
knowing pandas is sufficient, but the
challenges associated with pandas can
be addressed by firedesk automatically
Now the question is does it handle
any kind of pandas application?
Yes, it does handle any kind of pandas
application not only pandas application
but also the library that expect you
to provide the pandas data for example
seaborn matplotlib, scikit learn,
imbalance learn, category encoders all
the library that expect the you to input
the pandas data frame You can provide
a firedash data frame and it can work
seamlessly with those as well So no extra
learning no code modification You can
experience much better performance benefit
when switching from pandas to firetax.
Now, let's understand some
kind of demo with this.
So here in this example, I am using
some kind of Bitcoin data of the
last three to five years and it is
trying to perform some moving average.
Just load the data creating a window and
perform the average, perform the mean
average calculation and plot the result.
So the code is same in both
the left and right side.
The only difference is in the import
So left side is important pandas and
the right side is importing firedex.
pandas.
That is the only change But if you
see in the execution time, you can
see that pandas takes around 4.
06 whereas firedex can complete
it Within 275 milliseconds.
So this simple code No modification
you can experience 15 times build up.
So that is some kind of quick demo
I'll be talking about another demo
another thing in upcoming slides
for sure Okay, so with that let me
explain you the usage of firedug.
So first of all Firedux is currently
available for Linux only, so if
you're from the Windows or Mac
users, so at this moment, probably
you can consider using Google Colab
or the platform that support Linux.
For Windows, definitely you can try
WSL because it can work with WSL.
And the supported Pythons are from 3.
9 to 3.
12. So if you can satisfy these two
conditions, you can install it using pip
and you can use instead of import pandas,
import firedux pandas and that will
be sufficient to execute your existing
program using firedux and optimize it.
Now, how about zero code modification?
if you are using program that is you
importing pandas and it is importing
other modules All those module might
in turn importing pandas as well.
So do you need to replace
all this import by yourself?
No There is monkey passing thing.
So when executing the program using
the python command, just pass hyphen
option followed by firetus pandas.
It can automatically replace all
the pandas with firetus pandas.
And it can do the optimization for
you without any code modification.
For notebook like platform,
the same thing, your rest
of the notebook can be same.
Just on top of import pandas, you
can add this extension module.
And it can automatically replace the
pandas with fireducks pandas and you
can experience the benefit out of it
So now let's understand, what is the
challenge with seamless integration
with pandas like, Of course wire ducks
is something that i'm talking about But
there are other high performance pandas
alternatives as well, right like duckdb,
polars, dusk These are the library that
try to achieve the same kind of problem
like because pandas is slow So they
have their own version of optimization
that can address the slow performance
of pandas But the major challenge comes
with the compatibility with pandas
like, if you want to use those library
you have to learn that library first if
because Either they are not compatible
or they are not fully compatible.
So you need to understand the
library first and sometime it
may happen that pandas because
pandas is full of features, right?
But those library might
not offer that feature.
So you need to convert, the
library to pandas using from
pandas into pandas mechanism.
And, when, comparing the result in the
performance, once your complete program
can be migrated, you can compare the
performances, or taste the results.
So that are the challenges
associated with it.
So whether you want to take that
effort, For that cost optimization.
So there is always a cost performance
thing in your mind so yeah, you have
options like modern does vex, but
they are ideally for the multi Node
environment there is something called
polars that is for the single node
environment that is super fast But it
is not much compatible with pandas.
So if you want to use folders probably
you need to understand the library
in the very first place that is where
fireducks can help you like being it
highly compatible with pandas No code
modification, no node learning associated
with it And you can experience the
single node speed up If you're working
on the data and that can be fit into
memory, you can work with firetrucks.
Of course, it provides optimization.
it may happen that although you
have a bigger data, but you're not
interested in every part of the data.
it can do the optimization for you
and it can just selectively load the
target columns and rows so that it
can do a lot of justice with your,
like limited set of resources, the
memory and the number of cores.
let's see like how seamless
integration is possible with pandas.
For example, this is a demo notebook.
You can consider the actual
notebook from this link.
But let's understand
what it's trying to do.
It is trying to load parquet data
from InnoIC parking violation.
After the data loading is done, it is
trying to, perform a query where it is
trying to see, which parking violation
is the most commonly committed by
vehicles from various United States.
because of, in order to execute
the query, it does some group by
head and shorting kind of stuff.
So the basic code is
entirely written in pandas.
So there is nothing that you can identify
new So everything is written in pandas.
Now simply I executed the same
program using python followed by
the program name So you can see
that the data loading take around 2.
4 and the query one takes around 2.
8 seconds Overall, it takes around 5.
3 seconds But in order to execute the same
program with fire dogs, no code change
just add hyphenium fire dust and pandas
And it can be done much faster like almost
eight times can eight times faster but
the data loading as well as the query
processing can be done much faster when
we're switching to Pandas to firetrucks
just by adding a program option.
Nothing else.
So that is how it is very like Easy
to integrate once you download it.
It can be integrated to any pandas
application and you can experience
this better So definitely you can try
the notebook for Further exploration
So now let's consider the optimizing
features that is available in FireDogs.
So this is the design of FireDogs like
It looks like a pandas program because we
mock all the api that is written All the
user interface in a pandas like interface
But down the line everything is written
in c once the instruction is optimized
by the compiler So what happens is pandas
is like you write the program and it
execute it right after you click But in
case of Firedux, as I explained that it
will create some kind of instructions and
those instructions will be optimized by
the compiler and the optimized instruction
will be converted by a system call and
then it will be executed by the multiple
code that is available in your system.
So all the available code in your
system will be effectively used.
the system cache will be
effectively used, the vectorization
will be effectively used.
So because of this you can experience
much faster speedup when using firetux.
So now what is the offering
from these two layers?
So first of all there is a compiler,
so definitely you can expect compiler
specific optimization like common
sub expression elimination, date
code elimination kind of stuff.
So you can expect domain
specific optimization like get
pushed down a projection post
on that I talked about so far.
You can expect some pandas
specific tuning here as well.
So I'll be talking about
it in upcoming slides.
Now, what about the second
most layer that is the backend?
The backend is multithreaded first of all.
So If you have a very good, system with
multiple threads available, you can
experience much, throughput out of that.
The, it can take good, use of
the memory because it is backed
by Apache Parallel Memory.
The major data structure is backed by
Apache Arrow, so you can have Compact
usage of the memory as well and all
the kernels like join, group by filter,
drop in, everything is written from
scratch by our own patented algorithms.
So this kernel operation itself is much
faster when comparing to pandas or other
high performance pandas alternatives.
We'll be experiencing it
in upcoming slide for sure.
So yes, so let's understand what
is compiler specific optimization.
I took this example from one of the Kaggle
notebook that I recently noticed like you
can see that here df time is a column of
string type So since it is string type
and the pop the person wants to perform
some group by based on the year and
month he wants to find the average sales.
So what he does it he performed the string
column to date time In order to extract
the year field and the month field And do
the stuff but as you can understand the
two data itself is a complex operation
because you try to parse a string to
Convert it to datetime So if you do
the same operation the same data more
than once it is going to cost you when
your data is putting in size So ideally
what is better is You can just compute
it once put it in some placeholder and
use it wherever you need it So this is
something a basic programming know how
But because find x uses a compiler and the
compiler can identify this kind of common
expression So well, I already have do it.
So so because compiler will create
an instruction for that Again, it
will create an instruction for this
And then it will say, I already
have created the instruction.
So let me use that.
And wherever I, wherever it is
referred, instead of creating
a new instruction, this kind of
optimization possible by FireDogs.
So this kind of, CAC, Common
Sub Explanatory Elimination
Optimization Benefit, you can
definitely get from FireDogs.
Another thing is something
called Dead Code Elimination.
So for example, this
is a piece of function.
So where it is trying to merge x. Table
with the y table And after merging it
is trying to do the shorting operation
after shorting It is doing the group
by but the group by using the merged
variable not the shorted variable, right?
So in the entire function This is the line
that is used but have never referenced So
when you use pandas like eager execution
model, it will be executed because the
shorting is you ask it to short, right?
But fired us can identify.
Okay, you asked me to do That is fine.
I create an instruction,
but you never used it.
So I will not execute the instruction
I will eliminate that date code
out of my execution, graph, right?
So this kind of date code elimination
is possible when you switch to firetux,
from pandas if you want to explore more,
so you can definitely take, read the
article that explored about this kind of
compiler specific optimization details.
yes, now let's talk about some,
domain specific optimization that
we discussed so far like projection
pushdown and predicate pushdown.
for that, I have taken one sample query
from TPCS benchmark, the query, Q3 10
unshipped orders with the highest value.
Ideally it was written in SQL.
I first let's convert it to pandas and see
what it does So if you carefully notice
the query It doesn't perform any kind of
best practices that we understand like
kind of reduction the data in the row
direction the column direction It doesn't
do anything as such it load the entire
data from three tables customer orders
and line item After loading the data it
can Just join them to create a bigger
table such that it can perform Rest of
the operation like filtration and group
by rest of the stuff as per the demand of
the query So when we execute this query
using python using pandas, that pandas
took around 203 seconds and the memory
consumption was around 60 gb for the scale
factor 10 but when we execute the same
program using fire dogs just by adding
this Plug in, it can be finished within 4.
24 seconds and the memory
consumption was around 3.
3 gb Yes, because fire although we
have written it without consideration
of the optimization Fighters
compiler will do it for you.
It can figure out All those stuff like the
reduction of the data in the horizontal
direction and the vertical direction
and apply it automatically, because of
which you can explain much, much speed
up, from this kind of program that
doesn't take care of the optimization.
In order to understand that, let's
manually optimize this program.
So what is the best practices?
First of all, the practice is to instead
of operating on the entire data, reduce
the data in the columnar direction, right?
In the vertical direction.
So by carefully observing the query,
you can see that we only need these
two columns from the customer table.
Although there are eight
columns, we only need these
four columns from the line item.
Although there are 16 columns,
we only need these four
columns from the order table.
Although there are nine columns.
So instead of loading the entire data, I
will only load these selective columns.
Then I only need some particular
rows from these tables because
of the filter operation.
So I will filter all the target
table based on the given condition.
Then I will just join the tables
to the group by an aggregate
and the shorting operation.
Now when I execute the same optimized
query in pandas, it becomes 13 seconds.
So 203 seconds can be optimized
to 13 seconds with this manual
optimization and the memory can
also be reduced from 60 GB to 5.
5 GB.
Even when you use pandas effectively But
when you see the fire ducks, even though
you try q3 and opt q3 Manual optimization
is present or it is absent doesn't matter
It can execute with the same speed and
with the same memory command Because if
you do a panel optimization fair enough
when you cannot do it firedust can do
it for you So you can rely such optimize
rely for such optimization on fire ducks
definitely Now let's understand one of
the parameter tuning that is possible
in FireDogs, not FireDogs actually.
First of all, what is the parameter
tuning that you can do in Pandas, then
how FireDogs can take care of that.
So in order to understand that, let's
consider that this query where it is
trying to perform, Group by on the
department column of the employee table
followed by that it is calculating the
average salary and shorting the Salary
based on the descending order, right?
So what will happen it will create the
group So it group admin group finance
group corporate and sales group and it
will perform the average of each group So
that is ideally the group by operations
But there is a hidden cost associated
with it You And the cost is the group
by is by default has a parameter called
short and the value is true But the
meaning of the short parameter is It is
trying to short the result of the group
by based on the key column here The key
is the department so it will not only
compute the group by aggregation, but
also short the result by the key column
So admin will come first followed by
corporate finance id and sales shorted
by the department but In your query,
you don't need this shorting to happen.
Instead, you want the result to
be shorted by the salary with the
value column in descending order.
So again, because you ask the
pandas to do so it will do it.
It will short the result by the
descending order when it will
encounter the short values.
what you can expect that this is the
step that is taking place because of
this default parameter of group by but
this is the redundant step it can be
avoided, Even if we don't perform this
step, it doesn't impact my result.
So this is a redundant step.
How we can avoid it?
We can simply impute the short equals
to false parameter for this case.
And if we apply this, Pandas
will skip that step and we'll
get much better performance.
Now, this data have very less cardinality,
only 5 groups, but when you have a
very high cardinality in your data,
many groups are present, you can
expect that this will give you much
more performance in terms of speedup.
Like when I try with 100 million samples
with high cardinality, I expect that,
without short equals to false, it
was taking 50 seconds and with short
equals to false, it took 30 seconds.
the short itself has, A lot of like
almost like more than 50 percent
contribution for this query So
this is something called parameter
tuning and because of the compiler
in firedux it can detect that After
groupby you want to short the result.
So the default shorting in the groupby is
not needed And firedux can automatically
impute such parameter by making it false
such that you can avoid this kind of
performance cost which is hidden in pandas
So that is again one of the offering when
you will be using fire tax Now with that,
let me talk about some benchmarks So
this is a very popular benchmark called
deb benchmark where they have written
several around 10 queries of different
complex City of the data with different
cardinality and size for the join and
group operations So when you see the
comparison table, of course pandas is
slow So that is why it is on from the very
bottom But other hyperlink alternative of
pandas like colors dark divi and all you
can see the products is something That
can outperform all the other library as
well and it is something around the top So
now let's, if we talk about some general
overview of this popular library, so I
can have this kind of image at my mind.
So in terms of pandas compatibility and
single node performance, if we compare
this library, so we can see duckdb is a
library that duckdb and polars Are the
library that can work better on single
node performance Whereas park, dusk,
modin are the library that works better
on the multi node computation environment
because they're target for the multi
node In terms of pandas compatibility
duckdb has very less compatible because
it is for the sql api where polars is
not that compatible Although it somewhat
look alike interface with pandas But
firedogs and modding, these are the
library that are fully compatible
with, like pandas kind of thing.
And of course, Rapids has its own QDF.
That is for GPU, although that
is another, different story.
But Rapids is again compatible with
pandas, providing good performance.
But since it is for the GPU platform, so
it is something different than all these.
at this moment.
All the Polars has its
own GPU version available.
And so for the FireDUX that
we are currently working on.
Now, if we talk about the TPC H that
is one of the popular benchmark.
In this demo, I have used query three
only, but actually there is 22 22
queries for against Pandas and other
high performance alternative like
Polars and Modin, we can see that
Modin was working not that good, like
somewhat similar to Pandas, but older.
Was quite faster.
It was around 57 times
faster when comparing, when
performing the processing stuff.
But fire desks can outperform the
average around 1 25 times, so it can
work much faster without even modifying
a piece of existing partner code.
and if you compare the scalability of the
library in terms of TPCs framework also.
We can see that, the polars, duck,
db, fire, ducks are the library that
offer multithreading, where pandas
works same, even though we increase the
number of cores, there is no visible
change in terms of performance in
pandas, even if we include the I O or
exclude the I O. But, in case of duck
db and fireducks, that shows somewhat
good, scalability when we increase the
number of threads, during the execution.
Polars is again, doing scalability, but
to some, after some extent, the polars,
doesn't show that much of scalability
when, at least for the TPC benchmark.
till 8 cores, it was
fine, but after 8 cores.
The scalability was something that was
not quite good when we compared TPC H.
so here are some resources on FireDUX.
If you want to know more about it, explore
the articles written in, written for
FireDUX and other libraries, we can check
out this, Website that is there we can
follow on us on twitter where we publish
the information related to articles
the new development the new release
etc if you find any issue and want to
report back to us you can refer to the
github page you can definitely connect
us over the slack channel we'd be happy
to welcome you there and collaborate
directly with you if you have any
questions so with that let me conclude my
talk thank you once again for listening
to me And I hope you enjoyed the talk.
the key insight that I talked about in
best practices and how fire ducks can help
you to improve your journey with pandas.
So enjoy green computing
and explore fire ducks.
If you have any questions, I understand
that this is something online.
So probably I cannot make it interactive
this time, but if you have any questions,
you can connect me over the LinkedIn or
any other prefer social media network,
or you can definitely get in touch
with the Slack channel and other media.
I'd be happy to help you in optimizing
whatever problems you may have with
pandas and discuss some kind of
collaboration if you are interested in it.
Yes.
With that, I'm concluding my talk.
Thank you very much once again
for listening to me till this.
till this end, I hope you enjoy
rest of the presentation as well,
happy collaboration, happy learning.
Thank you so much.