Hello, everyone.
Thank you for joining today.
I am Vedant Agarwal, a senior
software engineer working on machine
learning at Walmart Global Tech.
Today, I am excited to talk
about mastering real time
personalization, innovations,
and neural ranking architectures.
In this session, we are going to explore
how new breakthroughs in neural ranking
are changing the game for real time
personalization, especially in e commerce.
We will cover everything from
embedding based indexing.
to attention driven models and see how
these strategies improve accuracy, reduce
latency and boost conversion rates.
Let us jump in and look at how these tools
can help us create better user experiences
and achieve stronger business results.
In this presentation, we will start by
understanding the challenges in real
time personalization, identifying the
complexities that need to be addressed.
Next, we'll focus on enhancing
accuracy, diving into strategies
that ensure recommendations
align perfectly with user intent.
We will then look at reducing latency.
where scalable solutions enable
faster and more responsive systems.
After that, we will explore how
these efforts contribute to boosting
conversions, turning personalization
into tangible business results,
and finally, we will wrap up with
conclusions summarizing the critical
takeaways and actionable insights.
Let's get started.
Let us take a look at the challenges that
many e commerce businesses face when it
comes to a real time personalization.
First, there is high latency, which
slows down the user experience.
In online shopping, Users
expect fast responses.
If the system takes too long to
give recommendations, it disrupts
their shopping experience.
This delay can frustrate customers and
cause them to leave the site, which
affects both engagement and sales.
Second, inaccurate
recommendations are a big issue.
Personalization works
best when it's accurate.
If the suggestions aren't right, users
may stop trusting the platform and feel
like it doesn't answer their needs.
needs.
Third, poor personalization
leads to lower conversion rates.
If recommendations are not
aligned with what the user likes
or wants, it means missed sales.
Personalizing experiences is
key to driving conversions
and building customer loyalty.
Without it, businesses could see fewer
repeat customers and lower satisfaction.
Lastly, Businesses need
solutions that can scale.
As they grow, the amount
of data increases.
Personalization systems need
to handle this data efficiently
without losing speed or accuracy.
This means building strong systems
that can work with large data sets
while still being quick and responsive.
Addressing these issues is crucial
for any e commerce platform that
wants to improve its personalization.
By reducing delays, Improving accuracy,
increasing conversion rates, and
scaling effectively, businesses
can create better experiences
for customers and drive growth.
We will dive into some strategies
and innovations that tackle these
challenges and help businesses
master real time personalization.
Let us look at three advanced
strategies to improve accuracy
in real time personalization.
First, multi tower architecture splits
the retrieval and ranking process into two
parts, making the system more scalable.
Tower 1 handles retrieval,
narrowing down a large pool of
options based on general relevance.
Tower 2 then refines these options by
ranking them based on user preferences
and other contextual signals.
For example, Tower 1 might pull up 100
products, and Tower 2 ranks them based
on things like the user's browsing
history, making the recommendations
more personalized and accurate.
Next, semantic search goes beyond
just keyword matching by using
embeddings and vector similarity to
better understand the user's intent.
This helps the system find deeper
connections between what the user
searches for and the items available.
For example, If someone searches for
comfortable office chairs, the system
can recommend ergonomic chairs or
those with memory form, even if the
exact words are not a perfect match.
This helps users find
exactly what they need.
Lastly, transformer based models like
BERT or T5 are great for understanding
complex queries and product descriptions.
These models analyze multi layered
questions, making sure that search
results are highly relevant.
For instance, if someone searches for
budget friendly laptops with good battery
life, These models can suggest the
most suitable options by understanding
the full context of the query.
In the next slides, we will dive deeper
into semantic search and transformer based
models and see how they can help improve
accuracy and boost user satisfaction.
Let's talk about how semantic search
boosts personalization by focusing on
context, relevance, and scalability.
First, contextual understanding helps
move beyond just keyword matching.
Semantic search uses word embeddings
to understand the deeper meanings
behind what users are searching for.
For example, if someone searches for
affordable running shoes, the system can
recognize the words like budget friendly
and economical means the same things.
So it can show up products that
match the user's intent, even if
the exact words don't line up.
Next, improved relevance.
is a big advantage to a semantic search.
By considering things like user intent
and context, the system can provide
more accurate personalized results.
For example, if a user has recently
checked out fitness trackers, a search
for running gear might show shoes
that work well with those trackers.
This way, the recommendations feel
more in tune with the user's need,
making their experience better.
Finally, scalability and
flexibility makes semantic search
a great fit for large systems.
It works well with models like
multi tower architectures with the
first tower retrieves broad matches,
and the second defines them based
on semantic meaning and context.
This setup lets the system manage
huge catalogs while still keeping
recommendations accurate and
relevant even as the dataset grows.
By combining these strengths,
Semantic Search doesn't just improve
accuracy, it adapts to user in real
time, making it a must have for
modern personalization systems.
Let's explore what makes transformer
based models so powerful, focusing
on their ability to understand
context and scale efficiently.
First, enhanced contextual understanding.
Transformers are great at picking up
the subtle relationships and data thanks
to their self attention mechanism.
Unlike older models, transformer look
up every part of a query or input in
relation to all the other parts, giving
them a deep understanding of context.
For example, in a search for affordable
noise cancelling headphones, the
transformer knows that affordable
applies to headphones and that noise
cancelling adds a specific feature.
This level of detail helps them
rank results with amazing accuracy.
Second, real time personalization.
Transformers can quickly adapt and
fine tune their recommendations
based on new information.
They bring in pre trained knowledge and
adjust to user behavior in real time.
For instance, if a user switches
from looking at fitness gear to home
gym equipment, the transformer can
update its suggestions right away.
And fitness
gear can be used to
show relevant searches.
Third, scalability.
New transformer models like
this deliberate are designed
to be more efficient, reducing
the computational load.
Techniques like model pruning
and quantization help speed up
processing, which makes it easier
to handle millions of queries
without sacrificing performance.
This means transformers
can deliver fast, scalable
personalization, even in real life.
What really sets transformers apart is
their self attention mechanism, which
lets them understand the big picture
by capturing global relationships
and data, and their ability to
handle inputs of different lengths.
These features make transformers
ideal for solving complex
personalization challenges at scale.
In this part, we will
cover four key strategies.
To improve the performance of
real time personalization systems
with some practical examples.
First, vector databases
for fast retrieval.
Vector databases like Pinecone are
great for quickly searching through data
using approximate nearest neighbors.
This means when a user searches for
something like running shoes, The system
can quickly match the result with product
data, ensuring fast and accurate results.
Model optimization techniques
help make models smaller and
faster without losing accuracy.
Methods like quantization,
pruning, and knowledge distillation
make the models more efficient.
For example, a recommendation engine
that's optimized using quantization
can make faster predictions even on
mobile devices with limited resources.
Caching strategies improve performance
for data that gets accessed a lot,
like user profiles or popular items.
By caching this data and using edge
computing, recommendations can be
delivered from servers closer to the
user, cutting down response time.
For example, during a flash sale, caching
ensures that users in different regions
get fast updates on trending deals,
giving them data and keeping them engaged.
Lastly, batch processing for
inference groups multiple queries
together to optimize resources,
especially when using GPUs or TPUs.
This is useful during busy times
when there are a lot of queries
as it reduces the processing load
and helps keep response times low.
I'll go into more detail on
vector databases and caching
strategies in the next slide.
Let's take a closer look at how vector
databases drive real time personalization
with speed and scalability.
First, efficient similarity search
helps the system quickly find items
that are similar to a user's search.
For example, if someone searches
for ergonomic chairs, the system
can quickly match them with products
that have key features like lumbar
support or adjustable height.
Next, scalability with advanced
indexing ensures that searches stay
fast, and the system can quickly find
items that have key features like
lumbar support or adjustable height.
Next, scalability with advanced indexing
ensures that searches stay fast,
and the system Even with millions of
items in the database techniques like
hierarchical navigable small world
helps the system manage large amounts
of data efficiently so it can provide
quick results even during busy times
like sales integration with the ranking
models make the systems even better.
After the system retrieves similar
items, ranking models fine tune
the recommendations based on
things like a user's preference or
purchase history, making the results
more personalized and accurate.
Finally, cost effective deployment
ensures that these databases are
optimized for performance without
wasting resources, whether they
are in the cloud or on premise.
They balance speed and cost,
making it possible to deliver real
time personalization at scale.
All these features make vector databases
crucial for providing fast, accurate,
and adaptive recommendations that help
businesses deliver impactful results.
Let's look at how caching strategies
can boost performance and scalability.
First, reduce repeated computations
by caching data that's accessed
often like embeddings, user
profiles, or query results.
For example, in a product recommendation
system, popular items are often queried.
By caching these results, the
system avoids recalculating
them each time, cutting down on
latency and improving efficiency.
Next, dynamic cache updates ensures the
cached data stays accurate and up to date.
With smart invalidation and refresh
policies, the system can quickly update
information, like trending products during
a flash sale, so that recommendations
always reflect the latest data.
The layered caching approach
takes this further by using
multiple layers of caching.
For example, in memory databases
provide super fast data retrieval.
Message queues help manage data flow
and distributed caching solutions
allow large scale data sharing.
This setup ensures that The
system performs well across
all parts of architecture.
Finally, scalable caching solutions are
key for handling high query volumes.
Tools that are optimized for scalability
can handle millions of requests,
ensuring that the system stays reliable
even during peak traffic times.
For instance, during a big sale,
scalable caching ensures personalized
recommendations are served
instantly to millions of users.
By using these caching strategies,
real time systems can cut down on
latency, scale efficiently, and
keep personalization recommendations
accurate and up to date.
In this slide, we are going to
look at four key strategies.
That boost user engagement.
Let us break each one down with examples.
First, behavioral embeddings capture
user actions like clicks, purchase
history, and browsing patterns.
These embeddings help the system
understand user preferences and
predict what they might want next.
For example, if a user Often
looks at sports gear, the
recommendations will focus on
related products like gym equipment,
protein shakes, or running shoes.
Next, neural networks enhance catalog data
by adding helpful tags, descriptions, and
keywords, making products easier to find.
For instance, a fashion retailer
Tag a plain white shirt as summer
wear, formal attire, or office
essential based on its features.
Similarly, a grocery store could label
items with tags like organic, low sodium,
or family pack, helping users find
products that match their preference.
Hybrid text based and semantic
retrieval combines traditional keyword
search with power of semantic search.
While keyword search look for exact
matches, semantic search understands
the meaning behind queries.
For example, a search for energy efficient
refrigerators might not include size or
features explicitly, but semantic search
will ensure that results show products
that are energy efficient and compact.
This hybrid approach gives precise
and relevant results based on
what the user really needs.
Finally, Dynamic feature pipelines with
streaming data use tools like Apache Kafka
or Apache Flink to process user actions
in real time, such as clicks and views.
This helps update features like
trending items or recently viewed
products instantly, ensuring that the
system stays fresh and relevant, even
as user behavior changes frequently.
These four strategies are the
backbone of effective systems.
In the next slide, we will dive
deeper into behavioral embeddings
and dynamic feature pipelines.
Let us explore how embeddings based
strategies by using the examples
of a user who's interested in
fitness to keep things consistent.
First, embedding generation.
When a user browses fitness related
products like sports gear or buys
protein shakes, neural networks can
create high dimensional vectors or
embeddings to represent their preferences.
These embeddings capture the
user's fitness focused behavior,
helping the system identify them as
someone into health and wellness.
Second, real time adaptation
ensures embedding updates as
the user's interests shift.
For example, If the user starts browsing
running shoes and then switches to yoga
mats, the system adjusts the embedding
to reflect the new interest in yoga.
As a result, recommendations will now
focus on yoga related products like
resistance band or meditation cushions.
Intent prediction builds on this
by using embeddings to predict
what the user might need next.
Based on the browsing history of
running shoes and yoga mats, the system
might predict an interest in fitness
accessories such as water bottles,
activity trackers, and suggest these
as the next things to check out.
Cross session learning ensures
that the system keeps track of the
user's preference across visits.
If the user comes back after a few
weeks and starts searching for home
workout gear, the system remembers their
fitness interest and recommends items
like dumbbells or assistance machines,
staying relevant even over time.
Finally, Seamless integration with
vector databases like Pinecone helps.
Quickly retrieve these embeddings.
For instance, when the user searches for
training gear, the system matches their
fitness related embeddings with relevant
product embeddings, suggesting items like
durable training shoes or compact gym
equipment that fits their preference.
These strategies can be used to Work
together to provide real time, adaptive,
and consistent personalization,
making the users feel understood and
engaged at every step of the way.
In this section, we will look at how
dynamic feature pipelines enable real
time personalization using a flash sale
as an example to show their impact.
First, real time data
ingestion is important.
Captures user actions like clicks,
views, and purchases as they happen.
Tools like Apache Kafka or AWS
Kinesis stream these events in real
time, ensuring that as users browse
and interact with products during
the flash sale, no data is missed.
Next, Feature Transformation
and Enrichment turns this raw
data into useful insights.
Tools like Apache Flink or Spark
Streaming processes the data by applying
transformations, like generating
embeddings or using time decay functions.
For examples, products that have received
a lot of recent clicks or views during the
sale are prioritized, so the hottest items
get more visibility in recommendations.
Then, we have contextual feature
updates, which adjusts user preferences
and product ranking in real time.
As users engage with the site,
features like session recency,
Our trending items are updated.
For example, if a product becomes super
popular during the flash sale, the
system immediately reflects that in its
recommendations, ensuring that users are
always seeing the most relevant items.
Finally, model integration for real time
predictions uses the updated data to
feed into deployed models like TensorFlow
Serving or Triton, which Generate
personalized recommendations on the fly.
This means the system can suggest
the best product for each user based
on their behavior during the sale.
Together, these components ensure that
the system stays adaptive, relevant,
and capable of handling high demand
solutions like flash sales while
delivering personalized results to users.
Let us quickly summarize the key
elements of a scalable system
for real time personalization.
First, scalable data pipeline architecture
ensures that system can handle millions
of user interactions like clicks,
views, and purchases in real time.
This is especially important during
high traffic events like flash sales,
where the system must remain fast and
responsive even during heavy load.
Next, Vector Database Integration enables
fast and accurate similarity searches.
By matching user preferences with product
features, these databases help deliver
relevant recommendations in real time.
Dynamic Feature Engineering
is another piece.
It allows the system to update
features such as session, recency,
or trending items on the fly.
This ensures the system can adapt quickly
to real time changes in user behavior.
Finally, A B testing and monitoring
frameworks allow businesses
to continuously refine their
recommendations by testing different
strategies and tracking metrics
like latency and conversion rates.
The system can be regularly
optimized to improve user engagement.
Together, these components create
a powerful scalable framework that
supports personalization at scale,
ensuring the system remains precise,
adaptive, and continuously improving.
With all of this, we have the question
of why is it that we must innovate
to make our recommendations better?
Personalization has shifted from a
nice to have to a must have driven
by evolving user expectations.
Today's users want real time,
highly relevant experiences
that adjust to their behavior.
Anything less leads to disengagement
and missed opportunities.
Scalability challenges
make this difficult.
Traditional systems struggle with the
massive amounts of data and the precision
needed for hyper personalized experiences.
As user interactions become more complex,
these limitations become obstacles for
businesses trying to stay competitive.
That's where AI infrastructure
conversion comes in.
New technologies like advanced neural
networks, vector databases, and dynamic
feature pipelines are transforming
how do we do personalization.
These innovations Allow systems to process
large amounts of data quickly, adapt to
user behavior in real time, and offer
recommendations with unmatched accuracy.
The business impact is huge.
Real time personalization
increases user engagement, drives
conversions, and builds loyalty.
Businesses that adopt these technologies
are positioning themselves to lead
in a competitive market where user
satisfaction is key to long term success.
Altogether, these factors show
that real time personalization
isn't just optional anymore.
It's essential for growth and staying
relevant in today's digital world.
Let's summarize the key takeaways for
mastering real time personalization.
Personalization is the future.
It is driven by advanced neural
ranking models and is crucial
for meeting user expectations.
In today's fast paced digital world, users
expect instant, relevant experiences.
Anything less risks
losing their attention.
Second, innovation drives results.
Technologies like Vector Database,
Dynamic Feature Pipeline, and Scalable
Microservices are changing the game.
These innovations improve accuracy, reduce
latency, and boost conversion, proving
their importance in modern systems.
Next, seamless integration is the key.
Combining AI models with solid software
engineering ensures systems are
scalable, adaptable, and sustainable.
A well integrated system can meet
current demands and evolve with
user needs and new technologies.
Finally, stay ahead.
Embracing these advanced tech
strategies give businesses a
competitive edge by providing
highly relevant user experiences.
Companies that invest in
these technologies are better
positioned to retain the users.
foster loyalty, and
achieve long term success.
Achieving these strategies highlights
the importance of innovation,
integration, and experimentation in
shaping the future of personalization.
By embracing these principles, we can
not only meet the demands of today's
users, but also stay ahead of the curve
in an ever evolving digital landscape.
That is all from the presentation today.
Thank you for all of your time.
I hope this session gave you some
valuable insights into mastering
real time personalization and how
it can transform modern systems.
If you would like to continue the
conversation or share ideas, feel
free to connect with me on LinkedIn.
I'm always up for connecting with like
minded professionals and discussing
new approaches in AI, machine
learning, and software engineering.
Let's stay connected and keep
learning from each other.
Thanks again.