Hi, everyone.
Welcome to my presentation,
Python and UX teams, smart ways to
support research and innovation.
I'm Liv McFarlane and I'm the
principal UX architect at Wheels.
So before getting started, I want to warn
you that this is not a technical talk.
I won't be showing much code
and I won't be demonstrating
how to implement anything.
Instead, I'm going to take you through my
journey of learning Python and applying
it so I could alleviate some of the issues
I and my team have faced since 2021.
You'll hear me talk a lot about having big
ideas, but then having to temper them with
reality because I don't have enough time
to build what I think should be built,
Or because I can't get support to deploy
my tools internally for others to use.
Or because I have to build something
that can be used by people whose
level of skill with Python.
Regardless, these concerns
haven't diminished the value
of Python to me or to my team.
In fact, I think they reinforce
just how critical having Python
skills on a UX team like mine is.
I would argue that Python is a critical
tool because as the product development
landscape evolves with advancements in AI
and machine learning, teams like mine have
to evaluate how they operate and evolve.
And I think that, at least for UX
professionals, that starts with
looking at our tools and processes.
Tools and processes are
linked to an extent, right?
So your processes, what you can
do with others and for others,
are impacted by your tools.
It's more nuanced though than simply
having more tools to do more things.
Sometimes more is just more.
A balance needs to be found between
the number of tools a team has
and the quality of those tools.
At the risk of sounding
cliched, tools should help us
work smarter and not harder.
We should expect to have
to learn a tool, right?
But we should not be
overburdened by a tool.
UX tools and processes generally
cover two big buckets for my
team, design and research.
And while they generally feed back
and forth between one another,
they do have separate concerns.
for example, on the design side, we need
to move quickly to create prototypes that
have to display large amounts of data.
Or we have to consult internally
to other groups about designs of
products, leveraging dashboards.
And then for research, we need to answer
a variety of questions that range from
the more tactical, such as are the
steps for completing a task, easy to
figure out to the more strategic like.
How have attitudes been changing
about our products and services?
And it doesn't end with doing
design and conducting research.
We have to ensure that information
we generate remains available
to our partners across the org.
And we have to do it in such a way that
we, the UX team, are not a roadblock.
We have to do it in a way that
encourages collaboration with us.
But does not infringe on the
autonomy of our internal partner.
Now, as you can probably tell from the way
I'm describing things so far, there are
a lot of tasks caught in these buckets.
And Python is a language that
enables me to do a lot of heavy
lifting for my team and others.
By me, just me.
One person on the team learning Python,
our UX team has been able to alleviate
pain points during prototype creation,
which has the great downstream effect
of leading to faster prototype creation,
create more realistic prototypes, at least
in terms of processing and displaying
data, support other teams participating
in innovation and product development.
Speed up data analysis for
research and create more valuable
insights by being able to perform
a wider variety of analyses for
qualitative and quantitative data.
And all of these things combined
have enabled us over the past several
years to build new partnerships
across the company with teams
involved in the processes for product
development, innovation, and research.
in today's presentation, I will
walk you through how our team
applies Python based solutions for
design, research, and collaboration.
Some of the things I will mention
have evolved since they were
first created and used on my team.
Some solutions have changed very
little, and we have gone so far as
to create our own guidebooks for
standards of use that we treat as
living documents and revise as needed.
Other solutions are still in
development and testing phase.
now that I've introduced you to all
my topics, I'll take us into the
design portion of the presentation.
And just to let you know, this will
be a shorter part of the presentation.
There are a lot of changes happening
on the design side due to the inclusion
of generative AI in some of the more
common UX design tools, and this has
impacted how I plan to continue working
with Python for design activities.
So for design, the key takeaway is
that Python support for prototyping
tools speeds up prototyping and
design exploration within the UX
team and with our internal partners.
Now, before digging into this
topic, I want to be very clear
that when I speak about design,
I'm speaking about prototyping and
not finished designs that look like
what you would find in production.
This is because the largest gains
we found for our team has been at
this point in the design process.
what's that gain?
Time.
And how do we get it?
Fake data.
many times we are creating
prototypes that require anywhere
between 50 to 300 data points to
make realistic seeming interactions
and reasonably realistic outputs.
the data points that feed into
these prototypes range from the
very simple to the somewhat complex.
And so just to give you some examples,
on the simpler side, we need first names,
last names, phone numbers, zipper postal
codes, cities, states, and provinces.
And then on the more complicated
side, we need VIN numbers,
license plates, company IDs.
As an added complication, we have
some restrictions for data points like
VIN numbers, where we want to avoid
accidentally creating a real VIN number.
So prior to the introduction of
Python, what did the process of getting
data for our prototypes look like?
it varied.
Sometimes people would create about 10
unique data points that they roughly
modeled off of client data in our systems,
and then they would copy and paste those
data points over and over, making changes
to them as needed, until they had the
number of data points that would let
them accurately depict the interaction.
Sometimes people would have a set
of links for multiple websites they
could go to, to create the data for
them, such as VIN number generators
and plate number generators.
all in all, there's a lot of time and
effort spent on making up data that seems,
realistic enough, or a lot of time and
effort spent jumping across multiple sites
and concatenating blocks of information.
And then doing cleanup to make sure
it fits the rules for how certain
data points look in our system.
as you can imagine, this is not only
time consuming, but it's error prone.
just to give you a very quick example,
say you need to prototype out a table
with filtering, sorting, actions like
creating, updating, and deleting.
if you aren't careful when differentiating
your data points, your filters will
capture too many data points, or you
might delete too many data points.
So then you have to go back
and you have to fix everything.
You have to hunt down where
the problem went wrong and
then put in your corrections.
Now, you may also be wondering at
this point, how long would it take
to make the data up on your own?
on average, 30 minutes up to an hour, not
counting the time you would spend having
to test the data in the prototype and
make adjustments if you found anything
odd in your prototype's behaviors.
so while this might not seem like a big
sacrifice, given that this should only be
a one time thing, there's a couple things
about our team I would like to point out.
First, we're not a large team, so it
isn't unusual for people to be working
on two or more projects at a time.
I, as the principal, don't do that.
I can be on four projects at a time.
And then changes might be necessary.
there's sometimes some moving
around of interactions or data
points that has to happen.
how is this whole process solved?
a little package named Data Generator,
which I'm showing in a rather
abstract manner on this slide.
And you can see that it's a collection
of Python scripts and text files.
And as its name implies, Data Generator
generates fake data that the user can
download as either an Excel file or a PDF.
they can then use that
data in their prototypes.
And the fake data includes
all of our core data points.
names, contact information, vehicle
details, any unique IDs, membership
category and subcategory IDs.
The Excel file output is probably the
most used output type on our team.
And this is because we use both
Acture and Figma as design tools.
And that file type is the
easiest to use with both of them.
The first generation of data
generator ran through a very
minimal UI built using MLJAR Studio.
however, allowing access became an issue.
the UI portion was abandoned and
it now runs from the command line
or within a Jupyter notebook.
that solved an issue for our team.
But there are other teams involved in
innovation and we're obligated to support.
For some time now, there's been
an effort to improve the quality
of our data visualizations.
Serve up new visualizations
and build new data products.
and since the teams aligned with
these efforts often roll up into
different departments from ours, the
UX team found we had some blind spots.
so we made time to listen to these
teams, and after hearing their
concerns, we took some time to
figure out how best to support them.
And this brought us again
to our prototyping tools,
and we found two things.
first, Acture isn't always the easiest
for creating higher fidelity interactive
data visualizations, or depending on
what you're doing, even static ones.
It's and then Figma can produce high
fidelity visualizations, but sometimes
the interactivity is a little bit lacking.
And this was a concern because, while
typically prototyping shouldn't always
be too tied up in being super detailed,
when it comes to data products,
higher fidelity designs and detailed
interactions can make a difference
during user testing between accurately
understanding feedback and incorrectly
interpreting feedback and actions.
another finding was we don't have enough
people on our team to always offer
support beyond consultation sessions
around implementing design standards.
we have a style guide that anybody in
the company can access, but it's not
right to simply point a team to a set
of guidelines and then abandon them.
So it became a question of what, if any,
tools exist that could solve our issues.
one of the teams we work with
happens to use Streamlet.
if you're unfamiliar with Streamlet,
it's an open source framework for
building data apps using Python.
again, and quite unexpectedly, Python came
through as a way to devise a tool that
saved the day for our team and another.
Now, that's not to say that everything
went smoothly right out of the gate.
For starters, our design system
components at that time were only
built out in a low code development
app So we had nothing in Streamlit.
Furthermore, our partners didn't really
have the time to take our standards
and adapt them to their products.
They also would not have access to the
location where all of our components and
assets live for our development teams.
So that meant that whatever solution
we did create for them would have
to be one that lived in their little
corner of the corporate world.
Thankfully though, Streamlit is flexible
enough that through a combination of
CSS and Streamlit functions, we're
able to recreate a substantial chunk
of our style guide, complete with
code snippets and examples of how
to use them for our partner team.
And they can then host that
app on one of their servers.
let me show you a little bit of work
from the earliest implementation
of what we made for them.
on this slide is our
page laying out colors.
for light mode.
And you can see we've provided
color chips, the CSS variable name
and the actual hex color code.
And we do the same thing for the dark
mode if you were to click on that tab.
and I do want to mention at this point
that as part of this effort, our team
supplied our colleagues with a style
sheet pointing to all the web fonts they
would need and with the light mode and
dark mode colors all set up for them.
And on this slide, you see a sample
from our icon library complete with
code snippets that can be adapted
as well as the file path to use.
And so I will add that the file path
is based on how we recommend other
teams to set up their images directory.
Again, our colleagues in this instance
aren't connected to where we have our
assets for the broader development group,
so we provided them with the necessary
SVG files to start and then gave a
recommendation on how to access them.
And, in case you're curious, I know it's
a bit hard to see, but on the left of
this slide is what the code looks like
for the Streamlit Icon Library page.
And you'll notice at the top two
lines, Import StreamlitComponents.
v1 as Components, and From Utils
Import LoadCSS, Generate Icon
Table, and Generate Footer.
I'm calling all of this out because
it's a great capability when
building out this style guide app.
in Streamlit, you can write Python
functions to generate chunks of HTML that
will then be treated like components.
if you look at line 54 in the image on
the left, you can see the call to generate
icon table that will display each of
the icons in the engine icons folder.
Then in the image on the
right, you can see the actual
generate icon table function.
I do want to stress though that
recreating our entire style guide
in this way is not possible.
There are multiple components in
our design system that have to be
created from scratch for use in
Streamlit due to styling choices that
were made before we knew Streamlit
even needed to be on our radar.
Some of those components include
buttons, radio buttons, tabs, input
fields, notifications, and modals.
it's a lot.
But the bright side here is that
Streamlit has tutorials and templates
for creating custom components.
So as time permits, These components
are being built using a React template.
And to date, only buttons and
input fields have been completed.
But we expect to have more time this year
to work on some of the other components.
Now, before wrapping up this section on
design, I want to state that I expect our
use of Python within design activities
to increase, despite the growing presence
of generative AI in design tools.
And this will be due in part to that
growing presence, but also to the
types of products and services we
will need to design and then test.
So for example, I expect that
Streamlit will actually be used
to prototype out dashboards and
reports as we build new data products
because more so than our other tools.
It can do what we need very well.
So next in this presentation, I
will talk about our use of Python
in the UX research process.
And research has really been where the
use of Python has shined for our team.
So if I were to identify the major
point of this section, I would say
Python expands our research toolkit
so we can provide deeper insights
and more widely apply our findings.
Now, before I jump into telling you
how Python has improved our research
practice, let me take a moment to
quickly tell you about the types of
research our UX team deals in so you can
understand why we use Python like we do.
one way to categorize our research
activities is as generative or evaluative.
Generative research creates a deep
understanding of user needs and
motivations to uncover problems for
which we can then build solutions.
And evaluative research evaluates a
solution, like a prototype product
or service, with respect to a problem
that's been previously identified.
another way to think about UX
research is to view it as either
qualitative or quantitative.
And this is probably the way
most people are familiar with
thinking of UX research, right?
qualitative UX research focuses
on the perceptions, behaviors,
and emotions of experiences.
And quantitative UX research focuses on
measuring aspects of experiences, both
subject and subjective and objective.
And based on these descriptions, you can
probably tell that depending on what you
want to know, you can lean more heavily
on qualitative methods or quantitative
methods, or you can even combine them.
And so the big takeaway from these
two ways of classifying UX research is
that they can be deployed in a tactical
manner or a strategic manner with the
objective that these two approaches
will play off of one another during
innovation and product development.
And so now, this is where I bring
up a topic that has appeared
repeatedly in this presentation.
The extent to which you can do things.
in this case, conducting research and
blending tactical and strategic research
activities depends partly on your tools.
obviously, the better your tools,
the better insights you can turn out.
For us, having better tools
means multiple things.
First, we can move faster.
Then, we can do a wider
variety of analyses.
We can communicate our findings better,
and we can expand the data sources we use.
And a really good example of how some
of these things fit together is in
the analysis of qualitative data.
And that's actually the bulk of
our data, qualitative feedback.
And so we get this data from user
testing, interviews, and surveys.
And mostly we're interested in
identifying topics or themes and
suggestions for products and services.
so typically the process for
uncovering what we're interested
in is rather slow and evolved.
there's a lot of reading and a lot of
manually applying tags to observations
in the data, and occasionally reaching
out to teammates to discuss how you
have interpreted and tagged the data.
observations.
So again, it's a rather involved process,
and that can easily take a week or
longer depending on how much data you
have, the tools available to you for
the work, and how big the team is you're
working with on the research project.
So from my perspective, this domain had a
lot of opportunity not only for speeding
things up, but also for experimenting
with what information we could extract.
And on that last point, incorporating
Python into the analysis process
enabled us to start looking at
sentiment and emotion, as well
as introduce topic modeling and
applying new data visualizations.
you might be unsurprised to learn though,
all of it started out pretty slow.
But over time, the values really added
up as I've included new libraries
and tried out new approaches to
see what fits best for our needs.
And so this slide lays out the progression
of how we started incorporating Python
as a tool for qualitative data analysis.
So going all the way back to
2021, I kicked off the effort
with sentiment analysis and then
expanded it rather quickly to
include some basic text metrics.
And this is because it's a fairly
common question to ask how the features
of text change with sentiments.
So for example, we might want to know
whether the length of comments measured
in word counts changes with valence.
and then for the second phase, and that
was, I would say late 2021 into earlier,
mid 2022, I began experimenting with
different types of topic modeling and how
to present the information from that work.
And the third phase, which I would say
is ongoing, has expanded to include using
pre-trained models from hugging phase as
well as some of the features of Spacey.
And it's really this phase
which has enabled our team to
provide deeper insights to our
partners across the organization.
As we can now blend activities from
all phases to explore links between
topics, sentiment, and emotion, and
see how the various text features
we track relate to those things.
and spaCy in particular has improved
how we analyze text data, as it's rather
easy to create domain specific NER tags.
So now we can quickly identify where
certain features and products are called
out in the comments, and then also link
those back with topics and sentiments.
Just as an example, another area where
we had a strong gain was in using LLMs
and some very basic prompt engineering.
And here we started with
scikit llm and OpenAI.
It was really just a test to see
how well an LLM would perform
at few shot classification
and zero shot classification
activities without fine tuning.
And the results were actually pretty
solid, both after I and another person
on the team reviewed the output.
as a team, we went forward
with developing guidelines for
using LLMs as analysis tools.
And at a high level, those guidelines
mentioned things like always pair
LLMs with a UXer, so somebody
with domain knowledge and project
knowledge can evaluate the output,
catch issues early, and change
prompt writing strategy if needed.
clarity and specificity of writing
prompts for analysis, which was
developed over time from our personal
experience and from recommendations
released by reputable sources.
And then finally, code
snippets to use for prompts.
as great as this was, concerns
mounted pretty quickly with the
safety of not using local LLMs.
we eventually shifted over to using Olama.
Now, OLAMA, if you're not familiar
with it, is a way for you to
download LLMs and run them locally.
with this change to OLAMA, we shifted
from using OpenAI models to Metas LLAMA.
And there hasn't been any downgrade
in terms of, the quality of results
we receive for the aforementioned
classification strategies.
Also, the shift to OLAMA brought
with it experimentation with
LangChain, and then, scikit olama.
And one thing driving this shift is
that while the use of LLMs and prompt
engineering benefits my team, my team
does need to be able to use the tools.
Not everybody on my team wants to
learn Python or has the time to do it.
So in that regard, scikit olama is a bit
more friendly for people who aren't really
familiar or comfortable with Python.
Another thing is, it's very
hard for me to create a UI and
then have it stored somewhere
internally for my teammates to use.
There's just not a lot of
support for that from IT.
So I have to find the simplest
ways to do things with lots of
plug and play code snippets.
Now, that doesn't mean I
abandoned the explorations of
using line chain with LLMs.
It has served as a key component
for some experiments that I'll talk
about later in the collaboration
section of this presentation.
So now, I'd like to talk a little
bit about how our approach to
quantitative data analysis has changed.
And our main sources of quantitative
data include surveys, ratings
from user tests and quantification
of aspects of qualitative data.
we have some web analytics,
but the vendor we use doesn't
give us much of the raw data.
They aggregate it for us, and
they make it very difficult for us
to go back and get the raw data.
for my purposes, it's useless.
So until all that's resolved,
it's not really a great source
of quantitative data for us.
But the quickest gains we got from
using Python were with exploratory data
analysis, data visualizations, and basic
methods like linear regression logistic.
So at this point, this is early
2021, and we had one survey that
had roughly 3, 000 data points.
So it's not a lot, but you can still
do something with 3, 000 data points.
And we combined.
This survey analysis with
sentiment analysis using VADR.
And so for our first attempt, our effort
was actually pretty well received.
So you might be wondering then, what won
the day for us with just this one attempt?
previously analysis was done using
Excel, which, no shade on Excel.
You can produce legitimate
analyses with it.
But with Python, we were able to produce
better and more varied visualizations.
Finer detail showing how responses
on one variable related to another
and then explorations of links
between ratings and sentiments.
So that one survey got our team more
credibility and enabled my boss and
I to keep pushing for more data.
we found other groups conducting surveys
or collecting data on interactions with
our customers, and we just simply asked
them for their raw data so we could devise
new hypotheses and try out new analyses.
So now in 2025, as you can see from
the timeline on this slide, the use
of Python as a tool for data analysis
has grown well beyond exploratory data
analysis, visualizations, and regressions.
And that's not to say we
don't still use all of that.
We do.
But where we have large enough data sets
to support such work, we can perform
cluster analyses, association mining,
and we've even done network analysis.
And so these methods have all helped
create new ways of thinking about our
clients that go beyond things like,
industry effects, fleet size effects,
or even fleet composition effects.
And they've also helped us understand
things like how attitudes toward
one set of services may impact
attitudes towards another set.
And so these are all insights that had
I not made the effort to learn Python
and apply it, our team likely would not
have been able to provide them ever.
but now, because of it, we have teams
even outside of product development
and innovation functions who take
an interest in this work that we do.
Now, while it's great that we're able to
provide such value using data provided by
internal sources, a key part of innovation
is looking outside your world, right?
Going externally for useful data.
And Python does a great
job of enabling that.
So let me offer you a very early
example with context, and I'll
share that my employer is a fleet
management firm, and as such, we
have an interest in understanding
attitudes toward electric vehicles.
So in the spring of 2022, using TWINT,
Twitter intelligence tool, I was able to
scrape several thousand tweets about EVs
for topic modeling and text analytics.
Now, while it's still possible to get
some data from X, we've since moved
on to other more reliable sources when
we want to explore specific topics.
And the internet is a very large place
and tools like Beautiful Soup and Selenium
have really helped us gather what we need.
Now this next portion of my presentation,
collaboration, covers some of the
recent and in progress experimentations
with Python happening on my team.
And the broader point from this
section is, Python can help provide
better access to information which
facilitates collaboration between
UX and our internal partners.
Now, if you remember during the research
portion of my presentation, I mentioned
that I was still exploring how to use
Lang Chain with LLMs, and one idea we
looked at in 2023, but deprioritized
was the use of Lang chain's, SQL
chain and a GPT model with a post gray
SQL database to interact with data.
and it started with simple
things like retrieving raw data,
generating counts, getting averages.
very simple.
And there were a few
reasons behind the data.
Idea, rather.
first, we have some data from
studies before I joined the team.
but it's all over the place, and so
trying to find that data, if you weren't
involved on the study, It can be a bit of
an adventure, let's just put it that way.
plus we're always generating new data.
So this activity would require getting
all of that data organized and stored
so that it could be interacted with by
us or by others across the organization.
second, not everybody on our
team wants to dig into data.
we are a mixed team of practitioners where
some people like me are more geared toward
research and analytical processes while
others strictly prefer design activities.
So I have to ensure that everyone is
supported regardless of their comfort
level and preference for activities.
And third, sometimes others in the
organization want to see our data.
the intent behind the proof of concept
was well received, but there were
questions about interacting with it.
the big one being, How do we control the
prompts given to the tool so that the
user will get back the specific data they
want with the correct SQL queries applied?
this ultimately led into a broader
discussion about database design and
maintaining data integrity that, frankly,
our team is not equipped to handle at the
moment given our size and project loads.
for these reasons, this idea
has been de prioritized.
Doesn't mean we gave up on it, we're
just not focusing a lot of effort on it.
however We still do have an issue with
others in the organization wanting
to see our past reports, or even
look at relevant UX or HCI research
from peer reviewed publications.
And while this isn't the exact
same problem as using an agent to
interact with data in the database,
it's not entirely dissimilar, right?
It's still a user feeding prompts
to an LLM that then goes to retrieve
information stored in a database.
And in general, this is a very
well documented scenario, right?
there are online tutorials you can
read on Medium or watch on YouTube.
So for the initial phase of this
work, I chose to pair ChromaDB
with LangChain and Olama.
While there are better options
than Chroma out there, I have some
constraints, like I have to move
quickly, I can't incur additional costs,
and there's nobody in IT to help me.
So knowing all of that, Chroma
seemed to be the best option for me.
Then I had the choice of testing this
idea out with different sets of documents.
So one choice was to use
our internal reports.
And these are templated documents
with consistent layouts and headers
where the only real difference
is the actual reported content.
And with everything being so similar,
there's not a lot of challenge here.
The other choice, though, was
to use a subset of PDFs our
team uses like a mini library.
And this choice is where things
got interesting because these
PDFs aren't just journal articles.
some of them are industry reports,
others are design toolkits.
So there are pockets of
consistency, but for the most
part, there's not a lot of it.
And then the next thing to consider
is the knowledge level of who
would be using a tool like this.
So regardless, if we're storing UX
reports and UX or HCI publications,
the people on my team are the ones.
who know all the jargon and how
we internally organize documents,
while our partners in product
management, for example, might
not know all that same stuff.
So there has to be a way to store each
PDF with some information that could help
the person interacting with the tool.
And so as a team, we thought that
information could include things
like title, authors, publication
dates, summaries and topic lists.
Now, the problem is we already have over
100 PDFs from external sources alone.
So assigning someone to go through
each article and generate this
information is not a good idea.
and considering that we will add
more documents in the future,
it's just even more unrealistic
to ask someone to do that.
But as our team has already discovered
though, LLMs with appropriate
prompt engineering can substantially
reduce this kind of workload.
the tool in this particular phase allowed
someone to submit a document, extract
and generate key pieces of information
from that document, and then store the
information along with the document.
And this current slide shows
the prompt used for testing the
extraction and generation activities.
you can see we assign a system role
as a helpful research assistant
and a user role as the entity that
would actually use that output from
the helpful research assistant.
And we use a formatted string
to present the request for a
summary, up to five topics, the
title, authors, and publication
date for a particular document.
And this slide shows the code for
accessing and printing the LLMs
output and the output itself.
as you can see, it's
fairly coherent, right?
but depending on the contents of the
document, the output quality dropped.
But from what I noticed, that seemed to
almost always be for documents that relied
heavily on visuals and less on text.
And so that would be more for things like
design toolkit documents, as opposed to
research articles or industry reports.
Those last two would always turn
out fairly coherent outputs.
So the next phase in this work that we're
hoping to make progress on this year.
looks at using LLAMA Index.
So if you're not familiar with
LLAMA Index, it's a framework for
connecting LLMs and data sources.
So basically, if you need a RAG
model for your application, you
may wind up using LLAMA Index.
And that's the next stage, really,
transforming this into a RAG application.
And for me, here, the question is,
What type of RAG model to apply here?
Graph RAG is probably not appropriate
here, but maybe RAG with re ranking is.
So there's going to be some time on my
part to do a little bit deeper dives into
the different RAG models and to talk to
some people in my company and get some
feedback and then just see what works.
Try it out, see what happens.
Now, we're almost at the end of the
presentation, but before we wrap
everything up, I would like to share
with you four things I think you
should keep in mind if you ever find
yourself in a situation like mine.
So first, find the problems to
solve that are repetitive, error
prone, or mentally draining.
You would be surprised what alleviating
tasks like that can do for yourself or for
someone else's well being on a project.
Second, if others will be using your
solution, don't assume they can do what
you can do or even that they want to.
and this is something I think it's
pretty innate to UXers, just because
of, The problems we have to solve,
but, helping others sometimes
means meeting them on their level.
like I said, while it's common for
UXers to have that viewpoint, I
think in general, it could extend
well to all creative and building.
third, know when to
step back from an idea.
So an idea might seem good or
sound interesting, but it may
not meet the greatest need, or it
may take way longer to implement
than the time you have to spare.
And if you have to step back, there's
nothing wrong with doing this.
Sometimes it's just a sign that now
is not the right time for your idea.
And then finally, don't let
a lack of support stop you
from building something out.
Sometimes you won't get the support
you need to bring the best version of
your idea to life, and that's okay.
Just adapt it within the
constraints you face if you can.
and show that off to others.
And when people see the value in
it, use them and their excitement to
help you get the support you need to
make improvements for your vision.
So with that, we've reached
the end of my presentation.
If you've stuck with me to the end, I
want you to know that I appreciate you.
So thank you for spending
your time with me today.
Bye.