Hello, everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
Hope you guys are doing good.
Today we'll be talking about
empowering non profiting with
enterprise data warehousing.
We'll be talking about what is
data warehousing, how we can
empower non profits with when
you build the data warehousing.
And we'll also focus off,
solution delivery, right?
seamless donation and
program management data.
Some of the predictive analytics with the
machine learning capabilities, how we can
automate data processing for consistent
results, and other important pieces,
secure role based access management.
Let's dive into our session.
We'll be talking about overview of
enterprise data warehousing, followed by
some of the benefits of your organization.
What is enterprise data warehousing?
A powerful centralized data ecosystem
that unifies all your organization's
information in one secure location.
Essentially, a foundation of tracking
long term trends, measuring impact,
and making data driven decisions.
That is our end goal when you build
the enterprise data warehousing.
How we can make sure our
data is so meaningful.
And it will impact the business.
Strategic tools that revolutionize how
nonprofits harness data to amplify their
social mission and create lasting change.
Let's talk about some benefits
for your organization.
Transform manual processing
to automated workflows.
Saving a valuable staff
time and the resources.
Make confident data backed decisions
by accessing comprehensive insight
across all programs and operations.
Strengthen donor relationship
through data driven personalization
and targeted engagement strategies.
Demonstrate your organization impact
with the precise measurement and
compelling impact to your reports.
Now let's talk about unlock the
potential of data for nonprofits.
So what are the stages we need if you
wanted to, unlock the potential of
data for your organization, right?
So we talk about the
three steps here, right?
One is strategic decision making, the data
automation, and empower your teams, right?
So when you say strategy, Strategic
decision making turn complex data into
compiling insights that guide resource
allocation, program development, and
impact measurements to advance your
mission with confidence and the clarity.
And the data automation eliminates
repetitive tasks and manual data entry
by building an integrated data ecosystem.
That connects all your system,
saving hundred of step hours
while improving accuracy, right?
So how best you are doing the
automation of your data, right?
Like now, you are bringing some
data into some system, and some
other person is bringing the
same data from the same system.
But a different, end goal of it, right?
instead of that, make sure you have the
streamlined process that will, avoid
all this, repetitive tasks, right?
and empower the teams.
Oh, this is one of the key area
which we need to talk about.
It's not only impact, while building
the enterprise data warehouse, but
it will impact overall organization.
The best you empower your
team, you will get to the more
benefits out of from the team.
Breakdown information barriers.
And equip your teams with real time data
access, enabling them to make informed
decision faster and focus their energy
on creating lasting social impact.
So if you focus on these three,
that definitely will help
us, to better shape our data.
In our organization now, let's
talk about some core technical
capabilities when you build the
enterprise data warehousing, right?
So let's talk about cloud based
infrastructure And the etl processing
advanced analytics engine Data governance
framework, so I am talking of these four.
the cloud based infrastructure i'm talking
now Because like now the whole world is
moving into the cloud based system, right?
And again, this is just
a suggestion, right?
Like now based on your, in your
organizations and the budgets,
we can choose whatever the
infrastructure best works for you.
just wanted to make sure that's scalable.
Secure and ensuring 24 by 7 data
availability and also you have the
disaster recovery plan in place.
So this is some of the organizations
I like know, tend to miss the
discovery, disaster recovery plan.
But this is one of the, one of the
key element we need to consider.
Like when you have the disaster recovery
plan, so you can, sleep, You can sleep
that, you, if something goes wrong, you
got all is a plan B in place, right?
And when you have the data, disaster
recovery plan, make sure it's updated.
whatever the schedule you have
from the main product system to
the, recovery, instances, right?
And then, let's talk
about the ETL processing.
we're not talking about
the, any specific tools.
There are some tools in the market,
but whatever works for you guys, you
can then definitely choose those tools.
but ETL processing will help us.
The data from the different sources
and, it will cleanse your data and
it'll make sure it's proper properly
transformed with the right rules
and, eliminating all the junk data.
and it's also helps to set the, the load
the data, With the right time, right?
What are the time frame, you and your
organizations, works for you guys, right?
So this will work in both ways.
one is to bring the data, right?
And to update the data
into the periodical, right?
So that's when the ETL processing
plays a major role, right?
And we'll also talk about SCD2,
how that will impact, right?
And then we'll talk
about that space as well.
And then advanced analytics engine,
built in statistical analysis
and machine learning capabilities
for predictive insights here.
So that's what I wanted to focus here.
so since everyone is talking about
the AI and machine learning, to
make that AI works better, right?
Our, the warehouse and the
architecture and our data should be
good enough so that way you will get
the, good value out of it, right?
if you have the bad data and if you apply
on the, the AI analytics on the top of
it, Technically we will get, we will
end up with, different results, right?
to avoid those things.
Like we need to make sure our
data is, qualified and quality and
other meet other aspects as well.
And, and another one is the
data governance framework.
This is also very important.
the part I would say when you're
building the enterprise data warehousing.
So if I put it in the simple term.
Why we need the data governance, right?
Yes, you can build the enterprise
data warehousing without a data
governance framework, but having
the data governance in place, which
means you are making sure the entire
organization is talking the same language.
Which means, for example, if
you talk about, A RIE example,
let's say country, right?
So maybe one source bringing
data, a country, say it's
like in the United States.
From other source, you may see
it's U. S. Another country,
you can see U. S. A., right?
All these three are valid, right?
And again, the departments also
use a different terminology.
But when the data governance
in place, so they'll make sure.
You wanted to use the USA or United
States of America or just US.
So they will make the decision that
they'll discuss with stakeholders and make
sure they understand why it is important.
And they will help us.
Okay.
From now on, if country
comes in, let's use as a USA.
All right.
the organization is, finalized the naming
convention, but it's just an example,
but we can talk a number of things,
which falls under the data governancy.
Yeah.
So I would say this is also one
of the important steps we need
to consider when you are building
the enterprise data warehouse.
Now
let's talk about the, the
power of data integration.
so why you wanted to
integrate your data, right?
it's really important.
We'll talk about the step by step, but
I'd like to give you, high level overview
before we dive into the more in detail.
So let's say in your organization.
You have data is coming
from the CRM system, right?
Most of the nonprofit organizations
in rely on a majority of the
transactions on the CRM platform.
And you have some other
fundraising platforms.
The data is pulling from some
other, the sources, right?
And definitely you will have the finance
system in your, in every organization.
And besides that, you will also have like
HR and other security and whatnot, right?
Different, the teams, right?
And, I would say business units
and different business units,
and they maintain the data into
the different, source systems.
Now.
If you don't integrate your data into
the single platform, so you got isolated
with your specific views, right?
Let's say if you're, If you are
only getting the CRM data into your,
any one of the database, right?
So you always end up with providing
the analytics out of that CRM data.
But some, in some scenario, right?
You want it to know the
analysis based on the CRM data
along with the financial data.
So then, you don't have, Option to create
or provide analytics to the management
system Combination of data is coming from
the CRM and the financial right and vice
versa or maybe you know if you wanted
to provide The high level summarize
over you to a senior management system
from combination of all the different
business units So if you don't have the
data integrated In a single platform,
and it's hard to, provide, provide the
analytics to the senior, that's, I would
say, one of the major benefit having that.
And then if you're looking about
the another aspect, like the
maintenance wise, or, so the single
team can maintain everything and
same template on the same platform.
And the maintenance is easy and you'll
have that in a single tune to maintain it.
And you'll have structured data, right?
Yeah, like that kind of, we have many
other, the benefits when you integrated
data from the multiple systems, right?
With that process, what we need, right?
okay, we were talking about
the data integration, but how
are you going to do it, right?
that is a key aspect here.
So what we need, right?
Like advanced data pipeline architecture.
The architecture is the
key role here, right?
The more strong your architecture
and when you build the architecture
It's worth spending More time when
you're building the architecture to
consider the 360 degree angles, right?
So that will help you to accommodate
the existing, some of the known issues.
And, the future, like now, what are the
issues we're going to end up, right?
this is the important thing, right?
that's what my another point
saying it's scalable architecture
is also one of the key here.
And secure integration protocols, right?
Like now, how secure you are
bringing the data and making
sure they're integrating, right?
So that's also one of
the key aspects here.
and, okay, you have, established
architecture, which consider
all the pros and cons and the
feature, error free system, right?
And you have also making sure like
all the, all the secure security
integration in place, right?
But how your data, Is going to be
the syncing in the process, right?
Like now, what time you
wanted to sync your data.
So are you wanted to go with the 6am or
the 7am or 8am when no business coming to
the desk, like now your data is happening.
So this is what we need to
discuss a little bit more.
when you set up the synchronization,
it's not just a synchronization, right?
Let's say business is asking for,
okay, I need the data every 6am, right?
So we can set it up 6am, but we need
to focus a couple of things here.
When exactly source
system is updating, right?
If the source system is
updating nine o'clock, right?
But if you set up your synchronization
in 6 a. m So obviously, we will
not have the updated data, right?
So we need to make sure and consider
both angles And explain to the business
saying that come up with a common decision
and providing the pros and cons, right?
So that is, one of the,
the synchronization, area
which we need to focus.
And, the data quality and
the monitoring, right?
I will talk about in detail
each and every, point here.
But yeah, so the data quality.
Scalable architecture and
compliance management, right?
So I would say, if you follow all
these steps So that will give us,
you know help us to get the a place
where we have the Data, we integrated
data in a well formed manner Okay.
So now let's talk about the building
a robust data warehouse, right?
So I would again call it about
the, four pillars here, right?
Data integration, data quality,
data modeling, and data
analysis and visualization.
So data integrations,
as we discussed, right?
Like we need to follow all that.
which we discussed, right?
And the data quality, implement,
validation rules and automated
cleansing workflow that catch errors
before they impact your decisions.
Our systematic approaches ensure your data
remains, pristine, liable, And they're
ready to drive meaningful action across
your organization and the data modeling.
This is really, the important,
one of the important part
which will play a major role.
So whoever is building the data model,
like normally people use like in the
data model also will call it is and we
have the couple of tools offered to build
the data modeling, but which are tool
which we are, which you are opting right?
Make sure our the large scale
physical data model in place.
And, so when you see the logical,
so you'll have all the table, And
how they establish the relation
between each tables and what is the
dependency and how they're related.
So the clear logical structure has to be
there and it has to run by, respective
teams, And then followed by, we need to
build the, A physical data model, which
will give you even more detail, right?
what is the table, right?
which table contains what kind
of elements, what are the primary
and foreign keys, and what is
the relationship between them?
What kind of data each table holds?
So this, two documents are really
key aspects to move forward To build
the enterprise data warehousing.
So again, like now, make sure we need,
we have captured this step and we
followed without missing it because
this is a step which we are going
to use as a future reference, right?
Like now if something
you wanted to see it.
So we, this is a place where
we are going to, in a reference
as a master copy, right?
And, and data analysis and visualization.
As everyone knows, our end goal is
to provide a best visualization,
with a, with a data analysis, right?
Um, so that way that meaningful
analysis, when, the, when the
management is saying they can take.
the informed decisions, based out of the
visualization, which we provided, right?
That's when our, we achieved
our end goal, right?
Just having the enterprise data
warehousing, and if you're not
providing any, analytics, Our
visualizations to remain as main.
that, that might be, the different
way of looking into it, right?
So how best, we can provide the
visualization side, like now operational
reports and, analytical reports.
So operational versus
analytical reports, right?
You can talk about, operational, report.
Reporting means, the reports
which business is looking for
near real time data, right?
And, when you're looking for analytics,
like now it's, it's you can set the rules,
whether it's the T minus one day data or
T minus two day data, based on, again,
your source system, how, you set up the
scheduling and how that works, right?
now, let's talk about
the data quality, right?
this is one of the key, I personally,
I like it because what I believe
here, no matter, how, The best
reporting visualizations, right?
Or no matter how big volume of data
you are, giving to your management.
If the data is not accurate, if the data
is not quality enough, so obviously,
it will lead to in other directions.
so that is the reason we wanted
to make sure what are the data we
are bringing into our warehouse.
It should be, quality enough and to
do that, you just need to ensure all
the steps we have forwarded, right?
Smart Data Validation, like we have
different ways of validating it, right?
So you need to connect to the Smart
Data Validation, Real time Quality
Monitoring, Clear Data Standards,
Advanced Data Profiling, Automated
Cleansing Workflow, and Data
Governance Framework in place, right?
So when you follow, this, the six
steps, and make sure in each stage,
you have, You have set the right
rules and you have validated and
everything and executed well, right?
So that's when you will get that quality
of the data in your warehouse along
with the, the data governance framework.
Now let's talk about the data modeling,
uncovering actionable insights.
As we talked about, right?
we divided it into two parts, right?
the large scale data model
and the physical model.
Okay.
the donor segmentation, right?
We wanted to segment
different level right here.
So create dynamic donor, persons using
advanced clustering analysis that
combine giving patterns, engagement
metrics, and demographic data to
deliver hyper personalized outcomes.
Outreach that increases
donor retention by up to 30%.
And then, the next step, program
performance analysis, and operational
efficiency tracking, and predictive
analytics integration, and
multidimensional data modeling.
to consider all these, we need to
build this, multidimensional data
modeling before we, start to build,
the enterprise data warehousing.
Now let's talk about the data
analysis and visualization.
this is the driving informed decision
making right, as we mentioned before.
So how this is gonna work, right?
Strateg decision intelligence.
And donor relations cultivation,
real time analytics integration,
operational performance optimizations,
interactive visualization tools.
Custom reporting framework, right?
so that based on the reports which
we provide based on the data in
our warehouse, that's when, try a
strategy decisions in, decisions,
simply, make the decisions here.
And this will also help to know
donor relationship cultivation.
So based on the visualizations
of the best of the data, which
we provided to the management.
So they will analyze, how the
donor, cultivation is, is working.
Yeah.
And yeah, real time analytics integration,
implement real time analytics capabilities
with automated data refresh pipelines,
enabling, immediate insights and
rapid response to changing conditions.
through live monitoring dashboards.
So this is what we were talking about, the
operational, the reporting system, right?
So we need to build and our warehouse
should be sustainable to provide
the real time data warehousing.
So again, like this
will work case by case.
Um, so your source and your, the ETL.
And, your, your job, your jobs
and, your reporting, what are the
reporting systems you're using?
we need to align in the same
place in order to provide the
real time analytics, right?
So it's not that easy, when we say
the real time data analytics, we
even want to get it, like, when you
plug in from source to, warehouse
and from the reporting, right?
So some reportings
work, the different way.
And some reports are working
in a different way, right?
Compared to the live connection
versus the extract connection.
So we need to make, smarter
decisions, based on the business
needs, like when the business is
asked for the real time analytics.
But, I haven't said, providing
real time analytics is not enough.
Is the key for any organization to take
informed decisions and on the fly, right?
Interactive visualizations, like
definitely that will gonna, the game
changer, like when you provide interactive
visualizations, like which means so when
I said interactive analysis means, right?
So when you click on, maybe, The map,
for instance, if you consider the
map, the US map having all the states.
So when you click on maybe New Jersey or
New York, like now you're going to see,
same, the state related entire information
followed by just one or two click,
based on the interaction, how we set up.
And then, having that custom reporting
framework, this will also helpful,
for any organization to set up the
template so that, we can follow the same
template for across the organization.
So these are all the steps will help us
to, provide the best analytics platform.
Now, transforming operations and
automation and collaboration, right?
Automated reporting, real time
analytics, cross department
collaborations, advanced integration hub.
And a predictive analytics engine.
So this all will help us, to
place where we, provide the, all
the automation, with the help of
all this collaborations, right?
So that's when we are going to, provide
a complete, And two and a hundred
percent automated, the analytics, based
on the cost department operations,
setting up the real time and I'll
take setting up the, automated systems
in entire, end to end flow, right?
so that will really help us, to
provide the transform operations.
Now, let's talk about
some case studies, right?
Outcomes of how that world
is successing these stories.
So implementing the enterprise
data warehousing, right?
so yeah, these are the some
statistics which I collected, right?
example of non profit
leveraging AWS, right?
Boost fundraising success.
So that way, that's when you can,
boost your fundraising, right?
And improve transparency and
accountability with automated reporting.
Align strategy goals with the
mission impact and achieve 60 percent
reduction in data processing time.
implement real time cross platform data
integration, enhanced data security,
and compliance framework, right?
So discover how enterprise data
warehousing or your evaluation non
profit operations, enabling organizations
to unlock valuable insights.
Boost efficiency and accelerated
social impact across, critical sectors.
So this is a real, this world example
demonstrate the transforming power
of, strategic data integration.
So each case study tells a
story of, innovation, right?
Yeah.
highlighting how nonprofits
have leveraged data to enhance
organizational performance, optimizing
resource allocation, and create a
measurable, lasting, community impact.
Through modern ETL process, a
cloud based architecture and
advanced analytics capabilities.
These organizations have transformed
their technical infrastructures while
maintaining focus on their core missions.
Now, let's talk about the building
a data driven future for nonprofits.
So increase fundraising success.
that's what.
our end goal at how we can increase
our fundraising success, right?
And improve transparency and
accountability and the strategic
alignment impact on scalable data
infrastructure, advanced analytics,
integration and automated data governance.
So it, Increased
fundraising success, right?
So let's talk about this,
how this is going to help.
So data driven fundraising strategies
enables nonprofits to personalize
appeal, identify potential donors, and
optimize campaign performance, right?
Based on all these steps, we can
increase our fundraising success, right?
How we can measure the
fundraising success.
And improve transparency
and accountability.
EDWs enhance transparency by
providing clear and consistency data
about donor contribution, program
outcomes, and financial performances.
And, strategic alignment and impact.
data driven insights enable nonprofits
to align their program and initiatives
with their strategic goals.
Maximize their impact and
achieving their mission.
now, let's talk about scalable data
infrastructure, as we discussed it, right?
your data infrastructure has
to be scalable enough, right?
Having 24 by 7 data up and
running and you have the latest
recovery plan in place, right?
So we need to consider the cost
of maintain and cost of engine
and the performance, right?
And advanced analytics integration, right?
A built in analytics capabilities
enable predictive modeling,
mission learning, and the real time
reporting for data driven decisions
making, automated data governance.
It's a robust data governance framework,
ensure data quality, security,
and compliance with the regulatory
requirement across all the system.
Now let's start with some of the
challenges in, when you're implementing
the enterprise data warehousing.
the complex system integration
requiring specialized expert expertise
to connect to multiple data sources.
As we discussed at
lifecycle, it's not just.
inter level people, can,
plug and play, right?
So we need to understand like, 360
degrees, of the user needs and existing
systems, the technologies we use,
all these things, time consuming
data, creating and transformation to
maintain the quality across the system.
Organizational assistancy to
new data systems, acquiring,
training, and change management.
We never know, right?
let's say today we have
four systems in place.
Tomorrow we may have one more system which
may be onboarded into our organization.
So we need to make sure we need to
consider the future systems as well.
All right.
To ongoing commitment to governance,
including security updates and compliance.
Performance and scalability
challenges a data volume grow, right?
So when you are building the data
warehousing, so your data value
may be, one terabyte, right?
You never know, that may grow, like
maybe, 5 TB or the 10 DB, right?
We just need to make sure, at least
you plan for the next, five years
with a predictive analysis, like
how our data is going to be and
where we are going to land, right?
Based on that, you can build your,
the entire, infrastructure, right?
the technical capability issues between
different platforms and interface, right?
When you're building it.
When we are dealing with
the different platforms.
So what are the technical
capabilities we may end up, right?
So we need to well document and
prepare for that, security and privacy
risks when handling sensitive data
across the jurisdiction, right?
This is a very, a key aspect, which we
need to consider and making sure in all
the security privacy risks, which we are
handled and we manage the data, right?
bear.
Based on the different environments,
and use your masking, how you are going
to handle the masking the data, right?
When you have the, the sensitive
data in your warehouse, right?
So we need to set up the rules based
on the data, making sure we follow the
security and the privacy risks, right?
Now, next, next steps to implement and
since we learned, some of the steps, how.
We can implement the
enterprise data warehousing.
So you need to have the defi, you
need to have the clear objective
and the right teams and the right
technologies and the project plan, right?
Yeah.
So we're going to talk
about those things here.
So define clear objectives
and success metrics aligned
with your nonprofit mission.
For my cross functional implementation
And this is current data landscape, right?
And what is going to be, our,
data volume like over the period,
based on the existing data, right?
We can do some, predictive analytics
based on the existing data.
So that, at least we know where we're
going to land next, five or 10 years.
yeah.
And, select and configure, an
appropriate data solution that
fits into your needs and budget.
Yeah, means the tools, right?
the teams, how they want to work.
So based on their needs right now,
that's when you need to, we need
to focus some of the areas here.
So develop comprehensive implementation
plan, including timeline,
resource and risk management.
so this is when, when you showcase
to the management, so you're going
with, the clear directions and the
timeline saying that, Hey, this is what
we are, like where we are right now.
And when you're implementing the EDW,
what we are going to achieve, right?
why we need to invest, so much
of money into the enterprise
data warehousing, right?
it's not just not benefit
like one thing, right?
you need to, Prepare that plan.
What are the teams you need?
what are the skills that you need?
What are the technologies you need?
If you don't have already in your,
in our organization side, that is a
prep work, which we need to, have it
before, we present this decision and
build secure data pipeline with proper
validation and the quality controls.
so that's when the secure pipeline
and the quality controls, right?
Like when you implement like now, when
if you wanted to build the historical
data, you need to implement SCD2, right?
when I say SCD2, it is one of the,
the concept where you maintain the
current history data, in, you call
it as a, we call it as a slowly
changing dimension type 2, right?
uh, SCV2 that is we call it.
Yeah.
So we need to make sure, we
call it the same and which will
maintain the current history.
that is one of the key aspects to
maintain your enterprise data warehousing.
Then launch staff training
program to ensure effective
system adoption and utilization.
So this again, like once we are
done, implement the solution.
So we need to have the staff
training program to ensure, system
is adopted and it is usable and
everyone is benefiting out of it.
Yeah.
So when you have all this plan
in your place and you can move
forward and again, so this is.
All the steps in which, which I
came across, in my journey, right?
You may need to tweak, based on your
organization needs and based on your,
organization budget, based on your,
organization, the data volume, and the
technologies and the resources, right?
But, primarily, if you follow, the
steps which we discussed, definitely
you gonna have the, really, a
secure, Cleanse, quality, data in
your enterprise data warehousing and
business will definitely benefit out of,
bringing the data from the enterprise
data warehousing as a, operational
and, analytics reporting system.
With that, thank you so
much for, joining my talk.
I hope, you learned something.
hope to see you, in some other time.
Thank you all.
Thank you so much.