Hi there, everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon and good
evening to everyone joining us from around
the world for con 40 to 25 python track.
We are super excited to have a talk on
building GraphQL microservices using fast
APA for the next few minutes, we'll be
discussing on these two technologies that
have gained significant traction in the
past few years, GraphQL and fast APA.
So these technologies simplify
the process of building
smarter and more efficient APS.
So we'll explain what GraphQL
is, why it's becoming so popular
and how can you start using it.
So GraphQL is an API specification
created by Facebook designed to make
APIs smarter and more efficient.
FastAPI, on the other hand,
is a high performance web
framework for building APIs.
So it's known for its speed, simplicity,
and powerful asynchronous capabilities.
So let's explore how this, powerful
pair works together to deliver
fast and flexible, APS solutions.
And, before we start a little
about us, maybe I'm Joseph.
And I have jealous with me.
we are both product engineers at U
S T where we are building Strollby,
a travel platform that helps people
explore and plan their journeys.
We have been working with GraphQL
microservices in Python for some time,
and we are also part of Tramantrum
Python community based out of Kerala.
and that's a little about us.
Let's jump right into GraphQL.
So what is GraphQL?
GraphQL is a coding language for APIs.
and the runtime that execute those
queries using your existing data.
Have you ever needed data from an API,
but ended up with too much or too little?
It's really frustrating, right?
That's exactly the problem GraphQL solves.
With GraphQL, you ask for exactly what you
need, no extra data, no missing pieces.
Think it like making a custom
query for your API, just like
how you query your database.
The server processes your request
and sends back only the data you
specified, nothing more, nothing less.
This means faster response, fewer
API calls, and better performance.
That's the power of GraphQL.
Let's dive deeper and see how it
works in real world applications.
Let's begin by understanding how
traditional REST APIs and why
they sometimes struggle to meet
the needs of modern applications.
REST APIs are built around
the idea of fixed endpoints
for specific pieces of data.
For example, if you want to fetch
users information, you could send
a request to slash users endpoint.
each resource is tied
to its own unique URL.
And when you send a request,
the server responds with all the
data related to that resource.
While this approach works well in many
cases, it often has two main problems,
underfetching and overfetching.
Underfetching happens when a
client needs multiple pieces of
data, only one, get one at a time.
For example, if you need both user
details and their associate post.
You could have made two separate
requests, one to slash request slash
users and another to slash post.
This leads to extra network
call and slower performance.
Overfetching is the opposite problem.
Let's say only you need only
your user's name, but slash users
endpoints inspect entire user
object, including their address,
email and other data you don't need.
This waste bandwidth slows down
your application and may cause
inefficiency, especially for
mobile devices on limited network.
Since different clients like mobile
application, web applications, and
dashboards often have different design
requirements, but REST APIs serve the
same fixed response to all clients.
For example, imagine a mobile
application that requires only the
user's first name for a simple display.
While the web application might
require both name and the address.
For a detailed profile, since REST
API returns a fixed data set, both
the clients should receive the same
response, even though one of them
needs only a small part of the data.
Here, it's the mobile application.
Another major challenge is
maintaining and scaling APIs.
When new features are added, all
the clients might still rely on the
previous version of the API to avoid
breaking existing applications.
Developers often create multiple versions
of the API with these challenges.
Rust API has become harder
to manage and inefficient,
especially as applications grow.
This is where GraphQL comes in.
So let's see how GraphQL.
This diagram shows how GraphQL
act as a bridge between the front
end and the back end, making data
fetching efficient and flexible.
On the left side, we have the front
end, this could be a web application,
mobile application, or any sort
of client requesting the data.
Instead of making multiple API calls like
the rest, here the client sends a single
request to the GraphQL endpoint, that is a
single GraphQL endpoint at slash GraphQL.
The front end defines exactly what the
data it requires in a structured query.
Before processing a request,
the GraphQL checks the schema.
Schema is a blueprint that defines the
available data types and relationships.
This schema act as a contract between
the front end and the back end,
ensuring the requests are valid.
On the right side, we have the backend
services, which might contain multiple
APIs, databases, and multiple services.
Unlike traditional APIs,
GraphQL does not store data.
It's act as a multiple layer that
fetches the information from multiple
sources like databases and APIs.
For example, a query requesting
user information, order history
and recent transactions can have
different sort of data requirements.
Fetch, data, it fetches the
data from the user database.
It, receives the order information.
in a different services or a different
A. P. I. And also it gets a transaction
info from a third party vendor.
All this happens in a single
request, reducing the network calls
and improving the performance.
Once GraphQL gathers the requested
data, it contains everything
into a structured JSON response
and sends back to the front end.
The client receives only the data what it
asked for, making data fetching faster.
optimized and more efficient.
This is why GraphQL is a game changer.
It's having a single entry point,
flexible coding and optimized responses.
So let's talk about the three main
operations supported in GraphQL, GraphQL
queries, mutations, and subscriptions.
So these operations define how a
client interacts with the GraphQL API.
So let's talk about, queries.
So queries are how we retrieve
data from a GraphQL API.
Think of them like making a request to
the database, but instead of getting all,
responses, all, object, we can choose
exactly what we need to in this example,
we are asking for a specific user with
ID one instead of fitting the ender data.
And like the rest, we are only
requesting the two fields,
first name and the last name.
no extra data is being sent.
Only the response of first name and,
last name will be fed back to the
front end from, the GraphQL server.
So next we have, mutations.
mutations are how we modify the
data, whether it's creating,
updating or deleting records.
here is an example.
We are creating a mutation named
create post so we can, once the
post is created, the server returns
its value as the confirmation.
If you want, we can also fetch
other additional fields like the
title of the post or content.
So the best part, unlike we might require
separate raw call for updated values
in REST, GraphQL returns the newly
created or modified values immediately
in the request, in the same response.
Thank you So the last one is
subscriptions, so it allows real time
communication between the clients and
the server instead of requesting data
manually, the client can subscribe
to events and get automatic updates
whenever new data is available.
For example, here.
The subscription on create listens
for new data being created.
Whenever a new post is created, the
server automatically sends to the
update, to the client, where, if it's
subscribed to this topic or this, end
point on create, which is a subscription.
So this is great for, real time
applications, like notifications.
or dashboards.
So unlike queries and mutations,
which follow a request response
model, subscriptions create a open
connection between client and server
making real time updates possible.
So just to recap, queries lets us to
fetch data efficiently, mutations lets
us modify data and get the immediate
response while subscriptions lets us
listen for real time updates without
constantly polling the server.
So this is what makes GraphQL so powerful.
It gives the front end the full
control over the data and making
it efficient and flexible.
Next is GraphQL Schema.
So think of GraphQL Schema
as the blueprint of your API.
It defines the types, fields,
and relationships that are
available to the client.
The schema uses schema definition
language SDL to describe the data.
Let's start with a simple
example, a user type.
In GraphQL, we use the type keyword
to define the data structure.
Here is how we define a
user type in our schema.
ID, which is a unique identifier for
the user and followed by exclamation,
which shows the field is record ID
and both name, email are both record
and having string, data state.
So now, whenever we refer to a user in our
GraphQL API, We know exactly what data it
contains based out of this schema type.
So next, if you want to create a query
to allow us to fetch a user information,
here it's get field, get user query.
It takes ideas and argument.
it returns the user object matching
that I. D. So clients can request
specific fields from the user object.
And, next we have a mutation.
So if you want to update the user's name,
so we can use update user name mutation,
which takes idea and the new name.
And it returns, the updated name.
So next, we can see the difference
between GraphQL and REST API.
So with the separate endpoint for,
getting user info in REST, rather than a
single endpoint GraphQL, and we can use
separate query for getting, each fields.
Of based out of the schema in GraphQL
and we got the entire payload in the REST
response while the requested fields are
only fetched from DB or the other source
of data in the response of GraphQL.
One of the simplest ways to understand
GraphQL versus Rust is comparing it
to ordering a burger at a restaurant.
So imagine we are walking into
a restaurant with a fixed menu.
The menu offers predefined burger
options with fixed ingredients and you
must order the ender burger even if you
want only a certain set of toppings.
So you can take the ender classic burger
with lettuce, tomatoes and cheese.
No customization allowed.
This is how the Rust works.
APS work.
And there are other set of restaurants
where we can customize our burger.
we can specify what exactly we need.
we can set the burger toppings,
and this is how the GraphQL works.
So in this analogy, the waiter
represents the GraphQL schema.
The waiter provides the list of
available toppings, just like
GraphQL defining, types with
available fields for the client.
Instead of browsing the fixed
menu, we can directly tell the
better what exactly we want.
So similarly, GraphQL schema
of data available and client
chooses which fields to request.
So with GraphQL, we get only what we
ask for, making it more efficient.
And here the chef act as the GraphQL,
resolvers at the server site, which
only prepares what the client requested.
So they will not add any extra
arguments or any extra, resolvers
will be acted, for unnecessary data.
And, we don't need multiple orders.
Everything will be handled
in a single request.
So that's how GraphQL versus Rust
is explained in LM and Tense.
Moving on to GraphQL Python Ecosystem.
There are multiple libraries available
for GraphQL support within Python.
When working with GraphQL, there are two
main approaches for building your API.
Code first and schema first.
Each approach has its own set of
libraries that help developers to
implement GraphQL APIs efficiently.
Code first approach allows
developers to define their
GraphQL schema using Python code.
Instead of writing the STL, code first
approach allows developers to define
their GraphQL schema using Python code.
you can define types and
resolvers directly in Python
using class and functions.
So this approach is great for
developers who prefer working
within the Python ecosystem without
writing any extra schema files.
So graphene and strawberry are examples
of code first and, in the schema fetch
approach, GraphQL schema is written
separately using STL and the schema act as
a blueprint and resolvers are implemented
in Python to handle this logic.
This approach is beneficial for teams
that want clear separation between the
schema and the business backend logic.
So now, moving on to Jayalashmi, for
adding the essence of FastAPI to GraphQL.
So moving to the next
topic, that is FastAPI.
Let me ask you something, what if
we could build APIs that are not
just super fast, but also super easy
to develop, maintain, and scale?
that's where FastAPI comes into play.
FastAPI is the high performance
Python framework that's built for
real world demanding applications.
So at its core, it runs on Starlet,
a lightweight but powerful ASCII
framework that it gives all
the speed and reliability that
you want to start developing.
But here's the fun part.
FastAPI takes Python type hints and turns
them into something way more powerful.
It's not just about a clean
code, but a smarter code.
So with the type hints and Python link
working in the background, you get
automatic validation, error handling,
and even interactive documentation.
Basically, everything a developer dreams
of happening as you write your code.
So why I'm so excited about this?
Because FastAPI doesn't just
stop at building great APIs.
When you pair it with GraphQL, it
becomes the ultimate tool for building
modern, scalable microservices.
So let's get into it.
So moving on to the next slide, we
have The key components are the core
components of FastAPI, which makes
it a high performance framework.
So we could find that at its core,
we have the Starlet, which serves
as the foundational ASCII framework
responsible for handling, routing,
middleware, and concurrency.
So it ensures that FastAPI
operates efficiently and reliably.
Next, we have the Python link on the other
side, which is one of the most critical
components that it handles the data
validation, serialization, and parsing.
By leveraging the Python's type hint,
Python ensures that incoming data is
validated automatically, reducing the
risk of errors and enhancing code quality.
So it also integrates with the uvconn,
we know, like it's a fast ASCII server
which ensures that optimal performance
in handling concurrent requests.
Also been powered by the uv loop
and uvcon accelerates asynchronous
operations, resulting in faster
response times and improved scalability.
So finally, these components are all
powered by the compiled Python, the
SciDun, and it forms the backbone
of fastAPI's execution environment.
this comes the core components and these
all components work together to de To get
FastAPI robust, scalable, and efficient
framework for building modern APIs.
So now moving to the next topic
that is features of FastAPI.
So the first one is the speed
and developers friendly.
And as we said in the beginning,
FastAPI is one of the fastest.
Frameworks Anavicon.
And with Python type hints and Pythontic,
it significantly boosts developer
predictivity, making coding smoother.
And next one is based on
OpenAPI and JSON Schema.
FastAPI automatically generates
OpenAPI specifications and JSON
Schema documentation for APIs.
providing industry standard way to
describe and interact with your endpoints.
Next comes, the documentation,
automatic documentation, and it
generates interactive, API documentation
using Swagger, UI, and etc.
So it makes it easier for
developers to explore and test
the API directly from the browser.
So next one is the asynchronous support.
FastAPI is designed to fully
support asynchronous programming,
like allowing your application to
handle concurrent tasks efficiently
and improving scalability.
So next one is data validation.
So Pythonic ensures that all the
data, like whether it's incoming
or outgoing, it's automatically
validated, preventing many common
errors before they could even happen.
And FastAPI also excels in path
operations, like allowing you
to define your API endpoints
with clear, concise syntax.
When it comes to security
features, we have, it, it.
It provides built in supports like JWT
and other authentication protocols,
making it simple to implement secure APIs.
And dependency engine is another
key feature, allowing you to manage
and ensure dependencies with ease,
promoting clean and integrable code.
And the last one, middleware
feature, like it, help us to
add our custom functionality to
your applications, like logging,
authentication, or session management.
That's it.
without cluttering the core logic.
So all these features collectively make
this fast API comprehensive framework for
building fast, secure, and scalable APIs.
So let's move to the next slide.
So now we can visualize the flow of
how fast API integrates with GraphQL
and the surrounding components.
So at the center, we have the fast
API GraphQL server, which acts as
the backbone for your application.
So it handles all the GraphQL
queries, process them and return
the corresponding responses.
So the GraphQL list is on the
top of FastAPI, where the client
sends the queries and mutations
to interact with the API.
The FastAPI process these requests and
through the GraphQL server resolves
the queries by fetching the data
from your underlying data sources.
So the client side Whether it's a web
application or a mobile app, the client
sends GraphQL queries or mutations,
usually over HTTP or web sockets to
interact with the FastAPI server.
And as Aby has already said that in the
previous slide, this is exactly where
GraphQL shines, that providing clients
with a flexible and efficient way.
to request exactly the data they need.
So at the bottom flow, we have the
database and FastAPI interacts with
the database to create modified
data based on the GraphQL queries.
And we know, as I have already told,
FastAPI is seamless asynchronous support.
And this ensures that these
databases interact happening
quickly and efficiently, making it
scalable for modern applications.
So this flow illustrates how
FastAPI and GraphQL come together
to create Powerful, flexible, and
scalable microservice architecture.
So now let's see an example
of GraphQL with FastAPI.
So at the top, we can see the
importing dependencies, and we
are using here Graphin, which is
a library used for creating the
GraphQL schema and defining types.
And uvicorn lightning fast as a
server to run the FastAPI application.
Also the FastAPI, the
framework we are using here.
Thanks so much.
And the Starlet Graphene 3, it's a
package providing the integration
between GraphQL and FastAPI.
And PostType class using Graphene.
ObjectType.
And this represents the structure of the
data we are exposing through GraphQL.
So here we have seen, the ID
field, which is, of ID type,
which is unique to each post.
And the title and the summary
fields are also using GraphQL.
Here, and they are using string
types, both marked as required.
So here's the beauty of GraphQL.
You can precisely define what
your API will return, making it
both predictable and flexible.
So next step, we are adding a query.
We create a query class,
which is essentially the entry
point for our GraphQL API.
So we define a field called post, which
allows clients to fetch data about a
specific And the result function, that
is, resultPost handles how the data is
retrieved when a client makes a query.
In this example, we return a
hardcoded post type object, but
in real world scenarios, this is
where you would interact with your
database or surveys to fetch the data.
towards the end, we are
integrating with the FastAPI.
We build the GraphQL
schema using graphene.
schema and pass the query as it is.
The root query, and then using
the GraphQL app from start of the
graphing GraphQL endpoint that is
slash GraphQL into our FastAPI.
And this is how FastAPI and
GraphQL are seamlessly connected.
On running the application, let's
see what will be the output.
you can see we are using the post
service, you can see on the top left
side, and also the endpoint slash GraphQL.
GraphQL, and that's the query we
are using that is posed in that we
are asking for ID title and summary.
And on the other side, we couldn't find
the response, which is a structured and
predictable response we are getting.
So this is a simple, very simple
example of GraphQL with fast API.
So next we could move to the next slide.
So now let's talk about GraphQL
Federation, a powerful approach
for scaling GraphQL APIs.
Thanks.
at its core, GraphQL Federation allows
you to combine multiple GraphQL APIs,
like each representing a distinct
service, into a single unified graph.
This means that no matter how many
services you have, your clients
can interact with all of them
through a single entry point.
what's so exciting about is that instead
of managing complex client side logic for
combining data from different services,
the federated graph handles it for you.
The router efficiently directs
requests to the appropriate services,
fetches the required data, and
assembles it to give the response.
So now, taking a look at the
diagram, you will see how various
web and mobile applications
interact with a single router.
Behind the scenes, this router
communicates with individual services
like here was service A, B, C, let it be
user, post or anything like that, ensuring
that everything works as a quasi system.
So with GraphQL federation, scaling
your microservice architecture
becomes not just easier, but smarter.
So let's see an example in the next slide.
So now let's see an example
for GraphQL federation.
We could see a schema here and
three services, post service,
review service, and user service.
At a schema of type post, we have title,
which belongs to the post service, reviews
belong to another service called review
service, and author, which belongs to
another service called user service.
So this is exactly how the
GraphQL Federation works.
That is.
We don't need to duplicate data or write
extra logic to stitch them together.
Each service defines only what
it owns and the federation layer
automatically resolves everything.
let's see, the output, or just we can see
the user's query and it can fetch the data
if, even if it belongs to another service.
this is how the GraphQL federation
works and there's a lot more to learn
in this, it's just a simple explanation.
So thus, we come to the end of our slides.
to wrap up things, today we explore
GraphQL, its flexibility, efficiency,
and how it changes the way we build APIs.
We did so how FastAPI with its speed
and developer friendly features make
integrating GraphQL even more powerful.
And finally, we dive into GraphQL
Federation, where multiple microservices
comes together to form a unified API.
So with all these tools, we are
not just building APIs, we are
architecting the scalable, efficient,
and future ready microservices.
So thank you all for
your time and attention.
Keep exploring, stay curious,
and keep building amazing things.
Stay updated and let's
continue learning together.
Thank you.