Hey everyone, I'm Guy Adornock,
founding engineer at Reverse, the
company behind LakeFS, an open source
platform for managing data at scale.
I spent the past few years working
on LakeFS, helping teams version and
manage their data more efficiently.
In this talk, we'll explore how
data workflows have shifted from
running locally to the cloud.
We'll look at Python libraries
like Pandas and TensorFlow and
how they handle cloud storage.
A key part of this transition is FSSpec,
a Python library that makes working
with different storage systems seamless.
We'll see how it helps both
users accessing object stores
and storage providers looking
to improve their compatibility.
Finally, we'll dive into how FSSpec
can be implemented for an object
store using Lake Office as an example.
Let's start by looking
at the local environment.
working locally is simple and convenient.
And here's why.
of all, built in library support.
Popular Python libraries like Pandas,
TensorFlow, and PyArrow have always
worked seamlessly with local files.
Second, standard file handling.
Python's built in file interface
makes it easy to work with files
using familiar methods like read
and write and setup required.
Just point, point to a file and it works.
No extra configuration needed.
As we see in these examples, working
locally is simple and straightforward.
Whether we're using pandas to read a
csv or tensorflow to load a model, we
just point to a file path and it works.
No extra steps, no setup required.
However, while working locally
is easy, it does have its limits.
As data grows and project scales, those
limitations become more noticeable.
cloud offers some clear advantages
in overcoming these challenges.
Let's look at the key
benefits of moving to cloud.
Redundancy.
Cloud storage keeps your data backed
up and protected from local failures.
Scalability.
You can handle massive data sets
without worrying about running
out of storage or compute power.
Collaboration.
Teams can easily share and access data
without needing to pass around files.
Security.
Cloud providers offer strong security
measures, often better than what's
available on personal machines.
And accessibility.
Your data is available from
anywhere, making it easy to work
across devices and locations.
So moving to the cloud unlocks
new possibilities, but it
also brings in new challenges.
Let's take a closer look.
At what this transition looks like
transitioning to the cloud poses
challenges, especially when it
comes to using familiar libraries.
How can we bridge the gap between
favorite tools and cloud storage?
One approach is to manually sync data
between the local and the cloud storage.
For instance, use AWS CLI or
border three and download and
upload the data all the time.
So while this approach
can get the job done.
It's not the most practical, and it
becomes error prone, cumbersome, and
hard to maintain as things change.
Another approach is using
library specific connectors.
Some libraries, like Pandas
and TensorFlow, offer built in
support for certain cloud storage
providers, making integration easier.
At first, this sounds great.
It allows for seamless access
to cloud data without extra
steps, But there are tradeoffs.
Not every object store is supported,
meaning if you're using a less common
provider, you might be out of luck.
library also needs to maintain
its own implementation, which
leads to duplicate effort.
And even when support exists, way
each library handles configuration,
dependencies, and even basic
operations, things inconsistent.
while this approach can work,
it's not a one size fits all.
we need something more
flexible and standardized.
That's where FSpec in.
The creators of FSpec saw the need
for a unified way to interact with
file systems, both local and remote.
Instead of each library implementing
its own cloud integration, FSpec
provides a standard interface
that simplifies the process.
FSpec.
com It provides a unified interface,
local and remote file systems behave the
same, multiple backend support, access a
variety of storage systems via the same
interface, of integration, libraries
and tools can leverage FSPEC without
worrying about backend specific details,
and enhanced capabilities, features like
caching, transactions, and concurrency
come built in improving efficiency.
Instead of every library re implementing
these best practices with FSpec,
we only need a single, optimized
implementation that handles them all.
Once it's in place, everyone can use it.
using FSpec, we get the
flexibility of cloud storage,
without giving up the simplicity.
Of working locally for the FS spec
audience, we have the end user library
implements and the backend providers.
So FS spec allows you to interact
with cloud storage just as
you would with local files.
For example, with Fs Specs,
S3 implementation, S3 FS,
can read a file from S3.
Just like a local file, moving to any
other provider will only require changing
the F initialization and the paths.
as you can see in the example.
FSpec simplifies the process in two ways.
Explicit configuration.
You can manually provide the
necessary configuration when
initializing the file system.
This gives you control over
how the connection is made.
The other option?
No initialization needed at all.
In many cases, you don't need
to initialize the file system.
With just an open function call, FSPEC
automatically handles the connection,
pulling the required configuration
directly from your environment.
Just like AWS CLI does.
this means you don't have to worry
about the underlying setup at all.
Library developers.
Some libraries integrate FSPEC directly,
allowing seamless cloud storage
access without additional setup.
For example, Pandas uses
FSpec under the hood.
This means that any storage
backend implementing FSpec
automatically works with Pandas.
beyond just using FSpec, you
can extend it by creating a new
backend for a storage system.
take a real world example.
as I mentioned earlier, I work at
Tervoz, the company behind LakeFS.
And one of the users from the community,
recognized the value of integrating LakeFS
with FSpec and decided to contribute
LakeFS FSpec to make that happen.
while LakeFS itself isn't an object
store, it adds data versioning on top
of one and can be accessed like one.
So we'll showcase the LakeFS FSpec
implementation and demonstrate
how it enables compatibility
with Pandas, PyArrow, TensorFlow,
and many other libraries.
before we dive into LakeFS
FSpec, let's take a step back.
and talk about what is LakeFS
and why is it so useful.
LakeFS is an open source project that
sits on top of your object store and
provides Git like capabilities such as
commit, merge, revert, tag, and so on.
we take a look at your current data
ecosystem, working with LakeFS is
almost identical to working with S3.
When accessing the data, the only
difference will be That now in
addition to the path, you need to
reference the branch you are working.
Lake Office is accessible by UI,
a CLI called Lake CTL, and clients
in Python, Java, and many more.
Let's take a high level
look at how it works.
Mainly to emphasize that there
is no need in copying data.
commit is a list of pointers to
objects in your object store.
we edit one file and commit it.
you can see, the next commit will
point to all the unchanged data
from before, but instead of pointing
to 790, we now point to 214.
if we were working on a data set of maps
that is a few terabytes, And we want to
test our code, all we need to do is create
a new branch, and we get a dev environment
in no time, and no duplication of data.
Or, if we trained our model a few months
ago, and we had some change in our code,
can just go back in time, check out
from a commit back then, and check our
updated model on the exact same data.
Now, let's see what would be needed in
order to implement FSpec for LakeFS.
In order to implement FSpec,
all we need to do is implement
the class AbstractFileSystem.
The class AbstractFileSystem provides
a template of methods that a potential
implementation should supply, as
well as default implementations of
functionalities that depend on these.
Methods that could be implemented are
marked with not implement error or pass.
Pass for directory operations that
might not be required for some backends
where directories are emulated.
Note that not all of the
methods are emulated.
For example, some implementations
may be read only, in which things
like pipe, put, touch, rm, and so
on can be left as not implemented.
might also choose to return some read only
exception or raise a permission error.
your backend supports async operations,
can implement async file system, which
extends abstract file systems, and that
way you offer asynchronous capabilities.
To register a new backend with FSpec,
you can use entry point and setup tools.
example, to add a new file
system protocol, myfs, You'd
add these to your setup UI.
Alternatively, you can register it
manually or submit it submitting
a PR to the FSpec Repository to
include in the known implementations.
LakeFS has an FSpec implementation
called lakefs fspec.
That was contributed by the
community, specifically by a
cool company called Material.
ai.
won't go into the full implementation,
but aside from optimization and caching,
most of it is pretty straightforward.
LS would call LakeFS LS using the SDK.
Copy will call LakeFS copy, and so on.
One particularly interesting aspect
is how they handle transactions
using ephemeral branches.
When a transaction starts, an
ephemeral branch is created.
Once the transaction is committed,
we do a regular LakeFS commit and
merge it back using LakeFS merge.
What's really cool here is how
naturally LakeFS and FSpec fit together.
FSpec defines a file system interface,
and LakeFS, with its commit based
model, happens to provide an elegant
way to support atomic transactions.
It's one of those cases where
the pieces just align perfectly.
By using ephemeral branches, every
transaction starts in isolation,
allowing changes to be done safely.
when everything is ready, we can merge,
making the process atomic and reliable.
This means users get the benefits
of versioning and consistency
without any extra complexity.
let's see FSpec in action.
so let's see the slide.
the first thing we'll do is go to LakeFS.
We have a cloud installation.
T Reverse organization.
We will need to log in.
Here's my Google Workspace.
I already logged into Google
Workspace, so it'll just take me there.
And we will create our new repository.
So you can see here a
bunch of repositories.
Let's create our own.
And call it fspec example.
We need to put, provide
a storage namespace.
This is basically place where
the data will exist in S3.
As I said, we don't save the data is in
our underlying storage, in this case,
it's S3, and we will add a sample data.
Okay, so this is our repository,
we have our sample data
here, and there's the lakes.
k file, we could take a look
at it, and, yeah, is this.
now, let's go back to pandas, and,
use, Fspec and LakeFS implementation
in order to read the data.
the first thing we'll do is import
pandas as pd and create a datatime.
ipv8.
get.
Let's go back and take the URI
for the object and use it here.
take a look.
That's it.
We basically used Pandas, and Pandas
uses FSpec, and FSpec has a LakeFS
implementation, so once we gave
the LakeFS schema, it all works.
let's take a look on a
transaction would look like.
let's say we want to make a few changes.
We want to create a branch.
Do our changes and eventually
merge them all back in.
So first of all, we would need to use
LakeFS FSpec so it LakeFSspec and we will
input the LakeFS file system initiate it.
we don't need to give anything because
it will read the configuration from our,
in this case, the Lake CTL YAML file.
And now let's do a transaction.
fsnc.
transaction.
We provide the repository
we're working on, fspec.
example, and branch.
Let's see what this did.
It's closed.
we started a transaction, and
now let's read the data frame.
it's basically this, but instead of that,
we will use the transactionSuppositor.
Instead of branch, we will
use the transaction, sorry,
the transactionBranchId.
Mmkay.
now, let's filter out
the lakes from Canada.
Okay, what's it?
Dixie.
And once we've filtered out the lakes
from Canada, Yeah, this looks Okay.
Yeah, this looks good.
we take the Canada lakes, write
them to pocket, write them on the
repository, on the branch, call it
Canada lakes, dot pocket, and that's it.
And now we can commit.
tx.
commit, and we add Canada Lakes.
Now let's do the same thing for Germany.
we'll take Germany Lakes, will be Germany.
And here we'll call it
johnX and then johnX.
once we run this, if everything
is correct, we will read the data
from, we will create a new branch.
as a transaction, read the data from
our ephemeral branch, out the lakes from
Canada, it in to our branch, commit it.
We will do the same thing from,
for Germany, commit that as well.
And once the transaction is
over, it will merge all the data
in one atomic action into main.
see, let's move here.
Let's look if we have any
branches, if we're lucky.
Yeah.
We could see the transaction branch.
So as you can see, the transaction
branch has two commits.
if I refresh, we won't have it anymore
because it was an ephemeral branch
and it was deleted let's go back.
Yeah.
As I said, it was deleted.
Now we have only one branch and as
we could see, we have the data here.
we could also take a
look and a look at it.
Of course.
Yeah.
So I took Canada lakes here.
You get it.
okay.
we could also see when
we inserted the data.
So we could do a blame and at the commit.
So this is the ad Germany lakes.
We could see what was added here.
See the changes.
We could see the parents.
one before was at Canada lakes.
also look at all comments and
we could see The last commit was
basically a merge commit that merges
the transaction branch into main.
yeah, that's about it.
to sum it up, we've explored the evolution
from working with local files to handling
data in the cloud, and how tools like
FSpec bridge the gap, providing a unified
interface for working with local files.
Various storage systems by
implementing FSpec for LakeFS.
We've seen how it enables seamless
integration with Python libraries
like Pandas and TensorFlow.
LakeFS FSpec, contributed by
the community, not only makes
LakeFS more accessible, but also
introduces powerful transaction
support using ephemeral branches.
ensuring atomic and reliable operations.
As data continues to scale,
solutions like LakeFS and FSPEC
help teams work efficiently, the
flexibility of cloud storage with
the simplicity of local workflows.
If you're looking to bring version
control and transactional consistency
to your data workflows, LakeFS with
FSPEC is a great tool to explore.
Thank you.
Happy to take any questions.