Hello, everyone.
My name is Saurabh.
I am the co founder and CTO of Kusho AI.
And today I'm going to talk about
practical tips for building AI
applications or AI agents using LLMs.
At Kusho AI, we have been, working
on building AI applications.
And, agents for the last, 18 months.
And, during our journey, we have
identified a bunch of unique
problems that people generally face.
And, we have also faced, those
same problems specifically while
building, applications using LLMs.
And, the, agenda for today's talk
is that, we want to, educate devs
about these problems, so that.
when they are building apps on top
of LLMs, they are aware of these
problems and, also discuss what
are, the solutions that work for us
and, the dev tools or tooling that
we use to solve these problems.
and, by, by sharing this information,
we, we want to save time, when
devs are, building applications
on top of LLMs for the first time.
The first thing that you will need
to solve when you start building
apps on top of, LLMs is, how
to handle LLM inconsistencies.
you, if you have some experience
building, applications using
normal APIs, you would have seen
that they don't, fail that often.
So, by building, general applications,
you don't really worry about,
inconsistencies or failures, that much.
if an API fails, you
just let the API fail.
And, the user, when they refresh
their page, you make another API call
and it will most probably succeed.
but in case of LLMs.
this is the first thing that you'll
probably need to solve, when you're
actually building an application
because, LLMs have a much higher
error rate, than your normal APIs.
And unless you solve this particular
thing, your application will have
a terrible UX, or user experience.
Because, in your application,
you'll generally use the LLM
response, somewhere else.
And every time the LLM gives you a wrong
output, your application will also crash.
So, this is the first, problem
that, you should solve, while
building LLM, applications.
Now, before we get into, like why, how
to solve this particular problem, let's
just talk about why this even occurs, in,
in these, in these specific applications.
so like I mentioned earlier, if
you are, if you are working with,
normal APIs, you generally don't
worry, much about the error rate.
in like fairly stable, APIs, but even
the most stable LLMs give you a much
higher error rate, than your normal APIs.
And the reason for this is LLMs
are inherently non deterministic.
so what do you mean by that?
so if you, if you, if you look at an
LLM under the hood, they are essentially
statistical machines, that produce
token after token based on, the input
prompt and whatever tokens have been
generated previously, Statistical
machines are basically probabilistic.
And as soon as you bring probability
into software, you're going to
get something non deterministic.
Now, what do we mean by non deterministic?
you basically, we'll get a
different output for the same input.
Every time, You, ask LLM for a response?
you could, I, and I'm, I'm pretty
sure like you are, you would have
seen this problem while using,
all the different, chat bots that
are available, like chat, GPT or.
the deep seek or cloud, chat, you
would have noticed that, every time
you give, give, given input, for
the same input, every time you hit
retry, you'll get a different output.
that's the same thing that
will happen with, the LLM
responses in your applications.
you most of the time don't, have
a lot of control or, will you
get the exact output or not?
Now, because of this particular problem,
which is, LLMs being non deterministic,
every time you give it an input, you'll
not always get the response that you want.
Like, for example, for example,
if you ask an LLM API to generate,
JSON, which is a structured output.
You might get more fields
than, what you asked for.
Sometimes you might get less fields.
sometimes you might
have, a bracket missing.
Based on what we have seen, if, if
you have like a normal stable API.
you will see an error
rate of something like 0.
1%, but if you are working with an
LLM, even the most stable, the LLMs,
which have been, here for the longest
amount of time, they'll give you an
error rate of, something like one
to 5 percent based on what kind of
task you're asking it to perform.
And if you're working with chained
LLM responses, like, basically you.
provide, the LLM API with a prompt,
you take that response, and then
you provide it with another prompt,
using the response, that you got
earlier, this is basically a chained,
LLM responses, you will see that
your error rate gets compounded.
And, this particular thing, will
probably not have a solution, in the
LLMs because of LLMs, like I mentioned,
are inherently non deterministic,
like that is, how the architecture is.
So this is something that needs
to be solved, in your application.
you can't really wait for, like
LLMs to get better and, start
providing better responses.
Like, I mean, they will definitely,
get better and, reduce the error rate.
But, I think as an application
developer, it's your responsibility
to take care of this issue
within your application as well.
So what are your options?
The first thing that you should definitely
try out is, retries and timeouts.
Now, these are not new concepts.
if you have worked in software development
for a while now, you would know what
a retry is basically, when an API,
gives you a wrong response, you try
it again with some, cool down period,
or, maybe not depending on how the
rate limits are, retry is basically,
you make an API call, the API fails,
you wait for a while, and then you
retry it again, as simple as that.
Now, when you are developing, general
applications, I think retries and
timeouts are something that, are not
the first thing that you would implement
because, you just assume you just go
with the assumption that the API response
rate is going to be fairly reasonable.
So.
they will most of the time work and,
like not adding APIs will, not really
degrade the application performance.
unless like you are working with
very critical, applications like,
something in finance or health
where, the operation has to finish,
in which case you will, definitely
start with the retries and timeouts.
But, in our general experience, if
you're working with normal APIs, you
don't really worry about these things.
but because LLM APIs specifically
have a higher error rate, retries
and timeouts are something that,
need to be implemented from day one.
So, timeouts again, I think,
I don't need to get into this.
A timeout is basically.
You make an API call and you wait
for X seconds for the API to return.
If it doesn't return in X seconds for
whatever reason, you dominate that
particular API and you try again.
this basically is protection against, the
server, the API server being down and,
So like, if you don't do this, and if
the API takes like a minute to respond,
you, your application is also stuck
for a minute and, so are your users.
So a timeout is basically protection.
So that if an API doesn't return in like a
reasonable amount of time, you cancel that
API call and you retry that API again.
that's where timeout comes into picture.
So, cool.
So how do you implement
this into your application?
I would suggest don't, write the
board for retries and timeouts from
scratch, because there are a bunch
of, battle tested libraries available
in every language that you can use.
And, with a few lines of code, add
these, behaviors to your application.
So let's look at a few examples.
the one that we actually use in
production is, this one called
Tenacity by, it's a Python library.
And, it allows you to add retry to
your functions by simply doing this.
you add a decorator, which is provided
by the, by this particular library,
you add it to a function and this,
this function will be retried.
whenever there is an exception or
error in this particular function,
now, you'd ideally want more control
over, how many retries to do, how,
like how long to wait after, every
retry and those kinds of things.
So, those all options are
present in this library.
You can, give it stopping conditions where
you want to stop after three retries.
You want to stop, stop after like.
retrying, you can add a wait
time before every retry.
you can add a fixed wait time.
You can add a random wait time, all
these, different kinds of, behaviors
can We added using this library,
with like a few lines, of course.
So, if you are working in Python,
this is our choice, has been working,
very well for us in production.
so, this is what we, have been
using for a very long time.
So I would recommend this, if you're
working in JS, there is a similar library
called retract, very conveniently.
that you can, that is available on NPM.
So, similar type of functionalities.
It gives you, retries and timeouts.
Oh, by the way, tenacity also
has, timeout related decorators.
works the same way.
if you want to add a timeout to
particular function, you just add
that decorator, specify the timeout.
yeah, back to.
This library, if you are working with
the JS application, retry is, our choice.
the third option is, basically, a
lot of people who are, developing
LLM applications are using these
frameworks, LLM frameworks to handle, JS.
API calls, retries, and like
a bunch of different things.
So the most famous LLM framework,
framework, which a lot of
people are using is Lanchain.
And if you are working on top of Lanchain.
Lanshan provides you, basically, some,
mechanism to retry, out of the box.
So, it's called, the retry output parser.
where, you can use this
to make the LLM calls.
And whenever the LLM call fails, this
parser will basically, handle retry
on your behalf, by passing, the prompt
again and, also the previous output,
so that the, L-L-M-A-P has a better
idea that, okay, the last out failed.
And, I'm not supposed to,
give this response again.
So if you're on , then it's
already sorted out for you.
You use the retry out pass.
All right.
So this sorts out how to
implement retries and timeouts.
The next most common reason for a
failure or LLM inconsistency is when
you're working with structured outputs.
So when I say structured output,
I mean, something like you asked.
The LLM to generate a JSON or XML CSV,
even list arrays, those kinds of things.
So, whenever you're asking an LLM to
generate a structured output, there
is a slight chance that, there'll be
something wrong with that structure.
Maybe there are some fields missing, the
extra fields, in case of like JSONs, XMLs,
there are brackets missing, might happen.
So how do you handle that?
The simplest way to do that is to, is
to integrate a schema library instead
of like doing it on your own every time.
So, a schema library could
be something like Pydantic.
And, this is what we
use, in our production.
So, Pydantic is basically, the most.
commonly used data
validation library in Python.
And what it does is it allows
you to, create classes.
in which you describe the structure
of your response, and then you use
this particular class to, check
whether the LRM response fits,
this particular structure or not.
it will check for, fields, extra fields
or less fields that will check for data
types, and a bunch of other options.
So on Python, just go for Pydantic,
it is a tried and tested library.
and, it will make the data validation
part when you're working with
structured outputs, hassle free.
similarly, if you're working with NPM,
there's something called EOP, same
stuff as Pydantic, data validation.
you essentially, Define
the shape of your output.
And, you basically use that shape,
which is essentially a class, JS class,
or JS object to, check or enforce,
the structure of your L responses.
and the idea is to use, these,
these, data validation libraries,
along with, retries and timers.
So.
what you basically do is when you
make an LLM API call, and you get
a response, you pass it through
Pydantic or YUP or, whatever data
validation, library you are using.
And if you get an error, you use the
retry, to like, like basically let the
LLM generate that structured output again.
most of the time, you will see that,
a couple of retries sorts it out.
Like, it's not like every API
call will fail in the same way.
So if let's say there are a few things
missing, you can in your structured output
the first time when you do a retry, the
next time you'll get the correct output.
but just, just as a, as a, general
advice, if you see that there are
particular kind of issues happening
again and again, you should mention
that, instruction in the prompt itself.
Because what happens is that, when you
do retry, like, an API call, which.
Was supposed to take five seconds
might end up taking 15 to 20
seconds and, it will make your,
make your application feel laggy.
because, at, at the end of that
API call, you're going to provide
some output to your users and,
they're waiting for that output.
so if, you see that there are particular
kind of, problems that are happening
again and again, like for example, if,
if you are, generating JSON, using.
JSON using an LLM API.
And you'll see that, like the
LLM is always using single quotes
instead of double quotes, which
will generally cause issues.
you should specify that as an
important point in your prompt so
that, you get the correct output
in the first attempt itself.
this is just like, an additional
level of check, but the idea is
that the first response should
itself give you the correct output.
So.
anything that is, that is known
should be mentioned in the prompt
as a special instruction, so that
you don't keep retrying and you use
this and not waiting for an output.
one, one additional option worth, one
special mention here is, the structured
output capabilities provided by OpenAI.
So, if you're using, GPT models,
and OpenAI APIs, what you can do
is there is a response format field
where you can specify a PyDynamic
class and, the OpenAI APIs themselves
will, try to enforce the structure.
but this one problem here, which
is if you want to switch out.
The model and use something else
like Claude or Grok, then you have
basically, lost the structured output
capabilities because those are not
available right now in other LLM APIs.
So, my suggestion is to just handle
the, schema enforcing and checking
in your application itself so that
like it's easy for you to switch out
the models and use different models.
That's all for handling
LLM inconsistencies.
Two main things, retries and timeouts.
Use them from the start.
If you are working with structured
outputs, use a data validation
library to check the structure.
You see the options here.
Any of these are good.
The next thing that you should, start
thinking about is how to implement
streaming in your LLM application.
generally when you develop APIs, you, you
implement, you implement normal request
response, like, you get an API call.
And, the server does some work
and then you, then you return
the entire response in one go.
in, in case of, LLMs, what happens is
sometimes it might take a long time
for the LLM to generate a response.
That's where streaming comes into picture.
Streaming, your responses allow
you to start returning partial
responses, to the client.
Even when, the LLM is not done.
done with the generation.
So, let's look at why, streaming is so
important while building NLM applications.
like I mentioned, NLMs might take long
time for, for generation, to complete.
Now, when, when your user is,
using your application, Most
users are very impatient.
you, can't ask them to wait for, seconds.
Like I'm not even talking about minutes.
if you have like a 10 second
delay in showing the response,
you might see a lot of drop off.
so, and, and like most of the LLMs
that you would work with would
take like 5 to 10 seconds for even,
you know, The simplest prompts.
So how do you improve the UX?
and make sure that your
users don't drop off.
that's where streaming comes into picture.
what streaming allows you
to do is, NLMs generate.
The response is token by token, like
they'll generate it word by word.
And what streaming allows you
to do is you don't need to wait
for the LLM response or output.
What you can do is as soon as it
is done generating a few words,
you can send them to the client and
start displaying them on the UI.
Or, whatever client you're using, in this
way, the, the user, doesn't really feel
the lag, that, LLM generation results
in, what they see is that, as soon as
they type out a prompt, immediately
they start seeing some response
and they can start reading it out.
This is a very common pattern
in any chat or LLM application
that you would have used.
As soon as you type something out
or you do an action, you start
seeing partial results on your UI.
That is implemented through streaming.
the most common or the most, used way.
The other way to, to implement
streaming is WebSockets.
WebSockets allow you to send, generated
tokens or vaults in real time.
the connection is established,
between client and server.
And then, until the entire generation
is completed or, as long as, the user
is, live on the UI, you can just like
reuse that connection to keep sending a
response, as and when it gets generated.
this is also a bidirectional,
communication method.
So you can use the same method to
get some input from the client.
Also, you know, one drawback
of, WebSockets is that they need
some custom, Implementation.
you can't just take like your
simple HTTP, REST server and,
convert it into WebSockets.
You'll need to redo your implementation,
use new libraries, probably
even new, use a new language.
Like, for example, if you are working on
Python, Python is not very, efficient,
way for implementing WebSockets.
You probably want to move to a different
language, which handles, threads or
multiprocessing in a much better way than
Python, like Golang or Java or even C
so generally WebSocket implementation.
is a considerable effort.
And, if all you want to do is
stream LLM responses, it probably
is not the best way to do it.
there is another, solution for
streaming, over HTTP, which
is called server side events.
which basically uses, your.
your, server itself, like basically if you
are on Python and you're using flask or
fast API, you won't need to do a lot of
changes to start streaming, using server
sentiments, code wise or implementation
wise, this is a minimal effort.
what this essentially does
is, it will use the same.
HTTP, connection, which your STPA call
utilizes, but instead of, sending the
entire response in one shot, you can
send the response in chunks and, on
your client side, you can, receive
it in chunks and start displaying.
Now, this is a unidirectional, flow.
It works exactly as a REST API
call, but instead of, the client
waiting for the entire response.
to come, the client starts showing
chunks that have been sent from
server, using server sent events,
implementation wise, it's very simple,
like you, just need to maybe implement
a generator, if you're using Python
and, maybe add a couple of headers.
we won't get into specific details
because these are, things that you
can easily Google and, find out.
But, Our recommendation, if you
want to implement streaming in your
application and you already have a
REST, setup ready on the backend, just
go for server side events, much, faster
implementation, also much easier to
implement, WebSockets is a bit heavy
and unless you have like a specific
use case, For, WebSockets, I won't
recommend, going that, that, on that path.
Streaming is a good solution if,
the particular task that an LLM
is handling, gets over in a few
seconds, like 5 to 10 seconds.
but if your task is going to take minutes,
streaming, Probably is not a good option.
that's where background
jobs come into picture.
So, if you have a task which can
be done in like five to 10 seconds,
probably you streaming and, it's
a good way to start showing, an
output, to the user on client side.
but if you have a task, which
is going to take minutes.
It is better to handle it
asynchronously instead of synchronously
in your backend server and
background jobs help you do that.
So what are these particular use
cases where you might want to use
background jobs instead of streaming?
think of it this way.
Let's say if you, if you are
building something like an essay
generator and you allow the user
to enter essay topics in bulk.
So if someone, gives you a single
essay topic, probably, you'll finish
the generation in a few seconds
and, streaming is the way to go.
But let's say if someone, gives you a
hundred essay topics, for, for generation
and that this particular task, doesn't
matter how fast the LLM is, is going to
take minutes at, at least a few minutes.
And, if you use streaming for
this, streaming will do all the
work in your backend server.
and, until this particular
task is completed, which is
going to be a few minutes.
your backend server resources are going
to get, hop or are going to be, tied up
in this particular task, which is very
inefficient because, like your backend
servers job is basically take a request.
Process it in a few seconds
and send it back to the client.
If you start doing things which take
minutes, you will see that if you have
a lot of concurrent users, your backend
server will be busy and it will not
be able to handle tasks which take a
few seconds and your APIs will start
getting blocked and your application
performance will start to degrade.
So what's the solution here?
You, the solution is, you don't handle.
Long running tasks in
backend server synchronously.
You handle them in background
jobs asynchronously.
Basically, when a user gives you
a task, which is going to take
minutes, you log it in a database, a
background job will pick that task up.
Till then, you tell the, you basically
communicate to the user that, okay,
this is going to take a few minutes.
once.
The task is completed.
You will get a notification,
probably as an email, or on slack.
And, what do you do is you use a
background job to, pick up the task,
process it, And once it's ready,
send out a notification, easiest
way to implement this is cron jobs.
cron jobs have been here for, I
don't know, for a very long time.
very easy to implement, on any
Unix based, server, which is
probably, what will be used in most
of, production backend servers.
all you need to do is set up a cron
job, which does the processing.
and the cron job runs every few
minutes, checks the database
if there are any pending tasks.
now when your user.
comes to you with, with a task, you just
put it in a DB and, market as pending.
when the cron job wakes up in a few
minutes, it will check for any pending
tasks and start the processing.
And, on the US side, you can probably,
implement some sort of polling.
To check if the task is completed or not.
And once it is completed, you
can display that on the UI.
But, this is an optional thing.
Ideally, if you're using background jobs,
you should also, sorry, you should also,
separately communicate, that the task
is completed with the user, because,
the general, idea is that, when you,
when, when a task is going to take a few
minutes, your users will probably come
to your platform, submit that task and
they will move away from your platform.
So they're not looking at,
the UI of your application.
So you should probably communicate
that the task is completed through
an email or a Slack notification.
so that the users who have moved away
from, the, you also know that, okay, that,
that, that generation has been completed.
this works very well, minimal
setup, nothing new that
you'll probably need to learn.
Nothing new that you need to install,
for the initial stages of your LLM
application, just go for a cron job.
what happens is that as your, application
grows, you'll probably need to scale this.
Now, if you run multiple cron jobs.
you need to handle which cron job, picks
up which task you need to implement some
sort of, distributed locking and, all
those complexities come into picture.
Basically, cron jobs are good
for the initial stages, but, like
we also started with cron jobs.
we still use cron jobs for some
simple tasks, but there will be
a stage, when you'll need to move
away from cron jobs for scalability.
and for, better retrying
mechanisms, that's where task
queues come into picture.
So basically think of task queues as cron
jobs with like more intelligence, where
all the, task management that needs to be
done, is handled by the task queue itself.
when I say task management, on a very
high level, what I It means is that,
you submit a task to the task queue.
generally a task queue is backed by some
storage like Redis or some other cache.
the task is stored over there and
then the task queue handles, basically
a task queue will have a bunch of
workers running and, the, the task
queue will then handle, how to allocate
that work to which worker based on
like a bunch of different mechanisms.
Like you can have.
Yeah.
priority queues, you can have
a bunch of different retry
mechanisms, and all those things.
So, two good things
about using task queues.
task queues are much easier to scale.
in a cron job, if you go from one
to two to 10 cron jobs, you have to
handle, A bunch of, locking related
stuff yourself, in task queues,
it's already, implemented for you.
So all you can do is increase the
number of workers in a task queue.
And if you start getting more,
tasks or workload, the, you can
just like, it's as easy as just
changing the number on a dashboard,
to increase the number of workers.
again, like all the, additional
handling of race conditions, retries,
timeouts, it's already taken care of.
All you need to do is,
provide some configuration.
you also get better
monitoring with task queues.
you, every task queue comes with
some sort of, monitoring mechanism
or a dashboard where you can see
what are the tasks currently running,
how much resources there are.
Eating up, which tasks are
failing, start or restart tasks
and all those kinds of things.
So, once you start scaling your
application, go for task queues.
The task queue that we use in
our production is called RQ,
which stands for Redis Queue.
And, as the name suggests, it's backed
by Redis and it's a very simple,
library for queuing and processing
background jobs with workers.
very easy setup, hardly takes
15 minutes to set it up.
If you already have a Redis, you don't
even need to, set, set up a Redis.
for RQ and, very simple, mechanism
for queuing and processing.
All you need to do is create a queue,
provide a red connection so that,
it has a place to store the tasks.
when you get a task queue nq, you
can, and, this is basically a function
which is going to get called in
the worker to process your tasks.
So, it's this simple and you can also
provide some arguments for that function.
And
the worker.
For the worker, you just need to start
it like this, on your command line.
And, it consumes tasks from
Redis and, process them.
If you, want to increase the number
of workers, you just like, start 10
different workers, connect them to
the same Redis, and, RQ will itself
handle all the, all the complexities.
of, managing which worker gets what
task, and all those kinds of things.
So, if you're on Python,
RQ is the way to go.
Celery provides you with a similar,
functionality, but we just found
that, there were a bunch of things in
celery, which we did not really need.
and it seemed like an overkill.
so we decided to go with RQ, which
was much simpler to set up on our end.
Prompted at what inputs are not working,
what models are working, what models
are not working and, things like that.
So, if you, if you want an analogy,
you can think of evals as unit testing.
So, think of it as unit
testing for your prompts.
So this allows you to take a
prompt template and individually
just test out that template with
a bunch of different, Values.
and, you can, there are, there are a
bunch of, reasons why you should ideally,
use evals with your prompt templates.
one, it allows you to just test
out the prompts in isolation,
which makes it very fast.
the same way unit tests are fast, because
you are just checking one function
against different types of inputs.
using prompts, using, sorry, I'm sorry.
using evals, You will be able to
figure out different things like which
input works, which input doesn't work,
which model works for a particular
task, which model does not work.
you'll be able to compare, costs
of different models for different
types of inputs and so on.
an additional, benefit
of using evals is that.
You can directly, integrate them
with your CI CD pipeline so that,
you don't need to manually keep
checking before every release.
If your prompts are still working the
way they're working just like unit test.
You just, hook it up
to your CI CD pipeline.
And, before every commit or, I'm
sorry, after every commit or, after
every build, you, straight up run the
evals and, similar to, assertions in
unit as evals also have assertions
or checks where you can check the
response, and, specify whether it
is as expected or not as expected.
And pass or fail an eval.
So, that's how on a very
high level evals work.
we have tried out a bunch of
different, eval libraries.
the one we like the most is promptful.
very easy to set up.
simply works using YAML files,
basically you, you create a YAML
file where you specify your prompt
template and you press specify a bunch
of inputs, for that prompt template.
And, using, so, Promfo is an open source,
tool, so you can just like, straight up
install it from NPM, run it in your CLI.
and at the end of the event,
you get a nice, graph like this.
which will show you for different
types of inputs, whether the
output has passed the condition.
it will also allow you to compare
different, models and, there is
some way to compare cost as well.
I don't think they have displayed
it here, but yeah, cost comparison
is also something that you
will get in the same dashboard.
And, you can start off with the open
source version of promptful, but they
also have a cloud hosted version.
So if you want more reliability or
don't want to manage your own instance.
that option is also available.
before we end the stock, let's do a
quick walkthrough of all the different
foundational models, or foundational model
APIs that are available for public use.
the reason for doing this is basically,
this landscape is changing very fast.
So the last time you had gone over all the
available models, so I'm pretty sure that.
By now, the list of models and also
their comparisons have changed.
Probably the models you
thought are not that great have
become very good and so on.
So let's do a quick run through
of all the available models.
What are they good at?
What are They're not good
at what kind of use cases?
you, what case, what kind of use cases
work with a particular kind of model?
let's start with the oldest player OpenAI.
OpenAI has, three main families of
models, which is GPT 4 0 4 O Mini, and,
Owen, which are available for public use.
I think they've deprecated
their three and 3.5 models.
so these are the models that
are available right now.
If you don't know what to
use, just go with OpenAI.
These are the most versatile models.
They work very well with a wide variety
of tasks, within these models, between
Foro and, Foro Mini, the difference
is mainly, the trade off between,
cost and latency versus accuracy.
So if you have a complex task
or something that requires a bit
more of reasoning, go for Foro.
if you are worried about cost,
or if you're worried about, how
fast the response is going to
be, go for 4 O Mini, but, it will
basically, give you lesser accuracy.
O L is something that
I have not tried out.
these are supposed to be,
open air flagship models.
but from, What I've heard,
these are like fairly new.
So, before you put it in
production, maybe, test them out
thoroughly, Foro and Foro Mini
have been around for a while now.
So I think, you should not see
a lot of problems, with them.
Also, like reliability wise,
as, according to us, OpenAI APIs
have been the most reliable.
so you don't need to worry
about downtime or, having to.
handle switching models because,
this provider is not working.
The next provider is, and stopping.
I think for a while, these
guys were working mostly on
the, chat, the, the, the.
APIs were not publicly available as
far as I know, but, I think in the
last few months, I think that has
changed, the APIs are available.
You can just directly, and
they're completely self serve.
You can just directly go, on,
anthropics, to Anthropx console
and create an API key, load up some
credit and get started with it.
If you have any coding related use
case, cloud APIs are your best choice.
I think, as far as coding is concerned,
coding as a particular task, cloud,
works much better than, all the other
models, which is also why you would have
seen that, everyone is using cloud with,
their, code editors as well, like cursor.
so yeah, if code is what
you want, work with Claude.
Next up is Grok, not to be
confused with XAI's Grok.
So Grok is, essentially, a company that
is building, special purpose chips.
They call them LPUs, for
running LLMs, which, makes,
their inference time on LLMs.
Very low, probably,
even the inference cost.
so if latency is what you're trying to
optimize, tryout, grok, grok, cloud,
which is their API, which are their,
LLM APIs, they generally host, most of.
Commonly used open source models.
So you have Lama, Mixtel, Gemma available,
apart from that, a bunch of other things.
Latency wise, they are much faster
than all the other model providers.
So if you are optimizing for
latency and these models work for
your particular task, go for it.
All right.
So AWS, mainly works kind of like rock.
They host a lot of open source models
on, and along with that, I think
they also have, their own models,
which we have not tried out yet.
but the biggest USP of using AWS,
bedrock would be if you're already
in the AWS ecosystem and you are,
worried about, your sensitive data,
getting out of your infra and you
don't want to like, send it to open AI
or cloud or any other model provider.
in that case, Bedrock
should be your choice.
One good thing is Bedrock
also hosts cloud APIs.
so, the limits are lower, as far
as I know, I think you'll need
to talk to the support and, get
your service quotas increased.
But, if you are worried about, sensitive
data and you're okay with cloud,
Bedrock should work for you very well.
and along with that, they
also host Lama and Mixtel.
And a few other, APIs, multimodal APIs.
Azure is, the last time I checked
Azure is hosting GPT models.
separately, like, the hosting, which
open AI does is separate from Azure.
And, the last time we checked, Azure GPT
APIs were a bit more faster than open air.
So again, like, Oh, if you want to use
open API APIs and you, want, a slightly
better latency, try out Azure, but
they'll make you fill a bunch of forms.
I think these APIs or these models are not
publicly available on Azure for everyone.
GCP, I've not tried out.
so, again, like, I mean, I think
the setup was a bit complex.
So, we didn't get a chance to give it
a try, but from what we've heard, the
developer experience is much better now.
So someday we'll give it a try again.
But GCP has a Gemini and the.
Latest, the newest kid on the block
is DeepSync, if you are active on
Twitter, you would have already
heard, about DeepSync, APIs, from
the chatter, it seems as if they
are at par with own APIs, again,
haven't tried it out, give it a try.
one concern could be, the
hosting, which is in China,
but, definitely give it a try.
probably you might find it, to
be a good fit for your use case.
And, one more thing, deep seeks
models are also open source, so
you can host them on your own.
And that's all from me.
I hope you find the information shared
in the stock useful, and it speeds up
your development process when you're
building LLM applications and, AI agents.
if you have any, queries or
if you want to, talk more
about this, drop us an email.
You can find our email.
on Kusho AI's landing page, or
just, send me a message on LinkedIn.
I'm happy to chat about this
and, go build something awesome.
Bye.