Hello, everyone.
Welcome to today's talk on integrating
C and Python at Conf 42, Python 2025.
I'm Hariharan, currently a software
engineer at AMD Advanced Micro Devices.
I previously worked as a lead software
engineer at Athena Health, and I've
also worked at other organizations
like Bain Capital and Bose Corporation.
My large areas of interest are
DevSecOps, distributed systems,
applied AI, And the two languages that
I frequently use are C and Python.
feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn
and also feel free to follow me on GitHub.
So for today's talk, I've split
them into around 10 parts.
So first we'll talk about, what the, about
the problem statement and then slowly move
on to similarities and differences between
Python and C Then, talk about, static
binding, dynamic binding, and then, brief
overview of Boost Python and PyBind11.
And then let's look at some actual code
and how the project is set up, some
minimal examples, a short demo, and
then touch upon a few advanced topics.
And then, talk about distribution
and packaging and then, wrap
it up with some top takeaways.
So let's get started.
in terms of introduction, in this
session, I'll share how you can
leverage the strengths of both C and
Python, to build robust applications.
The idea is to gain, insights into
tools like Boost Python, PyBind11.
And other dynamic binding tools and
learn how to seamlessly integrate,
cross language projects and discover
strategies to optimize the code base.
So the goal is very simple.
By the end of this talk, you will
understand when and why to choose
Boost Python, PyBind 11 or other tools.
And you'll walk away with a clear
idea on how to set up a project and
write minimal and functional examples.
So let's get started.
So before, actually diving into the,
diving into code and other contents.
So let's talk about why Python
in the first place, right?
So we know that Python, Python
currently is being rapidly used for
prototyping, due to, ease of learning,
relatively simpler interfaces and usage.
faster development.
But when we look at C and Python,
although, there are a lot of
differences, but there are a
lot of similarities as well.
Modern C is trying to get closer
and closer to Python, I would say.
for example, if you take a, if you
take a look at these two snippet of
codes, of course they're very simple,
where they try to add two numbers.
The idea is, even in Python,
you have type hinting.
In the recent versions, where you
can explicitly mention that a and
b are integers, whereas in C you
have, it is enforced and then if you
do not mention what type it is, you
essentially get a compilation error.
Similarly, like on the left you
have a function that takes a vector
of strings and then displays hello
for every string that it takes.
On the right you have a library called
typing from which you could import a list.
And clearly, say that the
function takes a list of strings.
Over here on the right, here we
have a class called box, right?
So there are other types called type
var and generic that allow you to
create classes and functions that
work with any type, which is very
similar to the concept of C templates,
which on the right hand side.
So on the left hand side, Type var
and generic are used on the right.
You can clearly see the equivalent
in, implemented using C templates.
The box class can hold any type and its
method reflect that type, which is the
underlying concept of templates as well.
So even though modern C is.
Heading closer to, syntactically, that's
a very broad statement, but even though
modern C is try, even though Python
and C are, having a lot of similarities
in terms of performance, right?
C is much, much faster than Python.
Although the recent versions of Python 3.
3, 3. 13 have introduced new modes such
as, modes where you can disable the
global interpreter lock modes where you
can, have another just in time compiler
you can, and it's set to be like 15
percent faster for module imports
and 10 percent faster for function
calls and other CPU intensive tasks.
but even in pure, even in, codebases
that predominantly use Python, For
data intensive tasks, we end up using
other packages such as NumPy, Scikit
learn, PyTorch, and so on, because,
they have APIs and abstractions
that are much more, high performing.
and when you look deeper into those
libraries, the core implementation
is either in C or C the performance
is just one side of the coin.
In one of my previous workplaces.
We've had teams affiliated
to a particular code base.
For example, the software development
team in an embedded space might just
be writing C code, whereas the testing
team might be writing Python code.
So sometimes when there has to be
collaboration between the development
team and testing teams, there needs
to be an overlap between C and
Python, rather the code that we write.
so there needs to be code that
talks with both, the C code
base and the Python code base.
there are other needs where, we have to
make C and Python talk to each other.
Rather than, the, so what, the point
I'm trying to drive home is, sometimes
we might have, a Python code base,
And we might want to optimize part of
that code base, for specific reasons.
So we might pick that batch of code
from the Python code base integrated in
C for it to be more highly performant.
On the other hand, two teams, two
different teams have to interact with
each other and they might have different
objectives, but, One development team can
be writing C code, whereas the testing
team can be writing Python code, but they
still have to interact with each other.
we might have to do some binding.
sometimes the need for binding
can be performance, sometimes
the need for binding can be cross
collaboration, but we'll learn more
as we, we'll learn how to do all that
as we move on to the next slides.
for the purpose of this talk, if you want
to follow along and actually try it out,
in your local IDE or compiler, some of
the prerequisites are you need to have,
a working C compiler that at least has
C 11, and, have, Python 3 installed.
you can either install it through,
if you're on Ubuntu, you can either
install all these through APT get.
Or if you are on, on a macro
system, you can use the Homebrew, to
install all of these dependencies.
build system like CMake is recommended.
That helps you to coordinate
compilation linking library parts.
And since we'll be talking about
Boost Python five 11, please, I mean
you can install it either through,
similar through like package managers
or, you can also use Cmec to fetch it.
or if in case of five 11 you can just copy
the headers into your project as well.
let's take a small look at, Boost and
PyBait11 just to understand what they are.
Boost Python is essentially part
of the larger Boost ecosystem.
It's actively maintained for many years.
It's stable, well documented, and
ships Python module in the library.
PyBait11 is a more modern alternative.
or rather I would say it's
slightly slower than Boost Python
also in terms of performance.
But, if you dislike additional library
dependencies and want an easy install,
PyBrain 11 just might be your choice.
But, when I show you like actual code,
I'll show you like both implementations
in both Boost Python and, PyBrain 11.
And I've also attached references
in case you want to check them out.
they have extensive documentation
for both these libraries.
Yeah, so let's take a look at actual
code before going to advanced topics.
so here's my ID.
So let's take a look at on the left.
we have on the left, I have a PI
bind and on the right, I have, boost.
So when we write in, so here we have a C
plus here to have C plus a score where we
have, simple, function process function.
Just to add.
And then we can actually expose it to,
we can define a Python module called
PyBindModule and essentially, add an, add
a doc string and then, expose it and say
this is a function to add two numbers.
And, I, the corresponding CMake lists
for this also clearly says that I want
to create a Python module and as a shared
library and call it as PyBain module
for this file PyBain underscore module.
cpp, which we see here, right?
So generally the code that
exposes it to Python is actually
written in a separate file.
But for the sake of simplicity
here, I have it in the same file.
so when this is compiled, so
I've already compiled it using
CMake for the sake of simplicity.
But when we actually compile this,
it generates a shared library
called a PyBain underscore module.
And this pyvain underscore module is what
is I actually, I can actually, and once I
actually like export, it to Python path,
I can actually directly import, the pyvain
module and then directly call the function
add, which is actually, implemented as
a C, which is actually a C function,
which takes two integers A and B, right?
So the corresponding, Python function
for that is over here, which is,
pi byte, pi, which we are directly
calling through the pi byte, pi bind
underscore module, which we, which is
actually like a shared library, right?
So a similar example in boost would be,
over here, where here we imported the
pi byte, PyBind11 header, where here
we import the boost header and then
here we basically say we want to create
a Boost Python module and this is the
function that adds two numbers, right?
So similarly, when I, when I compile
it, I create a, I again have a shared
library called boost underscore module.
And I can directly call the
boost underscore module in my
Python, file as boost module
dot add three, three comma four.
The syntaxes are fairly similar, but
they're not, they were different.
The setup is, different though.
with regard to our, so
this is very simple, right?
Look, just a function to expose, just a
function, just features have a function to
add two numbers and it is exposed in C and
we, and we expose it to the Python world.
We can do some advanced
operations as well.
for example, we can also have, a class
and, Here I have a class called person
and then you have a constructor with
name and age and then with getters
and setters for the age and a function
to get name and then some private
variables for name and age as well.
So in PyBind I can clearly say I want to,
I am calling this head library as PyBind
class module and I say that hey, I, this
is a class and I want to essentially allow
Python to call all these functions, right?
So similarly, when we go to some,
as I mentioned here, we could
directly import, and this also
I have pre built it over here.
I, once you, when you run CMake, it
generates PyBindClass underscore module.
And I can directly import the PyBindClass
underscore module, and then directly
call, directly call the constructor.
Say, I want to parse AliceN28.
And then it creates and person is like
the instance of that class and then I
can directly call the helper functions.
So this is another example to where you
can expose a C class to Python, right?
So similarly, we have, similarly,
we could also do it in Boost.
So we import the Boost header
and the class is very similar,
but then the exposing function is
like, slightly different syntax
where we use the Boost namespace.
So this is an example of how we
could expose C functions and C
classes onto the Python world.
But we can do much more advanced stuff.
We can also like, we can also map
C exceptions to Python exceptions.
We can easily parse vectors
other containers and iterators.
because both, PyBind11 and Boost
have HTL container support.
We could also, PyBind11 has a NumPy
header too, so we could also, and
Boost Python has a NumPy sub module,
so they can also be, easily be
parsed between those two languages.
So the idea is, when we have heavy
compute related operations, the idea is
to pick and choose them and move that
logic into C In terms of distribution,
packaging, as you saw, like when I
run cec, when I run CEC and built it
locally, I do get, for the I do get
like a do two.so files over here and
on and for, C and for Boost Python.
Then I also get a boost,
boost module Do so file here.
So the data, so file can essentially
be added to the Python path, and
then the Python scripts can be run.
But, but for larger projects, the idea
is to, use, create a pip installable
package where you use setup p or psych.
Or you can also use psyche.build
to publish the pipe or any
other container registry that,
that is of the user's choice.
So I have a simple P through which I
could, Push it, push the Pi by module
to a content registry of my choice.
And others can just grab that module
and then, add it to and install
it in their virtual environment.
And then essentially, run their scripts.
But, given all this, right?
So what about the overall
binding performance?
the idea is to, move part pieces of
code and read them, in C and then make
the two code, make the C code and the
Python code talk to each other, but then,
but in terms of binding performance,
are we like, are there any overheads?
There are definitely overheads, right?
Because data needs to go back and
forth between C objects and Py objects.
There's an implementation
difference between Boost.
py and PyBind11, where PyBind11,
everything is like a smart pointer,
so it heavily relies on smart pointers
and vectors, so it makes things slower.
So it's very imperative that we
choose the right parts of our code
and product that need to be optimized.
I did find some benchmarks
online that said Boost Python
is slightly faster than PyPy11.
And of course, C and Python are like,
raw C and raw Python are much faster.
but there are some countermeasures
that we can take to be, cautious.
Five 11 and Boost Python are special
types that directly bin Python and c plus.
So we can directly use those objects
like ic, instead of passing the
data, we can also use optimized
type findings like, array T double.
And we can also use smart pointers
instead of regular pointers.
because by being, garbage
collected language, we can
avoid the whole landing pointer.
Problem.
There is, when we use both, PyBind11
and GhostPython, we actually create
shared libraries where we statically
bind, the C code to Python, right?
but, there is also another concept
called dynamic binding, through, that
through another library called cppyy,
which directly writes C code into Python.
So there is no need for any sort
of like compilation and, uh, like
adding into Python path or putting
into a container history, we can
just write C directly into Python.
This is facilitated because
of the C Kling interpreter.
In this screenshot, that you could
directly write this Python code using
CPPY and then you could get that, you
can actually call it in the global
namespace, and print the output.
This is much, much faster than PyBrain
Python, and it's much more easy to use.
The advantages are, as I said, There's
no setup, no installation compilation.
It has a lot more support, for
templates, inheritance, callbacks, and
lambdas and other modern C features.
So the industry is moving towards using,
CVPYY, in cross language projects.
So overall, the top takeaways are,
Boost Python and PyBind11 are excellent
tools to blend the power of C and the
expressiveness, expressiveness of Python.
if you're already part of a
Boost ecosystem, It's probably
saner to use Boost Python and
use its robust set of features.
if you just want a lightweight,
open source project, you can
choose PyBind 11, but of course it
comes with performance overheads.
but the, but in terms of like static
binding, the idea is very simple.
Write the, choose which parts of
code that you want to edit in C use
a module defining macro to expose
it, and then compile it as a shared
library, and import it in Python.
But, and then you can also expose
it as a pip installable package,
or, put it in a context registry.
On the other hand, if you would like
to dynamically bind it, You can use
cppyy that uses the cling interpreter
and for reference, all the code that
have been mentioned in the slide
deck are in my GitHub repository.
So feel free to check it out
in case you want to run if in
case you want to run those code
locally and then get a feel of it.
Thank you.