Hi, I'll be speaking on the hidden
potential of Python's Dunder method.
About me, I'm a software engineer
with over five years of experience in
working for some companies globally.
I'm very passionate about
sharing knowledge and I do
this through technical writing.
I'm also an active contributor to the
open source community, and socials below.
What a Dunder method.
So before I dive into our
Dunder method, I would like to
just take us a few steps back.
So maybe most of us here have
worked with Python classes and
object oriented programming before.
You've probably written the
double underscore init method
to initialize your object.
Or perhaps you've come across the double
underscore string method while trying to
make your object print something readable.
But let me ask you this.
Did you ever stop and wonder what's really
going on behind those double underscores?
Or are they just some
really quirky convention?
They are part of something much
bigger because they help Python work
the way it does and they make our
code really flexible and powerful.
So imagine you're adding
two numbers in Python.
That's probably simple, like you
write five plus three and Python
instantly knows to return it.
Now, what if you want to add to object
you've created in your own class?
At first, Python might give you
an error, but here's the thing.
You can teach Python how to
understand what's an error.
The plus operator means for your
object, just like it does for number.
How can we do that?
We can do that using the Dunder method.
So this might sound like some really
advanced Python, wizardry thing, but I
promise it's not intimidating as it seems
so, Dunder methods or magic methods,
as often as most people might call it.
They're just basically tools, right?
That built into Python.
They let you define objects, how your
objects should behave when they are
used in familiar ways, like being added
or compared and maybe, subtracted.
So when methods, these methods, aren't
just something really technical.
They're just practical ways to
make your code really clean, smart.
And look like Python.
So for example, think about this.
Have you ever used the length
method function to get the size of
a list of string behind the scene?
Python isn't just automatically
going to know, the length, right?
It's going to call the Dunder
method, double underscore length.
And the same goes for printing an object.
Python calls the double underscore string
method to figure out what to display.
This methods are quietly doing a whole
lot of heavy lifting to make Python feel
as seamless and intuitive as it does.
But here's where the things
get even more exciting.
This Dunder methods aren't just
limited to Python built in types.
You can use them in your own
class to create objects that
feel just as natural to use.
So you imagine building a library.
Where users can treat your
object like they treat the list.
Like the trees list or numbers, they
can add, They can compare, they can
iterate over them without ever having
to read a really complicated API docs.
let me just give you a
glimpse of, how this works.
we've maybe probably worked with
popular libraries like NumPy, In
NumPy, you can add arrays together by
simply using the add operator, like I
should, like I'm showing in the slide.
And then the NumPy uses Donda methods like
the underscore adds to make this happen.
Or maybe, we've probably worked
with the SQL alchemy and it's a
library for working with database.
Yeah.
It's basically helps you, lets
you build SQL queries using Python
comparison operator, like the double
equal to, this is not really just some
hack it's done the methods at play.
So done the methods basically uses the.
Double underscore equal, method.
And now you can see that this library
feels so intuitive because they've really,
yeah, using the power of Python's methods
to blend seamlessly with the language.
so here we see.
that this libraries used on the methods
to integrate Python syntax without
their objects, but they are making
the objects feel very easy to use.
So done the methods goals beyond
using the double underscore in it, or.
The double underscore REPL for creating a
clustering representation of your object.
So we also have, the double underscore
get item, which enables you to get an
index based access of your, objects.
Or we have the double underscore iterate,
I T E R iteration, which basically
helps you or makes your object iterable.
What makes Dunder objects really
exciting is how they give you
ability to control how your objects
behave in nearly any context.
So you can define how they should
respond to arithmetic comparison.
Or even built in function.
And once you understand them, you
realize that they are not just a feature
in Python, they are a very key part
of Python design philosophy, which is
really simplicity and expressiveness.
So now you might be wondering.
Why should I care about Dunder Method?
The answer is very simple.
You are building applications, if
you are building applications, or
libraries, or frameworks, using
Dunder Method can make your code
really intuitive for others to use.
It means like you're writing an API
that feels really natural and familiar
reducing the learning curve for users.
And if you work on your own project,
Dunder methods lets you write code
really cleaner and really usable.
So today we are going to dive into how
this Dunder method works and, we're going
to see how we can use it to, Build our
own, custom class using done the methods.
if you're just a beginner or you already
have some experience working with
Python, this talk is just going to give
you like a really fresh perspective.
how they work.
like I said, there are core features of
Python that allows instances of class to
seamlessly interact with Python's built
in functions and operator of the language.
So the term done that just comes
from the word double underscore,
because this method starts and
end with two underscores, such as
underscore string and underscore in it.
why they may seem mysterious at the
first glance, they are well defined
rules and they are invoked at a
specific time in the Python interpreter.
So at the core, Dunder methods are not
actually magical in the sense of being
mysterious or some very arbitrary thing.
They are methods that are.
in Python's interpreter and and
Python interpreter implicitly
calls them when like a specific
action occurs in your program.
So for example, when you want to
assess the length of an object.
there are some characteristics
of Python's Dunder method, right?
Like I said earlier, it's a built
in, it has double underscore.
you can't Dunder methods are tied to
a specific operation or functions.
So such as like the, double underscore
call or double underscore add, right?
So you can't just come up with your
own, or you can't invent your own
Dunder methods you can't create a class,
for example, like what I did here.
And name your dunder methods like create
a method and just give it a custom name,
understand double underscore custom,
because in the real sense, Python will
not be able to recognize your methods
and there, it will make much sense.
this methods.
You, for you to be able to use Python
standard method, you have to use
what's already existing and you can
find the least of all these methods
in the Python's documentation.
so we're going to create
our own custom class, right?
It's called points.
when we create a custom class
called points, like we, most
of us here do, we, we can.
We already used the double
underscore in it, basically.
And what this does is that it
helps, when we initialize our class.
it's basically, passes or
initializes the object attributes,
what we passed in the constructor.
now We might want to print
out the class, right?
Like print out the class.
And then when we use print automatically,
Python uses the string double
score double underscore string or
double underscore repel metal to
define how this object should be
represented as strings by default.
Python shows this object types
in look type and the location in
memory, which isn't very helpful,
like what we have here in the slides.
to use, to display, more readable, Data.
When we try to print our class, we
can create by, or we can implement
the REPL method to provide like a
more meaningful string representation.
So here we, we added the REPL, method.
And then when we instantiated our
class again and printed out points,
what happened is that we were.
We could see the, a better output,
which is points and two, two and three.
So basically REPL just Python.
When we call the print methods,
Python knows to call REPL and
represent the string in a proper way.
what if we want to add.
We instantiate two classes
that are class twice, right?
So for example, here we have
1 and 2 and we decide to add
these two classes together.
What happens?
We get an error from Python
saying unsupported operand types,
because we actually cannot add
these two classes together.
the way the, add operator works by
default, it works with numbers or string.
So to make the add work with our class,
we have to define the add on the methods.
In our point class.
So let's define the addDundee method.
like you see here, we defined
it and we said, whenever the
plus operator is called, we try
to add the classes together.
And now when we try to instantiate
again, what happens is that we
add the point one and point two
class and we get an actual output.
now we've seen that we've been able
to tell Python how to handle the
plus operator in the, the point
object, because now you can add
both X and Y coordinates of the two
points and return a new point object.
let's look at the plus,
the equal to operator.
we can see that if we try to, like we
instantiated two class, the two objects,
two points object earlier, right?
If we try to compare both
objects together, right?
We see, we try to compare 0.
1 and 0.
2. We got true, but 0.
3, we got false, right?
we got false for both of them.
And oh, I'm sorry, I
missed something here.
So if we try to instantiate the
point objects twice and compare 0.
1 and 0.
2, we see that it is not equal, right?
So that's because if we don't have
the, don't, equal to method, right?
Equality methods.
So if we define that like we did here, and
we now instant, we try to compare them.
And we see that 0.
1 and 0.
2 methods.
now equal 3 are not equal.
So basically now we've been able to
create, the fact that we created the
equality done the methods now means
that when we use the double equal to,
it now works on our point objects,
comparing X and Y values for equality.
So another.
Methods that we can create is the
double underscore multiplication,
multiple collision, done the methods.
So like you see here, we added
the multiplication methods.
And what this does is that when we
try to multiply our class with, in
number, It brings out an actual output.
So we see that the multiplication operator
now scales the point by multiplying it
our coordinates by the scalar value,
which we passed here and three, which
is the scalar value we passed here.
We can also, yeah, several
done the methods, but another
very interesting one is the.
let's implement this iterator method
to make the point objects iterable.
So you can look through when we call
the, when we implement this method,
what it does basically is that we
can loop over like the coordinates.
So we can see how we, we did that here.
Okay.
but what happened is that now, when we try
to loop over our, point objects, we make
them feel like native Python collections.
So now we can be able
to loop through them.
Um, The next thing I'll be talking
about is why Python Dundun methods
are really interesting to use.
we do not just want to use them
everywhere in our code, right?
We do not want to abuse them.
So, this.
And, I think like we need
to use them when necessary.
So they are really powerful.
And personally, I think like you
should use them thoughtfully.
So you shouldn't like
overuse them or misuse them.
And because they can make the code
really confusing and unpredictable
or probably hard to maintain.
So there are several guides on
where not to use Dunder method.
And, so for example, don't use them
to solve like really simple problems.
So you can see here in our
calculator class, right?
We just had, an add.
we have the Dunder method add.
To multiply, the, to multiply data, to
multiply the values in the calculator.
So this is quite confusing because
we shouldn't use that, if we are
using the ad, it should depicts
adding values together, Another
thing too, is using the call.
like I said earlier, we don't want to,
we don't want to use the, there's a
double underscore call method, right?
We don't want to implement that
in our class because that's
quite unnecessary, right?
It's doing, it's, we might
not really need it, right?
Or imagine implementing a call method
that is actually adding numbers together.
So it doesn't make any sense.
So we want to use Dunder methods.
That depicts the right thing in your code.
So they don't become really confusing.
Also, you do not want to
invent your own dunder methods.
Like I said earlier, if you declare
a dunder method that does not exist
in Python native, in the native
Python, it won't work, right?
It's just going to be like, you're
going to be confusing everyone
because someone can hop on your code
and see it and get confused because
this doesn't really do anything.
instead just use a regular method.
Also, operator, we don't want to make
operator overload and really confusing.
like I said earlier, you don't want to
just, use an add method to, Multiply
several, numbers, you don't want to
use a multiply multiplication, done the
methods to add several numbers, right?
you want to keep it really
consistent and very predictable.
So another thing is that you don't
want to overuse it in your classes.
So you don't want to have
a class that uses all the.
The method just makes your
class really confused.
You want to use them only when necessary.
And another thing is that
you don't want to sacrifice
readability for cleverness, right?
So if you have a lot of this done,
the methods, your class, it might
look cool, but it might be very
difficult for others to maintain.
in conclusion,
using done, the methods
It's really powerful, right?
So we've seen how we're able to combine
Dunder methods to be able to build
the point class earlier and to make
it look really rich and intuitive.
So these are like techniques that you can
use to design objects that makes it feel
really natural in our applications domain.
For example, If you are working with
a graphic library, you might want
to use something like the Dunder
method underscore Dunder methods
add, or you're working like with
a game development library, right?
It might make sense to use the
equality Dunder methods for maybe
your collision detection, right?
So Dunder methods bridge the gap
between your custom object and
Python's built in capabilities.
Allowing you to design APIs, an
application that looks really
powerful, but also really easy to use.
Thank you.
Hi, I'll be speaking on the hidden
potential of Python's Dunder method.
About me, I'm a software engineer
with over five years of experience in
working for some companies globally.
I'm very passionate about
sharing knowledge and I do
this through technical writing.
I'm also an active contributor to the
open source community, and socials below.
What a Dunder method.
So before I dive into our
Dunder method, I would like to
just take us a few steps back.
So maybe most of us here have
worked with Python classes and
object oriented programming before.
You've probably written the
double underscore init method
to initialize your object.
Or perhaps you've come across the double
underscore string method while trying to
make your object print something readable.
But let me ask you this.
Did you ever stop and wonder what's really
going on behind those double underscores?
Or are they just some
really quirky convention?
They are part of something much
bigger because they help Python work
the way it does and they make our
code really flexible and powerful.
So imagine you're adding
two numbers in Python.
That's probably simple, like you
write five plus three and Python
instantly knows to return it.
Now, what if you want to add to object
you've created in your own class?
At first, Python might give you
an error, but here's the thing.
You can teach Python how to
understand what's an error.
The plus operator means for your
object, just like it does for number.
How can we do that?
We can do that using the Dunder method.
So this might sound like some really
advanced Python, wizardry thing, but I
promise it's not intimidating as it seems
so, Dunder methods or magic methods,
as often as most people might call it.
They're just basically tools, right?
That built into Python.
They let you define objects, how your
objects should behave when they are
used in familiar ways, like being added
or compared and maybe, subtracted.
So when methods, these methods, aren't
just something really technical.
They're just practical ways to
make your code really clean, smart.
And look like Python.
So for example, think about this.
Have you ever used the length
method function to get the size of
a list of string behind the scene?
Python isn't just automatically
going to know, the length, right?
It's going to call the Dunder
method, double underscore length.
And the same goes for printing an object.
Python calls the double underscore string
method to figure out what to display.
This methods are quietly doing a whole
lot of heavy lifting to make Python feel
as seamless and intuitive as it does.
But here's where the things
get even more exciting.
This Dunder methods aren't just
limited to Python built in types.
You can use them in your own
class to create objects that
feel just as natural to use.
So you imagine building a library.
Where users can treat your
object like they treat the list.
Like the trees list or numbers, they
can add, They can compare, they can
iterate over them without ever having
to read a really complicated API docs.
let me just give you a
glimpse of, how this works.
we've maybe probably worked with
popular libraries like NumPy, In
NumPy, you can add arrays together by
simply using the add operator, like I
should, like I'm showing in the slide.
And then the NumPy uses Donda methods like
the underscore adds to make this happen.
Or maybe, we've probably worked
with the SQL alchemy and it's a
library for working with database.
Yeah.
It's basically helps you, lets
you build SQL queries using Python
comparison operator, like the double
equal to, this is not really just some
hack it's done the methods at play.
So done the methods basically uses the.
Double underscore equal, method.
And now you can see that this library
feels so intuitive because they've really,
yeah, using the power of Python's methods
to blend seamlessly with the language.
so here we see.
that this libraries used on the methods
to integrate Python syntax without
their objects, but they are making
the objects feel very easy to use.
So done the methods goals beyond
using the double underscore in it, or.
The double underscore REPL for creating a
clustering representation of your object.
So we also have, the double underscore
get item, which enables you to get an
index based access of your, objects.
Or we have the double underscore iterate,
I T E R iteration, which basically
helps you or makes your object iterable.
What makes Dunder objects really
exciting is how they give you
ability to control how your objects
behave in nearly any context.
So you can define how they should
respond to arithmetic comparison.
Or even built in function.
And once you understand them, you
realize that they are not just a feature
in Python, they are a very key part
of Python design philosophy, which is
really simplicity and expressiveness.
So now you might be wondering.
Why should I care about Dunder Method?
The answer is very simple.
You are building applications, if
you are building applications, or
libraries, or frameworks, using
Dunder Method can make your code
really intuitive for others to use.
It means like you're writing an API
that feels really natural and familiar
reducing the learning curve for users.
And if you work on your own project,
Dunder methods lets you write code
really cleaner and really usable.
So today we are going to dive into how
this Dunder method works and, we're going
to see how we can use it to, Build our
own, custom class using done the methods.
if you're just a beginner or you already
have some experience working with
Python, this talk is just going to give
you like a really fresh perspective.
how they work.
like I said, there are core features of
Python that allows instances of class to
seamlessly interact with Python's built
in functions and operator of the language.
So the term done that just comes
from the word double underscore,
because this method starts and
end with two underscores, such as
underscore string and underscore in it.
why they may seem mysterious at the
first glance, they are well defined
rules and they are invoked at a
specific time in the Python interpreter.
So at the core, Dunder methods are not
actually magical in the sense of being
mysterious or some very arbitrary thing.
They are methods that are.
in Python's interpreter and and
Python interpreter implicitly
calls them when like a specific
action occurs in your program.
So for example, when you want to
assess the length of an object.
there are some characteristics
of Python's Dunder method, right?
Like I said earlier, it's a built
in, it has double underscore.
you can't Dunder methods are tied to
a specific operation or functions.
So such as like the, double underscore
call or double underscore add, right?
So you can't just come up with your
own, or you can't invent your own
Dunder methods you can't create a class,
for example, like what I did here.
you're done the methods
like create a methods.
And just give me the custom limb,
understand double underscore custom
because in the real sense Python will
not be able to recognize your methods
and they, it will make much sense.
this methods.
You, for you to be able to use Python
standard method, you have to use
what's already existing and you can
find the least of all these methods
in the Python's documentation.
so we're going to create
our own custom class, right?
It's called points.
when we create a custom class
called points, like we, most
of us here do, we, we can.
We already used the double
underscore in it, basically.
And what this does is that it
helps, when we initialize our class.
it's basically, passes or
initializes the object attributes,
what we passed in the constructor.
now We might want to print
out the class, right?
Like print out the class.
And then when we use print automatically,
Python uses the string double
score double underscore string or
double underscore repel metal to
define how this object should be
represented as strings by default.
Python shows this object types
in look type and the location in
memory, which isn't very helpful,
like what we have here in the slides.
to use, to display, more readable, Data.
When we try to print our class, we
can create by, or we can implement
the REPL method to provide like a
more meaningful string representation.
So here we, we added the REPL, method.
And then when we instantiated our
class again and printed out points,
what happened is that we were.
We could see the, a better output,
which is points and two, two and three.
So basically REPL just Python.
When we call the print methods,
Python knows to call REPL and
represent the string in a proper way.
what if we want to add.
We instantiate two classes
that are class twice, right?
So for example, here we have
1 and 2 and we decide to add
these two classes together.
What happens?
We get an error from Python
saying unsupported operand types,
because we actually cannot add
these two classes together.
the way the, add operator works by
default, it works with numbers or string.
So to make the add work with our class,
we have to define the add on the methods.
In our point class.
So let's define the addDundee method.
like you see here, we defined
it and we said, whenever the
plus operator is called, we try
to add the classes together.
And now when we try to instantiate
again, what happens is that we
add the point one and point two
class and we get an actual output.
now we've seen that we've been able
to tell Python how to handle the
plus operator in the, the point
object, because now you can add
both X and Y coordinates of the two
points and return a new point object.
let's look at the plus,
the equal to operator.
we can see that if we try to, like we
instantiated two class, the two objects,
two points object earlier, right?
If we try to compare both
objects together, right?
We see, we try to compare 0.
1 and 0.
2. We got true, but 0.
3, we got false, right?
we got false for both of them.
And oh, I'm sorry, I
missed something here.
So if we try to instantiate the
point objects twice and compare 0.
1 and 0.
2, we see that it is not equal, right?
So that's because if we don't have
the, don't, equal to method, right?
Equality methods.
So if we define that like we did here, and
we now instant, we try to compare them.
And we see that 0.
1 and 0.
2 methods.
now equal 3 are not equal.
So basically now we've been able to
create, the fact that we created the
equality done the methods now means
that when we use the double equal to,
it now works on our point objects,
comparing X and Y values for equality.
So another.
Methods that we can create is the
double underscore multiplication,
multiple collision, done the methods.
So like you see here, we added
the multiplication methods.
And what this does is that when we
try to multiply our class with, in
number, It brings out an actual output.
So we see that the multiplication operator
now scales the point by multiplying it
our coordinates by the scalar value,
which we passed here and three, which
is the scalar value we passed here.
We can also, yeah, several
done the methods, but another
very interesting one is the.
let's implement this iterator method
to make the point objects iterable.
So you can look through when we call
the, when we implement this method,
what it does basically is that we
can loop over like the coordinates.
So we can see how we, we did that here.
Okay.
but what happened is that now, when we try
to loop over our, point objects, we make
them feel like native Python collections.
So now we can be able
to loop through them.
Um, The next thing I'll be talking
about is why Python Dundun methods
are really interesting to use.
we do not just want to use them
everywhere in our code, right?
We do not want to abuse them.
So, this.
And, I think like we need
to use them when necessary.
So they are really powerful.
And personally, I think like you
should use them thoughtfully.
So you shouldn't like
overuse them or misuse them.
And because they can make the code
really confusing and unpredictable
or probably hard to maintain.
So there are several guides on
where not to use Dunder method.
And, so for example, don't use them
to solve like really simple problems.
So you can see here in our
calculator class, right?
We just had, an add.
we have the Dunder method add.
To multiply, the, to multiply data, to
multiply the values in the calculator.
So this is quite confusing because
we shouldn't use that, if we are
using the ad, it should depicts
adding values together, Another
thing too, is using the call.
like I said earlier, we don't want to,
we don't want to use the, there's a
double underscore call method, right?
We don't want to implement that
in our class because that's
quite unnecessary, right?
It's doing, it's, we might
not really need it, right?
Or imagine implementing a call method
that is actually adding numbers together.
So it doesn't make any sense.
So we want to use Dunder methods.
That depicts the right thing in your code.
So they don't become really confusing.
Also, you do not want to
invent your own dunder methods.
Like I said earlier, if you declare
a dunder method that does not exist
in Python native, in the native
Python, it won't work, right?
It's just going to be like, you're
going to be confusing everyone
because someone can hop on your code
and see it and get confused because
this doesn't really do anything.
instead just use a regular method.
Also, operator, we don't want to make
operator overload and really confusing.
like I said earlier, you don't want to
just, use an add method to, Multiply
several, numbers, you don't want to
use a multiply multiplication, done the
methods to add several numbers, right?
you want to keep it really
consistent and very predictable.
So another thing is that you don't
want to overuse it in your classes.
So you don't want to have
a class that uses all the.
Done the methods just and makes
your class like really confused.
You want to use them only when necessary.
I know that thing is that
you don't want to sacrifice,
readability for cleverness, right?
So if you have a lot of this, done
the methods, your class, it might
look cool, but it might be very
difficult for others to maintain.
in conclusion,
using Dunder Methods It's
really powerful, right?
So we've seen how we're able to combine
Dunder methods to be able to build
the point class earlier and to make
it look really rich and intuitive.
So these are like techniques that you can
use to design objects that makes it feel
really natural in our applications domain.
For example, If you are working with
a graphic library, you might want
to use something like the Dunder
method underscore Dunder methods
add, or you're working like with
a game development library, right?
It might make sense to use the
equality Dunder methods for maybe
your collision detection, right?
So Dunder methods bridge the gap
between your custom object and
Python's built in capabilities.
Allowing you to design APIs, an
application that looks really
powerful, but also really easy to use.
Thank you.