Hello all, thank,
welcome to con 42 python.
I thank you for attending this session
and, I would like to go over some of the,
use cases of python in, deep learning
and how it can help us in, building a
lot of deep learning and data engineering
and these kinds of transformative apps.
And, let me first quickly give you
a short introduction about myself.
I have total experience of eight
plus years in machine learning, data
engineering, as well as cyber security.
I graduated from Northeastern
University with information systems
with specialization in machine
learning and data analytics.
So in this presentation,
we will dive deep into how.
Machine learning and deep learning
have enabled transformation and all
these applications, they are built
on Python using kind of packages
like TensorFlow, PyTorch and all
the other deep learning packages.
So let's go through this slide
over here, which illustrates
about reinforcement learning.
So as we, as we know, there are a lot
of capabilities in machine learning.
These are related to.
Supervised learning,
unsupervised learning.
So these kinds of algorithms are
kind of very basic algorithms.
They are used widely in industries,
but right now reinforcement learning
is making a lot of inroads because
of a lot of good algorithms are
being developed on basis of that.
And these kinds of algorithms are
shaping the future and they are enabling
a lot of superhuman capabilities.
capabilities.
So these kind of reinforcement
learning they have once they are
trained in a very proper way manner
with less errors and higher accuracy.
These can lead to, you know,
building superhuman or, you know,
a deep brain kind of capabilities.
Like if you see chat, GPT and other LLM
models, they are generative and they
are able to Kind of do the thinking
and provide us with the answer.
So these kind of capabilities have
evolved through reinforcement learning.
For example, if you see DeepMind, AlphaGo,
then, recent breakthroughs in theory,
these have a lot of, reinforcement
learning involved, and these are shaping
the way for the future, especially
in robotics and various other fields.
Then we look into the
generative models over here.
So over here I have mentioned
about generative adversarial
national autoencoders.
So what is the difference between the two?
GANs are mostly generative models and
they are Kind of more of generation
image generation and that kind of thing
and they have They currently have higher
accuracy as compared to VAEs, but VAEs are
more powerful probabilistic models which
have capabilities of anomaly detection
Then threat detection working on the
data set in cyber security realm So, in
cyber security, these kind of VAEs are
very powerful and, they are utilized
and in future we might see lot of trends
of utilizing such kind of algorithms.
Both of these algorithms are based on
neural network based algorithms and
they have evolved and probably they will
make a system more capable and a lot of
applications will be developed in future.
Now we see over here the rise of
generative models in design and art.
So, currently machine learning and
deep learning technologies are being
used in as well as healthcare and
cybersecurity fields, but in future
we'll see a rise of these kind of
models being utilized in architecture,
art, and all those industries
because they have the capability to
kind of generate like They have the
ability to understand the pattern.
So if somebody has certain things in
mind, and if you enable such kind of
decision making, then these kinds of
models can generate certain kinds of
design, whatever you have in your mind.
And if you are able to convey it to
the model and the model will in turn
generate the design and art for you.
So it will become that kind of
a powerful system in future.
Now in, AI, AI is very useful in
cyber security, not because, it can
do all the basic tasks, but because
these generative models, they might be
able to do a lot of threat detection,
vulnerability assessment, fraud
prevention, and such kind of activities.
And this is because the algorithms
and, Algorithms have evolved in such
a high way that these kind of threat
detection, instead of taking sim tools,
we can use such kind of algorithms to
detect threats in the organization.
So for example, let me
give you a scenario.
If there are a lot of cyber criminals,
which are Using AI based tools
like chat GPT and various other
tools to do phishing attacks, DDoS
attacks and such kind of things.
So in threat detection, if we leverage
such kind of models, deep learning models
and train them using Python, then this
will become kind of good, kind of, it
will become, it will help us in developing
and mitigating such kind of threats.
And it will also enable vulnerability
assessment, fraud prevention, and such
kind of activities, which are not.
Clearly and not that powerful using
the existing tools, although I would
say, although these kinds of existing
cyber security tools are good enough,
but there is 10 percent chance
where such kind of tools might fail.
And in such kind of situation, If
we take help of AI tools like RNN,
Recurrent Neural Network, these
kind of AI algorithms can help us
to detect certain threats, then
predict vulnerabilities, some fraud
prevention, that kind of activities.
So these, these tools, instead of
relying on such kind of cybersecurity
tools, we can leverage AI algorithms,
which are trained using deep learning.
neural networks using Python and this
can enable us such kind of better
security posture within the organization.
There are multiple, many threat, many
algorithms like neural network, for
example, Microsoft, as well as Amazon
also has certain kinds of threat detection
algorithms, which they are training.
And building upon their AI tools
to improve the cyber security and
operations within the organization.
So, in future, we might see vulnerability
assessment and fraud prevention
activities done by AI, and it will
have better accuracy score in future.
Now we come to graph neural network.
So GNNs are also a powerful tool within
cyber security, which can enable us to
identify anomalies, predict threats,
do complex kind of transformation,
relationship mapping, and, maybe it
can, detect certain kinds of anomalies
within the data, vulnerability data,
which SIM tools like Splunk, AlienVault,
and such kind of tools cannot detect.
So these algorithms, if they are
trained and if they are able to
provide a good picture about the
anomalies and security posture, these
algorithms can become very useful.
Good helping hand in, uncovering
certain kinds of threats.
And what I am explaining over here
is not just using these kinds of
tools, but also integrating them with
the existing cybersecurity tools.
Organization can have better outcome.
of detecting DDoS attacks or certain
kinds of threat threat actors
and identifying cybercriminals.
So it's quite beneficial and these
kinds of models should be trained
so that security posture and threat
detection capabilities can be increased.
Now we come to future
of AI in cyber security.
So, There are multiple
aspects where AI can help.
This is right now in threat detection.
Obviously, it can help us to
provide some immediate inroads.
And in future, it can also help
us to identify the attackers.
If let's say if the attacker
is using AI based tools.
These kind of things can be kind of
detected by AI tools rather than using
the existing cyber security tools.
And organizations can improve their
security reporting then when there won't
be that many requirement of that many
folks to look into the basic aspects.
So basic security aspects and
reporting can be automated by using AI.
Whereas security engineers and other folks
can look into some other advanced aspects.
So the work can be distributed
and cyber security operations
can be improved in such a way.
And now we come to ethical
considerations in AI.
So over here, AI can be a good thing
in cyber security and other operations.
But AI, there are a lot of issues like
Privacy and security issues, then bias
and discrimination and all those things
and job displacement kind of issues.
So these are some ethical considerations
of AI, which we need to look
into as we try to fine tune and
deploy the models in production.
We use.
We need to look into the
compliance aspects as well.
Compliance and governance related
processes that AI would be able
to have any privacy implications
or security related implications.
So based on what kind of data you are
feeding to the AI algorithm, these
kinds of things needs to be discussed
with the compliance and I would say
the security and compliance team
and also governance and other teams.
All these things need to be discussed
so that the AI algorithms are
capable enough and they don't hamper
any of our ethical considerations.
Now we come to recurrent neural network.
So recurrent neural network, what
is a recurrent neural network?
This kind of a neural network is a very
advanced level neural network, which
focuses more on kind of detecting threats.
finding the anomalies in the dataset.
Then, predicting the anomalies
and that kind of thing.
It behaves very different from
convolutional neural network because
convolutional neural network, for
example, is used more into autonomous
driving and detecting images and
classifying images and such kind of thing.
Whereas is a neural network,
which is based on more of.
Detecting anomalies in a data set and
finding and improving the security
posture within the organization.
So those, those are the use cases of RNN
and RNN is currently very extensively
used in such kind of anomaly detection.
I, I would say before implementing RNN
algorithm, we should look into some basic
algorithms like XGBoost is one of them.
Then we have IsolationForest.
XGBoost.
which is also a very good algorithm,
which I have trained to look
into the cyber security data set.
We'll go through that
in our next few slides.
So the RNN architecture, this slide
mentions about the architecture of RNN,
and it has input layer, hidden layer,
Then activation function and output layer.
So it's like advanced features as
compared to neural network where he,
it has input layer, then hidden layer,
which are trained in a different way.
Then we have activation function, which is
also kind of, developed in a different way
as compared to traditional neural network.
And some of RNN are associated
to language modeling, generating
Then, speech recognition.
Then we have, translation of
machines, image recognition,
and such kind of things.
There are a lot of use case of RNN
currently in cybersecurity where it
can detect threats and then provide
details of the threats, vulnerability
detection, and that kind of thing.
The best, the currently the best
algorithm which can be used for
time series is the transformer base.
Time GPT.
So time GPT is the algorithm, the
model, which is developed by next law.
This company uses heavily transformer
based models to predict it provides a time
series analysis, and it is very powerful.
And the use cases are related to
finance, web traffic analysis, internet
of things, weather forecasting,
are related to anomaly detection,
finding anomalies in data set.
Classifying the anomalies
and such kind of thing.
So time series is also time.
GPT is a very important algorithm and
it's, since it is transformer based,
it has evolved quite drastically as
compared to traditional neural network.
And I would like to, I, I. We will
be able to see a lot of applications
of transformer based algorithms in
near future, because right now the
trend is going on where a lot of AI
applications are being developed on
a transformer based kind of models
like chat, GPT, and all those things,
all these kinds of applications are
developed using transformer based
models, even these kinds of algorithms,
which are being used in deep seek.
Kind of these kinds of companies
are using transformer based
models, which are trained in a very
different way as compared to normal
neural network based algorithms.
So I believe transformer based
models will have a lot of big
impacts in next few years.
Now we've come to this very good use
case of Python with Spark integration.
So I have done some work on Spark earlier.
So I am providing some
details about how Spark.
Can help backend and machine learning
engineers, because this is a distributed
framework for big data processing.
And it is very easy to use and,
it helps to integrate with REST
API and various other, databases.
Spark, currently has a capability
to integrate with these backend
data stores, like Cassandra, then,
MongoDB, then, all the, Elasticsearch
and other faster NoSQL databases.
Spark also integrates
very quickly with Kafka.
So, if your distributed system has
Kafka and all these tools, then you
should also consider Spark integration.
In Spark integration, what you
need to do is to use PySpark.
Where you try to write an API,
query the API using Spark, PySpark,
and then store it into the tables.
You can also store it into any kind
of databases, and it is very powerful.
It works with distributed systems.
It can, Provide you the transformation.
You can do transformation using
Spark and then dump the data
into any kind of a data store.
And it is very fast and
very scalable enough.
The real world applications of Spark are
related to big data processing, developing
ETL pipelines, performing transformations,
then querying and writing into APIs,
fetching, ingesting data from APIs.
And all those things and also machine
learning capabilities in spark is
also very good, but it is not very
much good like the existing deep
learning capabilities and streaming
spark applications are mainly used
for streaming, building streaming
applications and taking the data from
Kafka and putting it into any kind
of data store after transformation.
Now, next we will go into
deep dive into the code.
So this slide over here provides
details about the Python PySpark code.
This code is basically to
ingest data from a REST API.
And after, We ingest the data in from
REST API, we are writing it and this
code over here, it will try to take the
data from API and put it into a Spark
DataFrame and Spark DataFrame is very
powerful because it can handle tons of
data as compared to, and we can data store
after ingesting the data from web API.
Now we look into this.
This is a vulnerability data set, which
I was talking about, where, deep learning
and machine learning based capabilities
are good enough to detect threats.
So this vulnerability, this data is a
vulnerability data with, having multiple.
columns related to vulnerabilities.
Then, we want to identify these
kinds of vulnerabilities not by
using tool, but by using AI model.
So over here, I have developed
this AI model where I am
cleaning the vulnerability data.
And, we have certain criteria
over here where we are taking
the clean data with complexity.
Over here, we are trying to find out
high complexity and medium severity
and CV as a score of greater than six.
And then I have written this, first
of all, I have done perform cleaning
over here, and, After cleaning the data
set, I have performed transformations
and looked into certain features
which we require like CVSS score,
severity encoded, complexity encoded,
and then I have trained the model.
Isolation forest over here.
And, after I perform model
training, I have also, predicted
and developed the anomalies.
so this, anomalies of clean data consists
of, high, all those, rows which have,
complexity high, severity of medium
and CVS score of greater than six.
And, finally, I am able to, the model is
able to provide the anomalies and, this
can be obviously automated, by using,
other, highly capable models as well,
but I have tried using isolation forest.
And then, I had also tried, this kind
of anomaly detection using XGBoost and,
I am, trying to leverage RNN and other,
transformer based model to, predict,
certain anomalies in the dataset.
So.
in few months I will be using
transformer based models to predict,
certain anomalies within the dataset.
now we come to over here, the
convergence of AI and security.
So, AI and security.
these are, very different kind of, things,
but, AI can be used in cybersecurity,
in, Improving the security function.
So it cannot, generally replace
all the existing security tools and
features, but it can help us to provide
more, better mitigation, detection,
threat detection, fraud detection,
and those kinds of capabilities.
So it is likely to help.
The team in, building more, better,
security posture within the organization
and, transforming industries.
The impact of AI advancement is,
kind of helping in building more of,
autonomous systems, drug discovery,
and, developing personalized medicine.
So these kinds of things are the use
cases which can, be Done in future, but
right now the capabilities of AI are to
improve the cyber security as well as
some of the tech industry improvement of
the processes within the tech industry.
And, what are the key takeaways?
So in this slide, I have mentioned
about the deep learning since it
is, having a lot of, a lot of, AI
models like reinforcement learning,
generative models, and, all these
things, but it is critical to understand
what Use cases, they can help in.
So we have to understand the
use case in a better way.
And then, go into specific
models, which can help.
And, the basic things are to write, start
with the simpler models and then automate
it and improve upon, and then look into
some advanced modeling capabilities.
So in that way we can automate certain
processes, in our, In cybersecurity,
in data engineering, as well as,
analytics, and it can also help
in, building analytic pipelines.
So that's it from my side.
hope you like this session and
let me know if you would like to
have more, additional information.
Feel free to connect with me on.