Hello everyone and thank
you for joining today.
I'm Nickel Kati and I'm here today to
talk on a topic from milliseconds to
microseconds, how quantum computing
could transform real-time payments.
So to start with we are.
A fascinating intersection
of two major revolutions.
It's more of like realtime payments
and also the quantum computing.
So in today's talk, I will talk, take
you through how the quantum computing
technology once confined almost like to
just I would say more of a theoretical.
Physics model is now beginning to
reshape one of the most critical
pillars of our economy and also
the financial transactions.
So as we move from milliseconds
to microseconds, we are
not just talking about.
FSA payments here.
So we are also talking about a shift
in how value is exchanged globally.
So more about like how fraud is
prevented in real time and how
banking systems are rearchitected
to operate in the quantum speeds.
So imagine like in this, billions
of transactions per second optimized
across global networks with fraud
detection systems that don't
just react, they also anticipate.
So the potential economic impact of
this transformation is just staggering?
I would say so, just because I'm
just seeing that based on the
studies that usually suggest this.
So the studies in the recent ones
that I've been through suggest
more of like around four 11.
Billion Global Boost, and that's
just not only the beginning.
So as part of that, in this presentation,
I'll walk you all through the core quantum
principles that makes this possible.
And at the same time, the real world
pilot programs that already in motion, and
also the use cases in payment processing,
fraud detection, and risk management.
So as we move through the next slide,
so here we are going to discuss more
of quantum principles, also the quantum
day or like how it is approaching
and also the global initiatives.
So to start with on I would say like a
quick primer on the quantum computing.
It just more of not just a theory
anymore, at least for finance now.
So at its core the quantum
computing operates very differently
from classical machines now.
So instead of traditional bits
that are either zero or one,
like the quantum bets or qubits.
That can still exist in more of
a super position way that is both
zero and one at the same time.
So that is the difference here.
So combining this with the entanglement
and the interference, we can get a
system that can explore massive solutions
and also the spaces in parallel.
So what does this mean for finance?
So it means we can solve problems that are
currently in traceable or like optimizing.
I would say, global payment route.
So it's more of simulating
economic systems and also
detecting the fraud in real time.
So now you may have heard of QD
if not, so the QD is the moment
when the quantum computers.
Surpasses the classical
ones in commercial utility.
So that day is almost
approaching faster than expected.
So we are seeing a lot of breakthroughs
in error correction, stability and
qubit scaling from major players
like IBM, Google and D-Wave.
And that's not just a thing,
it's more of not just the tech
chains pushing the frontier.
Even the financial institutions
are getting involved too.
So one key initiative is by the
Bank of International Settlements.
It's called BIS.
So working with the central
Banks of France and Germany on a
more of a quantum leap project.
So it's more focused on transforming
cross border settlements and also
more of in a monetary infrastructure.
So as we move through the next slide
here, we are going to more of talk
about the fundamentals and also
different kinds of payment systems.
So here this.
I would say here, it more likely
works as a foundation of why quantum
really matters in the payments.
So the quantum computers use qubits, which
can exist in multiple states at once.
So I would say the quantum
properties like super provision and
entanglement that we were discussing
earlier, they give the ability.
To solve problems exponentially
faster than the classical mission.
So in payments, that means we can
optimize routing, detect fraud faster,
and also they handle massive transaction
volumes and it's just not theoretical.
The, and as I was mentioning, the Bank
of International Settlements is already
leading the real world pilots focused
on cross border quantum payments.
So these early experiments are
helping shape the quantum ready
infrastructure for tomorrow.
So now let's explore how this impacts
payments, speed and processing in general.
So as we move through the next
slide here, we discuss about the
accelerating this payment processing.
So this is where the quantum systems.
Start dwelling, real visible
impact, I'd say accelerating
payment processing end to end.
So traditionally payments
move in batch cycles, so often
delayed by processing windows.
Also like the settlement queues and
also the routing inefficiencies.
So with quantum computing, we are
looking at a more real time or
even microsecond level transaction.
So leap that changes how money flows.
Across the globe.
So through quantum enhanced routing,
payment systems can instantly evaluate
billions of possible paths and
select the most efficient one, and
also the factoring in the currency
conversion, regulatory constraints,
and also the network conditions.
So on a global scale, this means
the seamless optimization across
banks, regions, and also the digital
networks minimizes this friction
and also maximizes the speed.
So finally the impact on the
settlement speed is more prevalent now.
So I would say more important
and at the same time more, I
would say like much required.
So what currently takes hours or days
can even be reduced to milliseconds or
microseconds, dramatically improving
this liquidity, reducing risk, and
also the enhancing the customer
experience so the quantum doesn't
just makes the payments faster.
It also makes the entire financial
networks smarter and more
adaptive and also future ready.
So the next slide we are going
to discuss about enhanced
fraud and detection prevention.
As part of being feature ready is
just more of staying ahead of threat.
So quantum computing enables
an entirely new level of fraud
detection with quantum sorting.
So we can process massive financial data
sets in real time detecting anomalies,
patterns, and also the risk factor.
Than even before.
And also making it faster.
So instead of waiting for
fraud to occur, the real time
monitoring allows us to flag.
Suspicious activity even before
the transaction's complete.
So this is proactive and at the
same time reactive security as well.
So then when it comes to a ML, so a ML
stands for like anti-money laundering.
So the quantum analytics.
Vastly improve how we identify and trace
this suspicious financial behaviors
even across the complex transaction
chains and also the hidden networks.
So with Quantum, we are no
longer limited by scale or speed.
We are entering an era where
fraud detection becomes instant
intelligent and also global.
So how do we see the, this transformation
can happen in the management, right?
So it just doesn't stop with fraud.
So Quantum's power extends
deep into financial risk
management, reshaping how we.
Assess price and predict
risk at every level.
And also at the top of the stack
is the portfolio optimization.
So the quantum systems can analyze
massive combinations of assets,
constraints, and also the market
variables producing optimal strategies
in microseconds, not just ours.
So next is the asset pricing.
So where the traditional model simplify
to make calculations more tractable.
But.
Quantum algorithms can incorporate far
more variables leading to the quantum
level precision in the valuation.
The next thing, what we
have is the risk assessment.
So whether I'd say like whether in
the market credit or operational risk
quantum tools allow us to simulate
uncertainty at scale, improving
accuracy and response time for risk
managers, and also finally, the
consumer analytics with behavioral data.
Exploding the quantum computing helps
us understand customer patterns and
the preferences in more real time,
way, powering more personalized
and predictive financial services.
So altogether, this is just, I. Not
like an upgrade that we are looking
at in speed, but it's more of like
a paradigm shift in how financial
institutions quantify and manage risk.
So the next important thing would be the
security that we are going to discuss.
So when we come to the security
aspect I would say welcome,
quantum computing opens the door to
massive financial transformations.
As we were discussing earlier, it also
introduces the security issues, what
we call the Quantum Security Paradox
at the at the heart of its encryption.
So the financial systems rely on
RSA and also the ECC cryptographic
methods so that quantum computers can
break with enough qubits and time.
What we really consider secure
today could become more.
Instantly vulnerable in
a post quantum world.
So even more concerning is the
rise of the harvest attacks.
So these involve bad actors
collecting the encrypted data with
the intention of decrypting it later.
But once the quantum capabilities
catch up, these includes these
sensitive transactions, personal
data, even inter bank communications.
That's why building a quantum
safe infrastructure is more
required and urgent, I would say.
And financial institutions need to adopt
post quantum cryptography and also the
algorithms resistant to quantum attacks.
So this gives a more of a beginning
of the transactions before quantum
computers reach the full maturity.
So the security aspects must
evolve parallel with innovation.
Otherwise, the very technology that
empowers finance could also expose it.
So as we see here, so when we
discuss the total adoption, how it
is right now, it looks at different
industries are trying to adopt this.
And also at the same time
different industries as in
like in the financial sector.
So the financial institutions which
are running experiments with the
quantum applications especially
in the payment processing and
also the portfolio modeling.
So these.
Pilots, help them understand performance
integration and scaling challenges.
So the payment networks are just stepping
up so that the focus will be more on
developing quantum safe protocols to
ensure future proof, encryption and
also the secure transaction flows.
Meanwhile.
The central banks are exploring
how quantum can enhance settlement
systems, reduce latency in clearing
process, and also improve global
liquidity alignment, of course.
The implementation season, just
without challenges, but qubits remain
fragile, hardware is evolving and also
the timelines are still uncertain.
But with these pilots are
planting the seeds for quantum
native financial infrastructure.
So what is the takeaway as we see here?
So we are more beyond curiosity.
We are in the more of experimentation era.
So and so like those who start now
will have a serious competitive edge
with the qu the quantum computing as
it more matures in the overall system.
So how do we prepare for
the quantum payment future?
So as we see we, it's more of,
starts with a strategic roadmap.
The financial institutions
are beginning to define what
quantum readiness looks like.
So from assessing the talent,
they need to identify where
quantum can create the most value.
So there's more about like
long-term capability building,
not just short-term pilots.
So next is the regulatory frameworks.
As with any technical shift in
finance, standards and compliance
must evolve and, both ways.
So the government, central banks, and
also the industry bodies will play
more critical role in shaping these
policies and setting these benchmarks.
And also the supporting safe innovation.
And finally, the transition
planning is the key here.
So we can't flip.
A switch from old to
new systems overnight.
So a phased approach, starting with
hybrid models and gradually introducing
post quantum cryptography is the most
practical and secure path forward.
So the institutions, that start
preparing today will be best
positioned to lead tomorrow.
So quantum isn't just coming,
it's like just accelerating.
And the financial sector also
must mask keep up with the
peace I. As we conclude here.
So what I would like to say is that
the timeline is pretty clear, as we
have discussed in the previous slide.
So within the next decade, the quantum
computing will transform how the
payments work, making them exponentially
faster, smarter, and more secure.
So the early adopters, those who
experiment, invest, and plan today
will gain a massive competitive edge.
These institutions won't just.
Keep up with the change,
they'll also help define it.
And most importantly, the leap
isn't just about the systems.
I say it's more about people,
how they can adopt to it.
So the customer experience
will be reimagined, the instant
transactions, predictive security,
the seamless cross border transfers.
The trust and also the
convenience at a whole new level.
But to get there, we definitely
need a good strategic planning now.
So from encryption, upgrades
to the workforce readiness from
policy to platform, there's
general requires foresight,
coordination, and a bold leadership.
So quantum isn't just a
technological evolution, it's a
financial revolution going forward.
So it's time we start looking
forward and built towards that.
Thank you so much for the attention
and I'm happy to answer any questions
and I'm happy to get connected on
LinkedIn if anyone is interested to
know more about how quantum computing
is really revolutionizing and how it is
getting really adopted in some systems.