Three.
And by professional, I'm a data
scientist and ai enthusiast, but more
importantly, a builder by the experience.
For over the last two decades, I have
been deep in the trenches of data
battling on-prem like the bottlenecks
to navigating the cloud migrations.
Implementing AI systems across
different industries and now exploring
how quantum integr land and photonic.
Can unlock the dimensions of
computations we have only dreamed off.
If you have ever struggled to get
faster insights from your data or
if you have watched AI models play
to due to compute constraints,
this talk definitely is for you.
I'm going to walk through the real
world quantum algorithm, not just as
a mathematical novelties, but as a
game changer, as a game-changing tool.
Of it for a problem solving
optimization and innovations.
Will it a technical yes, but
it'll also be human because behind
every algorithm is a decision.
And behind every decision is submission.
Let's equal that together.
And by end of this session you will
definitely walk away with a foundational
understanding of quantum computing
insights into the real world business
cases, and clarity on where this.
Field is headed to, and how
can you be the product of?
So now I little bit discuss about myself
and you know a bit about me and let's
talk about what are you going to walk
away with in this next 30 minutes.
I'm not here to throw a kind of
like a expertise jargon on you.
My goal is to make sure that every
person who is watching this, whether
you are a researcher, you're a cloud
architecture product leader, or just
a quantum curious walk away with.
Something actionable and understandable.
You will grasp how quantum computing
truly differs from the classical systems
and what make quantum logic so powerful.
We will break down
Shor's algorithm growers.
Search and near hybrid approaches,
and you will actually see in the
production today, and from drug
discovery to fraud detection.
I will share with where quantum
is already being piloted and where
is headed because yes, some of.
Or what you hear out there is
hype, but a lot is a real, we will
distinguish fact from the fiction.
So you don't need to be a
quantum expert to get this.
You just need to be curious and
open, and if you are, I promise
that you will leave this session 10
steps ahead of where you started.
The greatest enemy of the
knowledge is not ignorance.
It is that illusion of knowledge.
I love this code from Stephen Hawing.
And Stephen Hawing is now just
about talking about the science.
He was talking about human nature.
We stop asking questions when we think
we are, already know the answer, and that
mindset has held back technology for that.
Okay.
Most of us have grown up believing
that all computers work the same way.
We process ones and zeros.
They follow instructions and
with more speed and memory,
they solve the bigger problems.
That model called Non Newman
architecture invented in 1940s has
taken us from floppies to the cloud
computing and is the foundation of.
Everything they use today, your
phone, your laptop, even I models.
But there is a cache.
It has limits.
And we have started to
hit those limits now.
And nature doesn't
compute in ones and zeros.
Nature is messy.
Probably stick nonlinear
at the atomic level there.
Things are not just on and off.
They exist in multiple states at once.
They influence each other without
touching, and they behave in
ways that seems irrational,
but are deeply mathematical.
So that to stimulate the nature to
model a molecule or understanding
quantum physics or solve the
certain optimization problems, we
can't keep using classical logic.
That trying to paint
the ocean with a pencil.
In, in, in 2019, world Quantum processor,
smore performed a computational
computation called random circuit
Sampling is not just a useful problem.
It is extremely hard for classic
computers Second, or solve it in.
In a 200 seconds, IBM argued their
classical supercomputer could
have done in two per five days.
But even that is a stack difference,
whether it was 200 seconds or 2,
2, 2 days versus 10,000 years, that
the point is classical computing
is not always the fastest tool.
Sometimes it's not even
the right tool as well.
So its quantum computing does not
replace the classic old computers.
It.
It compliments them by solving a
new class of problems that rely
on principles like superposition,
entanglement, and interference.
That's what we will explore today, what
quantum algorithms are, why they matter,
where they are being used, and how they
will change everything from crypto.
To the chemistry to ai.
So let's first understand from the ground
up, what makes quantum computing different
and why Everyone from IBM to nasa, I.
To startups like Zendo in
investing in this space.
Let's start with a simple
classical computer, like a phone
in your pocket or a server In the
cloud is a built on bits, right?
Each bits hold a value, either
zero or one, just two options
just like a live switch.
So it's either on or off.
This is the digital logic.
We have used since every
program, every video.
Every AI model made of billions of those
switches flipping on and off really fast.
But the quantum computers use
qubits, which is quantum bit.
And these behave very differently instead
of just being zero and one A can be both.
Both at the same time.
And this is called superposition.
It's like a spin point, whether
it's in the air or it's not head.
Not tails, but it's both.
Only when you measure it
does collapse into one.
Now imagine like you had two
spinning points in front of you,
but they are somehow entangled.
Meaning whatever outcome you get, no
one will instantly affect the others
no matter how far apart they are.
Einstein called this spooky
action at a distance, and this
is the magic of entanglement.
When you combine superposition and
entanglement, you can represent
and process many states at once.
A classical bait gives you one calculation
at a time, but in quantum based.
Cubits can represent
two possibility at once.
So that means two cubits, four state,
three cubits, eight and 10 cubits
already over 1,300 cubits, more
state at the au atom in the universe.
So now to be clear,
this is not just magic.
You still have to run a smart
algorithm to extract the right answer.
You don't just get all
the answer for free.
Quantum computing is not
about doing everything faster.
It's about doing certain
problems differently.
Problems like factoring factoring
massive numbers, simulating molecules,
optimizing delivery rules or training.
Quantum enhanced AI models.
Where the solution space is.
So vast classical machines hit evolve.
So classical computers is like
walking through every hallway
in a giant means, one at a time.
Quantum computing is like entering all the
hallways at once, but using interference.
Veterans to cancel out the wrong
paths and amplify the right ones.
The key concepts to remember are here
in this specific slide is superposition.
Abit can be many things at once.
In second is ments.
Keywords can build link beyond the space.
And number three is interference which
is used to find useful answer from noise.
So with these two quantum computer,
don't just calculate the explore.
Now let's go to the next slide,
which is a quantum advantage.
That, so that, now that we understand
what makes quantum computing different,
the real question is whether or
where does it matter what problems?
Actually solve better than
the classical computer.
The term we use is quantum advantage,
which means that quantum computing
solving problem faster or more
efficiently than the best classic
com computer supercomputer ever can.
So even with the unlimited time
and the memory there is not.
Theoretical in 2019, Google claimed that
quantum advantage for the first time
using a random circle sampling task.
While the usefulness of the task
was debated, the milestone was
clear for their specific problem.
Google computers simply couldn't keep up.
And let me break it down.
Like simulation of those quantum
systems and nature itself is a quantum.
So if we, if you want to simulate
in atoms, molecules, or materials
using plastic computers is like
translating poetry with a calculator.
So quantum computers are built
on the same physics, so they can
actually naturally simulate chemical
interactions, energy steers, and the
molecule bonding things that require
approximations on classical machines.
This has a huge implications for drug
discovery, material designs, and even
the sustainable energy development.
These show up and these shows up
everywhere, logistics, finance, traffic
systems, and even from machine learning,
hyper parameter tuning as well.
Classical servers like linear
programming are logistic are fast,
but they often hit the local minimal
or something that will limit not the
best solution, just a nearby one.
So quantum algorithms like the quantum
RO made optimization algorithm, which is
qa OA expo exponent exponentially more
options in parallel in offer offering
a global solution ensures algorithm
is developed in 1994 is perhaps one
of the most famous quantum algorithm.
It can factor large numbers at.
Exponentially faster than
the classical matters.
And why does that matter?
Because modern encryptions like
RSA is based on the assumption
that a factoring is hard.
If large scale quantum machines becomes
practical, encryption will break.
This is why we now talk about post quantum
cryptography, which is already atop.
Top priority for the
national security as well.
And it's very important to clarify that
quantum computer want replace everything.
It is not going to run your
Excel spreadsheet faster or
replace your phone's processor.
It shines very specific domains
problems where the search engines
grows exponentially or where Quantum
Interference gives it is unique.
Computational edge.
Think about searching a for a needle
in a haystack, a classical computer
is checked each straw one by one.
A quantum computer use uses growers
algorithm to search the entire block
or entire haystack in secure route
time which means like problem within
million possibilities can be solved in
about 1000 steps instead of million.
That's not just a speed, but that is
about, you can say, a new kind of a like.
Formula Quantum A is not universal,
but it iss a profound when applied
to the right kinds of problems
As simulation, optimization and
cryptography, quantum computer don't
just offer performance boost, they
offer is the only feasible path forward.
Nowness, I will walk you through.
A compute quantum of computer
in didn't just appear overnight.
It's a product of the DA
Deckers of theory Physics.
And engineering.
Many of them are initially dis
dismissed as impossible or just math.
But here we are.
Just a little bit of a history
in 1981, this all started
from a physicist, Richard.
Famous man who asked a simple
question in 1981, why can't we
simulate physics on a computer?
His answer, because computers are
not built on the law of physics.
But if we could build a computer
that behaves quantum mechanically,
he could simulate nature itself.
And this was a seed and it
launched a whole new field.
Then came the major shockwave in 1994.
Peter Shaw at Dell Labs.
Created an algorithm that could factor the
large number of exp expon exponentially
faster than any classical algorithm.
And this was not just a math
breakthrough, it was a direct threat
to the security of the internet.
Suddenly quantum computing
become not only a curiosity,
but a strategy priority as well.
Then love grower at Bell Labs,
develop an algorithm that will
search and sort databases in.
Scale route time.
This may not sound dramatic but in
the computer science going from ON
to the O scale route and is huge,
especially when n is in the billions.
So truly the early the field
shifted from the theory.
To hardware IBM, Intel and
Startups like D-Wave began
building actual quantum chips.
But they were spec, they were
like a skeptics, like the
main challenge was CIC agile.
They decor easily, even a breeze of
temperature or vibration can corrupt them.
So in 2019 will steam, published
a paper claiming that they have
achieved quantum supremacy, meaning
that their quantum processor solved
a problem that would practically
impossible for a classic computer.
While the use case was narrow,
random circuit sampling
industry milestone was massive.
It, it validated the deckers of the world.
So in less than four years, we have
grown from chalkboard theories.
Two functional computers processes
and that lightning speed compared to
the history of the classic computer.
But remember, we are still early.
We are in the NI SQ era where it's
called NOIs Intermediary Scale quantum.
The chip exists, but they are error
pro and small and still the pace
is accelerating really fast Now
now that we know about the quantum
computing team from let's look at
the algorithms that are turning this
theory into the real world impact.
And let's, okay, a few on algorithms.
The ones so you have
seen how many algorithms?
One is we have already discussed.
One is the hor algorithm.
In 1994, this one cracked the word
open Shor algorithm factors the
large intes exponentially faster
than the classical computer.
And why care?
'cause that's how RSA encryption works.
The backbone of the internet security
and if quantum computer, with enough
stable qubit sixes, it would break RSA
to 2048 in the days, while classical
computers will take millions of years.
So that's why governments are now
investing in post quantum encryption.
And then 1996 of growers algorithms
search a un sort data database.
It's like secure N times
instead of n. That's a quad.
Quad speed up there was like quad ready,
speed up and in the fields like machine
learning or bioinformatic, this can
save a number of years in competition.
Quantum approximate optimization
algorithm QA oh eight is a
hybrid algorithm is planned.
The classic classical and quantum
processing rate for the real
world optimization tasks like
the be routing and network.
De balancing and even the
financial financial mining as well.
Vibration quantum, which is VQE, is used
in the quantum industry, is estimates the
ground, state or energy of the molecules.
That means faster drug designs,
material innovation, and even
sustainable energy discovery.
So there are not sci-fi ideas.
They are already being tested on
IBM ion q Extendo, and others.
Quantum metal.
We don't want replace classical one
at all, but they will just unlock
what classical core cannot reach.
Use cases that, how is quantum
computing being used right now?
Let's look at some few sectors
that are not just experimenting,
but they're investing as well.
One of the companies like pharmaceutical
company, Roche and AstraZenca,
are partnering with a quantum
startups to simulate molecules and
predict protein folding something
classical computer can do at scale.
Quantum help identify drug
viable drug candidates faster.
Potential, say billions in r and d and
speed speeding up the time to market.
In finance industry firms like
Goldman SaaS and JP Morgan Chase are
exploring Quantum for optimizing the
answers portfolios and running Monte
Carlo simulation more efficiently.
These problem have expo
exponential complexity.
Quantum algorithms offer a better
way to explore risk scenarios
and logistics and supply chain.
Volkswagen and DHL are testing
quantum systems for traffic flow
optimization and road planning,
especially where classical computer
or classical systems get overwhelmed.
By too many variables.
The even one minute of save time
per vehicle can scale into millions
in the savings in energy sector.
ExxonMobil and BASF exploring the
quantum chemistry to discover better
catalyst for cleaner fuel production
and energy storage can simulate chemical
reactions that will take classical
supercomputers centuries to approximate.
Quantum computing is already
used in narrow high impact tasks.
Not to run your website but to reshape
definitely r and d, your supply
chain and your competitive edge.
Most of the quantum computers used
today, superconducting, cubics.
The tiny electrical circles cool
to near absolute zero, but there is
another approach gaining traction is
called photo toning quantum computing.
So instead of electrons
or ions, it's use photons.
Practic, there was a kind
of like particles of light
to represent the qubits.
Photons are naturally quantum.
They do not interact with their
environment easily, which means
they are less prone to noise or
any kind of like decoherence.
So one of the biggest challenge in
quantum hardware is like that un
unlike superconducting cubs for Tony.
Can operate at room temperature
and use existing fiber optical
infrastructure as well.
And the same tech in our internet cables.
So pump is x do in Canada and PSI
Quantum, which is in the US and UK, are
building the full scale quantum processor
based on the photo photon photonic.
Nic Alexander's Boreal
system was the first.
Photonic quantum computer to
demonstrate the sampling of the scale.
And this is very specific,
very hard problem.
But it proved that that photonic chip
can are not just theoretical, but
it's extremely practical as well.
But it still face some challenges.
Generating and manipulating single
photons reli reliably is really tough.
And building logic gates using
light alone is not as mature
as superconducting tech yet.
So if we crack scalable photonic
compute quantum com, we get faster,
cheaper, and most robust quantum
systems, and we can build them using
the same optical com components.
Already mass produced today.
And now let's talk about what
quantum computing can't you yet,
because we are still very in early
in any innings of this field.
Cubis are very fragile.
They lose their quantum
state within microseconds.
It is, this is called decoherence.
So even the tiniest heat or for
the vibration can throw them off.
This is why Quantum error correction
is one of the biggest bottleneck.
To get one reliable, logical curate,
you might need hundreds or even
thousands of the physical curate.
Today, quantum computers are called
some of the devices, which is noise
and power tolerance is missed.
Devices, noisy, intermediate
scale, quantum they work, they
are not fully far tolerance yet.
You can run small experiments, but
scaling them is still a hurdle.
Super connecting systems
can need extreme cooling.
Trapped I is needed trapped s lasers.
Photonic chips needs
precise light control.
And all these platforms have
strengths, but no one has
solved the scale challenge yet.
So most fundamental with them
today are still explore theory
but for many real word problems.
We haven't yet proven a quantum solution
that is truly better than the classical.
So there are there are,
there is also a high bubble.
Some companies make quantum solutions
that are not quantum at all.
As researchers and builders we have
to separate the science from the pr.
So yes, the potential is massive,
but we are not there yet.
We are not in the charge g PT
moment of quantum computing,
but this is a D tech field.
It's not just a finished
product and that's okay.
Is the internet.
To doctors as well, to to
come into the production.
So now we have to talk where we are today.
Now so where exactly are we?
Quantum roadmap?
The answer is early,
but accelerating fast.
So we are in NISQ era, which is a
noisy, intermediate scale quantum.
This means that we have real
machines, but they are noisy,
limited in the scale and not hot.
Torrance yet.
So not enough for full
cryptographic breakthroughs, but
enough for the experimentation.
Hybrid models and early
optimization trials.
There was a commercial pilots alive.
Big pharma like the pharma, finance
and logistics are running parallel or
limited powers to test world viability.
And then we are probably five
to 10 years from full scales
for orange quantum system.
But if you wait until then to start,
you will be too late in this race.
Now the quantum hardware landscape,
let's quickly talk about what's
under the hood, because not all the
quantum computers are built the same.
There are four main types of
the quantum hardware platform.
Number one is superconducting
qubits, which is used by IBM, Google.
They are fast but extreme but extreme
cooling for the near term you can say.
Experiment.
Then we have a second tab is a trapped
ion, which is used by Iron Q in Honeywell.
More stable and precise,
but slower GA speed.
Then we have for Tony quantum computers
like X extendo, A PSI, quantum, it's
leveraged the light room temperature,
great long term scalability.
Then we have neutral atoms
and topological qubits.
Used by QRL and Microsoft.
Still early stage, but
promising for error resistance.
So the race is not just over, we just
don't know which architecture will win,
but the diversity of the approaches
is what make this space so dynamic.
Here is what I will just
a little bit about that.
Where is still heading in
the next five to 10 years?
Let's break it down.
So by 25, 22, 28.
And then SQ maturity is that more stable?
Ubes Hybrid quantum classical models
become common in r and d environments.
From 2028 to 2023 to 32 error bracket
quantum computers, we will likely see
the first 1000 plus large cubit system
capable of be beating classical in
real production and post 2032 quantum
integration into cloud ecosystem, which
will be like quantum will become a service
embedded into AI and analytical stats.
And you will call it from an
API or like any other tool.
So we are moving from lab experimenting
to infrastructure grade tools like ai.
The winner won't just be like
those who build the tag, but those
who learn how to apply it early.
You don't need a PhD in physics to start
building quantum application today.
There are, these are tools.
Many are free and I'll let you experiment
right now in the cloud as well.
One is what I. Personally use as
well is IBM, which is a Python
based open source and back with
a real hardware on the IBM Cloud.
IBM, quantum Cloud, and
then we have a Google CIRQ.
Great for the NS algorithms,
especially the quantum circuits.
Microsoft Q Hash as Azure Quantum,
which is built for the hybrid
quantum classical workflows.
Then we have a Amazon bracket
native is connected to the
multiple hardware brackets.
IQ Rage, JT and Fops Ford.
And then we have a x. Spanning lane,
which is focused on the quantum
machine learning, integrates well
with the PyTorch and the tensor flow.
And whether the Azure data scientist
developer, or just curious you
can access the real quantum
hardware from your act today.
And I will say here's what I want to walk
away with today in three clear takeaways.
Quantum is not magic.
It's a math plus physics and
engineering and a blend of ai,
but it change what's possible.
Problems.
We thought unsolved people
are now being modeled.
We are still early, but not too early.
You don't have to wait for
perfection to get involved.
The learning curve has already begun.
The future will be hybrid, classical
and quantum AI and physics.
Quote and light.
And those who cannot connect,
those words will definitely
need now to start work on that.
Because if you connect these all doors
together today, that you will definitely,
there will high chances of leading.
And if there is one thing I hope this
talk did is I hope that give, that
this give you clarity, not confusion
and curiosity, not kind a fear.
And most importantly, a recent.
As well.
Thank you so much for your time and
your patience, and thank you all.
Thank you for being here.
Truly.
I know this is a complex topic, but the
fact that you showed up tells tell me
that you're not afraid of the complexity.
You are here to lead the
future, not just wait for it.
So if to spark any kind of
ideas, a question or even
doubts let's stay connected.
I share a lot on LinkedIn and I love.
Stalking shop, whether it's quantum ai,
data architecture, cryptocurrency, or
blockchain or wherever is converging.
So you can find me in the
Sara Chori or directly as well
from the LinkedIn messages.
And you can check me on
link Trace slash Sara Chori.
Quantum computing is not
just about faster answers.
It's not is about asking the
deeper questions and that's
where the transformation begins.
Thank you very much.