Hello all.
Good morning.
Good afternoon, and good evening.
This is Lex McCann Kumar, an executive
Director at JPMorgan Chase Bank.
This is for Con 42 Quantum Computing
2025 event, and the topic is bridging
classical and quantum computing.
Let's start with a quote.
Quantum Computing is not going
to be a replacement for the
classical com completing.
It's rather it's a transformation.
Classical to comp quantum
computing and how we use it.
So the kind of fundamentals is
your mind mindset should shift
considering it as a co-existence
instead of as a competition between
the classical and quantum computing.
The reality is the shift is real and there
are already major players like A-W-S-I-B-M
and Azure have quantum computing areas.
Example as the A WS bracket, IBM,
quantum and Azure Quantum, and there are
almost more than a hundred plus quantum
related patents filed in 2023 alone.
And there are many startups and
enterprises, r and Ds prototyping,
hybrid workflows between the
classical and a quantum computer.
It started with as a theory and it has
become a lab and now it's all cloud native
APOs available for quantum computing.
And these are all the proof points.
And let's think about what's between
the classical and the quantum
and what are the emerging needs.
The classical system is well known
for its performance, optimization,
security, and reliability.
The emerging needs, while we are
shipping or running in a hybrid
model of classical and quantum, would
be quantum for the combin material
optimization, machine learning
acceleration, and molecule simulation.
We need to have an interface to.
Have the classical event talked
to the quantum, using the driven
event driven pipelines, and to start
with, for enterprise architect to
know how and what needs to be done.
Here are some of the fundamentals
that we need to think about.
So the quantum 1 0 1 for classical
architectures, the quantum core
principles is about qubits,
super position, entanglement and
interference, and we need to understand.
The classical computing works on
binary, which are zeros or one, but the
quantum is, can have a state which is
simultaneously either a zero and a one.
So it's also more than more
as a probabilistic state
than as a binary state.
So your our thinking thought process
should change, of considering a
status as either or for as a binary
instead as a probabilistic state.
Next, what are all the challenges
we have in this journey of com?
Starting from the classical
to the quantum computing?
So the current state of the
quantum computing doesn't fit
into our existing DevOps stacks.
Major missing pieces are the job
orchestration, state isolation for quantum
workloads, and also the latency tolerance.
So these are the problems that needs
to be solved, but I'm sure in the near
future it'll be eventually solved and
it will be in a very mature state.
The next thing, let's talk about how a
hybrid architecture for a quantum and
a classical computing works together.
So your application layer, the first
tier could be all microservices with
the APIs and in your middle tier or
your orchestration layer could be
for quantum job routers and cubes.
And the lower backend services
could be, classical computing
and also quantum computing, or a
combination of both of them together.
So overall, still the problem for
quantum not fitting into the DevOps stack
is there, but still these models are
workable and there are prototypes and
solutions being done based on this model.
Next, the major design patterns.
What we need to consider for our
quantum computing area would be
quantum as a service, just like we have
infrastructure as a service, software as
a service, and everything as a service.
Quantum as a service is another same
pattern that's primarily being considered.
And also we have to consider all
the quantum triggers from the
classical event cues like a calf cup.
So when we club between the
classical and the quantum.
The communication medium could be a
popup model where the classical can be
producing an event to which a quantum
needs to react based on the event
that has, that classical has produced.
And we also need to be
predominantly working on the server
serverless, quantum microservices.
That's like a cell lambda, what we
have a lambda can trigger AWS bracket.
Next the middleware integration layer,
what we talked about earlier the main
responsibilities for those area will
be on the session management job cuing,
and the error ries result normalization.
So the strategy would be to solve
this problem area to decouple the
quantum logic from the orchestra logic.
So we should not combine them
as a single com computation.
Instead, it should be a two different
segregation of duty and major tools as
I mentioned earlier that would be used
would be the a s bracket, SDK, the on
time ci, GRPC and bridgers, and many
more out there in the queue Now with.
Cloud Naivity being the
forerunner at this point of time.
The cloud native abstraction for
the quantum area could be in the
areas of like containers running
quantum for local simulations.
Or you can have a ka jobs runners
which can orchestrate your quantum
flows and your serverless options.
As I mentioned earlier, the A DW Lambda.
Along with the bracket trigger and
the DevOps quantum job linking CA
CD4 quantum kernels in the future.
So these are the cloud native
abstraction that needs to be considered.
And the more important thing of whether
it is a classical or a quantum, would be
on the security interoperability, abso
and security, as I as mentioned in the
slide, you can see the authentication
across classical and quantum.
Ty should be.
We taken care very well.
It should be a zero trust model.
The interoperability between the
classical and the quantum would be
the protocol Standard issues like the
QAR and the open quo vendor neutral
interfaces are very important for the
interoperability will be much easier and
the observability will be for telemetry
for the quantum jobs and the integration
with the Prometheus and open telemetry,
just like how we have integrated them
in the classical computing today.
Here is a practical roadmap for
the enterprises to consider.
First, the step one would be identifying
the quantum able problems, like
example, like a scheduling machine,
learning model, tuning and more.
And the step two, after once we have
identified, is to build a dev sandbox
for the emulators for the quantum.
And once the emulators are
already, the third step would be to
integrate with chop orchestration.
Message buses.
So this message I mentioned earlier
will be the one we should be to
come a hybrid communication between
the classic and the quantum.
And the step four would be to come to
the pilot state where we have a hybrid
service, non-critical, in a non-critical
path, and gradually promotion towards
the production workflows as a step five.
And that will be Itrate next future.
Now, once we have all this in.
Happening in our hybrid model the
end state or the future state.
To have a non-destructive strategy would
be to have how we integrate modularly
or adapt layers to existing system,
and at the same time minimize the risk
using the polyglot as DGen simulators.
As well as a mature
hybrid, CACD pipelines.
So the goal would be to experiment
without rewriting the stack.
We should be maturing into the stage where
this hybrid model will works well or any
problems that will, we want to solve.
Further to that, the next five
years or even less is about the, is
not about the quantum dominating.
It's about.
Quantum augmentation along with our
classical, it's not a replacement.
As I said at the beginning, it is going
to be in conjunction with our classical.
The quantum also will be working
and solving the problem much better
than just the classical solving
or just the quantum solving.
And with that, we come to a end
and thank you for the opportunity.
Thank you all.