Hey all.
Today I'm here to talk about
quantum accelerated storage Systems.
As enterprises data
volumes grow exponentially.
Traditional storage and processing
systems are struggling to keep
pace with the demands of realtime
analytics, mission learning, unsecured
the data management in response.
Quantum computing is emerging
as a transformative force
redefining our enterprise store
retrieve and process data.
One of the most promising innovations
in this space is the development of
quantum accelerated storage systems.
Let me introduce about myself.
I'm go lead solutions architect solutions
specialist in the cloud engineering area.
I have around 17 years of experience
specifically focusing in data
engineering with a focus on cloud
technologies and automations.
I have consistently pioneered innovative
solutions that bridge technology gaps
and deliver measurable business impact.
My career has been defined by
developing cutting edge data
pipelines, cloud architectures that
have transformed operations across.
Multiple service lines such as healthcare,
insurance, and financial services.
I speared the implementation of
cloud-based data lake solutions that
revolutionized how organizations
can handle large scale of data
and storing them accordingly.
Let's move on to the topic the Quantum
Max accelerated storage Systems.
By integrating quantum processing units
pus with I based speed memory systems
and the classical infrastructure, the
enterprises can unlock unprecedented
performance for workloads such as realtime
fraud deduction, large scale and training.
Furthermore, quantum algorithms
applied to data storage can optimize.
Hierarchical memory usage,
improve error correction, and
enable more efficient data.
Lifecycle management as a technology may
choose quantum accelerated storage systems
or poise to become em cornerstone of next
generation enterprise data architectures
offering not only speed and efficiency,
but also new capabilities for secure,
intelligent and scalable data ecosystems.
Moving on the crisis faced by the
enterprises in the current world and
also addressing the storage crisis
they're facing how to handle efficiently
with the quantum computing storage.
Modern enterprises are phasing and
escalating data storage crisis, right?
Fueled by the as you can see in
the slide with the numbers, the
explosion of big data, IOTA and
realtime analytics organizations are
generating petabytes of data daily.
Traditional storage architectures
designed for sequential predictable
workloads are increasingly unable to
cope up with the sheer scale velocity
and the complexity of today's data.
Thereby comes the limitations
of traditional storage
architectures, such as scalability.
The bottlenecks, classical storage
systems scale linearly and as
therefore grows performance degrades.
Adding more storage often
leads to increased latency
and management complexities.
Number two would be
inefficient data retrieval.
Traditional indexing and retrieval
mechanisms struggle with high dimensional,
unstructured, or fragmented data.
Number three would be
constant energy consumption.
Maintaining large scale classical
storage requires significant energy
and infrastructure investment.
So the quantum storage, the paradigm
shift, we could say, because
this quantum computing offers a
fundamentally different approach to
data storage processing by exploiting.
Quantum states and prob computation.
Quantum accelerated storage
systems can address the limitations
of classical architectures
through several key innovations.
Moving on.
Quantum computing the
foundations for storage, right?
There are several foundations.
So we will go through briefly about
it Now, number one would be quantum
machine learning algorithms can
significantly enhance quantum computing
foundations for storage by enabling
enabling the intelligent data.
Coding, retrieval,
optimization and management.
These algorithms combine quantum
computing parallelism with machine
learnings, adaptability, helping
create smarter, faster, and
more efficient storage systems.
So there are key QML algorithms,
right machine learning algorithms
relevant to quantum story systems
along with how each contributes,
such as quantum K nearest neighbors.
Which is qk and N. The purpose of it
is classify or retrieve data points
based on similarity, and the storage
use case would be answers the past
and intelligent retrieval of data
from quantum memory by identifying
the most similar or relevant records.
So the advantage would be offers
a potential exponential speed
up in high dimensional space.
And the second would be quantum
support Vector machines Q svm.
The purpose of is finding the optimal
decision boundaries in the complex data.
The use case would be useful
for categorizing stored data for
compression, deduplication, or tiering.
As we could say, as an
example, art versus cold data.
So the advantage, the kernel
functions are computed exponentially
faster than in classical SVMs,
quantum resistant cryptography.
It can be called a p qc.
These are the frameworks are essential
for securing data in the future where
quantum computers may be capable
of breaking traditional public key
crypto systems such as RCDC and ECC.
When designing storage systems,
especially within quantum computing
foundations, this frameworks ensure
confidentiality, even quantum advers.
So we can say as a breakdown of the
main quantum resistant cryptographic
frameworks you can consider is for
secure storage systems, lattice based
cryptography, code based cryptography,
multi-variable polynomial cryptography.
These are the main, mechanisms,
we can use as a framework.
Quantum Ling is a specialized
form of quantum computing, right?
Designed to solve optimization
problems by leveraging quantum
channeling and superposition.
While it's traditionally used for general
purpose cryptographic or data storage
mechanisms, still it can be applied to
optimized aspects of storage systems
in quantum computing foundations.
And the last would be quantum
classical hybrid systems.
What it is, it's a system where
quantum computing handles parts
of a problem that benefit from
superposition and or tunneling.
We can say the examples
as optimization sampling.
Classical computing handles IO
control, flow, memory, and tasks
not suitable for quantum processing.
These systems do not store
quantum data directly.
That's the beauty of it.
Since quantum memory is not yet scalable,
but we can optimize on secure classical
storage systems using quantum techniques.
On what are the different
case studies, right?
In the quantum computing
world to storage systems.
So we go to explore about that.
The case studies, the Fortune 500
enterprises are increasingly adopting
quantum inspired algorithms to
enhance their storage infrastructures,
achieving transformative results
in areas such as optimization,
risk management, and data security.
So we can see some notable
case studies, right?
Logistics, cybersecurity.
So the company has integrated
quantum inspired algorithms within
its cloud services to optimize a
logistics and bolster cybersecurity.
By leveraging quantum techniques, company
enhances its recommendation systems and
strengthens data production measures,
ensuring efficient and service operation.
Across its vast e-commerce platform.
Then either you're leading car company,
which optimizes the traffic right?
Company in collaboration with Microsoft
has utilized quantum inspired algorithms
to address traffic congestion by
simulating vehicle movements and
optimizing routing strategies.
So company achieved a 73% reduction
in congestion and an 8% decrease in
overall commuting time, demonstrating
the potential of quantum inspired
methods in real world applications.
Then the other leading technology
company, which utilizes.
Advancements in the
risk management, right?
Using the quantum.
So it also partnered with Microsoft
to explore the application of
quantum inspired algorithms in risk
management and financial services.
By re-imagining the traditional
modeling techniques, the collaboration
aims to accelerate performance and
redefined problem solving approaches.
PAing the way for more efficient
risk assessment methodologies.
So in a nutshell, these case studies
illustrate how Fortune 500 companies
are leveraging the quantum inspired
algorithms to drive innovation and
achieve significant improvements in the
storage and infrastructure operations.
Moving on, so the quantum
for storage tiering.
Yeah, it's a tiering is a practice
right in the storage world for
organizing data across different
types of storage media categorized
by performance, cost, and durability.
For example, in tier zero NVM
versus CSSD, the cast would be some.
But the performance would be ultra fast.
The use case like the catching
streaming realtime data.
So there is other category in the
tier one, which offers the example
as SSD which will be fast, but not
like tier zero, which is ultra fast.
But we can use frequently access to files.
And moving on to the tier two storage
systems, where we can see the example
as HDD and the performance would
be a little slower, which can be
ideally used for archives and backups.
And the world has method as we
know every, everyone like tape
storage or cold storage, right?
It's very slow, but for the can be used.
So the challenge assign data object.
Correct tier dynamically and efficiently.
Okay.
Now the quantum handling is a method
for finding the global minimum of a
cost function by exploiting quantum
channeling and superposition, it
solves the problem formulated as QUBO.
So it's a quadratic, unconstrained,
binary optimization and ING models.
We can use.
So these D Wave one similar systems
implement quantum handling for
large scale optimization problems.
So the goal of quantum handling for
storage tiring is to minimize the
overall storage cost and the access
latency by finding the optimal mapping
of data blocks to storage tiers.
So subject to constraints like
performance requirements, capacity limits.
On optimization.
Applied.
Basically, it's a quantum enhanced
algorithms to reduce operational,
financial, or resource related costs
in more complex systems, particularly
those involving large scale data and
high dimensional optimization tasks.
Qml combines quantum computing with
classical machine learning to potentially
outperform classical one approaches
in specific problem domains such as
portfolio optimization, supply chain,
cost reduction, energy and storage
infrastructure, cost management,
cloud and compute resource allocation.
Okay, now comes the question, right?
Why we used to use quantum
learning for cost optimization.
Traditional machine learning or
models are powerful, but often
struggled with combinary complex
spaces, exponential time algorithm,
which is the best example for that.
Optimization under constraints,
spas, or high dimensional data.
So quantum algorithms can offer
through quantum parallelism, which is.
We are discussing frequently
about the superposition, faster
convenience in a certain optimization
scenarios, better sampling example
for probabilistic cost estimation.
So machine learning combined
with quantum QL is a rescue area.
What are the benefits of this?
QL radio reduces time to reach
cost efficient strategies, better
modeling of real world systems.
More accurate cost
estimation and forecasting.
These are the three benefits.
Ideally, I could say right on top of the
going on.
What is a quantum resistant
storage, security, quantum computers
can break classical encryption.
Algorithms, algorithms in the security
of the classical encryption such as
RC and EC can be efficiently solved
with short algorithm data stored today
might be decrypted in the future.
So stored sensitive data needs protection
that remains secured in a long term.
So storage systems need to
adapt to post threats for
confidentiality, integrity, and.
Oh, it can be implemented or achieved.
So there comes the post
quantum cryptography.
Pqc.
Cryptographic algorithms believed to
resist quantum attacks because they
rely on all mathematical problems, not
efficiently solvable by quantum computers.
Examples like lattice based examples
such as crystal for encryption crystals
s. And the LA as lattice based as a
code based example is multi-variant
polynomial based and ash based signatures.
So these are some examples of post
quantum cryptography application, how it
can be implemented, encrypt stored data,
authenticate users and device and secure
communication between storage nodes.
So these are the few
applications, right of Pqc.
Quantum safe, random number generation,
so it is one of the security mechanism.
QR entropy, randomness processes
improve key generation quality
and cryptographic strength.
The third one would be quantum resistant
authentication and access control.
So there are certain protocols
that verify users or device
identity without relying on quantum
vulnerable cryptographic methods.
And last would be quantum watermarking.
It's a technique to embed information.
Into data or classical data protected
by quantum resistant methods.
It helps data, authenticity, ownership,
and integrity in a way thats both
classical and quantum attacks.
On the quantum classical hybrid framework.
So what is this?
A framework, right?
So hybrid system, it's an
integration of quantum processors,
as we discussed earlier, QPU and
classical processes, which is CPU,
and collaborative computation.
The classical computer controls
prepares inputs four and processes
output from the quantum computer.
Feedback loop classical algorithms,
guide quantum circuits, parameters,
quantum circuits provide evaluation
results to the classical.
So what is a classical interface layer?
Then?
The definition would
be it's a layer, right?
Responsible for coordinating
and orchestrating interactions
between classical and quantum
parts of your hybrid system.
Then what's the purpose of it?
Yeah.
Enable seamless communication,
translating classical instructions
into your quantum operations,
and returning quantum measurement
results back to classical algorithms.
Then there is another
layer or a framework.
It's a problem translation layer.
It is a layer that takes an abstract
problem or algorithm specifications and
transforms into your quantum computable
representation, such as quantum circuits,
hamiltonians or quadratic unconstrained
binary optimizations formulations, which
we discussed in the last slide, QUBO.
The main purpose of it would be to bridge
the gap between the problem domain and
the Quantum's hardware operational model
and the quantum processing layer.
It is a layer that implements, runs
and management of all these algorithms
related to quantum by controlling
quantum hardwares or simulators.
So the purpose would be to perform
the quantum part of hybrid algorithms,
preparing quantum states, applying
quantum gates, performing measurements,
or running quantum enabling cycles.
And finally comes the integration layer,
the layer the dock states manages and
integrates the various software and
hardware components of your hybrid quantum
classical system into your cohesive hold.
So the purpose of this integration
layer would be having a seamless
interoperability between classical
algorithms, quantum programs, hardware
obstruction, and user interfaces,
enabling complex hybrid applications to
run efficiently, fastly, and reliably.
So what are the implementation results
right across the industry like healthcare,
financial services, and manufacturing?
So we'll take one, right healthcare.
So quantum key distribution, which is
QQED with the quantum resistant storage.
So what is the use case in the
healthcare industry, right?
Secure storage and transmission of.
Primarily the electronic
health records, right?
The medical records, EHRs, and imaging
data, so it's an ideal use case,
QKD and the quantum watermarking.
For medical data integrity, the use case
would be protecting medical images and
genomic data from tampering, quantum
inspired storage optimization algorithms.
Which managing right massive multimodal
healthcare data sets, genomic sequences,
medical imaging, and patient history.
This is one of the wonderful use
case for the storage optimization
algorithms implemented by the quantum.
Then the lastly we could say
securing multi-institution data
sharing via quantum networks.
So the use case, like the collaborative
research right across multiple
healthcare providers such as hospitals
and universities, we can use the
quantum networks in this case.
Moving on to financial services industry.
We could see 41% reduction in
operation storage expenditures while
processing with the four times more
transactional volumes, maintaining
consistent sub five millisecond
retrieval latency for mission critical
applications such as trading platforms
using quantum enhanced encryption
protocols, the manufacturing industry.
As we know very well improving
supply chain data integrity and
traceability would be the primary
objective in the manufacturing area.
But the challenge is complex.
Global supply chains generate
vast amounts of data that must
be accurate and verifiable.
So what is the impact made
by this quantum storage?
So this quantums.
Verify authenticity and prevent
the tampering of supply chain data.
Secure storage of traceability data
supports compliance with quality and
safety standards, so the result is
enhanced trust in supply chain data
integrity, reducing counteract risks,
and ensuring regulatory compliance.
So how can we implementation
perspective, right?
What is a roadmap for
implementing the quantum storage?
So I just segregated into
the different phases.
So the phase one would be the awareness
and strategy where we'll be assessing the
risks and needs, identify the sensitive
data and storage workloads, conduct risk
analysis regarding the quantum threats
such as ours now dec later attacks.
And educate the stakeholders, right?
Train the IT team, security and compliance
teams on quantum computing risks.
Post quantum cryptography, which is pqc
on quantum storage, technical technologies
such as QPD, quantum water marking.
Educate your team.
And defend the objectives.
Clear objectives with the goals.
What are your goals like
improving the data security?
Quantum resistant encryption
comes into play if you were, a
goal is enhance traceability.
Quantum watermarking is there if
the goal is quantum, that means
optimizing the storage efficiency.
Then quantum in algorithms you can.
Phase two would be the
pilot implementation, right?
Such as we can do proof
of concept and planning.
Select one or more pilot areas by
securing the backup encryption using
latest based cryptography, embedding
the quantum watermarks insensitive
files using the quantum handling
technique to optimize storage tiering.
So this is about the phase three.
Execution, the evaluation, right?
When you complete your proof of
concept, implement the pilot, right?
Encrypt store sample dataset
using an quantum methods.
And test it thoroughly.
Using the performance latency,
throughput, compatibility with
existing systems, security under
simulated threats and measure.
The results have a clear defined
metrics right to evaluate where results.
So results always should be measurable
using the encryption decryption
speed, such as data retrieval,
latency, storage, cost savings.
What are the optimization
use cases we have?
And the last phase would be deployment,
the enterprise deployment, right?
In the deployment phase, the
main challenge would be how
to scale up the deployment.
So you extend the quantum resistant
storage methods across if you are
using the cloud or on-prem storage.
Extend it.
I value data sets, right?
Such as customer data,
RD data, regulatory data.
That's about the roadmap
for the implementation.
And yeah, after discussing briefly about
all these quantum storage techniques
and how it can be implemented and what
are the advantages of it, so the key
takeaways for the storage computing in
quantum and what would be the next steps.
So it's a strategic response
to the emerging cyber threats.
So quantum resistant encryption
and quantum key distribution are
essential to protect sensitive data
from future quantum enabled attacks.
And the other key takeaway would
be quantum storage enhances data
integrity and the auditability,
quantum watermarking and quantum
secure digital signatures ensure data.
Tamper detection and traceability
critical for compliance.
Trust under digital forensics and quantum
inspired algorithms, optimize the data
infrastructure and also integration
with classical infrastructure is a key
practical quantum storage solutions today.
Completely, we can say hybrid, right?
Blending classical cloud edge storage
with quantum resistant protocols or
quantum assisted optimization algorithms.
So standardization of quantum
computing in storage and
readiness are still developing.
So NIST is finalizing a post quantum
cryptography, pqc standards, early
adoption positions, companies ahead
of regulatory and competitive curves.
Okay.
What would be the next steps for
organizations exploring quantum storage?
Conduct your quantum readiness assessment
pilot quantum resistant encryption.
Collaborate with quantum vendors, right?
And platforms engage vendors like p
PQS Shield, I-S-A-R-D-I-B-M, quantum or
Azure Quantum, right to access toolkits
and support, join consortiums like
Quantum Economic Development Consortium.
We would say QED dash CE tsi,
quantum Monitor standardization on
policy development, train security,
and IT teams design a roadmap.
For scaled implementation, right?
Start with the low risk pilot projects
such as archival storage, backups.
Yeah.
These are the low risk, right?
For any project or at
the enterprise level.
Start with it.
Then plan for enterprise wide rollout.
If you are successful with the pilot
projects right at the low level
you can make a wide rollout at the
organization with quantum safe encryption.
Security key management and
hybrid optimization workflows.
Yeah, that's it.
Thanks for the opportunity to discuss
about the different techniques,
frameworks about the quantum
computing in the storage systems.
Thanks for all for your time.
Thank you.
Bye.