Quantum computing impact enterprise
data achieving how 100% of is
going, we are going to achieve.
Okay, let me take you to the P. Okay.
And then why organizations today manage
two 7.3 across interconnect systems
without quantum can have strategies,
enterprise based competi orders.
So I want to explain about how quantum
technology is much more important
for today's data with of data.
Before going further digging that message,
I want to think about how exactly I want
to tell you about the, how the data is
going to be much, much bigger with the AI
evolution and how much of the GPUs have
we able to level at the same time how the
data inside is growing bigger and bigger.
Okay.
The more interface are drawing the
data than many hundreds of petabytes
of the data, as I said earlier,
across various systems, traditional
computing methods struggle.
To derive value from that
much data efficiently.
Quantum Computing offers a new approach
that can handle complete complexity
and volume at an annually large scale.
That being said, right now we are
talking about precis per, but every day
or every month, every year, the data
is going double, triple, so that the
legacy systems, we cannot manage that.
We cannot pull the dataset data.
Issues are data evaluations.
It should be done for the
quantum computing only.
The key is that embracing quantum
computing for data management can
give a company a major competitive
advantage earlier that have
seen the remarkable benefits.
For example, small business
reported double their benefits
that double their investment.
For example, if they put $1 within two
weeks, they're getting $2 more than that.
It's all about, I'm talking about
a small number, hundred 80 ones.
Otherwise it's pretty big one.
Why this matters.
Company's content.
Today's content, as I said earlier,
two 6.3 petabytes, enterprise
volume business integration systems,
and we are expecting 180% of data
increase and producing 24 months.
Whatever you're seeing right now is
going to increase how the quantum
enhanced solutions is working right now.
See the pillar, right?
How everything is changing the
quantum efficiency, the breakthrough
quantum algorithm, reducing
computational complexity and
cutting process time between 2%.
It's not small number price, it's
seven to a percent at the same
time, better qualities, increasing
leveraging quantum ation principles
to reduce error rates by eight 10%.
If you do the same thing
with the traditional models,
you may not see this much.
This eight 10% is a much bigger number.
Is revolutionary engagement based
frameworks driving 99% of data
connections across enterprise systems,
military grid, quantum position,
cryptography, engineering, regular,
comprehensive, and data already.
Okay, if I go back to that again our, how
the quantum mechanism or quantum solutions
going to help master data solutions
here That will go back one more step.
If you see here the same
thing, water, because here the
error actually is almost 90%.
At the same time, computational
performance increase up to 60% better
preparation time, easily reduce up to 80%.
That being set.
Our countdown point percent
by 17 decreasing 62.4% case.
That workflow that previously took.
Days now, complete center point
faster, allowing your team to focus
on static than the processing task.
With the quantum computing, you
need to spend much more time
on the ETLs and everything.
The quantum computing is
much more faster there.
You can leverage more time on the
analysis rather than the processing task.
Okay.
How quantum ation from better ventilation.
Parallel multi analysis, the
quantum algorithm simultaneously
level data quality dimensions
in a single competition.
Reducing validation time by 95%.
Advanced neur quantum pattern detection
systems leverage quantum chase to identify
software coalitions and analog invisible
to conventional computing frameworks.
Increase detection rates by 87.3%.
Enterprise quantum ation processing
billions of records with nine 10.98%
accuracy through and base verification
protocol that maintain coherence across.
Distributors.
Everything is not a small number.
Everything is a much bigger number.
We are talking with the currently
A and GPUs, and the data is now
moved from terabyte to petabytes.
We are talking, everything
is petabytes right now.
How the conversation going
to handle the data con rate.
We can go with the four approaches
and in spare models, high accuracy,
central repository, and for resolution.
Let's talk about in inspect
models, revolutionary quantum
frameworks reduce cross depart
ladder conflict space percent.
Admitting traditional information silos.
Previously we used everything, the silos.
Now the silos concept is gone.
Everything is centralized.
That way we can do much
faster and much accurate.
That's what I'm going to talk.
Quantum coherence maintenance and 0.8% of
accuracy rates across distributed systems.
Even with exponentially
scaling data volumes.
Central pository adverse to quantum
basic systems unify enterprise data
through coherent shared preservation
across distribute networks.
Faster resolution quantum
monitoring, decrease synchronization,
issue resolution time between
0.4% near realtime metalation.
So generally, if we talk about normal
way, all about models, accuracy,
central repository and FA resolution,
even when you talk about security,
how contract computer pretty much
secure computer legacy systems,
it's like encryption is there.
A random numbers.
Generations are then pri to
value violation detection.
It identifies 18 points and percent
of potential violations before they
outcome prevention is better than cure.
What we follow in general rate with the
quantum quantum data management, we can
do the violation detection much earlier.
This is a pretty much helpful, for
example, if I took a quantum how the
in is built here, the cost you can
save is 1.8 million annual savings for
large enterprise through complexity.
Continuous monitoring.
The monitoring will be always
continuous systems, track hundreds
of all parameters simultaneously,
and high ion checks all the time.
Your cost savings for eight to 7%, that
means every year if you're saving seven
to 40%, how much returns are y you have
how you can implement the same thing.
That part of the approach.
Quantum infrastructure establish
hardware and software requirements,
classical integration, quantum safe
security, and change management.
Always we change when something
goes wrong, happen all the time.
We need to go through that.
How the change can be implemented
in the system, it will help.
Finally, we talk about RI framework
with the quantum computing CP enhanced
operations, improve processing,
future proof architecture with
this three RI framework for sure.
With the marsh data, our data
management will be much easier and
faster with the quantum computing.
The key TKs, which we discussed
in a is competitive advantage.
Measurable impact action plan.
What is competitive advantage?
Quantum enhanced data strategies deliver
significant marketplace differentiation
organizations without quantum risk,
failing behind measurable impact.
Early implementers, c 1%
of RI within 24 months.
Benefits include, reduce address, improved
contingency and enhanced complaints.
How the action plan works.
We can begin quantum data assessment
now directly implementation,
incorporating infrastructure integration,
security and change management.
And with this how the quantum management
is going to help the data side with
the data is increasing much more bigger
size with all the GPUs and evolution.
For sure.
We need to, everyone should make it from
the link systems, the quantum computing.
It just for data management.
That way you can rely on the data
violations and data reconciliation,
data indicating otherwise always
your back always your behind.
But make sure quantum computing is a
real heartbreaking and game changer.
Thank you.