Good morning everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
My name is Siva Prakash, and it's a
genuine pleasure to speak with you
about what I believe is the next great
frontier in financial technologies.
For over two decades, I have had
the privilege of working within
the IT landscape, witnessing
wave after wave of innovation.
In my current role, I see firsthand
the immense computational challenges.
Point where the limits of
classical computings are becoming
increasingly apparent just
as a new paradigm is downing.
Today we are going to explore
that paradigm, the integration of
quantum computing principles with
real-time financial data processing.
We will be looking at a future
powered by quantum enhanced real-time
data shaping and feature stores
are future design for ultra low
latency demands of modern finance.
Understand where we are going.
We first need to appreciate where we are.
The world of finance today is
convergence of four powerful forces.
First, the demand from
financial application.
We are no longer in an era
of end of batch processing.
Finance demands microsecond level
decision, whether in high frequency
trading, realtime product preventions,
or dynamic risk assessment.
This is fueled by data streaming
technologies, which act as the global
financial system circulatory system,
enabling a continuous realtime flow of
market data, transactions and emails.
To make sense of this data, we rely
on feature stores, which centralizes.
The critical data ingredients, the
features that power our machine learning
models consistently and at scale.
And now entering this quantum computing,
which promises a fundamentally new
way to compute, leverage the principle
of quantum mechanics for powerful
exploration.
The reason this conversion is so
critical is because we're hitting a ball.
We call it the classical limitations.
For decades, we have relied on Moore
and advanced parallelization with
GPUs to keep up the data deluge.
But we are now facing
insurmountable BO bottlenecks.
The sheer volume of data from
market feeds news and alternative
sources one challenge, but the
bigger challenge is complexity.
When we analyze financial
data sets with hundreds of
correlating risk across finding.
Pattern across millions of
transaction, the computational
complexity through exponentially.
This is not a linear problem for a
classical computer doubling the number
of variable cans, square, or even
queue the time needed for a solution.
At a certain point, a realtime processing
becomes practically impossible.
We can build bigger data center,
but we can't out architect the map.
That is where we need a new tool, a new
approach, and the approach is quantum.
So what makes quantum
computing so different?
Let's demy and demystify it.
Imagine a classical computer bit.
It's like a light switch.
It can be either on or off.
It's binary and definite.
A quantum bit or qubit is
fundamentally different.
Think of it more like a bimmer switch.
It can be on off or crucially in
a state of superposition, a blend
of both on and off simultaneously.
This property of superposition is the
first key to quantum power because Abit
can hold multiple values at once a.
Number of possibilities concurrently.
While a classical computer checks
scenarios one by one, a quantum computer
checks them all at the same time.
This is what we call quantum parallelism
and it's what allows quantum algorithms
to dramatically reduce decision latency
for time sensitive financial transaction.
The second principle is entanglement
instance, famously called it
spooky actions at a distance.
When two qubits are entangled,
their fades are linked.
If you measure one, you instantly
know the state of the other no
matter how far apart they are.
For finance, this is a revolutionary.
It means we can use entangle.
Across vast financial data
sets without having to manually
sift through every data point.
These principles allow quantum computers
to solve certain types of problems,
specifically optimization, simulation,
and complex sampling exponentially
faster than any classical computer ever.
Code.
Now it's crucial to understand that we are
not talking about replacing our existing
data center with quantum computer.
The future, at least for the
foreseeable feature, is hybrid.
We'll use a combination of classical and
quantum system each playing its strengths.
This slide shows a high level of.
What the quantum enhanced
streaming architecture looks like.
At the bottom, we have our
classical infrastructure.
This is your high performance
compute, your network fabric,
your existing databases.
This workhorse layer
handles the 99% of task.
It's already good at data storage, basic
processing, and moving data around.
Next we have the real time
processing stream processing layer.
Using technologies like Apache,
Flink and Kafka, this is where
the real time processing happens.
This is a circulatory
system we talked about.
We're developing quantum aware
connectors that know when to route
a specific computationally intensive
task away from the classical part.
This data then feeds our features
storage there, built on platform
like Feast or a w SageMaker.
This layer is quantum optimized, meaning
it can store and serve a feature that are
either generated by quantum processes or
designed to be consumed by one, and at
the top, the pinnacle of the architecture
are the quantum processor processing unit.
These are specialized accelerator.
We don't send every transaction to QPU.
We send it the hardest problem,
the complex calculations and
pattern recognition task that
would choke a classical system.
In this model, the classical system
enables a workflow while the QPU acts
as a powerful co-processor tackling
the in intractable parts of the
problem before feeding the answer
back into the classical stream.
This is the pragmatic
path to quantum advantage.
Let us look into the use case.
One.
Quantum powered Trading.
Trading strategies.
Let's make this tangible.
How does this architecture apply to the
demanding world of algorithmic trading?
The goal in trading is to find a
true signal in a sea of noise and to
act on it faster than anyone else.
Quantum gives us an on both front
signal processing market data
is incredibly noisy Quantum.
Signal processing.
Leveraging principle from quantum sensing
can filter this noise and identify faint
patterns with incredible precision.
Often in nanoseconds, this
means getting a cleaner, more
accurate picture of the, market.
Faster pattern recognition.
Many trading strategies
rely on identifying complex.
Multidimensional pattern
and market behavior.
Quantum mission learning algorithm
can perform this pattern recognition
up to a hundred times faster than
classical methods, allowing to
identify and act on opportunities
that would otherwise be missed.
Simultaneously, scenarios, perhaps
most powerfully used powerfully using
super position, a quantum algorithm
can over thousand potential rating
scenarios simultaneously per microsecond.
This.
Includes modeling market
impact, running risk checks, and
optimizing execution strategy.
All concurrently, it represents a
monumental leap from the sequential
analysis of a classical system.
Next comes the ultra low
latency fraud detection.
Another critical area is fraud detection.
Every microsecond counts.
The goal is not just to detect
fraud, but to intervene.
Before the transaction is finalized and
the money is gone, anomaly detection.
Sophisticated fraud often involves
subtle deviation from normal
patterns spread across many accounts.
And transaction.
Quantum algorithms are uniquely suited
to spotting this microscopic pattern
deviation with sub microsecond position.
The feature extraction.
A key part of modern fraud detection
is analyzing the relationship.
Our quantum optimized feature stores
can deliver incredibly complex.
Like the correlation between a
group of new accounts making similar
transaction in picosecond, look
at the time it is in picosecond.
This is speed at a level,
classical system can't match
risk assessment and intervention.
Quantum parallelism allows us to
evaluate millions of risk vector
simultaneously for single transaction.
An instant highly accurate risk score,
which in turn enables ultra low latency
response capabilities to neutralize
fraudulent transaction before completion.
This is the difference between
foreign analysis after the
fact and a realtime prevention.
Finally, let's look at an application
focused on the end customer.
Personalized.
The dream has always been to provide truly
individual holistic advice that adapts in
real time quantum customer segmentation.
Today's segmentation is often
based on broad demographic data,
quantum clustering algorithm.
We can process billions
of behavioral data points.
Inquiries life events to create
hyper personalized client segment.
A grouping customer by
subtle shared behavior needs.
Quantum neural networks two
mo model the complex, often
financial behavior of individuals.
We can use quantum neural network.
These models can handle exponentially
more parameters than their classical
counterparts, allowing for a much
richer and more accurate understanding
of classical client needs.
Dynamic portfolio optimization.
This is a classic opt classic optimization
problem and a perfect fit for quantum.
A quantum system can continuously
recalculate optimal asset allocation for
millions of clients as market condition
and correlations shift in real time.
This is not a nightly reval,
it's a living adaptive p.
Personalized recommendation within
microseconds of market events,
imagine a client's portfolio being
automatically adjusted to mitigate risk.
The instant relevant geopolitical.
This is the future of financial advice.
Now it's essential to be realistic.
This incredible power comes with equally
incredible engineering challenges.
This is not easy.
First, the quantum environment
requirements are extreme.
Qubits are fragile.
They must be kept in highly isolated
environment at cryogenic temperature,
older than deep space, offered below
20 milli to maintain their quantum
state, a property called coherence
that is significant data, trans
translation, moving information from.
Latency costs that must
be meticulously optimized.
Error correction is arguably the
biggest hurdle because qubits are
so fragile, they're prone to error.
We must implement complex, full tolerant
quantum error correction code to preserve
the integrity of our calculation.
And finally, there is immerse
integration complexity in architecting.
Seamless high performance
interfaces between quantum, a
processor and classical system.
This leads to the critical
issue of data quality.
Garbage in garbage out is even
more true for quantum system.
We need advanced quantum noise
mitigation filters to eliminate signals
interfaced at the quantum level.
We need continuous calibration system
to maintain perfect data synchronization
between the quantum and classical
worlds with monitoring protocols that
ensure uncompromised data integrity.
And we need fault tolerant design using
techniques like multilayered circuited,
ancy to validate mission critical
finance and financial transaction
with near perfect reliability.
Architecting for the future.
The quantum optimized feature store facing
these challenges does not mean we stop.
It means we architect smarter.
This slide shows how we are
already re-imagining core
components like the feature store.
For this hybrid feature.
We are optimizing it at every level.
Quantum feature of competition, the most
complex feature and financial indicators.
Like derivatives, pricing and or complex
risk metrics are calculate, calculated
using quantum algorithms at unprecedented
speed feature transport optimization.
We use quantum inspired routing algorithm
to minimize latency in delivering
these features to the models that need
them, ensuring critical C strategy C.
The optimal placement of features in
the cache dynamically adjusting based
on realtime usage, pattern on demand
feature generation for rarely used,
but computationally heavy features.
We just in time computation, balancing
storage cost with performance need
by re-architecting our system with
this principle in mind today, we
will, the foundation, need to plug
in quantum processor as they mature.
Quantum feature of financial technology.
So what does the roadmap of
this quantum feature looks like?
Right now?
We are in the era of
early quantum advantage.
Specialized quantum algorithms are being
used to enhance every specific financial
task, demonstrating a clear alphabet,
narrow advantage over classical method.
In the next two, three years, we
will see hybrid system mature.
Integrating quantum, classical platform
will become more common capable of
handling complete financial workflows
for specific use cases like portfolio
optimization or fraud analysis.
Look out for five or more
years, we anticipate the rise
of quantum financial network.
This will be distributed quantum system,
possibly linked by quantum communication
channels that begin to transform the
global financial infrastructure itself.
And in 10 or more years, we can envision
the emergence of quantum native finance.
These will be entirely
new financial markets.
Of.
Quantum computing with real-time data
technologies, not science fiction.
It is a next logical step
in the evolution of finance.
Quantum is not a magic bullet that
will replace all classical computing.
It is a highly specialized tool for
new class of computational problems.
The problems of.
And complexity that are defining
the future of in our industry.
The journey of quantum advantage
is a marathon, not a sprint, and it
is fundamentally a hybrid journey.
The financial institution that will lead
in the next decade are the ones that
start preparing now by architecting for
this hybrid reality, investing in the
right skill and beginning to identify.
The specific high value problems
where Quantum can deliver a
true transformative advantage.
The future of finance will be
faster, smarter, and more secure,
and it'll be in part quantum.
Thank you very much for
your time and attention.
I would be hap happy to answer
any question you may have.