Hello everyone.
This is Na Krishna.
I'm a technical architect with
11 years of experience in AWS
Cloud DevOps, and automations.
Today I'm gonna discuss about quantum
computing and its implementation on
AWS Cloud Quantum computing promises.
To revolutionize how we
solve complex problems from
cryptography to drug discovery.
By harnessing the strange behavior of
quantum particles, quantum computers can
perform certain calculations exponentially
faster than classical computers.
This presentation explores how a
WCS democratizing access to quantum
technology and empowering mores to
explore the next computing frontier.
Deep.
The topics covered in this presentation
are classical versus quantum computing.
Quantum computing applications,
hybrid quantum classical computing,
quantum programming languages,
AWS quantum computing portfolio,
quantum hardware, and A-W-S-A-W.
Bracket architecture design
getting started with AWS
Quantum Computing access models.
And the final topic is future
of quantum computing, classical
versus quantum computing.
The current classical computers use
bits for calculations and computations.
The bits can maintain the state of
zero or one, whereas quantum computing
uses qubits where each qubit can
maintain state of zero, one or both.
To double the computation power of
a classical computer, we need to
double the beats, whereas to double
the power of a quantum computer,
we just need to add one more qubit.
That's the best thing
about quantum computing.
Quantum compute applications.
Where do we need quantum computing
in discovery, supply chain
and traffic flow improvements.
Especially in financial modeling for
portfolio optimization and disc analysis.
This picture explains about hybrid
classical quantum algorithms where you
can see both classical computer and
a quantum hardware or simulator work
together making it as a hybrid computing.
In hybrid computing, a classical computer
handles the most of the work by doing the
initial setup, pre-pro and final analysis.
And it controls a quantum
computer, like a co-pro.
And when it comes to quantum
computer, it tackles hard part it.
Quantum routines where the quantum effects
will help, like position and untanglement.
And then these results would
be sent back to the classical
computer for interpretation.
This explains a hybrid model of
classical and quantum computing together.
And let's discuss about
quantum programming languages.
So we have mainly four
The first one is Python
with Kiki from IBM.
Currently this is the most used quantum
SDK and Q Sharp from Microsoft and
circ from Google's Python framework.
And the final one would
be Amazon's bracket sdk.
This is the native to AWS bracket.
Let's discuss AWS Quantum
Computing portfolio.
AWS Quantum Portfolio comes
with main three aspects.
Amazon sub bracket, a WS
Center for Quantum Computing,
Amazon Quantum Solutions Lab.
Let's talk about AWS bracket.
It's a fully managed
quantum computing survey.
That lets design, test, and run
quantum algorithms on different types
of quantum hardwares and simulators.
AWS Center for Quantum Computing.
It is a research partnership
with Caltech to advance quantum
hardwares and algorithms under a w.
Quantum solutions and they help
various orations to solve the
quantum computing challenges.
Let's talk about various quantum hardwares
available on a WS for quantum computing.
The first one would be
superconducting qubits.
These are among the most mature
quantum technologies, and these
are provided by IQM and rete.
The second type of hardware is ion
trap quantum computers, and these
have been offered by Ion Q, and the
third one is neutral atom processors.
These use areas of neutral atoms that
are mandated by lasers, and this hardware
is provided by two ERA computing and AWS
also provides quantum simulators where
alterations can test their algorithms.
The simulators before actually
actually getting started on the real
quantum hardware so that they can do a
pre-analysis and analyze the results.
AWS Oxford Innovation, this is the latest
innovation being announced by AWS in
February, 2025, where this chip uses cat.
Where the qubit stays on superposition
of two states, like zero and one at the
same time, while being more resistant
to errors than the regular qubits, so
it reduces the error corrections by 90%.
This innovation helps the
development of smaller and more
reliable quantum computers like
our regular personal computers.
The Amazon user was
launched in December 19.
Now it's generally available and it
is a unified platform for multiple
quantum hardware types where our
missions can explore various quantum
hardware types as per the requirement.
And it is a pay as you go service
model where we, where our nations
need not to invest upfront, but
they can get started with the
service and they pay as they use it.
It democratized access.
It enables innovation for researchers
and businesses by simply using
a Ws in a simple and fast way.
How Amazon bracket works.
First, we create algorithms with Python,
SDK, and then we submit quantum tasks
to devices or simulators, then run the
hardware and classical computers like
we run hybrid quantum jobs on quantum
hardware and classical computers.
And then we compare the results,
and then we switch between hardware
with minor code changes based
upon how our results came up.
And this is the Amazon bracket
architecture diagram here.
On the side there are three ways we
can interact with manage notebooks.
D, Amazon Bracket Console.
These are the three ways where we
can interact with Amazon's bracket.
In this picture, in the middle, you can
see Amazon bracket, so it has managed
simulators that have been provided
by a s and in the backend you'll see
different types of hardwares, as we
discussed in the previous slides.
Hardware's approved by various vendors.
So based upon our requirement, we can
choose which hardware is suitable for us,
and AWS bracket can seamlessly interact
with other AWS services like Amazon
CloudWatch for notifications, Amazon S3
for storage of objects or data, and a s
management for permissions for management.
AWS key management for data production.
In this slide, it explains about
how the quantum computers will
process the operations, okay.
On a quantum computer.
So the smallest execution
is called a shop.
A single execution of quantum
operation on a device is called shot.
This one the first one
explains how a shot works.
So basically we call it as a circuit.
Okay.
If we have more than 10 shots, okay.
So we can combine it as
a task and submit it to.
Quantum computer.
So a series, it's, it executes a
series of shorts in a single task.
And the third option would be like hybrid
job, what we saw in the previous slides.
So basically a classical computer
and quantum computer work together
to make it as a hybrid job.
This hardware can be used on cloud on
AWS as a pay as you go model, or the
hardware can be set up on premises,
which would be incurring a cost.
We can use combination of both
cloud and local resources.
And this is how we can get
started with Amazon bracket.
In database console, we can search with
Amazon bracket or simply type bracket.
It brings us to a bracket console
where on the left side we can see
devices, notebooks, jobs, tasks.
On the part we can see
different hardware that.
So based upon the requirement, so we
can choose our specific hardware, what
we wanna use for our operations and the
notebooks, we can rate our algorithm here
and submit it to the quantum computer
and.
Final slide of the presentation.
So as we have seen that quantum computing
can help us to resolve more complex
problems, the current research is going
on so that in the future we can have
fault tolerance systems where we'll have
less errors in the quantum computing
analysis, and they can be used for
the regular commercial applications.
And then we can use it for cryptography.
And also we should be seeing more quantum
education coming up, like workforce
development for quantum economy.
At the end, we want to see a quantum
computer as small as like our
personal computer with economically
affordable and less and feasible
for all computing applications.
Very much.