Hi everyone.
Good morning.
I'm Pradeep Kana.
Today we look at how quantum computing
can boost Siemens Teamcenter,
or any other PLM tool, the PLM
system many of you already use.
So we can choose product options
faster and keep supply chain safer.
Think of this as a tool first,
we'll see the business pain.
Then a quick premium on quantum tech.
Real world cases, studies risk, and
finally, a step by step roadmap.
By the end, you should know why,
where, how to start a small but
meaningful quantum pilot inside PLM.
Let's start with pain
points in dollars and time.
A study from interior shows that
every big supply chain hiccups cost a
company about $22 million on average.
While the line has come down, we
burned roughly $1.5 million each day.
On top of that product
complexity is exploding.
The BMW Mini once offered
15 today and valid options.
Combination traditional rule
engines inside PLM, how to check
those options almost one by one.
An impassable task quantum
algorithm can search huge,
spacious infraction of these steps.
So we move from overnight bad
jobs to coffee break answers.
That's previous business case.
Two quick ideas.
Qubits are tiny elements that can be
one, zero or one at the same time when we
link cobits through entire entanglement.
A singular operation
explores many paths in power.
There are three main
hardwares styles in 2025.
Gate model chips like IBM's that run
gentle quantum logic enter layers
from D Wave grade for optimization,
neural autumn array like Pascals
that behave like flexible graphs.
Today's machines are still noisy,
so we wrap a small quantum core
with good old classical core.
That hybrid mix already beats.
Classical only solver uncertain
optimization problems.
Here is what actually available not
just in labs, but through cloud APIs.
TVA Advantage two 4,400 Kibitz.
Lives since May, 2025.
Pascal a hundred neural
autumn cubits on Google Cloud.
BM Eagle 1 27 cubit gate model
with a 1,386 cubit chip plant.
This year, Fugi digital and
linear 8,192 bits already.
Plants daily work at
Toyotas tsunami plant.
The good news.
Teamcenter can talk to each of these.
Through a simple rest core, the same way,
already sends jobs to an HPC cluster.
Nothing.
Here rewrites Teamcenter score.
Step one, pull the bill of materials or
supply data through active workspace.
Rest.
Step two, convert the data into
maths from the quantum mechanic.
Understands.
A QO metrics for optimization or a
probability model for simulations.
And the next step three,
send it to the cloud.
Wait for a few seconds,
get the best answer.
And the last step four, write the new
configuration or risk score back into
Teamcenter so everyone can act on it.
It's a bold on microservice,
not a rip and replace.
Remember those 15 trillion mini
options with a quantum handling, we
treat every rule as an energy penalty.
The machine naturally slides to a valid
low energy build in milliseconds Toyota.
The idea daily production
sequence runs drop by 90% for
a 10,000 line bombing bomb.
Engineers can now click validate
and see a feasible options list
before their coffee gets cold.
Exciting, right when a port
closes, planners run Monte or law
simulation to see projected losses.
Classically, that can mean
1 million scenarios with
quantum amplitude estimation.
We need only 10,000 to hit the same nce, a
hundred times fewer runs in D wave tests.
Scenario speed jumped from
12 to two 90 per minute.
Shrinking is six day
recovery study, 220 hours.
That can be difference between
scrambling and calmly rerouting parts.
Quantum is not just for logistics.
Three.
Design waves, battery cooling.
CFD covered 92% faster Crash,
FEA run counts fell 68%.
Saving 2.1 million per platform.
Polymer chemistry simulations
that used to take three days.
Now finish overnight.
Each result fits back into Teamcenter
Digital Twin, letting designers try
more ideas in the same project window.
This isn't sign fiction.
Big names are Live Toyota
Digital and Layer sequence.
It's line daily.
BMW Part plus Pascal.
Optimizing metal forming fur, lighter
cars, D-Wave running logistics
pilots for German manufacturers.
Their lessons start small.
Prove value, then scale.
Leadership is on board in January, 2025.
S-A-P-C-U said Quantum
could shrink week long.
MRP runs into one hour.
Siemens Digital Industries,
up its quantum r and d budget.
In March.
Board level conversations are
sifting from why to when and where.
Quantum computers can also
break today's encryption.
So we must protect as we innovate.
NIST release the first post
Quantum standards in 2024.
Cloud Flare already sees 2% of all web
traffic using P-Q-T-L-S Action item
Audit Team center, supplier portal
for RSA 2048 and plan a cutover.
Every new tech has hurdles.
Right show be decoherence.
We use hybrid error
aware code, vendor lock.
Insist on open standards like QIRK gap.
Trend quantum translators
inside the PLM teams.
Hype set phase gated ROI Checkpoints.
So projects live or die on real numbers
here.
A low risk plan, zero to three months.
Pick one high value use case.
Do a cloud proof of concept.
Four to 12 months YM micro
service into production.
Benchmark agne CPUs 12 to 24 months.
Roll out to more sites.
Swap supplier portal TLS to post quantum.
Each gate has clear goals, top metrics.
Keeping spender under control.
Yep.
Tech alone won't win.
We need people who can speak both
PLM and Quantum, create a quantum
translator role run internal hackathons
on real team center data and track
progress with new KPIs, like number
of quantum ator bond checks per hour.
That builds a culture,
not just a prototype.
To wrap up, hardware is still in.
So hybrid approaches and
good data, privacy rules are
vital, but the upside is huge.
Faster designs, safer
supply chains, lower costs.
Quantum PLM is moving from
labs to factory flows.
Teams that explore now will shape
that future instead of chasing it.
Thank you.