Hello everyone, and
thank you for turning in.
I'm m Pravin Kana, a
senior software engineer.
In this session, I will walk you
through a simple but powerful idea.
What if you could define and
run an entire quantum experiment
from a single JSON file?
No more learning notebooks.
Updating brittle scripts or
writing pipelines by hand.
Instead, we'll explore a schema driven
approach that helps researchers move
faster, build repeatable processes,
and gain built-in observability.
This is all without writing
front end or orchestration code.
Quantum research moves fast,
new hardware circuit designs.
Error mitigation techniques emerge
constantly, but our tooling often
lags behind copying notebooks
create fraile dependencies.
Document documentation drifts as
experiments evolve and auditing
becomes nearly impossible.
This slide captures the problem, constant
change in parameter and hardware, hidden
dependencies and logic buried in scripts.
Inconsistent documentation and
a series serious compliance
headache for regular industries.
To solve these challenges, we
built a schema driven framework.
At its core is a single adjacent schema,
a machine readable contract that defines
what an experiment can and cannot accept.
From this schema, we auto
generate three things.
First.
React based waveform.
So scientists never
touch HTML or JavaScript.
Second, a step functions
workflow to execute circuits and
post-process data, all serverless.
Third, a lineage tracker.
Every run is tagged.
Versioned traceable.
This means researchers are just a
manifest, not a monolith of scripts.
Here is how it all fits together.
The Chason schema is stored in AWS
S3 with object lock enabled, ensuring
it is versioned and also immutable.
A-C-I-C-D pipeline
triggers two generators.
One builds the react portal, the other
compiles a step function state machine.
The state machine calls Amazon Rocket.
To run quantum jobs, invokes for gate
containers for post-processing and stores.
Results in S3 observability
is handled by open Telemetry
with the dashboards in Grafana.
This system is modular, serverless, and
also designed for scale and traceability.
On the right side, you can
see the architectural diagram
and the components involved.
Let's compare traditional workflows
with our schema driven approach.
On the left is a notebook model.
Everything is hand coded.
The device on circuit chart
and output path, it works,
but it's Frazy and error Pro.
Also, every time some parameter
has to be changed, this notebook
model has to be updated.
The right is a compact J in
schema, 30 lines that describe
the entire experiment set.
The schema is used across the ui, the
workflow, and the validation logic.
Instead of cloning and modifying
notebooks, research, fill out a form
that is guaranteed to be a valid one.
This approach unlocks
four big benefits First.
Parameter exploration
becomes safe and structured.
No invalid values, no runtime surprises.
And the second one, collaboration
improves Schemas are version in git
with pull requests and differences.
Number three, configuration
errors go to chiro because
schema validation runs upfront.
Four.
Onboarding is dramatically faster.
New team members don't need to
learn your SDKs or internal scripts.
They simply open a form and run.
You get governance
without sacrificing speed
to.
To test this in real world, we
ran a 1 million shot VQE Sweep.
This bar chart shows the
results across five metrics.
Let's walk through it.
On the far left set up time, the time
to prepare a single parametal variant
dropped from 18 minutes with notebooks to
just three minutes with a schema portal.
Next is wall clock time, total
runtime for the entire suite, which
dropped from 13.4 s to 11.8 hours.
That improvement comes from better
concurrency and simulator fallback.
When QPU queues are logged.
Third is a configuration errors.
We went from seven errors in the
baseline to zero, which is a huge win.
Then cost.
The schema workflow saved around 200
USD largely due to more efficient
execution and fewer retries.
Finally, learnability researchers
rated the schema portal 4.8 out
of five compared to 3.1 for the.
Notebooks here, the learning is basically
straightforward for the researchers.
These aren't synthetic benchmarks.
They are based on real world jobs
running on a bracket with simulator file
back and post-processing in Fargate.
From
an engineering standpoint, this
system is compact and maintainable.
We use three CDK stacks.
One for frontend portal, one
for the state machine pipeline
and one for observability.
The schema file itself is
tiny, about 3 75 bytes.
The React bundle is 1.2
kb after it's jipped.
Using the GGP, the state
machine is six KBG sn with.
23 states fi service integrations
and no Lambda functions.
We test locally using local stack.
They apply with GitHub actions and
run cost effectively within AWS free
tier for most dev and test scenarios.
This is just the beginning.
We are expanding in
three major directions.
First.
Enabling multi key MA chaining.
So teams can compose multi-stage
pipelines where output from one
experiment feeds into another second,
I'm adding post quantum encryption.
The results will be automatically
encrypted with VER aligning
with net post quantum standards.
Third, we are making
workflow cloud portable.
We will support backend Azure Quantum,
Google Circ using the same schema and ui.
This will let researchers focus on
science, not the infrastructure.
Thank you for spending time with me today.
Schema driven experiment portals
bring structure automation
observability to quantum research.
Without slowing scientists down,
you gain auditability, cost
control, and repeatability while
freeing your team from code.
If you're working on quantum workflows,
I would love to connect and share
con code patterns or blueprints.
Thanks again and enjoy the rest of Con 42.
Quantum Computing 2025.