Hey everyone.
Thanks so much for joining today.
Before we go further, a little bit
about me, I'm Dennis Thema de Ulu.
Welcome to my talk.
So let's start.
I'm here to talk about something
that honestly keep me awake at night
and know it's not DI in products and
code at 3M that also held horrific.
But what keeps me up
thinking that is cloud build.
Especially what's going to happen
to our cloud wells when quantum
computing become mainstream.
So let me start with a story that
happened to me just last month
that made me realize we are heading
for a perfect storm of confusions.
So picture this one day I
hear about a person panicking.
She looking at her AWS bill and it
says around $10,000 for last month.
Her startup entirely
was, that is $2,000 only.
So what happened, one tiny mistake
in her auto scaling configurations.
Instead of scaling up to five servers,
it is scaled up to 50 and instead of
running for two hours, it runs for
three days before anyone noticed.
So we were sitting there looking at
this bill, trying to figure out what
net gateway's processing charge means.
And why is he paying for CloudWatch
logs data and what the hell is
load balance of capacity unit?
And that's when it hit me.
If we can't predict cost with the regular
computer technologies we have been using
for decades, then what's going to happen
when quantum computers enters the picture?
Let's be honest here, nobody, and I mean
nobody actually understand their bills.
You got computer charges, storage
charges, network egress charges,
network ingress charges and wait.
They charge you for data incoming to, then
there are, there's also cross availability
zone transfer and API gateway request.
Lambda called start penalties database,
lead capacity unit, and so on.
I once up lined with I items
for ideal load balancer time.
And my load balancer was not working
hard enough, and they decided to
charge me for its lack of motivation.
But here's the real problem.
Try this experiment right now.
Open your cloud dashboard and tell me
exactly not approximately, not around
$800, exactly what you'll spend.
Next month you can't do it.
Nobody can.
And this is what with technology,
we understand pretty well.
We know how CCP works,
we know how memory works.
We have been optimizing
these things for decades now.
Amazing.
Adding quantum to this equation,
here's a review of what's
coming and why you should care.
Even if you never plan to touch
a quantum computer, your quantum
algorithm might solve your problem
in 30 seconds or even in 30 hours.
There literally no way to no be.
It might do, it might re,
yeah, it might need to run
once to get the perfect answer.
It might need to run 500 times,
become quantum mechanics,
decide to be difficult that day.
It might use basic quantum operations
that cost little bit, or it might
need expensive quantum errors.
Correction that cost a hundred times more.
And though all this, the
cloud providers is going to.
For every second of processing time,
for every detra, for every error
correction, and for every failed attempts.
The same quantum job could cost you
$500 to $5,000, and you wouldn't
know which until you get the bill.
But before we talk about solutions, let me
explain exactly what quantum computing is
and why it create the billing nightmare.
Alright, let's get technical,
but I promise to keep it simple.
Regular computers, your computers,
your phones, your server
running, your applications.
They, you, they all use bits, a
bits either zero over, it's like
a switch either on or either off.
Simple, predictable, reliable,
as you can see in this slide.
Quantum computers use bits or qubits.
Now here where it get is interesting.
A qubit can be zero or one and
zero and one at the same time.
Think of it like a coin.
When you flip a coin, it
is spinning in the air.
Is it add or tail?
It actually both until it
lengths and you see the result.
A qubit is like a coin.
That can stay spinning until
you need to know the answer.
So this is called super position being
in multiple state simultaneously.
Now, why does it matter?
Because while the qubits is in super
position, it can explore multiple
solution to your problem at the same time.
It's like having thousands of
computer working in parallel, but
they are all same quantum computer.
So let me show you this with a example.
Imagine you are trying to find a exit
in a maze, and the classical computer
approach this systematically, it'll
try path one, which leads to dead end.
It will try part two, which also lead
to dead end, and he will try also
part three, part four, and so on.
And until he found the exit.
This.
This takes proportional to the
number of paths needs to check,
and at the same time, the quantum
computer can be much smarter.
It puts itself in, put super position
and explore all paths simultaneously.
Quantum State explore Path one and
Path two and part three and so on
at the same time in parallel, then
it collab collapse to the solution.
For certain type of problems.
This give you exponential speed up
problem that would take classical computer
Millions of years can be solved in hours.
But here's the catch, and this is
where our billing nightmares begin.
Quantum computers are fragile.
Before we get to the fragility problem,
let me explain one more quantum concept.
That make everything even more
powerful and more unpredictable,
that is quantum entanglement.
When two qubits become entangled,
they become connected in a way
that defies every day experiences.
If you measure one qubit and find
it zero and other, qubit instantly
become one, even if they are
opposite side of the galaxy and.
This select quantum computers coordinate
multiple calculations in way that would
be impossible with classical computers.
It's like having a team of workers
who can telepathically communicate
and coordinate their accent perfectly.
So now let me show you what a
Quantum Cloud bill actually look like
because this is already happening.
Here.
You can see in this slide a real
example of what you might see.
As you can see, it is too messy and
can't understand too easily, so your
algorithm work perfect for perfectly.
It solved your problem, but the universe
decide to be expensive that day.
This is why current Quantum Service,
quantum Cloud Services from IBM.
Google, Amazon and Microsoft are
struggling with pricing model.
They're trying to meter the UNM and
unpredic the unpredictable, predictable
insult classic cloud bill, like known
CP, known memory, known storage,
which is leads to predictable cost.
But whereas you can see compute, quantum
cloud bill, billing, like unknown
time, unknown errors, unknown Ries,
and don't know about a cost at the end.
So this is where the story get
interesting because there is a company
that looked at this whole mess and said,
what if we just don't meet cumulus?
Instead of trying to measure every quantum
operations and charge you for ease things,
they took completely different approach.
As you can see in this slide, there
is a comparison between traditional
cloud approach and a seamless approach.
As you can see, traditional approach,
which is step one, measure everything
and then complex calculations, and
that at the end surprises bill.
Whereas the seamless approach,
there is a pretty defined fixed
resources, fixed prices, and then
you will sleep well at night.
So Cumulus believes in providing
high performing fixed cost computing
power instead of selling every single
service and metering the users.
You can get started with S Cloud
platform for less than just.
Less than just a hundred dollars
monthly, no upfront cost, no long-term
commitments and no surprise bills.
It's just like Netflix for cloud
computing and you pay for monthly fee.
You get access to the platform
and you can use it without
borrow about the meter running.
You can get started with Ulus
Cloud platform for less than
just a hundred dollar monthly.
No upfront cost, no long-term
commitments, no surprise bills.
Just like Netflix for cloud computing,
you pay for monthly fee and you get the
access to the platform and you can use it
without worrying about the meter running.
Now let me explain why this
approach is brilliant for quantum
computing because ulus is built on
open stack, which is open source.
This means no vendor lock in, and you are
not trapped in anyone's quantum ecosystem.
Let me share a real example
of why this matters.
I talked to a startup that
moved from AWS to Ulus here.
What changed before AWS
monthly will somewhere between
eight $800 to the $4,000.
The time is spent off on cost
optimization is 20 20% of engineering
time and you can see sleep quality.
Ability to experiment is in the
limit and innovation rate is slow.
And on the other end you can see
at q plus monthly bill is now too
low, too less, and time is spent
on cost optimization is zero.
You can see sleep quality, actually
good, and ability to experiment
unlimited within the resources.
And other last one is innovation date,
which is three x faster than the AWS.
So the founder told me something
that I'll never forget.
The best fight is not
even the cost saving.
It being able to actually build
things instead of consistently
optimizing for AWS pricing.
When quantum computing become
mainstream, this difference
will be even more dramatic.
Company using traditional paper quantum
operations model is will spend more
time on time optimizing for cost,
then optimizing for the result.
Company which is using fixed due pricing
model will be free to experiment,
innovate, and actually solves problem.
Look, quantum computing is going
to reconstruct how we solve
problems, but it doesn't, hand
doesn't have to be transformed
your budget in the wrong direction.
The future belongs to the platform that
understand quantum unpredictability
and abstract it away from developers.
So fixed pricing.
It is not just better cloud
economics, it's the foundation that
make quantum innovation possible
without quantum sized financial risk.
So you can check ulus on the ulus.io
and see what transparent and fixed
pricing actually means in practice.
So the future is quantum and your cloud
bill doesn't have to be quantum chaotic.
So thank you everyone.
As this is a prerecorded talk, you
can ask me any questions or anything
related to tech or cloud, anything.
I'm happy to answer any questions
you might have just ping me
up on the LinkedIn or tutor.
And these are my handles you
can see in this light, so
you can follow me also there.
So thank you everyone.
Bye bye.