Hello everyone.
My name is Pavan Moti.
So I am a senior technical lead at
Oracle Corp. And so today my topic is
basically we'll discuss about quantum
computing and then how it impacts on
the cloud security and then how we
should be prepared for that actually.
This would be my topic.
Now for many years quantum computing
was some, something we thought as far
off like maybe 10 or 20 years away.
But that's no longer true.
Quantum computing is moving from theory
of reality very quickly, and as it
does, it poses some serious risk to the
cryptographic foundations we rely on
today to protect the cloud environments.
So this talk is really about
how we can start preparing now.
Before, the quantum computing
starts breaking the encryption,
like today's standard encryption,
and it exposes the sensitive data.
So first of all, what is
quantum computing, right?
So let's dig in little
more detail in that.
So quantum computing operates
using quantum bits or the,
it's called Q bits also.
So unlike classic bits which you
know, are zero on zero or one.
Qubits can be both zero
and one at the same time.
It's because of the property called super
position, so they can also be entangled,
meaning that the state of one qubit can
be linked to another, allowing for highly
parallel processing, extremely fast
computation for certain type of problems.
Now, why does that matter for security?
Because quantum computers
can run algorithms that are
fundamentally different.
And far more powerful
than the classic ones.
Let's take an example.
Short algorithm, right?
And it allows quantum computer to
factor large prime numbers exponentially
faster than the classic computers.
And this threatens RSA
and then ECC encryption.
This is basically the public key
cryptography views everywhere.
It's ubiquitous in the cloud systems.
So another example would
be the Grover algorithm.
The it can also get weakened by
the symmetric encryption, right?
So in short, quantum computing's
game changer for cryptography.
Now let's let's look at specifically
how quantum computing threatens
today's cloud environments.
So today's cloud security lies
heavily on R-S-N-E-C-C, for public
reintroduction, for identity
key exchange, TLS, everything.
A sufficient, powerful quantum
computer code use short solid rhythm
to crack RSA 2 0 4 right in minutes,
completely breaking these protections.
The is the quantum, the cloud-based
quantum computing market is
expected to be worth around like
$4 billion by in, in few years.
So we are actually in 2023.
It's this seven 98 million by
2028 in a couple of years, it's
gonna grow exponentially higher.
So we discussed about the, like the
quantum computing we discussed about what
the qubits are and then how it enables the
massive pallet processing and all that.
Yeah.
So now let's talk about like how
the quantum computing threatens
the cloud security, right?
There are like three key risks
I want to highlight, one is
breaking publicly encryption.
Today's cloud secure lies heavily
on RSA and and EC for public
publicly encryption, for identity
keys exchange, TLS, everything.
So as a sufficient, powerful quantum
computer could use short algorithm
to crack, like I said, that like
the 2 0 4 8 in minutes, right?
And then also it weakens the Semitic
encryption system again, like I've given
an example about the Grover algorithm.
How it gets how it gets weakened.
And then also there is the third
thing, harvest nav and decrepit later.
So this is the very scariest part.
Attackers are already stealing encrypt
data, knowing what, when quantum
computers become called powerful enough,
they'll be able to decrepit later.
So long-term sensitive data like health,
healthcare records, financial data,
government secrets, they're all at risks.
And then also the D cert.
The report says that 61% or more than
60% of our organizations are worried
about this, and this is with good reason.
Now how do we prepare for
quantum computing security?
So what can we do about it?
So there, here are the
five key strategies, like I
want to show showcase here.
The most promising long-term solution is.
The new cryptographic to come
up with a new cryptographic
algorithms that are resistant to
both classic and quantum attacks.
So in 2022 NIST selected four algorithms,
the crystal cuber for key exchanges,
crystal's, digital lithium, falcon,
and spinx for digital signatures.
So these are all part of
post quantum cryptography.
Like there's a new cryptographic
algorithms that we should, that
the industry should embrace.
As opposed to the the classic algorithms
to prevent from the quantum attacks.
And the second one is basically
the quantum key distribution.
This is a more exotic
but very secure approach.
Using quantum mechanics itself
is secure exchange keys.
Any attempts to eves drops can
be detected because measuring
a quantum state changes it.
QKD is still limited, high cost limited
range, but promising for defense,
finance and government sectors.
And the third one is basically
using hybrid cryptographic systems.
So in the near term, the best
path is to combine traditional
and quantum safe algorithms.
It's basically allowing backward
compatibility while also
gaining stronger production.
So Microsoft and Google are
already testing this, for example.
Kyber plus traditional Ts in
Chrome and Azure environments.
The fourth is basically the
cloud vendor initiatives, right?
Some major cloud providers
are taking steps.
Azure offers quantum safe,
VPN options, IBM Cloud.
I think they're te still in the testing
phase for post quantum algorithms.
And AWS already provides a
lot of cryptographic inventory
tools and migration guidance.
So basically partnership
with cloud vendors is key.
Quantum readiness will increasingly be co.
It'll be increasingly co differentiated.
So the fifth point is
basically the cryptographic
inventory and risk assessment.
This is very critical.
Organizations need to identify
where encryption is used, what
key and are in place, and where
the sensitive data is reside.
Long, long term data systems
like healthcare financial should
be prioritized for updates, and
then also zero test architecture.
We'll also help reusing if there
are any certain productions
which are weak or broken.
So we discussed about
all these five points.
Now let's talk about like how
to prepare for quantum post
quantum computing security.
Like we discussed this five points.
So now let's talk about the challenges.
So this transition is not easy.
There are three big challenges.
One is compatibility.
The migration cost and risk of inaction.
And for with respect to com compatibility,
like many quantum safe algorithms don't
work well with legacy systems and devices.
And then also migration cost also
it will be significant investment.
And then, the risk of inaction
is much higher than than like
the potential migration cost.
So basically the average cloud
breach already cost like around
like $4.4 million straight.
Okay, so once quantum attacks are
practical, that could skyrocket.
So doing nothing is the riskiest choice.
So what is the path forward?
So here are the practical steps every
cloud aligned organization should take.
Now the first is basically
like we discussed, like the
implement hybrid encryption.
Then also monitor the ISD standards.
And IS you this and stay current,
like with the as this post quantum
computing algorithms mature.
And then also please collaborate
with your cloud vendors such as
your AWS, Microsoft and IBM, and
then also conduct crypto audits.
So quantum computing, again,
is no longer a science fiction.
It's coming.
And then cloud security teams
need to start preparing now
to stay ahead of the curve.
Yeah.
So to wrap up so we are on the
verge of quantum computing era
and quantum era in the computing.
So this brings enormous potential, but
also significant risk to the security
foundations of today's cloud environment.
So by starting now through
hybrid encryption crypto
audits, cloud partnerships, and
zero trust, it can be ready.
Quantum resilience will be a key pillar.
Of cloud security in the thank
you and if you have any questions,
please reach out to me or my email.
Thank you.