Hello everyone.
Welcome to Quantum 42, quantum
Computing 2025 conference.
I'm Ga Jar Mohan.
I am a software engineer at
Microsoft and I'm gonna talk
about quantum powered iot today.
How iot is gonna revolutionize by
the quantum computing concepts.
So it's gonna change the entire
intelligence and security in iot space.
So let's get started.
So the first thing I wanna talk about is,
of course, like what is quantum computing?
In classical computers we
usually have like zeros in ones.
That's how we process it so that it
logical is always either zero or one.
You can see in the left side the bit is.
The logic is if it is existed as
one, and if it doesn't, it's zero.
But in the cons, in the case of quantum
computing, in the concept of quantum
world, we have something called a qubits.
Qubits actually exist in
a state of superposition.
Which means that it can either exist
in a state of, in between zero and one.
So it can exist at zero
and one at the same time.
So how, what is it?
Actually make an impact because
in a classical computer, you can
see the way we solve the problem
is if we are entering a maze.
Okay.
If the left one is blocked or not.
Yeah.
We keep continuing once we hit the
block and then we come back and
then we go and try the next route.
So it is serialized because
of the state of zeros in once.
But in the case of quantum computing.
You can compute these things very
parallelly because these can exist
in the state of both zeros and ones.
So in this way you can calculate
or solve a puzzle much faster than
a classical computer would do.
So there is also something called
as entanglement, which is a
concept in quantum computing.
It is the state of one
influence the other.
Basically, if you know that this
route is gonna be all gone, then
we don't even try that route.
We instead just cancel out those
possibilities and then just move
ahead so that you don't have
to, waste time in the compute.
So that is how quantum computing
is actually different from
the classical computing.
So how this is going to change the iot
space or any other space in general?
We will see that.
But first let's get into how we
are gonna focus on the iot space,
which is Internet of Things.
So Internet of Things is like any device
that is connected to internet, right?
But.
They also have a huge
bottleneck currently.
So the bottleneck, bottleneck
can be in the categories of
intelligence and security, and
that's what we're gonna target today.
So the quantum computing
can help in these two areas.
So if you wanna focus on intelligence
first, when we'll get into these two
subcategories, which is iot, data
analytics, and then IOT machine learning.
So first is in the intelligence space.
Let's get into the iot data analytics.
So internet of things
actually create a lot of data.
They are very unstructured.
They're very noisy.
We don't know where the device is coming,
how this sensor data can be made sense
because there's temperature coming,
pressure coming, and there's like whole
lot coming from one factory and there's
like lot coming every minute and second.
So the data is pretty huge.
So what does quantum computing
can do in this space?
What is the main purpose
of quantum computing?
It can actually analyze like
large set of unstructured data.
It can make sense out of it, and it
can actually be more efficient in
terms of space and time and memory
when compared to classical computers.
And also it can accelerate the
machine learning world because mission
learning environment has a unique
pattern where it needs to do multiple
computation at the same time, right?
So it can accelerate.
The anomaly detection and also it can
improve the inferencing at the edge.
So we'll get into that.
And also iot analytics in this
specifically will it improves the
pattern recognition because, the
quantum algorithms are very powerful.
HSL algorithm and quantum
game means algorithm.
They can find patterns in
very large exponential data.
It can actually try to look for
the main component of details and
then it can quickly find a pattern
of the data that you're looking
for and can give you an answer.
So an example would be Volkswagen using
a quantum algorithm to detect the traffic
flow and also patterns like which area
is more densely traffic area in the
urban areas, and also can try to optimize
the traffic systems in that space.
Other big, advantage of
in the intelligence space
is the anomaly detection.
So every time when we go to airports
or any even in healthcare, we wanna
find out that or manner, in order
to do that we really heavily rely
on the machine learning algorithms.
So what quantum computing can
do it, it can scan the multiple
possibilities simultaneously.
And as I said, it can actually, rule
out all the things which doesn't
make sense, and then try to get into
the solution directly so it can find
out those outliers and r events much
quicker than the classical computers.
And it can really help in cybersecurity
also, like in, for example, in Cambridge
Quantum, they have developed a highly
and enhanced anomaly detection.
So they have a tool.
To spot unusual patterns in
the traffics network traffic.
So anything that happens in large scale
iot, they're able to quickly identify
what is the anomaly of out there in
the network, if there is any fraud
happening or anything of that sort.
It, the quantum computing algorithms are
much, much powerful in detecting those.
So this can help in the iot
space when the network is much
more complex and continuated.
So next comes the recommendation system.
Actually, quantum inspired recommendation
systems have been proved to be better
than the usual a recommendation system.
So you can see Netflix and
Amazons are actually doing some
research to explore the quantum
based collaborative methods par.
It can filter out like the
preferences of the user and then
try to make a better recommendation.
Another very important thing in the
security space is the fraud detection.
So we know every transaction is, must
be very secure in the case of iot space.
So there is a quantum mono method
which actually provides more accurate
simulations, so it can find out if there
is any slight in prediction of any fraud
happening that it can actually detect
very quickly and it can actually find out.
If if the model if the fraud has
happened and it can quickly also notify.
So Goldman Sachs and JP Morgan are
actually investing in the quantum
computing because this is gonna make
a big difference in, in the future.
So next is the bioinformatics.
Bioinformatics is like in the genome
space, which is basically finding
out like how our DNAs and everything
basically studying in more depth of it.
So quantum computing is actually used
in the gen genomics sequence alignment.
So you can see these different
computations are actually happening,
which is very complex and heavy and to
understand and study the DNA sequencing.
So this.
Is a space where quantum
computing can really help.
And actually, D wave F system has actually
collaborated with the healthcare startups.
So they are doing this DNA analysis
workflows which can actually use the
quantum computing algorithms for that.
So next comes the main one, which
is the quantum machine learning.
So in the compute space, in the
intelligence space, the machine
learning is the biggest break
deal breaker in the coming future.
Because what happens, iot faces a lot of
problem with the respect to inferencing
in the edge because we always rely on the
cloud for inferencing for post-processing.
But now the way the world is
changing more towards edge, but we
also want a very backend powerful
way of inferencing at the cloud or
somewhere in the out outsource space.
So that is a place where
quantum computing can help.
Iot, as I mentioned, it can generate
lot of data, high intensity, high
high velocity data, and they're
very noisy and unstructured.
So these limited power and energy
at the edge can actually leverage
the compute quantum computing at the
backend so they can increase the need.
So basically.
Real time decisions can be made
if the inferencing is very fast in
quantum computing, and that can be,
offloaded to the quantum computer.
And this machine learning
just makes the whole process
from start to end much easier.
So the next part I want to talk about is
how it helps in the world of security.
Also I wanted to talk about.
How the inferencing happens in the edge.
So when we can also leverage
the help of training because
not just inferencing, right?
Inferencing happens in the edge,
but in the case of training
those models, large data sets, we
need the quantum support vector
machines, well as kernel estimation.
So these are models from the quantum
computing machine learning models.
They can actually improve
the predictor maintenance.
They can put, they can even like.
Predict before anything happens in a much
faster, in a much advanced, and also in
a very less time that it can actually be
very, really helpful for the predictor
maintenance and ma manufacturing and
factories and every other field which
needs which needs predictor maintenance.
And also it can handle high
dimensional sensor data.
Because right now sensors are
usually are zeros and ones, right?
So there is.
Some concept called a quantum
sensors, which can actually
do multiple sensor fusion.
So these kind of multi, multiple fusion
sensors can be used in smart cities
and smart agriculture, especially also
in the ag autonomous vehicle world.
So as I mentioned, backend influencing is
the very key process of machine learning
with the help of quantum computing.
So when we have a model
which is optimized for.
Quantum world and then in the inferencing
becomes much easier and much, much faster.
And this can really help
the whole internet of things
space using quantum computing.
So next is the security.
So we have touched based on how
quantum computing can really help
and break the intelligence space.
But the security is another side of the
coin, which is amazing because as you
see today's classical world, we actually
have RSAs encryption algorithms, which
cannot be broken today because the
classical computers are beyond that.
The keys are very long.
It's enough to break.
It is very hard to break them.
But in the world of con quantum
computing, RSAs, all this complex
security algorithms can be easily broken
because they are very good and highly
ly ruling out all the possibilities
and trying to get into the crux of it.
So the security becomes weaker as in
the introductions of quantum computing,
but also when it comes, it also comes
with an advantage that you can leverage
some of the principles of quantum
computing and en enhance security.
So in IOD space, the security is such a
big problem because in initially it was
not designed for our security in mind.
So the critical vulner liberties
that we have today, it can be
solved using quantum computing.
So there are four techniques that are
followed, which is defense against
quantum attacks, quantum key distribution,
as well as quantum random generator,
as well as identity management.
We'll look into all these four right now.
So the first one is the.
Quantum attacks, right?
So what happens, as I mentioned the RSA
is E-E-S-A-E-S is the most used algorithm.
So these are very vulnerable
to source algorithm.
If we have a quantum computer that
can uses algorithm and because it
can easily break the, it can find the
keys that were used to encrypt while
doing a ES and R sale encryptions.
So what happens is when we have a
quantum, when we have a. When we have
a very powerful algorithm coming up,
we have a quantum safe protocol that
can future proof the iot ecosystems.
Especially with these long, long
life cycles like vehicles and medical
and implants and satellites, they
can foolproof the whole entire
space when we use quantum computing
because it strengthens entire
strengthens is much better than
RSC and EECC that we have today.
So the next one is
quantum key distribution.
So right now we have the public and
public key and private key, a combination,
which will be used to set in one
place and authenticate another place.
But in the case of quantum queue key dev
distribution, we have this method, which
is a much secure communication which
uses the principle of quantum mechanics.
So the way it uses a quantum mechanism
is like to make it much more powerful the
way we exchange keys, the encryption keys.
This way, the keys are much more
secure and it's very, it takes very,
even more powerful to put a powerful
tool of condom computing to break it.
Also as gu, it also guarantees
detection of any eavesdropping.
If there is any facing that happens,
it can immediately detect and
also figure out like where it has
happened and notify it very quickly.
It also enables unbreakable key exchange.
So whenever we have IOT devices
from the cloud center and
as well as the edge devices.
So it enables that exchange
to be much more secure.
So for example, the secure key
exchange between the autonomous
vehicle and the roadside units, right?
So these things can be tightly coupled
when we use quantum key distributions.
So the next concept of security is
quantum random key generated, which
uses quantum phenomena to generate
truly random numbers because as we
agree today, if you use a ran function,
it actually generates some random
numbers, but they're not truly random.
But in order to get a truly random
numbers, you can use a quantum method.
So it enhances the encryption key
strength as well as, it can authenticate
it much better by using a very
stronger key example is you can use
ORNG for secure session initiation
for industrial sensors because
industrial sensors are, as I mentioned.
They need to first start
the nodes and then start
communicating the channel, right?
So once we, once they start with the
proper random generator, they can
actually secure it from the start itself.
So the last but not least is
tamper proof identity management.
So we have signatures today that we sign
and send so that it creates that kind of
an extra level of encryption and security.
But in the case of quantum enhanced
authentication method, we have
something called quantum signatures.
So these signatures are they ensure
that devices are verified correctly,
and they're not like spoofed.
And also the communication is traceable.
So anything, anywhere, any chain
breaks, it can easily detect it.
For example, in critical
infrastructures, only the authenticated
and quantum sign devices can
actually, send actuated signals.
So basically it can open the
wall and shut down a tower.
And so all these critical
things can be done.
So in this way, you're maintaining
the identity management much better.
So these are all the techniques
that we saw in the space of quantum
computing as well as quantum quantum
computing is doing the space of
intelligence as well as in security.
So hope you learn something
new and if any questions, feel
free to reach out in LinkedIn.
Thank you so much.