Hi everyone.
This is Kar Kti man from Frisco, Texas.
I'm an SAP project manager, having
long one years of experience in
SAP and almost la 14 years of
experience as a project manager.
In last seven, eight years, I did
almost less seven s 400 implementations.
And how experience of working
with the different industries like
manufacturing, healthcare agriculture,
pharma and chemical industries, and
also food and beverage industries.
Today I'm going to talk about SAPA,
transfer me to power technical insight
and industry specific applications.
We all know that SAP is an ERP
system and also now the world.
AI is sticking over the,
all the technologies.
So let's see how SAP and AI is integrated
together for this ERP business.
For multiple industries, SAP artificial
intelligence capabilities are izing
multiple industries through tailored
intelligent application built on the
business technology platform, BTP.
That is one of the package from SAP.
SAP AI seamlessly integrates
with existing enterprise systems
while providing sophisticated
machine learning, natural language
processing, and VE and capabilities.
These presentation explores how
SAP AI leverage is multi-layered
architecture to address industry specific
challenges across retail healthcare.
Supply chain energy and
agriculture sectors.
Let's see the detailed presentations.
SAP, business Technology Platform,
SAP, ai, core Architectures.
Let's see how business technology
platforms and the service are integrated
with the ASAP AI core architecture,
business technology platforms
integration layer, API management
and data orchestration capabilities
that form the foundation of SAP ai.
Solutions.
And also SAP says that machine learning
services classifications regression
clustering and an MLA detection algorithm
that power intelligent applications,
natural language processing, entity
extraction, sentiment analysis and
document understanding capability,
work and structured data, computer
vision object detection, defect
identification, visual inspection
technologies for image analysis.
Let's see.
So SAP and e-commerce applications working
together to help the retail and e-commerce
applications recommendation engines.
SAP AI recommends system employ
collaborative filter algorithms
combined with content based
filtering to create hybrid models.
Text the Select personalization.
These models analyze customer interaction,
purchase history, browsing patterns to
generate relevant product suggestions.
The implementation in Cooperates
Metric Federation techniques for
identifying data and futures and
deep learning neural networks for
processing and structured data means.
SAP is helping to model, analyze
the customer interactions and also
sure, also, gather the purchase
histories, the browsing patterns, and
generate relevant product suggestions.
And let's see, demand forecasting
for inventory optimization.
SAP integrate times and series analysis.
External factors such as market
trends, seasonal variations,
and social media sentiment.
Dark picture includes LSTM
Network to capture long term
dependencies in time series data.
The systems typically
employ and symbol methods.
Combining LLST and networks with
traditional RMI models achieving high
forecast accuracy rates for short term
and medium term projections, demand
forecasting and SAP is playing a
crucial role, the help of AI in this
ERP World Extra Healthcare application.
How it's helping care applications
with the AI optimization
patient admission prediction.
SAP healthcare AI solution utilize
multi-variate regression models and
classification algorithms to predict
admission rates with remarkable accuracy.
These systems analyze
historical admission data.
Seasonal illness patterns, local event
calendar, population demography, and
current facility utilization rates.
It clearly says that it is collecting
the illness patterns and also the local
event calendars with the helping patient
admission predictions to the hospitals.
And next care enhancement early.
This is a detection, leverages
natural language processing to
mine un unstructured clinical notes
alongside structured patient data.
The system employs transfer based models
for text analysis, anomaly detection
algorithm to identify clear inpatient
metrics and secure data processing
that maintains the HIPAA compliances.
It's also helping the hospitals
to make sure they're following
the HIPAA compliance processes by.
Following patterns which I provided
with the help of SAP clinical impact
facilities employing advanced NLP
for a clinical nurse analysis report.
Early introduction, increase for
high risk condition, corresponding
reductions in acute admission per
monitor condition, translating to
average cost reduction per patient.
It is like also helping in the cost
reduction and high risk introductions
eye finding acute admissions.
Okay, now let's see.
SAP integration with ai.
Applications for manufacturing
company data collections.
LOD sensor Gather equipment, elementary
and operational data in the real
time pattern analysis algorithm,
identify, anomaly and predict.
Potential failures.
Maintenance planning systems schedules
optimal interaction before failures occur.
Performance optimization,
continuous learning, improves
prediction accuracy over time.
Manufacturing facilitates employing
advance and predict to maintenance show
unplanned downtime reductions up to 50%.
And maintenance cost decrease of what,
10 to 40% compared to traditional
scheduled maintenance approaches.
These systems typically monitor thousands
of sensor per facility with edge
computing, noise processing, terabytes
of equipment, elementary data daily.
Here we can clearly see that SAP
integration with AI is helping good
data collection, pattern analysis,
maintenance planning, performance, or
optimization, which is like helping
the manufacturing industries to get
an advanced prediction maintenance.
Which is which shows like
it'll also helping to unplanned
downtime duction up to 50%.
Next quality with computer
vision image capture.
Analysis defect classification, product
integration, image capture, high
resolution camera capture, detailed
image of product on the production line.
AI analysis, conventional natural
network analysis, images, defects
with the precision exceeding human
inspection defect classification system
categorized defects by type and CVRT.
Enabling target process implements means.
The quality of the images increased and
also AI is going to analyze the neural
network analysis images, detect defects.
If you see any precision exceeding human
inspection, production integration,
real-time feedback to manufacturing system
enables immediate process adjustments.
CN based inspection system detect
up to 99% of surface defects and
structural cy compared to 80 to
90% per traditional machine vision
systems and human inspectors.
The economic impact translate to
documented disease in customer
reported quality issues and
assert variant claim reduction.
So it is also helping to reduce the
claim reductions and decrease in the
customer reported quality issues.
Finance and banking applications.
So finance and banking
are the most important.
And let's see, the fraud detection,
the document understanding
explainable AI financial processing.
Nowadays we are seeing like most
of the financial institutes that
using, aI platforms are AI apps.
So instead of talking to the human, the
AI will provide all the informations
and it is the banks and everyone is
saying that is an accurate information.
Let's see how it is going to detect
the fraud graph neural networks
model relationship between the
entities to identify suspicions.
Pattern means it's also detect the
fraud if any unauthorized persons
are trying to use your accounts.
P transforms.
Explainable AI shop and line
framework generate transparent
decision and rationals financial
forecasting reinforcement learning,
optimiz prediction across it.
Also forecast for some of the
apps, it forecast the financials
so that you can plan accordingly.
For example, if you take in stock markets,
it'll give the predictions and based
on that, you can invest on your stocks.
SAP's fraud detection capabilities employs
adaptive graphic neural networks with
optimized message passing mechanism.
That analysis system's ability to
identify abnormal patterns with
complex financial network demonstrating
market improved meant over traditional
rule-based systems means it is overall,
it is helping the financial industries
on the market based and traditional
rule based systems, supply chain.
Let's see how supply chain is
integrated with SAP AI and how
it is helping the supply chain
departments route optimization.
Multi objective, visionary
algorithms, balance, cost, time,
and environmental impact while
respecting real world constraints.
Early warning systems and simple methods.
Monitor diverse data streams to
identify potential disruptions
before the impact operations.
Digital supply chain twins.
Virtual representation enable
scenario planning through
sophisticated simulation capabilities.
Dynamic rerouting automatic response
to emerging constraints without
requiring manual intervention means
it is taking optimization, is giving
early warning systems and also a
digital supply chain with the dynamic
routing with the automatic response.
Energy and utility management.
Consumption optimization, balancing
multiple objectives in the cost.
Demanding grid capability means it,
it also give you the grid capability
means like when you open your energy,
app, which you are using for your home.
It gives all the information
renewable energy forecasting, hybrid
models, combining physics based
and machine learning approaches
not only for your home based apps.
It is for entire industry,
for utility industries.
And also for any manufacturing industry
any industries which are using energy
storage optimization, determining
optimal charging and discharging
cycles for diverse technologies,
microgrid management, enabling
reason and power delivery through
sophisticated balancing systems.
SAP AI implements competency
energy management solutions that
leverage reinforcement learning
techniques to optimize conception
patterns across complex utility.
Networks implementation study demonstrate
these approaches deliver substantial
improvements in key energy management
metrics, including e load reduction,
overall consumption efficiency,
renewable energy utilization rates.
So here you can clearly see that the
bottom, it says that it is really helping
the energy and utility management industry
saying that low reduction consumption
efficiencies and renewable energy rates.
Agriculture decision support satellite
energy analysis means it analysis
the computer vision algorithm
extract actionable insights from
multi-spectral data, enabling earlier
interaction for developing issues
including moisture stress, new newly
deficiency and pesty fixations.
So environmental mon monitoring field
levels, sensor networks, providing
granular data on soil conditions.
Micro variation, crop development,
creating a multi-dimensional
view of agriculture operations.
Yield prediction gradient.
Booster edition trees captures
non-linear relations between
environmental conditions, management
practice, and crop genetic to predict
production outcomes with high accuracy.
It's helping satellite
imaging analysis, environment
monitoring and yield production.
Technical benefits of SAPI implementations
a hundred percent enterprise integration,
seamless connectivity with existing
S-R-P-S-A-P-E-R-P and business systems.
99.9% system availability, high
reliability across mutual deployments, and
thousand extra query performance faster
than traditional database architectures.
And 24 by seven continuous learning.
Self BR system that adapt
to changing conditions.
So these A EA solutions deliver
substantial technical advantages through
an architectural approach that emphasizes
enterprise integration, scalability,
continuous improvement, and security.
This compromise approach to
enterprise AI represents a fundamental
advance beyond isolated machine
learning projects, transforming the
theoretical into practical business.
Through integration with
operational realities.
Thank you.
This is my today's presentation.
Hope you all like it.
Thank you once again.
Thank you very much.