Hello everyone.
Good morning, good
afternoon, good evening.
From part of the world.
You are listening to this presentation.
It's a privilege to speak to you today on
a subject that sits at the intersection
of cutting edge physics, advanced
computing, and the fast world of.
As we know, today's financial markets
are already driven by ultra low latency
trading strategies, massive data
analytics, sophisticated algorithms,
but as computing approaches the physical
and performance limits, we are standing
on the edge of a new technological
frontier with quantum computing.
Quantum computing isn't just another
leaking speed or storage, it's completely
re-imagining of how computation works.
By leveraging principles like super
position entanglement, quantum
computers are capable of solving
certain complex problems exponentially
faster than classical machines.
And this capability opens up.
Imagine a real time portfolio optimization
across thousands of correlated assets.
Imagine risk simulation that wants
to co reduced to milliseconds.
Imagine a trading system that
doesn't just react faster, but can
process and astronomically large
decision space, evaluating market
signals, counterparty behavior,
and regulatory impact nevertheless
simultaneously and in real time.
While the potential is vast, the
challenge are equally significant
from hardware limitations to algorithm
development and critically integration
into today's market infrastructure.
In this presentation, we'll explore
how quantum computing is being
harnessed in trading where the
real computational advantages lie.
Quantum accelerated financial
future might actually look like.
As you all know, these days,
this isn't fiction anymore.
This paradigm how markets move,
I'm senior techn with investment.
Specializing in delivering
high performance, cost
effective technology solutions.
My expertise spans across fixed
income trading, risk management,
regulatory compliance, client
reporting, and I have extensively
worked with the industry leading
products, trading products such as ion.
Broker, broker dealer, Bloomberg
and Wall Street fx, which is also
product of Ion brought carrier.
I built a reputation for managing,
designing, and optimizing advanced
technology infrastructures that
support business operations in the
capital markets and financial services.
I have a deep understanding of the
fixed income trading platforms and
the businesses, commodity trading
platforms capability, particularly
in managing and streamlining
fixed income trading processes.
I have involved in design development
optimization trading strategy that
leveraged advanced quantitative models
market might work, include implementing.
Trading algorithms, market making
strategies, risk adjusted grad
strategies that have significantly
improved execution and efficiency.
With that understanding of execution
venues, liquidity management, I have
worked to find tune algorithmic strategies
that optimize slippage, reduce trading
cost, and minimize market impact.
I have a diverse range of financial
experience in financial products
such as US Treasury, swaps, credit
equities, and OT OTC database.
That's a short summary about me.
Now let's deep dive into the
quantum accelerated trading systems,
which is revolutionizing financial
markets through computational.
Unprecedented volume of data leading
exchanges generating three 42
billion market data messages daily.
That's an incredible and
amount of data that we process.
Additional computing, architecture,
fundamental limitations, and
processing this efficiently.
Research how quantum computing A
are transforming H infrastructure,
offering significant
computational stake environment.
On the next slide, quantum
FinTech over recognition of
quantum computing transformative
potential in trading systems.
The significant improvements in both
processing speed and resource efficiency
demonstrate why leading firms are
rapidly adopting these technologies.
94% on the leadership recognition,
financial technology leaders
identify quantum advantage critical
for the next generation systems.
Calculation speed reduction in
complex calculation time compare
to the classical approaches.
78% of calculation speed
that has been reduced.
So things which used to take let's say one
hour, about 80% have been reduced in doing
the calculation for the high frequency.
67% of the resource efficiencies
decrease in the computational resource
requirements while implementing
quantum inspired algorithms
crossing capabilities.
The in parameter crossing capabilities
translates directly to competitive
in algorithmic trading models.
Sophistication drives profitability.
Quantum enhanced systems.
Systems leveraging quantum technique
demonstrated that they can process
optimization problems with 300 half
times more parameters while maintaining
sub millisecond response times.
This expanded parameter space enables
more sophisticated rating models
that can incorporate a wider range
of market factors and signals.
Simultaneously, traditional computing
approaches manages only 1.4.
Parameter capacity under
the same latency conditions.
Significantly limiting complexity.
These systems struggle to incorporate
the full range of relevant market
variables leading to less optimized
rating based on incomplete information.
The response times, as you see
in the chart, quantum enhanced
the in high frequency trading.
That nanoseconds can
become a profit or loss.
This advantage represents a revolutionary
leap forward in execution capabilities.
The integration of quantum algorithms
with acceleration has enabled superior
pattern recognition capabilities
and trading systems that this
technological combination allows for.
Industry average of about 1 45 microsecond
machine learning performance improvements.
These enhanced models can identify complex
market patterns, invisible to classical
algorithms enabling more precise entry and
accurate in volatile market conditions.
Quantum machine learning techniques have
demonstrated remarkable improvements.
Accuracy while maintaining the
stringent latency requirements.
Essential for high frequency
trading application.
The 41% reduction in
forecasting as you see in the.
Requirements, SUBSECOND
processing prediction accuracy,
41% reduction in error rates.
This is one interesting case
study implementation of a
three year one trading firms.
This case study followed three
trading forms through their complete
implementation journey, each organization
followed a similar process assessment
for our process of assessment,
development, integration, and evaluation
with performance improvements of.
Initial assessment, basically
identification of comput, computational
bottlenecks and existing trading
infrastructure, algorithm development,
creation of quantum inspired
optimization algorithms, tailored for
portfolio management, infrastructure
integration, deployment of hybrid
quantum classical computing architecture.
And finally, the performance evaluation
measurement of about like 80% of
reduction in calculation time across
the complex trading operations.
Classical hybrid framework.
This architecture has been validated
across multiple asset classes,
consistently delivering 99.9% execution
reliability, while enabling implementation
of advanced trading strategies.
Quantum classical hybrid
framework leverages the strength
of each computational paradigm.
Classical systems handle high volume data.
Quantum processors tackle complex
optimization problems and the hardware.
The F hardware provides a deterministic
execution with minimal la, the data ion
high throughput market data processing
via classical systems, ultra low latency.
Complex calculations offloaded to
quantum processors and the hardware level
implementation of optimized algorithm,
competitive implementation, timeline
advantage, classical computing approach.
The implementation of timeline
advantage represents perhaps most
significant competitive edge for early.
To market advantage translates
directly to capturing trading
opportunities before competitors.
This first more advantage is
particularly valuable in emerging
market situation and during the periods
of heightened volatility where the.
Heavy duty of sell and volatility in
the dealer to dealer platform or dealer
to client platform market happens then.
Market is huge classical
computing approach.
The traditional implementation
pathways require extensive development
cycles for new trading strategies.
The complex risk models and
optimization proteins can take months
to develop, test, and deploy using
conventional computing resources.
But the quantum enhanced approach
firms utilizing the Quantum Enhanced
Computing frameworks can implement
advanced strategies, which is
three enough times faster than the.
Acceler from both computational speed
and superior parameter optimization.
This self-explanatory if you look at
it at the equities fixed income, the
multi-asset performance analysis, latency
improvement, equities, person percent.
This is one area where the error reduction
can we have a lot of opportunity to
reduce to 50% latency improvement
is 80%, 75%, and the parameter
capacity is 3% for foreign exchange.
Amazing.
Return of investment for relatedly
implement using quantum systems.
Three.
Commodity trading, 79% ency
improvement, 3% sorry, three
times parameter capacity and error
reduction of 39% derivatives over 88%.
Latency improvement, 90% of latency
improvement can be achieved.
3.5% five times parameter
capacity, and 47% error reduction.
Equities and effect markets also
showed remarkable improvements,
particularly in latency reduction
and error rate minimization.
Our research validated the quantum
classical hybrids framework across
all major asset classes while
performance improvements based.
Most significant gains were observed
in derivative ratings where the
complex mathematical models benefit
most from quantum optimization.
Now the interesting topic challenges
now that we have spoken extensively
on the advantages of quantum
max related ratings, what are.
Second system reliability, third
incorporation complexity, and
fourth regulatory considerations.
Let's go through one by one.
The limited pool of professionals,
even both quantum computing
and financial markets.
Remember even get somebody with a
heavy duty map, knowledge heavy.
Comprehend the financial
markets presents a significant
barrier to the implementation.
Forward we identify for quantum computing
has to have extensive knowledge in
both finance and the technology leading
firms are addressing this through
specialized training programs and
partnership with academic institutions.
System reliability, early quantum
processes have higher error
rates than classical systems.
Hybrid architectures mitigate this by
implementing error correction protocols
and verification methods that ensure
99% execution, reliability, integration
complex systems with the quantum computing
systems connecting quantum processing.
And APIs that heal trading systems.
From the complexities of
quantum operation, why
maintaining the performance?
Finally, the regulatory and
compliance considerations.
Financial regulators are still
developing frameworks for
quantum enhanced trading systems.
Forward thinking firms are proactively
engaging with regulatory bodies to
establish operational standards.
So extensive analysis and research
are being carried out on the trade
surveillance and the spoofing related
activities, which is very closely
tried with the trading systems,
future outlook and
strategic recommendations.
The quantum revolution in.
They begin with targeted applications.
So developing a hybrid architecture
and preparing for a quantum
advantages advantage scaling
begins with a targeted application.
Start by for any future outlook, right?
Start by applying quantum
enhanced algorithms, specific
computational bottleneck.
Portfolio optimization in US treasury
rate rating rather than completely
expanding the scope across all the
rates, commodities red, but rather
narrow down to one particular segment
under the fixed income portfolio under
US treasuries, let's say focus only
on the keynotes or some level of US
treasuries and pricing applications that.
Built internal capabilities in quantum
classical hybrid system design.
The most successful implementation.
We leverage both paradigms using
quantum processes for optimization
problems while maintaining classical
systems for deterministic operation.
Preparing for quantum advantage
is scaling as quantum hardware
matures over the next three to five
years, prepare varying systems to.
Now we'll be positioned to rapidly fund
capabilities as the technology evolves.
Quantum revolution in, like I said, the
financial world is no longer a theory.
It's happening.
And several firms, the firms
which I am working are trying to.
Organizations that embrace quantum
enhanced trading systems that today will
establish competitive advantages that
will be difficult to fall to overcome
at the end of time Implementation.
Speed advantage compounds over time,
creating an expanding capability
gap between leaders and followers.
And that comes to the.
This presentation science.