hi everyone.
I'm Sai.
K. It's a pleasure to be here at the
conference 42 to share what I've learned
about the quantum computing today.
So when I first began exploring this
field, I vividly recall reading a paper
that described quantum speedups as almost
magical science, like fiction made real, I
felt excitement, mingled with skepticism,
of course, like who won't, right?
Could these fragile devices
truly deliver the things that
they're promising over time?
Small experiments convinced me
there is substance beneath the hype.
Today we live in a Nisc era where hardware
remains imperfect, but already offers
tangible benefits in scoped problems.
Over the next 20 to 30 minutes,
I'll guide you through where we
stand, why quantum matters, concrete
examples in the industry, and how
to prepare for what lies ahead.
Let's begin by setting the scene and
revisiting how we have arrived here
and why even early experiments matter.
So let's actually move on
to where we stand today.
What is the current quantum
computing landscape?
So classical computing has driven
incredible advances in smartphones,
cloud services, machine learning, but
certain challenges grow exponentially
harder as scale increases.
For example, the traveling salesman
problem, of course, who doesn't
remember the traveling salesman problem?
When you're reading about computer
science, this is one of the
most head scratching problems
that one has read about, right?
So with a few cities,
of course it's trivial.
Let's say take an example of two to
three cities, it's not as hard, but
as you add more and more cities.
Possibilities, literally explode
our molecular simulations, modeling
electron interactions in even
moderately sized molecules can quickly,
overall, because of the sheer number
of electrons, and frankly speaking
how they interact with each other.
Quantum computing introduces
superposition and entanglement.
Letting us explore many
possibilities in parallel and capture
correlations beyond classical reach.
So which is exactly where we what we want.
And in today's NSC hardware, we have
10 to low hundreds of qubits, noisy
operations, and limited coherence times.
Despite these constraints creative
algorithms and hybrid workflows often
yield advantages on scoped problems.
Again, as I said, the
problems need to be scoped.
I remember a pilot where a small
team simulated a simple molecule.
Raw hardware results were very noisy.
Yet after combining with
classical approximations and error
mitigation, they guided a chemist
away from a costly lab test.
Of course, we cannot afford to
make expensive mistakes these days
with so much technology available,
and as such, these things matter.
That success, even though felt modest,
a fraction of a larger pipeline, but it
actually built to confidence and skills.
Understanding this context
prevents over hype.
We pursue quantum even because even
small wins now build expertise and
position us for larger breakthroughs.
Of course, this is exactly how Industrial
Revolution started as well, right?
So think of it like learning
how you, how you set to sail.
You start with a small boat
in a calm, open waters before
you tackle the open ocean.
Now let's actually dive deep into the
core quantum principles in practice.
So at the heart of the quantum advantage
lies superposition and entanglement.
So again, like as you can see, basically
there are, there's a lot of jargon.
And frankly speaking it gets overwhelming
when you're trying to learn new stuff.
Of course, I can understand.
So let's take a simple example.
Imagine spinning a coin until it lands.
You don't know whether
it is heads or tails.
Similarly, a qubit can hold both
possibilities simultaneously when qubits
entangle their states link, so that
measuring one affects the whole, allowing
representation of complex correlations,
classical bits cannot efficiently in code.
So in practice, algorithms like quantum
approximation optimization, world
optimization objective into a circuit.
The samples candidate solutions
though current devices are noisy,
running shallow circuits and
combining outputs with classical
post-processing can reveal better
solutions than classical heuristics.
I recall sitting in a meeting like where?
Engineers framed a logistics routing
problem on a quantum test, so they took
a region with about dozen stops encoded
cost functions into a variational
circuit and ran hardware experiments.
Raw outputs were super
noisy and inconsistent.
But after collecting enough samples
and applying mitigation techniques
to mitigate the noise, they observed
candidate routes that classical
solvers could not even recognize.
So they tested those routes
in a simulation and saw slight
improvements in total travel time.
Again, I don't want to exaggerate
the advantages that we got because
these are small wins that we
are accounting for right now.
It wasn't earth shattering as I was just
saying, but it demonstrated that quantum
could contribute to something new.
So again, it's a well-defined
slice of a problem.
As you can see, the variation, the
variables are defined, the scope is
defined, so and so on and so forth.
That practical doorway, identifying
a manageable priest that matters is
where n era value emerges because
we want to definitely make sure that
we are working with the classical
computing, but again we want to make
sure that we do slightly better.
Even if possible.
Now let's actually try to see how
do we work with n constraints.
What are the challenges that
we are, do we are finding, and
how do we navigate around it?
So real hardware today isn't flawless
noise, corrupt calculations and qubit
counts limit problem problem size.
Instead of seeing this purely as
a barrier, let's actually choose.
Problems tailored to NIST machines.
For example, small scale portfolio
optimization, simplified molecular
models or routing sub-problems
in logistics fit within tens
of qubits and shallow circuits.
Again, you don't want to go into hundreds
of qubits because the, these are limited
for no error mitigation techniques such
as zero noise, extrapolation or randomized
compiling help extract meaningful results.
Despite noise.
I remember a team kind of running
the same circuit at different gate
durations to amplify noise and then
extrapolating data back toward a zero.
Nice estimate.
Results aligned very close
to the classical benchmarks
than raw readings ever did.
These steps require extra circuit trends.
Of course, you want to make sure
there are enough samples and basically
and classical computation, but.
Transforming noisy outputs
into actionable insights.
Hybrid workflows prove essential because
this is where I think, again, we don't
want to directly say either or that, so we
want to use a hybrid approach, classical
pre-assessing narrow candidate sets.
Once you can add narrow, the
candidate said quantum circuits
refine or evaluate them.
Classical post processing interprets
outputs a short list, a few dozen,
and then use quantum subin to
estimate energies more precisely
for that specific short list.
Guiding experimental decisions in
logistics are global routing problem might
be split into several regional slices.
Classical solvers handle the broad layout.
While quantum kind of pilots
refine the specific legs for
each of these constraints.
So embracing constraints creatively
is exactly what we are looking for.
So now let's take a
couple of examples, right?
How do we handle quantum quantum computing
in the financial services landscape?
In financial services optimization and
risk assessment draw very early interest
because that is exactly what we look for.
Whenever anybody speaks of financial
services, consider portfolio optimization.
Classical solvers may take hours
or days for large portfolios.
A quantum inspired ran mid-sized
instances faster, and suggested
allocations that improved risk adjusted
returns modestly in pilot tests.
Again, this is like purely pilot tests.
In one case, a wealth management
firm defined a pilot with 30 to
40 assets integrating expected
returns and core variance data.
They ran various circuits on
simulators and small hardware to
sample candidate allocations, and then
compared them to classical solutions.
The quantum assisted results sometime
offered slight shifts that went
back tested, showed a few basis
points of improved sharp ratio.
Those gains translate to meaningful
dollar value when assets under management
scale into hundreds of millions.
So another area is a
Monte Carlo risk analysis.
Classical Monte Carlo may require millions
of samples to estimate tail risks.
Quantum amplitude estimate
promises reduced sampling
requirements in ideal conditions.
So while full speedups evade more
mature hardware, NSCA hybrid sampling
methods have cut simulation time
modestly by integrating short
death quantum circuits to estimate
probabilities more efficiently.
A risk team ran a pilot feeding random
paths into quantum subin to assess
extreme loss bilities, while not a full
speed up yet, it sharpened tail risk
estimates in a fraction of classical
only pipeline time fraud detection.
Also benefits encoding transaction
at into quantum kernel.
Methods can highlight subtle
correlations, classical methods usually.
Miss in A POC, which was done.
Analysts coded features of transaction
graphs onto quantum circuits and
used outputs in a classifier.
Results card patterns that improve
detection precision slightly.
Again, as I said, small wins matter.
These remains absolutely proof of
concepts, but they teach teams how
to integrate quantum sub routines.
Validate outputs and align experiments
with compliance and security needs
organizations built this know-how now
that they're actually well prepared to
where the hardware can scale and how
to make sure we use hybrid approaches.
Now, let's take another example.
What do we do in a
pharmaceutical r and d case?
So drug discovery and molecular
simulation naturally aligned with
quantum comedic because that, that's
where it's supposed to shine, right?
Frankly speaking, chemistry based
quantum mechanics and classical
approximation struggle with electron
interactions in complex molecules.
Early experiments of small molecules like
hydrogen chains, small organic compounds,
demonstrate quantum circuits modeling
electronic structure more faithfully.
In one collaboration, researchers ran
hardware experiments to estimate ground
state energies of a small molecule.
Raw results were very noisy.
Yet after mitigation and combining
with classical methods, they matched
expectations closely enough to
filter out false lead, which is very
important and a huge way, frankly
speaking, that saved weeks of lab
synthesis and testing in another exam.
In another example,
completely different example.
A virtual screening pipeline
used quantum sub proteins to
define binding energy estimates.
For a short list of candidate ligands
targeting a known enzyme, classical
talking, produced 50 candidates,
quantum enhanced evaluation, trimmed
it down to 15 experiment essays,
then prioritize the top five, one
of which showed promising activity.
As you can see, there is
the filtering is done.
Very efficiently beyond small
molecules, teams explore protein
folding or binding side computations.
While classical AI tools like
alpha fold excel at predicting
structures, quantum methods may offer
complimentary insights into energy
landscapes or dynamic confirmations.
A startup ran hybrid loops.
Classical simulations suggested several
confirmations, quantum subro routines,
estimated relative energies under.
Different conditions.
Results informed lab experiments
in lead optimization.
Quantum enhanced machine learning,
refines predictions of toxicity
or solubility, encoding molecular
descriptors into quantum kernel models.
Some.
Some sometimes improved classification
accuracy on historical data sets,
guiding selection of safer scaffolds.
Pharma r and d also considers proper
optimization of clinical trial
designs, defining patient cohorts
based on multiple biomark biomarkers.
Quantum inspired algorithms
helps explore trial parameter
spaces to maximize statistical
power under budget constraints.
A biotech firm.
Ran a pilot to optimize trial arm
allocations given limited patient
populations and multiple endpoints.
Of course, the results while full
scale benefit evades larger machines,
the excise built institutional
understanding of mapping such
problems to quantum fend formulations.
These pilots show that investing in
quantum chemistry and optimizational
skills today speeds readiness
for larger simulations when
error corrected machines arrive.
Now let's actually see how to
do logistics and supply chain.
Again, we are trying to establish how
quantum computing can actually help
in various industries because of which
it's better to go over each and how each
of the POCs were done in each of the
industries and how understand better on
how quantum computing can help logistical
problems like vehicle routing, inventory
allocation, and scheduling often become
combinatorial mountains in pilot studies.
Quantum.
Inspired solvers explore routing
variance beyond classical heuristics,
uncovering alternate routes that reduce
total distance or delivery time by a
noticeable margin on scoped instances.
For example a delivery company
modeled a region with 15 vehicles
and hundred stops during peak season.
Classical SOLs found
good solutions quickly.
But a hybrid quantum test suggested
a slight rerouting for one vehicle
that literally avoided a traffic
bottleneck predicted by recent data
shaving of 5% of the total time, over
hundreds of deliveries that quickly
add up over lower labor costs, happier
customers, essentially speaking
inventory management benefits to.
So now.
Optimizing stock across warehouses
under capacity and demand.
Uncertainties can use
quantum enhanced heuristics.
A retailer pilot piloted a hybrid
workflow where classical forecast
predicted demand distributions,
quantum sub proteins, then optimized
inventory allocations the result.
Reduce overstock by 10% and out
of stock incidents by 8% compared
to classical only benchmarks.
So scheduling maintenance crews across
sites with various skills and time
is another combinatorial challenge.
A utility company tested quantum
inspired servers to assign crews
under multiple constraints.
Early results showed 15% better
utilization in simulated scenarios,
prompting deeper investigation.
Even demand forecasting sees
quantum exploration while classical
machine learning dominates.
Some teams test quantum machine
learning prototypes to capture
complex feature correlations.
In one pilot, a supply chain group,
encoded time series and categorical
features into quantum feature maps
and used, various clash variational
classifiers to predict demand spikes.
Accuracy improvements were
modest, but consistent across
several data scope data sets.
The key is basically isolating manageable
sub-problems, focus initially on critic
critical product line or regional hub
rather than the entire global network.
It's ba It's important for us
to slice the problem down into
multiple smaller sub slices.
Now let's actually move
on to how do we assess.
Quantum hardware and simulators.
Just a quick second.
Yeah.
So multiple platforms make quantum
export experiments accessible cloud
services provide entry points to super
contracting tab trap Dion, and enabling
devices AWS bracket Azure Quantum, IBM
Quantum, Google Quantum ai all offer
simulators with noise models and real
hardware queues when starting prototype
on similars to refined circuits.
Check correctness and
anticipate nice impact.
I recall juggling different SDK versions
one day testing on and then on circ,
then on an ion trap system via AWS.
Each had its own quirks, frankly
speaking, documenting dependencies,
gate sets, connectivity maps, and nice
parameters became part of these workflows.
So that upfront effort pays off.
You already know how to adapt your
certificate certificates to newer
devices, queue times and cost vary.
Of course, running many shots
on real hardware can incur daily
end expenses to manage that plan.
Experiments carefully simulate first and
then only run final circuits on hardware.
Use nice simulators to predict
outcomes and catch major issues early.
Keep experiments small.
If a problem, max to 60 qubits, but only
device only offers 30 with good fidelity.
Identify a reduced instance or partition
the problem into multiple sub problems.
Maintain scripts to log, run metadata.
Like date device, calibration metrics,
circuit version, so on and so forth.
So you can actually compare results
over time as hardware evolves.
Engaging early with platform communities
like forums, user groups, helps also
learn better practices and avoid pitfalls
because I have, I myself, have been
engaging in user groups for quite some
time and I learned quite a lot than just
using regular documentation over time.
This actually helps build
reliable experimentation pipeline.
So now actually, how do we do
software and algorithmic development?
Developing qu quantum applications
involves more than writing circuits.
First translate a business problem
into quantum friendly formulation for
optimization, defined cost functions,
and constraints that fit variational
algorithms or icing model mappings.
In a finance pilot, a team had to express
expected return risk, co variance as
cost Hamiltonian translating domain
concepts into qubit interactions.
Next, optimize circuits for hardware.
Choose qubit mapping, mappings
respecting connectivity.
Decompose gates into native
operations and limit depth to
stay within coherence times.
It's like customizing a recipe for
available kitchen tools, right?
You might want to swap an ingredient
here and there, and it just a cooking
time based on the stove during the
execution, apply error mitigation,
run circuits at varied or nice levels,
correct measurement, statistics, and
extrapolate towards ideal results.
I remember the ra.
I remember running the same circuit with
doubled gait durations to amplify noise.
Then using extrapolation to
estimate the zero noise output.
Though imperfect it gave a clearer signal.
Post-processing integrates.
Quantum outputs into
classical decision pipelines.
Feeding refined solution
into larger workflows.
It is key.
Basically simulate with
realistic, nice models.
As circuits run hardware tests, analyze
deviations, tweak again, over time.
Teams develop intuition.
You get to know this over time
and version controls matter.
Keep circuits and repository tag versions.
Track trans translation settings.
Avoid simulator tests
to catch regressions.
Automate, sorry, automate.
Simulator test or casual regressions
log results systematically
so that you actually get to
know what is really going on.
You can compare tests over
time, and so on and so forth.
Next, what goes on with the
organizational strategy, a structured
approach, maximizes impact.
First, identify use cases with
clear metrics and manageable scope.
Host workshops where domain experts
outline pain points, then assess
which might suit quantum pilots.
For example, a retail team might point
to seasonal inventory imbalances.
A logistic group flags,
dynamic routing challenges.
Second, build capability
train staff through online
courses internal hackathons.
Our partnerships with research labs, so
on and so forth, form small Quantums Conor
teams empower to prototype ideas quickly.
Third, execute proof of concept
experiments run on simulators.
Then hardware define success criteria such
as solution quality improvement over time.
S saving simulative to
classical baselines.
In one organization, they set a threshold.
If a quantum pilot could match classical
results within 5% of error, they
considered worthwhile stepping stone.
Even matching performance
builds familiarity.
You get to understand the quantum
landscape, so allocate budget
for cloud compute over time.
Maintain a roadmap that revisits
use cases as hardware matures.
Avoid ad hoc experiments with
no clear business alignment.
You would definitely want to
focus on measurable outcomes
and learning objectives.
I have seen companies spend months.
Running random circuits without
tying them to specific problems.
They end up with reports full of technical
jargon, but little business insight.
In contrast, teams aligning pilots to
concrete use cases actually do better.
So what is a near time?
What is a future of the
quantum business value?
I. Even in NSC teams report modest
but meaningful improvements, faster
optimization on scale, on small to
medium instances, I might save a
few percentage of delivery times.
A chemistry experiment might roll
out of all state early finance.
Test my Titan Risk Securities.
What starts as a pilot on
a reduced small scale model
becomes a full scale application.
Later the experience gained understanding
noise mitigation, hybrid design platform,
a platform quirks become priceless
when fault tire and machines arrive.
So by balancing realistic expectations
with curiosity and experimentation.
You actually understand how to harness
quantum breakthrough breakthroughs as soon
as they become practical in my, sorry.
In my experience, teams that
document every pilot success or
failure built a knowledge base that
later accelerated their work when
improving devices re sufficient scale.
What once was a dozen qubit experiment
becomes a stepping stone to hundreds
of qubits with manual faction.
What are the key takeaways right?
Quantum computing in today's SQA is not
a magic bullet, but if it, it offers
genuine opportunities when we choose
suitable problems, adopt hybrid methods
and building internal capability pace
dividends as hardware improves, I
encourage you to identify one well scope
use case in your domain, perhaps a small
optimization or a simulation that fill
tens of qubits and shallow circuits.
Run a pilot on simulators.
First, refine your formulation.
Test circuit designs, then move
to hardware runs, collecting data.
Document literally every step.
Share all your lessons across teams.
Engage with a wider com quantum community.
Over time, you'll build a repository of
patterns, common ways to map problems,
to variation circuits these patterns.
Reduce friction for future projects.
Allocate a mod and how?
Encourage a culture of exploration
balanced with pragmatism.
Celebrate small wins, which will
definitely help you set the groundwork.
Embrace this explore area
era of exploration with both
enthusiasm and pragmatism.
Thank you for listening.
I look forward to your
questions and your continued.
Conversations about how
quantum can actually create
value in your organizations.
Thank you again for joining Con 42.
Hope you all have a good time.
I.