Hi everyone.
This is Anush n. I'm a software
engineering manager at ai.
I have a couple of articles and
done some research on Edge ai.
Today I'm going to talk about how
quantum computing is supercharging edge
AI and how it impacts the processing
power size of the neural networks.
Power usage, latency, and cost.
By examining some of the real world
deployments across multiple sectors,
we will talk about how edge AI
technology is revolutionizing embedded
systems through improved processing
efficiency, reduce operational
cost, and enhance security measures
optimized through resource utilization.
Let's talk about the scale of a challenge.
By 2027, it's projected that there
is going, there are going to be 75
billion iot devices in the world,
and such massive data volumes at edge
is going to be difficult to handle.
With quantum enhanced ai, we can have a
3.2 x boost in the processing capacity
and a 41% reduction in operational cost.
The complexity of the edge data
at such a high resolution video.
Medical scans or autonomous
vehicle telemetry will require
faster and smarter processing.
As you know that the classical systems
need to keep up with the demands
like latency, power and scalability.
So deploying quantum enhanced techniques
in these fields is going to exponentially
get better results.
Then the classic systems.
Let's talk about a more hybrid approach
Through this problem, we have a quantum
solution and a classical one, but this
is a hybrid one, which is not purely
classical and not purely quantum.
It's synergy.
The quantum algorithms can handle.
Optimization heavy and very
high dimensional tasks like
routing, scheduling, or training
complex neural networks.
Classical systems can manage routine
or deterministic tasks like IO
operations or simple control loops.
The outcome of all these neuron
networks can then be processed with
a 3.2 x more parameters while still
meeting the sub 15 millisecond latency.
Comparing all this to classical only
systems, which plateaus at 1.4 x
capacity under the same constraints.
Now let's talk about some of the
improvements of using quantum.
These are some of the numbers you are
shared wherein you can see there is
a 78% faster optimization solving.
There is also a 67% reduction
in power consumption.
And a latency which has been reduced
to 30 millisecond compared to
the one 20 millisecond baseline,
which itself is a 76% improvement
in the overall latency parameter.
The model deployment speed is
also increased by 3.2 times
with the quantum enhancement.
So these are not just real
world impact, but these are.
Also, these are not even like lab results.
These are actually impacts that are
having on the real world case studies
and scenarios that we have seen.
They are feasible in the industrial
automation, autonomous vehicles
and infrastructure domain.
The reduced latency and increased
deployment speed can create
an edge AI infrastructure that
is both agile and powerful.
Now let's look about some of
the case studies shown here.
In the manufacturing enterprises
domain quantum algorithms
can be used in iot networks.
For achieving a better anomaly detection
of 82% and a reduced false alarm
rate by 43% in the healthcare domain.
Quantum algorithms have been used in medi
medical imaging algorithms, which has a
real time diagnostics with 91% accuracy.
And we also have a maintain HIPAA
compliance with all this implementation.
For a smart infrastructure,
quantum algorithms can be used
for dynamic energy distribution.
We achieve 37% of power savings
and faster response time with
our quantum classical systems.
So in every vertical that's tested,
the quantum classical systems have
outperformed the traditional ones.
Now let's look at some of
the neural network processing
capabilities of the system.
The classical system actually hits a
wall with only 1.4 x capacity, which
is actually increased if possible,
before latency becomes unmanageable.
This forces the developers to
compromise between complexity
and real time performance.
A hybrid model supports 3.2 times greater
capacity without latency sacrifice.
And how this can be achieved is
through quantum parallelization
efficient navigation of our systems.
In the enhanced quantum
ai, we also provide a high
dimensional parameter specs.
For this navigation, a superior
performance in spatial temporal pattern
recognition like movement tracking,
video analysis, and many other use cases.
Now let's look at some of the
resource allocation optimization.
Techniques.
So quantum units can be
optimized across compute, memory,
bandwidth, and network storage.
So the quantum networks actually
reacts to changes under 30
milliseconds, which are 4.2 times
faster than the classical methods.
For example, like in the Smart Cities
case study that we looked upon, it
is adjusting the power allocation and
the autonomous vehicle fleets case
study wherein it actually helps to
manage bandwidth and CPU dynamically.
So the optimization pipeline goes
through four different steps.
First is getting the quantum algorithms
detect the complex dependencies.
Next is to explore the millions of
possible configurations in parallel.
Then we execute with precision and
control and also predict and adjust
according to the conditions that evolve.
Now let's talk about some of the
security and cost benefits the quantum
enhanced technology can be used to for
cryptography in the following ways.
We have a lattice based key exchange
for managing all the encryption.
We have a temp tamper evidence
signatures implemented, and also
multivariate polynomial encryption.
The operational cost of these
systems have gone down by 41% because
of the quantum machine learning
algorithms that are being used.
It also uses less power and less
hardware, which requires less maintenance.
The reliability of the system has
really gone up with a 99.99% response
time with AI driven fall detection.
Self-healing infrastructure
and smart redundancy systems.
So this isn't just faster, it's
safer, cheaper, and more reliable.
Let's go through the implementation
roadmap for this quantum.
First, we review the current
infrastructure and identify where
quantum can be value added, for example,
where we can optimize the tasks.
Next, we can test the quantum inspired
algorithms on classical hardware and
validate the performance boost for
integrating the quantum algorithms in
the hybrid quantum classical workflows.
We obviously would optimize task
delegation and data flows, and the
system would scale at a enterprise
wide, and we would be monitoring
feedback loops for continuous tuning.
So this roadmap enables gradual low
risk adoption with incremental gains.
Let's talk about some of the
cross-industry applications mentioned
here in the autonomous vehicle domain.
We can get quantum to make the
sensor fusion faster by 2.7 times.
There is a 58% less power usage, which
would be beneficial in the longer
range and a better path planning
and real time decision making.
With smart cities, we have seen a 43%
reduction in traffic congestion and
a 30, even seven, 37% improvement in
energy efficiency, which also helps
in faster emergency response time.
In the industrial iot domain we
have seen a 67% drop in downtime.
Via productive maintenance, there is an
82% more efficient production scheduling.
So overall, we can see that
the enhanced edge AI is not
specific, it's to the industry.
It's also transformational across sectors.
Lemme go through.
Let's look at some of the future research
directions that we can see like here.
So first is the quantum
hardware that we have to get to.
So we do need a domain specific, hardware
for these particular edge devices.
We also see a distributed quantum
processing especially like a
quantum cloud in the edge, and then
we have quantum neural networks.
Now, this is an entirely new AI
paradigm that has to be looked upon too.
Now these developments could
multiply today's gains exponentially.
Even now we are seeing that this
is just a tip of the iceberg.
This is a long-term
technological revolution.
So thank you for listening
to my presentation about the
quantum enhanced edge ai.
If you have any questions, please reach
out to me on from my LinkedIn profile,
and you can have a study of all my.
Articles on edge.
Thank you and have a nice day.