Good morning and good evening, and across
the audience who is watching my video.
Many thanks for taking your
time to watch my recording.
I'm going to present today about
the cloud quantum Cloud Ops.
It's basically about the future.
Technology that is coming up which
we are going to envision tomorrow in
another, I, maybe in max of another five
years, we'll be seeing more about this
quantum processing, quantum technology.
Quantum.
There'll be a revolutionary
coming up, which we have to
be prepared for ourselves.
Hence, I'm taking this opportunity
to give some insight how it can be
and what we can be achieving more in
future and let's we welcome you all.
And let's dive into the presentation.
It's basically and the this
is more, I just want to cover
up my last, that small line.
It's basically to see the quantum
computing with basically we have our
cloud infrastructure, we have our DevOps.
Now with quantum technology coming
into place, how this amalgamation can
revolutionize the whole computer process,
the computer technology and the, it may
even come to our everyday day-to-day life.
This impacts, that's the intent of this
whole this one before I go into this
and I would like to take in a small
opportunity to explain what is this
quantum technology and everything the.
Processing.
It's, it is coming from a physics,
actually speaking it in this, right now
we have a traditional, I will call it
as a convention conventional processing,
which will basically and our computer
basically is a binary, it's a zero one.
One of the state will be there and
hence will be processing based on that.
But in quantum, it has it, the unit,
the small unit of work is called qubit.
It.
It basically has both the
values of zero and one.
It simultaneously can be in zero
and one that is called as a qubit,
and, but in case of a convention,
our traditional we'll have either
a zero or one, the binary, hence.
Based on that zero or one
the processing logical error.
But in quantum being in position of
both zero or one at any time until we
measure it, that is cause a super ion
and that super ion that makes quantum
to really prob give that flex that.
Upliftment of processing,
paralleling multiple tasks.
And that really gives us robustness
of this processing technology.
And that's where many companies
are investing on this.
The fundamentals of where it started with
physics and now they're putting a lot of
research projects so that we can really.
You leverage that processing technique and
make our the complex processing that we
really, not even with this ai, the complex
processing, so we have, the technology
is evolving, but if the underneath the
processing technology, like the processors
are not incapable, we are going to.
Hinder our technology.
That's the reason if the quantum
processing comes in place and with the
ai, we are really going to revolutionize
this whole, that's the intent of
where this whole exercise is going on.
And along with that, even the security,
right now we have a security with the
con, the convention approach of encryption
algorithm, but applying, thinking about
the quantum technology applying on the
top of it, the security will really the
increase, the 10 folds, a hundred folds.
So the thought the chances of getting
a threats will get reduced drastically
because it can really envision.
For example, I can, I'll go
more detail in the example so
that you can really understand.
I have a small example to going forward
how this security can, security or
processing, how this parallel processing
is happening with the content and
how we are getting benefited out.
That, I'll go with the other
thing which I want to talk about
is the innovation catalyst.
It'll even help us to, that we could not
dreamt that, hey, we can do this type
of complex processing with this quantum.
We can really feel conscious.
We can even achieve that one.
That's one of the, one of the security.
The other one is a performance and
the other one is the new innovation.
It'll lose.
It gives a a foundation for us to
think about some innovation that
we never could ever to dream about.
That is the intent of the whole quantum.
Let's move to the.
Next slide.
Quantum.
Sorry.
The hybrid infra architecture.
So we have our cloud infrastructure
currently, and we have our CICD
pipelines which were original DevOps,
and then we moved to the cloud.
Now everything is on cloud now, we
call it as a. Cloud ops tomorrow.
I think maybe it, maybe call a
quantum ops or anything, but the
point is, in quantum the main
important is unit processing unit.
Basically the qubit I'm
talking about, it'll enable us.
The foundation that is being, that
is laid on top of which quantum
is built, that will really help
us to really execute complex.
Quantum algorithms leveraging the
power of supervision, the supervision
I was talking about having, being in
both zero and one at the same time.
That's a supervision, which is calling
Quantum and the other one is entanglement.
There's another concept where I can
example like I, I'll take more time.
So in Quantum, basically.
Generally we have our zero one
comp processing, but in quantum
at a given moment of time, a a
state can be in zero and one both.
And it leverages both
the state and to process.
And that is called a superposition.
And that small you need to work of cubit.
Okay, now think about many.
When a chess player or when you are
playing a chess, generally when I play
chess or anyone I can really envision
or I can think about the 10 moves my
opponent can think about, I feel hey,
he may be doing this or he may, if
he does this, I may need to do this.
If I did this, I may need to do,
there are 10 combination max I can
think about, but think about if for
one of the 10 position, if it picks.
What are the other possible
10 options that can come?
I only can think one seamless, but
in quantum being in state of the
super position, what is advantages?
If the opponent takes one of this
10 position, what are the other
10 combination that can come and
from the 10 position, what are 10?
So it really takes a whole bandwidth
of combination and then process it,
and then it'll give us a result,
Hey, this is something that is
coming up, which is a future risk.
That level of.
Bandwidth of processing is what
is achieved, can be achieved.
That is called, is a complex processing.
That is being, that level of thought
process or processing is enabled
in the quantum that if we know.
Apply this processing to
security, you are able to envision
for certain security threat.
But think about if that security
threat comes or what is the
other thing that can come up with
this if there is another what?
So thinking ahead of multiple combination
with this quantum processing will really
help us to really take a proactive step.
How we can make the threats not coming
up from a security from a. Cloud
infrastructure operations management
point of view, or even financial, or
even in medical, everywhere you can
think about in everywhere, if you
look, really apply, if you increase
the scope of your bandwidth, of the.
Different health conditions wide wide
span, then you can really think about
what is the best approach for me to take.
Hence, that complex process is not
allowed because of the way we are
currently, the current processes.
But with this quantum processes, we
can take that leap and we can really
go forward and take more steps and
take a proactive step now for the
future that is coming in the risk.
That's the intent of the processing unit.
The classical infrastructure
basically is about talking about
our cloud infrastructure currently.
We have a cloud infrastructure that
delivers the convention, computer task
and system orchestration right now.
Applying the, we would like to leverage
the same approach that DevOps or CloudOps,
but apply on top of it, the cloud the
quantum, and so that we can really, I.
How the load balancing properly
distribute the workloads.
With this integration of the quantum
and the classical infrastructure, we
can really, what is the benefit we can
leave is we can really do the workloads,
distribution of and with the quantum
and classical optimal performance.
And the other one is with this small
integration layer, we can even,
it has the advanced translator,
workload, schedulers, and real time
processing system that unify d.
Computer algorithms, execution.
Also, basically the quantum
and the classical, both.
If you combine, you really getting a
very good benefit of for example, the.
The workload balancing
operation management everywhere.
I'll go more in deep where I can explain
you in a pictorial how the benefit the
investment, how the investment is more,
but what is the benefit out of it?
We get more out of this investment.
I'll go in my future slides.
DevOps no, I'm sorry.
My missed mistake.
Now, coming to the DevOps, we
started with DevOps and then we
moved now to call as a cloud ops.
Now think about what is the
transformation we need to do in
order to be prepared for our quantum.
Basically, we need to upgrade
our CICD pipeline so that we can
leave the benefit of for example,
quantum deployment and testing.
We need to make our C so that
we can deploy this new setup.
Quantum algorithm and
testing observability.
We have this log metrics and
everything for our observability to
make our operation life simple that
need to be enhanced for quantum.
The other one is the.
The operations models, right?
We have a lot of operation models that
are defined for our current DevOps or
CloudOps on-prem model on cloud that
need to be enhanced so that people need
to be trained so that to understand
how to manage this operations for the
quantum technology based applications.
Then automation, we do a lot
of automation for our systems.
To run automation to make
everything more smoother.
That automation now need
to be enhanced by quantum.
We need, so it's more of skill
development, enhancing the
existing processes that we
define, which are stabilized.
Now we know how we can make
this APAs, for example.
We need to know how to build an
a p for a quantum processing.
We need, because it cannot be same way
as late because quantum does more faster.
So we need to change the way of your,
I feel even the program in languages
like Java, they may even change.
With the quantum technology coming
up the way, the multi concurrent
processing, the multi trading
everything, the implementation
will change in a similar way.
Every technology will have its own.
Change or adaptability because
of this quantum coming.
And so we need to transform, be prepared,
and make ourself upscale, be prepared
for the new approaches for the operation,
new approaches for the CSCD or new way
of thinking of an observability so that
we can get more logs and do the data
analytics to untake the proactive steps.
This is basically how it can
impact the existing DevOps.
The key industries that benefit
from, sorry, my mistake.
The key industry that really that
benefits from this quantum, this
basically is the security I. Because
developing the quantum resistance and
encryption protocols to secure sensory
data against future quantum attacks,
cryptographic, basically it's security.
That is one of the key factor that will be
benefited from this because it can really
think about future combinations of threats
that can come and it'll help us a lot to
reduce the cyber tech attacks coming down.
The other one is the
algorithms, AI algorithms.
We built AI algorithm.
Current existing processor technologies.
Think of what quantum is coming in.
So we definitely need to change
this AI algorithms so that we can
leave the benefit of this parallel
processing that will be an impact.
The other thing that will be major
impact is on the pharmaceutical.
Right now, for example, in
Medicare medicine, need to
be come outta the market.
There has to do a lot of things.
Clinical studies, everything.
So one medicine to come out, it
may take years, but because they
don't have the liberty to do the
complex processing now they do the
incremental steps, sequential step.
But with this quantum, they can do the
concurrent execution of these studies.
They can do everything like
multiple ular combination to see
where's the impact coming up.
Time will come down, hence the clinical
study will come down and that will really
help us to give even, it'll even break
through some of the complex monocles
in combinations so that with this
quantum, and that may even bring some
new innovation, maybe even we may get a
Medicare medicine for cancer or something.
But basically it really helps us to break
through some of the innovation that we
never dreamt about with this quantum.
The other important thing on the finance.
As finance goes with the data analytics
pro, analyzing the data, predicting the
data, predicting the new future trends
of the market, is all based on the data.
And data need to be analyzed process
so that we can give the results.
We are limited with this conventional,
or we can say with this current
existing infrastructure, but with
this quantum infrastructure, you
can really make a difference.
It can even predict.
If I take this move for this something,
what is the future that, based on the
organization or based on the future
trends or based on the past tense
of an organization, whether I have
to invest it makes more, not only
that, it may co bring the combination
of AI with this data analytics.
It may even give us a very
good edition of where to invest
in everything there may be.
That's intent of where I'm going is the
quantum technology applying on finance
will help a. It'll not only for me
investment point of view, it even helps
for me this self, my portfolio and risk
assessment based on this analysis, whether
where, what should I do, where should
I invest, where should I not invest
adoption basically how
do we adopt this one?
So initially.
We need to build some Ps, right?
Generally, whenever a new technology,
we need to build a P for that.
What we need to do is we
need to upskill, we need to.
They'll definitely be a provider like
how we have now Azure, Amazon, Google.
They'll be a provider, one of these
provider who will provide us the quantum
infrastructure, quantum technology.
We need to partner with them.
Then create a POCs to understand,
explore I what are the.
How we can really start,
that's a foundation.
Then we need to build
a hybrid quantum class.
Basically now we have our classical
infrastructure and then we have
the, our quantum infrastructure.
Now we need to build an integration
phase where you build any APIs.
Based on the quantum integrate
with the the classical APIs.
See how the, it's basically
like a B2B communication.
How to establish, basically understand
the PC, understand the limitations,
challenges that we may come overcome that.
And so that is integration, right?
First build something.
Based on quantum, then see the way
how we can integrate this quantum
based application within classical
infrastructure that we call the current
classical is like a con or con with
this classical infrastructure to see
what are the challenges we have and
then once we, then we need to, with
an automation, how we can make sure
this integration more seamlessly so
that we can know where to build what.
Which is the best
platform for us to build?
What and how we can make it make
the benefit out of this integration.
Find the workload distribution basically
between the classical and then and
automate the quantum resource allocation
measure and improve the quantum things.
This is basically the
adoption you need to.
Adopt quantum to this classical, build
the application, integrate it, and then
optimize and manage it within operation
so that our operations on this integration
is more seamless and easy to manage.
So as I studied, what some of the
case studies that are going on
or that will come in future is
basically one of them is a medical.
Where I can see that a lot of companies
will really put investment on this
quantum so that they can make the
become medical study more faster.
That is one thing.
The other one where the investment
will go is all these cloud providers
will invest a lot on how do we
provision, make easy provisioning of
this quantum infrastructure so that.
They can get, they can invite
more customers to them so they
can get the customer base.
So there be a lot of inform on that.
The other one is the drug discord, which
I just talked, and the last one is how
do we make more to the applications?
Any given application, how do I leverage
where I should put my in investment?
On which area of an application in a
classical infrastructure, and where
should I leave the benefit of quantum?
It's not like everything
I built on quantum.
It may come with more cost.
So there should be a distinction
between within an application, which
is my requirement, where I may need a
complex processing and where I don't
need a complex or that distinction.
If you can make that level of design
level of distinction, if you make
it, you can really benefit honest if
you are, if you don't put a little.
Think through, you are
putting everything in quantum.
You may have more investment.
If you put more on the classical thinking
not required of quantum, then you may
not take the benefit of complex process.
So what Most of the applications when
we know this new start, when the quantum
is already made, sure the more critical
part is how do we differentiate between
where we need to build and deploy
our applications easily, classical or
this, and how do we integrate this?
This is another, a new set of design.