Hi everyone.
I am Ankita Saxena, senior project
manager at Amazon and alumni
of Carnegie and University.
I work on AI driven products and
focus on recommendation systems and
how these are shaping both customer
experiences and business strategy.
Today, I will walk all of you through
how these systems have evolved over
time and from just, you may also
like feature, it has become a core
infrastructure of multiple industries,
powering their business decision making
and improving their customer engagement.
So we interact with recommendation system
almost every day when Netflix suggests
you a show based on your viewing pattern.
Or Spotify starts building your
playlist or website, highlighting
what we may like the next.
These all feel very simple features,
but there's lot of intelligence behind
them in transforming industries,
and these are, that INT intelligence
system is now empowering the core,
core business infrastructure of.
Different industry areas.
So we'll today we'll talk about how
this sim how from simple suggestion
to strategic infrastructure this
has changed the four different
industry and what is its application
across different industries.
We'll talk about e-commerce platforms,
streaming services, digital retail
and enterprise marketplace, the
same technology, how it is adopted
across very different industry.
So let's go deeper into the each
industry and how the recommendation
system works and how it is impacting
the different aspects of the
business decision making there.
Let's start with
e-commerce platform first.
In E-commerce.
Now the system, the recommendation
system has evolved beyond the production.
For example, if customer is
frequently buying a what certain
kind of reusable water bottle, along
with a fitness care, the systems
forced that pattern leading to.
Leading retailer to bundle them or
increase supply or actually create
their own private level brand.
That's the business inside.
Now, the system gives you the
engine, and this way the engine is
shaping both the customer experience
and inventory decision making.
Let's go deeper into how the entire
technical architecture works in
e-commerce for the recommendation.
So the recommendation to architecture
in commerce starts with data collection
where real time capture of user
behavior, transaction and contextual
ness gets collected when customer
is interacting on the platform.
And then use with the collaborative
filtering, the item to item analysis
happens, identifying what are
the purchase pattern, what is the
product affinities for the customer.
Which gets feed fed into the
personalization engine, which is like
dynamic recommendation generation,
tailored to individual user profiles.
And the aggregation of these insights
give gets fed into the business
intelligence which helps businesses into
inventory planning, supplier management.
Even the product development decisions.
So just think about if be shoppers,
view a jacket, but don't buy it.
That system will flag it as a friction,
and the team may respond by either
adjusting price, improving the images, or
testing new messaging of the jacket to the
customer to improve the conversion ratio.
Now let's move into the next industry,
which is a streaming platform.
Streaming platform is focused
on hyper personalized discovery,
unlike the e-commerce platform.
And it is more complex because it not only
look at collaborative filtering, it looks
at MicroGen genre metadata tagging, and.
Multimodal analysis using visual
element audio characteristics, narrative
structure, plot content, and many more.
And what this recommendation supports
and helps with it guides the investment
decisions the production decisions,
regions acquisition targets for licensing
deals, and help platform understand
which genres and formats will resonate
with specific audiences and sector.
Yes.
So just think about if the millions
of your customers are viewing or binge
watching light-hearted comedy drama
content platform will definitely invest
more in that styles because the data
reveals there is a long term demand
and which can eventually convert into
a long time customer lifetime value.
So the recommender drives both
user engagement because customer.
The person, the customer is
seeing what they want to see.
And obviously business investment
because now customer business is
super clear on where to invest to
get more value out of the customer.
The most interesting piece of this is how
the multi-model analysis recommendation
system works and what is the detail of it.
So when you look at multi-model
analysis in streaming.
It does collaborative filtering.
It has a collaborative filtering layer,
which where it analyzes viewing patterns
across millions of users to identify
content with similar audience appeal.
Then it goes to micro genre metadata,
like which is grammar tagging
system, creating thousands of content
categories beyond traditional genre.
For example romantic is a traditional
genre, but it'll go more deeper into.
Romantic with multiple
couples and a Christmas team.
That's the granularity.
It goes on.
Then it analyzes video and visual
and audio and signals which uses
computer vision and audio processing
and attract extra characteristics like
cinemagraphic style, pacing, and mood.
Just think about, if the system
sees a viewer prefers a warm color
balance and slower pacing, it
recommends visually similar shows.
Even if the story is different, it
goes far beyond clicks to understand
aesthetic preference of the customer,
and that's where you bring in lot
of engagement from the customer.
And then the narrative structure mapping
na, natural language processing analysis.
Plot elements, themes, and
character ask for deeper matching.
That's how the entire multimodal analysis
happens, which gives a hyper personalized
recommendation to the customer.
Now, my most favorite, the digital
retail deal, and I will talk
more about the fit uncertainty.
Because that's the biggest pain point as
of now in the digital retail industry.
And obviously a misfit product ends
up into a poor customer experience,
lesser customer engagement, and
obviously higher return rates
impacting the company's revenue.
So this recommendation system.
Where we use visual similarity
algorithms and ar try-on capabilities
is surely helping to solve this problem.
So just think about if a shopper uses
virtual try ons for sneakers, the model
will suggest styles that match their
first shape and past certain behavior.
This reduce uncertainty, the number of
decision points a customer has to take.
And obviously in town reduces the returns
and the impact of this recommendation
system on digital retail is phenomenal.
It improves the conversion rates,
obviously reduced reduction rate.
We have seen a reduction of
almost five to 8% in return rates.
Wherever we are using the visual
similarity or virtual try on features.
And in turn, this has improved our
conversion rate by 15 to 25% on
average across the different digital
retailers, which, and it made customer
really happy because now they are
able to get better fitting, more
relevant alternatives without much.
Multiple returns,
and obviously this
improves the engagement.
A very interesting engagement data.
We, what we have seen is because customer
is seeing a lot of visually similar
item, it ended up engaging more and
the session duration has gone up about
20, 30% wherever the visual similar.
Recommendation system is being used,
and obviously more session time directly
converts into increased order value,
which is in the tune of eight to 12%,
which is a huge impact to the p and l.
And then the last, the fourth
one, the enterprise marketplaces,
which is a two-sided optimization.
My optimization system, and I will
say it is the most complex of.
Any recommendation system because it
has to work in a multi-agent reach for
reinforcement learning environment.
It, the agent has to not only optimize
for the buyer, it has to optimize
for the supplier as well, and that
is where the complexity comes in.
Let's dig deeper into how this
two-sided optimization system works.
And what is the benefits of using this?
So this multi-agent reinforcement
learning architecture works
on four different components.
There is a seller agent, which works on
maximizing visibility to qualified buyers
while managing inventory efficiency.
Then another one is a platform agent,
which balances marketplace health,
liquidity, and long-term sustainability.
And then the re regulatory agent, which
ensures compliance within regional laws,
logistics and payment requirements.
And the fourth one, the buyer agent
optimizes for relevant supplier
discovery and best value matches.
One of the great example you can
think about is if a wire wants low
shipping cost, but a seller wants
to clear the access inventory.
The system learns to pair the buyer
with the nearby supplier to satisfy both
sides, which is like optimizing for the
both the agents and the agent balances
competing, goes very intelligently
benefiting both and creating a win-win
situation for both s seller and the buyer.
That's the impact of the
recommendation system.
So another example is if the system
deducts there is a rising interest in
sustainable products, then it gives
a recommendation to the product teams
to expand that category, and marketing
shifts to the messaging and the
insight flow across the entire system.
That's how the entire recommendation
system impacts the businesses.
So I would say, the entire
recommendation system has multiple
business impacts across operational
excellence delivering a lifetime
customer value and revenue impact.
So you may think about when it
comes to operational excellence,
the recommendations system
helps supply chain optimization.
When it comes to demand forecasting,
inventory management, which is all driven
by recommendation patterns, same for the
resource allocation, like where we should
invent for invest for the content, if
it's a streaming services or what should
be the green field areas for the new
product development, where we are seeing
a huge demand, but lower conversion and
the patterns, there are common product
feature patterns under each demand.
And where should we expand the
market Next, what should be
our new next private level?
And obviously, and the most
important is efficiency gains.
We with the recommendations digital
system, we remove all the dependency
on manual search and all the friction
and lowering the transition cost.
And then if we focus on the
customer value with the.
Better recommendations and the
products which customer is looking for.
You bring a lot of retention.
You improve customer retention and
loyalty and creates a personalized
experiences for the customers, which
gives you a lot of competitive edge and
definitely the revenue optimization.
You can do cross selling, upselling.
You can discover the new
revenues work revenue streams.
Using the recommendation system.
For example, if two different products
are bought all the time together, you
can bundle it and sell it, cross sell
it to the same customer, and under the
recommendation system, and the most
important, the market intelligence,
it gives very deep insights into the
customer behavior, what customer is
looking for, and what's the new product
we should be building, which customer?
Think of, but not finding as of now.
So to summarize the recommendation
system is redefining the
personalization as a core foundation
layer of all the businesses.
So it's no longer just a
small feature recommendation.
It has become a fundamental architecture.
Powering business operations and it
is a cross-functional integration.
So once we have this foundation up
and running, it not only impacts one
section, supply chain, it, or marketing
plan, it impacts the insights of this
recommendation system flows across all
the sites of the business, marketing,
supply chain, product development.
Business strategy, customer ag engagement,
all of the functions of the business.
And once you start working backwards
from the customer, obviously it
creates a competitive differentiation.
Superior personalization creates a
defensible mode through a network
effect and advantages the same percent.
It becomes a foundation and not a feature.
And I would say companies that understand
behavior at scale, deliver more relevant
experiences, creating an advantage,
that new customer can't easily copy
that it, and that insights become a
strategic mode because you are the
one who knows your customer the best.
To end with AI powered recommendation
system represents the convergence
of customer experience excellence,
and a strategic business
intelligence organization.
And the organization that mastered
this convergence will define the
competitive landscape of their
industries in the near future.
So the strategic imperative is clear.
Recommendation system must be viewed.
Not as isolated technical
implementation, but as integrated
business platform that drive
decisions across entire organization.
From e-commerce inventory strategies
to streaming content, investment from
digital retail conversion optimization to
enterprise market marketplace security.
These systems are reshipping how
industries operate and compete.
Thank you so much for your time and
I hope this showed how recommendation
system act as strategic in engines,
not just customer features.
And thank they.
Have a great day.
Thank you so much.