Hello everyone.
It's such a pleasure to be
here with you all of you today.
So my name is Rinni Vasa Ti and
I currently serve as a engineer
lead at one of the largest
healthcare company in United States.
Let me talk briefly about my experience.
So over the past several years I
have worked at the intersection
of data analytics, healthcare
systems, and automation.
So today I'm truly excited to share
how advanced analytics and artificial
intelligence or transforming clinical
robotics and the future of healthcare.
In this session we will walk through how
data and a are shaping healthcare's next
frontier from from precision diagnosis
and robotic surgery to ethics, compliance,
and patient centered innovation.
By the end I hope you all see
that e and robotics are not just
technologies but they are instruments
of compassion, precision when
built and trust and data integrity.
Let's move forward and see how it works.
So let me move to second slide.
So let's talk about a, let's talk a
little bit about abstract and overview.
So let's begin with a quick
overview of what's that?
What's this transformation look like?
So healthcare today is moving rapidly from
reactive to prior to models of care, fuel
by data analytics and a power insights.
So we call this as a data
driven evaluation of healthcare.
Imagine a system where every heartbeat,
scan and record isn't just stored,
but learn from the real time.
So our unified framework brings
together SaaS analytics, mission
learning, and robotics systems.
So forming a single ecosystem
like that, that suppose predictive
maintenance, precise diagnostics,
and continuous improvements.
But this evolution also requires a
strong ethical foundation as well, right?
So we have to ensure that all the
government regulations and, P-H-I-P-I
data security, and then HIPAA and
GDP are compliance, transparency,
and explainability because healthcare
because in a healthcare trust
is the ultimate currency, right?
Yeah.
So that's what we are
going to talk about today.
So let's move on to next one.
The healthcare transformation.
So let's talk about the larger
transformation happening
in healthcare currently.
So we are witnessing a paradigm shift
from treating specific illness too,
predicting and then preventing it.
So this shift is powered
by a data explosion, right?
So now we now collect the data
from multiple sources from amazing.
Genomics and then wearables, the
wearable devices, and then IOT devices
and electronic health records, and an
incredible multimodal data set that
can completely redefine how how how
we understand the health overall.
And but here is a challenge that
the integration is very challenging
here because all of this data
lives in a different systems that
don't always talk each other.
So connecting clinic, clinical robotics
with AI analytics, but requires a
robust interoperability framework.
That means we have to make a. Seamless
channel or connection between all
these sources to talk each other
and bring the data with the, in
a near real time or real time.
So that, the clinical robotics will
take a decision based on the the
collective data from all the sources.
So when we achieve this when
we achieve that connection,
we can reduce medical error.
And then accelerate diagnosis
and enhance both patient outcomes
and overall quality care as well.
So let's let's move on to how
the, actually the clinical
robotics evolution happened.
Let's step back then, let's let's talk
about let's step back in time and see how
clinical robotics has evolved In the 1980s
and 1990s systems like the Puma five 60
and later, the Daven c surgical system
transformed minimally in VA surgery.
They showed us that emissions could
enhance a human precision in the, in 2010.
Robotics center, diagnostics and
rehabilitation, helping stroke patients
regain mobility and supporting the re
procedures with a high year accuracy.
So by 2020, AI driven, robotics begin,
stepping in nearly every domain like
a surgery, pharmacy, automation,
elderly care, and hospital logistics.
Now we are entering, in a era
called, I call it a integration era.
So where robotics data connects
directly with the patient analytics
to enable closer loop care means
like a system where feedback and
action continuously improve outcomes.
That's, that, that's important here.
When it comes to the integration area.
So let's move back.
Sorry.
Let's for move forward and see
how AI and mission learning in
healthcare really, play a works.
So by touching all the key important
points, like a deep planning models,
how the deep planning models work and
neural language, sorry, natural language
processing and the predictive analytics.
And then, reinforcement learning, right?
And then finally, now
the precision medicine.
So let's talk about each
concept in a very high level.
So deep learning models can now
detect disease and CT scans.
MRIs and pathology slides
faster than faster and more
accurately than ever before.
Right?
And natural language processing.
So our visualization, NLP usually allow
us to extract insights from doctor
notes and unstructured text turning free
flowing narratives into structural data.
Then let's, and then
move to predictive model.
Predictive analytics helps us
detect sepsis, heart failures
or infections before they come.
Become a critical it's about
moving from cure to prevention.
So then let's talk about
the reinforcement learning.
So it, it is being applied
to a robotic surgery teaching
robots to adjust their movement.
Based on the outcomes, much like
a human lens through the feedback.
And then we have a precision medicines
where ai analyze all the genetic
genetic data to design a personalized
therapies for each patient based on
its condition and many other factors
specific to that particular patient.
And then condition.
So this is how we move forward,
truly individualized healthcare.
Yeah, so I like to say here in the
past, doctors treated patients in the
future, the data will help doctors
know their patients well before
they even arrive to the, visit.
Yeah, that, that's all that's all about
the AI mission learning and healthcare.
In this in this slide, and then
let's move forward to the evolution
of healthcare analytics framework.
Has robotics and ai matured?
Our analytics frameworks
evolved alongside them.
So like we started with a, descriptive
analytics, simply reporting what happened.
Basic descriptive analytics is
nothing but take all the existing
un historical data and what we have.
In what our databases or in our
systems, and then just simply
reporting what happened, right?
Then predict two analytics
came into the picture.
So predictor analytics means like applying
some statistical models on top of what
on the top of the data that we have right
now in our system, and apply some mission
learning algorithms to forecast outcomes.
So now we are entering into the
era of prescriptive analytics.
Descriptive is done.
Analytics, predictive is done.
And then now prescriptive analytics
means recommending what actions to
take next based on predictive insights
that we have, predictive analytics,
and we have insights from that.
And then now.
Use this, by using this ai LLMs you can
just based on the predictor insights,
you can just recommending what kind
of, actions and, course of treatment
that we can design for the specific
patients and specific, conditions.
This shift is covered by a realtime data
pipelines, like using tools like a Kafka
spare and then Hadoop alongside advanced
modeling platform such as vo right.
And together all these tools enable
continuous intelligence where
analytics doesn't just analyze, but
it acts on the facts of the data.
And when we visualize in dashboards
and KPIs, key performance indicators,
these insights empower clinic
clinicians directly bringing
data from the server room.
Server room means the data from all
the source systems to the bedside means
where actually patient and and the
doctor actually, treats the patient.
So he has everything right now, next
to the patient and the next to the bed.
So the doctor's nurse, you don't
have to really go research, by diving
into multiple data sources and then,
take a call based on that or data.
But that AI and the system will really
do it for the doctor so that they
can just quickly take a call and take
a decision and then, by providing
some prescriptive NLA, on treatment.
So let's move on to.
So proposed framework.
So what we are trying to propose
here, so let's talk about the five
layer architecture that brings
all these components together.
So we are divided into different
layers, like a data equation
layer, processing layer, yeah.
And analytics layer, and then
integration layer, and then presentation.
So let's talk about each.
So data equation layer collects inputs
from robotics or electronic health
records like EHS and iot sensors,
devices, and emerging systems and
all other devices, what are all
medical devices Processing layer.
So processing layer converts this
raw data, whatever we getting
from all the devices and what we.
In this processing layer is basically
like we consider the data from all these,
systems and then we convert this raw data
into structure and usable information.
Excuse me.
And then the next layer is
like AI and analytics layer.
So where mission learning and predictive
models turn the data into inside, right?
We have a structured and usable
information from the presentation layer.
Now we apply the all these AM models
in this analytical layer and where
mission learning and predictive models.
The statistical models
turn data into insights.
They give, oh yeah this is
what the data shows tells us.
And then this is the information.
You have it.
And then, then but still, right?
Those are like a no
independent data points.
Now integration comes into the picture.
That's why we call as a integration layer.
So APIs and middleware, right?
And application interfaces and the
middleware ensures that interoperability
across the systems we have all the data
points, data, source data objects, right?
And then you need to integrate.
All the, data from different systems like
I sensor systems, scans and everything.
And then the move, the
data has to be collaborate.
Move between each systems and
then, collectively give make
some kind of summarized insights.
With that data that's
called integration layer.
Now presentation layer.
So when we have all the data yeah,
integrated data and provides provides
the dashboards alerts and patient support
directly to the clinicians, right?
And together these layers form
a unified ecosystem creating
end-to-end automation and delivering
insights the at the point of care.
So let's move on to let's move on
to the data pipeline architecture.
So this slide this slide shows how.
How that architecture looks in motion.
And first Apache Kaka, we,
let's talk about some technical
technical components here.
First Apache Kafka streams, robotic
telemetry and patient vital in real time.
Apache Kafka, really streams, flows,
sensor data almost in real time.
Like a patient vitals or robotic er,
whatever, robotic tools actually,
performing at the point of time.
And then it talks to the patient vitals
at the same time, and then Apache Kafka.
So process these data streams
across the distributor cluster.
And then usually we have a huge
amount of data so for faster
processing or accessing, we, dis,
distributed into different clusters
for the parallel processing.
So these Apache spa process,
all these, cluster data.
Very fast.
And then next to Hadoop, HDFS, actually
Hadoop, HD FS is the file system storage.
Excuse me, the structured and
unstructured data securely.
So HDFS has the capability of storage,
like even structured, unstructured,
and, we can use we can implement proper
governance on those data elements.
Now let's talk about the SaaS wire.
SaaS wire.
It's it's an analytical tool, right?
I mean it's it adds analytical power
power to that data which resides
on the HDFS and then visualization
forecasting and predictive modeling.
And finally, HHL seven and FHIS
standards ensures interoperability
with hospital EHR system, right?
That's is interoperability like.
Communication between all
these different data points.
They ask for health electronic
health record system.
So together, together this pipeline
entire, the pipeline allows a low latency
decision making in robotics workflow.
So meaning.
Meaning like a clinical rewards
can respond to changing conditions
within a millisecond, right?
When we read the data in real time, when
we stream the data in real time, when
we have the data, updating, almost in a.
In real time.
So robotics should be able to capture
those updated, vital or, whatever
that data patient data that come flows
through and should take an action
should, guide the patient doctors
almost like a, instantaneously.
So that's, that, that's what
another final goal is here.
So with another, the robots
should respond in milliseconds.
In essence, this is the digital
nervous system of a modern healthcare.
Okay, let's talk about mission
learning infrastructure, right?
When to make AI truly operational.
We need the right infrastructure now.
Yeah, we talked about different, software
components and, different pieces of
technology, how it works and how it really
integrates the data and it provides the
interoperability interoperability feature.
But in order to make you know all this to
work, we need the right infrastructure.
That's where the automated ML lifecycle
covers automated Emission Learning
lifecycle basically covers the data
preparation, featured selection,
and then date model training and
validation, all seamlessly automated
to save time and without any bias.
And a hybrid cloud setup it's like
a hybrid, like you have an on-prem.
You have a better control over all
the go, data and governance applying
some securities and, control access
to specific PHI and PI data to
the limited, very secure people,
secure, I mean in a secure way.
And, and then when it comes to
the cloud the cloud gives you the
opportunity either, what you call
them mean cloud actually help you to
scale the product ally or vertically,
based on your need, based on your
data, based on your processing power,
you can scale up and scale down.
So there a s and does, it
comes into the picture.
So basically like an hybrid
architecture, you can secure the data.
You can, scale the scale, the product.
That's how a we hybrid cloud setup
and obviously GPU cluster, right?
The GPU clusters enable, deep
learning models to understand
the images and medical images
like container medical images.
It requires a lot of, computational power.
So here the GPUs actually works very well.
For the, to learn, to understand
and, know deep, take a deep dive
into the medically amazing things.
And then now container is deployment.
Container deployment is
nothing but irrespective of
the operating system, right?
And underlying operating system, the tool
and the product should work seamlessly
because they're like nowadays the, there.
Infrastructure and underlying operating
systems are sh should not really,
limit the CAPAs limit the capability
of the product that you're building.
So that here, the containerized and
deployment ensures the flexibility
across multiple, across environments.
Now models are continuously
monitored for a drift.
Models are continuously monitored
for drift fairness and performance.
Okay.
And then, and when Drift is
detected retraining pipelines
automatically kicks in.
So some of the key algorithms in play
right include CNNs, like a convulsion
net natural networks sorry, convulsion
neural network for image recognition
and recurrent neural networks, RN
for patient time series prediction.
And the transformers for clinical text.
And then reinforcement
learning for robotics control.
This synergy enables the real time
adaptability where robots and algorithms
keep learning, not just, working and
that they should, train themselves.
They should keep learning and
then in keep working for us.
Okay, so let's move on to
data governance compliance.
Of course.
With all these intelligence comes
responsibility and so in healthcare,
data governance and compliance
are non-negotiable at any cost.
Very important.
And that our systems implement
HIPAA controls including role-based
access like a ES 2 56 encryption
algorithm and full audit logging.
And we align with JDPR principles such as
consent tracking and privacy by design.
And of course, line know security
architecture involves multifactor
authentication and multifactor
authentication and network
segmentation and what we call
that now, intrusion detection.
And we maintain a data integrity
through metadata cataloging and linear
tracking and data quality qua scoring.
Ultimately this builds a chain of trust.
Ensure like every data point is traceable
and then ethical and then transparent.
Makes sense, right?
And as often tell my team that
in healthcare, like data doesn't
just need to be accurate, it
needs to be accountable as well.
That is most important.
Hope I understand that.
Yeah.
So let's talk about next
clinical applications.
So you know, some practical
application, look at some practical
applications right in He enhanced
AI enhanced robotic surgery.
The workflow is divided into
three stages, like a pre operator,
in operator and post operator.
So ai creates a three DR one maps that
helps surgeons plan every incision
with a millimeter position, right?
That is very important because some of
the organs are very sensitive and very
minor, so it has to be the incision.
It has to be very accurate.
And then intraoperative.
Real time tissue classification
guides decision during surgery.
When the surgery happening, right?
The real time tissue
classification when you.
When you put some incision on any
of the tissue and that that, that
particular tissue need to be the robo
tick the component that, that is doing
the operation the robotic operation,
that has to read, understand the
understand the tissue classification.
What this tissue is and how it
reacts when we do an incision.
And then how it actually, works and
how it actually bleeds and everything
you need to, the robotic that should
robotic tool should understand this
tissue classification and then guides
the decisions during the surgery.
So it has to happen always
like a human right When doctor,
when surgeon cuts a tissue.
He knows what that tissue
is and how it works.
And then, if something, she finds
something unusual, he should take a
take call here and he should take a
decision and, he has to change the
course of surgery or maybe, do something.
So in the same way, like we
expect the robotics, should do
here in this situation as well.
Then postop.
Predictive models actually track
recovery and identity communications
early complications early.
So this predictor, we do right,
predictive means like applying some
statistical models on top of what
we know, what we have right now.
And then basically it tracks
it, track the recovery and
identify the complications like.
Early.
Okay.
Yeah.
This surgery this surgery gives more
complications in this particular area.
So we cannot simply guess it, right?
And take the data based on historical
surgeries, similar kind of surgery,
what happened, and and then what are the
complications and, and then apply some
static statistical models and that data.
And then, and then compare
it with the current surgery.
And then, then comes up with some kind
of, recommendations and saying that, hey,
this surgery or this post operation, these
are the, these probably these are the,
complications may arise and then, guide
the doctor and then treatment the patients
through doctor that, the post operator.
So these innovations have
reduced to operator times by 23%.
And then complications by
almost, one third like, and
then beyond the surgery, right?
And he also supports predictive
maintenance forecasting robotic component
failures with the, over 90% of accuracy
and reducing downtime by nearly 40%.
And finally, now, patient
risk satisfaction, right?
Satisfaction.
Patient stratification, like where
digital time as scoring helps hospitals
to prioritize, high risk patients
to and allocate resources smartly.
But that, that, that's yeah.
So that, that, that's a key here, right?
That, that's it.
This helps total hospital
admin, administration and to
control the resource wastage.
And also right person, right treatment the
critical person gets a treatment for us.
So each of these use cases demonstrates
that when analytics meets robotics.
We don't just treat patients faster,
but we, we treat them better.
Let's move on to, let's move
on to emerging technologies.
The next frontier lies in four kind
of technologies, for for powerful
technologies, quantum computing.
Edge computing, fer learning,
and finally explainable ai.
Right?
And then so let's talk about all these all
these that powerful technologies, quantum
computing will revelation, revolutionize
the genomics, drug discovery, and
molecular simulations by processing
massive dataset at quantum speed.
Edge computing will push AI closer
to where the care happens besides
bedside phases or even insert surgical
robotics, really surgical robotics,
reducing latency, and improving privacy.
Now federated federated learning.
So we enable hospitals across the globe.
To train a models together
without sharing sensitive data.
So a perfect balance of,
collaboration and privacy.
And finally, explainable tools
like, SHA and know Lyme health
clinicians understand why and made
a particular decision building.
Trust and transparency, right?
The clinician, that's
the most important thing.
They should understand why this
particular large language model or
some kind of together them really take,
made this kind of particular decision.
So that I know you can just try to, build
that trust, build that model output,
and also you can in a better position or
surgeon in a better position to explain to
the patient why they actually, that, that
kind of decision has been taken here and
these emerging technologies or extending
scalability, collaboration, and plus
across the entire healthcare ecosystem.
Let's move on to challenges
and limitations, right?
So now it's very important to
be honest with you about the
challenges what we face here.
So from technical standpoint inconsistent
data quality, interoperability gaps,
and high computational cost remains bad.
Yes, no doubt about it.
Because the data comes
like a, anything now.
So many variables, so many
iot devices, so many, systems.
Every system sends the
data in its own way.
And decoding the data and, understanding
and then making more, usable data.
It is very challenging.
And that is called,
interoperability gaps, right?
You get this data from here, you
get this data from, you get this
data from here, and then you need
to you need to make sure that you
know all the data data points are.
Should be should be, understand in a
way that makes sense to other systems.
Bringing the right point of data
from each system and, understand
the data in a, meaningful way.
And in order to do that, like it
requests a lot of computational
power, computational cost.
So means lot of gpu, a lot of, kind of
CPU power and lot of, things like that.
Cause a bit of more comparatively.
Keeping all the systems separately, right?
That it has advantage, but
it has, some cost involved.
So that is one challenge.
And the organizationally we face
clinicians' resistance often.
That, that makes sense
too, because like you.
Human no one.
As at this point, I don't think any
mission can really be the human brain
in, when it comes to take a decision.
And then when you call when do
something that is, you humans can feel
the thing, not the admissions, right?
I mean that, so that clinicians.
Can resist to, accept some changes
and often due to workflow changes.
And then we need to widespread upscaling.
That, that requires some kind of,
training and adaptability is required.
And then there are ethical
concerns now, algorithm bias,
black box decisions, and unclear
accountability in AI assisted outcomes.
It's always there.
Every new thing, new technology always
have there you some kind of know concerns.
And finally we have a regulatory and
clinical validation requirements.
Models must provide themselves
not just in theory, right?
And, but in real world evidence.
So it has to, prove that, okay,
this is not, I'm just, telling you
or giving you the results, not just
based on the input that you provide.
Now, these are the no real time
scenarios happen, different, cases,
different patients and the different,
situations so that makes actually, more
convincible and then more meaningful.
So while the technology races ahead.
Our responsibility is to ensure
empathy oversight and human.
Judgment always remains at the center.
Okay?
And then because no matter how smart AI
becomes, it must never lose a human touch.
This is very important.
So the, let's move on to best
practices and recommendations.
How do we move forward responsibly, right?
And start with a small pilot project
always as we do and validate a clinically.
Yeah.
And then scale gradually.
So that's the way we do projects
are, the things everywhere, right?
Rather than just jump and do it,
large scale and, for all third user
bases, we should slowly start small
and then go large and then adapt.
All the standards like h Hhl seven FHAR,
and then API the first architectures for
interoperability and use hybrid cloud
models for flexibility and compliance
as we talked in the previously.
Cloud and, hybrid cloud
is very important here.
And then implement continuous
monitoring for fairness and bias, right?
Create ethics committees and, and
data steward stewardship roles to
ensure the accountability and most
importantly keep clinicians, engineers,
and patients in the same conversation.
Because if I talk something, I mean as an
engineer, if I talk something, clinicians
may not understand and what clinicians
talk, I cannot understand fully.
And patient, he cannot understand
what we are talking, and
it has to be very the more.
Layman kind of conversation when
it comes to now patient, right?
You should understand and everyone should
understand like what we're talking about
because that is a collaboration must
is a real backbone for this innovation.
Okay.
And and then let's talk about
conclusion and future vision.
Okay.
As we look ahead I want to
leave you with this vision.
So the convergence, the convergence
of air robotics, AI robotics and
analytics is the most transformative
trial triad in modern healthcare.
So we are entering an era of
predictive, personalized, and.
And participatory care.
So where the medicine becomes proactive,
not reactive, the future includes
quantum AI for genomic discovery, edge
robotics for remote telemedicine, right?
And federated ai like for
global collaboration, right?
And then, but above all, it's about
keeping healthcare patient centered
guided by empathy, transparency
and ethical responsibility.
So let's, so let's build a system that
just, that don't just, process the data,
but truly understand the people behind it.
And as I like to say, the stethoscope
defined in 19th century medicine.
Data and the AI will
define the 21st century.
Thank you all.
Thank you all so much for listening,
and I look forward to, c other,
presentation in this conference.
Thank you so much and have a great.
Rest of the, we can, we,
present our conference time.
Thank you.