Yeah.
Hi everyone.
This is Han Pu from University
of Central Missouri.
Today I'll talk about building
regulatory compliance systems by
design not as an afterthought.
We will explore how architectural patterns
like event sourcing by temporal data graph
lineage CQRS, APAC and adaptive learning
can turn compliance into an enabler and
instead of a burden let's go to our.
Topic the regulatory pressure landscape
the regulatory pressure landscape is
evolving rapidly global institutions
face risking complexity in areas like
a ML data, privacy and risk management.
Traditional compliance methods often
come in late creating bottleneck
and always with penalties.
We will look.
At why this reactive
mindset is unsustainable.
Okay.
So if you look at the numbers say each
all escalating market growth in rec tech,
billions of dollars in penalties and
huge manual overload, the cost of doing
compliance is reactively massive instead
of patching systems after every new rule.
We need to architect them to
participate, to anticipate
regulation from like day one.
So for that.
The compliance by design
is what we introduced.
So as the name sets it all it
flips the mindset rather than
vaulting on controls later over.
Compliance is basically it's like a
design, structural design principle.
When compliance is built into
our architecture, like security
scalability, performance, reduce risk,
improve agility, and regular trust.
In simple words.
It's not a checklist anymore
it's a design strategy.
Coming to the next one let's
see, what are the patterns?
So these are the three fun,
foundational and fundamental patterns.
One is even sourcing by temporal
data and graph metadata.
So even sourcing is this is for like
immutable audit trails bitemporal data.
This is for like time accuracy and
graph metadata is for traceability.
Together all these three fundamental
patterns they make the systems
naturally compliant, transparent,
consistent, and audible.
Next event let's look
into this like one by one.
One is event sourcing.
Event sourcing means every change is
captured as an event never over return.
It's like keeping a diary instead
of editing yesterday's entry.
Technically it's an append
only lock with playable history
and cryptographic integrity.
For regulators, that means this
is like full traceability and non
reputation, so the data is ever lost or.
Ever hidden.
There is no concept of that.
So in this case, no data is lost at all.
So let's go to the Bitemporal data models.
Bitemporal modeling tracks two timelines.
One is transaction timeline.
The other one is valid time.
So what is transaction time?
So transaction time is nothing.
But when it happened in real
life what is valid time?
Valid time is nothing.
But when the system learned about it,
this dual view allows reconstruction of.
Reality at any point,
even after corrections.
It's vital for audit accuracy
and regulatory trust.
Let's go to our third pattern,
which is graph based lineage.
Compliance depends on knowing where
data came from and how it changed.
Graph based lineage uses notes
and edges to map data flow
across microservices and systems.
You can visually trace a report
number all the way to its data source.
This ensures transparency for auditors
and easy impact analysis for engineers.
Next is CQRS.
CQRS is command query
Responsibility Segregation.
So this one separates right and
read parts, the common side.
Validates transactions enforces compliance
rules while the query site is optimized
for audits monitoring and reporting.
So this separation improves
scalability performance.
It is reg it is basically ideal
for regulatory systems that
need both accuracy and speed.
A c. So a is attribute based access
control goes beyond u user roles.
It considers user attributes, data
sensitivity, and context in real time.
For example, an analyst in Europe
can access Europe data under GDPR.
While a contractor see MA data AB
AAC policies are declarative and
fully auditable making compliance
dynamic and policy driving.
Yes.
Yep.
Next adaptive, exceptional handling
and reinforce hand learning.
So compliance exceptions happen, but
what if systems could learn from them?
So this approach, this using
reinforcement learning, we can detect
exceptions pick optimal responses
execute and improve over the time.
The system evolves reducing recurring
complex issues and adopting to
new regulations intelligently.
That is what adaptive Exception says.
Coming to the next one, we
talk about the architecture.
So here is a view of implementation
of effort across all the components,
which we discussed so far.
So even sourcing and CQRS requires
significant work while AAC and
bitemporal models are lighter lifts.
This helps.
To prioritize a phased adoption,
like start small, prove
the value scale gradually.
Next, let's talk about the
business value proposition.
So the payoff is substantial.
From reactive compliance to proactive
assurance, from manual overhead to
automated reporting from risk management
to competitive differentiation.
So embedding compliance, boost
efficiency, trust and agility.
Next let's talk about its implementation.
This is a roadmap, a practical roadmap.
First one is you assess all the gaps,
map and map all the current obligations.
Second one is design phase, where
design around the core patterns.
Third one is pilot implementation.
You, we basically just pilot one
domain to validate the results.
Scale and optimize.
So this is like wide and optimize
this approach reduces risk while
building the internal capability.
So what are the key takeaways?
Let's discuss.
So to summarize.
Compliance is not a burden.
It's a structural principle.
Architectural patterns like
event sourcing bipolar bitemporal
models, graph lineage, CQRS.
Apac adoptive RL makes
compliance seamless.
By designing with regulation in mind.
We turn complex into co into
a competitive advantage.
Yeah.
Thank you for joining me.
I hope this gave you some practical
insights on building systems
that are compliant by design,
but not by ch but not by chance.
Feel free to connect on LinkedIn or
please reach out after this session.
I would love to continue the discussion.
Thank you.