Hi everyone.
Today we are going to talk about something
that's put urgent and often overlooked
how to secure robot networks for the
future where quantum computers exist.
The robots we are deploying today, whether
in manufacturing, healthcare, defense, or
even logistics, will still be operating
five, 10, even 15 years from now.
Meanwhile, quantum computing is
evolving rapidly even though large scale
quantum computers aren't here yet, the
threat landscape is already shifting.
Robotic systems combine long lived
hardware sensitive and operational data.
And real time autonomy, which makes them
prime targets for both current, future
current and also our future adversaries.
So my goal today with this topic
is to show you how robotics and
how can we architect systems
that stay secure for decades.
Let's start with this matter right now.
Quantum computers are expected to break
widely used cryptography protocols like
RSA and ECC using Shor's algorithm.
That means the algorithms that
secure our robot communications
command channels, and firmware
today will be eventually vulnerable.
Even more concerning is the
harvest now decrypt later strategy.
Attackers are already collecting encrypted
data, telemetry maps, sensor logs,
firmware, blobs so they can decrypt them.
Once the quantum capability becomes
available, robots generate long-lived
data, configuration files, mission
histories, telemetry archives.
They also receive update and commands
that must remain trusted for years.
That long-term value makes a perfect
target for quantum motivated adversaries.
Robotic has a unique attack
surface because it blends cyber
as well as the physical systems.
A breach in a robot is just about data.
It can cause physical disruptions as well.
Control and telemetry channels
can be intercepted and spoofed.
Firmware updates, especially OTA, are
a major entry point for attackers.
iRobot communication has high
bandwidth and low latency,
making it sensitive to tampering.
Then on top of that, it's not only that,
but we also now have cloud integration.
We also have APIs, we have
brokers, we have containerized
services that robots depend on.
So there are so many other cloud and
broker services plus API and so much
office services that they depend on.
And even with sensor data like
lidar or camera streams, they need
authentication because manipulated
sensor input can change a robot
behavior and can cause a hacker to
easily have control over a robot.
So every layer exposes a different
vulnerability, and quantum attacks
will only widen those gaps until
we upgrade our cryptography.
The good news is we
already have solutions.
NISD has standards.
The first generation of post quantum
cryp cryptography algorithm, the
two key ones that we'll talk about
is BER and the D lithium Kyber
is a key encapsulation mechanism
that provides secure key exchange.
Replacing RSA and ECCD Lithium
is a signature algorithm.
That ensures integrity, identity, and
trust perfect for things like command
authentication and firmware signing.
These algorithms are lat based, and
more importantly, they are ready today.
Open source libraries exist.
Implementations are maturing, and hardware
support is almost starting to land.
So after talking about the kit, let's
see how we can transition and how we can
bridge the gap with the hybrid models.
So transitioning an entire fleet
of robots to new cryptography
doesn't happen overnight.
This is where hybrid
cryptography comes in.
A modern runs a hybrid model runs
classical algorithms and post
quantum algorithms in parallel.
That means you have R-S-A-E-C-C based
systems keep working while PQC adds
a quantum safe layer on top of it.
So if one algorithm is broken, the
other still protects the system.
Now hybrid, TTLS or SSH is the first step.
It enables you to gradually upgrade robot
communications without even breaking the
compatibility with legacy components.
So it's our, it's the most practical
way out there to start your migration.
Today, when we design a quantum
safe robot network, we need to
think about entire lifecycle.
From the robot to the cloud to
all the systems it's tied to.
At the robot layer, we use
lightweight crypto for local
verification and integrity checks.
Since robot have limited compute and power
budgets, edge gateways become critical.
They can handle heavier PQC operations,
which offloads the cryptographic burden
from the robot while translating the.
Secure protocols and in the
cloud, all APIs, mod channels
and remote debugging interfaces
should use PQC enabled TLS or SSH.
Finally firmware and OT updates
must be signed with a quantum safe
signatures like de lithium that
ensures a robot trusts the update 15
years from now just as it does today.
In robotics, zero Trust
is no longer optional.
These system operate independently
and are often untrusted environments.
Zero trust means we verify every device,
every action, every packet continuously.
Robots should prove their identity
to maintain the least privilege, a
access, and provide behavioral telemetry
so system can detect anomalies.
This identity layer becomes
much stronger with PQC.
Quantum safe signatures ensure
that identity and trust can be
forged even by future adversaries.
Zero Trust gives us resilience
today, and PQC ensures that
it lasts into the quantum era.
Now let's talk about a little
bit how we can put into practice.
So if we have to operationalize
this, if we have to put a plan
to this, how will we do this?
First of all, step one is
cryptographic inventory.
Map every encryption and signing
mechanism across your robot ecosystem,
devices, gateways, and cloud pipelines.
Next, how do we prioritize
the risk across?
So the most critical areas are
firmware command channels, and the OTA.
Then pilot hybrid TLS.
Let's start small.
From there, perhaps a gateway to
the cloud, which is connecting
your robot to the cloud.
Observe the handshake, performance of
that latency, and even compatibility.
Ensure your hardware modules, HSM
and tpms, secure enclaves and are
capable of supporting the PQC.
Finally document the governance
and the incident response.
Quantum safe security isn't
only algorithms, it's also an
organizational process towards security.
As with any cryptographic
transition, there are pitfalls too.
Algorithm substitution is a real issue.
A vehicle algorithm unless you
enforce a stricter PQC policy.
Legacy systems often can't
suppose support PQC natively.
So rather than replacing them
immediately, you can wrap or
sandbox them in secure gateways.
Vendor dependency is another
challenge, so not all the vendors
you would use are PQC ready.
But making the decisions on the
spot is also difficult because
an organization from a business
standpoint is already engaged with
a vendor for such a big inventory.
So try to choose from those modular
crypto APIs and clear roadmaps.
And finally, independent
testing is also essential.
Cryptography is hard
to implement correctly.
But third party validations.
And then having professional services
helps catch subtle but critical flaws.
The transition to quantum safe
robotics should start now.
First inventory in your cryptography.
Second pilot PQC in control environment.
Third, build the policies and governance.
So transition is consistent and scalable.
Robotics is becoming central
to the industry, healthcare,
defense, and also society.
Eventually, the best time to
secure these systems was yesterday.
The next best time is today.
I encourage you to join open source
communities advancing PQC and robotic
security, and this is a collective
effort and the work we do today will
now define the safety and security
of tomorrow's autonomous system.
Thank you everyone.