Hi everyone.
I am Vi Nading, a principal software
engineer, and today I want to talk about
data governance in AI driven banking.
When you think about automation
in finance, think back to 2008,
the global financial crisis.
We didn't have generative AI then,
but we had algorithms making decisions
with opaque logic and incomplete data.
Fast forward to today, AI is
exponentially more powerful.
It's approving loans, flagging fraud, and
even advising investments in real time.
The difference, we don't ground
that ai, we risk repeating 2008,
but at mission speed, remember.
So yes.
Today's talk is about the least
exciting word in AI governance.
But ironically, it's the
one thing that keeps AI from
becoming tomorrow's headline.
So let's dive in.
In the last decade, banking has
quietly become one of the most
robotic industries on earth.
In 2016, for instance, JP Morgan
introduced its coin platform, a contract
analysis AI that completed in seconds.
What used to take lawyers $360,000 a year.
Around the same time fraud detection
models began processing billions
of credit cards transactions daily
AI isn't the future of ranking.
It's already embedded
in its nervous system.
Think of the last time you
got a transaction alert before
you even checked your balance.
That's AI driven.
Robotics in action scanning,
predicting, reacting, all gone
by data pipelines we rarely see,
but there's a catch.
80% of the financial institutions
say data governance is the
biggest barrier to scaling ai.
The average deployment
delay is six to nine months.
Purely due to compliance reviews.
When GDPR took effect in 2018, several
major banks had to pass their projects
for months just to trace how customer
data was flowing into machine learning
pipelines, one European bank discovered
30 different versions of the same
data set being used across models.
None with consistent consent tracking.
Remember, consistent
consent tracking is the key.
That's the governance gap.
AI moves at milliseconds, but
our controls move at human speed.
Without governance, AI innovation turns
into AI improvisation, and in banking,
that's expensive, not tolerable.
What do we do about it?
The legacy systems fall
short in several parts.
They're not designed for
business intelligence.
They're slow batch oriented
and blind to model lineage.
Remember the word model lineage.
The first generation of
governance tools emerged in 1990s.
They were built for static warehouses,
monthly reports, and Excel exports.
Then came AI pipeline dynamic, constantly
evolving auto retraining models.
Those old systems simply can't track what
happens inside a neural network trained
across 50 data sources, for instance.
When L-I-B-O-R Scandal broke in
2012, regulators demanded proof
of data lineage in risk models.
Most banks couldn't produce it.
They couldn't because their
systems had no unified trays.
From data origin to decision
output, why was this decision taken?
What was the input data used?
That's the kind of gap modern
AI governance must never repeat.
So here we are introducing
the unified framework.
To address this, we want to build
a unified data governance framework
engineer specifically for AI driven
robotics heavy banking system.
It embeds governance directly into
AI lifecycle from feature engineering
to model deployment and monitoring.
It has four pillars, meta management,
where it's the central catalog for
every single data, asset and model.
Then comes lineage tracking.
This is super important.
Every transformation, every
dependency visible end to end
Then comes quality monitoring.
Any automated drifts, anomalies
by and performance checks had
to be performed at rapid speeds.
Finally, the cloud native oversight.
Sub 200 milliseconds query response
tracking 5,000 or 10,000 model
updates daily because fraud does move
quicker, AI has to be on top of that.
For instance, if you follow the UK's
open banking rollout in 2018, regulators
required every participating bank.
To log data moment and consent lineage,
that same philosophy, transparency through
transparency, through traceability,
is what this framework enforces.
But for AI systems, it's let less like
a gatekeeper and more like a air traffic
controller, ensuring thousands of AI
models take off safely without colliding.
Then comes security.
Security is the other half of governance.
The 2020 Solar Winds breach reminded
us that software supply chains
can become invisible entry points.
For ai, the equivalent risk is
data lineage hijack when upstream
data is tamper and silently
corrupts the models and the output.
So what do we do?
We want role-based, role-based access
control for tens of thousands of users.
We want full audit trail for every
access event, we need integration
with enterprise identity systems.
Let's take examples.
The framework we build has
to support G-D-P-R-C-C-P-A,
basil three and BCBS 2, 3, 9.
For instance, it mandates risk data
to be accurate, complete, and timely.
That's nearly impossible without
automated lineage and validation systems.
For instance, when European
Central Bank audited AI credit
models in 2022, the number one
failure point was missing lineage.
Between feature data
and regulatory reports.
So governance season paperwork,
it's survival in banking.
Let's jump into a real world case.
For instance, a tier one global
bank adopted this unified
governance framework in 2025.
Within months, they achieved.
30% foster AI deployment, no
manual compliance bottlenecks,
40% stronger audit readiness.
Traceability became automatic a
hundred percent compliance across
GDPR basis three and BCBS standards.
And here is an interesting anecdote.
During an internal audit,
the regulator asked them to
trace a fraud detection model.
Back to its training data in
2019, that would have taken weeks
or months, even months in 2025.
The answer came up in 0.3 seconds
through a single governance query.
That's not just efficiency, that's
cultural transformation, and
that's what we are headed towards.
How do we scale this responsibility?
How do we ensure robotics ready?
Governance?
There are four pillars.
If you can think of foundation,
build on cloud native infrastructure
with embedded governance.
Link your AI lifecycle tools
directly to governance pipelines.
Automation, continuously monitoring
for bias, RIF compliance anomalies.
Finally, scale, expand innovation
safety across all AI workloads.
An interesting anecdote comes
to my mind in 2012 when Netflix.
Move its entire recommender
system to the cloud.
They built observability into
the migration from day one.
Banking needs to take the same approach.
Governance first, not governance later.
Here's what I want to leave you with.
Governance is an enabler.
It doesn't slow innovation.
It unlocks it.
Again, it doesn't slow innovation.
If we don't follow governance,
we end up slowing our business.
Robotics demands real time systems.
Governance must match AI's velocity
without which it won't work.
Compliance, trust.
Trust.
That's the cornerstone of AI adoption.
Every financial revolution, be it ATMs
in 1970s to blockchains in 2010s face
skepticism until governance caught up.
Today's AI revolution is no
different, especially for banking.
We are not just building models.
We are building systems that
society has to trust with its money.
So next time you see an AI approving,
a mortgage, flagging a transaction, or
detecting fraud, remember behind every
intelligent decision should stand and
equally intelligent governance system.
Thank you.