Good day everyone.
My name is a Sal from
End Living Technologies.
Today I will be discussing how we
can optimize Oracle and skill server
databases in cloud, focusing on
practical frameworks for achieving high
performance on AWS and Azure Clouds.
First, the critical role of
database performance As robotics
automation and data driven system
continues to expand database
performance become mission critical.
Every milliseconds of the latency
can influence real time decision.
I will cover why optimization of
database on Modern Cloud platform is not
just a beneficial, but it's essential
foundational optimization techniques.
Before we drive into cloud native
tools, it is important to understand
core database optimization principles
like a scale plan management, a WR
analysis, query, store insights.
These help maintain stability,
diagnose bottlenecks, and track
very performance over time.
Next, cloud Native Performance Tools,
both AWS and Azure provide powerful tools.
Like a WR. Performance Insights
helps you to visualize and diagnose
database load in real time.
While Azures intelligent tuning uses
machine learning to automatically
adjust and improve the performance.
Next query optimization query execution.
Identifying and resolving problematic
queries is central to optimization.
Using tools like a WR and Performance
Insights, you can pinpoint slow queries.
Review the execution plan and
apply targeted improvements like
indexing or query rewriting.
Next now we'll see into resource
utilization and workload throughputs.
Efficient resource management
ensures maximum throughput memory.
Ivo and CPU must.
Appropriately while connection
pooling helps reduce the latency
in high concurrency environments.
Exhibition plan stability
ensures predictable performance.
Using SQL Plan Management in Oracle and
a query stored plan, forcing in a scale
server, you can capture and enforce the
optimal plans to prevent the regressions.
Partitioning strategics for sales
partitioning improves performance
and simplified management with a
range hash or list partitioning.
It helps to target specific
data sets efficiently and
reduce the maintenance windows,
workload, governance, and resource manage.
Governance ensures critical workloads
get the resources and they need Oracle
Resource Manager and Escal Server
Resource Governance allows fine tuned
control over CPU and Memory and Sessions
cross-platform benchmark.
Comparing AWS and Azure performance
through standardized benchmarks helps to
determine optimal workload par placement
testing with KPS, like query response
time and TPS gives clarity on trade offs.
Now we'll go to the
strengths and of AWS and.
AWS offers deep visibility and
flexibility tools like Performance
Insights and Aurora Serverless.
Meanwhile, Azure provides machine
learning driven through hyperscale
database that supports massive workloads.
Cost management in cloud databases.
Cost to optimization is just as vital.
A right sizing instance.
Committing to reserve capacity,
optimizing storage, and setting up
monitoring alerts are key strategies
for sustainable cloud spending.
Now we'll go through the emerging trends.
We are seeing automat automation
evolve with machine learning
driven through serverless database.
Edge computing and greener infrastructure
that reduce the carbon footprint.
Now we'll see the roadmap,
how the roadmap will be.
Start by assessing your current
performance improvements, quick
wins, established governance,
and plan strategic improvements.
Remember, optimization
is a continuous process.
We cannot stop on a day.
It should continue as data
grows or infrastructure grows.
Finally, the takeaways.
Integrated traditional techniques
with cloud tools optimized across
all dimensions and prepare for the
future with adapt to architectures.
Thank you Finally.
Thank you for your time.
I hope this session give you the
accountable insights into optimizing
your database performance, cost
effective, and scalability in the cloud.
Thank you.