Everyone, good morning, good
afternoon, or good evening,
whatever time it is where you are.
Allow me to introduce myself.
My name is Charles Anthony Raj.
I currently serve as a senior manager
for systems and software engineering
at Collins Aerospace and RTX Company.
In my current role within the
Electric Systems Business Unit, I lead
engineering efforts focused on advancing
cutting edge aerospace technologies.
With about two decades of experience
in the aerospace industry, I've had
the opportunity to work across a
wide range of aircraft subsystems,
contributing to several major
platforms throughout my career.
Today I will be talking to you all
about DL 1 78 C in Multicore avionics.
Certification paths for electric aircraft,
the multi-core revolution in aviation.
The aviation industry is entering
the multi-core revolution after
having lived on the single core
processes for a very long time, and
it is driven by demand for higher
performance, efficiency, and autonomy.
Multi core processors are transforming
how next generation and electric
aircrafts are designed and certified.
Just look at the adoption rate.
Multi-core processors are now widely
deployed in multiple modern platforms.
From electric propulsion
systems to advanced avionics.
They enable greater computing power
and system integration essential for
the next wave of intelligent aircraft.
It does come with the baggage.
Certification delays many programs,
first face certification delays.
Due to the complexity of multi-core
timing and interference analysis,
these challenges highlight the
need for early planning and
robust verification strategies.
Teams are using proven partitioning,
measurement based timing analysis,
and early certification engagement.
To see significant time savings.
These best practices shorten compliance
cycles and help bring advanced
aircraft to the market much faster.
The multi-core revolution is here.
Success depends on pairing innovation
with disciplined proven certification
methods, why multi-core for air
electric aircraft demand faster,
smarter, and more efficient computing.
Multi-core processors provide
the foundation for this
generation of flight systems.
There are these three major advantages,
performance, integration, and efficiency.
Multi-core processors deliver enhanced
computational power needed for complex
robotic control and autonomous operations.
It enables an advanced flight
management sensor fusion and
onboard AI to operate in real time.
Multicore processor architecture
allows multiple avionics
functions to run on fewer hardware
platforms, which is a great boon.
This reduces weight wiring and system
complexity, all absolutely critical
for electric aircraft efficiency.
Multicore architectures enable
optimized power consumption.
Maximize maximizing energy
available for propulsion.
This balance of performance and efficiency
is essential in electric aircraft.
In short, multi-core computing powers the
Electric Aviation Revolution, delivering
performance, integration and energy
efficiency for the aircraft of the future.
The certification challenge.
Address the elephant in the room.
Multi-core architectures are transforming
avionics, but they also fundamentally
change how we certify safety critical
software under DO 1 7 8 C. Especially
for design assurance levels A through
C, the challenge lies in maintaining
predictability and determinism
across multiple processing cores.
Multiple core share cashes.
Memory buses and IO channels.
This competition introduces
unpredictable timing behavior,
which complicates safety validation.
Cross core interference can disrupt
deterministic execution, must for
flight critical control functions.
Ensuring isolation and predictable
scheduling becomes a key design focus.
Then we gotta talk
about wicked validation.
Wicked AKA.
Worst case execution time grows
exponentially harder to verify.
In a multi-core system, traditional
single core analysis no longer applies,
which means we need or require new
tools and measurement based approaches.
The certification challenge isn't
just technical, it's procedural.
Success means combining innovative
analysis methods with early
continuous collaboration with
certification authorities.
Let's talk about the frameworks to
certify multi-core avionic software.
We rely on two key frameworks, do 1 7,
8 C that we all know of and so used to,
and C 32 a. Together, they define the
foundation and the specialized guidance
needed for modern multi-core systems.
What is D 1 7 8 C?
That's the foundation D one seven eight C
software consideration in airborne systems
and equipment certification that set the
baseline for air airborne software safety.
It defines desu design assurance
levels A to E, guiding the rigor
of development and verification.
It also establishes expectations
for verification and validation,
configuration management and quality
assurance, ensuring traceability
and integrity throughout the cycle.
CAS 32.
A guidance issued by the
certification authorities focuses
on multi-course specific challenges.
It addresses interference,
mitigation, timing analysis,
and resource usage validation.
It also outlines documentation
expectations to demonstrate control and
predictability in multi-core environments.
In short, D 1 7 8 C provides the what?
The foundation for certification
and C 32 A provides The how
for multi-core compliance.
Applying both ensures safe,
certifiable, and high performance
multi-core avionic systems.
So the C 32 A, which is the position
paper, defines the objectives
and mitigation expectations
for multi-core processors.
And then e aa, which is the European
jurisdiction, they issued something called
the A MC 20 dash 1 93, which is acceptable
means of compliance for multi-core.
It supersedes the C 30 A for
applicants in the ESR jurisdiction.
FAA also.
Sent out an advisory circular AC 20 dash
1 93 back in 2024, which is fas acceptable
means of compliance, which aligns
with the AMC 20 dash 1 21 93 though.
All right, certification
objective summary.
Let's talk more about these early
multicore processing, pro multicore
processor planning and hardware
characterization is very important.
Resource usage, budgeting and
partitioning, demonstrating
wicked bounds under interference,
error detection, handling for MCP
specific falls and producing an MA
multi-core processor accomplishment
Summary for this CER authority.
In safety, critical avionics
partitioning is essential to protect
critical robotic control processes
from lower criticality functions.
The goal prevent failures from crossing,
design assurance levels, boundaries, and
maintain predictable system behavior.
Spatial partitioning.
This assigns dedicated memory regions
to each functions prevents unauthorized
access or data corruption between
partitions, which are crucial.
Then comes temporal partitioning.
This uses time sliced execution to ensure
every critical task gets guaranteed.
CPU access.
This maintains deterministic
performance even under high load.
And then comes resource allocation.
Careful core and cash allocation reduces
interference between partitions, optimizes
performance while maintaining isolation.
Then comes the validation, testing,
robustness and stress testing.
Verify that partitions remain secure
and stable under all conditions.
Confirms the integrity of safety
boundaries before certification.
Effective partitioning, underpins
both safety and reliability.
It's the foundation for certifiable,
multi-core robotic avionic systems.
Let's talk about interference channels.
Multi-core architectures introduce
interference channels that can
impact timing and pre predictability
of safety critical systems.
Understanding these channels
is essential for certification
and robust systems design.
Then comes cash interference.
Shared L two or L three
caches can EV affect data
unexpectedly affecting execution.
Timing of critical task, multiple core
accessing memories simultaneously can
create weight states delaying execution.
Peripheral access, right?
Shared IO controllers and DMA
channels may slow down critical
operations, if not managed carefully.
So core to core.
Communications across the interconnect
fabric adds unpredictable latency
to distributed functions, mitigating
these interference channels through
partitioning the right scheduling,
and the measurement based analysis
is key to ensuring deterministic
behavior in multi-core avionics.
We also need the right set of tools, the
right operating system and vendor support.
Successful multi-core avionics
development relies on a combination
of all of those RTAs, okay?
A real-time operating system
with multi-core partitioning.
Example, like the integrity 1 78
UMP proven in early multi-core
certification programs provides strong
spatial and temporal partitioning.
Essential for safety critical
applications, timing analysis, and
measurement suites like tools like
rapida, LDRA, vendor Tool chains and
vendor specific profilers help analyze
execution time, and verify worst
case execution times test harnesses.
Similar to TTC N'S support
structured repeatable test campaigns.
Hardware assisted tracing and
monitoring is a must have ETM or PTM
based tracing platform configuration
managements and QOS monitors enable deep
visibility into multi-cloud behavior.
These tools help detect interference,
validate timing, and ensure predictable
operation combining partition artis.
Measurement tools and hardware
tracing ensures multi-core avionics
can really meet both performance
and certification requirements.
Let's talk about the certification
strategy for electric
aircraft phase one, right?
Electric aircraft programs or
adopting proven certification method.
To safely deploy multicore
while staying compliant?
The phase one part of it is
defining partitioning strategies
to isolate critical functions.
Selecting a certified OSH with multicore
support to ensure a strong foundation
for creative critical software.
Phase two, you get into the analysis part,
perform performing interference analysis
to understand shared resource effects.
Start interference characterization.
In parallel with software
development ed work streams basically
automate instrumentation and
regression under stress harnesses.
Establish timing budgets following
cast 32 a. Guidance phase
three is our integration phase.
Use measurement based validation to
verify worst case execution times
ensure comprehensive test coverage
across platform and test scenarios.
Test stress scenarios.
Phase four is certification
compiler, evidence packages,
demonstrating compile compliance.
This is no different to what we
do on the D 1 7 8 C route that
we are doing on all the other
avionics platforms these days com.
Having the right amount of evidence
packaged together is very important.
In some cases use using
vendor provided certification.
PA packages again, when available
can help shorten evidence gathering
or generation engaging certification
authorities early and continuously
will help streamline the approval.
One.
Following these four phases accelerates
multiple multi-core adoption.
While ensuring safety, predictability,
and regulatory compliance, robotic
control system integration.
There's the critical considerations here.
Robotic control systems rely on precise
timing and deterministic execution.
Every control loop must behave
predictably, especially in
safety critical domains like
drones or autonomous vehicles.
On modern multicore platforms,
maintaining those realtime guarantees
becomes both essential and challenging.
Sensor data from imus cameras and
lighter must be processed in real time.
Assigning sensor fusion to
dedicated course prevent timing
jitter cost by other processes.
This ensures consistent data
availability for control loops.
Flight control laws with
guaranteed response times core
flight control algorithms demand
fixed low latency response.
Realtime scheduling and task
prioritization are vital to ensure
control commands are computed and
applied within strict deadlines.
Even microsecond delays
can affect stability.
Autonomous decision making
with temporal isolation.
High level autonomy, like path
planning, obstacle avoidance, things
like that should not interfere
with low level control loops.
Temporal and spatial isolation
ensures that computationally have
we AI tasks don't delay a time.
Critical control.
Threats fail.
Safe monitoring without interference.
Safety monitors and watch docs must
continuously check system health,
but without introducing any extra
latency, use separate cores or realtime
partitions to guarantee independence
and quick recovery in fault condition.
In short, successful integration of
robotic control systems and multiple
multi-core platforms depends on real time
determinism, isolation and fault decision.
Balancing performance and
predictability is the key to achieving
reliable, safe robotics behavior.
We gotta talk about documentation
and evidence For multi-core
safety certification, authorities
require clear defensible evidence.
That multi-core systems meet safety
and determinism requirements.
No different to the other ones
that we've needed all along,
even with a single core system.
But this just means more.
The goal is to show not just performance,
but predictable behavior under all
operating condition becomes a major point.
We gotta talk about interference analysis.
Start with the comprehensive
interference assessment.
Assessment.
Across shared resources, cash,
memory, buses, memory buses, and io.
Identify all potential
interference channels and describe
mitigation strategies such as
partitioning or bandwidth control.
This forms the foundation for
demonstrating multi-course safety.
Timing reports provide wicked validation
with confidence levels and margins.
The reports should show consistent
timing under load and justify that
real-time deadlines remain intact
even during contention in and test
results include robustness and stress
testing resulting results to prove that
partitioning mechanisms are effecti.
Show that once one course heavy workload
does not degrade another's timing or
safety performance, these results are
key to demonstrating practical isolation.
Finally, the compliance matrix and
certification artifacts present
a compliance matrix mapping
each cast 32, a objective to
corresponding verification evidence.
Include tool qualification
data for any automated tools
used in analysis of testing.
Summarize all evidence in the
multi-core certification plan.
Accomplishment summary, ensuring full
traceability to DO 1 78 C. Objectives,
strong documentation and traceability
are vital as the technical design itself.
A well structured evidence package
gives certification authorities
confidence in the system's safety,
determinism and compliance.
Let's talk about some of the common
pitfalls and how to avoid them.
Let working with multi-core
avionics, certain assumptions
can lead to costly setbacks.
Let's highlight a few common
pitfalls and how I provide them.
Single core versus multi-core OTs.
Don't ever again, don't ever assume single
core wickeds or worst case execution
Time applies to multi-core systems.
Shared resources.
Cost interferences, meaning multi-core
timing can be very different.
Second one is late platform selection.
Choosing your hardware platform
too late can cause major rework.
Early platform decisions enable realistic
testing and timing validation sooner.
Thirdly, incomplete interference testing.
Insufficient stress testing, leaves
hidden timing conflicts, uses
stress metrics that covers all
combinations of shared resources,
and ensure that you have enough.
So what is the solution?
Introduce hardware in the loop
testing as early as possible.
Use interference generators to
expose timing issues, leverage tools,
support or trace analysis for deeper
visibility into system behavior.
By addressing these pitfalls, early teams
can reduce rework, improve predictability,
and accelerate certification readiness.
I just wanted to show you guys a case
study here, the P 3000 Multi-Core
Certification success Story.
The P 3000 from CMC electronics
represents a major milestone in avionics.
It's one of the very first platforms to
achieve civil multi-core certification to
D 1 78 C dll level A. This certification
demonstrate that multi-core processors
can certainly meet the highest level
of safety assurance in civil aviation.
The key points here are, the P
3000 integrates the integrity one
70 A-T-U-M-P realtime operating
system from Greenhill software.
That the R task provides temporal
and spatial partitioning,
ensuring predictable deterministic
performance across multiple core.
The project provided real certification
evidence addressing CAST 32 a. Objectives
such as interference analysis, timing
validation, and core isolation.
It demonstrated that D 1 7 8 C DA a
compliance is achievable on multi-core
hardware and supported by rigorous
design verification and documentation.
So this P 3000 certification sets
a practical precedence for future
multi-core avionics programs.
It proves that with the right
architecture, verification strategy,
safety, critical multi-core
systems can certainly achieve full
certification without compromising
performance of predictability.
So what's the path forward?
Multicore Avionics are the
foundation of next generation
robotics driven aerospace system.
They deliver the processing power
needed for autonomy, AI if need
be, and complex mission functions,
balancing innovation and safety, right?
Innovation must be matched with
rigorous safety and certification
discipline, which is a must for.
Aircraft systems, we must integrate
new technologies without ever
compromising reliability or compliance.
Use trusted partitioning methods
to isolate critical functions.
This ensures false or contained and safety
critical task remain protected with them.
Apply measurement based timing
analysis to validate a real time
performance paired with comprehensive
test coverage to ensure predictable
behavior and under all conditions.
The most important part, early and
continuous engagement with certification
Authorities involve certification
bodies early in the development phase.
Maintain an open continuous dialogue
through streamline approval and
reduce rework the path forward.
Combines innovation, safety,
and collaboration by following
these three principles.
We can confidently advance toward an
intelligent autonomous aerospace future.
I would like to leave you all with
an example certification plan.
Basically, it's a recap of everything
that we've talked about so far.
The first phase is the selection
of the right platform, the R task,
making sure that you have the
multi-core risk assessment completed.
Platform characterization
and interference map.
Partitioning and resource
budgets are defined, which
includes time, memory, and io.
First case execution time analysis, under
interference testing, integration test
metrics, error handling verifications,
and finally, the multi-core processor
accomplishment, summary and submission.
If you have any questions or would like
to discuss anything on this topic, please.
Feel free to reach out to me.
Thank you all.