Hello and welcome.
I'm Sankar Subramanian and
I'm glad we can come together
online to explore today's topic.
I have over 20 years of experience
in control and automation systems,
bringing together hardware and software
expertise in area such as semiconductor
lasers, fiber optic transfers, and
electric vehicle RMD and manufacturing.
My work has often been about
integrating precise engineering with
intelligent, reliable automation.
Over past few years, I've been deeply
involved in exploring how modern AI can
be combined with robust programming tools
to solve real world industrial challenges.
Rust, with its focus on safety, speed
and concurrency, has quickly become
a powerful choice of building high
performance and reliable systems.
In the system, we will be looking look
at how AI powered Mission, mission in
Rust can deliver not only accuracy and
efficiency, but also the scalability
and suitability making it strong
option for next generation automation.
For next few minutes, I will share
key concepts, real world examples, key
takeaways you can apply to your own work.
Let's get started.
AI power mission interest, transforming
ev, manufacturing quality and automation.
The imperative of advanced division
system in EV manufacturing, electrical.
Electric vehicle represents a
fundamental shift in automotive design
on manufacturing complexity due to
its higher component density requiring
multi micron level precision critical
battery safety concerns and necessary
a hundred percentage inspection.
Manufacturing at scale demands foster
throughput, zero defect expectations
for safety critical systems.
So all this, because of all this
high demands in the manufacturing
traditional inspection methods
can't meet these demands.
Creating perfect application for
rust power automation mission systems
that combines performance with
the memory safety guarantees that
why rest the characters
that are mentioned above.
Makes arrest uniquely suited for EV
manufacturing where reliability, speed
and safety cannot be compromised.
The first characteristics you know,
that we can consider is memory
safety, zero memory related crash in
a production system through compile
time guarantees critical for 20 4K
seven manufacturing environments where
downtime cost thousands per minute.
Fearless currencies, safety process model.
Safely processing multiple camera
feeds simultaneously without, data
race a race conditioning without
any race conditioning, enabling
real time inspection across multiple
assembly stages and rest performing
performance is very close to c.
Speeds with the zero cost abstraction.
Allow processing of higher
resolution images at the line
speed exceeding 10 ports per
second throughput FFI capabilities.
Seamless integration with cc plus
vision libraries and emission learning
framework like 10 flow and by chart
while maintaining safety boundaries.
The real time inline quality inspection
systems, the higher resolution
component inspection that is quite
often in the manufacturing environment.
So Rust Vision System currently
deployed in production, environmental
use, rust resolution down to five
micron for critical cell inspections.
Processing speed of 12 to 15 frames per
second at a 4K resolution, arrow camera,
image resolution multi spectrum imaging,
like visible ir UV for comprehensive
defect detections, consistent performance
under variable lighting conditions.
These are all becoming, very essential.
And our multi-camera array leverage rust.
That's concurrent con, concurrency model
to process multiple inspection angle
simultaneously without frame drops.
The next presentation is next slide,
which is AI enhanced to defect detection
which is part of the inspection
systems, mission, vision, inspection
systems, and in the EV manufacturing.
So image acquisition,
which is a primary part.
That has high speed camera capture
capturing multiple views of components
at line speed, like approximately
like a 10 plus parts per second,
which is significantly higher
rate in the modern manufacturing.
Pre-processing rus, SAMD optimization
enables a realtime noise reduction
in our contrast enhancements
and then feature extractions.
AI based classification, custom neural
network detects subtle defect missed
by traditional threshold based systems.
And then automated responses, part
rejection rework, flow flagging,
or process adjustments based
on a defect classifications.
Our system have demonstrated a
37 percentage increase in defect
detection rate compared to
conventional machine vision approaches.
While rest, safety guarantees
guarantees prevent the system crash
common in a CC plus N environments.
And the next thing is battery
cell on a pack inspection.
On this electrode alignment verification
is one of the critical process
in, in, in the battery assembly.
Battery pack assembly, basically.
So it means assembling a cell into a pack.
Submillimeter precision measurements
or demand in this process.
For aligning for ano catho alignment
using structured light patterns.
And rust high performance
image processing is vital here.
Surface defect detection, all
a models identify microscopic
cracks, dents, and contaminations.
That could lead to a thermal runaway
events detecting such, such a defect
or critical in the battery cell and
pack inspections electrolyte filling
verification, and I are imaging
combining combined with the custom d,
detection algorithm, ensuring proper
electrolyte levels and distributions.
Thermal anomaly monitoring.
On the back level.
The IR cameras like FLIR,
which is a teledyne.
Now the IR camera integrates for
early detection of hotspots during
formation cycling with rust,
handling a real time thermal mapping,
advanced inspection methodologies.
Battery module level inspection is one of
the critical process in the manufacturing.
Our rust based system implementation
implements several cutting edge techniques
like wire bond quality assessments
using structured elimination laser
weld quality verification through
structural analysis, thermal imaging.
During module pulsing to identify
resistance anomalies on the welding
defects 3D profile mapping to verify
dimensional accuracy post assembly.
So Russ performance enable a realtime
processing of these complex inspections
routines without dropping a frame.
Lesser build inspection requires a precise
lighting under multiple specialized
camera to identify microscopic defects.
3D mission systems for
assembly automation.
When it comes for assembly automation.
The challenges are quite significant,
especially how precisely we are
able to detect the depth of multiple
components in a 3D perspective,
which plays a vital role.
So depth sensing, time of flight cameras
provides realtime spatial data for robot
guidance with two millimeter accuracy.
And then the other type could
be a dual camera setup with rust
optimized disparity mapping for high
precision and component handling.
We do use laser triangulation.
Basically a laser based sensors that,
that could measure up to sub micron
precision for critical alignment
tasks like, motor, straighter
assembly, those kind of processes.
And then point cloud processing
rust performance enables a realtime
processing of dense point clouds
for complex assembly operations.
So once the assembly and then is
done, the AI power division analytics,
that plays a vital role in in any.
High advanced manufacturing environment.
Deep planning, integration, I know
with our rust system it leverages
multiple AI approaches for neural
networks for defect classification
with a very high accuracy, close to a
hundred percent unsupervised anomaly
detection, identifying novel defect types,
transfer learning techniques to reduce
training data requirements by 80% age.
Russ FFI capabilities seamlessly
connecting to TensorFlow and
then OnX runtime interference.
Optimizing through Russ enables
the deployment of H devices
directly on the protection line,
eliminating network latencies.
Then it comes to manufacturing
execution systems integration.
In MES in the manufacturing environment,
component traceability is one
of the, prime role of having ME.
So OCR and the barcode reading are
the primary on the critical process
of traceability implementation.
So OCR and barcode reading capability
tracks every component from raw material
to finished vehicles with 99 percentage
or even close to a hundred percentage.
Read.
Process verification.
So vision system confirms the correct
assembly sequences and component
placements, and on a day and integrate
with the digital work instructions.
So every critical process was implemented
with this vision based assembly
sequence, verifications process step.
So quality data aggregation.
All this data, there's a tons of
data that are being collected.
All these data are getting aggregated
into a one digital form and then that
will be tagged to every component that
is being manufactured in this line.
Regulatory compliance compliances.
It also helps to automate
documentation generation for safety
and certification and recall readiness.
Rust.
Reliability ensures these mission
critical systems maintain uptime
exceeding close to a hundred percentage
essential for maintaining production
flow and traceability requirements.
So once the vehicle is assembled,
when it comes for advanced driver
assistance system calibration
under digital twin integration.
You know here also it
plays a critical role.
So adults calibration involves our
advanced distribution system validates
precise calibration for forward facing
camera for accurate land reduction,
LIDAR sensors for comprehensive
obstacle recognition, rather units
for reliable distance measurement.
Surround view camera systems
for enhanced parking assistance.
Rus unparalleled.
Performance and choose complex calibration
procedures for, that can be completed
within, under 90 seconds per vehicle
in a high volume manufacturing line.
So digital twin integration.
So real time vision data seamlessly
integrates into factory digital twin,
facilitating productive maintenance
through insightful trend analysis.
That tracks each of the process
equipments on the critical process line.
Dynamic real time process
optimization robust closed loop
control systems, efficient virtual
commissioning of a new product line
future directions and
implementation roadmap.
So current deployment, so bacteria and
powertrain inspection systems with the.
Basic AI capabilities achieving 30
percentage reduction in s escape defects.
Our near term target is to integrate
integration of a multimodal sensing like
a vision, ultrasound and thermal sensors
with advanced machine learning models
capable of product to quality assessments.
In the midterm, fully autonomous
inspection system with the self
optimized algorithm and automated root
cause analysis on, on, in cars for
long term, the cognitive manufacturing
system where vision and robotics.
And the process controls form a unified
AI production ecosystem which could
be achieved in a long term approach.
Rest will remind our foundation with
its ecosystem maturing alongside these
advance months to provide performance,
safety, and reliability requires for
next generation EV manufacturing.
That concludes my presentation.
I thank you all for your
time and attention today.
I truly appreciate your participation
and hope the session gave you
valuable insights into AI power,
the mission in rest language.
Thank you.