Hello everyone.
My name is Karthik Mohan.
You can call me Karthik.
I'm a software engineer with eight
years of experience specializing in
building and integrating complex systems.
My work is focused on
the Salesforce platform.
And cloud data solutions like
Google BigQuery with an expertise in
crafting everything from the intuitive
user interface down to the robust
backend architecture that powers it.
Today I want to talk about a
fundamental shift happening in
how we build enterprise systems.
We are moving away from a world where
everything happens in the cloud towards
a more balanced and hybrid approach.
My goal for this session is to
explore how we can effectively
bridge the growing divide between
edge computing and the cloud.
We'll look at two powerful
orchestration methods.
Patterns that will solve real world
problems and show how rust programming
language provides the perfect foundation
for these modern realtime systems.
By the end, I hope you'll have a clear,
practical roadmap for implementing
these ideas in your own organizations.
Okay, here's a quick look at our
journey for the next few minutes.
First we'll set the stage by digging into
the specific problems with traditional
cloud only architectures, especially
when it comes to real time applications.
Next, we'll dive into the core of
the presentation to transformative
orchestration patterns.
Those are.
The edge inference, cloud remediation
pattern, and the cloud insight,
edge reconfiguration pattern.
Then we'll talk about the why.
Why is rust such a game
changer for edge computing?
We'll touch on its key features
like memory safety and what
fearless concurrency actually
means for us as developers.
Of course every project
has its own huddles.
We'll honestly discuss the big
implementation challenges like managing
distributed state and security, and
the solutions we found to be effective.
Now let's start with the core problem.
As we deploy more and more IOT
devices in our factories our stores
or cities, we are pushing up against
the natural limits of what a purely
cloud-centric model can handle.
This creates some challenges,
the three major challenges.
The first one is latency, right?
So for many real time applications like a
robot or a medical monitoring device, the
roundtrip time to a distance cloud server
is simply too long, even though it might
be just a hundred to 200 milliseconds.
That is also too long to wait
for a decision when we need a
decision to be made in, let's
say, less than 20 milliseconds.
The second problem is, the bandwidth
the sheer volume of data from thousands
of sensors can be overwhelming.
Trying to stream everything to
the cloud 24 by seven creates a
massive network congestion and
can lead to astronomical costs.
Finally, there's one more challenge.
That's the availability.
If your critical operations are entirely
dependent on a stable internet connection
you are creating a huge point of failure.
Your edge systems needs to
keep functioning even when the
cloud connectivity is lost.
So these challenges make it clear that
the future isn't about choosing an
edge system or a cloud architecture.
It's about making them work
together intelligently.
Okay, now let's talk
about our first solution.
This is a pattern called edge
inference Cloud remediation.
This pattern fundamentally flips
the traditional data processing
model, and here's how it works.
Instead of sending the raw data to the
cloud we perform the initial analysis
right where the data is created.
On the edge.
We deploy like lightweight,
efficient machine learning models
onto the edge devices themselves.
These models can make immediate
realtime decisions only the results
the important insights or anomalies
or exceptions are sent to the cloud.
The cloud can then perform more
sophisticated analysis and decide if a
larger remediation action is required.
Let's say dispatching a technician
or triggering a workflow right?
The benefits of this is instantaneous.
Like you dramatically reduce the
latency for critical decisions.
The bandwidth needs are reduced
and a more reliable system is
built without crippling the without
being crippled by network outages.
This type of pattern is ideal for
industries such as manufacturing,
predictive maintenance, and
essentially any scenario where local
realtime responsiveness is necessary.
Okay, now let's go to the next one.
Now the second, pattern.
This pattern solves a completely
different kind of problem.
If the first pattern was
about local autonomy.
This one it's called Cloud Insight.
Edge reconfiguration.
It's all about creating a system
wide continuous learning loop.
So here's the flow.
The cloud analytics platform aggregates
the data from your, entire fleet
of edge devices that gives, so this
gives like a bird's eye view that
no single device possesses right.
From there machine learning models
generates like needed insights and it also
identifies like optimization opportunities
that are only visible and all the
data is present or visible at scale.
These insights are then translated
into specific policy generations
new rules or configurations that
are tailored for the individual
devices or the group of devices.
Finally, in the edge configuration
step, these new policies are pushed
down to the devices which update
their local operations on the flight.
Examples of this can be anything from
adjusting a price in a retail store to
chaining the timing of a traffic light.
It's a powerful feedback loop
when centralized intelligence
drives distributed execution.
Okay let's go to the next slide.
Okay.
Now let's talk about rust.
So Rust is the technology that makes
these demanding patterns possible.
Now, this choice of language
is also a strategic one because
there are many advantages of rust.
For example, rust provides
memory safety without the
overhead of a garbage collector.
This is like the holy grail
for embedded and IT systems.
It eliminates entire classes of
bugs and security vulnerabilities at
compiling without the unpredictable
performances Pauses that garbage
collect collection can introduce.
Second is fearless concurrency
edge devices are always
juggling multiple tasks.
So rusts compiler guarantees that you
don't have any data races which are
notoriously difficult bugs to track down.
This allows us to write highly
parallel code with confidence.
Third rusts absolutely fantastic.
Cross platform compilation
lets us write our logic.
Once and deployed across the diverse
hardware landscape of the edge from
the tiny a RM based sensors to the
powerful X 86 industrial computers.
Finally, rust has what is called zero
cost abstractions, which is like a fancy
way of saying you can write high level
expressive code without sacrificing the.
Bare metal performance which you'll expect
from language like let's say C. Okay.
Let's go to the next slide
and here are some numbers.
So this is not just theory.
There are some numbers
that we can see here.
Rust usually uses 50 to 80% less.
Memory than their counterparts.
When the counterparts are returned
in managed languages on a RM devices,
we see two to three times better
performance per what, which is critical
for power constrained environments.
And it's also consistently
having an interference.
Jitter of sub millisecond, right?
This means our performance is predictable
and reliable, which is exactly what
you need in real time applications.
So yeah.
Now that we've seen the patterns and
what's the best language to use, let's
see, some implementation challenges.
Okay, now the first major challenge is
managing state across a distributed system
with unreliable network connections.
How do you ensure that the
data on the Edge device and the
data in the cloud stay in sync?
The best solution would be
a hybrid consistency model.
Because we shouldn't use like a
one size fits all approach, right?
For critical data like
financial transactions.
We can enforce high immediate consistency,
but for a less critical analytics
data, we can relax the constraints
and use eventual consistency and to
resolve conflicts when they do occur.
We use, special data structures called
CDTs that can automatically and gracefully
merge different versions of the data.
Let's go to the next slide.
Okay.
So the next big challenge is security
edge devices often operate in a
physically insecure environment, we have
to assume that they are v vulnerable.
It's better if the architecture
is built on a zero trust model.
So which means every single request
is authenticated and authorized
regardless of where it comes from.
The rusts compile time security
needs to be leveraged to eliminate
entire classes of vulnerabilities
before they ever reach production.
Then.
Fine grained capability based
security model needs to be used to
ensure devices only have permission
to do exactly what they need to do.
Finally we need to implement like a app
machine learning based threat detection.
Let's go to the next slide.
And now our final challenge is squeezing
out every last drop of performance.
And we can do this in three ways.
Like first we need to use advanced
caching which might include the
predictive prefetching that anticipates
like what data will be needed next.
So this alone would reduce
the cloud query significantly.
Second, we need to use selective
data compression, right?
So by using content aware algorithms
instead of generic compression,
we can cut our bandwidth usage
with minimal CPU overhead, right?
And finally, for performance
critical hotspots, we need to write
workload specific optimizations.
Using low level SIMD instructions,
which can in some cases increase
the data processing throughput
by more than three times.
Okay,
let's go to the next slide now.
How can we get started on this?
This can be divided into let's
say four practical guidelines.
First, we need to start
with the business metric.
We shouldn't lead with
the technology first.
We need to identify the business KPI,
that we want to improve and work backward
to design the right architecture.
Second, we need to design
for degraded operation.
We always need to assume
that our network will fail.
Then we need to build our edge
applications to function autonomously
and then recover gracefully.
And the next implementation guideline
is we need to measure everything.
We we cannot optimize what
we cannot measure, right?
We need to implement comprehensive
telemetry from day one to
understand our system's behavior.
Okay?
And the fourth guideline would be
we need to use containerization.
Okay?
So deploying our edge
workloads in containers.
We'll give you consistency,
reproducibility, and make your update
process much safer and reliable.
So the rust code snippet that you
can see here shows a few of these
principle in action using parallel
processing and efficient buffer
handling to process the sensor data.
Okay.
Yeah.
So let's go to the next
slide, the final one.
Okay.
As we wrap up, I want to leave
you with three main takeaways
from our discussion today.
First, these transformative patterns will
give you a blueprint a proven blueprint
actually for designing responsive and
intelligent architectures that processes
data in the most optimal location.
Second the first provides the
ideal foundation for these systems,
offering the safety, concurrency, and
performance needed for mission critical.
Edge deployments.
And finally this all leads
to real business impact.
By thoughtfully combining the
immediacy of edge computing.
With the power of the cloud
we can create systems that
deliver truly measurable value.
The goal here is to build intelligent,
resilient systems that bridge
the physical and digital worlds.
Okay.
That wraps up our presentation.
Thank you all so much for your time
and thank you for giving me this
opportunity to speak at this conference.
Have a nice day.
Bye-bye.