Hello, welcome.
To Ang 2025 and thank you
for watching my presentation.
My name ista sat.
I'm a director of Solution Design and
Architecture at a TP, and I'm happy to
present today's topic on how Ang has been,
can potentially, revolutionize employee
experience across our organizations.
HR technology, as is one of the very
few enterprise systems that touches
every single person in an organization.
From the day a person is recruited
till their very last paycheck,
the stakes are very high.
A payroll delay can you know, trust.
A data breach can cost humongous
lawsuits and a slow benefits portal can
potentially damage employee experience.
Today we'll explore how RAs a very
modern systems programming language
is emerging as a serious contender to
power these mission critical platforms.
Rust brings in performance, safety,
and concurrency in ways traditional
HR tech stacks cannot often match.
And we'll see how this translates
directly into better reliability,
lower cost, and a more seamless
experience for both employees, HR
teams, and organizations as a whole.
Let's take a brief look
at our today's agenda.
Here's where we are headed.
We'll start with the evolution of HR
technology, where we've come from and
what that means to today's systems.
We will take a look at modern HR
i's requirements and why they have
outgrown our older architectures.
We'll explore how rusts technical
advantages and how they can
potentially apply to HR systems.
We'll break down a reference
architecture and see some sort.
Real world examples that
you could relate to.
And we'd also examine security
performance and integration
capabilities from a rust point of view.
And finally, a sort of a look ahead
into emerging trends and where
Rust fits in the future of HR tech.
Let's set the stage.
HR technology, if, as has
gone through three big eras.
They started off with a
manual era where, you know.
People data were stored in personal
files, paper forms, physical timecards.
Efficiency was extremely low,
and errors are extremely high.
Even today, there are organizations
who have manual paper forms for
their onboarding or for their,
personal action forms, et cetera.
And then keep the legacy digital era.
This is where the, HRIS platforms or
as an enterprise architecture in the
eighties and the nineties, digitized
records, but they ran on old architecture
such as stronger architecture,
such as mainframes or proprietary
systems like on-premise systems.
For example, many Fortune find
companies still have core payroll
systems that are written with cobol.
They're extremely reliable, no
doubt about it, but they're also
inflexible and very costly to update.
And then now we are currently
in the modern cloud era where we
have platforms like Workday, SAP,
SuccessFactors, we have Oracle
Cloud Head cm that deliver web-based
self-service analytics and integrations.
Now, what's the problem really
then even these modern platforms,
they often run into scalability
and performance bottlenecks.
And I've seen, open enrollment
windows where a system took.
Three minutes to load a single benefits
page or a single promotion for an
employee takes, seven minutes to run
simply because there are thousands
of employees in the database and they
were all trying to log in at once.
And this is the opportunity where
Russ gives us a way to build system to
avoid these choke points completely.
Modern H-R-I-S-A, truly modern HRIS
has to meet demands in forefronts.
One is multiple stakeholders.
Employees today expect very
intuitive mobile self-service
for personal data benefits leave.
They wanna do everything
at the click of a finger.
Managers want to do their actions as
performance, moving employee scheduling
for them, approving things, et cetera.
And then HR admins require
compliance ready tools and they wanna
report run reports instinctively.
There are also technical demands.
System must process huge volumes
of sensitive data, payroll,
drawn tax reports, performance
review without exposing it.
Integrations has to be strongly built
with finance learning identity systems.
There are so many that are non-negotiable
with technical integrations.
Think about scalability for a second.
What works.
A tech stack for a 500 employee
must also scale to 50,000 without
really rewriting the system.
Imagine a company like Deloitte,
scaling, onboarding for 200,
I hires for a month to 2000.
Hire in, because of a growth push.
Think about what a system needs to do.
And finally, data integrity.
A single payroll error can
mean regulatory fines, employee
attrition, and serious consequences.
Legacy languages sometimes let subtle
bugs slip through that rust compiler
would catch before deployment.
This complexity demands a tech stack
that can balance safety, speed,
and adaptability, which is where
rust fits in very beautifully.
Let's look at, talking about
all these requirements, let's.
Talk about what are rusts technical
advantages and how it brings its
strengths to HRIS development.
The first and foremost that I'd
like to talk about is memory safety.
Entire classes of bugs, like buffer
overflows, dangling pointers simply
cannot happen in a rust language
for an HR system holding things
like social security numbers, bank
details, sensitive, PII, that is huge.
Fearless concurrency.
Payroll runs, benefits
processing, performance analytics
all can execute in parallel.
Think about it, your payrolls are running
almost every other week, and at the same
time, if you're running a huge performance
cycle or your annual performance cycle
and running analytics out of it, all
of this needs to concurrently run.
And in an imagine in an organization
that's about 50,000 as associates,
the concurrency of processes
running together is very critical
for high volume deadlines.
Performance, zero cost abstractions
mean we can write expressive
code without slowing it down.
That's how you can run a global
payroll calculation across a hundred
thousand organization, employee
organization in a, in very few minutes.
Explicit error handling rust sort
of forces developers to consider
what happens when something fails.
For example, if a tax rate file is missing
or a benefit vendor, API is down, right?
It forces you to write the
error, logic, strong type system.
HR data is very complex, right?
Think about a very simple data
point, such just a job grade.
That's not a number.
It's a structure that's tied to bands.
That's tied to locations, and there are
rules that are running behind the scenes.
Rust enforces these rules
in the type system itself.
All of this in combination directly
addresses sort of core pain points
that you know I've seen or the
industry has seen in the HRIS domain.
Downtime, data errors, slow
processing, all of these are very
common pain points for clients today.
Let's take a look at RU'S
architecture and how the
implementation is going to be really.
Happening.
A rust powered HRIS can be
designed in many ways, right?
It can be in modular layers, right?
It rust can potentially
sit at a data layer.
It can work with SQL or
no SQL with compiled time.
Query checks, meaning no runtime surprises
when you're fetching payroll records.
Think about that.
API development, right?
Frameworks like act.
I think ActX web handle
thousands of concurring
requests with minimal resources.
This is so perfect for, ESS
portals, employee sensors, portals.
Thirdly, authentic authentication,
a very strong cryptography
and role-based access control.
Ensuring an HR admin can.
Can't see an executive salaries data
unless explicitly granted authentication
plays a very critical point from an HCM
domain because it really controls who
can see whom within your organization
and what can they potentially do.
HRI systems these days are looking to
get very granular with this, and Rust
can very strongly support this with its,
with its role-based access controls.
And finally background processing.
Async and awaits allow payroll
calculation, batches or compliance
report to run in the background
without really freezing the interface.
For example, think about a 40,000
member organization which has, which
is running payroll across countries,
right when we run tax calculations
for, in the background for each
jurisdiction concurrently, and then
merge the results, delivering those
final payroll reports and registers.
Would be a matter of few
minutes instead of a few hours.
So this modular architecture aligns very
well with microservices approach and gives
different aspects of HR functionality
to be developed, deployed, and scaled
Rest supports the entire can.
Potentially support the entire employee
journey if we are to think about it.
Recruitment, onboarding, right from
the time an apply applicant, is.
Is getting into the
system through their ATSs.
It can handle high volume searches,
it and state machine workflows.
It can ensure a candidate can't
be marked as hired without
a complete background check.
It can support potentially from a
performance management as an example.
It can do code tracking, it
can do feedback loops that can
update instantly even during high
traffic performance life cycles.
Benefits in payroll is one of the
very hot topics, like we've seen
so many examples so far that we
talked about real time calculations.
For, say benefit deductions or 4 0
1 case, et cetera, or stock options,
et cetera, without running errors.
And when you look at it from an
offboarding perspective, where you are
securely retaining the data and the
deletion rules to ensure compliance and
rest, like we said, has very strict access
controls and it can prevent ex-employee
data from being accessed later.
Think about an org organization
onboarding 500 seasonal staff in a week.
Say like a retail outlet, like
a Macy's, which does seasonal
hiring during Christmas.
Rest ensures no data conflicts,
no stale records, and no missed
payrolls for these seasonal hiring.
Talking so much about it, I think
it's very important to talk about
security and compliance in hr.
Security is non-negotiable, right rest.
This is where Rust provides
a memory safety guarantee.
Many security beaches are
cost by memory related bugs.
Rust makes those impossible
by design, right?
Role-based access control, like we
talked about, it's modeled in the
code, not just in config files.
It's there at the code level.
It ensures payroll processors
can see medical records, like
they don't have to, like managers
cannot see PII of their associates.
They shouldn't be.
It also allows for tamper
proof audit, logging.
Every access to sensitive data is logged
without degrading the performance.
It is very critical as you go
global for GDPR and HIPA compliance.
And finally, privacy by design.
RU'S ownership model makes it easier
to implement strict data lifecycle
controls like auto deletion, after
retention periods, purging, et cetera.
Like how we talked about security.
The other side of HRIS is what
is very important is performance.
In performance terms rust
can potentially deliver sub
millisecond API responses or even.
Even under heavy load it can handle
thousands of concurrent benefit
elections without crashing and
can use up to 50% less memory
than garbage collected languages,
allowing more services per server.
I also researched that one rust based
payroll system in financial services at
currently reduced the processing time
from six hours to under 45 minutes.
I think that is tremendous enabling
some of the day-to-day payroll
corrections, something impossible
with the old code cobalt set up.
We talked about security performance.
I think the next big piece for HRI
is technology to be a huge success
is integration APIs and how well your
platform can potentially connect.
And this is where Rust
plays a big piece, right?
There are high performance rest APIs
for connections to finance, learning,
recruitment and identity systems.
There is real time data streaming
for live dashboards showing
hiring progress compliant tasks.
Dashboards are.
Are a huge importance in the HCM, I
would say from executive presence.
And Rust easily offers this
message queuing to hold spikes.
For example, processing
thousands of time of request.
After a policy change announcement.
A large healthcare provider used,
actually used rust microservices to sync.
Employee scheduling data between HRS
and their patient care in real time,
and they eliminate manually eliminating
manual errors in shift assignment.
So all of these prove, gave me
the confidence that trust is
winning in every angle that you
look at from a HCM presence.
So I dug a little bit, and this is where
real world case studies where I picked
three organizations that have, how they
have utilized, rust as a programming
language there was a tech company
that completely replaced Java based
onboarding app that crashed during high
volume, graduating hiring with rust and
now to date handles thousands of new
hires per quarter with zero downtime.
Also studied about a financial
services company that migrated from
cobalt to rust, and it cut processing
times by 85% and it also enabled
mid-cycle payroll runs by the way.
And lastly, I, there was an interesting
case study about a healthcare that
built a rust based healthcare records
platform that integrated with HR data.
It met HIPAA compliance
without sacrificing speed.
The common thread that you, that I saw
in all of this was three big things.
There was reliability, there was speed,
and there was reduced maintenance cost.
So with all of this in mind some of the
best practices that I can potentially
conclude is, to succeed with rust
in the HCM space or in the HRIS
world, you should use domain-driven
design to model HR processes to code.
Of course and applying consistent
error handling so that pay
payroll failures, surface early.
Also making sure we are building
comprehensive tests end to end for
compliance and data incre integrity
across whatever solution we are
building into and minimizing unsafe
code and auditing third party libraries.
And also making sure that we're
documenting core HR logic so
that future development teams
can onboard very quickly.
Finally just to sum it up.
There is a future of HR tech with
definitely with rust and emerging
tech will reshape HRI with tech in
terms of building AI for attrition,
prediction talent matching rust
integrates with so many ML libraries.
You could potentially use.
Will reshape blockchain for
credential verifications.
You can run real time analytics for
engagement and productivity insights.
You can also have privacy preserving
computation for secure compliant data
analytics analysis in the HR world, and
also edge computing to serve, global
workforces with really greedy low latency.
Just as a conclusion while I wrap
up, all of this, rust isn't just a
new language, it's a platform choice
that can fundamentally improve HRIS
performance, reliability, and security.
It's already proving itself in small ways
in a real world systems that can handle
some of the sensitive high volume data.
But for HR tech leaders, I think this is
a chance to future proof their system with
whatever applications they are in today.
I think adding that layer.
Of whatever we saw, whether it's in
APIs or whether it's in, reporting
or whether it's in analytics.
Rust is giving them an option to deliver
the kind of speed, safety, and scalability
that the modern workforce really demand.
So I hope you enjoyed all my
insights with a good context with
hr and HCM technology and how Rust
brings a lot of advantages to this.
Thank you so much.
Have a good day.