Hi everyone.
I'm Prashan Koju, a network engineer
with our of experience in designing,
deploying, and securing large
scale network infrastructures.
I've worked on everything from
Enterprise Land one setups to data
center networking, wireless optimization.
As d integration, network automation and
zero zero trust, security architectures.
So my main focus is on building
reliable, scalable, and security
systems for telecom, industrial
control and education networks.
So today I'm thrilled to be here at Comm
42 and a huge thanks to Mark and his
team for this opportunity to connect
with such an amazing global community.
Okay, today we are diving into
why rust programming language is
transforming network infrastructure.
We'll explore how Rust delivers
unmatched speed, safety, and
reliability for critical systems.
Let's get started.
So here's our roadmap for today.
We'll see like in Introduction to
Rust for networks, like why Rust is a
game changer for network engineering.
And then we'll go through some rust
based network architectures, how
it's built, layered, and tested
with all the durable components.
And then we'll go through
at the SST n integration and
optimization techniques using rust.
And then we will see how AI
driven monitoring and tools are.
Aligned and synchronized using rust.
And then we'll go through some zero
trust security implementations.
And last, we'll go through some
case studies and a few takeaways
and key things regarding rust.
So why rust for network infrastructure?
Rust is revolution revolutionizing
how we build networks.
The thing is his why, number one is
memory, safety and and also the fast
performance and then coming to the
cones, concurrency, safety, and also the
compiled time, which guarantees rust is
the best in the current networking world.
So coming to the memory safety.
Rust ownership model and borrow checker.
Eliminate bugs like dangling pointers,
use after free errors and data races.
This ensures predictable behavior,
even under intense multi-threaded
workloads and also rust zero cost.
Abstractions delivers CC plus
level speed ideal for latency, and
still tasks like packet processing
where every microsecond counts.
And then coming to the concurrency
safety rust do handle tens of thousands
of simultaneous connections without
risking undefined behavior which
is like perfect for load balancers,
proxies, and SDN controllers.
And then we'll see the compiled
time, how rust is different from
other programming languages.
So it's a strong static
type ecosystem that catches.
Protocol and configuration
arrest before the hit production.
Reducing the runtime failures,
so Russ Ecosystem with tools like
Tokyo Hyper Tonic and makes it
practical to build high throughput.
Basically, production grade network
services and also adoption of using rust
has been searched in the last three, four
years in telecom, in data center sectors,
and also some industrial control over.
The past few years, which is, and rust
is also good for maturing support for
SGN Telemetry and Zero Trust frameworks.
Some might ask why not stick with CC plus?
Rust matches the same speed, but
it adds more safety built features.
And also it's critical in infrastructure
where downtime isn't an option.
So what is the Russ Base Network
architecture and you know how it works.
Russ, let us build in modular
type safe network architectures
that are robust and scalable.
Let's say like type safe configurations.
We use compiled time validated
templates to prevent misconfigurations
before they even reach the network.
So in layer two or layer three switching.
We use a deterministic approach.
And then the resource allocation ensures
low latency performance under heavy loads.
And then we coming to the wireless
optimization, rust powers, mu algorithms
for realtime channel allocation, and
also it maximizes the throughput.
And the last, but not least, it's
the latest as the Cisco cloud-based
platforms like Cisco Meraki, our.
Cisco, FMC you can use in
monitoring tools as well.
So US asing capabilities via Tokyo
deliver real time visibility and gives a
better control across the infrastructure.
And some might ask, what
is the measurable impact?
We have recently deployed in a large
scale modernization project for NYC
public schools, where we have seen
rust based provisioning scripts for
40% faster than the traditional setups.
And it made a significant
boost in deploying efficiency.
Coming to the next one, which is the
SDN Integration and Hybrid Cloud,
like how rust is aligned with this.
So rust science in software defined
networking and hybrid cloud environments.
So the dynamic provisioning, Russ Tokyo.
As sync runtime enables non-blocking
and eliminates any bottlenecks during
the resource allocation and reclamation
and coming to the traffic optimization
it is the best for precise timing
controls, ensuring the QS policies,
like the quality of service, prioritize
latencies sensitive applications like
video streaming are critical networks
like Scda or BMS or Delta V Networks.
And also the seamless security,
which is the top tire in Russ.
It's basically, zero cost abstractions,
power VLANs, and 8 0 2 0.1 x
authentication, balancing robust
production and high performance.
The 8 0 1 x authentication we can
definitely use in Cisco ice, or
we can align with Cisco as well.
So rust script.
Do support with Cisco ICE
and also Cisco umbrella.
So by integrating everything with
the SDN controllers, like owners, our
OpenDaylight trust do enable automated
provisioning, intelligent traffic
engineering, and rapid reconfiguration.
And then the coming to the next
step, which is the AI driven
and monitoring and analytics.
So we'll go through like how rust.
Works in AI monitoring and tools.
So rust machine learning
ecosystems, power powers, real time
analytics with minimal latency.
And the anomaly detection is very
fast and accurate within the systems.
That catches the issues
before they escalate.
So rather than rather than, an
issue triggering after a day or,
a certain amount of time, RAs well
simply, it triggers the alert.
And then you know, you will
get instant alert and then you
know you can be on top of it.
And then also the automated audits,
rust compares live configurations
against baselines streaming telemetry
via SNMV three and NetFlow, and
also the predictor analysis.
Forecasting minimizes false positives
and supports smarter city planning,
and also smarter capacity planning.
So rust ability.
To process high volume data streams
in real time, turns insights into
immediate action, which is a great
beneficiary to all the networking people.
So the next one is the zero
trust security, like how
RAs is changing changing it.
So as everybody knows that
how, what is zero trust?
Zero trust is basically never trust,
always verify, so rust makes it
practical, we use the microsegmentation.
We are a flight and trust sec
backed by rust type system, which
ensures configuration integrity.
And then we do use the identity based
access, which is the A oh 2.1 X and
certificate authentication, coded in
memory safe rust, and eliminate common
attack vectors, where this is one of the
key sections, like identity based access.
We can definitely use a Cisco.
Identity services engine, or we can
use Cisco umbrella where the external
networks or the external vendor is
trying to get into your network.
That's where Cisco umbrella
comes into picture.
And the Cisco is where, it's the
endpoint security for your organization.
Like it can be your phone, it
can be your laptop, it can be any
Linux workstation or any operating.
Device within your organization.
And the next thing is the encryption.
So the, we use the TLS and IP
six tunnels which uses formally
verified rust cryptography
libraries for proven security.
And on top of that, we have the continuous
monitoring capacity where lightweight
threading enables constant trust
evaluation without the performance hits.
So tools like Zscaler, integrate
seamlessly with rust based components.
Ensuring robust and high speed security.
So now we'll go through some
case studies the case studies
from the educational system.
So we have deployed recently in a
couple of borough in New York City
around 75 locations where we have
successfully post to 50,000 endpoints.
This is a one to one initiative
program for classroom connectivity.
And we have segmented all the
VLANs, for admin, student, iot and
all the other critical devices.
And these were isolated through
security policies by using Russ.
And the results we see
are like 99% of time.
And we have seen a 47% reduction
in security instance, the
provisioning, which is a key factor.
78% provisioning time,
which is like really good.
And then, even the bandwidth
utilization, we have improved a
lot, which is like much better.
Than our previous legacy infrastructure.
So Russ delivered the reliability and
efficiency at its scale as we expected.
And then the next one is, in a
different industrial facility.
This is a biotech firm, where we have
built cyber resilient networks are
the enterprise cyber resiliency, ECR.
So we have used the
VRS based segmentation.
And redundant pathways determining
the performance and also the backups.
For this, we have seen the results
are are similar as expected.
We have zero successful cyber intrusions,
and then we have the 99% up time.
And the maximum latency we have
seen is somewhere from 12 to 15
seconds for critical controls
which is like really good.
So here in this case, rust
did ensure mission critical
reliability and security as well.
And then you might be some might be
asking, what are the implementation
challenges, that we have seen
without hurdles, like basically
adopting rust isn't without hurdles.
So the legacy integration, older systems
often lack modern APIs as everybody knows.
So Russ.
Capabilities, safely wrap, legacy
code, extending its lifespan and
also the resource constraints.
Incremental rollouts prioritize
high impact security components for.
So you need to make sure, you
have to determine the approach.
When you modernize your network
infrastructure, you have to make sure
you have a clear picture of all the
end of life devices, try to evaluate
and then, slowly deploy using rust.
You can definitely see the results.
And also the evolving threats in
the current infrastructure trend.
The modular architectures allow targeted
batches and updates without down downtime.
So rust flexibility definitely helps
you over time and also overcome
these challenges effectively.
And here we see the performance metrics.
We can see the rust based implementations,
have been outperformed by traditional
architectures, here you can see
a lower resource usage, reduced
memory, and CP load, CPO load.
Here we can see a faster
processing, a decreased requesting
latency and higher throughput.
And also you can see the cost savings.
A leaner foot footprint
supports a seamless scalability.
These gains obviously translate
into a tangible operational
and financial benefits for your
organization down the line as well.
Okay.
And then here, what are the key takeaways?
And the important things about
what we have learned in rust
programming infrastructure is rust
is definitely a game changer for
network infrastructure because of its
safety and performance, because the
unmatched memory and concurrency safety
with C level speed that's that sound
undoubtedly better and good results.
And also the types of configurations,
which can prevent arrests before
deployment rather than during the
deployment and causing a huge outage.
Ru can definitely evaluate everything,
in a sandbox environment and do give
you an upper hand in the visibility.
And also coming to the zero trust we
have seen, it's practical high speed
security and it's proven and also coming
to the air driven operations, it's
proactive monitoring and analytics.
Have given you an upper
hand on this as well.
So the next steps obviously will
be, how you access have you access
your current infrastructure, and
also identify the critical and high
impact components for rust adoption
plan in a phase migration strategy
rather than jumping jumping in the in,
in the fly and, causing any issues.
And also start with monitoring for
immediate visibility gains like, try
to have monitoring tools, let's say
for any bugs or, any power alerts
or, any high throughput or, any
CRCR bandwidth errors within the
uplinks or, within your optimization.
To wrap up, you know what I can sell,
what I can say is Russ do empower
us to build network infrastructures
that are fast and, that are fast and
securable and also maintainable from
education to industrial systems.
We have seen measurable results.
Like higher up time, faster
provisioning and stronger security.
So I would like to connect further
to discuss more on Rust Power Network
networking share my insights and also
tackle any real world challenges.
So thank you for your time and attention.