Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42, rust Plan 2025.
My name is Vin Kana and I'm thrilled to be
here to talk about something I have been
personally passionate about combining the
power of Rust with AWS Cloud services.
Over the next several minutes, we will
explore how rust performance, safety,
efficiency, make it a great choice
for building cloud native applications
that scaled reliably instead of just
theory, we'll walk through our flowing.
Example system step by step.
So you live with a clear mental model
of how this can apply to a real world.
Workloads
when you build on AWS scale is
always central applications may
need to handle millions of events,
thousands of concurrent requests
and unpredictable workloads at that
level, every milliseconds of latency
and every MB of memory counts.
Rust combines predictable performance
similar to c RC plus with compiled and
guarantees that eliminates common runtime
issues for Lambda functions or ECS tasks.
Small binaries reduce cold start star
types and lean memory uses cut cuts costs.
This blend of performance and safety
makes rust an excellent choice when you
care about efficiency and reliability.
Let's compare rust agonist
to other popular languages.
In AWS Go is a strong for Lambda and
containers, thanks to go routines, but
it, its runtime is bigger than rust.
Java has massive ecosystem, but coal
starts and memory overheads are costly.
No JS offers fast development, but
struggles with CPU bound workloads.
Python is unbeatable for
prototyping and ML libraries.
Though it slows down at scale, c
plus delivers raw power, but manual
memory makes it error prone rust
balances performance near c plus with
safety and compiled and guarantees
that combine that combination makes
rust stand out for cloud workloads.
Where does rust shame for Lambda?
Small binaries equal for or
equal faster cold starts.
The borrow checker enforces memory safety,
preventing bugs before develop deployment.
With Tokyo, you can run thousands
of async calls to AWS services
without overwhelming threats.
That reduces CPU and memory lowering
costs In loan Lambda, ECS and EKS, strong
typing issues, requests are valid at
compiled, preventing misconfigurations
from ever reaching production.
But rust isn't perfect.
Compiled times can be long.
In large projects, ownership and
lifetimes have a steep learning curve.
The ecosystem is maturing, but Java and
Python have more polished libraries.
Tooling for Lambda is improving,
but Python and Node still offer more
templates and rust favors explicitness
over dynamic meta programming.
Which is safer but less
flexible for quick experiments.
Being aware of these trade offs
makes adoption decision realistic.
The A-W-S-S-D-K for Rust
provides strong support.
Each service is its own create,
so you input only what you need.
Shared configuration handles, credentials
and regions securely built on Tokyo.
It's first making it.
Efficient for input output.
With retries, ation and streaming
built in, developers can focus on
value rather than boiler plate.
To make this concrete, let's
build a file ingestion pipeline.
A user uploads to S3 and even flows
through event bridge into SQS.
Rust worker workers process,
it DynamoDB storage results
and observability keeps watch.
This example matters.
Real world patterns and highlights.
Russ value at each step.
Step one, upload files.
With Russ STK, you gain compiled time.
Assurance that requests are valid,
I think lets you upload many files
concurrently without blocking.
This builds confidence that what you
send to AWS S3 is correct and efficient.
Next triggering process.
C, even Bridge sends S3 events into SQS.
Trust workers consume messages safely
DC realizing them with third, A sync
workers scale out efficiently, letting
you process hundreds of events in
parallel without adding threats.
This is where Rust, A sync runtime shines.
For compute, we'd apply to Lambda Rust.
Binaries are small,
giving faster cold stocks.
Execution is predictable and efficient.
With As think a single function can manage
multiple tasks compared to Java or T
net Runtimes, rust Lambda are lighter,
cheaper, and faster After processing,
we persist results in Dynamo DB Rust.
Builders enforce correctness at
compiler as think queries let you
scale to thousands of operations.
The system stays responsive.
Even under heavy load
observability is essential.
With the tracing crate, you add
structured spans into a sync workflows
pair with open telemetry and metrics
stream into CloudWatch for errors.
Anyhow, are the errors capture
detailed context together, this makes
debugging faster and operations.
No, AWS system is complete Without
security and deployment use IAM
with the least privileged role.
And KMS to encrypt sensitive data for
Lambda Cross compiled to muzzle for
small static binaries in containers.
Multi-stage builds, strip unnecessary
dependencies, shrinking image
size, and improving security.
To recap, rust compile time.
Safety prevents runtime bug,
I think first makes it perfect
for input output workload.
The modular SDK is easy to adapt and
end-to-end patterns map naturally
compared to other languages.
Rust blend of performance
and safety is unique.
In closing, rust is ready for cloud.
It combines system level performance with
strong safety guarantees, makes making
it ideal for AWS workloads at scale.
The SDK provides the tools and our
example showed rust across AWS landscape.
If you're building next generation
cloud native apps, rust is not just
experimental, it's production ready.
Thank you and I hope this inspires
you to try Rust in your AWS projects.
I.