Hi everyone, and thank you
for joining this session.
I'm work as senior data engineer.
Seven years of experience specialize
in building high performance scalable
data solutions that connect innovation.
With the three year world impact, my
focus is on our systems that can handle
massive data volumes without compromising
speed, reliability, or flexibility.
I'm passionate about exploring
emerging technologies that push
the limits of what's possible
in modern data infrastructure.
That's exactly what brings us
here today to explore how rust
pair with data mesh principles can
completely reshape the way we think
about large scale production grade.
Datas in this session we'll talk about
how Rust can transform modern datas
by applying data mesh principles.
We'll explore why enterprises need to move
away from monolithic systems, how rusts
memory, safety, and fearless concurrency
enabled high performance, reliable
pipelines, and real world implementations.
We'll also look at benchmarks, advanced
risk patterns, strategies for integrating
with cloud infrastructure to build
scalable future ready data platforms.
Let's get started.
We are all aware of how
rapidly data is growing.
It's exponential.
The problem is that monolithic
architectures can't keep up
anymore and we end up with
bottleneck, any inefficiencies.
That's why moving to distributor
system isn't just an option.
It's essential.
Distributor systems give us the
scalability and flexibility we need
to manage these massive data demands.
This is where data mesh comes
in a decentralized approach.
That puts data ownership in the
hands of domain experts, improving
collaboration, reducing dependencies,
and scaling more effectively.
So first, memory safety.
RUS ownership model means no
data races, and let us write the
robust concurrent processing code
without sacrificing comments.
Then there are zero cost fractions,
which let us write expressive high
level code without any runtime penalty.
Finally, fearless concurrency trust makes
parallel processing safe and reliable.
Which is absolutely critical for
high throughput data pipelines.
When we talk about performance,
rust truly stands out.
One of the biggest gains I've
seen is in data processing speed.
Using rust as synchronous runtime,
we can achieve a through 10
times faster class sync compared
to many traditional solutions.
That's not just a small optimization.
That's a difference between a job
finishing in hours versus minutes.
Another huge advantage is building
memory Safe pipelines because
of Rust Strong type system.
A lot of the bugs that would
normally show up at runtime, things
like null point or errors or data
mismatches simply can't happen.
This means we production incidents.
And much more reliable systems.
And then there is stream processing.
If you have worked with JVM based
solutions before, you will know
they can be powerful, but also
heavy in realtime analytics.
Rest outperforms them.
Delivery low latency
and higher throughput.
That means we can process streams
of events faster, react to changes
more quickly and do it all without
consuming excessive resources.
In short, rest gives us speed,
reliability, and efficiency all at one.
And those are the three pillars
you need for any modern high
performance data pipeline.
Let's move from theory into practice
when we are actually building high
performance data systems in rust,
there are few tools and techniques
that really make a difference.
First, a synchronous crossing with Tokyo.
Tokyo is a high performance Synchron
runtime that lets us handle massive
amounts of concurrent work without
blocking threats unnecessarily.
In a data pipeline, this means we can
process incoming requests, transform
data and push results downstream, all
in parallel without choking the system.
Next, zero copy serialization with
survey in many systems, serialization
and D, serialization of bottlenecks
because you are constantly copying
data in and out of memory structures.
With ser, you can add those extra copies,
which not only improves the performance,
but also reduces memory treasure.
This is especially powerful
when you're transforming and
transmitting huge data sets.
And finally, column of data
operations with Apache Arrow.
Arrow.
It's a store and process
data in a column of fiber.
Which is far more
efficient from analytical.
In my experience, combining
rust with Arrow means we can
run high speed analytics on
large data sets that otherwise.
More traditional row
based tourist systems.
When you put all of this together as
in processing zero copy serialization
and columnal data operations, you
get a data pipeline that is extremely
fast and resource efficient.
This is where rust really starts
to shine in real world scenarios.
So now let's talk about building.
Infrastructure.
Infrastructure that supports these high
performance pipelines for me starts with
the high throughput Kafka consumers.
I use the Kafka RS Library,
which is a re around the battle
tested Kafka SEA Library.
It gives us reliable, low latency
consumption, xk, which is perfect
for ingesting millions of.
Even per second without dropping messages.
Then I focus on memory efficient
transformations, rust, iterators, and zero
allocation patterns are game changers.
Here, instead of creating temporary
objects that collect of memory and
put further on the garbage collector,
which rust doesn't even need downstream
transformations directly keeping memory
usage minimal and performance high.
Finally, I think about robust
HTTP APIs when we need to expose
data or services to other systems.
I like using frameworks like
Axiom along with top middleware.
This combination let me build APIs
that are fast, secure, and easy to
integrate into wider data ecosystem.
Plus, since these APIs are written
in rest, they inherit the same
performance and safety guarantees
as the rest of the pipeline.
All of these pieces, Kafka, consumers
efficient transformation and strong APAs
work together to create an infrastructure
that isn't just fast, but also resilient.
It's scalable for long
term growth performance.
Me.
So whenever I talk about rust in data
systems, one of the first questions I
get is, how does it actually perform
compared to Python, Java, or scaler?
So I make it a point to run real world
benchmarks, not just synthetic tests.
I take actual data workloads, that
kind you would see in production
and compare implementations
across these languages every time.
Rust, consistently shows lower
latency, higher throughput,
and better resource efficiency.
The tools I use for these benchmarks
are well established and reliable.
The measure, not just speed,
but also memory usage, startup
times, and consistency under load.
This isn't about proving that one
language is better in all cases, but
about having accurate performance insight
so I can make informed architectural
righteous, and the impact is huge.
These benchmarks directly
influence system design.
For example, if certain part of a
pipeline is performance critical,
real time event processing our data
transformations on massive data sets.
Rest often becomes the
clear choice by contrast.
For less time sensitive components,
another language might make
sense for speed of development.
Ecosystem support.
In short, benchmarking keeps us honest.
It ensures that we are picking the
right tool for the job, and more
often than not, it highlights where
REST can give us a major advantage
in high performance data processing.
Now we have covered
performance in infrastructure.
I want to share some advanced rust
patterns that I found especially
valuable when building large
scale distributed data system.
First active model implementations.
I like using the active model to isolate
domains within a distributor system.
Each actor has its own state.
It communicates through message passing.
Which not only improves modularity,
but also makes the system
much easier to scale in rust.
This model is both safe and efficient.
Thanks to the languages concurrency
guarantees Second custom derived macros
in big projects, I often need to enforce
certain rules consistently across the
code base, like validating the incoming
data structures with custom device macros.
I can automate that.
It means every developer on the team
gets validation for free without having
to remember to write it manually.
Indeed, it keeps the code
base clean and uniform.
And finally, web assembly for security.
This is where Ru Flexible really shines.
I can compile parts of the rest
application into web assembly modules and
then run them in a sandbox environment.
That's perfect, Phil.
Crossing data across different domains
and even different organization because
the isolation gives me an extra layer of
security without giving up performance.
These advanced patterns, actors, macros,
and web assembly, gives us the ability
to build system that are not just fast,
but also maintainable, secure, and ready
to evolve as requirements change for me.
A high performance data system
isn't complete unless it integrates
seamlessly with the cloud environment.
It's deployed.
Rest makes this easier
than you might think.
Start with seamless cloud integration.
Whether I'm deploying on Azure, a Ws, gcp,
REST applications can hook into existing
cloud services with minimal overhead.
I can connect to managed databases,
storage systems, message queues,
just as easily as I can work with on.
Components.
That means they get the flexibility to run
in hybrid or multi-cloud setups without
rewriting large parts of the system.
Next, look at microservices architecture.
Rust is good for building small focused
services that do one job extremely well.
When each service is independent, I can
scale them individually based on demand
scaling the ingestion layer without
touching the analytics layer, for example.
This is approach also makes maintenance
easier because the teams can work
on different services without
stepping on each other source.
And finally, data contracts.
Enforcement.
This is one of the.
Russ hidden superpowers by defining
strict data structures and when
forcing them at compiled time.
I can guarantee that data exchange between
services always in the correct format.
This eliminates a whole category of
runtime errors and reduces the need
for defensive coding when I combine
this capabilities cloud integration.
Microservices and
compiling data contracts.
I get a cloud ready architecture
that's sufficient, safe, and
designed for the long haul.
As we wrap up, I want to bring the
big picture back into focus for me.
Rust Isal, just another
programming language.
It's a game changer for how we
approach data architectures.
Combining rest with the data mesh
principles, I've seen firsthand how we can
build infrastructures that are both highly
scalable, rock solid, and reliability.
Looking ahead, the rest
ecosystem is evolving fast.
We are seeing improvements
in asynchronized.
New libraries for data
processing and even more seamless
integrations with cloud platforms.
All of these developments means the rest
is only going to get more capable for
handling the toughest data challenges.
My takeaway for you is this, if you are
working on system that need to handle.
Massive data volumes, low
latency and high reliability.
Rust should be on your short list.
Gives you performance with sacrificing
safety, without sacrificing
safety and scalability without
the typical complexity overhead.
And I will leave you
with a call to action.
Explore rest.
Try it on a small, high
impact part of your pipeline.
See how it performs in your environment.
You might be surprised at just
how much of a difference it makes.
This concludes my presentation.
Thank you for your time and attention.
Have a good day.