Hello everyone.
This is Uri and I working in ITO
20 years with cloud architecture,
security and performance engineering.
In my career, I've had opportunity
to help enterprises navigate the
challenges of multi-cloud environments
from avoiding vendor lock.
And ensuring compliance.
And by squeezing last bit of like
performance out of every penny we
spent and every infrastructure we
stood up there, I worked across
AWS Azure GCP, and very extensively
on the, on cloud environments.
So I've seen firsthand how
to manage multiple clouds,
bring enormous flexibility.
Also a fair share of headaches
comes with it, right?
Like performance, bottlenecks,
increased attack surfaces and
operational complexity often comes,
becomes a biggest roadblock for this.
Any kind of innovation, right?
So that's why like today I wanna share how
rust a language built for safety, speed,
and reliability is changing the game.
We look into how organizations are
using RAs to build high performance,
secure tools that run consistently
across heterogeneous environments.
And why the modern enterprise
like multi-cloud in is no
longer an optional thing.
It's a strategy imperative.
So let's talk about why Rust,
actually, why I choose rust or
any other, and why I wanna bring,
more attention to the rust, right?
Rust is like modern programming
languages which is designed for speed,
safety, and reliability, especially in
systems where performance is critical.
It runs nearly as fast as C but
without any memory risks of C.
That's one big thing.
And it is safe actually one of the
very safe product where it prevents
common bug, like memory leaks.
That's one big thing with C
and crashes and, data, right?
It's very reliable.
Encourages clear maintainable code that
works consistently across the environment.
It's popular in industries
where security and performance
matters most, like finance, cloud
computing, and embedded systems.
Companies use multi-cloud providers to
avoid lock-in cut cost, and to ensure
compliance and improve resilience.
But it's not easy, right?
Security risks and management
complexity grow without good tools.
Also, think of it like
managing multiple houses.
So you have a house and you have
a second house, a third house.
First house is fine.
A vacation house is okay, and having a
third, fourth house, then the problem
starts coming into the picture, right?
So similar like with multi-cloud, right?
Once one cloud, easy to manage, piece
of cake or two clouds, maybe it's okay.
Or hybrid architecture.
We are on form cloud.
Maybe it's okay but.
Once you expand beyond two, it's not easy.
And it comes with this
operational challenges.
Technological how people, how much
people need to know about each product.
The ops is like biggest
challenge for enterprise teams.
So y is an wire for a
multicloud excellence, right?
Performance security and develop
developer experience, right?
These are the three main things and
it is very ideal for building tools
like work reli across AWS Azure.
GCP, et cetera.
So it's very fast, very smaller in terms
of footprint and more predictable apps.
And also catches memory box
even before the code even runs.
Great tooling and cross-platform support.
So those are main things I would rust.
So what, why rust multi-cloud
impact areas, right?
What are the rust
multi-cloud impact areas?
So it's
performance container
orchestration excellence.
That's one thing.
Like container starts
faster and use less memory.
And when return the rust, no
delay from garbage collection
like some of the other languages.
Some files quicker deployment
and cheaper storage.
A big bank saw like almost.
I'll say 30% to 40% save in latency.
By choosing critical components
to rust, actually switching
critical components to rust.
And infrastructure as a code revolution.
We all know that it, this revolution
now infrastructure as a code.
So almost like two to three 2, 2, 2
third of companies are like, are trying
rust based tools for cloud setups.
Very few mistakes.
Thanks to restrict checks and
preventive and, other checks performs
and, faster provisioning or three
to four times quicker than the older
way ways of doing the business.
Deployments works like seamlessly across
different providers without any surprises.
Great advantage of being with this tool
resilience multi-cloud and microservices.
So the rust prevents problems in
the system that run across different
clouds at the same time, it forces
you to handle errors, properly
result apps that recover quickly from
failures and keep running smoothly.
That's a big, that's a big thing actually.
And coming to the security the
multi-cloud, the multi-cloud means like
more places to attack rust helps close
the dose, prevents the type of bug that
cause more severe cloud security problems.
It has a stronger protection against bad
dependencies and accidentals secret leaks.
And case studies and, global
financial Institute, as I said global
Financial Institute almost saves like.
Hefty amount of latency issues
are addressed, and it is like
excellent product, right?
It's a great product for healthcare
manufacturing, for data, for healthcare,
like data processing or HIPAA
compliance, or, any other cost saving
mechanisms they want put in place.
Like it's a great tool for them.
And also manufacturing, like
for better quality controls,
smaller updates for devices.
Smooth across cloud operations
and also coming to container
orchestration and excellence.
So container ecosystem from the backbone
of motor on cloud applications, but
traditional runtime phases, performance
limitations like rust advantages.
So it's way 40% faster than a normal,
traditional, bills and no memory overhead
reduces almost 60 to 70% of memory
overhead and it's very predictable.
Latency without GC pauses
during the critical operations.
Smaller binary sizes leading to the
faster deployment and reduction of
storage cost and fine grain resource
control for better multi-tenant isolation.
So this is like some of the
components I'd like to highlight when.
Coming on container orchestration
excellence, and also infrastructure as
a code revolution is we already spoke
about this in the previous slide where
it being almost like two to two, two
third of companies trying wide, trying
rust, and also multi-cloud microservices,
mi like rust prevents problems.
In systems that runs different co
clouds at the same time, forces you
to handle errors properly and results
apps that recover quickly from the
failures and keep running them smoothly.
So ownership model benefits like
prevent data raises in concurrent
operations guarantee, resource
cleanup, even during the failures
and enforce proper error handling.
And throughout the code basis, it may also
distribute system bound boundary release,
explicit and error handling excellences,
like another great tool where results
type forces explicit error handlings and.
Pattern matching for
comprehensive error cases, error
propagation with the operator.
Custom error types for the
domain specific handling.
So let's talk about the security.
This is one big thing with multi-cloud.
We all, we briefly touched it a couple
times already multi-cloud breaches
are like very expensive on an average.
And the single cloud instance due
to increased complexity and large
attack surfaces and memory safety
critical, like 70% of high severe CVS
or cloud infrastructure components
from memory safety issues precisely
what rust prevents by design.
And supply chain protection
like rust ecosystem offer.
Strong dependency verification
and reproduction bills.
Re reducing the supply chain
risk across cloud bond risk, and
also secret management, right?
That's one big thing.
Again rust compliance time guarantees
helps prevent accidental secrets exposure
between cloud environments, and it is a
very common source of breaches, right?
We are aware of that.
So in this case, study of a global
financial institute is a it's one of the
bank that replaced Java services with
rust and which runs faster, cost less.
And it was based way faster and safer.
It got higher up time and
smaller deployment times.
And no serious security issues
for months after launch.
That's one.
And coming to healthcare and
manufacturing they have faster data
processing, HIPAA compliance and cost
savings millions of cost savings.
It's and also coming to the manufacturing
like they have better quality control,
smaller updates for our devices and
smoother cross cloud of operations.
Emerging trends in the rust plus
multicloud rust becoming go-to
language for secure cloud services.
And it's leading in web assembly
apps that run the same on any cloud.
And it's great for edge computing
instant setup and reliable performance.
And let's talk about implementation
roadmap and key tech on this slide.
And it starts small with
non-critical services.
Low hanging fruits start something small
and target pain points like performance
bottlenecks which applications.
Has the highest pain points and, but
still has a very low hanging fruit.
Pick something like that and try to
address those pain points starting there
and build a reusable libraries for all
the clouds so that way it's easy and
faster for our for the deployments.
Measure improvements from
day one what you did.
And as you days progress, keep
measuring the improvements and so
that you can optimize better as even
things progress and scale successful
patterns and rust helps you.
Keep performance, security and reliability
consistent in complex cloud setups.
So yeah.
Scale success is pretty critical actually.
So expense successful patterns
across our nations with reasonable
components like and internal advocacy.
So these are a few things I
would like to bring on to notice.
Thank you very much for this opportunity
and listening to me all this time then.
Thank you.
I appreciate everyone's
effort here and thank you.