Hello everyone.
Welcome.
This is LaMi.
Today.
In this conference, I wanna talk
about building mission critical
emergency response systems.
In rush.
I'm a highly experienced cloud DevOps
lead with our 13 years experience
in IT industry, currently selling at
conent, I'm specialized in cloud native
architectures, con container orchestration
and infrastructure automation.
I have extensive experience in AWS Amazon
Web Services and Azure Cloud platforms,
Kubernetes, Docker, and continuous
indication, continuous delivery,
continuous deployment implementation,
using tools like Jenkins and configuration
management through Ansible and Terraform.
I have master's degree in cover
science from University of
Houston, clear Lake, which combines
strong technical capabilities.
Leadership skills, having LED
cloud migration projects and
jobs in transformations at
T-Mobile, AudioPro and conent.
This experience spans both traditional
middleware administration and modern
cloud native technologies, making
me a cloud technology provisional,
who consistently delivers resilient,
scalable infrastructure solutions,
building mission critical
emergency response systems in rush.
In an emergency, whether it is
a natural disaster or a chemical
spill or mask casualty event,
systems can't effort to fail.
Every millisecond matters.
Today I'll showing how Rust can GA
a game changer for building life
critical applications while performance
and safety are non-negotiable.
Imagine a major earthquake
hits a city within minutes.
Emergency calls, call volumes
spike 800% systems must process
over a hundred thousand messages
a second without missing a beat.
These systems don't get a chance.
Second chance to respond.
The operational environment is extreme.
We aim for 99%.
99.9% uptime even when infrastructure
is collapsing around us.
These are not just
performance requirements.
They are survival requirements.
The critical challenges
of life saving systems,
traditional tech tax fails here.
The average response delay in some
legacy setups is 17 seconds for
long, too long, which is too long.
84% of critical failures trace
back to memory safety issues.
In C or CPS space.
Java brings garbage collection, pauses
with sometimes to 35 seconds delay,
right when you need instant responses.
Problems with which
can't in public safety.
Why rest for emergency response systems?
Rush gives us memory safety
without a runtime cost.
Thanks to ownership and borrowing, we
get zero cost abstractions, fearless
concurrency, and deterministic
cleanup without GC pauses.
In fact, these our Rush implementation
delivered 42% faster response times
and 35% memory usage compared to.
Java Systems rushed illness critical
weaknesses while keeping speed.
Zero cost abstractions,
maintain readability scalability
without content penalties.
The fearless concurrency, which helps
data elevated compiled time, which you
42% concurrency faster response times,
and that if it percent lower memory
usage compared to Java equivalent.
Last ownership model making
invalid states and representable
ownership rules sound
simple, but they're powerful.
One.
One per value, exclusive or share
differences are no inval differences.
This means there are no leaks, no race
conditions, no null differences, even at
a high concurrency in emergency systems.
This means we remove anti classes
of bugs before they even exist.
This leads to emergency systems.
Invalid systems can't happen
even at extreme concurrency.
I want to provide analogy here,
like strict airport security.
Nothing unsafe gets through
the airport security.
To case study based
emergency dispatch system,
real system, real results.
Our dispatch system uses asynchronous a
eight for non rocking Ivo input output.
Tokyo for tasks, scheduling Kafka for
real reliable event streaming and web
assembly for secure edge computing.
We process real-time reports with
machine learning models at 90 93 0.7.
Accuracy and rush guarantees mean zero
catastrophic failures in production.
I wanna discuss in detail about
the architecture of the systems.
The first component is as Synchron I
wait for non-blocking input output.
I want to compare this with
traditional back blocking IO model
in traditional blocking IO model.
A third makes a network or file request.
Then the voice operating systems
OS puts the thread to sleep
until data arrive the third.
Can't do anything else
while it is waiting.
If you have thousands of requests
waiting on input output, Ivo.
You need thousands of threads,
which is memory heavy and
slow due to context switching.
The asynchronous heavy process
approach is totally different.
A function can pause when it's waiting
for IO without blocking the thread.
While the function is waiting, the
thread can run other ready tasks
while the completes the runtime.
The Tokyo resumes the function
exactly where it left off.
I want to provide an analogy here.
Think of a chef in a kitchen.
In blocking Iwo, the chef starts
boiling pasta and stands there
staring at the pot until it is done.
In asynchronous Iwo, the chef starts
boiling pasta, sets a timer and
moves on to a prepad while waiting.
The moment that timer rings,
they return to finish.
The pasta how it works in the and
a synchronous function, returns a
feature, a value representing this work.
This work will complete later.
If this feature is not
done yet, pass here.
Give control back to runtime
and resume me when it's ready.
The Tokyo Runtime pulls these features
and schedules them efficiently.
Coming to Next Component is
a, Tokyo is the most wide user
asynchronous runtime for Rush.
It's combination of task
scheduler, Ivo, even two timer
system asynchronous utilities.
A task scheduler decides
when asynchronous task run.
The I even group reacts to network
file timer events without blocking
the timer system for delays,
timeouts intervals coming to Kafka
for streaming events, which is the
next component to this architecture.
Apache Kafka is a distributed fault,
tolerant and even streaming platform.
It is used to send store
and process streams.
Our data at scale.
It works like durable
message bus, durable message.
Bus producers send events, consumers
read them and Kafka keeps them in
topics or for set retention period.
The core concepts are topic,
a name channel for events.
Partition is split off
topic for scalability.
Events in partition are strictly ordered.
The producer application
then writes events to Kafka.
A P Service publishing user actions,
the consumer that tweets even from
Kafka, the broker Kafka, serves
the stores topic per partitions,
multiple brokers from Kafka's cluster.
Why use Kafka streaming?
After discussing the core concepts like
topic, partition, what is partition,
what is producer, what is consumer?
We discuss about what the main
users of Kafka are streaming.
The high throughput can handle multiple
millions of events it at the same time.
Kafka gives durability.
Events are persistent to disk
and replicate across blockers.
It's scalable as partitions of
parallel process and it's real
time consumers can read data at is
arrives and enabling low pipelines,
and it also provides decoupling.
Producers and consumers don't
need to know about each other.
They just read right or write to topics.
How it works in architecture, producer
services receive events from clients,
then they serialize the data and
publish it to Kafka topics and Kafka.
Brokers store these events durably
and replicate them for fall tolerance.
Consumer services
subscribe to these topics.
Some do enrichment of transformation.
Others update materialized
views in database.
Some might forward even to web assembly
edge modules for policy-based routing.
So consumer fails, another in the
same consumer group takes over.
Continuing from the last complete offset
benefits of this context, it provides
loose coupling a PL layer and analytics
don't depend on each other as uptime.
Process historical events by
replaying from an earlier offset
and it provides scalability.
Add more partitions, consumers
to increase throughput, and it
also provides fault tolerance.
Data is replicated and consumers
can resume after crashes.
Next, coming to next component, we
assembly to secure edge components.
Web assembly is binary instruction
format that can run in its sandbox
environment, built for browsers, but now
used for widely used for out of them.
You can write coding languages like
rust, C, c plus, go and compile.
It is designed to small to be small, fast
and secure ideal for edge deployments.
Why use at the Edge?
Edge means running core and servers that
are geographically close to the end user.
Benefits of running web assembly.
It provides low latency, the which
can be processed locally instead
of traveling to a central server.
It also provides SEC security.
Strong sandbox model web assembly.
Can't access the host o directly.
It only uses a lot of APAs.
Portability.
Some web assembly module can run
on different edge providers without
rewriting, and it also provides fast cold
starts, modules load almost instantly.
And compared to countless of VMs,
ENC coding data domain safety in rush
type system with rust, we can encode
domain rules directly into types.
Patient ID is just not an inte.
Just an integer isn't just an inte.
It's type that can only be
visible Validly constructed.
This vari by construction
approach moves error detection
from unpredictable runtime.
Failure to predictable compar time checks.
This is where the business
rules bake into the compiler.
Coming to zero cost abstractions for
iot sensor integration for environmental
monitoring, to traffic surveillance
to building integrity checks.
Rush trade system uses zero cost
abstractions with we integrate
varied iot hardware without runtime
penalties, which is vital when
processing live data under load.
The real world Examples like environmental
monitoring for hazard hazards,
traffic surveillance for accidents.
Structural integrity monitoring
for buildings result are examples
of the realtime scenarios.
These traits allow hardware diversity
without runtime penalty crucial
in realtime data environments.
The core message of Euro cost abstractions
for iot sensor integration is DI sensor.
Same reliability,
web assembly support for edge computing.
With web assembly, we detect hazards 70
minutes faster than centralized systems
we keep running during network outages.
Product privacy by processing local leak
and cut bandwidth in cus crisis surges.
In disaster edge means survival
benefits continue.
W working offline keeps sense.
Two, data local and
reduces search bandwidth.
The core message of web assembly
for edge computing is resilience.
When central infrastructure fails
coming to performance benchmarks
we compare trust rest versus.
Traditional systems we, in this graph
you can see the response times memory,
UC utilization, and worst case pause.
That is GC pauses, garbage
correction, pauses.
The Benchmark Show Rush delivers
near C plus per near C plus Cs
with but without its memory risks
and it all performance Java while
avoiding garbage collection pauses.
For us, this means no compromise
between speed and safety.
The core message is Rush proves a
performance press safety equation.
A synchronous await for
non-blocking emergency processing.
Here it is a real emergency call flow.
In the rest, we geo geolocate the
caller pull their info query historical
incidents, and all concurrently then a
machine learning model, res resources, and
dispatches triggered rush asynchronous syn
uses concurrency without call back help.
Patterns for fall, fall
tolerant distributed systems.
In rush,
the implementation of circuit breakers
that automatically isolate failing
components prevents ca cascading failures
that might otherwise disable anti-system
while fallback mechanisms ensure that.
Critical operations continue even when
o optimal performance is impossible.
These approaches have prevent
essential for maintaining emergency
surveys functionality during
infrastructure disruptions.
While traditional systems often experience
complete outages when key components fail,
lessons from deploying
rushed in public safety.
In 18 months of operation, we had zero
memory related caches, strong performance,
co, easier compliance, and cost savings
and reduced infrastructure costs.
The challenges are the developer learning
curve, some missing legacy integrations
and longer compar times all solvable
with training and ecosystem growth.
The core message is successes
outweigh the challenges.
The key takeaways, lush ownership
model prevents catastrophic bugs.
It delivers C performance,
safety type driven design,
illness and type error classes,
and web assembly readable.
Edge computing in count.
We can the right response,
right choice for mission.
Thank you.