Hello everyone.
Welcome to conference 42.
My name is AU and I am a lead Guidewire
developer at Marque Technology Solutions.
It's an honor to be here.
Building high performance financials
with, I'm going talk about claims
management scale with high performance.
Financial is great for a, it allows
each developing or generating open
A PA documents and clients as well.
Both inbound and outbound
services actually is not a direct
programming language, but involves
the claims management if it comes
to administration and management.
Rush
Financial.
Handling annual.
So the agenda, so what is, how impacts
on financial services when it comes to
the impact on financial services, the
main financial service for imperative?
So understanding the unique challenges
of building mission critical
financial APIs, and while legacy.
Approaches fall shut.
So when it comes to legacy in-house
projects, there are a lot of complexities
when to fit into the digital world.
So to fulfill this one, so Rashti is
introduced high perform microservices
and APIs so that we can achieve.
Key advantages for financial
applications exploring memory safety.
So here when you're creating
the objects and mal the.
Collection so it'll be more safety that
it'll out reving from both directions
and obstruction once everywhere.
We're using the same so that
it'll give obstruction and
fearless con in financial context.
So when it comes, like
earlier, we are having.
Concurrent exceptions with
multi parallel tradings.
So every time it'll get deadlock.
So this, we are going to pay like the
fearless con in financial context, so
you won't get such type of complexities
when it comes to real performance
metrics and case studies with rush
examining concrete outcomes from
rush forward claims management system
crossing three $50 billion annually.
Yeah.
So when it comes to implementation
partners and integration strategies
but practical approaches for building
and developing Rush financial APAs in
production environments when it comes
to the security and compliance and
future directions rush is giving clear
man clear path to address financial
specific security requirements and for.
So it is giving the clear path
so that we'll get the security
as well as the future directions.
Yes, we discussed what is the imperative
in the performance perspective.
So we already discover, we already in the
last page, we have seen that it'll give
the, zero complexity when it comes to the
threat safety and the speed requirement.
So today's world, everyone is follow the
agile methodologies so that these rushed
knowledge, support, like if you see any
product we are getting with the libraries.
It has Yes.
Skeleton.
So we are going to use
that as a customization.
So that like in case of speed
require modern customers expect
instant claim decisions and immediate
fund access while companies.
Operations, so especially in the
claims management to process.
Pending approval.
From there, it'll go awaiting submission.
From there, it'll go for issues,
then it'll go to the clearance.
So the process, it'll take at
least three to 10 business days.
Now this one with rush, the speed
requirements in the sense like
subsecond best ones we're receiving,
of course, like the clearance
and all eight through batches.
It'll happen.
So probably we'll get in a day or shorter.
But when it comes to the security
imperative, trust systems handling
billions in transactions required
bullet through protection against
increasingly sophisticated attacks,
targets, memory vulnerabilities.
So with, especially if you're
taking insurance domain.
So we are reading the security.
Is o for example, if you're doing any
change in the claim or if you're adding
some coverage or modifying something in
the fields of exposure or in the process
of check immediately the change will go
to the is o from the ISO, again, there
are s like Lexi and other services so
that we'll get that if fraudulent claim
response, we we receive that response.
We can say like security.
That means we had security
wise, good performance.
Yeah, so reliability mandates,
so fi financials must 99.99%.
Sometimes we can say hundred percent,
but in real world, up to some 99.
So uptime by crossing millions of
daily transactions with perfect
data across distributed systems
if something is getting failing.
So entire world is faced problems.
We have seen that recently.
And their emergency,
all rights are delayed.
So these type of things in
the financial sector with rush
to, it was never happened.
Scale challenges, modern claim systems
must handle, as I said, like 26
million plus daily results request.
While maintaining the sub hundred
milliseconds response times
across global infrastructure.
So all the legacy systems they
have implemented with core
technologies like Java, net, Python,
they struggle a lot of issues.
And sometimes they're not meeting their
demands without significant oring.
Creating cost inefficiencies and
reliability gaps that directly
impact business outcomes.
Financial institutions need a
fundamentally different approach
to APA development, so why
rushed for financial services?
As I said rush in any combination
performance and safety guarantees that
may makes it exceptionally well suited for
mission critical financial applications.
Eliminate classes of memory error without
performance, preventing workflows and
user after vulnerabilities systems in.
C plus there we have introduced
object oriented program.
That means usually the garbage
collection whenever we're performing
small operation within the method,
when you go to the control there
intentionally it'll create the object.
So it'll fill once, it'll fulfill
that business logic, immediately,
it'll get off from that method.
The, all the variables which are
used inside method is G collected.
It'll get freed the memory, so
that memory will be used upcoming.
But the next statement, execution.
There we are creating the new object.
Those objects will again use and
the same process will follow.
And the zero cost obstruction.
If you see as I said we're having
like in case of claims or policy
or billing or contact manager.
So there is couple of products, like
especially one of the leading product
is Guidewire and certainly we have.
Some other competitors.
But here they're providing
the zero cost abstraction.
That means everything they have
defined, so we need to customize the
code, what they have provided with that
typecast so we won't get more issues.
That's what we're saying zero cost.
Even if you're customizing.
Finally it has to go the so type,
so that time we won't get any
issues like the compatibility.
Issues.
So when it comes to the abstractions,
I can build high level business
logic without performance.
So taking any performance so we can
get good performance abstraction
con, as I said, like there is no
dead in the performance issues and
no hanging out the application.
We subsecond response for
each and every request.
So even if you're 26 million
of request every day.
So without concurrent issues, we can Yeah.
Driven development complex rules
in the system, making invalid
states and representable.
Error before deployment.
So most of the tribe day one
things are handled at the time.
If you're expecting the application kind
of errors, those things, they're making it
as invalid and the forcing has requested.
So to perform the correctly.
Of safety and for whom has led adoption
by major financial institutions
for mission critical a P Systems.
So what is the measurable
impact on performance metrics?
So now if you see that like the crossing
time, it's rejected from the Lexi system.
So the digital world with rushed,
it's almost 85% reduction that time
so that we'll get the performance,
yes Subsecond restaurant everywhere.
Than 26 million gateway.
26 million daily request with
consistent of 90 90 millisecond.
That means across global
operations, so system that means
the performance is giving earlier.
It is.
99.7 to 99 point below 99.74
earlier, now it's more to 1990 9.9.
Sometimes most of the times
achieving the results.
Representing a reduction of 14.9 downtime.
Financial that'll.
And I think there now if we see all the
virtual missions came into the picture
significantly, lawyer, CPU and memory
requirement have 40% infrastructure
cost saving while improving performance.
These metrics comes from aggregated data
across multiple insurance major insurance
carriers and financial institutions
that have implemented rush based claims
crossing system the past three years.
The consistent pattern of improvement
demonstrates that trust for.
Translate directly to business
value in financial context.
So what are the challenges when you,
as you said, like the fraudulent
claims are fraud fraudulent
request we can easily achieve with.
A major insurance carrier needed to
analyze one 40 data points for claim
across 810,000 daily fraud signals
while mening the sub hundred millisecond
response time to enable claim.
So once he created the claim,
so it'll go checks like every.
Checkpoints, there are one 40 checkpoints.
Yeah, all these one 40 checkpoint, it's
crossing within hundred milliseconds.
So what is the rushed solution
implemented as synchronous.
The synchronous rod detection
means, so whenever you are going.
The transaction.
So irrespective of the services, it'll
go and complete that transaction.
Meanwhile, whatever service is called,
it'll get updated as a synchronously.
So rush synchronous waiting
with the Tokyo process, multiple
fraud signals concurrently, which
maintaining strict memory bots.
We should not lead memory leaks.
For that we are that competency copy DC
realization with reduced or passing most
of the things like it's native language.
So we'll get custom memory pool estimated.
What is the results if we're solution?
We're so 99.96.
Fraud checks completed
under 80 milliseconds.
Why we're missing 0.04.
So every day the hackers are coming with
the different techniques and technologies.
It a challenge for the major
carry insurance carriers.
So every time they're coming with
different religious to work on the,
with the hacker ideas and techniques.
The false rate reduction by 31%
through more sophisticated algorithms
enabled by performance every day.
The data analytics, their different
logic to get the more throughput.
So that'll go the performance
give the better performance.
Yeah.
System handles times traffic
spike without degradation.
70% straight throughput crossing
rate for eligible claims.
So the strip rules may mainly
play, will play the major roles
in case of claims applications.
So when it comes to the memory
management, so each and everywhere,
we have the memory related errors.
And unpredictable latency
specs to overcome these.
So we have to follow the techniques,
like we have to clean up the garbage
collections and runtime so that we
can achieve this latency issues.
And when it comes to the safe obstruction.
So always we have to use the
loosely coupling so that we
can get the safe obstruction.
So memory, safety impact on finance
system in traditional collected
language like Java financial systems
experience, unpredictable la latency
spikes during collection cycles, c
plus systems risk memory, corruptions
that can lead to catastrophic failures
that eliminates both problems through
compiled them, enforcement of memory,
correctness without runtime overhead.
So this rushed, all things are
eliminated during the comp time itself.
So the predictable for performance are
shown in the diagram characteristics.
Russia allowed us to eliminate the 19
9.9% latency spike that were causing
transaction time during peak periods.
So when it comes to the bundle.
Commit transaction during sot.
So how we can say the Fearless Conference,
as I said the Golden Systems in the
legacy applications we are having,
sometimes we have to wait for more than
10 minutes to complete the transactions.
So some people, they used to do
multiple times to complete the transac.
And if it is not succeed, they can.
They'll come for the
next day and they'll try.
But when it comes to the rush, so we
have, we're seeing that second response,
like the thousands of concurrent request,
while rendering data consistent across
shared resources, there is approach
force and unacceptable tradeoff.
So what are the problems with
the traditional approaches?
If you go with the course, grands safe,
but creates water next when it comes to
the fine logs, data performance, but risk
deadlocks, lock free algorithms I used.
For means, but extremely how
we are gonna achieve solution.
We're using the type, level
threat safety, so the compiler
prevent data, so compilation.
The one which is bottleneck
in the traditional approaches.
And here we're gonna send, so
whenever it's required, depend.
So always we'll go with so
exclude threat safety guarantees.
Guarantees.
That means concurrent threats.
It won't involve, and we can achieve
expected results within the span of time.
So it's not dependency.
We'll go for the either, I think and wait.
That means it.
No need to wait for that one.
Once we'll get the response,
automatically, it'll get
updated into the system.
So it'll like, through the
through we're going get the high
performance multitasking as well.
Safe communication
between processing stages.
So with these approaches, whatever
traditional approach, bottlenecks
and deadlocks, all these things we
can achieve through trust solutions
in production, financial systems.
Con crossing throughout improvements.
Three.
Ecosystem for financial, a ecosystem for
financial, a ecosystems set of libraries,
frameworks, especially beneficial for
building financial services applications.
So I think as in are seeing the high
performance if we see that the Tokyo
product, great synchronous runtime,
enabling thousands of concurrent.
Connections with the minimal overhead used
by 92% of financial rush application to
handle high throughput, a PA workloads,
and if you're using a P frameworks.
So it'll the cost and also fraud.
We can easily.
Yeah, tested web framework with
comprehensive middleware ecosystems
both offer performance for ex
traditional offering metrics and so
each and every step we have metrics
and monitoring, so when we can
easily trace where the exact, the
performance, the tracing, we can achieve.
Expected performance.
So when it comes to the comprehensive
instrumentation, libraries for production
systems, open telemetry example,
integration enables seamless monitoring,
distributed financial transactions,
in case some database access when it
comes to the database, access each
and every table view you or we are
reading the indexing so that we can get.
Like earlier like the response, we
are getting more than 10 seconds
with this index and queries.
So we are getting the subsecond
response, the serialization.
For security purpose, each and
everything, we serializing.
And sending the over the network.
And in case of that means you could
not able to the one which is shared
with the serialization security.
So we need memory crypto graphic
libraries providing high performance
TLS implementation critical
for security financing data in
transit with the minimal overhead.
Implementation pattern for error handling,
financial error handling in financial
system, unique challenges, error.
Yeah, as we discussed earlier, so these
errors, most of the 99.9% errors, we
are handling it compiled by itself.
So that remaining 1%.
So with the, with ENT programming,
with the rush, we're eliminating it.
So what is the impact
on production systems?
So financial institutions using
rush terror handling patents report.
So 99.92% system availability
under 94% direction.
In unhandled exceptions,
improve error enables.
Minutes enhanced complaints
through comprehensive error added.
So what are the integration strategies?
Adapting, rush incrementally.
Most financial institution can't
rewrite entire system advance.
So we see in the market all the ready.
So we, the system automatically
we can integrate the the hundred
percent reliability software we
can directly, we can integrate
with the as for our requirement.
So these proven integration
patterns enables incredible
adoption and performance.
Critical micro, if you see
the each and every program
we're using the microservices.
Better performance.
Identify impact in existing systems and
replace with the targeted microservices.
Common candidates include fraud detection,
payment crossing, and real time.
This approach delivered 70% crossing
time improvement at a major.
Disrupting core systems.
So the a p gateway, transform, implement,
gateway rate limiting and protocol.
This pattern reduced latency by 60 60%
for global payments while adding minimal.
Existing system.
The gateway became the foundation
for other rush adoption and foreign
function interface exposed functionality
to existing Java application through
foreign function interface bin.
This approach enables replacement
of performance critical components
while rendering compatibility.
With existing systems one bank
through transaction, through three,
3.2 times using this approach,
their Java core banking system.
If you see the loan systems earlier
they started using that systems data
in between if they're changing some
requirement, so entire process, again,
they have to start from the beginning.
So to achieve that one to
work on that problem we have.
When you're in need, we can win
that one and we can complete
within the, it's it model.
So even also it'll follows that model
so that we can achieve expected results
and in that time, and the product
will be in the market, having the.
So it comes to security.
Security advantages that directly
address financial industry requirements.
Those are memory safety guarantees.
So we already seen that memory
safety, like when you're or storing
the data so it always hundred percent
can achieve without any dispatch.
So fall compilation.
Foreign false interface boundaries.
When interfacing with legacy systems
rush provide safe obstructions or unsafe
code containing potential vulnerabilities
to well-defined boundaries.
This pattern has proven crucial,
secure incremental adoption.
I.
And data isolation requirement,
making it easier, multitenant.
So finance, treatment, face unique
security challenges like compliance.
We have different standards like DS d and
multi talent data isolation requirement.
It has all, all these regulations and
sophisticated targeting financial data.
So like the right time right
product when it comes to the
market, only the product having the
business value delivers measurable.
Business impact through a unique
combination of for and safety guarantees,
85% faster processing and 99.991
percentage uptime and 40% infrastructure,
cost reduction and incremental
adoption in practical, so financial
institutions can adopt through gateway.
FFI without risky System S, ecosystem
maturity provides production ready
libraries for all critical financial
API needs from synchronous into secure
database, as I said, the market.
So that skill and the whatever, like 99%
are providing the skeleton as libraries.
So we have just customized
in the financial.
Systems.
Systems, the what are the
next steps in the rush?
So identify high impact performance
bottlenecks in the existing
system as initial rush target.
Start with small bounded micros to
build team expertise so that we can
achieve the performance leverage.
Rushed memory safety
advantages for security.