Hi everyone.
Thanks again for giving me this
opportunity to talk about Rush
program rush programming, how we can
use this rush programming to build
automation, enterprise level automation.
Using this rush programming language,
we'll also see as a technical
exploration, we'll also see how we
we can, how we can build a based AI
solutions for transforming operational
processes across the industries
through high performance and memory
safe implementation and architectures.
Yeah.
Hi everyone.
Thanks again for giving me this
opportunity to talk about rush
program rush programming, how we can
use this rush programming to build
automation, enterprise level automation
using this rush programming line.
Which we'll also see as
a technical exploration.
We'll also see how we we can how we
can build US based AI solutions for
transforming operational processes
across the industries through
high performance and memory, safe
implementation and architectures.
As like memory safe programming language,
and it will go through like how it
is advantages for, and advantages
and why it's very useful for, and
or why it plays a very crucial role
for building AI based applications.
As we know rush is a programming
language that is perfect for
building this AI co-pilot because
it gives us three main advantages.
First one, it keeps our
system safe from memory error.
So that they don't crash or behave
unpredictability, and it does not show it,
it does not slow down during any processes
or any high level throughput, right?
It never slows down.
That is the biggest advantage.
And the second thing, it lets the
huge amount of data to process at
a time and without any problems
and without any race conditions.
And that means everything stays accurate
and everything stays under a heavy load.
That is the biggest advantage.
And the third thing is it allows
to build complex features without
any extra performance cost.
And in short, rust helps us to
keep, make sure AI systems that
are fast and safe and reliable.
So when we look at the
rust programming, right?
As we know rust is becoming more and
more popular these days and Rust is
becoming a popular language or pop fab
fabric language for many programmers
as we know it's a memory safe and it's
a low level code programming, right?
And earlier days in future
RAs might be place c C plus
place or any other low level.
System, system programming in
my future, we, these days we see
a lot of restorations, right?
Let us see how how ra RAs can be
utilized for building this copilot
or AI based application, enterprise
level applications, and how we
can use the biggest features of
rust and why it is advantages.
We'll cover all of that.
And that is a modern programming language
that is becoming fabric for many many fab.
Becoming favorite for many
developers these days, right?
Like the main advantage, the main
reason for it is first one is it's
a memory safe without memory safe.
That means without slowing down the
process it can handle many operations and,
and also in many other languages, right?
If you see memory errors and bugs that
cause errors and that cause crashes,
rash is designed to prevent all of
that that is a biggest advantage.
It's a memory safe.
Any errors related to memory
or any errors related to that
are causing crashes, right?
That can be Amen.
That is the biggest advantage and, and
it'll also it'll also prevent these
errors without adding any runtime cost.
So that is the biggest, that is
one more advantage and coming
to the second advantage, right?
Why it is called fearless concurrency.
The simple, it simply means like
a lot of tasks can be handled at
a time like multi multithreading.
Basically multithreading when it comes
to rest can handle this multithreading
very simply and very easily.
Massive sets, right?
Like for example, multi-threading or
multi-processing processes, right?
Like ma handling, ma massive data
sets or handling thousands of
transactions or updating hundreds
of systems at a time, or without
creating data mix ups or conflicts.
For example, if in a traditional
programming to handle a thousands
of transactions at a time,
it'll be very complex for us.
With the, if we are going the high level
programming language like Java or C Sharp,
it'll be very tedious job to handle.
But when it comes to rest by
default, that has that mechanism.
At the root level, it is very
easy for us to handle multi-level
threading multi-level processes,
especially this is helping this.
Can help us in banking sector or financial
domain because there will be mi millions
of transactions per second, right?
So Rust, that's why Rust is a fabricate
language for building a blockchain.
Technologies, which has lacks
of transactions, a hundred
thousand transactions per minute.
And third advantage, right?
Zero cost ab abstractions.
We can build complex automation
logic like decision making engines
or real time analytics without
slowing down without slowing down.
The systems, for example, as right?
Like when we are building the analytics
systems, like BI reports, visualizations,
like when it is processing when it
is processing huge data loads to
give the reports or do to show the
analytics also show the graphs, right?
We encounter a lot of vision.
Those kind of challenges we can fix
using this REST program language,
which is one of the biggest advantage.
So we put all together, right?
Let us create a let us create this AI
co-pilots using this rest programming
language, how we can, let us see
how we can create this AI co-pilots
or AI safe application, right?
AI applications using this stress
problem, which can handle this high, but.
Close and run without crashes.
Deliver results instantly, which exactly
what industry like finance, retail,
and manufacturing and other utility
utility companies are looking for.
Let us look at it.
The other slide.
Let us look at the main building
blocks that make the AI copilot work.
First we have the data extraction engine.
This is the system ICE and ERs.
It collects all the information
from different data sources like
spreadsheets, documents, databases,
or even for older file formats.
It works fast and it can process ma
multiple streams at once and does
not waste the memory as we know.
We can use this we can use so it can
process ma, as I mentioned, right?
It can process any.
For any kind of files like it
does not have any limits, right?
It can process ESE file, audio
file, or web file, or any kind file.
It can be processing.
And the next comes is the agent system.
This, think, this is
like a brain of Cooper.
It uses the AI models to understand
the data and make decisions, and
it can also coordinate the task.
It can even roll back actions if
something goes wrong and it can add up.
Based on the context.
And basically this is a context, a system.
I understand what exactly it is
working on and what exactly the user
is asking and what it can respond to.
And even it can handle
task automation, right?
Anything really.
It can perform some tasks.
Like basically if there is a prompt that
can not want execute any task, right?
That can be handled by this agent system.
This is like a brain that
handles all the instructions.
The main, core logic is present here.
The final one is the integration layer.
As we know, this is integration
layer, which is used to connect to the
different system like AI copilot if you
want to integrate the AI copilot with
the other integration systems, right?
Even though it's a modern or legacy
system, modern system that has
API or or the legacy system, which
does not have any a PS, it can work
seamlessly and it can integrate with
other systems safely and accurately.
And these main, majorly, these
three major parts of this copilot
that that ma the major three parts,
the data engine, AI brain, and
the integration integration layer.
They work together to make the
whole automation system much more
reliable and fast and easy to connect.
Especially in the industry environment,
especially where there are where there
are thousands of transactions, right?
For example, a financial industry or
retail industry, which has thousands
of transactions per second, especially.
That is the, this is ideal in those words.
We'll look at those
examples in the next slide.
We'll cover all of those use cases,
real time use cases in upcoming slides.
Yeah.
One of the best things about, about using
rust about using rust for copilot is that
we don't have to keep keep reinventing the
whole wheel again, once it is built built
like a component, like a data parer or a
reporting tool or addition making model,
we can reuse it for a different project.
It's like a module, like how we
use the DLL files in C or regular.
Regular programming language, right?
We can use it like if we build
one application, it can be used.
Any component can be re imported
or referenced into another project
and reused, taken this is possible
because the rust has very strong type
system and it's a modular design.
In simple terms, it means co the
code is like a building blocks.
It can fit together perfectly.
Even if they are used in different
business areas where we can create
generic versions of tools, the, and
then customize customize them, right?
For example we are building,
for example, I can give you,
for example, we built a small.
A POA system or a small application,
that's for a finance application.
It can be modularized or it can be it can
be customized or it can be configured.
For other industry.
For example, we built it for finance
and it can be configured for other
industry also, or has, or healthcare
or retail domain or other domain.
Also, it can be modular as we know, right?
ERP, like if we are building an ERP
system like ERP system, like SAP
using the rest, it can be modularized.
If we have 10 features that we build for
this ERP system and one company they want
to use only five, and out of that five
and other company want only three, it
can be easily customized, as I mentioned.
These are like, this is like a
building blocks or building blocks
the way the rust is built, the
programming language is built, right?
It's like a building blocks.
It can fit all of them perfectly.
That makes the rest rust programming
very seamless and work and everything,
all the components work together.
And another benefit of another Ben
biggest benefit is comp comply.
Compile time guarantees.
That means system checks system
checks everything before even it runs.
So if something does not match we watch
it clearly instead of finding out later
in production if even during the compile
time only all the error are checked
because in traditional programming or
in the current programming world like
usually we see a lot of production bugs,
usually some of the issues, we encounter
them only when we go to production.
Those kind of issues can be
analyzed and understood even
before, during the compilation.
We are using the REST program.
This usability has a huge impact on time
and cost in real world programs real world
projects like companies have 60 have seen
like 60 to 75% direction of development
time for new automation workloads
after they have reinvested once in f.
Well, especially rest, right?
As I mentioned, like you
say, system system friendly
language and low level prep.
And there are many frameworks that uses
this low code framework for building rest.
There are on top of rest, right?
They have built a subsets.
Basically these are like subsets
of basically the low code versions.
We are planning to build
any workflows, right?
We can utilize these workflows
for building new workflows
like workflow engines or.
Flows, especially business
process automation.
If you want to automate millions
of transactions, or if you
want doing any data pipeline or
data orchestration jobs, right?
We can leverage this RAs programming
language, which is very flexible for
building those kind of operations.
So instead of speaking, instead
of spending we spending weeks and
building the weeks and months on
spend building using these legacy
applications legacy programming
languages for development, right?
We can adopt, to this even we
have seen, as I mentioned earlier
like we have seen a 62, 70 5% of
reduction in development time.
In build in development time for many
companies, which started to use this
rush programming and a fewer bugs, right?
A major major advantage is it has a
faster delivery, which is faster delivery,
fewer bugs, main consistency, more.
Consistent quality and
quality across all consistent.
If we are using us as a main
Procore programming language
for entire organization, right?
As I mentioned earlier, we
can reuse these components.
One like if it is developed
once, it can be reused anywhere.
Let us look at how how this
works in real time world.
Especially with starting with
financial financial services.
One common one common example, is
a loan processing and automation
in the finance industry, right?
The speed and accuracy is everything,
and it makes it can make mistakes
also, can lead to compliance issues
or financial loss, especially you,
we are using with the rush powered
ai copilot can handle these thousands
of transaction that time, right?
Checking documents, verifying
information, making sure everything
meets the strict regulatory rules
and all the validations, right?
If we are going with this rest,
this can be solved very easily
because rest is a memory safe.
It is ideal for handling sensitive
data like personal details, income
statements, or credit reports, or even
we, or even without making any leaks
or errors in practical world, right?
Like we have seen document
extraction has only 99.9% accurate,
which means almost no mistakes.
I have seen applications, right?
Which uses rest for document
extraction which, or OCR, right?
Which has.
Very, which are very accurate
which that uses REST program, which
are very accurate compared to the
traditional traditional systems.
The system also validates almost all
the information even it's a real time.
So the it's real time and so the approvals
or rejections can happen very quickly.
So if you go with the legacy applications
or traditional applications it is, the
process, like a process of doing the OCR
process is handled by one system, and
approvals is handled by another system.
And basically the pre-process is
handled by the one system and push
process is handled by another system.
But when it comes to arrest, everything
can be handled together because.
It can support any kind
of application level.
We can build any kind of
applications using this.
And moreover, we can integrate,
for example we are building
only the processing the core
processing system in rest.
And we want to integrate office 365 or
core, our power platform, which has all.
Built in approval systems, right?
We can easily integrate this rust.
So one part will be in rust.
The major core part, the analysis
part will be in rust, and the
approval part will be in the
other systems like power platform.
And because of this because Rust is a very
high performance system that usually runs
smoothly even during the peak times, while
hundreds of applications are in single
hour, that means there is no delay to the
customers and no backlog for the bank.
And as we know rest it perform compared
to if you see the benchmarks of a
traditional programming, like a Java based
application or a do net based application
with rest, it's a low level program.
It can perform very high
high compared to high.
It has high, very high benchmarks.
It.
In terms of performance that,
that helps us especially
during the high times, right?
We have seen, especially in the banking
sector sometimes the systems might go
down because of the huge transaction.
Especially, for example, if you take
the trading trading world, sometimes
systems might crash or systems might load.
This can be used at this rest.
Programming language can be used in
such scenarios to handle very fast
loads, especially without handling the
crashes and handling the through handling
those especially during the peak times.
In short in finance, rush power,
copilots can deliver perfect mix
of accuracy, speed, and accuracy,
and which exactly is needed by the
current current finance sector.
Let us look at the industry application.
Second industry application
like retail sector.
How this copilot AI coate can be used
for in retail industry, in retail
in retail timing, and are critical
because every small delays can lead
to lead to empty shelves or mystery.
Yeah, rush powered.
The AI copilot can completely transform
real time inventory management.
It can handle distributed
updates and meaning.
That means it can keep track of
stocks or across the hundreds of
stores at the same time without risk
of two system overriding each other.
And.
And this is possible because rush has a
con, a concurrency feature that lets the
processes of multiple stores multiple
stores handle and update safely in a
parallel parallel on top of that, right?
Ai ai we can use ai.
AI for analyzing the sales data and trends
and parallel or, and make the predictive
ordering or predictive suggestions.
Basically, these are like
supply chain for example.
If you take for if you take in certain
terms, in certain items, right?
In certain items are selling faster
than expected, the system may system
can recommend of ordering of those
items even before it, it ran out
and, it does instantly instantly,
no matter how large the data set is,
it can process the data set and it
can give us the predictor results.
Another big advantage is
legacy po OS integration.
As we know already, most of the stores
still use the legacy systems, legacy
po o as a point of sale systems, right?
Many retailers still use those systems.
And more of, most of them does
not have the re APIs, right?
Like it cannot there.
It's not they're not like iot, which
can be integrated with internet or
which can, does not have any internet
connection or it does not have any APIs.
We can have, we can build an
integration layer that build, we
can build these integration layer
with those legacy systems using this
rest, which can translate regular
transactional data or p os data into
extract the data into this hour.
Based online system and do
performance and do do a analysis
on top of that as a result, right?
As we know, we can work on legacy systems,
it can be integrated with legacy systems.
It is it can both ly do do, supply chain
management and predict to analytics
and real time operations, right?
This makes RA based AI applications
or RA based applications a
best fit for retail world.
Now let's talk about
manufacturing and the utilities.
The two sectors where down
downtime and inefficiency can be
extremely costly in manufacturing.
A rest rest about ai.
Copilot can automate I automate pro
procurement and supply coordination.
It can manage real.
Orders or optimization.
An example check a supplier.
It can check the supplier availability.
Compare the prices, placing orders
in parallel without slowing down.
It can perform even negotiations.
Also even it can perform negotiations
with multiple suppliers at the same time,
it can ensure, quantity right quantity
right quality or doc right quality.
And also control the documents and
automatically process those documents
or process the communication, like
whatever communication that happens
during these processes, right?
That can be handled by
the same system itself.
We may not rely on the other systems,
especially, we have seen a situations
where for supply chain management,
they're using one system and for
the other processes, sales and
coordination, they're using outreach.
They're using a different systems, right?
Two different systems.
Those can be avoided.
If we are going with this rush based
approach rush can replace those
kind of, for example, in utilities,
in let take the utilities world.
In utilities many companies rely on
world infrastructure like SCADA systems.
Like Boulder Systems, flex
Rush integration layer allows
us to extend the system.
These by, without replacing them,
we can directly integrate them,
as I mentioned in earlier, right?
Like even license systems can
be integrated with recession.
That means without zero disruptions
or zero operations zero disruptions
to operations, like without having
disturbing the existing operations, right?
We can integrate, we can bring this
in into our, into our ecosystem.
We can we can add fault tolerance
monitoring that keeps working even if.
Part of the system fails as
we, as I mentioned, right?
This is a modular system.
Even though some part of it
fails, but the remaining part of
it still can continue working.
We can automate regulatory reporting
for the compliance teams can, don't
have to spend hours gathering the data.
So by default as most of the
modern enterprise applications
have the reporting a log or
transactional logs capability, right?
The same way we can implement
those kind of system, which can.
Which can capture all the logs
and all the transactions that
are happening on these systems.
Especially during the audit,
when audit happens, right?
If you want to if you want to see like
why why what happened and all the digital
stuff, the audit teams spending hundred
percent hours of time on on understanding
the data, analyzing the data, right?
We can use this output as.
We can save a lot of time for audit team.
The final key benefit of using Rusty is
it can handle large, complex operations
predictably, whether it is monitoring
thousands of meters in a power grid, or
coordinating suppliers across countries,
or the system remains fast and safe,
reliable, and without any downtime.
Now we have seen a couple of use cases,
especially in utility world, finance
world, and supply chain world, right?
Now let let us look at the number
numbers like how how rash is compared,
like how can rash can perform compared
to other, traditional approaches.
First is the memory usage.
Rushed ownership model means it uses
about 30% less memory care compared
to the regular or typical systems.
That is important because it allows allows
us to run the same workloads on smaller
and more cost efficient infrastructure.
Second one is a processing speed in real.
In real world testing, RAs can
perform data in incent intensive
operations up to five times faster than
compared to conventional platforms.
This is a huge boost when it, when
you are working on a high volume
transactions or real world analytics.
And the third third one is.
Concurrency and efficiency that can
handle a parallel task up to 200%
more efficiently without risk for
data corruption or race conditions.
This especially especially this critical
this is very critical in critical in
industries where multiple systems are
updating the same data at the same time.
Especially in the finance world.
These performance gains are, or
just theoretical they translate
into faster operations and lower,
lower the cost, and also a smoother
experience for both internal teams
as well as the, and the customers.
So beyond the, our performance
Rest Restore also delivers a strong
business and developer benefits.
First one let us look at the first one.
Computational efficiency with.
Computational efficiency with
zero zero overhead abstractions
and a smart smart memory model.
Rash can give us up to near near
C level performance CC programming
level performance while it is
being safe in practice in practice.
This means the 80% of 80% reduction
in infrastructure requirements, fewer
servers, fewer low fewer low cloud
clause, and predictable predictable
latency even when workloads changes.
Plus also there is no garbage
collection and pauses slow.
And there is no garbage collection,
which improves performance drastically.
Next one is the developer productivity.
Even even though Rust has a big learning
curve, once team gets familiar with.
Familiar with Thera programming,
it saves a lot of time.
We have seen 65% less debugging
time because compiler ca comply.
Comp compiler catches many error before,
even before the other program runs.
The carbo the cargo ecosystem
manages to manages dependencies.
The that makes e our developer life easy.
And the documentation and the tooling
are very excellent, as we know.
It actually is evolving so much.
These days.
There are a lot of, a lot of resources
for learning and it evolves so much.
There, there are a lot of resources or
a lot of tutorial available on web where
once the team or the once the team gets
familiar with this rush program it'll be.
Very easy for us to implement this.
Finally, infrastructure consolidation.
Instead of maintaining the
multiple specialized systems, a
single rush code base can replace
all of them as we know, right?
Industries tend to use the different
programming languages because of
that, they have to maintain huge,
different systems like for example,
Java based system or Linux based
system or windows based system.
All of this, that, that can be this
it can run on any kind of system.
Infrastructure wise, we can
eliminate those kind of limitations.
That means unified monitoring,
consistent development and consistent
development patterns or the consistent
and makes simple, makes the audit
simple and fewer moving parts and fewer
to manage and management wise, right?
I it infrastructure, we, it is very
hard to maintain different systems
for different applications, which
are not different ecosystems, right?
So rash makes that if we replace
those systems with rest it can, it can
default those kind of infrastructure
or maintena maintainability problem.
So rust isn't fast.
Rust isn't safe.
It also reduces operational cost,
speeds up development and makes
the system easier to maintain it.
In long term.
It saves lot of cost for the companies.
Yeah.
Now let's talk about how we can
implement this rest for AI automation.
Generally we, we follow a few proven
design patterns that make our system
both powerful and maintainable.
For example actor model let's.
Act for example, actor model that
lets different parts of the system run
independently and talk to each other
without stepping on each other's data.
But this is perfect for
the complex workflows.
And next one is the type state pattern,
which helps us to lock the correct order
or the step at the compile time, which
so we cannot, we can't accidentally
run the process in the wrong sequence.
And the third one is command pattern.
Which is useful useful for operations
that might need that might need to
underdone that might need to underdone.
It pack packages each task so
we can control we can roll back.
Its, when it is needed.
And another one is repository pattern
repository pattern extracts how we
can store and retrieve the data making
it easy to switch the databases or
backends without rewriting the logic.
As we, as we use feature flags to enable
or disable the features at the deployment
time, which is great for testing the.
Gradual rollouts.
We can also leverage the powerful
tools from rush ecosystem
like Tokyo for handling.
Lot of task at once and Saturday
for working with different data
coordinate REST belt, which is
a natural language processing.
And rayon for parallel data
processing and tonic for G GRPC
communication GRPC based communication.
By combining all these data patterns
the no known data patterns and the
right tools, we can build automation
systems very easily that are not.
Only fast, but also safe and reliable,
and which are flexible and adaptable.
Let us wrap up let us wrap up
the key takeaways from everything
we have covered till now.
First one is by investing in rest based
automation framework, organizations
can save up to 65 62 c, 75% reduction
in development time for new workflows.
And that is because once the core
components are built, they can
be reused across all the other
projects and other departments.
Second is memory, safety and
pre and predictable performance
that can lead to ni 89% of
reduction in production incidents.
That means fewer crashes, fewer bugs.
And more firefighting for the
development operation in terms.
Third one is the overall process
times overall process time can be
improved by an average of 83%, which
is directly translates into faster
service delivery, faster services and
faster deliveries, better customer
experiences, and higher efficiency.
So the message is simple, gives you.
Gives you fast, safe, and
reliable automation that can
that can work across industries
that can work across industries.
It's a foundation that balances
innovation and reliability, and it's
a proven it's a proven to world,
real world that the results in
performance, cost savings, and quality.
You for giving me this opportunity
to talk about how we can
leverage this s programming for
building AI based to copilot.
Now what next steps?
Coming to next steps rather
like the final conclusion?
I want to say the first step
is to evaluate your current
automation challenges and see.
Where the performance, reliability, or
scalability are critical pain points,
these areas are where we can fit the
rest and show the biggest impact.
Next is to consider the
starting a pilot project.
Choose the process that is
important for your organization.
Something where failure isn't an option.
And test rush powered AI
copilot platforms over there.
And from there you can expand
gradually reusing these components
you have built in the pilot and
to speed up the future projects.
Once this is override, you can
benefit ly faster development,
like faster development, fewer
issues, and more consistent results.
The goal isn't to replace everything
overnight, but it is about building
the solid foundation where future
proof of your automation given given
you the PA performance, safety, and
flexibility, you need to stay competitive.
Okay.