Hello everyone.
Good morning.
Good afternoon.
I'm from Jane to India.
Today I'm excited to present rest power
data engineering, building performance
critical systems for global impact
in a world drowning in data for 1
75 zetabytes process to annually.
How do we build systems that are fast,
secure, and ready for global challenges?
That's what we will explore.
Imagine processing petabytes of
data without crashes or breaches.
Traditional tools like Java or Python
of in Fall Shock garbage collection
causes cause unpredictability,
memory leaks, risk, corruption.
We need to rethink for safety and scale.
Rest offers that performance of low
level language with high level safety.
So why dust?
Let's break it down
First, memory, safety, rest Ownership.
Model tracks who owns data preventing
books like null pointer at compiled time.
No runtime overhead.
Zero cost abstractions.
Let lets you write clean code without
slowing down Petabytes processing.
Concurrency in the list.
The compiler catches risk conditions,
so no more debugging, deadlocks,
and also on the predictability.
New garbage collection means consistent
performance like c plus, but C,
in my experience, I've seen teams
spending weeks on memory issues on C
plus birth and rest eliminates that.
These aren't hypotheticals.
Thus delivers 10 times throughput
or JBM tools in streaming, 99.99%
uptime for massive workloads, 80%
lower latency at the edge, and 60%
saving while zero copy in production.
This means handling billions
of records without hiccups.
Think about your own pipeline.
Could you use an 80% latency kit?
Rust isn't alone.
Two Q Powers a sync IO
for high throughput.
Apache Arrow enables fast columnar data.
Great for analytics.
Data fusion is like a rest
waste spark for queries.
The ecosystem is booming,
making rust practical today, but
does this work in real world?
Let's take a look at the case studies.
The first case study is on
the client monitoring system.
Terabytes of satellite data is
stored in remote spots, needing real
time analysis on limited hardware.
The rest solution would be to
efficient pipe to develop efficient
pipelines that run flawlessly on
the edge, which pro which help us in
growing 65% faster processing, 40%
cheaper infra, and reach to remote
areas using this edge technology.
This powers global climate
impact and think monitoring
deforestation in real time.
For environmental engineers
here, this means deploying
AI where it's needed the most
in health systems, public health systems,
national scale data for epidemic tracking.
No room for error.
Ensure memory, safety, and
privacy at compiled time.
With quarries hitting eight millisecond
on billions of records, zero breaches
near perfect uptime during crisis.
This even sees slides by
enabling instant insights.
These wins comes from first core
features and let's deep dive on those.
Rest.
Ownership is key.
It prevents corruption by enforcing
single ownership or borrowing.
Buffer flows all at compile time.
This makes data flows clear
and maintainable perfect
for complex pipelines.
It's like a strict librarian where you
borrow a book, but obviously you can't
keep it forever or lend it out twice.
Here is a sync processing with Tokyo,
which read lines with zero copy.
It processes data.
Processes without copying data, and
also at the source, it parts passes
the streams efficiently, and once it
has passes the streamed stream data, it
can also transform the data in parallel
without logs, which in the next step
can serialize safely to the data sync.
This avoids overhead in high volume data.
Loop also reads without
blocking clear buffers to reuse.
Code creates array and batches.
Zero copy.
We share data without duplication.
Column data is used for first queries.
It also integrates with Python, which
is ideal for mixed language teams.
And if you're in analytics,
a arrows columnar format.
Speeds of aggregation, massively
building ethical data systems with rust,
where also we need to take a look at the
efficient query execution, and this is
also SQL is to optimize execution where
you can register your CSV, for example.
Run.
Like a VG temperature with average
temperature, with filters, and it
can provide you a zero copy results.
And this itself is a example
of data freedom in action,
which is vectorized for speed.
Rest is in this fast, it is ethical.
Tool ownership enforces privacy
boundaries, efficient bias
detection in ML without slowdowns.
It is also sustainable because it
takes low energy to process these
data, which in turn cuts carbon.
Dust lets us bend responsibility
responsibly at scale.
In this slide, it talks about
the lock free with automate and
the code shows a safer counter.
Where streaming with Tokyo Arrow
provides higher throughput.
It also optimizes for energy savings.
So start small.
Try risk pipeline in your next project.
These are just plug and play
experiment to see this in action
trends.
The future trends of first data
engineering, Western data engineering.
Obviously Rust is Cloud
native ML is integrated.
This is also specialized tool which
provides us the performance and safety
at lower cost, fewer vulnerabilities,
global scalability and this is why
Rusty is the future of data engineering.
In summary, rusty transforms
data engineering for impact.
Fast, safe and ethical programming.
Thank you.