Hello everyone.
I'm Chen Kabul from College of
Technology, pan India, and today I'll
be talking about building zero trust,
security infrastructure, and rust.
I will walk you through what zero trust
means and some of the fundamentals of it.
What advantages does
bring to this problem?
We'll also go through some of the
building blocks, just provide to
build a secure infrastructure.
Then we'll look at some implementation
patterns and close with some performance
numbers from real world implementations.
Let's start by looking at zero trust
security fundamentals in today's
threat landscape of sophisticated
threat actors and our advent of ai.
We have to always assume a brief
scenario for any system infrastructure.
This pushes us to lay down some
ground rules for zero trust.
First and foremost, we cannot
trust without verifying
the idea of any component.
Always design access using lease privilege
access, and have a very high standard
from monitoring and validation to detect
what's happening in your ecosystem.
Now with the background of what we
intend to achieve, let's see what Rust
has to offer when it comes to security.
First and foremost, systems built using
Rust gets advantage of rust ownership
model, which prevent memory vanities,
like buffer workflows and use after free.
This is a big trust advantage
for systems built using rust.
Rust.
Also provide predictable performance,
which helps with real time security
decisions using metrics and other
telemetry the ecosystem provides.
Next, let's talk about rust string
type system, which help perform
compile time checks for critical
controls like authentication.
Another advantage of Rust is the
security abstractions provided by
the language for fast and effective
operations when it comes to cryptography,
authentication, and authorizations, which
is critical to build a secure ecosystem.
Rust safety guarantees and
performance characteristics makes
it as ideal choice for a zero
trust architecture implementation.
Now let's dive into some of the components
which will help us build for zero trust.
These rest components are the
building blocks of foundation security
and helps developers and security
engineers achieve their goals.
I have broken these components
into three categories.
First, networking and TLS.
Tokyo Russ, TLS Web PKI, and Quinn
helps developer build for secure channel
implementation with high performance
and memory safety TLS implementations
on the authentication and IT side
Russ Ring and organ two provides the
primitive for strong authentication.
JSON Web Open and or two RS components
help build industry standard
authentication mechanism with ease.
Last, but one of the most important
aspect of security in infrastructure
is default network libraries
and observative capabilities.
Hyper end Tower provides
a robust networking stack.
While tracing and metrics provides
rich performance and diagnostic
data for a solid foundation
for monitoring and detections,
we just talked about how you can
use some of Rust core components
to build a secure software stack.
Now let's talk about a critical
NT of zero trust architecture, and
that is identity aware proxies.
As I mentioned in my opening, one of the
fundamentals of Zero Trust architecture
is verifying the caller and perform
fine, gain authorization decisions, and
also enforce policy based on context.
Rush provides a perfect ecosystem for
search architecture implementation
with components like Tower as
a middleware choice also, rush
trade system is a perfect choice.
Choice for a type safe policy
implementation, which also enables
compile time verification of policy
logic, providing very high security
assurance for policy checks, and best
part is there are no runtime surprises.
We touched on the importance
of observability for a
zero trust architecture.
Rust metrics and tracing libraries
makes metric data gathering a breeze
and comes with a high performance
benefit, which enables almost real
time analysis of metric data for
faster detections without penalizing
the performance of our applications.
Anomaly detection becomes so much better
when you use metrics, data, and rust.
Now let's dive a little deeper
for the secure communication,
implementation and Rust.
As I mentioned earlier, rust, TLS is
a great candidate for memory Safet,
LS implementation, which comes with
high performance and eliminates a
whole suit of ities, which can be
found in other S implementations.
Definitely a big win here.
Web PK ensures that certificate
validation for secure communication
is per RFC standards without a risk
of wrong configurations and possible
authentication, bypass van liberties
and Quinn adds the cherry on top.
If you want to implement quick protocol
for high performance and security, I would
highly increase to have a look at that.
Overall rush library ecosystem offered its
strong typing, compiled time detections
of errors makes it a perfect choice for
implementing error free and robust secure
communication platform and fulfills the
foundation needed for a zero trust system.
Now let's dive into the complex world of
supply chain security, which has caused
some of the biggest breaches of our times.
You must have definitely had of
SolarWinds and how a third party
developer system can compromise
security of overall secure system.
Rust cargo ecosystem ships with
all the tooling needed to maintain
secure dependencies and ensuring
supply chain developes are accounted
for while building the environment.
Definitely an amazing advantage
and make supply chain security
management less complex to implement.
Let's quickly look into some of
the performance characteristic of
rusts implementations, as there
is often a concern that security
comes with a performance price.
As you can see, that rust high
performance on JW validation with
a latency of just 0.3 millisecond.
Ability to make conference secure
connections at a high scale
and the a high availability.
High availability provided by no GC
pause in memory related crashes makes
it a perfect choice for implementing
components for zero test architecture.
Trust proxy is a perfect example
of such an implementation.
I would highly encourage to look at
Cloudflare's Spin Gora for such an
implementation and how CloudFlare has
achieved higher security and performance
at the same time, and providing the best
in class proxy for forest consumers.
Let's talk about some of the key takeaways
from our presentation before we close.
Rest brings lot to the table when it comes
to building security sensitive workloads.
Critical for zero trust.
First compiled.
Time enforcement is a superpower
when it comes to security assurances.
Second, you don't need to
compromise and performance.
And third, the ecosystem continues
to mature when it comes to
security focus, implementation.
And there is lot of open source
contributions in this space.
I will highly encourage all of
you to evaluate your current
stack for bottlenecks related to
authentication performance, secure
communication performance, and also
vulnerability is in those stacks,
and evaluate rust for those needs.
I'm sure you'll not be disappointed.
Thanks for listening my talk, and I
wish you best in your security journey.