Good morning everyone.
My name is Raul Tawa, senior Network
Cloud infrastructure engineer at Kyro
Technologies based out of Dallas, Texas.
Over the past decade, I have led large
scale in transformations for the global
enterprises, including migrating more than
2000 plus sites to SD-WAN in modernizing
manufacturing networks and implementing
AI driven routing architectures.
Today's session is about.
Building Next generation network
infrastructure using Rust, a language
that has fundamentally changed how
we approach a safety performance and
concurrency in production networks.
We'll explore how Rust enables zero
trust packet processing AI based routing
decisions and enterprise great security
without compromising on the performance.
So today's we'll break down
the session into five parts.
Why Russ, why rusts for the network
infrastructure's, real time, real world
case studies, practical implementation
techniques, security, enterprise options,
and key takeaways, and the next steps.
The challenge of modern network
infrastructure, the problem
is pretty clear these days.
Our networks are growing faster
and more complex than our tools.
We are moving from 10 GBPS pipes
to 400 GBPS backbones with sub
millisecond latency requirements
for high frequency trading.
5G core functions and real time analytics
recommendations are no longer static.
They're being driven by ML models
that need real time interference,
optimizing for latency, condition
jitter, and even energy efficiencies.
Meanwhile, in the legacy stack,
in such as C and C plus PE, carry,
dig of technical debt and security
package buffer overflows, dangling
binders, race conditions that
attackers allowed to exploit.
And the operational cost of
patching and hardening these systems
is growing substantially high.
In short, the gap between what the
network needs to do and what our current
tools allow our current tools allow
is widening to large extent why rust
is ideal for network infrastructures.
Rust solves the pro this problem
without forcing us to compromise.
The ownership model, memory safety
is enforced to compile time without
a garbage collector, no runtime
overheads, no pauses, and no leaks.
This matters in the networks where
dropping a packet is not an option.
Zero cost abstractions, right
code that looks high level, but
combines down to machine code as a
as efficient as a handwritten code.
We can design expressive APIs for
packet parsing without adding cycles.
Fearless concurrency, rust makes it
safe to share state between threads
without locks, enabling parallel packet
parsing without the race conditions,
which is a really great option.
Memory safety by eliminating buffer
flows and use after free rust removes
the root cause or root cause of
70% of CVEs in network software
over the last decade in production.
This means you can hit line rate
performance while guaranteeing
safety properties that were once to
impossible in the system language.
Zero copy packet processing with rust.
In traditional stack, a single
packet might be copied five times.
Nick to kernel user and kernel to user
base and the kernel back to the nick.
Each copy adds a latency and
burn CPU cycles at 400 GVPS.
Even a single extra copy can cost
millions of hardware over time.
With rust, we can eliminate most of it.
Map Nick Buffers directly into.
User space with safety abstractions.
Pass references instead of
making memory copies, use borrow.
Borrow, checking to guarantee no
dangling pointers or double freeze.
In integrate with this async
runtime like Tokyo for non-blocking
packets IO in our tests, moving
from traditional copying to rust.
Zero copy approach, reduced packet
processing latency by 40 to 65%,
and free CPU core for additional
workloads like telemetry analysis.
Let's do a case study, taking the
financial services industry through the
routing in the financial service industry.
This was a, this was for a major
US exchange with extreme latency
sensitivity security, which
is one of the most important.
94% of the vulner vulnerabilities
disappeared overnight simply because
rust made them representable in code.
No more emergency.
Midnight patches for the
buffer overflows latency.
Routing decisions dropped from one
20 milliseconds to 32 milliseconds.
That's nearly four times
improvement in the HFT.
That can be the difference between
winning and losing a trade.
Throughput, same hardware, 3.4
more transactions per second.
No extra networkers.
No extra CPUs.
AI driven routing in rust.
With rust, we can run ML reference
directly in the forward path.
No round trips to separate analytical
engine data collection telemetry at
tens of thousands of samples per second,
using zero cost obstruction model
training offline on historical routing
data with features like utilization
jitter packet and drops interference.
Rust based engines run these
models in microseconds.
Selecting optical parts in real
time, hard swapping hard swap out
models without stopping traffic.
Enabling adaptive learning
network techniques.
This makes it possible to have
truly self optimized network with
decision aware decisions are dynamical
dynamic as the traffic itself.
Practical roster techniques
for network programming.
These are the three powerful techniques.
Stand out efficient
protocol serialization.
Using ER for compact zero copy.
Serialization de serialization
of the routing, routing
headers and telemetry data.
Custom allocators, pre allocate buffers
with predictable latency at 400 GPS
and nanosecond matters Ring buffers.
LOP free packet queues with atomic index.
For deterministic throughput,
these patterns let us match and
often beat the performance of hand
optimized code while keeping rust
strong safety guaranteed intact.
Security advantage of rust.
The majority of the network CVEs
come from memory safety issues,
exactly what trust eliminates.
No buffer overflows, no
use of free after free.
No data raise.
Strong type system prevents
logic errors in packet parsing
and routing state machines.
Even when we do need unsafe blocks
for hard hardware access, the
rust forces us to isolate and
capsulate and audit that code.
This drastically reduces the
attack surface while keeping
performance at a bare metal levels.
Let's do a case study of a
manufacturing network, resilience
in a manufacturing industry.
Fortune 500 manufacturer has had
a recurring nightmare pro in a
production lines Hal halted by the
network outages I, and then the
recovery time was up to 17 minutes.
Gradually gradual performance
degradation from memory links
was also a ma major issue.
After implementing the rust
routing he, the manufacturer hit
the uptime of 99.998%, and the
failover and recovery dropped.
Under 200 microseconds milliseconds,
security patches applied without
taking the network offline via hot
patching, and the VP of Operation
told that rust and error handling
turn our network from a frequent
failure point into our most reliable
system enterprise adoption strategies.
So you don't have to rewrite
everything on one day.
It's basically starts by by targeting the
bottlenecks per safety and performance.
I improvement say performance
improvements will have the biggest ROI.
Use FFI Bridges to integrate rust
models with c cc plus legacy systems run
parallel deployments to validate trust
performance under production loads.
Use rust testing framework for unit
integration and property based testing
before rollouts Phase two deployments
start with non-critical parts, then
migrate to the code routing functions.
This approach minimizes risk while
steadily replacing fragile legacy code.
Key takeaways.
Rust lets us achieve safety
without sacrificing the speed.
Zero.
Copy processing and fearless
concurrency means fewer CPUs, low
latency and higher throughput.
Rust deterministic performance makes
it AI ready, enabling in the in path.
ML interference for the smarting.
Thank you for the opportunity.
Have a great day.