Hi everyone.
Good morning.
Thank you for ha attending my session
and also a big thank you to the
organizers for having this conference.
I'm Anush Wicker.
I am the software engineering manager
at ai and today I would like to tell you
about my interest of using Rust with ai.
Russ has been redefining edge AI
combining safety, performance, and
fine-grain control to meet the real world
constraints of embedded intelligence.
Now we do see that the Edge AI market
is exploring with the 44.2% of CAGR.
Now, this is not a hype.
This is just the adoption driven
by real performance demands,
27.8 billion market size by 2026.
That means there's a lot of app
opportunity for rust developers.
Also, the less than 50 millisecond
latency as a holy grail for edge
ai, which the cloud infrastructures
cannot reliably deliver This.
We need an optimize on device computation.
Okay, let me walk through some of the
advantages of using rust on Edge ai.
First is the memory Safety.
Without garbage collection, we
can avoid memory leaks and data
traces with the garbage without a
garbage collector slowing us down.
Also, we do have zero cost abstractions,
so the ability to write clean, expressive
code without paying in performance.
Also, it has a fine grain system
controlled, which means that an edge ai,
every byte in every CPU cycle matters.
Let's talk about some of the
real world performance advantages
that we have with Rust.
There is a 92% performance
improvement over other languages,
and these are production numbers.
Also, 82% cost reduction as
a big business driver also.
73.2% of memory usage reduction.
Now, this can be the difference
between fitting your model
on device or not at all.
Let's talk about some of the secret
weapons for using Rust of Edge ai.
First is the safe concurrency for a
multi-core arm, we can scale safely
across course without runtime penalties.
Also using an efficient single instruction
multiple demand with portable SIMD.
That is two of six x speed
without handwritten assembly.
There is also a seamless
hardware acceleration integration
that is from NPUs to DSPs.
Rust plays nicely with them.
Even in no SDD environments,
let's talk about a case
study on autonomous vehicles.
The challenge that we have here is
we need a 15 millisecond obstacle
detection challenge, and also we need
a 99.2% top detection success rate.
12.7 millisecond inference
time and 99.99% uptime.
That is why rusts is reliable
in safety critical applications.
Rusts compile time also guarantees
eliminating a lot of runtime errors, which
are actually being plagued to c plus.
This applications.
Let's talk about a case study,
which is a different one now.
It's called Industrial IOT Security.
There is a 99.85% of threat
detection accuracy, which is
observed on modest hardware.
With this rust on edge ai also we have,
we see a 22 millisecond response time
and a 4.8 years of battery life with.
P hardware.
So we do see a predictable
performance, which makes low power
edge devices viable for yours.
The Edge AI ecosystem consists of
candle code, which is a high performance
network library, which is used for
inferences with minimal dependencies.
Next there is a burn, which is a
deep learning framework with strong
type system and modular backends,
which enables model training.
And finally, we have a smart core, which
is machine learning, library implementing
traditional machine learning algorithms
and is also compatible with no SD.
Now this ecosystem is rapidly maturing,
which creates new creates and capabilities
emerging monthly to support the
entire edge AI development lifecycle.
Let's talk about the
implementation patterns for a
custom neural network operators.
So whenever we are creating a
neural network operator for rust.
In a GI, we need precise optimization.
Also, the there, these are some
of the key patterns to achieve
maximum performance and efficiency.
With no heap allocations, we achieve no
STD compatibility, which is very crucial
for highly constrained embedded systems.
And also guarantees deterministic
and low latency operations.
Optimized cache utilization, which will
be implementing cache friendly memory
access patterns dramatically reduces
the memory latency leads to a faster
processing time and execution speed.
Manual loop unrolling enhances the CPU
in instruction pipeline efficiency,
and also provides a high predictable
execution times for real time edge
AI task direct slides manipulation.
Optimized to remove the bound
checks in the release mode,
ensures maximum performance.
While maintaining RUS
score safety GA guarantees.
Now let's talk in detail about the
implementation patterns for optimizing
the arm and the risk processes.
Russ lets us combine binaries
that fully exploit the hardware.
So for example.
We can use Garbo features and CFG
attributes to enable the instruction
sets, which are specific to A CPU.
And then the RAs compiler generates a
highly optimized ARCHITE specific binaries
that actually leverage the capabilities
of ARM and the risk P processes, which
eventually leads to a peak performance.
Okay.
Using rust is actually better
as we have some of the drawbacks
of like c programming language
which can be nullified.
One thing is the direct safe control
of the hardware, which is possible
with memory wad hardware, accelerators.
The real world impact of using rust before
and after are mentioned in this slide.
Rust improves with the
memory related crashes.
Also, it reduces the average
inference time to 12.3 milliseconds.
It also helps with the heat dissipation,
issues with cooler operating temperatures,
and it has been instrumental in
extending the battery life by 4.7 years.
Also the mist detection rate has
been reduced to 0.08 percents now.
Rust actually changes this equation
and actually is more capable with
less cost and more reliability.
Some of the key takeaways from today's
session is that Rust and Edge AI will
actually enhance the performance of the
next generation intelligent systems.
Rust is also memory safe without
any compromises, so we can eliminate
in an entire class of bugs.
Without sacrificing performance of
systems programming for mission critical
edge applications, the Rust Edge AI
ecosystem is also rapidly maturing with
high quality of libraries and frameworks.
So there are a lot of opportunities and
alternatives while offering superior
safety guarantees the production
deployments, which you demonstrate trust.
Have advantages of 90% of performance
improvements, 70% of memory
reduction, and 99.9% reliability.
As edge computing continues its
explosive growth, rust is position to
become the foundation of intelligence
systems that combine unprecedented
performance with reliability.
You can always start with rust
on your system by using cargo at
Kind Core Burn and Smart Core.
Please let me know if
you have any questions.
You can reach out to me via chat
and also on my LinkedIn profile.
And once again, thank you to the
organizers of this conference.
Also you, the audience.
Okay.