Hello everyone.
I'm Tashi Kirk.
I am from Juniper Networks and
today we are going to address a
very serious problem in the cloud
infrastructure management, the hidden
limitation of static dashboards.
Dashboards are supposed to be
our eyes into the system, but in
reality so many operate on a delay.
That delay create blind spots,
and those blind spots can cause.
Uptime revenue, trust, a lot of issues.
So in this talk, I will ex,
I'll explain why this happens.
How Rust, help us eliminate those
blind spots with predictable
low latency mon monitoring.
And what happens when the
organization make that shift?
So let's see the agenda for the day.
We will start by looking
at the operational impact
of the static dashboard.
Then I'll explain why Rust
with its concurrency model.
Deterministic performance is ideal
for realtime telemetry processing.
We'll also explore some real word results,
including a large scale case study.
And we'll end with a phase
map for the adoption.
So let's begin with the static the
hidden cost of using static dashboards.
So most static dashboard, they rely
on polling, for example, collecting
data at the fixed interval.
It could be 32nd, it could be one minute.
It depends on the widget.
That we are using the dashboards
that's being deployed.
So now that means that even can happen
well before they appear on the ui.
So that is called the data stillness.
So we, me, we have measured
that across environments.
67% of the network operator reports
detection delays, averaging almost
8.5 minutes from the incident onset.
To the first visibility
to the network operator.
And because most dashboards they
use binary or threshold based health
checks, 73% of the anomalies, like
intermittent packet loss, degraded
latencies, they're never flag at all.
So when we combine staleness with
these missed anomalies, we end up
in a very dangerous blind spots.
So for that, we did they come
this reactive monitoring trap.
So what happens when
these blind spots occurs?
They forces teams into
the reactive pusher.
So reactive pressure is
when you are reacting.
After the act after the incident
occurs, so they respond only when the
issue is already impacting customers.
Statistically reactive monitoring
correlates with 2.8 times more
service disruptions and 7.4
hours of unplanned downtime per
month in the production system.
In contrast to this the event driven
real time dashboards, the kind
that we are talking today, cut that
downtime to 2.1 hours by detecting
issues as they happen to get there.
Though we need a system that can
process massive telemetry volumes
in real time with consistent low
latency, and that's where Rust fits in.
So how does changes everything?
So when we look at the platform
for real time monitoring, two
things are non-negotiable.
One is predictable low latency.
And second is high readability.
Reliability under load and
rust deliver both of them.
So if I keep the points read out the
points, it is zero cost abstraction
that let us push through high throughput
data processing without runtime over.
Memory safety without garbage collection
means there is no unpredictable GC pauses.
When there is a telemetry spike
ownership model and borrower checker
borrow checker that prevents the race
conditions and concurrent workloads.
Compile time guarantees that
eliminates entire classes of
runtime manner like NU D references.
So this combination make Russ uniquely
well suited for latency sensitive
workloads like containers monitoring.
Now the Russ ecosystem, although
the language is very powerful,
but the ecosystem is what?
It makes it completely production ready
to get it to the production stage.
We need maybe Tokyo for asynchronous
runtime, optimized for millions
of concurrent IO bound tasks.
That is perfect for the
telemetry ingestion.
So for zero copy serialization,
decentralization for massive js or proto
or even aro pay payloads act as any low
latency bear framework that can deliver
low live updates to the dashboards or
crossbeam that can have safe fund currency
primitives for multi-core scaling of
these telemetry processing with this type.
We can process millions of
data points per second while
keeping latency under control.
So let's see how this transformational
results the transformational result when
this kind of ecosystem was deployed.
So in a real world deployment
where we are replacing the static
dashboards with the rust powered
event driven system, we saw that
there is almost 63% reduction in MTTR.
So it was from 52 minute.
Down to 19 minutes, there were 37%
improvement for critical incident,
44% fewer operator errors, thanks
to the instant feedback, 31%
less downtime year over year.
And these aren't the
hypothetical improvement.
They come directly from the production
environment, from where the study well,
where these deployments were done.
Going forward let's take a case study
where we have a global financial
service provider with an environment
with almost 12,000 there more than
12,000 instances that are running
across multiple cloud providers.
The problem was faced that.
Almost 11 times average detection
time, 9.4 hours of downtime per month.
So after migrating to a RAs base,
realtime monitoring backend the pro
the process 3.2 million telemetry data
points per second, with less than five
milliseconds of pipeline latency, the
anomalies were detected 65% faster.
The incident detection was reduced
from 11 minutes to 47 seconds,
and the downtime, it was dropped
to almost 2.3 hours per month.
So from 11 minutes sorry, 9.54 minutes.
Two, 2.3 hours per minute per month.
That was a huge difference.
So that's the operational
differences that these real time
make in it's seen in the real time.
So along with Rust, there are
other things that can be done.
There are a lot of emerging trends these
days when we have real time telemetry.
There can be powerful capabilities
that can be added on top of it.
It could be AI driven anomaly detection.
More ML models can be can be added on top
of it that can catch these deviations that
are invisible to those static thresholds.
NLP based query interfaces can be added.
When natural language query interface
is provided, it can translate la
questions in the common language into a
structured telemetry searches, and even
on the ui a more sp more graph based
visualization, more interactive math.
Maybe maps of dependencies that can cut
diagnosis or time over time by over 40%.
So these can be added on top of it,
but the prerequisite, if we consider
is low latency, reliable telemetry
pipeline, which just already enables.
So let's see how we
want to implement this.
So a typical rust power monitoring
stack may include agent layer,
which is lightweight, rust
Aries, maybe less than 15 mbs.
Less than 2% CPO use.
And sending telemetry over GR PCs or web
sockets streaming pipelines that are acing
processing of multi-core parting real time
API layer that can deliver updates to the
dashboard in less than 50 milliseconds.
And then the reactive ui that's where it
is instead of polling it is getting events
from web soc, web sockets, or SSE based
dashboards that can update automatically.
So there, there are three common.
Now while adopting this stack, there
will be three common challenges.
One is.
Integrating with the leg legacy
environment, so that can be solved with
the just FFI or GRPC bridges so that you
don't have to replace everything at once.
The definitely a skill gap that we
can start with one self-contained
component to build confidence.
And then the data volume, the
filter and aggregate or add the
agent before sending data upstream.
So these challenges are real, but
manageable if it is rolled out in stages.
Considering the roadmap, we, it is
always recommended a phased approach.
So in phased approach.
The first month maybe can be for dedicated
for auditing all these blind spot,
defining baseline m TTRs and downtime.
Then couple of months.
To deploy agent in staging, validating
latencies, throughput detection, accuracy.
Post that a quarter maybe in rolling
out to production, integrating
with the incident response tools.
And beyond that it can be dedicated
for all these emerging trends.
Integration like adding ml, anomaly
detection, domain specific visualization.
So adding, doing in a phase
approach will keep the risk low
while proving its value lit early.
The key takeaways is static dashboard.
They create dangerous visibility
caps due to polling delays
and limited anomaly detection.
Rust deterministic performance,
memory, safety concurrency model
make it ideal for building real time
monitoring pipelines in production.
The this translate to faster
detection, fewer errors.
Significant, significantly low downtime.
So Rust Power dashboards aren't
just I would say tech upgrade.
They are more as an operational shift.
They let team move from reacting.
To protecting from, like
firefighting to preventing.
So once we experience this detecting
incident in under a minute, there won't
be no, there won't be any going back.
That's all from my side today.
Thank you.