Welcome everyone.
My name is Ti Patel from DRC system LLC.
Today I will walk you through how Rust
can help solve the problems and the
safety challenges of next generation 5G.
This talks brings together
my experience in system level
architecture and my current research
into rust based network system.
We will begin with the core
performance challenges of 5G.
Then I will explain Rust unique
strength that makes it deal
for the system programming.
We will dive into real world
implementation for traffic management.
I will share the benchmark result
and with the practical techniques
you can use in your work.
5G system requires extremely low
latency under five milliseconds,
and to end the must handle
massive concurrency and maintain.
Near perfect reliability, whether
traditional language like C and c plus
thread memory, safety for speed, which
introduce risk and a safe language like
Java, or go struggle with the real time
guarantee due to garbage collection.
Why traditional approach falls apart.
CNC plus offers speed, but at the
cost of MA safety leading to issue
like a buffer overflows, manual memory
management, slow down development,
and increased bucks language with
the garbage collector like Java and
a go are safer, but unpredictable.
Because of pauses, make them unsuitable.
For the realtime 5G workloads, we need
a solution that's both fast and safe.
That was rust Come in.
Rust unique advantage for the 5G system.
Rust, give us a mammary safety
without a garbage collector.
Thanks to its ownership
model, its zero Cost.
Abstraction mean you get the high level
core with the C. Like performance.
Fearless concurrency is built in rust.
Prevent data, racist.
At compile time and even when you
need low level control, rust unsafe
blocks are scoped and the control
ensuring overall system safety.
Smart network manager architecture.
So here's a Simplifi architecture for
the high performance 5G Traffic manager.
The radio interface layer process packets
are synchronously using zero copy buffer.
The traffic classification engine
uses rust types system for the
compiled time optimized matching
the routing core handle log free
concurrency and the performance mam.
Safe DMA operation for fast, safe routing,
zero copy networking in cc plus.
You have to manually manage
mammary if you forget to free.
You get a leak or crash rust model.
Let us use slices to create a
zero copy views of data safety.
Memory is automatically released
when it goes out of scope.
No leaks, no crashes.
This model help us achieve both
safety and a high throughout.
So there is a, our system achieves
like 4.2 milliseconds, end to end
latency even under heavy load, well
under the five milliseconds target.
We show 300% throughout the gain compared
towards similar c plus implementation.
CPU usage dropped by 65%.
Freeing up resources.
And over 18 months of deployment,
zero mammary safety, P memory
bandwidth improvements.
Rest zero copy techniques greatly reduce
how much data we have moved around
in the mammary that not only increase
speed, but also reduce the strain on
hardware, making it idle for the resource
constrained environment like H devices.
Advancing pattern.
So rust is a sync or a
weight model help us.
The non-blocking code that's
both fast and reliable.
We use the custom custom futures
and the stream combinator to
protect packets efficiently.
Unlike callback based in model
rust approach avoids spaghetti code
with the cutting down memory usage.
Rust type system in a hidden
superpower for performance.
With the compiled time polymorphism,
we write generic code that compiles
into highly optimized routines.
No runtime cost.
The type state pattern and code
app state in a system, eliminating
whole classes of runtime bucks.
Memory safe.
DMA operations DMA is accessed
in traditionally dangerous,
but we can wrap it up.
Safe rest abstraction.
Here we define the DMA buffers struck and
implement cleanup in a safe way using.
The result.
Direct Hardware access with the
safety guarantees sometime previously
only possible with the risky code.
Rest, give us a performance
without compromise, sub family.
Second lesson, latency and a total.
Memory safety, its ownership
model allows for zero copy data.
Race free networking you
can adapt in incrementally.
Start by replacing critical components in
CNC plus system without a full rewrite.
REST is not just a safe language, it's
the next generation system language
that 5G infrastructure demand.
Thank you for listening.
If you would like to dive deeper and
explore collaboration around 5G or
the system, feel free to contact.
Thank you.