Hello everyone.
I am PR Singh, a senior
software in Unit Meta.
Today we are going to talk about something
that's both a technical challenge and a
real world business necessity building
real time AI powered fraud prevention
systems for gate platforms in Rust.
And his exciting part,
this is not just a theory.
I will share some systems that are already
in production, blocking millions in frauds
every month, processing tens of thousands
of transactions per hour, and doing
it within millisecond decision times.
So let's deep dive into it.
So here is our roadmap for today.
We'll start with fraud
challenge in the gig economy.
What makes it so much harder than fraud
in traditional banking or e-commerce?
Then we'll see why Rust, specifically
rust is a perfect fit for solving it.
I will walk you through a multi-layer
architecture that's battle tested, we'll
type div into real world results from
food delivery and ride sharing platforms.
And finally, I will share some emerging
applications where Rust can push
the fraud prevention even further.
By the end, I hope you'll see
why the next generation of fraud
prevention could be written in rust.
So let's look into what's the
gig economy fraud challenge.
Fraud prevention in gig platforms
is a game of millisecond.
Imagine you are ordering food on
DoorDash or booking a ride on Uber.
If our system takes even one 50
millisecond longer than expected
to approve your transaction, you
might abandon the order, or the
driver assignment might time out.
That's a revenue lost instantly.
On top of that, Gigi is hyper
distributed, meaning workers and
customers are scattered across
cities, countries, even continents.
Meaning fraud patterns are geographically
different and constantly evolving.
Payments are instant.
Once the money is sent to a
driver or courier, it's gone.
There is no hold period to investigate
suspicious activity like in banking
and the throughput requirements.
We're talking about AI models
analyzing thousands of transactions
every minute without even choking.
Where is the problem?
The Python, Java, node js, they can work.
These are popular framework, but
under these constraints, they
often force painful trade offs
between a speed and accuracy.
We need both, and that's where
the rust changes the game.
Let's look at the common fraud
pat fraud patterns we have seen.
So fraud frauds are very creative.
And relentless.
Let's look at a few common attack patterns
that we have seen in gig platforms.
So one commonly is known as account
takeover, where attackers buy leaked
credentials and brute force their way
into legitimate systems or accounts.
Synthetic identity is another type.
Think of it as a Frank Tine
accounts, it stitch together
from real and fake details.
Another one is work
worker customer collusion.
A driver and a customer work together
to fake trips or deliveries, another one
called GPSS spoofing or geo spoofing,
where they fake their location to get
better jobs or to trick the payout system.
And finally, another type is payment
method fraud, where stolen credit
cards are used for instant payouts.
And here is the scary part.
Fraud tactics evolve
weekly, sometimes daily.
A fraud ring can exploit your platform,
make hundreds of fraudulent transactions
and vanish before your old detection
rules even notice something is wrong.
That's why our system have to be fast,
adaptive, and accurate all at once.
So why rust for fraud prevention?
So there are three big regions
for that first memory, safety
without garbage collection.
Fraud prevention systems
are security critical.
A buffer overflow, or use after
free bug is not just a crash.
It could be an exploit.
Rust eliminates those classes of
bug at compile time without runtime.
GC pauses.
Second c plus labor performance.
As we know, c plus is very
popular programming language.
So Rust has geo cost abstraction.
It has multiple L-L-M-V-M optimization.
You can hit near c plus speed while
writing safer and more expressive code.
Third, fearless concurrency.
The ownership and the borrowing
model prevents data races by design.
That means we can confidently run
fraud checks on many concurrent
transactions without corrupting the
shared estate in sort the rust gives
us a speed, safety and scalability.
The trifecta for prevention.
Let's look at the performance results.
In production benchmarks from a
major food delivery company, rust
reached 93% of c plus raw performance.
It was 6.2 times faster than Java and 2.4
times faster than Python with TensorFlow.
What is the P 90 latency Under
35 millisecond consistently.
And these are not just a synthetic test.
Even CPU ation was dropped
by 90% compared to Python.
These are real world numbers from a live
fraud perform fraud prevention pipeline.
And why and when you multiply tho that
efficiency across thousands of request
per second, the cost savings are huge.
Let's look at a multilayered
rust architecture.
So our rust based architecture
uses five layers mainly.
One real time stream processing where
Tokyo ingest transaction streams
and process them asynchronously
cutting latency dramatically.
Second rule-based detection.
Simple if else rules and fr
on pattern matching for known
fraud signals are sufficient.
Think if same card used in
three countries in one hour.
Flag it.
Third statistical OMA detection
time series models to spot unusual
spikes or dips in user behavior.
ML classification candle deep learning
models used with code exhalation
for GP inference, graph analysis pet
graph algorithm to detect sources,
clusters of users working together.
Each layer acts as a safety net.
Catching what others might miss.
Let's look at Rust Power in innovations.
Two things made a huge difference here.
Async Stream processing with Tokyo,
which lets us handle thousands of events
per second with almost no idle time.
And the second zero copy digitalization
with ade, which passes J or proto
above straight from bytes without
extra memory allocations on their own.
These are nice to haves, but in real time
fraud pipeline, they are the difference
between hitting your SLA or missing
it by 30 millisecond and losing money.
You can look at the some code snippet
here that have attached in this slide.
That you can use directly in your
code to use these frameworks.
Let's look at ML inference with candle.
If you have used PyTorch candle will
feel very familiar very familiar.
It's a pure rushed ML framework.
Supports ONNX, imports from PyTorch
or TensorFlow, and runs on cuda
and metal For GP insurance, the
best part, no python in production.
That means the whole fraud detection
pipeline is memory safe from end to end.
No language boundaries, no GIL.
No extra process overhead.
Isn't that amazing?
Let's look into graph
analysis with pet graph.
So as we know, fraud does not
always happen in isolation.
It's often coordinated.
Pet graph lets us map out.
Transaction graphs and run
algorithms to find what one connected
components, two centrality scores.
Three.
Structural similarities
over time, one real case.
32 drivers and 18 customers ran
a fake order scam for weeks where
a standard ML models missed it.
The graph analysis from
PET Graph caught it.
Isn't that amazing?
I have linked a code snippet here
again for you, for your reference.
Let's move on.
Privacy preserving techniques.
We can't fight fraud at
the expense of privacy.
In rust, we have implemented
homomorphic encryption, computational
encrypted data t learning, which
is like training across devices
without centralizing sensitive data.
Differential privacy, which is adding
control noise to protect identities.
Secure incls, which is running code
in hardware isolated environments.
And thanks to Rust performance, these are
not just slow, they're production ready.
Let's look at the guide
sharing case study here.
A right sharing platform was losing around
$3.2 million per month to Jupe spoofing
or GPS spoofing and fake identities.
We replaced their Python fraud stack
with rusted microservices, for example,
used Tokyo for Async, STTP, custom
device fingerprinting and rust,
WASM modules for distributed rules.
And we used candle for ML inference.
What's the result?
87% less fraud loss, 65% fewer
false positives enforcements.
And 99.98% uptime of
services over 12 months.
Isn't that unbelievable?
Let's look next at emerging applications.
So what's next?
So these are the four use cases that
we can use for us, and I think the
way rust can shape the industry.
So one is behavioral bi biometrics
typing, swiping motion patterns as
continuous authentication are possible.
Now with rust explainable AI
pipelines, which are under 12
to six to 12 months of pipeline.
In the roadmap, you can have sap
lime in rust for transparent fraud
decision, advanced fully homomorphic
encryption, also known as advanced
FHE, which is like 12 to 24 months in
the roadmap which for making a privacy
preserving fraud detection practical.
A NA native GPU acceleration, which is
around two plus years in the roadmap
where rust, GP, U, and candle can
be used for even faster inference.
So what are the key takeaways?
There are three main
key takeaways from this.
So one, performance matters.
So Rust gives us C plus label
speed and developer productivity.
Second, safety is non-negotiable.
Memory, safety and race free
concurrency reduces risks.
And third, the ecosystem is ready.
Tokyo Candle, pet Craft are
production proven ready today.
So thank you.
Let's build a safer
gig platforms together.
Thank you for listening.