Hello everyone.
My name is Shaka and I am a
supply chain professional.
I currently work at Meta Platforms as a
supply chain solutions program manager.
Today we are going to dive deep
into a topic that is at the
forefront of modern logistics,
transforming supply chain performance
through digital twin technology.
This isn't just about buzzwords, it's
about creating a virtual real time replica
of our entire physical supply chain.
This digital twin allows us to
stimulate, predict, and optimize
every aspect of our operations
with incredible accuracy and speed.
To achieve this, our approach
is built on two key pillars.
First, we'll explore advanced route
optimization, which goes far beyond simple
GPS, adapting in real time to traffic,
weather, and other unforeseen events.
And second, we'll discuss the power
of a rust powered infrastructure.
A choice we made for its superior
performance, security, and reliability,
which is essential for handling the
immense data generated by a digital twin.
Our ultimate goal is to present
a comprehensive cutting edge
strategy for truly revolutionizing
global supply chain networks.
Okay, great.
Let's walk through our roadmap for today.
Our agenda is designed to
guide you through a complex
digital transformation journey.
We'll start with the fundamentals
and build up to practical
real world application.
First, we'll lay the groundwork by
exploring the digital twin foundations.
We'll define exactly what this technology
is, how it functions, and why it's
becoming the cornerstone for every
supply chain management and delivering
unprecedented operational improvements.
And next, we'll dive into
key components of the system,
variance based route optimization.
This is a critical departure
from traditional methods.
Instead of just optimizing for the fastest
route, we'll look at strategies that
prioritize predictability and consistency.
This approach dramatically improves
shipment tracking accuracy and reduces
the frustrating surprises that come
with unpredictable transit times.
Then we'll talk about the underlying
engine that makes all of this possible
a rust powered infrastructure.
And I'll explain why we choose this
specific language for its memory,
safety, and speed, which allows our
system to process massive volumes
of high velocity data with micro
speed precision a non-negotiable
requirement for real time digital twins.
And finally, we'll bring it all together
with a look at implementation and ROI.
This is where we get practical.
We'll cover the data integration
requirements, the importance of change
management, and most importantly.
We'll show you how to measure
a substantial and documented
return on your investment.
And by the end of this session, you'll
have a clear understanding of not just
the technology, but how also leading
organizations are using this to achieve
transformative results with real world
case studies and documented metrics.
Alright?
All right.
Now let's talk about how this
technology is fundamentally changing
the way we manage our operations.
Yes, we are moving beyond the traditional
supply chain control tower, which
often just provides a dashboard of
historical data and into a new era
powered by digital twin technology.
Think of a digital twin as living,
breathing, virtual replica of
your entire physical supply chain.
It's not just a static model.
It's a dynamic, real-time representation
that enables unprecedented visibility and
control and the results for organizing.
Organizations implementing this
are tangible and measurable.
First, let's look at time to market
reduction by building a digital twin,
companies can now stimulate new product
launches and test different supply
chain configurations in a virtual
environment before ever committing
to a physical implementation.
This allows them to identify and resolve
bottlenecks in a matter of hours, not
months leading to product launches.
That are an incredible 30 to 45% faster.
This leads directly to significant design
and development savings by identifying
and mitigating supply chain constraints
virtually things like capacity limitations
or sourcing risks we can avoid.
Costly physical companies are also
seeing average cost reductions of about
two to five millions on new product.
In introductions alone, it's like having
a crystal ball for your supply chain.
And finally, the impact on
operational efficiency is profound.
The digital twin powered by AI allows for
continuous automated scenario planning.
It can dynamically reallocate resources,
optimize transportation lanes, and
adjust inventory levels in real time,
resulting in a 15 to 25% improvement
in overall resource utilization.
Ultimately, this is a paradigm shift.
We are moving away from
the reactive model.
Where we spend our time putting out fires
to predictive one, where real time digital
replicas enable continuous optimization
and automated exception handling
often before an issue even arises.
Okay, let's move from a
theory to concrete example.
This case study focuses on a real
world problem optimizing global
maritime shipping routes for years.
Traditional route optimization focused on
just two things, finding the fastest path
or the cheapest path, but our work with
leading global shippers shows that this
isn't the whole story we have discovered.
What truly delivers superior outcomes is
variance based route optimization, which
prioritize consistency over sheer speed.
This means we're not just looking
for the route that gets there
in the least amount of time.
But the route that gets there in the most
predictable amount of time every single
time, and the results are powerful.
First, this approach improved
shipment tracking accuracy by 37%.
When you can really predict when a
shipment will arrive, your tracking
data becomes far more accurate.
This predictability enables precise
inventory planning, and crucially
allows you to significantly reduce the
need for an expensive safety stock.
Our advanced algorithms were able
to identify entire shipping lanes
with a 42% lower transit variance,
even when their average transit
times were similar to other routes.
This means we found routes that
were simply more reliable and the
financial impact is substantial.
A Fortune 500 manufacturer was able
to achieve about 3.2 million in
annual savings simply by being able
to reduce it safe safety stock levels.
A direct result of more predictable
and consistent deliveries.
This level of optimization is only
possible with sophisticated digital twin
models that can simulate thousands of
route permutations while accounting for
a historical variance not just average
transit times, it's a game changer for
building resilience and inefficiency.
All right, moving on.
Let's talk about the key
capabilities of Rust.
First, let's look at Rust Score strength.
Starting with a memory safety, a
major source of bugs in software
comes from how it manages memory.
Rusts unique ownership model virtually
eliminates these bugs for supply chain
monitoring applications, which are often
left for run for months or even years.
This is a huge deal.
We can avoid the kind of gradual memory
leaks that cause systems to slow down
or crash, ensuring our applications
are cons, consistently reliable.
Next we have zero cost abstractions.
This is one of rusts
most impressive features.
It means we can write code that is
clean and high level, easy to read
and manage, but compli, but compiles
down to the same level of performance
as a low level language like C.
This lets us execute complex algorithms
with minimum overhead, which is
essential when you're trying to optimize
logistics and route planning on the fly.
Third.
Rust offers fearless concurrency.
The modern supply chain is a whirlwind
of data, especially from iot sensors.
We're talking about high velocity data
streams from thousands of touch points.
Rust makes this possible to
write multi-threaded code that
is completely free of data races.
This is a game changer for processing
massive amounts of data concurrently,
allowing us to keep up with the pace
of real time global supply chain.
And finally, the cross
platform development.
And this is about versatility.
Rust can compile to web assembly,
which means a rust powered analytics
and applications can run efficiently
on everything from tiny, low
powered, embedded shipping sensors
to powerful cloud data centers.
This allows us to have a consistent
and efficient code base across the
entire infrastructure from the smallest
decide device to a largest server.
So what does this all
mean for the organization?
These capabilities make rust
uniquely suited for supply chain
applications that demand both
extreme reliability and performance.
While Python is fantastic and
popular language for data science
and prototyping, organizations are
increasingly MA making a strategic shift.
They're moving to a hybrid architecture
where Python is used for initial data
analysis, but final mission critical
production services where failure simply
isn't an option, are built in rust.
Okay, now let's get a bit more technical
and look at how rusts architecture
directly benefits the organization.
Rusts ownership model is powered
is a powerful concept for 24 by
seven supply chain operations.
It eliminates memory leaks by
managing the lifespan of data.
Let's look at a simple example.
Imagine a function that processes
data from a container in the code.
When the process container data
function is called, it takes
ownership of the container object.
This means that once the function
is finished, rusts compiler
guarantees that the container
is automatically de allocated.
This prevents a common class of bugs
where memories accidentally used after
it's been freed, which is a major cost
of crashes in a long running system.
It's a critical feature for all the
always on monitoring applications.
Next, let's talk about the trade.
System.
This feature enables to create a
modular and interchangeable component
for things like route optimization
without any performance cost At runtime.
Consider a scenario where we have multiple
ways to optimize a shipping route.
We can define a route optimizer, optimizer
trade, which is like a blueprint for what?
A route optimizer we must do.
This rate simply states that any route
optimizer must have an optimized method.
Okay, we can then create different
implementations of the straight,
such as variance based optimizer
and then swap them out as needed.
The key here is that because of
how rust compiles this, there
is no or zero runtime overhead.
The compiler knows exactly which version
of the optimized function to use at
compile time, so we get a flexibility
of a high level object oriented design
without any performance penalty.
The end result of this approach is a
new class of systems that can achieve
microsecond level precision and maintain
incredible reliability even under the
most extreme op operational loads.
This is the kind of technological
foundation needed for model modern
digital twin implementations and other
next generation supply chain solutions.
All right.
Okay, now we'll quickly cover
the three core pillars of a
successful digital twin development.
First data integration.
A digital twins power comes from its data.
We need to connect thousands of data
sources from ERP systems to IOT sensors.
Processing over 10,000
data points per second.
Rust synchronous runtime makes this
real time high volume integration
possible, giving us a compile
holistic view of the supply chain.
Second.
Algorithm optimization data is useless.
Without smart algorithms.
We have seen a 25, 20 7% improvement
in predictive maintenance by
using high performance pipelines.
This is achieved through techniques like
parallel processing and GPU acceleration
for complex modeling, which allows
us to act on insights with precision.
Third, change management
technology is only half the battle.
A successful deployment
requires an organization.
Organizational transformation and all
our data shows that focusing on this
pillar leads to a 92% success rate.
To achieve this through skills training,
process redesign, starting with the
phased implementation to build momentum
and buy-in, and the most successful
implementations blend technical excellence
with organizational transformation.
By excelling in all these three areas,
one can achieve about 3.2 times greater
ROI from the digital twin project.
Yes, start with the small, highly
visible process, high visibility
process to demonstrate value and get
the entire organization on board.
All right, moving on.
To illustrate the power of digital twins,
let's look at a case study from a leading
global supply global shipping company.
The company needed to reduce operational
costs and envi environmental impact.
While improving delivery reliability
across this fleet of 1 47 container
vessels, their solution was a
digital twin platform powered
by rust based edge computing.
This system provided real-time
monitoring of over 1200 parameters
per vessel, enabling, dynamic route
optimization, predictive maintenance,
and AI powered fuel efficiency.
This architecture relied on rusts
performance and reliability achieving.
A five millisecond processing time
for critical data and almost a
hundred percent system uptime and
a small eight MB memory footprint.
Critically, its efficient data
compression, reduced satellite
transmission costs by 76 percents.
What were the results?
The implementation led to a significant
measurable improvement, operational
cost reduction, about 18%, fuel
efficiency improvements about 12%.
Reduced maintenance downtime above 32%.
This case study demonstrates that a
well-designed digital twin blending
excellence with a clear business
strategy can lead transformative
results in a demanding environment.
Alright, the digital twin market
in the supply chain is growing
rapidly at A-C-H-E-R of about
37.4%, driven by the need for
greater efficiency and resilience.
Organizations that daily implementation
risk falling behind is early adopters
need a powerful compounding advantage.
From the data, the most forward
thinking organizations are now
combining digital twins with emerging
technologies to unlock new capabilities.
Quantum computing integration is
leading to a 93% reduction in complex
system calibration time with rust
serving as the foundation of these
hybrid algorithms, machine learning.
Advanced machine learning models
built on rusts ecosystem are achieving
about 47% higher reception prediction
accuracy than traditional methods.
The early movers are developing
capabilities that were
impossible just 24 months ago.
This integration of digital twins
with these advanced technology
technologies represent the next frontier
in the supply chain optimization.
The time to act is now.
All right.
Let's look at the measurable ROI
of digital twin implementation
highlighting key three areas.
First one is real time optimization.
By using real time data and predictive
analytics, we can achieve a 21%
reduction in inventory holding costs.
This is a quick win with an implementation
timeframe of four to six months and a
payback period of just nine to 12 months.
Second one is transportation
and analytics.
The rust implemented dynamic routing
algorithms process over 50,000
permutations per second, resulting in a
17% reduction in transportation costs.
The project has a fast payback of six
to eight months for the long term.
Advanced analytics deliver about a 42%
improvement in forecast accuracy with
the payback of about 10 to 14 months.
Third one, the compounding effect.
These benefits are not one-time gains.
As the digital twins learn, we see
an additional 70 12% performance
and improvement year over year.
The key to maximizing this ROI
is a comprehensive measurement
framework aligned with the
business goals from day one.
Alright, all right.
Here's a proven 18 month roadmap for a
successful digital twin implementation.
Broken down into four key phases,
phase number one, months one to three.
The foundation.
This phase is all about
building a solid base.
We'll select a technology
stack, including rust.
Define the project scope, identify a pilot
process for initial development, phase two
months, four to six, initial development.
Here we execute on a limited scope,
launching a first digital twin.
We integrate core data from systems
E-R-P-W-M-S, et cetera, develop basic
simulations and start gathering user.
Feedback.
Third phase months, seven
to 12, which is expansion.
This phase is about scaling up.
We'll deploy IOTs sensors for realtime
data, improved advanced rust algorithms,
and establish a central control tower.
This is also when we'll perform our
first major ROI measurement and last
phase months, 13 to 18 optimization.
In the final phase, we move
towards a fully optimized system.
And enhance capabilities
with AI and machine learning.
Integrating external partners for
full visibility and work towards
fully autonomous optimization.
This structured approach balances quick
wins with long-term goals, leading to
about a 2.7 times higher success rate.
And remember to maintain executive
sponsorship and focus on robust change
management throughout the journey.
Alright.
To conclude, let's review the
key takeaways and outline a clear
path forward for the organization.
Digital technology.
Digital twin technology is transformative.
Digital twins are delivering
documented improvement in time to
market and operational efficiency,
offering unprecedented visibility
and control, variance based
optimized optimization performance.
Focusing on consistency over speed,
deliver superior results with about a
37% improvement in tracking accuracy
and significant cost reductions.
RUS provides the essential
technical foundation.
Its unique features like memory,
safety and fearless concurrency
enabled next generation infrastructure
that processes high velocity data.
With microsecond level
precision implementation
requires a holistic approach.
Success depends on excellence
in data integration, algorithm
optimization, and change management.
Organizations that excel in all
three achieve a 3.2 x greater ROI.
Here are the five immediate, actionable
next steps for any organization.
Conduct a digital maturity assessment.
Identify your organization's readiness.
Identify high value pilot opportunities.
Select a manageable project with clear
KPIs and measurable ROI Potential.
And develop a technical skills
roadmap, acquired the necessary
rest programming capabilities to
support the new infrastructure.
Establish data governance framework,
ensure data quality, security, consistency
for successful initiatives, and lastly,
create an executive steering committee,
establish leadership to guide and
support the transformation efforts.
Hopefully this session was helpful
to Y all, and thank you so much.