Good morning everyone.
My name is, and I'm a resource
driven IT professional.
With over 12 years of expertise
in software industry, my career
has been dedicated to ensuring
the reliability, performance, and
compliance of enterprise applications
across critical industries, including
telecommunications and healthcare.
Currently as a lead technician at
Spectrum, I swear, head software
initiatives for billing systems.
Validate so plus a PS and design
UI UX workforce, leveraging tools
like Postman sql, no SQL databases
and automation frameworks.
My work directly supports CICD
pipeline and Agile in ensuring seamless
integration and high impact solutions.
Previously.
Alert software efforts for Medicaid
chip systems under Department of Health
and Human Services for South Carolina
and IBM Vera Ensure HIPAA compliance
and federal data hub integrations.
Demonstrating my depth and
regularly demands with proficiency
in automation, defect tracking,
and cross-function collaborations.
I bridge technical and business needs
to deliver robust software solutions to
my portfolio includes 200 plus technical
documentation and thousand plus automation
revision suites and scalable testing
strategies that reduce the risk and
accelerate delivery accelerate delivery.
And I had a master's degree from
the University of New Haven, and
I'm passionate about mentoring
teams and driving driving
innovation in software practices.
I'm excited to share my insights from
experience and explore how we can
solve complex challenges together.
This is the this is about building
rust power AI for telecom from
reactive to predictive systems.
Today as we are driving into
transformative shift into
telecommunications, we are rush forward.
AI is turning reactive network management
into proactive predictive systems.
Imagine a world where outer is separated
and prevented before even customer notice.
This isn't science fiction.
It's happening right now.
The rust is the answer
here to make it possible.
Where cutting gate technologies
meets real world impact.
Let's explore how
revolutionary is unfolding it.
Yeah, today's agenda is how he's our
today's agenda, the telecom challenge.
Why today's break fix model is broken.
The second one, the rust.
How a language designed for safety and
speed solves decades, all problems.
The real world implementations from
anomaly detection to predicting cell
tower failures, and now about the
integration challenges, the gritty
reality of merging AI with legacy systems.
The fifth one is future roadmap.
How to face this into operations.
Why does this even matter?
Because every minute of downtime
costs silicon communication on
average of $5,600 per minute.
The stakes are high and
the solution is here.
The telecom challenges today.
So let's confirm the harsh
reality of today's networks.
72 percent's fault detection means 28% of
the issues slip through silently degrading
the services of the telecommunication,
sir, 3.7 hours for MTTR.
Picture a hospital losing connectivity
during an emergency every minute counts.
80% of today's are planned outages
where like mechanics changing on a
schedule where the engine is already
overheating all kinds of things, which
is the root cause, the fragmented tools.
Engineers today tools are
between 80 years to 12, 80 to 12.
Systems wasting 20 plus hours weekly
on manual correlation reactive mindset
alerts, fire after customers complying.
I worked with a European carrier last
year who discovered that 40% of their
sudden outages had clear procedures
like memory leaks or temperature spikes
visible in the tele data days in advance.
But without ai, no one connected the dots.
Now the cost is that's
the cost of reactivity.
Why rust for telecommunication ai?
Rust is in just another language.
It's a paradigm shift.
Let's break down why it is a
perfect for telecommunication.
We have the memory safety
garbage collectors in Java.
Python causes latency spikes
like 200 milliseconds.
Pauses us in telecommunication
industry thus enough to miss
a critical failure signal.
The RUS ownership model
elements, the elements.
This one, the real world
example, is a tire one.
Carrier company reduced elemental
processing from one 50 milliseconds
to millisecond to milliseconds
by switching it to rust.
The features of concurrency, traditional
threading leads to race conditions.
Rust Comply forces threat safety.
A case study saying that the processing 10
million data points per second across 50
threats with zero deadlocks, the zero cost
attractions for this particular thing.
CC plus risk level
speeding without crashes.
But benchmark of the rust process upward.
Hundred GB of network lags in 22
seconds versus python's eight minutes.
That is where the real difference
is the strong type system.
The compile time checks are caught.
A caught a critical API mismatch in
a billing system integration that
would cost a 2 million in NRS changes.
A fun fact about this whole thing is.
Most love language on Stack Overflow has
been for over the seven, eight years.
Why?
Because it's runtime disasters in compiled
time errors for telecommunication.
That's the difference between a hiccup
and a headline marking making outages.
This is about the performance
metrics, whether the traditional
implementation let's talk the numbers.
The slide compares rust power,
AI to the legacy systems.
The fall detection 92% was a 72% catching.
There's 20% more issues means
fewer midnight emergencies.
And PTR 47 minutes was a 3.7 hours.
That's a three hour save per incident.
The three hour save per incident,
customer searching down by 1.2%,
which translate to $8 million and
a year for a mid-size carrier.
One client said, why not just scale our
existing Python system as we tested it?
It's 5,000 requests per second,
their Python service cluster, but
the rust handle 85,000 requests
per second on the same hardware.
Sometime the tool is bottleneck.
The last powered AI algorithms.
This is about this thing.
The two algorithms are the game changers.
The first one is isolation forests.
How it works is randomly isolates.
Anomal is, instead of profiling
normal behavior think is it's like a
folding haystack and elevating hay.
It's detecting as A-D-D-O-S attacks
in, in three seconds by spotting
irregular traffic patterns, LSTs,
these neural networks predict failures.
By remembering patterns over time.
So this is the main, key
thing in this whole thing.
An example, a cell tower.
Power supplies typically de
degrades over six months.
The LSTM flag once failing for
every two weeks, saving almost
a 200 K in replacement costs.
See the real fear and the whole
kicker is the rust speeds.
Let us run these models
in line with data streams.
No batch crossing Python would need
15 times more servers to keep up with
this 500 K in year on this cloud as
its cost has been saved, particularly
using this rust techno rust language.
Thus this slide seven case a case
study about predictive maintenance
of the cell tower led zoom into North
American carrier results the 25 tb. Per
day of data from 5,000 cell tower cell
towers eco into 10 years of Netflix
streaming the LSDM predictions, the
flagged falling hardware 14 days in
advance with 89% accuracy results, which
in turns result to 60% fewer outages
and 42% fewer truckloads saving on
an average of $1.2 million in a year.
This is the best part where the NOCT went
from firefighting to strategic planning.
One engineer told me that
finally feel like I'm preventing
disasters, not layering them up.
That's a cultural transformation
in this telecom industry.
The next slide slows about the
unified pla platform architecture
in this particular thing.
So here is how the sausage.
Gets mo gets more, gets made.
So collection adapters, Russ normalize
the data from eight to 12 legacy
systems into a unified format.
Then the message bus, the message
base zero copied design moves
a five B in an hour with the
overhead of pass post-it note.
So explainability layer.
Where the engineers get plain English
insights like Transformer 42 fails
70% of the time during peak loads.
Now we can notice that in 1990,
Sarahs a Sonet system or rust, FFI,
the foreign function interface.
Lets let us wrap.
Its c code safety.
No re rewrite needed.
The client called it a time
machine for their stacks.
That's back in 1990s.
Era.
This are implementation challenges.
So no transformation in painless,
so it's always integration
Challenges are already there.
Here, how we can tackle this hurdles.
So the legacy integration, so use
plus FFI to wrap COBOL billing
systems, there's a tip there.
A first testing caught a memory
leak that would crash production.
And next is the data quality.
Rest scripts autofill, missing
timestamps using Marco chains.
And the next one is the black box sphere
added to y button next to every a alert.
That's how it is showing the
top three contributing factors.
A CTO once asked me how could
I sell this to my board?
The answers straightforward.
The straightforward, start with the
pilot on a non-critical towards.
When they saw 40% reduction in outages,
the budget approval took 10 minutes.
It just took 10 minutes.
No.
The next one is about the workflow
evolution of the operational rules.
So AI won't replace any engineers.
It redefines the roles before
the manual log scripting for the
outage triage after this one, the
20 motors and turning algorithms.
Once a team automated 80% of
the repetitive task instead of
layoffs they upskill everyone.
Their job satisfaction score jumped 30%.
Happiness engineers fix problems
faster than the regular one.
The next slide is about
the implementation roadmap.
Of particularly, there are four
steps in this implementation.
The phase one is about
the data foundation.
Deploy rust collectors.
It's a tip in instrument like one
tower type, first example 4G only.
The phase two is anomaly detection.
Use isolation for us to find quick wins.
Its example is a power supplies,
a faulty power supplies.
The phase three is predictive models,
training LS teams on historical failures.
Caution, start with a non-safety
critical system, sir, and coming
to the phase four is automation.
Auto restart.
Failed notes with, without an
even human oversight client.
As an example, a client faced this
over 18 months by six 18 months,
but by six, the ROI was 2.3 million
from reduced truck roll alone.
The boat the fast truck, the
whole thing the whole thing.
The next one is thank you.
Good.