Hello everyone.
My name is Shay Ter, and I'm
a director at United Lake.
Today I'm excited to talk about a
modern approach to web analytics
and business intelligence.
We are going to dive into how
we can build high performance
user-centric dashboards using Rust.
We will see how Rust can let us
deliver better user experience
through speed and reliability.
Before we get into the technology,
let me give you a quick background on
why I'm passionate about this topic.
I'm the director of IP Strategy
and Technology at United Lakes.
I'm based in Austin, Texas, in
the United States of America.
I lead the IP data science
team where we create innovative
solutions at the intersection of
intellectual property and technology.
I have been included in the I Am Strategy
300, a list of world's top IP strategists.
One of the products that our team
has developed is Vantage for I. It is
a patent intelligence platform that
processes hundreds and thousands of
patents using natural language processing.
It provides competitive
intelligence, evaluates patent
strengths, and uncovers licensing
opportunities amongst other things.
Two of my key focus areas are developing
deep learning models to e evaluate
patents and designing user friendly
platforms to convey those results.
So what exactly are the
challenges with modern dashboards?
I think we all have experienced this.
You open a dashboard with a lot of
data and it's slow, it's sluggish.
It's a frustrating user experience.
The root cause is often a
combination of three key issues.
Performance bottlenecks.
Heavy data processing and calculations
are typically done in JavaScript,
which is an interpreted language.
This leads to slow rendering and
poor user experience, security
risk, JavaScript, dynamic nature can
introduce vulnerabilities, running
complex, and sometimes untrusted code
in a browser opens the application
to various attacks, wasted resources.
Inefficient code and frequent
data transfers create a heavy load
on both the client, CPU and the
server wasting valuable resources.
So the question is, how do we
solve these problems without
sacrificing the flexibility
and richness of the modern web?
The answer is a perfect partnership.
Okay.
The perfect partnership of rest
and was, this is where the magic
happens, an incredible combination
of rest and web assembly or valve.
They work together to address
every one of those challenges.
Let's first talk about rust.
It feels like I'm preaching to the CO
as everyone here is familiar with the
benefit that trust brings to the table.
Yet for the sake of completeness, let
me highlight a few unmatched memory,
safety, rust ownership and borrowing
model eliminates entire classes of
bugs like null pointers and databases.
This isn't just stability,
it's a huge security win.
Zero cost abstractions, rust gives
us powerful high level features like
iterators and closures, but without
the performance overhead, you'd expect.
You get the best of both worlds built
for concurrency, rust type system makes
writing safe, parallel code much easier.
This is a game changer for
processing large data sets.
Now let's take a moment to understand what
web assembly is because it's the bridge
that brings rust power to the browser.
Web assembly isn't a new programming
language, it's a compilation target.
Think of it as the assembly
language of the web.
VSM is a low level binary format
for a stack based virtual machine.
It's what you compile languages
like rust, c plus, or going to.
Vast runs at speed that are almost as
fast as native code, which is a massive
performance jump for computation.
Heavy tasks compared to traditional
JavaScript VA modules run in a
secure, isolated environment.
This is crucial because it means a buggy
or malicious was module can't access the
rest of your webpage or the user system.
So how does we combine these
two technologies in practice?
Let's walk through the workflow.
The workflow is surprisingly
straightforward.
You don't have to rewrite your
entire application In rust.
We can be selective and strategic.
Write the core logic in rust.
This is the most important step.
Identify the performance critical.
Parts of your dashboard, data
aggregation, complex, filtering,
heavy calculations, and write those
specifically in rust compile to M.
Use a tool like Mack.
It's a key part of the process that
handles all the lift heavy lifting,
creating a web assembly file and
a JavaScript glue that allows your
front end to talk to the vast module.
Import and use the existing JavaScript.
Frontend simply imports the vast
module from the JavaScript perspective.
It just another library, but it's a
library that performs computationally
intensive tasks at near native speed.
Visualize with JavaScript existing
UI frameworks like React or View
can still be used for rendering.
The rust valve part is the high
performance engine under the hood.
JavaScript part is the
user interface on top.
This approach leads to a
clear, layered architecture.
We can think of this as a
three layer architecture.
Each layer has a specific job,
and rust plays a key role.
In the first two data
layer is the foundation.
This is where you use rust to connect to
data sources, manage memory efficient data
structures, and build type safe queries.
This ensures data is handled
correctly and quickly from the
very beginning processing layer.
This is where rust power
shine really shines.
This layer handles parallel data
processing, statistical analysis and
data transformation visualization layer.
This is the front end.
This layer uses high speed
output from the processing layer
to render charts and tables.
This is where you can leverage web
assembly for browser rendering on
native visualization for desktop apps,
this layered approach is only possible
because of the incredible rust ecosystem.
Rust community has built an
amazing ecosystem of libraries.
For each layer of our
architecture, there are robust and
well-maintained crates available.
Libraries like SQL X can be used
for database interaction and
polars for fast data frames.
Then libraries like Rayon can
be used for easy parallelism and
NDRA for numerical computation.
VA Mine Gen is the Last Rust
Library designed to facilitate
high level interactions between
VA modules and JavaScript plotters
for generating charts and tari.
If you're building a desktop, applications
theory is great, but look, let's look at
some real world examples of this inaction.
These are not just small projects,
these are major applications.
The challenge for Figma
was real-time multiplayer.
They needed to handle complex
synchronization for multiple users.
While technically not an analytics
dashboard, it has a lot of similarities.
Essentially, it requires processing
real time data and presenting visual
components in a smooth manner.
Their solution was to rewrite their
code multiplayer engine in rust.
The results were astounding, a
3.8 x reduction in memory usage
and six x reduction in CPU usage.
This proves that rust isn't just
for small optimizations, it's
for mission critical code logic.
Our next example is about a
graph visualization, which was
running at less than 10 frames
per second on heavy desktops.
This graph shows the relationship
between different artists on Spotify.
Spotify provides this data
directly from their API.
Users can click on an artist, see
related artist, or drag an artist node
and view other nodes, move together.
The user experience was shareable.
The solution was to move the heavy
calculations to rest and web assembly.
The result, the exact same
visualizations now run at 60 frames
per second, even on mobile devices.
That's a massive difference
for the end user.
Finally, in the world of financial
applications, processing massive data sets
with billions of rows is a common problem.
Data Bento provides real-time and
historical market data to its users.
They were struggling to process and
analyze large data sets with ease, which
would allow for timely and data-driven
decisions in response to market changes.
The solution was polars, a data
frame library written in rust.
Its performance is incredible.
Which benchmarks?
Showing it out outperforms pandas by
eight to 15 x. It's a game changer for
data wrangling and visualizing at scale.
Speaking of visualizations, let's look
at some of rush libraries that you
can use to build these dashboards.
As mentioned earlier, visualization
can continue to be in JavaScript.
However, the ecosystem of Rust
Visualization libraries is growing
and we already have some excellent
choices for visualization.
Plotters is a low level, powerful
library for plotting data.
Its versatile and can
output to various formats.
Charming is a great option.
If you're a fan of Apache Echarts,
it's provide a user-friendly
declarative rust, API on top of the
wok powerful JavaScript library.
Plotly is an option for more scientific
and statistical visualizations, leveraging
the extensive feature set of lead js.
Now that we have covered
the technical side.
Let's remember the most important part
of building a grad grade dashboard.
The user
performance and security are
vital, but a dashboard is only
successful if it's useful and usable.
We have to balance technical
excellence with thoughtful design.
Let's review some of the
key design principles.
Know your audience.
This is the most critical principle.
Before designing anything, you
must understand who the users
are, what their goals are, and
what decisions they need to make.
A CEO's dashboard will look
very different from an analyst.
Keep it simple.
Dashboard should be easy
to understand at a glance.
Avoid clutter and unnecessary visuals.
Use a clear, logical layout and
a consistent visual language.
The users should be able to
find what they need without
extensive searching or training.
Provide context, data points on
their own are often meaningless.
A good dashboard provides context
by showing data against a benchmark,
a time series, or a key performance
indicator with its target.
This help, this helps users
quickly interpret the information
and understand its significance.
Prioritize information.
All data is created equal.
Use visual hierarchy to guide the
user's attention to the most important
information First, this can be achieved
through size, placement, and color.
The most critical metrics should be
front and center, while supporting
data can be placed elsewhere.
Enable customization, give users the
ability to personalize their dashboard.
Allowing them to filter data, change
data ranges, or even rearrange widgets,
empower them and makes the dashboard
more relevant to their specific workflow.
Ensure interactivity dashboards
should not be static images.
Allow users to drill down into
specific data points, power
over charts for more details, or
click to explore underlying data.
This interactivity inter encourages
exploration and deeper understanding.
Choose the right visuals.
Select the chart type that best represents
the data that supports the user's charts.
For example, use a line chart to
show trends over time, a bar chart
to compare categories and a pie chart
for parts to hold relationships.
Using the wrong chart can lead to
misinterpretation, accessibility,
designed with accessibility in mind.
This includes using color palettes
that are accessible to users with
colorblindness, providing clear labels
and ensuring dashboard is navigable
with keyboard or screen reader.
By combining these design principles with
the power of rust and web assembly, we can
have a significant impact on our business.
Let's bring it all home and talk.
Why this is a big deal for our
businesses and our organizations.
Blazing speed.
This isn't just about faster rendering,
it's about delivering an outstanding
user experience, which leads to
better, faster decision making.
Ironclad security memory safety means we
eliminate a huge class of vulnerabilities,
which is critical for handling sensitive
business data and meeting compliance
requirements developer productivity.
Using a type safe language like rust
helps us write correct maintainable
and bulk free code from the start
saving time and money in the long run.
To wrap up, I want to leave you with a few
takeaways and some concrete next steps.
First, the key takeaways.
Remember these three points,
performance transforms, experience.
Safety creates trust,
user-centric design matters.
So what can you do with this information?
I encourage you to start small.
Assess your current bottlenecks,
identify a high impact use case, and
then build a small proof of concept.
Measure the results, and you'll
see the value for yourself.
This brings us to the end
of today's presentation.
While I'm not going into the details
of this infographic, I wanted to
include it as here as a bonus content.
This has helped me often to determine the
right chat type and hope it helps you too.
It was a pleasure to
cover this exciting topic.
If you have any questions or
comments, please reach out
to me on GitHub or LinkedIn.
Have a great rest of your day.
Thank you.