Good morning, good evening, good
afternoon, wherever you are.
Thank you for joining the session.
I am goes by Sid.
I'm going to talk about building a high
performance multi-agent AI system in Ross.
How do we use Ross to build a multi-agent
system and how it can achieve 40%
faster enterprise transformation
using its memory safety guarantee?
Let's deep dive into it.
Sure.
The enterprise challenge today,
every digital transformation
passes critical bottleneck.
The 70 per 73% of organization
struggle with the monolithic AI system,
creating a single point of failure.
Everyone they want to build AI
system, AI platform, but they
face a single point of failure
because the design itself is wrong.
The traditional centralized
architecture is definitely a
garbage collected language.
Suffering from an
unpredictable latency spike.
A memory of overhead can deploy
processing up to 300% compared
to RO based distributed approach.
So these are the basic critical bottleneck
people generally doesn't realize.
They're going to face a challenge in
their digital transformation and, and
in enterprise AI challenges together.
But advantage of cost is, for
a multi-agent system is it is
faster in process optimization.
It can reduce your risk.
It has a greater efficiency
and has a zero memory leak.
Compared to traditional language
and framework, Ross is 40% faster
and the lower implementation failure
through compile times safety, 60%.
And it's improve the throughput.
Aging Roth concurrency, which
is like a great efficiency you
get, which is like 80%, 85% more
than the other language we used.
It is always a zero memory leak.
Roth ownership model and zero cost
obstruction enables a back through
multi-agent framework and that deliver
a measurable enterprise advantages.
Let's talk about a little bit into the.
Architecture.
The distributed architecture using
Ross, it has a four different layer.
The first layer is the perception
layer, then cognitive layer,
action layer, coordination layer.
The perception layer is
specialized agent from a data eson.
It is using for filtering, normalization,
using the RO efficient ai preemptives.
The cognitive layer is like
little bit of intelligent
analytical layer, which use lost.
Processing for modern
inference and decision logic.
The external layer is
an education of agent.
It's really what it does and in
implementing your business logic in
the transactional flow and it's get
you the guarantee of the excellence.
The coordination layer is mostly
the orchestration of the managing
different workflow in an across
distributed system and boundary.
The key are.
Using, using ROS are mostly the memory,
safety, concurrency, performance,
reliability, and interoperability.
The memory setti is the
biggest deal using ros.
You like.
There's a zero memory leak across
50 plus million agent interacting
using RO or system concurrency by
using a Tokyo best S Sync on time.
It can handling 250% more concurrent
agent than it's equivalent
Python, or go on the performance.
40% reduction in workflow
education time throughout Ross.
Zero cost abstraction reliability.
It's 60% decrease in system failure
impact, lost compile time error
prevention, interoperability.
P zero three PI oh three and
was binding enables lost.
Its in interoperability with any legacy
system and its ability to do that
is close to 80% successful than any
other language provided in the market.
The memory set in multi-agent system,
which is critical for you to build any
kind of multi-agent distributed system.
The challenge is a complex oxy pattern
of agent of interaction, cascading
failure due to memory leak and garbage
collection, POS disruption, realtime
coordination among the system.
Roster is going to help you on this.
The Ross solution is, it's.
The model and compiled and guarantee
eliminate the entire memory related
bug crucial for your high performance
and real time multi-agent system.
The practical benefit you're going to
get are consistency in performance,
resource efficiency, and reduction.
Bugging our production system.
Demonstrate the zero zero
memory leak across 50 million
plus agent interaction and high
throughput and propag environment.
The concurrency in Tokyo.
West Agent Coordination.
So this is again, one of the
platform Ross provide you to use.
It's an asy on time.
It enables high, concurrent,
and efficient agent coordination
through an async environment.
This approach drastically reduce
your OV rate overhead and boost
responsible multi-agent system,
maximize throughput agent performance.
And then it's help you in my
patient resource utilization.
It's enhance responsiveness
is help you in robustness.
Our system is achieved generally 250%
more concurrent adjunct education than
it's equivalent to Python or go and
any, any other language used for it.
So this is this Tokyo, this, this platform
after us like Tokyo compound its impact
in the real world performance in terms of
a multi, multi-agent distributor system.
Performance is another aspect
of it zero cost obstruction.
If you see the last performance
versus the traditional one, it's, it's
like 40% reduction in workflow time.
Then any other competitor
compiled time optimization, it's
eliminate your on time checks.
No garbage collection.
Pause during critical operation
agent communicate overhead reduced
by 60% because of this architecture.
And this implementation has spread
pretty easy because it's a custom trade.
Zero overhead agent polymorphism
static dispersed, where agents types
are known, efficient serialization for
intelligent communication automatically.
It's built on this architecture by ro.
And then kiros ecosystem and tools.
As I said we used the Tokyo
based, I'm going to talk about
a little bit more on that.
And, but you have other, other different
type of architecture and platform.
You can definitely use it.
We used this Tokyo one, the first one.
It's a, a synchron on time
for an efficient agent,
scheduling and coordination.
It enables non-blocking
your AI across boundaries.
And then it enables
priority based on that.
Support complex workflow
and communication.
So and then similarly you have Actos
and Sled and then Kendall, different
type of interfaces and platform
to think about, system preventing
distributed system bug, like any,
any multi-agent distributor system.
You talk about it, there is a
common enterprise AI failure.
Either it could be a data loss condition,
it could be a parallel state update.
It could be inconsistent error
handling or a protocol violation.
Rust help you to overcome this
because it's a inbuilt compiler
help you to catches these errors.
80% chances, 78 to 87%.
Chances this box will be a catch before
your deployment compared to Python
or go any other languages you use.
So this is one of the greatest
thing you got from rust.
This is another case study.
And in the manufacturing company
we have built the challenge was
it's a global manufacturing company
struggled with an unpredictable
latency in quality control AI system.
Leading to 12% is a production delay.
It is a big deal for them.
When it's a multi billion company with
an MNC you do, this is a big problem.
The result was like 43% reduction
in high quality inspection time
with zero increase in defect.
Right.
And also the latency was less than 50
millisecond with the three X normal load.
And you give three x time of the
actual load still, the LA was.
Less than 50 millisecond, which
is the outcome of this whole
architecture after implementing it.
Soroto multi-agent solution.
It is, it is, it is.
It is like we, we built around
22 specialized agent distributed
across four architecture layer.
The one we we just signed, and the real
time coordination inspections and decision
and routing for different functions.
And the integration among those systems,
and also it bell integrated with the
legacy system of the company using
UI oh three and web centric pages.
Which is a great aspect of rust.
The implementation roadmap generally took
it takes a 20 week, a minimum depending
on what, what you want to do and know
how big or how small it is starting from
your architecture assessment to core
infrastructure to, and is on integration
with existing enterprise system and
production deployment and optimization.
Then the available resources are
like complete rust implementation
performance benchmark and deployment
strategy and integration pattern.
This has to be your main resource to
thought about and, you know go over it.
People, even you think
about implementing it.
Thank you for joining this session.
Hopefully this will help you.
Thank you very much.