Hello everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon,
or good evening, depending
on where you're joining from.
My name is Rafael and I'm a
senior software engineer and
also an independent researcher.
It is a pleasure to welcome you
to today's session where I will be
presenting on building high performance
Healthcare, a system, and rust,
a senior travel safety platform.
To begin, I'll first highlight the growing
need for a senior travel safety platform.
As global life expectancy continues to
rise and healthcare standards improve,
it is projected that by 2030, the number
of travelers aged 60 and above will reach
approximately 703 million worldwide.
However, these journeys are often
accompanied by unique challenges,
including chronic health conditions,
limited mobility, language barriers,
and uneven access to emergency medical
services across different regions.
Despite the rapid growth of this
demographic, the travel industry
currently lacks a comprehensive
digital infrastructure designed to
address the specific healthcare and
safety needs of all the travelers.
So why Rust?
Rust offers a powerful combination
of performance, safety, and
concurrency, making it an ideal
choice for developing AI systems that
handle sensitive medical data where
speed and security are paramount.
Asset score.
Rest ownership model ensures memory
safety at compile time, effectively
eliminating common programming errors
such as null pointed de referencing.
And data races.
This allows developers to manage
memory I density operations efficiently
without compromising safety.
An essential requirement for healthcare
AI systems where software reliability
can directly impact patient outcomes
from a performance perspective.
Arrest delivers native machine
level execution with zero cost
abstractions and fine grain control.
Making it highly suitable for real-time
data processing applications such as Edge
AI on medical devices and high throughput
image analysis significantly benefit
from risk performance capabilities.
RAs concurrency model further
strengthens its suitability for
healthcare applications by guaranteeing
threat safety at compile time.
This is critical when managing
multiple patient data streams
simultaneously, enabling robust and
continuous monitoring from wearable
devices and other real-time sensors.
Additionally, rust is well suited
for cross-platform development,
supporting deployment across a variety
of operating systems and hardware
architectures, including Windows, Linux
M embedded systems, iOS and Android.
With the cross compilation
support via rust, step, and
target specific tool chains.
Rust enables flexible, scalable,
and secure development across
platforms, making it a strategic
choice for building future ready
healthcare and infrastructure.
Senior travel healthcare platform
architecture is built upon a fully
integrated end-to-end technology stack,
powered by rust at every critical layer.
From embedded biosensors operating
on edge devices to cloud-based,
AI driven predictive analytics.
Rust enables high performance, safety,
and efficiency throughout the system.
The platform is designed to seamlessly
process real-time health data
from over 2,847 concurrent users.
Each with a unique health
profile comprising more than
47 health related variables.
Despite the system's complexity and scale,
it maintains a sub millisecond latency,
ensuring that critical data, such as vital
signs and health risk alerts are processed
and responded tomo almost instantaneously.
Furthermore, the infrastructure adheres
strictly to GDPR compliance standards.
Operating across 34 countries,
ensuring the privacy, security, and
lawful handling of sensitive medical
data in a cross border context.
In essence, this platform showcases
ecosystem, can power and advance
real time, secure and globally
compliant healthcare solution
purpose built for unique and
growing needs of senior travelers.
When it comes to performance,
high performance data processing
is a key advantage of rust.
One of the most significant
advantage of adopting rust is
its exceptional capability for
high performance data processing.
Rust is engineered for speed and accurate
efficiency, making it ideally suited for
applications where larger volume of data
must be processed quickly, reliably,
and with a minimal system overhead.
Rust Platform employs a custom
serialization pipeline based on rust
powerful survey framework, enabling
the processing of medical records at
speeds approximately 340% faster than
comparable implementation in Python.
This approach not only delivers
substantial performance gains, but also
offers fine-grained control over the DC
ization process, developers can precisely
tailor how data types are utilized.
C utilized optimizing for
both speed and efficiency.
The Tokyo on asynchronous runtime
is a cornerstone of RU ecosystem,
providing a robust and highly efficient
foundation for developing high
performance asynchronous applications.
From powering scalable web servers
to managing iot devices, Tokyo
is the most widely adopted.
A Synchron time and trust known
for its ability to handle demanding
workloads with a minimum overhead.
By leveraging Tokyo, the platform
efficiently manage continuous streams of
health data, maintaining responsiveness
and reliability, essential for real-time
healthcare monitoring and analysis.
Zero copy parsing of biosense data
interest is a highly efficient and
performance oriented technique.
This time to minimize memory
overhead, this approach is especially
well suited for embedded systems.
Real-time applications and data
pipelines were rapid data posting
and reduced memory allocation are
critical to system performance.
In essence, a zero copy parsing allows
structure data to be interpreted
directly from a by buffer, such
as rust lines without the need to
allocate additional memory or copy
of the data into new structures.
By eliminating these costly memory
operations, zero copy parsing reduces
latency and resource consumption,
thereby improving overall throughput.
The technique not only enhances the
response units of healthcare applications
that rely on continuous biosensor data
streams, but also supports the stringent
resource constraints often encountered in
embedded and computing environments types.
A type safe schema Evolution in rust
refers to the process of updating the
evolving data models over time without
breaking backward compatibility, while
preserving rust inherent type safety.
And compell enforce guarantees.
Rest strong static typing combined with
the features such as s and powerful
serialized framework provides a
robust foundation for managing schema
evolution in a safe and explicit manner.
Third, safe machine learning
pipelines Rest book.
Platforms employs can errors and TCH
first bindings to enable realtime
health risk assessment across
multiple concurrent user sessions.
This architecture ensures threat safety
and pre prevents databases providing
reliable and efficient AI processing.
Rest ownership model is a foundational
design principle that enables predictor
analytics engines to process over
around 150 risk factors simultaneously
while eliminating entire classes of
bug related to memory and concurrency.
Ownership based safety is rest
compiled DAM system for managing
memory and data access without relying
on a garbage collect collector.
By leveraging rust ownership model system
achieves robust memory safety and threat.
Safe concurrency critical for processing
large scale sensitive health data with
utmost reliability, the integration
of foreign and next runtime within
rust enables efficient deployment of
pre-trained machine learning models
with a minimal resource consumption
supporting both CPU and GPU acceleration.
By leveraging on the next run time,
rest applications can execute complex
AI models efficiently, delivering fast
interface while maintaining a lightweight
footprint ideal for production grade
healthcare AI system that demand both
performance and resource efficiently.
Creating a threat, safe health
prediction system in rust request.
Leveraging the languages sentence,
seeing traits, these choice ensure that
the model and, associated data can be
safely shared or transferred across
multiple threats, thereby preventing data
races and eliminating unsafe behavior.
During the concurrent execution, rust
code implements a threat safe health
risk prediction component leveraging
rust concurrency primitives to ensure
safe and efficient multi-threaded
access to machine learning mode.
Interface the risk predictor
struck and its predict method.
Demonstrate an rest pattern for safe,
concurrent access to mutable shared
state, in this case a machine learning
model by leveraging arc for shared
ownership and TEX for mutual exclusion.
The This implementation is crucial
in health critical applications
where concurrent predictions
across multiple user session must
be performed reliably and safely.
Web assembly allows running sophisticated
natural language processing models such
as ma machine translation engines directly
in the browser or on edge devices.
The integration of rust with
the web assembly where offers a
powerful solution for building.
Performance, secure and cross
platform medical translation
applications that run directly in
web browsers or edge environments.
RUS compiled web assembly modules enable
medical terminology translation across
23 languages, ensuring broad linguistic
outreach achieves and impressive 94%
translation accuracy while strictly
maintaining user privacy by processing all
sensitive data locally on decline device.
The use of vam by engine significantly
reduces translation latency by up to
60% compared to traditional server side
processing, enhancing a response units.
This approach is especially critical in
emergency situations where clear immediate
communication is vital to prevent.
Patient criticality via empowered
translation model empowers seniors
to communicate their medical needs
effectively, despite language barriers.
Without transmitting any sensitive health
information to external servers or cloud
services, this ensures data privacy and
security while improving accessibility.
In embedded systems such as biosensors,
resource constraints, like limited memory
processing, power and lack of operating
system services, associate lightweight
and efficient software solutions.
Rest now is steady environment offers
an ideal platform for developing
reliable, safe, and performant
firmware for biosensor devices.
No SAD refers to rust programs that are
compelled without the standard library.
It is designed for bare metal or
embedded environments where features
like dynamic memory allocation
threats, or oil abstractions
are unavailable or unnecessary.
Instead, core relies on the core
library, which provides fundamental
risk functionalities such as
hydrators slices and option.
Types, but excludes oil dependent
features, leveraging noise study
rust along with embedded hal hardware
abstraction layer with develop iot bio
firmware, optimized for minimal resource
usage and robust realtime performance,
which is which has minimal footprint
real time performance, continuous
monitoring, power efficiency as features.
And real the custom protocol
implementation in Rust is designed
to ensure data integrity and reliable
communication, even in environments with
the poor or intermittent connectivity.
Tailored to operate efficiently over
limited and unreliable network conditions.
Minimizing data loss and retransmissions
Employees are robust buffering strategy
that temporarily stores data locally and
forwards it when connectivity is restored,
ensuring no critical information is lost,
integrates end-to-end cryptographic checks
to guarantee data, authenticity, and
prevent tampering during transmission.
ENSURES medical data is transmitted
and processed with a higher priority,
facilitating timely intervention.
JDPR complaint medical data storage
solution is built using the SUBRA
framework, a powerful trust backed
blockchain development platform
to ensure security, transparency
and regulatory compliance.
Every data access and modification is
securely recorded on the blockchain,
creating tamr proof logs that guarantee
transparency and accountability.
Built in mechanisms enforce GDPR and
other region regulations automatically
ensuring adherence to privacy
laws across multiple countries.
Enable secure, seamless sharing of
medical data across JU restrictions
supporting coordinated care while
maintaining strict security standards.
Patients manage their data permission
directly on chain, giving them full
control over who can access their
sensitive medical information.
Rest based smart contracts, automate
consent management and enforce data access
controls, ensuring regulatory complaints
in maintained seamlessly without the
need of a need for manual oversight.
Medical record processing and rust
achieves a three, 340% performance
improvement compared to an
equivalent Python implementation.
This significant gain is attributed to
rust, zero cost, abstraction compiled and
memory safety, and efficient control over
system resources, making it ideal for
high throughput healthcare data pipeline.
Implementing medical translation,
interest compiled web assembly.
Asim delivers a 60% reduction in
latency compared to traditional
server side processing.
By executing the translation logic
directly on the client side, this
approach minimizes network overhead
while leveraging rest, performance,
and memory safety, enabling real time
privacy, preserving communication
in critical healthcare contacts.
Rest based medical translation engine
achieves 94% accuracy across 23 languages
for critical medical terminology.
This high level of precision ensures
that the vital health information is
communicated clearly and reliably,
even in multilingual or emergency
care settings, supporting safer,
more inclusive patient outcomes.
The risk assessment engine implemented
in Rust delivers sub millisecond
response time when processing over 40
cent health variables per user profile.
This ultra low latency enables real
time decision making and rapid alerting,
which is essential for time critical
healthcare applications such as remote
monitoring and emergency triage.
Case study was conducted with,
the remote with the emergency
response in a remote location.
And as per the case study, a
health alert trigger was invoked.
And we are able bio sensor detects and
irregular heart rhythm and elevated
blood pressure in a 72-year-old
traveler located in rural Portugal.
And.
A powered machine learning model
processes over one 50 health
risk factors in a real time and
defying a potential cardiac event.
In with the 92% confidence, the system
automatically locates the nearest
medical facilities and translates
the patient's medical history into
Portuguese ensuring seamless communication
with the local care provider.
Blockchain verified medical
records are securely shared with
the received receiving hospital,
enabling immediate informed treatment
upon the patient's arrival without
delays or manual data handling.
Challenges in adopting SPO healthcare
systems despite its strength implementing
rust in the healthcare domain.
Present several key challenges
limited availability of specialized
medical libraries and domain specific
tools compared to more established
languages like Python or Java.
Interfacing with the existing healthcare
infrastructure requires careful
foreign function interface handling,
and increases development complexity.
Ensuring strict adherence to
regulations such as G-D-G-D-P-R,
HIPAA and MDR can be a time consum.
Especially when adopting newer
technologies that lack pre-certified
components, rest, advanced compiled
time, checks and optimization can
lead to longer build times during
the early phases of development,
rest, ownership, and borrowing model.
While powerful introduces deeper
learning curve for teams, transition
from languages with the garbage
collection or looser memory management.
To address the key challenges of
using rust in a regulated healthcare
environment, the following strategies were
implemented, built custom domain specific.
Develop focused, tested medical
grants create a type safe bendings
using integrated compliance
checks into CICD pipelines.
Optimized to build process,
implemented target training programs.
The next steps and future learnings.
Federated learning privacy, preserving
ml using encrypted health data across
devices with those centralized storage,
releasing core medical data processing
libraries to foster healthcare innovation.
And extended language support expanding
medical translation to 40 plus languages
with a specialized re regional medical
terminology at JPA deployment, moving
more intelligent to wearable devices to
reduce the connectivity requirements.
Healthcare provider integration,
developing standardized APIs
for hospitals and clinics to
interface with our platform.
Thank you all for your
time and attention today.
I hope this session was provided
valuable insights into the
development of High Performance
Secure Healthcare, a PA AI system
using rust, wishing you all continued
success and innovation in your work.
Thank you once again for joining.