Hey, good morning, good afternoon,
and good evening to all.
I'm Vanta.
I have 23 years of experience
delivering projects in various
Dominic Healthcare, finance, oil and
gas, worked in AWS and Azure Cloud
environments, and have extensive
experience in big data frameworks
like Oop, spark, Kafka, et cetera.
Today I would like to share with you
the experiences I have gone through.
In developing cross language libraries,
we will travel through the architectural
patterns and methodologists follow
while creating the Spark JMS Connected
project and their application to them.
Last ecosystem development.
Let's go to the agenda and see
what are all the topics which are
covered as part of this presentation.
So first we'll cover
the project background.
We'll see what is the need.
Of the Spark JMS connector.
What are all the goals and
challenges we have faced while
developing this Spark JMS connector?
Then we will travel through the common
design challenges which we face while
developing a trans language libraries.
Number three, we will see the abstractions
and the interfaces of the both the JBM
provided interfaces and the registrate,
and we'll next we will navigate to.
The error handling strategies where
we will see the JBMs patterns and
the rust result based approach.
After that, we will see how we have
covered the implementation with
the comprehensive testing across
all the implementations, both with
the rust and the JBM and last, we
will see how we have generated the
YouTube and discover discoverable
interfaces with the documentation.
And a PA design.
We'll quickly go through
the project background.
Yeah.
Capital One, spark JMS Connector
is created because the source
is a message queue and we have
different message sources with the
different types of message queues.
You can see some JMS providers
provide the message in active queue,
some providing IBM and queue and
some providing SOS number two.
This JMS connector should support
the real time processing because we
are going to read the financial data
and we need to quickly respond to the
end customer as soon as we receive
them financial transaction from him.
Number three, this has to be the
enterprise data connector for
Apache Park because we are going to
reuse this connector library across
all the departments in the cap.
Next.
The importance of it is it has
to be critical and real time.
Real time data pipelines, and it has
to be part of the fraud detection
and last, but the greatest, it
has to be performance sensitive.
With strict reliability requirements,
you cannot lose the data customer gets
annoyed with if you lose the data.
The other challenge, which we
have seen is the input library.
The inputs which we are getting for this
library have different message patterns.
We need to combine all these
message patterns and make one unique
message schema and handle it to
different broker for implementation.
With this, we have covered
that departmental goals and the
challenges which we are going to
face by developing this library.
Next, we will go to the Universal Design
Challenges while creating a library.
A library always.
Should have abstraction boundaries
because the implementation may change
and you cannot expect the user of this
library to change his code because
your implementation has changed.
So there should be an extra abstraction
between your implementation and
the customer implementation.
We have created the, we need to create
the interfaces to hide the implementation
details for providing flexibility.
Number two, configuration manage.
You need to be able to configure the
things and customize the behavior
of the library based, or you have,
you should be able to enable or
disable some of the features based
on based on the configurations.
Number three, error propagation.
Error propagation.
You should be able to communicate your
your failures effectively, and also you,
you need to preserve the co context.
And the recovery options
and extensibility.
You should always leave the space for the
future enhancements, but you should not
be that future enha enhancement should not
come at the cost of breaking the backward
compatibility, performance constraints.
Yeah, you should minimize the
overhead while maintaining the
safety and the correct carriage.
First pattern we have identified
is the provider pattern.
The provider interface pattern we used
in the JJMS connector, fortunately has
a natural unlock in the restate system.
So we were a, we were able to easily
blend the JVM provider interface
with the respirate system, with the
as rest rate provides the zero cost
abstractions with the compiled time
polymorphism and the JBM site provider
interface is what we have done is.
Is we have implemented the
dependency injection pattern
to swap the implementations
based on the user selection.
Now, the next architectural
pattern is separation of concepts.
We need to isolate the component.
We need component isolation patterns to
transfer between the two ecosystems so
that those two ecosystems are cohesively
connected from the JBM implementation.
What we have done is we have.
Isolated the message consumers from
the connection management message.
Consumers don't know from where
the message came from and from
which message queue from the
message come from, come, came from.
In the same way, acknowledgement
strategies are also separated
from the message processing.
So message processing doesn't know how to
acknowledge it, is separated between the
connection and the processing connection
takes care of the acknowledgement.
And message processing
does the processing work.
Only
Number three, error handlers are
decoupled from the core business logic.
So they are used as a plug and play.
The error handlers can be added,
are remote based on the requirement
configuration validation.
We have separated it from that
usage now from the rust side.
Rust side, there are builtin
things, module system, which
naturally enforces the boundaries.
And though there is a ownership model
which clarifies the responsibility for the
resources, and as I said earlier, trade
objects for run temporal when needed,
and we did the type parameter checking
for the compiled plus borrow checker
also enforces the clean separation,
prevents the leaky abstractions.
If there are.
Okay, now let's come to the
error handling strategies.
So what we need to have is separate
approaches for both rush transition
and the JBM for the JBM approach.
What we have done is, as it is an
object oriented and relies on hierarchy
inheritance, we wanted to follow the sale.
What we have done is we have
created check and uncheck exception.
Exception throws and catches
everywhere for the errors to propagate.
Okay.
And we we e for every exception
throne we emphasized on the detailed
messages and the stack tracer, we
will be able to identify the exact
location of the issue and fix it.
And also, while creating the exceptions
and catching the exceptions we had, we
didn't compromise on the performance.
We considered the implications
of the performance because of.
Creating try because of the
exception throwing and catching.
Now, from the rust translation point
of view, we use the result, which is,
which encodes whether it is a success or
failure, forcing the compound actually.
And
we use the custom arenas from, for
cohesive comp and composable error
types, and for contextual training.
Training.
We used library anyhow, and this error
to provide agon context, tradition, and
for pattern matching, we have exhaust to
match the pattern, match statements to
ensure all the error cases are handled.
Now let's go to the comprehensive
testing methodologies where we will
discuss what are the unit testing
strategies and integration testing
strategies and property based
testing strategies, which we have
implemented to cover the test case.
Yes.
So we, for JVM, we used Marketo
for the interface mocking and
for rust we have used the mock
implementations of the traits.
And for integration testing, we have used
test containers for the broker instances.
In JVM in case of rust, we have
used container based testing for
feature flags or feature flags.
And in case of property based testing, we
have used WIC theories or Jake W for JB.
And for rust we have used prop test.
A quick check.
Now let's move on to the configuration
management pattern patterns like first
thing is JVM configuration approach.
We have used builder pattern for
the sensible defaults with the
sensible defaults, and we have used
immutable configuration objects and
we validated at the construction time.
And the hierarchical
configuration with the over rates.
So if you see this actually, so we
have used the builder pattern to, for
with the sensibility fault for the
JJBM configurations, rust translation.
Again, like in the last case, we have used
the builder pattern with the default rate.
It goes to the default rate if it
doesn't find any implementation
in case of builder pattern.
We use a type safe confi configuration
with the compiled and validation,
and we, for static configurations,
we used constant generics and we
used con config structures with
the validate validation functions.
Both a, both these approach
approaches emphasize the type
safety 10 validation before use.
But the advantage of rush over the j
or rush over the JVM is it can push
more validation to the compiled type.
Yeah.
Next let's go to the
performance considerations.
So what we have achieved after the
different optimization approaches
that achieved similar goals when we
have taken care of batch pro batch
processing, and JJVM JVM optimization,
connection, pooling, and reuse, instead
of creating the connections every time
to keep, to reduce the pressure on.
GC and the careful memory management
to reduce careful and reuse of the
memory management to reduce the G
GC pressure and jet friendly core
patterns we have used to reduce the
memory and from the rust optimization.
What we have used is we used
mono modernization where it
is zero cost abstractions.
We used explicit memory management
with the lifetimes, and we used
compiled time evaluation when possible.
And we used ownership model, which
achieved a fearless concurrency.
Now
with this, we have achieved the
performance improvement of 10 times and
with zero runtime overhead, and we have
H of 99.9% of the liability target.
Now let's move on to the
documentation and API design.
We have used a LA language.
First of all, like during the coding, we
have used a consistent naming conventions.
For example, for JVM, we used
Camel case for J Java variables
and snake case for rust variables.
And we have established a clear
domain specific technology.
Because that remains consistent throughout
the a PA. We made simple use cases.
We broke the complex use
cases into simple use case.
So that it'll be easy to implement.
They are advanced features are available,
but they are not required for the basic.
So both ecosystems benefit from the
tired APIs with increased complexity.
Both.
We have used both OC and Java DOC
to support the embedded examples.
Our JVM connector provided example
classes for the users to use it in stuff.
Document, it's worked better than the
documentation part and rust documentation.
Also, we have used the dock tests
that are automatically verified.
Yeah, we have explicitly documented
the errors, which you can throw and
the what are the errors which will
be thrown by the library, and what
are the recovery strategies interest.
That means we have documented
all the error variants that can
be returned from each functions.
What are the key learnings from
this library implementation?
The first thing is abstraction.
Principles are universal
for all the languages.
Good interface design
transmits the languages.
We can identify the right
abstraction boundaries regardless
of the language implementation.
Number two, you leverage the
strengths of each language.
Plus ownership model and trade
system provides the compelling
guarantees that required runtime
check in the JBM languages.
One of things and testing
is la language agnostic.
You have that the test cases might
be language language dependent test
case implementation might be language
independent, but the testing strategies
are, and that are like what, what
went between the ecosystems though?
Implementation details are
different, as I said, and.
When we are implementing and
the document intent, not just
implementation, while we are
implementing the code, we have explained
why a design is made as important.
It's as important for the documentation
and how to use an a PA so that while
generating the document, you'll get all
the information on how to use the a p
and how, what design cha choices you
have made regardless of the language.
Yeah.
Thank you.