Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining.
My name is Nish Kumar ti and
I'm currently a senior cloud and
application security engineer.
Over the past decade, I've been deeply
involved in securing enterprise scale
systems across AWS Azure and GCP with the
focus on integrating security directly
into the development and deployment
process, what we now call DevSecOps.
I worked on building.
And implementing security pipelines
that perform compliance checks,
vulnerability scanning, and real
time threat detection for everything
from traditional applications to
modern serverless workloads like
AWS Lambda and Azure functions.
I have led migrations from
traditional security platforms
like Prisma Cloud to more advanced
solutions like VIS IO closing gaps
in container and server security.
I have designed CSCD integrations
that block insecure bills
before the reach production.
Combining tools like VCLI, fortify
and AWS Inspector, I'm also involved
in a PS security with nsec defining
sensitive data handling strategies
and onboarding PCA and non PCA
workloads for continuous monitoring.
Today's talk, building memory
Safe DevSecOps at Enterprise
Scale is about a challenge I've
seen repeatedly over the years.
I've seen a recurring challenge.
Many security tools stem cells are
returning memory unsafes languages
like CC plus, which means the
tools designed to protect us can
introduce new vulnerabilities.
That's what led me to.
Explore rust.
A language that eliminates
entire categories of memory
safety issues at compile time.
Today, I wanna share with you how
rust memory, safety, performance
integration flexibility can help us
build safe security tools we can trust,
and how we can practically bring rust
into our existing security pipelines.
Without starting from scratch.
So that's a bit about who I am
and why this topic matters to me.
Let's take a quick look at what
we will cover today and so you
know exactly what we are headed.
Okay, here is what we will cover.
First, we will look at rust.
Memory safety advantage how its
ownership model eliminates entire
classes of vulnerabilities leading to
up to 40% fewer security incidents.
Next, we will explore technical
implementations, real world examples
like static analysis tools that block
insecure code before it compiles
lightning fast container scanners.
Cryptographic pipelines that
stop supply chain attacks and
memory safe policy engines.
Then we will review performance benchmarks
showing how rust tools can ramp 10
next faster than go or Python language
using 60% less memory with examples
from CloudFlare Dropbox and discard.
Finally, we will discover integration
strategies so you can bring rust into
your DevOp DevOps workflows, whether it's
a Gate hooks Kubernetes administration
controllers, or API gateways.
Without major disruptions.
Before we dive into RAs, let's first
understand the problem we are solving.
The memory safety crisis that's
affecting almost every modern systems.
The memory safety crisis.
From memory, safety flaws are still
top cause of critical security issues.
The Microsoft reports.
That 70% of its cvs come from memory
safety bug problems like use after
free buffer overflows, databases,
plug plague C, like C plus because
developers how to manually manage
memory, traditional scanner detect
these only after code is written.
And runtime monitoring can slow down
applications here, for example, in
a real world case, a buffer flow.
NAC plus based API gateway allowed
attackers to arrive session
data, gaining admin level access.
This is issues that cost millions to fix
and damages trust, and it's exactly the
type of risk rust is designed to prevent.
Now we, now that we know the
scale of the problem, here is
what rust changes the game.
It makes the whole categories of these
vulnerabilities impossible by design.
Rust memory safety guarantees, and
that changes the game by making
entire categories of vulnerabilities
impossible at compile time.
It enforces ownership.
So every piece of data has only one owner.
Notable, freeze boring rules and safe.
Ensure safe freeze and rights
without corrupting memory.
Lifetime.
Make sure and nothing out lives.
Its valid scope and fearless.
Concurrency means no data.
S even in multi multi-threaded code.
If you build a container scanner or an a
PA gateway, you are not just protecting
applications, you are ensuring the
tool itself is not a new attack vector.
Vector.
This is why companies like
Dropbox have reported zero memory
safety bug in rust based modules.
And this is not just theory.
When organizations switch to
RAs, they see real world results.
Let's talk about the
measurable impact it's having.
Enterprise impacts the name, the
number speaks for themselves.
Enterprise migrating critical
components from CC plus to rust have
seen a 40% drop in security incident.
Properly, a written rust code has
zero memory safety bucks, static
analysis tools and rust can reach 95%
detection accuracy with fewer false
positives, meaning security teams
spend less time chasing more noise
and more time fixing real issues.
For example, one of financial
services, from I worked with Saudi
vulnerability backlog, dropped
by 30% in three months after
introducing rust based scanning tools.
So how do we actually put rust to work?
Let's start with the static analysis,
catching unsafe core practice patterns
before they ever reach production.
Static analysis tooling.
Russ.
Passing libraries, select
Sim and Pro Marker two.
Pro Max two Make it perfect for
building static analysis tools.
You can scan code at and compile
times spots, SQL injections
patterns and block in secure
commits before they hit the ripple.
Compared to go based scanners,
rust tools run three times faster
and compared to Python based
tools, they are 10 times more.
Reliable in a security pipeline.
That means you can scan huge code
base in seconds without bottlenecks.
Imagine CI build that rejects
the vulnerable API endpoint
before it even deploys.
Starting analysis protects code
before it's built, but what about
the things we package and ship?
That's where container scanning comes in.
Rust really shines there.
What is container?
Let's start from the basis basics.
A container is a lightweight, portable
package that includes an application
and everything it needs to run the code.
Libraries, runtime, environment
variables and configuration files.
Think of it.
Think of it as a shipping
container for software.
It does not matter if the ship
is AWS Azure, GCP, or on-prem.
The container runs the same way.
Docker and Kubernetes have made
the containers the backbone of
modern application deployment.
The benefit containers are fast to start.
Easy to replicate and scalable.
But the flip side is you view package
vulnerabilities inside your container.
You are scaling those
vulnerabilities everywhere.
Why containers need security scanning,
a typical container image can meet up
of dozen of dozens of layers, often
pulled from public repositories.
This means, you are potentially narrating
vulnerabilities from someone else.
Score common container risks includes
outdated base images using open two or 16
version, or that's reached end of life,
and embedded secrets, like API, keys,
passwords, lifting, some environment
variables, vulnerable libraries
like log four J everyone knows that.
And or OpenSSL.
Misconfigurations, insecure
file permissions, et cetera.
Real world example, in, in 2021,
attackers com compromised Kubernetes
clusters by exploiting containers
running outdated alpine Linx images.
That's why scanning containers
before deployment is non-negotiable.
How traditionally scanning
works traditionally scanners
pass the container image.
Extract the file systems, layers
and com compare and style packages
like against known vulnerabilities
database like NVD or vendor advisors.
The problem with some existing tools,
performance bottlenecks, scanning hundreds
of images can take hours, memory leaks.
Scanners in unsafe languages
can themselves be exploited,
false to use, noisy results.
You know that wastes security team time.
In CSCD, slow or unlevel scans lead to
a tough trade off speed versus security.
And then that's where Rust
gives us a breakthrough.
Coming to rust based container scanning,
rust is designed let us built continuous
channels that are fast, safe and accurate.
The improvements rust brings
are like zero copy passing.
Parallel scanning, async reporting zero
copy parsing with creates like bias.
The scanners can read container
layers directly from disk without
duplicating data in memory.
This means faster performance and
no unnecessary memory use parallel
scanning using, rion or we can use,
we can scan 10,000 plus images per
minute without breaking his feet.
Sing.
Reporting libraries like Tokyo let
us send scan results to dashboards
or security tools without blocking
the scanner process end-to-end.
Let's walk through end-to-end.
Use case in in, in DevSecOps
pipeline developer pushes code.
That triggers the build pipeline
Docker image built a base image
plus an application code or packaged
into your container, and then
rust based scanner runs before the
image pushed into the registry.
The scanner analyze each layer.
Checks, installed packages against
CVE databases, flags, outdated O waste
components or insecure configurations.
Detect secrets left in code or
environment variables and scan results.
Evaluated if critical vulnerabilities
are found, the pipeline blocks the
deployment and sends results to,
however integration has happened.
It may be ServiceNow or Slack with
xera image push to registry only clean.
Ensuring production gets only safe,
verified continuous by embedding the
Rust Scanner here, you are shifting,
security left, stopping vulnerability
before they ever touch production.
So in short, containers are powerful,
but without scanning, they are high speed
delivery systems for vulnerabilities.
Speed is great, but
trust is non-negotiable.
A scanner written memory,
unsafe language can be exploited
via the very images in it.
Inspects rust memory model
makes entire classes of parser.
And current concurrency
bugs impossible by design.
So that tools is not a new attacker phase.
Restless as built scanners that are
both faster, safer than a traditional
tools, making it possible to secure
containerized replications at enterprise
scale without slowing in innovation.
Now we have scanned the container
vulnerabilities, but how do we
ensure no one has tampered with it?
Between build and deploy.
That's where cryptographic
validation steps in cryptographic
pipeline validation.
Supply chain attacks are on the rise.
So everything so verifying your
build artifacts is critical.
Rust ring and results libraries
give your memory safe.
Cryptographic P use, avoiding the.
Pitfalls of C based open SSL, you can sign
and verify artifacts without unnecessary
data copies using the risk of time
of check to time of use at x discord
implemented a rust based cryptographic
verification and si a hundred percent
drop in certain supply chain at accidents.
And finally, even the, within the
security measures we need to control.
What runs in your environment?
Let's see how RUS can power,
memory, safe policy engines.
Policy engines decide what's allowed
in your systems and if they are
compromised, you are in trouble with rust.
You can compile policies on.
Web assembly offered sandbox
executions or ensuring they're
run safely across platforms.
You can validate configurations without
risking buffer workflows or even
hard swab policies without restarts.
For example in Kubernetes, you
could enforce that only signed
images or deployed and updated the
policy in amply without downtime.
We are seeing the technical side.
Now let's talk numbers.
How much faster, safer, and more
efficient or rust based tools
compared to traditional ones.
If you look at the slide here
across real deployments at Dropbox,
discord, and CloudFlare, rust
based tools can morph faster.
I use less memory and produce fewer
false positive than go our Python.
Equal XA numbers three to 10 times
faster scans, 60% less memory
use lower false positive rates,
all without s sacrificing safety.
That's the definition
of security at scale.
Of course, none of this matters
it if it's too hard to adapt.
The good news is you can integrate RA
base tools into your workflows without.
Major
integration strategies.
You don't have to rewrite your
stack to benefit from rust.
You can integrate a gradually pre-commit
hooks to block, bad code add GitLab ca,
jobs of and automated scanning Kubernetes
admission controllers for runtime
policy enforcement, and API gateway mill
middleware for live request validation.
Key takeaways.
Rust eliminates entire classes of
vulnerabilities at compile time.
It delivers faster performance, lower
memory use, and higher detection
accuracy than traditional tools.
You can start small dependency scanning
with cargo, audit container scanning
with rest based tools and grow from
the grow from there, the future.
Of secure infrastructure is not
just better detection, it's making
certain vulnerabilities impossible.
Rust delivers on that promise.
Thank you.
Okay.