Hi everyone, my name is, so this session
of Con 42 Cy Engineering event of 2025
will focus on contextual understanding
and ation with high dimension using
generative artificial intelligence.
The session, focus on
the solution approach.
So that enhances contextual understanding
and ation by first encoding the user
inputs into the high dimensional embeds.
And these embeddings are then used
for the efficient sematic search
and of the relevant context, which
is inter integrated into prompt.
So for the chat completion model
that combines the powerful sematic
similarity capabilities with advanced
language integration, enabling accurate
and context of our interactions.
So with so much of information,
data, abundance documents, review
and analysis is a difficult task.
The challenge is with huge volume and
unstructured data's tough to extract
meaningful information from the data
and respond in a very personalized
and domain or contextual manner.
So business and product outcomes will be
impacted to not able to derive insights
on those specific domain or context
due to huge amount of data growth.
So there is no solution for domain
specific knowledge for ai applications.
There is no efficient solution
for context Adaptability.
So sentiment analysis model or natural
language processing or other models.
So have a lesser accuracy
on the context analysis.
This is all the solution architecture.
So the approach allows to do
provide domain information
available with the uploaded.
In the chat model what we develop.
So the uploaded document will be converted
to text and text embedding is done a
vector opting through text embedding
model, or stored in the vector dp.
For any new prompt or query ask, it would
do a similarity search from the list of
similar text and as and is filter on the.
Domain based response is return
for the query of the prompts.
And fine tuning helps to produce
the best results by pertaining with
large amounts of information upfront
and domain specific knowledge based
on the document analysis is done.
Analyzing the sentiment domain.
Context and the content of the upload
document, it generates responses
that are not only relevant, but also
empathetic on the circumstances.
Threshold helps to build the accurate
context with the prompt sent.
So with this, we would get the right
context to provide a final response
considering the domain in the text and
the text ratings to capture patterns
and semantics in, data is obtained
by converting the uploaded document
into text using certain passes.
So for our document analysis and
yeah, thereby with this approach, it
allows to provide a domain information
available in the uploaded document.
So this is how the solution we have this.
Web where we can see that can,
there's option to upload the document,
what you wanna derive the knowledge
based on the domain or the context.
So here I've uploaded English or
science textbook and that the uploaded
document content is seen as shown here.
And yeah, like in the chat model, if the
user ask anything related to the domain or
the document we'll get a better accuracy.
The AI assistant would provide
the response to the prompt,
to the query based on the, OR
domain ready inside the, on the.