Hi, this is Al Ity.
I help 70 needs of experience in
enterprise integration architecture.
Today I'm going to talk about
driving digital transformation using
Oracle Tech for e governance and
digital inclusion in rural areas.
In today's increasingly digital
world, rural communities often find
themselves left behind, disconnected
from essential services that
are residents take for granted.
This digital divide not only
limits access to information.
But depends existing social
economic in inequalities.
Our research explores how Oracle's
technological solutions are transforming e
governance and fostering digital inclusion
in underserved regions by leveraging.
Powerful platforms like Oracle, so suit,
apex, and E-Business suit communities
are experiencing remarkable improvements
in healthcare delivery, agriculture
support and administrative services.
The rural digital divide,
understanding the challenge.
3.7 billion disconnected people
globally without internet access.
65% rural gap of disconnected
people living in rural areas.
40% economic impact, income
disparity between connected
and disconnected communities.
The whole digital divide represents.
One of the most persistent forms
of inequality in modern society,
limited connectivity infrastructure,
high deployment cost under lower
population density, create significant
barriers to digital inclusion.
This technological isolation translates
directly into reduced access to education.
Healthcare, financial services
and government resources for
rural residents, this means fewer
opportunities for economic advancement
and diminished participation in
increasingly digital civic processes.
Oracle's Egon technology stack.
Oracle Cloud infrastructure,
scalable foundation for all services.
Oracle database and analytics,
secure data management and insights.
Oracle Server Suite integration framework
for connecting services, Oracle,
epic, and eBusiness Suite application
development and business process.
Comprehensive technology stack
provides a robust foundation for
rural e governance initiatives.
Delayed architecture enables
governments to build scalable, secure,
and integrated digital services that
function even in challenging environments
with the limited connectivity.
This integrated approach allows for
both rapid deployment of standardized
solutions and the customization to meet
the specific needs of diverse rural
communities, transforming rural healthcare
delivery, electronic health records,
Oracle Epic Applications enable secure,
offline capable patient record management.
Improving data accuracy by 40%
and reducing record retrieval
time from hours two seconds.
Telemedicine integration, so would
connect remote clinics with urban medical
centers allowing virtual consultations
and specialist referrals that could
otherwise require lengthy travel.
Healthcare antics.
Data driven insights help identify disease
patterns, optimize resource allocation,
and improve to care initiatives
targeted to specific community needs.
Healthcare transformation represents
one of the most impactful application
of Oracle technologies in rural
settings by digitizing health systems.
Communities gain access to higher
quality care despite geographic
isolation and resource limitations.
The ability to function in offline mode
has proven particularly valuable in
areas with intermittent connectivity,
ensuring continuous service availability,
modernizing agricultural support systems.
Crop planning.
Yay.
Forward recommendations for optimal
planting, resource management,
tracking inputs and optimizing resource
allocation, yield monitoring, realtime
production data and forecasting thing.
Market access, direct connections
to buyers and price information.
Agriculture remains the economic
backbone of many rural communities.
Oracle powered agricultural support
systems help farmers make data driven
decisions about crop selection,
resource allocation, and market timing.
These digital platforms have shown
particularly strong adoption rates.
When introduced alongside hands-on
training programs with the participating
formers, reporting hours income increases
of 15 to 20% after the first time growing
season, streamlining administrative
services, document digitization.
Converting paper records to Searchable
digital archives with Oracle Content
Management Process Automation,
streamlining workforce through Oracle
Business Process management, multi-channel
access, providing service access through
web, mobile, and KI Cisco interfaces.
Performance monitoring racking
service metrics and identifying
improvement opportunities.
Administrative to services like land
registration, business permits and
identity documents form the foundation
of citizen government interaction.
Our research found.
30% increasing administrative efficiency
after implementing Oracle E-Business
suit For this process, more importantly,
citizens report significantly higher
satisfaction with the government
services, with the average processing
times reduced from weeks to days or
even hours for many common transactions.
Case study, land
registration transformation.
A comprehensive land registration
digitization in situ in one study region
demonstrates transformative impact of
Oracle technologies by implementing
Oracle Blockchain for land records and
epics for citizen facing applications.
The regional government ensure dramatic
improvements across all key metrics.
The system now process over
50,000 transactions monthly with
minimal errors compared to fewer
than thousand previously sleep.
The increased transparency has
also significantly reduced.
Corruption complaints re
related to land transactions.
Overcoming rural digitalization
challenges, connectivity solutions, often
capable applications, and ME networks.
Digital literacy, community training
programs and simplified interfaces,
energy constraints, low power devices.
And alternative energy sources,
cultural adaptation, localized
content, and community engagement.
Implementing digital solutions
in rural environments requires
addressing significant infrastructure
and human factors challenges.
Our research identified
four critical barriers.
That successful programs must overcome
through adaptive strategies, pilot
to local conditions, communities
that implemented comprehensive
digital literacy programs.
Alongside new technology deployments
are adoption rate increases by 25%
compared to technology only approaches.
Highlighting the importance of
human-centered implementation strategies,
research methodology, and evolution.
Mixer methods approach our study
combined qualitative interviews
with one 50 PE stakeholders across
all implementation sites with
quantitative performance metrics.
Collected from Oracle systems
providing a comprehensive view of both
technological performance and human
experience, longitudinal evolution.
We track key indicators over a. 24
month period to assess not just initial
implementation success, but sustained
adoption and evolving usage patterns
as communities integrated digital
services into daily life compared
to analysis by comparing diverse
implementation approaches across.
Different regional contests.
We identified universal success
factors as well as contest
specific adoptations that enhanced
effectiveness in particular settings.
This rigorous evaluation methodology
allowed us to move beyond and
doctoral success stories to develop
evidence-based recommendations
for future implementations.
Notably our findings challenge
several common exemptions about rural
technology adoption, particularly
regarding the importance of often
functionality for connection, speed, key
findings, and impact expanded access.
Over 50% of rural population experience
improved access to digital services
with particularly strong gains among
previously marginalized groups.
Service efficiency, administrative
processing times decreased by an
average of 65% across all measured
services, with some process
showing even greater improvements.
Governance quality transparency ratings
increased by 40% point while reported.
Corruption incidents declined by
over 30% in distilled service areas.
Economic benefits, communities with
freely implemented digital services showed
average economic growth 1.2 percentage
points higher than comparable non areas.
The accumulated impact of Oracle
powered rural digitalization extends
beyond improved service delivery to
fundamental transformation in governance,
relationships, and economic opportunity.
These changes help particular significance
for historically underserved populations,
including women and minority groups.
Feature directions and
policy recommendations.
Invest in rural digital infrastructure.
Government should prioritize extending
high speed connectivity to rural areas
through public private partnerships and
innovate to large mile solutions like
community networks and satellite internet.
Develop integrated technology platforms.
Investments in comprehensive
platforms like rockets.
Integrated stack delivers greater
value than siloed applications,
enabling cost, sector synergies and
resource sharing, expand distilled
data literacy programs, digital skills.
Training should be integrated
into formal and informal education
systems with a special attention
to reaching adult learners and
designing culturally relevant,
continue evidence-based evaluation.
Ongoing research should focus
on quantifying long-term
social and economic impacts.
To guide future investments and
identify emerging best practices.
The future of rural digital inclusion
depends on coordinated action across
policy domains and stakeholder groups.
Our research suggested that technology
alone cannot breach the DI digital divide.
Success requires simultaneous
attention to infrastructure.
Skills, content and governance frameworks.
With the thoughtful implementation
of the recommendations Mo that
transform me to potential of Oracle
technologies can be fully realized
creating more equitable and efficient
role governance systems worldwide.
I hope you all
enjoy my session.
Thank you.