Hello everyone.
I'm Shika Kamp.
Welcome to the Site Reliability
Engineering Conference of 2025.
Today we are gonna discuss about
transforming monolithic SaaS,
the serverless evolution on AWS.
Welcome to our comprehensive exploration
of serverless migration strategies
for SaaS applications using AWS.
This presentation will guide you
through the journey from only the
architectures to flexible microservices
that can dramatically reduce your.
Operational costs.
While accelerating development cycles,
we'll examine practical implementation
steps, real world success, and
critical concentrations for security
business intelligence integration.
By the end of this presentation,
you will have a clear roadmap for
your own serverless transformation.
Now, let's say why migrate
to serverless architectures?
Serverless architectures deliver
compelling benefits that extend far beyond
the simple cost savings organization May.
Organizations migrating from
monolithic systems report dramatically
reduced operational overhead.
So with typical cost reductions
ranging from 30 to 60%, in some cases,
organizations leveraging event driven
serverless patterns per specific
workloads have seen cost reductions
exceeding 70% due to the precise resource
allocation and paper execution models.
So perhaps more importantly, these
organizations experience a 40% boost in
the developer productivity by eliminating
infrastructure management tasks.
This translates to fast innovation
cycles and significantly reduce
time to market for new features.
So studies indicate that serverless
adoption can accelerate feature deployment
by up to 50%, enabling business to
respond rapidly to market changes.
Furthermore, the inherent scalability
of serverless architecture leads to a
20 to 30% improvement in application
resilience, including downtime
and enhancing the USR experience.
So beyond the cost and productivity,
serverless architectures
contribute to improved scalability.
So which means like applications
automatically scale based on demand
handling certain spikes in traffic
with minimal manual intervention, or in
cases, no manual intervention at all.
This can lead to a five times more
increase in peak traffic handling capacity
compared to traditional architectures.
So reduced time to market developers
focus on code not infrastructure
leading to a faster development cycles.
Companies have reported to 25% decrease
in time, in the time required to
launch these new products or features
enhanced operational efficiency.
With managed services handling tasks
like patching and scaling operation
teams can focus on strategic initiatives.
This can result in a 15 to 20%
reduction in operational burden,
increased agility and flexibility.
Serverless enables rapid prototyping
and experimentation facilitating
agile development practices.
Organizations find that
they're able to test and deploy
these new ideas 30% faster.
Environment sustainability, paper
use models, reduced waste wasted
resources contributing to a more
sustainable computing practices.
So this one steady estimated a
potential 10 to 20% decrease in the
energy consumption, but a certain
workloads when migrated to serverless.
Global reach the server.
The serverless platform often provide
a built in global distribution,
simplifying the deployment of
applications to multiple regions.
Some services report latency reductions
of 40% when moving to a global second.
A global edge based service.
S serverless location, simplified
microservices implementation.
Serverless functions are ideal
for building microservices,
allowing for a granular scaling
and independent deployments.
Organizations see up to 35%
decrease in complexity of managing
microservice deployments, even
driven architecture adoption.
So serverless aligns naturally
with event driven architectures
enabling real time data processing.
And asynchronous workflows.
This has been shown to improve
real time processing speeds by
20 to 50% in certain use cases.
These benefits collectively contribute to
more agile, cost effective and scalable
development environment, empowering
organizations to innovate and compete
effectively in the digital landscape.
So when we un, let's try to understand
a bit more about the monolith.
Challenge monolith.
SaaS applications create
significant obstacles that
severely constrain the business
agility and market responsiveness.
They're tightly coupled
components Establish a critical
development bottleneck.
Where even minor modifications require
comprehensive testing across the
entire application, dramatically.
Ex extending release cycles
from days to weeks or months.
Specifically, a study found that companies
utilizing monolithic architecture
experienced and average release cycle
of 12 weeks for new features compared to
three weeks for those using microservices.
This translates to a 75.
Person reduction in deployment speed.
Furthermore regression testing
for a single feature change in a
monolithic application can consume
up to 40% of development time.
Diverting resources from innovation.
The fundamental inability to
scale independent components
leads to substantial resource
inefficiency, forcing organization
to over-provision infrastructure.
To accommodate peak demand scenarios.
For example, a typical e-commerce
platform using a monolithic architecture
might allocate a server capacity
for a black Friday level traffic
year around resulting in an average
of th 60 to 70% of ideal resource
utilization during normal operations.
This over provisioning leads to 32.
50% increase in infrastructure
cost compared to architectures that
will allow for granular scaling.
Moreover, the lack of independent
scaling often results in degraded
performance during peak loads with
reported latency increases up to five
seconds leading up to a 20% drop in.
User engagement.
So additional challenges include
technology lock-in monolithic
architectures often rely on a
single technology stack, making it
difficult to adopt new technologies or
integrated more than cloud services.
This limits innovation and can lead up
to 25% increase in maintenance overhead
as legacy systems become harder to
support increased risk of failure.
A failure in one component can
bring down the entire application
leading to a significant downtime.
So studies have shown that monolithic
applications experience a 40% more
downtime incidents compared to
microservices based architectures
difficulty in onboarding new developers.
The complexity of a large code banks
makes a challenge for new developers
to understand and contribute, resulting
in a 30% increase in onboarding time.
Limited ability to implement
continuous delivery.
So the long release cycles associated
with monolithic applications
hinder the adoption of continuous
delivery, PR delivery practices,
slowing down the feedback loop
and delaying the time to market.
Organizations report a 50% decrease in the
ability to deliver small frequent updates.
Reduced innovation velocity.
The complexity of changing the
code and the risk of associated
with changes slows down the rate at
which the new features can be added.
One study indicated a decrease
of roughly 20% in the number of
new features released per year.
Database contention.
Monolithic applications often rely on
a single database, which can become
bottleneck as the application scales
leading to the performance degradation.
So this can limit the applications
ability to handle high transition,
high transaction volumes.
Database contention can, has
been shown to cause 15 to 25%
reduction in transaction throughput.
These limitations underscore the
need for more flexible and scalable
architecture, such as microservices
or serverless to meet our demands
for the modern SaaS applications.
Now let's take a look at decomposing
the monoliths into microservices.
So these transformation of
microservices require a thoughtful
decomposition based on business
domains rather than technical layers.
The study suggests that organizations that
focus on business domain decompositions
here, 30 to 40% reduction in integration
complexities, post migration,
identify the service boundaries.
I. Let's add map.
So we need to map the functional
domains and business capabilities to
establish clear service boundaries
using domain driven design principles
and event storming techniques,
effective boundary identification
through event storming and context
mapping reveals and natural service.
Demarcations that aligns with
organizational structures
and business capabilities.
Specifically utilizing event
storming workshops can reduce
service boundary definition by the
time of by 20 to 25% and improve
alignment with business stakeholders.
Research indicates that well
defined service boundaries result
in 15 to 20% improvement in the.
Team autonomy.
So define the service interfaces.
Create robust well controlled
version APIs with well-documented
contracts that enforce loose
couplings and enable independent
service evolution organizations.
Implementing API first strategies report
a 35 to 40% increase in the developments.
P due to reduced dependency, adopting
open API specifications can reduce the
API documentation efforts by up to 50%.
And improve developer onboarding.
Further mode version control
of APIs has shown to decrease
breaking changes up to by 25%.
So refactor incrementally extract
services systematically through the
strangler pattern, prioritizing high
value low risk components while maintain
the maintaining the system stability.
Successful migrations leverage the
STR strangler pattern methodology
systematically replacing the monolith
functionality while preserving the system,
integrating implement a service mesh.
Deploy.
Sophisticated service discovery and
communication layer that enables
resilient interservice communication,
circuit breaking and observability.
A single mesh can improve latency back
to 10 to 20% and reduce service value
rates by 90, 50, 30% through features
like circuit breaking and retry policies.
Implementing comprehensive
observability with the service me
leads to a 40 to 50 person reduction
in the mean time to resolution.
It's called S-M-T-T-R for
service related incidents.
Additional points to consider
while decomposing the monoliths
into microservices could be
organizational alignment.
Should the microservice architecture
designs aligns with the organization
structure and culture that's fit
as more important automation.
Automate deployment, testing
and monitoring of update to
enable the continuous delivery
and reduce the manual error.
So implementing the CICD pipelines
can decrease the deployment times
up to by 60 to 70% security.
Implement robust security
measures including authentication,
authorization, and encryption to
protect the interservice communication.
Monitoring and observability.
Implement comprehensive monitoring
and logging to gain insights
into the service performance by
identifying potential issues.
Database management.
Address database management challenges
by considering patterns such as
database per service or shared.
Database with careful schema design.
So by focusing on these principles
and incorporating data driven designs
and organizations can effectively
navigate the complexity complexities
of microservices, navi migration,
and unlock the benefits of increased
agility, scalability, and resilience.
Now let's take a look at a
couple of the AWS services.
The first one would be the AWS
Lambda, the Serverless Foundation.
AWS Lambda serves as the computational
cornerstone of the modern serverless
architectures executing code in
response to events with zero server
provisioning or management overhead.
This paradigm shift fundamentally
transforms the economics of cloud
computing by implementing a consumption
based pricing model that changes precisely
for the compute resources consumed.
Studies indicate that the organizations
are shifting to Lambda based
architecture experience, a 60 to
80% reduction in the operational
overhead related to server management.
Event, even executions functions
instantly activate in response to
triggers from AWS services completely
eliminating idle resource consumption
and delivering true paper use
computing with millisecond precision.
In typical event driven scenarios,
lambda functions demonstr a cold stock,
cold start latency of under a hundred
milliseconds and 90% of invocations.
And subsequent worm invocations achieve
latencies below 10 milliseconds.
This precise, this precision in resource
allocation leads to a 20 to 30% reduction
in overall compute cost compared to
traditional VM based event processing.
Automatic scaling lambda seamlessly
in scales, concurrent executions to
match the real time workload demands
without any configuration overhead,
effortlessly handling everything from a
single request to thousands per second.
Lambda can scale to handle certain
spikes in traffic, achieving a
99.99% availability rate, and can
scale from zero to thousands of
concurrent executions in seconds.
Auto-scaling capabilities have been shown
to reduce the peak load latency by 40 to
50% compared to manually scaled systems.
Polyglot support developers can gain
freedom by leveraging multiple programming
languages across different functions.
Empowering teams to select the
optimal technology stack for
each specific microservice.
The flexibility has been reported
to decrease the development time
by 15 to 25% as teams can utilize
preferred languages and libraries.
Furthermore, teams reported 10 to 15%
increase in code maintainability by
utilizing the right tool for the job.
With Lambda millisecond billing
granularity and zero friction scaling
capabilities, organizations can
achieve unprecedented optimization.
Compared to traditional always on
server instances, enterprises typically
realizes 70 to 90% reduction in
compute costs for appropriate workloads
after migration, while simultaneously
improving responsiveness and
eliminating capacity planning concerns.
Additional data points and benefits
include reduced time to market,
improving default tolerance, simplified
operational complexity, enhanced security.
Like cost optimization for
intermittent workloads.
Integration with AWS ecosystem
and global scalability.
By leveraging these benefits,
organizations can achieve a significant
cost savings and improve operational
efficiency and accelerate innovation.
Now let's take a look at the key
serverless, a key AWS serverless services.
So AWS builds a robust ecosystem
of serverless services that work
harmoniously with Lambda to create
powerful cloud native solution.
So let's take a look at Aurora server as
dynamically adjust the database capacity
in response to application demands
without server management overhead.
So studies have shown that the
Aurora serverless can reduce
database cost by 30 to 50% for
applications with variable workloads.
It auto scales database capacity when
within seconds maintaining a consistent
performance and reducing the need for
manual capacity Planning for application
with unpredictable traffic patterns.
Aurora Serverless has been reported to
decrease database administration time.
By up to 60% API gateway simplifies the
creation of secure scalable APIs that
seamlessly trigger Lambda functions.
API Gateway can handle millions
of API calls per second, ensuring
high availability and low latency.
Utilizing the API Gateway reduces
development time for APAC creation
by 20 to 30%, and provides building
in features for authentication,
authorization, and request violation.
API gateway Caching features can reduce
can reduce a backend load up to 80% for
frequently accessed data, even breach.
So event bridge transform application
architecture by providing serverless
event bus that intelligently routes
events between decoupled services
and third parties as providers
with minimal configuration.
Even Bridge can process millions
of events per second with.
Near real time latency,
typically under 500 milliseconds.
It simplifies integration with third
party SaaS applications, reducing
integration time by 40 to 50% even bridge
filtering and routing capabilities.
Reduce the complexity of managing
event driven architectures, decreasing
development efforts by 25 to 30% S3.
S3 is called a simple storage service.
It provides durable object storage
that integrates seamlessly with Lambda
and other server service S three's.
High durability with 99.9 nines
and availability of 99.99%
make it ideal for storing and
streaming large volumes of data.
S3 when notifications can trigger
Lambda functions, enabling real
time data processing and analysis.
Organization utilizing the serverless
architectures with S3 for data
storage have reported a 20 to 30%
reduction in storage cost compared
to traditional storage solutions.
CloudWatch offers sophisticated
observability capabilities providing
monitoring, logging analytics for
serverless applications, CloudWatch
logs allows for real time log analysis.
Reducing troubleshooting
time by 30 to 40%.
CloudWatch alarms can automatic electrical
lambda functions or other AWS services
in response to performance metrics,
enabling automate automated remediation.
CloudWatch dashboards provide a
centralized review of application
performance, improving the visibility
and reducing meantime to detection by 20,
meantime to de detection by 25 to 35%.
So additional benefits and data
points to consider would be simply
simplified microservices architecture,
the cost optimizations, increased
development velocity, enhance
security, streamline, CICD pipelines.
So by leveraging these comprehensive
ecosystems, organizations can build highly
scalable, cost effective and resilient
serverless applications that drive the
innovation and business business growth.
Let's take a look at the
real world success stories.
A FinTech transformation, a leading
financial service provided slash
infrastructure cost by 45 percent,
while accelerating the time to market
for a new features from months to mere
days by migrating their transaction
processing system to lamb and animal db.
They achieved unprecedented operational
efficiency and customer responsiveness.
So a health healthcare analytics,
a healthcare analytics platform
revolutionized their operations by
implementing serverless architecture
that scales instantaneously
during peak reporting periods.
This eliminated persistent performance
bottlenecks while delivering a remarkable
52% reduction in operational expenditure.
Allowing resources to be redirected
toward page patient care initiatives.
Retail in recommendation engine,
an e-commerce retailer reimagine
their recommendation engine using
serverless microservices dramatically
reducing the response time from
two weeks to just 200 milliseconds.
This 10 times performance improvement
drove the substantial 30% increase in
conversion rates through hyper personal
shopping experience that adapt in
real real time to customer behavior.
These transformative case studies
illustrates the profound impact
of serverless architecture
across diverse industries.
Beyond mere technical improvements
organizations consistently
report enhanced business agility,
substantial cost savings, and new
fund capacity to rapidly innovate
and respond to market opportunities
that were previously unattainable
with traditional infrastructure.
Let's take a look at DevOps cis.
Continuous improvement
and continuous delivery.
First, serverless.
So server architectures requires
sophisticated DevOps approach that
fundamentally embraces infrastructure
as a code principles and fully
automate development pipeline.
So AWS code pipeline seamless integrated
with Lambda to enable comprehensive
continuous delivery workflows that deploy.
Function.
So a PA configurations and database
key changes are as unified atomic unit.
Studies shown that the organization
adopting to mature server DevOps
practices CF 40 to 50% reduction
in deployment related errors.
Infrastructure has code codify services
resources with AWS cloud formation or
the serverless framework to guarantee
reproducible version called as.
Infrastructure deployment across
environment they are version controlled
and it reduces manual intervention
errors up to 60 to 70% and accelerates
environment provisioning by 50 to 60%.
Version controlling IAC templates with
GI ensures auditability and enables
rollbacks reducing recovery time by
up to 30% Automated build pipeline to
establish a robust continuous integration
with AWS code build to automatically
compiled package and validate lambda
functions with the dependencies
code build reduces bill times by 70
to 80% compared to manual process.
Automated dependency management
system ensures consistency and
reduces the reduces works on
my machine issues by 40 to 50%.
Static code analysis and security
scanning with pipeline have been shown
to reduce vulnerabilities by 25 to 30%.
Comprehensive testing.
Deploy a thermal test environments
for thorough unit integration
and performance testing.
Of individual functions
end to end workflows.
Thermal testing environments reduce
the test environments reduce test
environments set up by 80 to 90%
and improve test reliability.
Automated performances can detect re
regressions early reducing the latency
issues in production by 20 to 30%.
Implementing contract testing for
a PS ensures service compatibility,
reducing integration edit by 15 to 20%.
Stage deployments.
Leverage AWS code pipeline with
canary deployment strategies to
methodo methodically introduce changes
while continuously monitoring for
anomalies and performance impacts.
Canary deployments reduce the risk of
widespread failures by 90 to 95% and
enable rapid rollbacks in case of issues.
Automated anomaly detection with
CloudWatch alarms reduce meantime
to detection by 35 to 45%.
Stage deployments combined with
feature flags, reduce the impact
of fail deployments by up to 50%.
Industry leading organizations implement
sophisticated stage deployment strategies
with intelligent rollback capabilities,
preserving the system integrity while
dramatically accelerating release cadence.
This transformative approach has enabled
the forward thinking companies to achieve
deployment frequencies measured in hours.
Sometimes minutes compared to the weeks
or months required with traditional
infrastructure models, specifically
organizations using automated server
as CICD pipelines report a 70 to
80% reduction in deployment times.
Let's take a look at securing
the serverless applications.
Securing serverless applications
require a shift in approach from
traditional infrastructure protection
to function level controls.
Each lambda function should operate
with minimal permissions, allowing
the principle of leased privilege.
With carefully defined IAM rules,
studies indicate that the organization
implementing a frying grained IAM
roll reduce the risk of lateral
movement after the security breach.
B two 40 to 50%.
Function level IAM rules implement
fine grain permission boundaries by
using the principle of leash privilege
for each lambda function, restricting
access to only required resources.
Implementing function level IM roles
reduces the attack surface by 20 to 30%
compared to broad service wide roles.
Utilizing the IM policies with resource
level permissions reduces the impact
of compromise Credentials by up to 35%.
Secrets management restored the
sensitive configuration in AWS Secrets
Manager with automatic rotation.
And secure retrieval by author
authorized functions only.
Secrets Manager reduces the risk
of hard coded credentials by
60 to 70% and automates secret
rotation, reducing the window of
vulnerability, implement the least.
Privilege access to Secrets Manager
ensures that only authorized function
can retrieve more sensitive data, input,
validation, implement strict schema
validation of API at API level boundaries.
Using the API gateway request
validators to prevent injection attacks.
API gateway validation reduces the
risk of a SQL injection and cross site.
The scripting attacks by 30 to 40%.
Implement input validation at the
API layer reduces the load on Lambda
functions, improving performance and
security dependency scanning, integrate
automated vulnerability scanning into CICD
pipelines to detect known vulnerabilities
in third party dependencies.
Dependency scanning reduces
the risk of exploiting known
vulnerabilities by 25 to 35%.
Implementing software composition
analysis, SEA tools in CICD
pipelines reduces the time to
identify remediate vulnerabilities.
Data protection remains critical
with encrypted requirements for
both data in transit and at rest.
AWS provides tools like KMS for,
encrypting key management partners and
partner store for securing configuration,
enabling a comprehensive security
posture for serverless applications.
So the additional data points and security
practices to consider would be networks
segmentation, runtime, security and
logging and monitoring security audits,
immutable deployments, ensuring that the
Lambda function deployments are immutable.
Preventing unauthorized modifications,
web application, firewall rules
encryption address, and in
transit, regular security updates.
This is keep all the dependencies
and runtime environments up to date
with the latest security patches.
Automated patches reduces these
vulnerability windows as well.
By implementing the security practices,
organizations can build secure and
resilient serverless applications
that protect sensitive data.
And minimize the risk
of security incidents.
Business intelligence integration.
Integrating business intelligence
tools with serverless architectures
creates opportunities for
real time decision making.
Analytics pipelines are built on
event principles can process data as
it generate, as it gets generated.
Eliminating the batch processing
delays and providing immediate
visibility into business operations.
Studies show that the organizations
adopting serverless analytics
pipelines, reduced data, progressing
processing latency by 60 to 80% compared
to traditional batch processing,
real time analytics pipeline.
Serverless architectures enable
event driven analysis pipelines
that process real time data
delivering immediate insights rather
than delayed batch processing.
Even capture via even bridge even
bridge allows to capture the e
realtime events from various AWS
services and SaaS applications.
Streaming processing with kinesys enables
realtime data ingestion and processing
kinesys data stream scan, ingest, and
process terabytes of data per hour.
Providing real time data flow.
Kinesys data analytics allows for a real
time SQL IES on streaming data, reducing
the need for complex transformation.
Transformation with Lambda Transform
Lambda functions, perform realtime
transformations and enrichments.
Lambda functions can process
events within milliseconds,
enabling realtime data processing.
Lambda functions can integrate
with machine learning morals for
realtime data analysis, storage
in data lakes or warehouses.
S3 data lakes and Redshift.
Data warehouses provide scalable and
cost effective storage for process data.
S3 Data Lake Scan Store petabytes of
data, enabling large scale data analysis.
Reshift Data Warehouse provide
fast query performance for
complex analytical queries.
Visualization with QuickSight.
QuickSight provides interactive
dashboards and visualizations
for real time data exploration.
QuickSight can generate interactive
dashboards in seconds, enabling
real time data analysis.
Amazon QuickSight.
Paper session pricing model, quick site's,
paper session pricing model reduces cost.
Intermittent users organizations reported
20 to 30% reduction in bi infrastructure
compared to traditional licensing model.
Direct integration with AWS data
sources QuickSight seamlessly
integrates with AWS data sources,
reducing the data preparation time.
ML powered insights.
QuickSight machine learning
capabilities provide automated
insights and anomaly detection.
ML powered insights reduce the time
to identify anomalies by 30 to 40%
embedded analytics capabilities.
QuickSight embedded analytics
features enable seamless integration
of dashboards and applications.
Embedded analytics improve user
engagement by providing data insights
within the application context.
Business outcomes.
The integration of server serverless
analytics deliver a tangible benefits
beyond technical improvement,
driving a better business decisions,
30% faster time to insight,
reduced analytics infrastructure,
cost democratized data access.
Serverless analytics enables self data
exploration, empowering business to
access data without IT intervention
improved customer experience.
Real time.
Insights enable personalized
com customer experience and
proactive service improvements.
Real time data driven responses.
Improve customer satisfaction
score by an average of 50 to 20%.
By leveraging these ties, organizations
can unlock the power of real time
data and significance business values.
So let's talk about our
serverless migration roadmap.
So begin your serverless journey
with a comprehensive assessment
of your current architecture.
Identifying the components suitable for
initial migration Studies indicate that
the organizations that perform a thorough
assessment before migrating ca 20 to 30%
reduction in migration related issues.
The ideal candidates are stateless
services with variable workloads.
That benefit from Lambda automa
automatic scaling and paper use
pricing model, specifically services
with intermittent traffic patterns
or even driven workflows have shown
to yield a 40 to 60% cost reduction
when migrated to serverless initial
assessment and component selection.
Identify the stateless services
such as a p. Points of data
transformation tasks are ideal for la.
Analyze work work workload patterns,
identify services with variable or
un unpredictable workloads services
with the peak to peak to throw traffic
ratios of fi five to one or higher
benefit or higher benefit significantly
from serverless scalability.
Evaluate cost savings potential.
Calculate the co potential cost savings
by comparing current infrastructure
costs with estimated lambda
execution, cost, assess complexity
and dependence and consider the data
processing pipelines pilot project.
And the next step would be the pilot
project and foundational elements.
Start with the pilot project.
Begin with the pilot project to
end to build team experience and
validate your approach Before broader
adoption, build a team experience.
Pilot project helps teams to
gain hands-on experience with the
serverless technologies and best
practices, validate your approach.
Use the pilot project to validate your
infrastructure as code templates and
CICD pipelines create reusable patterns.
Focus on creating reusable patterns
and infrastructure as code templates
that aate future migrations.
Establish foundational elements,
define standards and best practices
for serverless development, securing
and operation standardized practices.
Reduce operational overhead by 20 to 30%.
Implement observability, implement
cloud, CloudWatch, and other
observability tools to gain insights
into application performance.
Organizational change and upskilling.
Invest in upskilling.
Remember that serverless
transformation is both a technical
and an organizational change.
Invest in upskilling your
teams to maximize the benefits
of this architectural shift.
Foster a DevOps culture promoted DevOps
culture that emphasizes automation,
collaboration and continuous improvement.
Empower autonomous teams, organize
teams around business capabilities,
fostering autonomy and ownership.
Encourage experimentation, create
a culture of experimentation and
learning, allowing teams to explore
new serverless technologies.
Establish a center of excellence, create a
serverless center of excellence to provide
to provide guidance, best practices, and
support for teams adopting serverless.
Address security concerns proactively
Address security concerns by
implementing function level, IAM roles,
and other security best practices.
By following these guidelines,
organizations can navigate the
serverless journey to unlock full
potential of this transformational
or architectural approach.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
To conclude, we have seen how AWS
serverless architecture empowers us to.
Move beyond the limitations
of monolithic SaaS.
By embracing the microservices lambda
and automated pipelines, we unlock
potential substantial cost reductions,
accelerate the development, and
enhance security and scalability.
This transformation requires
a strategic approach.
Accessing your architecture, piloting key
services and investing in team upskilling.
The data speaks for itself.
Organizations adopting serverless
experience, significant improvements,
have seen significant improvements
in efficiency and speed.
Let's leverage the power of AWS to build
agile, resilient, and cost effective SaaS
applications driving the innovations and
achieving tangible business outcomes.
Thank you so much.
For listening through my presentation,
I hope you have gained some insights
into the world of transforming
monolithic into a cloud based
approach like AWS Amazon Web Services.
If you have any questions,
you can always reach out to me
at reach ika comp@gmail.com.
I'll be more than happy to talk about
this presentation or anything in general.
Thank you so much.
Thanks again.