Hey everyone.
Thank you for joining me today
for this critical discussion on
ransomware readiness, backup,
and recovery in the cloud.
My name is Sharri pti and I'm a principal
cloud and security architect currently
working for Trade and Track two, with
over 15 years of uni experience across
cloud, security, engineering, DevSecOps,
and cloud solutions architecture.
And then coming to this.
What is ransomware?
So ransomware refers to a business
model that a wide in a wide range
of associated technologies that
unauthorized users to use to export
money from entities, unauthorized
users or system vulnerabilities to
access data and then restrict the
rightful owner from accessing it.
So ransomware encrypts your
data, making it, inaccessible.
Until your ransom is paid, attackers
often demand payment in cryptocurrency.
So before we dive in, so
let's start with some context.
Ransom error attacks have
exploded in recent years.
It's hard to turn on the news without
seeing another company getting hit.
So according to the Sophos 2024 report.
59% of the organizations
surveyed, they were done.
Out of 5,000 organizations were
hit by ransomware in the past year.
That's just the attacks
that were reported.
Many incidents go unreported due to
various reasons, like brand reputation,
stock price impact, various other reasons.
So if you look at the report,
94% of victim, victims said
attackers targeted their backups.
So that means it's, you're just
not, that the attackers are
targeting for your primary data,
but also the backup infrastructure.
So 32% of the victims whose data
was encrypted also had data stolen.
So that means.
They, once your backups are compromised
or your data is compromised, they
will extract the data exfiltration
of data so that they can host
you as hostage for the data.
And then the attacks, 70% of
attacks result in data encryption.
So that means once they accelerated the
data out of the organization or network.
They encrypt the data.
And after that, so organizations
whose attacks began with exploitation
of unpatched vulnerability report
considerably more severe outcomes
than those were with the attacks
started with compromise credentials.
So based on these statistics, the
average initial ransom demand that
was being demanded is $2 million.
And then 98% of the organizations
that were attacked were
recovered their encrypted data.
So either by paying the
ransom or from those backups.
But lately the trend is slowly started
shifting towards the restoration is
happening from the backups that they have.
Which is a good sign.
And then the next one is.
The recovery.
So the average recovery
cost is $2.7 million.
So we excluding ransom payment,
so 30% of these organizations
had more than a month to recover.
So that means once they're compromised,
it's either due to lack of backups
or lack of readiness or playbooks.
There's no proper incident management.
So all these due to these factors.
It can take more than a month
to recover from those incidents.
That means once your applications are
down or your organization applications
are down, it can take 30 days to recover.
That's a lot.
In some scenarios, it can go beyond that.
Today's object two is straightforward
but crucial to ensure you understand
the critical nature of disaster
recovery planning in the context
of modern ransomware threats.
We will explore cutting edge backup
strategies, bat battle tested
techniques, zero trust architectures,
and automated recovery workflows,
transforming your backup infrastructure
from your potential liability into
your strongest security asset.
So let's take a look at
the ransomware landscape.
Ransomware is not a static problem.
The ransomware landscape
is constantly evolving.
You are playing chess with thinking humans
on the other side who can quickly adapt.
Just in the last year, we have seen
threat actors significantly evolve
their tools, techniques and procedures
like ransomware as a service, including
AI based sophisticated techniques.
For example, we have witnessed the rise
of intermittent encryption, so which
speeds of the encryption process and
awais the detection ransomware operations
have become almost industrialized
with the different specialized groups
handling different parts of the attack.
From initial incursion to negotiation
specialists, reactor objectives
are expanding beyond money.
So some groups are now taking
sides in geopolitical conflicts.
Meanwhile, cyber insurance
is falling short.
Major global underwriters are reducing
or re refusing ransomware coverage,
adding sublimates to policies.
And we have seen cases where
payouts were denied, but classifying
ransomware as an act of war.
And attackers.
Usually gain that attack
pattern is established and
repeating across ordinations.
So usually it happens like event
of chain a chain of events.
So attackers gain initial access through
infection vectors, including like
phishing mls in malicious attachments,
drive by downloads, vulnerabilities
in remote access protocols.
Exploited vulnerabilities both
in operating systems or in
framework language frameworks.
So compromise credentials, flawed
public facing applications, something
like S3 or weak authentication setup.
So from there they can get
into your infrastructure, cloud
infrastructure, and cloud storage.
So they do the discovery actions.
Then they can go to the next state
of events like a data destruction,
data exfiltration, data encryption.
So these can impact a lot of ways.
So they establish a persistence.
They move laterally
throughout the network.
They exfiltrate data before encrypting it.
They deploy encryption and demand ransom.
So sometimes in usual cases, some of
these organizations, the attackers were
so persistent that they can stay there
for months, like two to three months.
They will do the slowly
it, these operations in the
backend without any detection.
So once they hold all the footprint
what they want, that's when
they'll start encryption process.
And here is what the particularly
concerning in most organizations
making, it's much easier to block
inbound traffic than outbound traffic.
So making data exfiltration a significant
risk because the, before they do the
encryption, usually they try to exfiltrate
your data so that they'll try to demand
or they'll try to do the extortion.
They'll try to do the extortion
demand sim telling the sensitive
data to expose it public.
And that's what like the, those are like
the chain of events that it can happen.
So coming to attack scenarios, attack
scenarios are a little bit different,
like the same little bit on similar
way that what we just talked about.
So like data encryption.
So usually attackers log down
critical data and files making it
inaccessible, and then system disruption.
So they try to halt your, all your
systems, like operational systems
or rendered unusable, disrupt
critical systems and services.
So that means you cannot operate
anything inside your organization.
Related to infra infrastructure,
IT infrastructure DA acceleration
is a sensitive data is
stolen before encryption.
So they try to have this data before
encryption so that they can demand
ransom payments or threats saying
that this will be released to public.
And then the next one is
the extortion demands.
So they demand ransom payments to
restore access with threats or public
data leaks, like you pay the ransom
through the crypto cryptocurrency.
Then they'll ask, they'll
tell you to give the key.
They'll promise you that,
it never goes that way.
So the common fit Pauls.
In ransomware response is when an attack
happens, organizations often make critical
mistakes that compound the damage.
So these areas are little bit wider here.
So there are inadequate
crisis communications.
So that means too often organizations
lack a clear crisis communication plan.
In the midst of an attack.
You need to know exactly who's involved
and who takes ga specific actions.
Accounting to a P WC study.
Pricewater Cooper study.
69% of our nation that
successfully navigated a ransomware
attack had a documented and
practiced communication plans.
So having that practice and documentation
will really help you when in need.
And there is.
The other one is insufficient
logging and monitoring.
So usually security teams depend on these.
They need access to logs to build
an incident response timelines.
That's how they know when the
attacker enter into the network or
when the data has been compromised.
But many organizations discovered too
late that their logging was inadequate.
So research reports found that
organizations with proper security
monitoring detected breaches 74 days
faster on average than those without.
And the next one is unprepared
for ransom decisions.
So many crucial questions arise
when there is a incident happened.
Who can authorize a ransom payment?
Has your board approved such payments?
Do you have cryptocurrency available?
Are there legal implications?
The user, US Treasury Department,
has sanctioned several ransomware
groups, making payments to them
potentially illegal, so making this
option completely off the table and
then underestimating recovery times.
So most of these organizations often
assume recovery will be quick, but
I. But the co but comprehensive
incident response takes a lot of time,
sometimes without any preparations.
So IBM's cost of data breach
report indicates that the
average time to identify and
contain a breach is 2 77 days.
That's over nine months.
So that's, those are like the common
pitfalls in ransomware response.
So without that proper response,
you will be doomed when there
is a real incident happens.
And then there are back of failures
happens because this is perhaps
the most devastating pitfall.
So many organizations discover
too late that their backups are
either compromised or encrypted.
Incomplete or too or doted to be useful,
inaccessible when needed, most unable
to be restored in a timely manner.
So here the key takeaway, it's not
if, but when ordination should be
ready for ransomware situations.
So how do you do this recovery
planning and the recovery planning
considerations or strategy?
The When planning your recovery
strategy, four key factors will
impact both effectiveness and cost.
So one is scope.
This tells you how much data needs
protection, and then our people,
so recovery point object you.
How much data can you
offer to recreate or lose?
And the third one is r table
recovery time objective.
So how quickly.
Must you recover?
What is the cost of downtime?
And then the last one is copies.
So how many backup copies
do you need to maintain?
So different workloads will have different
requirements, and then these things
can be derived if you, in order to do
the recovery strategy or you want to
do the optimize that recovery strategy.
The critical thing that you need
to do is the data classification.
You need to have, you need to make sure
you have your organization has a data
classification already done or defined.
Take a step back one step back
to like I did mention RPO and
RTO as part of the strategy.
These are critical in defining what kind
of strategy that you want to design.
And to do that, you need to define these.
And you will define based
on the data classification.
So when it comes to RPO and RT O, how
much data can you afford to recreate
or lose when a disaster happens, like
of the disaster happen couple of days
back, can you withstand these two days
downtime or two days loss of data?
That's called RPO.
Then the other one is how
quickly must you recover?
What is the cost of downtime?
That means how long you can
offer to lose your downtime.
So that means your own application is
down, like how long you can offer that.
So you are, you can you offer one hour?
You can, you have eight
hours, can you 10 hours.
So that's our table.
And then.
Coming back to the data classification.
So that's a critical thing in
order to discover your R-P-O-R-T-O
or the scope or the copies.
So how do you decide the criticality?
So if you look at here, you need
to understand what type of data
you have and who owns it, and if
it is critical for your business.
What does actually critical means?
So does it impact your customer?
Does it impact your cus business revenue?
So how do you determine your, the
criticality of data criticality
or data classification?
So you do this by simple flow chart here.
So you can define is your data
operation so operational, that means
your data is being, operated or not.
So that means you have, assuming
your data is completely lost.
So what do you do?
So if the business was to move forward
without the data, or would there be
an impact, if there will be an impact,
that means can the data be recreated?
If you cannot recreate, that means that
is your critical, true, critical data,
and then you should go for a backup plan.
If the data is not that
it can be recreated.
So that means it takes how long
it'll take to recreate the data.
Can it take in minutes or hours?
So based on that new further
guidance is required, and if the
data where there would be impact.
If there is no impact, then
it is not a critical data.
So that's how you simply follow
the chart and determine what
kind of critical data that.
You have.
So first you need to know your data.
And then there's a different payer
and different RP and RP RTOs defined
for each of these kind of bus de,
depending on their data classification.
Generally the Michigan mission critical
systems, these are like re required true
disaster recovery solutions, typically
highest cost here, like example payment
processing, critical infrastructure.
Which typically they have RP and
RTO within less than 10 minutes.
So that means without these systems
you'll be losing a lot of money.
And the next one is
business critical systems.
These are like required for these require
robust disaster recovery solutions.
Examples like ERP systems or customer
facing applications, and generally
these RPOR tvOS for these type of.
Business critical systems is
around less than one hour.
And the next kind of hitting is
business Operational systems like
these are, like, can we often
use standard backup solutions?
The RPO and RT O is like less than eight
hours, like examples, like internal
collaboration tools, reporting systems.
So even if they are down, that's
the impact is not much for any
customer or revenue generation.
And the last but not least,
is administrative systems.
These are like standard.
You can go for standard backup
solutions that are sufficient like
exams and HR systems or documentation
repositories, something like that.
So these typically the RQR and
RQO fall in 24 to 48 hours.
So depending on these that you define
RT o at RPU and the data classification
and critical systems, you can design
your, strategy against your resilience.
So how resilient you want to test set up.
So if you take this one, this
slide gives you three scenarios.
Like one is a backup scenario, how much
it costs, and what are the RT word and
RPO, and then the disaster recovery.
So what are the typical RP and RT was?
Remember that every minute
of downtime costs money.
So according to Gartner, the average
cost of it downtime is $5,600 per minute.
So which extrapolates to over
300,000, 300,000 per hour.
This will help you determine what
kind of application or what kind
of data that you have and what kind
of strategy that you want to build.
Resilience strategy like we, whether
you want to go for backups with RP and
RTO within hours, or you want to go
with the disaster recovery, which has
RPO and RTO within seconds and minutes.
Or you can go for R-P-Y-R-T-O
in real time, near real time,
literal, within seconds.
Like basically this is
a high availability.
So this is this high availability
is designed in the phase of
architecture, operational mechanisms.
That's when you design these things.
Obviously the cost association
will be something respect to
the, each of these strategies.
Then coming to the next part
which is my favorite thing.
So let's talk about a functional
element of ransomware readiness.
So the 3 2 1 1 0 backup tool.
This is an evolution of the
traditional 3, 2, 1 backup strategy.
So design specifically to enhance data
production, again, as modern threats
like ransomware, while ensuring reliable.
Recoverability.
So back in the days when I used to
work on the infrastructure, which
is hosted in the on-prem, this used
to be a standard now like 3, 2, 1,
and then now everything is cloud.
Most of our nations moving towards
cloud and it's imperative that a lot
of the attacks that are also happening
in the same space now, there's a
need to evolve that traditional.
Rule to customize or adapt for the new
threats, modern threats like ransomware.
So let's go a little bit
more in detail on these.
What is 3 2, 1, 1 0 backup rule is,
so the starting one, three through.
So to maintain three copies of your data.
So basically it says you need to maintain
three copies of data, including your
production, so one primary copy, which
is a production, and two backup copies.
This ancy ensures that even if
one or two copies are compromised,
you will have a reliable backup.
And the next is number two.
Use two different type of storage
media storage store backups on at
least two different storage types.
So traditionally it should be
like hard drives, SSDs tapes.
Now with the cloud, you can do
with the cloud storages like block
storage or object storage based
on the Your data classification.
Yeah, in the data tire, this
diversification minimizes the
risk of simultaneous failures due
to hardware or software issues.
The next is one, so keep one copy
offsite, so at least one backup should
be stored in a separate location such
as a remote facility or in the cloud.
These products against local
disasters like fires or floods that
could destroy all on premises data.
Or if it is the cloud, then the
clouds does have regions that
available to zones they do can hit
with these natural disasters like
fires or floods or earthquakes.
So you need to be prepared for that.
And then the next one is store one
copy offline or make it immutable.
So this part is a new.
In adoption of ransomware
readiness or ransomware production.
So you need to make it I immutable.
So this is crucial for
ransomware production.
So one backup must be either offline,
like a gap, completely disconnected
from networks, making it inaccessible
to ransomware, and then immutable,
so cannot be altered or deleted
even by the administrators adding
an additional layer of security.
The last part is zero.
So the zero represents ensure zero backup
errors through regular verification,
regular test that backups are error free
and can be successfully restored ac.
According to your Veeam survey, 40%
of recovery attempt fail and 70,
70, 70 7% of our nations don't test
their backups frequently enough.
I did mention a couple of terms there.
One is immutable, other one is AirCap.
So let's see.
What are those main terms?
So the immutable backups or write ones,
read many, like one model apply to
backup data provides immutability to
recover from accidental or mania ions.
Once data is written to your warm
compliant backup system, which is.
Right ones read many.
It cannot be altered or deleted.
This immutability is your first line of
defense against both accidental deletions.
And the next one is a gap walls.
So this a gap walls is
the key to secure backups.
But immu immutability alone
isn't always enough, like what
we talked about just before.
So we did say that this immutability
is your first line of defense,
but it's not just always enough.
With the recent threats, technology
or sophistication that what is going
through these hands on wear, we need
to take it to the next step further.
That's where the concept
of a gap vault comes in.
So imagine a secure, isolated
location for your immutable backup.
This vault is logically separated
from your primary environment.
Make it significantly harder
for threats to reach and
compromise your recovery data.
With the air gap vault, the immutable
backup copies are locked by default and
further protected through encryption
using service provider owned case.
It's not a custom manager
or customer created keys.
These are with the Hyatt highest
level of encryption, like a S 2 56.
Encrypting recovery points within
service provider owned key, not only
safeguards against accidental or unwanted
deletions of user management keys,
but also reduces operational overhead
and key management costs for users.
I. The Logically aid gap Vault
simplifies sharing backups for
restore purposes across accounts using
Resource Access Manager called ran.
So customers can share the vault
data with the specific accounts,
including cross organization, cross
region for faster direct restored.
Once the vault is shared, the
backups can be directly restored.
Removing the step where backups are
copied into the destination account
first this reduces the operational
overhead time to recover from a data
loss event and cost of extra copies.
These walls can be configured
in couple of modes.
So one is governance
mode and governance mode.
So what is the difference?
Like what is governance mode
and what is compliance mode?
Governance mode is intended to allow
a war to be managed only by the
users with sufficient IAM privileges.
So that means specific level of
administrators can only administer them.
Vault lock is deletable if needed.
So all the recovery points in the
vault are locked and cannot be
deleted until the lock is lifted.
So that's the governance mode and the
compliance mode is a little bit different.
So this is designed for backup walls
in which the vault is expected to
never be deleted or altered until the
data retention period is complete.
So when a vault is comple
is in compliance mode.
Is locked.
The lock can't be changed
because it's immutable.
No one including the root user or your
service provider can manage or remove it.
However, you can define a grace period,
also known as cooling off period before
the war locks and becomes immutable.
The only method to remove the
lock is to terminate the account.
However, doing so also.
Deletes all your previous
backups if needed.
Accounts can be restored from cloud
service providers within some time limits.
So example, AWS, if your account is
getting deleted, then you can always
restore it back within the 90 days.
So that's an AM amount of time.
And then implementation tip.
So AWS backup and Google Cloud now
offers logically walls that are immutable
by default with compliance mode.
Wall log.
These walls support cross account
sharing with the resource access
manager and use service phone KMS keys
to protect against key compromise.
Along with these two providers,
there are other custom providing
solution providers like, veeam.
And then there's other one,
ELAs osteo, there's a red bear.
So there are multiple these different
multiple vendors that who supports
these kind of AAF vault solutions.
And then moving on.
So let's move on to the
advanced backup architecture.
So let's discuss how to implement a
ransom resilient backup architecture.
So if you look at this so before
I go into the architecture diagram
explanation, so I'll just do a little
bit approach like so how this is
approached to recovery architecture.
So it's a multi-layered approach.
In the security world, there is a
concept known as defense and depth.
So let's take a very similar approach
in terms of making it harder for bad
actors to be able to compromise backups.
But defense and depth, similar to
the analogy of casl, the A medieval
casl where you have multiple layers
of defense, you'll have a MO filled
with water, you'll have big capes.
A big approach is no different
in the security world.
So you want to make it as hard as
possible for the bad actors to be
able to achieve those objectives.
So implement a local backup walls
for operational backup needs.
Create a logically air gap
walls in dedicated accounts
to store immutable backups.
So implement these logically air ga walls
for multi-cloud environments as well.
So you can apply that for both
multi-cloud provider or standalone cloud
provider design, a cross design cross
region world architecture to provide
production against regional disruption.
So we do want to specify this because.
If you are doing the backups in the same
region, when it comes to the disaster
recovery, if something happens in that
region, could be natural disaster like
floods, fires, earthquake, anything.
So this will really help you.
So this will serve the boats of
both purposes, disaster recovery,
as well as the ransomware recovery,
ransomware, backup and recovery.
And then establish a clean room, so
which is like a new account for data
validation from the aid gap world.
So if you look at the diagram, so here,
so I have the main production workload
accounts, which is in region one.
So I have all these different type of
workloads starting from object stores,
block storage, like computing resources,
relational databases, those equal
databases or graph TVs or document ds.
So all these are being, locked or
backed up to a local backup vault.
So this local backup vault is being
encrypted with a, either a customer
managed key or a service provider key.
So this will help you in case of any
operational purposes, say you have
some issue happen with your database
and you want to reach, restore the.
Yesterday's backup or right before the
snapshot, right before that incident.
So not related to the security
incident, but basically any
operational incident that happened
internally or some deployment
happened, which corrupted the data.
So you want to roll it back.
So in those case scenarios, this
local backup port will help you.
And the next one.
So we are designing this, the air gap
vaults, to be in a dedicated account
so that way, even if your primary
account gets compromised, you don't
want the attacker to be connected to
your air gap vault account, so that
way your Air Gap vault account is
completely isolated, cannot be reachable.
Neither through network setup or your or
national network or production network to
the dedicated account because you don't
need a network access kind of thing.
It can be either in the
same region or cross region.
So for instance, for
demonstration purpose, I showed
you here as a region too.
So that means we are calling
this as a data bunker account.
So where you'll be saving or centralized
account to manage your a gap.
World datas this one is being
guarded with a service provider keys
itself instead of your custom keys.
So that way.
Even if something happened or attacker
gets gain access to the account, he
cannot do anything without the keys.
So since it is not being created by
custom customer or custom key, it's a
service provider, which he cannot, it's
impossible to get me access for the key.
So that makes it more harder for the
attacker to even touch the ACAP walls.
So even if the account gets
account being compromised.
The account, the backups are
immutable so it cannot be
touched or altered or tampered.
So all they can do is delete the account,
even if the account is been deleted.
We just talked about
it a little bit before.
The accounts can be always be restored
within after some days or within a
few months, so that way you still
have a chance of recording your data.
And then the next crucial point here is.
You have the backup account data,
bunker account where you are keeping
your backups, and then, if the incident
happens, like if the ware attack happened
and there is a need to restore your a
reward backup stuff to your account.
We don't want to do that back to
your primary account like production
account again, back, because you never
know, the attackers still may have
access to your network somewhere.
So don't assume that assume that it is
screen compromised, so don't ever put back
your restore or backups or restored backup
solutions into the same account again.
It'll be compromised again.
The attacker can get an access and then
again, the same, repeated the same thing.
So that's the first thing.
So don't assume that
it's being compromised.
You don't want to go back to that account.
And the next option is you
create a, either you recover
in the same backup account.
Or you can create a fresh account so
that way you can deploy them clean.
So that way you are sure that
attacker doesn't have any access
that's clean, only you have access,
or your automation have access.
Sometimes even if there's a the
assuming the backups are good
is a is also a big mistake.
So you need a security controls
for your backup systems.
So you need implement multifactor
authentication for backup system access.
Use role-based access control
with principle of least privilege.
Enable geofencing to restrict access
from specific IP ranges because
when in case to access the backups
you don't need, everybody doesn't
need, doesn't access your backups.
So only the administrators
or corresponding teams only.
Do the just specific job, so you can
restrict that through the geofencing
and set up detailed audit logging for
all your backup system activities.
That means when these backups are being
done or initiated or completed, so make
sure these actions are being logged so
that way you have a trail log and then
deploy animal detections to identify
suspicious backup behavior in case.
You wanna make sure if somebody trying
to tamper with your backup solutions
as well, or backup systems or walls.
So you need to make sure you have an
MLE detections enabled on these things
to identify that kind of behavior.
And also, next thing is
automated backup testing.
So having backups a backup isn't a backup
until you have successfully restart it.
So that means a crucial, but often
overlooked component is regular
automated testing of your backups.
So according to Gartner, 30% of our
nation that test their disaster recovery
plans find critical gaps that would
have prevented successful recovery.
So it's pretty important to have that
kind of automated backup testing.
So in this scenario I explained or
design in such a way you, you can either.
Do the automated testing in a different
account called the forensic account where
you will be doing the backup, restore, and
then to a actual resource type that which
you want to deploy the data to restore to.
Using that, using the ram
like resource access managers.
You don't need to do a
copy manually or anything.
So it's easy with the air gap vault with
the resource access manager management
access, so you can simply give the
access to a cross account or external
account, anything that you trust, you
can configure that policy so that your
walls are being accessed to the your
resource can be accessed to the backups.
Once you restore the backups in
the account or in the same account,
you can test that backup data that
you need to make sure that you
validate data integrity, verify the
recoverability metrics, and then also
schedule the regular test scores.
So you do that and then you can
also add additional step on top
of it, like a scanning, scan your
data that you restored, so that way
your data is clean, malware free.
Or any kind of ransomware kind of
malware, so that way you can set
up alerts if something like the
automation, automated backup testing
completed successfully or not.
So that way you will be informed and
if it is something happened, you have
a way to track it and then pay the pay
immediate attention to that step or alert.
And then automatically
clean up the test resource.
So once you're done with automa, automated
backup testing, you need to make sure
you clean up your resource because
this is going to incur cost costs if
you want to keep them running, because
it's just not a one-time iteration.
It'll be keep happening every day
or every, based on how you schedule
that kind of backup validation.
It could be weekly ones, daily ones
monthly ones, something like that.
So make sure you document
results for compliance purposes.
And then the last one
is how do you recover?
So in case of actual incidents
happen now you have all these
precautionary steps all in place.
You have the eight gap walls, you have
the locked vault locks, you have the.
Game as Keys service
provider game as keys.
You have the Restore automated test,
backup testing capacities, including
the scanning of the restore resources or
data and the data integrity validations.
So all these are steps
are already been placed.
So now I. It's a one step thing that you
can restore your data in case of actual
incident, if some attack happens and
you cannot use your primary production
environment, you can simply create
a new recovery account or clean room
and then provide the resource access,
management access through the ran.
Through your backup air gap ward to the
new account that you created, and then
you can restore the backups straight.
You don't even need to copy the
backups from the Air gap ward account
to the new clean room because that's
the beauty of air gap ward log.
So you can just assume that role and
then deploy it, restore, restored
into your new clean room, and then
your applications, your all your data
is being restored and ready to go.
So that's a that's a design of a
ransomware recovery architecture, how
you can implement that's effective.
We have, and then the.
As I mentioned earlier, restore
testing is a critical piece
that you need to consider.
So most often this has been overlooked.
Backup, restore testing can assess re
recoverability of your business data
against data loss events and prove the
recovery posture of for compliance using
custom defined resource testing plans.
Because sometimes organizations do
have different kind of complaints
that they need to follow, depending
on type of industry they are in
financial healthcare kind of things.
So those, this will really
help in managing that posture
strong periodic resource test.
The supported resources
that's been backing up.
This will give you a much confidence
on restore care capabilities.
And then moving on to the next
section, which is a ba what factors
impact the cost on these backup cost
associations or backup cost factors?
You can say.
So there are four areas like scope,
how much data needs protection, and
then frequency, how often should
backups occur, and then retention.
How long should backups be stored.
And then the last one is copies.
How many redundant copies are necessary?
So based on these things,
you, your cost can vary.
So if you look at here, so that the
re resiliency options that you want
to choose in the cloud environments,
so usually the backup and restore,
that's a least cost associated because
your RPO and RT was typically in ours.
And then the pilot light,
which is like a ready to go.
But it can take a little
bit recovery point.
Object too can be minutes.
And recovery time object is an hour,
so that means your data is within
the tolerable time, like a few
minutes, but your restore time is
within one hour or one and a half,
two hours, something like that.
And then the warm standby, this will
increase the cost as well because you
are almost maintaining a secondary
kind of setup or environment.
But you will get a good RPO and RTO in
minutes, but the cost will be much more.
Then coming to the last one, act
two Act traditionally in the on-prem
infrastructures architecture kind
of thing, used to have Act two.
Act two, like we used to have a
act two data center, and then there
disaster recovery data center set
up where you have the global load
balancers for every application.
If something goes down in one of
one data center, automatically,
the other one will pick up.
The route traffic will be routed, so
it's like within seconds you won't
see any customer impact or anything.
So it's within seconds
or within real time.
Your RPO and rts are close to real time,
and then cost is much more because you are
paying twice your production environment.
So that's that you should be wary of.
And then coming to cost
optimizations or use cases.
So where this majority of your data
being sitting in your environments
majorly you have three kind of storage
places where one is a block storage.
Something like if I want to take
an analogy of AWS, like it's
EBS volumes, like ideal for high
performance applications requiring
fast access to data, and then
the other one is object storage.
These are best for unstructured
data and large scale storage
needs, like logs or anything.
So this is something related to,
you can analogy with S3 in AWS.
And then the other one is relational
database or the non-relational databases.
This is suitable for applications
needing complex queries and transactions.
Typically, this is like
your RDS in the AWS.
It could be anything.
It could be my QL Postgres,
M-S-S-Q-L, or even the No SQL DB
Cassandra, something like that.
So these are the usual cases there
where you will be mostly, you'll be
placing or holding your data onto.
So based on how your application is
designed when it comes to the automation
best practices, since we know the which
kind of what kind of cloud storage
that you are using for your use cases.
Based on that we can derive the
cost optimization based practices.
So in terms of block storage, so this
is especially like block storage,
something like EBS know your change
rate and projected gout, so you know.
How much data you'll be accumulating or
what is the growth that you projected?
Accumulated data and retain backups
only as long as needed because this
could cost you a little bit more and
use cold storage when appropriate.
So if you, if your data is not
in operation that you just need
it for some kind of rare usage
you can use a cold storage.
That way you can reduce the storage
storage cost for, especially
related to block storage.
And then the obs object
storage, so something like S3.
So use continuous backups with periodic
backups, delete order back object
versions and clean up expired, delete
markets markers, adjust backup retention
and copy frequency retention if needed.
Because those are the few ways
that you can optimize your costs
in the object storage class.
And the third one is database
or relational database storages.
So you can leverage free backup during
continuous backup retention periods.
Some providers offer these kind of
initial free backups, and then you only
keep backups past continuous backups.
Factor in backup copies costs because
based on your database size, you are you.
You can incur a lot of costs when
you want to have number of copies,
more number of copies, so that
will impact directly to your costs.
Associations access and understand your
current cloud backup costs because you
can assess your, what is your current
storage costs are, cloud operation
costs are, and then how, what kind of
backup solution that you are planning.
Like we, we just discussed our couple of
our picture styles or our pictures that
can pull foolproof ransomware readiness.
So these will give you a little bit
more understanding on your backup costs.
Implement lifecycle policies to
automatically move older backups
to lawyers cost storage tiers while
maintaining appropriate accessibility,
because that's, you don't want to
have these ever-growing storage
needs on a hot or hot storages.
So you can go for in infrequent
access or glacier storage,
something like that kind of things.
So that can reduce your storage
costs, especially related to
the cloud optimizations or cost
optimization best practices,
especially related to the storage.
So moving on.
Building a ransomware
incident response plan.
So despite.
Your best efforts, a ransomware attack
may still occur, so therefore, it's
essential to have a robust incident
response plan in place to minimize the
impact and facilitate a safe recovery.
So you need to, there are a few
areas that you need to focus on.
So define roles and responsibilities.
So you need to make sure, establish
a cross-functional incident
response team clearly define
who makes critical decisions.
Include technical, legal, communications
and executive stakeholders.
Document backup escalation
contacts for each one, each role.
Believe me, these things will help you
a lot when you are in a real incident
and then create communication protocols.
So when some when things get seized,
you don't have a way to communicate in
a normal organization, the communication
channels can be down, depending on
what type of incident happened on the
type of ransomware attack happened.
So it could be your administrative
tools or platforms got
encrypted or, systems impacted.
So in those cases, you don't have a
way to communicate in a regular way.
Instead, you should create
your communication protocols
in case if something happens.
So establish secure outand communication
channels, develop templates for
internal and external communications.
Include notification procedures
for regulatory requirements,
document contact information for law
enforcement, and third party experts.
Document recovery procedure is also
important because you need to create a
step-by-step recovery playbook so that you
know who you know, who needs to do which
parts, and what are the sequence of steps.
And you need to include decision
trees for various attack scenarios
and document restore procedures
for inform immutable backups.
Maintain up to date system
conversation documentation.
So these things.
Excuse me.
And then the last one, practice regularly.
This is the most oftenly over liquid item.
So until, unless you test your backups.
Unless you test your backups and they're
valid, you cannot call them backups.
So you need to practice these regularly.
So conduct tabletop exercises quarterly,
run full recovery simulations at
least annually or semi-annually.
Update processes based on
exercise findings involve
executors in practice scenarios.
Remember that in the heat of incident
documented procedures are invaluable.
The National Institute of Standards and
Technology reports that organizations
with documented incident response
plans resolve incidents 40% faster
than those without these plans.
So coming to the end, so I'll just
to do a few conclusion and key stake,
key takeaways from this session.
To wrap up today's discussion.
So let's emphasize these critical points.
So ransomware is evolving and
inevitable, so it's not going away.
So you need to, it's not
a matter of if, but when.
So that threat landscape continue
to evolve with attacks becoming
more sophisticated and demanding.
So how, it doesn't matter how,
what kind of shift left kind
of strategy that you follow.
Predict two or pro to or detect two
kind of tools that you implement
or technologies that you have.
The scale that it is evolving, the
ransomware is evolving, the threat
landscape is abnormal so that the
sophistication is also extended with
recently with the ai introduction.
So you know for sure it's not.
It's not if, but when, and then
backups are your last line of defense.
So believe me.
So if, but only if backups are
properly protected, tested,
recoverable, adopting the 3, 2,
1, 1 0 rule that we talked about.
Zero.
Trust, ransomware architecture, and
immutable backups provide a solid
foundation for ransomware resilience.
And the third one, recovery
capabilities must be tested.
So untested backups often
fail when needed most.
So regular testing is essential to
ensure your recover capabilities are
functional and prepare preparedness
preparation reduces impact.
So orations with documented and
practice response plans recover faster
and experience less financial impact.
And then the last but not least
is incident response requires
cross-functional collaborations.
So the technical teams, executives,
legal, communications, and other
stakeholders must work together
tirelessly during an incident.
So I would like to close with this part.
Ransomware readiness isn't
just about technology.
It's about people,
process and preparation.
The organization that handle
ransomware incident most effectively
are those that have invested
time in planning, practicing, and
preparing before an attack occurs.
Thank you for attending
today's UDE conference.
Hope this session is useful
for you and your our nation.
Thank you.