Hey there.
I'm Paige Cruz, a former SRE, current
open source observability advocate at
K Chronosphere and Forever Bravo Holic.
Now, today I'm sharing how the Real
Housewives have taught me valuable
lessons about running effective
postmortems, and even understanding
the nature of reality itself.
Let's dive in.
For those unfamiliar the Real
Housewives follows groups of
affluent women in different cities
as they navigate relationships,
businesses, and social lives.
Now what makes Reality TV fascinating
to me is how it reflects the multiple
layers in perspectives on reality
from the housewives themselves to the
producers, and even us as viewers at home.
My central argument today is that the
power of an effective postmortem, like
a productive Housewives reunion isn't
about establishing the objective truth.
It's about engaging with multiple,
valid, incomplete, and yeah, sometimes
competing perspectives to uncover
deeper insights about our system,
our responses, and ourselves.
Now, there are plenty of ways
to adapt traditional postmortem
templates and meetings approaches
accordingly, which I'll be sharing.
But really the genesis of this talk
really came to mind while I was
rewatching Beverly Hills season one.
There was a typical she said,
situation between Kyle and Camille.
Kyle claims.
She simply asked, why would
they film you solo in Hawaii?
Camille claims that Kyle asked.
This question instead, why would they be
interested in filming you without Kelsey?
Kelsey Grammar her celebrity husband.
Both women remained convinced of
their interpretations as the truth
of what happened, and each filtered
the conversation through their own
context and, mental model and biases.
The kicker, this conversation
happened off camera, off mic, so
there was no objective evidence.
And fans often try to
decide who was right.
Was Camille Insecure about being
in her celebrity husband, shadow,
and thus Prime to hear dismissal?
Was Kyle familiar with production
logistics, having grown up on Hollywood
sets and genuinely was curious
about practical filming concerns?
What made this conflict illuminating,
both during the season and at
the reunion where they rehashed.
This was how it revealed the
underlying dynamics and motivations.
Camille was feeling vulnerable as
her marriage was ending, and Kyle is
always concerned about her position of
security within the friend group, and
it was really seeing how their different
backgrounds and perspectives created
this perfect communication storm.
And those insights were only able to
emerge by giving both parties space to
share their perspectives rather than
crowning one version as the truth.
So reunions every season ends with
one, and it's where all of the
cast reconvenes to rehash the major
events of the season and address
simmering, unresolved conflicts.
And here again, multiple
realities exist simultaneously.
Viewers at home, we see this polished
production with a narrative arc, beginning
with pleasantries diving into the drama
cast member by cast member with carefully
placed commercial breaks at peak tension
moments ending with everybody coming
together, even if they're still holding
onto grudges, but clinking their glasses
and raising a toast to next season.
This is a view that's a little
bit closer to what the Housewives
see during the reunion.
They're split pitted against
each other across two couches.
They're tired from having woken up
at the crack of dawn to get to set,
get into hair, makeup and styling,
sitting for hours under hot lights
with a whole crew directing their
attention, focus, and energy to.
Water's gonna be a fairly
dramatic rehashing of events.
They're sitting there all knowing that
the next season's contract and continuing
to keep their jobs and cash their
paycheck depends on making a splash.
This mirrors our technical postmortems.
They're the engineers who are
on call remembering the stress
and pressure of troubleshooting.
There are engineers who weren't
involved at all and perhaps only
see the final post-mortem report.
There are managers focusing on impact
team dynamics and velocity, and as
always, there are executives who
sometimes misguidedly seek assurance
that this can never happen again.
Despite sharing the same incident,
each person experiences and prioritizes
different aspects of the response based on
their roles, focus and responsibilities.
Even our objective evidence, telemetry
data, monitors, dashboards, runbooks,
have already been filtered by what we
collectively decided was important enough
to track, instrument or write down.
Recognizing the validity of these
multiple perspectives is going to
create the foundation for open sharing,
empathy building, and productive
learning, which is exactly what we want
the outcomes of our postmortem to be.
So pour yourself, whatever beverage
helps you process this new paradigm.
And let's dive into seven lessons
from The Real Housewives universe
that can transform your postmortems
from reliability theater into
valuable learning opportunities.
Lesson one, bring receipts.
When a housewife makes a bold claim at a
reunion or during the season, castmates
immediately demand, show me the receipts.
That's evidence like timestamps with
texts, screenshots, or rolling back the
tape to reveal exactly who threw the wine
on whom and at what point in the evening.
I have your perfect formula,
receipts, proof, timeline, screenshot.
Everything in that clip, Heather
was accusing a fellow castmate
of being behind an Instagram
account that had been trolling
and harassing the women for years.
Her revelation landed precisely
because her evidence was irrefutable.
In SRE, our receipts are more
like monitors, telemetry data
like traces, logs, or metrics.
Errors, dashboards, maybe the series
of updates posted to the status page,
all of which are crucial pieces for
reconstructing an incident timeline.
But here's where we should
diverge from the Housewives.
Our evidence shouldn't be kept
secret for a dramatic reveal
or used for a gotcha moment.
I believe that our incident reports
should be a portal allowing anyone
to explore the incident and system
interactions on their own term and time.
Imagine a future engineer who's
really hungry and curious to learn
more about the system, who stumbles
across your incident writeup.
How far could they explore and engage
with the data that you have presented?
I'd say if you're providing
a screenshot to a dashboard.
Go ahead and provide a link
that's pinned to the exact time
range for that incident duration.
Allow people to see data.
Get curious and then
follow the breadcrumbs.
It's really powerful to see something
interesting, be able to go review
the data, inspect queries, maybe
tinker with aggregations or time
windows, and really engage with
this material in a hands-on way.
My other pro tip is to add enough
context and details so that engineers
who are outside of your team or
domain area of expertise are able to
understand the gist of what happened.
This is all about making your
receipts accessible, not weaponized.
Lesson two.
It's not just the facts that
matter, but our feelings as well.
I don't think that he's good for you.
How do you know what's good for me?
That's my opinion.
Meet Tamara, judge of Real
Housewives of Orange County.
Dramatic yes, but also deeply human.
This wasn't a petty argument over
shoes or missing party invitation.
She was sharing her real feelings
and opinions about the man her friend
Vicki was dating who'd embroiled Vicki.
Among other things, a very long con
fabricating a cancer diagnosis just
as emotions run high at reunions.
They also shape our incident coordination.
I. Response and reflection feelings
during an incident can span a wide
spectrum from despair to vigilance to
shock at discovering that deprecated
API isn't actually deprecated to pride.
Watching your team confidently dive
in, investigate, and collaborate.
And when reflecting on incidents,
we often focus on the negative, the
stress, fear, anxiety, and exhaustion.
This negativity bias causes our brains to
hold tighter onto those bad experiences
more strongly than the positive ones.
And while we shouldn't invalidate
these challenging emotions, postmortem
reports, in my opinion and experience
typically overemphasize them.
Three ways that you can counter
this negativity bias is asking what
prevented this situation from worsening?
What aspects of our response
are you most proud of?
And where did we get lucky?
These questions reveal strengths that
we can deliberately amplify, not just
highlight weaknesses and deficiencies
that need to be addressed through
a laundry list of action items.
Lesson three, facilitation is a skill.
Let's roll the tape.
During your fight with Carol, you
got in a jab saying, at least I'm not
50 years old, but you stopped there.
What was the rest of your insult
before you cut yourself off?
That's Andy Cohen, host and executive
producer of The Real Housewives.
What you just witnessed
isn't facilitation.
It's provocation designed to generate
viral moments at the expense of
participants comfort and dignity.
This approach creates the exact
opposite of psychological safety.
I. It's an environment where
vulnerability is weaponized.
Mistakes are spotlighted for
entertainment, and participants arrive
on the defense and armored for attack.
In our world, this is a bit of an
anti-lesson because for technical
postmortems, psychological safety
is the foundation of upon which
all of our learning is built.
It does mean that we need to create
conditions where people can speak.
Honestly about what they saw,
what they did, and what they
thought during an incident without
fear of career consequences,
punishment, or public humiliation.
When this type of psychological safety
exists, people shift from defending
their actions to examining them
objectively, alongside others, and
this transformation isn't just nice.
It's necessary for meaningful learning
to occur, and you can cultivate this.
By modeling curiosity rather than
judgment when asking questions
explicitly stating that the goal is to
learn not to blame, and acknowledging
your own mistakes and limitations.
Balancing airtime is another
crucial aspect of facilitation.
This chart comes from an account
called the Bravo Analyst that
tracks the screen time each cast
member gets throughout the season.
What makes this data so fascinating to
me is that all of the women are filming
roughly the same amount of time and
hours, but as we can see, some dominate
the final edit and others barely appear.
This reveals the invisible hand of
production, the deliberate choices made
behind the scenes about whose stories
get amplified, whose conflicts drive
the narrative, and whose perspectives
are going to shape the viewer's
ultimate understanding of events in
our postmortem, the facilitator plays
this producer role and without careful
attention to balancing airtime, the
loudest voices, often the ones with the
most seniority or sway can dominate.
This means different perspectives
get filtered out, not because
they lack value, but because they
don't have space to be expressed.
Notice how Andy's question, what
was the rest of your insult?
Immediately would put
anybody on the defensive.
It frames the housewife as the
aggressor and invites judgment
rather than understanding.
In contrast, effective
postmortem questions focus on
the how rather than the why.
Why questions often come across as
accusatory and trigger defensiveness.
Why didn't you check the logs?
Implies a failure or deficiency?
How?
Questions, however, invite,
description and exploration.
How did you approach
troubleshooting at that point?
Which open space for the responder to
share their context and thought process?
And I'll just add, facilitation is
absolutely a skill that can be learned
and honed through practice in feedback.
If you're looking to develop this
skill in yourself, I highly recommend
the debriefing facilitation guide from
Etsy circa 2016, but totally evergreen.
And lastly, as a facilitator.
Your mindset and energy sets the
tone for the entire meeting and the
vibe of the room, and it doesn't
have to be stuffy or sterile.
At SR Econ Katie Wilde from sny shared
that she begins every incident review by
playing a specially selected song that
she thinks relates or ties to the outage.
This change transformed
postmortems into anticipated
meetings, creating a buzz around.
What song was Katie gonna pick and play?
I think this is a fabulous way of
getting people primed, open, feeling
creative, and ready to share.
If you need musical inspiration from
the Housewives universe, an incident
relating to a cloud spend surprise, try.
It's expensive to be me by Erica Jane.
If you've got a security breach, insecure
by Candace, we'll have your back.
And delayed logs causing a log jam.
Don't be tardy for the party by Kim
Z. This brings us to lesson four,
the meeting before the meeting.
Part of SRE involves influencing
without authority, and I've interpreted
this mostly as strategic networking
because while formal postmortem
reports and meetings are essential.
Significant value can emerge
from conversations outside
those official channels.
I haven't heard from her
in a couple of months.
She sends me a text yesterday
basically trying to silence me.
It was so manipulative.
It was so calculated here.
Kyle was attempting to control the
narrative through backroom deals and
secret packs, which fans refer to as
self-producing or in the corporate world.
We might call the meeting
before the meeting.
The other thing I noticed in that
is Dorit splashy dramatic reveal was
likely egged on by her own producer who
was incentivized to get high ratings.
And producers again remain
largely invisible despite.
Wielding enormous influence.
They're the ones asking leaning
questions and confessionals.
They create situations designed to
trigger conflict and ultimately are
the ones who decide what narrative
threads to develop in air and what
gets left on the cutting room floor.
But an SREI do think we could put on
that producer hat and wield narrative
shaping power for positive outcomes.
Amy.
Toby introduced me to the concept of
one-on-one debriefs in her brilliant
talk at SR Econ, one-on-one SRE.
Unlike Kyle's manipulative texting
these one-on-one debriefs strengthen
working relationships and deepen
collective understanding where Kyle
sought two silence perspectives.
These one-on-ones deliberately
create space for voices that
might otherwise remain unheard.
Amy's approach includes some
powerful questions like.
What surprised you most
about this incident?
Were you able to access the support
you needed during the response?
Did our tools and documentation
serve you effectively?
And my favorite?
Did you practice self-care
before and during the incident?
This question rarely appears in
standard postmortem templates, which
is wild because Responder Wellbeing
fundamentally affects everything from
incident duration to the quality of
the long-term solutions proposed.
This is just a handful of the
recommended questions from Amy, the
ones that resonated most with me.
I really encourage you to watch the
full talk or leaf through her slides.
For the full list.
I tried this one-on-one debrief approach.
After an incident we affectionately called
Kaf Apocalypse, which was major multi-hour
incident resulting in data loss.
By consciously producing these pre-meeting
conversations and weaving together
the resulting insights resulted in
uncovering layers of understanding
that just wouldn't have surfaced
from our typical group setting.
Single hour postmortem meeting.
What was most important to me was
that the developers who experienced
acute stress felt heard, and that
their experience was meaningfully
acknowledged and received by the org.
This brings us to lesson
three, let the Mouse Go.
Which became a memorable legendary
housewife's moment from Sutton.
Streck said it five
years ago when I met her.
Let the mouse go.
Seriously.
The backstory is that another castmate had
invited everyone to a party and said there
would be a special guest in attendance.
Somebody.
They all knew Sutton.
Anxiety spiraling had somehow
convinced herself this special guest
was somebody she actively was having
a business conflict and beef with.
It wasn't, and the whole thing could
have been forgotten except Dorit
kept bringing it up, exaggerating
Sutton's reactions and remarks at
every opportunity culminating in this
explosive blowup at an all cast dinner.
The takeaway here is don't be the dori.
Know when to let the mouse go.
What do I mean by that?
We all have our reliability soap
boxes or longstanding systemic issued.
We'd like to see addressed and
have been bemoaning for years.
And if this is you, it is really tempting.
I will admit.
It is so tempting to use these
incidents and impacts as validation
that you are right all along.
And dear God, could somebody
just listen to you, give you
a roadmap and fund a team?
Let's be real.
Unlike the infamous psychic Allison Deis
from the dinner party from hell, you
aren't clairvoyant and no, you couldn't
predict exactly when and how an incident
could unfold or what the impact would be.
If you could, you would be
called AIOps and at least triple
your current take home pay.
So remember that these I told
you so moments actively undermine
our collective learning goals.
And they shift the focus from
understanding what happened
to assigning credit and blame.
I'll note this isn't about
suppressing legitimate concerns.
It's about strategic focus and supporting
the goals of the postmortem at hand.
Lesson six time box, it.
If you've ever suffered through a three
Part Real Housewives reunion filled
with endless flashbacks and circular
arguments, you understand the pain of a
meeting that doesn't know when to end.
Let's see how co-facilitator Andy handles
the long day shooting at a reunion.
I've had an incredibly
difficult last two years.
Don't you dare.
I'm sorry I didn't.
Okay.
I like being able to have
that banter with my friends.
Am I boring you?
I didn't have the desire.
No, I'm sorry.
I swallowing you.
Are you me?
Are you kidding?
I'm sorry again.
I'm really two.
Sorry.
I'm like, sorry.
Let me pull it back so I
can not be long winded.
Andy says, we're well past the
point of you being long-winded.
Post-mortem meetings like reunions
need clear time boundaries,
and this isn't revolutionary.
It's basic meeting courtesy.
Deeper discussions emerge that require
more time than you have allocated.
Go ahead and schedule those separately,
but don't let them derail your
primary objectives as a participant.
If you know that you tend towards
veracity, gather your thoughts ahead
of time, and when you're speaking,
keep an eye on the clock to note how
long you have been chattering away for.
Or perhaps challenge yourself
to listen first and only speak
after multiple people have shared.
On the flip side, if you're the
facilitator, you should probably
have a sense of who might send things
off track and prepare strategies
to reroute the conversation.
Respect everyone's time by staying focused
on your learning goals and on time.
No mega multi-hour
marathon meetings, please.
We do not need a three part postmortem.
Finally, lesson seven.
Most important of all.
Avoiding the blame game.
The way we talk about blame, at least
within tech and reliability, has evolved
across my career span from blame as the
default, which unfortunately is where
many organizations are stuck today
to blamelessness, which I think also
somehow lost its way after becoming
buzz worded, leading us to today's
measured blame aware approach, at least.
That's what we're using the last time
I checked the blogs and I'm happy
to give you an apology, Meredith.
Here's a few things that
I'd like an apology for.
Number one,
gotta love SLC.
In that clip, Angie wasn't willing
to hold herself accountable until
Meredith apologized for the very long
list of grievances on that prop scroll.
Angie clearly wasn't seeking
understanding or forward movement.
She was casting blame and
withholding accountability.
Blame seeks to find the person
or people or team responsible
for causing the incident.
It creates a retributive culture
focused on punishment, which erodes
trust, harms relationship, and
importantly prevents learning.
It also increases risk.
Secrecy.
A new word to me which I've read,
is the tendency to hide mistakes
or information that might get
those fingers pointed at you.
The alternative is a restorative
culture founded on trust,
learning, and accountability.
It seeks to understand what not,
who was responsible for an incident.
Here's the truth.
People don't come to work
intending to cause incidents.
Developers don't wake up and say, what
level of sev should I cause today?
And similarly in the housewives world,
castmates don't join franchises planning
to betray decades long friendships.
People make decisions that make
sense given their understanding,
available information and
pressures that they're under.
Recognition of this shared humanity is
where our valuable learning can begin.
Here's a particular passage
from Sydney Decker's.
Stop blaming a passage that I
clearly vibed with on my first read.
People didn't make bad choices.
They probably had bad choices, and your
org has a gigantic role in having handed
them out based on my emphatic highlights.
I wonder if you can guess which type of
culture I was working in at the time.
This book, stop Blaming outlines
how Blameful cultures harm us, and
importantly provides a roadmap for
building a restorative culture.
I highly recommend you check it out, spin
up a book club at your company, and invite
the executives to read this one with you.
Now, these seven lessons from
the Fabulous Ladies of the Real
Housewives can transform how
we in SRE approach postmortems.
Both of our worlds involve humans trying
to construct meaning from complex,
evolving, and emotionally charged
situations with limited information.
And I'd be remiss not to mention that our
worlds do differ in a couple key ways.
First, Housewives are incentivized
for drama and viral moments.
Their paychecks literally depend on it.
We, thankfully, are not rewarded for table
flips or throwing drinks, but instead,
success metrics around system stability.
Learning and continuous improvement.
And the second difference
is obviously the fashion.
Now, I'm not gonna co-sign
all of these outfits, but you
cannot deny they've got style.
I have yet to walk into an incident
postmortem where folks showed up
in color coordinating floor length
gowns or sky high Louboutins.
I'm not opposed to it.
Maybe this is another lesson we could
take from the ladies, but beneath these
surface differences lies a profound truth.
In both reality TV and technical
incidents, there is not a
single objective reality.
There are only perspectives in
complete, biased and uniquely valuable.
The most powerful insights and learnings
emerge when we listen deeply to each
other's experiences, and when we approach
complexity with humility and curiosity.
Next time you're in a postmortem,
remember to bring the receipts, honor
those emotions, facilitate with care.
Try out those incident
one-on-one debriefs.
Know when to let the mouse go.
Respect time boundaries,
and resist the blame game.
If this type of practical and tactical
information on making operations
on call and incident response more
effective and sustainable for us humans.
If this type of content is your jam,
check out my podcast off Call at off
call dot simple cast.com for more.
Season two is dropping very soon.
Thank you.