Today I'm excited to walk you through
how we used SRE Principles and
Advanced Mission Learning to solve a
real business pain point fraud in MCC
reimbursement, the fraudulent activities
within the Michigan Catastrophic
Association reimbursement System.
Industry billions annually with
insurance for 40 billion in
across all non insurance sector.
The c. C faces increasingly
sophisticated challenges.
The traditional detection on manual review
and rule based system have proven in.
Trans fraud prevention in
MCC reimbursement landscape,
so this scale of insurance fraud,
the fraud in insurance is not
new, but it's growing US Insurance
fraud costs over 40 billion a
year, excluding health insurance.
MCCA reimbursements are particularly
vulnerable due to high value
nature of medical claims.
Traditional systems catch
fraud late or not at all.
Imagine catching it after
millions are paid out.
That is not sustainable.
We need a real time in
intelligence system.
The MCC.
Auto insurance claims that exceed
standard coverage thresholds,
making it particularly vulnerable
to high value fraud schemes.
These sophisticated operations
often involve networks of
providers, attorneys, and claimants
working in to exploit the system.
The financial impact extended beyond
direct losses affecting premium
rates for all policyholders and.
The limitation of fraud detection.
A legacy method involves manual
review and rule-based systems.
Problems are, rules are outdated and
easy for fraudster to work around.
Manual process do not scale.
We're talking about
thousands of claims per week.
Data silos across systems
and direction limit context.
The results, which is most fraud
is detected after the post-payment
and some is not caught at all.
The traditional methods struggles
to emerging fraud patterns.
High value claims present, particular
challenge environment where sophisticated
fraud schemes can easily bypass
conventional detection approach.
So advanced mission learning advantages,
the mission learning models learn patterns
and it uncover and improves with the data.
Flag suspicious claims before payout,
reducing risk and operational burden.
The mission learning at speed scale,
consistency, the things which humans
alone can't manage effectively.
So advanced mission learning
transforms broad detection by a.
Processing vast amounts of data.
Instant, these systems can identify SubT
connection between seemingly unrelated
claims and detect organized frauds
that might otherwise remain hidden.
Key mission learning technologies,
which c. Scan images, data from medical
documents and detect tampering or
duplication, which is basically visualize
the data such as medical images, extend
photos and scan documents, and then it
can detect manipulated or inconsistency.
Esry often used in the.
Excel, identifying suspicious patterns in
claim histories, treatment sequences, and
billing that human reviewers might miss.
And the last one is transformer models.
State of natural languages
processing technology that
examines narrative descriptions
in the claims for inconsistencies.
Language patterns associated, these
technologies have demonstrated
23% improvement in fraud detection
accuracy compared to early methods,
substantially reducing losses while
streamlining the claim process.
Using modern streaming stream
protic processing tools like
Kafka Flink, we are enabled.
Subsequent fraud detection claims are
now screened in real time with the
all generated before once released.
This drastically reduces false.
Focus on focus only on high
risk prioritized cases.
With the advanced machine learning
system, it's gonna be enable near
instance fraud detection, and it's
gonna reduce the time between the claim
submission and fraud identification.
The speed is crucial for high value
MCC claims where early detection can
prevent substantial loss and reduce
the complexity of recovery efforts.
So the realtime analysis allows insurers
to intervene before payments are issued.
Shifting from a reactive to
proactive fraud prevention approach.
Feder learning cross
jurisdiction data sharing.
So a breakthrough in data
collaboration, federated learning.
It allows insurers are agencies
to retain shared models
without sharing sensitive data.
Each party trained share raw.
Compliance and privacy.
This help us identify cross fraud
drinks without violating data laws.
So the Predator Learning allows
in rare regulators and MCCA
collaboration on fraud detection
while maintaining data privacy and.
Approach, 85 to 90% of centralized
detection accuracy while keeping
sensitive data within its original
direction, enabling unprecedented
cross organization collaboration.
So the miserable business impact, and you.
These results are speaking the volume,
50% drop in fraudulent payouts in
pilot areas, reduce manual review by
70% and positive rate drop meaning
fewer delays for genuine claims.
All this leads to better
customer satisfaction, which.
So 50 to 60 reduction in losses
within the first year of deployment,
and additionally, there's a 40 to
50% decrease in manual as AI systems
screening, allowing human investigators
to focus on complex cases requiring.
Friction in the claims claim process
and increasing overall satisfaction,
emerging technologies and
future predictions directions.
So these emerging
technologies, what is next?
Next?
The process are evolving and so must we.
So what are the next gen capabilities?
Biometric, which is basically
a multifactor that combines
facial recognitions.
Verification, this advanced system
that can authenticate medical records,
police reports, and other documentation
by analyzing the microscopic printing
patterns, signature and constant
consistency, and the predictive modeling.
This is next generation algorithm that
identifies potential fraud schemes
before by analyzing emerging patterns
and anomalies across the industry.
These technologies prevents cutting
edge of fraud prevention, offering the
MCC and in unprecedented capabilities
to stay ahead of increasingly
sophisticated fraud schemes.
Each builds up upon the foundation
of current mission learning
language systems while addressing.
So what are
regulatory complaints,
considerations when using the
Sable results?
That can be justified to
regulators and policy holders.
This includes documentation of training,
data sourcing, and addition factors,
data privacy, compliance, maintaining
compliance with the state and federal
privacy regulations while leveraging
comprehensive data or fraud detection.
This requires robust data.
To prevent outcomes in automated
fraud detection systems with
regular audit, potential bias,
human oversight intervention.
So we need to establish protocols
where human experts review algorithm
decision, particularly for.
Implementation, careful attention to
regulatory requirements and ethical
standards by designing system with
the compliance in mind from the
outset insurers, and avoid refall
while maximizing fraud detection.
So the implementation.
First, we need to assess the current
process, which is we need to evaluate the
current vulnerability and data readiness.
Started small.
We need to start with the pilot
program and start with the
targeted implementation, high
risk areas, trained models.
It.
Bring the staff and develop ai.
Human collaboration scale
gradually adding more claim types
and integrating across regions.
So the key was cross-functional
collaboration and agile iterations.
Successful implementation of
A-M-L-M-C-C, A fraud prevention
request, a strategic approach.
Begin with the assessment.
Current fraud vulnerabilities
and data management capabilities.
Develop a pilot program, target high
risk claims categories to demonstrate
early wins and refine the system.
Gradually scale the solution across
all claims types while fostering an
organizational culture that effectively
combines human expertise with the mission.
Mission intelligence.
This balance approach delivers
a great impact while minimizing
disruption to operations.
Thank.