Welcome everyone.
I'm Alo Engineering Manager for
Storage Platform at Dropbox.
Today we will discuss how we scaled
observability with Grafana Lokey.
Our agenda covers the context
of our observability challenges.
The technical and operational
requirements, we faced our evaluation
of different logging solutions.
And finally why we chose Lowkey.
Before we dive in let me give you
some context about my background.
I'm currently an engineering manager for
the storage platform team at Dropbox.
Prior to this I worked at Big
Switch Networks, VMware and Cisco,
primarily focusing on storage
systems and scalable infrastructure.
My team at Dropbox is responsible
for ensuring our storage systems
can handle massive scale while
maintaining security and performance.
To appreciate why this problem was
so challenging let's first look
at the scale at which we operate.
Dropbox serves over 700 million
users globally with more
than 18 million paying users.
We are handling over a trillion pieces
of content and, we are processing
over billions of new files, uploads
every single of every single day.
Let's start by defining what we mean
by unstructured logs so we can better
understand our problem statement.
Unstructured logs are essentially
raw data outputs that don't adhere
to any defined schema, unlike.
These structured logs, right?
Hi records or traces, which are
neatly formatted at Dropbox.
These logs come from various sources,
including our first party code and
third party debug files, such as
those found in wall log Dropbox.
Because these logs lack a
predefined structure, they offer
a high degree of flexibility and
detail making them incredibly
useful for realtime troubleshoot.
However, that same flexibility
means that analyzing them can be
challenging and time consuming,
especially when you need to quickly
pinpoint an issue during an incident.
Let's go over our problem statement.
As I said, unstructured logs are stored
in wire logs prior to, our implementation
or our adoption of lowkey, we didn't have
an actual logging solution at Dropbox.
Developers used to SSH
into individual boxes.
We had a host rotation
policy of seven days.
That means after seven days, the
host will be rotated out, so all the
logs on that host will be deleted.
Around that same time, we were
also migrating from standalone
host to containers, and as
containers are even more ephemeral.
They can just vanish any moment.
Also, as searching into a container.
To, exactly go to Word log.
Dropbox was also not that easy.
That was also a little cumbersome.
So this was the entire problem statement.
So from there we gathered
a high level requirement.
We needed to provide a user friendly
and secure interface that makes it
easy for production service owners
to look at their unstructured logs.
As I said, our current process
involved manually as searching
into hosts to retrieve logs, which
was not efficient and error prone.
We wanted to automate and
simplify this process.
We wanted to make sure the system is
capable of in ingesting the entire
stream of production logs without any
mo modification to our application code.
Finally the architecture should be
designed to, seamlessly integrate
logs from our acquisitions
and other corporate assets.
Yeah from there we gathered
some more requirements on the
reliability and security side.
We wanted to provide at
least one week log storage.
And as you can see since there was
seven day host policy, host rotation
policy, this requirement came directly.
From there, we analyzed our metrics
and figured out we were ingesting
approximately 150 terabyte.
Per day of logs.
Today it is way more than that,
but that's where we started.
We wanted to make sure the latency
for P 99 ingestion is less than 30
seconds and queries for queries.
It should be less than 10 seconds.
We wanted to make sure our
availability goal is 99%.
We wanted to make sure we have.
MTLS enabled right from the day itself.
So that, we are ensured that every
connection is authenticated, secured.
We wanted to implement strict
access control based on service
ownership by segmenting access.
We could, audit we could
provide provide better auditing.
We can ensure only authorized teams
can view and manage their logs.
To further secure our logs.
We wanted to make sure we are
encrypting all the stored data using
some sort of key management practice.
And we wanted to finally, we wanted
to provide a way to, or a mechanism
for detecting, filtering and redacting
PII information if it ever leaked.
We also wanted to make sure
we call out some non goals.
We did not want to mandate any
changes to our existing log format.
We wanted our system designed in
such a way that it can work with any
unstructured logs we already have so
that teams don't have to migrate to it.
Our goal wasn't to replace any of the,
structured logging or structured logging,
tracing, or any of the metric systems.
We didn't want this system to,
we only wanted this system to
be used as a complimentary tool
which focuses on troubleshooting.
Rather than serving as any other,
observability solution we wanted
to make sure that the solution
was not going to be a replacement
for any of the analytic system.
And lastly, we didn't want to impose
any new logging practice on teams.
We wanted to avoid mandating any,
anything like how logs are produced
or what the format would be.
So that existing team owners
don't have to feel any burden
when this new system is added.
Next, let, next let's take a
look at the evaluation metric.
These, metrics provided us
with a framework for comparing
different approaches.
Cost was definitely the highest priority.
We wanted to make sure that the total cost
of ownership including both opex and CapEx
along with any, potential contract risk
our accounted for performance was another
critical metric we wanted to make sure.
The loading solution could
handle our ingestion rate and,
matches the query latency.
We had in mind.
We definitely wanted a rich
ux, a rich query engine.
And, since our engineers are, were
very familiar with Grafana, we
were highly interested in solution
which could integrate with Grafana.
Okay.
And along with that we wanted to make
sure there is ease of integration
with our current observability tools.
The solution, we wanted a
solution to seamlessly work
across our existing infrastructure
structure without major changes.
And finally, security.
Like we wanted to make sure the there
is robust data protection so that we can
minimize risk of sensitive data exposure.
All right, and yep.
Now let's consider the
do nothing scenario.
The pros of course, were no
additional envi investment.
Cons was we would have to continue
with manual, non-scalable,
inefficient troubleshooting.
So ultimately the status quo
was was not meeting meeting
the, modern observability needs.
So that's why we didn't proceed.
Now let's examine our evaluation of
all the other logging service options.
In this slide, we'll compare several
potential solutions side by side.
So the first one was
externally managed SaaS.
Here we'll be using some we
will use a logging solution
offered by a third party service.
Of course, the pros where it reduces
in-house management overhead.
But the cons was very
high cost of operating it.
And also since we would be sending
entirety of our logs to a third
party service, there was a potential
risk of exposing PII to them.
So that's why the solution was rejected,
both because of cost and security concern.
The second option was managed cloud
logging where things like, managed
search and logging solution will
be hosted on a cloud framework.
Pros was these kind of technologies have.
But have matured enough,
they are scalable.
But again, even for this option
at our scale, the operational
cost was going to be very high.
And we looked at few solutions and we felt
UX was still not where we wanted it to be.
The third option was self-hosted
enterprise, where, we will host
some enterprise grade log management
system on our premises pros where,
you get all the rich feature set,
you get very robust vendor support.
But the cons was the licensing was
still going to be very expensive.
And it would still need to
run on our infrastructure.
So that cost is there plus
overhead of maintaining it.
So that's why we rejected this as well.
The last option was building our own
logging solution just build a custom
developed solution, which fits our need.
Obviously this was the most
exciting option, but this
is not our core competency.
And we realized that it's the, the
observability feel like the vendor
over there are so mature that it is
better to go with some established
solution than, reinventing the meal.
Now let's focus on Grafana.
Loki being open source.
Loki offers a low.
Total cost of ownership compared
to other proprietary solutions
which made it an attractive
option from a budget perspective.
It's optimized for Dropbox Scale, log
ingestion and querying, which means it
can handle our massive volumes of logs we
generate without compromising on speed.
Loki provides a native unified
observability interface through Grafana.
And that was one of the major factors.
Gr loki's structure is architecture
is pretty distributed, so it is
designed to, grow alongside your needs.
Ensuring that, as data volumes
increase our observability
capability would also remain robust.
So overall Grafana, lowkey ticked all
the boxes by combining performance,
cost, efficiency, ease of use and
scalability making it an ideal
choice for our logging needs.
What is Loki?
Loki is an open source project,
meaning it's free to use, inspect and
contribute to, and this has led to, a
very strong community engagement and
ra, rapid iteration, helping it to
evolve into a production grade solution.
Actually.
It is built to scale out across
multiple nodes ensuring that it can
handle increasing volumes of log data.
Lokey is designed with high availability
in mind, so it remains, resilient
even if individual components fail.
I. The system supports multi-tenancy
you, you can securely isolate log
data for different teams or services.
This was critical for our
diverse production environment.
Loki draws inspiration from Prometheus
and it leverages a similar approach to
metrics collection and querying, which
makes it familiar to many of our teams.
Because our internal metrics
system is also quite similar
to to Proteus added score.
Lokey is a log aggregation
system that efficiently, collects
indexes and stores log data while
minimizing resource overhead.
Now that we have talked about why
Lowkey exists and how it differs from
traditional logging solutions, let's
dive into how it works At a high level.
The first thing you need to get you need
to get logs into Lowkey is an agent.
For that, we have prom tail.
One important distinction to make
here is that unlike Prometheus.
Loki does not use a pull model.
Instead of scraping
logs, Loki pushes them.
This is one area where Loki
is different from Prometheus.
So why not follow the same
pull based model as Prometheus?
The answer is simple.
Logs are fundamentally different from
metrics logs has generated at very high
volume and need to be streamed efficiently
rather than pulled periodically.
Before we dive into the technical
details let's start with the
fundamental reason why Lowkey exists.
Many existing log logging
solutions are difficult to
operate and expensive to scale.
Loki was built to solve these
problems by being very simple to
operate and very cost efficient.
One of the key design decisions
that sets Loki apart is that it
does not perform full text indexing.
Instead, it only indexes
metadata about each line.
So why does this matter?
Because in most logging solutions the
biggest cost driver is maintaining
a massive index for full text search
indexing every single word from every
log entry means you need gigabytes,
sometimes terabytes of index storage,
leading to a very high memory
users and expensive infrastructure.
Loki takes a different approach.
It focuses on efficient metadata
indexing instead instead of, full
text indexing, making it much
more lightweight and scalable.
Now let's break down how
logs are structured in Loki.
Every log entry in Loki consists
of three main component,
timestamp, label, and con content.
A timestamp provides precise time
information for when the log was
generated down to the nanoseconds.
Labels are key value pairs that
serve as the metadata index.
Helping Lokey locate logs efficiently.
Content is the actual log message
itself, which is not indexed, but
stored efficiently for retrieval.
By keeping the index small and focusing
only on labels, lokey allows for
faster ingestion and querying with
minimal infrastructure overhead.
This architecture is what makes
Loki highly scalable compared to
traditional logging solutions.
One of the core concepts
in Loki is the log stream.
A log stream is simply a
collection of log entries that
share the exact same level set.
This means that the logs generated
from the same application on
the same server with the same
metadata are grouped together.
For example let's look at
those these log entries.
So logs from dummy service running
on example node one form OneStream,
and logs from dummy service.
Running on example, no two
form a different stream.
By structuring logs.
This way we ensure that the log remains
organized, queryable, and scalable without
the overhead of full text indexing.
Now let's talk about how low
key stores logs efficiently.
Logs in low Loki are grouped into
chunks based on their label set.
Here is how this approach works.
Each log stream is stored
in separate chunks.
These chunks are sorted
in timestamp order.
A chunk continues collecting logs until it
reaches a target size or a timeout occur.
Once a chunk is full, it is compressed
and then flushed to an object store
like AWS S3, Google Cloud Storage Azure
blobs, or even a local file system.
This chunk based approach ensures
that logs are stored in the most
cost effective way possible.
Instead of relying on expensive
databases, lowkey leverages scalable
object storage to reduce cost and
improve re improve retrieval efficiency.
So how do we retrieve logs efficiently
in Loki when a query is executed?
Loki first looks at the metadata
index to determine which chunks
contain the relevant logs.
For example if we query service
equals dummy service and node
id equals example node one.
For logs between timestamp T five
and T seven looking only fetches the
chunks that fall within the time range.
It does not need to scan through
all the logs, just the ones
that match the query criteria.
This makes queries fast, efficient,
and scalable even when dealing
with massive amount of log data.
Now what if we need to query
logs across multiple streams?
Let's say we want logs from both
example node one and example node two.
In that case, Loki will use the index to
determine which chunk match our query,
retrieve only the necessary chunk.
Instead of scanning all the logs
then it'll combine the result and
display them in tools like Grafana.
This query efficiency ensures that
even large scale logging systems.
Remain performant in addition to Grafana.
Loki provides command line utilities
like log CLI, which allow developers to
interact with logs from the terminal.
And you, it can be integrated
with other scripts and workflows.
By leveraging stream based querying
and avoiding full text indexing,
Loki provides a scalable and
cost effective way to store logs
when working with Loki,
label selection is critical.
High cardinality labels like trace id,
user ID, or, dynamic path values can
explore the number of unique log streams.
Hurting performance and increasing cost.
Instead we should favor low cardinality
label labels, like cluster app or
file name to keep things efficient.
For example even combining just three
labels, like log level, status and
path with a few possible values.
It can easily create 36 unique
streams in this case, four into three.
So it adds up pretty fast.
Now let's talk about how
we deploy Loki at Dropbox.
But first let's take a look at a
simplified diagram of Loki's architecture.
At the top, we have the main components
of the right and read paths in yellow.
On the bottom we have an object
storage S3 for storing logs in green.
And on the right side we have some
shared components like the memc clusters
in blue and cluster wide services
like compactor and et CD in orange.
Starting with the right path, logs
are written to the distributors.
Which hash the log
streams log stream labels.
Then they look up the hash ring
in et CD and route them to the
inges that own their hash range.
The ingestors buffer the log chunks in
memory, then eventually flush the logs
to the object storage in the background.
The com the compactor merges
the log indexes, index files in
object storage for faster queries.
For the read path, the query front
end receives a query and splits
it up into subqueries, which are
processed by different queries.
The queries fetch recent logs from the
cache in the ING adjusters, or it fetches
the older logs from the object storage
for a sense of the scale
of our low key deployment.
Here are some top level metrics.
We are processing on the order of 10
gigabytes of logs per second, and we
store these logs for 30 days, which takes
up about 10 petabytes in object storage.
Excuse me.
We have around 1000 tenants.
And our users are making less
than one query per second.
So as you can see, the system is heavily
que skewed towards right over leads.
With Dropbox being a storage company, one
thing we did is use our internal object
storage as a drop in replacement for S3.
This has led to cost savings,
especially the data transfer costs.
With these lower costs, now we are
able to increase our log retention
from one week to four weeks.
One other big difference between
S3 and our internal storage is some
per performance characteristic.
We we noticed that S3 would gradually
scale out to handle large reads.
And because most queries are scanning
many logs, this would lead to timeouts.
Whereas our internal systems
they have reserve capacity and we
also have emergency capacities,
so we don't have the same issue.
Another thing is because the
index files are so large we
still have to write them to S3.
Lowkey supports isolating the access
and storage of logs by tenant.
At Dropbox, a tenant is a service,
which is a group of projects.
Because the logs are stored by tenant,
there are performance implications.
For one service, we had to use
project as the tenant instead of
service, because that service just
produces too much of, too much logs.
Excuse me.
Before Loki, engineers had to
use production SSH access just
to view logs which were present
on, on the service house.
With Loki, we red, we have
redefined the model so that each
service acts as its own tenant.
This means we are aligning with
our existing permission model.
What worked for accessing a service
is now used to secure log access.
So we have extended this model by
adding a group permission, enabling
teams to grant access to their
logs to other teams when needed.
And naturally some teams even
have permissions that allow
them to access all logs.
To pull it all together, we
developed a custom query art proxy.
This proxy intercepts each query
to ensure that the user has.
Proper permissions which avoids
the complexity and cost that would
come from using Grafana as native
RAC an approach that would also,
require us a separate data source
per tenant and also would've needed
us to, update to Grafana Enterprise.
One thing that comes up a lot is teams
trying to share logs with other teams.
For example, if Team A wants to
share their logs with Team B,
team B. Must request permission.
But because the permission is owned by
the logging team, only we can approve it.
While there is a incident or a sev
going on, this delay can be costly.
So our solution for that was break
glass which allows any user with
a justified reason to temporarily
gain access to any service logs.
And we keep an audit trail and
use safeguards on the amount
of logs a user can access.
We run Lokey in two data centers in
separate geographical reasons, and
so that in case one data center goes
down, we still have a availability.
At Dropbox we call this multihoming.
Both data centers use the same
object storage and to route logs and
queries to the correct lokey cluster.
We integrate our DNS
servers with load balancers.
And now I'm going to co go
over some of the scaling
challenges we faced by default.
Locate key ingestors store
a right ahead, log on disc.
That way if the inges crashes before
flushing the logs, it can recover them.
At Dropbox, we disable the
right ahead log to prioritize
availability over durability.
Loki supports per tenant rate limits
to avoid the noisy neighbor problem.
So what we did is set conservative
default rate limits, and teams are
notified by an alert when their
service goes over those limits.
Loki supports overriding rate
limits per tenant in a file.
And we distribute those overrides
to Loki in minutes using our
distributed key value store.
And we hot reload these override
files in Loki component that use it.
To scale, read and writes lowkey
uses a hash ring to shard logs.
Each inges owns a range in the hashing
and periodically registers its range
and health status in the ring, which is
stored in a distributed key value store.
The distributor, which receives logs
from applications uses that ring to
route logs to the correct ingestors.
Plus replicate the logs
to other ingestors.
Here is an example of that.
When a log is ingested, the labels
for the logs plus the tenant, which
is usually the service in Dropbox, is
hashed, and then the distributor takes
the hash and does the lookup in the ring.
Originally, we used et CD as
the backing store for the ring.
Et.
CD is a distributed, consistent.
Key value store that's often used
for coordination and configuration
in distributed systems.
It is notable for being the
default for Kubernetes, and it is
also now widely used at Dropbox.
One issue we had with
HCD was right contention.
Each inges would send a heartbeat
every minute and update the ring.
Also, when an inges joins or leaves
the ring, it updates the ring.
At CD stores, the whole ring as
a binary blob in a single key.
And every time the ring is updated,
the whole ring is replaced with
a read plus a compare and swap
operation with a replication factor
of three and 67 ingestors for each.
We had 201 total ingess.
So as you can imagine, there was
a lot of right activity going on.
Some ways the right contention would
manifest its deployments would take hours
because inges were pushed one at a time,
and these pushes would often fail because
an availability alert would fire also,
because CD is a single point of failure.
We had some outages when ET.
CD went down.
Luckily Grafana made member list
the default distributed key value
store for low key and other projects.
So we replaced et CD with it.
Our member list is a peer-to-peer Gus
protocol, so we no longer had to maintain
another component with member list.
The ring updates are propagated as
smaller deltas instead of the whole ring.
However, one downside is,
it is eventually consistent.
So unlike ET CD, which offers strong
consistency, this means we still
have to deploy the injustice slowly.
But the pros are we no longer have
to deal with right contention.
A single point of failure and
honestly, we haven't had any issue
in the last year using member list.
We are also able to double the amount of
ingestors after migrating to member list.
Log indexes determine the query plan,
including how many log chunks needs
to be fetched and scanned so they have
a good deal of impact on performance.
Grafana changed the index format
from Bold DB to TSDB, which
is based on Prometheus TS db.
So it just works better
with the log label.
In summary, our goal was to scale and
improve observability and Rob box.
We are facing challenges with
manual SSH into hosts and dig
through unstructured logs.
It was a slow error prone
and hard to scale process.
We evaluated several solutions and
ultimately chose Grafana, Loki for
its performance, cost efficiency,
and native multi-tenant support.
As a result, we have significantly
improved log retention, lowered
cost, and enabled fast secure
access to logs across teams.
So that's all for my presentation.
Thank you.