Hi there.
Welcome to my talk show at
con 42 Site Label Engineering.
So today's topic is data engineering
in healthcare, how it is transforming
personalized medicine and diagnosis.
So data engineering is transforming
the healthcare in big way fundamentally
changing the personalized medicine
and diagnostic approaches, and also
implementing a clinical settings
by creating robust infrastructure.
Basically the data engineering enables
comprehensive patient profiles that
supports truly personalized treatment.
So this also taking care of the
foundation, addressing complex
challenges, which are including the
data integration across all systems, and
also the scalability of exponentially
growing information volumes.
Data governance, quality governance,
and advanced analytics requirements.
As healthcare continues, its digital
transformation, data engineering, evolving
challenges related to privacy production,
and this also taking care of edge
computing for point of care diagnostics.
Includes the design for
diverse populations and ethical
implementations of artificial inte.
In clinical workflow, the found the
foundation of personalized healthcare.
So there are certain f the foundations
which are which plays the important
role, which are genomic information,
that clinical history integration, and
the lifecycle and environmental data.
And the data engineering infrastructure.
So for the genomic information the cost
of this is going to be like, dropped
dramatically from a hundred million
2021, 2001 to just thousand in 2023.
Enabling widespread critical
approach and coming to the clinic.
History integration this is a
confidential patient profiles
incorporate medical records.
Treatment is three and the diagnostic
result across previously sliced systems
and the lifetime and environmental data.
So these are the certain variable devices
and environmental sensor providers,
continuous monitoring, contributing to
the 48% of annual growth in healthcare
data volume and coming to the final
data engineering infrastructure.
This is where the data
engineering design complex.
Pipelines to process the data
which is 2, 3, 1 4 exabytes of
healthcare data expected by 2030.
Data collection and
integration challenges.
Healthcare data is in credibility,
diverse from the EHRs and
images to variable and genomic.
Sequences.
So each of these the genomic
sequencer, wearable devices and
patient reported outcomes, each
with unique format and standards.
And there is also the unstructured
clinical information, which is up
to 80% of the clinical relevant
information, which is existing, the
unstructured format, which has to be
bring it to the structured format.
Using some natural language
processing to extract the data
and the system fragmentation.
A single hospital typically manages
over 50 disposable clinical information
systems, each with unique data
models and exchange prototypes
that must be reconciled to create
unified patient representation,
data quality and governance.
So there is a certain process we follow
for the data quality and the governance.
Initially is to start with the lineage
tracking and the master data management,
standardization and validation.
So these are the four steps
which are involved in the data
quality and the governance.
And this will definitely improve
efficiency of personalized medicine, reli
fundamentally on pristine data quality.
Advanced analytics infrastructure,
so the high performance computing,
stream processing, lops pipelines,
interactive visualization.
So these are the four standards
that that improves the technology,
which I have been used in the
advanced analytics infrastructure.
So supporting the analytical requirement
of personalized medicine requires a
sophisticated and computational resources.
Tailored to the unique characteristics
of the healthcare data.
Genomic analytic workflow for clinical
applications typically requires 122 240
CPU hours per patient for comprehensive,
varied analysis and interruption.
Data engineering technologies
have demonstrated a significant
quantitative impacts across various
aspects of healthcare delivery.
So the natural language processing
system now achieve over 90%
accuracy in extracting the clinical
concepts for narrative text.
While implementing data province
frameworks reduces errors by 35%, so
FHIR based data models, which improves
the query performance an average of 50%
compared by traditional relational models.
So a well-designed clinical visualization
that reduces decision time by 25%, and
also that agnostic accuracy by 20%.
How the genomic medicine is transforming.
So first, the rapid sequencing
and then the efficient storage,
and then the automated interation
and population integration.
So these are the four topics how the
genomic medicine is transforming which
is available in the current situation.
So the rapid sequencing, which
which, the sequence now completed
in halon instead of weeks.
And this enables critical genetic
diagnosis for critical ill
newborn and immediate intervention
and the efficient storage.
So we have the efficient devices where we
can store that data in the current systems
and also the automated interpretation.
There are sophisticated vari annotation
pipelines, integration filters.
Millions of genetic variations down
to 20 to 25 clinical significant
S for targeted treatment planning.
So data engineering team at leading
academic medicine center have a
revolutionized genomic by developing
efficient processing pipelines
that analyze complete genomics,
unpredictable diagnostic evaluation.
So the early warning system predict
clinical ation five to two hours
before traditional sign, and then
multidi multimodal integration.
This process, 250 to 400
variable per patient, including
continuous waveform data.
Advanced analytics apply time series
analytics to identify sub pattern
predictor of disease progression.
Continuous learning.
This automated ation workflow incorporate
new data to ma maintain model accuracy.
So pioneering the healthcare system are
harnessing sophisticated data engineering
to deploy early warning systems that
detect clinical hovers before every.
Patient profile that captures
psychological status according to multiple
patterns which unprotected precision.
So these are the four sub basis where
we identify the disease and then we take
certain actions to protect the patient.
And this shows the clinical
impact of our data engineer.
What are the metrics and what is
the traditional approach and also
the data engineering approach.
The diagnostic time has reduced.
Of pretty much on a huge number.
So before the diagnostic time used
to take a lot of time, and now
the time has come down by 43 and
the treatment selection physician.
Based on the data analytics, they can
decide how this patient has to be treated.
And this information will help the
doctor to take 60% more precise.
A faster way to treat the selection
precision and the time taken to
diagnostic for critical cases.
So normally it takes around 16 days to
take the necessary steps for diagnostic
of the critical cases, but now it takes
only two to six hours to take a decision.
And the whole genomic analysis.
This used to take around
two to three days.
Right now it's taking around eight hours
and the variant review efficiency, so
there are millions of variants before
and now as of now in the market, it's
30 to 50 s. The treatment outcome
prediction before that additional
push was to see it as a baseline, but
right now that is 30% more accurate.
And in-hospital mortality is a baseline.
And that has reduced by 23%.
So right now what are the
challenges in healthcare?
Data engineering.
So there are certain ethical
implementations and which which
also includes to designs, the edge
computing, the privacy protection,
and exponential data growth.
So these are the five steps which
we might cross across in dealing
with the future challenges in
the healthcare data engineering.
And that will definitely help healthcare
data to, to grow at approximately 36%
annually, significantly outpatient
storage capacity, expenses.
And also the future of healthcare delivery
risks firmly on the shoulders of robust
data engineering by building the technical
infrastructure that enables personalized
medicine and advanced diagnosis.
Data engineering are not merely
supporting healthcare, but
fundamentally transforming it.
So the solutions for data integration,
quality management, analytics, and
ethical implementation creates cycles.
Where increased information,
accessibility drives improved clinical
outcomes, so generating more data
to further refine predictive models.
As personalized medicine initiated
expands beyond academic centers to
community settings, the role of data
engineering will become increasingly
central to healthcare evaluations.
Thank you very much for taking
time to attend this session.
Again, this session is again about the
data engineering and transforming the
healthcare, so you have a wonderful day.
Thank you.