Hello everyone.
Very warm.
Welcome to all of you.
I'm really excited and honored
to be part of this conference.
I want to share my thoughts
with all of you today.
I'm Bala working as an expert software
engineer in one of the incidents leading
Nsurance companies in the United States.
Today I'm going to talk about how
artificial intelligence and human
expertise are working together.
Drive operational excellence
in the insurance industry.
Insurance is something we all experience,
whether it is a health insurance or
insurance at home insurance, but many
people do not realize how much technology
works behind the scenes to make the
process faster, safer, and better.
My goal in this present presentation
is to explain how AI helps
insurance companies become smarter.
More efficient, but at the same time,
human skills like empathy, judgment,
and experience are still very important.
We'll share real life examples from
insurance operations so that everyone
can easily understand this topic.
Let's begin the journey together.
Let's first understand
how AI brings a major
shift in the way of the way
insurance companies operate today.
AI is changing insurance
operations in a big way.
It helps in three important areas,
improving efficiency, increasing
company growth, and reducing cost.
Let's talk about improving the efficiency.
A improves the efficiency by
automating tasks that use to take this.
For example, when someone applies for
health insurance, a systems can check
their medical reports, analyze risks, and
provide a premium code within a minutes.
And the second one is AA helps companies.
Grow by creating a smart pricing models.
For instance, if a customer installs a
smart device in their car to monitor safe
driving, the company can offer discounts.
This attracts more to the customers so
that they can expect more customers come,
will come on onboard to our insurance.
Carbon is they reduce operational
cost by automating routine work.
Earlier insurance companies
had a large call centers to
handle the customer questions.
Now a chat bots can answer basic
questions, but four by seven,
it's saving a lot of time and
money to the insurance companies.
All these changes are helping
insurance companies to offer
faster
processing, better decisions,
and more personalized services.
Despite all these technologies,
human expertise remains criticals.
Let us see why humans are still
important in in this AI driven world.
While AI handles many tasks, there are
something that only humans can do well.
There is a car accident involves.
Multiple vehicles and legal disputes.
A human claims adjuster is required to
handle the situation fairly in fraud.
Detections A can catch patterns,
but human investigators are better
at identifying lies are unusual
behavior during a call in customer
service, especially during a sensor.
Situations like that claim
are a major accident policy.
Only a human can provide
empathy and comfort.
That is why human expertise
will always be sharing insurance
industries to handle complex
emotional sensitive situations.
Now let us look at how AI
users data to make smarter
risk assessments.
A systems use advanced data analytics
to evaluate risk more accurately.
For example, in health insurance, a
can analyze years of medical reports
for particular personal to understand
how, which, like smoking or drink
drinking, increase the health risk.
It can also monitor customer
behaviors like exercise
habits using fitness strikers.
This allows insurance companies
to offer better plans.
For instance, a person who access
daily needs healthy may get a lower
premium and compared with other process.
Similarly, AI can adjust car insurance
premiums based on the driving
behavior of the persons people
who can drive those cars safely
and following the speeding limits.
And if they don't have any.
Decades that are issued at so that
they will get a better pricing.
AI also helps detect hidden
patterns in past claims, which
humans may miss, essentials,
accurate risk prediction,
and fair pricing.
Now let's see how AI helps
managing risk in real time and
protect customers.
A,
a enables real time monitoring of risk
and provides proactive alert to customers.
For example, a, a systems track,
weather patterns and can select then
the alerts about upcoming flights,
storms to the customers so that the
customers can react immediately.
And if there is a spread in a
particular area, a customer may
receive a message just to move there.
Um, car and family to a different
locations and take the safety measures.
AA three calculate risk level
based on changing situations.
For example, the customer
installs a smart, smart
security device at their home.
The risk of the theft goes down and
then insurance premium may reduce.
This prior to risk management, not
only protects customers, but also
helps insurance companies reduce
claims and lose losses.
So let's go into the next slide.
Let us explore how
companies balance between, um,
automation with human judgment,
but better decision making.
It is perfect for handling
routine and tri tasks.
For example, a customer files a claim
for a small repair, like a broken window.
A can verify the details and approve
the claim instantly within few minutes.
But for complex cases, like a major
plan accident are a liability dispute.
AI systems plank the
case for human review.
So human upgrade their experience in
this scenario, assess the situation
deeply and make the final decisions.
This collaboration, nqs speed,
accuracy, and customer satisfactions.
Let us now see how AI
improves claims processing and
makes life easier for customers.
AI has completely changed
how claims are processed.
Earlier when you look at, uh, the way
the claims are processing, the customer
have to submit a claim and it has to
be manually, uh, reviewed by, uh, some
human and they have to take the decision.
The entire process took around some
three to five business days, but coming
to the aa, what we can do is, and
use some OC technologies and whatever
the documents that customer uploads.
We use the AI technologies
and we extract that data.
We can, a, can take the decisions whether
it has to process the claims or not.
Within emanate,
uh, this has reduced the efforts
and improves the transparency and
increase the customer satisfaction by
30% in many companies.
It does now look at how we
a, a detects fraud claim.
Effectively, a is very
powerful in detecting
frauds.
It analyze large amounts of data
to catch eligible claim patterns.
For example, the same person files
multiple claims for different
locations for the same Danish.
A systems can catch this
pattern very easily.
AI also does network analysis, which
means that maps the relationship between
the claimants and service providers
to predict the fraud rings behavior
analysis, which helps us to identify the
suspicious languages in claims forms,
which means, uh, it means a person
changing their story multiple times.
System alerts a human
investigator is needed.
This has increased the fraud detection
rates by 35% in many insurance companies.
Now let us understand why human
tech is still necessary in
complex cases.
A cannot handle emotional situations
or complex negotiations, for example.
Disaster like
customers needs help supporting to
guide them through the claims process.
In disputes involving multiple parties.
Human adjusters handle legal discussions
and make fair decisions since the
negotiations like setting a life
insurance claim require empathy and
understanding only humans can provide.
Provides the data support, but
humans handle the conversations
and emotional aspects.
Let us now look at how
the market for AI and
insurance is growing rapidly.
The AI insurance market
is growing very fast.
The report suggests that the market
will grow at the rate of 47% til 2027.
Health insurance will be the
largest segment contributing
35% of the total market value.
Many leading insurance companies are
ing in like card bots, automated claims
processing, and predictive analytics.
For example, the customer today
can generate their insurance codes,
file claims, and check policy
details on their mobile apps.
It is all powered by a.
This trend shows that
AI will play a huge role in the future.
Insurance.
Finally, let us see how AI and
human collaborations will shape in
future.
The future of insurance lies the perfect
collaboration between AI and humans.
AI will handle work, it improves
the efficiency by party percent and
reduce the operational cost by 25%.
Human expert will continue to handle
complex and sensitive situations.
Customer satisfaction is as expected
to improve by 60% because of faster
and more personalized services.
For example, a may offer a
personalized insurance plan based on
the customer behavior, and a human
advisor will discuss the benefits and
help the customers choose the best
option, which is provided by the a.
A, this collaboration issues.
The best of both words.
Technology for
speed and accuracy, and human
touch for care and apathy.
Thank you all for
attending my session today.
I really appreciate
your time and attention.
If you would like to stay connected
with me or if you have any further
questions, please feel free to reach out.
You can connect with me on LinkedIn.
Just search for.
Alternatively, you can also email
me at contact lacma@gmail.com.
Would love to stay in touch, share
knowledge, and discuss ideas.
Thank you so much.
Wishing you a wonderful day ahead.