Speaker 26: Hello everyone,
and thanks for being here.
I am Rohit Wawa, and today I want
to present something on predictive
workflow integrity for SRE and
Autonomous triage at Global Scale.
To begin with, what does
predictive workflow integrity.
PWI stands for, think of it as a system.
Supposedly you have an
automated PISA delivery system.
In traditional world, an alarm
would go off if your PISA
arrives out of the oven burned.
But with PWI, you are not
looking at just the output.
Rather you are looking at
the entire workflow journey.
In this case with PWI, you would
probably have PWI checking if the oven
temperature is good, if the dough is too
thin or too thick, and rarely it'll try
to ring an alarm if any abrupt behavior
is happening, and it'll also help you.
Fix those issues so that we don't get
any outcome of the issue in first place.
We live in an era of distributed
microservices with distributed
microservices, architecture.
It helps us to scale and modernize
our application, but at the same
time, it brings plethora of issues.
In case of complexity,
SRE, challenges at scale, these
are the most common challenges that
we face in our real life state.
Divergence think it as a system where,
you know, within the system one service.
Stops interacting with other service
and state divergence happens.
Latency.
Variability in your system.
Suppose one of the surveys is, has
slowed down or there is a latency.
It can actually destroy your entire system
because it folds or multiplies across
your entire system and it slows down.
Third is cascading failures.
If one of your system or service
fails, it produces a ripple or a domino
effect that can lead to widespread
outage of your entire system.
Currently, we have a mean
time to detection of around
12 minutes with 12 minutes.
If you think about.
We come to know that there is an issue.
And on top of that, think
about on fixing those.
This can actually produce a
significant, can impact on the services
and on your infra and can cause
massive disruption on the clients.
This is where actually the
need of PWI comes into picture.
How we can reduce.
Mean time to detection
with PWI.
There is a shift of workflow level
observability that helps you enable
better detection and management of a
complex interaction between your systems.
How we do that, this comes
in the following slide.
What PWA anomaly detection is.
It looks for three basically red
flags or warnings in your systems.
One is delayed convergence.
Delayed convergence occurs when
workflow do not reach their expected
states within the designated time.
That means one or more of the
services did not follow the
correct signals or instructions.
And ultimately there is a delayed
convergence on the system and
you did not get the fruitful
output within that duration.
Second is conflicting ownership.
This arises when we have multiple
teams working on a common platform
or common workflow that can cause
a confusion and inefficiency in
resolving the issues that may occur.
And third is abnormal execution path.
Your system, one of the service can
detour or route to a different unexpected
workflow path, and this can lead to
degraded performance of your services
and ultimately leads to a failure.
After Im implementing PWI, the MTTD
reduced from 12 minutes to just 58
seconds and not just at reduction.
It has also responded to the incidents
much more faster and have reduced the
inflows of incidents creation because
PWA, not just rectifies the solution,
but also it tries to predict the
issues that can happen and ultimately
fixes that before even it arises.
This has significantly reduced
the meantime to detection.
Now, understanding how autonomous
incident triage mechanism works,
so with PWI, it actually correlates
logs, metrics, and traces and bundle
them together into a common map.
And then we apply some machine L
learning algorithms on that map.
That helps to prioritize incidents
based on the severity and also faster
and more efficient resolution of those.
It also helps to improve the accuracy
and adapt adaptability of the system.
As a result, organization can achieve.
Much more resilient and responsive
IT infrastructure, minimizing the
downtime and optimizing resource
allocations so engineers can just
focus on building the products.
And PWI will take care of running the
existing systems without incidents or with
minimal incidents, and also resolving them
at its own autonomous incident triage.
So as I mentioned.
With PWI, we collect the different
logs metrics and we create
a unified map of the system.
It also helps to do real time
prioritization that is of most
importance to the SRE world.
That helps to address the
critical promptly and also ensures
the operational excellence or
efficiency in this environment.
And third and final is.
Which is most important is automated re
remediation because it, as I mentioned,
doesn't just identify the issues.
It actually based on the machine learning
algorithms, it predicts the what issues
can arise and automatically fixes those
issues that enables a faster recovery.
So issues doesn't arise in
first place and helps a lot.
We have also applied a ring based
geolocation routing strategy where we have
different rings based on the geolocation.
Think of as a system, suppose
your application is being used in
East Coast, but your servers are
based off West Coast locations.
One is definitely a latency.
Latency can arise because you are hitting
the servers on a different geolocation
where your application is running.
And also think of a system where
worst case, if your system has some
failures or system, goes down, it can
actually impact your entire application.
So we have localized the servers based
on each different geographical location.
And that helps us ensuring
a good response time and has
enhanced a server reliability.
This has actually improved the latency
by around 80% from S to cloud latency,
decreasing it approximately from five
seconds to under one seconds, which
has improved the overall responsiveness
and user experience of the application.
And has delivered efficiently and
re reliably across the Global Pro
platform highlights of a large
scale enterprise deployment.
We have successfully deployed PWI in two
thousands of nodes, both across edge and
cloud, which have seamlessly been working
fine and has have reduced our incidents.
By a large scale has improved our latency
and also has reduced our L two issues
because the issues are being predicted
and also analyzed and fixed by PWA.
We have this been working in like
thousands of nodes and have been
very successful with this journey.
Practical, SRE takeaways.
So what?
SR takeaways are with PWIs.
It focuses on end-to-end
workflow observability.
We don't think of just the incoming
and outgoing request, but rather we
considered it as an entire workflow,
entire user journey, which PWA takes care.
It does predictive detection.
Because with predictive anomaly detection,
you monitor the system for the faster
response time and actually also helps
to downtime you during critical events.
And third is autonomous triage.
Because PWA doesn't just detect
or predict the issues, it ac
actually reduces the alert noise.
By fixing these incidents
and also enhancing the trust
and efficiency of the system.
Summary is predictive workflow integrity.
PWI, it actually transform the SRE
practices, enabling self-regulating
system that enhances your operational
efficiency and also improve your
reliability across the global platforms.
This is of utmost importance
to this SRE world.
Thank you for your time and attention.
I hope this helps our cause.
Thank you.