Speaker 21: Hello everyone.
My name is Rajesh Kumar bsu.
I have total of 20 years experience
in database engineering and
administration and cloud architect.
I'm here today to explain about
conference for engineering
cloud Cloudability practices.
So in my past 20 years experience,
I worked for different customers
in public sector and universities.
I worked for retailers, pharmaceuticals,
and many other customers.
I worked as a cloud architect and
Oracle Cloud Fresh itself, and plus
Cloud and Google Cloud platform.
I played a major role in database
layer design, storage layer
design, and network layer design.
And I was part of security
layer design as well.
I did a lot of stand shift migrations
from on premises to different
clouds across different customers.
So here I am today to walk you
through about conference 42 site
reliability engineering SR 2026.
Again.
So here can show you how to building
high ability databases with the
cloud native availability practices.
So majorly it'll contain I'm working
for database architect as a an a gap
technologies INC, so from last 20 years.
So I can walk you through.
The main session is ina.
So the site availability, engineering
for database high ability,
it's majorly into three phases.
So one, reliability assessment
planning, which is S LVO definition,
infrastructure review, capacity
planning and traffic controls.
And second cloud native platforms for
SRE containers, Kubernetes, ci, cd
pipelines, and operational metrics.
Third structured migration with
six R is a major thing in database
high ability for SRE, which depends
analysis, phased execution principles,
and post migration optimization.
And why?
Database reliability demands.
SRE one.
As organizations modernize
production systems, database are
often the last mile of availability.
I can show you the architectural gaps.
What becomes outages?
So the first thing, so up
temperature, it's a business.
SLS increasingly demands five nines
nine, 9.99, nine percentage, which
leaves five minutes of downtime annually.
And hidden S-P-O-F-S.
So legacy environments have, hiring
single point of failures that surface
only during instance, and next
operational drift, aging components.
And undocumented workloads make
availability unpredictable outages for,
databases and applications, environments.
Next, defining reliability
objectives, the chapter one.
So before going any architecture changes
for SRE must establish reliability
targets, in business requirement,
not only aspirational guesses.
So the main thing, SL service
level object objective is a target.
Up time should be like.
99.99%, which leaves every
database and applications with
five minutes downtime annually.
And next recovery time.
Objective.
TiVo, which is maximum acceptable time
to restore your application or database
services after a failure of any win.
And next recovery point.
Object to our people.
Maximum tolerable.
Tolerable data loss window.
Driving backup and replication frequency
and latency thresholds across the
regions or across the data centers.
So P 99, query response targets, defining
acceptable read, write, performance,
bounce, and next infrastructure review.
Finding what breaks in the, SRE
is structured, review surfaces.
Hidden reliability risks before
they become production instance.
The first thing, single point of
failure, identify standalone database
notes and single region deployments
or unmetered storage volumes.
And the major components is aging
components like end of license or old
hardware or database or application
software versions or any end of support
windows platforms or Linux platforms and
next workload saturation, CPU spikes,
memory pressure and iops ceiling.
That ERO reliability, A under P cloud.
And finally, it's a security gaps.
Unencrypted connections or overprivileged
service accounts or application
accounts and missing audit logging.
So these are the major things we
have to review in infrastructure
and next capacity planning.
Traffic controls the
observable capacity metrics.
Effective cap Capacity planning is
metric driven, not institutional driven.
Key signals to traffic, the CPU memory
utilization trends and peak transaction
rates and concurrency patterns, storage
growth, velocity and iops, headroom
connection pool saturation rates.
The major goal of this capacity planning
metrics is maintain reliability, headroom
without over provisioning the cost,
which will, cost more for the customer.
Traffic distribution failover.
The foundational reliability
controls using battery tested tools.
Example, NGNX, it's a seven layer load
balancing upstream health checks and red
replica routing, or can use HA proxy,
TCP level proxying for active passive
failure and backend health monitoring.
Next as a chapter two, I can walk
you through cloud native practices,
map to site reliability engineering
outcomes in cloud native platforms,
or not just deployment tools.
They are reliability that directly
supports service level object two,
achievement when configured intentionally.
So the main components for, carbon.
Availability engine as a Kubernetes,
the main thing is like container
based consistency, which is immutable
images eliminated environment drift
between environments like development,
quality assurance production, and
second self hailing orchestration.
So Kubernetes detects pod
failures where liveness props.
And restarts automatically, which
will reduce MTTR and third, workload
driven scaling, HPA and KEDS scale,
replicas based on CPU, memory
or custom queue depth signals.
And finally, and CICD with rollback
criteria, automated pipelines
and force quality gates rollback.
Triggers on the error rate bridge.
And next in chapter two, operational
metrics which signals reliability
help for applications and databases.
Cloud native practices must be
evaluated against dura alignment
metrics, connecting engineering
activity to reliability outcomes fast.
Deployment frequency, so how often you
ship validated changes, higher frequency
with stability signals a mature pipeline,
and next it's a very important thing.
The meantime, recovery MTTR, the time from
instant detection to fully restore our
application or database services, the core
of SRE requirement and change value rate.
Percentage of deployments
causing degradation or requiring
rollback quality signal.
And as a chapter three, the major thing
in SRE for applications and databases
is like Sixers migration framework.
So six s migration framework for evaluated
and executing database migrations or
application migrations, balancing.
Reliability, continuity
with modernization goals.
So first or rehost.
So rehost is like lift and shift from
on-premise just to cloud infrastructure
with minimal downtime or or changes.
And second replatform.
So replatform is migrate
with minor optimizations.
Example.
Managed S or Aurora instead of self-hosted
instances and third repurchase.
So repurchase is like moving to SaaS
database model, replacing self-managed
instances and fourth refactor.
So refactor is ti for cloud native
patterns like microservices,
event sourcing, QRS, et cetera.
And the fifth retain, retain is to
keep premises where latency compliance
or cost justifies the, migration.
And finally, the sixth one retired.
So retirees to decommission databases
or applications with no active
consumers reduce attack surface.
So this is a major success
for migration framework in,
site availability engineering,
so the actual migration execution
from analysis to optimization.
So the major highlights,
like dependency analysis.
So dependency analysis, majorly, it's a
map all upstream, downstream consumers
before touching any schema or connection
stream in databases especially.
And the second one, the
total cost evolution.
So which includes compute,
storage, egress, and igra rules,
licensing and operational overhead
cost, not just instance pricing.
And next post migration ops optimization.
So it, which will validate SLS tune,
query planning, right size, resources,
and decom any old hardware machines
across the different environments
like development, qa, and production.
And next.
In chapter three, report
four is a database migration.
So the main is high availability.
It's a core availability requirements.
So the first thing, redundancy.
So redundancy for databases and
applications will come through multi
region or multi zone replicas to
eliminate single point of failure
at the infrastructure layer.
Next automated fail failover.
So which health?
Health check driven promotion
of standby replicas for every
production to minimize human in LO,
MTTR, and next data replication.
So data replication is synchronous
replication for zero RPO, asynchronous
for zero distribution rescaling.
And then silencing testing, regular chaos
experiments and fellows drills validate
he ha assumption before instance too.
So finally, the key takeaways.
So what every SRE and database
architect should carry forward
from this session, especially
for site little bit engineering.
The measure 0.1 is measure
before you migrate.
Define service level
objectives, or recovery time.
Objective or record point object to first.
Every architectural decision should
trace back to the three targets,
these three targets, and next.
Kubernetes amplifies availability, so
which helps in self hailing, scaling,
and CICD rollback criteria or SRE
tools, not just developer conveniences.
And third, the six R
prevent costly mistakes.
Not every database needs refactoring.
Choosing the right migration
path protects stability.
Finally ha must be tested, not
assumed so, which means redundancy
and failover configurations
are only reliable when regular
exercised and realistic conditions,
and this is well high conference,
42, site reliability engineering.
Thank you.