Hello everyone and thank you
for joining this session.
My name is Kumar, and today I'll
be talking about a challenge
that many airlines and NDC
platforms are currently facing.
How to scale NDC shopping traffic,
while maintaining pricing,
accuracy and system reliability.
As airline moves towards modern
retailing and dynamic offers,
the number of shopping requests.
Has increased dramatically at the
same time, each request now requires
significantly more competition than it
did in the traditional distribution world.
So the key question becomes, how do
we scale n DC shopping infrastructure
without sacrificing speed,
reliability, or pricing integrity.
In this presentation, I'll walk through
how intelligent caching architecture can
solve this problem, allowing airlines
to handle massive shopping demand while
maintaining real time pricing alignment.
Let's start by looking at
what is happening across the
airline distribution ecosystem.
Over the past few years, the number
of shopping requests hitting airline
offer engines has grown exponentially.
Requests are coming.
From multiple sources, airline
websites, online travel agencies,
meta search platforms, and even
out automated reprising systems.
In many environments, a large
portion of this traffic is repetitive
or near duplicate searches.
At the same time, airlines are
introducing real time offer
generation, which means every request
now require complex competitions
involving fair taxes, inventory
availability, and merchandising laws.
The result is that the infrastructure
behind NDC shopping is now under
immense operational pressure.
This leads to two major consequences,
higher latency, and significantly
higher cloud infrastructure costs.
From a systems engineering perspective,
the fundamental problem is redundancy.
Many shopping requests represent
the same underlying demand.
For example, multiple aggregators
searching the same origin destination
combinations within second of each other.
However, without caching, the
system still recompute the full
offer calculation every time.
This means that platform are
effectively scaling infrastructure
to process repetition rather
than incremental revenue.
Demand the consequences increase
latency, high operation costs.
Risk during traffic spikes
instead of continuing to scale
infrastructure vertically, the
smarter approach is to identify
repeat, demand and reuse previously
computed response wherever possible.
Now, this is where the caching becomes
a powerful architectural capability.
Caching allows the system to store
previously computed offer and reuse them
when identical request appears again.
This dramatically reduces
the computational workload
placed on the offer engine.
Now the three major benefits.
First, it significantly reduces
backend processing load, freeing
up infrastructure resources.
Second, it allows platform to deliver
sub-second responses, which is
critical for customer experience.
And third, it provides stability
during certain demand spikes, such as.
Fair promotions or peak
travel search periods.
In other words, caching, transforms
the architecture from a model based on.
There's no single caching model that
works for every airline environment.
Instead, modern NDC
architectures typically combine
multiple caching strategies.
The first is full offer caching, where
the entire completed offer is stored
in return instantly when the system
when the same request marker again.
The second is hybrid anchor search, which
combines CASP components with real time.
Third approach is partial component
caching, where individual elements of
the offer, such as taxes, where rules or
availability checks are cashed separately.
Each approach offers different
tradeoffs between performance
flexibility and pricing freshness.
Now let's talk about full offer caching.
Full offer caching provides the
fastest possible response times.
In this model, the system stores
the complete offer exactly as it was
generated during the initial competition.
When a similar request arrives the
system simple retrieve that offer from
the cash and returns it immediately,
this avoids the need to rerun the entire
pricing and availability calculation.
This strategy can dramatically reduce
latency and infrastructure low.
However, it works best in markets where
pricing conditions are relatively stable,
or where the cash window is carefully.
Hybrid and partial caches.
In more dynamic pricing environment,
hybrid or partial caching
approaches become more effective.
Hybrid caching anchors certain stable
component of the offer while recalculating
the elements that change more frequently.
For example, pay structure might
be cached while availability,
while dynamic price adjustment.
Partially caching goes even
further by storing specific
components of the offer pipeline.
For example, tax calculations,
fair rules, or scheduled data
may be cashed independently.
This approach reduce STA data risk
while still improving performance.
A common concern when implemented caching
is the potential for pricing drift.
If cash offer remain in system too
long, there is a risk that they
may no longer reflect the latest
inventory of pricing condition.
To prevent this robust governance
mechanism must be implemented.
These include freshness thresholds,
which limit how long offer remains valid
in the cash realtime cash in validation
triggers which remove cash data when
pricing or oil will take changes.
Elastic control that ensure the
system can handle large traffic
spike while maintaining consistency.
With the right governance,
caching can deliver scalability
without sacrificing accuracy.
Another critical component
is operational monitoring.
Business.
Intelligent dashboard can
provide visibility into metrics
such as cashed rates, system
performance, and pricing alignment.
This allows engineering team to quickly
detect anomalies and inconsistencies.
In addition, automated alerting
mechanism can notify team immediately
if pricing discrepancies occur.
These monitoring system ensure
that caching remains aligned with
real-time pricing environments,
maintaining both operational
reliability and customer trust.
To illustrate the impact of
these strategies, consider
high demand promotion period.
During these events, shopping traffic
can increase dramatically within minutes.
Without caching, the offer engine
would be forced to recompute every
request, creating a significant
risk of performance degradation with
properly implemented caching strategy.
However.
The majority of requests can be served
from previously completed offers.
This allows the system to handle massive
traffic volumes while maintaining fast
response times and accurate pricing.
To build an SR ready NDC shopping
architecture, several best
practices should be followed First.
Implement layered caching strategy
that combine full hybrid and
partial caching approaches.
Second, establish clear cash business
policy and invalidation rules.
And third, integrate strong monitoring
and observable observability tools to
track performance and pricing accuracy.
When these principles are applied
together, airline can achieve both
scalability and operational STA stability.
As airline retaining continues to evolve,
the volume and complexity of shopping
traffic will only increase, rather than
relying solely on real-time competition.
Modern NDC platform must adopt
smarter architecture approaches.
Caching allows airline to reuse
work that has already been performed
dramatically improving performance
while reducing infrastructure costs.
When implemented with proper governance
and monitoring, caching becomes a
key enabler of scalable, reliable,
and high performance shopping.
Thank you very much.