Speaker 30: Hello everyone and
thank you for joining this session.
My name is Ti Uri.
I work in enterprise systems testing
and reliability, mainly in regulated
enterprise platforms where systems do
not just process requests, but also
make important business decisions.
And that is exactly what I
want to talk about today.
The title of my talk is from
Testing to Reliability Strengthening
Regulated Production Systems.
The simple idea behind the session
is this, in many enterprise systems,
especially regulated ones, reliability
cannot stop at infrastructure.
It is not enough for service to be
up a PS to be fast and dashboards
to be green because a system can
look healthy, technically, and still
produce the wrong automated decisions.
And when that happens in a regulated
workflow, the impact is much bigger
than just a normal production defect.
It can affect business outcomes,
compliance, validations,
and audit readiness.
So over the next 15 to 18 minutes,
I'm going to walk you through a
specific and particular framework
for detecting the class of failure.
I just described workflow level,
silent failures in regulated systems,
and for building the reliability
instrumentation to catch them before
your users, your regulators, or
your incident response team does.
So on this slide I will explain when a
healthy system still fails the business.
Imagine a machine in a factory.
The machine is still running perfectly.
The motor works.
Nothing is overheating.
The control panel shows everything is
normal, but the pro product, which is
coming out of the machine is wrong.
The mission is technically working,
but the result is incorrect.
So this situation is very
similar to what happens in many
enterprise software systems.
Now on this slide, the left side shows
what most teams are used to seeing.
Like we see infrastructure status such
as uptime is 99.99%, error rate 0.01%.
P nine nine latency is 42%.
CPU usage is 31%.
Memory is 48%.
So if I am an engineer or an on-call
person looking only at this view,
my first reaction is very simple.
Everything is fine.
All systems are operational.
Nothing looks broken, right?
But then look at the right side.
Now we shift from infrastructure to the
business workflow data ingestion passes,
which is good, but then rule engine
processing shows an error after that.
The decision output is wrong, then
compliance validation is skipped,
and the audit log has a gap.
That means the system is still
running, but the actual business
workflow is no longer trustworthy.
And the most important line on the
slide is the warning at the bottom.
Rule misconfiguration, no
infrastructure alert triggered.
That is the heart of the problem.
Nothing is crashed, nothing is timed
out, and no big red alerts have appeared,
but the business process still failed.
So this is not the kind of failure
traditional monitoring is good at.
Finding.
Traditional monitoring tells us
whether the machine is running.
It does not tell, always tells us
whether the machine is processing
the right result, and that is.
The difference between technical
health and business correctness.
Now, if we look at how reliability is
usually measured, most organization
focus on very familiar set of metrics.
Things like service availability,
error rates, latency, CPU, and
memory infrastructure uptime.
For example, on this slide, we
see service availability at 99.9%.
Error rates at 0.02%.
Latency around 38 milliseconds, CPU,
and memory around 45% and infrastructure
uptime at a hundred percent.
There is also a latency view with
an SLO of 50 milliseconds and
error rates by service like API
gateway odd rules database, and.
Now, all of this is very useful.
We absolutely need them, right?
They help us detect outages, slowness,
instability, and service degradation.
But the problem is that these metrics
measure technical health, but they
do not measure decision correctness.
That is exactly what the
slide says at the bottom.
These metrics measure technical
health, but not decision correctness.
So even if every service meets its
s hello, and even if every chart
looks green, the system may still be
making the wrong business decisions
and in regulated systems, that
is not a simple or small issue.
Because the real question is not
only did the service respond, but
the real question is, did the service
respond with the correct decision?
With the right compliance checks
and with the complete audit trial,
that is much higher standard now.
In this slide, we will see
reliability beyond infrastructure.
This slide helps us see
why that gap exists.
It breaks systems like into layers.
We have infrastructure layer like servers,
databases, networks, and cloud resources.
These are usually monitored very well.
And below that we have
application services like APIs,
microservices, queues, and caches.
Again, these are also monitored
very well, but then we come to the
business workflow layer and this
layer is marked as a missing layer.
This includes things like claims process.
Underwriting policy adjustments,
compliance validations, and audit logging.
These are not just technical activities,
these are actual business outcomes.
And below that is the compliance outcomes
layer, correct decisions, regulatory
compliance, audit trials, risk controls.
And notice how the slide describes
these two layers as the business
workflow layer is under monitored.
Compliance outcomes are often unmeasured.
So what does that mean in practice?
So it means many organizations know
whether the server is alive, they
know whether the latency is low, they
know whether Q depth is acceptable,
but then they may not know whether
an automated workflow is making
correct t auditable decisions.
That is why the statement at
the bottom matters so much.
A system can be operational while
automated decisions are wrong.
That is really the whole
talk in one sentence.
Now, let's make this more concrete
with the example on the slide.
The scenario is very realistic.
A claims processing system shows
normal infrastructure metrics.
So again, the operations
dashboard looks healthy.
Then a rule configuration change
silently alters approval thresholds.
That is super important.
Not a server crash, not a major outage,
just a rule configuration change.
Then what happens is a question,
infrastructure monitoring remains
green throughout, so if the team
is only watching the standard
operational dashboard, they
will think everything is fine.
But meanwhile, automated decisions
drift from expected outcomes, and that
drift is undetected by monitoring.
Now, let's look at the impact section.
Incorrect approvals or rejections
may be processed at scale.
Compliance exposures increases because
the regulatory audit trial may be
incomplete and no infrastructure
alert is triggered, so the problem
stays invisible to the on-call team.
That is why this call.
A silent workflow failure, it is silent
because the system still responds.
It is a workflow failure because
the error lives inside the business
logic, not the server health.
And the sentence at the bottom is
exactly the lesson System health does
not guarantee decision out correctness.
That is very important.
Shift in mindset.
If technical health is not enough for
should teams monitor is a question, right?
That is what the slides answer.
We have to start defining
reliability at the workflow level.
This means watching each important
step in the business process.
For example, at the data input
stage, we ask is the input
validated at the rule engine stage?
We ask.
Are the correct rules being used
at the decision output stage?
We ask is the outcome
within the expected range?
At the compliance validation stage,
we ask are required fields complete?
And at the audit log stage, we ask,
is the record immutable and complete?
Now from these checkpoints, it
gives four practical indicators.
The first is decision accuracy rate.
That means the percentage of
automated decisions falling
within the expected outcome range.
The second is approval or rejection.
In a volume that means detecting
statistical deviation from the
historical decision baseline.
So if approval rates.
Suddenly spikes are drop
in an unusual way, right?
That becomes a signal.
The third is compliance field completion.
That means checking whether
required audit attributes are
populated for each transaction.
And the fourth is rule
execution correctness.
That means verifying that rules
execute as configured, conformed
against known test cases.
This is very strong slide
because it shows that workflow
reliability is not a wake idea.
It can actually be turned
into concrete indicators.
So this slide shows how silent failures
propagate at first things look healthy.
Data ingestion is healthy,
infrastructure is okay.
Validation service is healthy, so
infrastructure is also healthy.
So again, early in the
flow, nothing seems wrong.
But then we reach the rule engine here.
The slide shows critical point,
like silent fail, and it says
config error, no alert fired.
So the failure starts there.
Then what happens next is a question.
The decision output
shows propagated impact.
Then downstream processing
also shows propagated impact.
And throughout all this, the
infrastructure monitoring layer is
still green and no alerts are triggered.
That visual is powerful because it
shows how a small logical issue in one
place can spread throughout the workflow
without any infrastructure symptom.
Then the slide list, common causes
of silent failures, like rule
configurators, data mapping issues,
decision through threshold drift,
missing compliance attributes.
These are exactly the kind of issues
that enterprise teams often deal with,
and none of them necessarily crash
the service, but they can absolutely
create wrong decisions, compliance
risk, and operational exposure.
So the lesson here is simple.
Just because infrastructure is green,
that does not mean business logic is safe.
Now we move from problem to the response.
This slide is important because it
connects testing and reliability.
It shows the flow testing,
deployment, monitoring, instant
learning, and improve testing.
So instead of thinking about testing as
something that ends before production,
this slide shows a feedback loop.
Testing becomes part of
continuous reliability validation.
Then the slide gives four
practical implementation methods.
First is synthetic business transactions.
This means replaying production
representative requests continuously
against live role engines.
In simple words, we create
realistic transactions patterns
and use them to check whether the
system still behaves as expected.
Second is critical workflow monitoring.
This means tracking decision
outcomes, approval rates, and
rule execution in real time.
So now we are not just monitoring
c, p or latency, we are
monitoring business behavior.
Third is rule validation in production.
This means comparing rule
engine outputs against expected
baselines after every deployment.
So after a release, we do not just
ask whether deployment succeeded.
We ask whether the rule engine is
still producing the right outcomes.
And the fourth is decision
and moral detection.
This means.
Alerting on statistical deviation
in automated outcomes, not
just on technical error rates.
That is a major shift because
sometimes the first sign of a
production issue is not a 500 error.
Sometimes the first sign is a strange
pattern in approvals, rejections,
or workflow results, and that is
why the line at the bottom matters.
Testing evolves into continuous
reliability validation.
That is really the bridge between
quality engineering and production
reliability, how teams can
implement workflow reliability.
This slide brings it all
together in a practical way.
It shows four steps teams can take.
First is define workflow
level reliability indicators.
That means instrumenting
metrics like decision accuracy.
Compliance field completion
and rule execution validation.
This is all in addition to
uptime and latency, so we are not
replacing any traditional metrics
here we are just extending them.
Second is monitor automated decision
outcomes, track approvals and rejection
rates, decision distributions, and
output ranges, and alert when patents
move away from expected baselines.
Third is detect anomalies in
approval and rejection patterns.
Use statistical thresholds to surface
drift and automated decisions before it
turns into a larger compliance issue.
And for this feed production
insights back into testing.
Use real decision distributions to improve
test cases, update expected thresholds and
validate rule changes before deployment.
Then the slide gives a very clean
summary testing plus observability
equals workflow reliability.
That is a very strong statement
because it captures the whole strategy.
Testing alone is not enough.
Observability alone is not enough,
but together they give us visibility
into whether production systems are
not just up, but correct and running.
Draw this together into a single frame.
Reliability in a regulated enterprise
systems is not a single layer property.
It has three layers, and most
engineering teams are only covering
the first one, which is infrastructure
monitoring, like uptime, error
rates, latency, resource utilization.
And things like this.
This is the layer which is necessary,
which is non-negotiable, but it is
not sufficient because it cannot
tell you whether the decisions
your system is making are correct.
Next one is workflow reliability,
like decision accuracy rates,
rule execution, validity,
output, distribution, monitoring.
This is the layer most
SRE teams do not have.
It is also the layer that determines
whether your system is running
and doing its actual job, not just
running, but running correctly.
S. And the final one is competence
validation, like audit trial integrity,
regulatory field completeness,
verified automated outcomes.
This is a layer that regulators
examine when it fails.
The consequences are
financial and reputational.
So the final sentence on this slide
becomes the true definition of
reliability in this environment.
Reliability in regulated enterprise
systems means ensuring automated
decisions remain correct.
T and auditable.
That is the, that is broader than uptime
and latency, and that is the reliability
as the business actually experiences it.
So as I close, I want to leave
you with one simple idea.
A system can be up and still be wrong.
It can meet latency targets, show
low error rates, and keep every
infrastructure dashboard green
while still producing incorrect
decisions, skipping comprehensive
checks, or creating gaps in order.
And in regulated systems,
those are not minor issues.
Those are reliability issues.
So if we want stronger production systems,
we need to extend our thinking for sure.
From testing before release
to validation in production.
From infrastructure health to workflow
correctness, from uptime alone to
decisions that are correct T and
auditable, that is how we strengthen
our regulated production systems.
Thank you so much for your time.
I hope this has been very useful.
I would welcome the opportunity to
discuss any of this ideas further.
Goodbye.