Hello everyone.
I'm excited to be here at Con 42 SRA 2025.
My name is Villa Kumar here and
I'm senior cloud platform developer
with over 20 years of experience.
Today I will share cloud native
reliability strategies that blends
automation, multi-region, archite, and ai.
All aimed at minimizing downtime and
maximizing confidence in your platforms.
Cloud native reliability strategies.
So today we will explore how cloud
native environments can be designed to
maximize uptime, umbrella automation,
and integration with AI tools to
prevent outages before they occur.
Whether you're running microservices,
Kubernetes cluster or multi-region
infrastructure, this talk will arm you
with best practices and strategies.
Why reliability matters.
Downtime is more than a technical issue.
It's a business risk.
It directly impacts the revenue,
customer satisfaction, and brand trust.
In a cloud native world where
systems are always on reliability
must be intentional and proactive.
It's not enough to react to the incidents.
We must prevent them, detect
them early and recover quickly.
That starts with treating reliability
as a core architectural goal.
So what are the key cloud
reliability challenges?
Cloud native systems bring
agility, but also complexity.
You have likely faced latency spikes from
autoscaling, case scaling failures between
services and the fatigue of noisy alerts.
These challenges are amplified by dynamic
environments and ephemeral infrastructure.
The key is visibility, knowing what
happening in your en, in your environment.
When and why And creating system that
can withstand this unpredictability.
So multi legion failover one
pro and reliability strategy
is geographical redundancy.
Deploying your application
in multiple regions.
Protect against zone outages,
network dis disruptions.
Or cloud provider failures,
but redundancy is not enough.
You must test it.
Regular failover rails, kiosk engineering
and synthetic traffic can validate your
setup before a real incident occur.
Active models give the best availability,
but that requires more engineering effort.
So self-healing automation, we
all know that humans don't scale.
Self-healing systems are your best
defense against unexpected disruptions.
With Kubernetes, you can
autostart containers.
With tar Terraform, you
can rebuild infrastructure.
Declaratively Ansible can
automate your incident responses.
The goal is to detect, react, and
recover, ideally without a pager.
Alerting a human at 3:00 AM so AI driven
reliability AI is no longer futuristic.
It's here and helping
us keep systems online.
AI model can forecast anomalies,
reduce alert fatigues, and
with intelligent filtering.
Identify root cause faster than we think.
Platforms like New Relic, ai Dyna, and
Azure Monitor are already embedded in
enterprise ob observability tracks.
This isn't about replacing engineers,
it's about giving them superpower.
So what are the best practices?
Here is the checklist
designed for failure.
Simulated with chaos tools, automate
deployments, observe everything, logs,
metrics, traces, and real time user data.
Promote share responsibility.
Reliability is not just the SRE job.
Define the tracks.
SLOs, SLI and other budgets adopt
infrastructure as a code and ops workflow.
So what are the final takeaways?
If there is one thing I hope you
live with, it's resilience isn't
just about preventing downtime,
it's about earning users trust.
Cloud native reliability is a continuous
journey for a better design, smarter
automation and collaborative culture.
Let's build system that predict
failures and keep your environment
up and running with minimal downtime.
Thank you.
I would like to hear
your questions thought.
Or challenges you face, please reach
out to me or an email or LinkedIn.
Thank you.