Hey everyone, and welcome to this
session on Reliability Patterns,
information Doctor Systems.
Your host today is maybe we will be
too, and I preferably go by the name.
Great.
I currently work as an SRA and I've spent
several years focusing on reliability
engineering in distributed systems.
I've spent the last three years
building our permission systems
blockchain networks like capital fabric.
You got checkups like Key 12 does the
link and here in outside work stuff.
I like philosophy and mathematics.
So in this talk we are going to
explore, proving architectural and
operational patterns that can help
you keep your fabric network highly
available and silence to failures.
I'll walk you through everything on
how to cluster nodes for foster arounds
to handling Byzantine scenarios.
The practical performance tuning
and yeah, maybe in the end we'll
talk about reward incidents.
Yeah, this session overview so quickly,
we're going to have a fabric overview,
so that we're aligned on the basic
components of like fabric network.
Then next hour we'll dive into
fourth tolerance, no clusters,
focusing on peers and ordering.
Then we'll look at Byzantine
fourth tolerance and how fabric
is evolving in that area.
Then after that, we'll
discuss network partitioning.
How you handle network partitions
because, things like this
happen, bad things happen.
The nurse will talk about performance
tuning for high availability.
Then we would cover monitoring
and all alerting strategies.
So you can detect issues early.
Then we'll review reward failure
scenarios and, learn from them.
What is fabric?
Hyper Fabric is a modular.
Permission blockchain framework or system.
So unlike public blockchains
like Bitcoin, Orum, or Sona it's
designed for environments where
participants are known or semi state.
So you are going to find this in
government or you're going to find
this in financial institutions or
supply chain, that kind of stuff.
Fabric main confidence peers, they
host ledgers and smart contracts
which you could also call chain codes.
Then the ordering service,
puts transactions and put
transactions into blocks.
So we would see how raft, MD ft
can be used there for reliability.
Then maybe shift service or cs or.
Certificate authorities the
issue and manage identities.
Then chain code is a smart contract logic.
Chain codes are installed on ps so
what chain codes to is to endorse
and, and, validate transactions.
We'll talk about we're going to talk
about how to prevent that time data loss.
I know.
Of catastrophic failures
in such a system like this.
And fabric.
The way fabric is designed to
have reliability, it has, it
does like a distributor system
where, you know each and everyone
knows kinds of dough replication.
The consensus is also configurable.
So you can either run
Raft or PFT even solo.
Kafka is also deprecated.
And yeah, the way these peers
sync is or the way this system
sync is through the protocol.
Yeah, this is an example diagram
of a multi organization fabric
network in this organization.
There are about in this network
there are about four organizations
the root organization, which
the ordering service could run.
And established partner needs to have a
separate or there are organization where,
yeah this network has a art organizations.
Organization one, two, Andre.
And if you look at each of these
organizations have at least one
pair running in them a could.
A good a, a good example of a network
that's built for redundancy will
have at least two pairs on them.
So you could see organization
one is running about, about
eight Ps and organization two and
three are running one pair each.
And also like the ordering services
the road organization is running about
three orders which are built on Rev.
So as this store goes on I think a
lot of things will make sense here.
Yeah, it also, if you notice, each of
these organizations are running ac to
manage identity, the big picture here
is that each org has multiple peers.
These peers talk to the
ordering notes to get blocks.
So we, and the way each of this component
talk is through the gossip protocol.
So we rely on the basic protocol for peers
to share their data among themselves.
Yeah, like I said, I architectural
patterns each or two to three PS for
redundancy plus protocol for ledger syn.
The ordering service could have three to
five orders, and you need to select an org
number because NCES runs on this thing.
And yeah, if you're running raft.
Okay, yeah, we'll get more on that.
Yeah, CAS you, the cluster running
with that CAS might not be a problem.
Ca, ca. Cas if you, if your ca goes
down, that will probably not a problem.
The network will still run.
But in cases where clients have to renew
certificates or you want to enroll a
new certificate, that becomes a problem.
So you probably want to have a backup
on cas and yeah, if you are running
on Kubernetes, there's a feature
in Kubernetes for anti affinity.
So you want to spread the Ps or
other ports across different modes.
You don't want all of them running in
same Kubernetes mode because if that
Kubernetes no should go down, for example,
you have your home network going down.
So yeah.
In this, in this section we're
going to talk about force tolerant,
no clusters, how you build fault
node level, force tolerance.
So like I said in fabric you
have two types of nodes, the
PS and the ordering service.
The p at least each org should
have at least two or three years.
Oftentimes in a good network trade.
If one feels the other one can
endorse transactions or save queries.
Go see, ensure that, they
keeping consistent ledger copy.
Yeah.
For the ordering service, we, you
typically roll three to five other if you
are using raft for crash for to Rails.
So if one fill the cluster will
select a new leader as long that
there's still a majority up.
So Raft is based on
leader based consensus.
So at each, every time the
cluster needs a leader.
There's a leader election that goes
on if one of if a leader crashes
or dies and, if you want to, if
you want higher 40 tolerance, it
could go as high as five nodes.
So in five nodes it could probably
be able to tolerate two crashes.
So keep adding, yeah, keep adding
nodes for, higher 40 tolerance.
You should ensure it's a high no.
So we also want to make sure you are not
adding a lot of notes because there's,
you, do you want to make sure that
you are not having so many notes that.
Throw out the cluster from equilibrium.
So this architecture, is crucial
because if we had only one ordering
node, or if we had only a single
pay, any downtime, we just host
the network or the entire network.
We could see why this is,
This is, important.
The way raft works is by having a node.
So we'll just talk a little
bit on raft mechanics.
Raft works by having one no.
As a leader, that leader
proposes transaction batches.
When a majority of the nude
or Fullers acknowledge the
block is considered committed.
If the leader fails one of the follower
steps or, and becomes a leader.
So in a three, no plus losing
one no doesn't necessarily stop
the show because you still have
two nos forming the majority.
That's how we keep ordering online
despite hardware failures or crashes.
Yeah, so to avoid single points of
failure, to summarize the key is
to avoid single point of failure.
No single other error is always a cluster.
Multiple Ps For organization,
you want to have three at least.
So if your identity issuance is
mission critical or very important,
you want to have a backup.
And if you are running a ities, you want
to set up anti affinity to make sure that
ports are not necessarily on the same.
Post as a rule of thumb, you
consider your failure domains like
rejoin data center or even the rack
and, spread the nodes according.
So let's talk a little bit on
fault, uming fault tolerance.
So fabric default.
Consensus is craft is crash fault
tolerant, which means that is raft.
Raft is crash fault tolerant.
But if your nudes, what if your
nudes could be outright initial?
For example, one of your nodes is trying
to reorder the order of transactions.
So yeah, that is a form
that, doesn't take care of.
Bezant for tolerance means that the
system can tolerate notes that act
actively misbehave or attempt to
fuck the chain, or attempt to crazy
things like reorder transactions.
So Fabric introduced A BFT ordering
service called BFT in professional trade.
So this requires three F plus one.
No.
To tolerate failures means that
if you want, for example, one to
tolerate, if you want to tolerate
one 14 root, you need to have four.
So that is three times one plus one.
Yeah.
So every f is the number of
failures or malicious nodes you
want to be able to tolerate.
So if you want to be able to tolerate, two
40 or malicious notes, that is three times
two plus one, which is about seven nodes.
So it, yeah, it's more resource intensive
and has more a message overhead.
You get a stronger guarantee, but
you get a stronger guarantee that the
network will remain consistent even
if some participants act maliciously.
The use cases for this is, if you are
in an environment where you are, you
don't really trust the other members.
Yeah, VFT is really suitable
for this all in know, very
high value finance environment.
You have to summarize raft handles, crash
failures well, but not malicious ones.
So VFT can handle both.
Yeah most deployments would
not immediately jump to BFT
because it's still, it's still
something very new in fabric.
But if you have a, use a use case
for truly un untrusted participants
yeah, then it's worth evaluating.
So yeah.
Let's let's look at
handling network partitions.
So real distributor systems must
handle like a case where the network
itself fails or, becomes segmented.
So let's discuss other partition, let's
say the set of other partition themselves.
So with Ralph, the only
partition, the partition that
has a majority of other roles.
Would continue producing blocks.
So the minority side stores
doesn't create a fork.
So when the, once the partition heals
the minority automatically catches up.
But for pair isolation, if the pairs
are isolated, they stop receiving
blocks with when connectivity returns.
They do a course C based catch up that
is pulling missed blocks from the.
Healthy ps. So as architects, we want
to distribute moves across different
zones or data centers so that we
can still achieve a mi a majority,
even if a region is fought off.
This is a partition diagram.
This network shows, this
diagram shows that the majority
partition keeps ordering.
Going, why the minority stores?
So the big takeaway here is
that no F happens, right?
So the minority side, eventually,
since once the network is restored.
So let's discuss performance
tuning for high availability.
Reliability is not really just
about redundancy, it's also about
ensuring that the system can
handle those without feeling.
Yeah, just like some tips, increased
block size for throughput, you
also want to watch for latency.
You have to tune this for your workload.
If possible, use more
looser or flexible policies.
EG, any two of three orgs can keep
you running if one of the org is down.
So strict policies can cause
a stall or hold if a required
organization goes offline.
Then also like for the
study, level DB is faster.
But CouchDB supports switcher queries,
that is adds like some form of overhead.
Then you also, want to have multiple
channels like izing, workload for
scalability or isolating issues.
Past SSD enough, CPU, you want to ensure
that you are beefed at the hardware level,
so you enough, CPU, memory, SSD, and
even network bandwidth running upgrades.
Update one at the time.
Yeah.
So to avoid total art.
So this is a sample raft config.
So you can see in the XRP how
we define ants in other tmo.
So this is sample other
TMO for a raft cluster.
If you, the key parameters here,
like tick interval, election, tick
and heartbeat, it can be tuned.
Based on the network latency.
Many times default values are often fine
but in high latency or global deployments,
you may want to increase them.
So yeah, you can tune this election
tick a b tick, and also concern us.
So this is an endorsement policy example.
It's like a Jason snippet.
That requires any two or three orgs.
So this means that one org would be
completely offline, but will still
be able to get valid endorsement.
This is much more silent than a
policy that is requiring, or three.
Which means that if one organization
store, then the whole network is
stored or transaction in the is stored.
Yeah, for monitoring and all alerting.
So you want to proactively catch issues.
So we need monitoring.
Kissing notes include like no
health and container restart.
You want to also look like
block production rate, leisure
heights to dictate lacking those.
You want to also check transaction
throughput, latency, resource
usage, and, set expiration.
So a popular combo is a
parameters plus Grafana.
But I think you can use stuff like a LK.
You can also use stuff like
a LK Splunk Datadog for.
Log analysis.
Until you want to out for, you want
to out for no new blocks has been
created or, or even resource tion.
Yeah.
So yeah, all that.
Like proactive, all alerting you
could do is detect ano early.
So you want to check if
the RAF lid has changed.
You want to check on, you want
also all alert on cause failures
or monitor stuff like this.
And if possible, you have taken,
this matrix a lot, a long time.
You want to do like historical
trend analysis on, on this.
Yeah, these are some, like even with all
these patterns, something can go wrong.
So let's look at some examples.
Audrey?
No Audrey, no.
Crash.
Ralph would quickly elect a
nude, neither and the metal.
So this needs no really
manual intervention.
Yeah.
So PS out of sync.
Gossip sometimes can,
automatically catch up.
Only stream, probably the net, their
network failures outside of fabric.
All down strict endorsement policy
probably has frozen the network or
you don't have enough organizations.
Set expiration.
I think if a most case of this
is what happened with T Cash on
CBDC when it went down for months.
I've also, when I worked at gala.
The chain was also based
on Hyperledger fabric.
There are some instances where,
set exploration caused big issues.
Yeah, put sometimes to things like
chin code bugs, like a container
can panic, but other peers.
And also there's partial,
continuity network partition.
Only majority sites.
Keep, only majority side
continues, so minority will
be stored until it reconnects.
Sometimes you have like denial service
act where they are valued in pair
with proposals that leads to slow
endorsement or maybe even a store.
This is going to need rate limits.
So from this incident, we have seen
like that even multi mode setups,
flexible policies, automatic renewals,
and to monitoring are crucial.
So in all of these, I think
monitoring is really important here.
So industry, there's some
industry use cases and, lessons
industry use cases or fabric.
And we've seen fabric
in financial services.
I've seen, fabric and supply chain.
The financial services you is
typically like multi joint deployment,
so three to five afternoons.
If they like, they could also use BFD
also zero down time updates and very
heavy on monitoring supply chain.
This is high volume, so you
need, parallel channels.
And you also have to meet, data is
always available even if some peers feel.
For identity systems very small,
very security focused networks,
they'll po possibly adopt BFT
for malicious fault tolerance.
In every of these cases, the
ops team heavily invest in
monitoring, scaling, and testing.
Best practices, like a
recap of best practices.
You want to have redundant peers and
other nodes, like redundant components.
You want to have flexible endorsements
avoid single or endorsement if possible.
And you also don't have
to require every org.
Regular certificates management
and backup of admin credentials.
Two block sizes and
endorsements for your workload.
Active monitoring actively monitor also
fill over and rolling upgrades stone.
Minimize time.
Time and yeah, to test your assumptions.
You could, shut down, or simulate in
partition to see if the network recovers.
So like sometimes do some chaos testing.
So the conclusion here is hyper
fabric can be very reliable if we
take advantage of its architecture.
If we distribute other replicate pairs,
set up to full endorsement policies,
and build a solid monitoring track,
we have looked at both crash force
tolerance and byzantine force tolerance
and how to handle network partitions.
And how to two performance and
how to avoid reward pitfalls
like certificate expiry.
So by following this reliability
patterns, you'll be well on your way to a
resilient enterprise ready fabric network.
Thank you for your attention and yeah,
this was I hope this was a good talk and.
Gives you some perspective on how
to design reliability patterns
in permission blockchain systems.
Thank you.
Bye.