Speaker 4: Hello everyone and welcome.
Today we are going to dive deep
into compute charted stream
processing at petabyte scale.
It's a critical topic covering
streaming data pipelines, latency
and site reliability issues.
I'm thrilled to be presenting this year.
Let's get started.
Let's go to next slide.
Before we jump into the
details, a quick introduction.
I am Aikman a senior software
engineer at Microsoft.
My day-to-day work revolves around
large scale distributed systems.
Specifically my work focuses on realtime
data pipelines, stream processing
architectures, and cybersecurity
and analytics infrastructure.
We spend a lot of time in engineering
and building fault tolerant data
processing architectures and
SRE oriented system reliability.
This is to handle petabyte
scale telemetry ingestion.
Now in the next slide, I will talk over
the agenda on what we are going to cover.
First, we will examine the detection
latency problem and discuss
exactly why batch based seams
architectures are failing us at scale.
Second, we will look into the
architecture design focusing on compute
charted stream processing principles.
Third, we will cover
ingestion and detection.
Exploring schema agnostic pipelines
and hybrid rule ML detections.
Fourth, we'll discuss multi-region
resilience and how we ensure geographic
fault tolerance and consistency.
And finally, I'll share some
validation and case studies to
highlight measured outcomes.
Let's go to next slide.
The adversary does not wait.
Let's talk about the problem.
A bad actor does not
wait for your batch job.
Modern attackers operate with incredible
speed and automation techniques
like lateral movement, credential
harvesting, and establishing persistence
can often be completed in minutes.
Unfortunately, this often happens
with a single batch prow window.
This creates a massive detection gap.
That cycle introduces minutes to
hours of latency, which in a window
that attackers exploit fully.
The alert delay means that by
the time a traditional seam
finally generates an alert.
The threat actor may already have
persistence in your environment.
Add this to the severe scale Mismatch.
Petabyte Scale Telemetry simply overwhelms
architecture that are originally designed
for gigabyte scale data volume pipelines.
Let's go to next slide.
Why traditional architectures break.
So why do traditional C
architectures break at scale?
Put simply, they were
designed for a different era.
They rely heavily on
scheduled batch cycles.
This introduces structural latency.
And to be clear, this
isn't at tunable latency.
It's an architectural latency baked
deeply into every layer of the pipeline.
At petabyte Scale, this structure
flaw creates compounding problems.
Your ingestion queue backs up your
correlation window growth tail,
and ultimately your alert fertility
severely degrades under the load.
Let's go to the next slide
to solve this problem.
The core architecture based on
compute, charted stream processing.
This flow moves from telemetry
ingestion to compute sharding
into parallel processing, and
finally to detection and response.
The brilliance of this system is
that it distributes both data and
computation across independent prosing
nodes utilizing consistent hashing.
Because of this, each chart
operates autonomously.
We are effectively eliminating
centralized bottleneck while enabling
linear horizontal scaling as our
data volume continues to grow.
Next slide.
Now let's double click on how
we distribute work without
creating centralized bottleneck.
And why do we use consistent ashing?
Consistent hashing allow us to assign
both data and streams and compute
workloads to the node in a virtual ring.
This gives us predictable
deterministic shard assignment.
The major benefit is elasticity
when nodes are added or removed,
only a minimal subset of key maps.
This means we can scale out with
minimal rebalancing overhead, and
with a full reshuffle of the system.
It is also highly fault isolated.
If a no fails, it only affects
its specific key range.
Finally, it enables a stateful
stream correlation per shard without
the need of global correlation.
Let's go to the next slide.
Another major hurdle in legacy
system is data integration.
Security telemetry is heterogeneous.
You're dealing with firewall logs, EDR
events, cloud audit trails, network
flows, and identity signals requiring
predefined schemas create a massive
integration friction and slows down how
fast you can expand your threat coverage.
Our solution is schema agnostic
ingestion allowing us to
onboard any source intently.
We rely on dynamic schema interface,
meaning the ingestion layer in
first structure at run time.
This completely eliminates upfront
schema engineering for new sources.
The result is.
Faster source integration.
New telemetry source can be
onboarded without pipeline halts
or complex schema migration cycles.
We apply lightweight normalization at the
ingestion boundary to ensure downstream
processing consistency without bogging
down the system with heavy pre-processing.
Let's go to the next slide,
continuous stream processing.
This brings us to the showdown.
Continuous stream processing versus
bad cycles By moving to streams,
structural latency is eliminated
and bad systems Data is processed in
discrete schedule windows, so every
event has to wait until next cycle runs.
Continuous stream processing evaluates
every single event as it arrives.
This enable correlation and detection
within seconds rather than minutes.
Let me emphasize this.
The latency gap is not marginal.
It is an order of magnitude and that
the delay compounds across multi
hub detection chains pretty easily.
That is why it is really important
to have a stream processing
whenever alerts are critical.
Let's go to the next slide.
Hybrid detections.
With the data flowing continuously,
how do we catch bad actors?
We use a hybrid detection model,
combining rules and machine learning.
Not single detection strategy covers hot
landscape of all the threats that we have.
So we deploy two complementary
detection layers.
First, we have rule-based detection.
This handles known attack
signatures, compliance checks,
and threshold based alerts.
It offers low latency, high precision,
and well-defined threat patterns.
Second, we combine that
with ML anomaly detection.
This maximize our coverage area
and fidelity by using behavioral
baseline, statistical deviation
and unsupervised clustering.
The ML layer catches novel behavior
and zero day techniques that
don't have redefined signatures.
Let's go to the next slide.
Multi-region resilience.
Operating at petabyte scale
means operating globally.
Multi-region deployment is necessary
for resilience at a global scale.
Geographic distribution isn't
just reliability strategy.
It is a strict compliance
and performance necessity.
For global enterprise security operations,
we ensure geographical resilience
through region failure isolation.
So region outage does not compromise
our global detection coverage.
We utilize localized processing to meet
data residency requirement and process
telemetry within its designated region.
Boundaries to keep everything aligned,
distributed consensus mechanism,
maintain cross region consistency
for detection rules and state across
all active regions without tight
coupling and for fault tolerance.
Automatic shard reassignment,
and region failover.
Ensure processing continue to even
under node or zone level failures.
Let's go to the next slide.
Validation and results.
So what does architecture
actually deliver?
Validation across our deployment
environment demonstrate consistent
measurable improvement over batch based
system in all key operation dimensions.
For latency reduction detection,
latency was reduced by an order of
magnitude compared to scheduled batch
cycles for sustained throughput.
Our pricing throughput remained
stable under increasing workload with
absolute no de degradation at scale.
In terms of resource utilization, we
saw improvement in compute utilization
per unit of telemetry processed when
compared to centralized architectures.
Most importantly, for incidents, we
achieved a measurable reduction in time to
respond across our case study deployments.
Let's go to the next.
If you are SRE team looking to
build real-time cybersecurity
pipeline at scale in production,
here are four key architecture
principles and operational lessons.
Takeaway first design for
horizontal scale from day one.
Vertical scaling hits sailing very
quickly at petabyte scale volume.
Your sharding strategy must be
first class design vision, not
something you try to retrofit later.
Second.
Decouple ingestion from processing,
implementing schema, agnostic
ingestion layer allow you to expand
your data sources without pipeline
freezes, which is critical for
maintaining threat coverage velocity.
Third, instrumenting everything.
Alerts on SLO metrics like
processing, lags, short
rebalanced duration and detection.
Pipeline depth, RSRE grade SLAs.
You must define these SLOs before
your production rollout both.
Test failures, moan, not just happy
path, node loss, region partitions,
and back pressure cascades across
multiple systems can create a big
mess if things are not working.
Remember, resilience is not
emergent, it is engineered.
Let's go to the next slide
to conclude detection Latency
is an architectural vision.
We must build systems that are fast
enough to matter when it counts.
Thank you all for your time.