Speaker 2: Hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
The Failures You Do Not See on
Dashboards, A reliability case study
in workflow latency and response time.
I'm guessing most of
us are engineers here.
We are great at handling outages,
the alarms player, the graphs spike.
We jump into the incident channel,
we figure it out and we fix it.
But today I want to talk about the
most expensive reliability failures.
They aren't outages.
They're the quite and partial
failures and the slow humans down.
While our dashboards look
completely normal, they look green.
Before diving into my talk,
I'm gonna introduce myself.
My name is Aman Val.
I'm an engineering team lead at
Bloomberg for security services.
You can reach to me via LinkedIn.
Now let's picture a day
when your system is healthy.
All the service level signals are fine.
Your errors are low, latency is normal.
Your saturation is stable, your
traffic is flowing Normally, if
you're an SRE, that usually means
that we are safe, but in this case,
the response time worsened anyway.
Not the response time for the system,
but the response time for humans.
So what does that feel
like inside the workflow?
That's the fog of war.
Fog of war isn't panic, it's ambiguity.
You are fighting an outage.
You are fighting uncertainty.
The hardest question becomes, are we
seeing everything that we should be seeing
because of the answer is no, or maybe then
every conclusion becomes provisional, and
that's how the response time stretches.
Before we dive into my talk, let's
set some quick boundaries about
what the talk is and what it is not.
This is an anonymized case study
and a reusable SRE pattern.
It is not a breed story, not a got
hacked story, not a proprietary
architecture description of Bloomberg.
The goal is to take familiar
SRE practices and extend them
to a multi-system workflow.
For human in the loop workflows.
To show you what I mean, let's take a
look at a scenario that my team face.
We maintain a high volume security
pipeline, like many of the
workflows, it looks like this.
The events enter into the system ticket
process, the results surface in a ui.
A human analyst validates them and
then they take action based on that.
But for a long time, everything seemed
perfect, but then the first crack started
to appear in our system, and a low
severity alert was fired by an analyst.
The counts had diverged
between various stages.
We sh we saw earlier.
This is where the thriller starts
because the system is technically
up, but the coverage is uncertain.
Our edge gateway, which receives
the events, said it received a
hundred thousand events, but the
downstream analysis engine, which
is supposed to process these
events was only showing 90,000.
Even nothing has had crashed until now.
Everything is working as it should be.
But then there is a gap, and
in these workflows, uncertainty
is operationally expensive.
The question becomes, is this
expected transformation lag or
is it a visibility gap here?
Why this is a trap.
The same system can mean
two different things.
It can be two different realities, and we
need to figure out what is the true thing.
After this alert, we lived in fog of
war For some time, our management kept
asking, are we missing any threats?
Luckily, we did not miss anything.
Finally, after a log of
digging, we uncovered the truth.
The processing engine
worked perfectly fine.
The safety checks had happened, but the
telemetry agent had silently failed.
And drop the logs before the real R
UI in which we were seeing the logs.
Our compute health was a hundred percent,
but our cognitive load was overwhelmed.
The system worked as it should have,
but we just couldn't prove that it
was working like the way it should.
This incident forced us to ask
a hard question, why didn't our
standard SRE alarm catch this?
Why did it take a human noticing a volume
drop and then firing an alert for my team,
and then we triggered an investigation.
It's because our alarms were
looking for a long, wrong thing.
Ses rely on the golden signals.
As we saw earlier, the four golden
signals, latency, traffic, errors,
situation, they all were fine.
In our scenario, they answer.
Is the system alive, but in a complex
pipeline like ours, it completely
missed The most important question,
is the workflow explainable?
We realize we are measuring
the wrong type of latency.
A service latency measures the
milliseconds between a request and a
response, but we needed to measure a
workflow latency, the time it takes
for a human to go from seeing a signal.
To confidently taking an
action based on that signal.
When telemetry drops, workflow
latency usually skyrockets, and that's
what had happened in our scenario.
To fix this, we decided to stop
treating this like a logging issue.
We started treating and started
seeing the entire human workflow
like a distributed trace.
We needed to measure.
End to end latency, including
the human validation step.
Once we shifted our mindset
to tracking the workflow, the
solution became more clear.
We implemented three specific
SLIs to measure the health of the
pipeline, and a three design tactics
to fix the overall architecture.
Our first slide was tracking the
end-to-end duration, not the API speed.
But the P 50 P 95 time from the
moment an event hits the ingestion
to exact moment, it is visible to
the user in the ui, and we started
alerting when it is consistently
worse than the workflow requires, and
that's what we would recommend to do.
This catches the slow degradation
even when the service appears healthy.
The second SLI we took
was count integrity.
We started comparing the counts
across the pipeline stages when
with an explicit model of expected
deltas and lags, for example, we
don't just alert on a hard mismatch.
We define expected lag windows.
So if a stage A and stage B diverged by 2%
for five minute, that's normal divergence.
If they diverged by 10% for an
R, the invariant is broken, and
we started alerting on that.
The last SLI that we took was about
seeing if pipeline is truly open or not.
We couldn't wait for the real traffic.
So we introduce a synthetic canary, a
known good event, injected continuously
to prove the workflow was functioning.
If you only take one thing away
from my talk today, it's this.
Introduce a canary and
verify them at every stage.
This tells you not only that the system
are up, but also if the workflow is
producing observable, trustworthy outputs.
End to end.
Those SR. SLIs that we had said gave us
visibility, but we also needed to change
how the system behaved under pressure.
We needed a new architectural
standard, so we came up with our
fifth signal of core of SE and we
started calling it as collaboration.
The system must be able to
reveal its own coverage gaps
and surface its own degradation.
When the telemetry is missing, the
system should say, when the coverage
is reduced, the UI should show it.
Reliability includes the system's
ability to explain itself.
Now let's dive into some of the design
tactics or the architectural changes that
we can, we learn from our from our system.
And then maybe you can take those.
The in variance are your
reliability contracts.
Everything received is eventually
that what gets surfaced within a known
time window and with a known transf.
So if you make those invariants
observable, you can turn your
ambiguity into a measurable state.
Next.
What we changed in our design tactic
was not treating up and down as the
only state partial degradation should
also be treated as a first class state.
If the logs drop out, don't just keep UI
looking normal surface, the telemetry has
been delayed, the coverage is reduced.
This helps.
Usually this prevents false confidence
and reduces the wasted time.
The last one, if the humans
are a reliability endpoint,
measure the friction.
You can proxy repeated queries, pivots,
escalations, reopen rates, proxy them.
Before we fix this, we
watch escalation loops.
Multiply tier one analysts couldn't
trust the RUI, so they escalated
everything to the engineering to
run the manual database queries.
The friction was our metric.
This is your true error rate.
I would recommend to measure it.
Now, I have a checklist for
you which you can apply from.
Say like next week, pick one key
workflow, define your in variance at one
synthetic canary instead of workflow, SLO.
And that should be able to help.
And with that.
I'm gonna leave you with one thought.
Silent failures don't
always take the system down.
They take the certainty down, so the
dashboards only measure compute health.
We can miss cognitive failures.
Reliability is not just keeping
the system running, it's about
keeping the decisions fast.
Explainable and
trustworthy under pressure.
You don't need to keep a perfect
system from start to end.
You just need one workflow
made measurably explainable.
With that, thank you
all for listening to me.
If you're interested in learning
more about Bloomberg, you can
check us out@techatbloomberg.com.
Or if you're interested in joining
Bloomberg, you can check us out
at bloomberg.com/couriers or
reach out to me via LinkedIn.
Thank you.