Hello everyone.
Welcome to Site Reliability
Engineering Conference of 2025.
My name is Ani.
I am from Rapid Cloud Infrastructure
and I'm very excited to talk about
zero downtime ML observability Today.
Today we will explore how to
implement observability into
machine learning systems without
causing any disruption or downtime.
To the services that rely on them.
Machine learning is no longer
on experimental playground.
It has become a reality and it has
been used pretty much in all production
systems, but it brings with itself
unique set of operational challenges.
Today we'll explore some of
those SRE challenges that are
being faced and how we can make.
Okay, the ML systems more
observable, scalable, and reliable.
So let's dive right in.
As you can see, there are
two different worlds today.
One is of ML engineers and then of sre.
These two work on very
different philosophies.
ML engineers are experts
at building models, whereas
SREs are experts at running.
So.
Systems.
ML engineers tend to be focused
more on experiments and they
work in an ator process.
SREs are more focused on the service
level agreements and the service
level objectives of their services.
ML engineers tend to focus more
on the accuracy of the models and
the predictions by the models,
whereas SREs are focused more on.
The uptime and the latency of
their distributed system services.
ML engineers work more on an offline
setting where they evaluate their
models, train their models, work in the
inferencing of it, whereas the SRE are
working on real time production matrix.
As you can see, there is a gap
between both of these worlds.
So now when SREs are tasked.
With running machine learning services
in production, they would likely face a
lot of challenges because they have not
designed these models and they don't know
how the these models are supposed to run.
And what are the
predictions along with it?
Right?
So let's try and understand what
are, what are the traditional
observatory matrix that looks like?
Today's traditional tools for
observability that are equipped
for distributed systems are more
along logs, matrix, and traces.
That tells us if the distributed
service is running up or if it is
running into error, if it's hundred
percent available, and so on.
But it doesn't necessarily tell.
If the model that is being run by
the service is working correct and
in an accurate fashion, and if it is
predicting the correct output for which
it was designed, so the errors tend
to be pretty silent when they occur
in this ML systems in production.
The predictions returned by these models
could be very much or super biased.
But it is more than likely that an
SRE engineer won't get to notice this.
There could be drift that is arising
in the data and it is degrading
the performance of the model.
But when an SRE looks at all the
matrix, but it, it shows that all
the services are running up and fine.
They're meeting their SLAs and the sles.
So as we see, there are no standard
SLOs that are defined for ML quality
today that an SRE can track their
accuracy and the fairness and the
correction ratio of this models.
So what are the other challenges
that ML engineers are face facing and
the SREs are facing, who are running
these systems as we spoke about it?
There are these silent
failures, which often grow.
Undetected system is producing incorrect
output, but SRE has no way to notice this.
There are data drips happening, and
we'll talk about the different kind of
data drips in the next section, but the
data distribution has changed over time.
The data drifts are happening.
There could be prediction drift, but there
are not enough tooling around it today.
That an SRE could use,
it is slowly changing.
The model could very well get
stale if it is not retrained.
So the model is losing its effectiveness,
and an SRE should be equipped to deal
with it and to detect it early on.
There could be very much a lot of
debugging issues that could arise, and
the features that are being tracked
by the models often lack visibility.
There could be more versioning problem.
The code version may not match
with the model version and the
latency issues could also arise.
The inferencing latency could be
more, the loading of the model could
be more, which will be resulting.
In some delay at the customer end for a
good ML monitoring service work, all of
these challenges needs to be addressed.
So an ML observatory model should
be able to monitor, debug, and be
able to understand these complex and
complicated systems that are in product.
The data that is ingested by these
models need to be very accurate,
should mimic real time traffic
and not any synthetic traffic.
So the data quality needs to be high
and should be consistent over time.
There should be way to track
the distribution of the
features over time, and so that.
SREs are able to see if there is any
change over time in this distribution
and be able to catch it early on.
The model performance should be
detected using Matrix over time
so that we can detect if model is
performing accurately and correct over
time and hasn't changed its trend.
That should be.
For SREs to identify changes in the
input and output data distributions
that is known as drift detection,
a way to track different versions of
the model across retraining, and then
last, the model should be compared
with the live traffic and not with the
three traffic on which it was trained.
Think of observability here, not just
as monitoring the pipeline, but as
observing the health and reliability
of the data logic and the outcomes.
It's like adding an x-ray
vision to the black box.
Let's look at the simple ML
monitoring system in production.
An ideal model monitoring
service should be sitting right
next to the prediction service.
With it should not just ingest the
data input that is fed to the pipeline,
but it should also be ingesting the
predictions that are emitted by the model.
With this, it'll be able to make some
complex calculations and feed it to
the monitoring and visualization tools.
Now, these tools could help SRE.
To look at any alarms or matrix
that could be generated if the
model is not behaving at par.
And whenever possible, there should
be B matrix calculation that looks
at the historical data and compares
it with the ground truth, and see if
there are any changes along the way.
From an SRE perspective, the system
looks very much like a service.
This, but this service correctness
depends not just on the binary,
but on dynamic external input data
and its own historic behavior.
Let's look at some simple matrix, which
are out there for a shopping cart.
As you can see about, there is an average
latency for every region, and there is
something known as R, which is basically.
Root means squared error.
A ma a metric, often tracked in machine
learning world to see how far the
prediction is from the ground root.
It should be as low as possible.
Then there are real user metric data.
For example, there are page views
that are being track and the number
of checkouts, and towards the end we
can see an end-to-end conversion rate.
Which tells us how many users visited
the, uh, the shopping page for browsing
sofas, how many of them added those
sofas into the cart, and how many of
these sofas were actually checked out.
This is some of the good matrix that
SREs could track, especially the RMSE.
Now let's go and take a look
at the different types of drift
that we spoke about earlier.
There is prediction drift,
data drift, feature drift,
and feature attribution drift.
Today there are tools available that
would be able to track these drips
and an SRE can detect this early on.
As SRE supporting ML workload, our job
doesn't stop once a model is deployed.
In fact, that's where it really starts.
One of the key challenges is understanding
if and when the model starts behaving
differently, and this is where the
drift modeling becomes very crucial
and critical, even when ground truth is
delayed or unavailable monitoring drip.
It helps us maintain the model quality,
reduce the customer impact, and triggering
retraining workflows at the right time.
Let's talk about prediction drought.
This is when the distribution of model
prediction starts changing over time.
Let's take an example.
Let's say we have a recommendation
model that suggests product.
Normally it suggests a mix of budget
and premium items, but over time we
have noticed the model is heavily
skewed towards premium products.
So now that's a prediction shift.
Why could it be happening?
It could be because of the shifts in the
user behavior, seasonal shopping trends
like Black Friday or some festivities
or even boxing.
The upstream service, feeding the model.
Importantly, we don't need
ground truth to detect this.
Just monitoring the shape of
the predictions is enough.
Predicting drift can be the very
first alarm bell that an SRE
can see to detect if there is a
prediction drift happening or not.
Now let's go on to the next drift.
The data.
Data drift is a typical example
of a wide gap between the training
work set versus the real work
set on which it has been trained.
For example, if a model hasn't
seen any data coming out from a new
geography, it is unlikely that it's
going to predict correct output.
So this data drip happens typically when
the model hasn't seen this type of data.
And it could be for reasons like the
business has expanded in new geographies.
A new product has been rolled out, but
the model hasn't been trained on it.
Or there could be new marketing
campaigns due to which this new
data has been, uh, rolled out.
Now let's look at, take a look at one more
granular drip, which is a feature drip.
It is much granular as compared to data
drip, and this also happens because.
Of a change in data, but
for a particular feature.
For example, if there is a shift in the
values of input for an individual feature.
For example, let's say we have
a user location data, and most
of the time it used to capture
70% urban and 30% rural data.
But now over time it has flipped.
Maybe due to a regional ad
campaign that must have happened.
Now that change in the future feature
distribution is known as feature drift.
This often results from changes in
how or where the data is collected,
all shipped in the user population.
It is especially important to
drag these features that are
heavily weighted in your model.
So you would want to track the most
important features of your model
and take a careful look at these.
Feature drips specifically that are
affecting the model in a higher ratio.
The last trip is the
feature attribution route.
This is a shift in how important
feature is to model prediction,
especially across retraining.
Now, let's take an example.
Initially, our model rank prizes the most
important features of predicting code.
But after several regions and
over time, suddenly brand emerges
to become more influential.
Now, that's an attribution drift.
Why could it be happening?
Usually caused by retraining on new data.
Sometimes that could be subtle label
noise that was introduced, or there were
feature core relations that have happened,
or it could be due to an over of a model.
Do that the model has learned over time
to make decisions differently than what it
used to previously attribute distribution
doesn't always show up in the raw data,
but it changes how the model thinks.
We can have a very stable input data
and still see a noticeable performance
drop because of the attribution shift.
These are typically little hard.
To catch.
But as SREs or platform
engineers, we are not just
monitoring CPU and memory anymore.
We are monitoring the health of our
algorithms and adding drift matrix
alongside traditional observability matrix
have become all the more crucial ship,
and it'll bring the right attention to
all the silent failures that is happening
in ML systems that we could catch.
Very early on and hopefully
mitigate any large scale events
or any ML related incidents.
Now let's spend a little bit of
time to look at what a good ML
observability model looks like.
Starting with the data logging, as we
spoke about earlier, the model or the
monitoring service should not only
capture the raw inputs, but also the
prediction to make the right set of.
And next is the feature monitoring.
Each of the important features that
track by the model should be captured
and the drift should be populated.
Then comes the prediction Monitoring.
The monitoring service should
have the ability to compare the
predicted outcomes versus the actual
outcomes that are based on ground.
Truth then comes the version.
There should be a way for the service
to model predictions and the versions
and dust and the most popular one.
An SRE should have dashboards through
which they can visualize latency, the
throughput, and most importantly, the
drips that are happening over time.
So how has.
The SRE practices changed.
We have already started seeing that
the SRE practices have emerged.
In our world, the traditional SRE
practices were more around the latency
monitoring and the health checks, whether
the candidates are running fine and the
incident response was catered around it.
But now the ML aware
SRE practices lets us.
Do monitoring of the prediction
drift and all of the drifts
that we spoke about earlier.
There are enough data pipeline
checks, shadow deployments are also
happening, and the incident response
is cd from an ML perspective.
Now, what are the tools that
one can use for detecting these?
There are enough open source tools that
could be used like evidently while.
The major cloud providers has also
rolled out, uh, tools like Vertex AI is
a popular one from Google, and Amazon
SageMaker is one other one that is
quite popular amongst AWS customers.
Let's look at why zero downtime matters.
Zero downturn matters per any distributed
system service, but especially for
real time or customer facing systems.
Any monitoring or analysis steps
that disrupts availability can
lead to significant business
impacts and revenue loss.
So zero downtime is non-negotiable.
Now, as we spoke about earlier, when we
are deploying a new model, we need to
send light traffic to a shadow wood and
compare decisions with production and
flip it only when we are fairly confident.
Having said that, all the observability,
uh, monitoring should happen
asynchronous to the inferencing path.
It should not come in the
way of the critical path.
Otherwise, it'll impact the latency.
And if at all, the model is not
predicting or is giving wrong prediction,
there should be graceful degradation.
Last but not least, the
observability has to be part of
every CICD pipeline in production.
Action.
Wrapping up with my very last
thoughts, ML systems fail differently.
They brought silently, they don't
always crash, but they decay as SREs.
We must evolve our observability mindset
to include these nuances and build systems
that don't just deal up, but stay smart.
Thank you for your time.