Hello all.
Good morning, good
afternoon, good evening.
I'm Shar and first of all, thank
you for joining this session.
So today I will talk about how we can
achieve the reliability excellence
with SLO Management product.
Let me introduce myself.
I have a 12 plus years of IT experience.
Currently I'm working with Naka software
as a DevOps and a platform lead, and
I love to talk about DevSecOps Cloud
Engineering, SRE Platform Engineering.
And I'm happy to connect with you
guys via the LinkedIn and the mail
that I have already put it here.
So let's start the session.
So the agenda of the today's session
is about the quick understanding of
the SREs the principles and practices.
Then we see what are the challenges
that we face for the SLOs in
the complex environment and what
should be our approach to solve it.
Then we look for the solution by
understanding the SLO management.
Then we have and one use case.
Here we see about to how we can
define the SLOs, and as well as we
check how we can basically measure
the reliability of the system.
Then we'll look for the SLO
management products whatever
available in the markets.
And then we see some comparisons
in between those products.
So let's start with the session.
So in, in SDLC that we know that
the developers want to go as fast.
Like they want to do a development
feature as fast as possible.
We are in parallel like
operation teams that they look
down to slow down the things.
They just, they want to
make a system reliable.
That's why this kind of a misalignment
happens in between these two teams
and it often create tensions.
So that's why the SRE
comes into the picture.
SRE.
Is basically what introduced by the
Google in the early 2000 and it is useful
to basically measure the, and to solve
the operational challenges and issues.
SRE, it's a job role.
It's a mindset, it's a set of metrics
that we used to measure and to manage
the overall system reliability.
So there are some key principles of SRE.
First is service level indicator.
Service level indicator are the
metrics that used to measure
the quality of the service.
So there are the.
Couple of different metrics.
Mostly that we use is availability,
throughput, and the latency.
Then we have an service level.
Objective service level.
Objectives are the the target
level of that particular.
Metrics.
Basically that the 99, 9 9% of
our system should be available.
So this is a target
level that we set this.
So this is, SLO is for
the internal benchmarking.
So SL is a goal rather than a promise.
But it is also help for the customers.
That we define the specific metrics
and we have some kind of in shorty
that our system would be available
up to this kind of a target so
that we promise, to the customers.
Then we have an service level agreement.
So it's a contract between the end
users and the service provider.
So if the the promises are the breaks,
so the service provider is need to pay or
they have some consequences are related,
to the different payments and they need to
expansions of the different subscriptions,
then we have an error budget.
But before moving to the error budget,
we need to understand that there is a
misconception in the overall SRE one.
So the misconception is that we
always look for the a hundred
percent of the system reliability.
But not, this is not true.
If you look for the a hundred percent
of system reliability, it means that
our system is available a hundred
percent and every time it should be up.
But that, that can't be a case, of
course in the practically your system.
Sometimes it would be down and some
kind of a disruption can be happen.
And it also affect the overall
product lifecycle because if we.
Go for the a hundred
percent of availability.
Then of course developers need to focus
on the reliability of the systems.
They can't focus on the
feature development.
They can't focus on the innovation side.
So that's why like the development teams
operation teams and the product teams
they look to and to have the common.
Target level that need to be
set for the overall the system.
So that's why error budget
comes into the picture.
Error budget is the it is just
unavailability of that of the particular
system that the teams can be tolerated.
Basically, so how much time that our
system could be unavailable and which
is fine for the overall, the life cycle.
That's why.
So when you have an advocate have
educate error budget, so it means you can
focus on the product development part,
but your error budget is threatened.
It means that you need to focus.
On the SRE part of the
reliability of that system.
Then the caution is how we can
basically practice this principle,
implement this principle.
So we have a different kind of practices.
With the metrics monitoring alerts,
so of course if we look for the system
reliability, so we have a proper defining
of the monitoring systems, we need to be,
have correct metrics for the services.
We need to be set the alerts for
the error budget, so if the error
budget is threatened, so we can
have that alerts and we can focus
on the system reliability part.
Then the demand forecasting
and capacity planning.
So we we, this is one.
A key practice where we have enough
resources available for the system
reliability part if something
happens so that the resources can
focus on the improvement sites can
also focus on the reliability part.
This is, one of the key practice.
Then we have a change management and the
emergency response where the each teams,
like the development teams, operation
teams can should know about the overall
process defined for the change management.
Like how if the change, if the, even
though change is small basically, so they
should focus on like how we can basically.
Overall do the changes and
it'll improve the overall
reliability of the applications.
Then the emergency response, that
of course, in the practically if
you, you have a system sometimes
that the system would be down.
So you need to be like ready with
what kind of emergency comes.
So you.
You need to be focused and you
need to be to work on that.
How early just you can like
back your system up and running.
And then of course the culture and
to management is one of the one of
also the key practice where it is
operational workloads that how you manage.
So in SREs of course there are.
Each and everything.
You can't automate.
So there are such kind of a manual
practices that you need to be
followed and accordingly, you
need to be manage that overall of
your operational workloads part.
These are the.
Some kind of a basic
understanding of an SRE one.
Now, let's move to the what are
the challenges that you faced
of as o for the complex system?
So here, the complex system means it,
it could be your microservices base,
it could be your distributed system.
So let understanding the
problem, what is a problem.
So sometimes what happens when
we, like to define an SLOs
for the complex environment.
We SLOs are not aligned
with the business goal.
It means that the
priorities are misalignment.
Like we, we focus the SLOs on the focus
on the different metrics, but our business
goals needed a different kind of metrics.
So this is the.
One thing and the target
level is also changed.
This is the one challenge we face
with the system as well as we mostly
don't look focus on the data driven
approach because if we define the
SLOs we also need to be, ensure that
what are the previous, checks for the
data and accordingly we can measure it
and define the SLOs for the systems.
And sometimes we, our, the SLOs
have we just set unrealistic SLOs.
And the other KPIs are
the completely different.
And so we need to be, understand the
system first and accordingly we can set
the realistic approach for that systems.
Then of course the distributed
systems and interdependencies.
If we have a distributed systems,
multiple microservices and APIs
and one microservices dependent
on the other service, and they
have some other interdependencies.
It is it is really difficult
to find out the pinpoint of
where the SLOs is violated.
So this is the also one of the challenge
we faced in this kind of environments.
And we don't look on
the priority components.
It means that according to the
system, we need to be define
it, what exactly user is doing.
So we need to be look for
the, their user journey.
And accordingly we need to be
center priorities of the system.
And then we can define an SLOs as well.
And, of course the tool limitations
is there, whatever the tools we have.
So we have the limited capabilities
with respect to that tool.
So that is also one challenge.
And at the end, of course, the
dynamic and evolving systems.
We work in the agile environment
our system is also upscales.
We are also upgrades and we work
on the continuous deployment.
So we always have the
new features comes in.
So accordingly, we need to be again,
set the SLOs as per the changes.
So these are some kind
of a c cha challenges.
So what should be our approach
to solve this kind of issue?
So first is we need to be
understand the system correctly.
Like what, what is particular system, what
are the different services in the system?
What is the.
User is doing like in
your day to day activity.
So the critical user journeys also
need to be understand of that.
Then we can go with the designing
part how we can define design and SLOs
of that part of critical services.
And then we can set metrics.
For that.
And then at the end, of course,
how we can use it effectively.
That, that is the one approach that
accordingly we can move it and we can try
to solve this complex issues for that.
But.
The question is what would be our
actual solution for this issue?
The solution is the service
level objective management.
SLO management it's cover, it's
a lifecycle that we need to be
defined within our organization.
So it involves basically to
define the OS by aligning the.
User journey with the business objectives,
whatever the business goals we have.
So accordingly, we need to be,
define the user journey first.
Then set a realistic target for the KPI
like the uptime, latencies and error rate.
So that is the one of the key
practice that we need to be do.
Then we have a a different like
SLOs, like the composite SLOs.
So composite SLOs is basically
a combination of individual
SLOs that we define it.
So if we look to measure the liability
of a complete system, so we need a
holistic view of that particular system.
Composite Aslu comes into the
picture in that case where.
We have individual SLOs
for the different services.
And basically aggregation of
that services that SLOs is is
made to create a composite SLOs.
And at the end the correct measuring
and the monitoring of system is
needed where we are defined the
correct alerts for the budgets.
And the monitoring of the complete system.
So what benefits we can get of
course the overall system liabilities
and performance would be improved.
We have a less downtime.
We have a less incidents.
We have a less priority issues on that.
If we focus on the data driven that.
That we have already discussed before.
So the data driven decision making is
one of the key factors to prioritize
improvement because if you look for
the previous data to understand the
system better on that one and then.
Cost to the proactive
monitoring of the systems.
So it'll also reduce the meantime
recovery of the system as well.
And communications and
collaborations within a team as well.
It'll also help to share the understanding
for the overall reliability process.
Then we have a customer
satisfaction of course.
Why overall by defining this
practices and process, and we focus
on the innovation part on that.
Now, let's see understand
the use case of that.
This is a simple like the product
lifecycle of a user journey.
Yeah, the user is to go into
the shopping app and they just
put some product into the cart.
And do the payment.
And after that overall the backend
process comes, whereas the warehouse
that received it and dispatched orders
then invoicing happens and the user
get the confirmation via the mail.
So overall, this journey,
let's break into the two parts.
So first is the pre-purchase,
and second is the post-purchase.
So in the so in the pre-purchase the.
The first, we understand that the
user part is that that the put the
products overall, the per repurchase
system should be available.
And user has just purchased the product.
So the availability of the overall,
the pre-purchase system is needed, and
of course the payment of the system.
And then the secondary
part is a post-purchase.
So the availability is the more
important than the latency.
This is the one thing.
Of the system and the services are in
the pre-purchase order are the more
important than the post-purchase start.
So in the po, in the pre-purchase website,
availability is a slightly more than
the payment availability, of course.
Because the, if the website is not
available, so user can't go and
purchase the part, and then the
payment part availability is needed.
So accordingly from this user journey,
so this, we need to be defined it
which are the critical components,
which are the critical services.
And which are the services.
And accordingly, we need to be to find
the matters metrics for that services.
And then at the end, pulling
the post purchase, of course,
the warehouse and the invoicing.
Slightly more important than the emailing.
If you will get the email after sometimes,
then of course that, that would be fine.
But your order should be dispatched
and you will have the invoicing is
also we should be created then after
sometimes the, if you get an email.
That is fine.
So the thing is like that, how
we can measure the reliability
of this complete user journey.
First is identify the services.
And their dependent components.
So from according to this user journey.
So we have a store website,
we have a payment, invoices,
emailing and warehousing.
So these are a services
that we have identified it.
Then we will set up the
individual SLOs for each service.
With respect to the different metrics
like the availabilities and latency.
And based on the understanding, we
will define the composite SLO part,
like the pre-purchase user experience
and the post-purchase user experience.
And at the end we will
look for the composite slo.
As I said, composite SLOs are the
aggregations would be about to.
So we have, the pre-purchase user journeys
and post-purchase user journeys and
aggregation would help to make the to
understand the overall system reliability.
This is the simple use case of of
the overall reliability process.
Then we have the SLO management
products who can help you to define it.
The SLO management lifecycle.
It also help you to give
you the good features.
It would also give you the
features like the composite os that
also give you the user journey.
In this overall product.
The HA and Nobel nine are the, I will
say, the leaders in that because they have
the such kind of different, features were
like the composite solo part, like the
user journey part, even in the harness.
It is a complete 360 degree platform.
It also give you the specific
feature for the service reliability
management in which we can analyze it.
We can easily gather to know how, why the,
our system is getting failed and it also
help you to to set up the governance with
the open policy agents where the noble
line is also help you to keep the three
years of old data so you can have the
previous data to understand your system
and accordingly you can make a decision.
It has a good composite feature
part and it also have to define
the user critical journey.
Then we have some other tools like the
fire head end Scott Car, ServiceNow,
new Relic, which is just, fit it
under the monitoring part incident
management part, but it is not a
specific SLO management product.
These are some products
well in the market.
And now there are, like, I have done
some the comparison on the basis of
the different capabilities like the
real time error budgeting tricks and
map SLOs to business capabilities.
And RCA.
And of course, the customized
dashboards and reports help you.
And of course the automation part auditing
parts and the overall, the customized
visas with respect to the business.
You can see they have some
tools, have some capabilities.
Some are good in the specific.
Features, some are like fit
under the complete category.
So the harness is mostly the noble
line is there, so accordingly you can
choose it, whatever the requirement.
And you can just use the overall
features of that products.
This is for this session.
So thank you very much
for joining this session.
Thank you everyone.