Hi this is Cypress, the Moala.
I'm working as a enterprise architect in
Focus INC. Today I'm going to talk about
site reliability at scale, architecting,
resilient, multi-cloud infrastructure,
multi-cloud reality.
I'm going to talk about strategic
advantage, technical resiliency.
Cost optimization coming to the static
advantage, eliminating single point of
failure is one of the most effective
way to build a resilient, capable,
and reliable cloud infrastructure by
embarrassing diversified cloud partnership
and vendor agnostic architecture.
Business can ensure continuity, reduce
risk, and achieve a greater flexibility.
This strategy is crucial in maintaining
business operations even when certain
cloud services, expensive outage or
issues coming to the technical resilience.
Technical resilience refers to your system
ability to maintain high availability,
reliability, and performance, even in the
face of failures or unexpected disruptions
in the context of cloud environments.
This means design your infrastructure,
so it can withstand yet quickly
recover from any issues minimizing
downtime and services disruption.
In multi-cloud environment,
workloads are distributed across
more than one cloud provider,
enabling you to benefit from each.
Providers strength and
mitigate potential risk.
Coming to the cost optimization in
today com, tive Cloud landscape,
optimizing the cost is a crucial
part of any cloud strategy.
Each cloud provider has its unique pricing
structure, services, and strengths.
By strategically leveraging these
differences, business can maximize
the performance to cost ratio
and ensure the best value for
their cloud infrastructure spend.
For example, one, provide provider
may offer more cost effective
storage while another may be.
Better suited for compute heavy workloads,
allowing business to allocate resources
in a way that minimize expenses.
Cloud native architecture, evolution,
monolithic apps, microservices,
containerization,
Kubernetes orchestration.
Monolithic apps.
Monolithic apps
have been the traditional approach
for building software system for many
years in monolithic architecture,
all components of application such
as user interface, database, business
logic, and data access layers.
Are tightly coupled and
reside in a single core base.
While this approach has its
advantages, it also comes with
significant limitations, especially
as a application grow in size and
complexity, coming to the microservices,
decoupled, independently deployable
services that communicate through.
Well-defined APIs.
This architecture enables targeted
scaling, improved resilience, and faster
delivery of individual components.
Containerization, isolated, lightweight
and portable runtime environment
that package applications with.
Their dependencies, ensuring
consistency across development and
testing and production environments.
Coming to the Kubernetes orchestration,
a production grade platform for automatic
deployment, scaling and management
of contention applications it use.
Declarative configurations and
built in fall to tolerance to ensure
high availability and resiliency.
AI powered incident management,
MTTR reduction, 68%.
Operational cost to savings, 47%.
Incident response acceleration, 3.2 x.
So coming to the MTTR reduction, 68%
AI powered diagnostic engine utilize
advanced algorithms to analyze vast
amount of data in real time quickly
identifying the root cause of incidents.
These systems can automate process
of isolating and diagnosing issues.
Eliminating the need of manual
intervention and reducing the take
it taken to resolve an incident.
This precision leads to substantial
reduction in meantime to resolve
by ensuring teams focus on the
most accurate diagnostics first.
Rather than wasting time on
trial and error approaches,
operational cost reduction, 47%.
AI driven predictive models use
historical data, mission learning
algorithms and pattern recognition to
detect anom analyze before they evolve
into major issues By identifying.
Our potential systems failures early
AI can trigger preventive actions
such as automated adjustments,
resource scaling, or alert IT teams.
This not only reduce the need for costly.
Emergency fixes, but also lower
downtime and the resources spent
on reactive maintenance, driving
operational cost reductions, independent
response acceleration, that two
point x neural network optimizer,
trial prioritization and routing.
By using rural networks,
AI can intelligently.
Access incoming incidents and determine
their severity, urgency, and impact
based on historical incidents, data
system performance, and contextual clues.
This optimized triage system
ensure that critical incidents
are routed to appropriate teams.
Faster and with higher precision.
Instead of wasting time on manual
prioritization, the AI system
speed up decision making, reducing
incident response times by therefore,
overall impact the integration of
AI into incident management is.
Clearly a game changer, reducing MTTR,
lowering operational cost, and spending
up response by leveraging precision.
Diagnostics, predictive analytics
and neural network optimization
organizations cannot only solve
problems faster, but also prevent them
from occurring in the first place.
Edge computing and 5G revolution,
edge computing, distributed
processing and reduced latency,
complex reliability models.
5G integration, distributed processing.
Computing resources strategically
positioned at Network Edge two.
Latency reduce bandwidth consumption,
and enable real time data
processing closer to the source.
Reduce latency, ultra responsive
sub millisecond performance,
enabling crucial operations where.
Time timing is paramount from
autonomous vehicles to industrial
automation and tele mite applications,
complex reality models, sophisticated
resilience frameworks, incorporating
operating echo, geo distributed
redundancy, productive maintenance,
and intelligent traffic routing.
To ensure continuous operations despite
node network or regional failures.
5G integration revolution,
revolutionary connectivity,
delivering up to 20 gigabytes
throughput with 99.99% reliability.
Creating new possibilities for
argumented reality 4K and eight K
video streaming and Ivo T devices.
Portal federation.
Distributed observability challenges,
comprehensive metric collect collection,
scalable log management, cross servicing,
tracing, intelligent anomaly detection.
Comprehensive metric Cion, implementing
uniform telemetry protocols across
heterogeneous infrastructure components.
Scalable log management, orchestrating
real time aggregation from thousands
of distributed edge points.
Cross servicing, tracing,
maintaining request context.
Propagation through complex multi-cloud
service meshes intelligent anomaly
detection, leveraging mission
learning algorithms to identify SubT
performance deviations before cascade
security, reliability, integration.
There are two approaches.
Traditional approach, integrated DevSecOps
coming to the traditional approach,
security teams operate in isolated
silos, detached from core operations.
Fragmented monitoring creates
critical visibility gaps between
security and reliability.
Conflicting security and performance
objectives, force unnecessary trade-offs,
complex approval workflows and testing
cycles, delay, vulnerability remediation.
Coming to the integrated dev SecOps,
automated security control embedded
directly through infrastructure as a code.
Unified tool chains provide seamless
visibility across all operation domains.
Continuous security validation
through automated compliance checks
in CICD pipelines, shared metric,
cross-functional accountability drive,
collaborative incident responses.
Breach impact analysis.
Security breaches carry significant
financial consequence that extend
for beyond immediate losses.
Our analysis reveals that comprehensive
cost to breakdown across key impact areas,
demonstrating how indirect cost often
out outweigh direct financial damages.
Recovery operations, legal penalties,
customer compensation, brand damage.
As illustrated brand damage
represents the most significant
financial impact at milli dollars.
8000008.3 millions AC accounting
for over 35% of total breach costs.
Legal potential follow at $12.4 million.
Highlighting the growing regulatory
consequences of security failures.
Organization must implement proactive
security, reliability, integration to
mitigate these substantial financial
risks, balancing innovation and.
Stability.
Gradual feature rollouts, cement
systematic deployments strategy
with intelligent automated rollback
mechanism to mitigate risks,
experimentation, frameworks,
regressively.
Controlled A and B testing in
production environments to validate
changes with the real world data.
So before moving to the
production data needs to test
done, test and dev environment.
Once the testing is done and everything
is looks good, then move to the
production reliability guard trails.
Implementing robust service level
objectives as crucial quality
gates for deployment authorization
infrastructure as a code.
Fully versioned.
Systematically testable infrastructure
definitions enable consistent repeatable
environments implementation framework.
He access current state,
define service level.
Object to build.
Observability platform, automate
remediation, practice, chose engineering.
He access current state, conduct
comprehensive infrastructure
audit, and identify critical
reliability vulnerabilities across
your multi-cloud environment.
Define service level objectives.
Establish quantifiable reliability
metrics aligned with business outcomes
and customer experience requirements.
Build observability platform,
deploy unified monitoring solution
with cross cloud visibility and.
Contextual alerting capabilities, automate
remediation, implement self-healing
infrastructure with ML driven prediction
and autonomous recovery workflows.
Practice shows engineering
systematically introduce.
Controlled failures to validate
resilience, mechanism and
uncover hidden dependencies.
Key takeaways, multi-cloud
standardization, AI driven incident
response, edge computing, architecture,
security, reliability, integration.
So multi-cloud standardization, implement
consistently observability frameworks
and shared metric across cloud providers
while maintaining, provide specific
optimization, AI driven incident response.
Deploy ML powered prediction
models with autonomous recovery
workforce to reduce MTTR by.
To by up to 70% edge computing
architecture, extend reliability practices
to accommodate 5G enabled edge deployments
with distributed observability solutions.
Security, reliability integration
establish cross-functional accountability
to mitigate financial impacts exceeding.
$30 million from brand damage and
regulatory penalties, and thank you.
Thank you.
This opportunity.