Speaker 12: Welcome everyone.
Today at Con 42 Cyber Liberty Engineering.
I'm presenting on building
reliable AI driven mobile platforms
for healthcare and commerce.
I am Dihi from Northeastern
Hill University, currently
working at Walmart Global Tech.
This presentations draws.
Experiences from real world experience
building platforms that serve
two incredibly demanding domains
simultaneously, the intersection
of healthcare and commerce presents
unique challenges that require careful
architectural conservations and
robust reli engineering practices.
This presentation will ectomy
take around 17 to 20 minutes.
And I will walk you through the unique
challenges we face, the architectural
patterns we have implemented,
and the key lessons learned from
operating the systems in production.
We'll cover everything from regulatory
compliance requirements like HIPAA
and GDPR to AI driven personalization,
observability at scale, and how
real liberty directs impact clinical
outcomes in healthcare applications.
Let's begin by understanding the
fundamental challenge we are addressing.
What is a challenge?
We are building a platform that
serves two different elements, each
with their own critical requirements.
On the healthcare side, we
have HIPAA compliant data
handling, which isn't optional.
It's a legal requirement.
We are managing prescription life
cycles, which means tracking medications
from prescriptions to delivery,
ensuring patients never miss a dose.
The consequences of failure
here can be life threatening.
We also need to integrate with
insurance systems and pharmacies
each with their own API data formats,
and reliability characteristics.
On the commerce side, we have
different but equally demanding
requirements around performance,
user experience, and scalability.
The key challenge here is building
one platform that can reliably
serve both domains without
comp compromising on either
on narrative today, follows a clear
arc. We'll start with the problem space,
discuss the real reality challenges.
Inherent in multiple domain platforms.
Then we'll dive into architectural
foundations we have built to address
these challenges, which are the
patterns, the principles and practices
that makes reliability possible.
Finally, we look at the outcome,
both quantitative metrics and
quality of improvements in how
the systems operate in production.
This structure will help us
understand not just what we build.
But why we built it this way and what
we have learned along the journey.
Let's talk about the
architectural foundations.
The cornerstone of our approach is
resilient microservices, architecture.
We have organized services by
domain scope, pharmacy services
as separate from retail services.
We just separate from
user management services.
This domain scoping allows for
independent deployment cycles.
We can update pharmacy features without
touching reli retail functionality.
But more importantly, we have implemented
circuit breakers and bulkhead patterns.
Circuit breakers prevent
cascading failures.
If the pharmacy a P is down, it
doesn't bring down the entire platform.
Bulkhead patterns, isolate resources.
Surge individual traffic doesn't stop
pharmacy services of compute resources.
These patterns aren't theoretical.
We have seen them prevent outages
in production, and I'll explain more
use cases where it's being used.
When a downstream pharmacy
integration had an outage, our SAR
case breakers activated, and the
rest of the platform just continued
serving users normally, for example.
During a major pharmacy, API outage last
year, our circuit breakers detected the
failure within seconds and automatically
routed traffic to fallback systems.
The rest of the platform just
continued to operate it normally,
and users could still access retail
features without interruption.
Now, the regulatory compliance is
often treated as a checkbox exercise,
but we treat it as a first class
architectural requirement from day one.
Very important.
HIPAA and GDPR aren't just enough
encryption, though that's critical.
They're about designing systems where
protected health information and
personal data are handled correctly by
default, not just as an afterthought.
Our APIs are designed with encryption
in transit using TLS and encryption
address using database level encryption.
But equally important is
role-based access control.
Not everyone who has access to the
system should be able to access
protected health information, and we
maintain auditable access logs for
every interaction with sensitive data.
These logs aren't just for compliance
audits, they're critical for
security, incident response and
understanding system behavior.
This architectural approach
means compliance isn't
something we build on later.
It's built into every layer of the system.
For instance, when we designed
our prescription API, we built
encryption access controls, and audit
logging into the initial design.
This prevented us from having to
retrofit compliance features later,
which would've been very much
more expensive than error proof.
Now let's talk about AI
driven personalization.
This is where things get
interesting from an SRE perspective.
Our predictive refill models use
machine lang language learning to
anticipate when patient patients
will need prescription refills.
The models analyze field history.
When did they last fill his prescription?
They look at adherence signals.
Are they taking medications consistently?
And they consider supply chain EV
chain avail, which can actually
fulfill the refill when needed.
The system then triggers proactive
reminders before gaps occur.
This is critical because missed dose can
have serious health tions for the users.
From an architecture perspective,
this means we are running
ML inference in production.
At scale with real time requirements,
we need to monitor, model performance,
handle model drift, and ensure
the system gracefully degrades.
The ML service is vailable.
This isn't just about accuracy,
it's about reliability.
A model in theory, that 90 per is 90%,
99% accurate, but fails 1% of the time.
It is less reliable than a simpler
model that work consistently.
In practice, we have seen our predictive
refill models reduce missed doses by 40%
compared to fixed interval reminders,
but we also have fallback mechanism.
If the ML service is unavailable,
we fall back to rule-based reminders
based on prescription fill days.
Observability is CR crucial for any
production system that's granted, but
it's specially critical when EIC involved.
We need to observe model inference
latency per request path is a
pharmacy refill prediction slower
than the product recommendation.
This helps us identify bottlenecks.
We monitor feature drift.
The input feature to our models changing
in ways that could affect predictions,
and we track prediction confidence
scores, low confidence might indicate we
should fall back to simpler heuristics.
We track fallback
activation rates by service.
How often are we falling back from
ML predictions to rule-based systems?
This tells us about model reliability.
For healthcare, we monitor PHI
access patterns and anomalies.
PHI is personal health information.
Unexpected access patterns could indicate
a security issue or a bug, and we also
track down integration error rates.
If pharmacy a PS, for example, is
fading, we need to know immediately.
This observability is
in just for debugging.
It's how we understand system health
and make informed dec decisions
about reliability improvements.
For example, we noticed that
prescription review predictions were
taking longer during peak hours.
The observability, we dis, we discovered
that feature competition was the
bottleneck, not the ML inference itself.
We optimized the feature pipeline
and reduced latency by 60%.
Self failing systems are the goal, but
they start with detection and isolation.
When you detect an anomaly, maybe
prescription ripple predictions are taking
too long, or error rates are spiking.
We need to isolate the fall quickly.
This might mean routing traffic away from
a failing service instance or switching
from AML predictions to rule-based fall
fallbacks or activating circuit break
breakers to prevent cascading failures.
The key is that detection and
isolation happen a automat.
Without human intervention.
By the time an on-call engineer
is notified, the system should
already be taking corrective action.
This request careful design of monitoring,
alerting, and automated response systems.
We can automate everything, but we
can automate the common failures
more so we have seen in production.
Here is a real example.
When one of our pharmacy integration
partners had an A PA outage, our system
detected the increased error rates within
30 seconds, activated the circuit breakers
and switched to a backup pharmacy partner.
Users experienced no interruption and
the on-call engineer was notified but
didn't need to take any manual action.
Very important.
Accessibility and localization
might not seem reality.
Concerns, but they are absolutely are.
A DA compliant design screen reader.
Support sufficient color contrast,
proper touch target sizing.
These things ensures consistent service
quality for users with disabilities.
When these are and implemented
correctly, users can complete
task leading to support,
escalation and reduce reliability.
Localization goes beyond translation.
It's about ensuring the system works
correctly for users in different regions
with different languages, currencies,
and reg regulatory requirements.
A system that works perfectly
in one region but fails
in another isn't reliable.
We have seen cases where data format
differences, cost prescription
reminders to be sent on the wrong day.
There's a reliability issue with
health, real health consequence.
This concerns needs to be built
into the architecture from
the start and not added later.
For instance, we discovered that our
prescription reminder system was sending
reminders on the wrong day for users
in using in a different date format,
instead of unexpected date format.
This was a reliable issue that
could have led to missed doses.
We fixed it by standardizing ISO 8 6
0 1 date format throughout the system.
Prescription adherence is
where real liberty Engineering
meets clinical outcomes.
This isn't just about uptime or error
rates, it's about whether patients
are taking medications correctly,
which directly impacts their health.
Every missed notification, a
reminder that doesn't arrive.
It's a potential patient risk event.
Every failed refill trigger when the
system doesn't recognize a patient needs
a refill, can lead to treatment gaps.
Every synchronization error between
pharmacy systems and our mobile platform
can cause confusion and missed doses.
We measure prescription
entering as a reliable metric
if a system is 99.9% reliable.
But that 0.1% failure rate results in
missed doses, which we need to improve.
This is a powerful example
of how SRV principles apply
beyond traditional IT metrics.
Liberty here has real world
consequences for patient health.
We take prescription adherence
rates as a key reliability metric.
Our target is 90% 5% adherence,
meaning 95% of patients take
their medications as prescribed.
We have found that systems reli
directly correlates with adherence
when remainders reminders fail
or refills aren't triggered.
Adherence drops,
er powered commerce presence,
different but equally challenging
reliability requirements.
AI try-on experience or vision
and eyewear products requires
frame accurate rendering.
Users need to see exactly how
glasses look on their face in real
time with tight latency budgets.
This demands edge optimize inference.
We can't run air RA rendering
in the central data center
and expect acceptable latency.
We need edge computing with ML
models running closer to users.
Asset delivery needs to be efficient.
3D models, textures and other
assets need to load quickly without
consuming excessive bandwidth,
and we need graceful degradation.
If AR isn't available due to device
limitation on network conditions,
these should still be able to
browse and purchase products.
This is another example of how reliability
requirements vary by domain in use case.
Requiring careful
architectural considerations.
We have implemented edge computing for
air rendering, reducing latency from 200
milliseconds to hundred 50 milliseconds,
but we also have fallback modes.
If air isn't available, users can still
view products in 2D and make purchases.
This ensures even when advanced
features aren't available.
Let me share some implement
implementation patterns.
What we have learned from operating
the systems in production, the This
slides highlights four critical
patterns that have proven as essential.
The first pattern talks about decoupling
health and commerce data planes.
The shared infrastructure is cost.
Personal health information and
transactional data must traverse
separate encrypted pipelines
with independent audit controls.
Mixing them creates compliance
exposure and complicates
incident in investigations.
What it means, it practices.
We have separate database clusters
for healthcare data and commerce data.
Even though they might run on the
same cloud infrastructure, they're
logically and physically separated.
Our pharmacists APIs use one
set of encrypted pipelines
wherever retail APIs use another.
Each has its own logging and audit system.
This separation becomes
critical during an incidents.
One of the incident that happened last
year when we had a data access issue,
we could immediately determine it was
isolated to the commerce data plan
and not healthcare, which saved us
significant compliance investigation time.
You can clearly understand without
the Z coupling, we would have
had to audit both systems, which
would've taken days instead of hours.
The second pattern.
It's like building fallback
parts before you need them.
Define and test degraded mode behavior
for every AI driven feature before launch.
A feature that fails closed returning,
nothing is more damaging than one
that returns a rule-based default.
We learn this the hard way early
in our ML model deployment.
When our prescription refill prediction
model fail, the system returned nothing.
No reminders at all.
This was worse than sending a
reminder based on a simple rule.
Now, every AI driven feature
has a fallback path, clearly
defined and tested before launch.
For example, our AI try-on feature
for IUR history, fallbacks levels
first, which is fully air ending.
If that fails, 2D image, if that
fails, standard product image.
We test these fallbacks regularly Through
Chaos engineering, we intentionally
break the air service and verify that
users can still complete purchases.
This pattern has prevented
multiple potential outages.
The third pattern is instrument
outcome and not just operations.
SLI is tied to business
and clinical outcomes.
Refill completion rate, offer
engagement, accessory task as essay.
This all gives engineering team
early D warnings before operational
metrics breach thresholds.
Traditional operation metric like CPU
usage and API latency are important,
but they don't tell the whole story.
We found that business and clinical
outcomes metrics are leading indicators.
For example, if prescription refill
completion rates starts dropping,
then often a sign of a problem
before you see it in API rates, we
track refill completion rate as a
primary SLI, if it draws below 95%.
We investigate immediately, even if
all operational metrics look healthy.
Similarly, we track accessibility tasks.
Success rate.
If users with screen readers can complete
tasks, that's a reliability issue.
Even if the a p is responding
quickly, this outcome based SLIs
have a help us to catch issues 30
to 60 minutes earlier than we would
have with operational metrics alone.
The fourth pattern is treating
localization as a deployment pipeline.
Localized content must pass through the
same validation as staging gates as code.
Incorrect prescription instruction in
any language are a patient safety issue.
It's just not a translation book.
We treat localization as code.
All translated content goes through
code review, automated STA testing
and staging environments before
it, making it to production.
We have automated stats that
verify prescription instructions
are correct in all languages.
We learned this lesson when a translation
error in Spanish prescription instructions
could have led to incorrect medication
timing Now, prescription content is
validated by both automated systems and
native speakers review before deployment.
This pipeline approach means
location issues are caught in
staging, not in production,
preventing patient safety risk.
All these four patterns that
we have discussed are essential
to our platform's reliability.
They're just not theoretical.
They are better tested practices from
operating the systems and productions.
Now, let me summarize the key
takeaway from this presentation.
These slides highlight six critical
principles for building reliable AI
driven platforms in healthcare and common.
Point one is compliance is
architecture not an audit.
The compliance isn't something you
add later or verify through audits.
It must be built into the
architecture from day one.
HIPAA and GDP are requirements are
in check boxes to take up the launch.
Their architectural constraints
that shape every design decision.
In practice.
This means our APIs are designed with
encryption access controls, and audit
logging built in from the start.
We don't retrofit
compliance, we design for it.
For example, our prescription API
increase PHI at the fill level before
storage, which again implements role based
access at the API gateway and maintains
immutable audit locks for every access.
This architectural approach
means compliance Audits are
straightforward because the evidence
is already there in the system.
Design, not something
we have to reconstruct.
When we designed our pharmacy integration,
we built HIPAA compliance into the
architecture, separate encrypted
pipelines, field level encryption,
and comprehensive body trail.
This wasn't added later.
It was the foundation of the design.
As a result, when auditors review
our system, they're reviewing
the architecture itself, not
separate compliance documentation.
The second point is about graceful
degradation, which is a feature.
Graceful de degra degradation
isn't a fallback mechanism.
It's a first class feature that
must be designed and tested.
A system that fails completely
is less reliable than one
that decrease gracefully.
We design every AI driven feature
with multiple fallback levels.
For example, our prescription
instruction prediction has three
tires, ML based predictions, rule-based
fallbacks using pres prescription
history, and fixed interval remainder.
As a last result, our AI tryon feature
degrade from full air rendering
to 2D overall to standard product.
We learned these lessons very
early when our ML model failed.
The system written nothing,
which is over worse.
A simple rule-based prediction now.
Now, graceful degradation is a
requirement for every VI loss.
We test degraded modes regularly
through Kio Chaos Engineering.
We intentionally break services and
verify that user can still complete their
tasks just with reduced functionality.
The third point is AI needs
outcome observability.
Traditional operational metrics
aren't enough for AI systems.
We need to observe outcomes, not
just operations model accuracy,
inference latency and error
rates matter, but business and
clinical outcomes matter more.
We track prescription refill completion
rate as a primary SLI if it drops.
That's often a leading
indicator of problems.
We see them in API metrics.
We monitor offer engagement
rates for commerce features.
If personalized recommendations
are in being click.
This tells us something more
about model performance.
That error rates don't.
For our prescription adherence
models, we track clinical outcomes.
Are patients actually taking medicine?
The outcome metrics has helped touch
catch model drift 30 to 60 minutes earlier
than operational metrics would have.
We also track prediction confidence
codes, low confidence triggers fall back
automatically preventing poor prescription
models, predictions from reaching users.
The fourth point is about
accessibility failures.
Which are SL breaches.
Activity isn't just an optional,
it's a reliability requirement.
Again, when users with disabilities
can't complete tasks, that's a
service failure, and it's not
just not a nice to have feature.
We treat exhibit failures with the
same sever severity as API outages.
If screen readers can navigate
our prescription reminder
interface, that's an L Bridge.
If touch targets are too small
for users, it's motor impairments.
That's a level issue.
We track Acceler tasks,
success rates, s sli.
If this drop, we investigate immediately.
We have seen cases where best
caption and reminders aren't
accessible to screen reader users,
which means those users couldn't
manage a prescription effectively.
This just wasn't a translation
bug or a minor issue.
It was a patient safety concern.
Now, exhibitive testing is part
of a deployment pipeline, and
exhibitive failure triggers the same
incident response as API outage.
Point number five, fault isolations,
which protect flows, clinic and
commercial data flows must be ISO
isolated to prevent faults in one
domain from affecting the other.
This isolation isn't just logical,
it's physical with separate pipelines,
databases, and audit controls.
We have separate encrypted pipelines
for healthcare and commerce data.
Even though they might share
the same infrastructure,
they're completely isolate.
When a Commerce API has an outage,
it doesn't affect pharmacy services.
When a pharmacy system needs
maintenance, retail features
continue operating these isolations
becomes critical during incidents.
The point number six is data integrity,
which is personalization and safety.
Now data integrity serves true
critical purpose, enabling
effective personalization, and
ensuring per patient safety.
We can't have one without the other.
Personalization requires accurate data
and safety requires real level data For
personalization, data integrity means
our ML models receive e rate timely data.
If prescription fills history, if
prescription refill history is incorrect,
our refill prescriptions will be wrong.
If user preferences are corrupted,
recommendation will be poor.
We validate data at multiple points
at ingestion during processing, and
before model inference for safety
data integrity means prescription
in instructions are correct.
Medication instructions
are accurately detected.
And refill triggers are
based on reliable data.
We have implemented data violation,
pipe validation pipelines that catch
integrity issues before they reach users.
For example, prescription instructions
are validated against medication
databases and any mismatches triggers
and alerts, and prevents incorrect
instructions from being sent to users.
These six principles that we discussed
from the foundation of reliable AI driven
platforms, they are just not theoretical.
They're battle tested practices from
operating the systems in productions.
I'd like to thank you all for watching
this presentation on building reliable AI
driven mobile platforms for healthcare.
Throughout this presentation, we
have explored how to build platforms
that serve two of the most demanding
domains, healthcare and commerce.
We have discussed the unique
challenges, the architectural
patterns we have implemented, and
the practical lessons learned from
operating these systems in production.
The key message I want to leave you with
this reliability is not a feature you add.
It is a property that
emerges from every design.
Decisions made across the intersystem
is a foundation on which clinical
impact and commercial performance
both depend a platforms that fast,
but Unreal doesn't serve patients.
A platforms that feature reach, but
unreal level doesn't serve cost.
Customers reliability isn't just optional.
It's essential.
If you're interested in diving deeper
into any of the topics we have covered
today, I'd be happy to continue
the conversations whether you have
questions about observative strategies,
how we track and monitor system L
or compliance API patterns, how we
design HIPAA compliant endpoints,
or AI fallback architecture, how we
ensure ML systems degrade gracefully.
I'm here to help.
We also have additional resources
available, including architecture
reference diagram that show how
these patterns fit together in
practice and further reading on
HIPAA compliant microservice design.
This resources can help you apply
this principle to your own system.
The journey to reliable
systems is ongoing.
Every incident teaches has something new.
Every deployment is an
opportunity to improve.
And every design decisions matters.
Thank you for your time today, and
I hope this presentation has given
you valuable insights into building
reliable AI driven platforms.
Let's continue building platforms
that aren't trust platforms that
serve users reliably, whether they're
patients managing their health
or customers making purchases.
Thank you.
Have a great day.