Speaker 23: Hello everyone.
Today I'm gonna talk about migration from
on-prem messaging systems to the cloud.
This is an introductory session
about messaging system migrations.
In this presentation, we're going to
discuss what a messaging system is,
the common pathways for migrating
an on-prem messaging system to the
cloud, the benefits of migration, why
you should consider going serverless
architecture, and the key factors or
questions you should discuss with the
team during the migration process.
Lastly, I'm also going to show you
some Python code to help you get
started interacting with the Rapid MQ
brokers as a client, and compare those
interactions with the Amazon SQS service.
So let's get started.
For messaging system, there
are usually two categories.
The first is what we call
traditional message orientated
middleware or message brokers.
Typical examples include
IBM mq, or Rev mq.
These are usually dedicated hardware
or infrastructure designed to connect
upstream and downstream services
through messaging transactions.
The other category is what we call cloud
native serverless messaging services.
For example, in Amazon Web services,
we have the Amazon SQS service and the
Amazon as a service, which helps with
queuing or broadcasting use cases.
Messaging systems, applications
are used across all industries.
The reason is that they allow you
to build loosely coupled, highly
scalable and fault tolerant systems.
Different industries use them in slightly
different ways for financial services.
Team use them for trades and transactions.
For retail, we usually see them using
other processing for healthcare.
They're used to retrieve
clinical data or patient records.
And for data, we use them for image or
video processing, just to name a few.
Some industries have slightly
different use cases and demand
for their messaging systems.
For example, in retail industry, you'll
usually see a higher demand during peak
hours, like during weekdays, but then a
lesser demand during midnight or weekends.
Because of this difference,
retail industry usually requires
much higher scalability in terms
of how the system is designed.
On the other hand, customers from
financial or government organizations
usually require their messaging
system to be durable and can
be recovered during incidents.
The good news is that all of these
can be migrated to the cloud, and
we see actual real world use cases
of those industries applying their
messaging systems to the cloud.
When starting a migration, you begin
with your own on-prem messaging systems.
When you maintain your own on-prem
messaging systems, you will soon
realize there are a few drawbacks.
The first is definitely the
expense you have to manage.
Usually you have capacity
and operational cost.
Those are burdens you have
to deal with from the start.
For example, if you want to scale up
or double the capacity, you need to
spend additional budget on provisioning
more infrastructure just to maintain
the same features of your system.
Additionally, you will need to allocate
specific engineers with specialized
skillset to set up, maintain, and
monitor those mon messaging systems.
This is a significant operational overhead
and it can be difficult to scale up.
Therefore, a lot of organizations
decide to migrate their
messaging system to the cloud.
There are a few different approaches.
The first is called lift and shift.
We essentially provision cloud instances
and try to mirror the same environment
you have on-prem to the cloud.
This is quite quick for migrations,
but there are some obvious drawbacks
that we're going to discuss next.
The next is another approach is
called replatforming, which is moving
the system to a managed platform.
For example, in AWS, we
have Amazon MQ service.
This provides additional benefits
compared to lift and shift approach,
and it's commonly seen with customers
who still want to use traditional
client broker interactions, but
want to reduce operational overhead.
Lastly, you have the cognitive
approach, which typically requires
you to refactor the client.
However, the benefit of doing that
is you will get a fully service
architecture that allows you to s
scale up easily without ever having
to worry about the need or demand of
your system throughput beforehand.
The scaling and maintaining of the service
itself, as the service name suggests, are
now owned by the cloud service provider.
For example, AWS.
As I discussed earlier, once you
migrate from on-prem to the cloud,
the responsibilities gradually shift
from yourself to the cloud service
provider for on-prem services.
When you own the entire messaging
application, you definitely own all
of the responsibilities from the
very low end of the physical layers.
For example, the storage, capacity
management, physical security,
all of that up to the application
and business level logic design.
Everything is managed by your own team.
Now, when you move to infrastructure
services like EC2, the physical
service and the provisioning of
the actual instances become the
responsibility of the cloud provider.
However, the team still have a
shared responsibility for security.
Physical security is managed by
AWS, but the team still have to
manage infrastructure level and
configuration level security, right?
So the team have to manage like OS
level configurations, low level broker,
engine maintenance and security patches.
All of that still have
to be done by the team.
So there are still some
operational overhead.
That is why we have managed services
beyond infrastructure service, where you
already using cloud instance cloud service
provider to manage the physical layers.
Managed service also handle low level
tasks like security and system patching.
This, leave the team with more
focus on capacity planning,
application and business level.
When the team decides to go full
serverless, let's say Amazon is QS or
SNS service, the only responsibility
now becomes the business logic itself.
Capacity and scaling are not fully
managed by the cloud service provider.
It will be transparent for the client
using the service, allowing the team to
focus the directly or entirely on the
business logic, confident that system
can scale up or down based on demand.
Serverless architecture has a few
benefit compared to traditional
infrastructure based messaging brokers.
First off, it allows you to
decouple the infrastructure concern
from the actual business logic.
Service architecture is serverless, so
you don't have to worry about scaling up.
Server scaling is managed by the call
service provider or the service itself
based on demand and usage patterns.
Pricing model are also
changed to be on demand base.
So for example, back to the retail
industry I mentioned earlier where
there might be not a lot of use
volumes during weekends or midnights.
The team don't have to worry about waste
resources because it will automatically
scale down during those slow use hours.
The team are only getting charged for
the API calls to make to a service
as compared to keeping up an entire
broker fleet running just to keep the
system operational during those times.
Surveys architecture also allows the
team to maintain high availability
and resiliency because the backend
infrastructure is maintained and
managed by the cloud service provider,
in this case, the SQS or SNS service.
Now let's talk about different
migration strategies.
The quickest way to
migrate is called rehost.
This is quite straightforward.
You deploy cloud instances and try
to mirror the entire system from
the OS level, the broker engine,
configurations all that too much.
Of your on-prem systems.
This means you don't usually have a lot
of changes needed on the application side,
and you have a lot of customization and
control when selecting the type of OS
broker engine or broker versions you want.
However, because essentially only
the physical layers are moving to the
cloud, a lot of the infrastructure
and operational overhead is
still retained within your team.
You have to manage the security
patching, broker monitoring,
and security configurations.
It'll also be a little bit difficult
to integrate with other services like
IM services or CloudWatch monitoring
to see if the broker is healthy or
operational or how many clients are
connected because those metrics are not
natively integrated with the EC2 service,
which is only an infrastructure service.
That's where a managed
platform comes into play.
For example, you can use Amazon Queue
as a managed broker hosting platform.
There are a lot of benefit to this.
To start, when you set up,
you'll only need to focus on a
few key areas of configuration.
You'll focus on the type of deployment
you want, whether it is a single node
deployment or a cluster deployment.
Then you will configure
the instance sites.
You will now need to configure the
OS version, memory, or CPU course.
All of that is now simplified
into instance sites, just
one single configuration.
You don't have to worry about inter
integrations with monitoring systems
because those are also natively
integrated and enabled by default.
When you want to scale up the
infrastructure in the future, let's say.
Demand grow in two or three times.
You can simply add the broker to a
higher instance size with just a few
clicks and a reboot, you'll have a much
larger instance capacity in comparison.
If you deploy the same broker
on EC2 instances, you have to
manage the configuration yourself.
You have to go into the web MQ
config file, reconfigure the
memory usage, and parameters.
Now all of that is not fully
managed by the Amazon MQ service.
That saves your team a lot of
operational overheads because
it is managed service security
already follows the best practices.
For example, it enforces TLS transactions
between the client and broker.
Allows you to set up a CAMS key to
encrypt your data at rest as well.
Security patching and broker
maintenance are also automatically
managed by the service.
The customer or your team can
select a weekly maintenance window,
allowing the MQ service to update and
maintain the broker during that time.
As a team, you can select a time
where is the broker is not heavily
used for example, midnight for retail
industries, allowing that service
to automatically patch up and reboot
the broker during the maintenance
window for optimal performance.
Now let's take a closer look to
the Amazon MQ servicing detail.
First, it supports the same protocol
you commonly see in web MQ brokers,
such as a mqp 0.9 0.1, and 1.0.
When you deploy the broker, it comes
by default with management plugins
that power the Web IQ Web console.
As far as the shovel and federation
plugins, as I discussed earlier,
you natively have integrations
with CloudWatch Matrix.
This allows you to see how many clients
are connected, how many connection
or channels are open, how much ramp
the broker is using, and how many
messages are there in the broker.
You can even see metrics at
destination level, like how many
message are there in each queue.
Additionally, you will have
data logs for the broker.
Those logs allow you to see warning or
error records for further troubleshooting
or monitoring, just in case.
Let's say a broker experience like
TRS connection issues with the
client or gets oral valve by traffic.
As discussed, there are two types
of broker deployments, single node
deployment, and cluster deployment.
Let's discuss both in detail.
For a single node deployment, you have one
instance deploy in one availability zone.
From an availability perspective, this is
not quite ready for production use cases.
For example, if there's a downtime in that
availability zone, it usually means that
you'll lose access to the broker entirely.
However, it is cheaper compared to a
cluster deployment broker, making it
ideal for profile, concept, or development
use cases, allowing you to set up
as a broker while saving some costs.
When you want to move into
production, we do recommend moving
into a cluster deployment mode.
In cluster deployment, messages are
mirrored across three different nodes
in three different availability zones.
So even if one of the availability
zones becomes inaccessible
or one of the node crashes.
Teams still have two other
availability nodes for clients
to connect to because the message
are miriad, no data will be lost.
This is a critical feature for production
and we do recommend organizations or teams
using at a production capacity to deploy
their broker in a cluster deployment mode.
Now let's take a look at how a Python
client interacts with Web MQ brokers.
The first thing you want to do is set
up the basic connection parameters.
You have to first define the connection
protocols and parameters like
encryption through TRS 1.2 version.
Next, you define the connection
endpoint for the broker.
Then you set up the connection and
the channel using the Packer library.
The channel is essentially just a
library connection used by the client
or process to interact with the
broker as a producer or consumer.
Once the connection is set up, you can
define your producers and consumers and.
For producers, you first need to declare
the destination Your message are going
to, you can declare a queue defined
by name and then send a message to it.
You can also send a message to an
exchange, but the default exchange
will simply draw the message to
the queue using a queue name.
So it's essentially the same as
sending the message directly to the.
Because this is a connection based
protocol, you must make sure to
close the connection once we finish
publishing or sending messages.
Otherwise, the connection will remain open
and voice resources on the broker side.
So that means you will see your broker
memory and CP utilization creeping up
gradually as a use a broker through time.
On the consumer side, you can use a get
message function and sify the name of the
queue you want to pull the message from.
Once you get a message, you have
to use basic act, acknowledging the
message so that the broker knows
it is received by the client and
can remove it from the broker side.
Without this acknowledgement,
the broker will eventually
consider the consumer application
inactive and close the connection.
So make sure.
To acknowledge the message
in your client code.
After acknowledging and present the
messages, always remember to close the
consumer channels and connection itself.
This ensures it's probably closed, freeing
up the resources for other connections.
To continue for more marginalized
services, or if you want to embrace a full
service approach, you must first refactor
your client and messaging systems.
During this refactor, the first
thing you consider is separate
the roles of the process.
You need to clearly separate the
producers from the consumers.
The reason for this is to decouple them
when deploying the cloud, allowing them
to scale independently and be updated
without dependencies with one other.
For example, if you have a background
in the queue and you want to drain the
queue, you can scale your consumers
without ramping up additional
producer connections, and that can
definitely be helpful in the long run.
You also want to understand
your method delivery models.
You need to determine whether you
need a point-to-point delivery,
or published success model.
The difference between
these two is simple.
When a message is sent to a destination,
do you want to be received only
once by a single consumer, or do you
want a forecast across all consumers
subscribe to that destination?
Essentially, it's about whether
the method is processed once
overall or once per consumer.
From a MQ broker prosthe, you can
handle both models within a single
infrastructure or a single broker.
For publish subscribe, you can use
topics or exchanges depending on
whether you use active MQ or Web mq.
Engine MQ Brokers also have queues for
point of point interaction, allowing
message to be processed just once
in a roro manner across consumers.
However, when you move to serverless
solutions like Amazon SQS and SNS,
these two are distinct services designed
to handle different delivery models.
Amazon SNS, the Simple Notification
Service uses the publish subscribe model.
You have a topic, consumers subscribe
to that topic, and all consumers receive
the same message from the producer.
On the other hand, simple Q Service
SQS uses a point-to-point delivery
model, allowing a message to be
received and processed only once
by a single consumer, rather than
process across all the consumers.
Now, let's take a look at some example
for interacting with SQS and will compare
it to how they interact with brokers.
As I showed you earlier.
First with SQS, there's no
real connection management.
You only need to define or manage the
queues and then send and receive messages.
Because you don't have persistent
connection to manage, you can
focus more directly on the business
logic of handling each message.
To start, you can create a queue.
In SQS using the create queue
method, you define the name and basic
characteristics of the queue, such
as the message retention, period,
message, text, and access policies.
You can then use Qna to
get the queue handle.
You can also remove the queue
once you have the queue handle
by calling the q delete method.
When working as a producer
client, you send message through
the send method, API call.
You first get the queue by Q name
to get the queue handle and then
send the message to that queue.
You define the message body and can also
include various attributes or message
text attached to the message such as
like for example, trace I or auto I,
so that you can give the message more
context or environmental variables.
On the consumer side, you can
use receive message call to
pull message from the queue.
As you can see here, none of them
require you to close or open connections.
So those are all API based transactions.
Similar to web MQ where you
have to acknowledge a message.
After receive a message on the
SQS side, you have to delete
it using a delete operation.
Once you get the message, you receive a
message handle in its response, which you
will use it to call the message, delete
operation to remove from the queue.
If you do not delete the message will
return to the queue and become visible
again after a certain period of time.
That will define.
When refactoring your client to move
from a traditional message broker to
services like SQS or SNS, the first thing
to consider is protocol compatibility.
A typical broker relies on
connection based protocols like
A MQP web socket or open wire.
But when working with serverless
architectures, the protocol now
becomes H-T-D-P-S or GMS APIs.
Those are API based connections, not
persistent connections, so therefore, the
client are making API calls to a service
for sending and receiving messages.
You also want to consider whether you
need strict message ordering or you
can sacrifice a little bit of other
preservation for higher scalability.
For example, SQS offers standard cues
and FIFA first in first all cues.
FIFA cues.
Maintain the exact order of
messages while standard cues provide
best offered ordering, but allow
you to scale almost infinitely.
Additionally, because those are service
architectures built within the cloud
ecosystem, you gain much more visibility.
For example, you can enable Cloudera
to log all data, request This give
you a detailed request level look
to see when the message was sent.
When it was received, the
original IPR of the client.
The user roles involved, allowing for
far better tracking and monitoring.
Furthermore, because those are native
A Ws services, they integrate easily
with IAM or I am Identity Center for
authentication and authorization purposes.
In contrast with Web mq, even if you
host it on Amazon MQ platform, you might
have to set up like an LDAP server rather
than using IM roles or users for the same
authentication or authorization purpose.
There are some limitations to be aware
of from migrating to SQS or SNS services.
For example, there's a default pay limit
of up to one megabytes per message size.
However, you can get around this by
using Java or Python extension libraries
built by AWS, which allows you to have
a message body up to two gigabytes by
utilizing S3 service at the backend.
What that means is that when you send
a message through SNS or SQS service,
instead of sending the entire payload.
The library uploads a message object to
an S3 bucket, and only send a pointer
of that object within your message.
Producer transfers a pointer
as a message to the consumer
effectively increasing your message.
Site limit from one megabytes
all the way up to two gigabytes.
Those are some key factors to consider
the M new messaging system to the cloud.
You need to understand the technologies
to see if there are any limitations,
constraints or changes compared
to your current environment.
You also need to plan how you will
handle authentication and authorization.
Your clients need to engage with
the service, so understanding
the available security methods
is critical to ensure seamless
integration with your current systems.
You also want to consider
the deployment settings.
When deploying on-prem, you have
complete customization, but once you
move to managed services, certain
configurations are taken out of
your deployment settings and managed
entirely by the service itself.
For example, you cannot re, you cannot
loosen up the security protocol to say
without TRS connection for client to
rev MQ broker on Amazon MQ services.
Lastly, you need to understand how you
want to operate and monitor the service.
On an on-prem messaging system,
you can connect directly to the
server to get full set of data.
But in a cloud environment, usually
depend on monitoring services like
CloudWatch, utilizing matrix and
logging to manage and monitor the
health of the mon messaging systems.
This brings us to the
end of the presentation.
Hopefully you now have a better
understanding of the migration
process from on-prem to the cloud.
We have covered the overall benefits
from migrating to a service architecture,
the different pathways from migration,
and the fact that migration requires
both application level or call level
changes and adjustment to how you operate
at a business and operational level.
Thank you.