Good morning everyone.
I am ti and today I will be discussing
our research on resilient health
monitoring system, specifically
engineered for disaster zone.
The subtitle of my presentation
captures our core mission, transforming
proof of concept health monitoring.
Into battle tested system capable of
operating when infrastructure fails.
This is crucial work because
traditional health monitoring system
are designed for control environment
with reliable power and stable network
connectivity conditions that simply
doesn't exist in disaster zones.
When earthquake strikes, hurricane
hits, or other catastrophe occurs.
Conventional healthcare infrastructure
collapses precisely when it's necessary.
Most, our research addresses this
challenge by re-imagining health
monitoring technology from the ground
up, focusing on resilience, power,
efficiency, and reliable communication.
Even in the most challenging
environment, the ultimate challenge.
When designing the health monitoring
for Disaster Zone, we face three
critical challenge challenges that form
what I call the ultimate challenge.
First, we need to provide
life critical monitoring.
This means tracking vital signs,
including heart rate, blood, oxygen
level, SPO two body temperature, and
respiratory functions parameters.
That can mean the difference
between life and death.
Unlike consumer fitness tracking trackers
that can tolerate occasional inaccuracy,
our system must maintain clinical
accuracy even under extreme conditions.
Second, we operate in hostile
environments when traditional
infrastructure has collapsed.
Think about post earthquake scenario.
When no power grid, no internet
connectivity, extreme temperature,
dust, and debris, our system must
continue functioning reliably
despite these conditions.
Finally, we are targeting 99.99% of time.
This means our system can only
afford about five minutes of
downtime per year when lives
depend on continuous monitoring.
This level of reliability isn't a
luxury, it's an absolute necessary.
The BLE connection, resilience.
To meet these challenges we have developed
several innovations in BLE Connection.
Resilience first are dynamic
device discovery enables automated
reconnection protocols that continuously
adapt to challenging environment.
This means that as healthcare providers
move patients or as condition changes, the
system automatically rebuilds connections
without requiring manual reconfiguration.
We have implemented multi-part
communication that ensures signal
persistence even when primary route fails.
Our field testing shows that
approaches has increased connection.
Reliability from 92.4% to 99.7% critical
improvement when lives are at stake.
The system includes sophisticated
signal degradation handling that
maintains core functionality even
at minimal signal strength, even at
signal levels as low as minus 95 DBM.
The system continues transmitting
essential vital signs.
Perhaps most importantly, our device
from mesh networks where they can rely
on data when direct connection fails.
This creates a self-healing network
architecture that can route around
damaged or disconnected nodes,
maintaining continuous monitoring
capabilities despite localized failure,
power optimization, breakthrough.
Yes.
Power management represents one of
our most significant innovations as
it directly impacts how long these
systems can operate in the field.
Our dynamic sensor sampling intelligently
varies collection frequency based
on the patient's criticality and
remain power reserve and remaining
power reserves for stable patients.
Sampling rates can decrease to conserve
power while critical patients are.
Monitoring more frequently.
This approach has demonstrated as a
remarkable 62.4% reduction in power
consumption for stable patients
while maintaining clinical standards.
We have implemented advanced edge
computing algorithm that analyzes
data locally drastically reducing
energy intensive transmissions.
This low power processing
approach has reduced ideal.
Current consumption, idle current
consumption from 4.2 milliamps
to just 0.8 milliamps and 81%
improvement that directly translates
to longer operational life.
Our transmission optimization
uses strategic compression and
scheduled data delivery protocols
to reduce radioactivity cycle by
coordinating transmission windows.
Across multiple devices, we have
achieved a 28.3% reduction in
overall power consumption as compared
to standard BLE implementation.
Finally, we have integrated innovative
energy harvesting technology that captures
kinetic thermal and ambient RF energy.
These micro generators create
self-sustained power systems
that can extend operational.
Duration by 18 to 26% under
favorable conditions, potentially
providing indefinite operation
in some field settings.
OTA update in constrained networks.
Maintaining software currently in
a currently is vital for security
and functionality, but traditionally
update mechanism, traditional update
mechanism fails in disaster environment.
With limited connectivity, our
Delta update approach transmits
only modified components rather
than complete firmware images.
This reduces bandwidth demand by over 80%
with typical update payload size, dropping
from 48 to 96 KB to just eight to 12 kb.
This efficiency is critical when network
resources are severely constrained.
We have developed proprietary extreme
compression algorithm that can
shrink update payloads by nearly 83%.
This enables critical patches, even
on severely limited network, the
traditional updates would be impossible.
Our partial update recovery use
sophisticated checkpointing to
allow interruptions, interrupted
updates to resume from break points.
This eliminates redundancy.
Data transfer during network fluctuation,
ensuring updates are complete even
with intermittent connectivity.
Finally, our intelligent rollback
safety mechanism automatically
reverts to the last stable version
if deployment integrity check fields.
This ensures continuous device operation
even when updates, encounter problems
with field testing demonstrated in 92.2%.
First attempt update success rate.
Next, let's talk about
distributed observability.
Maintaining visibility into the
system performance is crucial
in disaster scenarios, but
traditional monitoring approach fail
without reliable infrastructure.
Our system provides comprehensive
real time virtualization visualization
across all deployed monitoring
devices in the disaster zone.
This gives emergency responders
and medical personal immediate
insights to, into both system
health and patient status.
We have implemented dis distributed
tracing capabilities that provide
crucial visibility into patient
interaction during network destruction.
This allows us to maintain
accountability and data integrity
despite challenging conditions.
Our advanced machine learning algorithms
can provide identify potential system
failures and psychological emergency
before critical incident records.
Field testing shows our system can
detect deterioration of two 13 point five
minutes before conventional indicators,
potential life saving, early warning.
Finally, our intelligent bandwidth
optimization prioritization,
transmission of life.
Critical metrics when communication
infrastructure is severely compromised.
This ensures that most important
data gets through even when
bandwidth is extremely limited
error Budgeting for critical care,
we have adopted the site reliability
engineering concept of error budgeting to
ensure our system maintaining, maintain.
Approximately reliability, appropriate
reliability for different functions.
For overall system reliability, we have
targeted 99.9%, which means a maximum
downtime of just five minutes per year.
This ensures that healthcare providers
can depend on the system being available
when needed for critical alert delivery
notification that can be lifesaving.
We aim even higher with 99 point.
Nine, nine, 9% reliability target.
This translates to less than one minute
of annual downtime For these critical
functions for non-critical function, we
allow slightly more flexible flexibility.
With a 98.5% target, the strategic
approach allows more innovation in
secondary features while maintaining
the ionic lag reliability for
the most important capability.
This error budgeting approach ensures that
we focus our reliable efforts where they
matter most on the functions that directly
impact patient safety and outcomes.
Healthcare specific SLIs and SLOs.
We have developed healthcare
specific service level indicators
and service level objectives that
directly relate to clinical outcomes.
For vital sick sign latency, we
target less than one second with a
critical threshold of three seconds.
This ensures that healthcare providers
are working with current patient data,
not historical information that might
no longer reflect patient's status.
Alert delivery type is even
more stringent with a target of
less than 200 milliseconds and a
critical threshold of two seconds.
When a patient's condition deteriorates
every second counts and rapid alerts
enable fast inter intervention.
Data accuracy targets 99.5% with
a critical threshold of 98.5%.
This high standard ensure that
critical decisions are based on
trustworthy information, reducing risk,
reducing the risk of treatment error.
Finally, battery life prediction
accuracy aims for a plus minus 5%
error with a critical threshold
of plus minus 10% Accurate battery
prediction prevents unexpected device
failure that could leave patient
unmonitored during the critical periods.
These healthcare specific metrics
ensures that our system meets
the unique requirement of medical
monitoring in disaster in the.
Minutes,
graceful degradation patterns.
When resource become constrained,
our system implements sophisticated
graceful degradation patterns
to maintain essential functions.
Our priority based functions
shedding disabled non-essential
features first, as resource es.
Preserving critical monitoring
functions until absolute failure.
This means.
Capabilities, like high resolution
wave or historical data access
might be reduced before vital signs.
Monitor is affected.
Data resolution scaling dynamically
adjust sampling rates and precise
precision based on patient status.
This mainten maintains higher resolution
for abnormal readings, ensures
critical accuracy when it matters
most while conserving resources.
On stable patients, our first, our
local first processing approach
shifts to autonomous operations when
disconnected from central infrastructure.
Local alerting continues without
central system ensuring patient
monitoring continues even when
the network fails completely.
Finally across, finally, across cross
device redundancy allows nearby devices
to assure monitoring reliability.
For failing units, patient data is
seamlessly transferred between devices.
Maintaining continuous monitoring,
even when individual component fails,
real world impact.
Our system has already demonstrated
significant real world impact
across multiple scenarios.
During the Napal earthquake, we
successfully monitored over 5,000
patients across 15 market makeshift field.
Hospitals with 99.3% of time during
critical disaster response operation.
This provides continuous continuity
of care despite complete collapsed
infrastructure, enabling more
efficient triage and resource
allocation following Hurricane Maria.
Our system was rapidly deployed
when hospital infrastructure
collapsed, providing 17,000 patient
hours of uninterrupted vital.
Monitoring in an extreme condition.
This allows healthcare providers to
focus on treatment rather than manually
monitoring, significantly improving the
efficiency of limited medical personnel
beyond immediate disaster response.
Our technology has transformed
healthcare delivery by extending
critical monitoring capabilities
to facilitate 200 facilities in.
Underserved regions without reliable
power infrastructure to demonstrate how
innovation driven by extreme requirements
can broader impact on global healthcare,
across global healthcare access.
Key takeaways to conclude,
I want to emphasize that SRE
principles can transform healthcare
technology, reliability, and
extreme conditions when human lives.
Lives depends on uptime.
Traditionally reliable standards
and approach simply aren't enough.
Our research demonstrate that through
focus, innovation, and in connection,
reliance in connection, reliance, power
optimization, update mechanism, and g
graceful degradation, we can create health
monitoring system that functions reliably
even in the most challenging environment.
The impact extends beyond immediate
disaster response, potentially
transforming healthcare delivery
in resource constraint environments
worldwide, and establishing new
standards for medical device reliability.
Thank you for your attendance.
I'm happy to take any questions about
our research or the specific technical
approaches that we have developed.
Thank you again.
Bye
bye.