Speaker 28: From alerts to answers modern
SRE with observability AI and agent ops.
So we are going to discuss about key
problem, which is noise, data rich
and information poor infrastructure
of observability for SRE today.
The data rich information, poor paradox.
The shift.
We moved from monoliths to
microservices, increasing
telemetry volume by a hundred x.
The fatigue is SREs are drowning
in high cardinality noise.
Too many alerts, not enough context.
The goal, we do not need more alerts.
We need answers.
And the bottom line here is
traditional monitoring just identifies
the symptom, but SRE still have
to manually hunt for the causes.
So challenges with current observability
is why the old way failing is because of
siloed data matrices, logs, traces exist
in separate tools with no correlation.
The dashboard mirage looking at
50 dashboards during an outage
at a time increasing cognitive
load rather than reducing it.
Alert fatigue, static thresholds, lead to
80% flapping and non-actionable alerts.
Knowledge leakage.
Incident resolution depends on tribal
knowledge rather than encoded patterns.
So coping with signal bias and noise.
We have a new framework, which
is signal to context framework,
where to handle huge signal bias.
We shift focus from raw data to
meaningful contextual events.
Golden signals are reimagined, focus on
latency error, traffic saturation, but.
Through the lens of SLOs, that is
service level objectives distributed
tracing as backbone using trace
ID to stitch together the user
journey across mesh dimensionality
reduction, using AI to group thousand
connection refusal logs into one
database connectivity cluster event.
So how we can handle signal bias
and noise using this context driven
observability is by having consistent
tagging and metadata that is unified
tags metadata across application.
Environments and services having
end-to-end lineage, that means a clear
path of source and origin of the alert to
its journey towards dashboard using data
flow and dependencies and finding out the
end-to-end path of the alert and error.
Having automated root cause analysis
programming where we have AI driven
programs and methods where RCA could
be auto detected and reported AI
powered anomaly detection algorithms,
where we find out using behavioral and
historic analysis and IM implement.
Dynamic anomaly detection,
correlation and causality.
Looking at linking the links together,
logs together historical matrices
together, and finding out the
changes and correlation and causes.
So what are the key features of
context Driven Observability?
Here is consistent tagging and
metadata, enriching telemetry data
with uniform tags, application name,
environment, service tier owner,
correlation, causality, tools, use.
AI and ML two automatically
correlate unrelated data points
into a co picture of problem.
This include linking links linking
logs, matrices, traces to specific
code changes, infrastructure
components, or business impact.
End-to-end lineage showing how
data flows, which downstream assets
are affected by an upstream issue.
This helps with impact analysis
and root cause identification, AI
powered anomaly detection instead of
relying solely on static thresholds.
Context aware tools.
Learn normal behavior
patterns and flag anoma.
And automated root cause analysis,
which find out the ultimate goal of
context is to expedite RCA to go beyond
detection and automatically triaging
incidents and suggesting potential fixes.
One of the other methods here is using
agent TechOps, where an agent can apply
reasoning to find out the error logs and
to reason why an error or a log appeared.
So the first agent will observe a
spike, for example, in 500 errors,
analyze the, and queries these traces
and sees a specific downstream.
API is timing out or it's down.
Act upon that means it checks the recent
CICD logs, the recent deployments iden
identify as a bad canary deployment
and triggers the rollback and report.
Either in a form of message in
Slack or email or report directly
to the human he's reporting to.
And roll back take gives a specific
action that he roll back to a
different version for the API handling
and API latency troubleshooting.
And here is the trace
Evidence Observability.
Can be done in four major steps.
First is to observe second analyze.
Third is act, and fourth is reporting.
In the observe phase, the agents
monitor real time golden signals via
any tools like Prometheus, Grafana,
and other observability tools.
Just when they find out anomaly in
the normal patterns, they find out
the trace root causes for those.
By acquiring all the logs distributed
traces, I identifying any dependency
failure or any service which is
down act upon it, that is mitigating
incident check, CICD logs.
Identify a bad Kennedy trigger rollback,
or even inform to an a human agent.
And finally reported to the team along
with a detailed summary that what
was the cause, how it was fixed what
caused it all the specific details
about the alert or about the anomic.