Speaker 17: Welcome everyone
to Kant 42 SRE 2026.
I am Moly Ama, a senior staff
software engineer at Gallier
Financial Technologies.
Today I wanna talk about something that
most SRE teams overlook, the front end,
specifically how we apply SRE principles
to frontend architecture at Carillo,
and the production results we achieved.
A bit about my background, my
career has spanned high throughput
systems across several industries.
I spent time in the gaming industry,
building infrastructure at scale, worked
on high volume document generation
systems like bank statement pipelines,
and I've also been deep in enterprise
platform architecture at Galleo Financial
Technologies, which is a part of SoFi.
At Galleo, we build B2B
operational platforms serving
over 200 enterprise clients.
These are the tools that customer
service agents and relationship
managers use every day.
More recently, I have been driving
AI adoption across our engineering
organization from developer productivity
tooling to governance frameworks
for enterprise LLM integrations.
So my perspective on front end
architecture comes from the intersection
of enterprise scale operational
reliability, and the practical
realities of agent facing platforms.
Lemme set the stage with some context.
The industry numbers are well established.
53% of users abandon applications that
take more than three seconds to load, and
that climbs to 71% above four seconds.
Now, our platforms at Gallo are B2B,
and agents and relationship managers do
not have the option to abandon the app.
They're stuck using it, but that does
not mean slow performance is harmless.
It's actually worse in some ways because
the damage is silent and cumulative.
Every extra second of load times
multiplies across hundreds of agents.
Doing that, thousands of interactions
per day, that compounds into longer
handle times, eventually extremely
painful for our end users, and more
errors under the time pressure.
It causes agent fatigue over full
day sessions, so the cost is real.
It's just harder to see in a dashboard.
So how did we get here?
So we were in the single page
application era for a long time, and
it was a genuinely great step forward.
They gave us rich, interactive
experiences in the browser, but they
came with costs that compound over time.
At Galleo, we were seeing
JavaScript bundles of two to
three megabytes per page load.
First content page.
Contentful paint was hitting three to
four seconds on constrained networks.
And the real killer was the variance.
Under degraded network conditions,
client heavy rendering would
collapse unpredictably.
You could not set reliable SLOs
against that kind of variance.
That's a core argument
of the stock at Gile.
We made a deliberate decision front,
and latency is not a UX polish issue.
It's an operational reliability
problem, and here's why.
Slow rendering were increasing handle
times per agent interaction in high
volume workloads, agent in eight hour
sessions were hitting rendering variance
timeouts, and accumulated UI drift.
Client inefficiency was
increasing downstream API.
Pressure and compute spends across
a multi-tenant environment and the
platform degradation under load was
reducing the volume of interactions
agents could perform daily.
Once we frame the front end performance
as a reliability concern rather than a
cosmetic one, we could actually apply
some of the SRA thinking to solve it.
Here's what the legacy
architecture looked like.
Every page load went
through this pipeline.
Download the full JavaScript
bundle, render everything.
Client side, make API calls after
hydration, and only then could
the user see a meaningful paint.
At Galileo, we are seeing about 300
millisecond server response times.
Which were reasonable, but
all the clients had overhead.
On top of that, made the
actual experience much slower.
Our cash hit rate was around 65% with
clear room for improvement, and the
rendering unpredictability was elevated
across agent workflows and tenants.
So here's the shift we made,
and I'll walk through each of
these three strategies in detail.
But the core principle is simple, more
computation from infrastructure you do
not control, which is the user's browser.
Onto infrastructure that you do
control, which is your server strategy.
One is server components, essentially
moving business logic server side.
Strategy two, two is streaming
SSR, which is delivering HTML
progressively to decouple time to
first byte from time to interactive.
And strategy three is a hybrid
rendering model, matching each content
type to the rendering mode that
fits its reliability requirement.
So server components, they're the
foundation of our architectural shift.
Business Logic that used to execute in
the browser now executes on the server.
Only.
Minimal serialized UI
payloads reach the client.
Hydration becomes more
surgical rather than wholesale.
The benefits slowly compound client
CPU usage drops because the heavy
competition happens server side.
Memory overhead decreases because
fewer components need to be hydrated
and stability increased and improved
across the full range of agent hardware
and terminals, which matters when your
users are on corporate machines with
varying specs running your app all day.
Streaming SSR was the
second major strategy.
Traditional server side rendering
makes you wait for the entire
page to be computed before
sending anything to the browser.
Streaming.
SSR basically breaks that coupling.
You send HTML progressively as it
becomes available for SRE practitioners.
The important thing is not just
that it is faster, but that it
makes performance more predictable.
Lower variance means you
can set meaningful SLOs.
At Gallier, we measured at 42%
improvement in time to first meaningful
paint and 45% faster initial page
loads across production routes.
Then the third strategy
is hybrid entering module.
Not every piece of content has to
have the same reliability requirement.
Static generation is su
applied where data is stable.
This maximizes cash efficiency and theory
and leverage with the near zero fail rate.
Server components handle dynamic
personalized data without client overhead
and minimal client JavaScript is reserved
for genuinely interactive UI elements.
The operational benefits include
deterministic performance,
improved observability, and the
reduced failure surface rate.
It also enhance Reliance under load.
One thing that people generally don't
talk about is the build systems, but
I wanna make a case that it actually
should be at Gallo Legacy Tooling.
A Legacy Build Tooling was a
hidden constraint on our ability
to evolve the architecture.
We evaluated and introduced rust based
tooling, specifically Turbo Pack, which
gave us significantly faster compilation.
The result was AAN X improvement
in cold start, build speed.
For SRE, the connection is direct.
Faster builds means short,
shorter feedback loops, which
mean faster rollbacks when
something goes wrong in production.
Barr tree shaking means smaller payloads,
which means a smaller blast radius.
On any given reply I, here's the
consolidated production results,
60% reduction in JavaScript bundle
size, 45% faster page loads.
43% improvement in time
to first meaningful paint.
Cash hit rate went up from 65 to eight
or 9%, servers upon times reduced by 50%.
And these were results that we gathered
across multiple production results.
The impact went beyond performance
metrics, architecture modernization
changed how the engineering
organization at Glee operates.
We saw a 35% reduction in
time to market actually.
A lot of the new features
that were being developed were
bundled in at a much faster rate.
The productivity increased by
almost 50% across multiple teams.
We saw fewer rollbacks, which means
improved release confidence and
reduce incident driven reversals.
The architecture did not
make the product faster.
It made the team ship faster
and make it more confident.
Wanna leave you with three
principles first, for frontend
reliability belongs in SRE.
Client site performance must be
owned by the reliability engineering
and not treated as something the
front end team handles on their own.
Second server centric architecture
scales, SSR and server components
provide a durable, scalable foundation
for enterprise create web systems.
And third, started the architecture
layer performance engineering.
That begins with bandaid optimization.
On top of a flawed architecture
is costly and incomplete.
This methodology is not
specific to financial platforms.
It's transferable blueprint for any
large scale high availability system.
For those interested in the data
behind the talk the industry ref
re research references include web
performance abandonment statistics,
the react server components, technical
docs, and turbo pack build systems
from Vercel and the next J ecosystem.
All production metrics were collected from
galia, financial technologies, production,
and monitoring and observability systems.
Thank you for your time today.
I hope this stock has given you a concrete
framework for thinking about front end
architecture as a reliability concern.
If you're interested in discussing
any of these strategies further,
I'd be happy to connect.
Thank you.