Hello everyone.
Good morning.
Good evening.
My name is Murli Kdi Manou.
Welcome to Con 42 Site
level Engineering 2025.
Today we'll talk about scalable
interconnect strategies for
GPU accelerated HPC clusters,
GPU Interconnect Challenge.
The problem, GPU computational
capacity has evolved exponentially
outpacing interconnect bandwidth
improvements by three to four
times per hardware generation.
This widening gap creates severe
performance bottleneck in large scale
distributor systems limiting the effective
throughput of multi GPU computations.
So how does it impact in
modern HPC applications?
Interconnect latency.
A network congestion can consume 30
to 50% of the total execution time.
The substantial overhead persist
even in meticulously optimized
computational computation intensity
workloads significantly reducing
overall system efficiency.
So what do we need to do next?
Generation solutions must address
three fundamental challenges,
bandwidth saturation at extreme scale.
Topology aware routing inefficiencies
and the substantial synchronization
overhead of collective operations
across thousands of distributed GPUs.
Let's look at some of the
traditional interconnect limitations.
First, bandwidth saturation.
GPUs generate data at rates that
overwhelm network capacity causing.
Memory buffer congestion and forcing
computational pipelines to stall
across distributed compute nodes.
The second routing inefficiencies.
Static routing protocols cannot
adapt to realtime network congestion,
creating traffic bottlenecks,
enforcing data through suboptimal
paths during high throughput workloads.
Third synchronization overhead.
Multi GPU collective operations require
precise barrier synchronization,
where even nanosecond latency
variations compound exponentially,
severely degrading performance as
systems scale to thousands of nodes.
Let's dive into some of the top
policy innovations that are.
In the marketplace First
Factory architecture.
This network topology architecture
delivers non-blocking communication
with full BI section and bandwidth
and deterministic latency scales
effectively to thousands of nodes,
but requires exponentially increasing
switch count at higher radis.
3D Taurus Network topology.
This topology implements a mesh like
structure with wrapped around connections,
minimizing I wiring complexity
while maintaining low hop counts.
Optimized for nearest neighbor
communication patterns.
Common in physics simulations,
dragonfly network topology.
This topology leverages.
Hierarchical organization with high
erratics routers to minimize network
diameter and cable length achieves
near optimal trade off between local
and global bandwidth while reducing
the cost and power consumption.
Let's understand RDMA
direct access efficiency.
RDMA enables CPU bypass, which enables
direct memory to memory transfers
across the network fabric without
CPU intervention, which dramatically
re reducing crossing overhead
and system resource consumption.
This also enables low latency.
Achieves up to 55% reduction in
end-to-end communication latency,
allowing near instantaneous data
sharing between distributed GP nodes
in computing intensive applications.
This also provides higher efficiency,
which delivers 97% protocol efficiency
for medium sized message transfers,
virtually eliminating network overhead.
And maximizing effective bandwidth
utilization across the cluster.
Let's look at some case studies.
First one, frontier supercomputer,
20 point 24.8% gain was realized
by dynamic adaptive routing
algorithms significantly outperformed
traditional static approaches.
In high traffic simulation workloads.
This also uses slingshot interconnect
proprietary congestion control mechanisms
dynamically adjust packet priorities
and pathways to maintain optical
optimal throughput under extreme loads.
This also employs dragon fry to
policy as we reviewed previous slides.
Enhanced network architecture
delivers near uniform global bandwidth
distribution with minimal diameter,
reducing worst case latency by 37%.
Let's look at another case
study, which is Nvidia Seline.
This uses Infinity Band, HDR.
This is revolutionary to 200
gigabit per second interconnect.
Between compute nodes with full
bisection bandwidth architecture,
eliminating network congestion and
ensuring seamless parallel communication.
This also implements R-D-A-R-D-M-A,
which delivers exceptional 97%
protocol efficiency for medium-sized
data transfers while slashing
end-to-end latency by up to 55%.
Dramatically outperforming
conventional networking approaches.
This also implements NCCL optimization.
Precision engineered GPU to GPU collective
operations maximize throughput with
advanced topology aware algorithms
that intelligently adopt communication
patterns based on workload demands.
Okay.
With that, let's get into some of
the software optimization strategies
that are being used in the industry.
First one, adaptive routing
intelligently reconfigures network
pathways in real time based on traffic
analysis, reducing congestion by up
to 40% and delivering sub microsecond
latency across complex workloads.
Okay.
Topology aware algorithms,
sophisticated communication frameworks
that precisely map data, exchange
patterns to the physical network
architecture, reducing network diameter,
traversals by 60%, and MA minimizing
cross switch traffic overhead.
N-C-C-L-Q, advanced customization
of GPU collective operations.
That orchestrates communication patterns
with nanosecond precision, eliminating
t transfers and achieving near the
theoretical bandwidth utilization
load, balancing sophisticated
traffic distribution algorithms that
dynamically allocate bandwidth across
multiple pathways, preventing resource
contention and maintaining consistent
95% plus throughput efficiency.
Under extreme computational demands
future interconnect technologies
that are evolving integrated
network processing units.
These are purpose built silicon accelerate
packet processing and routing operations
at line rate, complete off offloading
of communication protocols from GPUs.
This liberates computational
resources for core workloads.
Photonic interconnects, silicone photonics
enables multi tera data transfers using
wavelength, using multiplexing power
consumption decreases by 65% compared to
the electrical interconnects while sub
nanosecond latencies become achievable.
Third in package integration,
high bandwidth network interfaces.
Co-pack with the GPU substrate
using advanced chip plate
architectures, drastically reduced
signal paths, minimize propagation
delays, and unlock unprecedented
GPU to network through output.
Let's look at some of the
performance metrics and benchmarks.
Traditional ethernet maximum
is 12.5 gigabytes per second.
End to end latency.
10 microseconds.
Peak performance utilization, 65%.
InfiniBand, HDR.
Maximum dropout is 25
gigabytes per second.
End-to-end latency 3.5 microseconds.
Peak performance utilization
is 85% NVIDIA and NVLink.
Maximum throughput is
50 gigabytes per second.
End-to-end latency, 1.8 microseconds.
Peak performance utilization.
93%
future photonics.
Maximum throughput is a hundred
gigabytes per second end-to-end
latency 0.5 microseconds.
Peak performance utilization up to 98%.
Let's review key takeaways and next steps.
Analyze your application
communication patterns.
Conduct comprehensive workload profiling
to identify critical data, movement,
bottlenecks and communication hotspots.
Select appropriate network
topology, strategically align
infrastructure investments with
specific application requirements to
maximize performance to cost ratio.
Implement software optimizations,
fine tune collective communication
operations specifically for
your network architecture.
To eliminate redundant data transfers,
pre prepare for emerging technologies,
develop modular systems and abstraction
layers that can seamlessly incorporate
next generation interconnect advancements.
Thank you.
If you have any questions, yeah,
please reach out to me on my LinkedIn.