Today.
Today we'll be talking about a
very hot topic, SRE versus DevOps.
We would answer the
question, are they the same?
Are they competitors?
Are they secret allies?
And by the end of this talk
you would know exactly how they
differ, where they overlap, and
how to make them work together.
So let's dive in.
So the myth under reality, right?
Many people think SRE and DevOps are the
same thing, but with different labels.
This is just a myth.
The actual realities that they
share the same goals, but they
solve different problems, right?
So same goals, different problems.
You should think of them like, cousins.
Different personalities, right?
DevOps is all about speed.
Collaboration whilst SRAs more about
reliability and engineering rigor.
So the magic happens when
you use them together.
So what are the core philosophies?
DevOps emerged, to break down.
The silos between development
and operations, right?
It's it has a mantra to move fast, right?
To automate everything.
If you viewed it, you should run it right.
Whilst SRA on the other hand, was born in
Google actually, and its more about how.
Engineer reliability into our systems.
So we don't just wanna build
softwares that works, right?
We wanna make them reliable, right?
So both of them sort of love
automation, but SE, adds things
like metrics, metrics like sli.
So the focus of DevOps is.
Silos between dev and ops, right?
And the focus for SRE to make
systems reliable in a nutshell.
So what are the key differences, right?
So this is where we get technical, right?
And not just technical,
we get tactical as well.
So DevOps measures the success
of development frequency.
Or so one of the key things to say
DevOps is successful is by measuring
the deployment frequency whilst the SRE
is more concerned about uptime, right?
We don't really care much about the
speed or it's more about uptime, right?
So DevOps uses ci cd tools whilst SRE.
The monitoring dashboards.
So they both rely on Kubernetes like tools
like Kuber, Kubernetes, Terraform, and,
most importantly like a blameless culture.
The difference though is that DevOps
removes the war, the whilst SR Ebu
like guide rails in the Nutshells.
So what are the secrets?
Weapons, right?
Here's where SRE gets spicy.
Error budget quantifies the risk, right?
If your system has for three minutes
of downtime this month, then SRM
might hold feature release right
until you improve reliability.
Whilst DevOp teams might see this
as no, just a speed bomb, right?
It's fine.
It's just a speed bomb.
So the trick is to align
these perspectives early on.
When you start using your team,
as soon as you can, right?
So then that makes a question,
when do we use DevOps?
When do we use s?
I think people for example, like
the answer is that startups often,
pick DevOps for speed, right?
They need to get their products
to market as soon as possible.
Yeah, they care about reliability, but
it's not like the priority at that stage.
Whilst enterprises.
Complex systems, they, they, now
they've gotten to a stage where they
care more about like reliability.
But what should the best themes, like
what the best themes, what should they do?
I think the best things should
borrow from both, right?
Netflix, for example,
uses SRE for streaming.
But it uses DevOps for its internal tools.
So it's, it's your turn to,
determine where your team
fits and decide accordingly.
So how do we bridge the gap, right?
How do we bridge the gap between the two?
Conflict happens when DevOps
says, oh, we need to ship, right?
And SRE says, no.
It's not reliable.
We can't ship yet.
So how do we fix this?
Or how do we resolve this conflict?
So the main thing is
to collaborate, right?
Have the SRE teams join, sprint
planning meetings and let it evolve.
Team.
Define the s right.
Always should always share the
blame and the credit as well.
So let's take a very quick,
brief case study, right?
Say we have a SaaS company, right?
They currently struggling and the
DevOps team is like burning out,
fixing nightly outages, right?
They brought the SRE team to set SLOs.
Now they would be able to like track
error budgets in their ci cd pipeline.
So the results will be that
they now have like fewer.
Midnight outages and more high
fives, which is a win for everyone.
So the main thing is if you
notice, for example, you're having
more reliability issues, right?
Then that might be like a good indicator
that you need to consider SRE, right?
The key takeaway is that I
would like is that, DevOps.
It's not the same as SRE, but
they reinforce each other, right?
They work best when combined.
So you don't need to choose between them.
You don't need to choose
DevOps over SRE, right?
You need to decide, based
on your requirements.
So my suggestion would be that we, you.
Lead to SLOs to your next sprint or
invite the sre, to a DevOps retro.
And tiny steps leads to
big wins and I think, yeah.
So the next steps what
should be the next steps?
So the main thing is that you should
be a champion for change, right?
The bridge between DevOps and SRE
thinking, especially in our like teams.
Also it's to continuously learn, read
Google SI read books and dev books
and lastly is to implement, right?
You need to begin measuring SLI for
critical services, but then it's
all about your specific needs and
you know the needs of the team.
Yeah.
Thank you for watching
and have a good day.
Bye.