Hi, this is Ika nda.
I'm working as an SAP consultant
from the last 14 years.
Have experience working in
SAPS four Brim CRM SD models.
I have done a lot of implementations which
include subscription management conversion
charging, mass moduling integrating
with SA systems like F-I-C-O-F-I-C-O-M.
I have done a lot of
implementations around sales,
marketing, service management.
Currently I'm working as a
technical program manager at Discos.
In this role I'm responsible for an
SAP Brim implementation which includes
my responsibilities as architecture,
design, and integration efforts.
Prior to this I'm working, I worked
as an SAP as for Hana Brim Manager.
As Spring and Consulting I lead a lot of
SAB projects, which includes Om C, and ci.
In this, video.
I'm going to explain more about the
ai, how it is impacting the revenue
management how we can leverage predict
analytics and AI for revenue optimization.
In enterprise level.
Currently in the present world we could
see that a lot of things we can optimize
using ai in this, in this video we'll
examine how the real world results
and the infrastructure requirements
and ethical considerations are helping
different organizations how AI integration
can position your organization.
This presentation explores more on AI
technologies enabling gains in forecasting
accuracy, price optimization, customer
intelligence, and retention strategies.
First, I would like to talk
about the AI revolution in the
enterprise revenue management area.
I would like to talk how this AI is
helping to shift from traditional
business to to the AI cloud area.
By building in inte systems from
ground up companies are creating
self optimization revenue engines.
That continually, continuously adapting
the market conditions, operation
constraints, and customer behaviors.
There's a lot of sustainable financial
environments using ai, how AI can data
can help you for building your new
strategies and building your business
complex solutions based on the data.
Next, I would like to give you
some forecasting the demand,
how AI is helping for building
revenue for the organizations.
There's a 45% reduction cost
in forecasting error when
doing this AI power tools.
There's a 92% accuracy on the data.
How can the strategies can
be built for organizations.
And there is a 30% I rate
turnover increase using this ai.
And this is directly impacting the
bottom line through improved cash
flow and reduced carrying costs.
Pricing is helping organizations
to leverage the market conditions
inventory levels and customer behaves
retailers that are implementing
this AI driven pricing report.
Improvements, eight to 12% on average
with an increase of up to 16% during
the peak seasons of the market.
Next, I would like to talk about the
lead identification and how can you
convert conversion automations, how AI is
helping to pick the leads and implement
their, convert their leads to business.
By focusing resources on high potential
leads, organs are achieving convers
30% higher conversion rate rates.
Using this ai these systems continuously
learns from successful conversions,
becoming increasing accuracy day
by day, and adapting to evolve
based on the customer behaviors.
And we have the next thing
is about the data collection,
how the AI is analyzing it.
How these how the recommendations
are made by the ai based on the data
of the customers and the consumers,
and how is it impacting the revenue?
It is impacting almost a three, 300%
increase in the revenue using all these
tools by AI and by delivering relevant
experience at precisely the right moment.
These systems create stronger customer
relationships while simultaneously
maximizing the revenue opportunities,
which is a big thing for our organization.
These sophisticated systems
content recommendations, and I
interfaces to match each customer's
unique interests and needs.
And the next, I would like
to talk about the customer
retention and joint pretension.
How how we are identifying the
risks based on the behavior
of the customer using the ai.
Risk identification, we can reduce
the risk to 35% using this ai, and the
return of investment is increasing up
to two 70% using these technologies.
Next I would like to talk about the
best best action intelligence, which
is called NBI Next best action.
Using this data, the AI engine has
thousands of potential next steps and
selects the optimal action for each
individual customer balancing revenue
opportunities with long-term relationship.
It also, it is a proven that like 20%
higher customer satisfaction and 28%
improvement in sales with these AI tools.
Next how the enterprise data
infrastructure is helping.
Is getting evolved using this ai when
you use these robust infrastructures,
which is which is a forms of
foundation for the AI driven revenue
optimizations, architecture involved.
It is high standards and it is highly
complaints and is very much real time.
Enterprise grades implementations
process a maximum of nine to
10 million records per hour.
Which are, which have a
response of 95% transactions.
This performance is essentially for
types and applications like dynamic
pricing and personalization, which in
which helps the organization to improve
their revenues, revenue opportunities.
So you have everything real
time with using this AI driven
tools and infrastructure.
And it process a high volume in less time,
which is a big thing for an organization.
To build their strategies and the made
up like how you can ethically do your
business, like fairness, privacy, and
data security and talent transparency
while making decision making with
the stakeholders the future of ai.
It gonna impact, it, gonna do a lot
of things in the in building a revenue
and, it'll do a lot of changes to the
integrated core AI revenue systems.
Establishing robot frameworks for
using, for ensuring AI systems operating
fairly transparently in compliance
with the regulatory and how these AI
applications will help you scale and
optimize continuously and it'll help you
to develop the unified data architecture.
Which can help you to improve your
systems customer satisfaction and revenue.
Thank you.
Thanks for giving me this opportunity.
Looking forward for the confidence.
Have a nice day.