Hey everyone.
I'm really excited to be
here at Con 42 SRE 2025.
Today I want to talk about something
that's been gaining a lot of momentum,
especially in the world of distributed
systems and that's edge intelligence.
As more and more data is generated outside
traditional data centers like in factories
on vehicles or in remote locations.
We are seeing seeing a shift in how
we build and manage reliable systems.
And that's what the stock is all about.
How we can apply SRE principles to this
new decentralized environments in a way
that's practical, scalable, and reliable.
Before we dive in, let me give
you a quick intro about myself.
I am a senior software engineer where.
I work on building systems that are
designed to scale reliably and securely.
My focus has been on cloud native
platforms, distributed architecture
and observability, basically
making sure things are running
smoothly, even as complexity grows.
Over the past few years, I've
started looking more closely at Edge
Computing and what it means to bring
the reliability mindset of SRE.
Into environments that are far more
unpredictable and decentralized.
That's the foundation for today's session.
So now that we've got that set,
let's talk about what's actually
driving the shift to the edge.
Perfect.
So what's actually driving the
shift towards edge computing?
For a long time, the default approach was
to send everything to the cloud, collect
data from devices, send it upstream, and
process it centrally, and then respond.
That worked when data volumes
were manageable and latency
wasn't a huge concern.
But now we are in a world with
millions of sensors, real time
feedback loops and limited bandwidth.
Especially in industries
and or remote settings.
So what we're seeing instead is a move to
process data, right where it's generated,
whether that's on a factory floor,
inside a vehicle, or the network edge.
This has massive benefits, like
lower latency, better responsiveness,
and reduced cloud costs.
But.
It also changes how we architect systems.
We are no longer relying on
centralized infrastructure, and we are
building intelligence into the edge.
And that introduces new
reliability challenges.
And that's where we start thinking
how do we bring in SRE principles
into these kind of environments?
So now if, if worked in SRE or reliability
Engineering, a lot of the core ideas
like error budgets, SLOs, automation, and
observability are probably familiarity.
But when we take those ideas and try
to apply them to edge environments,
things get a little trickier.
The edge is messy.
Devices might be low power, they.
Might have limited connectivity and
they're often running in conditions
we can't fully control, so we
can't always expect five nines
liability or seamless deployments
like we do in the cloud, right?
That means we need to adapt SR
PRI principles or practices to
fit this particular context.
For example error budgets might
need to account for connectivity
gaps or power limitations.
And SLOs should reflect what's
realistic for each location or device
type, not just a global average.
And coming to automation, it still
plays a huge role, but it needs to be
lightweight, resilient, and designed for.
Patchy networks.
When it comes to observability, we have
to rethink how we collect data because
shipping logs and metrics to the cloud
in real time isn't always feasible.
So overall, it's not about abandoning SRE,
but it's more about reshaping it to work
in the real world conditions of the edge.
Great.
Now coming to the DevOps and container
containerization at the edge.
One of the ways we've brought
consistency and speed to backend
systems is through this meaning
DevOps practices and containerization.
And now we are extending
those same ideas to the edge.
But of course edge environments
have very different constraints,
so we have to adapt accordingly.
For starters, our traditional containers
can be way too heavy for edge devices,
so we lean on lightweight container
ima images using things like apen
based belts or even dustless containers
that strip out everything you don't
need that helps reduce memory usage
and start up time dramatically.
Sometimes over 90%.
Then there's CSED.
Edge deployments need a different
approach, especially because
devices may have limited bandwidth
or unreliable connections.
So we use more progressive rollout
strategies, automated canneries,
rollback mechanisms and smart sync
pipelines that can resume where they
left off if the connection drops.
And finally, configuration management.
We still want GitHub style
workflows, but tailored to the edge.
That means treating device configs
like version code and using
tooling that can sync and enforce
config states even at scale.
And it should be across hundreds
or maybe thousands of devices.
So DevOps at the edge is
absolutely possible, but it
just needs to be tuned for the.
Environment it runs in.
So once we've deployed applications
to the edge, how do we know they're
actually working the way we expect?
That's where observability comes in.
But again just like with
automation, we have to rethink
how we approach it for the edge.
In a typical centralized setup, we might
collect a ton of logs, metrics, traces,
and send them all to the cloud and
analyze them there in our general setup.
But at the edge, that's
not always practical.
We might not have the bandwidth
or the connection might be
intermittent, so the strategy shifts.
We focus on collecting the right data
and doing smart aggregation locally
before pushing anything upstream.
For example, instead of sending
every log line, we might detect
anomalies at the edge and only
forward summarized or critical data.
Some platforms now even support
lightweight anomaly detection directly on
the device so we can catch issues early
without waiting for any cloud analysis.
And we still aim for end-to-end
visibility using distributed
tracing so we can follow requests
across the edge and into the cloud.
But we build it in a way that
respects the resource constraints.
So in short, observability at
the edge is about being smart,
selective, and efficient.
So we stay informed without.
Overwhelming the system.
Okay.
Now here's where things get really
interesting because we are not just
collecting data at the edge anymore.
We're actually running
intelligence at the edge.
With the help of lightweight AI
models, we can now deploy logic that
doesn't just react, but actually
predicts and heals right on the device.
A great example is predictor maintenance.
Instead of waiting for a sensor to
fail, edge devices can run small models
that look at vibration or temperature
trends, detect anomalies and trigger
alerts before something breaks.
One real world use case.
Manufacturing facility reduced downtime
by 37% just by deploying local models
that caught early signs of machine wear.
Then there's autonomous healing.
Imagine a system that detects performance
degradation or corrects it automatically
by rerouting traffic, restarting services,
or simply adjusting resource usage
without any human inter intervention.
And this is happening.
We are seeing this in smart grids
where devices can reconfigure
power distribution path.
When there's an outage keeping critical
infrastructure online, what's amazing
is that these capabilities are running
on resource constrained edge hardware
and not some big cloud clusters.
It's a huge leap forward in reliability
and a perfect complement to the kind of
self-healing systems we aim for in SRA.
We've talked about the why and the
hub, but let's take a look at what this
actually looks like in the real world.
There are just a few examples of
industrial IOT systems that have
embraced edge intelligence with
the really powerful outcomes.
The first one comes from
smart manufacturing.
A major automotive company
deployed edge based analytics
for realtime quality control.
On their assembly lines.
By analyzing sensor data right
onsite, they were able to reduce
defect rates by 23% and at the same
time, they cut down on cost cloud
data transfer costs by nearly 80%.
And coming to the oil and gas
sector remote well monitoring
is a perfect edge use case.
One setup was able to maintain.
Visibility and control during a full
three day cloud outage, avoiding
any downtime that would've cost
over a million dollars per day.
That kind of resilience simply isn't
possible without edge first design.
And in maritime logistics where
connectivity is often unreliable, edge
devices on shipping containers allowed
real time tracking and monitoring.
Even when completely offline,
ensuring end-to-end supply chain
visibility possible in this use case.
So what ties these together isn't
just the use of edge, it's the
way SRE principles were adapted to
environments that are unpredictable,
distributed, and often disconnected.
It shows that with the right
architecture and mindset, we can build
highly reliable systems anywhere,
even in the harshest conditions.
Now, let's talk about how we actually
design these edge systems to be resilient
by default, especially in environments
where failure isn't a matter of f, but.
We often say everything fails eventually,
and at the edge that's even more true.
So we built with that in mind always.
One of the most effective tools is
circuit breaking, where a component that's
struggling or unstable can be isolated
before it causes a chain reaction.
This helps us contain problems instead of
letting them spread across the network.
We also use intelligent failover
mechanisms where systems can automatically
switch to backup nodes or fallback
services when something goes wrong
and then comes data replication.
It is another big one.
When devices are scattered across
locations, we need to make sure that
data isn't lost if one node fails, so we
replicate it smartly often in real time.
And then there's mesh networking,
which is super valuable in
remote or mobile environments.
Devices can talk to each other
directly rerouting around failed
connections, forming self-healing
networks that maintain uptime even
when parts of the system go dark.
So together these patents gives us
a foundation for building robust
edge systems that stay operational
even in unpredictable conditions.
Perfect.
So once we have designed these edge
systems for resilience, the next
question is, how do we manage them
at scale without losing our minds?
That's where infrastructure
automation becomes critical.
First, we start with
infrastructure as code.
This let's us define edge
environments declaratively, just
like we would with cloud resources.
We voice and control everything, so we can
re reply repeat deployments consistently,
whether it's 10 devices or 10,000 devices.
Next, we bring in policy as code
Before any deployment goes live,
we validate it against security,
performance, and reliability rules.
It's like a safety net that
prevents bad configurations
from going out to edge devices.
Where rollback might
be slow or impossible.
And finally, we layer on GitHubs.
The, this gives us a clean, automated
sync between what we've defined and get
and what's actually running in the field.
If something drifts, it gets
reconciled automatically.
What's great about this approach
is that it gives us a single source
of truth and repeatable workflows.
Even across disconnected
resource constraint environments.
In other words, we bring the
discipline and automation of cloud
operations to the edge without
compromising reliability or control.
Okay.
One of the biggest architectural decisions
we face with edge systems is this.
What should run locally and
what should stay in the cloud?
Not everything makes
sense to push to the edge.
Some workloads are better centralized,
especially when they're compute
heavy or require global view.
But for the other tasks like real time
control, anomaly detection, or basic
analytics, we often can't afford the
latency of cloud round reps. These
are the kinds of operations that
need to happen right at the source.
So what this slide shows is a
way to think about that balance.
On the left, we have workloads real
time decisions, anomaly detection, and
basic analytics, things that benefit
most from being processed at the edge as
we move to the right, into things like
historical analysis or machine learning.
Model training, those are
typically still better handled in
centralized cloud environments.
So successful edge architectures
find the speed bot.
They combine local autonomy for fast,
reliable reactions with centralized
intelligence, like for learn for
learning, optimization and visibility.
This hybrid model.
Where we combine both is really
the key to getting the best of both
worlds which has, which will have low
latency, local action, and high level
coordination and insight from the cloud.
Alright, let's wrap it all
up with a few key takeaways.
First, implementing edge intelligence
isn't just about performance.
It delivers real measurable impact.
On average, we have seen a 40% reduction
in latency when not time sensitive
operations are processed locally.
That's the difference between reacting
on time and reacting too late On the cost
side, moving analytics to the edge can
cut cloud data transfer by up to 65%,
especially in data heavy environments
like, manufacturing or logistics.
And when we combine that with the proper
SRE practices, customized for edge
environments, we can realistically aim
for 99.99% reli reliability, even in
decentralized resource constraint systems.
So with all these key takeaways
in mind, what are the next steps?
Start by looking at your architecture.
Identify which workloads need
real time processing and which
ones can stay centralized.
Then define SLOs for your edge systems.
Think locally, not just globally.
And finally, build in the right
observability, automation and
infrastructure management so
you can scale with confidence.
It's Edge computing isn't a future trend.
It's already here, and with the right
mindset and tools, we can make it just
as reliable as anything in the cloud.
Great.
Thank you so much for
joining me for this session.
I hope it gave you a fresh perspective
on how SRE can evolve for the edge
where systems are more distributed.
The stakes are higher and
the challenges are different.
But remember, no less solvable.
So if you're working on anything
in this piece or just curious about
edge infrastructure, observability
or reliability, allow to connect and
learn from your experience as well.
You can scan the QR code on
the slide to connect with me on
LinkedIn, or you can just use the
handle attached to connect with me.
Thanks again for your time and
enjoy the rest of the conference.