Speaker 32: Hi everyone.
I am Sya Nja, an engineering manager
with a decade of experience in
large scale distributed systems.
Today we are going to discuss human
governed automation loops for reliable ai.
In the SRE world, we know that as
systems scale, manual interventions
become a bottleneck, but blind
automation is a liability.
We are going to talk about how
to bridge that gap using HGAL to
understand why we need a new approach.
Let's look at the sheer pressure
our modern systems are facing.
Modern AI systems today process millions
of decisions in seconds at this scale.
Latency, availability, fault
isolation, arens metrics, they
are the backbone of reliability.
Think of a global payment processor,
a hundred milliseconds delay isn't
just a lag, it's a bottleneck that can
stall millions of dollars in commerce.
When these high speed systems
fail, they don't fail quietly.
They fail at the speed of network.
Now let's move on to see what is the
reliability gap that exists today?
In always on systems failure can
spread rapidly across network
leading to massive disruptions.
Understanding the impact radius
is essential for designing
resilient architectures.
Think of a simple retry storm, and
automated service starts retrying.
Fail request and accidentally
DDoSs its own backend without
governance to recognize the impact.
It'll eat into your
error budget in seconds.
The problem is that our current
safety nets are simply moving too
slowly to catch these failures.
Now comes the important topic of
looking at our governance processes.
Current governance methods are
often offline, asynchronous,
resulting in significant delays.
To meet SRE demands, the governance
must be real time and continuous.
It's like a postmortem that tells
you why you went down last week.
That's helpful for the future, but
we need governance that observes
the service level indicators.
Immediately to say there
is a five x failure.
With the recent bad deployment
and before the outage happens, it
helps us revert back the change.
This brings us to the core of my proposal,
the human governed automation loops.
Simply put it is fundamentally
separating the decision generation
from decision authorization.
This ensures AI systems can adapt quickly
while remaining reliable and authorized.
This architecture allows us to keep
the cap and the governance in control
of the copilot, the automation.
Let's look at how this actually fits
together in a system architecture.
Moving on to the system architecture.
The system architecture here is
that it integrates AI decision
engines with governance mechanisms
and has a control plane.
This setup ensures scalable decision
making across complex systems.
Think of this as a policy, as code.
The control plane acts as a
gatekeeper for every automated action.
This allows for constant
high speed synergy between AI
proposals and human intent.
Now moving on to see how we can build
a continuous decision generation.
AI proposes actions while human governance
ensures they are authorized appropriately.
This enhances overall system
reliability and accountability.
In a dynamic pricing or a traffic
shaping model, the AI proposes ships
every minute to match demand, but the
governance layer prevents actions that
would breach our service level objectives.
Of course, a human cannot look at every
single one of these decisions, so how
do we delegate in order for us to scale?
This is a very critical.
Element of the proposal.
The decision delegation boundaries
define when automation can operate
independently and when it must escalate.
We use dimensions like confidence impact
context to manage tool automated disk.
Cleanup at 80 percentage
hits pretty straightforward.
This is an independent task, a database
failover that hits an escalation boundary.
Designing these boundaries effectively
is the difference between building a
self-healing system and a runaway failure.
Now moving on to share, how do we do the,
do design these delegation boundaries?
We establish clear confidence thresholds.
We prioritize actions that carry minimal
risk and create guidelines for escalations
when significant effects are anticipated.
This is where we incorporate
context awareness.
If the system is already in a
fragile state due to a high latency,
we tighten those boundaries and
require more human authorization.
For this to work in production,
governance becomes the key here.
It needs to be baked in
into the infrastructure.
Moving on to share how
how this is practiced.
Integrating governance seamlessly
into the control mechanisms is
essential for rapid response.
Governance must be
programmable and observable.
This allows for system
level objectives based.
On policy as a code.
If your policy says no automated
restarts, if the error budget
is less than 10 percentage, the
system follows that in real time.
So what does it look like in practice?
HEAL facilitates enhanced
decision making across domains.
Like personalized recommendations,
timely notifications.
For instance, it allows us to scale
experimentation and system self
remediation without losing the safety
net required for robust AI interactions.
When we scale this, the benefits
for the organization are massive.
HEAL improves system
reliability and consistency.
It fosters trust through increased
accountability and traceable decision
making in a blameless post martem.
Instead of asking why the automation
failed, we can audit exactly why the
decision was authorized or denied
based on the SSRIs at that moment.
To implement this successfully,
we need a roadmap.
The key things to consider here are the
design principles, delegation boundaries,
evolving governance, monitoring
mechanisms, but we have to be honest about
the challenges that we might run into.
Organizations typically face complexities
like managing latency, trade-offs, and
evolving human governance models, training
staff to manage automation while balancing
oversight and efficiency is crucial.
It is like shifting from manual
firefighting to designing the firewalls.
We focus on secure data pipelines.
Organizational adaptability.
Despite these challenges, the path to
reliable automation is pretty clear.
Moving on to summarize some of the
takeaways, a better collaboration
between human oversight and mission
processes is very essential.
There are three things.
That I wanted to highlight,
continuous monitoring.
Regularly evolve your practices
to match operational needs.
Design boundaries.
Focus on the thresholds that
maintain your accountability.
The third and final one, embed governance.
Keep it within your control
planes for real-time oversight.
And that brings us to the end.
Thank you for your time today.
Let's build systems that
are safe as they are fast.