Hello everybody.
My name's Sanjeev.
Today my top is ensuring it
infrastructure, reliability through
robust monitoring and alerting.
So this slide is about introduction.
What is monitoring what is alerting.
So let's begin by understanding.
Why monitoring and alerting are
essential to system reliability in the
cloud in today's fast moving digital
infrastructure cloud system handle
huge amount of dynamic workload.
Any small issue like high latency.
Memory spikes can quickly
snowball into service disruption.
That's where monitoring alert, step
in monitoring tool give us a real time
visuality into system health metric
like CPU uses latency and through output
allow us to detect problem easily.
Actionable alerting is just as important.
It is not enough to get notified.
Alerts must be meaningful,
targeted, and free from noise.
This helps avoid alert fat,
which happens when team gets
over blamed with non-critical
alerts and start ignoring them.
As the research showed, integrating
reverse tool like Datadog New Relic
reduced downtown downtime approximately
50% while improving resource utilization.
Ultimately, this translate
into greater system stability,
fastest incidents response, and
better experience for the users.
Why monitor matters.
Now let's talk about why monitoring is
critical in today's cloud environment.
Cloud platform like AWS Azure
and Google Cloud have made it
incredibly easy to scale application,
but that flexibility comes.
Complexity service services are spread
across regions API, microservices,
containers, and sometimes even
across hybrid or multi-cloud setup.
In such dynamic system,
things can go wrong fast.
You might see unexpected
latency, intermittent failure,
or even complete outage.
And often without a monitoring system
in place, you wouldn't know until
you, until user start complaining.
Monitoring tool XA eyes and ears.
They continuously track performance
indication and system health in real
time without this layer of observability.
You are essentially flying blind.
You are reacting after the
fact rather than productivity.
So solving issue in essence,
monitoring, safety, your approach
from being reached to preventative.
It's become your early ING
system, helping to maintain system
reliability, performance, and trust.
So what are the tools in action?
Let's look at the tools that
bring monitoring to life
in real world environment.
I have evaluated three popular monitoring
tool that is premature and open
source metrics based monitoring tool.
Great for containerized environmental
like Kubernetes number, those.
Number two is Datadog e-commerce
assess solution that integrate well
across cloud service and provides
powerful dashboard and alerts.
And number three is like New Relic
known for application performance
monitoring, real time observability,
and user experience tracking.
These tools were tested across.
Three major cloud platform
that is AWS Azure Google Cloud.
In addition to simulated environments,
they were deployed in a real world health
insurance company using Micro soft Azure.
This added practical depth testing
how these tools perform under.
Actual workload such as high
traffic during claim processing
and compliance driven application.
The goal was to understand their impact
on latency, resource users throughout
and cost, and most importantly, how they
help detect and resolve issue easily.
How they help detect.
Resolve.
Easily.
This hands-on deployment gave us
valuable insight into the strength
and trade of each tool in both
test and production environments.
Now let's talk about the
essential factor to monitor.
Essential factor to monitor one is
latency throughout output, CPUN,
memory users and operation cost.
Let's go one by one when it comes
to the monitoring, knowing what to
measure, it just as important as having.
Right tools.
Let's walk through the four essential
factor that need to be tracked.
Number one, latency.
Latency.
This measures the time it takes for
a system to respond to a request.
High latency can frustrate user
and signal system slow down or
backend issue through output.
This is how many request or transaction
your system can handle per second.
A high thought put means better
stability and more efficiency.
Resource utilization.
C-P-U-C-P-U-N Memory uses monitoring
these tells you how you, your
infrastructure is being used.
It spikes many indicates performance
bottleneck or in efficient
application operation cost.
That is also one factor.
Other overheaded overlooked, but.
Critical monitoring itself use resources
and some tools incur additional costs.
You need to track this.
Two, ensure that the benefit of
monitoring overweights the expense.
These metrics to together give you
comprehensive view of system health.
They help.
Identify patterns, bottlenecks,
and opportunity to improve
performance before user affected.
Now let's let's see, like what
was like outcomes from using
those tools, monitoring tools.
That is a real world impact.
What is the impact for it?
Now let's look at the real world
impact these monitoring tools had
across different cloud platform.
After integrating tools like
Datadog and New Relic miserable
improvement were observed on AWS
latency drop from a hundred MS to
80 milli per second on all Azure.
Through output increased from
1900 to 2,400 requests per
second across all platform.
Overall, downtown was
reduced by around 15%.
These number might seem iCal at
first, but in cloud environment,
especially with high traffic.
Or mission mission critical application.
Even a few millisecond of latency
or a few percentage point of uptime
can make a huge difference in user
experience and business opportunities.
This shows how effective monitoring tool
doesn't just provide visuality, it's.
Actively help you optimize performance,
scale smarter, and deliver a
more reliable service or users.
These kinds of performance gain also
build trust, and with stakeholders,
especially in regulated environment like
healthcare, finance, where downtime and
delay can have serious consequences.
Let's talk now, trade off and
overheads with monitoring ly board
system performance and reliability.
It is important to understand that
it comes with trade-offs first.
There is a CPU uses overhead in the study.
CPU uses increased by five
to 8% at cross platform after
integrating monitoring tools.
That's because of these tools.
Collect, analyze, and sometimes
visualize washed amount of
data in real var real time.
Second, visa rise of
operation cost around.
12% on average.
This include the cost of the
tools themself and the extra cloud
resources needed to run them.
The these overhead are not necessarily
bad, but they need to be managed smartly.
For instance, avoid full stack
monitoring if only application
level inside are needed.
Tune data collection intervals.
Do you need metrics every second
or every five minute enough?
We need to think on that as well,
monitoring the most critical KPI
instead of tracking everything.
The key takeaway here is that the
monitoring should be a strategic
hand done the benefit far.
The cost, but blindly enabling
all features can lead to the
resource waste and unexpected Bill.
Now let's talk about the preventing alert.
So one of the most common challenges
monitoring is alerting for you when
teams are bombarded with so many alerts.
That they start ignoring
them, even the critical ones.
To prevent this, we need to external and
intelligent alerting, not just noise.
Start by defining a smart threshold.
For example, don't alert when CPU
uses goes over 50% alert when it says
above 90% for a sustained period.
Second use dynamic baselines.
Tools like Datadog and New Relic
can learn what normal looks like.
An alert only hand behavior deviates
significantly group related alerts
together using alert correlation
so teams see the bigger picture
rather than isolated symptoms.
Most importantly, make sure
alert are routed to the right
team with proper context.
So responder know exactly
what action to take.
By doing this, you keep your team
focused on meaningful incidents,
reduced burnout, and respond to real
problem faster in thought effectively.
Alerting should be guide not over.
What may be the best practices?
Now let's bring all together
with some best practices for
effective monitoring and alerting.
Choose the right tool
for your environment.
Not every tool fits every
use case, for example.
Premises is ideal for the
Kubernetes environment with Datadog.
While Datadog signs in hybrid cloud
setup with a strong integration needs
continuously evaluate the cost benefit.
Tradeoff monitoring should be
enhanced reliability, not drain
resources, monitoring what matter
most and fine tune data collection.
Frequency to avoid over conjunction
focus on ana actionable KPIs.
Track metrics that directly impact user
experience and system health latency
error rates throughout output ETC.
Avoid getting lost of divinity
metrics integration, LRT into
the incident response workflow.
Use tool like page duty, slack,
or ServiceNow, to automatically
notify the right team and reach
alerts with contact and speed up
resolution, review and refine.
Alert regularly system, and
evolve what was critical six
months ago might not be today.
Keep alert, up to date, and align
with current performance goal.
Following these practice, ensure
your monitoring setup is efficient,
scalable, and responsive, not
just technically sound, but also
aligned with business needs.
Other way and or future scope
may be AI driven monitoring, so
predict issue before they occur.
So it can be achieved by the ai.
Use AI to analyze pattern
and defect anomalies early.
Preventing outage and performance drops.
Second optimize performance automatically
enable self healing system and dynamic
threshold that has just in real time
reducing the need for manual oversight.
Third, reduce cost and resource users
implement smart auto-scaling energy.
Percent workflow placement and
noise, reducing alert system
to lower operation cost.
Now let's go to the conclusion.
So looking ahead, the future of
monitoring is the increasingly being
saved by AI and machine learning.
Traditional monitoring relies heavily on.
Predefined threshold and aesthetics
rule, but with AI driven monitoring
system can learn from historical
data, detect complex patterns, and
even predict issue before they occur.
Imagine being alert not because
of CPU just spike, but because
the system learned that.
I learned that a specific pattern
of memory and disc behavior
typically precedes a failure.
That is the power of prediction,
monitoring product predictive monitoring.
This approach helps reduce the need for
continuous manual monitoring, minimizing
alert noise and false positives.
Optimize.
Resource allocation Dally
based on expected demand.
AI can also help with auto remediation
where a minor issue are fixed.
Without human inter intervention, saving
time and improving uptime, the next
generation of tools will be smarter, more
adaptive, and better aligned with the.
Evolving complexity of cloud native
environment like container and service
serverless organizing that embrace
these technology only will gain
completely as through the higher system
relevance and lower operation cost.
Thank you for listening me and let
me know if you have any question.
Thank you.