Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42 Site Reliability
Engineering 2025 conference.
My name is Ravata, and today I'm going
to talk about the alert and monitoring
and the strategies for identifying
and resolving performance bottlenecks.
So let's just get started.
System failures can have
severe real world consequences.
Impacting finances, safety, and
critical infrastructure in finance.
Trading glitches like the 20 20
12 Night capital group trading
algorithm failure resulted in a
loss of 440,000,045 minutes while
banking outages disrupt transactions.
Another example is the Amazon Web
Services outage in 2021, which caused
major losses across multiple businesses
while banking outages, disrupt
transactions, and customer access.
Healthcare, failure in medical
devices or hospital regard systems
can delay treatments and risk lives.
Transportation failures such
as aviation software crashes or
self-driving car malfunctions led to.
Delays accidents and safety concerns.
Power grid failures like the 2003 North
American blackout affect millions while
cyber attacks on infrastructures such
as the colonial pipeline attack, disrupt
supply chain, and fuel availability.
Data breaches.
Like the 2017 Equifax hack exposes
sensitive information leading
to financial fraud and theft.
Even defense and system space
systems failure can compromise
national security affecting military
operations and GPS navigations system.
Downtime in major tech platforms
can hurt businesses and
impact global communication.
Faulty AI decision making in areas
like fraud detection, hiring,
and credit approvals can lead to
unfair biases and legal challenges.
These risks highlight the need
for a robust engineering rigorous
testing, cybersecurity measures and
resilience system designs to prevent
the catastrophic failures and ensure
reliability in critical services.
System failures can severely disrupt
business operations by halting
critical services, delaying production,
and causing financial losses.
For example, software outages can
prevent employees from accessing
key data or applications leading to
inefficiency and missed deadlines.
In customer facing systems, failures
can result in poor user experience,
loss sales, and damage reputation.
Payment processing issues can hold
transactions affecting revenues.
Supply chain disruptions due to system
errors can delay production, delivery
and create inventory shortages.
Additionally, data breaches or
cybersecurity attacks can compromise
sensitive information leading to legal
liabilities and loss of customer trust.
Ensuring system reliability is
crucial for maintaining smooth and
continuous business operations.
Monitoring is essential for
maintaining uptime and system health.
By providing realtime insights into
system performance, it helps detect
issues early, such as slowdowns
errors or security breaches before
they can even escalate into a major.
Problems.
With proactive monitoring, teams can
quickly address potential failures,
minimizing downtime, and reducing
the impact on users and operations.
It also allows for continuous
optimization, ensuring systems run
efficiency and securely by tracking
key metrics like server load,
response times, and error rates.
Monitoring helps maintain a stable
environment, ensuring consistent C service
delivery, and preventing disruptions.
Alerting plays a critical role in
ensuring rapid issue resolution
by notifying team about potential
problems as soon as they arise.
It provides realtime alerts based
on predefined thresholds, enabling
immediate action before issues
impact users or system performances.
By prioritizing alerts according to
severity, teams can focus on critical
issues first, reducing downtime and
minimizing business disruptions.
Prompt alerts also ensures that the
right team members are informed, enabling
faster collaboration, and quicker
resolutions in fast paced environment.
Effective alerting helps maintain system
health, improves response times and
ensures continuous service availability.
Monitoring is the ongoing process
of tracking system health to ensure
optimal performance and stability.
It involves continuously observing
key system metrics, such as
server load, response times, and
error rates to identify potential
issues before they escalate by
maintaining constant visibility.
Monitoring helps detect anomalies,
performance bottlenecks,
and security threats early.
Allowing teams to take proactive measures.
This continuous oversight ensures system
remains reliable, efficient, and secure.
Minimizing downtime and supply.
Supporting smooth business operations
monitoring is essential for maintaining a
healthy high performance IT environment.
Key components of monitoring include data
collection, analysis, and visualization.
Data collection involves gathering logs.
Sorry.
Log metrics and events from servers,
applications, and infrastructure
to capture system behaviors.
Analysis is the process of detecting
patent trends and potential issues.
By examining this data for anomalies
or irregularities, visualization helps
in interpret system performance through
dashboards and reports, providing
clear insights into the system health.
Together.
These components enable proactive
management and ensure quick identification
and resolution of problems leading
to improved uptime and efficiency.
Infrastructure monitoring focuses
on tracking the health of the
underlying hardware, such as
CPU usage and disc utilization.
This helps ensure that the system
resources are not overburdened
preventing slowdowns or crashes.
Application performance monitoring.
Also called as a PM, measures
the performance of application by
monitoring response times and database
queries, allowing system to identify
bottlenecks and optimize performance.
Network monitoring focuses on latency.
Packet loss and connectivity issues,
ensuring smooth and communication between
systems and minimizing disruptions.
Lastly, securing monitoring involves
tools for anomaly detection and
intrusion detection systems, which
helps identify unusual activity
or potential security breaches.
These four areas together provide
a comprehensive approach to
maintaining system health, optimizing
performance, and ensuring security.
Effective monitoring helps identify
performance bottlenecks early,
allowing steam to detect slowdowns,
high resource usage or inefficiencies
before they impact operations.
This enables proactive problem resolution,
which ensures our addressed before
they escalate into major failures.
Reducing downtime and minimizing
business disruptions by continuously
tracking key system metrics.
Monitoring help ensure system stability
and smooth user experience preventing
unexpected crashes or performance issues.
A well monitored system runs
efficiently, maintains reliability,
and keeps users satisfied.
Ultimately supporting seamless business
operations and long-term success.
So components of alerting.
Alerting its process of notifying
teams when an issue arises,
ensuring that potential problems are
addressed before they are impacted.
Users,
it allows it.
It works by triggering real time
alerts based on predefined thresholds,
such as high CPU usage, slow
response times, or security threats.
Alerting prevents unnoticed system
failures by continuously monitoring
critical components and immediate
flagging anomalies, reducing
the risk of prolonged downtime.
It plays a crucial role in ensuring
quick response time to incidents,
enabling teams to act swiftly,
resolve issues efficiently, and
maintaining system stability.
Effective alerting minimizes disruptions,
protects users experience, and
helps maintain business continuity.
Alerting consists of key
components, triggers notification
channel and escalation policies.
Triggers are the conditions that active
alerts such as high CPU usage, server
downtime, or security breaches, these
predefined threshold ensures that
teams are notified the moment an alert.
Arises issue arises.
Notification channels determine how
alerts are delivered, including email,
SMS Slack or PagerDuty, ensuring that the
right people are informed instantly as
soon as the issue is started occurring.
Escalation policies ensures that
if an alert is not acknowledged,
it is forwarded to the next
level, guaranteeing a response.
Together these components create an
efficient alert ring system that helps
teams react quickly, prevent unnoticed
failures, and maintain system stability.
To build an effective alert system,
it's important to set clear alert
thresholds so teams are notified
only when issue truly need attention.
Ensuring alerts and actions are
helps prevent unnecessary noise
by providing relevant details
and clear steps for resolution.
Prioritizing alerts is crucial to avoid
alert fatigue, ensuring that critical
issues are addressed first while lower
priority alerts don't overwhelm teams.
Finally, using automation to resolve
common issues helps reduce manual
interventions by automatically handling
repetitive problems, improve response
times, and maintaining system stability.
A well-structured alerting should keep
operations as smooth and teams efficient.
An effective alerting system
can cause serious challenges.
Too many alerts can overwhelm
teams leading to alert fatigue.
Where critical issues may be
ignored, false positives and
false negatives create confusion.
False positive triggers, unnecessary
responses while false negative
causes real issues to go unnoticed.
Delaying action, lack
of context in alerts.
Makes it difficult to diagnose
problem quickly as alerts
without relevant details.
Force teams to spend
extra time investigating.
Finally, delayed responses can turn minor
issues into major outages, impacting
system uptime and user experiences.
A well tuned alerts strategy
ensures timely, accurate,
and actionable notifications.
To improve alerting effectiveness,
it's essential to tune alert
thresholds, carefully balancing
sensitivity to avoid both excessive
noise and missed issues implementing.
Structured on-call rotations
ensures that alerts are handled
effectively, preventing burnouts,
and ensuring 24 by seven coverage.
Leveraging ai, ML based anomaly
detection helps identify unusual patterns
and reduce false positives, making
alerting smarter and more precise.
Lastly, ensuring logs and metrics
provide enough enough context allows
teams to quickly diagnose and resolve
issues without unnecessary delays.
Optimized alerting system enhances
the response times, reduce fatigues
and maintains system reliability.
An effective alerting process
follows a structured approach.
Step one would be monitoring system
health and collecting data to track
key performance metrics in real time.
Analyze logs and metrics.
Detect two.
Detect anomalies and identify potential
issues before they actually escalate.
Third would be a step up alerts based on
the critical thresholds, ensuring teams
are notified only when action is needed.
Step four would be automate responses
for faster recovery, reducing manual
interventions, and minimizing downtime.
Step five would be continuously
refining alert rules to improve
efficiency, reducing false alarms,
and ensuring alert remains relevant.
The structured approach helps
maintain system stability and
ensures the rapid issue resolution.
There are various tools available
for monitoring and alerting.
Ramus and Grafana are popular
open source solutions.
That provide powerful monitoring
and visualization capabilities.
Datadog and New Relic are commercial
observability platforms, offering
real-time insights, application
performance monitoring, and
an advanced analysis for cloud
environments providers offer built-in
solutions like AWS CloudWatch.
Azure Monitor and Google Cloud operations,
which integrates seamlessly with
cloud services to track performances,
detect issues, and trigger alerts.
Choosing the right tool depends
on system requirement, scalability
needs, and budget, ensuring.
Efficient monitoring and
proactive issue resolutions.
When choosing monitoring tool.
Consider your team's expertise,
budget in budget, integration needs
and specific monitoring requirements.
The right tool ensures seamless
tracking, quick alerts, and
efficient issue resolution.
Effective incident management and
alerting, rely on the right tools.
Page of duty and ops chiney are powerful
incident management platforms that help
team handle alert automation workflows
and escalate critical issues to the right
personal, ensuring quick resolution.
Slack, VictorOps and Microsoft
Teams enhanced collaboration
with built-in alerting, allowing
teams to receive notifications,
discuss issues in real time, and
coordinate responses efficiently.
Additionally built in cloud alerting
solutions like AWS CloudWatch Alarms,
Azure Monitor Alerts, and Google
Cloud Operation Alerts provide native
monitoring and automated notifications
within cloud environments, helping
teams detect and address issues
before they escalate together.
These tools enables fast response
times, streamlined communication,
and improved system reliability.
Imagine a scenario where an e-commerce
platform experiences a sudden surge
in traffic during a holiday sale,
but due to a poor monitoring system,
the system fails to detect the high
CPU usage and database overload.
As a result, pages low started loading
slowly, transaction fails, and customer
abandon their cards leading to lost
revenue and customer dissatisfaction.
The issue remains unnoticed for
hours, significantly impacting
the business operations and sales.
After implementing proper monitoring
and alerting the company set up a
real-time performance, tracking automated
alerts and AI driven anomaly detection.
Now when traffic spikes alert, notify
the teams immediately allowing them to
scale resources and optimize database
queries before user experience issues.
As a result, downtime is reduced by 60%.
Response time improved by 40%, and
customer satisfaction scores increases.
This example highlights the critical role
of monitoring and alerting in preventing
failures, ensuring system stability,
and maintaining business success.
To build an effective monitoring and
alerting strategy, it's essential
to follow the best practices.
First, define key performance indicators
that matters most to your system,
such as uptime, response time, error
rates, and re resources utilizations.
These metrics help track system health
and detect potential issues early.
Second, choose the right monitoring
and alerting tool that aligns with
your infrastructure, whether open
source solutions like ERs and Grafana
or commercial platforms like Datadog
and newly finally continuously
irate and improve by analyzing
system behavior, refining alert.
Thresholds and leveraging
automation to enhance efficiency.
A well optimized approach ensures
reliability, minimizes downtime, and
improves overall system performance.
Real-time dashboards provide a
centralized view of system health by
displaying key metrics such as CPU
usage, memory consumption, network
activity, and application response times.
These dashboards offer instant
visibility into performance trends,
helping teams detect and address
issues before they escalate.
For example, a server monitoring dashboard
might track CPU load and disc usage.
While an application performance
dashboard could display
response times and error rates.
Security dashboards can also
provide insights into login
attempt and potential threats.
Real time insights enable proactive
issue resolution by alerting teams
to anonymize anomalies as they occur
instead of reacting to system failures
after they impacted the users.
Teams can identify pattern, predict
potential failures, and take preventive
actions, ensuring stability, reducing
downtime, and improving user experience.
They allow customization to display
the most relevant KPIs for different
teams, such as latency error rates,
throughput for engineering or user.
Engagement metrics
metricses for product teams.
Monitoring dashboards, consolidate
data from multiple sources like logs,
APMs, infra metrics, metricses into a
single view, enabling faster diagnosis,
streamlined communication, and informed
decision making across stack holders.
The image shows a monitoring
dashboard in Azure.
From Azure Monitoring Services this is for
a CH one real retail app AI application.
It presents real time insights
into system performance across
four key areas, usage, reliability,
responsiveness, and browser performance.
Usage displays, unique session and
user currently 6.5 a users showing
trends over the past 24 hours.
You can change this time window and
see it for 12 hours, 48 hours, seven
days, or any specified time window
reliability highlights the field request
with 16.63 K and server exceptions
helping identify system issues.
Responsiveness tracks server response
times, which is 1.2 seconds as an average.
And CP utilization is 15.15.
Ensuring system efficiency.
Browser performance monitor, average
page load times 73 milliseconds
network and 5 37 milliseconds.
Client and browser errors.
This dashboard helps teams quickly
access system health, performance
trends, and potential failures,
enabling proactive troubleshooting.
The future of monitoring and alerting is
evolving with our advanced technologies.
AI powered anomaly detection is
transforming how systems identify issues.
Using machine learning to detect
unusual pattern and reduce false
positives, predictive men, maintenance,
and automated issues as solution,
allow teams to proactively address
potential failures before they occur.
Minimize downtime and
improving reliability.
Enhanced integration across cloud and
on-prem systems ensure seamless monitoring
in hybrid environments, providing a
unified view of system performance.
Additionally, there is an increased
focus on security monitoring with
AI driven threats, detection, and
real-time alert, helping organization
protect against cyber threats.
These advancements are making
monitoring more intelligent,
proactive, and efficient.
Key takeaways.
Effective monitoring and
alerting are essential for
maintaining system stability.
Monitoring provides valuable insights
by continuously tracking performance,
helping teams detect and prevent potential
failures before they actually escalate.
Alerting ensures a quick response
by notifying the right team in real
time, minimizing the impact of issues
and reducing downtime by implementing
best practices such as settling clear
thresholds, using automations and
refining alert rules, organizations can
significantly enhance system reliability.
A well-structured monitoring and
alerting strategy led to better
performance, improved user experience,
and seamless business operations.
As applications, scale and
architecture evolve, monitoring
strategies should be revisited to
ensure continued effectiveness.
Regular audits, feedbacks, loops, and AI
driven insights can improve detection,
accuracy, and reduce false positives.
Example, if a company shifts from
a monolithic to a microservices,
architecture monitoring tools
must evolve to track interservice
communication and dependencies.
Thank you all for your
time and attention today.
I appreciate the opportunity to ensure
to opportunity to share and in share
my insights on monitoring and alerting.
I would love to hear your
questions or thoughts.
Feel free to ask or
share your experiences.
If you would like to connect or
discuss further, you can reach me
out at my email or at LinkedIn,
which is mentioned in this slide.
I look forward to continue
this conversation outside
of this conference as well.
Thank you.