Hello everyone, and
thank you for joining me.
I'm excited to explore how site
reliability engineering practices
can power high performance payment
systems in emerging markets.
Now with the limited banking
infrastructure, but widespread mobile
use, these digital payments play a
crucial role in bringing financial
services to underserved communities.
Let me move on to the next slide.
Let's begin with an overview of the
technical architecture that supports
financial inclusion in these regions.
I'll walk you through how various
components like APIs, blockchain,
and analytics and hybrid cloud
edge setups come together to build
a resilient payment ecosystem.
Now the objective is to
deliver a reliable, low latency
transition transactions.
I'm sorry, even in areas with
intermittent connectivity.
Moving on to the next slide.
Emerging markets present a unique
challenge, power outage, limited internet
speeds and regulatory complexities.
Now.
For overcoming all these barriers, we
need a fault tolerant design offline
capabilities and adaptable compliance
frameworks to navigate these obstacles.
Now think of rural areas where
two G or 3G networks dominate
and power might be out for hours.
Our systems must still function.
Now that's where we are
talking about reliability.
Reliability metrics that really matter.
The reliability metrics become
essential in measuring how well we
perform under these Haas conditions.
Now, hybrid chlor cloud edge models often
show near perfect reliability, but then
processing locally and a synchronizing
one's connectivity is risk stop.
That kind of an approach is very good
for in these kind of situations of these.
Further, these approaches help maintain
97 percentage or higher transaction
success rates, which already impacts trust
and user adoption in underserved areas.
Moving on, let's look at specific
SRE practices that have driven
significant improvements in reliability.
All of these concepts are very
important for reliability, like we
were talking about in the previous
slides, where there are several
other infrastructure situations that
we'll have to take take care of now,
advanced observability and distributing
tracing across all the services and
helping pinpoint issues and complex
heterogeneous environments all those
things is very important in this aspect.
And again, automated remediation.
And how engineering prepare
our systems to self-heal and
recover from regional failures.
That is very important in the
situation where we are talking
about power infrastructure not
being available for multiple hours.
Now, coupled with procession, SLOs,
these strategies have cut payment
failures by over 60 percentage.
We move on to the next slide.
So to implement these SRE strategies
effectively, we follow a phased roadmap.
First, we establish a baseline
metrics and simple monitoring.
Then we introduce distributor
tracing and AVA testing.
Finally, we move to AI
driven productive analytics.
Now, this approach provides incremental
wins while steadily advancing
towards a robust mature reliability.
Cultural change is equally important.
Reliability champions must be embedded
in dev teams, so that is equally as
permanent as the other aspects of this.
Moving on, SRE in emerging markets also
calls for a context adjusted SLIs in SLOs.
For instance a 99.95% success rate
might be adjusted to 97 percentage in
rural zones where connectivity is beyond
our control Now, ensuring fairness
and realistic targets just to make
sure you have a fair ground to play.
Now we pay tailoring these service level
objectives to real world conditions.
We keep teams motivated and still
accountable for what they can influence.
Moving on.
AI powered capabilities amplify
our resilience, shifting from
reactive to predictive reliability.
Now mission learning flags, unusual
transaction patterns, readouts data
around poor networks and blocks a
suspicious activity in real time.
With ai, up to 87 percentage
of the potential incidents are
caught before the effect uses.
That's a very huge jump from
threshold based systems.
Now let's examine a real world case.
Wherein we are talking, we
are gonna talk about a rural
healthcare payments platform.
This was one of the very
important and widely recognized
implementation world case.
That real world case that was
discussed in several areas.
Serving millions of patients under two
G connectivity and frequent power autos.
They've applied offline first
architecture and regional SLOs.
The result transaction reliability sold
from 78 percentage to over 99 percentage,
which is almost a hundred percentage.
And patient satisfaction
jumped significantly, which
is crucial in this aspect.
So for a technical deep dive service,
mesh architectures have shown tremendous
values in these payment environments.
Oh, where starting networking,
security observability of mesh empowers
apps to focus on business logic,
even in a hybrid or legacy system.
Now in several cases, incident
resolutions has become 83
percentage faster, and security
incidents dropped by 76 percentage.
Once policies were uniformly enforced
across all services, now that uniformity
accounts for making sure that your systems
are robust, that performance oriented,
and you have a very highly secure system.
Moving on.
I just wanna quickly wrap up with
some key takeaways for tech leaders
aiming to become, bring financial
services to emerging markets.
First, adapt, SRE Best
practices to local realities.
Use the region specific SLOs and offline
capabilities like we were talking
about, how to make sure we have a
fair play on for every one of us that.
Secondly, design for resilience
in corporate edge computing,
caching, and robust synchronization.
Third, remain user centered reliability,
must directly enhance financial inclusion.
Lastly, adopt a phased approach to
implementation, and these will make sure
we have a great implementation in place.
So finally, thank you.
Thank you so much for your attention.
I appreciate your time and I hope
these strategies for context of
our SRE help you build reliable,
inclusive, and payment systems.
If you have any questions or would like
additional details, please let me know
and be allowed to discuss and how we
can collaborate to advance financial
inclusion in challenging environments.
Thank you very much.
Bye.