Hey everyone.
I'm Li a senior, a software
engineer in the FinTech industry.
Today we are gonna take a technical
deep dive of mobile payment systems,
the end-to-end flow, and how they're
handled in the real world, dealing with
I potency and synchronous processing
and making it a scalable solution.
I.
Mobile payments have transformed global
finance offering, enhanced convenience,
security, and efficiency through
various mobile payment platforms like
digital wallets, apple Pay, Google
Pay, alipay and other forms of mobile
payments using QR codes, et cetera.
We'll examine the innovations
driving the revolution and challenges
ahead for the worldwide adoption.
We'll also discuss the role of SE
Ari in the high stake financial,
mobile payments environment.
Site reliability engineering plays
a crucial role in maintaining the
high up time demanded by the payments
platform, SREs practice in and practices
and insurance fault tolerance, rapid
instant response and continuous
monitoring that prevent costly
outages and security breaches in this
mission critical financial systems.
The global eruption trends has
been on the rise throughout the
world, and you can see the numbers.
People who use mobile payments are
in hundreds of millions in each
country, and the transactions are
happening in billions of dollars.
Now let's take a quick look at the
players in the mobile payments flow.
The who's, who in the payments
processing flow in general, customer
this is the individual making
a purchase and initiating the
payments using their mobile device.
Merchant, I. The, this is the
business of the person accepting
the payments for goods or services.
It can be through a point of sale,
physical device or online checkout or
some me medium of payment acceptance.
They interact with the customer
and the payments processing
system, which is the backend flow.
They're the middle man.
The third person is the acquirer.
This is the financial institution
that process the payments
on behalf of the merchant.
Sometimes they provide the merchant
with the point of sale terminal device.
It could be the payments.
A processor or the payment gateway
to acquirer receives and forwards the
transaction data for authorization
the hold funds temporarily during
the settlement, and finally deposit
funds in the merchants account.
Issue.
This is the financial institution
that issued the customer's credit
or debit card, which is linked to
the mobile wallet used for payment.
They verify the customer account
details and balances, authorized
transactions and debit customer's
account for approved payments.
The other other player is the payment
network, which access an intermediary
between the acquirer and issuer, enabling
communication and transaction routing
for authorization and settlement.
Some of the most common payment
networks could be the card
brands like Visa, MasterCard,
African Express Payment Gateway.
It's a secure interface.
Connecting the merchants mean of accepting
payments like the pause or online
checkout UI experience to the payment
processor and the payment network.
They support and integrate with various
payment methods and payment networks.
They also offer fraud detection
and prevention tool risk
management and verification.
It, they secure the payments
information as it travels
through the transaction process.
It forwards the transaction data
to the appropriate payment network.
For further processing, token service
provider secures the mobile and online
place online payments by replacing
sensitive call card holder data with
nonsensitive substitutes like tokens.
Token service provider can be the payment
card networks like Visa Master Card.
They generate and manage token specific
to their respective car payment.
This can be the payment gateway provided
to example Stripe, PayPal, tree Braintree
provide tokenization service, which
enables a merchant to offer streamlined
checkout experiences where customers
don't have to reenter their card details.
Mobile provider, mobile wallet providers.
These provide the digital wallet app
that customers use to store their
payment card information securely and
conveniently to make mobile payments.
Some of the examples most of which
are most commonly used are Apple
Pay, Google Pay, Samsung, and Pay.
Venmo has their own wallet.
Alipay Capital One Wallet chase app.
Taking a deeper look into how
digital wallet works, they have
revolutionized how we make purchases
using our phones with just a few taps.
The core of these wallets is tokenization
the car details when added in a wallet.
The wallet provider replaces your
original card information with a token
obtained from a token service provider,
which we previously mentioned could
be a cardboard network provider or a
third party to organization service.
Token generation and mapping.
The token service provider creates a
secure mapping between the generated
token and the user real card information.
This map mapping is
stored in the token world.
This token a randomly generated
number access a substitute for
your actual card number, and is
safely stored at hardware level.
The token is linked to your device and
specific card, and it cannot be accessed
and cannot be used on other devices.
Let's take a look at the end
of end-to-end flow of actual
payment going through this flow.
When we are making a payment
with a digital wallet
customer initiates a payment.
The customer chooses to pay pay
using their digital wallet at a
physical store or an online checkout.
They authenticate their
identity on their device.
It could be through a fingerprint, a face
ID, or a pin to unlock the digital wallet.
Tokenization, as I previously mentioned,
we have a secure token linked to the
customer actual car store on the device.
If it's a in-store purchase, the
customer tabs or waves the device near
the merchants contactless point of sale
terminal using a nearfield communication,
which we commonly known as NFC.
The token is transmitted to
the point of sale terminal.
If it's an online checkout, the customer
selects their digital wallet at checkout.
The token is securely passed
to the merchant's website.
The merchant's payment gateway.
After the device, after the token is
transferred to the merchant website
or the terminal, the, it's passed
to the merchant payment Gateway.
The tokenized data is passed to the
merchant payment gateway, the gateway
access in secure intermediary verifying.
Encrypting the data.
The payment information is verified
for fraud detection and it is routed
to appropriate payment card network.
The card network receives the
transaction request and ask for
authorization from the issuer to
ensure sufficient funds are available.
The issuer verifies the customer account
balance and the transaction limit
and any other security measures and
authorizes it the network, putting a hold
on the funds in the customer account.
The authorization message, travel
back through the card network payment
processor and the gateway to the point
of sale, terminal or online checkout.
The customer receives the confirmation
of the successful payment, the payment
gateway I aggregates the authorized
transaction from the merchant throughout
that day, or specific interval.
The acquirer receives from the card
network based on the settle transactions
based on the response from Payment
Gateway during the settlement time.
The acquirer then deposit deposits
the fund into merchant's account
minus any processing fees.
There are many other ways of making
mobile payments across the globe.
And the flow might differ in a few ways.
One, one of the type is
a QR code based payment.
The customers can secure code
displayed by the merchant
using their mobile payment app.
The customer's app generates a payment
request with the transaction details
and sends it to the payment provider.
An example for this would be to would
be an Alipay or WeChat pay the customer
authenticates within their app using
as previously mentioned, of some kind
of biometrics or pin, and the payment
provider verifies their accountant
balance upon successful authorization.
The provider notifies both the customer
and merchant of the payment qr.
Code based payments often lead directly
involved often directly involve
debit card debit slash the credit
card of the customer's bank account,
or linked payment account within
the mobile payment app, bypassing
traditional card networks in some cases.
Sometimes it could be a card linked
to, in which case, tokenization
card networks, again come into play.
In the case of bank transfer apps some
of them examples will be like z the
customer enters the recipient details
or the merchant details in the case of
payments like example, their phone number
or email address link to their back.
Account funds are directly
transferred from the customer's
bank account to the recipient's.
Accounts offered in near real
time, the customer authenticates
now within their banking app
and the transfer is authorized.
These methods typically leverage
existing bank transfer networks,
like example a CH in us.
Faster payments in UK facilitating
direct account to account transfers.
Mobile payments process is a complex
ecosystem requiring careful design to
handle massive transaction volumes.
We need to ensure SEC security and
provide a seamless user experience.
This introduces unique
challenges for I impotency.
What is item impotency?
It's ensuring an operation applied
multiple times has the same
effect as it is applied once.
This is very important in the case of
the financial transactions because when
we make a transaction, we don't, and
by mistake, if we retry it or due to
accidental network calls at financial
transaction can be made twice, which and
despite being it applied multiple times,
the transaction should go only once.
Network.
Network interruptions are common on
mobile devices, which potentially
lead to duplicate requests or
unclear transaction statuses.
Sometime hardware configurations
or human error can lead to multiple
transaction requests or multiple
retries due to client error handling.
These increase the changes
of duplicate request.
Duplication of financial transactions
should be handled carefully to
avoid duplicate transfers and handle
retries and errors in a gracious way.
There are different methods to
follow to handle item potency
in financial transactions.
Let's go over them.
Some of the technical solutions.
Having an item potency key, which is the
most common approach, the key is a unique
identifier generator by client or in some
cases from the server side, which is the
payment gateway is included throughout
our payments processing request.
The server will be able to recognize
the key and prevent duplicate
processing request that this might
need a database constraints and
maintaining the transaction status.
If the key is not present in the
database, the system process the request.
If the key is found, system retrieves
the store result, which is, which might
be in process or completed, and return
it without reprocessing the transaction.
In addition to item potency key, A due
duplication video can be implemented to
define a timeframe during which duplicate
transaction requests are checked.
This duplication check can be done based
on customer merchant transaction account.
The window of this duplication window
time period may vary from case to case
when a payment request is received, the
system checks if an identical request
was processed within that time window.
Effective state management is
essential for maintaining I dependency.
The payments processing system should
be able to accurately track the state
of each transaction, even in the event
of system failures or network issues.
We should store the state of each
transaction in a per persistent
storage that can survive
system restarts and crashes.
We can use distributed caches
to quickly check duplicates and
retrieve transaction statuses.
Sometimes during payments processing,
we would duplicate requests due to
transaction failures or retrain logic on
the client side to handle such scenarios,
which we will, we, it's important to have.
Implementation of retries
with exponential backoff.
The request is retried after a
delay and this delay is increased
exponentially with each try.
Each retry like delays of one
second, the second transaction
with a delay of two seconds.
The third time delay with the
exponential increase of four seconds.
And eight seconds the next time, so on.
This helps in preventing duplicate
transactions caused by repeated
request due to temporary failures.
The delay increases exp exponentially
with each retry attempt, reducing the
load on the server, and increasing the
likelihood of successful processing.
I Item potency can also be handled
on the client by client side by ui,
handling it to an extent like disabling
payment button after the first click
to prevent the duplicate request.
If a transaction failed
due to temporary issues.
Provide a clear and safe way
for users to retry, ensuring a
proper item potency key is used.
So if the transaction is processed
and appropriate, status is provided.
Otherwise, retry with the
new I item potency key.
A robust transaction status
handling is also important.
We can provide imme immediate response
to the users about the request status
or do a synchronous processing of
transactions using polling or web
hooks to update the transaction status.
This leads the way to a
synchronous payments processing.
Modern applications demand, robust
user-friendly payment system that
cater to a variety of scenarios.
Traditional synchronous payments
processing often fall short,
leading to slow responses and
potential point of failures.
That's where the trio of message
queues, callbacks, and webhooks
step into enable efficient, robust,
and, and reliable asynchronous
payments processing message queues.
These are very important in case of
hand in case of handling asynchronous
payments processing requests,
and they help or also help in
handling traffic spikes gracefully.
Preventing system overload during
peak hours ensures payments are
processed, even if temporary errors
occur with dead letter queues.
Further digging in deeper of a
synchronous payments, processing,
callbacks and web hooks can be used.
They play a crucial role in facilitating
a synchronous payments processing.
A callback is a function that is passed
as an argument to another function,
which can be executed at a later time.
In the context of payments, a callback
can be used to handle real-time
notifications or updates about
the status of payment transaction.
Webhooks on the other hands are
user-defined HTTP callbacks that
are triggered by specific events.
When a payment event occurs such as a
successful transaction or a failure,
the payment gateway sends A-H-T-T-P
post request to a specified review,
URL, which is the webhook endpoint.
This allows the merchant servers
to receive instant updates about
the transaction status, even
if the original payment request
was processed as synchronously.
By using callbacks and webhooks,
merchants can enhance the user experience
by providing timely feedback about
payment outcomes while also improving
the efficiency and reliability of.
Of the payments processing systems,
callbacks and webhooks both facilitate
a synchronous payments processing and
online payments and mobile payments, but
they differ in how they're implemented
and how they communicate the information.
The direction of
communication is different.
Callbacks in the context of payments.
Callbacks usually involve the
server to server communication.
The payment processor directly
communicates with the merchant server
after a payment even has occurred.
This is usually set up during the
initial payment request where the
merchant specifies a return URL
to which the payment processor
will send a status updates.
Webhooks, unlike callbacks are set
up through, through a push mechanism.
So callbacks are a pull mechanism.
Web hooks are a push mechanism.
The merchant registers a webhook
URL with the payments processor.
And when an event related to the payment
occurs, like transaction success or
failure, or update the pyramid processes
and htp, HTTP post request with the
event details to the register, URL
the setup are differences between
the callbacks and the web hooks.
So the callbacks are typically defined
on a. Per request basis, meaning
they need to be set up every time
a payment request is initialized.
So like it's on the go webhooks these
are configured once at system or at
account level and can be reused across
multiple events and transaction.
Once said, the web hook listens
for events it's subscribed to
regardless of specific transaction.
So let's discuss about the use
cases for callbacks and WebBook.
Callbacks are generally used for
direct responses to a payment request,
often used for intermediate direction
handling right after a payment process
process for instance, taking the
user to a success or failure page.
There are more what webhooks are
more versatile and used for a broader
range of actions, such as updating
payment status in the database.
Sending email notifications or triggering
other backend process that do not
require immediate action from the users.
In terms of reliability, callbacks can be
susceptible to issues if the destination
URL isn't available immediately.
When the response is sent, this
could cause loss of information
if not properly managed.
Webhooks are typically designed
to handle failure better.
They can employ mechanisms
like retry, ensuring that data
eventually reaches its destination.
If there are even temporary
issues with the receiving server.
So in summary, while both callbacks
and webhooks aid in a synchronously
payments processing information webhooks
provide a more robust and flexible
solution suitable for automation task
beyond immediate transaction response.
Whereas callbacks are often limited
to handling direct and immediate
response to payment requests.
Okay, putting it all together.
Using asynchronous payment processing
for better experience during high traffic
loads we can use queues as digital post
offices communicating between different
microservices that process, the payments.
Use callbacks and webhooks for proper
updating the status of the transaction
that's been that's been going on.
This approach allows for a decoupled,
scalable, and responsive payment
system improving both user experience
and application reliability.
Not only in terms of making payments
great strides have been made in terms
of payment acceptance as well tap to
be on iPhone for contactless payments.
Gives merchants large and
small easy and secure way.
To accept contactless credit
card and debit cards or even
accept payments through apple Pay
and other digital wallets using
their iPhone or Android phones.
No additional hardware or payment
terminal is required on the Android side.
PayPal and Stripe also
provides something similar.
The payment processing flow is similar
when using your phone as, the point
of sale device, there is additional
step of payment service provider the
merchant app now, which initializes
the payment session with apple Payment
Framework or with PayPal or Stripe.
In a similar way.
The merchant app sends the transaction
to the payment process API, similar
to how the payment flows go through
once the information has been
transferred to the device securely.
Apple provides private a PS for
power and private payment process
to integrate with tap to pay for
token and session management and
configure payment per parameters.
Stripe provides this feature
through terminal Android SDK.
These can, these features can be
integrated easily into an iOS and
Android application, providing the ease
of accept and acceptance of payments
in various financial applications.
So all in all, some of the major
enabling technologies for mobile
payments and its large adoption
are the NFC technologies, QR codes,
tokenization, cloud infrastructures,
enabling highly scalable payments.
Site reliability engineering teams
are integral to the success of modern
payment technologies such as N-F-C-Q-R,
core and Tokenization Systems.
By ensuring the infrastructure
behind these technologies highly
reliable, secure, and scalable,
and is dealt with low latency.
SRE teams employ robust automation,
continuous monitoring, and effective
instant management to maintain
healthy systems and performance.
This proactive approach minimizes the
downtime and ensures fifth resolution
of issues and low latency, which
is crucial for processing real-time
transactions securely and efficiency.
Furthermore, their efforts in handling
token generation and management uphold
to uphold stringent security standards
are necessary for protecting sensitive
payment information and preventing fraud.
By optimizing the technology
infrastructure and refining instant
responses, SRE teams enhance user
experience and build customer trust,
which is essential for widespread our
adoption of these payment technologies.
The major success factor for mobile
payments is having an intuitive experience
for customers to to use to which makes
our mobile payments more adaptable.
We, having a wide range of
acceptance, network and banking,
interop, interoperability can
support that, can support and process
payments across different financial
institution and card networks.
Gives a great advantage in this market.
Ha having, or we if providing open source
SDKs and APIs to integrate with and
enables large range of options to to make
an access mobile payments, leveraging
them, the mobile payment solutions can
be integrated into existing merchant or
customer application checkout experiences.
This leads to better mobile
pen mobile payments penetration
and adoption in the market.
Security innovation is the key in
the success of mobile payments.
With large adoptions comes greater
chance of risk and frauds, advanced
fingerprints, facial recognition
and voice verification technologies
create unique identity sickness that
dramatically enhance account protection.
Using hardware level biometric, ver
verification has been a great boom.
SRD teams implement automated
candidate deployments for biometric
verification service, ensuring the high
availability with the low response times.
Military grade cryptography.
Pro cryptography protocols ensure
complete data security throughout
the entire transaction journey making
interception virtually impossible.
SRE practices include
secret rotation automation.
Encryption cer automation certificate
encryption monitoring and chaos
engineering tests that verify security
resilience during infrastructure failures.
Sophisticated machine learning algorithms
and risk verification continuously
analyze each transaction pattern to
identify and block suspicious activity
before fraudulent charges occur.
SRE Observable observability
platforms provide real-time metrics
or model performance with automated
rollbacks when a false positive
rates exceeds the defined threshold.
Layered security approach combines
something something you have know and
are creating multiple verification
barriers that significantly
reduce unauthorized access Risks.
SRE teams implemented distributed rate
limiting and circulators to protect
authentication service during traffic
spike and maintain sec consistent
security verification performance.
Okay, because of financial the, that we
are discussing here, we obviously have
financial regulation, data protection,
banking standards, and cross borders
rules through which we navigate SRE
teams implement automated compliance
monitoring with the realtime dashboards
that track regulatory requirements across
markets, ensuring 99.9 adherence to.
The changing financial standards SRE
practices include data re, residence
automation, consent management,
observability and chaos testing of privacy
controls to maintain regulatory compliance
while preserving the system reliability.
SRE designs design service level
objectives aligned technical
performance with regulatory
requirements, providing measurable
reliability metrics that both satisfy
banking needs and user expectations.
SRE teams deploy region
specific infrastructure.
Infrastructure with automated regulatory
checkpoints and edge computing
capabilities that maintain compliance
across diverse international jurisdiction.
There are some technical and practical
challenges in adoption of mobile payments.
One is the infrastructure gap.
Rural and developing areas face persistent
connectivity challenges with unreliable
or non-existent internet accesses,
creating digital payment deserts.
SRE team implements edge caching,
offline transaction queuing, and
progressive enhancement strategies
to maintain service availability,
even in areas with intermittent
connectivity, device limitations,
budget and legacy smartphones, like
advanced process and secure elements
necessary for implementing robust
encryption and authentication protocols
or storing encrypted information.
SRE practices include resource
aware degradation parts, lightweight
cryptographic alternatives, and
client capability detection to ensure
consistent service reliability.
Across di diverse device ecosystem,
there are interoperability issues.
Proper proprietary payments ecosystem
created fragmented user experience
forcing consumers to juggle multiple apps
and limiting merchant adoption rates.
SRE teams develop unified monitoring
dashboards and inputs implement
service mesh architecture with
standardized reliability metrics to
identify interoperability failures
before they impact the end users.
Backend integration, decades old
backend infrastructure and some
of the payments ecosystem built
on co COBOL and batch processing
struggles to interface with modern API
driven real time payments protocol.
SRE engineers deploy a release resilient
integration layers with circuit breakers.
Automated retry mechanisms and
comprehensive observability tooling to
maintain high transaction reliability
despite legacy system constraints.
There are some practical real world
barriers as well, which we cannot avoid.
That is the deep rooted nature
of cash preference and technical
technological ignorance and trust.
Trust issues are some of the barriers.
This is slowly changing with
the technology penetration
and mobile adoption globally.
Mobile payments is no exception
to cyber security risks through
malware threats and phishing.
Strong encryption is needed
for transaction request.
Otherwise, they can be exploited
by intercepting and alternating tra
transaction data over network through
kind of man in the middle attacks.
However, the future how's the
future looking from for mobile
payments is always good to look at.
So in with the mobile payments and
payments in general with the growth of
crypto, cryptocurrencies will be soon
supported in mobile payment platforms.
Frictionless transaction will
eliminate a checkout process entirely.
Systems will automatically identify users
and process payments with the help of IOT.
Another thing which we already
have in the market, but will still
grow in future is super apps.
These are all in one platform,
which will combine payments
with broader services, removing
interop, interoperability barriers.
These echo systems will centralize
the financial activities
with the other functions.
Let's quickly go over some more roles
of the SRE and overview of the of
the responsibility and the payments
processing and mobile payments.
SRE plays a critical role
in mobile payment systems.
In payment processing systems and
mobile payments SRE team bridge the gap
between development and operation, while
ensuring that the financials systems
meet stringent availability, latency
and compliance requirements, SRE teams
implement comprehensive monitoring
systems that detect anomalous payment
patterns and transaction velocities.
Maintaining hun high protection rate
through automated threat response
protocols and real time security.
Posture visualization SRE practices
will reshape a payment infrastructure
resilience through automated error
budgeting and chaos engineering
like self-healing payment network,
and predict outage prevention.
Ensuring data protection and
compliance with regulations by
implementing strong encryption.
Access controls are intrusion detection
systems and reg regular security audits.
Having a clear defined SLOs and SLIs
specific to mobile payments such as
transactions, success rate, latent of
processing, and system up times will
help in measuring and maintaining
the reliability of the services.
Predicting traffic patterns and scaling
infrastructure accordingly is crucial
to prevent outage during the peak
demand Sr. Utilizes historical data and
forecasting techniques for efficient
resource allocation during peak loads.
For example, during events like
Black Friday or holiday seasons.
SRE teams implement culturally responsive
monitoring systems and localized
reliability metrics to add address
adoption resistance and failure handling.
SRE teams deploy progressive
user experience patterns,
simplified authentication flows
and visual interface alternatives.
That respect cultural preferences while
maintaining high availability across
demographic, diverse user population.
So SREs have a really important
role in mobile payments.
Thank you for listening.
Hope you've got some insights into
the technical aspects of large
scale fault tolerant payments,
processing flows and the payments
processing systems and how they work.
In the case of mobile payments.
We have also discussed key factors
in the success and the rise of mobile
payments, so of the technical and
cultural barriers and the technological
advan advancements that are happening.
We have also discussed the
key and important role of SRE
in the payments ecosystem.
Once again, thank you.