Jumping into how micro frontends
are changing the way big
companies build their front ends.
These big all in one monolith
system, comes with a lot of
headaches, like everything being
connected too tightly, teams getting
block and tricky deployments.
Micro frontend, fix that
by splitting things into a
smaller parts, separated parts.
That way it easier to manage and scale.
The shift isn't just some new trend, it's
really a future for the modern apps and
with the AI stepping in, imagine the tools
that auto front end layouts based on user
behavior pattern it closer than you think.
Let's take a look at why
monolith front ends are tough.
When things are tightly connected,
changing one part can break
others that makes updates risky.
Then you are got team bottleneck.
When a lot of teams have to work on
the same code they get in each other
ways and deployments, they need ton
of testing and perfect timing, which
makes the whole thing stressful.
Over time, this builds up a technical
depth and everything slow down.
Microfund end helps by letting
you build a small, separated part
that don't mess with each other.
Microfund ends are all about
breaking things into smaller
parts, each with its own clear job.
Each part work on its own
and can use its own tools.
That means a team can pick whatever
framework and the libraries.
Work best for them.
They can also fully own a section of the
products from building to launching it.
And because each part can be launched
on its own, things move faster and there
are fewer dependencies to deal with.
It's a great way to give teams more
control and speed things up and
in the future, AI could even help
spot which part of your monolith
are ideal for splitting based on
code complexity and team velocity.
When building microfund 10, there
are some important ideas to follow.
First is domain driven design.
That means we split the app
based on real business areas.
On each part makes sense
and fit together well.
Next is loose coupling, which
just means the different part.
Don't rely too much on each
other so they can grow and
change without breaking things.
Resilient integrations
means if one part goes down.
The rest will works fine.
And finally, a team ownership means
each other in the charge of the P
pieces from building to shipping it.
That kind of ownership helps team
move faster and try new things.
And in the future, AI power
assistance could even guide teams
through a domain modeling base on
user flow and feature requests.
There are three main.
Way to build macro Frontends
first web component.
These are browser friendly
customer elements.
They use something called shadow
down to keep things separate, and
they works with any framework.
Second is Module Federation,
which comes with a web pack file.
It let different apps shared
JavaScripts on the fly, which is
great for loading only what you need.
And lastly, the server side composition.
This is when the backend put
together the different part.
Into one page.
Mostly, PHP language and awesome
for SEO and fast loading, so it's
works well for the public websites.
We are also seeing early tools that
use machine learning to recommend which
strategy, web components model federation
or server side composition best fit your
app based on traffic and usage pattern.
Let's talk results.
Teams using microphone time often
cut their deployment time by 60%.
That's a big deal.
Around 70% of teams say they have
more freedoms since they don't need
to check in with everyone else.
For every changes, rigs drop by
40% because changes are smaller and
more focused, and the best of all
releases, release speed, triples
this number, unadjusted theory.
They come from the real
companies and the real project.
You get faster innovation,
safer changes, and happier user.
Some teams are already using AI
tools to test their front end
automatically catching edge cases
and traditional test misses.
In those cases, performance
is super important.
Start by loading the most
important stuff first.
There is called progressive lazy loading
weight to load the rest until it needed.
Keep file sizes small by sharing common
stuff instead of repeating it, you
share component libraries to keep things
consistent and avoid redoing work and
set up real time performance monitoring.
It's not just about keeping the site
online, it's about knowing how each
part is doing so you can improve
things quickly and in the future.
The AI power observability
tools are getting smart enough
to predict performance dips.
They happen.
Big companies are already seeing
a great result with micro.
HSBC redesigned their online banking
using their setup, and teams were able
to deploy faster and cut bug by 70%.
Ikea used micro frontend to build
out product pages by category,
and each team focused on their own
sections made it better for customers.
Providence helped build a separate
micro frontend for different part.
Of their patient system, which held their
privacy rules and made update easier.
These real stories shows that
microfunding really scales
across all kind of industries.
Some enterprises are even starting
to use machine learning to
personalize microfund content based
on the real time user behavior.
Of course, nothing.
Is perfect.
Sometimes the user experience
can feel messy if different teams
design things in a different way.
And you can fix this with the
shared design systems, common
components, libraries, and a UX
team to keep everything aligned.
Another issue is performance.
And hit per performance hits and
when combining product run time.
But you can solve that by optimizing how
things load and caching share models.
And even though micro front and
lead teams work independently,
they still need to talk clear API.
Good documentation and
regular team check-ins help.
Keep everything working together.
In future, we may see a very driven
code linker that ensure every team
stick to share design guideline.
Switching to micro frontend
is a step by step process.
First, take a good look at your
current setup and figure out
where the natural boundaries are.
Then pick a simple low risk project to
try things out, set up your pipeline
and tools to get ready for the future.
I. Growth after that,
break things up slowly.
Moving pieces by pieces based
on what makes the most sense for
the business features, and keep
checking in with your teams.
Watch how things performs and
make improvement as you go.
That way, your shift to the micro front
end will be solid and long lasting.
Imagine using machine learning to simulate
different migration path and pick a safe
first one based on predicted user impact.
The future is looking awesome.
Pretty soon AI will help build an improve
component on its own saving ton of time.
Smart tools will help you see how
everything connect and suggest
better way to link things up.
Macro frontend won't just power website.
They support mobile apps, IOT
devices and even AR and vr.
That and eventually, we'll, we
will have a standard rules for how
to connect micro frontend across
different companies and tools.
We likely see AI recommending
how your frontend should adapt
to new platform in a real time.
Let's talk about web
assembly or WASM for short.
This is some next level technology.
It runs super fast code, almost like
a native app right in the browser.
You can even use languages
like c, c plus or rest.
Web assembly runs safest
in its own little sandbox.
So it's put, so it's fit perfectly
with the way macro frontend works.
It not just faster, it's safer and
more flexible, tool and secure.
And with AI optimized compilers even.
Non-expert will be able to convert
code into high performing wa SM module.
So try it out.
A powerful combination when you put
micro frontend and web assembly together.
You are unlocking the whole new level of
frontend power web assembly boosts the
speed of your most important features.
Team can use whatever language
suits on, suits their job best.
And because web assembly itself save,
contain, it fit well with the micro
frontend ideas of keeping things separate.
This compote you.
Up for the future From mobile apps
to AR platform, start by finding the
lowest part of your apps and try adding
a web assembly to speed things up.
We are heading toward AI models that
can recommend when to switch a JS
module to WSM for peak efficiency.
Thank you so much for sticking
with me through this deep
dive into micro frontend.
I hope you pick some useful
ideas, not just what they are,
but how to actually use them.
Whether you just exploring or already
on this path, micro frontend, especially
when you pair them with tools like
WebAssembly, give you the way to
build a front end that are best,
flexible and ready for whatever next.
The next wave is maybe a ai co-pilot that
help architect your front end from scratch
based on business goal and user data.
So try it out.
Thank you.