Speaker 7: Good morning everyone,
and thank you for being here.
My name is Sai Ria Raja Moga.
Today I'll walk you through how site
reliability engineering principles
were applied in a regulated biological
process development environment.
To automate a critical
analytical workflow.
That was mouthful.
This presentation focuses on the
integration of the bio profile Flex
Two Analyzer into the Amber two 50
Upstream development platform, and
how we approach that transition using.
Structured risk managed SRE inspired
thinking while SREs traditionally
associated with software systems.
This case study demonstrates how
those same principles can strengthen
reliability, compliance, and scalability
in laboratory manufacturing environments.
A little bit about myself.
Again, I'm a senior associate scientist
with Fin's, PSS, supporting Janssen, JJ
company at Malvern, Pennsylvania site.
My work focuses on upstream biologics,
process development, analytical
automation, qualification, validation.
And improving operational reliability
in high throughput cell culture systems.
In regulated environments, every
improvement must maintain compliance,
audit readiness, and data integrity.
And constraint and this constraint,
how we approached this integration.
So the agenda for today is
I'll walk over five key areas.
The operational problem we faced
with manual analytical workflow.
Overview of the Amber two
50 and Flex two platforms.
The structured implementation journey
from evaluation to validation, the
equivalency studies that de-risked
the transition and operational
impact and multi-site scale out.
This is a practical case
study of controlled automation
in a regulated setting.
So the problem is manual
workflows do not scale anymore.
The Amber two 50 platform supports
parallel micro bioreactors, which
means high sample volume and high.
Data density, however, analyticals
that we were using was still manual.
This created three challenges
reliability risk due to operator
dependent sampling variability,
operational overhead limiting throughput.
And compliance burden, increasing
audit and data integrity exposure.
From an SRE perspective, the system had
high toil and a large error surface area.
So as a platforms that we were using
was Amber two 50 and Nova Flex two.
The Amber two 50 is a high throughput
micro bioreactor used for upstream
biologics development, enabling
parallel two 50 ml vessels for rapid
process screening and the NOVA Flex.
Two is a multi parameter analyzer
measuring metabolites, blood gases,
electrolytes, osmolarity, and cell health
metrics from a single small sample.
This opportunity was to integrate high
throughput biological platforms with
a high efficiency analytical engine.
Why these two platforms together?
Amber two 50 generates a large number
of small samples and without automation.
Each sample required manual process
across multiple instruments.
Novo Fluex two consolidates all critical
parameters into a single automated run.
Aligns with Amber two 50 sample
volumes and support structured
audit ready data output
compatibility with GXP requirements.
This resolved the throughput mismatch
and reduced system complexity altogether.
And what was the implementation timeline
from December, 2022 to August, 2024?
The integration followed a
structured phase gated model
independent analytical evaluation.
Instrument qualification through I-Q-O-Q-P
Q4, structured EQ LC studies, validation,
and super user deployment and full
operation implementation in August, 2024.
This mirrored control production
migrations using used in
software reliability engineering.
We conducted four AQAL
studies using, again, the SRE
approach to transition risk.
Four structured comparability
experiments were conducted before
decommissioning these existing analyzers.
Each Amber derived sample was tested
simultaneously on NoFL two and as
well as an existing standard analyzer.
The parameters evaluated was pH PC O2
glucose lactate, glutamine, glutamate,
ammonium osmolarity, viable cell density,
and just the viability cell viability.
So the instruments that were used
to evaluate these parameters were.
Three different instruments or
four different instruments versus
NoFL actually consolidating all
of these into one instrument.
The acceptance criteria was predetermined
according to internal validation and
regulatory standards of the company,
as well as the upstream department.
What were the study outcomes?
All four equivalency studies
met acceptance criteria.
NoFL two demonstrated
analytical comparability
across all critical parameters.
This provided the documented
evidence required for compliant
and validated transition.
How did this now impact our workflow?
Before integration, sampling
required multiple instruments,
like I mentioned, and manual
steps, so humans and manual labor.
And after integration, a single NoFL two
ran delivered a full analytical panel.
Per Amber two 50 sampling event, and
we were able to schedule the sampling
much more appropriately timed wise,
rather than having someone come into
the lab to take care of, the Amber
system, the sampling and running
across multiple analyzers or systems.
So this reduced the touch points,
minimalized handling errors and
produced, structured analytical
outputs for reviewing and trending.
What was the operational impact?
We reduced 40% in manual labor per amber
run four equivalency studies, covered all
parameter groups which was again approved
by the Upstream development department.
12 super users were trained across
two different sites in Pennsylvania
and two independent sites.
These two independent
sites were also enabled.
This improved our efficiency,
resilience, and also scalability,
qualification and validation.
So all instruments underwent.
Independent qualification, installation
qualification, verified the proper setup,
operational qualification, confirmed
performance within defined ranges.
Performance, qualification, demonstrated
consistent routine performance,
and automation was implemented only
after these documented validation.
And the super user model is a
structured, super user modeled.
Ensure sustainability.
Eight Super users are trained for
primary site for Amber, two 50
operations and the routine flex
to use, and four we're trained at.
The other Pennsylvania location and
both of these locations are able to
independently troubleshoot without
relying on one person, one specific SME,
so there's no single point of failure
risk and ensuring long term ownership.
Whoops.
Cannot find my cursor.
All right.
What are the SRE principles that
were applied to biologic analyticals?
So the key principles that I think
we applied is we eliminated toil.
By reducing the manual tasks and protected
the reliability through controlled change
management and improved observability
with structured data, distributed
ownership, and prevent knowledge silos.
And I think these principles have
strengthened both reliability and com
and the compliance in our locations.
Just again, this is this project was
not simply just a instrument upgrade.
This was a structured reliability
improvement within a regulated
biological environment.
And by combining.
Rigor with SRE principles, we
created a scalable, compliant,
and resilient analytical workflow.
This is s ra a. Again, I'm open for
any feedback, discussion, or questions.
Thank you so much.