Welcome everyone.
My name is Teta.
Today we are discussing about SNT Cloud
native integration and SRE approach
to enterprise digital transformation.
Digital transformation demands a new
approach to integration as our nations
increase a adopt cloud technologies, the
reliability and operational excellence.
Of integration platforms have become
paramount to business success.
This presentation explores how SRE
or Site Reliability Engineering
principles can revolutionize
cloud native integration, enabling
organizations to maintain exceptional
uptime while accelerating innovation.
Drawing from the real world implementation
across multiple industries, we will
provide actionable strategies for.
IT professionals looking to build
more T integration architecture.
The Now let's dive into the
evolution of integration challenges.
So integration architecture have evolved
dramatically over the past decades.
Traditional integration patterns,
face significant challenges
in distributed environments.
Where complexity increases exponentially
with each service and data source.
The move to cloud native architecture has
amplified these challenges, introducing
concerns around dynamic monitoring,
scaling, and cross cloud dependencies
that traditional monitoring approaches
struggle to address effectively.
Let's take a brief journey through
the evolution of integration.
We started in the monolithic era with
centralized point to point connections.
Then say, then came the service oriented
architecture that introduced enterprise
service buses and improved reusability.
Today we are in the age of cloud
native integration where distributor
microservices and containerized
deployments rule the day.
And now we are moving towards
an SRE driven approach.
That focuses on reliability Through
advanced observability and automated
operations, each stage has brought new
challenges and our current environment
demand even more robust solutions.
So now let's dive into the core SRE
principles for integration excellence.
Now let's look at the principles
that drive integration excellence.
First, strategic reliability.
Aligning business objectives with error
budgets and service level expectations.
Next, comprehensive observability.
So end-to-end tracing and
metrics to monitor every
part of the integration flow.
Third, automation.
First, implementing self-healing
systems and auto remediation
to reduce manual intervention.
And finally, the continuous improvement,
learning from the incidents and
chaos engineering experiments.
To constantly refine our systems.
These principles allow us to
balance innovation with the
stability that business demand.
Now let's look at the defining
effective service level objectives.
So service level objectives or SLOs,
or the foundation of the reliable
integration for availability.
SLOs define uptime expectations
for integration endpoints.
Message brokers and API gateways based
on the business impact measuring both
synchronous request success rates
and asynchronous message delivery
guarantees with latency SLOs.
Established performance thresholds
for data processing pipelines with
both average and percentile targets.
A code for variable
workloads with context aware.
Thresholds based on payload
size and complexity.
And for throughput SLOs define capacity
objectives for message processing rates,
concurrent connections and transaction.
Total transactional volume
include elasticity metrics that
measure how quickly the system
scales to meet demand spikes.
Now let's look at building
observability into integration flows.
Observability is critical to
understanding what's happening in
our complex integration environment.
We start by instrumenting our code,
embedding tracing metrics and logging
at every integration boundary.
Then we collect and aggregate
this data into centralized systems
for analysis, visualizing these
patterns through dashboards.
Give us a clear picture
of end-to-end flow.
Health and intelligent alerting based on
SLOs helps us react swiftly to anomalies.
This comprehensive approach reduces
our mean time to diagnose issues and
keep our services running smoothly.
Kios Engineering for
integration resilience.
Now let's talk about the kios engineering.
Proactive approach to resilience.
By deliberately injecting control
failures such as API rate limiting
or message broker outages.
We can observe how our
systems react under stress.
We start with a clear hypothesis,
inject failures, measure the
system's response against our
SLOs, and then refine our design.
This it alternative process helps us
building self-healing integration flows
that can gracefully handle disruptions
and continue operations under pressure.
Now let's dive into a case study
where we have for a financial
services integration platform.
So here is a, there is a real
world example from the financial
services sector, a global firm.
Transformed its legacy integration
architecture to a cloud native platform,
supporting over 3000 APIs and processing
more than 500 million daily transactions.
They achieved 99.99% availability.
Reduced incident response times by 70%,
increased throughput fivefold, and reached
85% automation in incident remediation.
Their success story underscores how
comprehensive observability and automated
canary analysis can prevent outages
and drive continuous improvement.
Now let's dive into securing our
distributor integration architecture.
As our integration platforms
span multiple services and clouds
security became a paramount concern.
We adopt a zero trust architecture to
ensure service to service authentication
regardless of the network location.
By centralizing secrets management
and automation, automating
credential rotations, we reduce risk.
Data lineage help, helping tracking,
maintaining visibility of the
sensitive data as it flows through
integration pipelines with automated
compliance checks, runtime protection.
Deploy API gateways with threat detection
capabilities to identify usual patterns,
unusual patterns in integration traffic.
It's a. Security is not an add-on.
It's a integral part of
the resident integration.
So now coming to automating
integration operations automation is
a cornerstone of the SRE philosophy.
We start with configuration
management, storing every detail as
code, and managing changes via tops.
With deployment automation,
we implement a blue or green.
And canary strategies that automatically
roll back if SLOs are breached.
Effective incident response is achieved
through predefined runbooks and automated
diagnosis, while capacity management
users predict two, scaling based on
historical data and business patterns.
Automating these operations,
minimize the human error and allow
our teams to focus on innovation.
So coming to building a
shared reliability culture.
So technical measures
alone are not enough.
Building a culture of shared
reliability is essential.
This means creating shared
accountability between development
operations and business teams through
joint metrics and regular reviews.
Encouraging knowledge sharing
helps everyone understand the
dependencies in our integration flows.
Celebrating reliability
milestones and adopting a
blameless learning from Postmas.
Fostering an environment where
continuous improvement is the norm.
This cultural shift ensures
that reliability is a
collective ongoing priority.
Now let's dive into implementing the
roadmap and next steps to wrap up
our strategy here is a actionable
roadmap beginning with a thorough
assessment of your current integration
flows and reliability metrics.
So define SLOs, so establishing
business aligned, reliable reliability
targets for key integration
services, implementing observability.
So instrument integration components
with consistent telemetry.
And last one, automate operations
build CICD pipelines with reliability
gates and auto remediation.
This roadmap is designed to guide
you on your journey towards a
resonant cloud native integration
architecture driven by SRE principles.
Last.
Lastly, thank you for
attending this session.
I hope today's presentation provided
you with a valuable insight and
actionable strategies for transforming
your integration platforms with SRE.
Thank you.