Hello people.
Welcome to my presentation today
I wanna talk about virtualized
GPU for AI in enterprise storage.
To optimize to provide a
cost optimized solution.
With the evolution of artificial
intelligence there has been
increasing demand for powerful
GPUs to support the AI workloads.
The organizations currently face a
significant challenges related to
the infrastructure costs, operational
complexity and deployment efficiency.
In this presentation I'm gonna
talk about how Dell Technologies.
VMware and Nvidia have collaborated
to develop a virtualized GPU solution,
specifically designed for enterprise
storage environments and creating a more
flexible and cost effective solution
approach towards AI implementation.
Now let's talk about the GPU market
and its performance potential.
So the present GPU market holds up to
11.8 billion market share when this
projected to grow up to 29% by 2030.
A study show how, virtualized GPUs
exhibit an average overhead off
about 18% across various workloads.
But benefits of this implementation
like resource utilization, market
flex management, flexibility and
cost optimization, which will offset
these performance considerations.
The collaborative approach of industry's
leading tech companies like Dell, VMware.
And Nvidia is gonna solve upcoming
compute challenges for AI implementations.
This strategic alliance has produced
an exceptional outcomes demonstrating
near linear performance scaling from
one to eight GPUs within a single server
for deep learning training workloads.
Independent research conforms
that the state of art virtual GPU
implementations consistently deliver.
Up to 94% of native bare metal
performance across diverse
artificial intelligence workloads.
Here is the comparison of the
performance metrics with like
virtual GPUs versus bare metal GPUs.
The metrics clearly
states the virtual GPU.
Performance meets almost 92% of
the efficiency as traditional
bare metal configuration.
Achieving the most, a achieving
a significant portion of what
traditional traditional virtual,
bare metal GPUs has been producing.
Here are the key components of the
solutions, the enterprise ready validated
architecture integrates NVIDIA's AI
Enterprise Software Suite, empowering
the organizations, leveraging VMware.
We spear to efficiently virtualize
and containerize mission critical
artificial intelligence workloads.
Comprehensive performance testing that
has been done has shown an exceptional
results with deep learning training
workloads achieving up to 96% of what
traditional bare metal GPU performs.
So interference workloads
almost demonstrate.
Even more impressive resulting results
reaching to up to 98% of what a
traditional GPU has been giving to us.
So in the, if you look at the various
components of the, this solution
that has been designed, there is a
virtualized deployment layer where it
offers a flexible implementation across.
OnPrem on-premises infrastructure or if
it's a cloud service provider, we can
always containerize the applications.
Accelerate and simplified
AI workload deployments with
optimized resource utilization.
And the Nvidia AI enterprise software
suite offers optimized software
for virtualized AI workflows.
Let's compare how a virtualized GPU
has been performing when compared to
bare metal GPU in different use cases.
So when it comes to deep learning training
for ai, 96% of the bare metal performance
in the virtualized environments has
been achieved with minimal which
is like a minimal performance.
Reduction when you compare that off
with traditional bare metal performance
in the interference workloads
the study shows we have achieved.
The GPUs have virtualized, GPUs has
achieved 90 per 98% of the performance.
Compared to that of our traditional
traditional GPUs in the tensor
flow image classification it
was quite a significant mark.
It has achieved 95% of
performance retention processing
up to 4,500 images per second.
In the general AI workloads
you see a remarkable of 96% of
performance efficiency across
standard enterprise AI applications.
When it comes to the memory intensive
workloads, 92 per approximately 92%
of the performance retention has
been achieved, which shows like, only
four to 5% of the decrease the come.
Decreased performance compared
to non-virtualized environments.
Let's see.
What are the operational benefits
of, implementing virtualized GPUs.
So you see a significant
reduced deployment time.
So infrastructures provisioning
tasks, infrastructure provisioning
tasks usually used to take weeks.
That can be overcome within even,
I mean in days or even hours.
Reducing up to 60% of deployment time for.
All the AI workloads, you see a
remarkable, improved operational
efficiency with organizations
leveraging the VMware expertise for
AI deployments achieved that, that
has, they have achieved like 83%.
Or greater operational efficiency and
required 30% less specialized training
I mean to, for their employees.
Those implementing a dedicated AI
infrastructure, you see an enhanced a
resource utilization when compared to
physical GPUs traditional bare metal GPUs.
So organizations implementing these
virtual GPU solutions achieved
approximately three times better
resource utilization than dedicated AI
infrastructure and reduced maintenance
overhead by approximately 54%.
And also about all these the total
cost of ownership is very much low.
The unified approach developed by all
these three tech giants reduced an
overall IT operational expenses by 33%
and lowers the total cost of ownership by
approximately 40% over a five year period.
Let's see how organization improve
their operations from going to by
implementing virtualized GPU solutions
around the workload deployment time.
The AI workload deployment time
reduces up to 60% of their timelines.
Transforming like week long
projects into days or even hours.
The operational you see a significant
operational efficiency where 83%
greater operational efficiency for the
organizations leveraging existing VMware
expertise, specialized in training.
You don't have to.
You don't have to plan on like training
your employees for a specialized training
which reduces like up to 30% of your
time, resources cost in, in training
your employees compared to implementing
a dedicated AI infrastructure.
Resource utilization has been
improvised up to three, three times
better when compared by implementing
the virtualized solutions.
Maximizing, maximizing the
company's rate of investment on
returns, maintenance overhead.
You reduce about 54% of 54% of
reduction in ongoing maintenance
requirements compared to traditional
siloed AI infrastructure.
Here are some of the platforms where
AI has integrated where AI has been
integrated and, let's discuss about
how the AI has virtual GPUs has
helped with the AI integration on
these platforms coming to the human
resource sector AI powered like.
AA helped this area in talent acquisition
where systems are able to hire where the
companies are able to hire their employees
with reduced time of 37% while improving
the quality of the candidates by.
Quality of the human resources by 28%.
The application, these applications these
applications process these applications
being are able to process an average of
6,000 resumes per day while requiring
only 52 with only 50 to 20% of the
computational resources needed in.
Non-virtualized environments.
So organizations implementing these
solutions through virtualized GPU
infrastructure, reported achieving a full
deployment time of 42% more on efficient
than using than using a dedicated system
in the information technology area.
Area AI has enhanced ai, got
enhanced, cybersecurity solutions,
demonstrated impressive results
with organizations reporting a 47%
reduction in security incidents.
And a cost saving averaging about 3.33
million annually from prevented breaches.
Organizations adopted virtualized
that has adopted virtualized GPU
solutions for their AI initiatives.
Reported an average of return of
investment of one 34% over a three
year period where the deployments
cost 20 up to 35% lower than a
dedicated infrastructure approaches.
In the customer service industry the
organizations coming to the customer
service industry, organizations
deploying AI powered conservation
systems could handle 65% of more of
these customer interactions while
reducing the staff requirements by
23% with virtualized GPU solutions.
Enabling these systems to be deployed
like 3.5 approximately three,
three times, or four times faster
than the traditional approaches.
Leveraging a common infrastructure
platform across multiple departments
was a critical success factor with
38% lower training cost and 41%
faster implementation timelines.
Let's now see a department wise
the platform wise benefits of AI
implementation with virtualized GPU.
So in the human ser resource area or
industry the industry has seen, the
recruitment has accelerated with 37%
reduction in time to hire, and which
enhance the talent acquisition with 28%
improvement in quality of higher metrics.
It has strengthened the workforce
stability through about 24%
improvement in employee retention.
So boost, it also boosted the operational
effectiveness with about 30% increase
in the workforce productivity in
the information technology area.
You have seen like security
posture with with 47% reduction
in the critical in incidents.
By delivering like about 3
million in annual cost savings
from PREVENTED breaches.
So it also generated a substantial
one 34% of return on investment over
a three year implementation period.
It all, it has also achieved up to
35% lower infrastructure deployment
cost in the customer service industry.
You have seen you, you'll see the
research shows there's a dramatical
dramatically expanded capacity with
about 65% increase in the customer.
65% of increase in the
customer interactions.
It has also optimized resource
allocation with 23% reduction
in staffing requirements.
And also expediting the implementation
process with three times faster.
Faster than traditional approach.
It has also reduced the operational
expenses about with that, about reducing
the training cost and the hassle
of employees getting that trained.
About 38%
to summarize accelerating the
virtualized GPUs has accelerated.
Enterprise AI adoption.
Because the, because of the unified
infrastructure approach where the
collaboration between tech giants
like Dell, VMware, and Nvidia
represents a significant advancements.
In enterprise AI infrastructure addressing
both technological and operational
challenges that have traditionally
impeded widespread AI integration a
significant comparable performance.
So the performance
analysis confirm analysis.
The performance analysis confirmed
that virtualized GPUs on virtualized
GPU environments deliver results
comparable to bare metal implementations.
For most AI workloads while
offering substantial operational
and financial benefits, including
faster deployment and improved
resource utilizations the enterprise
wide implementation, the solutions.
Support for these G solutions.
The virtualized GPU solution support for
diverse AI requirements across enterprise
departments enables organizations to
implement comprehensive AI strategies
without creating infrastructure,
silos, or operational complexities.
It has finally, the end resulted
end result is acceleration
in AI transformation.
While as AI continues to transform the
business operations across the industries.
The virtualized GPU approach provides a
pragmatic path for enterprises seeking
to balance technological innovation.
With operational efficiency
and cost optimizations.
This concludes my presentation.
Hope you enjoyed my presentation and
gained insights about virtualized
GPUs, which is going to be a remark, a
significant development in the industry.
Thank you.