Hi everyone.
This is Nickel cai.
I'm a software engineer specialized
in cloud AI and FinTech.
I'm super excited to be
here at Con 42 SRE 2025.
I'll walk you through how we can
supercharge distributed systems using
Kubernetes, not just for orchestration,
but for realtime optimization.
Driven by ai, we'll explore
how to stay resilient.
Scale, smart and also respond and
milliseconds, all while reducing
costs and also improving uptime.
Whether you're an e-commerce, finance,
IO ot, or SRE at scale, you'll
walk away with practical ideas.
You can apply today.
Let's dive in and get to the next slide.
Now let's get back and look at
what we are really solving here.
Today's distributed systems are powerful,
but they come with c Ds complexity.
First, we are scaling like crazy, more
data, more nodes, and also more regions.
But are we scaling smart?
The thing is often not really
without a clear strategy.
This leads to cows components,
bottleneck services, draft out of
sync, and also things break under load.
Latency also can become a killer.
A few milliseconds of delay can
mean the difference between smooth
UX and also the customer drop off.
And then thing is the downtime.
So that's not just annoying.
It also costs revenue and damages trust.
Even a short outage can ripple across user
basis and without complexity comes risk.
The more moving parts you have, the
harder it is to maintain security
and availability, especially
when the attack surface grows.
Most systems are still reactive.
We fix problems after they occur,
when alerts, fire logs explored,
and also like the users complain.
But what if we could get
ahead of this all cows?
What if we could predict failure,
detect anomalies instantly and scale
intelligently before things break?
That's where this talk leads to today.
I'll walk you through how the use
of Kubernetes plus AI to shift from
reacting to predicting, preventing
and optimizing is going to work.
Let's next get to the next slide.
So here we just discussed
like what are some basic
foundations of modern resilience?
As we say, like Kubernetes forms a
core of our architecture and for a good
reason to, so first, it offers auto
scaling, which means the system can
instantly respond to traffic spikes or
depths, and no manual tuning needed here.
Then there self-healing.
If a container crashes, Kubernetes
just pins up another without anything,
or like anyone lifting a finger.
Rolling updates, let us push
changes without downtime.
Keeping systems available while
deploying new features, and also with
service discovery and built-in load
balancing routing traffic is seamless,
even as services scale or shift.
And the next thing, what we can
discuss ideally is like affinity rules.
So these are very important as we
see affinity rules help play spots
on the right notes, optimizing
for performance or isolation.
And the last and final thing is
the security policies and resource
limits, which gives us the guardrails
to keep everything secure, stable,
and fair across different workloads.
So Kubernetes gives us the
operational muscle, but what
if it could also think ahead?
That's where AI comes in.
So let's get to the next slide
and see what we can do with ai.
So we can just think about how
the system architecture can
be enhanced using artificial
intelligence on a high level here.
So here's how we made our system not
just reactive, but also intelligent.
At the base, we are collecting
live metrics and logs from
all across the cluster.
Things like CPU memory and POD
status and traffic patterns
are monitored and collected.
These streams feed into our AI ML layer,
which does the heavy lifting forecasting
resource needs, spotting anomalies,
and also optimizing the placement.
Then we have the decision
engine, the brain of the system.
It combines modal outputs with logic
to make decisions that triggering or
scaling, moving workloads or even.
Alerting is serious, and over
time it learns becoming better
with every decision it makes.
So we are not just automating here,
we are anticipating at a higher level.
So the next thing, what we
would like to discuss here is.
AI models that the, that's the
power of the system, right?
So AI models, let's talk about the brains
behind this operation are AI models.
We use LS CM models or forecasting.
They give us a heads up on resource
spikes so we can scale before even
things get tied for anomaly detection,
isolation forest helps us spot severe
behavior like crypto jacking or container
escapes or react fast can be also done.
We use PPOA reinforcement learning
model to figure out the most efficient
placement of workloads across the cluster.
This alone improved our
resource usage by 18%.
18% seems like a small number,
but ideally in terms of a
resource is 18% is really huge.
And finally, random for us.
Help us product if something is
likely to fail so we can fix it
even before it breaks These models.
Turn our infrastructure into a smart
predictive system, not just like a.
More of a, just like a reactive one.
Going to the next slide, we can
here discuss real time scaling
and resource allocation here.
The, I would say like real time
scaling and resource allocation.
This is more like a game changer.
I would say ai.
Helps.
I would say like AI helps us scale
before even what's the right word?
Even before we suffer.
So in traditional systems, we wait
for CPU to spike or latency to
creep in and then scaling kick.
But by that point, users
may already feel the lag.
With AI driven forecasting,
we know what's coming.
We can scale up or down
proactively, not reactively.
The result, the smoother ex user
experience, and also like lower
infrastructure costs altogether.
And also like the minimal risk of over
poisoning can also be handled here
because we respond in subsecond time.
The system stays ahead, always ready,
and also like always optimized.
The next thing I would like to discuss
here is more about the security,
which is really important in any use
cases, even like even if it is with
Kubernetes, with ai, without AI anytime.
It's really important.
So when we think about availability,
most people, I really focus on
infrastructure and traffic, but
what really brings systems down
fast are the security threats.
That's we build AI directly
into our security stack.
First, we use behavioral threat detection
to identify suspicious container or
power activity like crypto mining,
privileged escalation or unexpected file
accesses before it can impact services.
Our smart API monitoring here
tracks how internal and also
the external APIs access.
If something deviates from the norm,
it's flagged immediately and action
is taken before any performance step.
On the network side, our system spots
anomalies like data acceleration
or DDoS attempts within extreme
LI low false positive rate.
It was like very, pretty much I
would say I. Good improvement for us,
because low false positive rate is
something really important in general.
So what is the biggest win here?
So threats are mitigated in under
three seconds, and also that
keeps latency, low force, and also
availability high even in the face of
active attacks and with self-learning
models, the system keeps evolving.
Improving its detection,
accuracy, and also as it
encounters new patterns and risks.
The security here isn't
about just protection.
It's critical piece of insuring uptime.
And the next thing I would like
to discuss here is the disaster
recovery and fault tolerance.
I would say let's face it, however, like
how optimized or secure any system is,
the failures will still happen, right?
So what happens, or like what
matters most is how quickly and
intelligently we can ideally recover.
Our system uses AI to continuously
scan for early warning signs.
Whether it's discs, we may leaks.
Or degrade in node health and it
predicts failures even before it occur.
Once a risk is detected, the risk
assessment engine evaluates how
critical it is and in seconds it
generates a disaster recovery plan
tailored to our life cluster state.
We are relying on predefined
static playbooks here.
These plans are adaptive and
dynamic before the current.
Moment.
In fact, if action is needed, that
platform can orchestrate failover
on the demand or like automatically
keeping our RTO under 15 minutes.
In the real time replication in
place, we keep RPO under five minutes.
So the data loss is minimal to none.
All of this is AI driven,
automated, and first helping us
stay resilient, available and always
ready even during the unexpected.
And the next thing I would like to discuss
to see overall like real world results,
how they are pleased, and also like how
AI plus Kubernetes can be put in action.
Here's all what are the tools
like when it's real in production
at scale across industries.
In e-commerce, AI powered auto scaling
helps one platform cut infrastructure
costs by 31% while maintaining
99.99% uptime across thousands of
nodes, even during FLA seals or like
even during the seasonal spikes.
In financial services, the combination of
predictive security and automated failover
reduced incident by 45% and achieved
five nine's availability for their most
critical systems, even including trading,
which is the most important thing here
for iot platforms, which run at the edge.
AI helped optimize.
Resource usage, cutting data
transfer cost by 40%, and also
improving edge performance by 35%.
That's a massive win with every
MB and millisecond that matters.
And in pharma.
Also air driven forecasting and disaster
recovery, kept supply chains stable
during global disruption, preventing like
stockouts when demand was unpredictable
and also logistics or chaotic.
These are rare results made possibly
by combining AI's intelligence
with Kubernetes orchestration
power and the next thing in
the future, what can be done?
So ideally, like there are some.
Whenever we develop something,
there's always something we
can expect in the future.
Like a new things that can help us
given getting better and better.
So getting to that point, like how
the automation towards autonomous
infrastructure can help here.
Let's end by looking at
where this all is going.
So what we have built so far
with AI enhanced Kubernetes, it's
powerful, but it's still automation.
The future is autonomy.
Imagine infrastructure that
doesn't just scale or heal it.
Things.
It forecasts, it makes decisions.
AI agents will soon make real time
infrastructure choices, rerouting
traffic, spinning up clusters,
preemptively blocking threats, and often
we are even aware of the issue, right?
And to build.
I would say like into be trust in
these autonomous systems, we'll need
explainable ai where every scaling,
even security block or even securities
steps, or even the recovery steps is
traceable and also like justified.
We are also heading toward
federated intelligence here.
That is also one possible way that
we can expect in the future where
clusters learn from each other
across geographies and environments.
Imagine global resilience
turned by shared insights.
This all leads to the autonomous
sari where machines don't just assess
humans, they take charge of operations.
As engineers, our role shifts
from operators to strategists.
From writing rules to
the training systems.
So this is what I wanted to talk
about on a very short note, like how
Kubernetes plus AI can really help
these systems like scaled and also
with high availability, and also on the
level of security on different levels.
Thank you for all
listening to my talk today.
I'm ready to answer any questions
or any concerns or any other
queries that everyone have here.