Hello everyone.
This is Gina Abraham.
Today I would be presenting
modern reliability framework
for high speed infrastructure.
This is a comprehensive approach to
reduce service disruptions and improve
incident detection and resolution
in complex distributed systems.
So key takeaways on the
infrastructure growth.
Over the past few years, we have
seen an unprecedented growth
in infrastructure components.
Systems are scaling at 10 x the previous
rate, creating both opportunities
and significant challenges.
As infrastructure grows, it becomes
increasingly difficult to manage this
scaling means that we need to adopt.
Sophisticated management solutions
to ensure that systems continue to
operate smoothly without disruptions.
One of the biggest challenges
here is monitoring these systems.
Distributed systems create visibility
gaps, essentially, blind spots that
mask potential failure points, making
it harder to detect and address
issues before they impact operations.
So let's just look at
some key SRE challenges.
Site reliability engineering teams or
SRE teams are often faced with, uh,
several critical challenges in maintaining
the reliability of modern systems.
First, monitoring gaps
are a significant issue.
In fact, incomplete visibility is.
Responsible for 68% of
extended service outages.
When we can't see everything happening
in the system, failures can go
undetected, leading to longer down times.
Second, service degradation
is another challenge.
This refers to a gradual performance
decline that is often undetected
until it reaches a critical point.
These small issues accumulate
over time and cause major
disruptions, if not address early.
Lastly, detection delays are common.
On average, there is 42 minute delay
between when an incident occurs
and when an alert is triggered.
That's a lot of time for
the issue to escalate.
Now let's dive into the core components
of our modern reliability framework.
The framework aims to address
the challenges mentioned earlier
and provides powerful tools
to improve system reliability.
One key benefit is 85%.
Faster detection.
By using advanced monitoring and
analytics, we can identify issues
significantly faster than before.
Next, the framework also
reduces false alerts by 65%.
This is important because false
positives can overwhelm SRE
teams and lead to alert fatigue.
Reducing the effectiveness
of response efforts.
Additionally, 93% co coverage of
system components with service level
objectives ensures that we can define
measurable reliability goals for nearly
all aspects of the infrastructure to.
Now let's look at how automated
anomaly detection works.
This section focuses on one of the
most powerful tools of our framework,
the automated anomaly detection.
Dynamic thresholds are used
to adapt to evolving traffic
patterns and system behavior.
This allows the system to automatically
adjust its detection criteria based on
current load, significantly reducing the
occurrence of unnecessary alerts during
expected fluctuations in system behavior.
Machine learning powered analysis plays
a critical role in identifying subtle
deviations in system performance often
before they evolve into major incidents.
This proactive detection of anomalies
allows us to react to issues
earlier and with more precision.
The framework also includes.
Predictive alerts which provide early
warnings based on emerging patterns.
This allows teams to intervene before
systems reach critical thresholds,
potentially avoiding system-wide failures.
System level objectives are a
cornerstone of this framework,
providing a clear set of goals for the.
Reliability and
performance of our systems.
For instance, we are able to track core
resources such as CPU, memory and IO with
99.9% accuracy, ensuring that we have a
clear picture of how our infrastructure
is performing at any given time.
Additionally, the framework is
capable of pre-production bottleneck
detection, which allows us to identify
95% of potential issues before
they even make it to production.
This reduces the chances of performance
degradation once a system is live.
Another benefit is capacity planning,
which allows teams to forecast
resource needs 30 days ahead.
Preventing unexpected performance
degradation due to resource shortages.
Managing complex systems for organizations
that rely on multi-service architectures.
It's important.
To have tools that streamline
incident detection and response alert
consolidation reduces duplicate new
notifications by 75% when multiple
services are impacted by the same issue.
We can avoid overwhelming SRE teams
with redundant alerts, intelligent
filtering, prioritizes alerts based.
On context, ensuring that critical
issues are addressed first and that
resources are used efficiently.
Dependency mapping automatically discovers
and visualizes service relationships,
making it easier to understand how
different services are interconnected.
This insight is crucial for identifying.
And resolving issues that affect
multiple parts of the system.
The correlation engine connects incidents
across services providing a unified view
of service health, and making it easier
to pinpoint root causes of problems.
Cascading failures where one failure
triggers a series of problems across
interconnected systems are among
the most damaging types of outages.
One of the way ways we mitigate these
failures is through early detection.
These.
Real time anomaly detection
to catch deviations before
they spread across the system.
Circuit breaker is another
critical mechanism.
By deploying intelligent boundaries
between services, we can isolate
failing components and prevent them
from contaminating the entire system.
Load shedding algorithms dynamically
route traffic to preserve mission
critical services during periods of
high load or degraded performance.
This ensures that even when.
A part of the system is under strain.
Core services remain operational.
Graceful recovery involves orchestrating
service restoration in a way that
respects dependency, minimizing
the impact on system stability
as services come back online.
Now, let's look at how AI can.
Help with observability.
Observability here.
Artificial inte intelligence
plays a critical role in improving
observability and helping teams
stay on top of system health.
Anomaly classification.
Using AI offers 90% accuracy in
identifying type of issue, reducing
manual in investigation efforts,
and speeding up the response time.
Predictive maintenance can forecast
failures 24 to 48 hours in advance,
giving teams a head start on
addressing potential issues before
they cause real major disruptions.
AI also aids in root cause analysis,
reducing investigation time by 70%.
Instead of manually correlating
fail logs and metrics, AI tools can
quickly pinpoint the root cause,
allowing for faster resolution.
Finally, AI can improve on-call
efficiency, reducing unnecessary
escalations by 60%, which minimizes.
Fatigue and allows SRE teams
to focus on critical tasks.
Now let's walk through the implementation
phases of the framework assessment phase.
During this phase, we conduct a
gap analysis to assess current
monitoring capabilities and
identify areas of improvement.
We also organize workshops to
define SLOs and for and form the
implementation team deployment phase
in the, in the deployment phase.
We start, we set up the core
observability platform and begin service.
Instrumentation.
This is also when we start training
our machine learning models to
recognize patterns in the system.
Lastly, the optimization phase.
The final phase focuses
on refining the system.
This involves tuning alerts to ensure
they are both precise and actionable.
Automating run books to streamline
incident response and con and.
Continuously improving the platform
based on feedback and new data.
In conclusion, thank you
for your time and attention.
This framework is designed to tackle
the modern challenges of distributed
systems and provide proactive
solutions for ensuring reliability
and minimizing service disruptions.