Speaker 22: Hi everyone.
I'm going to talk today about
resilient AI platform for crisis
ready, health and financial system.
Let me introduce myself.
I'm Rakesh Kumar Al, a technical
architect with 17 years of experience in
designing and development and delivering
enterprise level software solutions.
Across healthcare, banking, financing,
e-commerce, and deep expertise in
distributed systems, resident platform
design, and AI infrastructure.
For mission critical environment, I'm
a certified Google professional cloud
solution architect and AWS Solution
Architect Professional, and AWS
certified machine learning specialty.
With hands-on experience in Kafka
on premises and Cloud, my day-to-day
activities are bridging the gap
between enterprise reliability,
engineering, and real world crisis
preparedness, particularly for the
healthcare and financial systems
serving vulnerable communities.
Today we are going to talk
about, major crisis iio?
Sure.
The extreme weather events, pandemics
and economic shocks are not hypothetical.
They are recurring realities that
expose the ity of most critical systems.
Healthcare Undertrained hospitals
faced major search three to five times.
Above baseline during regional disasters,
while legacy infrastructure buckles,
as we know financial systems, stress
payment networks and aid distribution
platforms fail precisely when
vulnerable communities need them most.
What exactly the SRA responsibility
then ensuring uptime during crisis
is not just a technical challenge.
It's a ethical obligation.
Let's go to what exactly we are gonna
cover today and deep drive into the
designing, building and operating
AI driven platform that holds up
when everything else breaks down.
There are five major things
which we wanna cover.
The first major thing, which I
is nothing but the problem space.
As we know the crisis pattern
system, failure modes, and the
gap in the current SRE practice.
The second major one is platform
architecture, as we know
we are in the AI world now.
Then AI load balancing it's intelligence
and context aware reconfiguration,
which covers the third major thing
is as we know, which is dealing with
the hardware and software stack.
The ized infrastructure, mobile first apps
and disaster equipped equity protocols.
And the fourth major one, as we know
as we want to tell about SRE practices
and migration stage hybrid migration,
fallback protocols and compliance.
The last one is nothing about
the outcomes and key takeaways.
What are the major improvements
which we need to take care, and
what are the actionable guidance for
every orination need to follow that.
With that, why existing
systems fail during crisis.
The major three patterns are
consistently across healthcare
and financial systems During.
Documented crisis events and each requires
a distinct architectural response.
Demand spike, ity loss, nce gap,
the common thread legacy platforms
are designed for average deal load.
The lack of what?
It's a predict.
Capacity to anticipate demand surges.
And the other major thing is
offline first capabilities.
When networks degrade equity aware routing
to prioritize vulnerable populations, the
dynamic reconfiguration without human S,
that is the very most important thing.
With ai, we are going to achieve it, and
each gap translates directly to the delay.
Which care Failure,
transactions and human harm.
Let's talk about introducing
the resilient AI platform.
What we are going to achieve with this,
what are the major things which we are
going to talk about here is like the a
purpose built enterprise architecture
that maintains availability, scalability,
and compliance under extreme demand
and infrastructure in stability.
Which are like four
major things I would say.
Where is AI driven?
What is AI driven is all about.
It is predictive load balancing and
autonomous reconfiguration, which gives
us like the way the traffic need to be
balanced, the way the prediction need to
be happen that will take care with this.
The next other major
thing is like age first.
This is one of the beautiful functionality
I would say, where intelligence at
edge, that means the functional,
even without cloud connectivity,
as we know that cloud connectivity
is major thing, but still this edge
first will cover that major part.
The third major one is like
equity aware, what exactly
this equity aware is all about.
When there is a disaster,
protocols that actively prioritize.
Underserved populations, that's,
this is one of the best I would say
and come to the complaint by design.
As we know hipaa, HIPAA is nothing but
the Health Insurance Portability and
Accountability Act where DG RP P, which
is nothing but the general data production
regulation, and at the same time.
Global data protection stands, bake
in When it goes, comes to the core
air capabilities, there are the
indigenous layer, which we have.
There are the four major
capabilities I would say.
What are those?
When we say about predictive
load balancing, these are
nothing but the models.
There are the AI models which analyze
historical crisis and real time signals
to prescale capacity before demand peaks.
Not after system begin, it fails.
That is the beauty of it.
And it comes to next one, it's like
context aware reconfiguration, which
I was talking about that is like
serves automatically reprioritizing
workloads based on the crisis type.
Like when there is a crisis, then that
would be a automatically right there is
like smart, which is like hurricanes or
pandemic or any other economic shock.
Each triggers a different response
profile where the patterns are
already in place, which serves that
reprioritizing and automatically
happens, those workload to be shifted.
Coming to the edge intelligence
that local interference at edge
nodes sustains essential services.
When Central Cloud connectivities
degraded are completely lost,
this edge intelligence will act.
A smart one when the
connectivity is not there.
With respect to the cloud, when it comes
to the fallback protocol engine, this
is a paid SLA back to fallback sequence.
Ensure graceful degradations critical
functions stay alive, even as in
non-essential services are shared.
Let's go to the journey of
the software stack built for.
Design philosophy when each layer is
independently operate, a failure in
one layer does not cascade to other.
That is the beauty of it because the
layers will not impact the other layer.
This is a crisis grade modularity
where AI load, balancing route
traffic with sub-second latency
decisions and transaction processes
maintains financial rails.
Under network partitions, mobile
first apps delivers aid workflow
on networks with offline sync.
As you know that equity protocols
encoded, prioritized rules,
not manual operation decisions.
When we spoke about hardware
layers, now this is a deep drive
into that where how exactly the
infrastructure that serves disasters.
Resilient edge clusters.
These are the four major things
which we are going to talk how
exactly the hardware layer will do.
Distributed compute notes positioned close
to the service delivery points, hospitals,
relief centers, and bank branches.
When you talk about financial things.
Ized servers.
This is a hardware rated for extreme
environments when there is a heat,
humidity, and intermittent power
for the disaster prone regions.
There are many problems which wanna
come, but this region servers while
gonna be having the controlling the
hardware extreme environment when it
comes to the low latency networks.
This is what the mesh networking
devices that operate across satellite
LTE and fiber are automatically
selecting the best available path.
The offline, one of the best thing
is offline first cloud hybrid
data synchronization protocol
that recycle edge state with cloud
when connectivity is restored.
Let's go.
Other major concept, which is nothing but
the SRE practices operating at scale under
pressure as we know that how exactly the
monitor recover, predict and response.
This continuous loop replace reactivate
incident management with the proactive
AI assistant operating models,
purpose built for crisis conditions.
What are those world support for this?
There are nothing but like dynamic
capacity planning, decentralized encrypted
storage, global compliance by default.
Then what exactly is
dynamic capacity planning?
The platform is architectured to
handle millions of concurrent users.
We combining horizontal auto-scaling
with AI driven pre-provisioning
based on the crisis signal feeds.
Millions of Conent users can access
this one, which is dynamically increase
the capacity based on those planning.
When it comes to the decentralized,
encrypted storage, as we know that there
are millions of press patients are there.
How exactly this patient records and
financial data are distributed across
the cloud and edge nodes and end-to-end
encryption, which is one of the major
critical thing when it comes to the cloud,
when it comes to the data sharing and no
signal point of data loss during regional
outage when there is a regional outage.
We don't want the data to be lost
anywhere in any point of time.
The other major important point, which I
want to talk about is global compliance.
By default, as we know, hipaa, the
Health Insurance Portability and
Accountability Act, and other major
one is general Data Protection
Regulation, GDPR, and the local data.
So requirement and enforcement,
that infrastructure layer, not
blotted on post deployment.
Now here is the major migration
strategy from Legacy two.
Crisis Ready.
Replacing critical systems overnight
is not feasible or safe, but the
platform uses a stage hybrid migration
approach that minimizes the risk while
progressively building resilience.
What are the stages?
There are three stages when
it comes to the stage one.
Nothing but of the coexistence offline.
First models deployed
alongside existing platforms.
No disruption to live services.
That is the beauty of this when it
comes to the second stage, what is that?
It's AI takeover.
AI driven models progressively assume
non-critical, then mission critical
workload with continuous validation and.
Third is nothing but the full resilience.
Legacy systems retired as we know that
there are like systems are getting
migrated, then legacy systems will
be moving away and we are getting
the SLA backed feedback protocols
and equity protocols fully operated.
We talk about all the major things,
but this is one of the important.
Protocol strategy where disasters,
equity protocols, how exactly
reliability as a social commitment,
who gets served fast during the crisis?
We all know that not all the
users have the equal access,
but there will be alternates.
What are those?
How exactly are we gonna achieve them?
The platform encodes equity
aware, routing directly into
its service recognition, logic.
What are those major points?
Elderly, disabled, and
low income population.
This is prioritized bandwidth and
compute allocation, which is one of
the major thing which we need to use.
The prioritization.
What is the other major point which
we talk about is that a distribution
apps are optimized for low end
devices and low bandwidth networks.
The third important point is nothing
but the offline first design.
Ensures across even when
infrastructure has completely failed.
This is not just good engineering.
It is a right to do.
How exactly are we gonna measure?
Here is the beauty of
the measured outcomes.
Organizations adopt this architecture
have demonstrated meaningful,
quantifiable improvements across both
operational and financial dimensions.
When you talk about the percentages,
like 60% of fast service delivery,
reduction in service delivery times
during active crisis events, 20 to 30%
of financial improvements, that is a
major improvement when you talk about the
cost savings through optimized resource
allocations and reduction disruption cost.
When it talks about 99.9%
target availability.
The SLS as we know the bad Time
up commitment for mission critical
services under Crisis Road.
The other major thing is scale headroom,
the three times revisioned capacity
to absorb sudden demand surges.
Without manual intervention as
we know that nowadays there is
no manual interventions, which we
want to use as smart AI features.
So that will be the giving
the more good things.
When it comes to the key takeaways
for SRE teams, what exactly the key
takeaways, which we need to take from this
predict don't react, which is a beauty
of ai, where AI driven predictive load
balancing must replace manual scaling.
The crisis move faster
than human response.
Time edge is not optional,
it's just a cloud only.
Architectures are a
single point of failure.
Edge is intelligence is a
reliable equipment, not a feature.
The other major thing is like equity and
SA low with these vulnerable populations
must be explicitly modeled into UR.
Service prioritization, which
is a very important thing, very
major thing where the no left to
change our manual overrid, right?
We are going to take over that manual
overrid where we can get this equity.
The other most important thing, I would
say, the key takeaway is migrating
stages, stage hybrid approaches, reduce
risk and allow AI modules to prove.
Stem cell before assuming full
mission, critical responsibility,
and I would really thank everyone.
It has been a privilege to share
this work with SRE Community.
Resilience is not just about keeping
system online, it's about keeping
people safe when it matters most.
I have sharing my LinkedIn link here.
I would request everyone please
suggest if anything is there.
Thank you so much everyone,
for giving a great opportunity.
I.