Speaker 14: Hello everyone.
My name is Makran Gujarati.
I work as a senior software engineer and
an individual researcher, and today I'm
going to talk about how we can use ai,
specifically large language models and
the model context protocol to improve
incident response in distributed systems.
The title of this talk is AI
Assisted Incident Response using
LLMs and MCP in Distributed System.
If you have ever been on call for
a microservice based systems, you
already know what that insurance can be
painful, noisy, and slow to diagnose.
In this talk, I'm going
to cover five main things.
While diagnosing incidents in
microservice environments is so hard
how we can use the large language
models or LLMs together with MCP to
assist engineers during incidents,
what kind of context and documentation
we need to make this actually work?
Some lessons learned from
trying this pattern in practice.
And finally, what next steps you can
take if you want to explore this approach
in your own team or organization?
Let's start with the basic
problem we are trying to solve.
Modern backend systems are
no longer simple monoliths.
A single user request can easily
touch five to 10 microservices each
with its own database cache, queue
configuration, and deployment pipeline.
When an incident happens for example,
when latency increases or error rate
spike, the challenge is not just
what is wrong with this one service.
The real challenge is which
combination of services is involved.
Where in the call chain is the bottleneck
or failure, and which telemetry signal
should we really pay attention to?
Logs, metrics traces or ad hoc queries.
On paper, we have a lot of
tools observability platform,
centralized logging, metrics and
dashboards, distributed tracing
and sophisticated alerting.
But in practice, during an incident,
the on-call engineer has to maintain
a mentally connect signals from
all these places across multiple
services and under time pressure.
That is the core SRE
challenge I want to address.
Making it easier and faster to understand
what's going on in a complex microservices
environment when something breaks,
let's look more closely at what
actually happens during an incident
today and where the pain really is
First, engineers often spend two
to four hours just on investigative
investigation for non-trivial incidents.
This is time spent not fixing the
problem, but trying to understand
where the problem really is.
Second, there is a lot of manual
correlation across different data stores.
For example, you run SQL queries against
a data warehouse or time series store.
You open a logging tool
like Ban or Splunk.
You open dashboards for
metrics in Grafana or Datadog.
You might also open a tracing
UI and maybe some deployment
logs or feature flag dashboards.
None of these tools share
a common mental model.
The only thing that ties them together is
the human on-call engineer who manually
jumps between them and connects the dots.
Third, expertise takes
a long time to build.
Senior engineers know
which dashboards to trust.
They know which metrics
truly indicate user impact.
They remember which services are
actually behind certain APIs.
Junior engineers typically don't have this
context yet, so they end up waiting for a
backend expert to join the call and help.
Fourth, we have overwhelming amounts
of telemetry, too many logs, too many
metrics, and often too many dashboards.
The problem is not lack of data.
The problem is making sense of
it quickly and connect correctly.
All of this together means
that we have limited effective
visibility during incidents, and
this slows down our response.
This is exactly the gap where AI
can help, not by magically fixing
the systems, but by supporting the
reasoning and correlation work that
engineers are currently doing manually.
Leveraging LLMs and MCP technology.
Now let's talk about the proposed
solution, AI assisted incident response.
The core idea is to combine two
things, large language models or LLMs,
which are good to add, understanding
natural language and working with
structured data and the model context
protocol or MCP, which gives these
models a set standardized, safe way.
To access telemetry data
and schemas in practice.
What does AI agent actually
do during an incident?
First, it takes a natural language
description of the problem from engineer.
F for example, we are seeing
increased IXX errors from the backend
checkout service in the Euro region
for after the last deployment.
This could be a simple problem that
analyst can provide to the AI agent.
Then using MCP, the AI agent can in
inspect elementary schemas, it can
see which metrics logs and tables
exist and how they are structured.
Based on that, the agent can
generate s QL queries or equivalent
queries to the telemetry systems.
These queries are tailored
to investigate the specific
incident, described the agent.
They can then refine these queries.
Alternatively, it can zoom in on a
specific service region or version.
It can compare before
and after a deployment.
It can correlate metrics, logs,
traces across the services.
This is not about fully
automating instant resolution.
It is about assisting the human on-call
engineer by reducing the manual effort of
writing and rewriting queries, surfacing
relevant events or data more quickly,
and highlighting correlations that
might not be obvious at first glance.
To make this approach safe and
reliable, we need a controlled way
for AI agents to talk to our systems.
That's where the model context
protocol or MCP comes in.
MCP is a standardized interface that
sits between AI models and tools or
data sources such as telemetry systems
in the context of incident response.
MCP does a few important things.
First schema introspection.
The AI agent can ask questions like what
tables are available, what columns do they
have, what metrics exist for the service?
This removes guesswork.
The agent sees the real schema, not
some assumed or hardcoded structure.
Second, controlled query execution.
Instead of giving the model direct
unrestricted database access MCP exposes
safe read only operations, the AI can
request certain SQL queries to be run.
The system enforces limits, such as
Readly access and safe query patents.
Sensitive or personally identifiable
data can be filtered or must.
This gives us the
guardrails and auditability.
Third, a standardized
pattern across tools.
Whether your data lives in BigQuery,
snowflake, Lakehouse, Prometheus,
or a lock store, the AI speaks to
them through a consistent protocol.
This means we don't have to
custom integrate the AI with each
system in a totally different way.
We can log and monitor
what the AI is doing.
And we can swap or extend tools
behind the scenes without changing
how the AI agent is written.
In short, MCP is what turns the
LLM from a single chat bot into
a tool using telemetry aware
agent with safety boundaries.
Now let's walk through the typical AI
assisted incident workflow, step by step.
Step one is a natural language input.
The engineer starts by describing
the incident in plain language.
For example, we are seeing a
spike in SGDP 500 errors for the
checkout service in the US West two
region, starting at say 10 15 UTC.
The last deployment happened
about 30 minutes before that.
Can you investigate what's going on?
The AI agent reads this and extracts
key details like the affected service.
The region, the timeframe, the
relevant event like deployment
shortly before the spike.
Step two is SQL and
telemetric query generation.
Using the telemetry
schema exposed via IMCP.
The agent then generates one or more
queries, for example, a query to get
error rates by endpoint over time.
A query to compare latency
before and after 10 15.
A query to see request volume broken
down by version or deployment id
a query to look for changes in
downstream dependency performance.
The engineer doesn't have to
remember table names, column
names, or joint conditions.
They can simply ask questions in
natural language, and the AI maps
those questions to concrete queries.
Step three is the iterative analysis.
Once the results come back,
the ad just doesn't stop there.
It enters an at loop,
it analyzes the results.
For example, the 500 errors increased
sharply at 10 0 12 UTC mostly on the slash
pain point and only for version one point.
2.4, it then proposes or
runs the next logical query.
For example now check if there were
configuration changes or dependency
failures at that same time.
It keeps going correlating metrics
and logs across services until it
can propose a. Plausible hypothesis.
After a few attritions, the AI might say
something like the 500 error spike is
limited to US West two on version 1.2
0.4, mainly on the payment endpoint.
At the same time, the payment
provides timeout errors increased,
starting just after the rollout.
This suggests a change in
the payment integration is
causing downstream timeouts.
Now throughout this process, the
human engineer can interrupt,
steer, or refine the investigation.
The AI handles the heavy
lifting of writing, running, and
correlating many queries quickly.
The value is speed and coverage.
The AI can explore more angles
more quickly than a human manually
pivoting across the interfaces.
For this whole approach to
work well, context engineering
is absolutely critical.
If you simply connect an LLM to a
production database with no documentation
and no structure, we should expect poor
results and possibly unsafe behavior.
There are three main components
of context engineering here.
First is the schema documentation.
The AI needs to understand
not just names, but meanings.
For example, what does a particular
column actually represent?
Is the timestamp in seconds,
milliseconds, or something else?
How do we join logs and
metrics for the same request?
Which field represents a service
name, region, or version?
Good documentation helps the AI
generate correct and meaningful
queries and avoid misinterpreting data.
Second is the curated query libraries.
We don't want the AI to reinvent
every query from scratch.
Instead, we provide a library of
pretested reliable queries for
common investigation patterns.
For example, show error rate by
endpoint over the last 12 hours.
Compare P 95 latency before
and after the deployment.
Show the top end services by error
volume during the incident window.
Compare traffic patterns this
week versus the last week.
The AI can then reuse these queries,
adapt them to different services or
regions, and combine them in new ways.
This improves the reliability
and reduces the chances of
inefficient and incorrect queries.
Third is the architecture diagrams.
Architecture diagrams give a clear picture
of which services, talk to which, what
are the deployment or dependencies are,
and where the data flows, data flow goes.
When the AI knows, for example,
that checkout needs or depends on
payments, inventory, and user profile
services, it can, sorry about that.
It can automatically suggest
investigations like check latency and
error rates for the payment service
in the same region and timeframe.
Check if inventory latency correlates
with checkout slow slowdowns.
These diagrams shorten the lifetime
from symptom to likely cause,
because the dependencies are
explicit and machine readable.
The key point is AI assistance is only
as good as the context you provide.
Investing in documentation, curated
queries and architecture diagrams
is what turns AI from a generic
assistant into a powerful domain
specific incident Investigator.
Everything we have discussed so
far depends on the telemetry, and
telemetry itself is challenging
in distributed systems.
There are several types
of complexity here.
First di diversity and heterogeneity.
In a large organization, different
teams log in different formats.
Metric names are
inconsistent across services.
Some teams use one tracing library.
Others use another.
Some services are well instrumented,
others barely make useful data.
This makes cross service correlation
difficult for both humans and ai.
Second is the timing issues and data
quality metrics might be aggregated
in one minute or five minute buckets.
Logs might be near real time or delayed
traces might be heavily sampled.
Aligning all of these signals on a single
accurate timeline can be very hard.
Third, the need for aggregation and
normalization To compare behavior
across services and regions, we need
consistent labels such as service
region, version deployment, underscore
id, and user underscore id, et cetera.
Shared naming conventions for
key metrics such as latency,
error rates, and request counts.
Without this, it becomes very difficult to
ask comparative questions, spot patterns,
or automate any kind of reasoning.
Fourth is alerting challenges.
If alerts are too sensitive and the
team experiences alert fatigue, if
they are too relaxed, serious problems
might not be detected in time.
AI can help analyze patterns and
suggest better thresholds, but it still
depends on the underlying data quality.
Finally the culture and collaboration.
Good.
Telemetry is not just a tooling
problem, it's also a cultural one.
It requires agreement on standard
across teams, collaboration
between development and operations.
Continuous improvement based on
what each incident teaches us.
AI assisted incident response does
not make telemetry problems disappear.
What it does is help us navigate complex
telemetry more efficiently, but only
if we invest in making that telemetry
reasonably consistent and discoverable.
Okay.
Now let's talk about the impact.
What can we realistically expect
from AI assisted incident response?
When it is done well from early
prototypes and case studies, we
typically see things like a significant
reduction in investigative effort.
In other words, the time between
alert fired and we have a reasonably
confident hypothesis decreases a
reduction in meantime to resolution.
Especially for incident types that occur
repeatedly where the AI can recognize
patterns and reuse previous knowledge.
The exact numbers, like X percent
reduction in effort or Y percent reduction
in the resolution time will depend on how
mature your telemetry stack is, how much
context engineering you have done, and
how comfortable your engineers are with
using the AI assistant in their workflow.
However, the quality feedback
tends to be consistent.
Engineers say they go, got a
plausible root cause faster.
Junior engineers say they could drive
investigations without constantly waiting
For a senior expert teams notice that far
more queries and correlations get run in
the first 10 or 15 minutes than before.
In short, this approach compresses
the investigation phase and frees
your experts to focus more on decision
making, remediation, and long-term fixes.
Let's make the difference more concrete
by comparing the situation before the AI
assistance and late after AI assistance.
Before AI assistance investigations
can typically easily take up to two
to four hours for complex incidents.
Engineers manually write SQL and
build complex filters and dashboards.
A small number of senior
experts become bottlenecks.
People wait for them
to interpret telemetry.
Correlating data across service
requires a lot of copying, pasting,
and switching context between tools.
The result is longer resolution
time, more user impact, and higher
stress for the on-call team after AI
assistance the S QL query generation
is automated from natural language.
The AI supports fast
conversational refinements
correlation across service
and data sources improve.
Because the AI is able to navigate
telemetry schemas quickly and
systematically, time to resolution
decreases, especially for
recurring or pattern based issues.
And importantly, junior
engineers are empowered.
They can lead much of the investigation
by asking the AI questions.
They only need to pull in experts
in for judgment calls and complex
decisions, not for every basic query.
This transformation is not about
removing people from the loop.
It is about making the loop much faster.
And less reliant on a
handful of individuals.
Now I will briefly summarize the overall
architecture pattern behind this approach.
There are three main pillars.
First is LLM integration.
At the center is the large
language model connected via MCP
to various telemetry systems.
The models responsibilities
include understanding natural
language descriptions of incidents.
Generating and refining queries,
synthesizing data into explanations,
timelines and hypothesis.
Typically, this is exposed to engineers
through a chat-based interface.
Integrated into tools like
Stack Slack teams or an
incident management dashboards.
Second is the context engineering.
Around the model, we have schema
documentations, curated query libraries,
architecture diagrams, and sometimes
predefined incident playbooks.
This context turns generic LLM into
a domain specific SRE assistant that
understands your system structure
and your telemetry semantics.
Third is the human oversight.
Finally, we preserve a strong
human in the loop model.
The AI can suggest que repose hypothesis,
highlight suspicious patterns, and
even suggest possible remediations.
But critical actions remain under human
control, rolling back deployments,
shifting traffic, declaring major
incidents, communicating externally.
This combination gives us the speed
and breadth of AI driven analysis
while maintaining the safety and
judgment of experienced engineers.
From actually trying to design
and operate systems like this,
a few key lessons emerge.
First lesson is curated query.
Libraries are extremely valuable.
They help standardize how
investigations are done.
They reduce the likelihood of slow,
inefficient, or incorrect queries.
They provide the AI with strong
foundation of known good patents.
Second is the comprehensive schema.
Documentation is essential.
The pre, the more precisely you
document field meanings, units.
Relationships between tables and metrics.
Service naming conventions, the
better your AI assistant will be at
generating precise and useful queries.
Third is the balance
automation with human judgment.
It is tempting to automate everything, but
incidents are often messy and ambiguous.
A practical approach is
you use AI to recommend and
explain, not to silently act.
Start with the readly low risk
automations, such as pre-running a
standard set of DI diagnostic queries.
When an alert fires gradually increase
automation, where you have strong
confidence and clear rollback strategies.
This balanced approach builds the
trust with engineers, prevents over
lines on the AI and lets you scale
up auto automation slowly as you gain
more experience and more confidence.
Looking forward, there are several
promising directions for improving
AI assisted incident response.
First is expanding
incident pattern catalogs.
Over time, organizations see similar
types of incidents again and again
by capturing these as patterns.
For example, typical memory leak
behavior, typical dependency timeout
pattern, misconfigured feature flag,
the AI can recognize similar structure
signatures in the telemetry and suggest
likely root causes more quickly.
Second is the enhanced
model context techniques.
We can improve how we feed context to
the model using automatic retrieval
of free owned documentation,
embedding based search over the past
incidents, structured representation
of service, topology and dependencies.
Third is the broader integration with
the tools beyond logs and metrics.
AI agents can connect to CI CD pipeline.
Feature flag systems, ticketing
tools, knowledge bases, and wikis.
This enables end-to-end analysis from
a code change to a deployment, to its
effect on production behavior, and finally
to incident tickets and postmortems.
Fourth is the adaptive
learning from incidents.
After each incident, the system can learn
which queries are were most helpful.
Which hypothesis were correct,
which remediation steps worked.
This allows the AI assistant to get
better with each incident, turning
painful events into long-term
learning and automation opportunities.
All of these directions move us
towards incident response that
is faster, more consistent, and
less dependent on few experts.
If you are considering trying this
approach in your own environment,
here is the simple three step path.
First is assess telemetry maturity.
Ask questions like, are our logs metrics
and traces reasonably consistent?
Do we have clear schemas for
our main telemetry stores?
Can we have reliably, co,
reliably correlate database,
service, region and version?
If the answer to is mostly no, then
your best first investment is not ai.
It is improving the
basic telemetry engine.
Second is the develop context materials.
Once the basics are in place, you can
work on creating schema documentations,
architecture diagrams, curated query
libraries, and short focused run books.
Think of this as a, creating a
knowledge base that both humans
and AI can use during incidents.
Step three is the pilot AI diagnostics.
Start with the small choose one or
two services or one specific domain.
Integrate an MCP enabled AI
assistant with read only access.
Use it during real incidents,
always with human oversight.
Then collect feedback.
What did the AI do well?
Where did it struggle or hallucinate?
What additional context would've helped?
I trade on the context, the
guardrails, and the user experience.
Then expand to more services and
more teams as confidence grows.
Thank you everyone for your attention.