Speaker 9: Hi everyone.
I'm Daniel Raskin, chief
Marketing Officer at Verana, and
I'm here with David McNerney.
Director of Product Management from Verana
and today we're gonna host a session for
you called When the Stack Lies, finding
Root Cause in Distributed Systems.
And so we're grateful to be here today
for this session and hope you enjoy it.
We're gonna walk you through
what we see as a pretty.
Interesting story around how the modern
enterprises changed and the impact it's
ha having on SREs pretty dramatic impact.
And, we're thinking about
this topic pretty regularly.
So I'm at a company called Verana which
focuses on full stack observability
across every axis of the enterprise.
So from bare metal all the
way to application and.
When we're thinking about what's going on
in the realm of observability, there are
some pretty significant changes going on.
The first being that the modern
application has changed significantly.
When we think about the modern enterprise
it is getting more and more complex.
Applications are no longer the
self-contained classic three-tiered
architectures that where we're just
living in the code, but they've
become more and more distributed.
They are distributed across
every aspect of the enterprise.
It could be living in the cloud,
it could be living on-prem.
It's broken into microservices.
It's tied to dependent services
like identity and access
management capabilities.
As we get more and more into the
realm of ai, we're seeing machine
learning models and AI workloads
running as part of these applications.
And so the world is becoming
much more distributed.
Because of that, it's having
a very huge impact on what it
means to be a site reliability
engineer in the modern enterprise.
And so we're gonna break down
what this means and how we need
to shift our thinking about it.
But the key takeaway is the
application has become much more
decomposed and it's distributed
across every access of the enterprise.
Now the challenge with that is when
we're talking about applications, we
could be talking about some of the most
mission critical applications that are
sitting out there, whether it be airline
reservation systems or in the realm
of financial services, ATM networks.
And these things have to be up and
running When these things go down, not
only does it have a massive impact on
the usability for the customer, but it
can destroy a company's brand equity.
It can cost an exorbitant amount
of funds, and these failures can
be related to all types of things.
The airline reservation system
may fail because of upstream
services or the A ATM network may
fail because of database latency.
There are all kinds of issues
from infrastructure contention
to pipeline stalls and so on.
And when these things are struggling,
nothing may be technically down.
But the whole system could stop
working because of all of these
relationships and interdependencies.
So when we think about the
application becoming a system that
is distributed across every aspect
of the enterprise, we have to think
in the context of that system.
And once failures occur,
those failures are systemic.
The scope and complexity of
what we're navigating is just.
Exponentially greater
than what it was before.
Now, when we think about this in the
context of what's going on in the
enterprise, there's a huge paradox
going on because when you sit within the
enterprise, everyone is obsessed with ai.
Everyone is focused on wanting to refactor
their applications to support AI workloads
or connect them to AI factories to
automate and incorporate services that
have never been as powerful as before.
Leveraging things like the LLM for
natural language exploration or doing
predictive analytics or predictions
around using machine learning models.
There is a ton.
In terms of upside around
ai, the challenge is if you
look at the executive level.
There's a very different perspective
on where we are verse where SREs
and practitioners think we are.
And this is basically from a
study that we commissioned out
across global 2000 businesses.
And what we saw was that executives were
for, forging forward into the realm of ai.
Thinking everything is going great.
We're ready for ai.
We're on track to incorporate AI
factories in terms of what we're doing.
We need to be plowing forward
at 150 miles per hour.
The practitioners, on the other
hand, are looking at this and saying,
oh my God, we're plowing forward
into the realm of AI and we still
have a number of visibility gaps.
We're not necessarily ready for this.
Things are fragmented.
There's a lot of risk.
This dissonance is creating a lot
of struggle because, we could be
plowing forward into something
where it could be disastrous if
we don't have the operational
sophistication in place to handle it.
And so this means that on from the
perspective of SRE who are worried about.
MTTR and wanting to ensure that everything
is running and is highly available, that
we need to be thinking about how to shift
things very quickly to adjust to this
new world and ensure that we can plow
forward fast and catch up to where the
mindset of the executive team is sitting.
So this means that.
We have to think about observability
in a different way and how we monitor
different components of the application.
Because when we look at this, you
could look at this from the realm
of silos, which is historically
how observability has been handled.
We've had application observability
or infrastructure observability or
AI factory observability, and all of
these are built from the standpoint
of silos that look at a certain.
Portion of the stack, but they don't
look at the end-to-end application.
And the problem with this is when we
look at this, something could go wrong
and every single dashboard across these
different silos is gonna show a symptom,
but none of it is gonna show the cause.
So in this case, I could
see all the way to the left.
My application observability solution,
or my classic application performance
monitoring solution might be showing
me some kind of symptom or alert
that the application is struggling
or down, but they won't be able to
see necessarily that it's an LLM.
Inference delay because that silo
or component isn't gonna have a
view into the AI workloads and
what's happening in that realm.
So we need to get out of this
situation of seeing symptoms but
not seeing the cause because in
the end, if something goes down, we
all know the executive team doesn't
care what specifically is going on.
They care that someone is on
the hook to fix it, and they
want it fixed immediately.
So we need to be thinking
about this more holistically.
And what this means is we need to
shift our thinking of application
monitoring network monitoring,
infrastructure monitoring, et cetera.
And we need to think about full stack,
system aware observability that can
see the end-to-end picture and allow
us to know when any aspect of the
application is struggling, what's
going on, and how to resolve it.
This is where we need to stop thinking
about the old world of application
performance monitoring, just thinking
about the application layer and code.
And we need to think about
the end-to-end system.
And so when you are looking at this
slide, it's showing you classically
where the realm of a PM has focused.
Now that we're talking about this being
much more distributed and cutting across
every aspect of the enterprise, we need
to be thinking about the service layer.
So all the dependent services that
sit underneath the app that tie into
things like the API gateway or identity
services or other shared dependencies
that ensure the application is running.
We need to be thinking
about the AI factory.
And if we're starting to use things
like GPUs or LLM observability to be
able to understand what's going on
with tokens and things like that, the
currency of AI workloads, to ensure
that they're functioning correctly,
we need to be able to see across
the network storage infrastructure
to ensure that's all working.
So when we think about the application,
it's no longer just this top layer.
Of the infrastructure, it is the
end-to-end piece from application
all the way down to infrastructure.
And again, cutting across every access
of the enterprise so that we can
clearly see when resource contention
arises or infrastructure bottlenecks,
or if there are noisy neighbors.
This lives outside the code, right?
So we don't wanna live in code
level observability anymore.
We need to live in system
level observability.
And this is where, I'll just put in a plug
for Verana for for a second because this
is where we have focused our entire vision
around observability, is we want to be
at the forefront of breaking these silos.
We want to enable people to understand
the end-to-end system and be able to
forge forward into that realm of ai,
knowing that their applications are
running, that the networks are all
functioning properly, that storage is
functioning properly, that the end users
experience is functioning properly.
And so we think about this from the
context of how do we actually, have
application observability and AI observe
factory observability and infrastructure
and service all under one view.
And the reason this is so important
is again, is when you have this
end-to-end view of the system, your
ability to handle things like root
cause analysis is gonna be faster.
Your meantime to recovery
is gonna be faster.
We're gonna be able to see relationships
across the distributed systems
that understand the interconnected
interconnectivity across these different
layers and be able to do things like cross
layer correlation to help you not just see
dashboards, but to see operational truth
and to resolve that operational truth.
Now.
Why this is also so important
is because from the standpoint
of the SRE, the architecture for
observability is quite different.
So when we think about this, we can't
think in terms of component products and
discreet observability components that
have visibility gaps between one another.
So when we think about this,
there's a couple of things
that are really important.
One is.
When you have data coming in from all
of these different layers, you need
to be able to co collect it across all
the different types of metrics, right?
Whether it's metrics, events,
logs, traces, things like that.
But just capturing that information
in a data lake isn't enough.
We need to have a system dependency
graph that can take all of this data and
continually analyze it to discover all
the relationships across the stack so that
when something breaks, we can actually see
that it's not just tied to infrastructure.
Data that's coming in, but there's a
complete connection and relationship
to what's going on in the network.
So the system dependency graph is
really important because it's the
thing that's gonna understand the
logic across all of these different
components, and it's also the thing
that's gonna make AI so smart, right?
As we start forging into
the realm of autonomous IT
operations, it's not just about.
Slapping agents on top of our existing
observability architecture, it's putting
it on top of the best data MOS model
possible to get the best outcomes, right?
So the more data you have with
relationships and correlations figured
out, the smarter your AI is gonna be.
If you're just doing application
performance monitoring and you have
an agent sitting on top of just that
layer analyzing what's going on in that
realm, just like humans are gonna have
visibility gaps, not be able to see
what's going on in the other layers,
the AI is gonna have the same problem.
So your agent is gonna make the
same pro mistakes as the human,
but just now at machine speed.
The data model is critical and
that's where things like the system
dependency graph are so important.
Now, once you have that data in the
right place, your machine learning
your ML models, et cetera, are gonna be
able to make smarter decisions, right?
'cause they're gonna have be better
data, not only in terms of relationships,
but that time series data tied to it.
Looking at trends and things
like that are critical as well.
Your autonomous agents are gonna be able
to traverse that data and do things like
automated root cause analysis faster.
When you have things like a MCP
server sitting on top of that, you're
now able to expose all that data
to the breadth and ecosystem of ai.
So you could start using things
like large language models like
Claude or OpenAI or Gemini to do.
Natural language query
and response on this data.
So you're democratizing this so
you're not just relying on a specific
individual who understands a script
that could access this data, but rather
you can now democratize it and open
it up to more people on the team to
access this data and make sense of it.
So there's a lot of power in terms
of re-architecting your observability
to think about this from the s
the standpoint of the system.
To capture that data into a system
dependency graph where you have
these relationships and now to
leverage your AI and ml and the
agents and whatnot to have smarter,
better decisions coming out of it.
So the observability architecture
here is really critical.
So we wanna kind of dive in from
here to kinda show you some examples.
Of how this works in the wild.
So we're gonna show you some
examples of how we think about this.
And so I'm gonna hand off to David
McNerney, our director of Product
Management, to walk you through some
of this and demonstrate for you how
we can apply this through Verano.
Speaker 10: Thanks Daniel.
And like you mentioned, I'm gonna
jump through a quick demo of
Tana's application observability.
I'll talk about how we can give
visibility across those distributed
systems that, that Daniel was just
mentioning and then walk through.
A live scenario of we get an alert
that our checkout is timing out.
We need to go and investigate,
find the root cause, and get
a fix as quickly as possible.
And then, and I'll also show how we can
pull some of that same data into our,
through our MCP server to be able to go
out and provide it to other AI agents.
So I, I'm here in the Verana
platform like Daniel mentioned a
modular platform, so I can see the
other modules up here at the top.
And I'm here in our global
trace topology view.
So when we talk about the
application being a distributed
system, I think we increasingly see
that as a hybrid system as well.
Imagine you're an organization where
you have workloads running in Google
Cloud and GKE autopilot clusters.
Azure on traditional VMs and storage
that's living in the data center
and is never gonna move there.
But your applications span
those hybrid environments.
You need visibility
across that entire system.
And that's this what this view here that
I'm showing our trace topology gives you.
So I can see here my checkout application.
I can see the data coming into it
from our booking agent through our
front end and where the errors request
times and latency might be spiking.
And then I can see after checkout,
people are gonna go into the product
catalog, shipping cart, email can
track that application request
throughout the hybrid environment.
What's really powerful about this
though, is we want to have that overall
visibility into the hybrid system.
And we have that right here
with our vertical topology.
So I could see my application hops
throughout the system, and then I can
see here my checkouts lives within this
astronomy, namespace, and my OCS flow.
Cluster or node.
And then on in my larger astronomy
cluster this will work across
those hybrid environments.
So it could be running in a VM on
premise, could be running in any of the
cloud providers and can see how those
applications are talking to each other.
You'll also get, some good
details, like all of the related
trace paths for this service.
All the overall trace paths for
the system that we're seeing.
So that's how we can really see
across those hybrid systems.
But where we see customers oftentimes
struggling is when something breaks.
Maybe our logs live in one tool.
We have an infrastructure
monitoring for our data center.
We have a cloud native monitoring
for our AWS environment.
I need to correlate that
across my entire system.
Set up a war room with five different
teams where we spend two to three
hours arguing about who's responsible.
So I'm here on my alerts page and
I've got this alert coming in that
our web server has a response time
breach, and I'm gonna jump into it.
One of the agents that we've been
building into our platform actually gives
you a nice plain English response so I
can see here exactly what happened, my
response time's up to three seconds.
Our normal SLO value is 0.09 seconds.
Definitely something I
want to take a look at.
One of the things a lot of
our customers like is, this is
all generated out of the box.
You can go in and tweak thresholds
and set manual thresholds but we'll
automatically learn what's that normal
behavior and then how is it performing.
So I can see a lot of interesting details
just here on the what happened and I
can see the exact, this is my threshold
and this is where we are currently.
I can jump into the influencer metrics.
So when we're talking about observing
the whole system, I'm now bringing in
the underlying infrastructure metrics
that application is running on.
I, this is running on Kubernetes.
I can see things like my node disc
utilization, my IO bandwidth, my
deployment status, and replicas
but all the data that you need to
troubleshoot this alert, and I can
see it across my node, my trace,
my pod, or my trace services.
No related alerts here, but if there
are, they'll be automatically correlated.
And then I'll show that
same related ology.
So I can see in this case, the
traffic's coming from my web server.
We're starting to see slowdowns between
cart cache and cart service with some
errors and then some additional errors
between cart service and DD service.
So we know we have a slow response time.
How do we troubleshoot it?
This is where the VERANA
troubleshooting tab comes through.
I think we have a couple of different
root cause analysis engines throughout
our platform as we're looking at
different types of telemetry data.
But here we're looking into
an application slowdown.
So I've got a nice again, agent
based summary of where my, not only
symptoms are, but my detected cause.
So I can see with the legend, any
of my yellow bells or a symptom,
any of the pink or magenta.
Is gonna be my detect detected
cause so I can see my DB service
is having some disc errors and a
certificate expiration warning.
We're seeing increased error
rates concentrated with slow query
detection and timeout errors.
So I know that my DB service is
my root cause and that's where I
need to go and implement a fix.
I can see that this is also impacting.
Other parts of that flow.
My part service, it has
some increased error rates.
My part cash service is
also seeing error rates.
We're seeing some events in other
places in this transaction, and
you can see this all visualized
down below in our fishbone diagram.
So you can think of this as our s se
SRE in a box help go through the set of
standard checks to uncover the root cause.
So I can see on my web server, we
have some resource metrics that
are out of band, some performance
metrics, some operations and events.
My cart service similarly, but
let's jump into the root cause one.
So looking at my DB service.
I now in my troubleshooting package have
all of the information at my fingertips to
be able to troubleshoot it to this alert.
I've got my trace path volumes, my
service latencies, my operation latencies.
I can see that disc error event
that's being correlated automatically.
When I talk to our support team, the
first thing that they do when there's an
issue is they want to go check the logs.
So you're gonna have the related
logs available right here.
I can see these are my ones
with errors and exceptions.
So we had to fail to export trace.
And then that here's that DB service
timeout that we just had surfaced.
All tied together with where it
sits within your infrastructure.
So I've got now in about two
minutes I've gone from, there's
an application slowdown and I know
the root cause is my DB service.
This is something when I talk to
customers, if I have those point
solutions, my, my cloud monitoring, my
infrastructure monitoring, my application
monitoring, this would be jumping
between 3, 4, 5 different screens.
Having this all at your fingertips.
So once we know what's wrong
next, it's time to fix it.
And this is where Tana's
action engine comes in.
We can run policies directly from,
or execute actions directly from the
alert as well as track that history.
So I can come in and I
can see the activity.
In this case, we had the RCA
based on the anomaly condition.
When we're talking about those activities.
And when I talk to customers it's a mixed
bag of how automated they want to go.
Maybe it's a low risk situation.
We're looking at cloud cost and we want
to go delete an unattached DBS volume.
Sure the system can go
do that automatically.
But if we're touching production, we
wanna make sure we have a human in the
loop and then can come and meet our
existing implementation methodology.
So maybe we use Ansible and I
want to go create a playbook.
Maybe I need a Jira ticket that.
Three different people need to approve
before we kick off that, that playbook.
And that's where the Verana
alert response policies come in.
So just like everything else with
verana, a lot available out of the box.
But then you can come in and
customize based on your use case.
So going back to that DB service
error, I've got my copilot here.
We can do, it's as simple as, when
DB service has a certificate warning.
Create a Jira ticket to update
cert and we'll assign it to Daniel.
So Daniel, you're getting
an action item here.
So as simple as this, the onic co-pilot's
gonna take my plain English explanation.
It'll take a second as it runs
and we'll spit out a yamo based
policy that I can then customize.
So here we go.
It's gonna create a D Jira ticket when we
see that DB service certificate warning
and it's gonna assign it to Daniel with
a priority to high that we need to go and
update the certificate and fix the issue.
This could be a full, automation, go
resize a vm, add additional storage
while all keeping that human in the loop.
So just walk through how Verana gives
that visibility across the hybrid system.
How when there's a application
slowdown, we can correlate that
to the underlying infrastructure
and really point to the true root
cause, which is just the symptoms.
When I think about what's next
and Daniel mentioned this, we hear
everybody talking about ai and r.
Version and that's where we've started
to roll out support for an MMCP server.
So let me grab that same
alert for an example.
So here's this SLO Trace Path Alert
that we are just looking at it.
And I'm gonna jump into my go window.
And Daniel, let me know if you're not
seeing this 'cause of my screen share.
But I can come in and Goose is a, an
open source agent agnostic orchestrator.
So I'm running with my Gemini API
key, and then I can use this to
hook into other MCP servers like
Jira, ServiceNow, and extend this.
But I can come in and ask those, what
can you tell me about Alert Blank?
And just to save some time, I'm
going to jump into my prebuilt one.
So you can see the MCP is gonna go
through, fetch that alert, it's gonna
come back with that same summary data
that we were just looking at I can also
do, additional investigation there.
It's, tell me about other
alerts fired at the same time.
We'll be able to go and do that ongoing
investigation, being able to bring,
leveraging the MCP server to bring
Tana's intelligence to other tools and
solutions where we can kick work on it.
So that's that's what I had for you
all in terms of a quick demo of.
Tana application observability.
Always happy to answer additional
questions or feel free to connect
on LinkedIn or things like that.
Speaker 9: That's great, David.
Thanks for sharing.
All of that great stuff
on the Tana platform.
And in particular, I think the whole
piece of seeing, not just the fact
that we're talking about system where
observability, but just seeing how
autonomous agents can help us scale.
The job of the SRE to help us resolve
these issues and also the whole
portability of this into the broader
AI ecosystem so we can leverage all
the great tools that are out there
or that are coming out over time.
So we hope you enjoyed this session.
As David mentioned, please feel free to
connect with me or David on LinkedIn.
We'd love to continue the conversation
and appreciate the opportunity
to participate in this event.
Thank you very much.
Speaker 10: Thanks everybody.
I.