Hello, friends.
Hope you are all doing great and
having a great time in this conference.
My name is Jit.
I'm working as a test architect with
about 15 years of experience spanning
across various industry types, like right
from manufacturing and then banking,
financing, retail, telecom, crm, whatnot.
And in fact I got a, opportunity to
work with various clients across the
globe, right from, my first project is
in Tokyo, Japan, and then I worked in
Singapore for about four years, and then
India, then Europe, few countries in
Europe, and then last 10 years in USA.
Okay, before getting into the topic, I
would like to thank Con 42 for giving
me this opportunity and helping me to
bring out my ideas in front of you.
So today's my topic is building a
resilient test automation, a universal
framework for service access.
So it's a revolutionary approach to
tackle software testing challenges and
enhance efficiency across the enterprise.
Okay, so before getting into the topic,
I would like to show you what are the
challenges currently the software testing
is facing and how I'm going to address it.
Okay, so this is software
testing as a whole.
It consists of 30 to
35% of the project cost.
So any software or any app on your
phone, it undergo a rigorous testing.
So to have a bug free product into
the market, there goes in lot of
testing effort, which is almost
30 to 35% of the project cost.
But still there are a lot of
challenges there and there is lot of
improvements and transformation needed.
And more importantly, even the
AI right now is not anywhere near
to replace a software testing.
Yes, it can replace the development
programming, but it's not anywhere
near to replace the software testing.
Okay.
Now, let's see, what are
the major challenges?
So one is a tool fragmentation
any organization will have
thousands of tools in their stack,
hundreds of tools in their stack.
And every tool, it, it has its own
advantages, disadvantages it needs a lot
of effort and a lot of strategy to bring
out a proper tool to, help with the test
automation and then maintenance overhead.
So as we bring in so many tools in
the market variety, it needs regular
maintenance, not just that software
testing or test automation is all
about writing a piece of code to test
the another piece of code, right?
So as the application grows.
Even the testing code also will grow into
tons and tons of lines of code, which in
reality becomes unmanageable code, right?
Because the.
Software testers are not professional
developers and professional
developers will not have that testing.
Real creativity.
See, testing is a creativity job, right?
So to bring the best things in
place and achieve a, applicable
solution is like highly impossible.
And that insufficient coverage.
Yes.
Most of the times, the software
automation test script would be
under maintenance and it'll not be
available for us to achieve the.
Optimum coverage.
So every time it'll be like targeted
functionality, targeted screens,
specific screens will be automated,
and then resource constraints.
So looking at these levels of
complexity, handling hundreds of
tools maintaining tons of lines
of code and last minute hiccups.
So a resource should be highly skillful.
Highly knackle and he has
to have a huge strategy.
So generally, organizations
struggle with maintaining automation
across diverse tools and mostly
achieve pass partial discovery.
So as of today, test automation
ease a loss making business.
Yes.
So now what is my solution?
What is my solution is
targeting to achieve?
If you all heard about the buzzwords
in the market right now in the test
automation market, script plus automation
is the mostly heard buzzword, right?
But my solution, it's beyond script
plus it's instant automation.
So even script plus automation also
requires to configure the objects,
create the flows, maintain the tons
of flows in the application, right?
So all these I achieve, using
a tool agnostic architecture.
So in respect of the tool,
application or the domain, the
architecture remains always same.
And this architecture is flexible
enough to cater to various testing
domains like functional testing,
database testing, API, testing, whatnot.
And the soul and heart of my applica.
My framework is virtual
application modeling.
So in general, most of the automation
efforts goes in UI automation.
So here we bring in virtual
application modeling that
will help save tons of effort.
So I'll show you how we achieve
it, and then unified approach.
As I told you the core framework
remains same, and it is.
Not going to change.
And even the, the plug and play of the
peripheral tools around this architecture.
So it's all unified, so it's like
a breeze for anybody to just jump
in and achieve the automation.
So to, to sum it up, it's a
UUF my, it's my framework.
Universal automation framework transcends
traditional script plus solutions by
delivering gen new instant automation
through groundbreaking innovation.
So far you would not have heard
about in instant automation,
and this is it for you.
Okay, so let's look at
the know my architecture.
As I told, my architecture will have
a tool agnostic OB object repository.
So right now there are many open
source tools which will help you to
create a standalone object repository.
So using this object repository,
my framework will generate
a virtual application.
You might be a little wondering
what is this application, virtual
application, what is its name?
Generally manual testers
write their testing.
Assuming there is some application
and there are some fields.
All, it's all their imagination, right?
And they write in a kind of whiteboard,
just write some text out there
and, embed the test data there.
So for anybody to use the test steps
or test data, it is highly impossible
unless they manually copy the data
and use it in for the scripts.
But here the virtual application, what
does the virtual application does is
so going forward, the manual testers
write their test case, looking at
the application next to their screen.
And also they can use this virtual
application to enter the data validation
points and then sequences, right?
So this captures all of that.
And we have a concept called routines.
So when a manual tester starts
written manual test case, there will
be a lot of repeated steps, right?
So every time we did not do it manually.
We have a routine.
So just.
Create a routine and pick that
pull that flow from a routine.
So that means we are automating the
manual test generation process as well.
So now let's say we have
developed some test cases.
We have entered the test data
in the virtual application
instead the plane text boxes.
So now what our framework does, ease.
So based on the data given in the virtual
application, it'll generate a keyword
driven data sheet, so to its name.
This keyword driven data sheet drives
the testing test automation tool.
So we have a test automation tool.
We have a generic framework, which
is very common component across
all automation frameworks and which
hardly takes any time to develop.
So this generic framework is
driven by the keyword data sheet.
That means as I write the manual
test case, my data for automation
and my framework are ready.
All I just need to need is to trigger
the test and in fact, we have a
generic reporting structure as well
where it saves all the data un until
the leaf level and it's up to us to
plug in any third party reporting
tool and get the level of details.
We want, okay, so this is
all about my application.
Now you understand, right?
What does instant automation means?
Going forward, I need not touch
my automation data or automation
framework, automation tool, or anything.
I just have to update my manual
test case and my automation ready.
So forget about what kind
of tool you are using.
You just pick any tool in the market.
Every tool in the market is compatible
with keyboard driven framework.
Yeah, that's overall my architecture
and how it is going to help so
these are the efficiency gains.
We see, we saw on an average of 78% of
maintenance reduction because in fact
there is no maintenance at all because
we are not writing any line of code or
to say, 10% of line of code compared
to traditional automation because we
have to generate the generic framework.
But still this maintenance, the 20 22%
of the maintenance is also contributed
to the manual test case update.
Which is already included in
the manual testing cost, but
still we want to put it here.
And then our development is 65% faster
and we increase the coverage 82%.
So what this coverage means, like in
general when you have to execute test
run a test for my production release.
At least, 30 or 40% of my test
cases would be under maintenance.
But here, since there is a least
maintenance effort, maximum test
cases could be executed for my
releases and then cost savings.
So we have taken a lower point of 40%.
But in fact, it is more why?
Because there is no
maintenance cost at all.
So as you see, it's already reduced.
So all that we need is to maintain the
framework and its robust robustness.
So organizations implementing uf reports
significant implements across key metrics.
So cost benefit equation as we
see in traditional approach.
You have to maintain a big
suite of tools and the licensing
costs across multiple platforms.
And the major time ma major cost
expenditure is on the resources training.
And then their management.
And then significant ongoing maintenance
costs because we will be using all
our energy resources, everything on
the maintenance and then T effort.
Yes.
Why we have to do the redundant effort
when the tool can take care of it.
So now you have approach.
So we substantially reduce
the tool dependencies and
associate licensing cost because.
We use tool for very less amount of time.
Basically the number of licenses
would be reduced because we are
reducing the development effort.
And streamline skill requirements and
then centralized efficient centralized
maintenance and maximize resource
sharing because our core framework
is going to be standard, right?
My resources can work any project across.
All that they need to know is
little bit of functional, and
any troubleshooting with the
automation scripts, they can do it.
So not just that, it also enhances the
team collaboration, as we see, it's
a crawl, cross-functional alignment,
the common language across all teams.
It boosts productivity, resource sharing
as we discussed earlier, and then
knowledge transfer is just a breeze.
So enterprise integration benefits,
as we discussed, it's a unified
platform for any tool, any application
including API database, whatnot.
And then it's a, it
supports multiple stack.
And then instead of having a lead
and then architect for every team,
we will have a centralized architect
who overall maintains the robustness.
And in fact, I have my own framework.
I can hand it over to you.
If you need, okay.
And real world success scenarios.
We implemented in a finance service form,
we reduced 90% of script maintenance.
Yes, as there is no script at all,
so there is nothing to maintain.
And then healthcare provider.
We automated fi x more test
cases and saved millions to them.
And then retail enterprise increased
coverage from 40 to 85% and the
defects are down to 70% because
we started using automation in
the unit testing phase itself.
So this is the most interesting
part of which I want to stress
out is the future already.
Yes.
As we discussed earlier, programming
AI can replace the programming,
but not testing because testing
is still a creative job, right?
But by standardizing the testing
process, we, and automate many of
the the testing process activities.
For example, creating tests automatically
based on usage patterns and migrating.
The script from one tool to the, its
later version, or migrating the scripts
from one tool to one technology stack
to a different technology stack.
All these areas we can use AI
and then predictive analysis,
like anticipating potential
failure points before they occur.
So we can use ai to read,
analyze our reports.
And then come up with a predictive
analysis and then IOT device
integration in general iot
device is a huge, tedious task.
Since we are significantly reducing the
amount of time invested in developing
the test, we can use that time in
invest in developing the instructure,
developing the infrastructure.
That's how we can focus more time
on integrations and achieve iot
device testing with multiple device.
One of our project we
implemented mobile testing with
50 different mobile questions.
And then security integration testing.
So this is not exactly
the security testing.
This is all about the,
accessibility and workflow testing.
So where we have a thousands of
resources lacks of thousands of
profiles and lacks of scenarios, right?
Yeah, take action.
Implement UAF.
If post this session, if anybody have
questions, you can reach out to me.
I'm always happy to help and
happy to see you success.
So basically, I can help you in assess
your current stage, define, implement
strategy, train team, measure results.
I think hope you got the idea,
but in still in any case, if you
need any help reach out to me.
I'm happy to help.
That's all folks.
Thank you very much for listening to
me patiently and I hope you're able
to, get some information and you'll
be able to appreciate my efforts.
Thank you once again.
Bye.