Hello everybody.
Welcome to Con 42 SRE Conference.
I'm Shania Prasad, a senior product
manager at Cisco Systems, and I'm really
excited to be here and present to you all.
The topic for today is building
resilient digital infrastructures,
integrating networking and security
for agile secure operations.
So let's get right into it.
We are combining networking and
security in a smart, flexible way
so that businesses can run securely
and adapt quickly to change instead
of treating these as separate silos,
for example, a network team and a
security team working independently,
they're being brought together so
everything works smoothly and securely.
Here we've dug deep into some
statistics to understand why this
is important and what returns an
organization can expect to get.
Organizations that take this approach
of a unified networking and security
can see a 15% reduction in breach costs.
That is because integrated systems help
detect and respond faster, minimizing both
financial loss and reputational damage.
They can also achieve faster containment.
For example, let's say ransomware
starts spreading inside a network.
An integrated setup can automatically
segment the threat, threat, alert
the right teams and block lateral
movements all in a fraction of
time compared to silo tools.
And they can also
experience better incidents.
Management teams can work
cross-functionally with better
visibility, governance, compliance.
No more chasing data across
dis disconnected systems.
In short, integration is
not just about efficiency.
It directly improves your ability
to respond to threats, protect
your business, and stay agile.
With that, let's talk about a lot of
these key convergence technologies that
are coming together in the industry
such as software defined networking,
secure Access, service Edge, or
sass, e and zero trust architecture.
These three technologies are reshaping
how we build secure agile infrastructure.
Software-defined networking brings
programmability into the network,
making it easier to scale, automate,
and adapt as business needs change.
It's like moving from static roadmaps
to real time traffic control, SSE on
the other hand, and brings networking
and security together in the cloud.
It's how companies can protect their
users and applications at the edge without
back howling all their traffic or adding
complexity for security inspection.
Zero.
Trust architecture is something that
you may all have heard a lot of it.
It changes the security model entirely.
Nobody is trusted by default.
Every user device request name, it has
to be verified each and every time.
And their posture is being tracked
consistently and new policies are new.
Policies are applied every single
time the posture changes together.
These will form the backbone of a
modern converged infrastructure,
one that is secure, flexible, and
built for the way that we work today.
With this, let's start
looking at some market trends.
Where technologies are
gaining a lot of traction.
This chart is highlighting the projected
growth of the security service edge
market over the next five years, and the
trend is clear demand is accelerating.
What is driving this?
The shift to hybrid work, increased
resilience on cloud applications,
the need to secure users and data
outside the traditional parameter
is all driving this change.
Organizations are looking for integrated
cloud delivered security that scales, and
SSE is right at the center of that demand.
As the market nearly triples between now
and 2028, it's clear this isn't just a
passing trend, it's a strategic shift.
And vendors who can deliver this
convergence across networking and
security are best positioned to lead.
Great.
Now let's move in to understand a little
more about this entire process and how the
silos are, uh, formed in the first place.
This pyramid here illustrates the journey
from siloed operations to two integration.
Why does this matter for security and
operational effectiveness at the base?
As you can see, we have siloed operations.
When networking and security are
managed by separate teams, they have
different tools, different goals, and
often they have limited communication.
This is where many organizations start,
and it's where the friction, blind spots,
and delayed responses tend to live.
The first step in all of this is adopting
common tools, bringing teams into shared
platforms so they can at least work on the
same data and use consistent technologies.
It is not full integration yet,
but it builds a foundation.
Next step is where organizations begin
aligning processes, harmonizing workflows,
handoffs, and incidents response.
This removes the guesswork and
finger pointing that slow teams
down when time matters the most.
At the top of the pyramid, we reach
integrated teams where networking and
security professionals are not just
coexisting, but collaborating as one.
This is where we see the greatest gains in
agility, risk reduction, and performance.
Security becomes proactive.
Networking becomes intelligence.
And together they create a
much stronger defense posture.
So the message here is simple.
True security convergence isn't about the
tools, it's about people and processes.
And the higher you climb, the stronger
and more resilient your operations become.
So now let's start with understanding
the operational benefits.
To begin with, we can talk
about enhanced performance.
When security is directly built
into your network, traffic can flow
more effectively and efficiently.
There's no unnecessary detours.
There are fewer bottlenecks and
there's faster application access.
Users get a better experience without
compromising on the protection.
Next there is faster response.
Integrated systems can detect threats in
real time and act immediately, whether
that means isolating a device, blocking
traffic, triggering alerts, you name it.
The days of slow manual
handoffs between teams are gone.
Next is cost efficiency.
When you consolidate tools and unify
processes, you're reducing redundancy.
Not just in licensing costs, but
in overheads, in training, in
operational complexity, and so on.
You are doing more with
fewer moving parts.
The final thing I wanna talk
about here is stronger protection.
A unified approach closes the gaps
that attackers can often exploit.
You get consistent policies, broader
visibility and seamless convergence across
users, devices, and location, whether
they're on-prem, remote, or in the cloud.
So these aren't just technical
improvements that actually business
enablers, performance, speed,
savings, security all together.
When.
They come together improving the whole
system, the silos start to come down.
In this slide, we're gonna
talk about AI and how that is
covering this entire system.
As threats grow more complex and
more faster, traditional security
models are not able to keep up.
This is where AI powered convergence
steps in turning reactive operations
into proactive, intelligent defense.
It starts with threat detection.
AI constantly scans network traffic and
behavior patterns to spot anomalies,
things as humans might miss, but that.
Will stand out any day, right, because
it's, it's done by a machine and it's
trained on millions of data points.
From there, we move to analysis.
Machine learning engines evaluate these
anomalies, filtering noise from risk.
They reduce false positives and
give security teams clarity.
They're not drowning in alerts.
They're focusing on threats that matter.
Then comes response.
With integrated systems, AI can take
immediate action, whether that's isolating
a device, blocking, suspicious activity,
or escalating to human for review, the
key is speed, minutes, or even seconds
can make a huge difference in the impact.
And finally, adaptation.
AI doesn't just react, it actually learns.
Every incident makes a system
smarter, turning detection models
and response playbooks automatically.
The more data that it sees, the better
it gets at defending your environment.
So this isn't just automation,
it's intelligence at scale.
AI is bridging the gap between
networking and security, accelerating
detection, reducing the manual
effort required, and also improving
resilience with every single incident.
As we talk about the benefits of
convergence, it's equally important to
acknowledge the real world challenges
that any organization might face
when they're trying to implement it.
First, there is a skills gap.
There is a clear shortage of
professionals with expertise across
both networking and security.
Only 24% of IT professionals are
proficient in both the domains.
This makes it very
difficult to design, deploy.
Manage converge solutions without
upskilling or bringing in outside help.
Bridging that gap requires
training, investments and closer
collaboration across teams.
Second challenge can be legacy systems.
Most organizations are still running
on outdated infrastructure that
was not built for integration.
These environments lack compatibility
with modern security frameworks,
making convergence very difficult,
and it's like retrofitting a jet
engine into a propeller plane.
Moving forward means serious
investment, not just in tech, but
in rethinking architectures and
third organizational resistance.
Even with the right tools and
people, culture can be a blocker.
Networking and security teams often
operate in silos, as I mentioned
earlier, each with their own
priorities, tools and ways of working.
Merging them requires more
than just a technical plan.
It takes change management,
execute a sponsorship and a shared
vision of what success looks like.
The good news though is that
these challenges are solvable,
but only when they're addressed
head on with clear strategy.
That includes people, processes,
and program alignment.
Let's now move into understanding
Cloud native security integration.
Securing cloud environments is not just
about lifting and shifting existing tools.
It requires a fundamentally new approach,
one that is built into the cloud, cloud
fabric from day one, and that's what
we're gonna talk about in this slide.
First, we're gonna talk about
identity, identity-based access.
A distributed world users are everywhere.
Working from home on mobile
across SaaS and cloud platforms.
The parameter is no longer physical.
It's identity that matters.
That means policies must follow the user
and not the device or the data center.
Identity becomes the
control plane for security.
Next, distributed security devices.
In a cloud native environment,
traffic doesn't just pass through
a central gateway anymore.
Security must be embedded at every single
access point across users, devices,
workloads, APIs, you name it, whether it
is east-west traffic within the cloud,
or access from external endpoints.
Protection has to be
everywhere and all the time.
Lastly, but not least, the cloud
network architecture itself.
Security cannot be bolted
as an afterthought.
It has to be part of the initial
infrastructure design integrated
into the way that the services are
deployed, connected and scaled.
This includes microsegmentation, service
meshes, and cloud native firewalls
all embedded into the way that the
network operates in the first place.
The key takeaway here is that Cloud
Native security integration is
proactive, scalable, and user centric.
It's all about building security
in and not just bolting it on or
adding it on, so that protection
becomes how the cloud works and not a
separate process running alongside it.
Lemme try to give a real life example.
Um, just to make this
a little more clearer.
So we'll take an example from
the financial services sector.
Let's say that a global bank was facing
a growing number of attacks across
its distributed network, and this is a
challenge that only became more common
with hybrid work and cloud adaptation.
Now their biggest bottleneck wasn't
just the threats themselves, it
was the response to the threats.
The security and networking
teams were siloed.
They were working in parallel, but
they were not working together.
And that disconnect caused
delays in threat detection and
response, increasing the risk.
To fix this, the bank rolled out a SAS
E framework, combining networking and
security into a single architecture.
And they also paired that with
integrated SD-WAN to optimize
networking and control at their edge.
But technology wasn't enough.
They also stood up a joint network
operations center, bringing together
both teams under a unified model.
The impact of this was
immediate and measurable.
They saw an immediate reduction
in the threat detection time
from hours previously to minutes.
Now, they cut a huge budget annually in
operational costs by eliminating redundant
tools, streamlining their workflows,
and also improvised performance.
They also got a boost
in network efficiency.
Users got faster and more reliable access
without really compromising on security.
This, as you can see, is a clear
example of what convergence looks like
in practice and why just a technical
upgrade is not enough, but a it.
It's also a business enabler.
Finally, I just want to leave
you all with a few thoughts.
When it comes to converging networking,
security success depends on having
a clear, actionable roadmap.
And this is what I'm gonna
talk about in this slide.
It starts with assessment, evaluating
whether your current state, your
architecture, your tools, and your
organization silos are present.
Uncovering where the gaps are and where
integration can drive the most value.
Many organizations find that they
have overlapping tools, fragmented
policies, and misaligned teams.
This is their chance to
reset the whole foundation.
From there on, you can move into STR
strategy development, and this is
where you define the future state,
a unified framework that brings both
security and networking together.
Again, it's not just about the technology.
It means defining the governance roles
and responsibilities so everyone knows how
they need to operate in this new model.
Next comes the pilot implementation.
Now, this is a very critical phase.
Rather than roll out everything
at once, you test integrated
solutions in smaller controlled
environments, you validate that.
That performance is actually improving.
Risk is decreasing, and
operations are getting simpler.
Then you gather feedback and fine tune
your system before a broader rollout.
Last but not the least, you move to a
full deployment in your organization.
At this point, you scale the proven
solution across the enterprise.
But you don't just stop there.
You establish a continuous improvement
loop because threats are going to keep
evolving and you so will the business.
So ongoing refinement will
keep you ahead of both.
The key takeaway here, and my ending
note here is that transformation does
not have to be risky or overwhelming.
Start small, measure the outcomes
and expand it with confidence.
Thank you so much all
of you for being here.
It was my pleasure to present to
all of you and I'd love to hear
as well what your thoughts on.
Thank you so much again.