Hello everyone.
Welcome to my session.
My name is Samuel Bafi.
I'm an in pretty simple
solutions architect with AWS.
Today I'm gonna be presenting about
Amazon, Aurora DS L, which is a new
relation database offering on AWS.
So let's start talking a lot, a
little bit about some of the current
relation database challenges, right?
We can give an example about
running a Postgres database.
In whatever, service or platform.
It could be on your own EC2, it could
be on your on-premise, or potentially
it could be on RDS as a service as well.
Some of the challenges that
we have is scalability, right?
Traditional databases have the
capacity limitations that you would
have a instance, and that instance,
that server is your limitation.
So customers would be constrained
by these capacity limits of
this traditional database.
And it becomes very hard to rightsize your
application for this specific server that
you might need to configure when you're
provisioning this specific instance.
S also availability because it's a
challenge because now if you have only
one server and you know that server
goes down, we have lower resiliency
that could potentially lead into
unplanned down times, and it could
impact your database availability.
Of course, there are ways that you
can have, read only replicas and
you can potentially help alleviate
some of those concerns, but those
are not very easy to manage.
And there are a lot of pros and
cons about ab, about that, right?
So those are the functional challenges.
When you look at the operational
challenges, one of the things
that is very common, and I keep
hearing from many customers, is.
Infrastructure management, like patching,
upgrades requiring a lot of engineering
time to, prepare potentially the database,
prepare the server, test those, and
that is a lot of engineering effort
that goes just to keep your database
up and running, also is the complexity.
Right now you have a
lot of infrastructure.
You need to make sure you're installing
the operating system, you're installing
the database, like the Postgres, your
parts, that you're doing a lot of fine
tuning configuration, which that only
not, that not only requires engineering
effort, but also require expertise.
That becomes very challenge, right?
So with some, if not all of
these challenges in mind.
AWS have announced in December of
2024, the reinvent Amazon, Aurora
d sql, which is a cloud native
serverless distributed SQL database
with virtually unlimited scalability
and the highest availability of AWS.
We are on this talk, we're gonna
talk about how that was possible.
All the behind the scenes important
architecture decisions that were made
in order to make these available.
So you have virtually unlimited scaling.
That is one of the core concepts of
our RDS QL because you have the compute
and multiple steps of the compute that
are independently managed and scaled.
You can have rights and reads also
being scale separately and, both will
be up and down as you need it, right?
That allows you to have a
business continuity because
you can now have a active.
Multi-region distributed relation
database on databases that is
completely managed for you.
And you're gonna talk, spend a
lot of time on the talk today
explaining how that actually works.
How does it mean?
Because we know with traditional
relation databases, actually all the
relation databases there is a lot of
locking issues and how to make sure,
the consistency across different
replicas in different regions.
How does that work?
Okay.
Another aspect that has been designed
from the beginning is serverless.
There is no server to provision.
There is no server to patch.
There is no software niching
style, or maintain or operate.
It's completely serverless.
Serverless native serverless.
And fast and easy is the idea of RDCO is
very inspired on other, their offerings
on the AWS ecosystem for serverless.
So I'll give an example of
create a diamond db table.
Just create a D DB table and you can start
querying and actually insert data on that.
The same idea is trying to be
replicated here on our RD sql which,
it should be very quick if you
have familiarity Postgres because.
Our Rd CO is a Postgres compliant
database where you can run some
of the capabilities of Postgres.
If you are interested of some of
the capabilities and limitations,
please check our documentation,
but let's dive into the first.
Way you can run our RD sql.
So the first one is you can run our RD
SQL on a single region cluster if you
do not have the necessity to running
active multi region applications,
because those are, those can be expensive
and not every single application
requires you to have a active solution.
So if you are okay, have
as you've been running.
Potentially other traditional
databases on a single region.
You can create the s
QL on a single region.
By default, of course, because this
is a managed offering on AWS, when
you create a single region cluster,
you operate it active across three
availability zones always, right?
So you can see you have your VPC with
your application, you're gonna receive
an endpoint for that specific database.
You're gonna use that endpoint both
for reads and writes the compute.
The transaction logs, which you're
gonna talk about in the future of
this presentation, the storage are
actually replicated independently
across three availability zones.
This provides a 99.99% of availability
and all the transactions are
fast and local, and also maintain
acid properties of your database.
The transaction commits goes across
availability zones, ensure data
transactions are durable, isolated
anatomic, of course trying to maintain
actually maintaining the asset property.
So this is the single, region cluster
that I create, you'll have an option
if you want a single region cluster or
if you want a multi region cluster if
you're going to the multi region cluster.
Now Aurora, the SQL delivers five nines
of availability across multiple regions.
And the way this works, it's
very unique and very interesting.
So multi to region clusters provide two
regional endpoints, and on this scenario
we are talking about a linked region.
The way it works is you go on
your AWS console or use the CLI or
the API, you can create an neuro
DSL and you can say, I want a
secondary region as a linked region.
So in this example, you can
see that we have three regions
here into this architecture.
We have, region one, region
two, where each region it's
gonna have its own unique.
Endpoint.
So we are gonna talk about how reads
and writes work, but the good thing
about having a endpoint region is all
the reads that are gonna be done in that
specific region, using that specific
endpoint are always gonna be locally.
You don't need to go across
region, and that's one of
the main benefits of the sql.
But also rights are gonna be synchronous
getting replicated across regions.
At the time of commit, we are
gonna explain what that means.
In a moment, the regions are equal peers.
There is no leader or master
node in this situation.
And because you have the synchronous
replication between regions,
you always have a RPO of zero.
Which is really important for
mission critical applications.
Now you see here that we
have also a witness region.
So the witness region is
just replicating the journal.
So we will call that journal,
but that is where the transaction
logs of your database are.
And in case of a failure, we're
gonna explain in the end of the
presentation, in the case of failure.
Of that, of one specific region.
You also are gonna, you always
are gonna have a quorum because
this third region, which is the
witness region, but on the witness
region, you do not have an endpoint.
It's just a witness region that is
there to actually replicate it at
the transaction lock for the quorum.
So you have always three up and Right.
So let's talk a little bit
about the components of the sql.
So if we think about the components
of the C COEs, you have the front end.
So the front end you can think about,
the endpoint on each specific region
that you're gonna talk to, you know of.
Of course, that front end is being.
Being served to you across multiple
load balancers that are replicated
across multiple availability zones.
But the interesting part here
comes with query processor.
So the query processors are responsible
for executing the customer SQL,
returning data in response to reads,
buffering data in response to rights
and running the transaction protocol.
So that's where Postgres will be
running, then we have ad adjudicators.
Adjudicators are responsible for
deciding whether a transaction can be
commit while following isolation rules.
We're gonna explain how isolation rules
work in a moment for working with the
journal in order for the transaction to
actually be committed into the storage.
Everything you see here from the edge
educator to the crossbar are only gonna be
necessary if you're doing a right, right?
If you're doing a transaction
that requires a right.
The journal are an order data stream that
makes transactions durable and replicated
data between regions and availabilities.
The crossbar is just a way
that it can replicate it.
Your data into the storage
and of course the storage.
Where is the data is gonna be
completely replicated across
different storage partitions.
And, DSL takes a very interesting
approach of, replicating the different
pieces of data across different storage.
So we have the replication and
the performance capability.
Benefit given to you by default.
You don't need to even, you don't
see any of these components here.
We are just talking about
these components, so we have
an idea how it actually works.
So let's talk a little bit about how
different transactions, like a re
transaction, a right transaction operate,
so you understand how these components.
Which potentially by now are still
a little bit confusing, but how
these components will be put in
place and how do they work together.
So if we look here, let's just try
to illustrate how all works together.
So we reduce the complexity.
We'll follow a transaction from ra.
We are going to start with a RET
transaction and a base select statement.
Okay, let's imagine that a user is on a
specific region US is one, and that user
is looking to order pizza from a local
restaurant in let's say Virginia, right?
So what happens there is the user
decides what food he wants from the
restaurant based on a specific rating.
So in this case, let's select
all the restaurants where
ratings equals to four, right?
What happens behind the scenes at this?
From this point because you have
select, you've done the a select
statement, which is a read statement.
How does this SQL manage that statement?
So let's look into that.
So you have the client will
connect to the front end.
That means a specific regional endpoint.
This could be a
multi-regional linked cluster.
It could be a single reach for the
examples you're gonna provide today,
let's say they are all multi reach.
So when you do this specific request,
that request will go through a load
balance from the front end, and then
we will create a query processor.
It's where your, transaction
will actually happen.
The query processor will actually
use a start time, and this is one
of the very unique benefits and
capabilities of the SQL and AWS is.
This time that is being retrieved from
a local clock is using what we call
the Amazon Time Sink Service, which AWS
uses highly accurate global standard
time by leveraging satellite GPS signals
alongside with atomic clocks references,
which is crucial to ensuring that.
Time in one region and time in another
region are actually are actually aligned
because, speed of light and how clocks
are aligned can be problematically.
If you're not using atomic clock and
you have, satellite communications
to pinpoint that, right?
So when a query gets processor by the
query processor, we have time at the
start, which is a local clock, right?
So you receive that data.
Then the query processor, what it does is.
In this case, because it's a read
because it's a read statement, read
transaction, the query processor will
look for the shard map of the storage,
where the data is being stored on the
storage layer, and you go to the read
path, you go directly to the storage.
It doesn't need to go through
any adjudicator, any journal.
You go to the storage and then you
return, if you look here now you
return the data back to the query.
Processor and the query processor
will return the data to the front
end, return the data to the client.
So now these results, of
course, will be merged here when
it'll be sent to the customer.
There you go.
And you see the specific the specific
pizza place that you have selected.
Let's look at more complex query.
Where maybe the user does not
only want to run a simple select
transaction, but also wants to do some
interactive transaction potentially,
inserting data into the database.
So the query, of course, you're gonna
create a transaction, this case select
in a restaurants with rate four.
I actually want to see a specific,
a restaurant id, and I want
to see specific item, right?
You're selecting the item, then
you're saying, I want to order this
item, which is a pizza and then,
put this pizza into my order table.
So you selected the restaurant,
you chose the item you want,
and you placed the order.
Order.
Let's look at how these actually
worked behind the scenes with this sql.
So again, we, what we're gonna do here
is we are gonna have a transaction t
time using Amazon time sync, right?
What is gonna happen here
is the query processor.
We get a snapshot of the data
from that T type that they
start type the T star, right?
That snapshot is gonna be load into
the query processor and then every
single read and every single write will
only be done within that is specific.
Query processor is not
touching the storage yet.
He's using optimistic locking, which
allows, for concurrence concurrent.
Rights should be done at the
same time if they're not actually
using the same roles, right?
So in this S ql, the care processor
acts as holding tank for all these
statements waiting for a commit statement
before it sends the full transaction
to adjudicators to be checked.
We're gonna talk a little bit about what
Edge Educator does in a moment, right?
Think about the query processes
being displaced here now.
The cool thing about how this works
right is once you have a start of
the transaction, you have that tee
time you have, the cross region
transactions proceed very similar
to a single region transaction.
The red path is barely changed, so
you can just grab the data from the
storage nodes that have the charts.
Now when you do the select in
insert update, no cross region
interactions are required here.
Because the optimistic locking
that the CCO implements.
So the way this works is the latency
is only incurred at the commit time.
So on the query processors you're
gonna go through, you're gonna do
select, you're gonna do insert,
and you're gonna do update.
And once you finally have your snapshot
with all the commitments and sorry,
with all the data that needs to be
commit, it sends to the adjudicator.
And we're gonna talk about the
adjudicator in a moment, but it sent
to adjudicator and the goal of the
adjudicator is to go across both regions
that you have and make sure that after
your t start, you know that no is,
no other data has been transacted.
Into your storage and your journal that
you conflict with your specific request.
If there is only one of them is gonna
be committed and the other one's
gonna be aborted and they need to
ry, but if not, you know the commit
is when you incur the latency.
So you're not gonna incurring the latency
into every single select insert an update.
That is not how it works.
You only get the latency when
you're doing the commit cross reach.
So this means that reads, writes,
and updates are just as fast as they
would be in a single region database.
Only the commit part is where you incur
the cross region latency and the cross
region latency could go between 15 to
a hundred plus milliseconds, depending
how far each region that you have
linked together are from each other.
If they're close to each other
in, into the us, they're gonna
be a little bit faster between
20 to 30 to 40 milliseconds.
If they're far apart, it could
be hundreds of plus milliseconds
at the commit time because, speed
of flight is something that.
We cannot expedite, at
least for the time being.
So let's talk a little bit about
the query processor, because there
is a lot of innovation that has
been created behind the scenes.
So as you've seen, the query processor
is doing a lot of work is the HA Heart,
or where the SQL Architecture runs.
It runs inside what we call a fire crack
virtual machine, micro virtual machine.
Which is where the query processor
host within a server, in this
case, a bare metal instance, right?
A micro firecracker.
Micro VM was created and built for
Lambda in 2018, and this is the
same technology that the SQL Query
processors is using behind the scenes.
It's an open source micro
VM that AWS has open source.
And, we've used to put a secure
box around the Postgres engine.
So Postgres will be running on top of this
query processor, which is a micro view.
So the cool thing about this is as
your database grows in a scale and a
demand, this can literally scales to
little tens or one query processor at
any given time or zero if you don't
have any requests to tens of millions
of query processor is being created.
Each query is gonna create a query
processor, like each transaction, sorry,
is gonna create a query processor.
Another good thing is the
support of I snapshot isolation.
So in this SQL, we support an isolation
level call snapshot isolation.
So what does act this actually mean?
It means that each transaction
operated operates on a consistent
snap snapshot of the database as it
exists at the start of the transaction.
So when as you do the right from
the storage, and you see here on the
right of the screen, the when there is
snapshot is being created into the query
processor, that is a shot isolation
who only exists on the query processor.
If you have any rights and
updates and inserts, then you
will try to do the commit.
If it's multi-region use, use the
adjudicator to make sure there is no
there is no conflict across the commits
across different regions, right?
So the transaction begins, proceeds
through the SQ execution phase where
the read see the consistent snapshot
being put back into the micro view.
So when the right operation occurs,
like an insert or update, they
are not immediately applied to
the storage, and that is a very
important thing to think, right?
Very different than other databases
and how databases are architected.
If you would do a read or an
update or an insert, it would be
automatically done in storage.
At this time, because we are using
Optimistic Locking, what it does is uses
that snapshot that it got from, your read
pad, and every time it has a right, like
an update on insert, you run that locally.
Instead of we spo, of course, we spo
these rights locally and you create a
private workspace for this transaction.
What this approaches allows you
to do is read your rights so you
don't need to subsequent read.
Within the same transaction that can
see pending changes on the storage that
increases performance and the scalability,
which is one of the very incredible
things that the CQ allows you to do.
But as you are doing these rights
locally on your a credit processors,
there is a challenge, right?
What happens if there is
another transaction that is
trying to write at the same.
A role that your existing transaction has.
So let's say you have transaction
and transaction B, you need to have
a capability on your database engine
that can look across these specific
transactions and decide is there a
conflict or is there not a conflict?
And that's what the
adjudicator allows you to do.
The job of the dedicated should detect
and resolve conflict between transactions
and ensure their rights are consistent.
Because you have relation database,
they need to be asset, and by having
that, they need to be consistent, right?
So when you look at transaction
a, for example, when you create
a payload, you have a T start.
And remember, the T start is the
time when you are actually receiving
the reads from the storage, right?
Then you can do a write
of sets, post images.
That is the payload.
You send the payload to the adjudicator,
a payload will contain the right
sets, which are the items that you
modified copies of the table, roads,
applying effects of a transaction.
The payload also contain, contains the
transaction start time, which is the
T start, which is crucial element in
committing or aborting the transaction.
So let's look at how this works.
So coordinate once only at commit time.
So you have your query processor once
it's ready to, once the query processors
have done all the transactions that has
been given, what the query processor
does is sends you the adjudicator and
pretty much says to the adjudicator, dear
adjudicator, here are the keys I intend
to write, and here are my transaction.
Start time if no other transactions
have been reading these key since.
They start time that I've done my read.
Pick a time for a commit and write
these changes to the journal.
Your friend query processors
what the adjudicator will do.
You'll never allow another
conflict transaction to pick
a lower T commit, right?
So if behind the scenes there was
another transaction that comes.
Few seconds after this and says,
oh, I have actually a transaction
that is started, after the T
start, but before the T commit.
The adjudicator will be like, you
are not gonna be able to do that.
It's gonna abort your transaction and your
application need to retry the transaction.
That is one of the things that you need
to be aware of as building applications
with this SQL that you need to retry.
If.
That transaction gets abor by the
seco because there was a conflict.
I'm gonna show you in the multi region,
active scenario, that adjudicator is the
piece that grows across the region, right?
That is the piece that
goes across the region.
And, it shards different
keys across different regions
sorry, d those two regions.
So it needs to send the data for, a
specific query across the regions to make
sure it's actually able to do that now.
So if you have two specific transactions
that are changing the same role, right?
So if I have transaction one that
you start at 10 0 9 33, but 10 0 9
35, if I have the two transactions,
A and B, and they start roughly at
the same time, but transaction A
sends a commit for the transaction is
likely before transaction B. What will
happen in this case, in this case.
What would happen is the
adjudicator look at, are you
trying to write at the same row?
In this case, adjudicator discovers
inter in intersecting rights, right?
And so you compare the payloads from the
query processor it's looking for, right?
Any rights that have a T start time
and propose what needs to be in index.
In this case, as you can see here,
is trying to update the same payload.
So only transaction A is gonna be
approved because both can change
the same role at the same time.
So transaction A is gonna get committed
where our transaction B must be
aborted, and your application must
retry because then when your application
retries, you actually go to the storage
layer and retrieve the new data, the
transaction they have just updated.
So you don't have any loss of
data or in any inconsistency.
Now the cool thing about adjudicator is if
the transactions do not intersect, in this
case you can see one of the, maybe it's
too small for you to see, but transaction
A is trying to write on item 93 and
transaction B is trying to write item 97.
Even though some other selects are exactly
the same, both transactions are gonna be
allowed to be committed and both commits
will proceed, which is really good.
Another very interesting thing about the
SECO is in traditional databases, the
durability happen at the storage layer.
Transactions are only committed once
they are durably written in the storage
layer that is for traditional databases.
So the storage layer is expected
to be able to recover al committed
transactions from storage after any phase.
These requirements add significant
complexity to the database engines,
including logging, coordinating systems,
APIs, and need to keep a storage
consistent with more for recover purposes.
On the sql.
The durability is given to the
journal, and of course the journal,
if you're using a multi-region,
active solution is replicated across.
Multiple multiple regions.
And this is where, if you remember
when I said I have the witness
region, that witness region is
a replication of the journey.
Journey is just where all your transaction
logs for your database are stored.
So this CCOs manages this complexity
by making the journal response
responsible for the short term dur.
Both transactions are considered committed
once they are reading to the journal.
Not once they are reading to the
storage, the journal can escape
horizontally and transactions
can be reading to any journal.
They coordinated to provide a totally
order stream of committed transactions.
Remember, because now the adjudicator
makes sure that the priority and the
order of the transactions are in place.
The journal now have these
transaction logs that are ordered.
And the crossbar component uses the
journals ordering to ensure that
the updates that are applied to the
storage are in the correct sequence,
even when there are multiple journals.
So this is the cool thing, right?
Because now you have this journal.
That, can you scale horizontally and any
transaction can be written to any journal.
But because the ordering that adjudicator
allows you to do is the crossbar
components, we use that journal ordering
and ensure that the storage is also
save the data into the correct order.
And this is actually pretty cool, right?
So the payload and the timestamp
are sent to the journal.
Once the journal acknowledges.
The right, the updates then
are sent to the storage nos.
The journal sends a success code
to the query processor, which sends
back a success code to the client.
From the user perspective,
the transaction is done.
And this is the interesting part
because now the journal is where
the durability happens, right?
And journal is the place that
says, okay, it's good to go.
You go because it's replicated across.
Multiple availability zones and
multiple regions, and it has the
consistence and the order that you have.
So we talked a lot about the S QL
so far, and I have a couple more
slides before I am the presentation.
Our RD SQL uses optimistic
concurrence control.
So rather than putting a lock
when you are starting an insert
and you need to do multiple.
Selects and multiple, insert
multiple updates on the row.
That is not how it works.
Doing a pessimistic log allows you to have
a concurrence play here, which makes a
crucial row for multiple transactions to
occur Simultaneously, we, without leading
to inconsistency of data, you might need
to retry some of those transactions if the
transactions are within the same period
as I explained the capability and the.
And the row of the adjudicator.
There are no deadlocks conflicts
will be detected at the transaction.
Commit by the adjudicator.
You have a multi-region concurrency
protection now because every single
data that is committed is guaranteed
if you're using an active multi
region architecture that they are
consistent across these regions.
Now we have an efficient storage
layer from synchronous replication
because of the journal capability.
This and allows you as a developer
to really design new capabilities and
new design patterns for developers.
So there are multiple things here that we
could talk about it, but what I'll show
you some of the extra documentations that
you can go and do a little bit of reading.
There is great reinvent videos
also posted on the AWS channel.
What I want to show you is behind
the scenes, how is the architecture
for an active DCO database?
So when we look at an active
architecture, you have three regions.
Like I said, you have one region,
two regions with endpoints, region
A and region C in this diagram.
And region B is what we call
the witness the witness region.
You have, one router on each of
those regions that have endpoints.
Those are the endpoints.
And then, even though it says one
query processor here, one box, think
about that being, the micro VM from
firecracker, which is gonna run
the Postgres engine there, right?
So you can have multiple query processors
each actually transaction is a query
processor invocation on its own.
Thes l internally will actually host
across multiple availability zones, right?
So realistically, ER stack would be
duplicated across three availability
zones in each of these three regions.
And here you have the adjudicator.
And you can see here the adjudicator is
the only one that is responsible, the
only one that requires you to have a
cross region communication at the right.
At the commit of a right, and
you can see that adjudicator will
have specific keys that are led by
specific adjudicator in this case.
Because that's how you know,
you guaranteed the consistency
across the transactions from
multiple places, multiple regions.
Then you have the journal and you can see
the journal is actually replicated across.
All the three regions because
that's where the durability happens.
So the journal is where the transaction
logs are stored, and it's a key
critical key component of the sql.
Then you have the storage, of course,
that will read from the journal.
You have a crossbar that is not
on this diagram that you read
from the journal and actually make
those changes into the storage.
So the journal only witness, which
is region B, ensures that if there
is a split between those two regions.
The available side can continue to be
available and consistent for client.
On the other side of the partition,
for distributions that go across
large geographies, you can put the
witness kind in the middle, right?
So if you have, let's say, one region,
apologies, one region in the US
and you might have another region.
In Australia, you might wanna
put another region maybe in the
Middle East on Europe, right?
That is a nice sort of additional
property that you can actually
optimize for latency as well, right?
So let's talk about what happened
if Ency in this case goes down, not,
let's knock on the wood here, but
let's say if there is a catastrophe or
something happens with the region as
sea goes down, which is very uncommon
but let's say that region goes down.
Any adjudicator leadership that short
leave state for doing an isolation
moves out of their region regency
and remain into the health region.
Because remember, you need all
the keys for the adjudicators
to make you know the control.
Now the journal is splitted
across region A, region B, which
is region B is the weakness.
So you still have that durable storage in
the, in two regions and only the health
side of the database remains available.
Of course, the endpoint of Regency won't
work, but endpoint region will continue to
work for reads rights at any given time.
So you do, you then need to move traffic
to the health side, so of the partition.
So you can, just either use that specific
endpoint or you can do a route 53.
Lat sensitive routing with
health checks and so on.
It's how you are using
endpoint on an application.
It's completed for you.
You can just have one specific endpoint
for the region, or you can actually
potentially just create a DNS with
Route 53 that you know, will you do
the routing with health checks for
that specific regions that is working.
So this is what I wanted to
present to you about this S ql.
This que is currently in public preview.
Hopefully soon it'll be in general
available that you will be able
to run production workloads.
But if you have interest, please
feel free to reach out on LinkedIn.
Again, my name is Samuel bfi,
but also you can scan this here.
Codes.
We have, the documentation of the
cco, some of the dsco or public
web pages, and also the useful blog
posts that have that have we shared.
And I've mentioned there are great
Ring van 2024 talks that are available
for you to consume on YouTube, and I
highly recommend for you to do that.
So let us know what
you thought about that.
Hopefully you'll be building new,
exciting, resilient, and highly
available applications on top of the SQL.
And we are very excited
to see what you can do.
So thank you so much for taking
the time to watch my session.
And I'll see you soon.
Bye bye.