Hello everyone.
I'm excited to present enhancing
enterprise security with ai,
a strategic framework for
automation and threat management.
As cybersecurity threats continue to
evolve in sophistication and frequency,
organizations are turning towards
artificial intelligence as a game
changing LA to their security operations.
This framework explores how AI is
transforming enterprise security
automation and threat management.
In this presentation, we'll examine
the essential components of AI
driven cybersecurity architecture,
how it enhances network security.
Automates reporting and enables proactive
security, pro poster management.
Ultimately creating more resilient
systems that can adopt to continuously
changing threat landscape.
AI is changing how we protect our
networks and systems from cyber threats.
It helps us detect potential issues
faster, respond more efficiently,
and adopt our security systems
to new and evolving threats.
This is important because
cyber attacks are becoming more
sophisticated and frequent.
AI brings us the ability to not
only defend against known threats,
but also to predict and stop
unknowns before they can cause harm.
Imagine you are a
security guard at a bank.
Traditional methods would only
help you spot obvious threats
like a person trying to break in.
But AI would help you spot subtle
signs like a person trying to
gather information about security
systems even before they act.
The growing AI security adoption
landscape, the adoption of AI powered
cybersecurity solutions has witnessed
exponential growth over past five years.
Organizations across industries are
recognizing the value of integrating
AI to their security infrastructures.
Therefore, trend is driven
by compelling results.
The key benefits of implementing
AI is reduced breach life cycle.
AI powered solutions significantly shorten
the time from threat identification
to contaminant cost savings.
Organizations utilize AI in their security
operations, realize cost savings up to 60%
compared to traditional security methods.
Let's take an example.
Think about a company dealing with
hundreds of security alerts daily.
Without ai, the security team has
to manually check each one leading
to delays and missed threats.
But with AI, the system
automatically filters.
And prioritize alerts, making it
much easier for the team to focus
on critical issues, straight away.
Core components of AI
driven security framework.
A robust AI driven security
framework is built upon multiple
interconnected components.
At its foundation is a comprehensive
data collection and analysis
that fits intelligent systems.
Intelligence power machines,
learning models that accelerate
identifying anomalies that signature
based approaches often miss.
The middle layers enable automated
incident response through orchestration.
Technologies that accelerate
remediation at the top.
Predictive capabilities provide
pro defense by anticipating
potential attack factor before they
materialize a security poster that
stays ahead of emerging threats.
We, we would also like to integrate
a zero zero trust architecture.
Let's take an example.
It's like setting up an automated home
security system where sensors detect
motion cameras, monitors suspicious
activity, and alarms go off before
a burglar even tries to break in.
AI enhanced anomaly detection,
pattern recognition.
AI algorithms detect septal patterns
and correlates in network behavior
that human analysis might miss.
Behavioral baselines.
Machine learning establishes
normal operation baselines,
flagging deviations with greater
accuracy and fewer false positives.
Real time analysis.
Continuous monitoring provides instant
threat assessment and actionable
intelligence for security teams.
Adaptive learning.
AI systems evolve by incorporating new
data, improving detection capabilities
as threat landscape changes.
Let's take an example.
If an employee who usually logs in
from one location suddenly logs in
from a foreign country, AI spots this
anomaly and flags it as suspicious.
Even though it might not be a direct
attack yet, let's take one more example.
An employee who logs in normally
from eight to five has an
unusual login somewhere around
3:00 AM or maybe, 2:00 AM.
So AI flags those suspicious
activities and based on that.
It can take some action like blocking
that account or analyzing the severity
and criticality of the application.
Based on that, it can take actions.
Automated incident response capabilities,
alert evaluation, AI evaluates
incoming alerts based on severity,
context, and potential impact.
Organizing critical threats.
Contextual analysis enriches alerts with
relevant intelligence and environmental
context for more informed decision making.
Orchestrated response automates
the executions of predefined
playbooks and response procedures
across security systems.
Verification and reporting verifies
the effectiveness of remediation and
provides detailed documentation for
compliance and future improvements.
By using all this, AI can prioritize
what critical threats, and based
on that it can take an action.
Let's take an example.
Imagine you get an alert that an
employee clicked on a suspicious email
instead of manually investigating
ai, quickly analyzes the risk and
either wants the employee or isolate
the issue to prevent the further harm
vulnerability management revolution.
Intelligent continuous assessment.
AI moves beyond traditional scanning
using machine learning to evaluate
vulnerabilities based on exploitability
attacker behavior and asset criticality.
Risk-based prioritization, AI
prioritizes remediation efforts based
on actual risk to the organization.
Rather than relying solely on CVSS
scores, faster remediation AI can
recommend or even implement fixes.
Significantly reducing the time
from discovery to resolution.
AI is fundamentally transforming
vulnerability management by
moving beyond simple scanning to
intelligent continuous assessment.
Machine learning algorithms
evaluate vulnerabilities.
This revolutionary approach
prioritizes remediation effects
based on actual risk rather than.
Generic ratings ensuring security
teams focus on what matters most.
Let's take an example.
Let's say your system has
vulnerability that is only exploitable.
If an attacker is already
inside your network.
AI can consider this and tell you to
focus on fixing other vulnerabilities
that are more likely to be exploited from
outside automated compliance monitoring.
Continuous assessment, real-time
monitoring of systems, configurations
against regulate regulatory frameworks
like nist, P-C-I-D-S-S, hipaa, and a
SO 27,001 Documentation Generation.
Automatic creation of compliance
reports and audit trails,
reducing manual documentation
efforts for creation maintenance.
Drift detection, immediate
identification of configuration
changes that may impact compliance
status and enabling rapid remediation
by using automated compliance
monitoring, it is very easy to maintain
our certifications because AI will
take care of all the monitoring
that are necessary and all the
documentation that is necessary
for maintaining the certification.
Let's take an example.
AI works like an automatic compliance
audit that never misses anything.
It continuously checks if your
systems are following regulations,
so you don't have to scramble
to prepare when an audit is due.
Threat intelligence, integration,
collection and aggregation,
gathering threat data from diverse
sources, including commercial
feeds, open source intelligence.
Dark web monitoring
and industry I-S-A-C-S.
Analysis and enrichment.
AI processes raw intelligence to identify
patterns, relevance, and create actionable
insights specific to environment.
Operational integration, automated
distribution of intelligence to
security controls for proactive
defense across security stacks.
Advanced natural language processing can
analyze unstructured threat data from
security blogs, forms, and social media.
While machine learning algorithms
identify correlation between
seemingly unrelated incidents, the
result is significantly more robust.
Defense poster that anticipates
and counters emerging threats.
Let's take feedback and refinement,
continuous evaluation and adjustment
of intelligence parameters
to improve future analysis.
Let's take an example.
If a hacker shakes new shares, a new
exploit tool on a forum, AI can detect
it, learn from it, and update security
systems to protect against that specific
tool before it's used in an attack.
Just in time security remediation.
Just in time security remediation
represents a paradigm shift from a
static defense to dynamic protection
measures that adopt in real time.
The approach leverages AI to continuously
evaluate risk and automatically
implement appropriate security
controls precisely when needed.
Dynamic protection shifts from
static defense to adoptive real-time
security measures that continuously
evaluate and respond to risks.
AI driven security AI automatically
implements context aware security
controls precisely when needed,
reducing unnecessary exposure.
Reducing attacks surface by moving away
from traditional always on-premise.
Organizations can significantly lower
their attacks surfaces while maintaining
operations efficiency cloud environments.
This approach is especially beneficial
in cloud environments where perimeter
based securities in insufficient.
Let's take an example.
It's like adjusting the
security level in your home.
When you are home, you don't need
high security locks everywhere.
But when you are away, AI sets up
strong protections automatically.
Just in time.
Security remediation has three
main components temporary access
controls, adoptive security
boundaries on demand isolation.
By using these things, it'll only
implement when the security is needed,
and other times it can relax so that
systems can perform more effectively.
Performance optimization
through AI integrations.
By using AI integration we have, we
can reduce the false positives by 85%.
You can respond to incidents by increasing
your speed by 67%, and you can improve
the resource utilization by 73%.
AI driven security solutions significantly
reduce false positives, helping.
Elevate alert fat that often burden
security teams faster response.
Automated orchestration capabilities
have cut incident response time
by over two thirds, enabling
quicker mitigation of threats.
Intelligence, resource allocation, AI
optimizes resource users allowing security
teams to achieve more with existing staff.
Improved security and cost savings.
These efficiency gains result in
stronger security poster and direct
cost savings for organizations.
Let's take an example.
Think of security team constantly
overwhelmed with alerts.
AI filters out unnecessary ones and
help the team focus only on what
really matters, reducing burnout
and improving their effectiveness.
Building your AI cybersecurity roadmap.
Implementing an AI driven cybersecurity
framework requires a strategic
phased approach tailored to your
organization's specific needs.
Begin with the comprehensive assessment
of your current security poster
and clearly define objectives of AI
integration, strategic phase approach.
Begin with the
comprehensive assessment of.
Your current security poster and
define clear objectives of AI
integration pilot projects start with
focused AI initiatives, high value
areas like phishing detection and
endpoint production to demonstrate
early value and build confidence.
Integration not replacement.
Emphasize integrating AI with
existing security tools and
practices rather than replacing them
entirely Continuous improvement.
Regularly assess the effectiveness
of AI solutions and refine the
approach as technologies mature.
Let's take an example.
It's like building a new bridge.
First, you need to assess the
land, plan, the design, and then
start with small test sections.
Once you've got it right, you
build more and refine the process.
In conclusion, AI plays a critical
role in improving cybersecurity
By making systems smarter and more
responsive, it helps detect threats
faster, respond more efficiently, reduce
human errors, and improve compliance.
AI makes security operations
more efficient and reduces costs
while keeping organizations safe.
Just think of an AI as a superpowered
assistant that works 24 by seven,
constantly improving and ensuring your
systems stay ahead of potential threats.
That's all.
Thank you.