Speaker 13: Hello everyone.
My name is Kush Bonum, and I work
as a cloud architect focused on
observability for cloud native systems.
In this session, I want to talk about
a problem I see SRE teams face quite
often as distributed systems scale, they
generate massive amounts of telemetry.
At first glance, having motor
telemetry seems like a good thing.
But when an incident actually occurs, the
real challenge is not collecting the data,
but making sense of the collected data.
And that's exactly why the central idea of
the talk is correlation over collection.
Instead of trying to collect more and
more telemetry teams should focus on
an intentional observability design.
Adding the right context to existing
signals so engineers can connect
the dots quickly during an incident.
When we look at modern distributed
systems, they generate many
different types of telemetry.
You might have matrix from
infrastructure, application logs,
distributed traces, deployment
signals, and multiple alerts set up.
So in most cases, we actually
don't have a data problem.
We already know how to collect
telemetry, what tools to use.
The real challenge is clarity.
Each of these signals is valuable on its
own, but they often exist in isolation.
They don't automatically tell a
structured story about what is
happening inside the system, and
we generally need more context.
So when an incident occurs, all
of these signals compete for
attention at the same moment.
And the engineer investigating
the problem becomes the manual
integration layer, trying to connect
the dots between the fragmented data.
That's why the core issue
isn't the volume of telemetry.
The real issue is clarity.
Now let's look at what typically happens
when an incident actually begins.
The investigation timeline often
starts with a user request, then
something unusual may happen.
For example, latency starts increasing.
Soon after that, a monitoring
alert fires and the engineers
start looking into this issue.
But at this point, there
is an important gap.
Many signals can tell us
that something is wrong.
They show the symptoms of the problem.
But very few signals immediately
explain why the problem is happening.
So the first question an engineer
usually asks during an incident is
not what happened because the alert
already tells us something is wrong.
The real question is what changed data?
A new version of the
service gets deployed.
Did infrastructure, A performance
degrade or did an external
dependency start failing?
Without that context, the investigation
becomes slow, manual, and stressful
because engineers have to search across
many signals to reconstruct the story.
And this is also where the
distinction between monitoring and
observability becomes important.
So a quick recap of that.
Monitoring focuses on detecting
known failure conditions.
For example, we define thresholds such
as CPU usage above 90%, or request
latency above 500 milliseconds.
And when those thresholds are
crossed, an alert is triggered.
These are what we call the known nos.
We already know what unhealthy
behavior looks like, and we want to
avoid that, so we configure alerts
to detect it, but distributed systems
rarely fail, only in predictable ways.
That's where observability
becomes important.
Observability helps engineers deal
with the unknown unknowns, meaning the
failures that we did not explicitly
anticipate when designing alerts instead
of just telling us that something
is wrong, observability helps us
investigate and explain systems behavior.
Now, even when we understand what
observability means, it still may not
help us if our telemetry lacks context.
In most modern systems, we collect
many different signals, for example.
We might see Matrix showing a latency
spike logs reporting a payment timeout
error traces revealing a slow API span
and deployment data showing that a new
version of the service was released.
Each of these signals is valuable.
They are important and should be
collected, but without a shared
context linking them together.
They cannot explain why the
incident actually occurred.
The signals exist, but they don't
automatically tell the story of
what happened, and this is why
the telemetry should not simply
be collected in large volumes.
Telemetry should be designed for
correlation so that engineers can
connect signals across the system.
And understand and reach the root
cause faster and more efficiently.
To tackle that problem, I want to
introduce the layered observability model.
Instead of organizing telemetry
by tools or signal types, this
model organizes signals by the
investigation question they help answer.
Each layer provides a different
piece of context during an incident.
At layer one, we start
with application traces.
The key question here is,
where is the failure occurring?
Tracing helps us follow a request
across services and identify which
component in the transaction is failing.
At layer two, we look at
Kubernetes metrics and events to
understand the platform health.
Here the question becomes,
is the platform healthy?
For example, we might look at things
like node resource pressure, pod
restarts, or scheduling issues.
Here at layer three, we examine
CICD telemetry to understand
what recently changed.
This could include deployments, version
updates, or pipeline events that may
correlate with the start of the incident.
By structuring telemetry in these
layers, engineers can move through an
investigation systematically instead
of jumping randomly between signals.
Now let's see how this layered
model actually appears in a
real system using a sample cloud
native application architecture.
So in this example, I have a detailed
microservices application, which is
running on a managed Kubernetes cluster.
A user interacting with this application
is shown on the left side and this
user's request enter the application
through a load balancer and then moves
on to interact with the web frontend
service, which is the first microservice.
And the second is the API backend service,
which has couple of operations of its own.
It then interacts with an
external database, which is
also within the cloud platform.
The telemetry collected from the
different components here, which are
the application Kubernetes and the CICD
pipeline is done using a combination
of open telemetry collector and cloud
native services, and they are posted
into different backends focusing on
application monitoring, log analysis.
Matrix monitoring.
So open that metric collector here.
Also do one more additional thing,
which is enriching the application
traces with useful context.
And this enriched telemetry is what
allows us to correlate signals across
different layers of investigation as
what we will see in the coming slides.
Let's focus on layer one,
which is application traces.
When a user request enters a
system, the trace follows entire
request path across the services.
And in this example, the request has
moved through the web service, then
the API Service and the API service
includes the payment operation, and
finally the request reaches the database.
Each span in the trace shows how
long that particular operation took,
and by comparing the latency of
each span, our user can understand.
We can understand that which component in
the transaction is slowing things down.
Like in this case, payment service span
is the one which is significantly slower
than the others' paths, and therefore
slowing down the entire transaction.
So this is how races helps us
answer where is the failure
occurring in the request part?
Now that we have seen how traces
help us answer where the service
is failing, the next step is to
determine whether the issue is
coming from the application itself.
Or from the platform it runs on, and
this is where layer two Kubernetes
matrix and events come into picture.
At this layer, we look at different
matrix, or we look at logs and
events that define the health of the
Kubernetes platform, for example.
Matrix can reveal node resource pressure,
such as CBU or memory exhaustion
that might be affecting the workload.
Kubernetes events could explain
situations such as p the pod lifecycle
events like crash loop back off.
And in addition, scheduling and
orchestration signals can tell us
whether pods are failing to start
being rescheduled or encountering
resource constraints within the cluster.
These platform signals help answer the
second investigation question that is
the platform healthy or is infrastructure
instability contributing to the failure?
Now before we continue to further layers
and investigations, there's one important
point that I would like to clarify.
When working with Kubernetes in a cloud
environment, in managed Kubernetes
platform's, responsibility for
different parts of the system is shared
between cloud provider and the users.
So at the top of the stack is the
control plane, which has components
such as API server, et cd, and in most.
Managed Kubernetes services.
These components are operated and
maintained by the cloud provider, so
it's good to just check that what all
goes into the cloud operated category.
And you can contact a cloud provider
if anything goes wrong with those co.
Components.
The second and third category are related
to note operations and application
workloads, which are generally
completely managed by the end user.
So when you are working
with managed Kubernetes, do.
Figure out the policies
of your cloud platform.
Understand what all telemetry, such as the
matrix and logs are also made available
by the cloud provider for the components
that they manage, so that you can take
the right path when an incident occurs.
Now let's move on to the
third layer of observability
here, which is CICD telemetry.
While traces and platform signals
help understand where a failure occurs
and whether the platform is healthy,
CICD telemetry helps answer another
critical question during incidents.
What changed CICD systems record important
signals such as deployment events, version
updates, and pipeline execution results.
These signals capture the lifecycle
of an application change from
commit to build to testing, and
finally deployment into production.
When an incident occurs, these
records allow engineers to quickly
check whether a new version of the
service was deployed, a configuration
change was introduced, or a pipeline
failure occurred around the same time.
By correlating incidents with
deployment telemetry teams can
determine whether the issue is related
to a recent change in the system.
This layer therefore provides
the change context needed to
complete the investigation.
Now let's look at a real trace example.
This trace shows the sequence of
operations involved in a single request.
Each row represents a span
which corresponds to a specific
operation, such as verify inventory
status, our charge payment.
And in this example I've
highlighted the span, which is the
payment service operations span.
And it clearly shows an.
Error along with a higher latency
compared to the other paths.
So from this trace, we
learned two important things.
First, where the failure
occurred in the transaction.
Second, which service is
responsible for the problem.
At this point, the investigation
has already narrowed from the entire
system to a single component, but we
still need more context to understand
why that service is failing, and
that's why we move to our layer two.
Now that we have identified the
failing span, we need a way to trace
back to the infrastructure where
this request was exactly executed.
The most effective way to achieve
this is by enriching application
telemetry with Kubernetes metadata.
In this example, we are looking at the
same payment service span, but in detail.
Here the span has been enriched with
Kubernetes attributes such as the node
and pod name and the pod IB address, which
also I have highlighted on the right side.
These attributes allow us to quickly
identify which pod handled the request
and which node it was running on.
At this point, the investigation can
pivot from the application layer to
the platform layer, and we can now
examine the relevant infrastructure
signals such as if this about this
nodes resource usage, this pods, events,
or scheduling activity to determine
if that is what is causing the issue.
So this correlation steps allows
us to separate platform issues
from application faults much faster
during incident investigations.
Now let's look at a practical
example of how CICD telemetry
helps explain incidents.
Here we correlate the incident with the
deployment that introduced the change
so we are looking at the details of the
same span and further down the span.
Metadata also includes a service
version, which tells us exactly which.
Release, handle this request.
If the infrastructure appears healthy,
but errors begin after a new deployment,
we can immediately connect the incident
to that specific version of the service.
And having that metadata in the span
quickly helps us in knowing that which
serv service version we have to look at.
The span also includes the error
message, which is captured due to the
instrumentation of the application code,
and this helps us see exact failure
reason returned by the application
by combining deployment metadata.
With SPAN context, we can quickly identify
which change introduced the issue.
Now when these three layers work
together, telemetry stops being
just a collection of signals and
instead becomes structured evidence.
First traces identify the specific
service and operation where the
failure occurs within a transaction.
Second platform signals help determine
whether infrastructure, conditions, such
as node pressure, PO restarts, or resource
limits contributed to the problem.
Third, deployment Elementary
provides a change context, allowing
engineers to see whether a recent
version update or the configuration
change correlates with the incident.
By moving through these layers
systematically, engineers are no
longer exploring signals randomly.
Instead, they are building a
hierarchy of evidence where each
layer narrows the investigation
and provides additional context.
This structured approach significantly
increases confidence in identifying
the true root cause of an incident.
To summarize, modern systems already
produce enormous amounts of telemetry.
The challenge today is
not collecting more data.
The real challenge is making
that telemetry useful.
When incidents occur during afters
or failures, engineers often struggle
to quickly understand what is
actually happening inside the system.
The approach we discussed to use
application traces, Kubernetes
platform matrix and events,
and CACD telemetry together.
When these signals are enriched
with contextual metadata, they
can be correlated across layers,
allowing engineers to connect what is
happening in the application platform.
Recent deployments when telemetry is
structured and correlated, this way,
engineers can move from scattered
signals to clearer investigation
parts and more confident incident
analysis, and that is when
observability becomes the most powerful.
I hope you find this session useful.
Thank you.