Hello everyone.
In this talk, we are going beyond
rockets and rowers to explore the
engine that quietly drives space
missions which is data engineering.
Space missions today aren't just
sending satellites into orbit.
They're sending back
massive volumes of data.
We are talking hundreds of gigabytes
per day from just one mission.
And it's not just about storing it,
it's about collecting it efficiently,
processing it in real time, and making it
usable for scientists across the globe.
Think of it this way.
If rocket science is a body of
the mission, the data engineering
is the brain and nervous system
that makes it all work together.
Let's talk about the scale of the space.
Data today space is vast,
but so is the data it sensor.
The ISS alone generates nearly a
terabyte of data every single day.
Imagining downloading every season
of a streaming show every day.
That's the scale we are talking
about to handle this, they have built
powerful distributed systems that
split workloads across missions,
almost like a factory assembly line.
And what about the compression?
It's like vacuum packing your
clothes so you can fit a whole
wardrobe into a carry on.
With compression ratio as high
as tennis to one, we make every
bite and every bit of bad count.
Imagine trying to stream Netflix with
only dial up internet connection.
That's what we would face without
these innovations in space data.
These numbers tell a story.
Data engineering isn't just
supporting space mission.
It's powering them.
So now let's talk about
distributed data systems.
Here's where it gets exciting, right?
The distributed architectures,
instead of one gen computer crunching
all the data, we use a network of.
Small computers working together,
like a team of chefs in a kitchen,
each preparing a part of the meal.
These systems enhance mission,
success, and scientific outcomes.
Enable efficient data management
across missions are built on a
distributor architecture with
parallel crossing across mini notes.
Picture a relay race where data is
passed across runners or processes to
input throughput and reduce bottlenecks.
These architectures allow space
agencies to scale on demand handling
up to one 50 simultaneous data
requests from multiple missions.
Next, we move on to advanced
compression techniques.
So space data travels a long way,
and there's no room for bloated
files on this type network.
So we compress data smartly, not just to
shrink it, but to preserve what matters.
It's like organizing a cluttered
closet, filter out what unnecessary,
keep what's valuable, and arrange
it so you can find it fast.
From the moment data is captured, it
goes through a series of smart steps,
the initial cleanup, priority tagging,
analysis, and long-term storage, all
optimized for speed and scientific value.
Now let's go a bit futuristic
which is quantum computing.
Imagine a normal computer as someone
reading a Jane book one word at a time.
A quantum computer reads
a whole page at once.
This leap could change how we plan
missions, navigate deep space and
even encrypt sensitive data, which is
exponential Processing power like quantum
computers can solve space algorithms
much faster than classical systems.
Enhancer encryption using quantum
cryptography to secure spacecraft
comments and data optimization problems.
Solving complex challenges in
mission planning and navigation.
Think of a classical computing
as checking every possible
path through a maze one by one.
Quantum computing explores
all the paths at once.
It's still early days, but the
potential to revolutionize trajectory
planning, resource allocation, and
deep space analytics is massive.
Now let's talk about edge
processing for space applications.
Have you ever used your phone's
face recognition without internet?
That's what the edge processing is.
Similarly, today's spacecrafts are
smart enough to do some of the data
crunching onboard instead of sending
every bit back to earth the filter
and prioritize it themselves, saving
bandwidth and reacting faster.
With they have on onboard processing,
initial filtering and compression,
intelligent filtering prioritizing
the most important data, autonomous
decisions, making mission adjustments
in real time optimized transmission,
sending only what matters.
It's like having a smart assistance on
onboard the spacecraft, one that decides
which photos to keep and which to delete
before uploading them to the cloud.
This says energy and bandwidth and
boosts real time decision making.
All at under five watts per node.
Next let's talk about high
performance computing architecture.
Think of space missions as
having a three type data brain.
One is in orbit, small but
tough processors that can handle
radiation and code on earth.
Jane Supercomputers for
heavy duty analysis.
And in between cloud platforms,
connecting them for seamless coordination.
It's like having your smartwatch,
laptop, and data centers all
working together in a sync.
So now let's talk about real time data
processing capabilities, like with less
than 10 milliseconds latency spacecraft.
No process and act on data
faster than you can blink.
Which has data acquisition
sensors capture raw input.
Processing data is evaluated in
milliseconds autonomous action.
The spacecraft makes realtime
decisions and ground notification.
Critical events are related to earth.
This is vital for handling solar,
flas, animal, or system fault,
especially when waiting 20 minutes
for a signal from me isn't an option.
Let's talk about James Webb's
Space Telescope, the golden
child of a modern astronomy.
It sends back about 40 gigs of data
every day, capturing the most detailed
images of space we have ever seen.
But raw data alone isn't useful.
The data goes through on onboard
filtering, then to earth, where it's
processed by layered pipelines to
transform those light signals into
breathtaking, imaginary and discoveries.
So space data isn't just for
scientists, it's a major driver of the
global economy from GPS and weather
tracking to agriculture and finance.
Countless industries rely on
space derived data to operate.
In fact, satellite communications
is a largest slice of a four
23 billion space economy.
And what fuels that data engineering
quietly running behind the scenes.
So what's next?
Where This is mainly for AI driven
autonomous spacecraft that thinks
and reactive smart as systems, a
delayed tolerant interplanetary and
internet to connect future mass spaces,
quantum data centers for solving
problems we can't even imagine today.
And orbital com cloud computing where
spacecraft collaborate by sharing
compute and storage resources.
We are talking about the cloud in literal
space and it's closer than you think.
To wrap it all up, as space gets more
ambitious, so much of data systems,
it's no longer just about launching
rockets, it's about managing the
data that comes back, making it
actionable, accessible, and powerful.
So thanks for joining me today.
Let's continue to engineer the future
of space one data packet at a time.
Thank you.