Speaker 3: Welcome everyone.
I'm AB Today I'll be speaking on
reliable AI for clinical handoffs, SRE
Lessons for Safer Care Transitions.
Clinical handoffs are one of the
most critical moments in healthcare
delivery because they involve the
transfer of responsibility, context,
and patient information from
one provider or team to another.
But those transition transitions
are incomplete or inconsistent.
The risk to patient safety
increases significantly.
In this presentation, I'll explore
how AI can support better handoffs and
more importantly, how principles from
this site reliability engineering,
can help make those AI systems safer,
more dependable, and more useful
and real clinical environments.
To begin to begin, it's important
to understand why clinical handoffs
remain such major challenge.
Clinical handoffs are.
Known risk of patient care.
Because communication breakdowns during
these transitions can directly affect
clinical outcomes at the time of handoff.
The receiving clinician depends on
the quality, clarity, and completeness
of the information being transferred.
If patients are missing, delayed, or
poorly structured, it can result in missed
warning signs, duplicated work, medication
issues, or delayed interventions.
Other healthcare organizations have
adopted structured communication
approaches and digital systems
to improve this process.
Handoffs still remain vulnerable because
the workflow itself is often fast
moving complex and highly variable.
This is why improving handoffs, it's
not just a documentation problem, it's
patient safety and reliability problem.
To solve that problem, we first
need to understand the main reason.
Handoffs breakdown.
There are three major challenges that
make clinical handoffs difficult.
The first is cognitive overload.
Clinicians are often managing multiple
patients, shifting priorities and
time pressure all at once, which makes
it easier for important details to
be missed during these transitions.
The second challenge is
fragmented HR data, even when
the necessary information exists.
It is often distributed across notes,
labs, vitals, medication lists, and
other parts of the record, making
it hard to synthesize quickly.
The third challenge is
variable handoff quality.
Even when team use established frameworks
such as the consistency of execution can
vary from clinician to clinician and from
shift to shift together, these challenges
create preventable safety risks.
And show why might more structured
intelligent support is needed.
This is exactly where an AI augmented
handoff system can add value.
An AI augmented handoff system
should be designed to reduce
the burden of manual synthesis.
It can take in both structured data such
as vitals, medications, orders, and lab.
And unstructured data such as provided
notes or clinical documentation
and transform them into a concise,
clinically relevant summary.
A key advantage is that the summary can
be aligned to an established communication
format, making it easier for clinicians
to use immediately within their workflows.
The purpose here is not to
replicate human decision making.
The purpose is to reduce variability.
It surface the most relevant
information and help receiving team
get faster situational awareness.
In practical terms, this means
less time searching through
records and more time focusing on
patient care and clinical judgment.
But in healthcare, usefulness
alone is not enough.
The system ha also has to be
reliable under real world condition.
This is where the site reliability
engineering or SRE becomes highly
relevant in a healthcare setting.
An AI system must do more than
produce intelligent outputs.
In ideal situations, it must remain
dependable under pressure, even when data
is incomplete, inconsistent or delayed.
Reliability here means resilience to
failures, continuous monitoring and
safe behavior when uncertainty is high.
It also means explainability because
clinicians are more likely to trust
and appropriately use the system when
they understand why recommendation or
summary was generated From an asari
perspective, this includes observability,
fault tolerance, incident awareness,
and proactive system maintenance.
In other words, a clinical AI
system that must be engineered
not only to performance, but
for stability, transparency.
And safe degradation.
This is a critical lesson on
applying AI in patient facing
or safety sense to workflows.
When you compare this reliability
focused approach with traditional
handoff workflows, the difference
becomes much more visible.
In traditional handoffs, workflow,
clinicians often spend time manually
gathering information from multiple
parts of the record and then
summarizing it under time pressure.
This process increases cognitive load
and creates variability in what gets
communicated in an AI augmented workflow.
The system helps organize relevant
information, highlight risks, and present
more structured summary in real time.
That improves consistency and
supports faster understanding
of the patient's condition.
Another advantage is that these systems
can learn from workflow patterns.
And help teams identify where
communication frequently breaks down.
So the benefit is not simply speed, it is
improved prioritization, reduced cognitive
burden, and more dependable transfer on
critical information between providers.
One reason this, one reason it
this becomes practical is that the
information can be structured in a
way clinicians already understand.
A strong way to make AI generate generated
handoff summaries useful is to align
them with aspar framework, situation,
background assessment, and recommendation.
This matters because Aspar is already
familiar in many healthcare settings and
provides a clear communication structure.
The situation section captures
the patient's current status
and immediate concern.
Background adds the relevant history.
And context as assessment highlights,
meaningful trends or changes
in the patient's condition and
recommendation identifies the next
step or points requiring attention.
AI can help ensure that each of
these sections is populated with
the most relevant and timely
information, making handoffs more
standardized and easier to act.
Act on.
There's a good example of technology
supporting established clinical practice.
Rather than forcing an entry
entirely new model, even with
strong summaries, the system still
has to be used in the right way.
And that brings us to the human role.
Human AI collaboration is
essential in this kind of workflow.
AI should function as an assistant, not
as a replacement for clinical expertise.
The role of system is to
synthesize, prioritize, and
surface information efficiently.
While the clinical clinician remains
responsible for judgment, interpretation,
and final editions, this balance
matters because patient care is
contextual and no model can fully
replace domain expertise at the bedside
or during clinical decision making.
Explainable outputs are
also important here.
If the system highlights a risk
or recommends attention for a
specific issue, the clinician
should be able to understand.
What drove that output?
This improves trust
supports adoption and risk.
Reduces the risk of over reliance the
ideal outcome as a workflow where AI
can a handles routine synthesis, and
clinical clinicians focus their time on
high valuable reasoning and patient care.
Once the human error relationship
is clear, the next challenge
is deployment and governance.
And in this slide will go over
governance and clinical deployment.
Governance is a clinic critical
part of any AI implementation.
A system like this must be validated
carefully before broad deployment,
and it must continue to be monitored
after deployment for accuracy,
reliability and workflow impact.
Staff training is equally important
because even a well-built system
can fail if users are not clear
on how and when it should be used.
Clinical deployment also requires
attention and transparency, ethics,
accountability, and instant response.
If system behaves unexpectedly,
our produces questionable outputs.
Team need clear escalation
path and oversight mechanisms.
Adoption depends on trust.
And trust comes from strong governance,
clinician involvement and implementation
approach that respects the realities
of clinic clinical practice.
When this foundations are in
place, the bigger value of
this approach becomes clearer.
The ultimate goal of improving
handoff is better patient safety.
If AI can help identify.
Deterioration signals earlier.
Improve the transfers and essential
information and reduce the chance of
important details being missed during
shift changes when it creates real value.
It can also contribute to the more
proactive care model through real
time analysis, pattern recognition,
and support for timely interventions.
But it is important to stay balanced
in how we frame the benefit.
Safer care do not come
from automation alone.
It comes from combining machine
support, structured communication, human
oversight, and reliable system design.
In that sense, AI becomes part
of the broader safety framework
rather than a standalone solution.
Strong.
The strongest systems will be the
ones that support clinicians without
disrupting sound clinical practice.
So the key question becomes how
should organizations move forward
with this kind of capability?
A practical implementation strategy
should begin with pilot programs
rather than large scale deployment.
Start with clearly defined use cases,
involve clinicians early in the
workflow designs and build governance
onto that process from the beginning.
This allows organizations to test not
only technical performance, but also
usability, trust and operational fit.
Continuous training is important because
adoption is not a one time event.
Teams need ongoing feedback, refinement,
and alignment with clinical realities.
It's also important to measure outcomes
and learn from actual workflow behavior.
The organizations that succeed in this
space will be the ones that treat a
implementation as both technical effort
and an operational challenge effort.
Safer handoffs require not just a
good model, but a reliable system
and a discipline deployment approach.
To conclude the central idea is not
simply introducing AI into handoff,
but introducing it responsibly.
So in closing, the reliable AA has
the potential to improve clinical
handouts by choosing variability,
supporting better communication.
And strengthening patient
safety during care transitions.
But in healthcare, intelligence
by itself is not enough.
The systems must also be dependable,
transparent, and designed to work
in partnership with clinicians.
Thank you for your time.
Thank.