Hello everyone and welcome
to the SRE at 2025.
Today.
The topic that I'll be talking about is
SRE at scale building resilient cloud
infrastructure for higher education
enterprise resource planning systems.
Now welcome to this technical deep
dive into site reliability engineering
SRE practices for cloud-based
enterprise resource planning systems.
In higher education today, we'll explore
how applying sophisticated reliability
principles can transform fragmented
legacy systems into resilient cloud
architectures that deliver consistent
performance during critical periods.
Drawing from real world implementations
across various institutional settings, I
will share the strategies that achieve.
99.99% uptime during peak
registration periods and reduced
security incidents by 78%.
Let's explore the technical
foundations of reli operations
in educational environments.
So.
Before we get started into the details,
let me tell you something about myself.
I'll give you a background of myself.
My name is Jeev pga.
I have studied from the Vicious
Area Technological University.
I have 21 years of experience working
in multiple projects around the globe.
Currently I'm working as a program
manager at amazon in United
States, in the Washington State.
And prior to that I have worked
for many projects for the state,
for the higher education domain.
And the experiences that I have
gathered is what I'm going to
share in this presentation.
So next, so the next, we are talking
about the higher education ERP landscape.
Now higher education, enterprise
resource planning landscape.
It can be distinguished into three major
areas, which is cloud-based system, which
is the modern containerized solution.
Then we have the architecture of a
hybrid architecture, which bridges
between cloud and on-premises.
And then we have the legacy systems, which
is a fragmented institutional databases
that we have seen over the years.
And, the, and we have seen different
challenges that we have with the
legacy systems, which are fragmented
in different campuses be, and they
don't share data with other campuses.
Now, higher education institutions
face unique challenges with
the their ERP implementations.
Many begin siloed, departmental complex
integrations needs and technical debt.
Legacy systems often struggle with
modern security requirements and
scaling demands and security is a big
concern when it comes to any industry,
especially when it comes to higher
education industry because you have
sensitive so many sensitive information
that the educational institutes collect
from the students and the staff.
Now the trend towards cloud-based
ERP solutions offers tremendous
benefits, but it requires
careful architectural planning.
Institutions must balance accessibility,
compliance requirements and the
seasonal nature of academic workloads,
all while maintaining constant
uptime for critical services.
And that is what makes the
higher educational ERP landscape.
Challenging for implementing
any ERP solution.
Now in this slide we are going
to talk about the microservices
architecture for educational workloads.
Now, what is this microservices
architecture for educational workload?
Here we are seeing on the
left hand side we are talk
talking about containerization.
Then we are looking into orchestration
in this phase, and then we are
looking at the service mesh, and
then we are looking at the security
layer, which has been applied.
Now, what is conization?
It's a docker based services
with education specific.
Configuration, which which is done
for the, for the users to consume the
the information which is being sent.
So that is what is containerization.
So if we are working for any educational
institute, it's the logo of the institute.
It's the what information needs to be
shared with that particular you know,
user is what is containerization now.
Orchestration is the Kubernetes clusters
with automated scaling policies.
And then we have the service mesh, which
is the Istio powered traffic management
with encrypted east waste traffic.
So what kind of, how do we manage
the traffic during peak period
is what is the service mesh?
And then we come to the security
layer, which is a zero trust network
policy with identify with identity
verification, which is very critical.
To the higher education.
Now, breaking monolithic ERP systems
into containerized microservices
has proven transform transformative
for educational institutions.
This architecture, what it does is
it enables independent scaling of
critical components during registration
period and financial aid processing
season, because what we have seen
is during the registration period.
More resources needs to be allocated
so that the students can register
during financial aid processing.
Also, we need more resources which
can be allocated to those functions.
So that is how we see that this
architecture helps during those
peak periods in managing the
workload, we have implemented
automatic failover configurations
that maintain service continuity.
Even when primary systems
experience issues.
So these are the challenges that we
have seen in the monolithic ERP systems,
but can be overcome by using this
framework of microservice architecture.
I.
Next we will look into how can we
establish education specific SLOs.
Now looking into the SLOs that we can,
we need to implement for any higher
education ERP system implementation
is student portal availability.
So student portal availability is key
to the business of higher education.
So 99.99% uptime during registration
period with 500 millisecond response
time SLO, lower threshold during
off peak periods to optimize
resource utilization and cost.
The next is financial
system reliability, 99.999%.
Transaction consistency with dual fees.
Commit protocols.
I. Prioritize during financial
aid, disbursement cycles, and
dedicated infrastructure resources.
The next is faculty service,
performance, grade submissions, and
course management operations with
1.5 seconds maximum response time,
and 99.9% availability with extended
thresholds during non-teaching periods.
Service level objectives for educational
ERP systems must reflect the cyclic
nature of academic operations.
We developed custom error budgets
that vary throughout the semester,
allowing for more experimental
deployments during quite periods while
enforcing strict changes change freezes
during critical academic events.
It is very important that there are
some you know, change freeze times so
that it does not impact the peak period.
This approach has allowed it teams
to balance innovation with stability,
and our dashboards provide real time
visibility into remaining error budgets,
influencing deployment decisions
and maintenance scheduling across
multiple institutions and stakeholders.
Multiple institutional stakeholders.
Moving on to the next one, which is
comprehensive observability stack.
So what are the different observability
stacks that we need to look into?
Metric collection.
So Prometheus based telemetry
with educational specific gauges.
Log aggregation, centralized
ELK stack with P two.
AWARE filtering, altering, altering
alerting systems, which is pager
due to integration with role-based
escalation parts distributed tracing.
Yeager implementation tracking
cross service transactions.
Effective observability proved critical
for maintaining ERP reliability.
We implemented custom instrumentation
for student facing services,
capturing not just technical metric,
but also user experience indicators
like registration completion rates
and form submission successes.
Our observability stack.
Includes specialized monitoring
for authentication framework.
Given the complex identity management
needs in educational settings,
we track federation's performance
across multiple identity providers.
I. And maintain visibility into
single sign-on performance with
alerts triggered when authentication
latency exceeds predefined thresholds.
So it's very important to have thresholds
to measure those service SLOs and SLAs.
Next, we are looking into chaos
engineering in educational context.
The the game day exercises,
which is structured failure
simulation with cross-functional
teams during maintenance windows.
Next is automated failure injection
programmatic infrastructure and network
degradation during non-critical periods.
Next is schedule resilience testing
quarterly comprehensive system
test with increased complexity.
Next is documentation, update
run books and recovery procedures
refined after each exercise.
Now, these are some things some steps
which are critical because even after
implementation, these are some of the
tests which needs to be done to make sure
that when the peak is reached or when
we are going through the peak or when we
are going through the critical period of
registration and financial aid awarding.
The system is able to meet the
demands or meet the needs of
the educational institutions.
Now, chaos engineering practices
have proven invaluable for
validating ERP resilience.
We designed experiments that
simulate realistic failure
scenarios, including database
unavailability during registration
periods, identity provider outages.
And network partitions between services.
This control exercises reveal subtle
dependencies and failure modes that
warrant apparent in architectural reviews.
By systematically injecting failures,
we identified and remediated
critical vulnerabilities because
they affected production systems.
Each KIOS experiment resulted in
improved recovery procedures and
more resilient system design.
So that is where the Kios
engineering in educational context
is very, very relevant as well.
Next is automated remediation workflows.
Now anomaly detection is the first step.
Next is automated diagnosis
and then self-healing actions.
Now, what is anomaly detection?
It's the machine learning powered
baseline deviation identification.
Next is pattern recognition with
contextual analysis, which is automated
diagnoses and the self-healing
actions is Kubernetes operators
implementing recovery patterns.
Our implementation of automated
remediation workflows reduced mean
time of recovery, which is MTTR by 65%.
We developed a tiered
approach to automation.
Level one remediations execute
automatically without human intervention.
Next is while more complex, level two and
level three actions require progressive
levels of approval and oversight.
The system leverages machine learning to
detect anomalies specific to educational
workloads added that precede incidents
when potential issues are detected.
Self-healing mechanisms can execute
predefined playbooks from simple PO
starts to complex databases, failovers,
and data integrity verifications.
Next is resilient, API
gateway architecture.
Now legacy system integration.
Our API Gateway implementation
includes specified adapters for legacy
systems with protocol translation
and data transformation capabilities.
This adapters maintain backward
compatibility while enabling
modern security practices.
Circuit breakers prevent cascading
failures when legacy components experience
issues gracefully degrading functionality
rather than allowing complete outages.
Next is authentication and authorization.
The gateway handles complex
authentication, flow common in
educational settings, including SAML
federations with research institutions.
Oau integration with cloud providers
and legacy authentication methods.
Fine-grained authorization policies
enforces appropriate access
controls while maintaining audit
trails for compliance requirements.
So that's a authentication and
authorization plays a critical
role when we are developing a
resilient API gateway architecture.
Next is the traffic management.
Which helps in making sure that there
is no delay or we are meeting the SLAs.
Now, sophisticated rate limited protects
backend service during peak periods.
I. Implementing fair scheduling
algorithms then that prioritize
critical operations during high demands.
Events like course registration, dynamic
routing capabilities enable gradual
rollouts of new services with cannery
deployments and AB testing configurations.
The EAPI gateway serves as a
critical reliability component.
Providing a consistent interface
while abstracting the complexity
of underlying systems.
This architecture proved particularly
valuable during migrations, allowing
incremental modernization without
disrupting service availability.
Because, because any kind of an, any
kind of institutions, it's a, it's
a large project and, it is better
approach with an agile approach.
And when we are doing an agile
approach, it is implemented in
different iterations and phases.
So when we are implementing in different
iterations and phases, it is very
important that we follow the resilient
API gateway architecture where some
of the systems have been modernized
while some are still on legacy systems.
So that is why where this resilient
API gateway architecture, while
implementation becomes very critical.
Next, moving on to immutable
infrastructure for scaling now
infrastructure as, as code terraform
modules with specif specialized
configurations for educational
workloads, version controlled and
peer reviewed, which is very much
critical for infrastructure as
code now automated A A MI creation.
Packer pipelines producing hardened images
with pre-installed monitoring agents and
security controls are very much important.
Pre-deployment validation, automated
compliance and vulnerability
scanning, integrated into CICD.
Continuous improvement and
continuous development.
Pipelines are very important.
Blue-green deployments.
Zero downtime implementation with
automated rollback capabilities
based on health metrics.
This is very much in.
Important because while implementation,
if anything goes wrong goes wrong, then
there should be a way to look into the
different metrices to see whether the
implementation was successful or not.
If it is successful that gives you
a confirmation to roll it out to
all the users to start to have them
start using the new ERP system.
If it does not go right, then it's
very important that we have a rollback
capability and rollback plan as well.
Now implementing immutable infrastructure
principles transformed our ability
to scale during peak periods.
Rather than patching or modifying
running systems, we deploy new instances
from validated images and templates,
ensuring consistent configuration
and eliminating configuration drifts.
This approach enables
rapid horizontal scaling.
During high demand periods like
registration and financial aid deadlines
pre-provisioned capacity plans based
on historical usage patterns, ensure
resources are available when needed,
while allowing, allowing for efficient
cost management during quieter periods.
Now moving on to the next one,
which is security as a code
with continuous compliance.
Now, automated vulnerability scanning
is the first one, which is continuous
assessment of infrastructure
and appli application components
against education sector, threat
models, and compliance framework.
Next is policy S code OPA based
guardrails, enforcing security
requirements across container
orchestration and cloud resources.
The third one is Secret Man Secrets
Management Vault Implementation with
dynamic credential generation and
automatic rotation for sensitive systems.
Next is compliance reporting,
automated evidence collection and
documentation generation for FERPA,
GLBA and other regulatory requirements.
Security as core practices have
fundamentally changed how we approach
GRP protection by coding security
policies and compliance requirements.
We have integrated them directly into
infrastructure provisioning and app
application deployment processes.
This approach reduced security incidents
by 78% while streamlining compliance
processes, continuous validation
against frameworks like NIST 800,
slash 1 71 and fair part requirements.
Ensure systems maintain compliance
throughout their lifecycle
with automated remediation of
deviations from security baselines.
So that was the end of the session.
I thank you for joining this session.
Have a wonderful day.
Thank you.