Hello everyone.
I am Numan.
Today I will be speaking on a big data
and machine learning in healthcare
and how these technologies are
driving improvements in diagnostic
accuracy, personalized treatment
planning, and operational optimization.
We will explore the data landscape
and scalable processing architectures
and the role of machine learning in
analyzing patient's data at scale.
Healthcare data is growing
exponentially by 2025.
It's projected to reach 2,500
exabytes growing faster than any other
industry, including finance and media.
Here's the kicker, 80% of
the data is unstructured.
Things like imaging, clinical nodes,
and sensor data from variables.
The opportunity healthcare
providers using big data have
reported cost reduction of to 20%.
And improved patients outcome by 30%.
But to get there, we need systems that can
handle this data reliable and securely.
And at scale source of healthcare
data, let's take a look closer.
Look at where this data comes from.
EHRs includes patient's history,
medications, labs, and physician notes.
Medical imaging makes up the bulk
of healthcare data by volume.
A single radiology
department may generate.
A hundred thousand images daily.
Genomic data sequencing costs have
dropped from 10,002,000 USD, but each
genome still adds 200 plus GB of data.
Variables collect 10 to 20 biometric
points per second, generating
five to 15 MB daily per person.
That's a massive stream
of heterogeneous data.
Right for EML, but challenging
for traditional infrastructures.
Three core challenges define this
space, data heterogeneity, and volume
and velocity and data quality issues.
Let's go one by one and explore this
data heterogeneity structure, the
databases, free text notes, time
series, vitals, and images, all coexist.
About 80% of the unstructured and
meaning SQL alone won't cut it.
A single 300 bed hospital might generate
50 terabytes per year from EHRs.
ICU.
Monitor can emit 2000
plus readings per second.
Data quality issues.
For instance, smoking status
is missing in 60% of records.
Diagnosis codes vary between hospitals.
We need smart pipelines.
Fault tolerant systems and flexible
schemas to make sense of the chaos.
So here's where scalable data
frameworks enter Apache Spark provides
in-memory processing, idle for large
scale, batch and steam processing.
One provider reduce training time for
clinical models by 88% after moving
from disc based system to spark.
A W SEF supports petabytes, scale
queries and cost effective storage.
Your hospital in Germany reported
40 percentage of infrastructure
cost savings after migration.
OOP handle semi-structured
and unstructured data.
Your public health network used it
to integrate radiology scans and
clinical nodes from 10 plus hospital
enabling ML based triad support.
These platforms are the foundations
of model healthcare analytics.
Cloud-based healthcare data
lakes, the traditional warehouses
force early schema decisions.
But in healthcare where data types are
dynamic, we need schema on reflexibility.
Cloud-based Data Lakes solves
that the consulted structure and
unstructured sources supporting more
data formats than legacy systems.
One US network built a data lake that
combined imaging EHS and real telemetry.
Result.
The analytic pipelines that once
took days now run in another an hour
and dashboards refresh in real time.
The ETL process in healthcare
are in just about moving data.
They are about preserving clinical
meaning steps in encode extraction
from different systems, normalization,
using snowed CT loin and RX nom.
Data quality validation to catch
testing and inconsistent entries.
Transformation for models,
readiness and incremental loading.
To support the steaming
data efficient ETL.
Reduce pipeline latency from 2.5 days to
11 of us at one hospital, resulting in
realtime validating for critical care.
Is reshaping how clean
clinicians are making decisions.
A declining model for 30 day readmission
predicted achieved A A UC of 0.87
outperforming traditional models.
Disease risk models predicted diabetes
at 94.3% and heart disease at over
90% and various cancers with up
to 96% accuracy for deterioration.
Prediction.
LSTM networks trained on ICU
time series data flagged.
Patients decline six to 10 hours
earlier than manual methods hospital.
Using these tools are seeing fewer
readmissions, better outcomes,
and improved resource allocations.
Medical imaging is a
primary area for ml CNN.
Detect lung nodules on x-rays shows
sensitivity and specificity comparable
to the expert radiologist unit.
Architectures enable on our
typical segmentation, reducing
manual processing time by 60%.
In one pilot, a assistor radiology
system help clinicians detect
pneumonia and chest scans with a
9% boost in diagnostic accuracy.
These tool accelerate diagnosis
improvement precisions, and help
radiologists manage increasing workloads.
NLP helps us tap into rich
but messy free text data.
NLP engines extract structured
insights from discharge summaries.
Pathology reports and clinical notes.
Clinical trial matching platforms.
Now automate patient enrollment
using NLP, reducing switch times
by weeks, adverse event reduction.
Using NLP saw recall rates
jump up 28% in one hospital.
One model achieved F1 score, so over 0.90.
For extracting medication dosage
and side effect information.
This enables real time text analytics
that complement structure S, but
it's not solve smooth sailing.
There are some limited
implementation challenges for being.
Security and privacy.
Over 60 of healthcare breaches
stem from access control.
Misconfigurations, HIPAA demands,
multi-layer protection, encryption,
role-based access and audit logs.
Workflow integrations.
Doctors already spend two to three
hours on EHRs per hour for patient care.
Any tool must integrate seamlessly
into their workflows, ideally,
within existing systems.
Ethical oversight, we need transparency.
If a model denies care.
Our gives poor recommendation.
We must know why.
This means explainable AI and clearly
defined accountability structures.
Engineering AI for healthcare means
building for trust, transparency,
and clinical usability, so to control
big data and mission learning or
transforming healthcare, but the success
on robust label and responsible systems.
And we are uniquely potent
to enable this future.
Ensuring performance at scale,
enforcing security, and keeping
patients outcome at the center.
Thanks for the time.