Speaker 29: Hi everyone.
I'm Shruti Raker, an engineering manager
at Broadcom leading VM service in VCF for
the past decade at VMware Broadcom, I've
contributed to foundational technologies
like vMotion and VM service that help
bridge traditional virtualization with
cloud native infrastructure today.
I'll be talking about how a unified
control plane for virtual machines
and container-based workloads can
be achieved using VM service, A VCF
offering, and why this approach is
critical for platforms that demand high
availability and operational excellence.
Let us first understand.
What are the challenges
that SREs face today?
One of the biggest pain points
that SRE teams face today is
operational fragmentation.
Containers are typically managed
through Kubernetes native tool.
While virtual machines are
handled through an entirely
different stack of infrastructure,
tools, dashboards, and APIs.
The result here is an operational drift.
SREs will have to correlate alerts
that come from different systems,
and troubleshooting now becomes hard.
Troubleshooting requires switching
context that come from different
systems, and automation becomes
difficult to standardize.
VM service and offering in VCF
fundamentally changes this model.
Okay.
Instead of treating VMs as external
infrastructure, it integrates them
directly into Kubernetes control plane.
That means SRE teams can now
manage both VMs and container based
workloads using the same APIs,
workflows, and operational patterns.
This dramatically reduces cognitive
load and enables a unified operational
model for hybrid platforms.
Why is hybrid platform
difficult to manage?
Most enterprises still run critical
workloads in a virtual machine
while newer services run in
container based infrastructure.
The challenge here is these two are
fundamentally different platform
based workflows, and these two worlds
traditionally operate with completely
different lifecycle management models.
VM Service solves this by making virtual
machines first class Kubernetes resources.
That means a VM can now be
declared, deployed, scaled.
And managed just like a pod
or a deployment using familiar
Kubernetes based primitives.
This brings infrastructure and
application operations closer together.
Instead of managing two parallelly
different systems, platform
teams can standardize these
workflows using Kubernetes.
This alignment enables
smoother migrations.
Simplifies hybrid application
architectures and allows organizations
to modernize incrementally
without forcing legacy workloads
to be containerized immediately.
The operational challenges for SRE
teams, like I mentioned earlier,
is fragmented failure modes,
divers tooling, and cognitive load.
SRE teams encounter increased complexity
due to these fragmented failure modes
across hybrid platforms and use of
multiple tools for monitoring and
incident response that result to
inconsistencies and high cognitive load
from managing various systems that affect
SRE system's ability to respond quickly
and adhere to their SLOs and SLAs.
Let's talk about introducing
VM service in VCF.
Treating virtual machines as first
class resources in Kubernetes
via VM service A VCF offering.
Enhances integration, simplifies
management, and improves reliability.
One of the most powerful ideas in
Kubernetes is declarative infrastructure.
You described the desired state and
the platform continuously reconciles
to maintain that state VM service
extends this model to virtual machines.
Instead of manually provisioning
these VMs through infrastructure
consoles or scripts or automations,
teams define VM specifications.
Declaratively using Kubernetes manifests.
The platform then handles
provisioning, lifecycle management
and reconciliation automatically.
This dramatically improves
repeatability and automation for VM
based workloads, just like containers.
It also enables Git ops style workflows,
where in VM infrastructure can be version
controlled alongside application code.
For platform teams, this means
infrastructure becomes predictable,
auditable, and automatable at scale.
Additionally, VM service supports
DevOps practices, enhancing continuous
delivery and integration, fostering
innovation and adaptability in
a changing digital landscape.
Simplifying operations is yet another
I important advantage of VM service.
A major advantage of VM service is
that it collapses operational silos.
Traditionally, SRA teams might
monitor containers through Kubernetes
tooling while troubleshooting VM
based workloads through vSphere or
any other virtualization dashboards.
VM Service removes the separation
by allowing both workload types
to be observed and operated
through Kubernetes Control plane.
This unified interface improves
operational efficiency and
significantly accelerates incident
response when something goes wrong,
engineers don't have to determine
which system owns what workload.
They simply interact with Kubernetes.
How powerful is that?
This not only reduces operational
complexity, but also enables teams
to apply the same automation, same
policies, and same operational
playbooks across containers and VMs.
Additionally, robust security features
ensure data integrity and compliance
in a dynamic digital landscape.
Let us talk about benefits
of a unified control plane.
A unified control plane delivers
far more than just convenience.
It fundamentally improves reliability.
When VMs and containers operate
under the same orchestration layer,
observability becomes standardized.
Alerts become consistent.
Capacity planning becomes simple.
And FI failure, isolation becomes easy.
Alerts are generated consistently.
Metrics follow same patterns.
Observability signals become
standardized, and orchestration
layer becomes standardized.
Incident response workflows
become predictable.
Capacity planning also
becomes significantly easier.
Instead of managing separate resource
pools for containers and VM based
workloads, SRE teams can reason about
this infrastructure holistically.
This enables more efficient resource
allocation, consumption, and
better forecasting and planning.
Total cost of ownership
becomes easy to reason about.
Ultimately, the unified control
plane allows organizations.
To improve from reactive
firefighting model towards a more
proactive, reliable based model
across their hybrid environments.
Enhanced failure, isolation also
reduce the impact of incidents
and enabling teams to manage mixed
workloads effectively and maintain
system stability during incidents.
Fragmented tooling that we had before is
changed to a unified control plane with
VM service in VCF before VM service.
Hybrid platform of platforms
often suffered from fragmented
tooling, inconsistent automation,
and noisy alerting systems.
Each infrastructure type required
its own lifecycle processes
and operational expertise.
VM service standardizes the these
workflows by bringing VM Lifecycle
management into Kubernetes.
The standardization means provisioning,
scaling, patching, and monitoring
can follow the same automation
centered around Kubernetes.
Regardless of the workload type for
SRE teams, this impact is phenomenal.
Fewer tools to maintain and becomes
extremely dramatic, lesser contact
switching during incidents and faster
mean time to resolution to adhere to
their SLOs and SLAs instead of operating
multiple platforms simultaneously.
Teams can operate a single
consistent infrastructure platform
centered around Kubernetes.
A unified Kubernetes control plane
standardizes, lifecycle management,
streamlines operations and enhances
reliability and enabling SRE teams
to handle incidents more effectively
across their hybrid infrastructure.
Let's learn about some
reliability lessons.
VM Service also enables reliability
practices that are traditionally
associated with cloud native platforms.
Because VMs are managed through
Kubernetes policies for rollout safety,
resource, isolation and security
can be enforced programmatically.
For example, platform teams can
implement safe rollout strategies
similar to container-based workloads.
Failure isolation also improves because
Kubernetes scheduling and policy
enforcement can limit the blast radius.
These capabilities allow organizations to
bring more modern reliability engineering
practices to legacy workloads that still
depend on traditional virtual machines.
Tailoring observability for
hybrid environments, essential
for day two operations.
Enabling SRE teams to identify issues
swiftly and recognize patterns and
respond to incidents effectively.
The key differentiator for VM service
is unified telemetry and visibility.
Observability is where VM service
becomes practically more powerful
in many hybrid environments.
Telemetry from VMs and containers
flow through completely different
monitoring pipelines, making correlation
extremely difficult during incidents.
VM Service enables unified telemetry
collection across both workload types.
This allows SRE teams to correlate
signals such as CPU pressure.
Network anomalies or latency
spikes across the entire platform.
Holistically, with this holistic
visibility, teams can identify systemic
issues earlier and use alert noise.
Instead of chasing symptoms across
different fragmented tools, engineers
can see the entire infrastructure
stack in a single operational view.
How powerful is that?
This allows businesses to adapt
quickly to changing demands.
It also enhances security
by providing comprehensive
visibility into potential vulner
vulnerabilities across all platforms.
As a result, teams can proactively
address concerns before they
escalate and maintaining optimal
performance and reliability.
The final takeaway from VM Service is
that it enables incremental modernization
rather than disruptive transformation,
you can adopt VM service using full
VCF stack and VM service to treat
VMs as Kubernetes resources alongside
your container-based workloads.
This streamlines operations and enhances
reliability across your hybrid platform.
Organizations don't need to
immediately containerize every
single legacy application to adopt
cloud native operational practices.
With VM service, existing VM based
workloads can be brought under
Kubernetes governance while newer
services continue running in containers.
This creates a unified platform that
supports both modernization and stability.
For SRE teams, the result here is a
simpler operational model that supports
automation, reliable engineering
practice, and scalability without
forcing teams to rewrite their whole
critical legacy application sets.
Other than standardizing tooling
and IMP improved observability,
it defines safe rollout practice.
Thank you so much for
listening to me today.
If you have any more questions, don't
hesitate to reach out to me on my email
or in the question and
answer section below.
Thank you.