Speaker 20: Hello everyone and welcome.
Thank you for joining
this session at Con 42 SE.
My name is Prakash and I have
Sprint the last 18 years working
at the intersection of technology,
healthcare, and business transformation.
Throughout my career, I have
focused on implementing large scale
systems, launching products, and
helping organizations turn complex
organizational challenges into
scalable and reliable solutions.
But what motivates me the most is the
impact technology can have on healthcare,
especially for underserved Americans who
depend on Medicare and Medicaid programs.
These populations often face
barriers in access, coordination
of care, and timely services.
When technology systems fail or
processes break down, the people
who are reflected the most are
often those who can least afford it.
That realization has shaped
how I approach my work.
I focus on identifying gaps in
healthcare workflows, automating
complex processes and building
solutions that make the systems more
reliable and efficient for healthcare
organizations serving these communities.
For me, technology is not
just about building systems.
It is about improving access to care.
Enabling better outcomes and making
healthcare systems work better for
the people who rely on them the most.
I am really excited to share a journey
that sits right at the intersection
of healthcare operations, software
reliability, and artificial intelligence.
The topic today is engineering
reliability in letters.
From manual risk to AI driven automation
stands for utilization management.
And if you are not familiar with it,
think of it as the process health
insurance payers used to review
and authorize medical services.
Every decision made in the process.
Whether a treatment is approved, denied,
or requires more information must be
communicated to the member and their
provider through what is called a letter.
These letters are not just
routine communications.
They are legally regulatory
binding documents.
And yet for a long time, the process of
generating and delivering them has been
highly manual, fragile, and risk prone.
In this session, I will walk you through
the full journey from understanding why
these letters are harder than they look
to the risks involved and the automation
we built, and finally, how we are
using AI to make these letters not just
faster and more reliable, but genuinely
better for the underserved Americans.
Let's get started.
Why are letters more
complex than they appear?
When most engineers first hear
about generating a letter,
they think, how hard can it be?
You have a template
you fill in the fields.
You send it done.
But letters are fundamentally different
from typical application generated
documents, and I want to spend a
moment here making sure we appreciate
that complexity because it's the root
cause of everything that follows.
Let's start with the regulatory dimension.
Letters are regulatory artifacts.
They are not just communications.
They are legally required notifications,
governed by state and federal law.
The center of Medicare and Medicaid
services, state insurance departments
and RAC accreditation standards
all have specific rules about what
must be in these letters, when they
must be sent, and in what format.
Miss the required statement.
That's a compliance violation.
Use the wrong language for
the wrong state violation.
Again, then that is a
turnaround time or PAT pressure.
These letters often have strict
timelines, sometimes as tied as 24
to 72 hours after a decision is made.
In healthcare, delays in communication
can directly affect patient care.
A member waiting on an approval letter
to proceed with surgery or provider
waiting on a denial to understand
the next steps every hour matter.
Add to that, the operational complexity.
You have multiple decision types,
approvals, denials, extensions, and
additional information request, each
with their own templates, logic and
regulatory language requirements.
And every state can have
different requirements.
A letter in California may
need a different language.
And the same denial in Texas or New York.
So you are not dealing
with one letter template.
You are dealing with the metrics
of decision types crossed
with specific variations.
Finally, these are people involved.
Members and the providers both
need timely a curate updates.
And coordinating all of that
through manual processes creates
enormous operational burden.
This is why letters are not simple
document generation problem.
They are a reliability and
complaints engineering challenge.
So let's talk about the key
challenge in the letters.
Now that we understand why letters are
complex, let's look at the specific
challenges we faced before the automation.
The first category is template
and the content issues staffs.
Were manually selecting the
templates from a library.
Which introduced the very human
risk of selecting the wrong one.
Copy paste errors in the clinical
rationale sections where nurses or case
managers could paste content from the
clinical system into the letter where
a persistent problem and state specific
language variations meant that even
when the right template was chosen.
Additional manual edits were often
required to comply with local regulations.
Second category is
fulfillment and delivery.
Letters had to be physically routed to a
fulfillment center by printing or mailing.
That handoff was manual.
Sometimes PDFs were being handled by
individuals saved to share drives,
emailed to the letter fulfillment vendors.
This created delays, version, confusion,
and occasionally letters simply not
making it to the print queue at all.
And if letter needed to be
pre-printed, that means more cost,
more manual work, and more delays.
The third category is visibility and risk.
There was limited observability
into the letter in its lifecycle.
Was it generated?
Was it sent to the fulfillment center?
Was it actually printed or it is
mailed without real time tracking.
Identifying delays was reactive.
Someone would notice a complaint
or an audit flag before anyone
realized something went wrong.
And underlying all of this
was the risk of PHA exposure.
Which is called a protected health
information of the patient data.
The patient data was moving through
manual human driven workflows.
Every manual touchpoint is a
potential security risk together.
The three challenge areas, the template,
content, errors, fulfillment, friction,
and the limited visibility form the
foundation of what we set to solve.
Let me now put some weight behind
why solving these challenges was
urgent, because it's not just
about operational inconvenience.
The risk for the health insurance payers.
In this space are
significant and quantifiable.
Here is a striking statistic
that shaped our thinking.
A minor failure in the letter
process, even a small as a single
missing required statement or a
one day delay that can lead to 75%
increase in the compliance violations.
That's not a theoretical risk.
That's a documented regulatory reality
in the healthcare complaints space.
Think about that.
You're not talking about a
catastrophic system outage.
You are talking about a subtle
process gap, the kind that goes
unnoticed in manual workflows that
can nearly double your violation rate.
From a financial standpoint,
the risks compound quickly.
Letters not sent to
fulfillment set mean reprints.
Reprint means cost.
They also mean delays which can trigger.
SLA breaches.
SLA.
Breaches lead to escalations from
regulators, from accreditation
bodies, and from members and
providers filing grievances.
Then there is auditing when a
regulatory body audits the process.
They want traceability.
They want to see when the decisions were
made, when the letters were generated,
and when they were sent, and when
it was received in a manual process.
Assembling that audit trail is painful.
It's even possible.
And the risk extends
beyond financial penalties.
Brand trust in healthcare is deeply
tied to the communication quality.
A member who receives a confusing denial
letter or worse even or not receiving
it all loses the trust in the insurer.
That has the long-term membership
and reputational consequences.
These risks collectively made the
case for the investment in automation.
Undeniable.
The question wasn't whether to automate
it was how fast we could do it safely.
I wanted to talk about our
transformation timeline.
Now let's look at how we approached
this transformation because
it wasn't a big bang overall.
It was a deliberate, phased journey that
we have been executing in several years.
In 2023, we laid the foundation with
letter configuration and implementation.
This phase was about building the
infrastructure, the systems, the
frameworks, and the configuration
capabilities that would support
everything that followed.
We needed a platform that could
handle template management, state
specific rules and integration
with clinical decision systems.
In 2024, we tackled the
denial metrics implementation.
D denial letters are the most
complex type They require the precise
language, the complex rationale.
They carry the highest
regulatory scrutiny.
Building out the denial metrics,
the logic engine that maps that
clinical, IANS to the right letter
content was a critical step.
In 2025, we delivered the
approval letters, automation.
We started with approval letters
because it was str, structurally
simpler and less variability.
Getting them right quickly
demonstrated the value of
automation to the stakeholders.
In 2026, we rolled out the denial
extension and the additional
information letter automation,
bringing the full denial.
Decision spectrum into
the automated workflow.
And alongside that, we are beginning
the AI inclusion phase in 2027.
We are focused on the human review
layer, building intelligent workflows
where a human reviewer is brought
in at the right moment for the right
decisions rather than at every step.
And we are completing the compliance and
safety framework to ensure all of this
operates within a robust governance model.
And beyond that, the roadmap includes
expansion across additional line of
business, each phase built on the
last, each one delivered value while
preparing the ground for the next.
That's the architecture of the
sustainable transformation.
And that really helps the Medicare
Medicaid population who are underserved.
So let's get concrete about what
the world looked before automation.
Specifically for the approval letters,
the process was fundamentally queue based.
When a utilization management decision
was made in the clinical system,
it would drop into a work queue.
A staff member would pick it up and
identify the right template, populate
the required fields, often copy paste
the clinical content, and then manually
route the PDF to the fulfillment center.
Every step in the chain
requires a human intervention.
Every human touchpoint is a potential
point of failure, delay or error, manual
PDF handling was particularly problematic.
Files were being saved, emailed,
and transferred across systems,
creating version, confusion.
Audit trail gaps, and because PHI was
embedded in these documents, every manual
transfer was a potential HIPAA risk.
Delays in printing and
dispatch were common.
The fulfillment center had SLAs, but
feeding them through a manual queue
made that backlogs could form without
visibility until someone noticed a
complaint or a deadline was missed.
There was no real time status,
no dashboard that told you
this decision was made.
This letter was generated, this letter was
sent to print, and this letter was mailed.
You were flying blind.
This was the environment we were
operating in and it was clearly
unsustainable as decision volumes group.
Now let's look at what automation
changed and the contrast is significant.
The core design principle of our
approval letter automation was end-to-end
workflow automation with zero manual
intervention required in this standard.
When a utilization management decision
is made, the system automatically
triggers the letter generation.
No human needs to select
the appropriate letter.
Letter generation is now real time.
The decision is made, the letter is
generated, and it is transmitted directly
to the printing and fulfillment system,
all with the same workflow execution.
What used to take us or days
in a manual queue now happens
within seconds or minutes.
The reduction in human
error is substantial.
Template selection is rule driven content.
Population is automated.
Routing is programmatic.
The opportunities for copy
paste errors, wrong template
selection, and routing mistakes are
eliminated from the standard path.
PHI protection is now built into
the workflow architecture rather
than depending on human discipline.
Data flows through secure
authenticated integrations.
It is never sitting in a shared folder
or be getting emailed between systems.
SLA performance improved
dramatically because generation and
transmission happens in real time.
The time between decision and letter
delivery shrunk significantly.
TAT metrics that were previously
difficult to meet consistently
became reliable, and we now have the
audit traceability what we needed.
Every step in the workflow is logged.
With the decision timestamp,
letter generation, timestamp,
transmission, timestamp.
When a regulator asks for the audit
trail, we can produce it instantly.
This is what a well-engineered
automation looks like, not just
faster, but fundamentally more
reliable and more trustworthy.
Automating denial, extension, and
additional information letters was a more
complex undertaking than approval letters,
and it deserves its own discussion.
The complexity comes
from multiple dimensions.
Denial letters must include the specific
clinical rationale for the decision.
The regulatory citations, the members
appeal rights, and the state specific
language, all of which vary based on
the type of denial, the state, the line
of business, and the member's plan.
Our solution centered on a
business rule engine, specifically
the denial metrics we built.
This matrix encodes the logic that
maps each combination of decision type.
State and the plan to the correct
template, the correct language blocks,
and the correct regulatory citation.
It's essentially the brain that
knows what each letter needs to see.
Template selection is
now entirely rule driven.
The system evaluates the decision context.
What type of denial was it in
which state for which service and.
Selects the appropriate
template automatically.
No human judgment required
for that selection.
State specific language is
inserted automatically based on the
geographic context of the decision.
The system knows that a denial in
New York requires a different appeal
language than the same denial in Texas,
and it handles that differentiation
without any manual intervention.
For this category of letters, we
did design a human review step
before the final print Dispatch.
This is intentional denial letters, carry
a significant member impact and regulatory
weight, having a reviewer confirm.
Confirm that the letter
has all the information.
The key difference from the old world
is that the reviewer is now reviewing a
fully formed, correctly structured letter
rather than building one from scratch.
And this human in the loop design sets
the stage perfectly for what comes next.
AI enhancement.
Automation solved the reliability problem.
EA is now helping us solve the
quality and comprehension problem,
and this is where I think the real
impact on patient outcome li lives.
Let me explain the challenge,
even a perfectly automated.
Denial letter one that is legally correct.
Regulatory compliant, and delivered
on time can still be a terrible
experience for the member receiving it.
Healthcare language is dense, clinical
terminology is confusing, and a
member reading a denial letter often
can't understand why their treatment
was denied, what their options are.
Or what they should do next.
And when people don't
understand, they disengage.
They don't file appeals.
They are entitled to, they don't follow
with their provider, they lose trust.
Our a enhancement player is designed
to address exactly this problem.
It operates on top of
the automated complaint.
Letter and transforms it into
something a human being can
actually understand and act on.
The first capability is member
friendly language simplification.
The AI rewrites the dense clinical
and legal language into plain English
without changing the meaning or removing
the required regulatory content.
It's not about dumbing it down,
it's about making it accessible.
The second is empathetic tone enhancement.
The AI evaluates the tone of
the letter and adjusts it to be
compassionate and respectful.
A denial letter doesn't have to
be feel cold, are bureaucratic.
It can acknowledge the member's
situation while being factually precise.
Third is personalized explanation.
The AI generates a plain language
explanation of why this specific
decision was made tailored to the
individual member's situation, not
just a generic regulatory statement.
Fourth is detection of
missing appeal language.
The AI validates that all required
appeal rights information is
present and clearly communicated.
If something is missing or unclear,
it flags it for the human review.
Throughout all of this, there is a
human in the loop validation step.
As we discussed earlier, the AI's output
is reviewed before the letter goes out.
This ensures the accountability catches
edge cases and builds the trust needed
to expand AI's role Over time, this AI
being used responsibility responsibly.
To improve human outcomes, not
to replace the human oversight.
So key benefits of AI
driven in the letters.
Let me now consolidate the value
of everything we have built
into the key benefits, because
ultimately this is why it matters.
Isn't it?
The first benefit is
clarity for the patients.
The members now receive letters
that clearly explain what
decision was made, why it was
made, and what their options are.
For many Medicare and Medicaid members,
healthcare communication can be
complex and difficult to understand.
Clear and comprehensible letters help
them truly understand their situation.
That clarity leads to the second
benefit, empowering members to make
informed decision about their care.
When individuals understand the clinical
reasoning behind their decisions and
their appeal rights, they can actively
participate in the healthcare journey.
They know what they can appeal,
seek second opinions or discuss
options with their providers.
The third and the fourth benefits are
strong relationship and the trust.
When healthcare organizations
communicate clearly, compassionately and
transparently, members feel respected
rather than processed for underserved
population who may already feel
disconnected from the healthcare system.
That transparency builds
trust and confidence.
Operational improvements also translates
into better care for these communities.
Automation reduces manual work, minimizes
errors and lowers compliance risks.
More importantly, it allows healthcare
staff to redirect the time and the
expertise towards activities that
directly support the patient care
instead of administrative tasks.
Another important benefit is the speed.
Faster letter generation means faster
decisions for members and providers.
For patients waiting on approvals
or next steps in their care,
reducing the turnaround time
can make meaningful difference.
Finally, the system is
designed to scale efficiently.
As healthcare programs grow and serve
more Medicare and Medicaid members,
the architecture can support increased
demand without creating operational
bottlenecks or delays taken together.
These benefits go beyond
technology improvements.
They contribute to a healthcare system
that communicate better response
faster, and ultimately serves the
Medicare Medicaid members, many of
whom are underserved with greater
clarity and dignity and efficiency.
As we build more AI capability
into this process, governance,
compliance and safety became.
Increasingly important, and I want
direct about how we are approaching that.
A guardrails and validation
checks are built into every
step where AI participates.
The AI cannot independently
publish a letter.
It can enhance, suggest, and flag, but
every output goes through a validation
logic before it proceeds in the workflow.
Human review remains a non-negotiable
component for the critical decisions.
We are not building toward a
world where AI writes the denial
letters and no one reviews them.
We are building toward a world where
AI does the heavy lifting of language
transformation and quality checking.
And a human reviewer spends their
time on adjustment and accountability
rather than formatting and compliance.
Lookups, full audit traceability
is maintained across the entire
workflow, including the AI actions.
We log what the AI changed, when and why.
This is essential for regulatory
review and for building internal
confidence in the system.
Version control and regulatory monitoring.
Monitoring ensures that the
regulations change and they change
frequently in the healthcare.
Our templates and business rules
are updated systematically.
We track such regulatory success.
Monitor the updates and manage
template portions with rigor
and observability dashboard.
Give us the real time visibility
into the TAT performance error rates.
Review the queues and the system health.
We can spot a problem before it
gets into a compliance issue.
This compliance and safety
framework is what makes AI adoption
possible in the regulated industry.
Without it, you are not deploying ai,
you are making an unquantifiable risk.
Next steps.
Looking ahead.
Our roadmap continues to push the
capabilities of this platform forward.
Real time compliance scoring will
allow the system to evaluate every
letter against the current regulatory
requirements before it leaves the system,
not after an audit, not after a complaint,
but at the moment of generation.
Predictive risk detection will use
historical patterns to flag letters that
have a higher probability of issues.
Before they are dispatched, think of
it as a proactive quality assurance
rather than reactive error correction.
Automated regulatory rule updates
will reduce the manual overhead
of keeping templates current
as laws and regulations evolve.
The system will monitor regulatory
sources and propose template
updates for human review.
Enhanced fulfillment confirmation
tracking will close the loop on letter
delivery, giving us visibility not
just into what was sent, but what
was actually delivered and when.
Continuous AI model refinement
will ensure that the AI's language
capabilities improve over the time,
informed by the reviewer feedback, member
satisfaction data, and the appeal reads.
And expansion across the line of business
will bring these capabilities to other
areas beyond the such as appeals,
grievance, et cetera, extending the
value of the platform to more members,
more providers, and more decision types.
The foundation is built, the direction
is clear, and the roadmap is ahead.
That is exciting.
I want to close with four principles that
I have guided this entire journey because
I think they apply well beyond the letters
to any complex automation and AI initiated
in a regulated high stakes domain.
Automation reduces the time, the
manual work that was consuming
clinical and operational staff.
The template selection, copy,
paste, PDF routing, that's not
where the expertise should be spent.
Automation frees people to focus
on what only humans can do.
Judgment, empathy, and accountability.
AI enhances clarity.
Not every problem needs ai, but in a
domain where tense, legalistic language.
Creates barriers between the
institution and the people they serve.
AI has a genuine role to
play in bridging the gap.
Used well, AI can make communication
more human, and it's not nice.
Human oversight ensures safety
in healthcare and in any domain
where the stakes are high.
AI is a tool, not a decision maker.
The human in the loop is not the
limitation of the technology.
It is a deliberate design choice that
reflects both regulatory reality and
it's also an ethical responsibility,
and reliability builds trust.
Ultimately, everything we have
built, the automation, the ai,
the compliance framework, and
it is in service of one goal.
Building the trust.
The trust between the health
plans and their members.
Trust between the
providers and the payers.
Trust between trust in the systems
that mediate those relationships.
Thank you so much for your time today.
I hope this journey has been useful
and I would like, love to connect
with if you are working on the similar
challenges in your organization.
Thank you.