Hello everyone.
Welcome to corner 42 SRE 2025.
I am a pian a technology infras
specialist, and I will be talking
about how adopting effective site
reliability engineering practices can
significantly reduce operational it
streamline infrastructure deployments and
enhance our overall system performance
in multi-cloud infrastructures.
In agenda I'll be focusing on the overview
of multi-cloud infrastructures and their
complexities, and then role of SRE in
multi-cloud and how we can leverage SRE
best practices to to reduce or operation
over it and observability, automation
and tools and security and much more.
So multi-cloud infrastructures involve
leveraging multiple cloud providers.
Simultaneously to achieve optimal
flexibility, resilience, and performance.
So organizations are rapidly adopting
multi-cloud infrastructures to
capitalize on their distinct advantages.
But this also introduces
operational complexities that
blocks effective monitoring
security enforcement and performance
optimization across environments.
F first complexity like operational
and architectural complexity.
So whenever you adopt multiple
clouds,  you are dealing
with different architectures,
APIs, and service offerings.
So which significantly increases
complexity in management and operations.
And second one,  visibility
and observability caps.
So maintaining a clear visibility
and a consistent observability across
various cloud environments often
becomes difficult due to different
monitoring tools and standards.
And the third one,  data
silos or fragmentation.
So using separate monitoring and
logging solutions for each cloud
results in fragmented data that
limits the ability to have a unified,
comprehensive view of the entire system.
And Atla the scalability and cost
management so efficiently managing
the scalability of data ingestion
and the retention across clouds,
while ensuring you remain within
the budgets can present substantial
financial and operational challenges.
Next, we can focus on the
role of SR in multicloud.
So E core SRE principles so in
multi-cloud, we rely on clear measures
like SLI service level indicators to track
the performance SLOs, like service level
objectives to set reliability targets and
error budgets to manage risk proactively
across distributed environments.
Why SRE is critical in multi-cloud.
Like for coordination and standardization.
SRE provides a unified approach ensuring
consistent processes, tools, and practices
human across diverse cloud providers
and for reducing operation over it.
No.
We, if we implement consistent automation
leveraging self feeling infrastructures
and centralized observability, SRE
helps reduce manual intervention and
those streamlines the operations.
Also for performance and
reliability management.
If we establish clear performance
baselines and reliability thresholds
it help effectively manage the
complexities and dependencies between
different cloud service products
and that last like
collaboration and organization.
So for cross-functional teams, like if
you follow the effective multi-cloud
SRE, that involves like collaboration
among teams from operations, development,
security, and cloud providers
that helps, share fosters shared
responsibility and efficient workflows.
And also if we clearly align the SRE
objectives with organizational priorities
that ensures the reliability and
performance initiatives directly support,
broader business strategies and outcomes.
So next is architecting for
reliability in multi-cloud.
The first, like we need to focus
on designing resilient services.
So when architecting resilience
services, it's critical to
choose architectures wisely.
Adopting microservices or model
designs help because each component
can scale and update independently.
And also it helps us to reduce
the downtime and enhance the
reliability of the systems.
So additionally implementing active
or active passive strategies across
clouds that ensure high availability
and provides seamless failover in
the event of disruptions or outages.
Also planning for failure and cross
cloud dependencies so we can proactively
simulate potential failure scenarios,
ensuring that fallback mechanisms are
not only effective, but tested regularly.
We can also focus heavily on maintaining
the data consistency and efficient
replication and synchronization
across multiple cloud environments.
And at last like network and data
management, so reliable network
and data management form a backbone
of resilient multi-cloud setup.
So we we can employ secure and high
performance data transfer designed
explicitly for multi-cloud environments.
So it is vital to manage data carefully
because achieving consistency across
clouds without excessive replication over
it and that helps balance the performance,
reliability, and cost efficiency.
So next we can see how we can
leverage SRE practices for re
reducing the opportunity over it.
First is the automation and self feeling.
By adopting IAC, the infrastructure
as code practices and human driven
automation may the organizations or teams
can minimize the manual interventions
and mitigate configuration drift.
Second is the standardized CICD pipelines.
So implementing consistent CICD
pipelines across multiple cloud
providers that support uniformity and
reliability and software delivery.
So this standardization simplifies
the deployment processes, s
errors, and accelerate the time
to market for critical updates.
And the other one is the
observability and monitoring.
Deploying the advanced observability
frameworks can no provide or
support comprehensive logging
metrics, collection and tracing.
To provide a deep visibility into
the system health and performance.
So this empowers various teams to
proactively identify agonize and
address issues rapidly that helps
improve overall operational resilience.
And at last, the capacity planning
and performance optimization.
Leveraging realtime performance
metrics and predictive analytics
enables proactive resource management
and efficient auto scaling.
So this approach ensures optimal resource
utilization and minimizes the cost over
next, how sari can improve
the performance reliability.
For performance optimization, we
need to clearly identify and target
the most critical performance areas
that reduce latency and improving
the throughput with residency and
geographical dispersed setups.
And the next is the
proactive capacity planning.
We can leverage predictive analytics
and forecasting to efficiency manager
resources that prevents both research
shortage and over provisioning.
And next the engineering.
So if we integrate some fault
injection tests across multi-cloud
environments that helps us to detect
weaknesses and also we can confidently
validate for any failover strategies.
And at last resource allocation.
If we strategically distribute
workloads to balance the cost,
efficiency and performance.
We can, and also leverage the
ephemeral and serverless computing
to minimize the hover it without
sacrificing the reliability of systems.
Next, we talk about one of
the most crucial component
of sorry, like observability
monitoring and instant response.
First is the unified monitoring.
So we leverage unified monitoring
techniques to seamlessly aggregate
metrics, logs, and traces
from diverse cloud vendors.
So delivering it helps us to deliver
comprehensive visibility through your
through single path or pan of class.
And the next is a distributor tracing.
So distributed tracing ensures,  end
to end visibility by tracking requests
across microservices or environments
that span different cloud service
products provide that helps provide
deep insights into performance,
bottlenecks, and service interactions.
And the other one is the
electing and incident management.
So if you configure the alert thresholds
and unified incident workflows, that
helps us to reduce the alert noise and
minimize the operational description.
And also it enables the faster
resolution times and improve
overall service stability.
And that lasts the tools and
platforms tools such as open
telemetry Prometheus and Grafana.
Support, multi-cloud visibility
and real time insights.
So these powerful tools empower teams with
actionable data, accelerating response,
and enhancing proactive management
across diverse cloud infrastructures.
Next, the automation
and tooling strategies.
First is the automated
C-I-T-C-D pipelines.
If we establish automated continuous
integration and deployment pipelines
that helps us like streamline
multi-cloud deployment releases.
Also, it minimizes the human
error and prevents configuration
drift across platforms.
And the other one is the the configuration
management and policy environment.
Enforcement.
The tools such as like Ansible,
chef, puppet, and open policy
agent that consistently enforce
security policies compliance and
standardized to configurations
across the complex infrastructures.
The next one is the self filling
mechanisms so we can design like
intelligence systems capable of
proactively detecting, mitigating
and recovering from failures or
performance issues autonomously.
So that helps us to reduce
any operational challenges.
And the last platform engineering
and developer enablement.
We can implement some intuitive
self-service portals or platform
that interacts with the developers
to seamlessly build, deploy and scale
applications without any involvement
to work on any infras activities.
They do not require to have
our infrastructure expertise.
And the next is the security
and compliance in multi-cloud.
The first one, it's like your
unified security frameworks.
So if you implement a comprehensive
security scanning, automated
configuration checks and continuous
posture management, that helps us
to maintain a consistent security
baseline across diverse cloud providers.
And next, the IAM identity
access management.
So if you establish a
centralized IAM solution.
That helps us to unify roles, permissions,
and enforce the least privileged
access models that can support,  IAM
policies across multiple cloud environs.
And the third one is the data
production and encryption.
And we can adopt some robust
encryption methods for data
first and in and in transit.
That leverages integrated key management
systems that operate eff effectively
across different cloud provided platforms.
And at last, the zero trust architecture.
So zero trust principles strategically,
can verify and secure every
communication and transaction between
sources, applications, and users
within complex multi-cloud landscapes.
And at last, to see future
trends and considerations.
See here the evolution of
cloud native technologies like
organizations will increasingly
leverage serverless architectures.
Or like function as a service to simplify
the operations and optimize resource
usage across various cloud platforms.
Nowadays  AI driven practices or
like strategies known as  AI ops
or becoming, I know essential for
managing the scale and complexity of
large scale multi-cloud environment.
Next is the advanced SRES approaches.
SRE practices will evolve through
advanced reliability modeling advanced
observability frameworks, proactive
chaos engineering and continuous
resilience testing to ensure systems are
robust in multi-cloud infrastructures.
And at last year, the shifts in
industry standards and compliance.
So we can anticipate more rigorous
and expansive data governance
regulations associating like
proactive adaptation and compliance
across global cloud infrastructures.
Thank you.