Hello everyone, myself, Ian.
I'm here to present how we can use
generative AI to optimize hybrid
cloud workloads and infrastructure.
The in integration of
generative AI into hybrid cloud
environments has revolutionized.
Enterprise infrastructure management,
transforming how organizations
handle complex computing workloads
across distributor systems.
This presentation explores
how AI driven optimization.
Creates more efficient,
secure, and resilient work.
Hybrid architectures enabling enterprise
to move from reactive to proactive
infrastructure management while realizing
significant cost benefits and performance.
Improvements.
Let's understand the
complexity of hybrid cloud.
You have the data centers, the
on-prem data centers with high
control, but limited scalability.
The public cloud resources.
Like AWS Google Cloud Azure,
which are highly scalable with
consumption based pricing model.
You need a complex network topology
to connect both the on-prem data
centers and the cloud resources
with careful optimization.
Keeping the security
and compliances in mind.
Cross environment protection require
requires consistent policies.
Keeping the security in mind.
The traditional management approach
falls short, manual provisioning,
time consuming processes that
can't keep pace with the changing.
Workload demands leading to resource under
utilization or performance bottleneck,
like e-commerce website during the, during
the black Friday, there's a, the huge
traffic inflow during the black Friday.
So accordingly the resources has
to scale up as per the demand and
scale down when the demand goes down.
Secondly, the static resource allocation.
Fixed resource assignments that fail
to adopt to fluctuating workload
patterns, resulting of excess
capacity or performance constraints.
Reactive troubleshooting traditionally.
Addressing issues after they
impact users instead of preventing
them, increases downtime and
degrading the user experience.
The conventional approach react
the conventional approach.
The conventional approaches create
significant inefficiencies in
hybrid environments where workloads
must move seamlessly between the.
On-prem and cloud infrastructure
to maintain optimal performance
and cost effectiveness.
AI powered predictive workload.
Generative AI examines the historical
workload, workload patterns like
various metrics, logs, historical logs
to identify usage trends and predict.
Future demands machine learning models,
forecast, resources need before demand.
Spikes occur
after pre, after predicting.
It optimizes the allocation.
Resources automatically scale up and
down across the hybrid environments.
Lastly, it reduces the cost.
Eliminating the lower provisioning we
to significant infrastructure savings.
By implementing AI driven predictive
scaling enterprises can achieve
up to 35% of reduction in the
infrastructure costs while ensuring
application have the resources that
need precisely when they need them.
The AI
in inte, the AI's intelligent Security
framework identifies anomalies and pattern
anomaly patterns that indicate potential
threats using behavioral analysis,
continuous verification across
hybrid environments that makes
a zero trust architecture that
verifies each and every
connections coming inside.
The infrastructure, immediate threat
containment without human intervention
with your automated responses.
The generative AI enhances security by
creating synthetic attack scenarios to.
Test differences.
Identify vulnerabilities
before they could be.
Explore exploited these
intelligent frameworks continuously
learn from new threats.
Adopting protection strategies
across both on-prem and cloud
infrastructure in real time.
The year
adoptive network optimization, the
real time monitoring of network
flows and application demands by
analyzing the traffic, the network
traffic that flows between the
on-prem and cloud infrastructure.
Dynamic path selection based on
current condition routing optimization.
And intelligent distribution of
traffic across variable resources,
which are situated in various regions
or zones.
AI driven network optimization
can reduce latency by up to 40% in
hybrid environment by continuously
analyzing the traffic patterns and
adjusting routing configuration.
This adaptive approach ensure.
Optimal application performance,
even as the network conditions
change throughout the day.
Automated decis decision making.
The uses infrastructure as code
AI generates and optimizes the
infrastructure templates based
on the workload requirement
using various tools like Ansible.
Kubernetes is terraform for infrastructure
as code automatic detection and
remedi of infrastructure issues.
Self-healing systems like the
AI looks into the logs and try
to understand if there is any
issue, if there is any errors.
It self-heal.
It detects those errors and remediates
immediately for faster resolution.
Continuous optimization ongoing
refinement of resources, location, and
performance tuning if there is any.
Any long running queries
that is using huge
resources like memory.
It does a continuous refinement
of resources allocation.
And does the performance tuning?
Yeah.
Recommends architectural improvements
based on evolving patterns that
gives a proactive suggestions.
By automating routine infrastructure
decisions, IT teams can reduce
manual intervention by up to 80%.
Freeing, valuable time for innovation
and strategic innovative initiatives.
While ensuring more consistent system
performance across hybrid environments,
what are the business impacts when
we are using generative ai One.
Cost reduction, lower infrastructure
expenses through optimized resource
utilization, up to 35%, reduction
in cost, faster recovery, improved
disaster recovery timeframes
with yay orchestrator processes.
And 60% performance stability, reduction
in response time, variably across
applications, 45% of team productivity.
The team.
Concentrate more on, on the innovation
rather than on the maintenance of
the systems, that gives 45% of team
productivity when using ai, generative ai,
let's look into the real
world success stories.
A leading bank, reduced
infrastructure cost by 30%.
While improving transaction processing
speeds up by implementing AI driven
workload optimization across their hybrid
workload, saving over 15 million annually
a hospital network improved patients data
access speeds by 45% while maintaining
stringent compliance requirement through
intelligent data placement and access
control across hybrid infrastructure.
An automotive part manufacturer
achieved 99.99 production system
uptime by implementing AI powered
productive maintenance and workload
balance balancing across factory
floor and cloud analytic performance.
What are the challenges and the solution
implementation challenges and solutions?
Integration complexity.
Implementing incremental AI adoption
with focused use case could in
expanding to enterprise wide deployment.
Start with clearly defined workload that
offers measurable optimization potential.
Skill gaps.
Develop internal expertise through
targeted training with leveraging managed
services for specialized AI capabilities.
Create cross-functional
teams that combine cloud.
Skills, build confidence
through transparent AI decision
processing with human oversight.
During initial phase, document
and communicate successes to build
organization, buy-in, data quality
issues, establish comprehensive data.
Governance and cleansing processes
to ensure AI model receive high
quality inputs implementing in
continuous data validation pipeline.
What is the future of generally ai?
With hybrid cloud
and edge, the convergence of edge
computing with yaka optimized
hybrid cloud creates unprecedented
opportunities for real time
processing of all the data source.
While maintaining centralized management
and analytic capabilities, organizations
embracing the this integrated approach
with benefit for more resilient,
responsive, and efficient infrastructure
as AI capabilities continue to evolve.
We will see increasing automation of
complex infrastructure decision making,
eventually leading to self designing
systems that continually optimize
themselves based on the business
requirements and technology landscapes.
The convergence of edge computing
with AI optimized hybrid cloud creates
unprecedented opportunities for real
time processing of the data source.
Of the data source.
While maintaining centralized management
and analytic capabilities, organization
organizations, embracing this integrated
approach will benefit from more resilient,
responsive, and effective infrastructure.
As AI capabilities continue to evolve, we
will see increasingly automate automation
of complex infrastructure decisions.
Eventually le leading to self designing
system that continuously optimize
themself based on changing business
requirement and technology landscape.
Thank you.