Hello everyone.
Let's deep dive and explore how social
determinants of health commonly known
as SDOH are significantly impacting
healthcare outcomes of member
populations, particularly in rural
healthcare settings where integration
into clinical workflows, presence,
unique challenges currently in us.
10.2% of households are facing
food insecurity and nearly
580,000 member population is
experiencing housing instability.
Addressing these SDUH factors through
structured healthcare interventions
is crucial for health equity.
This presentation offers evidence-based
strategies for screening, operational
integration, and community
collaboration to effectively incorporate
SDOH into healthcare systems.
Let's explore how standard tools
and advanced analytics can transform
care delivery leading to measurable
improvements in patient outcomes
and organizational efficiency.
Let's look into what healthcare and SDOH.
Factors are the important SDOH
determinants of health are
housing, food, security, safety,
transportation, and utilities.
Let's deep dive housing.
Housing stability, or the lack of
stability, quality, and affordability
of the members for related to housing
directly impacts health outcomes.
Where unstable housing is linked to
increased emergency department visits
and delayed care food security.
Access to nutritious food affects
chronic disease management with food
insecurity is, which is prevalent
in 10.2% of US households today.
Safety, interpersonal safety concerns
can prevent proper healthcare
engagement and significant impact.
Physical significantly impact
physical and mental health.
Transportation.
The lack of real reliable
transportation is disabling access
to healthcare services where 3.6
million Americans today are missing
medical appointments due to lack of
transportation and having those barriers.
Utilities, any access to
electricity, water communication
services directly affect medication
storage, telehealth participation,
and overall health management.
There are evidence-based
impacts of SDOH integration.
We, it has been seen that once SDOH
has been integrated into the clinical
workflows and healthcare framework.
Almost 86% of gain has been
achieved in completion of member
screenings, where initially there
were, the outreach was decreased.
But once the integration of SDH
has been successfully completed,
the rate of screening for all these
members have been achieved up to 86%.
It has been proven that the number
of percentages of emergency visits
by the patients in these rural
settings have decreased by 28%.
Once the SDOH intervention
has been implemented.
Let's look into how these screening
F framework and how we can
standardize this screening framework.
There are several steps to it.
Effective ING implementation
requires careful consideration of
patient population characteristics,
clinical workflow integration
points and staff capacity.
Organizations have to monitor
screening completion rates and positive
screening follow UPS metrics to
continuously refine their approach.
There are a couple of ways to do it.
One implementing Core Five screening
tool, which is nothing but adopting
standardized questionnaire, addressing
food insecurity, housing instability,
transportation barriers, utility needs,
and interpersonal safety concerns.
Next comes determining how, and
when the screening has to occur.
That is determining the frequency,
establishing protocols for initial
screening and periodic assessment
based on risk stratification
with high risk patients.
Screened quarterly is important.
Next is how do we integrate this
into the clinical workflows?
Embedding screening within EHR
systems at key clinical touch
points, including annual wellness
visits, transition of care, and
chronic disease follow-ups is vital.
The last step comes into training
the clinical staff, providing
comprehensive training on screening,
administration, response interpretation,
and appropriate intervention.
Pathways are needed to identify who is
and how much staff training is required.
Organizations that have implemented
this re, this Restructured Care team
model report significant improvements
in patient engagement, where previously
it was difficult to reach populations.
Currently with this implementation,
they have shown about 75% participation
in recommended interventions.
This integrated approach ensures
that the clinical and social care
coordination is at the maximum.
Let's look into, let's compare
the traditional clinical team
and the enhanced team structure.
The traditional clinical team
consisted of finish physicians.
Nurses, medical assistants, and
all of their focus was on medical
diagnosis and treatment, where
limited capacity was focusing on
social, addressing social needs.
Whereas the enhanced team structure is
an integration of social workers and
community health workers who specialize
in SDOH assessment interventions
and community resource navigations.
The enhanced definition of workflows and
responsibilities give a clear delineation
of roles with structure protocols
for SDOI screening interventions,
referrals, and follow up processes.
One more important aspect is the
ongoing performance evaluation, regular
assessment of team effectiveness
through metrics including intervention,
completion rates, and patient
outcomes and resource utilization has
also proven to be very beneficial.
Let's look at some analytics that are
related to SDOH risk stratification.
Advanced analytics enable healthcare
organizations to move beyond
reactive approaches to proactive
identification of social needs.
There are multi-dimensional
data sources that providers can
prioritize outreach to patients.
Let's look at what are they one pro
productive modeling machine learning
algorithms today provide 89% accuracy
in identifying high risk populations.
Integrating data by combining
clinical claims and community level
data sources is an important factor.
Geospatial analysis, how do we
track consensus, track data,
neighborhood level, SDH, risk mapping.
That is also a vital factor at the end.
Clinical data foundation.
The entire documentation that exists
in EHR and structural assessment is
important for overall analytics and risk
stratification done by SDOH framework.
Proper EHR integration also has shown to
enhance data quality by 45%, which is a
significant improvement from the current
situation that is is aimed in today's.
Where referral accuracy and
care coordination shows sign
significant improvement.
Organizations implementing comprehensive
SDOH data standards report better
clinical decision making and more
effective resource allocation.
Let's look into some of the critical
factors, structured data capture.
How implementation of standard SDH
data, hand data elements like law and
SNOMED and ICD 10 ensures consistent
documentation and interoperability
across systems utilizing fire based
APIs and HSM standards facilitates
secure information sharing between
healthcare systems, community-based
organizations and public health entities.
Outcome tracking, creating dashboards
and reporting mechanisms to monitor
intervention effectiveness, referral
completion, and population level SDH
trends over time has been crucial.
Deploying automated alerts and
intervention pathways triggered by
the positive SDUH screenings with
tailored research recommendations
based on identifying needs as vital.
Studies also show that structured
community partnerships lead to 70% better
outcomes for vulnerable populations
compared to isolated interventions.
Successful healthcare organizations
invest in relationship development
with community-based organizations
to create sustainable support
networks addressing, excuse me,
addressing identified social needs.
Let's look at some of the
variations and factors involving
how community partnership
framework can be well can be done.
Resource mapping is number one,
comprehensive intervention inventory
of community resources with
capacity eligibility criteria and
service details is important of
how the resource mapping is done.
Formal partnership agreements,
structured MOUs, defining roles and
responsibility on how the data sharing
and sharing protocols have to be done.
How the agreements have to be
done is part of this framework,
shared outcome measurement.
But today, where everything is, the
data is not shared with this joint
evaluation frameworks, it helps to assess
partnership effectiveness and impact.
Let's look into what kind of
implementation strategies are IMP
are beneficial in a rural setup.
Number one being telehealth integration,
leveraging virtual care platforms
to extend SDOL, screening and
intervention capacity across geographic
barriers that improves significant
store and forward capabilities for
the nurses and healthcare workers.
The transportation issues
that are currently there.
SDOH implementation brings solutions to
that developing ride share partnerships,
volunteer driver programs, and mobile
health units to address distance barriers,
coordinating appointments, scheduling to
minimize travel burden through clustered
appointments and regional service hubs.
Alternative payment.
Payment models like out adopting
outcome-based reimbursement structures
that recognize SDH intervention
value with rural organizations
reporting 58 persons increase in
successful social interventions
through value-based care arrangements.
Let's look into what kind of technology
infrastructure requirements are
needed to implement this SDOH based
framework and healthcare system.
Number one, being a secure cloud
infrastructure, having a HIPAA t hosting
environments with role-based access
controls and end-to-end encryption
so that there is sensitive SDH
data is encrypted and is important.
For integration, any integration,
metalware requires an API management
platforms, which facilitate secure
data exchanges between EHR systems,
community resource directories,
and referral management tools.
Multi-channel access mobile applications,
and responsive web interfaces, enabling
SDO, screening and interventions across
diverse clinical and community settings.
Offline capabilities for rural areas
with limited connectivity is crucial.
Primacy framework is one more aspect.
Comprehensive consent management
systems addressing various
sharing requirements for SDOH.
Data granular permission structures,
allowing patients to control
information disclosure is vital.
Let's look at the implementation
roadmap and key success factors.
On a very high level, the program design
today takes about one to three months.
This involves assessing organizational
readiness, establishing governance
structure, and defining specific
SDH focus areas based on community
needs and organizational capacities.
The next set of months from
month four to month six, deals
with infrastructure development.
We're implementing in technical
infrastructure, including EHR,
customization, analytics platform,
and developing standard workflows
and staff training programs.
That is where this month
four to six consists of.
Next comes the initial implementations.
From month seven to nine, launching
the pilot program with targeted
pa, targeted patient population,
establishing baseline metrics,
formalizing community partnerships,
and is involved in this phase.
Next comes expansion and optimization
in the following months scale to
full patient population, refining the
processes based on initial outcomes and
implementing advanced analytics that
we just went through for continuous
improvement and also developing
sustainable funding mechanisms.
All of this is a overview of how
an implementation roadmap and what
are the key success factors of
implementing SDH framework looks like.
Successful SDH implementation
hinges on executive leadership
commitment, dedicated resources,
and a culture of continuous crosses.
Quality improvement organizations
should establish clear metrics for
success, including clinical outcomes
by following the structured approach.
I hope I was able to provide you a high
level at yet a detailed overview of
SDOH and how the care delivery models
are ultimately improving health equity
and patient outcomes at the same time,
optimizing resource utilizations.
Thank you.