Let us dive into observability
today and how it helps us
boost operational efficiency.
It is important for us to be operationally
efficient when it comes to maintaining
and scaling distributed systems.
Hi, I'm Harri Patel.
I have around 20 years of experience
in tech industry working for small
startups and large enterprises.
I hold master's degree in software
engineering from Bits Alani.
I have held various tech leadership
roles at high tech places like Yahoo,
Symantec Group on PayPal to name a few.
I have had opportunity to lead teams
of sizes ranging from five people
to 30 plus people, organization,
including engineers, leads and managers.
In my most recent 10 years of experience,
I have had opportunity to design
and develop large scale distributor
systems and big data architectures.
Let us start by going through various
challenges that we face while developing
and maintaining distributed systems.
Distributed systems
are inherently complex.
This complexity stems from the fact
that they provide one system view to
underlying tens or maybe sometimes
hundreds of interconnected services.
Hence, our traditional
monitoring is not adequate.
Distributed systems usually
undergo rapid changes.
With advent of continuous
development and deployment.
Systems are constantly evolving, so
to pinpoint issues it becomes harder.
There are certain scale issues, so when
it comes to reproducing issue, they
only surface at scale, and our current
test systems usually are not equipped to
mimic production scale, which further.
Toughens the problem of
identifying the issues.
Given these challenges, it is
important for us to step back and
understand different ways and means
to achieve observability for such
large scale distributed systems.
So let's take a look at three
pillars of observability that exist.
The first pillar is metrics.
So metrics are essentially
numerical data points.
Collected at regular intervals revealing
system performance patterns and health
enables metrics enable identification
of trends, anomalies, and potential
bottlenecks before they become critical.
Hence, they are key ingredients
in helping us achieve proactivity
instead of reactivity.
The second pillar in observability
are logs, so logs are.
Timestamp records of discrete events
and actions within the system.
They help us by providing rich
contextual information for
debugging forensic analysis and
understanding the sequence of events.
The third pillar of
observability are traces.
So traces are a means to depict end-to-end
journey of a request as they flow through.
Interconnected mesh of services
in distributor systems.
They help in highlighting not only
complex interactions, but also to detect
latency issues and dependencies that
impact overall system performance.
Now that we have gone through key
ingredients that forms the basis
of observable observability, let us
explore vital metrics that really
matter in such distributed systems.
So first popular metric is called system
latency, and it is a measurement of
response time across service boundaries.
So in other words, it is overall
turnaround time taken for a
request from hitting a service to
receiving a final response from it.
We usually track P 95 and P 99 percentiles
to quantify the latency of systems.
And services.
The second metric, which is equally
popular is called error rates, so rate at
which errors occur or are encountered with
respect to successful execution of service
Requests are essentially error rates.
Depending on the business impact
and use cases, we can configure
and watch for different thresholds
of rate at which this error occur.
For instance, mission critical services.
Will have lower thresholds
versus relatively non-critical
services will probably have
higher error rate thresholds.
The third metrics that matter is
resource utilization, so metrics,
collection of resource utilization
is a way of keeping track of various
resources, including compute, memory,
network, IO storage, and so on.
In this case.
The idea is to stay on top of these
utilizations and prevent resource
exhaustion even before they occur.
This one if configured diligently,
can help us stay proactive.
User experiences are
another set of metrics.
They imply measuring interactions
associated with actual user experiences.
It helps us connect backend
performance to front-end experiences.
As you can see, these are some of
the key metrics that we can possibly
integrate and automate for staying on
top of various issues that could occur
in large scale distributed systems.
Now let us take a look at our typical
example of distributed tracing in action.
When it comes to distributed tracing, it
is a sort of a chain or lifecycle from the
time request enters the system and goes
through various hops as it goes through
as part of interconnected subsystem and
services to cater to the end user request.
So it start, as you can see from
the left-hand side, it starts all
the way from front end request.
User interaction initiates a traced
TDP request with unique correlation id.
It then propagates trace context
while routing to downstream.
Microservices at the database query
level spans indicates performance
bottlenecks with 200 millisecond
latency exceeding threshold, and finally
completed trace shows full request path
with timing metrics across services.
It's called response chain.
So now that we have discussed pillars of
observability and key metrics that matter.
Let us understand typical business
impact of observability and what
gains can we possibly realize
by employing such measures in
large scale distributed systems.
So with appropriate observability
in place, we can drastically reduce
time taken to identify and locate the
underlying root cause by at least 60%.
This.
Immediately translates and results
into faster troubleshooting Times
mean time to recovery is a popular
KPI in industry that helps us measure
mean time taken to resolve the issue
through means of observability.
It is seen to be improved by
at least 25% and improved.
MTTR is used to measure
systems overall maturity.
Uptime is another KPI that is widely
used to measure reliability of
highly available user facing system.
And it has been assessed that with due
observability in place we can realize
increase in uptime by at least 30%.
So in summary, with proper attention
to designing and configuring
observability, we can realize
business impact to increase uptime.
Reduce.
MTTR.
And faster root cause analysis.
So on one hand it is about building
observability in the system
through designing and configuring
various metrics and tracking KPIs.
While on the other hand it is about
alerting from the system with when
some or all of these metrics and
thresholds hit at the runtime.
Alerting helps us notify teams.
Systems and stakeholders of detected
anomalies during its operation.
It is systems way of saying something
needs an immediate attention.
As you can see here, it starts
from the bottom of the pyramid.
We usually start by
watching capacity trends.
This capacity could be compute,
storage network, io, and so on.
Through means of thresholds, we keep
track of possible early warning signs,
things that could potentially become
catastrophic through monitoring critical
infrastructure components we treat.
We keep track of overall systems health.
All of these result into configuring
alerts that impact business
metrics, issues that affect
end customers of the service.
After going through all these concept
concepts, you might wonder how do
we go about it and how do we set
ourselves up for success when actually
implementing these observability
measures throughout the system?
So observability implementation roadmap
typically looks something like this.
It starts with defining key metrics.
That identify critical signals
that indicate system health through
keeping focus on business outcomes.
The second aspect is instrumenting code.
Instrumenting code is about adding
metrics, logging, tracing to the
application code through means of using
standard conventions and coding practices.
Once the metrics are collected, once
the metrics are tracked, they're
collected at a centralized place.
So designing solutions to harvest
these metrics into common, configurable
and scalable storage solutions enable
co. It enables correlation across
interconnected services because
they're stored at commonplace.
The last aspect of it is
visualizing and alerting.
So we create dashboards and alerting
rules and carefully ensure to continuously
eliminate noise and false positives
so that it's a high quality alerting.
Display mechanism.
Now let's see.
What are common pitfalls to avoid
while implementing these observ
observability measures in the system?
Alert fatigue.
It is very common to fall trap to too
many alerts resulting into your team
ignoring the critical ones amidst
unmanageable stream of alerts instead.
We should focus on high quality,
actionable alerts that are meaningful
and helps everyone with meaningful
message and corrective actions to be
taken to resolve the issue at hand.
Cost overs, collecting everything and
storing it can turn out to be expensive,
both on the dis storage as well as
the code that further slows down as
it is running metrics computation
logic besides actual business logic.
Idea here is to sample high
volume telemetry and stay at just
enough threshold of collecting
metrics and computing KPIs too.
Overload.
Using too many disparate systems can be
challenging for the teams to adapt, so
try to consolidate wherever possible.
Streamlining and standardizing
tool is an ongoing process.
With system becoming more mature.
Teams tend to gravitate.
To fewer number of tools leading
to system-wide standardization
processes, vanity metrics.
It is easy to fall into the false
notion of everything is important.
Instead of tracking everything,
focus on metrics that tie to business
outcomes, metrics that matter from
enhancing business impact perspective.
Now, as we come close to
the closing this session.
Let us go through key takeaways
that we have learned and
understood as part of this session.
Observability is essential
and not optional for any large
scale distributed systems.
When it comes to wholesome observability.
Integrate all the three pillars,
that is metrics, logs, and tracing.
Measure business impact, connect
technical metrics to business outcomes.
The ones that enhances meaningful business
impact build observability culture.
This one is the most important one.
We have to train our teams to develop
appreciation and I to leverage
these observability metrics that
will help them connect the dots.
I hope this session was.
Helpful to all of you to understand
and acknowledge the importance of
designing and developing various
observability measures to further
enhance operational efficiency in
large scale distributed systems.
Thank you for your time today.