Hey everyone, this is Asaf Mabu, and
today we are diving into how we can
revolutionize legacy systems with
the power of t net and microservices,
thereby transforming your rigid,
monolithic architectures into an
agile and more scalable ecosystem.
Now, legacy systems, although
reliable, they bring with them a
lot of complexity and are often
inflexible with the capabilities
of a modern framework like T net.
We can redesign these systems without
needing a complete rebuild from scratch.
By using microservices, we break down
these legacy systems, also sometimes
known as monoliths into smaller,
more independent and more manageable
chunks that allow for scalability
and adaptability, depending upon
the changing needs of your business.
Now, using microservices not only enhances
your applications, agility, which is
the speed with which your code can adapt
to your changing business needs, but
it also provides a certain degree of,
future proofing into your applications.
you get faster deployments, you get
quicker turnarounds, you get better fault
isolation, and essentially more efficient
use of resources with this approach.
So in the next few minutes, we'll
explore how dotnet and microservices
work together and, transform legacy
systems and, why this transformation
is essential for your organization.
So let's get started.
in my experience, legacy systems present
major challenges for organizations.
They act as roadblocks to innovation.
They slow down growth and they
prevent development of new features.
Now, over time, the cost of maintaining
these outdated systems also rises,
and the specialized expertise that
you need to support them becomes
harder and more expensive to find.
Now, beyond operational concerns,
legacy systems also pose serious
security risks since they lack
all of these modern protections.
So that leaves the organization vulnerable
to compliance issues and cyber threats.
So if we want to remain competitive, we
must, address these challenges head on.
Modernizing our technology is not
just an IT initiative anymore,
it's actually a business necessity.
So let's take a small example
to illustrate the challenges and
issues with legacy systems and
this monolithic architecture.
Right now.
Let's consider this video
that I'm currently recording.
Let's say I recorded this entire
session in a single continuous,
recording, and then I need to apply
some effects between each slide.
So I write a script that will apply
certain effects at certain timings
In this video and on post review,
I decide that slide number X and
slide number Y need to be updated
and I need to record them again.
So since this is a continuous
session, I would either have to redo
my entire session, or I would have
to use certain complicated tools to
replace these parts of these videos.
So then I would have to write, rewrite the
timings on my script, and all subsequent
timings would also need to be adjusted.
It.
So you see how a small change easily
snowballs into this massive effort.
On the other hand, if I were to record
this session as one video per slide
and later just merge all the videos,
making edits to individual sessions
would just be as easy as rerecording
that particular slide video and
then merging them all over again.
My script would not have to be
reworked because, each script
would be built to be run at.
the end of a particular slide and the
timing on the slides would have no
effect, as to when the script ran.
Now, of course, this is a very simplistic
way of, looking at this whole thing,
but I hope this gives you an idea of,
how monolithic systems differ from
these, microservices based architecture.
like I said, modernizing your
system is no longer optional.
It's actually a strategic necessity.
The key drivers are clear,
better user experience, reduced
costs, enhanced security.
And improve scalability.
Now, intuitive and user-friendly
interfaces are essential to provide a good
user experience and improve productivity.
At the same time, modernization reduces
maintenance and operational expenses.
it delivers significant cost savings.
And with the ever-growing cyber threats,
modern security measures are all the
more important to protective, your
sensitive data and ensuring compliance.
as your, organization grows, your
scalable systems will allow you to
expand without, compromising performance.
And by embracing modernization,
organizations position
themselves for long-term success.
They offer better user experiences.
They lower costs, they
strengthen security, and they
prepare for future growth.
Now, the Dotnet platform has undergone
significant evolution over the years.
It began with the Dotnet framework, which
was a Windows only platform that offered.
rich Libraries and Services.
this was then followed by T Net
Core, which was an open source
cross platform version, which was
designed for better performance.
And then starting with T Net five.
And as of today, I think it's dotnet
nine, the latest version of T net.
Microsoft Unified these two worlds.
So T net now combines the robustness
of dotnet framework and also the
flexibility and speed of dotnet, code.
So this timeline visually
highlights the key milestones in
the journey of, the doted platform.
So here are some benefits that
we saw at our organization by
moving to this new architecture.
we now have a 24 7 development cycle with,
continuous operations across three shift.
So this ensures that our software is
constantly evolving and improving.
Modernizing our DO net
infrastructure has also accelerated
our development speed by 67%.
this allows us to, deliver
new features faster than ever.
Also, by optimizing our computing
resources, we have increased efficiency
by 40%, and this enables us to achieve
more while, using fewer resources.
So what are microservices?
Microservices are essentially small,
independent services that collaborate
to deliver specific business functions.
Each microservice performs one
and only one business function.
Now, unlike monolithic architectures,
microservices are decoupled, this
means that microservices can be
independently developed and deployed.
The key characteristics of microservices
include being loosely coupled,
business focused, independently
deployable, and resilient.
Now, this slide offers a high level
introduction to the microservices
architectural style, and this is the
foundation for the rest of the session.
Now, why should we use microservices?
microservices architecture allows us to
scale individual components independently.
It supports up to 40% annual growth
in system capacity, and, this
design enhances fault isolation.
what is fault isolation?
if one service fails, the rest of
your system remains unaffected.
So greater reliability.
It also gives us the flexibility
to choose the best tools and
technology for each service.
This avoids the limitation of,
this one size fits all approach.
So if I want to develop a microservice and
t net because, it gives good performance
in database suites and, develop this other
one in, Python because it has this one
library that performs this particular math
function very efficiently and quickly.
I can, most importantly, the modular
structure allows us to deliver new
features and fixes faster, which in
turn means faster time to market huge
advantage in a competitive landscape.
Microservices architecture allows, teams
to deploy new features independently
without updating the entire system.
it reduces the overhead of coordinating
with multiple teams in order to release
a new feature or bug fix, and eventually
it accelerates development, deployment,
and most importantly, innovation.
It also supports a fail
fast, learn quickly mindset.
This allows teams to experiment with new
ideas and test them with minimal risk.
more.
Our microservices align seamlessly
with modern DevOps practices.
So think automation and
continuous delivery.
This boosts agility and helps teams
deliver value faster and more efficiently.
So how do we go about modernizing
our, legacy applications?
there are four primary approaches
and each of these have varying
complexity and, impact.
The first is rehosting, also
known as lift and shift.
This simply moves your application to
more, modern, infrastructure and does
not alter your code in any shape or form.
The next one is refactoring.
Now this improves the internal code,
quality and structure, but keeps the
applications, external behavior the same.
then we have re-architecting.
Now this involves more significant
structural changes to your
code, which then unlocks newer
capabilities for your application.
and the final one that we have is
rebuilding, which involves fully
recreating the application with,
modern technologies and approaches.
Now, of course, each of these method
offers distinct benefits for your
organization, and it all depends
on your goals and your, resources.
To kick off our modernization
journey, the first step is a thorough
analysis of your current system.
We'll begin by identifying
key stakeholders.
This includes business users, IT
teams, and other critical players.
this will help us understand the
business context and the user
needs, which will then allow us to
capture the essential requirements.
Next, we'll create detailed system,
architecture diagrams, document all
components and the dependencies.
And, this will allow us to gain a complete
picture of the current environment.
Finally, we'll assess the
system's technical debt, which is
evaluating the code quality and
identifying performance bottlenecks.
and anything that requires our attention.
A deep understanding of the current state
is absolutely essential before we can move
forward with our modernization strategy.
So as we embark on this modernization
journey, it's essential that
we define clear business
objectives and success metrics.
we need to find the right strategy
for each system component.
Now whether that's re-platforming,
refactoring, re-architecting, it
all depends on the specific needs
and goals of your organization.
detailed roadmap should then be developed.
we need to outline the transition
steps and the timeline.
Finally, we need to secure full
stakeholder alignment and ensure we have
the necessary resources and support as
that is critical to executing this plan.
Successfully.
as monolithic applications
grow in complexity, they can
become difficult to maintain.
So breaking them down into
smaller focused microservices,
can help solve this problem.
The first step in this process is
identifying your bounded context,
so essentially mapping business
domains to, distinct context
and defining clear boundaries.
This ensures that each of your
service will have a well-defined
scope and responsibility.
Next, we define the service boundaries,
which is designing each service
around a specific business capability.
The aim is to keep the
services focused and cohesive.
this avoids complexities that can,
arise from trying to cover too many
areas in, one or many services.
effective communication between
these services is also key, so
APIs and messaging patterns are
used to define integration points
and data flows between services.
thus ensuring smooth interactions.
Finally, we create service templates
to standardize development processes,
enabling, consistent implementation across
teams working on different microservices.
Now, this approach helps us,
achieve better scalability, better
maintainability, and, of course agility
in your application development process.
By migrating to scalable cloud
databases, we can utilize managed
services to dynamically expand
our data infrastructure as needed.
by implementing repositories, ORs,
and data abstraction layers, we
will be able to simplify our data
access and, improve usability.
Maintaining data integrity across services
and employing eventual consistency
strategies, is crucial for ensuring that,
we have consistency in our distributed.
Systems.
Lastly, enforcing encryption, strict
access controls and, robust data
protection measures will, greatly
strengthen the security of our data layer.
Now, implementing A-C-I-C-D
pipeline is a key step in
automating your software delivery.
This ensures a consistent, reliable,
and scalable deployment process.
So the key components include
automated bills that, compile your
code and then run your unit test.
containerization to package your
application and its dependencies.
an orchestration platform like Kubernetes
to manage and scale your containers.
And then a deployment automation
with, release gates and monitoring.
Now these, elements enable
fast and confident delivery of
your new features and updates.
The diagrams on this slide showcase
the technical components and
flow of a modern CICD pipeline.
this is all crucial for,
cloud native development.
The S-O-L-I-D principles are
five key design guidelines
and, they promote maintainable,
extensible, and testable software.
two important design patterns
for, data access are repository
and unit of work, patterns.
These help organize and
manage your application data.
also you have the factory method and
dependency injection patterns, which
enhance flexibility and testability.
when you're optimizing for the
cloud, it's important to focus
on autoscaling load balancing
caching and resource optimization.
this ensures both performance
and cost efficiency.
Incorporating these principles and
patterns into your refactoring process
will lead to improved code quality,
improved scalability and maintainability.
Modernizing legacy systems comes
with a significant challenge.
First, there's a skill gap because
teams need new training, on the
new tools and practices, which
can then affect productivity as
they climb that learning curve.
second resource allocation.
it's important to balance resources
across services to prevent, performance
issues during this transition.
Finally, managing distributed
complexity is a major hurdle as,
troubleshooting across various
services can become difficult when, the
components interact with each other.
To successfully navigate these
challenges, a strategic and
thoughtful approach is necessary,
when you're looking at modernization.
This case study showcases the, successful
modernization of a core banking platform,
at a leading, financial institution.
And, it delivers some remarkable results.
there was a 50%, reduction in operational
costs, 30% improvement in response time,
a 75%, faster deployment time, basically
reduced from a hundred to 25 hours.
there was a 40% increase
in developer productivity.
So basically these outcomes highlight,
the significant business benefits that
your organization can, gain as part
of a well executed, modernization.
As someone who's gone through this
exercise myself recently, I'd say
begin with small pilot projects to
demonstrate the value of modernization.
Before you go full throttle on
scaling up, focus on training.
Focus on upscaling your, team,
to, make sure that they have the
skills and the resources that are,
needed for this ongoing learning.
make sure you prioritize your
security, embed it at every stage of
the process and ensure that you have
compliance throughout this process.
Lastly, implement strong observability
and monitoring to continuously define
and optimize the transformation based on,
data that you collect from your world.
Now let's look at some of the future
trends in dotnet and microservices.
there's serverless architecture,
particularly, function as a service.
this is becoming a new standard due to
the cost effective pay execution model.
We have machine learning, which is now
being integrated as, into services,
powering intelligent applications
with predictive capabilities.
there's edge computing, which is bringing,
processing closer to data sources.
thus, minimizing your latency
for your time operations.
also web assembly, which is delivering
neo native performance and, browser
unlocking, your, new distribution
possibilities for, applications.
Lastly, digital transformation is not
just a one-time event, but an ongoing
journey of continuous improvement.
by, embracing modernization, organizations
can stay ahead of the competition
and seize, new market, opportunities.
It's essential to build adaptable
foundations so that even with,
emerging technologies and newer
future trends, you will be poised
perfectly to evolve with them.
Staying agile and committed to constant
improvement will make sure that with
rapid, changing business environment, your
organization is in a position of success.
and with this, I conclude my talk on
transforming legacy systems with.net
and microservices to build a more
scalable and agile application.
I hope you enjoyed this talk and
we'll consider some of these talking
points, when embarking on your own
journey at your own organization.
Hope you have a wonderful
rest of the conference.
Bye.