Good afternoon or good morning everyone.
I'm Google B Nation, and I'm thrilled
to be here at Con 42 to talk about
something close to all our hearts
enterprise integrations today.
The talk is titled Beyond Rest
Exploding Modern A PA, paradigms
for Enhanced Enterprise Integration.
As integration architects and
developers, we know that traditional
rest model has served us well, but
the digital ecosystem is changing fast
and it's time to explore what's next.
Let's start with the bigger picture.
Over the few last few years, we have seen
the shift in how enterprise approach.
A PA design and rest is
no longer the default.
Organizations are exploring graph
ql, event driven models, a PA
misses, serverless, APAs, and
even hypermedia driven designs.
Why?
Because our integration challenges
are getting more complex and rest
isn't always the most efficient
way to solve the problem.
Why?
Why move beyond the risk?
So what are the pain points?
Such slow development with risk
complex data often means multiple
endpoints, multiple calls, and
a lot of developer frustrations.
Then there's a data overhead risk.
A PA tend to over deliver data leading
to inefficiencies, especially for
mobile or bandwidth sensitive clients.
We also run into breaking changes
as systems scale versioning.
Rest points become a nightmare,
and of course, scaling risk wasn't
designed for a high throughput.
Event, high end heavy enrollment,
and that shows under peak loads.
So graph ql, data efficiency breakthrough.
Let's talk about the graph ql.
It's a major leap forward
in how we query the data.
Rather than juggling multiple endpoint
or getting too much or too little
data, GraphQL gives the client control.
A single query returns
exactly what's needed.
Nothing more or nothing less.
And the impact is some companies have
seen 60 to 70 percentage reduction
in the data transfer volume and
significantly faster development cycles.
It's not just about speed, it's about
developer experience and maintainability.
So next, let's start with
event driven architecture.
Now onto the real time needs.
Enter the event driven architectures.
Instead of pulling or relying on a
synchronous call, services publish events
when state change occur, these events are
streamed and consumed as synchronously.
Allowing systems to
react in near real time.
This is also a loose coupling, which
helps to build a build system more
scalable and resilient, especially
in microservice landscapes.
So a PA based, so one big challenge
in the modern architecture is EXPLO
explosion of point to point integration.
That's where a PA mesh comes in.
It offers a unified gateway that can
route, compose, secure, and cast records
across the multiple microservices.
Instead of having a individual team
built ad hoc integrations, the mes
abstract and simplifies architecture.
Think of it as an orchestrator and a er.
So next, the serverless
APIs scale on demand.
Now let's talk on scale.
So imagine the infrastructure that
scales exactly what as you need
it and disappears when you don't.
So that's the promise of serverless a
p. They bring up to 78 percentage cost
reduction with cold stats averaging
over just three seconds and warm
responses as fast as two 50 milliseconds.
It's the ultimate pay as you
go model for your compute.
a enhanced APIs.
So we are also seeing a big leap
forward with a enhanced APIs.
So these APIs use special learning
or intent recognition, anomaly
detection, and even predictive caching.
So the systems start serving.
Serving when user will need,
not just what you ask for.
It's smarter, more active, and even it's.
It's the direction many enterprise
platforms are heading towards.
So hypermedia APIs are self-documenting
systems, so unless finally it's
not a overlooked hypermedia api.
These might seem old school, but
the idea about idea of APAs that are
self-documenting and guide the client
through resource discovery is powerful.
The, they reduce breaking changes
by 65 percentage occurring to
some studies and make client site
development much more intuitive.
Now let's zoom out.
choosing the right a PA
paradigm isn't just a technical
discussion, it's a strategic.
You need to know, you need to look at your
business goals, data patterns, consumer
expectations, and scalability needs.
Know one size fits everything, but the
best architecture often blends multiple
paradigms to match the specific use cases.
So let's discuss the key takeaways here.
So if you remember nothing else
from this session, let it be this.
No single solution fits all.
Blend strategies, apps
needed, evaluate, trade off.
Every model has a pros and cons.
Start smile, find a pain
Point, implement and learn.
Impact.
Always try your architecture to outcomes.
Thanks so much for joining me.
I hope I gave you a first lens to look
into integration, not just as a technical
hurdle, but as a powerful, driver
for business agility and innovation.
I am happy to take your questions,
to shoot me, if you have any
questions, and thank you for giving
the opportunity to present this.
Thank you so much.