Speaker 24: Hi, this is Berman Mann and
we are here to present about Cruise Cube.
It's a new tool that it's a new
open source tool that we have come
up with for PO level optimization
PO level resource optimization.
And the things that it is good at is it
performs, it does just in time resource
optimization along with inplace Port.
So we'll go into a little bit
depth about what the tool is and
how it actually does what it does.
So starting with introduction, so I'm hum.
I work at True Foundry.
I have a BTech from it ti in total
I've worked for around nine years
and I'm a core contributor at Q,
which is a CNC of Sandbox Project.
Speaker 25: Thanks.
Hi, this is Ram.
I'm creator of BX Explain on
dev tool for coding agents.
I'm also a cloud native consultant at J
Lab, about five years of experience in
distributor computing and enjoy these,
Speaker 24: thanks Jim.
The question basically starts with why
do Kubernetes clusters stay expensive,
even though people understand that
lower request means lower cost?
So the problem starts with the
fear of CPU throttling and m kills.
So if you are over under provision
a particular node with respect to
memory, you're going to get mki, which
is going to actually bring down your
pod and does your complete workload.
This will lead to a business downtime.
So people really fear it and they tend to
over provision at for CPU and for memory.
The other part of the problem is
people don't want to think, the
developers don't want to think about
how to rightsize the workloads a lot.
And even if you a, actually do an
analysis the process of editing YAML
files to actually keep things optimized
again and again is quite tedious and
no one would want to really do it.
What the the reason that this
becomes even more important is
because over provisioning, and
at the request side also leads to
over provisioning at the node side.
So we are end up with underutilized
nodes and this basically forces
cluster auto scalers into
inefficient and costly decisions.
So first thing that we that
anyone comes up with why can't
we solve this at the node level?
So basically create more nodes as the as
the requirement increases, and re remove
nodes as the requirement decreases.
The problem is that if you are
actually over provisioning at the
request level this gives this leads
to over provisioning at the node
level, at an even higher level.
So the problem has to be solved
at the request level before you
can actually save any cost at all.
Moving on.
There is another tool which
belongs to Kubernetes.
It's called VPA and it
does something similar.
But the difference between VPA
and Cruise Cube is in terms of the
optimization model and what view
of the cluster we actually take.
So the optimization model, the way that
VPA tries to solve this problem is through
periodic analysis and recommendation.
What this means is you have these
analysis running for a particular
workload, and that has to come up
with a recommendation, which has to be
true for a significant amount of time.
Ky, on the other hand, tries to
come up with recommendations, which
have to be true for a very limited
point, limited time in the future.
So it is a continuous feedback
driven control loop which actually
looks at real time PO usage, and
comes up with recommendations.
The level at which cruise Cube makes
a decision is at the individual
pod in, in its own node context,
will go much deeper into why the
node context is important here.
While Kubernetes VPA takes a decision
at the workload level and those
workload ports could be distributed
across different nodes in different
with different requirements.
Again, like it has a node local view.
While VPA is at the VPA does not
take the node node level view at all.
And as I said, the time horizon
for cruise is very small against
VPA, which is a little bit longer.
Moving on.
The question then becomes why is it
that what is it that has changed in
the industry, which actually brings
us to this point where we can perform
closed loop right sizing with very
close to real time optimizations.
So in Kubernetes version one point 35,
which is the latest version, and came
out quite recently, in place POD resource
update has become generally available.
It has become ga and what that means
is you can update the resources for us
for a particular pod without a restart.
This minimizes disruption and this also
means that you don't have to change
things at workload level, but you
can make decisions at the pod level
and the node that it's running on.
The other thing is
pressure stall information.
Basically, PSI metrics is
something that has become beta
with Kubernetes v version 1 34.
This means that you get contention
information per container
on every node separately.
So even if like you don't specify
CPU limits, you get the contention
information at the node level, which
you can use to actually rightsize
the workload and actually correct
the CPU request that you have set.
So you have two.
So we basically use two signals,
the CPU usage and the C-P-U-P-S-I
metrics to figure out what is the
final CPU request that the portal
or workload should have Moving on.
As I mentioned earlier, a lot of
decisions are taken at the node level
and the reason that the node level
context becomes important is because
we have a lot of pods running on a
particular node and the different pods
have different headroom requirement.
So what headroom is basically
the difference between its burst
capacity and its base capacity
and its base requirement.
So burst is so bursts all the CPO
workloads tend to burst a lot like we
have seen figures of up to 10,000 times.
And these happen, these tend to happen
very infrequently in most cases.
So your difference between a
75th percentile and a nine and a
hundred percentile would be a lot.
So what we can do is we can share this
re this headroom space for multiple
pods running on the same node.
So we take the maximum of all the pods
running on a particular node and as, and
reserve that resource, reserve that space
on that node so that it can be used for
different pods to as they require it.
Moving on.
To explain how Cruise Cube works and
the different components that are in
there I'm handing over to Raman, so
he'll tell us about the components and
details of Nitty integrities of how
Cruise Cube has actually been built.
Speaker 25: Hey, thank you.
Sh so as Shung mentioned that we follow a
loop strategy where, and continuous loop.
So we have multiple stages in
this lifecycle where we start with
the first observing your cluster,
basically collecting all these stats.
And historical metrics
around all the workloads.
We store them in the, in a database.
And based on the data which has been
collected, we learn from that pattern.
Basically if at a particular time
in last seven days there was a
peak at certain point we can learn
from it and the recommendation
can be generated based on that.
And the third step we have another loop
which goes and create these recommendation
for all the workloads and safely we start
to apply these changes in your cluster.
And this is a continuous process
as she mentioned the start,
that we are very frequent and
we look very less in the future.
So we are short term, we look
short term in the future.
And when applying this.
There are two phases of optimization.
The two places where basically
we apply this optimization.
The first is at the time of admission
when whenever a new pod is provisioned
somewhere, we have a admission web book,
which goes and look at the historical
data around that workload or port.
And based on that it gets the
recommendation for it and it
applies on recommendation.
So in case if a particular port
got restarted because of O kill
we will know that, okay, there was
a reason Om kill was the reason.
So next time it gets
provision, we will immediately.
Apply the recommendations to it.
The second phase is the continuous
time optimizer, which goes in
a crone way and goes and apply
recommendation across all the workloads.
And as Elia mentioned, that
these are recommendations are
not aware and they're in place.
So there are no restarts which are
done unless some eviction is required
in a certain part to make sure that
it can be provisioned to a higher.
Not with the higher resources.
These are the components which
makes all of this happen.
Starting with the source of all the
metrics and stats is Prometheus and.
Controller is in the center of
it, orchestrating everything.
It goes and collects stats and then
it basically transform those stats and
store them in database for later use.
This is done by the statistics engine,
which is creates stats for all the
workloads continuously as the new
spikes or new data keeps coming in.
We have the runtime optimizer,
which goes in, read those stats
and generate recommendation on top
of it and continuously apply them.
Keep optimizing your cluster mutation.
WebBook is the second place of the
runtime optimizer where the changes
happened, where we get a signal from
the QAPI server whenever a new pod
is provisioned and we again go and
understand the previous data on, on,
on it and apply recommendation for it.
All of this can be accessed by a
dashboard we expose as a front end.
And yeah.
Now the question you might have
is that we are making changes to
a cluster and sometime if you have
something very critical for it.
So we have guardrails for that.
By default, everything, every workload,
which for which the stats are created,
the recommendation are generated.
Those recommendations are not applied
till the time you explicitly enable.
Accrued mode than them, which
is the signal for it to apply.
Otherwise, everything is
just recommend only mode.
The second is the criticality slash
priority of eviction, where we
understand that which workloads are
have higher priority, and if they
are higher or basically they're more
critical, then they're not evicted.
If they're less critical,
let's say if a workload has.
50 pods.
We might have less priority for it
if it has just one pod, it might
have a medium priority, but if,
and you can also always edit it.
In the dashboard as mentioned earlier,
we also have a feedback loop for the All
Om Kills and we look at the node pressure
and the memory pattern from the past which
led to the last basically highest reported
memory for it, which led to the Om kill.
And accordingly, we go and Cruise Cube
go and apply those recommendations.
Coming to the dashboard, like
you have a lot of features there,
including the feature to enable
cruise mode or recommend mode.
On different workloads, you can do a
brief overview of, look at the brief
overview of resources across your cluster.
What are the allocatable requested,
the original requested and so on.
You also get to see I a little
timeline on these resources.
Second.
The third thing is saving tracking.
So the whole reason of this project is to
help you save cut costs on the cluster.
So we have a way of tracking that as well,
that how much you're currently saving
and how much can you save on top of it.
We'll see more of it on in the demo.
Then you have a policy
management, basically you can.
Again, set priorities on top of things,
enable cruise mode or disable it.
And even there's a feature on disruption
window where if you're using carpenter
and you have some workloads which
have DND and they're blocking the,
auto-scaling of your nodes, shrinking
decreasing the node counts in that
case, you can have a disruption window.
And those kind of features are also there.
You look at the demo now.
Once you have installed Cruise
Cube on your system, you get to
access the dashboard shift with it.
There you see the monthly cost.
Your cluster is incurring every month.
The current saving you have by installing
Cruise Cube on your cluster, basically
the already optimizations, which has
been applied, and then you get to
see the untapped saving, which is.
How much more can you save from that
cluster if you enable it for all the
workloads you get to see the number
of notes you have and the cumulative
resources you're requesting that
you have Allocatable allocatable for
CPN Memory, the current requested.
From all the workloads, what those
workloads had originally requested,
and the recommended requested,
which Cruise Cube has suggested.
Same for memory.
You also get to see historical timeline
from 30 days till as minimum as six hours.
That how these requested or these
resources have changed over time.
You get to see the cost saving or
the impact you have by enabling it,
the impact of running your cluster
without Cruise Cube and running
your cluster with Cruise Cube.
Let's go a little deeper
into workloads and workloads.
You get to see all the workloads
you have apparently on that cluster.
You can filter it by different
types and for each workload you have
recommendations generated here where
you can see for the current CPU, this
is the recommended value and this is
how much you save, which has been.
Also mentioned in possible probable
money, you will save off it.
But since it is in recommend only mode,
right now no recommendations are applied.
So it'll still be requesting PPU,
but the moment I enable it, now
it's been successfully enabled.
Now Cruise Cube will start applying
these changes into your cluster by.
During your requested based on data, you
can see all the changes which has happened
in your cluster by going to events.
You can look at all the events, or
you can look at individual events by
just selecting a particular workload.
With workload id is it have?
Then you can see all the changes
that have applied to that particular
work, and you can also look at
the changes that has been applied.
As you can see, this is memory recommended
and it decrease the memory requested.
And once you apply, enable cruise queue
for all your workloads you can see
that right now it's saving about 60%.
So that's how you can access the dashboard
and that's how you can use Blue Cube.
There are other features like.
Disruption window where if you are
using carpenter and you want carpenter
to make changes to a cluster, but
if there is some blocking, do not
disturb a rotation on some workload.
Where is blocking the
consolidation from the carpenter?
You can add a window for the disruption
in that window, we will assume that
it's safe to disrupt that particular
workload and make changes to it.
That's how overview of
Cruise Cube looks like.
Feel free to install it on your
cluster in just recommendation board
and just see how much you can save.
Thank you.
Yes.
So that was the demo.
Thank you.
We can jump to the last part of it.
The best case is where to use
it and when not to use it.
So right now we suggest that you use
with workloads, which are stateless and
not necessarily holding data in them be
recommended for the dev and staging mode.
I think it's perfect for it.
And idle for shortlived jobs or
shortlived services, which you have.
You can still enable it or you can still
use cruise queue with recommendation
mode in these use, use cases as well.
But we suggest that you, we take some
precautions when applying or when
enabling cruise mode in such cases.
For example, if a particular
service is latency sensitive and
if you start to go and make some
changes, it might affect that.
So that's not recommended right now.
But you can still generate recommendation
on top of it, and you can then manually
go and tune it once in a while.
Then that's also possible.
Straight, full apps again if you have some
database or some c or from some queue,
which you are, you have in your cluster.
And we suggest you just use
it in the recommendation mode.
Places where you have HP enabled.
Right now, we are still working
on making SKU work with HP enabled
workloads, but that's yet to be released.
But yeah, right now we just suggest
that you yeah, there's not the
right use case for it, but I think
for every use case you can still
use it in the recommendation mode.
That is great.
That is the end of this.
Talk and you can reach out to us on
Discord or after this call, after
this talk, and please do start the
report and do look at the code.
Everything we have talked about
so far is open source as an
effort to get more people to,
start checking it out and saving.
Yeah, then thank you so much.