Hi everyone.
Today I'm excited to share with you the
story of our transitions from transitional
cloud services to the serverless
architectures and a journey that not
only simplified our operational, but also
delivered real and miserable benefits.
Our ship to serverless was not just
about keeping up with the technology
trends, it was driven by the need of.
Tackle complexity, reduce cost, and
acceler accelerate our development
process along the way we experience
significant cost saving and a
drastic reduction in incident and a
boost in our deployment frequency.
Also in the next few slides.
I will talk you through the key
challenges we faced and how we implemented
serverless ens, and the impact it had
on on our cost and incident management
and overall developer productivity.
Let's dive in.
Let's move to the second slide.
Okay.
So in this slide our initial
infrastructure challenges, that is what
I am just going to discuss all about.
So at the outset, we are facing
mounting challenges with our
like traditional infrastructures.
So as our business grow did
our infrastructure expenses,
unfortunately, this cost were growing.
Then our actual business needs.
So underutilized servers were
draining resources and leading to the
inefficiency and unnecessary expenses.
So our team were spending an over
William amount of time managing
the servers and infrastructures.
Those type of things and these constant
operational took focus away from what
truly mattered and core innovations and
building new features for our users.
Now our traditional architectures
was simply not built to
handle sudden traffic spikes.
So these limitations caused the
significant issues including the
customer facing failures which
impacted user experience and trust.
So these challenges made it
clear that we need the change.
Okay, now let's move to
the second third slide.
So here I'll be discussing like
why we choose the serverless.
So there are a couple of
reasons like we choose.
Serverless has a strategic
force multipliers.
Not because it's a one size fits all
solution, but because it gives us a
distinct advantage in terms of speeds,
cost, efficiency, and scalability.
By adopting serverless, how our
engineers and can focus on building
features and solving a business problem.
Instead of spending time on managing
and maintenance infrastructures,
serverless architectures automatically
scales to meet the traffic demands,
ensuring the optimal resource
utilizations without manual intervention.
Now paper use models
in these sections like.
Where like with the serverless, we only
only pay the actual compute resource use.
So that is the most important thing,
which provides the cost efficiency and
reduce the need of over provisioning.
And these combinations of agility
and the cost effectiveness and
the scalability made serverless
the right choice for our needs.
Yeah.
Here I'll be discussing about the,
what the technical approaches we took.
And because the initial project
I actually took like a we had
decided to go with the AWS services.
So to address our challenges,
we turned to the AWS Suite of
Power Pool serverless services.
So services like AWS Lambda the Core
Compute Service for running our business
logic in a serverless environment, Lambda
allows us to execute the code without
managing the servers, automatically
scaling based on the demands.
And another one, like the Dynamo db
that is another service we choose.
It is a fully managed NoSQL database
with auto scaling capabilities.
DynamoDB adjust to traffic changes
in real time, ensuring that high
availability and the performance
and seamless data management also.
And and another thing is like a API
gateway, which is a fully managed
service for creating and managing and.
Securing the API endpoints at scale
API gateway simplifies API deployment,
allowing us to connect our frontend
and backend services effortlessly.
Another one like the S3 S3 is another
major component, like when we are
driving through any development cycle
or any applications to store the data.
So highly durable pro objects storage
for the static assets and the data.
AWS S3 provides reliability.
Reliability and the cost effective
storage for everything from image
to backup, ensuring the seamless
data retrieval and the scalability.
Another important thing
is the CloudWatch logs.
So a monitoring and logging service
that helps us to track and analyze
the log data in a real time.
CloudWatch provides insights into the
system performance and operational health,
enabling us to detect the issues early.
And optimize optimize our infrastructure.
So it is a really very important component
to choose like for the logging purpose.
Another one like the though it is not
mentioned here, but there are a couple of
other component like the Secret Manager,
which is a service to secure store
manage sensitive informations like the
API keys currencies and other secrets.
Secret Manager help us, helps us to
ensure the sensitivity data in securely
handle without the risk of exposure.
And the for izing
containerizing the applications.
We use the Docker to ensure the
consistency across the environments and
Kubernetes, specifically the Amazon elect
elastic Kubernetes service, like it is
called, like EKS, allows us to scale
and manage microservices efficiently.
Together, these services enable us
to build flexibility and reliable
service serverless architectures.
With these services in place, we were
able to achieve the scalability and
the efficiency of what we needed.
Let's move to the next one.
And here I'll be discussing regarding
overcoming initial resistance.
Like a, like any major change we face
some resistance along, along the way.
So many engineers initially doubted
that the real world benefits
and the serverless architecture.
So there were the concern about
the performance, scalability,
and the potential risk of.
From that additional infrastructure
to address this concern, we
conducted a couple of works of proof
of concepts like a POC projects.
And these hands-on demonstration actually
helped the team to see the practical value
of serverless and providing the clarity
and how it could solve our challenges.
Now we identified the supported and
early adapters within the teams who
embraced our list and the server, and
focused successful implementations.
Their positive experience helped building
confidence across the organizations.
And then finally, we use the metrics
to validate the business impact of
the serverless transitions and data
on cost saving, incident reduction,
and improved deployment frequency,
provided concrete evidence of benefits.
So over the time this helps shift
the mindset across the team and
build strong support for our journey.
Let's move to the next.
Our implementation strategy was
a step by step process to ensure
a smooth transition actually.
So the first step was to break
down our monolithic applications
into the smaller applications.
Functions side pieces.
By identifying key components,
we were able to transition a more
modular and scalable architecture.
So that is the first point we took it.
And then the pilot project, like
we began by launching the pilot
project with non-critical workloads.
And this allowed us to experiment
and refine our serverless approach
without risking core operations
while also gaining valuable
insight for larger implementations.
Our next step was to refactor existing
applications to make them stateless,
ensure they are they were like
optimized for serverless executions.
This process involve adapting
our code and workflows to align
with the serverless model.
I. And again, like another
one, like the CICD pipeline.
To ensure the smooth deployment, we
focused on building the optimized
serverless specific CICD pipelines.
This allowed for a continuous
integration and delivery tailored
alert for a serverless environment,
enabling fast and reliable updates.
This strategy allows allowed us actually
to success and scale progressively.
And NCO, the transition was as
seamless as possible, moving to
the next, yeah, as with the complex
system, observable observability
become a significant challenge.
And dis distributed tracing across
the multiple serverless functions
was inherently more complex and
the execution context for each
functions was more limited, making it
harder to gather detailed insights.
We also had.
To content with unpredictable
cold start latency with impacted
performance, as well as highly valu,
highly variable resource consumptions.
Making consistent monitoring and
difficulties to tackle these challenges.
We implemented several keys of solutions
are like fastly introduced end to end
correlation ID to track the request
across the functions, providing a
full view of each request journey.
And we then deployed the centralized
logging with structured data, ensuring we
could capture and analyze log effectively.
Custom function specific dashboards
allowed us to monitor performance on a
granular level and a dynamic alerting
based on the statistical baselines
helped us to detect issues early today.
Our sophisticated monitor monitoring
infrastructure provides the comprehensive
visibility into our wireless ecosystem.
And allowing us to have proactive detect
issues and resolve them rapidly, ensuring
a smooth and efficient operations.
Now here to ensure our serverless
journey remain cost effective.
And we implemented several key op cost
optimization strategies right side
function resources is one of them.
Memory allocation has a. Direct
impact on both performance and cost.
To optimize these, we implemented
automated testing to determine the
optimum memory settings for each
functions, and ensuring that we are
using the resources efficiently.
We without our provisioning.
And another one, like a
optimized cold starts.
And yeah, like cold start latencies can
significantly affect the performance,
especially during traffic spike.
So to mitigate this, we reduced
the size of our deployment package
and implemented the provision
concurrency for critical parts.
This strategy ensured a minimum cold
start impact even during the traffic
traffic functionalities and all.
And monitoring the execution s by closely
we were able to able to identify the
functions approaching timeout thresholds.
These proactive monitoring prevent
costly timeout loops and helped us to
avoid the execution in efficiencies
and saving both time and money.
We introduced the tagging standards
and deploy deployment policies to keep
our serverless architecture organized
and avoid unnecessary resources.
So governance ensured that serverless
resources were used strategically,
and that the infrastructure remained
manageable and cost effective.
Together these strategies allowed us to
optimize both performance cost across
us across our serverless architecture.
So this slide we'll discuss
about the measurable result.
Yes.
And looks looking at the result,
our serverless transitions.
We have some truly impactful outcomes.
So we successfully decreased our
infrastructure expenses by 62 percents.
And thanks to the efficiency of
serverless architecture and optimize
use of resources now, operational
failure were reduced by 78% leading to
a more reliable and stable environment.
So with few disruptions to our
services and customer experience.
And our deployment frequency increased
by 3.5 times, enabling faster iter
sense and more frequents driving
innovations and improvement for our
users and which is a big achievement.
Developers satisfactions
increase actually to 94%.
And as the team spend more time focusing
on building the features less on managing
infrastructure contributing to improved
improved user experience and productivity.
So these reserves actually highlight
that, the tangible benefits observer
list, both in terms of cost and
in terms of productivity as well.
So as we reflect on our
serverless journey, we have
learned a few keys of license.
So the flexibility of serverless
architecture was allowed
us to adapt quickly to.
To changing her business needed.
We have learned that this agility
is a key ops staying competitive
in a fast and placed environment.
Serverless is not only one-time solutions.
We are constantly iterating on
architecture and process, ensuring
that we are always optimizing
performance, cost, and efficiency.
By freeing up the resource from
infrastructure management our teams
have been able to focus more on product
development and innovations which is
driving the future of our business.
I. And looking ahead, we plan to
extend our serverless architecture
to more workloads continuing refining
our harm monitoring systems as well.
And explore new AWS services
that can drive even more
efficiencies and capabilities.
So the journeys from over and
the future looks bright, I think.
Now as we continue our serverless journey.
So we I want to provide the resources
to help you on our own path.
It'll be like the next step as well.
Access to our comprehensive serverless
templates and architectures patterns.
These resources provide
a solid foundations.
For your own serverless implementation
and saving your time and effort, and
reviewing our architecture decisions and.
We made throughout the journey.
These records will help to guide
your decision making process and
provide insight into the challenges.
We overcome and use open source utilities
to taste and the benchmark performance.
So that is mostly important thing,
and these tools are designed to help
and you measure the efficiency of
your serverless architecture and
optimize it for your own needs.
Join these channels what I mentioned
here, and to connect with experts
and peer who can actually provide
the valuable implementation advice
and share with best practices and
collaborate and ask the questions and
learn from others in the community.
And same thing.
I actually followed, like during my entire
journey, and these resources are here
to help you, you help you and succeed.
And I also look I also look forward to
supporting your serverless endeavor.
In future if you want.
That's fine.
You can contact me.
Okay.
And so I appreciate your time and
today I hope my HR D has inspired you
to explore the power and serverless
architecture and for your own project.
If you have any questions, if
you want to learn more, feel free
to reach out to me and I have my
contact informations and LinkedIn
here so you can message me anytime.
I will respond as per my time.
Thank you so much.