Speaker 37: Hello.
Good afternoon.
I'm
IT Development Manager
at Sales Minnesota today.
Want to talk about something?
SLE teams increasing the struggle
with reliable data at scale.
Because in modern SLE availability isn't
only about, is service up, it's also
take a lot of things into conservation.
Is the data correct?
Is it fresh enough to make decisions
and can we scale it without creating
operational risk, et cetera.
Today we'll compare traditional UTL
tools and unified data platforms.
It will give you a practical way to
decide which fits to your environment.
Also we go why data be in harder
and necessary environment?
Then we'll look at traditional ETL
tools, what they do well and where they
tend to break under modern demands.
Then we'll shift to unified data platforms
and they're becoming more relevant for
scalability, observable, and governance.
I will close with the ation in a framework
and quick scenario to make it practical.
Okay.
Let's start with what is driving
the treasure and complexity?
Increasing data complexity as
enterprise data volume surges.
SRE teams face new challenges because
we are not only dealing with structured
transactional data anymore, we are
also dealing with logs, even traces,
customer behavior signals, multiple
format, multiple speed, and the more you
know, diverse the data types, the harder
it is to keep reliability guarantees.
Pipeline fails, schema changes
upstream, systems drifts.
Then suddenly our incident respond
depends on data we don't fully trust.
For example, think about
an e-comm incident.
The site slows down if your pipeline
can't correlate, app latency with
checkout, even send inventory
updates quickly, you lose time.
Okay, complexity leads directly to the
next challenge, which is scalability.
Now, scalability isn't about compute,
it's about whether you want data,
movement and transformations can keep
up, especially when there are spikes.
And here, the SLE angle, when
you are, data platform can
scale you get blind spots.
Delayed dashboards, missing metrics,
and now we seeing many signals.
Okay, so that brings to the classic
approach Most organizations starts,
started with traditional VTLs is.
Understanding traditional EL tools.
These tools are built around a structured
data flow, extract data from sources,
transform it and load it into your
warehouse, or reporting destinations.
So the benefit is predictability.
We know exactly what, what runs,
then it runs what it outputs.
This work extremely well for
stable reporting environment.
But the limitation is that it
often assumes your world is stable.
Schemas don't change frequently.
Workloads are predictable
and latency isn't critical.
So its great for end to end day finance
summaries, complaints, reporting,
or weekly business dashboards.
Next we'll, moving on to
your ETL batch oriented.
Let's talk about that.
So understanding unified data platforms
unified data platforms, covered
and integrated, distributed archite
for managing diverse data types.
They focus on seamless integrations
and centralized governance, and
they support real time or near rail
time processing much more naturally.
So the big shift is in stuff
stitching together multiple
tools with many hands off.
You get a platform designed to
keep data accessible, relatable,
and secure across environments.
Example, instead of ETL.
Stays in to, in a warehouse From
there, separate streaming tools,
separate observable layers, team often
consolidate into fewer moving parts.
Okay.
That brings to the next topic
about reason Unified platform is
their architecture, scalability.
If a look at the traditional
ETLs often relates on vertical
scaling, bigger machines, bigger
capacity until you fit bottleneck.
Unified platforms typically scale
horizontally, enabling elastic
resource allocation, so they
handle specs more gracefully and
support real time processing.
Example with ETLs, you upgrade the
server with the unified platforms,
you add nodes and scale out and data
system fee balance automatically.
So with that will be jumping
onto the next topic, which is
a flexibility in data handling.
So traditional ETL Excels with
structural data and predefined.
In our sch.
So this gives consistency and predictable
workflows, unified platform support
structures and structured and unstructured
data, making them better suited to modern
elementary and even driven architectures.
This is going to shine.
Then the new filed to an.
Unified platform can a est and equal
more gracefully reducing firefighting.
So with that, move on to the reality.
Everyone cares about operational costs.
Operational cost.
TL tools can have lawyer initial costs,
but maintenance can escalate its volumes.
Complexity growth of un unified
platforms that required a higher upfront
investment, but they could reduce long
term operational costs through productions
and reduced from SRE Prospect to cost
includes operations low on in time.
Complexity.
For example, a cheaper solution that
needs constant manual fixes cost
you engineering time and time is,
so with that I like to simplify the
patients using three lenses, which is
scale, the label D and integration.
Not every team is a unified platform
today, but every team should understand
when the tipping point is approaching.
Okay,
Speaker 39: so
Speaker 37: okay.
If you look at the scale and performance
in a batch, tools is a great fit, then
you know workloads are predictable
and cost efficiency with some
latencies acceptable unified platform.
Essential and real elasticity and
high voltage tions become critical
and if you to national logging
into pipelines recommendations.
Anomalies detection, forecasting.
You want to, you want a platform that
support those integrations relay.
So platform choice directly impacts.
Okay, so talking about reliability.
Fault tolerance and monitoring
platform choice directly, impacts
fault and incident detection.
The more observed is self-healing.
Your data pattern are capacity detect
issues and the faster you recover.
So unify unified platforms,
often baking, monitoring, and.
Which can reduce N-T-T-L-E-T-L
can be available too, but you
may need additional tooling and
tighter operational discipline.
Okay, cost considerations, upfront
investment versus long term savings.
Cost decisions should
blame upfront investments.
With long term savings, but also factor in
resource availability and skillset because
we have powerful platform that nobody
can operate will fail operationally.
So total cost of ownership into those
tooling, compute people, instant
time training and vendor support.
Example.
Two platforms may look similar
in licensing, but one requests
constant manual churn that
will cost more over year.
Now that's guaranteed.
Oh, similar you application for framework.
Imagine a mid sales eCommerce company
where transaction volume is urging.
They're facing data challenges that
start impacting operational reliability.
When you are, when you come compare
ETLs to UN unified platforms.
In the growth scenario, UN unified
approach is usually then on
scalability and flexibility because
the business needs faster insight
and fewer operational bottlenecks.
The business.
Able to launch promotions, all
spikes, support ticket spike.
If data discipline, I mean if the data
pipeline can't keep up, leaders can't
answer basic questions in real time.
Is checking out failing or is it
regional or inventory correct.
So these kind of issues, okay,
so there are three takeaways.
ETL remains effective for stable
batch upload, unstructured
data, unified platform shine.
Then scalability, flexibility,
and real time needs.
And three user edition
and framework scale.
Relatability targets and integrates
needs to guide the choice rather trends.
Okay, so the goal isn't to
change modern architecture.
The goal is relatable decision at
scale with the platforms your teams
can operate Contently, finally
yeah, thank you for your attention.
And also thanks for your time.
If you wanna discuss your can environment,
any questions you can feel free to reach
out on my contact in the deck side.