Speaker 27: Hi guys.
This is Sanjay Baso.
I work with TCS in the
retail and the EI vertical.
And today I'm going to go through the
at scale and how to operationalize it.
Specifically we'll talk about
today in the cognitive commerce
in the grocery retail space.
There is a shift from
experiment to mission critical.
So l LMS are no longer
proof of concept stage.
They have crossed that stage and there
are applications which are getting
deployed in the production environment.
The first question that
we always encounter is why
lums break the conventional.
The site and reliability
engineering assumptions.
It's a non-deterministic inputs or
sorry, outputs and the same prompt
in different results across calls
in Variating traditional corrects.
The second is a token latency variability.
So which means that the response time.
Scales without output length.
Third is the evolving context.
Rep dependencies, there's a prompt
embedding context, window, et
cetera, change continuously, right?
So that all affects the
conventional assumptions.
The retail stakes are uniquely very high.
It has to cater to the
peak of traffic spikes.
For example, the flash sales
like a cyber Monday, right?
Or the product substitution
in case of no inventory.
And the substitution has to
be the right substitution or
personalization is happening at
a scale where n is equal to one.
Or there is an inventory accuracy,
which has to be predicted.
The redefining of the s or prob realistic
systems which means that semantic
accuracy for the SLOs, which is a
percentage of expenses, responses that
pass automated semantic evaluation right
against ground, truth, intent, et cetera.
The top find the time to first.
Okay.
Then has hallucination rate
budget, acceptable error rate.
Rate, and the cost per inference is low.
Second is that we are talking
about architecture resilience
patterns wherein you the customer
facing allocations and customer
facing experiences cannot degrade.
Which, brings us to something which
is called on hybrid decision players.
And so what I propose is a hybrid
decision layer, which means a decision
layer wherein the rate engine forest
does all the hard business constants,
et cetera, which are all deterministic.
Then LLM is used as a reasoning layer.
Where you have the decision space and
the decision rules are taking place based
on the a LM and then the post inference
validation, the output is recheck
against the rule engine before surfacing
to customer or downstream systems.
This ensures that there is reduction.
There is very low
hallucination, which happens.
Now with respect to when it comes to
the availability framework for the AI
systems, now we are talking about, logging
every prompt and a template version.
We are talking about semantic evaluation
appliance which is your automated tele.
To charge the screen on sample production
draft, right hallucination detection.
Embedded based embed based
similarity checks within the model
output and the retrieval context.
Then the drift monitoring.
Where they're tracking the
semantic distribution shifts
across the model, et cetera.
And then we are talking about the chart,
which you're looking about is the cost.
Our scaling tokens, paint
as infrastructure tokens.
Paint is the first thing they
which is followed by macro
across the retail value chain.
If we look at from customer experiences
like semantic search, conversational
shopping assistance, et cetera.
Then we have got merchandising, right?
The demand signal interpretation as
assortment optimization, et cetera.
Then you've got a supply chain, which
is a supplier communication automation.
Then we have got an ity detection
in the fulfillment data, and then
inventory forecasting, et cetera.
And if we look at what we have
been seeing the, are getting
used across the value chain.
Now when it comes to agent Tick l
lm, the logistics and the last mile
delivery we are talking about agent tick
architectures where l lms automatically
plan they take they, involve the tools
and then take the decisions which is
needed and require in case of an agent,
take KLM for that last mile delivery.
Now incident response for AI induced
failures wherein, follow a five
state method wherein your detection
is happening as a safe one which is
your semantic valuation pipeline for
alerting, hallucination, et cetera.
The second is a containment which
is your automatic traffic shift to
rule-based fallback layer, and the
model traffic throttle in percent.
Then we are talking about the diagnosis
of that, which is a prompt, telemetry,
replay, isolates, offending, template
version, or embedding refreshing
which happens by default, right?
From an from an diagnosis perspective.
Then you're talking about
remediation which is your rollback,
prompt version or shadow model,
traffic restoration, et cetera.
We are talking about post incidences
where the SLA breach review the evaluation
pipeline, et cetera, hardening is
happening when it comes to security,
compliance and guardrail enforcement.
We are talking about input, guardrails,
prompt injection detection, which
is your pattern classifiers on
all user generated input before
the 11, before the LLM is invoked.
Then we have the PII scrubbing, which
is your named entity recognition
streams personal data from the content
window before the inference tech space.
Then you're talking about regulatory
filters which are part of the the output
s. Hard blocks on for example, the, from
a regular filtered perspective, we are
talking about alcohol, drugs, pharmacy
age related or products, et cetera.
And recommendations, which are,
verifying the eligibility of such.
Then you're talking about the
toxicity of bias screening.
The last thing we want is a
bias creeping into the whole
the whole enforcement thing.
We are talking about a pragmatic
approach for cognitive commerce,
which is your redefine your which
means that you extend your resell
framework to cover semantic accuracy,
hallucination rate, TT f et cetera,
and then cost per inference as part
of the first class reliability signal.
Then the second is that you architect
for degradation so that the the
customer experience remains intact.
There.
There is no.
And that there is no failure
on the customer side.
So every call a master, a deterministic
fallback resilience is designed,
not not bolted on the after the
fast production incident, right?
So it has to be preemptively
and accurately being managed.
Then you have got instrument, everything,
which is your prompt telemetry, semantic
evaluation, drift monitoring, cost per
tracking, et cetera, which will happen.
Then we are talking about the
bound of agent autonomy, which is
your, the action budgets, rollback
triggers, and human evaluation ratios
as we enforced the orchestration
layer for every agent workflow.
So this is some of the this is a
framework for the cognitive commerce.
The most important is that we have
to understand the the the SLAs.
The s sub study, the SLOs which will
redefine which needs redefinition.
Thank you for your time today.