Hi everyone.
My name is cio and today I would like
to tell you my story As a known database
administrator running managed databases
on the cloud, specific AWS for Rob.
I will share my.
Mistakes, my hard challenges and
hopefully as well some lesson and
some things to learn along the way.
Quick agenda, I will give you a
brief review of my how D has journey
so far, why that is important.
Why does that help to understand
what I will explain later on, I
will show some interesting cases
and by cases mean support cases.
I'll discuss some challenges,
hopefully as well, some solutions.
And I will go through some, what
I call super simple experiment.
I wouldn't call them benchmarks, but
something to give an idea about how
to run our DS and manage databases.
And we'll recap with some lesson learned.
But before starting, I would
like to remember you one number,
a hundred thousand record.
Think about how you can.
Store a hundred thousand record databases.
Sounds like a very simple
task, but how do you do it?
How long does it take milliseconds?
10 seconds, one minute.
Who knows?
Depends how you do it.
We'll see that later on.
My RDS journey so far, I've been
running databases on the cloud
for over a decade, since 2011.
That makes me old,
doesn't make me an expert.
I've been mostly running
my databases on Amazon.
RDS, Amazon DS is a service that was
introduced by Amazon just about, yeah,
15 years ago now this is the post that
Jeff Barr published in October, 2009.
That's almost the entire post
that give you a really, an idea.
What was at that time.
Are this a very simple database
compatible with my SQL 5.2.
One back in 2011 when it started, so
not long after it was announced the key
part of the service were simplicity.
There was not much to choose.
We see that later on what the benefits
and what the limitation of that are.
There were of course, a lot of
constraints and when we talk about once
upon a time and a good time when the
cloud was simpler we tend to forget
that was very much more expensive.
At that time.
So anyway, what was the feature?
What, why?
First of all, I started
to use managed databases.
I was, and I'm still
somehow a software engineer.
I started as a Java software developer.
I was familiar with web application,
java, web application but databases.
Yeah, I was using them.
Was I able to install my SQR
postcards on my machine or run one?
Yes, definitely.
Was I able to manage a cluster?
Absolutely.
No.
I had no idea how to do failovers.
I had no idea.
I was scared about full tolerance.
I had no idea how to
manage a, active master.
How to do a failover,
how to manage a replica.
What actually, even at that time, I
dunno, a delay on replication meant so.
What was the feature that drove
me to move to the cloud was multi
Z. Multi Z was a very simple
feature conceptually from Amazon.
RDS was the idea that here is your
endpoint, a c name, that's your
my Sqr instance, and behind the
scene we do the failover for you.
The replication is done
for you out of the box.
You can have backups, you
can have whatever you.
Whatever you want out of the box that
drove me and many other people to the
cloud and to use managed databases on RDS.
When I say that the good of time when
there were many, not many choices
were, is rather more expensive time,
was that even without considering that
the new latest systems are much, much
better as processor than the old one.
The benefits are well
beyond the just the price.
You can see that even the price
of an instance, if you can
see an extra large instance.
Went down along the time.
So IM seven G instance is actually cheaper
than an M1 instance over a decade ago,
and it's definitely much more performant.
So when I say there were many limitations,
I means that in 2011 was somehow simple.
The job of a cloud architect,
somehow it's much better for you now.
If you start now or if you work now on the
cloud, because you have many options with
many options, have a lot of responsibility
in your choices at that time once you have
made the decision to move to the cloud.
It was pretty simple.
There was just my SQL it was just
one engine with 5.1 and no much else.
There was no A ranges.
There were no process,
no SQL, no Maria db.
And actually many people think that
I'm not an expert, but I'm a big
sport, a big fan of my SQL actually.
When I moved to the cloud, I
was running a posts database.
I moved to Mascar to be able to
have a managed service on a, on AWS.
That time there was no
choice on storage class.
There was no GP P two, no GP
three, no provision io no i,
O one, IO two or whatever.
You had magnetic and that was it.
You were paying for how many operation
you were doing on the storage,
and of course there were no fees.
Like of course there was no
Amazon Aurora at that time.
There was no performance in size, so
no, no advanced money, no kind of.
Previous feature that you used to
find just on the that you were not
used to find in the communication.
So the very first lesson of this talk
that you should take on is with you, is
keep iterating keep yourself up to date.
We love to go to reinvent.
We had a big conference, not just
on AWS and even clap when they do
announcement of new cool features.
Reality is that's the moment when your
deployment might become a bit obsolete.
I'm not saying change immediately,
but roof time after two, three years,
you haven't changed anything on
your deployment, on your database.
Probably are missing out.
I'm not saying it's more
expensive than before.
It's just that as a cloud architect
is your goal to keep yourself
up to date and take advantage
of new feature and reduce costs.
I would like to now move to some
what I call interesting cases.
I call them cases because they're
actually AWS support cases.
Big.
What here?
Those are 10 cases that
I opened myself on.
The AWS support using tickets.
Some of them come from having enterprise
support, some other with business support,
some other with developer support.
Actually, it doesn't matter that much.
I just want to use them as an example.
And the very second lesson I want to
share is I think interacting with AWS
Apple has been one of the biggest way
I've learned using and the service
and as well the limitation of service.
The subject are actually as they
were I removed the case number, but.
You can see quickly scanning through
them is, some of them are issues.
So I reported issue, I don't know,
the replica was broken after scaling
up, or, I dunno the RDS was stuck
in storage optimization, 99% for
almost 24 hours or whatever else.
But some of them are actually,
you can see I've just questioned
the roadmap, minor roadmap versus
the years of Amazon Aurora, or.
Build on transaction compression support
for Linda to be redo log capacity.
And those question, why do I open them?
Because it's not just to have information.
They help you as well to drive decision.
What do we mean by that?
I mean that if you have an idea how
you're gonna change your database also
for storage operation, that might be hard
to revert and might take a lot of time.
Throw, write down your idea and how
you're gonna do it and the doubts you
have, and double check with support.
If they see an issue sometime, I'm not
saying ask them, oh, how do I do that?
I'm just saying, give what you have
in mind to do and check if there's
something wrong that they can help a lot.
And as well, maybe you say, okay, there's
no transaction compression support that
is available in the community edition.
Okay, it's not there in R Ds.
You can open a case and just advocate
that they're gonna have it, but as well,
you can ask, okay, then it's not there.
How can I achieve that?
How can I reduce the size of my binary?
There are other ways, of course
there's not gonna be compression, but
maybe they help you in other ways.
So let's go to some challenges.
A solution.
Let's take some of those cases
that we say a few seconds ago.
First one is.
I said, when you play with a
managed database, you have to
think about storage on Aurora.
That's pretty simple.
You pay for the storage,
you use, you have not.
To allocate anything, so that's cool.
That's no brainer.
What do you do on RDS?
On RDS, you allocate the storage up front.
You decide on what storage you want.
It might impact how many
I oaks you have upfront.
For example, on GP three, if
there's storage, the size of
this is below 400 gigabyte.
You have 3000 iops.
If you're above, you have 12,000.
But there are many different combination,
but generally you're just thinking about
how much storage you need, how much free
storage I need to avoid to fill up my
disc, can end up that my database crashes.
One is the option is to
enable out scale storage.
It's been there for a few
years and that's cool.
When you go below 10% for the
storage is cased automatically.
The problem with that is
pretty hard to go back.
Actually until recently, there
was no real easy way to go back.
Now you can do some blue, green and
re reduce the storage, but it still
requires some significant work because
you need to create the BlueLine
and you need to swap the point.
So it's still not a easy task for
large database, but this is an example.
There are two terabyte
of free storage is a lot.
It's little.
Why did it jump?
It jumped there because I did a mistake
to go to do a optimize of a large table,
or you can as well do an altar table
that requires a copy of your, so that is
not a in place that you're copying the
data from your old table to the new one.
And what happened is my outer
scaling was initiated on my instance
was the implication of that.
That basically.
That's a rocky mistake that the moment
you're doing something very intensive
from the database that is modify your
schema or change your data, the last
thing you want is that first that you
increase the free storage that you might
not need because maybe that ten three
percent that you had was good enough.
And secondly is.
You're doing an operation that is very
heavy on iops and you are actually
triggering a system operation that is
applying changes to the storage that is
actually consuming your IOPS as well.
So that's the full first lesson I learned.
The other way was disable out scaling.
Anytime you do some optimization on
some methods, so your database anyway.
You may wonder, apart from application
reason, why do I, how and why I want to
do an al alter optimize an email DB table.
We'll come back to why I want to
optimize a table in a second to recover
storage and why is that important?
But how do you do a AL
table or optimize as well?
You have different, you can do
an alter table using the engine.
So on my sqr, I can do
alter table, whatever.
Change the way I want.
I can as well use third party tool
that sometime allow me to control
better how I do it in term of
load on the production database.
So I might want to do it in a
slower way, but it affects less the
production or that is recoverable.
So for example, pera PT
online schema changes.
Part of the per toolkit is perfect
for that, but there are other option
in the open source world as well.
The key questions as well.
Being on the cloud where there are so
many options, where do I do my change?
I might do it on the primary node is
a small table or I want to take the
risk, or I want a simple approach.
Simple approaches.
Go on the database on my multi z, go on
the connect to the primary node and do
alter table that has some disadvantage.
If that might kill my database,
I might be able to roll back,
may have some challenges.
Second approach is.
Create a replica node.
If the change I'm applying for for
example, adding a column is compatible
with the replication, I might stop the
replication, apply the change on the
replica, re-enable replication, and then
at the end do the swap of the endpoint.
That's much safer, a bit more
complex with a lot of flexibility.
Or I can do it with Amazon, RDS
Bluegreen, something that's been
around now for a couple of years.
That is a wrap around my
replica note approach.
That is basically you
have a blue and a green.
You decide to do changes on your own.
Green deployment, and then you swap.
That's cool as well.
The end result is that the free storage
space you have might change a lot if
you do alter table and optimization.
And remember how much storage you need.
It's not just the storage of the table.
You are copying that, so at
least that extra storage.
So if you have a large table of
one terabyte on a database of
three terabyte means that you need.
Quite some free storage on
that table to be able on that
database to be able to do it.
But as well, if you, for example,
stop the replica for a certain amount
of time, you might build up a lot of
binary doc that you need to replicate.
And that's that you need to apply.
So it is on your replica, so you
might even need more storage.
So consider front how much storage you
need for those changes and make sure
that there's no automatic change in
storage while you apply those changes.
Why do I say optimizing
your table is vital?
One of the things you want to have a
managed database and what you love about
managed databases that they are managed
so as well, backups are out of the box.
There's nothing to be done.
They are there.
And even Amazon from day one tells you
how well up to a hundred percent of your
total database storage for a region.
It's free backup.
That's nothing to be done.
Our expert database means
they'll tell you the majority
of customers don't pay anything.
That's pretty much true
if you don't write a lot.
And if you keep maybe one, two days
of point in time recovery, if you
have a backup point in time, recovery
of 30, 35 days, that is the maximum.
You might start to pay for that.
Actually, that's.
Second lesson I want to share is
sometimes CPU is overestimated.
It's overrated.
I hear a lot of conversation at
a coffee machine at conferences
where we discuss what's the best
instance class, what's the best CPU
utilization for that specific workload.
I have you already moved from
M six G to M seven G. Are you
using our instance or whatever?
How they hear people discussing,
or at least not as often people
about storage and backup.
This is an example of a production
database that I'm managing.
You can see that it's a. In
three years, the CPU is going on.
There's some reserve instance behind.
It's a healthy project going up and
costs are going up because it's a
healthy project that is growing.
That's cool.
But you can see that the CPU is not
even half of the total cost of your
database and back up is significantly,
it's almost as costly as the CPU.
And why is that significant?
Because if you think about your cables.
How a backup is done.
Backup is a bit like
a snapshot on the EPS.
There's no magic on our DS that's incre.
Yes, it's incremental.
The data backup is incremental.
But what does it mean incremental?
If your data is spread around your
table is not optimized once in a
while, your data that you modify
every day maybe spread around.
So at the end, your back
daily backup, that incremental
might be a lot of incremental.
So you can see here
that the daily gigabyte.
Month, the usage you have.
I think this one is a month by month view.
Changed a lot.
And those fluctuation and those
increase really depends as well on,
of course on usage, but as well on
optimization done on the tables those
fluctuation is after some optimization.
And when you spend 6,000 euro month
on backup, maybe at 20% saving after
some optimize or significant or one
2000 euro a month, you're saving.
So next one.
Graviton, this a provocative
tweet from Quin, I think
you're all familiar with Cory.
And the point is you're
using a managed database.
Why do I care if he's running a Graviton
or Intel or whatever else behind?
And it's provocative,
but it's a good point.
It's an interesting one actually.
I was a very early adopter of Graviton
and the reason why I was very.
Every adopter of movie from M five Intel
to M six G on RDS for MySQL was that
is with managed is incredibly simple.
You don't have to think about if you need
to change the build the jar, whatever.
Like with Lambda is, you just simply
have to switch in the console and if
the new instance is cheaper, that's it.
Nothing else to be done.
They take care of the engine behind.
Why don't you do it?
You do it, but it's sometimes
it's not that straightforward.
Here's a post that I wrote a few
years ago, how we were managing at
that time, the outer scaling of RD
assistance in al, using a simple
logic using patient command line.
So basically using some matrix and
CloudWatch, we're deciding when was the
time to scale up and down our RDS cluster
and go down according to time of the day.
Memories, users, number of session.
You build your own logic,
some matrix, and you do it.
That's cool.
Everything works.
So now you switch to Graviton and that's.
What I had at that time, you had a crush.
Okay.
If there's a crush,
that's not your problem.
Of course there's a bag in the build,
so you open a ticket, you talk to
Amazon, but at the end, what you
realize is that, yeah, it's true that
moving to Graviton is transparent.
It's free.
But the challenge there was that,
yeah, that was a bug, but the main
issue was that I was running out of
memory and why I was running outta
memory is that because basically
in instances were very different.
The ratio between memory and
number of CPU is different.
So if, for example, you optimize my
questionable parameter, I call them the
your parameter group to get out every
single benefit from your instance.
You might reach the point of, on the
graviton behave slightly different.
Here is an example.
For example, here I optimize
certain things like the
memory, the buffer pool size.
I was a bit more aggressive,
probably is a good idea.
But the message was to say is that what
happened in this scenario to me was that
the optimization had in place for intel.
Was perfectly fine to do my logic
of auto-scaling with the graviton.
What happened day one was that I
reached the crash running outta
memory before being able to scale.
My instance.
So lesson learned was
keep an eye on optimizing.
When you optimize, minimize
changes to your parameter
group, there's a limit between.
Yes, you want to optimize, but
keep in mind that you might need
to change the instance both in
size and class as a minimum.
Keep the variable, keep the
changes you make as variable on the
instances class memory at least.
One more challenge, one
more things you have.
You might think, okay, I want to make
a read from my SQL on RDS to Aurora.
That's something we have all
done and we all love Aurora.
So how do you do it?
According to Amazon, in 10, 20
minutes, you learn how to do it with a
intermediate exper experience, and you
know how to do it without any downtime.
How do you actually do that?
If you go and look at the video and if
you read documentation, the way you do
those things is simply create a replica.
The replica of RDS is an
number of replica, and then
that's when you're ready.
You just promote that is
your new primary easy.
Any challenge here?
The challenge is going
too fast, missing Aurora.
That's what happened to me the
very first time I tried that.
Just for the documentation can upgrade
my, this is an example, a more recent
one from my SQL 8 0 39 to Aurora three.
What's wrong there?
Reality is that you have to think
how muscular or any basis release.
There's a foundation for Postgres.
There's a Oracle for my SQL that
release every once in a while, a
minor version and a major version.
My SQL is every quarter there's
a minor, and after a few
weeks that minor is supported.
Usually if there are no big bugs on
RDS, Aurora may take a bit longer.
Aurora may be a few quarters
later that support that specific.
Venture because that's a fork.
And what you need to keep in mind is
that the replica you can create to
RDS as Aurora need to be at least at
the same level of your primary RDS.
So if you have a primary, it is 8 0 39,
you need our order that's post that.
And if that Aurora is not out
yet, you are not able to migrate.
So if you want to keep your production
database, always the option to migrate
to Aurora to have that safety net.
If you want to grow whatever reason.
Remember, you cannot keep yourself
too close to the latest miner.
You need to keep to the latest
minor supported by Aurora.
Now, let's change topic from,
go from, cP manual release
to RDS and running out iops.
I wrote many blogs many one
that no one wrote, but still
today the most popular blog.
I have a blog post I have on
my own website.com is this one.
RDS is running out.
Iops, what can I do?
I wrote it 68 years ago.
Even if this one is out of,
it's absolutely relevant.
Now, the content is not up to date.
It's still the most popular because
it's a very challenged topic.
So we're doing by running out of iops and
what I learned in this decade, first one,
you tend to always underestimate iops.
You always think you have enough,
you often eat the limit, whatever
during an halter table, a scale
up exchange, optimization of
your table a peak in your usage.
The kind of newish was
not there many years ago.
Total matrix is very useful,
but don't rely just on that one.
The total EOPS is give you a feeling
of, oh, if you think you have 12,000
iops just if to, to that match, you can
have a feeling if you're getting close.
Remember that GP two GP three.
By design, I'm not supposed to guarantee
you a hundred percent of the time.
Those iops.
So 99% is a lot of time, but
there's still, sometimes you
might not eat those numbers.
GP three versus GP two, they
are at the same price on RDS.
So how do you decide they have a
different model in term of iops,
GP three, when you are over 400
gigabyte, you get 12,000 iops.
With GP two, you have three
iops per single gigabyte.
With a basic simple math, up to
four terabyte of storage, GP three
delivers more iops over four terabyte.
GP two is technically provide
by the full more iops.
The difference is you cannot
just choose according to that.
The main difference is that
you cannot change the baseline.
You cannot pay to have
more AOPs on GP two.
While GP three is more flexible, you
can decide how much the throughput
and iops you can configure them
separately from the size of the
disc, and that's really helpful.
This is IO one and IO two, that they are
the provision iops IU one is the very
first provision iops available on RDS.
They've been there for many years.
Last year, IO two Express came out
and the thing, the key point is IO two
is at the same price point of IO one.
But it's better just use
IO two whenever you can.
Not every single business card can
support it, but usually newest one.
Yes.
The key point about provision AOPs, yeah,
it's good to have it, but it's expensive.
And when you think, when you say
that the CPU is overrated think that
yes, of course if you get if you
put provision IOPS on a production
database, it's better not to have them.
But you have to think about
the overall cost of your.
Database solution.
Do you really need them or you
need them temporary because you
have battery designed database?
Maybe sharding the database on
multiple RDS give you 24,000 iops
without having to pay for provision
iops and so on and so forth.
The other, so the lesson is
use them, but be careful.
Think if there a way to improve
your product without having them
almost all on very large database.
And if you use provision apps,
remember to watch out for copies,
replica tests, staging environment,
because when you create from a
snapshot, they by default the storage
the same class as the one you had.
So you don't want to have a provision
database app, staging database
with a lot of IOPS provision
and paid quite expensively.
So I call it blue, green, and purple.
So that's the next lesson.
So previous lesson down storage,
blue, green, purple blue.
Green is the newest nice approach to
change database do changes to database.
Now this screen that I want to
share with you and take a second
about what we have here what
happened between August 25 and 28.
Actually this is a performance
inside and there's no data.
Why does the database is so
low and there's no data before?
Reality is that when I did a bluegreen
switch using A-W-S-R-D-S bluegreen,
my performance inside data is gone.
I have no data Before A was 24th and
the data between August 25 and 28 are
the one from the the deployment that
was the passive one, the green one.
When you check the documentation tells
you that the green, what is the green
environment have, it's a copy of theology
of the production environment, includes
feature used by the instance, for
example, red replica storage, DB snapshot,
automatic backups performance inside.
And so you expect when you use.
Green deployment, everything is there.
Everything is there.
But remember that when
you rename, things change.
So this AWS when I ask them, why don't
I have my old data performance side?
Performance side is there is enabled,
but performance side of the old
blue instance will not be carried
to the new blue instance after the
blue green deployment failover.
Is that an issue?
Usually I love as an engineer
and the operation to be able to
look at my data back months here.
So if you update a miner of a database,
you have to use bluegreen, maybe?
Yes.
Depends.
Or maybe not remember as well.
The drawback.
The drawback is you might lose
certain data is significant because
actually one of the reason after a
blue green deployment, I would like
to compare the data before and after.
If I don't have the data before, that's
a bit of a problem That doesn't apply
to CloudWatch Matrix because they.
Apply to the name, but that apply
to performance inside on only.
Same with backup.
You might have with Bluegreen
30 days you have decide to
have backup retention 30 days.
It might be as well as something you
have by contract with your customer.
You cannot keep the
data more than 30 days.
But what type you do?
Blue, green?
The older distance is there.
You may.
Decide to stop it or delete it.
And when you delete it, it tells you do
you want to keep your old data yes or no?
If you say yes, the data is there,
but it's there for other 30 days.
So retain, automatic backup
are removed by the system.
So what happen is if you use Bluegreen
on any time you kill your instance with
automatic backups, you have to remember
that any retention period you set 30 days.
It's not incremental on every database.
So the backup of 29 days ago
will be deleted tomorrow.
No, all the data backup will be
deleted in 30 days from today.
That have, might have cost implication,
but as well some compliance implications.
So keep that in mind.
You might want to deploy
your own logic to avoid that.
Anyway, the last lesson I want to
share is underestimate time for a
change that I've done many times.
I say before we create a replica.
So I create my replica, and it might take,
you see it here from the Matrix that how
long does it take to create a replica?
If you look at the replica, maybe
after half an hour, the console
say that the replica is available.
But what happened to my replica
is that after he is available.
The lag, the replica keep
growing because my production
database is under heavy load.
So keep growing, because my disc on
this snapshot, there's no magic there.
The replica starts with a cold disc.
It's gonna take time to retrieve
data from S3 and warm up.
At that point, by the time I'm able
to, to have a replica, really, it's
gonna be days or at least hours,
but sometime this is three days.
After three days, I was actually
able to use my replica because until
the replica leg is zero, I cannot
really do any significant attack.
I can stop it and do the al
table, but still, at some
point I will have to catch up.
So remember that the time for a change
is not just the time to have the
replica ready or to have the instance
up and running from a snapshot,
but the time that instance is work.
So if you don't do that, when you
swap between a green and blue,
what you see what happen here
around 15, 10 minutes past 15?
15, 15 what happens there?
That the disc depth explodes and
explodes because my new blue instance
is actually still very cold, the drive.
So what happened is as soon as it's
hit by the load of the production
database, it's taking ages to recover.
So for.
Four hours.
I was basically struggling with a database
that was not, was underperforming.
And the scary part about that is
that you have nothing you can do.
Thus, you can just wait.
You cannot modify the instance.
You cannot do anything that
is significant at that point.
So let's go close with some, what
I call super simple experiment.
I said before, I want to save a
hundred thousand records in a database.
So let's do that experiment.
And that's why I want to do
it because I want to test.
Couple of simple things I want to
say is the Aurora faster than RDS?
For my SQL, is my SQL better than
Maria DB is I one really better
or worse than IO two Express?
I want to do just simple
comparison and to stick.
I decide to use a setup of 400
gigabytes, so I have 12,000 iops on.
GP P three and GP P two.
I use an Insta Co comparable
on Aurora and RDS.
So in this case I use R seven G large.
It is the smallest instance I
could use on my credits that
they want to spend too much.
But you might wonder how you,
let's say, okay, I insert one
meter record or a hundred thousand
records, whatever you want, and I
want to insert one record at a time.
Those are my only rules.
It depends because otherwise you
say it depends how you insert and
you can load 1 million records.
No, I want to insert, I'm using.
Interaction one, one at a time.
I want to use a single thread.
So no, not a pool, nothing fancy, and
I want to still stick to assets, so I'm
not loading my data in a single query.
So you might still say it depends.
It depends on the CPU,
it depends on the table.
It depends on the storage of
memory, on latency, on version,
on which database engine.
You're on the developer how you implement
your logic, so let's even simplify more.
I want to ask you the question otherwise.
So let's say I create a simple table
and my table as simply a data time
and a value, and I just load my a
hundred thousand record because I
don't want to load more than that
because it will take too long or.
Or not, I don't know.
And call the Lord demo.
Why do I do it?
With function?
It's simply, it's a simple experiment.
If I do it with function, the cool
thing is that there's no latency.
There's no nothing.
It's just that function.
So the question I have
is, how long does it take?
Seconds, minutes, many seconds.
I dunno.
Simple.
Let's compare the execution of
this one on the different one.
So I'm using the C large, it's gonna take
milliseconds, hour, seconds, minutes.
We could do a demo, but we
have no time for a demo life.
So here are my results on RDS is 0 39.
It takes five minutes and 49 seconds.
Now, Aurora 2.7 seconds.
What?
2.7 second versus five minutes?
Something wrong there.
I'm just using the full
configuration and I'm doing mostly
a. Experiment makes no sense.
It's, I'm inserting user function, 1
million record from the server anyway.
The difference here is the server.
But is that true?
Yes, it's actually true.
If you do my demo and you look at the
time, you count the record, you have 1
million record, you have a minimum, the
time and a maximum target is different.
So they being inserted one
at a time and, so well, cool.
Any difference between MariaDB and my sql?
Actually no, that's the same time.
And the reason it's pretty
simple, the difference here is
just really the storage layer.
The main difference between Aurora
and RDS is the storage layer.
Will you get the 60 per benefit
using real production workload?
Absolutely not.
The latency and other components
multi try, are gonna make.
Very different result.
The reason I did that experiment was
to show that you really need to be
careful when you trust benchmarks
unless you know who is doing that.
This Maria DB versus you can see the
counter second is similar around the
experiment twice, and that's the,
you can see that the time are very
similar, iops, again, the logic, but.
I say I want to test the third case.
And the third case is IO two.
Block express for me, shown
critical is the new version
of IO two that was announced.
Now, one year ago.
Is that better?
I one, because they say in the
announcement they say something
that is pretty cool that is faster.
So same price.
So if I switch from a one to IO two.
For 1 million record, I go from
five minutes to two minutes
20 for the very same price.
Quite a big difference
considering that as well.
I'm using the same concept, RDS instance.
There's no difference
engine, no difference.
Anything else.
And if you look at the what you
really see that difference, the
number of record per second is, so
what's the key point of this one?
Is that.
Switch from IO one to IU two whenever
you can, because you probably
don't get that two per benefit.
But you definitely see a big difference
on IO one for the same price.
So I'd like to close with a
simple question that I offered.
Are you really noted
database administrator well?
I'm not, but I argue that on many
service on AWS or any cloud provider,
you actually need to be a database.
This is a cool slide that was
shared by Amazon many years ago,
but I still think it's relevant.
The data database message of time spent
on premises is mostly on the platform
access and very little application
level on RDS as a database administrator
spend most of the time looking at
performance Inside cloud was you actually.
Able to help the developer, optimize
the application and as well the database
sche and you do some money, but you
hardly have any, you don't care too much
about the assets and platform level.
So what are the key
takeaways of this session?
First one things I learned the hard
way I allocate RDS storage might
take hours of the plan accordingly.
RDS is a man service, but
logs, performance schema
parameter are all available.
So yeah, it's a man service, but you
can still look under the, you can still
ask, suffer for some help to understand
what's going on behind the scene.
Avoid changing parameter group
setting for short term gain.
You may need to scale your data.
That's what I say about
Graviton, for example, is.
Try not to over optimize.
Yes, it's good to optimize
for your specific use case,
but always think long term.
Those short term optimization, layered
back, validate can stress that you have
you're finding with AWS operating have
as well access to the backend of your
database, not to your data, but how
the database run to the file system.
So that helps a lot.
Warm up your database replica.
Super important before
directing traffic to it.
The storage might still be cold, eh,
cost optimization is important, but don't
focus only on the CP eastern size, but
think as well about backups and storage.
And finally you can get crazy
result doing some simple benchmarks.
So approach any benchmark
cautiously and think.
What's the reason between
behind that matrix and what
message they want to sell you?
But if I have to summarize the entire
presentation in a single message, I will
simply say leverage manage databases.
So take advantage of them.
Resist changes.
So apply them cautiously.
Think that default exists for a
purpose, but almost all try to
understand what runs under the hood.
It's not an excuse that they're
managed to ignore what's happening yet.
There's no magic understanding
what's happening behind.
It's gonna help you have
a successful deployment.
With that one, a big thank you.
It has been a pleasure.
Goodbye.