Hello everyone.
Thank you for being here today.
I'll be presenting on a topic scaling
conversational AI, SRE, challenges
and solution for high availability.
CCA. Systems.
C. CA systems are increasingly used
to handle millions, even billions
of customer interactions every day.
These systems, power virtual
agents, automated chat responses,
voice recognitions, and much more.
With this scale, reliability
becomes absolutely critical.
In this session, we have explored the
unique site Reliability Engineering
Challenges in CCAI and the proven
strategies to overcome them from
observability frameworks and
automated remediation to progressive
rollouts and chaos testing.
I'm excited to share the practical lessons
and battle tested techniques that can help
build more resilient AI driven platform.
The CCA reliability challenge.
Let's start by understanding the scale
and constraints we operate under.
In CCA systems, we aim for 99.99% uptime.
That's just over five minutes
of downtime per month.
This is a non negotiated standard for
enterprise systems, especially when we
are dealing with customer interaction.
The key requirement is latency.
Our target is maximum of 300
milliseconds response time.
This is incredibly tight for
systems powered by heavy NLP models
and multi-service dependencies.
With automation, we've been able to
reduce MTTR mean time to recovery by 73%,
which is a huge win in improving customer
experience and operational efficiency.
Unlike traditional web apps.
Failures in CCA are immediately visible.
They can frustrat customers
cause escalated and directly
impacting business KPIs.
What makes CCI even more challenging
is the unpredictable nature of traffic
and the complex of above integrations
like cms, speech systems, third party
APIs, et cetera, plus the AI model
themselves are not easy to interpret.
They are black boxes in many ways.
This all add ups to a very unique
reliability challenge, which we'll
be discussing in the next slide.
Traditional monitoring limitations.
Traditional monitoring tools were
never built with AI systems in mind.
For instance, transformer based
and LP models, which power intent,
recognition and response generations
are essentially black boxes.
We can't inspect their
internal states easily.
Tools that work well with
microservices often fail here.
Another big problem is load patents.
CCA systems don't follow
typical usage trends.
You might have traffic spikes during
product launches, seasonal sales,
or even random social media trends,
threshold base electing doesn't work
well because it can't predict or
adapt to these irregular patterns.
Then there is issue of
complex dependency chains.
Again, a CA sessions might involve
APIs, databases, voice engines,
third party integrations, et cetera.
A small failure in one backend can
ripple through their entire AI stack,
and traditional monitoring might
not have been able to detect this.
That's why we had to build a new
AI observability model, which will
be discussing in the next slide.
CCA observability framework.
To solve these gaps, we developed a four
layer observability framework tailored
for CCA systems, one business impact
metrics like conversation, completion
rates, and c, a customer satisfaction.
These tell us if users are
getting what they need.
Two model performance metrics.
We track intent, accuracy, fallback rate.
And entity extraction quality.
These gives us insights into
how well the NLP models are
performing system performance.
Here we look at latency, error
rate, throughputs, et cetera.
These are all a traditional ARI
metrics for infrastructure health.
This is about CPU memory,
discus H, and system saturation.
By combining all of these,
we can map a symptom.
Like an increase in fallback response to
its root cause, whether it's a model drift
back in slowdown or infrastructure issue.
This observability model helps
bridge the gap between business
impact and technical telemetry.
Moving on to the next slide,
automated remediation strategies.
Now even with great observability
incidents will happen.
So our next priority is
automated remediation.
Reducing the recovery
time when things go wrong.
Our process starts with anomaly detection
using ML based pattern recognition.
This lets us spot unusual conversation
flows or system metrics in real time.
Then we triage and classify the issue
automatically based on patterns we
learned over time, like intern re
degradation or resource starvation.
Once classified, we trigger
a remediation action.
This might involve scaling up,
rerouting the traffic, throttling,
or even restarting specific services.
And finally, we have a feedback loop.
Each incident teaches a system
something new every time, improving
future detection and resolutions.
This automated approach has helped us
reducing the MTTR by more than 70%.
Which means user barely
noticed something went wrong.
Scaling strategies for peak loads.
Let's talk about scaling,
particularly during peak loads.
Traffic spikes in CCA systems are
hard to predict, but not impossible.
We use predict auto-scaling to anticipate
these based on historical data and events.
Next, we use token based rotting.
A fine-grained way to control
the number of conversations being
processed, preventing overload, while
prioritizing the high value queries.
We also implement conversation shading,
distributing different conversations
to different clusters or chats, so no
single resource pool gets overwhelmed.
And during extreme loads, we
use model optimizations like
switching to lightweight models.
Or reducing precision temporarily
to maintain responsiveness.
All of this helps escape latency
under 300 milliseconds, even
during 10 x traffic bursts.
Moving on to the next
slide, common CCA patents.
Through our operational experience, we
identified several recurring failure
patterns, unique to CCIA, again,
intent classification, degradation.
This often happens gradually.
A new product name or slang throws off
the model and accuracy drops over time.
Latency amplification cascades a
small backend delay gets compounded.
As a AI pipeline processes
laing to exponential latency.
We resource starvation.
A single edge case user query
might consume excessive memory
or CPU affecting all sessions.
Dependency chain failures.
When a single external API or a
backend service goes down, it can take
down the entire conversational flow.
Knowing these patterns helps us
build better detection, alerting,
and chaos testing frameworks, which
will be discussing in the next slide.
Chaos engineering.
This brings us to chaos
engineering, but with a twist.
One that's tailored for ai.
Our goal is to proactively test
what happens when things go wrong
in the AI layer, specifically,
not just infrastructure.
Again, we stimulate scenarios like
corrupted conversation, memory,
misclassified intents in a sequential
order, or even model component
failure due to memory overflow.
Again.
Now the process involves of
performing hypothesis about.
Failure modes, designing targeted
chaos experiments, executing them with
safety controls, and then analyzing
the results and hardening the system.
This AI focused chaos engineering
help us prevent unknown failure modes
from surprising as in a production
progressive deployment models.
All models evolve fast.
But deploying them safely
is also very crucial.
So we use progressive
deployment modes first.
We do shadow testing where a new
model runs alongside production
but doesn't serve real users.
We compare results quietly.
Next we move to a candidate deployment.
We are, a small slices of traffic is
routed to the new model where we monitor
closely again, then we gradually expand.
Traffic based on performance metrics
and confidence level, often adjusting
during business hours to minimize
the impact if anything goes wrong.
We have automated rollback
mechanisms in place.
Once we validated everything,
we move to a full deployment.
This stage rollout ensure we
are innovating safely without
affecting the end user experience.
Moving on to the next slide.
SLIs and SLOs for cost optimization.
Let's now talk about how we balance
performance with cost SLOs or
service level objectives don't
just help ensure reliability.
They also help us avoid over provisioning,
but carefully tracking metrics like
response latency, query throughput,
resource utilization, and intent accuracy.
We can right size our infrastructure.
For example, if a model performs just
as well with 50% fewer GPUs during off
peak hours, that's a massive cost saving.
Across the board, we've seen 30 to 40%
cost optimization by aligning SLOs with
actual user needs and system capacities.
Moving on to the next slide.
Building reliable CCAI.
Key takeaways.
To wrap up, here are the key takeaways
for building reliable CCA systems.
Observability must include AI
specific and business level
metrics, not just CPUs and memories.
Automation is key.
Self feeling systems
drastically reduce downtime.
Use balanced SLOs to avoid
unnecessary cost or refer while
still maintaining a great experience.
Finally, a progressive deployment.
Progressive deployments are very
critical for rolling out changes
without breaking user flows.
These strategies help us build systems
that are both innovative and reliable.
The foundation for enterprise
scale conversational ai.
Thank you all for your time and attention.
I hope the session gave you a useful
insight into unique reliability
challenges of conversational AI systems
and how SRE principles can address them.
I'm happy to take any questions
or feel free to connect with me
later for deeper discussions.
Let's continue building AI that's
not only smart, but also resilient,
scalable, and productivity.
Thank you all.
Bye-bye.