Good morning, afternoon, everyone.
Thank you for joining me.
Today we are going to explore a
key shift in how we approach system
monitoring and incident management.
As distributed systems grow in
complexity, traditional monitoring
methods are simply not enough.
Today we will see how a powered
observability, specifically
with Splunk, can help us.
Beyond reactive troubleshooting
and into the realm of predictive
sub minute incident resolution.
By the end of the session, you'll
have a deeper understanding of how
to improve system reliability, reduce
downtime, and take control of incidents
before they affect your users.
Let's dive in.
The observability challenge.
Today's distributed architecture have
triggered an observability crisis.
Traditional siloed monitoring tools
produce floods of uncorrelated
alerts, leaving IT teams were and
struggling to respond effectively.
Modern systems generate vast
volumes of metrics, logs and
traces, but capturing the right
data in context is the first hurdle.
Detecting meaningful patterns across
diverse signals is increasingly difficult,
and without intelligent correlation,
alerts remain noise rather than insect.
The real challenge is turning the
data into actionable insights,
ensuring observability translates into
better performance and resilience.
The evolution of observability in
the early 20 century monitoring
was about basic metrics like
CPU usage, memory, or the space.
It was reactive, just an alert.
When thresholds were crossed in 2000
tens, locks became central to debugging
with tools like ELK and Splunk.
Aggregating them for better visibility,
but locks were still siloed.
Then in 2010, sorry, we saw the shift.
To full observability, not just about
what's happening but why it's happening.
Bringing metrics, logs, and traces
together, providing richer insights today.
Yay.
Powered observability
takes it even further.
Analyzing trends, predictive failures,
and even initiating automated responses.
Moving us from reactive to
proactive incident management.
Observability as a strategic imperative.
Most 94% of enterprises now consider
digital services critical to their
core business, reflecting how
essential software and infrastructure
are to delivering customer value.
Eight 54% of organizations still lack.
Full stack observability.
Without comprehensive visibility across
infrastructure, applications, and user
experiences, teams struggle to detect,
diagnose, and fix problems quickly.
This lead to downtime, lost revenue,
and damages damaged customer impact.
The good news organizations embracing
a powered observability have reduced
their mean time to resolution by 45%,
and those with mature practices are
seeing a 3.5 times return on investment.
Observability has evolved beyond it.
It's now a strategic capability
driving business performance.
Observability platform.
Splunk uses machine learning to
detect anomalies across different
data layers in the metrics layer.
It learns normal behavior over time,
like memory usage or request rates,
and adjust thresholds automatically.
Whereas in the log layer, it
analyzes patterns using NLP.
To spot rare or unexpected log
entries like authentication failures.
And in the traces layer, it detects
abnormal latencies or service hubs
in microservices, which helps to
spot issues before they escalate.
The real power comes when these
anomalies are correlated across layers.
For example, a spike in response time.
Tied to an error log burst and traced
back to the slow backend microservice
instead of just more alerts coming from
all the systems, Splunk gives you cross
layer visibility, reducing investigation
time, and increasing understanding.
Once the pattern is detected,
Splunk can automatically execute
remediation actions like tree
starting service or scaling resources.
Automatic remediation with yay.
Power observability isn't
just about directing problems,
it's about taking action.
When a pattern is detected,
automated remediation can kick in.
This is where playbooks and intelligent
decision making comes into play.
For example, if there is a spike
in CPU usage, the system might
scale resources automatically.
Start service if it detects
degraded performance.
DA doesn't just stop there.
It learns from past incidents improving
its ability to respond to future issues.
In complex environments like Kubernetes
or hybrid clouds, this proactive
approach is crucial in ensuring minimal
downtime as and faster recovery times.
Let's dive into technical architecture
data collection.
We started the source data collection,
Splunk universal forwarders and
lightweight agents designed for reliable
log forwarding from on-prem systems.
For metrics and tracers, we leverage open
telemetry and open source vendor neutral
standard that allows deep instrumentation
across apps and infrastructure.
Splunk also supports out of the box
integration with cloud services like
AWS, Azure and GCP, making it seamless
to ingest data from cloud native sources.
As the data is gathered, now
we need to process the pipeline
process using pipeline, sorry.
Once the data is ingested, it
enters Splunk processing pipeline.
Here we perform field
extraction and enrichment.
Adding context like geolocation,
device info and mode normalization
ensures that regardless of the
source, your data is structured.
And searchable in a unified format.
Then we inject correlation IDs, which
are essential for tying logs, metrics,
and traces together across services.
This allows true end-to-end observability.
The AI L layer, this is where
the intelligence kicks in.
The A ML layer starts
with feature extraction.
Identifying signals from noise.
Splunk then applies pattern recognition
models to baseline system behavior Over
time when deviations occur, anomaly
detection engine alerts you often before
users even notice something wrong.
Visualization and response, whatever
we have process now becomes actionable.
Splunk offers rich real-time dashboards
that display KPI, error rates,
service latency, and more automated
alerting routes, insights to the
right teams via Slack or PagerDuty,
or email or any alerting mechanism.
And with remediation workflows,
you can go a step further
regarding scripts or runbooks to
fix common issues automatically.
Here the Splunk strength
we should consider.
Splunk is built for massive scalable
to handle millions of events per second
without compromising query performance.
The system is distributed for all
tolerant and optimized for high ingestion
environments, which makes it strong fit
for enterprise grade observability needs.
Feature selection and model tuning.
When building AI models for observability,
what we feed into the model is just
as important as how we tune it.
We go beyond basic metrics
like CPU and memory.
We combine signals from infrastructure,
application, behavior, user interactions,
and business performance to get the
complete picture of system health.
A good model needs careful tuning.
If it's too sensitive, you get noise.
If it's too specific, you
miss out real problems.
We refine our models using real
world failures, improving accuracy
and reducing false alarms over time.
Let's look at a case study
of an e-commerce company
during their annual sales event.
Traffic spikes to 10 times.
Its regular volume.
Critical services like payment
processing comes under immense pressure.
Using Yay powered observability.
The team trained machine learning models
on normal operating behavior and potential
failure patterns as traffic client
yay detected a bottleneck in payment
processing, which detected 15 minutes
earlier than traditional alerting system
would've triggered Autoscaling actions
this earlier.
Helped prevent a slow checkout
process that could have cost
2.3 million in lost sales.
This shows how a driven observability
can turn data into real time
actionable insights to prevent
issues before impacting the business
building autonomous remediation workflows.
Now let's explore autonomous remediation.
It starts with anomaly detection,
using machine learning algorithms to
spot deviations in system behavior.
Next, the system performs root cause
analysis, leveraging correlation
engines to identify the cost of issues.
Once the cause is determined, the system
selects the appropriate remediation
response based on the historical data.
For example, if scaling resources
worked in the past, it might
trigger that action again.
The system then executes
these actions automatically.
Finally, after the remediation, the system
verifies the results, gathering feedback
to continuously improve its responses.
This learning loop.
Allows the system to handle more complex
incidents automatically over time.
Implementation framework To implement
AI powered observability, we start
in identifying critical services and
defining instrumentation standards.
This ensures that data collection
is consistent and comprehensive.
We also set data retention policies
to balance cost and compliance.
On the technical side, we deploy
correlation agents, configuring
data pipelines, and build service
map to visualize dependencies.
We implement machine learning
models to detect anomalies and
align our observability data
with incident management process.
This framework is designed to provide
incremental value at each stage.
From initial data collection
to full maturity, which takes
about four to six months.
Next steps on your observability journey.
Start by assessing your current maturity
using an online tool to identify
gaps in your observability practices.
With this assessment, you can
develop a tailored strategy
to enhance your observability.
Next.
We recommend running a pilot project in
the targeted area demonstrating quick
wins while minimizing risk as you scale.
Building internal capabilities through
training ensures long-term success.
Our team is here to help guide you
through these steps, ensuring you maximize
the value of a powered observability
and make your system more resilient.
I should talk about the challenges.
Like any technology, yay, power
observability has its own challenge.
Implementing this solution requires
solid data strategy integration
with existing systems and continuous
tuning to ensure accuracy.
Additionally, there may be an initial
learning curve as team adjusts to the
predictive nature of AI power tools.
A power observability with Splunk
can revolutionize how we manage
monitor modern distributed systems.
By moving from reactive monitoring to
predictive management, we can not only
reduce instant resolution time, but
also improve the overall reliability
and performance of water systems.
Thank you for your time today.