Hi everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon,
good evening, wherever the
location that you're joining.
In the session, we are gonna talk about
how can we get a single pane of view of
all the telemetry data that collected
in the enterprise digital landscape.
How can we get a unified view of
all the entire IT landscape so that.
We can easily, quickly detect the
problems and we don't have to switch
between the tools and see what is
affecting the performance and stability
of an IT systems so that we can
spend more time in innovating rather
than finding where the problem is.
So in this session, we are
gonna talk about open source
tool, like Open Telemetry and
also using the Grafana stack.
How can we achieve this unified already?
Okay.
Let's dive into.
What are these unified
help can we achieve?
Quick introduction about me.
I am, I'm a co-founder of Gohar Tech,
where we provide SRE as a service.
I also have our 20 years of IT
experience where performed various roles,
architecture consulting, performance
engineering, set up SRE landscape
at SRE team for big enterprises.
Also we've got the patent in risk
management, risk assessment with respect
to reliability and change management.
Also, one more patent filed.
I'm also an active speaker in the
Chaos Con, so also contribute to
open source community as well.
Okay.
Let's directly get into the
evaluation of observability.
So we talk about monitoring in the
earlier days, but now we started
talking about observability.
The first version of observability.
It's like foundation for all.
I. Modern application development.
And this really helps to
understand the system behavior.
When we write a code we have
an infrastructure there are
middleware components in it.
So this really helps us to gain some
visibility into the IT infrastructure
and the application as well.
So what are the characteristics?
And the components like metrics is
one of the key aspect of observability
on 0.0 where metrics is like
more mostly a time series data.
For example, like a latency or throughput
or error or even the backend system or
infrastructure, CPU, resource utilization,
memory disk, and so on and so forth.
Traces.
This really helps us to troubleshoot
any of these latency or error
problems call tree kind of view.
Where, when there, in the run time, when
there is a transaction or an API or task
getting executed, what are the different
methods and the different services?
What are the things being
actually called that?
How much time it took, how
many times being called?
So this really helps to
capture those information.
And logs.
It's a traditional way where both
system level logs or application level
logs, where whatever the information
we wanna share to the analyzers
or whatever the information that
system is spacing at this point.
It could be informational troubleshooting
purposes are error are feral.
The profiling.
This is also getting added as one of the
signals in Absorbability earlier days.
This was not is one of this is only
for applicable for lower environments
or non-production environments where
the sampling is gonna, is very higher.
So it's gonna affect the performance of
the system if we run in production scale.
But as, as soon as that, after the
Google's dapper algorithm came in,
our team actually found a really
how can we do it in a lightweight
and for production scale system.
So this, there's like advanced level
of tracing is this actually provide
minute level of information in terms of
CPO, how the memory blocks are getting
allocated from which line of code.
So this really helps to solve
a lot of memory leak problems.
So in, in a recent observer
teams, we see a continuous
profiling with EVPF coming in.
It captures all the
cannel level statistics.
What are the things getting
executed and really helps to
troubleshoot code level problems.
I. User monitoring.
So just to understand
instead of a synthetic.
So just how the actual users are
facing the how their experiences
are while using the system.
So this really helps to understand
the user behavior and experience.
Application performance management.
This is there for a while.
So which provides capability of
all these other things we saw.
But this also play vital
role in getting the runtime.
Apart from these, getting a runtime
visibility, if the Java application, how
the Java heap utilization is, how many
threads are there, connection, pooling
and all, if it's a goal and application,
how many sub proteins are span, but
how the ang memory is being used.
So it gives more
visibility apart from this.
So now it can.
Think about, we have all the relevant
signals are capabilities and observability
1.0, but are we in this right path?
Are we using observability 1.0?
Let's see, what are the
characteristics of this?
So we talked about all these things, but.
The challenge here is that it's all
siloed tools, so we have to have
multiple tools to measure individual
characteristics like metrics.
We have to use separate tools, for
example, like Prometheus collector
or our specific agent, which collects
inform metrics and so on, so forth.
Traces like open tracing or open telemetry
just to collect our Eger or zipkin
just to collect the traces alone and
inject it to the backend and the logs.
Any framework which actually helps
to gather the logs and events.
Profiling.
And again, separate tools are separate
instrumentation, radio user monitoring,
again, like amp for any JS application
or any other instrumentation or
agentic base to collect the radio user
monitoring and the APMs a as well.
So these are mostly silos.
Some of them are club together
to get the unified view and
mostly it's a reactive approach.
So we usually capture these
after the fact of some of the
incidental issues already started.
And limited and no correlation.
So that's a gap of this
observability on 0.0.
And it leads a lot of manual analysis
because of the cellular tool.
So we have to look multiple
tools to do a correlation and
find out where the problem is.
So now it get into deeper.
Silo data we saw, I saw about it.
It's really data silos really the
hindering of a ho holistic view.
So we cannot get an end-to-end
picture even in the traces
if you're not collecting the
data from across the system.
So it'll still the manual
correlation needs to be done.
And so limited insights.
So if, even if we don't, instrument
any one of the component of the layer.
So we will not get a complete
end-to-end visibility.
So then if there is any problem
happens, it's hard to troubleshoot.
It's a black box.
So that's when the observability 2.0 was
born, where it really helps to elevate
the insights in the digital ecosystem.
So it, when there is a system with like
thousands of microservices really helps
to understand where exactly the problem
is and how to troubleshoot and fix it.
Where it come, whatever the
signals are, what are the
characteristics of observing at 2.0?
But it brings more context to the
traces where it, it gives a, where.
This request is originated from,
so where we'll have a parent-child
relationship and adds more attributes
or dimensions to those executions.
So it really helps to find out if you
wanna get a trace of this particular
user at this particular order.
It'll be easy.
The context really helps to find
out a little down those levels.
And events.
So logs mostly it's like unstructured
unless otherwise we follow some templates.
Like we have access logs, have the Apache
format and but at the backend, most of
the container logs, unless otherwise we
enforce it, it's gonna be like formatted.
So that's when the events really
helps to do a key value pair with
the formative structure of data.
When there is a critical events
or change in the system happening,
really helps to correlate the issues.
Next, next level to the
real user monitoring, the
user experience monitoring.
So this really helps to understand
as soon as we receive the
data, the UI receive the data.
So how much time it takes to enter the
frame, and how much time it takes for each
of those activity that you ui is doing.
So how the, what is the real user
experience is when they do the
action or when, app start time
mac crashes and handle exceptions.
The data stream.
This is another important with the recent
AI ml world where we deal with like
terabytes and petabytes of data and also
with Kafka streams and all with a lot of
events processing through, especially in
the iot kind of systems where how can we
get deep insights and visibility into it.
So this really gives a
separate perspective with that.
Business metrics.
This is another important, so other than
user experience, we also need to measure,
get the business insights to it so we
can make some data driven decisions.
So like how many artists being
made, how like different.
The user is coming and viewing the
product, but what is a conversion rate?
So whether he's gonna do a checkout
and make a price like order $2, how
much time and how much percentage
of users getting converted.
So those kind of critical metrics.
So if there is any dropouts and what
is a reason for it, if there is any
technical reason or is something else.
So this really helps
to gain those insights.
And alerts in the traditional way.
We mostly set a threshold based, which is
not scalable and in a dynamic environment.
So sometimes you tend to miss
some of these gaps, especially
when the business metrics and all.
So that's where the composite alarm
really helps to avoid these alert static
and reduce the alerts to noise ratio.
So really combine those when
there is an incident happen.
So if multiple layers are
failing, so we're gonna not
gonna have multiple alerts, it's
gonna combine and have a single.
Alarm and really helps
to focus the problem.
So with this, what are we gaining?
The characteristics of 2.0 E helps us
to provide a single source of truth.
Obviously, with the context and formatted
events, we can quickly troubleshoot
or filter out only what we need.
And really with the open telemetry
and open standards and the agents,
we really have low code or no code
instrumentation to get the data.
We'll see what what are those
instrumentation types, how to do
it, and also open standards and
interoperability really helps to have
a kind of no vendor locking situation.
And it also, it's a cloud agnostic
where it can, it'll really
support both on-premise or hybrid
or cloud native environments.
And the absorb funnel I just
touched upon a little earlier.
So when there is any.
Digital ecosystem or digital
IT application runs on any
underlying infrastructure platform.
The absorbability really
helps to capture the capacity,
utilization and saturation level.
So this is the very foundation where
all the code gets executed in binaries
and on top of it we'll have all these.
Downstream systems where data re
resides, where we need to capture
durability, consistency, integrity,
and also recovery aspects.
If you want to have a high availability
solution, scalable solution, on top
of it, we'll have a connector layer,
middleware layer, which actually needs to
propagate the context and also provides.
The resilience view, how the health
of the downstream, do we have a right
circuit baker, a fallback retrace pattern.
So this really helps to get that
perspective of it, that health
of the backend, of downstream
systems on top of connector.
Actual origin of these
business logic are a PA calls.
We mostly measure the golden
signals, the latency throughput
at a rate and saturation level.
Real actual a PA consumers from the web
website or an app site to where it'll
have a get the customer journey map.
So what are the different activity
customers are doing so that we
can get real actions happening in
the app in terms of business usage
and also what users are seeing.
And all the, apart from all these
technical stuff, the on top of
it, the funnel, we have a business
metrics where we'll get clear
visibility into the business
functions and what are the outcomes.
So the idea for this funnel is when
there is a. Drop in the business, or
when the user's complaining about some
of the things not working or not working
as expected, then we need to correlate
to any one of these technical layers.
So that is the intention of this funnel.
So to have a mostly composite
metrics or alarms, and also
to gain visibility of business
interruptions due to any technical
failures or technical challenges.
So this will definitely help us
to have a reliable, resilience,
scalable and SE secure platform.
So now let's get into how can we
achieve this single source of truth?
The reference observability architecture,
I would say, where we have the target IT
system where instrument using the no-code,
low-code agents are the SDKs, which.
Send the telemetry signals to the
data collector in the periodic
interval so the data collector will
receive and, converts and sends it
to the data pipeline where this is
where actual data massaging happens.
Where pipeline not only combines data,
add relevant additional context to it
which cluster it is running on, and
additional masking if there is any
sensitive PI information is there.
We wanna mask it.
And convert it into any other format where
the data lake accepts any common format.
Like it doesn't accept key value there.
It's a column, store column or store.
It's a time series store.
If you wanna split that or if you
want to convert that, it'll also
happen during, in the pipeline site.
Once the data getting converted and it's
ready to store, then it'll be pumped
into enterprise telemetry data lake.
So this is where all the
telemetry signals come and stored
in a single source of truth.
That's where we'll not have a different
perspective, different time zones all
these problems that we usually face
Earlier, we'll have all the signals
like metrics, traces, logs, events
profiling, even profiling data,
and also all the front end business
insights data, user experience data.
So this really helps us to visualize
so we can get a single pane of view.
Not only that, but also helps
us to create a composite alarms.
If there is any standard
DVR anomaly detected.
Really it helps us to correlate
where the issue happens.
And also really helps to run those
synthetics to make sure we try
to capture if even user sees it.
So if there any chance to capture
it earlier and also helps us to
set the, define the SLO thresholds
and also helps to track those SLOs.
And not only that, it also helps to.
Make data recommendations, or since the
data is in a single place, it really
helps to run these ML R Foundation
models to understand the data and
really helps to solve the problems.
Now let's talk about open telemetry.
It's a open standard and it's
is, as everyone knows, a second
project in CNCF, how does it really
help us to get the unified view?
So this is cloud NATO and really helps
to avoid any vendor lacking situation.
So once, we're all instrumented.
So wherever we wanna store
the data really supports it.
And it supports 20 different languages.
For all the four different signals.
They provide what is the later state
of individual programming languages.
And instrumentation is where we, it's
really key where there are, we start out
low code and no-code instrumentation.
So open telemetry supports
most of the language commonly
used languages like Golan.
Java our python with auto instrumentation.
But one challenge is auto instrumentation
really provides us all the coverage
for all the HGTP modules or any
other GRPC based any calls that
it makes between the se services.
So it really helps to auto capture these
information like metrics, cases, and logs.
But but if you want to have a
business insights or business metrics.
Our business events.
So that's where we have to touch a
code a little bit, add an SDK way
of having things get some custom
metrics added or trace and the spans.
So then we need to have
additional lines of code in there.
So otherwise it really supports
the low code just simply through a
couple of lines of configurations
and bring the binary into a model,
and it automatically captures this.
Typically it's like an agent
based instrumentation, how these
traditional a PM tools work.
But the code is really going to
give more granular level details
and additional information.
So once we instrument, the next step
is to collect and correlating the data.
So this Open Telemetry agents really
collect the telemetry and send it
to the Open Telemetry collectors.
Where it actually helps to I'll process
the data and store it into a data lake.
Then the correlation really happens
by leveraging all the metrics.
So when the, when there is a high latency
span absorbed, then it can really give a
correlation of what is a. Actual service
resource utilization at that time.
What was the services
latencies during that time?
Is it only for this particular request
or it was al already performing poor?
What was the error rate?
So it really helps us to give the
contextualize view for a single
pane and really provide unified
view of the system behavior.
And with the help of this context
of, with the custom attributes, we
can even really filter the traces of
spans specific to that particular.
Customer attribute.
Maybe it's a customer email or
a customer id or order ID or
whatever the business attribute is.
And once we have all these data coming in,
the correlation, and so it really helps to
visualize the traces, metrics, and logs.
And Grafana.
Grafana is a wonderful visualization tool.
Lot of the prebuilt dashboards are there.
So we really provide us a single
pane view of all traces, metrics,
logs, and profiles as well.
So it, it also give an interactive
exploration where if you want
to drill down further so you
see a specific anomaly there.
So it really helps us
to further drill down.
It provide hyperlinks to other
views and dashboard and also
helps to build a custom dashboard.
There are plenty of dashboards
available in JSON format, so we don't
have to build new one, especially
for tech common technologies like.
Kafka or Kubernetes or any
cloud specific services.
So a lot of things are out
there, especially for Linex.
I've seen this very big dashboard
which covers entire Linex stack.
So really useful.
So it's ever growing so that it
definitely provide a contextual,
unified, single pane view.
And Grafana also growing.
They've had a lot of other stacks as well.
So this is the complete RAF absorbability
stack where it collects through the agents
through like a Prometheus exporter for any
metrics or open telemetry or affluent bit.
It collects into the
open telemetry collector.
They own open telemetry collector
and also stores in Tinder.
LGTM stack are low key for logs,
Grafana for visualization, tempo
for traces and MiiR for metrics.
And also it provides a continuous
profiling through pyro scope.
So once we have all these data stored
in these data lakes be, definitely
will have a complete visibility.
So we'll have application
observability, which front ends,
and also calculate the service map.
So provide service map views
and through the traces.
Also give EVP of perspective for how
the profiling happens and what are the
hotspots there, and provide infras,
absorbability to fall Kubernetes from
the server VMs or databases, or any
cloud native integrations as well.
And it really helps to have a incident
management in terms of providing
alerting capability on-call support
and for incident tracking and also
even the service level objectives.
So apart from this to shift left and
really the case, it's really helps us
to simulate the load in terms of backend
as well as for the browser testing.
So definitely it's a unified single
place to go for this observability stack.
And it also integrates with a lot of
other big data sources where once the
collection layer there, if you don't wanna
manage these data, we can really ship to
all the commercial products out there.
So now the empowering alerting
and incident response.
So these alerting is very key
there for timely incident response.
So this really helps us to, the
composite alerts really helps us to
have a rules based and multiple data
sources combining into a single alerting
system so that it really helps us
to avoid these alerts to nice ratio.
And also really helps us to automate
root cause analysis to the integrations
with web hooks really helps us to
trigger a workflow where it can go
and look at, based on the knowledge
graphs and the service maps to find
out in the ecosystem or in the chain
of events, what exactly gone wrong
what is anomalies or correlation, and
provided the RCA as soon as possible.
So with these Absorbability 2.0,
what is the future of Absorbability?
So definitely to accelerate the
innovation where the time to detect
and time to isolate and time to
recover is gonna be shorter and shorter
With these tools, definitely really
helps to accelerate the innovation.
The unified absorbability, definitely
the single source of truth is going to
empower to make the data driven decisions.
Intelligent automation.
This really with the evaluation
of a Agentic frameworks and a and
mission learning, really helps to
detect the anomaly and trigger a
workflow for quick Auto RCA and
even do the runbook automation, or
having it self-healing system built.
It auto recovers itself.
And also let's not forget
about the security aspects.
So it really helps to analyze those audit
trails and events, to have a security
threads and vulnerabilities by detecting
the behavior and pattern analysis and
really helps us to find, find any security
threads and vulnerabilities there.
That hope you've learned something today.
Thanks so much for joining us and
if you have any follow up questions
and feel, Brad, please connect me
over LinkedIn and thank you so much
and have a good rest of your day.