Hello everyone.
This is Akala.
As you guys know, mainframes has been
around in multiple industries over,
over the last couple of decades.
They have been supporting with very
robustness, scalable, and have been
supporting operations, like financial
transactions, insurance processing,
healthcare transactions, and all of that.
But however, at some point we have to
modernize these mainframe applications.
The, and the best way possible is right
now to use an AI powered approach.
And basically see how AI is basically
enhancing the reliability in this
legacy trans system transformation.
I. As enterprises continue to rely
on mainframes for mission critical
applications, AI basically offers
groundbreaking approaches to modernize
these application, these systems,
while maintaining operation stability.
Today we are going to talk about
what are the different technologies
and tools AI basically offers to
enable this transformation journey
and focus primarily on the reliable
engineering principles as we do that.
As you can see, that, there are some
key features from AI that, that are used
as part of this transformation journey,
which is automated code analysis,
intelligence testing, predictive
monitoring, and showcasing how these site
liability engineers teams harness these
capabilities to ensure that seamless this
transition is seamlessly done even in
the most critical environments possible.
Now let's talk about some of the
challenges that we encounter when
during this modernization process.
One is the legacy dependencies.
There's a lot of logic and code built
over the years that with limited
documentation that we need to basically
start identifying and tracking down.
We have to, there's very complex
interdependencies between
systems built over decades.
The next would be the knowledge gap.
Most of these mainframe systems
are built based on cobol.
The COBOL is a very obsolete language
today that we don't have the people
with the right skills to manage and
maintain the system or even understand
what the code in the current system is.
The next would be the operational risk.
Since, as we mentioned earlier, that
these mainframe systems are used in very
highly transactional operation systems.
The risk and stakes are very high
when they're during this transaction
and there is downtime required.
The last would be performance.
So when during modernization, the
expectations are usually very high.
That you know the performance should
be subpar in your and to ensure that
it, it outperforms the traditional,
the old legacy transaction system.
But the scale, there are factors,
a scalability that needs to
be taken into concentration.
During these, during this transition.
Transition.
Next would be how AI is
basically enabling us.
To determine how what kind of resources
and scaling that are required for
mi for this specific migration.
As you can see on the graph that we
have three different types of tracking.
One is a traditional tracking method.
That means, traditionally if you don't
use ai, you come up with a prediction
of this is how it's supposed to be
for how it's supposed to be scaled
as part of this modernization.
Second, that in the green you, that you
see that's an AI driven approach wherein
it understands the existing system, tries
to identify the dependencies and gives
you predictability of how much resources
need to be allocated to make this happen.
Then when you start to compare
with the actual usage, you see
that actual usage correlates highly
with how the AI is predicted.
By, by leveraging these AI different
techniques, you can reach accuracy
levels of 95%, 95%, and in very mature
app implementations even the best of the
best traditional, mature implementation,
we achieve only to 60 to 70% accuracy.
Next we talk about basically how
natural language processing is
playing a very key role in trying
to understand, trying to basically
transcript the existing documentation.
So what NLP does is what AI brings
into the picture is it basically can
start to document any kind of manuals,
documentation available and starts
to learn and train itself, and trying
to provide you actionable insights
to determine how reliability and
scalability needs to come into picture.
Then at the same time, as we mentioned
earlier, by reading through this
documentation, it tries to identify
the different dependencies and
starts to create a semantic analysis
and mapping around the different
components of this implementation.
And the last would be knowledge graphing.
The knowledge graphings, basically
trying to create a map around the
different sources of information
identified as part of the documentation.
An LP with AI basically provides us
the capability to, to pass through this
unstructured documentation and provide
you very valuable insights, which are very
key for any kind of migration activity.
Next, let's take a case study, an active
case study, which is implemented out
there in the financial services industry.
So the project scope, as you
can see that it is a 30-year-old
legacy core banking system.
With comprising of around 5.2 million
lines of complex COBOL code and 400
mission critical dependent applications
over the decade, and then there is strict
zero downtime requirement because this
is a financial services environment,
how AI basically enabled this migration.
First, it was able to do
comprehensive automated dependency
mappings as we mentioned earlier.
That using NLP, trying to
understand documentation, trying
to create those semantic mappings,
it was able to achieve that.
Next, next would be to, to
use AI to to generate advanced
predictive incident prevention.
That means you have to understand
how to leverage AI to, to understand
what kind of issues might foresee
while doing a migration activity.
An AI can provide you better tools
and enablement to, to catch ahead
of time and try to save save the
time for debugging and trying to
resolve it ahead of time itself.
The next would be the real time
performance monitoring with alerting.
So while set, while doing
the migration transition of.
Piece by piece or sections
of each of the of the system.
This real time monitoring basically
enabled us to basically start to see
if there is any dip in performance or
new spikes that we are noticing that
we are not aware of, and also generate
alerting alerts to to enable users to
understand where it is going wrong.
And then the last would be this is
the most important critical piece
while doing a migration from one,
from the legacy to a modern system.
The key is testing.
So how manual testing over the years
has always been a skew in entire
project planning and pro project
planning or migration planning.
AI basically enables us to do automated
intelligent test generation, which will
automatically do the testing for us.
While we transition the core
from one system to another, so
the outcome of it, these are the
outcomes that we have encountered.
We have basically reduced 72% in
critical production incidents.
We have mi, we have cut
chart, the migration timeline.
We have 14 months and in overall
cost savings, we have saved on
$4.3 million and 99.998% system.
Our time maintained through,
through throughout this
implementation of this migration.
Next, let's talk about as I mentioned
earlier the criticality of this
testing is very key during any
kind of a migration initiative.
There are four different capabilities
that AI offers during this,
creating a testing framework.
One it gen, it provides you
with this generation capability.
It provides a comprehensive test
scenarios based off the documentation,
the migration, the user stories, the
product documentation, all of that.
Then the automated execution, once the
code is ready automate automatically.
The AI basic in provides us the tools
to pick up the code, run through the
testing scenarios and tell us whether
it is working or not, or it also
tells you which part of the code is
basically causing the issues as well.
Then based off the results that
we have encountered over a period
of testing, it also enables us to
basically create pattern recognitions
in all of the testing outcomes.
It'll enable us to predict in future code
migrations how we can leverage all of that
predictability to to write better code
and to do better migration activities.
And then the last piece
is the test refinement.
So as we start to train the model
to understand what the different
test scenarios could be, and when
we start to implement these product
scenarios via code, it starts to start
to self-improve itself and starts at
better testing, testing scenarios and
provides a better testing coverage.
Us
next.
This is, I'm talking about, this
is the implementation framework.
How do we implement ai?
First thing is the assessment phase
During any kind of migration activity,
the assessment phase is very key
because that is where you catalog all
existing systems, identify modernization
candidates, and establish reliability base
baselines using automated discovery tools.
Next, we start with the pilot.
We basically take a simple MVP and
then start to migrate that or modernize
that based off using these, using
AI driven reliability improvements
and scalable approaches and refining
approaches to, to do that implementation.
Once the SA pilot is successful,
then is basically the implementing
AI at a larger scale, then we will
leverage AI to, and tooling to within
existing SRE practices, focusing on
code analysis, predictor monitoring,
and automated testing capabilities.
The last would be scale, the deployments.
Now that we have implemented a
pilot, you have now implemented
the integration capabilities.
Now we have to, we will leverage AI to
determine how much scaling is required for
this to successfully work the way it is
supposed to work or a perform even better.
So we extend proven approaches
across the enterprise, maintaining
continuous learning, learning loops
to provide modernization outcomes.
Then what are some of the common
challenges and mitigation strategies that
we need to consider during this migration?
One, data quality issues.
Primarily when we move from one
system to another system, we have
to take into account, but that the
EO system acts in a different way.
It ingested in a different way.
It reads data in a different way,
so we need to basically implement
very data cleansing pipelines and
verification algorithms to ensure.
AI systems receive reliable inputs,
and then we have to establish data
quality scoring mechanisms and
trigger human review for edge cases.
Then technical debt.
Ideally there's a lot of technical
debt which is involved during
any kind of a migration activity.
We basically need to use AI to
quantify that and quant categorize
the technical depth, creating
prioritization, remediation, roadmaps.
Then we have to make sure that we
implement automated refactoring
tools to systematically address
high impact issues first.
So the prioritizations and
everything are very key to any
kind of tech technical data.
So whatever product backlog we have,
technical backlog we have to ensure
that we prioritize it and then start to
roll it out according to that itself.
And then comes the skill gaps.
So as we mentioned, as I mentioned
earlier, the primary problem with.
With legacy mainframe systems
is to find people who have that
COBOL understanding and knowledge.
So we need to basically start to bridge
the limited set of mainframe veterans
that we can identify and bridge them
with AI specialists to basically do
a proper knowledge transfer and then
ensure that that AI is properly educated
along among these mainframe veterans to
understand and then bridge the product
gap and bridge, bridge the technology gap.
Then now let's talk about some future
directions, like how quantum computing
applications will, is a game changer
in this specific migration activity.
First it would be around
complex optimization problems.
Quantum algorithms will dramatically
accelerate optimization, challenges in
resource allocation and performance during
mainframe transition, solving in minutes.
What currently takes days.
Quantum computing basically gives you the
capability to process problems or solve
problems in very, in a very fast method.
I'm talking about
microseconds, not even seconds.
It is that fast.
We are still not there today, but in the
future day when once we get into quantum
computing, it solves many other cases.
Not just pertaining to modernization,
but it solves many other scenarios and
questions as well, including space travel,
including automated language learning.
There's a lot of areas that
quantum compute can help.
Then next would be how the
enhanced security modeling of
what quantum computing offers.
Quantum resistant cryptographic
systems will safeguard
sensitive data during migration.
While quantum simulation will identify
potential security vulnerabilities
possible to detect with classic computing.
What this means is it provides you
the different tools and encryptions
possible while transitioning data
from one system to another system.
We have a traditional encryption
methods that we follow today.
But this cryptographic encryption
is taking this to the next level the
vulnerable, it, it'll proactively identify
all system vulnerabilities, security
vulnerabilities, and try to identify what
remediations can be in place and provide
better encryption and cryptographic
capabilities to, to safeguard it.
Then the last the next capability
is system behavior prediction.
Quantum machine learning models will
achieve unprecedented accuracy and
predicted system behavior under load,
enabling perfect fit cap capacity
planning during critical migration phases.
What this means is basically it
allows you to provide you high
levels of accuracy while predicting.
A certain scenario, whether it is
system behaviors, whether it is
capacity planning, whatever it might
be in every migration phase, it can
give you unprecedented accuracies
when when trying to implement
predictability in that scenario.
So early research basically now
suggests that quantum approaches
could possibly reduce complex
migration timelines with 30 to 40%
while improving reliability outcomes.
That is a big number.
Then practical guidance for SRE teams.
So for site reliability engineering
teams, some of the things that
we need to consider why AI needs,
why AI is a major player in any
kind of an SRE environment is one.
It basically reduces the incidence by 89%.
It is a proven fact done and
implemented and validated
across multiple implementations.
Average reduction in critical
incidents during modernization when
using AI driven reliability tools.
As reduced by 89% compared
to a traditional approach.
Then the ROI is very key.
The money plays a major factor
or any kind of an ROI plays a
major factor during an investment.
So any kind of a mainframe
modernization project has to
be backed with an investment.
So with AI being a major part of that
migration activity it has proven that,
or theoretically we have identified that.
Around we have the ROI is basically
generated 3.7 times what it was
supposed to usually provide in a
traditional migration activity.
Then using AI assistance, we can save
the time and planning efforts required
as part of as part of the analysis.
So during planning phases,
analysis phases, we were able
to, there were proven cases.
The studies say that we were able to
achieve 65% of time savings during that
in, during analysis and planning phase.
Us.
So overall, I want to make sure this
is this is how I want to conclude that,
AI plays a very major role in how the
reliability, scalability is, plays
a major factor during any kind of a
complex migration activity involved.
So all of your, all of my friends
who, who are thinking about migrating
legacy system, please ensure that
AI is implemented as part of that
and all of those key and use my
inputs to basically drive your your
leadership towards understanding what
the different benefits AI can offer
during any kind of migration activity.
Thank you so much for everyone's time.
Have a lovely day.
Thank you.
Bye.