Hi everyone.
Today I am really excited to talk
about a critical aspect of ID
operations that ensures the stability
and reliability of our systems site
reliability, engineering, or SRE as
you may know, and incident management.
These processes are the backbone of
any organizations' ability to deliver
seamless services to its users while
maintaining operational efficiency.
In this session we'll explore three
connected processes, incident management,
problem management, and change management,
and how they work together to minimize
disruptions, resolve issues efficiently,
and ensure long-term system stability.
So with this, let's begin by diving
into incident management, which
is the first line of defense in
handling it Service disruptions.
So let's talk about navigating
incident management.
Incident management is the process of
identifying, managing, and resolving ID
service disruptions to restore normal
operations as quickly as possible.
Think of it as the emergence response
team for your IT infrastructure, but
let's not confuse incidents with requests.
Sometimes users or requesters will lose
access to certain tools and will be
unable to perform certain operations
and create an incident ticket.
But just to keep something in mind
that those should be logged as request
tickets and not an incident ticket.
So that would be a huge difference
between incident tickets and
our ITMs or request tickets.
So the key objectives of
incident management, first, it
aims to minimize the impact of
incidents on business operations.
Every minute of downtime can have
significant consequences like lost
revenue, frustrated customers, and
damage to the brand reputation,
which is sensitive, right?
Second, it ensures incidents
are resolved within the agreed
SLA or service level agreements.
So what is SLA?
SLAs?
Define the acceptable timeframes for
resolving issues, ensuring accountability
and consistency in service delivery.
And why is this important?
A structured incident management
process not only reduces downtime.
But also maintaining, maintain
service quality by ensuring issues are
handled efficiently and effectively.
Let me illustrate this with an example.
Imagine a critical e-commerce
platform that goes down during a
major sales event like Black Friday.
Without a robust incident management
process in place, it'll be utter chaos.
Teams will scramble without clear
roles or priorities prolonging the
outage, but with a structured approach.
The incident is S logged, the categorized
escalated, and the issue resolved
swiftly minimizing disruption with this.
Let's move on to another topic,
which is very much intertwined
with incident management, which is.
Problem management.
So while incident management focuses
on immediate resolution, problem
management takes a step back to address
the root causes of this incidents.
Its goal is to prevent recurring
issues by identifying and
resolving systemic problems.
Some of the key activities, or I would say
the key activities in problem management
is root cause analysis or RCA, which
involves investigating underlying issues
to understand why an incident occurred
in the first place and implementing
permanent fixes are workarounds, so
once the root cause is identified,
teams work on permanent resolutions or
interim fixes to prevent recurrence.
Now you might wonder, how does problem
management relate to incident management?
The two processes are closely interwind.
Problem management uses data from
incidents, patterns, trends, and
recurring issues to identify, sorry,
systemic problems that need addressing.
For example imagine
repeated server outages.
Traced back to a
misconfigured application.
While incident management
resolves each outage temporarily.
Problem management steps in to
permanently fix the configuration
issue by addressing these root causes,
problem management ensures long-term
stability and reduces the likelihood.
Of future disruptions now.
Isn't that great?
So let's move forward to discussing our
third topic, which is change management.
So this third pillar we'll discuss
today is change management, which
focuses on planning, approving
and implementing changes.
To ID systems while minimizing risks
changes could include anything from
software updates to infrastructure
upgrades or new feature deployments.
Changes often arise as solutions
from problem management.
For instance, if problem management
identifies outdated software
as the root cause of recurring
issues, change management insurers.
That updates are deployed safely
without introducing new problems.
The key principles of change
management are risk assessment, which
is before implementing any change
is crucial to evaluate potential
risks and their impact on operations.
It did, it should not take down an entire
development or production environment.
Just saying testing and phase development
would be the second point of it.
As a key principle, changes should
be tested rigorously in control
environments before being rolled out
in phases to minimize disruptions.
An example would be, suppose
your team identifies recurring
performance issues with the database
system during problem management.
Change management would oversee a
phased upgrade of that database system,
testing it thoroughly before rolling it
out across all environments to ensure
minimal risk of downtime or new issues.
By integrating change management with
incident and problem management processes,
organizations can implement fixes safely
while maintaining system reliability.
So before we wrap this up, let's
take a moment to reflect on how these
three processes, incident management,
problem management, and change
management work together seamlessly.
As we know, incident management
addresses immediate disruptions
to restorative services quickly.
And problem management
investigates the root causes to
prevent these recurring issues.
And change management ensures that
fixes or implements are implemented
safely without introducing new risks.
These interconnected processes form
the foundation of it, stability
and operational efficiency.
So let's discuss some.
Quick tips for effective incident
management to standardize incident
logging, categorization, and
prioritization processes so teams can
respond consistently and effectively.
For example, a P one or priority
one incident to one team member
should not be a P three or
priority three incident to another.
The second point is to use
automation tools for communication
and escalation to ensure.
Service level agreements or
SLAs are met without delays.
Sometimes sending out manual comms can
interfere with timelines for sending out
comms during an incident bridge, so it's
best to have comms automated as per need.
The third point would be regularly review
SLAs and priority metricses to ensure
alignment with evolving business needs.
Also to note to keep track and follow up
on root cause or SLAs that are assigned
to respective teams so that those
deadlines are not missed out as well.
To conclude this section, our
final thought that I would like
to share is a well integrated
approach to incident management.
Problem management and change
management is essential for any
organization aiming to enhance.
Operational efficiency
while reducing downtime.
By focusing on these processes as part
of site reliability, engineering hacks,
we can ensure business continuity and
deliver exceptional service quality
even in the face of challenges.
So while wrapping this up, let's
discuss some tips and tricks for dealing
with difficult in incident bridges.
And I promise you, you will definitely
come across at least one in your lifetime
if you are if you start working as SRE
incident manager, or if you're already
working as SRE or an incident manager.
So whenever we are on an incident
bridge, it is very important to
understand the impact of the incident.
Most times, users or requesters
will incline on driving their
issue as P one, not priority one.
However, if the impact does not align with
our priority metrics, it's best to convey
the user on why it stands out as a lesser
priority incident rather than only being
aggressive about switching the priority.
The second point that I would like to
bring up is oftentimes while dealing
with bridges, we tend to lack empathy.
Sometimes even when we are unable to
assist the user due to low priority
incidents or incidents not being in
our domain, it's best to guide the
user are requested with next steps
if we are aware of any, instead
of just leaving them straight.
And the third one.
And one of the most important points
is to maintain boundaries over bridges.
Sometimes we'll get a pushback on
following our standardized priority
metrics and escalation procedures.
It is important to be assertive when
needed to prevent unnecessary use of
our resources and time and invest those
where there is an actual need of them.
So it's very important
to keep that in mind.
So moving.
But moving to my last slide and the final
topic for discussion is something fun.
It's actually interview hacks for SI
or Im, or it's a general hack, I would
say that I have experienced and I
wanted to share that with whoever is.
Struggling or looking for some
tip centric for interviewing.
So oftentimes, I come across
fresh graduates asking if it's
okay to ask questions back to the
recruiter when they're reached
out for a call or interview.
I would recommend asking as many questions
as you need until you have a clear
idea on what you are signing up for.
It will not only help you to do
better in the interview, but also
will help you to understand if you
really want to move forward with the
opportunity, which is very important.
The second point to discuss is that
know your audience, which means
know your interviewers if possible,
research on how they interview and
what their skill sets are in the job.
Which might give you some understanding
on what to expect during your interview.
The third point that I would like to
discuss is enhancing your skillset,
the smart way for interviews.
Focus on short and fast courses on the
skillset requirements for the job that you
are interested in, rather than going for
a whole week's tutorial that will help to
build your confidence for the interview.
And most importantly, be confident.
Do not hesitate to share that you do
not know the answers to something,
share how much or how little so with
this, I wrap up this presentation
and I hope this was helpful.
So thank you for your time today.
I look forward to hearing your thoughts
or answering any questions that you
may have about this vital processes.
Say hi to me on LinkedIn.
Also, this is my email,
shamali dot rc@gmail.com.
Thanks everybody.
It was great speaking for you guys.