Hi folks.
Greetings of the day.
This is pun Gupta here.
Today I'm going to talk about adaptive
power calculation for low power
or battery operated chips design.
In today's scenario, when we look at
our live, we are using lot of systems or
devices which are battery operated and
has become essential part of our life.
Thus, it becomes very necessary
to make sure that those
power runs longer on battery.
You don't need to charge again and again,
and whenever you need it, the battery is
available to supply the adequate coin.
How we can make sure that's happening.
We can design a system.
We can design the chip.
With the correct specification so
that we can deploy the battery,
which can provide the adequate
current whenever it is needed.
So a proper calculation is required
when we are designing the system.
We are designing the shape or any
other part of this overall device.
What we will be using
in our day to day life.
Some of the examples of these
devices are smartphones.
What we use day to day life.
We want to charge it for a small time,
we want to use it for a longer time.
Tablets are there cars,
are there many more things?
So let's just go through this presentation
and see what are the components which
are responsible for power calculation.
What is the current state of power?
How we are calculating nowadays, what
are the problems or flaws in our current
methodology and flows right now during
the power calculation for the chips
and how it impacts the overall process.
So first slide.
So power calculation challenge.
What are the challenges which makes
this process a little bit difficult
or insert the incu accuracies
when we calculate the power.
So there are a lot of power parameters.
What we need for power calculations
are dynamically change, like
changing in day to day chip design
process, or they keep changing as
chip design process progresses.
So if we look at any holistic chip
design process, we can divide it into
multiple sub persons, like architecture.
Then we have RTL, then we have physical
design, and then we have final sign off.
These parameters can be based on the
formula, the toggling file, the load cap.
Sometimes we look at the frequency
and voltage variation level.
Also.
So all these parameters are
dynamically changing and when we try
to calculate those things, if those
are changing, our power estimate
for the power may not accurate.
Early inaccuracies are the, another
set of components, like when we started
with one of set of the architecture,
we did not consider few features.
And if those features we are
adding at the later stage.
And those are some high frequency
switching features that may
change the power computation.
And it can cascade with many other
things in the later stage of the design.
The distributor network is huge.
Also comes in the picture when
we calculated the power at some
numbers and then we designed the
power network when we are using it.
The lot of things has been changed
in terms of, let us say we added
the feature, we changed the RTL,
that increased the area of the
design and it need more current now.
And when we more current, we need to
add, make the power network robust,
and that will add the load cap stands,
so the total power of the design.
So these are some of the
challenges, what we are seeing in
day to day chip design process.
Current state is the fixed
calculation, how we are doing it.
We have some specification
based on the architecture.
We are looking into it, say
we are doing CPO design.
So batch will be happening in this cycle.
So this logic will be switching only in
this particular cycle for two cycles.
This amount of logic will be off, so
only leakage will be there and so on.
So we have this kind of scenario,
but actually we cannot accumulatively
look at the entire design switching
that, how this will be switching.
So there is a possibility
that we are still leaving a
significant margin of errors.
Us, we are using aesthetic
design parameters like okay.
We will be having this much area, the area
will grow by this much and this is how it
is going to change our load curve stance.
But there is a possibility that
when we are going through the design
closure phase, these parameters may
change and if we will not include,
we may see that the calculations,
what we have done for the power may
be inaccurate or less approximate.
Sometimes what we see that.
During the late stage, when we are
done with all these things, we figure
out, okay now whatever the power
we were estimating has changed.
The reason maybe during area
conversions, what designer did, he did
use lot of el leaky cells, ELBT, or
ELBT cells, which reduced the area,
but actually increased the power.
And all these things mixed and match
will result in a suboptimal designs where
it can have higher power conjunction.
It can have like lower performance
and at the same time the battery
may be leaking really fast.
So all these things are in the current
state of the chip design, how we
can overcome of all these things.
So we know that when we are starting
the design, we have some architecture,
but can we account for some extra
feature if we know about it?
Okay.
Can we model such some kind of
additional margins when we are
competing on the power initially?
So actual toggling file based on
the design requirement we get at the
end of the physical design closure.
When we run gate level simulation, but
can we model these kind of FSDs in the
starting so that have, we can calculate
the power in a more approximated way,
so the calculation can be done based
on the comprehensive power estimate
and using preliminary specification.
Also, we can use some statistical
models based on the prior prior
experience, prior design experience,
prior technology experience.
And based on what we are thinking
that this feature will be
adding or something like that.
Now, at the same time, we can dynamically
incorporate these real time measurements
data and can refine our parameters.
So at the architecture level,
we estimated, okay, this much
switching activity will be there.
But when we are moving further, we are
not able to do enough clock getting.
Can we change that kind of parameters
and can do the recomp computation
of the power, adjusting those power
specification and then announcing the
procession of those power computation
will help us to optimize the battery life.
And then after that, we can
validate those results at the
same time by benchmarking against.
Whatever the test factors, we have
to see that whatever the improvements
we have done are actually going to
meet the power requirement or not.
Or still, we need to provide the feedback
to the architecture or to the RTL team
or to the physical design team that we
are not meeting, and we can take this
adaptive methodology and can go through
a couple of different cycles to close it.
Now key milestone for
adaptive recalculation.
So as I mentioned, based on the
architecture definition, that
is the baseline power S where
we have a specification and we
can use statistical modeling.
We can do this through
the RTL development.
So when we know that this is the RTL,
this is the activity will be there.
We can do the some simulation at
that time and can do the all the
analysis for the power based on the
workload analysis and available RTL.
Next is the physical design.
When design is placed off clock three,
synthesis is done, routing is done.
We have more realistic
value of load cup stents.
We can have a good quality of toggle
rate file and we can do much more
accurate power profiling at physical
design stage, sleek and validation.
When a design is ready to tap out,
ready to go to for masks generation
to the foundry at that time, what
kind of power calculations are there?
So we can do rigorous power computation
based on whatever FSDV we have.
We can have functional FSDs, we can have
DFT based FSDs, and in those two scenarios
also, there can be multiple modes.
So for each and every mode,
whatever we were expecting, are
we meeting those goals or not?
So we can check at that time not tracking
input quality at each and every stage.
As I mentioned that.
When initially we are starting
the design, we can account for
some of the factors toggling rate.
Okay?
That all the sequential and all
the input outputs should have
at least 45% activity annotated.
The parasitic data can be assumed
to be 80% based on the model,
20% based on the real one.
Same can be scaled going further.
So during the Synthes stage, we
can consider, okay, 65% toggle rate
should meet parasitic data can be
little bit more accurate beyond the
55 or more percentage because we have
physical aware synthesis capabilities
available place in route, we expect
80 to a hundred percent, or I'll say.
In ballpark favor between 95 to a
hundred percent toggle rate to meet.
And then the completeness of
parasitics should be 85 to a
hundred percent, and then we can
calculate a more accurate power.
And then why like here the numbers
are a little less because we are
not considering the optimization,
so we can calculate these numbers.
At the, just before, at the starting of
the place and route and at the end of
the place and route at the final design.
So that's where the 95%,
200% comes, and 80%.
So when we have these kind of collateral
sub level, we can include few things
based on the statistical models and few
inputs are the actual, and we can have a
very much approximated power calculation.
Automation spread, G so in trend we can
make our methodologies or process in
such a way that we can intelligently
identify available and put parameters.
So like flow.
If this file exists, like
FSDV file exist, use it.
Otherwise use a pessimistic toggle rate.
Implementation mod opt implementation
of optimal co calculation models
based on the data maturity.
So how we'll be going for the, whatever
the data maturity will be there.
Based on that, we can refine our models
and proactively we can flag Okay, FSDV
is missing, this library is missing
the toggle rate looks really low.
All these things we can flag and
can report it to the actual owner.
If it need to be feedback to the
RTL or if need to feed back to the
architecture or if need to be feedback
to the physical design engineer.
Wherever there is a gap of
something missing, we can bridge
with the help of predictive models.
So let us say if initially
D-F-T-F-S-D-V is missing.
Can we generate some kind of model which
can predict the activity and those can
be leveraged in these competitions.
Any historical data can also be
included and self prediction also
available if we can utilize ai.
I at the same time, when we are doing
all these computation, we can provide our
feedback to all the cross team members.
We can work with the like
design verification team.
Okay.
This is what we are seeing.
This is what we should see where
is the mismatch, and can look at
all these industry standard tools
to make sure that whatever the
power analysis we have is accurate.
Kind of dashboard also we created,
which can be shared across all
the teams and they can look at
it at the same time and take the
proactive and whatever is required.
So power distribution, network
optimization is part, also part of it.
So based on the initial computation,
we designed some kind of power network.
So we need to precisely calibrate to
match the dynamic power requirements
so that we can provide the adequate
current to all the circuits at the
required frequency and voltage.
We need to make sure that we
do not have any IR drop issues.
We do not have any electro migration.
We need to have a good network
which can supply adequate current.
At the same time, we need to
make sure that we are leaving.
Enough routing resources for the
clocks and for the signal routing
so that we will not run into the
crunch or congestion situation.
And that overall we will see that
we have enough power getting done at
like when there is a certain amount
of logic doesn't need to switch.
We have power getting done available.
Or any kind of operation which can
provide more battery life, like
dynamic voltage and frequency scaling.
At the same time, let us say we can
reduce the frequency, reduce the voltage,
and can perform that operation at a
slower rate or a kind of camera example.
When we are not using it, the tool
or the system should automatically
switch it off, so those kind of.
Optimization can be done
to get better battery life.
So when we use these kind of
techniques in real life, we see that
we can save 30% to, for 30 to 40%.
Or in my case, I have seen 37% power
saving during the chip operation.
We saw that when we calculated the
accurate power and designed our network.
We were able to improve the efficiency
in terms of performance by 42%
without any area penalty and battery
longevity improved by 2.8 times.
So all these things came coming from
one of the battery operated devices
running at very high frequency.
Implementation roadmap.
As I mentioned that all these statistical
models or aesthetic models, excuse me,
learning based on the prior designs
can be integrated in the tools and
methodology and flow, the team or
of the engineers all the way from
architecture to RTL and implementation.
Can be trained on the adaptive power
calculation methodologies so that they
can look at each and everything very
carefully and can provide the right
input or they can do the right job.
Or for a physical design engineer,
if they are looking at more power
in their reports, they can analyze
and develop why the power is more,
are they using the right toggling?
Or they to open the leaky cells or
something else, process updates.
At the same time, when we are implementing
these kind of methodologies, we need to
have a checkpoints which automatically
triggers the power calculation and
tells us so like in the flow itself,
when we are running synthesis, we
need to write all the power reports
when we are running play soft.
It should write power report at the end,
after the clock off and after the routing.
So when we are tracking it through various
phases, we can see the difference and
we can easily identify the root cause.
If there is any differences
systematically, we can define
these prediction models or fds
or any other required input for
the computation, and that always
helps to have more accurate power.
So key takeaways from here when we are
doing adaptive methodologies versus
the aesthetic, we have more accurate
power computation at each and every
stage, and we can collaborate with the
right team to provide the feedback so
that they can enhance their process to
provide better inputs to the next stage.
Like I have seen that.
My, I have four cores, which are
switching simultaneously at the same
time and consuming a lot of power.
I provide this feedback to
the architecture team and they
can came up with a solution.
Okay, let's not turn on all
the core at the same time.
We will turn on the cores based on the
load requirement so that we are not
drawing the power at the same time.
And if there is a need of all four
scores switching at the same time, we
can distribute the load so that when
we distribute the load in such a way
that based on the clock is queue, all
the switching will not be happening.
At the same time, data driven approach
is always good for any kind of
methodology and process in engineering.
When we have comprehensive input,
quality tracking, what kind of
qualities there is this going to
give us the correct computation or
not, or anything else is missing?
What kind of margins we
can have to avoid errors?
So all these calculations based
on the data can assure that we
have the right design choices.
Automation, of course, when we
have AI and ML available today.
We can fetch lot of data, we can
model missing gaps and can utilize
it in a like a day to day process.
And also at the same time, these can
be easily integrated in the EDF flows
and can provide accuracies to our
implementation and other methodologies.
Also, it makes really
fast when we are doing.
These calculations using a IE and
machine learning, though there is a cost
function of actually cost as well as
runtime and high computation requirement.
So this is all from my side for today.
Please reach out to me
if you have any question.
Thank you very much.
Have a great day.