Speaker 18: Hello everyone.
Really glad to be here
at SRE Conference 2026.
My name is Oral Lua and I spent
the last few years building
Reliability Systems at Scale.
Today I wanna talk about something
that has been genuinely transformative,
that is moving beyond just detecting
problems to actually making
smarter decisions about risk.
Before things go sideways, the talk is
called AI Driven Risk Aware decision
making for Scalable Reliability Systems.
I know that sounds like a lot where
I promise we are going to make it
very concrete and very practical
agenda.
Here's our roadmap.
We'll start by asking.
What's actually broken about
the way most teams do SRE today?
Then we'll get into a framework
for making risk aware decisions.
Look at the AI patterns that power
it and ground all of that in the
real production case study with real
numbers, not demo numbers, but cherry
pick benchmarks, real production data.
We'll close with the stuff.
Nobody tells you the pitfalls that
will bite you if you are not careful.
The problem with reactive SRE,
let me start with the story.
Most of you have probably lived, it's 2:00
AM your phone goes off and a alert fires.
You stumble to your laptop, spend
45 minutes onto the root cross,
push a hot fix and go back to bed.
Two weeks later, the exact same
thing happens, and the worst part
is it is not even a unique incident.
It is the same class of failure
wearing a slightly different
disguise, that loop of failure.
Lap weaker hunt, hot fix.
Repeat his reactive aria.
These three numbers tell you why
it is crushing us 14 minutes.
That is the every time
just to detect an incident.
Not fix it, just dictate it.
70% of a lots are noise.
The fire someone looks and
nothing is actually wrong.
That is not just an inconvenience.
It is a lot fatigue slowly,
training engineers to stop caring.
There are lots that really matters.
Get buried in the ones that do not.
45 minutes.
That is the average time to mitigate.
Once you know something is broken.
The deeper year is not tooling.
It is the mental model.
We have built systems that are
very good at screaming at us after
something breaks, but terrible has seen
something is probably about to break
risk aware decision framework.
So what does that shift
actually look like in practice?
It comes down to four steps.
Observe, score, decide, act, observe.
This is your existing stack.
Matrix traces, logs, L bond rate.
Nothing new here.
And that is intentional.
We are not asking you to throw
away what you have already built.
Score.
This is where AI enters the picture.
Instead of just watching For threshold
breaches, we calculate a risk score in
real time, the probability of failure
multiplied by business impact, divided by
how more time we have before it matters.
Decide a policy engine.
That takes call and makes a call.
Is this a log and a monitor situation?
Do we autoscale or do we
page something immediately?
Think of it like a tired respons
playbook, except instead of a human
flipping through a wrong book at 2:00
AM the system is doing it milliseconds
and doing it consistently every time.
Act.
The system executes automatically
and consistently even at 3:00
AM when nobody's watching.
The formula is right there on the slide.
Risk score equals failure
multiplied by business impact,
divided by time to impact.
Failure is what your machine learning
model output business impact.
Might be something like this.
Checkout service going
down cost $5,000 per hour.
Time to impact at urgency.
The closer we are to a
bridge, the higher the score.
A risk that might materialize in
six hours looks very different
from one that is 10 minutes away.
The formula captures that
dynamic automatically.
AI integration patterns.
Now, how does the a i piece actually work?
There are three patterns used and
the layer on top of your existing
observability stack and normally detection
with isolation forest or LSTM models.
You train on baseline traffic
patterns when behavior shift.
Not just crosses a threshold but
actually drifts the model catches it.
This helps you get ahead of your SLO
instead of reacting after the fact.
One reason I like isolation forest is that
it is lightweight and uninterpretable.
Your engineers can usually understand
why it fired ltms work better.
When you have richer sequential
signals, I need to catch more
sub two temporal patterns.
SLU bond rate prediction.
This is time series forecasting that
tells you something like at the current
bond rate, your error budget will
be exhausted in about 40 minutes.
That gives you 40 minutes.
To preemptively scale or shift
traffic before a customer
notices anything, change risk.
Scoring every, deploy, every config
change, every feature flag gets a blast.
Radio score before it touches production.
Gradient boost work really well here
because the land effectively historical
incident that all three of these run.
Sidecars, they plug into
Prometheus, open Telemetry,
Grafana, whatever you already have.
There is no re and replace.
I cannot stretch this.
If you walk into your engineering
organization and say, we need to
replace our entire observability.
Start to do this.
The project is dead on arrival.
The whole point is that this layer
on top of what you're already run.
Production case study.
All right, let's talk real numbers.
We deployed this system on an
e-commerce platform processing
50 million events a day.
This is a high stake environment.
Black Fridays, traffic
spikes, flash seals.
The old thing we ran.
For six months here is what happened.
Meantime, to detect dropped
from 40 minute to 2.3 minutes.
That is an 84% improvement.
False positives went from 70% down to 18%.
Engineers stopped ignoring a lot
because the actually means something.
We also measure this qualitatively.
On call satisfac satisfaction
surveys improved.
People stopped dreading their rotation.
Meantime to resolve went from
45 minutes down to 11 minutes.
This is 76% faster, and SLO
breaches per month dropped from
22 to four and 82% reduction.
The quote on the screen
is from SRE on deployment.
I think it captures perfectly.
The AI scorer becomes our most
trusted on-call team member.
It pages us before our customer
es anything that is a goal.
Not replacing engineers, but making them
faster and better equipped to respond,
scaling and pitfall.
Now, here is the part, most talks keep.
What actually goes wrong?
Model drift traffic patterns,
change a marketing campaign, a
product launch, a seasonal spike.
Suddenly your model is current risk
against a baseline that no longer exists.
The fix is straightforward.
We train weekly using a rolling
window and track drift with
population stability index.
Or PSI before it quietly
degrades your scoring.
A alert from storm risk.
If you roll this out and immediately
set everything to auto pitch on call,
you have basically recreated the
program you were trying to solve.
Start a log only mode, watch it
for two weeks, then graduate to
auto skating only then introduce,
paging, and always keep a human.
Hoover override.
This is not about removing
humans from the loop.
It is about making sure humans only get
pulled in when real judgment is required.
Latency, overhead scoring needs to be
fast, ideally under five milliseconds
by then batch and synchronously,
and use feature catching for eye
cardinality labels to keep it as smooth.
Data quality.
This is our usual one,
but it matters the most.
Cabbing garbage.
If 30% of your metric data
is missing, do not score.
Return now and annually.
Upstream, a bad score
is worse than no score.
One more practical tip.
Build data quality monitoring
before you build scoring model,
you will thank yourself later.
Key takeaways.
Let me leave you with
five things to take back.
One reactive.
SRE is technical depth.
Every 2:00 AM page that could have been
prevented is like compounding interest.
Two, the formula failure, multiplied by
impact, divided by time to impact gives
you a single actionable signal out.
Four, the observability noise.
Three.
Start simple one, isolation
first model, and one Prometheus
metric is enough to begin.
Do not wait for the perfect architecture.
Perfection is the enemy of shipping.
And your two M incident are not waiting
for your architecture review to finish.
Four.
Automate.
The bone tough first, low risk action.
Build trust.
Full autonom concept trust.
Five.
Measure everything.
Meantime to detect meantime to
resolve false positive rate, error.
Budget, bone, if you cannot
measure it, you cannot prove it.
Thank you.