Hey everyone.
My name Isman Carla.
I'm a senior technical lead and
a cloud DevOps engineer with
seven years of work experience.
Thank you all for joining my talk.
Today we'll explore how AI is
transforming how we build and deploy
the software from the collaboration
world of DevOps to the future of no ops.
Initially we'll talk about
how DevOps is evolved and how
we are transforming to NoOps.
Initially we started the DevOps to
remove the gaps between development
and operation team so that we can
accelerate the deployments from lower
environments to higher environments.
There are automation tools that improve
efficiency, but human oversight remains
crucial in each step from continuous
integration through continuous deployment.
However with the rise of no ops we
are fully envisioning automation
with the minimum human interactions.
The primary reason behind
this transformation is
because of a and MI models.
R. Driving this huge transformation
in the world of DevOps.
Now we'll talk about how AI is
playing a crucial role in DevOps
automation, AI powered continuous
integration and continuous deployment.
Pipelines are built so that we
can deploy the application with a
minimal human input and interaction.
This also helps us to find anomaly
detection and also root cause analysis
using machine learning algorithms.
And also it offers a self-healing
system that detects and
fixes issues automatically.
Also, a ops, our real time operational
insights and alerts that helps us to
give more information about an issue that
is happening in various environments.
This helps us to resolve the
issues quickly and also to get the
application up with a minimal time.
And also a driven infrastructure
management a has becoming smarter in
terms of provisioning infrastructure,
for example if an infrastructure requires
an order, scaling it predictive analysis
helps us whether to up the application or
down the application based on the traffic.
And also AI is helping us to
manage Kubernetes clusters
with a minimal human inputs.
This helps us to minimize the cost
and also improve the performance.
In the long run, AI is helping.
In terms of infrastructure as a code with
intelligent valuation, this says that
while improving the code AI is helping
us so that we can focus more on the
problem rather than syntax, for example,
Datadog, which helps us to visualize.
The information from the clusters
and also it also helps us to
understand how the infrastructure
is behaving and also application
metrics, infrastructure metrics,
and also the usage of the resources.
Now when coming to challenges and
risks of New Ops, there are quite
number of challenges while implementing
the new ops because A requires a
high quality data and data tuning.
If we rely completely on automation that
might miss root causes for many problems.
And also security
concerns are the biggest.
Discussion because developers cannot
have the expertise in security in
finding anomalies and fixing them.
Even the automation tools have the
vulnerabilities so that it might cause
security threat to, or it operations.
This is not just about shifting to tools.
It's just more about software
development lifecycle.
Also the future of AI in DevOps.
This has become really efficient
in generating a code and
also configuration changes.
For example, GitHub Coate helps us
to generate Kubernetes configuration
files based on our prompt eight.
Reach all the code in our repos and
generate a particular required AML file,
and then it deploys into the production.
Also hybrid model helps us combining
human oversight with AI automation in
the future DevOps engineers transitioning
into mostly a supervisors and strategies.
This is a visual representation of a
driven evolution in cloud operations.
If you see we initially started with
manual interventions with scripted
automations and DevOps collaborations.
With the time we moved to a
driven continuous integration
and continuous deployment anomaly
detection and also health self.
Healing systems also in smart
infrastructure based on the predict
analysis, autoscaling can be
take place based on traffic that
improvises cost as well as efficiency.
In the second and challenges and the
ethics is more about data quality, AI
transparency, role and transformation
now the future and no ops, which
we'll discuss in the next slide.
So now real question is that can
AI truly replace human operations?
The answer is not yet.
The rise of NoOps doesn't end the
signal of DevOps because DevOps can
be used for a more strategic and
complex problems, whereas NoOps can be
used for a simple, automating tasks,
full ops is still aspirational, but
human oversights remain critical.
DevOps is still evolving,
but not disappearing.
However, with AI as a co-pilot, we can
generate more sustainable and stable
application across all environments.
This is all about DevOps to
NoOps can a automate everything.
Thank you all for joining my talk
and I hope you all enjoy con 42 Site
Reliability Engineering Conference.
Thank you.