Hello everyone.
Welcome to our session on Resilient by
Design, a data-driven migration from
monoliths to event driven microservices.
Hello, I'm Amlin Go.
I have over two decades of experience
in architecting software solutions
with a focus on modernization from
monolithic applications to microservices
based event driven architecture.
So today we are tackling one of the most
pressing challenges in modern system
architecture, the transition from monolith
system to event driven microservices.
This transformation while promising
unparalleled scalability and
agility demands meticulous planning
and execution to maintain system
stability Throughout the journey.
In this talk, we will explore
a data-driven framework.
Designed to address these challenges head
on from understanding system domains to
designing robust schemas and implementing
progressive migration techniques.
We will highlight strategies
to ensure resilience, fall
tolerance, and seamless operations.
So let's dive in and discover how
resilience is engineered by design.
While microservice offer undeniable
benefits like modularity, scalability,
and fault isolations, the road to adopting
this architecture is far straightforward.
I. Transitioning from a monolithic
system to an even driven
microservices architecture comes
with its own set of challenges.
This include handling data consistency,
managing distributed systems, and ensuring
system resilience during the migration.
This is where SRE principles and
data-driven strategies play a crucial
role in overcoming these challenges.
Okay, migrating.
Let's get into some facts.
Migrating to a new architecture
is no small fit and the numbers
speak for themselves about the
challenges enterprise encounter.
68% of enterprise identifies
stability concerns.
As their primary migration
challenge, downtime or disruptions
during this process can severely
impact business operations making
reliability a top priority.
43% of migration fail on the first
end due to insufficient architecture.
Planning a rushed or poorly
designed approach often leads to
incomplete transition or disruptions.
37% of the project face cost overruns.
Traditional migration methods
often underestimate the complexity
leading to unplanned expenditure
with stability concerns, first time
migration failures, and cost overruns
posing significant challenges.
It's clear that traditional migration
methods often fail, fall short.
So how can we overcome these hurdles
and ensure a smooth transition?
So the answer lies in adopting a
well-defined data-driven approach.
So enter our event driven
migration framework.
This framework is designed to guide
enterprise through the complexities of
migration from monolithic to resilient,
scalable, and event driven microservices.
It addresses these challenges head
on by combining robust architecture
principles while real-time data insights.
So let's explore how this
framework can pave the way for
successful future-proof migrations.
So let's start at the base.
The domain driven design.
So the domain driven design is a
strategic methodology for monolithic
complex systems by aligning software
architecture with business needs, it
emphasizes the use of ED context to
create clear service boundaries that
encapsulate specific business logic,
ensuring modularity and scalability
essential for microservices migration.
Additionally.
Ubiquitous language, foster seamless
communication between developers and
domain experts, reducing misunderstanding
and improving collaboration by leveraging
tools like context mapping and even
storming domain event design simplifies
identifying sub-domains and their
interactions enabling a structured
approach to managing complexity
and building resilient systems.
This makes domain driven design of
vital framework for transitioning to a
event driven microservices architecture.
Next comes event sourcing.
So event sourcing is again, a
technique that preserves the entire
system history through immutable
event logs, allowing every change
to be logged.
And recorded these logs are invaluable
for reliable state reconstruction
making system robust and fall tolerant
by enabling precise recovery of the
system state at any point in time.
Key use cases include debugging issues
auditing for compliance replaying events
to recover from failures or errors.
Tools and frameworks like Apache Kafka,
even store Exxon framework, provide the
necessary infrastructure to implement
event sourcing efficiently, ensuring a
resilient and auditable architecture.
Next is our event driven patterns.
So even driven architecture is
a design approach that ensures
responsive and reliable in dis in
reliability in distributed system.
By enabling components to communicate
through events, it fosters decoupling
making system more scalable and adaptive.
Architectural safeguards like
circuit breaker pattern prevents
cascading failures by isolating
problematic services while bulkhead
com compartmentalization workloads.
To protect critical resources.
Additionally, fault isolation
mechanism ensures failure in one
microservice don't get impacts others.
Maintaining overall system stability.
These patterns not only enhance
resilience, but also aligned with SRE
principle of reliability, fault tolerance,
and proactive problem mitigation.
Next is our continuous delivery.
Continuous delivery.
As it's essential in the resilience,
but also it aligns with SRE principles
of reliability, fault tolerance,
and proactive problem mitigation.
Reducing time to market for updates.
Automated testing serves as the
foundation of safe deployments,
ensuring high code quality and catching
issues early in the development cycle.
Rollback capabilities further ensure
quick restoration of system functionality
in case of deployment failures, tools
like Jenkins, GitLab AWS code pipeline.
Are widely used to implement these
practices effectively driving stability
and innovation in development processes.
So distributor systems are the backbone
of modern applications, but they come
with their own share of complexities.
Complexities that often
challenge site reliability.
Engineers tasked with ensuring
stability and reliability.
From managing state changes to debugging
issues and ensuring fault tolerance,
maintaining uptime in such systems
requires robust tool and approaches.
This is where event sourcing shines
as an alternative pattern that not
only reduces complexity, but also
aligns perfectly with SRA principles.
Today we'll explore how event sourcing can
transform the way we manage system states.
And reliability, focusing on
capturing events, building
event logs, reconstructing,
state, and enabling projections.
So even searching align seamlessly the
the event sourcing align seamlessly
with SRE principles by reducing system
complexity and enhancing reliability.
It begins with capturing events
recording all state changes as
immutable timestamped objects to ensure
accurate tracking and observability.
This is followed by building
an append only event log.
Which serves as the system's definitive
source of truth, providing resiliency and
auditability through state recognition.
The current application state is derived
by sequential processing of the event
streams, enabling swift debugging
and efficient incident response,
critical for mentoring upline uptime.
Lastly, projections.
Allow tailored data model to be generated
from the same event sequence, improving
operational insights and empowering SREs
with actionable metrics to proactively
manage reliability and performance.
Together this practices create a
robust fall tolerant architecture
well suited to SRE goals.
So we explored how event sourcing reduces
complexity and enhances reliability
by aligning with the core principles
of site reliability engineering.
But how does this play out in practice
to truly understand its impact?
Let's dive into a real world example, the
migration of a Fortune five, 500 retail
companies system with a monolithic to
event driven microservices architecture.
So this case study highlights
the practical application of even
sourcing in solving challenges
related to system downtime,
scalability, and incident response.
It showcases the SRE practices, combined
with event driven patterns enabled
the company to achieve an operational
exp excellence, reduce complexity, and
build up system resilient enough to
handle millions of daily transactions.
Let's look at the challenge we faced,
the solution we implemented and the
key outcomes from this migration.
So let's delve into the practical
application of event sourcing and
microservice migration through
the journey of of this use case.
So this migration illustrates
the principle of SRE.
So now let's take a closure look at how
site reliability engineering principle
guided the migration journey from a
monolithic to event driven architecture.
This migration, this transformation
was carried out into four phases.
So now let's take a closer look at
how this the principles guided us.
The SRA principles guided
us in the migration journey.
So the first phase is during the
assessment phase the team model domains,
and identify service boundaries.
This strategic effort not only broke down
the monolithic system into manageable
components, but also ensured modularity,
a critical factor for minimizing risk
and maintaining operational stability.
Second, the focus shifted to even
schema design, where the team
created 47 distinct event types,
along with a versioning strategy.
By structuring event data with
clarity, we laid the foundation
for precise tracking and debugging,
empowering SREs with enhanced
observability for issue re resolution.
The third phase that ran parallel.
Saw a development of Macroservices
alongside the legacy monolithic
application, ensuring the existing system
remained functional during the transition.
This dual approach aligned with
the SRA principles of minimizing
disruption and maintaining uptime
while introducing new components.
Finally, the progressive migration phase
enabled incremental traffic shifting to
the new architecture with zero downtime.
This gradual rollout shared stability,
allowing SRE to monitor performance
and address any issues proactively
while keeping reliability intact.
These four phases demonstrate the power
of combining event driven architecture
with SRE practices to create a system that
is both scale, scalable and resilient.
So now let's explore the measurable
outcomes of this migration and
the tools that made it possible.
Even schema design is crucial for
ensuring reliability and scalability
in an event driven architecture.
Key base practices includes exp explicit
versioning, which incorporates schema
versions in event metadata to maintain
compatibility during updates, domain
aligned events, leverage ubiquitous
language from the business domain
for naming events, ensuring clarity
and alignment with domain logic.
Temporal con context embeds
creation of timestamps and casual
metadata within the events, enabling
accurate tracking and sequencing.
Lastly, even should be self-contained,
including all necessary context within
the payload to minimize the dependency
and streamlining the process processing.
This practice collectively enhance
observability, fall tolerance,
and operational efficiency.
So having established the importance
of an well-designed event schemas,
the next step is to explore how
to enhance system reliability.
I. With resilience patterns
implementation, right?
So resilient patterns such as circuit
breaker bulkheads and fault isolation
mechanisms are integral to building
robust, even driven systems for SREs.
These patterns not only
help in mitigating failures.
But also aligned with the core
principles of uptime, observability,
and proactive incident management.
So let's now dive into the resilience
pattern, discussing the role and
ensuring high availability and how
they can be effectively implemented
in a distributed architecture.
So resilience patterns are essential
for maintaining system ability
reliability and fall tolerance
in distributed architecture.
This circuit breaker pattern prevent
system overload by f failing fast
when dependencies are unhealthy,
reducing cascading failure by 85%.
And enabling automatic recovery with
configurable threshold for each service.
The bulkhead pattern that isolates
components to contain failures
within bounded context, utilizing
resource pool isolation, trade pool
segregation, and requested limiting
to protect critical services.
Meanwhile, retry with backup handles.
Transient failures through intelligent
retry mechanism, leveraging exponential
back of algorithms, jitter for load
disruptions, and dead letter cues to
manage unprocessed events effectively.
Together this patterns
align with SRE principles.
By improving this system, stability,
scalability, and operational
efficiency, again, with the
resilience pattern in place.
The next critical step for ensuring system
reliability is real time monitoring.
In event of architecture, event driven
architecture, real-time monitoring
provides the visibility required
to maintain operational excellence.
And proactively address issues before they
impact the users from SRE Perspectives.
This strategy provides pivotal in
tech tracking key metricses detecting
anomalies and ensuring adherence
to service level objectives.
So let's delve into how realtime
monitoring implementation.
Monitoring compliments resilience
patterns and supports a proactive
approach to system reliability.
So realtime monitoring strategies
align with SRA principles by
enhancing visibility and enabling.
Proactive Reliability management, so
aggregation, centralizes matrices while
preserving context Through correlation
IDs, ensuring accurate analysis across
service, alerting tri alerts, the
alerting triggers notification in
response to service level objectives.
Violation enabling rapid intervention
before issue gets escalated,
then comes your investigation.
Investigation fate facilitates your
tracing request flows across distributed
services, helping pinpoint failures
and streamline debugging efforts.
Lastly, instrumentation that embeds
telemetry in every service and event
flow, providing continuous insights
into system performance and help
together these practices ensure
effective monitoring and operational
excellence in complex architectures.
So now that we have explored the
strategies for real-time monitoring,
let's, IM it's important to
evaluate how different migration
methodologies stack up in the context
of reliability and scalability.
From SRA perspectives, selecting the
right migration approach is crucial.
To minimizing downtime, maintaining
system stability, and meeting
service level objectives.
In the next section, we will compare
popular migration methodologies,
analyzing their strengths, limitations,
and alignment with SRE principles
to help determine the best fit
for the resilient architecture.
So when evaluating migration methodologies
through the lens of reliability
and scalability, it's clear that
traditional approach and event driven
strategies often vastly differ outcomes.
The traditional approach often
relies on big bang cutover strategy,
which involves extended downtime.
Windows mi downtime windows migrating
monolithic database, and relying on
mutual and manual verification process.
While this method can work, in
some cases, it has limited rollback
capabilities posing significant
risk to system stability.
On the other hand, our event approach
prioritizes incremental service migration.
Enabling zero downtime deployment
and ensuring system availability
throughout the transition with data
synchronization, powered by events,
automated cannery analysis for gradual
testing and instant rollback mechanism.
So this methodologist aligns with
our SRE principles and delivers.
The required results by adopting
this event driven migration strategy,
organized, can minimize risk,
maintain, uptime, and achieve a more
scalable and reliable architecture.
With the migration methodologist
compared, the next step is to outline
a clear path of execution through an
implemented implementation roadmap.
A well-defined roadmap ensures
a structured transition.
So with the migration methodologist
compared next step is to
outline the clear path, right?
A roadmap.
So now that we have established the
importance of the structured migration
process, let's walk through the key stages
of our implementation roadmap, and that
is designed to ensure reliability and
scalability while aing to SR principles.
So number one that we should discuss
is about the domain analysis, right?
We begin by mapping business
domain to bounded context and
identifying clear service.
Boundaries.
This ensures modularity and lays
a solid foundation for decomposing
the monolithic into microservice
microservices, then comes event storming.
The next step involves close
collaboration with domain expert to
document core events and commands.
This phase ensures that the architecture
aligns with real world business processes,
enabling payer system behavior modeling.
Next is our schema design.
Here we define even schemas and
implement a compatibility strategy with
versioning to handle future changes.
This step is crucial for maintaining
system integrity and ensuring
consistent communication between
services infrastructure setup.
With Schema ready, we deploy our
event broker, set up observability
platform and create robust.
Continuous integration and
continuous deployment pipelines.
These elements form the backbone
of the reliable and scalable event
driven architecture, and then
is our incremental migration.
Finally, we migrate one bounded context
at a time using progressive delivery.
This approach allows us to
validate each step, ensuring zero
downtime while maintaining system
stability, and that is what we.
Are doing as a systems
site reliability engineers.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.
Thank you for joining today.
In conclusion, we have explored the
transition to event-driven architecture,
emphasizing the importance of SRE
principles in ensuring reliability.
And scalability and resilience.
From implementation to roadmaps,
to migration methodologies and
resilience patterns, these strategies
collectively paved the way for
modern high performing systems.
Thank you for your time
today and your attention.
It's been a pleasure discussing this
impactful practices with you, wishing
you continued success in driving
innovation and reliability in your system.
Thank you.