Speaker 19: Hi everyone.
Hope you are having a good time.
I'm Project Alate.
I work at the intersection of data
strategy, analytics, and business
execution to measure performance
and turn insights into decision.
Today we are going to talk about
operating predictive analytics at scale.
And how SRE principles can meet
predictive systems, reliable in
high stake education, finance.
If you have ever shipped a model
and then watched the production
do something completely different,
you are in the right place.
When education finance
moves, everything moves.
These platforms run forecasting, risk
assessment and decision systems that
influence funding, availability, payment,
timing, and the most important thing,
continuity of students' education journey.
And here is a hypothetical business
challenge I want you to think of
for the rest of the talk with me.
During the peak disbursement cycle,
freshness and reliability matter as
much as the accuracy because teams
must plan their cash availability
against the fixed enrollment
timelines and payment commitments.
What makes this hard is
of course, the reality.
Where inputs shift, such as school
calendars, certification, timing,
enrollment changes, and even some
student updates, and the disbursement
window is expected to create
predictable spikes with tight deadlines.
Plus everything has to be explainable,
traceable, defensible, because audits and
compliance and the rest of those stuff.
So here's a path for today,
a quick SRE principle.
What breaks without guardrails?
What changes when we operate analytics
like a service and the practical
toolkit such as pipelines, degradations,
SLI, SLOs, drift, and observability.
And we can end with some key takeaways
that you can bring back to your team.
Quick translations, so we are
all on the same page here.
SRE stands for Site Reliability
Engineering, which works
on some few principles.
The key one, SLI, which means
service level indicator, and
that's obviously an indicator.
The metrics we track latency, freshness,
drift, availability, and so on.
SLO is the service level
objective or the target.
We have committed to, and the error
budget is how much unreliability we can
tolerate in terms of cost and resources
before reliability work takes priority.
So what changes when we apply
SRE to this predictive analytics?
Without SRE, the pattern is
optimized offline accuracy and
hope that the production behaves.
But with SRE, we define targets.
We observe behavior, and
we can plan the fallbacks.
The outcome is not just a matter model.
But it's a reliable explainable decision,
which can happen even under the stress.
That's it.
You don't need a PhD with
in SRE to be with me.
Okay, let's dive a little bit deeper.
Now.
Traditionally, weak signals,
silent wrongness, or manual
recoveries might break the process.
We detect problems a little late.
Ski mask can break null spikes or
even STA inputs, which are discovered
only when someone downstream says,
Hey, can you take a look at this?
It looks a little bit weird.
Then we get the silent wrongness.
The pipelines have run.
The scores are produced.
The dashboards look alive, but
trustworthiness has secreted
and recovery becomes manual.
Pausing the decisions.
Digging through the logs back, filling
fixes after the fact, which is not
exactly the kind of vibe you want
during the peak financial operations.
So here's the disbursement week story.
The feeds have arrived, but the
format was a little bit drifted.
We missed the early warnings.
Our models rang and the scores returned
rate later, some anomalies were found.
The team is now in the diagnosis phase.
If this repeats, the business loses
its confidence in the prediction
service, and once the trust is lost,
you know that everything becomes harder.
Even if the, even if you go and fix
the root cause, that's the worst
nightmare for a modeler and model that,
that his model appears to be usable.
Okay, now let's put a number on it.
You have about 96% offline accuracy
and still the zero decision
value if your forecast is still,
when the cash planning happens.
That's why SRE, because a product.
A prediction that's unavailable,
unobservable or untrustworthy at
the time of decision is effectively
going to be useless no matter how
good it looked during our testing.
Basically, the model might be right,
but it's right in the wrong universe.
Hence, we operate the forecast like a
production service with three reliability
properties, availability, which means
the stakeholders can access prediction
when planning decisions are being made.
Observability, the teams can see
their drift latency data quality and
understand what's happening and why.
Trustworthiness, the outputs must
remain correct and explainable
even under the stress, or they
should be able to degrade safely.
It's the same different context, but
very different operating posture.
Now we add our cart rails,
which stop bad data early.
With quality gates keep the
decisions moving with cash
predictions, deterministic rules
or manual review flags and recover
faster with run runbooks rollback,
retaining triggers and audit logs.
The difference is not
just better accuracy.
It is the better system
behavior under the stress.
Now, this is a fault tolerant framework.
That's going to be our operating model,
data ingestion, transformation model
creation, serving it to the larger
group and in the decision making.
And the decision goal is very simple.
A degraded upstream step
should never become a silent
downstream prediction error.
Now every stage gets an independent
control, which can be quality case
schema on null checks, drift and health
checks, your governance access share
fallbacks with confidence levels.
When failures happens,
systems shouldn't go in dark.
Continuity of the business is the essence.
We use a degradation
ladder short time to live.
Snapshots as fallback When la, when
live inference isn't available,
confidence flags that annotate,
freshness and uncertainty.
Rule-based fallback when
model health drops below.
Defined SLOs.
The point is we need to keep
planning moving while being
honest about our system.
State
treating models like service
means defining measurable
targets beyond accuracy.
For example, for latency P 99, which is
the 99th percent type for gas response,
should be less than or equal to your
120 seconds under the peak volume.
For freshness.
It could be that our data age
should be less than or equal to 24
hours for stability of the model.
Drift needs to stay within the bounce,
like PSI, which is a population stability
index, less than or equal to two 0.2
over the rolling window for availability.
Meet high availability
during disbursement windows.
Now these are some targets which
can be changed based on your
business healthy operations.
Isn't that the model works?
It is that the system needs its
goal when the business needs it.
Drift is the core reliability
challenge feature drift,
where the inputs can change.
Label drift is when the outcomes
shift over time and concept drift.
This one is the hardest to detect
because it's changes that are there
in the underlying relationships.
Undetected, drift, silently
creeps in and ups the predictions.
And again, silent wrongness is
the most expensive failure mode.
This table is like your
operational checklist.
I'm not going to read the entire
table, but the pattern is very simple.
You need to detect early,
isolate fast, and recover safely.
The two examples which matter most in
our disbursement cash flow story is data
drift, where the input shift and the
model can quietly fail and auditability.
Where we need traceable,
defensible decisions.
The same controls can apply on
the other risk areas as well.
For sure.
You can't fix what you can't see.
For predictive systems, observability
must cover model behavior and not
just the infrastructure and alerting
should be action oriented, system-based
alerts on SLO burn rate data quality
gates to block batch records,
anomaly detection on output dis
distributions to catch silent wrongness
because if every alert is urgent.
Eventually, none of them are including
the ones that actually matter.
Automation and AI enabled workflows,
compress cycle times earlier, anomaly
detection, fewer cascading failures,
and consistent correctness at scale.
This is where reliability becomes
AC CR level, not just a safety net.
This is the key shift in strategy from
reactive response to proactive resilience,
proactive drift, governance error, budget
management, and continuous validation
through shadow deployments and canneries.
Reliability is the foundation
that lets predictive system on
trust and stay in production.
Now there's a payoff.
Reliability turns accurate.
Pla, but for child into useful,
under pressure issues surface in
minutes, fallbacks keep decisions
moving, run books, reduce the
recovery time, and auditability
protects the compliance and trust.
When things go wrong, fail
safely and recover deliberately.
A good model doesn't choose
between uptime and correctness.
It chooses the safest mode available.
Remember, detect, isolate, remedy,
and review, and the loop continues.
Now I'll leave you with a
simple thought If you remember
the Disbursement Week story.
The lesson is simple.
It is not enough for a model to be
accurate in a calm and controlled
test In the real world, decisions
happen under deadlines, inputs
shift, and the cost of being wrong
or unavailable builds up rather fast.
So don't just ship a model.
Operate one as a forecasting service.
Define SLIs and SLOs beyond accuracy.
Designed for a graceful degradation.
Watch the model's behavior
end-to-end and automate the
recovery with built-in auditability.
And the best part is this mindset
travels well, whether you are
an SRE data analytics or ops.
Now thank you for listening.
If you would like to connect, my
LinkedIn is, enjoy the rest of your day.