Welcome back.
Come 42 site level to Engineer 25.
Today I'm going to talk about AI
driven cloud solutions, overcoming
challenges, and ensure ethical deployment
and site liability engineering.
So the convergence of artificial
intelligence and cloud computing is
revolutionist industries creating
unprecedented opportunities.
While presenting any challenge for site
engineers, as organizations rush to
harness a potential in cloud environments
size, face complex obstacles in security
integration and operational efficiency.
So this present, this presentation
explodes the rapidly evolving
landscape of AI in cloud computing,
examining the critical challenges
facing SRE and providing.
Data backed solutions to address them.
We'll investigate security concerns,
integration complexities, and
ethical consideration that must
be navigated for successful AI
implementation in cloud systems.
So next, so this is the
growing of AI cloud market.
The current AI cloud market evolution
more than 1.2 billion by two three.
So 30 30 upon 6% the growth rate, 68%
reduction rate, 31% de efficiency gain.
Next, security challenges in AI
cloud integration, especially data
privacy concerns, the model production
security instance, the deficiency
represents the foremost challenge for SR
implementing AI in cloud environments.
Our nation struggle with.
Production sensitive training data
while maintaining model accuracy.
Simultaneously, a models stem cell
required production from increasingly
sophisticated, a adverse attacks
that attempts to manipulate outputs
or extract convention information.
So coming to security solutions
with implementation of homomorphic
encryption enables computation on
encrypted data without decryption.
Preserves privacy through
or the processing pipeline.
Secure and clear, isolated
execution environments, operations,
hardware level production.
For am model inference with
implement is differential privacy.
Mathematical frameworks
to limit individual data.
Exposure balances data utility
with privacy production.
So the measurable results, 92%
Directions in privacy instance, enhance
production against address attacks.
So advanced security technologies
are emerging to address unique
challenges of AI in cloud environments.
So these solutions enable SRE to
implement robust security measures
while maintaining the performance
and functionality of AI systems.
Next, the integration of operational
challenges, the main technical
ation deployment difficulties,
performance monitoring gaps,
the cost management complexity.
So SR has faced numerous
operational challenges when
integrating AI into cloud systems.
So the challenges can significantly
impact billability performance and cost
effectiveness, if not properly addressed.
So coming to operational solutions
for s. The main, A powered
monitoring, the predictive normally
detection and automated limitation.
Service missed architecture, enhanced
visibility under control across
microservices, so lops frameworks,
streamline model deployment and versioning
with the dynamic resource optimization.
So a resource allocation for
cost efficiency, so implementing.
Next generation operational solutions
can address the integration challenges
SR space or merchants adapting these
approaches has seen 92% improvements
in service discovery and fall a
40% reduction in operational cost.
So these technologies enable
SR to maintain relatability
while accelerating AI adoption.
So the adoption of LOP Streambox Ally
has reduced to model deployment time
by 78%, allowing for more frequent
updates and improvements to AI systems.
In production environments.
Next, ethical AI consideration.
So the main four pillars, the
fakeness and mitigation explain
builtin transparency, the regulatory
compliance, the human oversight.
So ethical considerations are
paramount when deployment,
deploying AI in cloud environments.
So SRS must work alongside a
ethics specialist to ensure systems
operate fairly and transparently.
So organization is implementing
beyond system frameworks have improved
fairness metrics by 40%, while those
with robust governance frameworks
achieve 96.8% regulatory complaints.
So the ethical dimensions of AI deployment
extended beyond technical implementations
to encompass organizational values
and social impact required holistic
approach from technical leaders.
So next, implementing
responsible AI frameworks.
So the main model documentation we
detection mitigation explainability tools.
Okay.
So implementing responsible AI frameworks
requires collaboration between SREs data
scientists and business stakeholders.
So automation that they have adopted.
Competency frameworks
report 70, 74% higher, 38%.
For regulatory approval for EA systems.
So next, the case study financial
services ca transformation.
So the main challenge identification,
SR lead solution designs.
The implementation on testing
and measurable outcomes.
So this case study demonstrates
how SSRE principles when applied to
AI Cloud integration can transform
operational performance while maintaining
security and ethical standards.
So the financial issues that should dis
implements while simultaneously reducing
operational costs by 31% due to their
success was the early involvements of
SRE in the AI system and design process.
Ensuring deliverability and
security requirements were addressed
from the being other than ract.
So the next best practices for s the
first one, the ship ship left security.
So integrate security practices
early in the development lifecycle.
So with automated scanning and
verification for AI components.
So this approach has shown to reduce
security instance by seven, 6%
compared to traditional methods.
So infra code define our cloud
resources on AM model deployments
as code enabling portion control
reproducibility, and rapid recovery.
So our nation's using infra code for
AI deployments report at 3% faster, 30
recovery times, so that AIOps integration.
So leverage AI to manage ai.
So implementing intelligent
monitoring and automated
remediation based on pattern ations.
So early adapters now reduced
remain time to resolution by 64%.
The finally the, so I established
knowledge sharing between data science
and the survey teams with regular
cross plan collaborative instance.
So this cultural practice strengths
overall system relativity.
So these are best practices form.
The foundation of successful AI
integration in cloud environments.
So automation that I have adapted
these approaches, support report
high reliability, improved security
posture, and more efficient operations.
So the finally the key
takeaways are next step.
So the integration of AI into
cloud computing presence.
Transformative opportunities alongside
significant challenges for SR. So by
implementing advanced security measures
like homomorphic encryption and secure
enclaves, Orions can product sense
to data while enabling AI innovation.
So operational excellence requires
adapting AA, power monitoring service
mesh architectures and frameworks.
So must.
Central to AI deployment with
frameworks for beyond objection,
explainability and regulatory complaints.
So our nation that successfully navigate
these challenges push themselves to
fully leverage AI potential while
maintaining that label and security
that modern cloud systems demand.
So the next step for most automatically
is conducting a comprehensive readiness
assessment, identifying gap areas, and
developing a. The security operational,
unethical consideration simultaneously.
Thank you.
Thank you very much.