Hello everyone.
Hope you are all doing good.
My name is Esh Maralla.
I have around 17 plus years of experience
in it with major focus on enterprise
architecture and designing distributed
systems, APIs and micro UI applications.
Today I'm going to talk to you
about enhancing systems, resilience
and efficiency with microservices.
Practical applications
and its real world impact.
And discover how microservices,
architecture, reshapes distributed systems
with real world application examples.
So during the whole talk, when
you watch the video, please feel
free to connect me in LinkedIn.
You can search for my name Kumar
Gun, and feel free to share your
questions, our discussion points, and
I'm more than happy to talk to you.
I will try to put in as much content as
I can with this presentation so that you
can see how it is working and you can
leverage the knowledge on your day-to-day
software development activities.
Alright, let's let's jump on to the talk.
So microservices as an architectural
style have revolutionized distributed
systems offering unparalleled
flexibility and efficiency.
In today's fast-paced business landscape
unlike traditional monolithic systems
where all components are tightly
integrated, when the service go down,
the entire application will go down.
Thereby limiting access to
the application as a whole.
The customers will not be able to
access the application at all since
the entire service will go down.
But microservices enable this division of
functionalities into independent services,
thereby fostering agility and innovation.
And when a specific service is down,
only the functionality related to
that service will be affected and
the users can continue interacting
with the rest of the application.
And moreover, microservices offer
unparalleled benefits for the developers
and the technical teams that are involved
in each of the microservices teams.
So that they can work in parallel
in the different microservices
teams that the developers are in.
So today we will delve into the
transformation power of microservices,
exploring their principles.
Design patterns and
implementation strategies.
So throughout the practical
applications and compelling case
studies, we will uncover how
microservices empower companies
to innovate, overcome challenges,
and achieve business acceleration.
Join me as we navigate the
fascinating journey of financing
system resilience and efficiency.
Through the adoption of microservices.
Let's move on to the second
slide where we will talk about
the microservices revolution.
The rise of microservices has
marked a transformative shift in
how modern enterprises approach.
Software architecture With 74% of
organizations now using microservices
in production, it's clear that most
of the companies like this approach
and has moved beyond the trend and
become a standard for scalable,
efficient, and agile development.
So the advantage of microservices
is microservices breakdown large and
complex applications into smaller,
independently deployable service.
Thereby allowing teams to
work on different components
simultaneously without stepping
on each other's code base.
And one of the most compelling reasons
that most of the companies are trying to
adapt to microservices is the significant
boost in the development speed.
On an average organizations report
up to 35% increase in development
velocity when compared to our
traditional monolithic systems.
In addition to speed, microservices also
offer considerable cost saving benefits.
Enterprises have reported at 28% reduction
in infrastructure costs after migrating
to a microservices based architecture.
This is often achieved through more
efficient resource utilization,
better scalability, and the ability
to tailor infrastructure more
precisely to each services needs.
So the microservices revolution is not
a, is not just a change in technology.
It's a fundamental evolution
in how teams collaborate.
Deploy and maintain software.
Let us delve into some of the
core principles of microservices.
At the heart of microservices,
architecture is the principle of
service independence which means that
each microservice is designed to run
as a self-contained unit, managing
its own processes and maintaining
clear boundaries from other service.
This separation enables teams
to develop, test, and deploy
individual services without infra
in interfering with others, right?
Another core principle is modularity.
Where in rather than building
a single massive application,
microservices are organized around
specific business capabilities.
So each service represent
a distinct function.
Such as user management, for example.
And then typically in e-commerce we
have payment processing where you can
separate it as its own microservice
or an inventory tracking can be
taken it into its own microservice.
Another core principle of
microservices architecture is.
The fault isolation.
Since each service operates independently
failures are contained within that
service alone and do not necessarily
affect the rest of the system, right?
This isolation improves overall
system reliability and resilience.
Making it possible to identify or
even, troubleshoot and fix the problems
without dis disrupting the entire
applications, as I told in the beginning.
Alright another core principle
is the concept of loose coupling.
Where microservices communicate with
each other through well-defined APIs,
avoiding tight interdependencies, which
makes it easier to replace or upgrade
individual services without having to make
widespread changes across your system.
So loose coupling also allows teams to
use different technologies or languages.
For different services, offering
flexibility in choosing the
right tools for the job.
Apart from the basic four found four
foundation principles that we spoke
we have few other concepts like
decentralized data management, where
each service typically owns its own
data store, and we have scalability and
autonomy where each microservices can
be independently scaled based on the
demand for that specific microservices.
We have DevOps and continuous develop
continuous delivery alignment where each
of the microservices can have its own
DevOps pipeline using CICD practices.
And we have observable observability
and monitoring where each of the teams
can detect, diagnose, and resolve
issues quickly just in case if there are
issues arise with these microservices.
Let's move on to the next slide.
We'll talk about some of
the key design patterns.
One of the most critical design pattern.
That we use in microservices
is the circuit breaker pattern.
Let's take an example of an electrical
circuit breaker where this pattern acts as
a protective mechanism that Hals calls to
a failing service to prevent the failure
from cascading throughout the system.
Like when a service is unresponsive
or repeatedly written, errors,
the circuit breaker trips and
redirects request to fallback logic.
Or error messages and in implementing
the circuit breaker pattern can improve
overall fall tolerance by up to 42%
which helps to maintain system stability
even under a tremendous strain or, maybe
a partial out outages in the system.
Alright.
Another important pattern is the saga
pattern which is particularly useful
for managing distributed transactions
across multiple microservices.
The saga pattern coordinates a
series of local transactions with
compensating actions in place in
case any part of the process fails.
This ensures data consistency
and it has been shown to reduce
transaction failures by 37%.
Especially in environments with high
concurrency or fluctuating, fluctuating
loads like in e-commerce web applications
where lot of shoppers shop and have
heavy loads on the web applications.
Another important pattern is the
API gateway pattern which plays
a central role in managing how
clients interact with microservices.
So rather than clients communicate
with each individual service directly,
the API gateway acts as a single entry
point, which handles the routing.
To specific services.
It can handle authentication,
it can handle the rate limit
and protocol translations.
There are so many other features
available in API gateway, right?
With the centralized handling like
API gateway in place most of the
organizations have reported up to 56%
improvement in the request efficiency.
Another important pattern is the
containerization, which is another
powerful pattern that supports the
microservices to be packaged and
deployed in its isolated containers.
Typically we use containers like
sorry, container tools like Docker and
Kubernetes, which helps us to ensure
consistency across environments.
Implementing containerization leads to
an improved resource utilization by up
to 62% as containers can be orchestrated
dynamically based on the workload demand.
All right.
Let's jump on to the next slide
and we will talk about the
business impact of microservices.
The first one being development speed.
So by breaking down applications into
smaller independent services development
teams can work on different components
simultaneously reducing bottlenecks and
exhilarating the delivery of features.
To achieve faster time to market, right?
The companies leveraging microservices
reported 35% increase in development
velocity compared to the traditional
monolithic architectures.
Another one that we are going to
talk about is the operational cost.
With precise scaling and better
resource utilization businesses can
optimize their infrastructure costs.
By better allocation of resources
with some of the organizations
reporting even a 20 per 28% reduction
in infrastructure costs after
transitioning to microservices.
As, as the scaling and resource
utilization are much better
in microservices most of the
organizations report a 28% reduction
in the infrastructure costs.
Another important aspect is systems
scalability where each of the service
operates independently, allowing
it to scale horizontally without
impacting the rest of the system.
The modular design of microservices
ensures that systems remain
flexible and capable of meeting
user demands no matter how complex
or, unpredictable it may be right.
Another important aspect
is time to market.
Traditional monolithic architectures
often struggle with lengthy development
cycles and deployment cycles.
Thereby making time to market
of the product very slow.
In contrast, microservices empower
teams to implement changes.
Fix bugs and deploy updates on
its own on its own by means.
What does it mean by on its own is that
each microservices has a responsible
team so they can fix bugs and deploy
their updates much faster than a
traditional monolithic application.
The study shows that, this leads
to an improvement of 50% in the in
the development time which makes
microservices to go to market quickly.
Alright let us move to the next
slide where we will talk about an
e-commerce case study which is one
of the luxury retailer where they,
they converted to microservices.
So before adapting to microservices,
the, this luxury retailer faced
significant challenges stemming from
its rigid monolithic architecture
because of its inflexible system.
It hindered innovation, preventing
the company from responding
quickly to the market demands.
So deployment cycles were ex exceptionally
long, taking almost up to six weeks
to roll out new updates or features.
Such delays not only impact impacted
the time to market, but also limited the
retailer's ability to stay competitive.
All right.
Additionally the monolithic nature of
the system made scaling very inefficient
as it required, duplicating the entire
application, which consumed the extensive
resources and entire resources as the
entire application will be replicated
to a separate node which led to high
infrastructure utilization almost at 87%,
resulting in performance bottlenecks.
Once this retailer shifted to
microservices, this really marked
a turning point for the retailer.
By breaking down the monolithic
system into independent services,
the company achieved remarkable
flexibility and agility.
The transformation enabled rapid
innovation, empowering teams to implement
new features more efficiently than a
traditional monolithic application.
Infrastructure utilization dropped from
87% to 42%, enabling the company to reduce
operational costs by an impressive of 35%.
This efficient resource management ensured
the retailer could handle high traffic
volumes during peak shopping periods,
while maintaining a very good performance.
These ADMA advancements really help the
retailer to strengthen its reputation
as a leader in luxury e-commerce
thereby driving customer loyalty
and increasing customer revenue.
Let's move on to the next slide.
We will talk about some of the
implementation implementation challenges.
Transitioning to microservices
architecture is a significant undertaking
that requires addressing various
organizational and technical challenges.
One of the most critical obstacle is
organizational change, which normally
involves like restructuring teams
and fostering a shift in culture.
And then, some learning curve.
Alright moving from mono monolithic
structure to microservices.
Demand decentralization where individual
team takes ownership of specific services.
Another challenge that, that I
see is the service coordination
like in a microservices ecosystem.
Each microservice operates independently,
but they're interconnected,
relying on each other to deliver
a unified experience for users.
Another challenge that I see is in the
distributed testing, unlike monolithic
system where testing is centralized
and straightforward because the
entire application is monolith and
they can test the entire application
whereas microservices require testing
across multiple independent services
which are which, and the, these
services interact in dynamic ways.
Another challenge that I see is the
technical complexity which seems to
be a major hurdle in implementing
microservices because configuration
management deployment and monitoring
become exceptionally challenging as
the number of microservices increases.
Lastly it's also vital to address
the learning curve for teams
transitioning to microservices.
As most of the engineers and developers
might have got accustomed to working
in a specific monolithic style these
teams might find it challenging
to adapt to the decentralized.
And the distributed
nature of microservices.
Okay, let's move on to the next slide.
We will talk about some of the
observability strategies that we can
use in microservices to ensure the
smooth operation and maintain the
resilience of microservices architecture.
Alright, metrics collection
is a foundational strategy for
observability, which enables the
tracking of key performance indicators
across all different microservices.
Metrics like response times, error
rates, and resource utilization
provide a quantitative understanding
of the system's performance.
Another vital component of observability
is distributed tracing, which provides
a comprehensive view of how requests
propagate through the service mesh.
Distributed tracing helps us
identify bottlenecks, the latency
issues and the service level
failures by actually pinpointing
the exact service or the component.
Responsible for the errors, or
you can say disruptions, right?
Centralized logging is is is the
one that enhances observability
by aggregating all the logs.
From all the services into
a single platform, right?
Logs capture valuable information
about events and errors.
If you have centralized logging, enable
all of these logs can be aggregated and
captured into a single platform, right?
Thereby making troubleshooting easy.
Another strategy is
implementing proactive alerting.
Proactive alerting basically
enables teams to address potential
issues before even it affect users.
Because because developers can get
automatic alerts when a, when an error
occurs in a specific microservices thereby
the developer can take a proactive step
to identify the issue and then fix it.
We will talk about testing
excellency in this slide.
As for any application testing is the
backbone to ensure the reliability
and performance of the application.
Even for the microservices
testings testing become, becomes
the backbone to make sure the
application is for good quality.
So we have strategies like
unit testing where it serves
as the first layer of defense.
By testing each service independently
developers can verify that its
core logic function, correct.
Functions work correctly without
external dependencies, right?
This method increases
the code coverage by.
Almost 32%.
Building on unit testing
integration testing.
Basically verifies how services
work together when they are
deployed together as a whole.
To deliver seamless functionality
and integration testing checks.
The compatibility and correctness of
communication protocols, data flows,
and shared APIs between services.
So it reduces integration
bugs by almost 47%.
Another strategy is the contract
testing where which plays a
vital role in maintaining a PA
stability across microservices.
Contract testing ensures that APAs
remain compatible and fulfill agreed
upon expectations between service
providers and different consumers.
This not only improves a PA
stability by 56%, but also
fosters trust and consistency in
within the service interactions.
Another innovative testing approach.
Is chaos testing, which validates the
system, re system's resilience under
adverse conditions by intentionally
introducing failures or disruptions.
Chaos testing evaluates how the system
responds to unexpected challenges.
This practice usually enhances the
system reliability by around 38%.
We will talk about some of the
migration strategies in this slide.
So migrating from a monolithic
architecture to microservices
is a strategic and also the
complex process, which requires
careful planning and execution.
So the first step in this transition
is decomposition analysis, which
involves identifying bounded context
within the existing monolith.
And by breaking down the monolith into
these smaller and independent units,
organizations can lay the groundwork
for creating the microservices platform.
Another widely used approach is the
strangler pattern which allows for gradual
and risk minimized transition instead
of attempting complete system overhaul.
The strangler pattern involves replacing
the specific functionalities of the
monolith with microservices incrementally.
So over the time, the monolith strings
as more functionalities are being
trans transitioned to microservices.
Another approach that is that
we can use is the pilot service.
This approach involves identifying
a non-critical service within the
application that can serve as a test
case for the migration by starting small.
Excuse me.
By starting small teams can learn
the nuances of deploying, managing,
and monitoring microservices.
Another key component of a
successful migration strategy
is developing a full ecosystem.
To support microservices.
This involves setting up the necessary
infrastructure, tools and processes
to manage the complexities of a
distribution distributed systems.
And finally the key takeaways.
So the adoption of microservices
architecture has revolutionized
how businesses achieve
acceleration and agility.
In their operations.
So by breaking monolithic systems
into smaller, independent services,
organizations have unlocked faster time to
market and enhanced customer satisfaction.
Microservices over development teams to
deliver features rapidly often reducing
delivery timelines by almost 45%.
This capability not only helps
businesses respond quickly to market
trends, but also provides a significant
competitive edge in dynamic industries.
Say for example, like an e-commerce.
Another critical takeaway is the
ability of microservices to enable
operational excellence through
enhanced scalability and resilience.
Traditional monolithic architectures
often struggle to scale efficiently,
especially under varying traffic loads.
Where however, microservices allow for
independent service scaling, optimizing
resource utilization, and reducing
operational costs by as much as 32%.
Microservices also foster technical
agility, allowing teams to innovate
faster and adapt to changes seamlessly.
With services operating independently,
teams can experiment with new
technologies, frameworks and
approaches without affecting
the overall architecture.
This flex flexibility translates
to a 56% improvement in development
velocity, enabling organizations
to continuously innovate and
stay ahead of the disruptions.
So in conclusion microservices
architecture is not just
a technical framework.
It's a paradigm shift that
empowers organizations to achieve
agility, resilience, and innovation
in today's fast paced world.
So from transforming rigid systems
to accelerating fisher delivery.
Microservices offer a strategic advantage
that goes far beyond efficiency.
As you have seen through practical
applications and real world case studies,
microservices have the power to drive
business acceleration, reduced operational
costs, and improved customer experiences.
So with this I encourage you
all to take this opportunity to
rethink how your systems are built.
And embrace the future of
our distributed architecture.
Let us all move forward together in
leveraging microservices to create
smarter, scalable, and more innovative
systems that meet the demands of tomorrow.
All right.
I hope you like this content.
Please feel free to leave your feedback
by connecting to me in LinkedIn.
Again, my name is Smar Go.
You can search for my name in
LinkedIn and please connect to
me if you have any questions.
Alright.
On that note, thank you so much
for your time and attention.
You all have a wonderful day.
See you guys.
Bye bye.