Speaker 34: Hi everyone.
Today we are gonna speak about
the impact of Gene AI on ses as
Stack Overflow found late in 2025.
Most of software engineer
are already using AI tools.
Microsoft reported that 30% of their
code base is already written by Gene ai.
Tropic today's reporting that up to
90% of their code base is written by
Gene AI and ER founder in mid 2025.
Say that 1 billion lines of
code were accepted every day
just with cure cell, right?
So that does not account for cloud
or codex and wither and so on.
And researcher led by research
across 5,000 software engineers
at Microsoft, Accenture, and
another big Fortune 500 company.
And they found that developer using
gene AI gain in productivity, they
were able to produce 15% more commits.
And more importantly, they were
able to increase the number of tasks
they were able to achieve by 25%.
So what the impact of all of this for
sre And while the impact, can have like
multiple things, I wanted to look at the
incident rate and I wanted to anchor.
This around the formula.
This is a raw formula.
Lambda is your baseline failure rate.
We're not gonna speak
too much about this one.
It's a constant.
But CN, p, the variable are what's
interesting, C is the number of
times, number of changes that
happens to your code base or your
system in a given amount of time.
And P is the probability that one of
this change is introducing a failure.
So we're gonna use this
formula across the talk.
So now you may be wondering
why I am giving this talk.
I'm working for rootly.
We are an on-call and
incident management platform.
We also recently released an AI SRE.
Literally, our job is to help company
like Nvidia, LinkedIn LinkedIn,
Dropbox rep. To manage their incidents
as well and fast as possible.
So incident is our job, my role
there, I lead the AI labs for root.
The role of the labs is to explore what
AI can bring to the world of reliability.
We do this by working with fellows,
either like people who have been
in the industry for a while and
students we build in the open.
It's a lot of pro prototyping.
We build a bunch of open source
tools and we do a bunch of research.
Everything is shared on our blog
and GitHub, so yeah, if you're
interested to use some of the
tools or some of the findings that
we've uncovered, can find us there.
I'm a former SRE and when I'm not
helping companies to manage their
incidents, helping bees to manage
their incidents with beekeeping.
Alright, so getting back to our
story, we just saw that Gene AI is
empowering developers to do more.
And so getting back to our formula
C is drastically increasing.
Statistically the number of
incidents that you may have
to handle will look like that.
This is obviously an
artist representation.
I wanted to actually look at the data.
So I look, looked at the
trend with users on Rootly.
And over the course the year, like
from 2023 to today I saw a three time
increase in the average number of
incident per customer, quite a jump.
So now as a necessary, it might not
just be that you have to handle more
incidents, but the tool that you will
have available to you or the help
rather, that you will have available.
It's gonna change.
Let me explain this.
Now, when you read you know you're
an incident and you need help from
developer, and you get blame and reach
out to this person who wrote the code,
the answer they might give you is Hey,
sorry, I didn't really write this code.
Actually, I prompted my agent to do
it, and so I don't really know how
it's working under the hood, right?
So I cannot really help you.
The other trend that we are seeing,
let's say you are in a, say zero.
A tricky incident where you are
having database issue and you'd
like to, get I don't know, progress
or networking expert to join you
and help you find what's going on.
This also might be become harder
and harder to find these type
of people because of gene ai.
People like practitioner are
becoming more and more generalists.
And so the summary is that.
You may have to handle more
incidents with less help.
While your manager is like, Hey chop.
You should do more, right?
Because you have ai.
That's the trend that we've been
hearing in the tech industry.
Okay, so now you know, we've been
speaking about the pace of change
and how can this impact you.
Now let's look more specifically about how
AI is screwing up or might be screwing up.
And when I speak about, AI slope,
I just want to make sure that we
don't speak about this type of AI
slope, but that type of AI slope.
I think the term is like quite
broadly used now, nowadays, but I
just wanted to make sure we were
speaking about the same thing.
The first one that's fun and maybe before
I start, some of this example may or may
not be true for the latest frontier model.
Improving super fast, but the
patterns are real, and I think it's
still happening at scale and it's
especially true for open source model.
And yeah the first one I
wanted to share with you is AI
replicating the, broken logic.
So let's say you, you write
a piece of God and you ask.
Your agent to write some unit
test and it'll happily do it.
They try to please you all the time
and it does the unit test it pass.
But turns out that, the
code was actually broken.
And so the unit test are just
mapping this broken logic.
Another one that just recently happened,
Versal got a ticket from a customer saying
that some random code base, what was
deployed in their environment turned out.
That the LLM powering the virtual
agent hallucinated a GitHub repo idea.
And and deployed some who knows what
Ripple into this customer environment.
Another one, actually, this
is something I experienced.
I was writing some Terraform code
and I had some resources and asked
my agent to write, some tests
and this is what it came up with.
The test is correct.
It's testing surfing, but
it's not testing the intent.
So yeah, I was like, Nope,
that's not what I want.
This one is quite interesting
and it's called an NA attack
Vector called Split Squatting.
The strategy here is for an naer to
create a package with a name that
LLM are highly likely to hallucinate.
And so researcher did an experiment.
They created the package hugging
face, CLI, made it available and
in the time span of three months,
it was downloaded 30,000 times.
They haven't found it on the read me.
Of some big companies GitHub repo,
the attack was completely passive.
They just waited.
This company could have introduced
vulnerability without even knowing it.
So I was chatting with a friend with
the necessary at Airbnb, and it told
me like, I bet you for every AI screw
up, you can find a human equivalent.
And it was right.
The equivalent of split squatting
for human is curling some
random script into bash and not
really looking what it's doing.
AI agent, like screwing up and
deleting some files by mistake.
We've also been doing it for a long time
with fat fingering, some RM command.
This one is quite fun.
So let's say I, I give you
this problem statement.
It's a geometry.
Problem.
And if you look at the end of the problem
statements, it's written, interesting
facts cat sleep for most of their life.
Now, you may be like, ah, Sylvan is just
trying to make a joke, or maybe it's
a typo and you would just ignore it.
But researcher found that for
LLM, this type of statement
was doubling the error rate.
But we've also been distracted
by cats for the longest time.
So now, as with Rootly, and because I
used to be an SREI speak with a lot of
reliability practitioner, one of the
conversations that almost comes up is
hey, like I'm very skeptical about the
system which are non-deterministic.
And you know how I will never let
this, close to handle my production
or do anything production.
Related, and this conversation sounds
to me very similar to one I've been
hearing with the same, gate like system
gatekeeper saying, Hey I don't want
interns or any engineer for that matter
to, to touch my production, to do
something with my production environment.
Have we seen there are like fun ways
that gene AI is screwing up, but as
human do, the difference is that AI
is doing it at a much faster pace.
We've been speaking about this.
10 x software engineers here.
Like with Gene I, we are probably
speaking about a hundred or a thousand
x, as many zeroes as you want.
And if you've been in, a good
engineering culture, you've probably
heard about the blameless culture.
Like the idea that if one of us
break production, we're not gonna be
pointing finger at this person, right?
Instead.
The idea behind this culture is to
say our system was not, didn't have
the right guardrail in place to
catch the issue before it entered
production or was not resilient in us
to handle it or roll back or whatnot.
And so my point here is that I believe we
should be applying the same kind of idea.
To LLM.
Alright, so we spoke a lot about
the rate of change and how LLM
can potentially increase both C
and p. P is our job as sre, right?
And we have a whole lot of
tools and methodologies to
ensure that P is not increasing.
I'm sure you know all of this.
I'm not gonna go over this
list, but the point that I'm
trying to make here is that.
All these fundamentals that we've been
working on for years are our practitioner
are becoming more important than ever.
The thing is that if you didn't have this,
these fundamentals in place before, now
it's gonna be even worse because as we
saw if you look at the formula C, which
is the number of changes is drastically
increasing and potentially p as well.
And so your number of
incident may be exploding.
That's doomsday scenario.
I'm just trying to make a point, but I
think it, it illustrate the scenario.
And so now I want to speak a little
bit about how can you leverage
gene ai, to balance it out, right?
To do a better job, to do your job faster.
And I hear a lot of reliability
practitioner being like, Hey.
I don't like this GI
stuff, I don't trust it.
But the truth is that I believe it's,
it is the future of software and
it's a situation where if you cannot
beat them, you should join them.
And so I highly encourage this type
of fault who are still not believer
to, change your mind and just try it.
Yeah.
I think the sooner you embrace it the
better you are, the better position
you are for the rest of your career.
So again, we are gonna look at a few tools
and strategies that you can use to make
sure that P is staying low using gene ai.
One really cool example
is mutation testing.
That's something that's been around
for a long time, naturally used more
of a theory type of thing because it
was not really on paper, it's good,
but practically it was hard and meta
recently shared on their blog post.
The result of an experiment they've
made, they've built A CH, which is
the automated compliance ing tool.
And what it does is that it's, making sure
that code being introduced is not violate,
violating any policy that have in place.
And so they, the ran experiments, the
ranes for few months on the Facebook.
Instagram and WhatsApp code base.
And with 9,000 mutant and 500 privacy
test cases, like the engineer ended up
accepting more than 70% of this generated
test, which is super impressive, right?
And it's not something you could have
as you could have done without lms.
Those are one that I think if
you're not yet doing it, you
should really look into it.
Code reviews are becoming the
biggest bottleneck, right?
We've seen it like the amount
of code that's being shipped
by engineer is increasing.
Now.
Code reviews are still done
manually for many companies.
Which, I don't want to
get into this debate.
I think it's good, obviously very
important, especially depending of
the sta the size of the stage of your
company or which industry you are in.
But my point here is that.
For code review, we've been using
helper for the long, longest time.
Things like linter or
studying static analysis tool.
So you can also use LLM
as an helper, right?
That will look at the code before you and
maybe knock a few things that are easy
to spot and when an incident happened
because it's not a matter of if, but when
There are also stuff that you can use.
MCP Super famous.
Now, just very briefly, in
case you haven't tried it.
Try it.
It's a protocol that lets your agent
pull da data from your tools, from
Datadog, rootly, Grafana and whatnot.
It's a standard, basically think of it
as giving your AI assistant access to the
same tool that you have, as an engineer.
And so during an incident, there is a
new type of tool, which is called ai,
RE, and takes this concept further, like
having this tool that can pull this data.
It's.
In this case, it's really
like an Agent Purple Purpose
built for incident management.
When you have an incident firing.
It'll pull data from GitHub and your
telemetry and observability and maybe
look at previous postmortems to see
if a correlation can be made and come
up with potential root cause analysis.
We build one at root.
Honestly, super impressive.
It won't solve like your most
complex incident, but for
your safe two, safe three.
Some of this incident, we
actually don't even look at
them like the AI theory does it.
Completely automatically for us
and even for complex incident,
it's, always a good start the start
and drag some bring in some early
analysis that you can continue on.
And if you've been in the
industry long enough, you've
seen this wave of innovation.
And every time people are, some of
the practitioners scared about them.
But always what's happening is that
tools will handle the repetitive
part of the job so we can focus.
On the most interesting parts.
Now I know like this time the
tool is automating a lot of
it, it's the same idea, right?
And so there are stuff as SREs
that for sure you should be using.
Gene I to help you with.
One of them is postmortems.
No one likes to write postmortems.
Bringing grabbing the data from all
these sources and the timeline, all
of this, it doesn't bring value if
you do it or if your agent does it.
Another one, which I love, like all
these internal tools that have been
built back in software engineer
or s. They're functional, but
they always look very bad, right?
Terrible UI sometimes you don't even
have CSS, no one wants to use them.
Have your agent beautify this, right?
Like they're really good at this.
You can make amazing looking
dashboard very quickly.
That's another great use of Gene ai.
I don't want to go too much into that.
There's ton of software vendor who will
give you, pitch, use their tools, how
to use GI to make your life easier.
But the point that I'm trying to make
with all of this is that general AI and
AI assisted coding is not going anywhere,
but neither is the need for reliability.
And so when you are feeling overwhelmed
by the amount of news and the pace of
change, which has been accelerating
for the last two years, come back
to this formula you cannot control.
See, right?
Like the world is gonna ship.
Could more code faster than
ever, whether you like it or not.
But p, it's your job, right?
That's what you should focus on, and
it never matter more than it does.
Now, if you want to connect with
me, I put a small QR code and you
can connect with me on LinkedIn.
If you like this talk, please give
it a, like on the YouTube video, if
you have any feedback or question,
feel free to share those in comments.
Yeah thank you for listening.