Hello everyone.
This is Sathi and today I'm going
to talk about designing for failure
and how to build a resilient
system that can take failures.
Let's start with a quick
thought experiments.
Imagine it's a busiest day, like
some black Friday day if you're
in retail or month end, close if
you're in finance or tax season.
If you are filing tax on April 15th
or the last day, suddenly a critical
part of your system goes offline.
Customers are frustrated, maybe
revenue stops flowing, this scenario
isn't hypothetical, but it's the
reality of the complex systems today.
Things will fail.
Hardware breaks, networks get congested
of warehouse bugs, dependencies become
un, unavailable humans make mistakes.
So for decades, our primary
focus has been to make.
Systems resilient to failure.
So we are trying to prevent
failure at all costs.
We aim for perfect systems
that never will go down.
But here's the reality.
Preventing failures is impossible,
especially as system grow
more complex and distributed.
So what if instead of trying to prevent
failure, we are designed for it.
So what if we accepted failure
as inevitable and build systems
that could gracefully handle it?
So that's what we are going to talk
about today designing for failure.
In the next 10 minutes, we'll explore
why this mindset is crucial and look
at some of the core principles for
building truly resilient systems.
Okay, getting to the next slide.
So why design for failure?
So let's talk about that.
Firstly, as I said, prevention
of failure is a myth.
Chasing a hundred time, a hundred
percent of time will only is
a prevention tactics that.
Leads to diminishing returns, it
becomes exponentially harder and more
complex and expensive to prevent.
Make systems up a hundred
percent of the time.
Secondly, impact of failure in
unprepared systems is often catastrophic.
For example, a small glitch in
one service can cascade and break
down all the entire application.
So think of something
like a Dom domino effect.
So this leads to prolonged outages,
terrible user experience, and
significant business and customer impact.
Designing for failure on the other hand.
Aims to limit blast radius.
It's about building systems
that can withdraw turbulence
without fully collapsing
gracefully degrade functionality
instead of completely failing.
Recover quickly when
failures inevitably occur.
It's not truly about.
Giving up on stability, but achieving
true reliability by acknowledging
and planning for imperfection.
So moving on to what core principles
and techniques we could use.
So let's talk about the core principles
and techniques that we can use.
So this boils down to how do we actually
do this now that we agreed that.
Preparing for failure is a good idea.
Let's talk about what are the
different ways we could do it
and what works for your systems.
On a high level, there are
several key principles and
patterns that we could follow.
Let's touch on a few core ones.
First is redundancy.
So this is one of the fundamental pillars.
Never have a single point of
failure for critical components.
Run multiple instances of your service
services databases, load balances,
ideally across different physical
locations or availability zone.
So if one instance fails the
traffic can be routed to healthier
redundant or backup system.
This is a simple concept,
but it has a massive impact.
Okay, next is isolation.
So think of bulk heads on a ship.
If one compartment floods, the bulk
heads contain the water and prevent
the entire ship from sinking.
And similarly, in our distributed
or complex systems that we are
building, lets isolate components.
A failure in a user profile service
shouldn't bring down the entire processing
payment processing service, for example.
We can achieve this
through techniques, right?
Assigning different resource pools for
different parts of the service following
microservice architecture or Q based
communication and things of that sort.
Next, let's talk about circuit breakers.
Imagine calling a service that
currently is overloaded or down.
Continuously hammering it to make
things works for everyone and making
it, in worst cases, unrecoverable, a
circuit break breaker pattern is used
to address these kind of situation.
For example, if certain failures
reach a threshold the breaker trips
and it stops sending requests for a
short period, returning an immediate.
Error will fall back.
This protect the calling service from
wasting resources and it also gives
the failing service time to recover.
After a timeout, it might let a few
test requests go through to see before
the system is deemed healthy again.
So think of this as like a circuit
breaker in electronic terms.
Next is timeouts and retries.
Don't let your service wait indefinitely
for a response from another service.
Implement aggressive time modes.
Either if a call times out, you
might retry, but do it carefully.
You can use techniques like exponential
back off and limited number of e retries.
Otherwise, you can accidentally create a
retry storm that intensifies the request
to an extent that instead of solving
the problem, it creates a new problem.
Okay, next, let's talk
about graceful degradation.
Sometimes offering partial functionality
is much better than offering nothing.
If a non-critical feature falls, like
for example, displaying some news
articles on a news site can the core
functionality like reading the main
article still work or design new systems?
Keeping this in mind, try to make
your core functionality separate
from the noncritical functionality
so that if noncritical ones fail, it
doesn't affect the core functionality.
And next we talk about now that we have
discussed various strategies, now coming
to the monitoring and observability
aspect which is an absolute must.
Into understanding your system's health.
So add robust logging metrics
failure detection, understanding
the impact, diagnose the root cause,
and verify that your resilience
methods are working as expected.
So you can't really manage
what you can't measure.
So it'll be both helpful in recovering
from a failure as well as doing a
root cause analysis once your failure.
Has been recovered so that you can
prevent it from happening again.
So monitoring is one of the most
important things that you would def
should definitely add to your system.
Alright, now let's move
on to the next slide.
Now that we understood what are the
different ways you can make your system.
Resilient towards a failure.
Let's just try to see how to shift
your mindset because this is, we are
entirely shifting from a prevention
of error to making sure your system
actually works when an error comes.
Let's just talk about that.
Implementing these patterns is not just
about code, it's about a cul cultural
and architectural and mindset shift.
It means developers, testers, operating
teams, operation teams, SREs should
be constantly asking, what happens if
this part that I'm working on fails?
How will the system behave?
How can we contain the impact?
So it encourages practices like kiosk
engineering intentionally we should
encourage, but, practices like kios
engineering, where you intentionally
inject control failures into production
environments to test how the system
actually responds and uncovers weakness
before they actually cause real outages.
So it's about proactively
validating your s resilience.
Alright moving to the next slide.
Concluding I would to talk about.
Failures in our complex systems especially
distributed systems or machine learning,
engineering included systems isn't
an if, but when, or trying to prevent
every single failure is losing battle.
So by embracing the designing for failure
mindset and implementing patterns like
redundancy, isolation, circuit breakers.
Graceful degradation and timeouts
enterprise all supported by strong
monitoring and observability.
We can build systems that are
truly resilient systems that handle
failures gracefully, minimize
user impact and recover quickly.
This leads to higher availability,
better customer trust, and
ultimately more successful product.
Go back to your teams and start asking
this question, what happens if this fail?
Start small.
Pick one critical component
and analyze its failure modes.
Introduce one resilience pattern,
build that muscle, expect failure.
Test it out by injecting the failure,
design for it and build resilience.
Alright, that's all I have.
Thank you.
Let me know if you have any
questions or you can contact me.