Speaker: Hello everyone.
Welcome to the Con 42 Title Level
Engineering Conference 2026.
I'm Uma Mora.
I lead the product for
resilience testing at Harness.
I'm also a co-creator of
Litus Chaos, chaos Engineering
Tool that's hosted at PNCF.
In this session, we are going to talk
about what is resilience testing.
And why it is very important in
the software development lifecycle
that it is almost non-negotiable.
Is resilience testing a negotiable
process in software development lifecycle?
Is it negotiable or not?
That's the topic that we are
trying to delve into here.
For that, let's talk about the outages.
They are inevitable.
No matter how well you are prepared, you
are designed, your systems for resilience.
Outages are inevitable.
Most of the cloud service providers are
top notch in terms of providing good
quality of service, so on and so forth.
But there are outages that we
keep seeing from time to time.
There are different types of outages here.
I've taken two of them.
One is related to the
physical destruction.
For example, the Don strikes caused
the AWS Middle East data centers to
go out of service to some extent.
And what fell there is really
the entire data centers.
Similarly, there are other types
of outages on Azure, for example,
which are related to the policy
or software misconfiguration.
There are different types of values
that happened, one related to
the regional infrastructure laws
or multi az infrastructure laws.
In other cases, service outage
happened because everybody retried
and caused more load on a given
service, and eventually there was
an outage for more than six hours.
The message here is the outages are
inevitable and your businesses need
to be resilient against such outages,
and how can you build your business?
Services that are resilient is a different
topic, but here we are talking about.
Testing if your business services
are really resilient or not,
so that you can take proactive
and informed decision, right?
So just because it is validated
once during the design time,
hoping that it is resilient against
multiple types of failures is not
a good strategy because the type of
failures also keep getting updated.
From time to time, there are new
types of values, new types of
service values that keep happening.
That could be the thing that is changing.
It's not your system design, right?
So don't hope for resilient
systems being there.
You need to verify them, right?
Hope is not a good strategy
against being resilient.
Before we go into the resilience testing
a little bit more, let's talk about
what is resilience in this context.
Resilience is not about validating
that systems are not crashing, and if
they're just standing up your systems
not, are not really resilient, right?
Resilient systems really mean that.
They are gracefully coming back
from failure to active, right?
Resilience is defined in this
context as the grace with which
the systems are handling failures.
Either they are the generic
failures or load or disaster, right?
How your system is handling these
three types of failure and failures
and coming back into the active state
is really defined as resilience.
So the problem around this resilience
nowadays is most of the teams think
that, Hey, it's a data issue, but
now everything is tested, let's.
Go and push it into production, right?
Sometimes the teams think that it's
not my issue, it's an insert issue
because all just happen in production,
so let them deal with it, right?
So that's really the problem,
and that's where the risk is
starting to happen, right?
So the real strategy is to do continuous
testing of resilience, verify,
document it with every shipment.
Which happens most of the
time, very frequently.
So you are continuously testing the
resilience in your delivery process in
your software development life cycle.
That's a better strategy.
So let's summarize once again the
resilience of business services.
If your business services
ought to be resilient.
They need to be resilient against system
failures, load conditions, and disaster.
Just because you tested in one area
you are leaving the risk for other type
of failures, and overall your business
services are going to be active.
So where to focus is the next question.
Obviously, because they are happening
across different types of values, you
need to do them, you need to test them
continuously with every delivery, and
that's where the SDLC outer loop comes in.
So testing is an important part of SDLC,
and then you need to consider doing all
types of testing, not just functional
testing, unlimited load testing there.
Resilience testing really means that your.
Introducing the full fledged load testing,
full fledged kiosk testing, and we are
testing in your software development
lifecycle process in your organization,
and you're looking at resilience testing
as a holistic process, not just as
a three independent different things
done by three independent different
teams, so on and so forth, right?
So if you look at the cost of
not doing resilience testing.
Resilience is almost like
a technical debt, right?
So in technical debt, you are leaving
some known issue on the table and that
can hurt you at a later point of time.
Something similar is
resilience too, right?
If you're not for testing,
the resilience risks.
In your SDLC process, you are leaving
the resilience debt on the table.
That can cause business impact
later on in production, right?
The more resilience, just debt you
have, the more business impact that
it can cause at later point of time.
And the resilience when
the failures happen, right?
And the failures really happen.
With the modern cloud native
and distributed system and the
dynamic nature of them, it's almost
certain that failure will happen.
It is a mathematical certainty.
So with that context, resilience
testing is not a negotiable thing, and
it should be included in your SDLC.
You look at this eight quarters or
10 quarters time, this is what it
takes for your resilience testing
to come to a type of maturity
level that you would be results in.
The more resilience test coverage
that you get, the more feedback
you will receive, your teams will
receive and you'll act on them.
And the business impact, potential
business impact keeps reducing
'cause you have a clear data on what
works, what does not work, right?
And you have acted upon them.
So this is another way of
looking at if you want to have
less impact on your business.
You need to do resilience testing
for a period of time, and you
need to continue to increase the
coverage of that resilience testing,
which is generally a process that
is followed in the SDLC, right?
SDLC.
Things keep improving or a
period of time, either design
dev or tests, so on and so forth.
So the summary here is resilience testing
is not a negotiable thing in SDLC.
If it is not negotiable.
Let's learn a little bit more
about resilience testing.
What are the risks that you would
unearth, so on and so forth.
If you look at this table it's
an integrated systems resilience
risk table where various risks
are listed on your left hand.
And you can see what type of testing you
would use to unearth such a risk, right?
And sometimes the same type of risk
can be uncovered or validated against
more than one type of testing.
For example, a resource saturation.
Or bottlenecks in your systems can be,
tested using chaos as well as load.
But the intensity of such risks can be
different in different types of testing.
So here the message is, the
risks are really of multiple
types that can be unearthed
during multiple types of testing.
We need to look at them as a holistic
type of testing rather than independent
type of testing, house load or d.
And the same thing is depicted here.
Integrated resilience testing can
sometimes give more advanced risk pattern
than they are tested individually.
For example chaos testing and load
testing can be done together and a lot
of, chaos tests that you have developed
can be reused in dr. And you can do more
DR tests more efficient DR tests, more
number of DR tests, so on and so forth.
So you can verify your RPO or
DVO targets more frequently.
And more scenarios can be covered with
the given bandwidth, so on and so forth.
Similarly load when chaos is added
onto the load testing you are
really testing the limits of the
system and the failures, right?
So there is an opportunity to uncover more
types of risks at more frequent intervals.
When you look at all three
types of testings together.
Let's does what and.
The same team, same environment is being
used by two different teams, the load
testing team and the chaos testing team.
And there are time sharing such
infrastructures, which is a
typical problem, the infrastructure
availability for doing this testing
in most organizations, there is an
opportunity to collaborate on the
infrastructure as well as on the
type of tests that that you're doing.
And improve the overall efficiency.
So for example, chaos testing is
done in most environments, right?
The production and load testing
is also done in most environments
or in all environments.
Predominantly in qa but Dell also
can do it for benchmarking and
the services, so on and so forth.
And SS can do load testing for
aligning to the compliance around
a new really withstand against
certain load numbers, especially
if you are providing SaaS services.
Similarly, DR testing needs to
be considered by all personas.
Even developers can contribute to DR
testing by making sure that there's
well validated infrastructure code
systems and in pre-production platform
engineering teams and SRDS can
coordinate together to make sure that.
The DR tests are validated
in QA before they're actually
used in production, right?
So as you can see that the
personas need to come together.
The environments need to
come together and reuse.
The tests that are done for different
purposes in other type of tests,
for example, chaos testing DR.
And chaos testing load can
gel really well together.
So the next one is the role of ai, right?
In most organizations, there is some
sort of effort that's under progress for
developing agent AI frameworks, right?
You want to get better to
whatever you're doing using ai.
So what's the role of AI or how
AI can help in resilience testing,
resilience testing will do well
when you have the best tests and
they are run at the right times.
You can have a huge number of tests and
you don't know when to run them right?
And if you try to run all of them,
that may not be optimal as well.
That's where AI can help, right?
Or you can use AI for that purpose.
You can feed the data that you have
on your proprietary systems, such as
the knowledge base the Wiki pages.
And your incident subscription
data, incident tools, and your CACD
deployment pipelines and so on and
so forth, your infrastructure data.
All of this can be fed in into the
AI agent, and AI agent can give
recommendations about what all the best
load tests, what are the best chaos tests.
What are the best scenarios for
DR testing, so on and so forth.
And it can also look at the
events at runtime and tell you
what would be a good test to run
at a given point of time, right?
That's could be a potential role of ai.
Some of the products are already
trying to move in this direction.
Now let's talk about a tool that does
all these three testing ads together.
That's harness resilience testing.
Harness resilience testing is an
upgrade of Harness Chaos Engineering.
We have seen customers trying to
do chaos testing together with the
load or using chaos testing for Dr.
So we have introduced native
capabilities of load testing
and DR testing in the product.
We named it as resilience testing.
It does exactly what it was doing for
chaos, but in addition, can create and run
load test visually or together with chaos.
Similarly, you can create your
workflows along with already
created kios and so on and so forth.
So this is a OneStop shop for doing
the resilience testing of any type
or a different types together.
Here is a screenshot that you can see.
The module has three different
types under one single product.
Or you can do this testing
through a single pane of glass.
It also gives you an opportunity to
bring all the type of risks together.
The risks that are.
Detectable through chaos or through
load, or through dr. All risks are
coming together so that you can have a
comprehensive look at what are the risks
of the system or what are the trends of
this risks that are being found in SDLC
and ACT account act upon accordingly.
So do give a try of
resilience testing module.
It's available as a free version as well.
You can find more details on Harness Ivo.
With that, let me summarize the
content of this session, resilience
testing, is it negotiable?
Really not?
The business impact will keep
growing with resilience debt.
So you need to tackle resilience
testing as a holistic picture
at the earliest in SDLC.
You need to bring all personas, all teams
together and try to reuse the resources.
Not only the test, but
also the environments.
Create a joint action plan so that
you are doing an improvised overall
resilience testing and use your
a efforts to to do more efficient
resilience testing, both in creating
resilience tests as well as running
the resilience test at the right time.
And finally have a look at the harness
resilience testing product that provides
the entire end-to-end capabilities
related to resilience testing.
That's all I have for this session.
Thank you very much.
Have a great rest of the conference.