Welcome everyone.
My name is, and I'm excited to
talk to you today about network ion
harnessing EBPF for Cloud-native
observability superpowers.
We are embarking on a journey to
explore how this powerful technology
EBPF is fundamentally changing how
we observe and understand our cloud
native environments, essentially
granting US observability superpowers.
As organizations increasingly adapt
containerization and microservices,
particularly with Kubernetes, the
networking layer that invisible
mesh connecting everything
becomes incredibly complex.
It often turns into a critical blind
spot for operations and SRE teams,
we find that standard monitoring tech
tools frequently struggle to provide the
necessary depth and real time insight
required in these highly dynamic systems.
This talk aims to demystify EBPF,
which stands for Extended Berkeley
Packet Filter, and demonstrate how
it provides deep surgical visibility
directly from the Lenux kernel itself.
A key advantage will explore is how it
achieves this level of detail without
imposing the typical performance overhead.
We often associate it with traditional
methods like deep packet inspection
or extremely verbal s logging.
Over the next 20 to 25 minutes, my
goal is to bridge the gap between this
powerful low level kernel technology and
the practical actionable strategies you
can implement in your own environments.
Let's f first clearly define the
problem we are addressing the
Kubernetes networking blind spot in
cloud native architectures, especially
when employing service measures are
dealing with hundreds of microservices.
The communications pathway between
them become incredibly intricate.
These invisible connections and complex
dependencies are often dynamic and not
fully captured by static configurations or
even infrastructure as code definitions.
This is where traditional monitoring
approaches often fall short.
Many rely on sampling, grabbing
data points intermittently or
aggregating metrics over time.
While useful for high level trends,
this inherently loses the fine
grain detail needed to understand
transient issues or the exact sequence
of events during network problem.
This leads to limited visibility.
Operation teams are left grappling with
troubleshooting challenges, trying to
diagnose complex distributed issues
without detailed realtime insights
into the actual network traffic flow
between parts, services and nodes.
It's like trying to debug a tangle mess
of wire with the lights partially off.
So what is EBPF, how it helps
us see through this complexity?
EBPF stands for Extended
Berkeley packet filter.
While the original EBPF was primarily
for filtering network packets,
EBPF is a revolutionary technology
that acts like a lightweight.
Sandboxed virtual machine
inside the Linux kernel itself.
This allows us to run custom event
driven programs whenever specific kernel
event suckers like network packets being
processed, system calls being made, or
kernel functions being entered or exited.
This kernel level integration is key.
We are getting data right from the source.
The extended part signifies
its program loyalty.
Going far beyond simple filtering.
This enables surgical precision because
EBPF programs run in the kernel context,
they can access data structures and
react to events with minimal overhead.
Capturing detailed information at
microsecond resolution without relying
on sampling, think specific protocol
details, latency measurements for
individual requests or tracking.
Specific system calls related
to network activity, all without
the heavy cost of traditional
packet capture or tracing tools.
Crucially.
EBPF prioritizes safe execution
before any EBPF program is loaded.
It undergoes a rigorous
verification process by the kernel.
This verifier checks for loops.
Auto bond, memory access, and other
potential issues to ensure the program
cannot crash or compromise the kernel,
this safety guarantee is what makes
EBPF suitable for running directly
in the production systems at scale.
Let's crystallize the differences between
by comparing EBP of based monitoring side
by side with more traditional methods.
Looking at data collection,
traditional approaches typically
use sampling at intervals or rely on
agents pulling metrics periodically.
EBPF in contrast, performs
continuous event driven capture
directly at the Len Kernel level.
This fundamental difference
signifies significantly impacts
performance traditional agents.
Especially those doing deep inspection
or relying on user space processing
can introduce noticeable overhead.
EBPF being kernel native and highly
efficient boosts a near zero performance
penalty for many observability tasks.
Then there is visibility depth.
Traditional monitoring often provides
aggregated or service level metrics
useful for, but often lacking granularity.
EBPF allows us to dive much deeper
accessing packet level details,
system call information, and
fine grain latency measurements.
Implementation also differs.
Traditional methods often involve
deploying user space agents or site cars
while EPPF integrates directly with the
kernel, often managed by a platform or
agent that leverages kernel capabilities.
Finally, realtime analysis.
Traditional methods are limited by
their collection intervals, whereas EBPF
can observe and react to events at the
microsecond level, enabling true realtime
insights and even automated actions.
The shift to EBPF isn't
just an academic exercise.
It delivers tangible.
Significant improvements
in real world operations.
One of the most dynamic
impacts consistently reported
is a massive reduction.
In meantime to resolution MTTR
for network related incidents.
Organizations frequently see
MTTR slashed by over 70% complex
baffling issues that previously
took hours or even days to diagnose.
Can often be pinpointed in
minutes with deep visibility.
EBPF provides beyond
reactive troubleshooting.
E-B-P-F-M powers preventative detection by
continuously monitoring granular network
behavior and establishing baselines.
Teams can detect septal anonymous,
like increased latency, unusual
connection patterns, or rising
error rates before they even
escalate into user facing outages.
This real time visibility enables
proactive responses and adjustments.
Furthermore, this deep understanding
of network traffic directly
translates to cost optimization by
precisely, identifying
inefficient communication pattern.
Like Charity services sending unnecessary
data across availability zones or external
networks, our nations can optimize
traffic flow and resource allocation.
As mentioned, one enterprise
saved over $200,000 annually by
optimizing cloud networking costs.
Based on this EBPF insights,
a standard capability enabled by.
EBPF is the ability to automatically
discover and visualize the intricate web
of service dependencies in real time.
Because EBPF sees a all network
traffic at kernel level, it can build
a complete topology map of which
services are communicating with other
how often, and with what latency.
This is incredibly powerful
because it often reveals
undocumented legacy or simply.
Unexpected relationships that aren't
defined in Kubernetes manifests
or service discovery systems.
We move beyond static diagrams
to a live view of reality.
We can also perform temporal analysis,
watching how this dependencies and
communication patterns evolve over time.
This helps understand application
behavior under different
loads or during deployments.
By analyzing traffic patterns, like data
volumes and communication frequencies, we
can pinpoint bottlenecks, identify overly
chatty services, or discover opportunities
for caching or communication optimization.
Crucially, EBPF allows us to
trace complex dependency chains.
We can follow a request as it hops
between multiple service, even across
different namespace or clusters.
Providing the true end-to-end
visibility needed to troubleshoot
distributed systems effectively.
EBPF continuous granular data stream
is perfectly suited for sophisticated
realtime anomaly detection.
The process often starts with
baseline establishment, where
EBP powered monitoring systems
observe traffic over time to learn.
What constitutes normal behavior for
specific services and communication paths?
This could include typical latency
ranges, error rates, protocols
used, or connection frequencies.
Once a baseline is established, the
system performs deviation detection.
It continuously compares live traffic,
again as the learn baseline automatically.
Identifying statistically significant
deviations or abnormal patterns
without requiring engineers to
manually set and maintain potentially
brittle static thresholds.
When an anomaly is flagged, EBPF
provides rich contextual alerts.
Instead of just saying high latency
detected, an alert might be specific
like latency between service A and
service B increased by 300 milliseconds.
Affecting the specific
parts via this network path.
This context, drama drastically
speeds up diagnosis.
Furthermore, this realtime detection can
trigger automated response mechanisms
based on pre-define rules or specific
traffic patterns detected by EBPF.
Example, a certain surge in D-N-S-R-S.
You could trigger automated
workflows for remediation.
Like restarting a part, rerouting traffic,
or collecting more detailed diagnostics.
Adapting.
EPPF might seem daunting given its
kernel level nature, but there are
practical approaches to get started.
The key recommendation is to start small.
Don't try to boil the ocean.
Begin with single Kubernetes cluster.
Maybe even just spec, just a specific
namespace or application, focus on
addressing a particular pain point first,
perhaps improving troubleshooting for
a critical service, or simply mapping
the dependencies of complex application.
Next, you need to select tools.
There's a vibrant ecosystem.
Open source projects like
Cilium, which uses EPPF effect
extensively for networking.
And security Pixie from New Relic
focused on auto instrumented.
Observability are Hubble.
Part of cilium for network
visibility are great starting points.
Commercial platforms often
built upon these, offering more
integrated experience, longer data
retention, and enterprise support.
You'll need to enable kernel support.
Most modern Linux distributions
and cloud provider images support
the necessary kernel version.
Generally four point 18 or later.
For broad features, though,
newer is often better.
Ensure your notes, meet the
prerequisites for the tools you choose.
Finally and crucially,
integrate workflows.
The insights from EPPF are most valuable
when they feed into your existing process.
Connect the data to your primary
observability platforms like
Grafana, Datadog, et cetera.
Integrate alerts into your response
systems like PagerDuty or Ops Gen,
and use the visibility to inform
your CSAD and deployment strategies.
Let's illustrate the potential with the
real world case study from the demanding
financial services sector, a global
payment process dealing with stringent
performance and reliability requirements
implemented EBPF based observability.
Across their extensive Kubernetes
platform, they were facing challenges
managing the complexity of over 200
interdependent microservices where
network issues could have immediate
and significant financial impact.
The results were striking.
They achieved 70% faster troubleshooting
critical payment processing issues,
which previously could take hours of
painstaking lock creation and guesswork.
We are now consistently
resolved in minutes.
Thanks.
Thanks to the granular
visibility provided by EBPF.
They gained complete visibility into
their service mesh successfully mapping
the intricate dependence between all
200 plus microservices, uncovering
previously unknown interactions.
Perhaps most impressively, they
leveraged EPPF capabilities
for automated remediation.
By detecting specific network
anomaly patterns in real time,
they were able to trigger automated
self-healing actions for approximately
85% of common network issues.
They encountered significantly
improving platform resilience.
This case highlights how EBPF delivers
not just insights, but also enables
automation and improve stability in
complex mission critical systems.
While operational stability and
faster troubleshooting are major wins.
EBPF also unlock significant cost
optimization benefits by providing
unparalleled insight into exactly how
your network resources are being consumed.
A major driver for cloud costs is often
network egress by providing EPPF to
precisely identify and quantify traffic.
Flowing between different availability
zones or out to internet organizations
can pinpoint inefficiencies.
Optimizing this cross zone traffic
patterns based on EBP of data has led to
substantial savings with examples showing
reduced egress scores of up to 43% sim.
Similarly, EBPF can reveal
unnecessary or overly chatty
communications between services.
That might be consuming valuable
CPU memory and network bandwidth.
Eliminating or optimizing these
communications guided by EPPF
insights leads to lower resource usage
overall, sometimes by as much as 28%.
Furthermore, having precise
real-time visibility into actual
service traffic loads enables
much faster scaling decision.
Instead of relying on cores, grain
metrics or guesswork, you can
rightsize your deployments based
on observed demand leading to more
efficient resource utilization and
potentially faster scaling actions,
improving both cost and performance.
One report indicated 52%
faster scaling decisions driven
by these precise insights.
Hopefully, you are now seeing
the potential of EBPF and
wondering how to get started.
In your own environment, here's
a practical path forward.
First, learn, dive into the fundamentals.
There are fantastic resources online.
Check out like example, e
bpf.io, vendor blocks, conference
talks, and documentation.
For specific projects like cilium
or pixie, understand the core
concepts like tropes, maps, the
verifier, and common use cases.
Second, experiment theory is great,
but hands-on experience is the key.
I. Set up a non-production environment,
maybe a kind cluster on your
laptop or a dedicated dev cluster.
Deploy some of the open
source tools we mentioned.
Try instrumenting a sample application
and explore the data you get back.
Third, measure.
Once you have something running,
quantify the benefits in your context.
Can you troubleshoot a known issue faster?
Using the EBP of data, can you
identify an optimization opportunity?
Gather metrics to build a
case for wider adoption.
Finally, once you have demonstrated
value and build confidence, you can
scale plan a phase rollout to your
production environment, integrate
EBPF observability strategically into
your standard operating procedures.
Start small, learn, measure,
and then scale with confidence.
So that brings us to the
end of our exploration.
Of network excavation using EBPF.
We have discussed the challenges
of observability in modern cloud
native systems and seen how E-B-P-F-A
powerful solution by offers a
powerful solution by providing safe,
efficient kernel level visibility.
We have touched upon its real world
impact from drastically reducing
troubleshooting times, and enabling
proactive anomaly detection to
visualize complex dependencies and
drive significant cost optimization.
The key takeaway is that EBPF is no
longer just an niche kernel technology.
It's becoming a fun foundational
component for robust, efficient, and
observable cloud native platforms.
I strongly encourage you to investigate
the tools and techniques we discuss
today and consider how they provide
superpowers for your own team and systems.
Thank you for your time and attention.