Hey everyone.
I am Dave back, and welcome to my talk.
Today I will discuss about how
AI is transforming healthcare
claim adjudication, an area that's
historically been bogged down
by lots of manual processes and
inefficiencies that leads to rising cost.
We will explore how AI technologies
enable faster, smarter, and
more accurate claim processing.
While also helping reduce fraud
and improve overall satisfaction
for the providers and members.
So let's get started.
So those who are familiar with the United
States Healthcare System, they know us.
Healthcare spendings a lot.
To put it into prospective, last
year in the year of 2024, US spent
like approximately $4.9 trillion.
That's roughly 17.6
percentage of nation GDP.
And that's a lot.
And when that, there's a wastage happen
on that close to $5 trillion, even a tiny
percentage seems a lot to give some stats.
On that roughly 30
percentage of the claims.
In, in all the insurance companies
together, they do manual processing and
that means real human efforts for every
third of a claim, and that's a lot.
Administrative costs in US healthcare
is roughly three $50 billion annually.
It's a massive chunk of it goes into
processing and reprocessing claims.
The average claim cycles is
about 45 days from submission
to payment to the providers.
And there is also roughly 7.5 percentage
error rate, which can lead to denials,
resubmission and provider members.
Frustration of course.
So as you can see, this entire
process needs a lot of disruption
because claim processing takes a
lot of spending in various aspect,
and also that involves fraud.
So we have to see how AI can
help this entire workflow.
So to, to get to get started, we have to
see how AI is stepping in to improve this.
There are multiple ways.
The first would be the automation through
RPA, which is robotic process automation.
That helps process routine
claims which are rule based,
repetitive and has a pattern logic.
Definitely takes away a lot
of manual efforts out of it.
And the next one would be the,
some kind of an intelligence.
No, via machine learning ai that can
identify patterns, detect anomalies,
and even learn from its own adjudication
outcome so it can get better.
And another one is.
Going to be through some NLP.
That plays a significant role by
extracting structured data from
unstructured clinical nodes and documents.
Because healthcare system is full
of different entities, each of
them maintains their own system.
So there is a potential for.
Lot of unstructured data.
So NLP can help to make them structured.
So some kind of an intelligence
can help to process those, make the
process more efficient and faster.
And finally it's gonna be the
validation through some AI based
ruling gene that can dynamically apply
peer policies to, to incoming claims
so that the policy check intact.
And we know whatever intelligence
is applied, it's being validated
and thoroughly checked.
So going from here what does all do?
We implement all of
these what it can help.
So the first is going to
be the faster processing.
Of course.
It's definitely gonna be faster
than manually adjudicating millions
of claims some organization have.
Noticed that it reduced adjudication time
up to 75 percentage, and that's a lot.
It also comes with accuracy improvements.
Error rates can drop up to 80 percentage,
which means fewer claim denials and
fewer appeals either from members.
Other providers.
This also leads to a 30 to 40%
reduction in operation cost.
So that means fewer people, fewer
correction, more claim process per day.
So the efficiency definitely increase.
And of course the last.
Not the least is most important
is everyone is happier
when things process faster.
Provider get providers get paid
faster and the members experience
fewer delays and the complaints.
So overall the system gets
more efficient, streamlined.
And smarter, so everybody
gets benefit out of it.
Now, if we look into some case
studies, there are a few there are
a few insurance companies that the
insurers now or the peer, they have
tried various AI stack in their.
Claim adjudication, workflow and and
observed many significant results in us.
There are many insurers.
Some of them are highlighted
in the case studies.
One of, one of the example involved.
Implementing machine learning for
complex claim types like specialty
pharmacy claims that needs a special
type of approval authorization
approvals and processing those claim
because it's a very high dollar claim.
Auto adjudication as a result of
implementing AI improve almost 80
percentage resulting in millions of dollar
in annual savings and higher provider.
Satisfaction.
Another peer adopted NLP to analyze
clinical document documentation in
real time which led to a 65 percentage
reduction in processing time and
significantly improved fraud detection.
And last one is a robotic process
automation helped increase monthly
claim capacity by 1.5 million claims.
And that's a lot.
Because oftentimes we get a lot of
claims based on a commercial health plan.
And you have to process them on
time so that you don't get delay
on provider payment, otherwise
you have to pay interest.
So if we apply some kind of RPA
stack in the claim processing
workflow, it definitely helps.
And it makes things faster and oftentimes
accuracy also increase than your
manual trim processing because whenever
there's a manual process involved, that
oftentimes leads to a manual error.
Now.
Now let's talk about the fraud
detection because it's also one of the
important part of claim education now
how it can help specifically how AI
can help to detect the frauds and be
compliant with your compliance like
hipaa and other healthcare compliances.
So the first one, it can spot
unusual behavior in the billing.
That comes in the regular claim files
whether it's medical claims other
hospital claims like UBO four or CMS
1500, no matter what type of claim it is.
In your EDI gateway.
You can filter it through all this
unusual behavior and the AI can also
check the historical pattern from the
same providers or the across various
providers to match it up and map all these
animals to detect the unusual relationship
with the claim and the providers.
That certainly helps
with the claim volumes.
And the second one is, can automate the
alert system, some kind of a suspicious
claims on the very early on, on the
claim adjudication cycle before even it
goes for a full adjudication routine.
So that oftentimes reduce
the system load and more of a
detection at the very early on.
So overall fraud detection
accuracy can improve as much as.
60 percentage with AI compared
to traditional rule-based system.
So now moving on the
implementation roadmap.
So if you as a healthcare
insurer wants to implement AI in
your daily claim adjudication.
Workflow, how do you do that?
So there are multi-step process.
So the first one is definitely going
to be the assessment, understanding
your current workflows, identifying
the highest impact area for automation,
because that's gonna be your main focus.
And then from there on, you pilot you
pilot your assessment into a pilot
program targeting few set of claims.
See how your AI model results
and validate those results.
And if your validation comes
through positive, you can expand
this to a large number of claims.
So basically you scale the solution
across more claims categories.
And finally, once that is.
Stern, you can integrate everything
into your core architecture
for seamless operation.
That's that way you can eventually
get the benefits of the AI
implementation in your claims stack.
Now what's next?
Now the next is very in
terms of AI is very bright.
A lot of industries are definitely
implementing ai, healthcare of time
lags because we have to comply with
lot of regulation, compliance and
government and stuff like that.
But it has many things that
we can certainly incorporate.
The things that it can go is towards
the self-learning AI models, meaning
they just don't follow the rules,
but they also continuously adapt.
I. To new types of claims
and improve themselves.
The timeframe might vary, but I am looking
to see next three to five years, we will
have like tremendous amount of growth
on that area where when the AI models.
Are more matured handling
privacy handling healthcare data.
Then we can also include the
blockchain validation that is also
gaining a lot of traction because
it's transparency and immutability.
So you can basically verify on a open
ledger and potentially reducing the
disputes and enabling the smart contract
based adjudication routine, and and the
last one we will also see a lot of these
probably is not already happening is that
AI and the and the human kind of an hybrid
system where AI handles all the bulk of
decision ma making map decision making,
that's a more rule-based repetitive.
And then you have your human experts
that focuses on the more complex logic.
Now the challenges and the consideration
that we need to look, even though we
are so excited about having AI into our
workflow, not just healthcare for any
industry, every industry specifically
healthcare comes with a lot of challenges.
The one that I have already mentioned.
There are many entities in healthcare
industry and everybody follows their own
data, streamline various data structures.
So data quality is one of the
biggest that it has to overcome.
So AI always work with some kind
of a input data that is clean,
consistent, and standardized.
So if it is.
Not that, then it'll definitely
has lot of room to improvement.
So we have to focus on that, and
that's, right now it's a challenge.
Second one is going to
be regulatory compliance.
That rightly because healthcare is a very.
Privacy focused sector where
information about the member
and the provider has to be kept.
Private and regulatory involvement
from the government is very important.
So we cannot just let any ai to
to handle those data without any
following rules and guidelines.
So that's very important.
And we also.
Have to be careful when we implement the
staff training and change management.
AI changes, oftentimes job roles, and that
transition must be done very thoughtfully.
And finally, the ethical
implementation is very critical
because algorithms must be transparent.
Explainable and free from bias.
Bias is very important because it
oftentimes can take any decision
that may go wrong, specifically when
it comes to the healthcare system.
Now comes to the ROI
and the business case.
Now, at this point of time, it's quite
evident that eventually every business
will implement some sort of an ai.
Healthcare is not prone to that,
not immune to that implementation.
But at the same time, there is
a clear case of of good ROI like
the business case is very strong.
Most organizations see ROI within.
12 to 18 months when it is implemented
fully, and productivity also increases.
There's a cost saving there,
there's a reduction in error.
And when we give enough time from the
full implementation till three years,
fast forward, as you can see on my
screen, the maximum potential is achieved.
And that's where.
Things started to get compound when we
scaled the solution in a large scale.
When you process millions of claims
on a regular basis and you start
to see your ROI and other metrics.
Now moving on, what's the next step and
the resources now, if you are considering,
in stepping into this journey where you
wanted to plug in different AI stack
into your claim adjudication workflow,
the first step is, would be to have
some kind of an implementation guide or
some sort of a playbook in your roadmap.
Any possible schedule a consultation
to assist readiness to some experts who
are who are expert in the field or who
have already done it, and if not, attend
some kind of a workshop training session
to upscale your team and then possibly.
Leverage some kind of an ROI tool that
can give you a prediction of how much
savings you can do if you implement
some kind of an potential some kind
of an AI stack into your workflow.
But no matter what, the transformation
doesn't happen overnight.
But with the right strategy,
it can absolutely be achieved.
So keep that in mind.
Whenever you implement this going
forward in any of your health plan.
Now, with that, I would conclude my
talk and I would like to thank you.
So thank you for tuning in.
This is give valuable insight about
how AI izing healthcare adjudication
system and if you'd like to explore
more further, feel free to contact me.
I would love to continue have
this conver conversation.
Thank you so much.