Hello everyone.
Welcome to my talk.
My name is Rahul Amte and I
work as a cloud architect.
I've been working in IT and in cloud
technologies for more than a decade now.
Today my topic is AI and chaos and energy,
and how we can implement smarter failure
system testing for resilient systems.
We'll start with introduction.
AI is transforming chaos.
Moving from manual failure testing
to intelligent, productive, and
automated resilience validation.
We'll cover foundational concepts
and then look into AI integration
and real world use cases.
So what is our agenda today?
It is the flow.
We'll begin with chaos
engineer and its evolution.
Then explore why and how a AI enhances it.
We'll go through the architecture
tools, case studies, and close with
the best practices and future trends.
With that, we'll move on to
explain what is chaos engineering.
Can you imagine your systems going down
at 3M in an night, but coming back by
themselves, by recovering by themselves?
But what if there is no
human intervention needed?
But before which, what if you can
test the whole scenario that in simple
words, is inducing chaos engineering.
Chaos engineering involves
running controlled experiments
to test the system's ability to
withand turbulent conditions.
Netflix was the first one to introduce
this to ensure system reliability,
especially for distributor systems.
Next, we'll move on to core
principles for chaos engineering.
These principles guide the practice, so
we start with a steady state hypothesis,
introduce real world disruptions, run
in production, automate the process, and
always minimize the risk of blast radius.
Let's now talk about
the evolution of chaos.
Engineer.
How did it start?
Netflix Chaos Monkey.
From an ecosystem to a full ecosystem
of tools like Lin and Litmus Chaos,
chaos Engineering has matured into
a discipline engineering practice.
It is now integrated with CICD pipeline
and the all workflows to induce chaos
engineering and test the systems.
Going on to the limitations.
So what are the limitations of
traditional chaos engineering?
Traditional methods are limited.
They rely heavily on manual
scenario selection and lack of
automation in analyzing results.
This slow down learning and scale
where AI can jump in and help us
and solve the problem, we'll move
on to why AI in chaos Engineering.
How does it help?
AI actually can enhance chaos, meaning
by making predictions generate.
Dynamic test scenarios and analyzing
system behavior in their time, reducing
the manual overhead significantly.
But what are the key AI capabilities
to our resilience engineering?
We'll look into that.
Key capabilities conclude
anomaly detection through machine
learning, forecasting component
failures, and reinforcement
learning for scenario planning.
Of course NLP.
Analyzing incident reports.
Incident reports as in data is definitely
a key AI capability for chaos engineering.
How does the workflow work?
Let's look into AI and the chaos
engineering workflow together.
So this is how AI fits in.
From collecting the observability data
to generating hypothesis, designing
chaos experiments, injecting forms, and
using real time analytics for insights
and remediation in the bottom line.
Your observability data, as in your
logging monitoring observability data
is a very important component for this.
So let's actually now look at a sample AI
power architecture on AWS cloud provider.
This is how the whole integration of
integrating and inducing the Chaos
Monkey works for your systems like EC2.
Also, there's multiple other use case
architectures where you can include
parameters open elementary as input
and AI ML models for anomaly detection.
So what are some of the
tools in chaos engineering?
Let's look at some popular
tools in chaos engineering.
A snapshot of popular tools
includes Chaos Monkey.
As I mentioned, Netflix started all,
basically when you're watching a
stream, a show on Netflix, and you
will not even know that the systems
were down on the backend on Netflix.
How?
Because they have tested it multiple times
using Chaos Monkey and made sure it's
a seamless streaming for the audience.
MBR also offers a SA
model, which is another.
Chaos Engineering tool limit Chaos
is a Kubernetes native tool and
chaos toolkit is fully open source.
And again, all these tools have their
strengths and all AI integration ship.
Let's look at how these tools integrate
AI into the existing tools which
your enterprises or companies or
organizations might be already using.
AI doesn't need to replace existing tools.
It can enhance them.
For instance, chaos Toolkit can
use AI based probes for validation.
Lin can use ML insights
for targeted attacks.
Litmus chaos on the other side supports
the AI driven workflows as we speak.
Let's look at couple
of quick case studies.
As I mentioned, Netflix
was the first to try this.
The tool is called Chaos Monkey.
It's just one part though.
They now used corrective analysis
and AI based simulations sim
simulations to such resilience
of the global streaming services.
That's why we never see at least 9.9% of
the times we don't see Netflix being done
resulting in highly available systems.
Another case study we can talk
about is Lin, which is another
AI chaos engineering tool.
They come with integrated with ml. It was
used in a Fortune 500 form and it actually
proactively rejected risk systems and
states and resulted in the reduced inquiry
time by 60%, avoiding major outages.
This is very big win for thems since they
are operating critical trading systems.
So now, so what are the benefits
of AI driven if you want to
integrate AI into chaos engineering?
There is fast reduction of failures,
reduce downtime, more accurate
tests, and serve learning systems
that adapt to changing environments.
It's a big leap from what we
have to the traditional static
testing to the AI driven.
But of course, every benefits
comes with challenges and risks.
So some challenges and risks
are air brings complexity.
Morning tuning is very important.
You'll have to trust in its decisions.
Data quality issues and governance.
So it is critical to keep a human
in the loop when AI is used for
resilience testing, as well as making
sure the models are fine tuned as per
the observability data, KPI metrics.
Next, let's move on to best
practices for implementation.
Always start small experiment in
your dev environments, sandbox
environments, make AI explainable.
Collaborate with multiple teams
like S-R-E-M-L, ai DevOps teams,
and most importantly track APIs
like availability, latency and
TPR to measure the real impact.
That's how we can put into practice
and make the best use of this.
And there are some amazing resources
from awesome chaos engineering.
It talks about the tools,
papers, and community projects
and open source initiatives.
It's a very good difference
for interested to check out.
To conclude, what is the
future of chaos Engineering?
Things self failing systems, autonomous
chaos agents, root cause analysis,
powered by gen, AI and chaos testing
across hybrid and multi-cloud platforms.
AI will lead this evolution, and
you don't have to answer a, call it
3:00 AM anymore because your chaos
engineering software is taking care of
it because you have tested, experimented,
and tested it multiple times.
Thank you for your time today.
I appreciate it.