Good morning everyone.
My name is Mark Izu.
I'm the lead DevOps
engineer at Botanics Labs.
I wanna start with a confession.
I love failures and not just because I
enjoy watching systems crash and burn.
But because each failure teaches us
something profound about our system
that success could never teach us.
And that's just a personal opinion.
But think about it, when was the last
time we learned something deep or a very
deep engineering lesson from something
that's working perfectly or a system
of use that is working perfectly?
That's right.
It's the failures that shape us.
It's the failures that force us to
grow the reveal, the hidden weaknesses
in our most carefully crafted
systems, in our most stable system.
It's the failures that teaches
us the flaws in our designs.
It's not the social stories,
but the failures and the fixing.
The fixing of the failures.
That is what Teach forces us to grow.
I wanna thank you for joining me in
my talk today on engineering failure
resilient systems and proactive strategies
for distributed network reliability.
I would say I've spent the last couple
of years in the trenches building and
sometimes breaking distributed systems,
but yeah, that's just for the fun of it.
Today we're gonna cover why failure
is innovative in distributed systems,
common failure patterns, proactive
resilience strategies, and building
resilient teams and culture.
I would say it's a
meaningful presentation.
Just I try not to be too technical and
just go over the, just go high surface.
It is three.
The systems are down, services are halted.
A lots are blowing up.
What now?
Your boss is on your neck.
The whole team is gathering up.
Need the dashboard is all
painted red services are down.
What do you do?
MI microservices can't connect.
No external assets.
We've all had that point in time
in our career where we've had to
wake up to those annoying alerts.
It's unavoidable.
It's really unavoidable.
It's what?
It's what makes us engineers essentially.
Failure is not the exception.
It's to brew every time something,
everything fills all the time.
Where NoGo is the Amazon CT o set in
distributed systems, failure isn't
just possible, it's inevitable.
The question is since if your
systems fail, but when, how, and
at what cost, what would be the
cost of your system failure, what
is in that service level agreement?
What is in what are those indicators?
What is the cost for a system for you?
What is the cost for that?
One hour of no assets to the systems.
What does that cause The system.
The key point here is in systems
with thousands of components,
something is always filling something.
One system is receiving
more traffic than the rest.
The something is always
happening here, essentially.
I had ask this question, how
many of us here have experienced
the failure in production?
Again, you can see all hands are up.
Essentially that's just to tell us
the output and what it feels like.
Essentially having a system failure.
We've all experienced
that outage in production.
We've all experienced that quick
fix, that deployment gone wrong.
That no running out, running
really high on temperature.
We've all experienced that.
Every hand here represents a
lesson learned about resilience.
I. That's, we can, as a Spiderman
meme indicates we're all pointing
fingers and pointing hands, but no,
we shouldn't point hands at ourselves.
These systems are bound to fail.
It's all about engineering this
system to be failure resilient and
knowing what to do and what next on
the next line of action essentially.
Then we look at the cost of downtime.
What is the real cost of downtime?
As asked earlier, when Amazon's S3
experienced the four R outage in
2017, it cost companies over the.
Over 150 million.
These failures creates ripples around in
industries, reliant on cloud services.
Look, think about the customers,
how they felt regarding this fall
out during this fall out outage.
This shows how.
Interconnected.
We are in the or hyperconnected.
We are and reliant on certain services.
And this is, this asks the question,
what is the real cost of downtime?
What?
What is the real cost of downtime in
your system, in your service beyond
traditional reliability engineering,
which focuses on maximum uptime
through redundancy at four tolerance.
These approaches are necessary,
but are they sufficient for today's
complex distributed environments?
We ask ourself due to the limits
of uptime metrics, resilience of
our redundancy, and preparing for
the unknown Metrics like uptime and
availability are no longer sufficient
for just to ensure system reliability.
Modern infrastructures must plan to.
Must plant for failure proactively.
You must.
These systems must be designed
and architected for resilience.
They must be architected for to plant
for failure within them, essentially,
because failure is not the exception.
It's the rule.
Here we talk about the pillars
of resilience, engineering, and
the five pillars of resilience
engineering as outlined here.
They are antifragile architecture,
chaos, engineering processes, system
breaker design, circuit breaker
design, architecture patterns,
dynamic resource allocation, and of
course monitoring and observability.
Because you cannot fix
what you do not know.
You cannot fix what your, you
can't monitor, essentially.
So we look at to antifragility,
what Antifragility looks like.
Anti.
What is anti fragility?
The question is, unlike resilient systems
that re resist failure, anti-fragile
systems grow stronger through disruptions.
They use adversity to evolve and adapt.
This is incorporating chaos
input, real time feedback, and
diversification to create systems
that optimize on that stress.
The key word, optimize
on that stress here.
And then we look at chaos
engineering practices.
The case study here would be
Netflix's Chaos Monkey two.
Which one do terminates
production instances?
This wasn't madness, it was survivor.
Think about this.
Look at it in this way.
Your systems are gonna fail either ways.
There's always gonna be that increase in
traffic or in increase in system load.
So why not recreate it yourself?
Why not plan for it
yourself where you have.
Total visibility on the system where
you have, when you know and you
can monitor what is going on and
how, what failure looks like when
you are in charge of the failure,
you are orchestrating the failure.
Exactly.
So that's what Chaos Monkey is about.
I'd advice you looking
to the Chaos Monkey.
So because that's
learning true, deliberate.
Failure.
The key points there, determinates,
random instances in production.
Ensure systems can handle failure
component and just transformed into
this, an entire discipline of chaos,
engineering, and multiple companies
all around the world incorporate this
type of care, this type of discipline
in their services, basically.
Basically, because you have to learn.
True deliberate failure.
You have to plan for the failure.
You need to take control
of what failure looks like.
Then we look at circuit breaker
architecture part design patterns.
A circuit breaker is a pro is a
protective and safety mechanism
that prevents the application from
continuously making requests to a
service that has problems or is done.
This is basically isolation as a strategy.
Think about, a distributed system
where of 10 nodes, where two nodes are
down and you have a circuit breaker
in in, in front of the systems.
When you implement a circuit breaker
design part down the traffic and
traffic would never be directed to
the 14 nodes because the circuit
breaker is, are aware that those nodes
are 40 and therefore traffic would
be directed to the held in nodes.
Circuit breakers prevent
cascading failures by failing.
First when downstream services
degrade, essentially, then we look
at dynamic resource allocation.
Here.
We encourage or we.
We come coincidence with self
healing system that automatically
respond to changing conditions.
We look at Kubernetes portal
auto scaling as a case study that
scales based on cost metrics.
We look at predictive scaling systems
that analyze historical patterns and
scale preemptively resource portals that
automatically redistribute adequate.
We distribute capacity during
degraded performance and intelligent
load that prioritize traffic base
on business impact Then of all.
Monitoring of and observability,
like I earlier said, you
can't fix what you can't see.
Logs, traces, and metrics together from
the backbone of modern observability stack
that gives engineers actionable insight.
Monitoring must always establish
baseline behavior and detect anomaly
automatically is your monitoring and
observability stack should always
be able to distinguish between noise
and actionable signals because you
do not want your engineers waking up.
In the middle of the night for noisy
signals for or un actionable alerts.
Basically, that's why you have to build
at a stable and proactive monitoring
observability stock for your service.
Now we look at common failure patterns.
This is fine.
So failure pattern number one,
we look at cascading failures.
The look at multiple case study
here, which will be, provided
in the documentation we look
at Slack's 2021 global outage.
We look at the Netflix Eve, Netflix,
Christmas Eve outage in 2012.
These are example of retry stops.
We look at failures due to
resource contention, the
Robinhood trading outage in 2020.
These are example, these are public
examples of what failure or what
common failure patterns look like.
E essentially.
Secondly, we look at operational failures.
We look at when there is a configuration
drift, a deployment problem, or
human error configuration drift.
Firstly, when there is a slight change
in configuration, maybe from a a
third party provider or even from a
user, we, the case study here is the
Salesforce database outage in 2019.
Look at data deployment problems.
Look at TSB Bank.
Migration failure in 2018, which
occurred when they tried to migrate
their services from one provider to
another provider, and they run into
deployment issues because this were not
planned for this deal, not preemptive.
Look at the night capital trading loss
in 2012 and the Amazon SD outage in
2017, which a whole lot of services
globally were heavily relied upon.
We look at.
Failures due, operational
failures due to human error.
GitLab data loss in 2017 were
where a GitLab engineer mistakenly
deleted production db and the
outage was due, was out for, and the
services were out for four hours.
These are things we do not want to happen.
But they are common failure patterns.
Failure due to human error.
Look at failure pattern number
three, which is software failures.
Failures due to resource
exhaustion, dependency failure.
We look at the GitHub details.
I would encourage you to look at
the GitHub leaders incident in
2018 and the Reddit outage in 2016.
These are failures due to resource
exhaustion when systems aren't
architected or built in resilience
or to act to scale for when there's
when there is an increase in traffic.
This is what happens, dependency failures.
When the.
System is updated or there's a system
upgrade and there is no accountability
on what dependency looks like.
Look at that Stripe.
A PIA case study will be the
Stripe API Outage in 28 in 2019,
and fastly CD CDN outage in 2021.
What was achieving 99.999?
Reliability look like the five nine.
Reliability just means five
minutes of downtime per year.
Is that possible?
When broad says downtime,
it's can we do that?
Is that achievable?
What does achieving down?
What does this look like?
What does achieving five
minutes of downtime look like?
It looks like eliminating
all single points of failure,
implementing zero downtime.
Deployments and rollback.
Designing for partial availability during
degradation, redundant infrastructure,
resilient network architecture,
comprehensive monitoring, and also
on the code level microservice design
pattern with resilience patterns.
Essentially, that is what achieving
five nights means, essentially
five minutes of downtime in a year.
It's achievable.
It is, it's possible when we plan for.
A reliable system.
That is what we achieve basically.
So we look at the resilience
engineering toolkits, what's how
we can identify fragility code, PA
code and patterns, and monitor and
measure for identify fragility.
We use architecture, architectural reviews
and failure modeling to look at single
pain of failure and fragile dependencies.
By fragile dependencies, we
look at mean dependencies that.
That are actively updated or
actively wrote that we don't want
to design our systems on those
kind of dependencies because we.
We need to be able to
account for those changes.
Essentially, we look at how we architect
our code and the kind of part, the kind
of software partners we used in designing
our applications, because basically that's
where the that always is the bottleneck.
If we don't have accurate foundational
patterns or proper foundational patterns,
then we also need to monitor and measure.
Monitoring our measurement in our
resilience code toolkit because we
need to define our SLIs and slus the
indicators and the objectives and the
error budgets, and we also need to
have proactive dashboards and treat to
observe this system health in real time.
In conclusion, I feel.
Can only be embraced essentially.
That's why we need to embrace the
inevitable is your system built
to break and bounce back stronger.
Failure is not a risk, it's a certainty.
Building failure, resilient distributed
system requires bold design and continuous
experimentation and culture of resilience.
With the right tools and mindsets,
we can build systems that don't just
survive chaos, but thrive in it.
Thank you very much and.
I will be willing to answer any
questions about system resilience.
Thank you very much once again.