Hello everyone, this is Peush K. Thank
you for joining me today here I have
more than 20 years of IT experience in
US healthcare, developing and maintaining
software projects and programs.
So here today we are going to talk
through a topic that's rapidly
gaining traction across healthcare it
implementing AI driven observability.
As SE practices for reliable healthcare
systems, the integration of artificial
intelligence in healthcare systems
offer tremendous potential to improve
patients' outcomes, but it is also
presenting unique reliability challenges
when AI systems supporting critical
healthcare functions experience downtime.
The consequences can
directly impact patient care.
This representation and this presentation,
which we are going to discuss here will
say how site reliability engineering SRE
practices are being successfully adopted
to maintain exceptional availability
in AI powered healthcare platforms
based on real world implications.
Across multiple healthcare institutions,
our focus on how these practices ensure
the reliability of AI powered platform
is critical for healthcare environments,
when even milliseconds of downtime
can have a life altering consequences.
Whether you are a healthcare provider,
a tech vendor, or an SRE team.
Is stepping into regulated domains, you
will walk away with actionable insights
and established blueprint for implementing
these practices in real world environment.
In this slide, we will discuss the
AI healthcare reliability challenges.
So we start how this unique
reliability challenges.
Are affecting healthcare, artificial
intelligence, AI systems increasingly
influence clinical decision
making, diagnosis, treatment
planning, and patient monitoring.
A model failure or downtime doesn't
just create technical issues.
It directly affects patient's
outcomes, regulatory compliance.
Hipaa, FDA and other healthcare
standards, we have to comply with
all these standards based on the
geography to successfully implementing
and using AI in healthcare facility.
From a regulatory standpoint, we
face a stringent requirements, hipaa,
which is health insurance Portability
and Accountability Act in US GDPR.
Which is General Data Protection
Regulation in Europe and Food and
Drug Administration, FDA, they
all see AI as a medical device.
This imposes a strict controls
on how we update, monitor,
and validate these systems.
Healthcare AI system faces unique
challenges that the traditional
SRE approaches must adopt.
To address patient safety directly
depends on systems reliability,
creating zero tolerance situation
for certain types of failure.
Meanwhile, complex regulatory
requirements add additional constraint.
To how system can be
monitored, tested, and updated.
Finally, there is a constant push and
pull between innovation and reliability.
AI evolves rapidly, but
healthcare infrastructure is
built on safety and stability.
This mismatch requires.
A refined approach to SRE
one that merges technical
robustness with clinical caution.
So here, let's move on to third ipo.
Important aspect, how it is affecting
the case studies, which shows the
automated observability and its benefits.
The observability transforms into
impacts our case studies, access
multiple hospitals and shows a 78%
reduction in meantime to resolution
and TTR for critical incidents.
But how?
By integrating AI powered observability.
Platforms that continuously
monitor not just technical metrics,
but clinical relevance too.
These systems achieved a
92% variance detection rate,
capturing early sign of AI drift or model
flatness before they could affect care.
65% decrease in incidents we
saw year over year in clinical
incidents, and that is under 30.
It is a practice.
Our multi-institutional cases studies
demonstrates dramatic improvements through
implementing automated observability
tools, healthcare organizations.
Participating in our research deployed
specialized monitoring solutions
designed to detect subtle anomalies
in AI prediction patterns before they
manifested as clinically relevant issues.
Organizations like Mount
Sinai and Mayo Clinic are
developing AI to prevent issues.
Rather than reacting to them, the key
is a shift from reactive monitoring
to proactive variance detection
using machine learning techniques
on logs, metrics, and user behavior.
Now, let's cover how establishing
meaningful SLIs and SLOs.
For healthcare, AI service
level indicators, SLIs and
service level objectives, SLOs
shapes the foundation of SRE.
However, in healthcare, they
require a tailored lens.
We categorize them into technical,
clinical, and operational indicators.
Let's cover technical sli.
Inference latency, less
than 200 milliseconds
and model drift, which we aim to keep
below 0.5% to ensure diagnostic relevance.
Batch processing completion, 99.9% API
Availabilities for supporting systems.
99.95%. Clinically, we track
diagnostic suggestions, accuracy
and override frequency, an indicator
of clinicians trust in the system.
Operational metrics includes
time to detect variance.
And recovery time objectives
under clinical and uh, sli.
You can see here that there is a
documentation completeness score.
There is a clinician's override
frequency under operational recover,
incident response time, recovery time
objectives, and change failure rate.
By aligning these with key clinical
performance indicators, KPIs.
Like treatment relevance or documentation.
Completedness, we ensure that our AI
goals serve both system and patients.
The collaboration between SRE teams
and clinician is very crucial here.
SRE teams across participating
healthcare organizations
established novel SLIs and SLOs.
Is specifically designed for AI systems.
The most successful implementations
balanced traditional reliability metrics
with healthcare specific indicators
tied directly to clinical outcomes.
In one project, we found that
tracking clinician override
frequency was more informing.
Then raw model accuracy, and it directly
indicated trust and ultimate adoption.
These metrics were developed through
close collaboration between SRE
teams and medical professional.
Ensuring then technical reliability is
aligned with the patient care priorities.
Chaos engineering.
In healthcare ai, a safe approach.
When you see, and you read and listen,
this word chaos, you definitely
want to go far, far away if you
are in the healthcare industry.
But here I would say that the
chaos engineering may sound
risky in a healthcare context,
but with the right safeguards,
it's a game changer We conduct.
Fault injection experiments in sandbox
environment using synthetic patient data.
That would be a isolated environment.
Then we move on to control failure.
As you see here, it is graduated
fault injection with safeguards.
What does it mean?
So this allows us that we will
go to conduct intentional.
Fault injection experiments
in the Sandboxed environment.
This allows us to test
resilience of AI system.
Like what happens if an inference
service slows down or if a
prediction pipeline fails.
Every step is reviewed by clinical
experts and before it even go to
pre-production, and the result is.
Better system is strengthening.
For example, we identified a
cascading failure risk in a sepsis
decision model that would have gone
unnoticed without simulated faults.
With a graduated testing approach
and a tight clinical oversight, chaos
engineering becomes not just safe.
It essential for reliability.
Our framework for chaos engineering
practices safely applied to healthcare
AI systems and it revealed how controlled
failure testing identified resilience
gap in prediction pipelines before
they affect production environment.
Organization implemented,
graduated approach.
Beginning with fully isolated
environment using synthetic data as
confidence grew more sophisticated.
Failure models were tested, and always
with multiple layers of safeguards and
clinical experts oversight to prevent
any potential impact to patient care.
Now let's cover the error budgeting.
For clinical AI implications,
error budgeting is another core
SRE principle, and it adapts
beautifully to healthcare ai.
Here we define reliability
targets based on the clinical
impacts of each system component.
For instance, an AI system
generating post visit summaries.
Has lower risk compared to one
recommending oncology treatment.
We are going in a step
by step progression here.
Define reliability targets, then
allocate error budgets, then move on
to implement graduated alerting, which
is a tiered by budget consumption rate.
Then we move to balance
innovation and stability.
Where we adjust deployment pace based
on the budget of the facility, we
distribute error budgets accordingly.
We use safeguard alerting and
aligned deployment pace with
the remaining budget one.
Hospitalist studied.
We saw a 64% reduction in non-actionable
alerts after implementing this approach.
How impressive.
Importantly.
This allowed them to innovate more
rapidly in low risk areas while
safeguarding critical functions.
This tiered approach allows more
aggressive innovations in the low
risk areas, and enforcing is stricter
controls or components directly
influencing clinical decisions.
And as I just told you, it's
very impressive reduction rate.
So now let's discuss how
continuous verification of AI
model in production is required.
We all know that AI is based on the
data and we, nobody can disagree that
the real world data is ever changing.
So unlike traditional softwares.
AI models degrade over time.
So what happens here?
Continuous verification helps
us manage that degradation.
Predeployment, we validate
models against benchmark dataset.
We then use shadow deployments
running new models.
In parallel without affecting live
outcomes to observe their performance.
AI models are living systems,
they degrade, and so we
treat model verification as a
continuous multi-phase pipeline.
The step we took here is all you can
see on this screen, pre-deployment
validation, shadow deployment in parallel.
Canary rollout with rollback
triggers and live drift
monitoring and age case flagging.
Canary release allow controlled
traffic shifts with rollback triggers.
One organization reported a 72%
drop in model related incidents
using this multi-stage verification.
Continuous verification techniques
in AI model enable safe deployment.
And this approach combined traditional
AB testing with healthcare specific
verification steps, including
clinical review panels, and, and we
have seen an impressive reduction
in the incidents Importantly.
We don't just rely on statistics.
We include clinician panels to review
age case scenarios before full rollout.
This ensures safety while
supporting innovation.
Next slide.
We are coming here.
Git Ops for healthcare, AI
compliance and reliability.
I have captured into three broad
segments here, infrastructure and
code, automated deployment pipelines,
and then compliance automation.
Git Ops brings the consistency
of software engineering into
healthcare AI infrastructure.
We define infrastructure as
code and what does that mean?
We versioned infrastructure definitions,
declarative system configurations,
automated compliance validation,
and change history documentation.
We have continuously watching the
continuous integration and continuous
deployment ci cd pipelines here.
This supports regulatory
mandates from hipaa.
High Trust, which is health Information
Trust alliances and GDPR by ensuring
DUPLICABILITY and auditability.
Automated pipelines include clinical
sign-off and auto rollback mechanism.
Automated deployment pipelines also
covers that SLO value violations.
We would be able to
roll back automatically.
Immutable artifact management,
progressive delivery patterns,
PHI, which is protected.
Health information is tightly
controlled and rollback is triggered
if the SLO violation is detected.
Git ops let us deploy changes confidently.
Even in regulated environments.
Several hospitals, networks
are now using tools.
Like Argo CD and Flex
CD for the same purpose.
This is how we are really using
and enhancing the SRE system.
Let's talk about the financial
impact of SRE in healthcare ai.
So that's all the numbers
we are showing here.
Initial investment in observability
and SRE tooling is non-trivial.
Definitely there is a initial, significant
investment is required, but the ROI
comes fast across cases studies.
The average time to break even
was seven and a half month.
Some institution got returns
in as little as four months.
Financial analysis across participating
organizations demonstrates that
despite initial investment healthcare
system achieve substantial returns
within months, there is also
a softer but critical benefit.
IT clinicians trust and satisfaction
improved due to fewer disruptions.
Leading to higher
adoption rate of AI tools,
one large hospital system saved
over $1.2 million annually.
After adopting these practices
and saw a noticeable boost in AI
adoption and clinical satisfaction,
how impressing it is because if
the clinicians are satisfied.
They will be motivated to use the
AI tools, and that is where we need
to make sure that their satisfaction
index continuously grows and
improves through SRE practices.
Here comes the time when we want
to bring all of that together.
If you are thinking of adopting these
practices, here is the blueprint.
First of all, we need to make sure.
That we formulate a cross-functional
team and what the team comprises of
it should have SRE engineers with
healthcare background, clinical
stakeholders, compliance and security
specialist, and then AI ML engineers.
Then we move on to
assessment and planning.
Then these assessments maps out.
Critical system and evaluate
your technical depth.
It is part of system inventory,
current reliability metrics, baseline
compliance, requirement mapping,
and technical depth evaluation.
Third step would be
foundational implementation,
including observability tools.
Service level objectives, their
definitions and continuous
implementation, continuous
deployment, pipeline improvements.
It includes the, and that's the
foundational, because we don't want to
go at a larger scale in the beginning,
and that's very important aspect here.
So we go slow, but we go.
With less and less errors and
more benefits, uh, very soon,
organizations that follows these
phased approach showed significantly
higher reliability scores and smoother
scaling of their AI initiatives.
This actionable blueprint provides a
structured approach for SRE leaders.
Implementing and maintaining
reliable AI systems.
Our research identified that
organization that achieving the
highest reliability score followed
a similar implementation pattern.
Starting from the cross-functional
team formulation and to ensure
both technical and clinical
perspectives are well represented.
The most successful implementation
maintained a phased approach.
Establishing core observability
and measurement capabilities before
advancing to more sophisticated
practices like chaos, engineering
and advanced automation.
So what are the key
takeaways and next steps?
So, healthcare, ai, right?
It needs to be specialized AI approaches.
A standard SRE practice must be
adopted to address the unique
reliability requirements and regulatory
constraints of healthcare environment.
Financial ROI is achieved and it's
significant, but before we come to
the ROI, we also want to make sure
that we go with the cross-functional
corroboration and then we go smart small.
Measurable constantly and then
expand method methodologically.
So the most successful implementation
bridge the gap between the technical
reliability and clinical impacts through
structured collaboration between SRE
teams and healthcare professionals.
The future of AI in healthcare.
Depends on our ability to make
it safe, scalable, and stable.
Despite initial investment requirement,
healthcare organizations constantly
achieved substantial returns through
improved reliability, reduced incidents,
and better resource utilization.
The integration of AI in healthcare.
Continues to accelerate making
reliable operations, not just
a technical consideration, but
patient safety imperatives.
By implementing the SRE practices
outlined in this presentation, healthcare
organizations can reconcile the seemingly
competing demands of rapid AI innovation.
With the stability requirement of critical
care infrastructures, as I told you that
SRE is the crucial part of this journey.
Thank you.