Hello everyone.
I'm Prakesh Wanger.
Overall, 13 years of exchange experience
specializing in AWS Cloud engineer
and identity access management.
Currently serving as an AWS
data engineer, designing and
implementing scalable and secure data
pipelines, leveraging a W Services.
I'm really excited to be here
to talk about something that
at the intersection of ai.
Cloud infrastructure and real
world business impact using Cloud
native A to fight financial fraud
in real time and doing it reliable.
Today, financial institutions
face critical challenging
detection, sophisticated fraud
pattern across billions of digital
transactions while maintaining
system reliability and performance.
In this session, we.
Drive into how site level engineers
are SRE Empower financial institutions
to build cloud native AI systems
that detect fraud at scale.
Without compromising speed, availability,
or user trust, we will explore how to
architecture infrastructure capable
of subsecond responses, time handle
mass, transactions, volume, and still.
The gold standard of 99.9% of time.
This is about more than
just dropping fraud.
It's about building resilient in inte
and systems that form the backbone
of modern financial security.
Going to next slide.
The challenge faced in this is ma,
mainly speed, scale and security.
Let's start with the problem.
Create financing systems, processing
billions of transactions daily,
exposing them to constraint
sophisticated fraud attempts.
Legacy systems which analyze data in
batches, however often transaction
happens, simply don't work anymore.
The challenge is huge.
Detect fraud in real time across.
Master volumes while keeping
latency under a second and blocking
increasingly advanced attacks.
For SRE Site Engineer, this means
balancing performance, scalability,
and security all at once.
Going to next slide, our experience
from batch to steaming bank,
mentioning the architectural evolution.
We started with a traditional batch
processing system where analyzing data
happened hours after transaction happens.
That delay led a lot of false
prostitutes and frustrated customers.
To fix this, we transitioned
to a streaming architecture.
This was a big shift.
We introduced Kafka team to process
even in a real time, ensuring data
flows continuously instead of.
In Changs, we added future store
to provide low latency access to
historical data, giving our models
the context they need instantly link.
This gave us real time insights and
fraud detection that keeps us the modern
threats and we move to microservice based
models are enabling real time interference
with auto-scaling so we can meet.
Demand without sacrificing
speed are reliability.
Going to next slide.
Let us see the resiliency
patterns for a Systems.
A Systems bring new kinds of failure modes
that traditional SR methods, sometimes
they return results too slowly to handle.
These we adopted.
Specialized resilience patterns.
We use circuit breakers to detect
when models are overwhelmed,
falling back to similar rule-based
system to keep transactions flowing
and avoiding cascading failures.
We built graceful degradation
paths where critical fraud checks
continues, even if deeper analysis
needs to be passed during peak.
Loads and with automated canary
analysis, we deploy new models to
just a small portion of traffic.
This let us monitored metrics like latency
and false positives before a full rollout,
reducing risk, while improving quality.
Going to next slide.
Specialized observability for ML systems.
Traditional monitoring tools weren't
enough for our a fraud detection systems.
They simply couldn't capture the
complexity of model behavior or connect
technical issues to business impact.
We need to see how our A models
were performing and how that
performance affected the business.
So we built a specialized
observability stack focused on model
performance, data quality, and.
Business relevance.
We now track interference latency
prediction, competence, and compute
usages across different model versions.
We monitor data drift by detecting changes
in statistical properties of input future,
so we know when real world transaction
start to differ from training data with
explainability tools, we visualize why.
Transaction was flagged.
This is a key for both debugging
and gaining stakeholder trust.
And finally, we correlated technical
metrics with business outcomes like
fraud, losses, our customer friction.
So we are not just monitoring systems,
we are tracking what actually matters.
Going to next slide.
Then we have service level objectives
that balance, security, and experience.
Setting service level
objectives for fraud.
Detection isn't just about uptime.
It's about balancing multiple,
often completing goals, security
accuracy, posture, approvals,
and a smooth user experience.
Traditionally, service level
objectives focused only on
availability, but that wasn't enough.
So we built a multi-dimensional
service level objectives framework
that combines both technical
metrics and business impact.
We track availability at 99.9% while
keeping detection latency under 200
milliseconds for a seamless experience.
To ensure quality, we aim for a false
positive rate below 0.5 percentage, and a
fraud detection rate above 98 percentage.
And to maintain trust, we required a
hundred percent explainability with
clear reason codes for every decisions.
This framework help us to make smart
trade off when we need to balance depth
of analysis with real time performance.
Going to next slide,
s Engineering for fraud systems.
Fraud detection is a
high stake environment.
Failures he can lead to
immediate financial loss.
So traditionally, K os
engineering, which often involves
breaking things in production.
Instead, we designed a specialized
approach that safe and controlled
within chaos experiments in replica
environments that matter production, using
synthetic transactions data to stimulate
both normal and fraudulent behavior.
Each experiment is hypothesis
driven, targeting specific failure
modes, and most importantly, we
evaluate that degradation path work.
Payload triggers correctly and
automatic recovery mechanisms
do what they are supposed to do.
This way we gain the confidence
of Kio testing without risking
real money or user trust.
Going to next slide.
By applying SRE principle tailored
specifically for aid driven fraud
detections, we saw a major gain across
both technical and business dimensions.
The biggest win was a 78% reduction in
detection time, which let us intercept
fraud before transactions were completely
preventing laws instead of trying to
recover it later, we also cut false
positives at by 60, 63% days, which
directly improved customer satisfaction.
Favor legitimate transactions
were wrongly flagged.
Few users experience
delays at the system level.
We maintain 99.99 percentage
availability, ensuring constant
production without downtime.
And finally, we you a 42% cost
production efficient infrastructure.
Going to next slide in financial services,
we are bound by strict regulations
which can clash with the fast moving.
Trade to nature of tech to balance both
our SR team built specialized workflow
that supports continuous compliance
without slowing down innovation.
We translate regularity requirements
into technical controls using
infrastructure as a code to ensure every
deployment is repeatedly and immutable.
We also established a robust
models governance framework.
Document training data model logics, and
how each ties back to a business need.
Lastly, we implemented
automated audit trail logging.
Every system change in detail.
This allows to reconstruct systems
state at any time, ensuring traceability
and audit readiness at all times.
Going to next building a. AI
fraud detection systems is in
just about adding more power.
It's about thoughtful architecture.
Our blueprint focused on decoupling
components, so if one fails, it
doesn't brings the whole system down.
We built in redundancy and ensure a full
observability, not just for technical
metrics, but for business impact too.
We break the system into reliable
domains, each with its own scaling logics.
This given us flexibility, especially
when deploying new ML models, which
often have unpredictable demands.
At the foundation, we use scalable cloud
infrastructure with multi-region failover.
Our data layers uses resilience event
stream from guaranteed delivered.
The model layer is with the
smart loading balancing.
And finally, the observability
layer uses end-to-end insight
across system health model behavior.
Going to next slide.
A fraud detection systems can be
seen as risky and complex, but
with the Rights R practice, they
become a community advantage.
When reliability is built into a
foundation, our nation can deploy more
sophisticated models faster with greater
confidence and lower operational overhead.
And this value doesn't
stop at fraud prevention.
The same fraud structure can support
personalization, risk scoring
are market analytics creator a
multiplier effect across the business.
To get there, we recommend
a three steps approach.
Assess current capabilities.
So identify reliability gaps and
performance bottleneck using SRE
principle, building foundational
patterns before scaling.
Implement key patterns like
circuit breakers and observability.
Measure business impact.
Align technical reliability with outcomes
like reduce fraud, losses, and better
customer experience by doing this.
We turn relatability into, not just by
technical goal, but a business strategy.
Finally, thank you.
Thank you all for your time.
If you are working on fraud detection AI
system just trying to make your systems
more relatable, I would love to connect.
Let's keep building systems that
are not only smart, but also
strong, forced and trustworthy.
Thank you.