Hi everyone.
Good morning, good
afternoon, good evening.
Depending on where you are when you
are listening to this presentation.
I'm Smith Verma and I'm thrilled to
discuss how AI powered autonomous systems
are revolutionizing incident response
for site reliability engineering teams,
and how AI is transforming the way
the things are done, and by making a
significant impact on security landscape.
My goal for this session is to
explore the challenges of modern
infrastructure, the transformation
role of AI in incident management,
and then provide practical steps to
implement these systems effectively.
So let's dive into the challenge.
In today's digital landscape, SRA,
teams are getting overwhelmed with
the volume of alerts, sometimes
numbering in thousands per minute.
Obviously with that many alerts, it's
nearly impossible to manually triage and
respond to these alerts, especially when
mere minutes can mean the difference
between stability and cascading failures.
The complexity is further amplified by
the modern architecture, microservices,
containers, hybrid cloud environments.
These technologies, while they
are powerful, but they introduce
interdependencies, that traditional
human-centric incident response model
struggle to manage even the most skilled
teams find it that challenging to
maintain system reliability at this scale.
Let's try to understand this
with a hypothetical situation.
When a microservice in a contra
containerized environment starts
exhibiting latency, the single issue
can ripple through dependent services
leading to widespread degradation.
If we were to manually identify and
mitigate such an issue between thousands
of alert, we can compare the situation
to finding a needle in a haystack.
So now let's talk about how
we can better the situation.
So enter AI powered autonomous systems,
a paradigm shift in incident management.
These system use advanced pattern
recognition to detect anomalies
across vast and disparate data sets.
Identifying subtle correlation
that is undetectable to
human operators in real time.
Beyond the detection, these systems
excel in intelligent classification,
assessing threats in within the context
to prioritize response effectively,
they can execute predefined playbooks
at machine speed, ensuring that there
is rapid mitigation of incidents.
Moreover, these con, the continuous
learning capabilities mean they
evolve with each incident, be
becoming more experienced over a time.
So let's take an example.
Imagine an AI system that detects unusual
pattern of database queries, which
indicates a potential SQ injection attack.
It classifies the threat, it blocks the
malicious IP and alerts the security team.
All within seconds, isn't it?
Just awesome.
Now, this doesn't end here.
The implementation of these
AI powered autonomous system,
the yield amazing results.
So let's look at them closely.
Let's talk about meantime
to resolution reduction.
We have seen that organizations
have reported significant decrease
in meantime to resolution with
some achieving even 60% over 60%.
This acceleration in resolution
time minimizes downtime and
enhances user satisfaction.
Now let's talk about false positive.
These advanced AI systems,
they have achieved a false
positive rate as low as 5%.
Ensuring that alerts are
both accurate and actionable.
These precision reduces alert
fatigue and allows teams to focus
on genuine threats 24 7 coverage.
So unlike human operators AI systems,
they can provide continuous around
the clock monitoring without fatigue.
Ensuring that these incidents are detected
and addressed promptly at any hour.
And last, but not the least, the return
on investment, the efficiency and accuracy
of these systems, they translate to a
substantial ROI, with some organizations
even witnessing a 95% return within
the first year of implementation.
These metricses underscore the
profound impact of integrating AI
into incident response workflows.
Now imagine a situation where a
financial situa financial institution,
they implement an AI driven incident
response system and observe a 60%
reduction in MTTR, meantime to resolution
reduction and enhancing their service,
availability and customer trust.
Wouldn't it be just
great for their business?
Modern autonomous systems, they're
equipped with sophisticated response
capabilities that were once the domain
of seasons human experts, network
segmentation, automatically isolating
Compromise network segments to prevent
lateral movement of threats effectively
containing the potential breaches.
Container isis isolation, immediately
quarantine the suspicious containers
while maintaining service availability
through redundant in instances,
ensuring that malicious activities
occurred without disrupting operations
dynamic resource allocation.
Intelligently redistributing compute
resources to maintain critical
service performances during incidents,
optimizing resource utilization
and ensuring service continuity.
Automatic rollbacks, just
instantaneously reverting to known
good configuration when deployment.
Trigger performance
degradation, minimizing the
impact of faulty deployments.
And the key advantage,
it lies in the speed.
These autonomous systems, they operate
at a machine timescales often containing
and mitigating threats within seconds.
Example take an event of detected
malware outbreak within a container.
The system can automatic
autonomously, isolate the affected
container, deploy a clean instance,
and reroute traffic seamlessly.
That's such a great experience.
Now let's try to dive
deep into case studies.
Let's examine a real world incident of
preventing cascading database failures.
So in t plus zero seconds an anomalous
query pattern is detected in the primary
database cluster in t plus 1.5 seconds.
The AI system classifies this as a
potential resource exhaustion event.
In t plus three seconds.
An automatic query is throttling,
tottering is activated for
noncritical services to alleviate
load in plus six seconds.
The re traffic is rerouted
to secondary replicas to
distribute the load effectively.
And then in D plus 30 seconds, an alert
is generated for the SRE team with
comprehensive diagnosis diagnostic data.
So in this scenario, the autonomous
system identified and mitigated the
threat within seconds, preserving the
system's availability and preventing
what could have been a major service.
Outage affecting millions of users.
And if you were to think of this in a real
world scenario, consider an e-commerce
platform during a peak sale event.
An unexpected surge in database
queries could overwhelm the system.
So an AI driven response can detect
the search, throttle the non-essential
queries, and maintain service continuity.
Now let's take another case study.
Mitigating a zero day vulnerability.
So in another instance, a previously
unknown vulnerability was exploited
in a web application framework.
So a couple of things here.
We had behavior anomaly detection.
So the AI system, it identified unusual
process behavior across multiple instance
indicative of a potential compromise.
Traffic pattern analysis.
So they were able to co correlate
these anomalies with suspicious
network connection, strengthening
the suspicion of malicious activity.
Next, in the containment, the
isolated affected the isolated,
the affected containers.
And implemented traffic filtering
rules to prevent further exploitation.
And then forensic package creation.
They generated comprehensive forensic
data for the security team to
analyze and address the root cause.
The rapid autonomous response that,
that contained the attack before the
sensitive data was exfiltrated showcasing,
showcases the critical advantage of
behavior based detection over the
traditional signature based approaches.
Now, if I were to think about this
from a real world example think of a
tech company which has faced a zero day
exploit targeting their web servers.
An AI driven system would be able to
detect irregular server behaviors, isolate
the compromised instance, and provide
detailed logs for forensic anana analysis
effectively neutralizing the threat.
Now let's talk about implementing
challenges, implementation
challenges, and solution.
So implementing AI powered
autonomous incident response.
Is not as easy as, plugging in us on a
smart system and forgetting about it.
So it requires thoughtful
planning and problem solving.
So let's just talk through the top
three challenges that we have seen
that businesses face and what are
the strategies to overcome them.
So the first one is algorithm reliability.
So the toughest challenge is trust, right?
These systems, they are making
decisions during high stake incidents.
What happens if the model faces
something it has never seen before?
So we can mitigate this by
introducing confidence scoring.
If a model is uncertain, the system
will es escalate the incident
to a human rather than guessing.
Additionally, we continuously
retrain models with fresh incident
data and regularly run adversial
test to make sure that the system
is resilient to the edge cases.
Next is integration complexities.
So most companies, they don't have
a single source of monitoring truth.
Instead, they use a patchwork of
tools across different environments.
We address this by building
standardized API adapters for all major
observability and logging platforms.
We also roll out integration in
read-only observation mode at first.
This gives the team a chance to
evaluate the AI performance without
risking the unintended actions and
the third piece is human oversight.
So we don't want to replace SREs.
We want to free them from the noise
so they can focus on what matters.
We apply a tired tiered
au autonomy framework.
So systems starts with minimal
authority and gradually earns
trust as they prove themselves.
Everything is auditable and the teams
always retain the ability to override
or reverse autonomous decisions.
The challenges are real, but with the
right strategies, they are solvable.
Next, let's talk about maintaining
observability and transparency.
So transparency is the
foundational requirement.
SREs doesn't, don't understand
how a system made a decision.
They will never trust it no matter
how accurate it's, so we use three
pillars to maintain the transparency.
The decision tracing, which means that
every automate automated action is
logged in full details, including the
input signals, the confidence scores,
and the logic or the model that is used.
This enables SREs to trace any incident
postmortem and understand exactly what
the system saw and why it acted that way.
Next is explainable ai.
So we have implemented visual tools
that break down complex decisions into
digestible human readable formats.
This might include a heat map of
signal anomalies, a decision tree
visualization, or an incident replay
that shows how the event unfolded.
These tools built trust and they also
help identify areas to refine the ai.
And third human AI
collaboration interfaces.
So we don't want AI in a black box.
Our dashboard will surface every
autonomous action, explain its
relational rational, and allow
one click override or adjustments.
This creates a partnership between
automation and human judgment.
The system handles routine noise and the
SREs focus on strategy and edge cases.
Ultimately, our goal is to create
AI that's just not powerful, but
understandable and accountable.
Now let's talk about
implementation roadmap.
So let's walk through the roadmap of
rolling out autonomous incident response
in a safe and scalable way safe.
So this is a blueprint that
we have successfully used
in enterprise environments.
So the first phase is
the assessment phase.
So here we start by cataloging incident
types and current response workflows.
So look for patterns where, you
know high volume, low risk events
that could be safely automated.
Next, monitoring enhancements.
So before we automate
anything, we need visibility.
So this phase will focus
on improving telemetry.
Adding richer signals, reducing noise,
and tagging data for better context.
Then passive learning mode.
So deploy AI systems in
observation only mode.
They watch incidents, they make
predictions and generate recommendations,
but they don't take any actions yet.
This phase is critical for trust building.
Teams can compare the system's suggested
responses against actual outcomes,
and start to validate the value of
the AI supervised AU automation.
So once the confidence is high,
begin allowing the system to take
actions, but only with human approval.
This is like supervised driving for ai.
SRA still have a hand on the wheel.
And then last step is full autonomy.
So as a system earns trust,
expands its expand its au autonomy
for, understood incidents.
So the goal is not to automate
everything at once, but to scale
up and safely and progressively.
So each phase is designed to manage risk
while building confidence and capability.
So let's talk about key takeaways
and next steps and wrap up with that.
So one, speed is critical.
So in complex systems, every second
counts and autonomous systems operate
at machine time scales containing
incidents before human could even react.
And that's how we prevent
outages and protect customers.
SM start small and scale fast.
So you need, you don't
need to boil the ocean.
Start with narrow, understood use cases.
Maybe just automate responses
to disc space alerts.
And as the system proves itself,
expand to broader incident types.
And then human AI partnership.
So this isn't, remember, this
isn't about replacing sre,
this is about elevating them.
Removing repetitive firefighting so
that they can focus on architecture,
reliability, and innovation.
And the AI becomes a force multiplier.
Measure everything like, from
false positive rates to time to
resolution Metrics are essential
for demonstrating that ROI and
guiding continuous improvements.
If you can't measure, you can't
trust it, you can't improve it.
So measurement is very important.
Next steps identify high volume incidents.
Deploy AI in observation mode, build
trust before granting autonomy and
focus on transparency and audit.
Auditability autonomous incident
response is in the future.
It's the present and it's how we scale
SRE to meet the complexity of systems.
To wrap up.
I wanna say autonomous instant response
isn't just a tech upgrade, it's a
strategic shift in how we protect,
scale and operate our systems.
It's about moving from reactive
firefighting to proactive resilience.
And with AI on our side, we no longer
are limited by human speed or scale.
So if there's one message
that I want you to take.
With you today.
It is that smart.
Start small, start safely, but start now.
The future of SRE is
here and it's autonomous.
Thank you very much for your time.
I'm very happy to take questions or
chat more, so feel free to reach out
to me and once again, thank you a lot.
Thanks a lot for your time today.