Speaker 33: Hello everybody.
My name is Stuart Clark.
I'm a senior developer
advocate here at Spotify.
And today I'm gonna talk about
scale or fail the abstraction
paradox which we learned at Spotify.
So what I'd like to do is, I'd like to
start with a question that might keep
some of you up at night times, and it
certainly has for me in my experience,
is that you might have been in, say
a critical incident where the person
who built the system wasn't available.
And the abstraction, which is to most, to
make everything simple for you and help
you has just become your biggest enemy.
And so in this session, I'm gonna share
a story about, here at Spotify we learned
this the hard way, but more importantly,
on top of this what we did about it.
This isn't just gonna be about
abstractions in code, it's actually
gonna be about the operational knowledge.
Which keeps all of our systems
running and how we scale that
knowledge as our teams grow.
So first of all, the thing that I
wanted to address really is what
we call the universal challenge.
And these challenges might seem
similar because these are challenges
that we all face within our industry.
These are things such as onboarding
engineers to complex systems whilst
we are trying to maintain velocity.
And maintaining operational excellence
during a rapid growth, balancing
develop productivity with transparency
and building abstractions that
are there to enhance rather than a
hinder something like an incident.
Response.
But before we go into a lot of those, I
want to go back just a little bit to like
how this all began for us at Spotify.
And so this means going back
to like around 2014 for this
sort of like reality check.
So if we go back in time to 2014,
Spotify was in this middle of
this really big growth explosion.
What we were doing was we were
transitioning from just being a music
streaming app to essentially becoming a
personalized audio experience platform.
During this time, we were
hiring at breakneck speed.
Lots of engineers.
Lots of developers, and unlike a lot
of companies who are in this hyper
growth mode, our mantra was always
the same ship, fast ship often, right?
But here's what a lot of the
growth metrics didn't show.
Once we were celebrating our user
acquisition and all of these, people
were joining and signing up for Spotify
and downloading the app, something
troubling was happening internally.
Our engineering productivity was
actually declining, and the time it
took a new engineer to reach their,
say, 10th pool request, which was
a key milestone, which we tracked,
had ballooned to almost 60 days.
If we looked further, the key
onboarding metrics, these had
deteriorated dramatically.
And when you think about
it, that isn't onboarding.
This turns into archeological excavation.
But the question then became
to us okay, was this happening?
Because on the surface, our systems
looked great, they looked amazing.
We had built these beautiful clean APIs.
We had well-documented interfaces, we had
elegant extra abstractions, and these hid
all of the, the messy complex underneath.
Our senior developers had essentially
done what we had asked them to do.
They'd created these great layers of
abstraction that made common tasks
super simple and really straightforward.
But this is what we discovered
during these painful incidents.
The kind of thing which happens at
3:00 AM when the things often break,
because that's when they do break.
All of these beautiful abstractions
just became opaque walls.
Our new engineers who had just
started couldn't follow a happy path.
They could ship features when everything
worked perfectly, that's great, but
the moment that something went wrong.
They all hit a cognitive brick wall.
So picture it this way, you are say, in
a incident room, the service is down.
And the engineer or developer
who built this critical
component is just on vacation.
They're away for whatever reason.
And there you are staring at that
abstraction that tells you something
failed in the data layer, but what failed?
Where did it fail?
And even more importantly,
why did it fail?
This abstraction that made all of your
development processes faster is now making
the recovery pretty much impossible.
And this is what I'm gonna refer
to as the abstraction trap.
The point of that very thing
designed to help you now
becomes your biggest liability.
And at looking at this, we
realized that our abstractions
were essentially optimized for the
90% of cases, normal operations.
But the incidents always happen in
the 10% cases, in the edge conditions
in those places that our abstractions
were not designed to illuminate.
Now we are all about learning from failure
and learning from failure as a culture,
but here is what made the difference in
how we approach this problem at Spotify.
Learning from failure isn't just
something we do after incidents.
It's a core cultural value.
This means our incident reviews
don't just aim to fix what is broke.
They're designed to surface patterns.
They're designed to understand things
like black swan failures, and most
importantly, they're there to help
distribute that learning across
our organization, across our teams.
This cultural foundation is crucial
because it means that we aren't just
trying to prevent failures, that
we are trying to build systems and
teams that could learn from them.
The real cost here wasn't just longer
incident resolution times, or those
admittedly are gonna be painful.
The hidden cost is knowledge atrophy.
Our senior engineers are now relieved
that junior engineers can ship
features without bothering them.
Gradually, the ones who truly
understood how things worked
is now being distributed.
This means that we are creating
these great term knowledge silos, but
these knowledge silos were disguised
as good engineering practices.
And so when we think about how
abstractions work, the abstractions
versus oversimplification is that paradox.
This experience taught us something
fundamental about all of our
software engineering practices
and software engineering at scale.
There is this huge critical
difference between abstraction
and oversimplification.
Putting it simply, abstraction
should reduce cognitive load while
preserving the ability to dig
deeper when and if you need to.
Oversimplification just hides
complexity until one day it
just explodes in your face.
So the question to us became
how do we build a system that is
approachable for newcomers, but
yet is transparent enough for our
senior engineers and for our experts?
How do you create an abstraction that
would educate rather than an obscure.
Our scaling challenges in this
instant led us to develop backstage.
And if you're not new to Backstage
or you are new to Backstage,
backstage is a unified developer
portal, or if you prefer IDE, and it
reimagine our developer experience.
So instead of adding another tool.
We needed to fundamentally change
how all of our developers act
interacted with complex systems.
And this could be likened to
a really good technical book.
So if you think about your favorite
technical book, when you start reading
chapter one, it just gives you the
basics, but the appendix gives you that
deeper and provides much more follow
up information if and when you need it.
Our abstractions provide
three levels within this.
We have layer one, which
we call our happy path.
This is 80% of what our
users need 80% of the time.
Layer two, our context layer, which shows
what's happening actually under the hood.
And then layer three is our
deep dive, full system access.
When and if things break.
The abstraction should teach, not hide.
And what I mean by this is that each
level naturally leads to the next
when needed to rather than hiding it.
So this again is another sort of
mind shift that we had to overcome.
We shifted from thinking about
abstractions as just black boxes to
thinking about them as educational tools.
The very best abstractions progressively
reveal complexity in a way that
builds greater understanding.
And this pivots on three
main core components for us.
It.
Pivot on Golden Paths software templates,
which encode this operational wisdom.
It's not just boilerplate stuff,
but distilled lessons on building
the services that we run at
Spotify and we run at scale.
Then we have something
called a service catalog.
This doesn't show just a, that say service
A depends on service B, but it also
shows the nature of the dependencies.
The reliability and the metrics
and the also the failure scenarios.
So if A breaks what happens down the
line, say B or C. And then we have another
piece which kind of builds all of this
together, which is called tech docs.
And this is a foundational tool.
And the foundational tool works
for every operational education.
It works in every interaction.
It deepens system
understanding and knowledge.
This is built all around our
plugin architecture, and the plugin
architecture allows for customization
while encoding collective operational
wisdom through its own defaults.
Of course, it's human nature
to want to deviate and you can
deviate, but the system helps you
understand the implications if
you do how does this all scale?
It sounds good in practice,
but how do we scale this?
The real problem for us wasn't
just solving about the abstractions
itself, it was about scaling
the operational knowledge.
So how do you take that hard one
wisdom of your most senior and expert
engineers and then distribute across
this, across a growing team without
creating such a thing like bottlenecks?
You've heard of knowledge sorry.
Infrastructures, code
and documents of code.
But think about it as knowledge of
sorry, knowledge as infrastructure.
What we learned here was to
treat knowledge just like
we treat our infrastructure.
So just as you wouldn't build a
system without considering how it
scales, you can't build abstractions
without considering how operational
knowledge scales alongside them.
Our unified developer portal approach
that we built delivered four key
outcomes to help us achieve this.
We wanted to reduce the sort of like
troubleshooting and share the operational
wisdom, which is encoded in the platform,
meaning that all of our new engineers
can follow our expert debugging paths
as if an expert was stood next to them.
We would be able to provide such
a thing as continuous learning so
that every system into action then
becomes a learning opportunity.
Building operational institution and
institutional knowledge, which previously
might have taken years for somebody
to develop with inside a company.
And then there's this thing
called knowledge freshness.
Systems evolve.
They grow, and things change.
And as these systems evolve,
knowledge must evolve with them.
This prevents one thing,
documentation, rot.
This transforms into a multiplier
sorry, multiplier effect and
the transformation of this.
We could see in our onboarding
metrics how they improve dramatically
and how our developers and our
engineers were more operationally
capable at certain key milestones.
Our senior engineers now can just
focus on building better systems.
Instead of being that sort of like
constant and being always interrupted,
the new engineers or junior engineers
or developers made great progress while
building understanding rather than
being blocked by these knowledge gaps
and having to jump into get support.
So the solution that we developed,
which we eventually open sourced as
backstage and we open source this
in 2020 and donated it to the CNCF.
This represents our belief that these
challenges aren't just unique to Spotify.
We know that the principles of building
abstractions and those principles
of building abstractions must teach.
They must create a graduated disclosure
and treating knowledge as infrastructure.
This is applicable across
all of our industry, not just
here at Spotify and our own.
And so our hope is.
Our hope is that all of these patterns
that we've learned can become foundational
experiences to developer experience.
We want this to happen in developer
experience in the same way that
container orchestration has become to
infrastructure management, for example,
all of the operational resilience
outcomes ha don't happen at once.
And the ultimate goal wasn't just faster
onboarding or making something look
pretty and having a wonderful interface.
It was about building operational
resilience and making things more stable.
The key component here is that when you
abstractions teach, while they simplify,
that is what they're there to do.
When your tools build understanding
rather than high complexity, this
means that you can create teams
that can handle the unexpected.
You build systems that don't just work
when everything goes right, but remain
Deb bookable when things go wrong.
And so if I'm to leave one thing here and
to suggest what the final takeaway is.
Is that anything that we've learned
from this lesson here is that at the
abstractions you build, whether they're
deployment tools, monitoring dashboards,
or incident response processes, they're
not just built as functional tools.
They're also built mainly as
knowledge distribution mechanisms.
Just take a few seconds to ask yourself.
Does this abstraction help people
understand the system better, or
does it just hide more complexity?
When this breaks at 3:00 AM will it help
the on-call engineer learn something
about how our systems work, or will
it leave them even more confused?
To make this simple, there's
a three question framework.
Before you build your next
abstraction, ask these three questions.
'cause it will really help.
Can I trace through this when
something goes wrong, can I follow the
breadcrumbs to understand what happened?
Does this teach me something?
Am I learning about a system
through using this tool, or am I
just following a rooted procedure?
Can I graduate?
My understanding is there a natural
path from basic usage to deep system.
Understanding the future of reliable
systems isn't about hiding complexity.
It's about making it
approachable and manageable.
Abstractions should be bridges to
understanding not solid walls around it.
The best abstractions that we
see don't just solve problems.
They help transfer knowledge
and build capability.
Whether this is building tools,
contributing to open source or
designing processes, focus on systems
like we did that scale operationally.
This is where knowledge grows
alongside the technology.
If you have any questions, there's a QR
code for you to scan at the end here.
You can always send me questions, but
I'm always happy to answer questions
about building systems that truly scale.
I hope you've enjoyed this presentation
and look forward to seeing you soon.