Speaker 6: Hello everyone.
My name is Ais Univers Current,
and I currently work as a systems
engineering at Value Guard Solutions.
Over the past 20 years, I worked across
systems engineering, DevOps, enterprise
data platforms, and large scale production
environment where reliability is critical.
In recent years, we have seen a major
shift in how organizations use data.
Traditionally, analytical systems were
separate from the operational systems.
Data would be collected during
a day, processed overnight, and
insights were generated later today.
Model was completely changed.
AI system now cooperate differently
inside the production platforms.
They power things like fraud, detention,
recomme, ization, systems related models,
and real time analytical platforms.
These systems influence millions
of automated station every day.
But a moves deeper into the
pro production infrastructure.
We started to see something interesting.
The challenge is not only building
accurate models, the challenge is
ensuring models behave reliably
inside operational systems.
So today we'll focus on how to design,
design, AI architecture that prioritize
reliability from the beginning.
Today's agenda is.
In this session we'll walk through
the four orchestral areas that help a
system operate level lead in production.
First in workload isolation boundaries.
This product, core application services
from unpredictable analytical workloads.
Second is diminish exhibition parts.
This ensure influence pipeline
behave predictably, and stay
within operational constraints.
Third is addition, traceability
and exhibition lineage.
This allows engineers to analyze weekly
automated editions when incidents occurs.
Fourth is long-term opera ability.
This includes drift detection, control
rollout strategies, and human oversight.
To get these principles form what we
call reliability first, a architecture.
The core problem.
Before discussing the architecture
patterns, we need to understand
why AI systems create a
new operational challenges.
One key factor is compute.
Demand influence workloads are not always
predictable during peak events, request
volumes can increase dramatical leak.
Each interference request may
require future extraction,
pre-processing, and model execution.
All of this consume compute resources.
If this workload share infrastructure
with transactional systems
resource contention can occur.
Another factor is OPEC execution behavior.
Traditional applications
follow deterministic logic.
When something goes wrong, engineers
can read, trace the code path.
AI systems behave differently.
Their outputs driven on iCal.
Pattern learned during training.
When unexpected behavior occurs, the
cause may not be immediately OB obvious.
The third factor is
complex data dependencies.
AI system depends upon future
pipelines, data transformations,
and multiple upstream services.
These dependencies can increase
the architectural complexity,
how AI surface in post incident reviews.
When organization analyze incident
involving GA workload, several
patterns appear frequently.
One pattern is latency, amplification
inference, workload, compete
with other services for compute
resources, this increases the
response time across platform.
Another pattern is
cascading failures Is low.
Interference in service can
propagate, delay, upstreams
causing, and additional load.
This can quickly escalate
into a broader outage.
A third pattern is observability gaps.
Traditional monitoring tools,
track CPU usage, memory
utilization, and request latency.
But a system introduce new signals
such as prediction, commands,
future distribution, drift, and
in reference latency percentiles.
Without monitoring the signals,
teams may detect problems only
after the users are affected.
What decision covers?
To address these challenges, we introduce
four architectural guardrails, isolation
product critical services from analytical
workloads, execution constraints,
ensure predictable system behavior.
Traceability enables system systems
engineer to understand automated
decisions, operational governance
support, long term system stability.
Together these layers provide defense in.
In depth for AI systems,
workload isolation boundaries.
Isolation is one of the most
important reliability principles.
AI workload should not compete directly
with the transactional systems.
For compute resources, consider a
consider an e-commerce platform.
A recommendation engine might share
infrastructure with checkout service.
During peak traffic recommendation
request increased dramatically.
If recommendation system consumes
larger percentage of compute
capacity, checkout latency increases.
This directly impact customer experience.
Isolation mechanism help prevent this
example include dedicated compute
pools for interference services,
resource quotas, iner orchestration.
Environments and separation
exhibition cues for the analytical
workloads, the goal is simple.
Ensure that analytical workload
can interfere with mission critical
services, isolation, PA patterns that
works, several architect patterns
helps enforce isolation effectively.
One approach is namespace
and quota enforcement.
In container orchestration
environment resource quotas,
ensure interference workload cannot
consume unlimited compute resources.
Another approach is net
network segmentation.
Separating analytical traffic
from transactional traffic reduces
the blast radius of failures.
The third approach is priority
aware scheduling the schedulers.
We should prioritize mission
critical servers over analytical
workload during resource contention.
This mechanism help maintain
platform stability even during
traffic spikes real world pattern.
Let's consider a real example.
In one production exam environment,
a recommendation service
consumed 40% of shared compute
capacity during peak traffic.
The model itself was accurate, but the
architecture lacked resource limits.
As a result, checkout latency
increased significantly.
The solution involved introducing
dedicated compute pools, enforcing
CPU limits and implementing circuit
breakers within one really cycle system.
Reliability was restored.
Detailed istic execution parts.
The next architecture principle
is determin istic execution.
The SRE practices depends upon
predictable system behavior.
Yay.
Pipeline must operate within
strict operational constraints.
First, input validation.
Ensure malformed inputs are rejected
at Lee Second, execution timers
prevent long-running and reference
request from blocking resources.
Third output schema validation.
Ensure prediction
followed expected formats.
These constraints transform
interference pipelines into
predictable systems components.
Performance constraints as first class
design, yes, we must operate with
clearly defined performance budgets.
Example, include maximum acceptable
interference, latency, budget
capacity, head room, and rate
limits for interference APIs.
Defining this constraints during
system design help preventing
reliability issues later.
Decent traceability and execution Lineage.
When an automated edition
trigger incident investigator
must answer several questions.
What in what input data
would the model receive?
Which model version generated
the production prediction?
What future value influence this without
res, without reasonability answering?
These questions become extremely difficult
operational as a lineage,
as operational tool.
Operational line requires
input, snapshots, version
pinned, modeled artifacts, and
distributed trace identifiers.
These capabilities allow Nina to
the predictions during incident
investigations replay functionality
significantly reduce the meantime for
resolution, security, and monitoring
as inherited reliability properties.
Security boundaries are
also influence reliability.
Access controls limits.
The blast of radius monitoring systems
should capture both infrastructure
metrics and AI specific signals.
AI specific observability signals AI
system requires additional monitoring
signals beyond traditional metrics.
Examples includes prediction,
confidence distribution, future
distribution monitoring and
interference latency percentiles.
These S held reliability issues early.
Long-term probability drift
rollout and human oversight e.
E model deployed in production.
Eventually experienced
drift user behavior changes.
Data pattern evolves.
System must therefore detect
and respond to these changes.
Managing model drift in production.
Drift management involves continuous
monitoring, shadow deployment,
and automated rollback triggers.
This mechanism convert unexpected
failures into controllable operational
processes, control rollout strategies.
Safe rollout strategies include
shadow deployments, Canada releases,
and champion challenger testing.
These approaches values validate
models under real traffic
conditions before full deployment.
Preserving human oversight
in automated systems.
Automation should always
include human oversight.
Context threshold can route uncertain
predictions to human review.
Future flex allow engineers to
visible models quickly, during
instance, bringing it together to
give them these principles Form a
reliability fat class A architecture.
Isolation products, workloads,
deterministic execution,
ensure predictability,
observability, and traceability.
Animals investigation.
Human oversight, ensure governance.
Key takeaways for SREs.
Four key takeaways.
Isolate AI workload early, enforce
execution constraints, bold lineage
from day one engineers system to
detect drift reliability must designed
into AI system from the beginning.
Thank you.
Thank you for your time.
I appreciate the opportunity
to share these ideas today.
Thank you.