Hello and welcome to com 42 Site
Reliability Engineering 2025.
My name is Ricardo Karo and
today we're going to see what
can we, what we can learn from
Formula One incident Management.
What are we going to cover today?
I'll start by setting the stage.
We'll see a natural F1 incident, and
we're going to see how a team, namely
Red Bull went, the series of steps
that they took and the learnings
that we can take from that incident.
To overcome and actually have
a car that could run and score
points at the end, we'll see how,
why all of this is important.
So let's start by setting the stage.
So the year is 2020.
So after a series of years of Mercedes
just winning both the drivers and,
and the constructions championship.
2020 year was probably the first
year when there was a feeling that
some other team could challenge the
title, where this is the third race.
So Red Bull is one of the contenders
for both the drivers and and
constructions championship.
And Maxwell Staffer is their star driver.
During the qualifying, max didn't do a
very good job, so he qualified seventh and
during the Formation lab this happened.
So what happened here?
So the formation lab is when the
drivers try to warm up the tires
and get them to the most optimal
temperatures that they want.
As you guys can see, the track is
is wet because it had been raining,
and what happened was that max.
In a, in an effort to warm up the
tires as much as he possibly could.
He tra he brake too late and he had a
lockup by locking up and a track being wet
max just sl just went through the barriers
and he actually crashed into the wall.
Let's see our first lesson
that we can refer today from
and start with a small video.
So I don't see if you noticed, but there's
a timer around the top left of the video.
This means that at this point,
red Bull has under 23 minutes
to do something so that the car
is able to to be driven by Max.
So what's happening here?
So Red Bull needs to make a decision.
They either go into the pit lane or
they try to fix the car on track.
So they need to make a fast
decision and they have very
little information at this point.
They have sensory information and the
feedback that Max has been giving them.
So no mechanic.
No mechanic has ever has seen the cardiac.
So although they understand that they
probably have a broken suspicion, they
don't really know what's in there.
So by making this decision, if
they go into the pit lane, they
have everything there, there's
their garage, all their tools are
there, all their parts are there.
But if the race, when the race
starts, Marx start, max starts last.
If they do it on a track, they lose
four minutes, but, and they have to take
everything in there, so they need to make
a fast decision with limited information.
So they need to act decisively even
if they don't have the full picture.
Why is that?
They want to minimize exp impact.
They act fast and they want
to stop small problems from
becoming big couches in our world.
It's this worry that we need to
act fast before a small incident
becomes a very big outage.
Also, in our context, we need
to protect our customers.
We need to protect their assets and.
Everything that we own from them, of
course, come from a company perspective.
We want to preserve revenue.
These the quick actions that we do reduce
downtime and reduce our financial losses.
And of course, we want to
maintain customer trust.
Customers need to understand that
we are in control and we're doing
our best to solve the incident.
As engineers, we need to become
comfortable with this discomfort.
It.
And we also need to keep in mind that
many of these decisions will oftentimes be
sub suboptimal or even completely wrong.
So using F1 as an example, they,
no mechanic has ever even seen
the car, and they decided to go
to the track and fix it there.
Let's see what they did next.
As we can see here red Bull
is moving everything from
their garage into the track.
So you see everyone speaking
clearly very commonly.
So people are asking for tools,
people are asking for parts.
People are asking who is doing what.
So it's very clear, so
there's no confusion.
People are speaking in a
calm voice and very clearly.
So clear communication.
It's all about sharing the
right information with the
right people at the right time.
This will lead to faster
resolution of sance.
Clear communication will get
everyone on the same page.
This will reduce efforts
because good communication will
prevent confusion and mistakes.
It of course, improve coordination
because everyone will be working
together to fix an incident and
it'll increase transparency.
Open communication will keep everyone
informed and will build trust.
So takeaways from here from this
good communication helps everyone
understand and resolve incidents faster.
It will allow for everyone to be in the
loop and mentoring just during incidents,
be them with stakeholders or clients.
Let's see what comes next.
So as you can see here, we see an engineer
asking for a front wing, and immediately
someone who's coordinating the incident
just raise the awareness that they
have clear processes to do everything.
So this means that they should
follow a predetermined process
to actually fix the car.
Why is this important?
So clear processes are, it's all about
following defined steps that will help
us be effective in incident resolution.
By following these processes,
we can enable a faster response.
This will enable quick rea
reactions to incidents.
It'll reduce chaos so everyone knows
what should be, do the what shape they
should be doing and at time, so they,
this will bring some order and will
prevent confusion during an incident.
It, of course, will enable
consistent execution.
These processes will ensure that incidents
are handled every time in the same
way, and it'll improve collaboration.
Everyone understands their part, everyone
understands what they should be doing,
so it'll be making clear that person
A and person B should be cooperating.
So we need to plan for incidents
before they happen, right?
So we need to try to do, to have
these processes defined and we need
to try them, we need to test them out.
We need to have simulations
how these are done.
And by doing that, these clear
steps will make for a fast response.
So next we talk a little
bit about teamwork.
Let's, so let's see an example.
As you guys can see here, it's a bit
a little bit of the process of taking
stuff into the into the track and
communicating what should be done.
So if there's no good teamwork
there, this would be possible.
They are literally transferring
a garage onto the track.
So collaboration and shared responsibility
will allow for a faster resolution.
So there's a diverse skill
set for faster fixes.
So different people will be,
bring different strengths for to
incident response, and they need
to cooperate and work together.
Of course, teamwork makes a dream work.
Collaboration will lead to small,
smoother, and faster resolution.
Everyone plays a part and they need
to understand in their processes
where they should be leaning into.
And of course, we will all learn together.
Teams that learn from incidents together
will get better together, so teams that
work together solve problems faster.
There's not one person who
fixed a whole incident.
It's a teamwork, and of course,
teamwork builds more resilience and
more effective response to incident.
Next we talk about columnists.
So let's see an example.
So at this point, red Bull has
under seven minutes to get a car
running ready to be driven by Max.
So you hear communication,
you hear no one screaming.
Everyone keeping calling.
You hear Jonathan Whitley
asking for updates, right?
He's not screaming.
He's very calm.
He knows that his engineers
are under enormous pressure.
They need, they not only need to get
a car fixed, they're going, they're
having a car that's going to be driven.
And over 300 kilometers an
hour for 50, 60, 70 labs.
So it's not only about fixing the car and
making it run, it needs to be driven at
fast fast speeds under immense g forces.
So they need to nail this
right and Max will trust them.
So keeping calm, it's all about think
and post under pressure to be able to
think clearly and make good decisions.
If we have a calm mind, it means that we
can, that calmness can help us have, make
good decisions during the whole incident.
Of course, calm teams work better without
the other pressure of someone screaming
or someone asking constant feedback.
It'll reduce stress and will
help everyone to work better.
We have to stay tough in this, the, in
these situations we have, we need to
build our mental strengths to be able to
handle the strengths of these incidents.
So we should tr we should have
simulations before of actually
doing these things to actually
build that toughness over over time.
And we don't need to rush, right?
So we need to take as much
time as necessary to assess
and plan before taking action.
Like I said before, they not only
need to assemble the car, but they
need to keep in mind that someone
will be driving that car over 300
kilometers an hour for 67, 80 times.
So a coal mine will make the
better decisions during incidents.
So we need to train our teams to
handle these stress situations.
So by simulating these situations
before so for example, in our
world, it'll be using game days
or using chaos engineering.
We will start to build that toughness
and their that control during incidents.
Next, we touch on technical proficiency.
So at this point, this is more
on the beginning of the incident.
Red Bull is assessing if
they can do it or not.
So they basically are saying
that they need to do it faster
than they ever done it before.
So this means very high
technical proficiency.
So they need strong skills to
be able to efficiently diagnose
and resolve the incident.
So in an incident, skills
will matter, right?
If you have strong skills,
they will be essential for a
quick and effective incident.
Resolution.
In an incident.
Knowledge will be power.
The more a team knows about
incidents, about their systems,
they will be better equipped to
prevent and handle those incidents.
And as F1 drivers, our teams needs
to be, need to be sharp, hone their
skills and train them over time.
So stronger technical skills means
that stronger, a stronger incident
response, and teams will need the
right tools to empower them to
resolve incidents effectively.
Last but not least, we have postmortems.
So let's see an example here.
So for Formula One, teams are
famous for doing brutal postmortems.
And when I say brutal, it means
that they go into very detailed
of what happened during the race.
They're famous for doing not only
when things go wrong, but also
when things go right as well.
So they really want to
understand how things went.
In this video, we saw an example
from the Mercedes, a MG team.
They are very public about their
postmortems to the extent of what
they can divulge, of course, without
compromising themselves and giving
secrets to their competition.
So postmortems, it's all about learning
from incidents to prevent future problems.
So after an incident is resolved,
we want to find the root cause.
We want to dig deep and understand why an
incident happened, not just what happened.
So we want to understand the why.
Why did this thing happen?
Also and very important, we
want to learn from mistakes.
We want to use incidents as opportunities
to improve processes and prevent
that incident doesn't happen again.
Very important is that we
have no blame postmortems.
We need to focus on learning and
improvement, not on blaming someone.
Postmortems will help teams learn from
incidents and get better over time.
They need to be focused on fixing
problems, not finding fault.
So why is this important?
At the end of the day,
here's what we want.
We want to prevent
incidents from happening.
When an incident happens, we
want to meet again, mitigate and
fix them as fast as possible.
And of course, we want that.
The same incidents don't
happen over and over again.
Unfortunately, many organizations
don't have many of these
practices that we see in mind.
But as we could see here, some of
the top engineering organizations in
the world do this because it works.
So either if you and independently, if you
like F1 or not we can all agree that F1
is one of the top engineering disciplines
in the world and these are the things
that they do to actually fix an incident.
And if I had to start somewhere,
I would start with postmortems.
Postmortems.
It's all about learning, right?
Learning from what happened.
And I think that postmortems will
help you develop all the others
because when you have an incident,
you do postmortem, you'll learn,
you understand, you will over time
will build the other capabilities
because you are constantly learning.
So at the end, what happens, let's see.
So let's take a moment here
to understand what happened.
So Max crashed his car, the radio
formation lap in under 20 minutes.
The mechanics transferred
their garage onto the track.
They fixed the car, and that allowed
Max to go from seventh into second.
This is amazing, right?
So all of these skills and all of these
items that you see during the presentation
allow for someone who had a broken car
and in under 20 minutes had a car able to
be driven to go from seventh to second.
This is simply amazing.
So here are just a few links
if you want to learn a little
bit more about this incident in
particular and see the whole video.
So the first one is the video.
So the video is roughly eight
minutes, but it's, it was reading it.
So the second link is about that grand
Prix that we just saw that was in Hungary.
And the third one is the Mercedes
a MG channel that has a lot of
forced postmortems that you can
see and see how they handle them.
And this is all for my part.
I hope you enjoyed it and I hope
to see you again in another day.
Thank you very much, and
follow me on my socials.