Hello everyone, and
thank you for joining me.
My name is Loh Kumar Ma and I'm a senior
Azure data engineer with over 15 years
of experience in designing advanced
data solutions for large enterprises.
Today, I will walk you through
a transformative architecture
I design that combines.
Data factory with the predictor, modeling
and real time analytics to manage risk
more intelligently, especially during
times of financial and market and ity.
This framework not only process, reduce
this processing time and cost, but
also improve pipeline reliability and
give leadership teams the ability to
act quickly on risk signals with data.
Let's begin with the problem.
So today's data challenge, let's begin.
Modern organizations are joining in
data spread, so we are talking about
the petabytes of data structure,
unstructured, scattered across cloud,
enter around, and legacy systems, and
third party APAs and internal database.
This creates.
Challenges, and there are three major
challenges explosive data growth.
So constant increase in data from web,
iot, traditional transactional systems and
third parties and integration complexity.
So data comes from the many formats.
At a different speeds.
And with the varying
schema and business rules.
So maintenance burdens.
So traditional ETL frameworks
are code heavy, error prone,
and time consuming to maintain.
So when risk is dynamic and data
is in timely, and your business
decisions are all already outdated,
So the solution is Azure Data Factory.
It's a game changer.
So we needed something that could scale
with the data or respond to change
quickly and reduce manual effort.
So that's where Data Factory came in.
So my solution leverage A DF is low-code
pipeline design with visual interfaces
and pre-built connectors to a hundred
plus data sources and reusable components
for consistency across projects.
Template driven workflows
to register them to market.
So we developed limited data
driven architecture where business
logic could be modified without
changing a single line of code.
This meant faster iterations, better
testing, and Jira deployment overheads.
Let's move on to the next.
And measurable business impacts.
Let's talk about the numbers
because measurable outcomes.
By creating Azure Data Factory
pipelines and we reduced operational
cross dropped 40% thanks to dynamic
scaling and optimized scheduling
pipeline success rates improved
in 99.9%, virtually eliminating
manually restarts and broken chains.
And these aren't just stats.
They really reflect agility, resilience,
and especially when making high stake.
So let's talk about the
architecture best practices.
That's, we followed the backbone
of this success was carefully
architecture framework, built on
four best practices, so model design.
So breaking pipeline into
functional units like ingestions
and clinging transformations
and loading pipeline template.
Templates using parameterize and templates
to quickly roll out new use cases.
Metadata driven executions
to control everything.
Source file types, schema mapping
from a tables incremental loading, so
load only delta, and registering both.
Compute this usage and pipeline runtime.
So this allowed us to scale seamlessly,
reuse proven logic, and adapt rapidly
to new data sources or business roles.
And the governance and line monitoring
that we followed a robust data system
is incompatible without governance.
Here is what we implemented track.
Thing.
Every transformations from how to refine.
Along with the timestamped logs, audit
frameworks ev Every activity was logged
researchable, searchable and tied
to user credentials and operational
dashboards built using Power BI and Log
Analytics to monitor pipeline health
alerting systems, alerts for performance.
Threshold to notifications.
This not only supported complaints
but us proactively detect
before.
Once the pap was stable and we focused on.
So using Power BI and Azure Analysis
Services, we enable self-service analysis
for business teams, reduce report
generation time by up to 70% and connected
directly to streaming sources for real
time dashboards for financial services.
This meant instant visibility into
key metrics like exposure, risk,
operational losses, and market trends.
Let's compliance and security,
so financial end compliance,
encryption and transit using Azure.
So we were stored all the
keys into the Azure Q keyword.
So role robust access controls
to enforce least privileges.
So audit trail generations
and version controlled and
configuration for every change.
Thatm masking right to be
forgotten and constant tracking
for privacy laws like GDPR.
So this control ensure we passed
multiple compliance audits with.
So the solution I built is not just a
pipeline, it's a strategic platform.
We have already started enterprise
rollouts across departments.
We're also training internal teams
to manage the platform, build
new use cases, and improve data
maturity levels across the board.
So looking ahead, I see this evolving
into see self-learning, AI-driven risk
intelligence engine with auto-tuned
pipelines ready to failure alerts and
embedded models that forecast financial
risks based on real data patterns.
This is the future of data-driven risk
management, and we are ready on the path.
We are already on the path.
So to wrap up I invite you assess
your current data architecture.
Identify areas where intelligent
automation could reduce cost and
complexity, and consider how scalable
frameworks like the one I have presented,
can help your organization make
faster, safer, and smarter relations.
Thank you for attending.
I'm excited to share this
journey with the Conference 42
Community and I, and with thank.