I wanna talk about hybrid quantum,
classical neural networks and
their application to the field
of Cy Hybrid Engineering.
As you'll know, like the quantum
computing field is picking up,
Google has launched a new chip
Willow and so has Amazon recently,
and they have passed the benchmarks.
But to make use of them practically
now for especially the emergence of AI
and machine learning, we are looking
into the hybrid approach of hybrid
quantum and classical neural networks.
I have briefly split the agenda into
hybrid quantum classical neural networks.
I'll say HQC and Ns.
Very long to pronounce the
challenges that are in this
approach, the practical applications.
And the SRA aspect of it.
Okay, so
the left column talks about
the quantum advantages.
So quantum computing takes advantage
of the quantum principles of physics.
Which is super position.
Super position has the ability of
data to be in all the possible states
at once before it's being observed.
If you take in binary, we call it a zero
or one, it could be a zero or one, or.
Both zero and one before
it is being observed.
So this arises to the concept of parallel
invoices and the ability to solve the
problem parallel, in parallel invoices.
And quantum ment is the
ability of one qubit.
Qubit is the basic unit of like
a bit of quantum computers.
Ability of one qubit to to
affect the other, to the same
state respect of their distance.
This adds tremendous power
to quantum computing.
And the modeling, the modeling of quantum
states using hilbert spaces, provides
unprecedented power to solve problems.
And as the classical strengths, it's
well established like what charge
GPD is using or, any other tropic
or any other your network is using.
They're using regular binary com,
or not regular, but established
high GPU classical computers
when you fuse both of them.
So basically, you are using
the accommodation of classical.
You basically provide the
problem in classical, which
is encoded into quantum state.
And you return the result back
in classical after validation
that provides unprecedented
problem solving capabilities.
Okay.
Now enters the.
Parameterized quantum circuits, but they
are quantum algorithms that incorporate
tunable parameters within quantum
gates, enabling optimization of tasks.
As you can see in this dis, in this
graphic, the presentation, so there is a
feature mapping part below which basically
maps the classical part features to the,
classical features to the quantum states
and the quantum parameters are tunable
elements with within the quantum circuits
that enable optimization for specific
tasks such as quantum machine learning,
classical gradient based techniques.
The one that is used in the last piece
classical optimization, are tuneable
elements within quantum circuits
that enable optimization for specific
tasks and techniques like gradient
doesn't are foundational, which
it iteratively are just parameters
to minimize the cost function.
Okay.
I think the slide is slightly.
Your slide is slightly bigger.
So this one, it this slide compares
the HQ CNNs with the traditional
classical neural networks.
And you can see that HQ CNNs
consistently outperform the.
The classical computers and their,
the Neur network approach, despite
having noisy data, and we still have
stability issues with qubits, which
just had to be resolved, especially in
a complex, high dimensional tasks like
medical diagnostics or drug discovery.
So it's got a huge implication on
basically us think of it like this,
if you can find the vaccine for Q
Covid within hours rather than months.
See the impact can have on the
number of lives that we could save.
So there is a potential of this approach.
Okay, I'm going to reshare.
Okay,
so now comes how do we train
quantum circuit, steep quantum circuits.
First is the circuit initialization.
Where you structure quantum layers
with appropriate gate operations
and parameter optimization, applying
grade dissent based methods.
Next is error mitigation.
And finally, you evaluate the model.
Basically, you take a known known
benchmark and you, you run it both
in the classical as well as on the
hybrid quantum computer, and then
confirm that the quantum works.
Or it is within the benchmark of the
classical, computers for accuracy.
Okay?
Yeah.
So the advantages of high dimensional
computation, as in the sa in the slide.
It speeds up like qu the
things that we talked about.
It's made up of qubits and it
has got the the typical quantum
advantages of superposition and
entanglement and quantum parallelism.
So basically it is almost like having
parallel invoices to solve a problem.
You can think about the consequence
of that thought and, especially
on high dimensional data.
High dimensional data which
requires basically a lot of possible
ways to look into the solution.
They offer, they're very greatly
efficient, especially compared
to the classical representation,
efficient optimization, quantum
gardens boss solution landscapes,
like assume you have you want to come
up with a financial modeling and.
You want to say what happens
when I do it on this day?
If you want to take the 365 days of a
year and calculate the interest and the
subsequent pension that you'll receive
after six 60 years, the classical computer
will struggle, but whereas the quantum
can easily model that in just a fee.
Yeah.
The dimensionality advantage hybrid
architectures seamlessly integrate
both quantum and classical data sets.
Basically it maintains the regular
computing advantages, the practical use
of it, and also the quantum advantages,
which is the ability of IT to solve
problems with high emission spaces.
Yeah.
Now let's look at some
of the applications.
It's very exciting.
Like we, whatever we talk till
now, it's more like a theory,
but this is practical, right?
Especially in medical diagnostics,
like if to read an MRI scan or a or
combining multiple data, multiple
scans together and deriving conclusions
out of it, or, which can be critical
for the patient's diagnosis.
So this offers unparalleled potential
drug discovery, as I mentioned.
Like we.
Already we are doing a little bit like
Covid was done pretty fast, but quantum
can do it within no time, almost like
minutes or day or hours, which basically
gives us the ability to think about
novel drugs, which can completely change
the life of people and cure diseases.
Yeah.
The other frontier is the
personalized medicine.
You have multiple data sets, right?
You have the clinical data where you go
to a GP or have your medical test and
the environment that you live in your
pre predisposition, your genomic data.
The HQ n they can combine all of
these and produce very personalized.
Medicine, like the one that
perfectly works for you, depending
on all the parameters, which may
not be so easy to do right now.
As I talked the model the potential
applications are in financial modeling.
Gimme one second.
Trying to move this.
Okay.
Financial modeling.
Then again the supply chain logistics
it's like an operational such problem.
You have limited resources and what
is the best way to, for the cost being
optimized or the faster delivery.
For critical medical emergencies
or it's a very good area to
work on supply chain logistics.
And it can help itself.
It can design efficient quantum and
classical circuit layouts, which
can make it even more efficient.
Efficient.
And also one benchmarks like they
have demonstrated that for 200.
Plus training iterations.
The variance is only between 2%,
which is pretty high for accuracy.
Stability,
okay.
The way we train a quantum
hq, hybrid QU hq, CNNs is.
We have to first have the dataset
create a classical dataset, and then
we have to prepare it into a format
that's digestible by the quantum
computers, like amplitude amplitude.
So basically you convert that into
a voltage or a, or direction, like
a phase sample, and then encoding
the feature ma maps to preserve
the critical relationships.
Okay.
And next, like executed forward pass
is, they do one iteration, move forward
to perform complex transformations on
the encoded data, and then the data is
sent back to classical back propagation.
Propagate propagation is enabling
efficient organization across the quantum
and class, so quantum has computed the
data is available in the quantum format.
You need to pass it on to the classical
format and hybrid optimization.
Systematically refined parameters to
iterative quantum classical feedback log.
So basically the earlier ones that we
created, indecent, we saw that, right?
So you keep on doing iteratively
to optimize the hybrid system.
It's not very straightforward.
There are a lot of challenges.
It's in the much, still in the state of
infancy, but it's quite an interesting
problem and eventually we'll get there.
So one is quantum de coherence, like
the challenges I mean despite we say
that the qubits have we have made
it much better than what it was, but
still they suffer from instability.
And the error mitigation techniques
are still work in progress.
And
scalability is one issue.
And barren plat like when the.
Is a critical training problem in quantum
machine learning, QML, specifically in
training p QCs, parameterize quantum
circuits using gradient based methods.
So basically when the when the quantum
circuit becomes deeper and deeper the.
The gradient vanishes.
So that is a problem, that's
a common problem or a problem
that's studied deeply.
Barr plats and the classical quantum
interface, the data transfer between
our classical systems and quantum.
They create bottlenecks and hybrid
algorithms must minimize the server.
Okay, so the future outlook, as Google.
Amazon, Microsoft, everyone is working
towards, even in media, they're working
towards more quantum computing chips with
more qubits, coherence and gate fidelity.
And on the software side, the
algorithms are also improving.
No hybrid architectures are created.
And the other thing is know we are
talking this is now happening in
labs in some universities or in some,
like top top companies, labs, or
RD divisions, but it has to become
a widespread industry adoption.
And the quantum and machine learning
has to become a standard, HQs,
but they will surely revolutionize
the computational approach.
And when this matures solving the
problems that we could not solve earlier
or could not even think about earlier.
Now the relevance of, now we, we discussed
about quantum, we discussed about
classical and how HQ c, hybrid quantum
quantum computing neural network model
like computers how how they work and how
they can help us in drug discovery and
personalized medicine, financial modeling.
We talked about all that.
Now.
What are the problems from Ari?
Perspective?
One is the handoffs is a point of
failure and because the movement
of data from classical to quantum,
so that's a point of failure.
So we from ARI perspective systems
have to be Ari, have to design robust
interfaces and ensure that, that there
is no data loss or data transformation.
The other, one other important piece I
want to talk about is the observability.
Okay?
Now, if you have a cloud computing
system, you have a way to observe it.
So how do you observe a quantum state?
How do you observe quantum noise?
How do you observe quantum decoherence?
And how do you observe latency?
How do you know the
models performing well?
Is it not drifting away?
How do you know all those things?
So observability is a many important part.
Part of it.
And error mitigation strategies, right?
If there is an error during a handoff or
initial data encoding, how do you come
up with ways to, mitigate the errors?
Okay.
And scalability is another problem.
And deploying.
Okay.
There suppose be there is a new model
that's getting deployed, so how do
you deploy it into the quantum space?
Do we need any special orchestration
techniques, ization strategies
where the have to come up with
new models and something that they
have not thought about till now.
And
SREs were supporting that they have to.
They have to ensure that they can deliver
a level of repeatability, load drift.
And even when the system is loaded
with a heavy model or load tested
parallelly, it should not drift.
And it, it produces the same
consistent, pro consistent
performance even during load.
Okay SRE must manage the handoffs,
error mitigation as we talked
about earlier, and monitoring and
observability and scalability, right?
Like how do you suppose you want more
clusters, how do you scale on demand?
Can you do it within few milliseconds so
that there is no loss in the performance.
Those kind of things are very critical
for for an SRE and I put together, put
put together a set of references for you,
the one from IPM and the parameterized
quantum circuits, and, or how to build
reliability by IBM and practical use.
Recently U Austin, they came up with
a way to test whether the numbers that
are generated by a quantum computer is
really random using a classical computer.
I put across some references
or you like it and it's, you
learn something out of it.
Yeah, that's all I have.
Hope you like it.
Thank you very much.