Building large scale for tolerant
and reliable systems is a, the
long process is a hectic process.
It goes over multiple iterations,
but everything that's large and
long starts with some basic blocks.
And one of the basic blocks here
is having the right mindset.
The stock will explore about framing your
thoughts, having the right mindset and
cultivating it over the period of time so
that you get your infrastructure right.
Hello, everyone.
This is, I work for Google on Google
search infrastructure and the stock.
I will be talking to you through the
lessons that I have learned over the
course of these years, and basically
building high, highly reliable,
fault tolerant, and scalable.
Webscale applications.
My experience ranges from like small
scale startups to this large behe North
Google, and I'll be laying down some
basic principles that are really required
for you to define and decide what should
be your thought process while going
about building any large scale systems.
Before we actually start taking deeper
into how do we cultivate the mindset of
being an sre, let's try to understand what
a, what a definition of an SRE is and how
that has really evolved over the course.
Over the course of last 30, 35
years, I feel there has been lot
going on in the computer society and
the computer as far as in 30 years.
We started somewhere around main
competitors, used to set up, used
to set up switches, all handheld.
It has evolved to a state where in
2000 there was a dotcom bubble, a
dotcom post where like thousands
of dotcom sites came online.
People started thinking internet
as a new way of, of basically,
serving services, giving out
information, and tons of companies
came online and did the rock compost.
Internet was an era.
And last 10 years, what I see is there's
something called a cloud burst that
has really happened where multi-tenant
architectures, SaaS applications
have really taken a long haul.
You see like tons of applications
SaaS applications are now thriving
in the industry, and they all
really started around two.
Pick any big cloud providers, they
are thriving as of today, and that
has really made a drastic shift from
like, you know, what, managing a, a,
a mainframe computer was what managing
the physical color was, what was what
you really need to do when you're
dealing in virtual your environments.
You don't have to deal with all
the physical environments, but to
some degree, the principles have
still stayed the same, but there
has been a big that has happened.
If you move ahead.
Like the present era.
The present era is kind of an AI era where
you see a big boost of agent applications.
And what I see here on is like in
next 10 years, this agent applications
would be the next big thing.
And that probably you might have something
you come up after the next 10 years,
but if you see the relationship between
a server and a client, it has evolved.
So has the technologies
that are basically pairing.
These two things together have evolved.
I mean, look at the very basic
technologies like Evolution of two G,
internet, then it went to 3G, 4G, 5G.
You are essentially talking about the
number of bits that are sent over the
network and those are exponentially
going up as those number of bits
that are sent the network have.
So have the threats, so have
the technologies powering them.
So have the customer expectations of
experiences that you should be delivering
to your customers have evolved and so
has the operations that were basically
necessary to support this kind of
heavy internet traffic has changed.
So that's how the evaluation
of computer has basically
evolved the role of engineer.
I should certainly mention that
security and compliance is also a
very important thing that has evolved
with this ever evolving landscape.
And as a site reliability engineer,
I think our perspective of looking
at security and compliances has
changed a lot with lot of things
like G-D-P-R-P-C-I, hipaa, FedRAMP.
And those kind of compliances
are basically making a move site
reliability engineers nowadays
have, have started thinking into how
do I make a system more reliable?
At the same time, I cannot be
compromising on the security
and the compliance aspect of it.
So I think as the reliance on the internet
has increased so has the so has the
feature offerings or the applications
that are served over the internet have.
Streaming very basic application
informational content.
Now we are in the age where you are
basically delivering very critical,
very sensitive information over the
internet and lot of lives, and lot of
people are dependent on the internet.
There there is a big spectrum where you
can basically, basically deliver all
the gamified, gamified, TikTok kind of a
content to delivering critical human care.
So I think it, it becomes more and
more necessary to ensure that your
systems are reliable and people,
real people are depending for
their real needs on the system.
I mean, looking at this thing, I,
I, I, I still feel what has really
made SRA now think is as the systems
have evolving, as this new things
are built, built, we really need to.
I think as as we are mindset the first and
the foremost question that I would really
ask myself is, what's the size of the
problem am I really trying to solve here?
And when I say the size of the
problem, it essentially boils down
to what size of the company, what is
the number of fuses are we talking
about, and what are the company prior?
The priorities and are align
the goals of your role with
the priorities of the company.
For a, in companies of different
sizes, let's say it's a small
scale seed state startup where the
resources are pretty constrained.
You really have limited number of users.
The priority of the company is basically
delivering x number of features.
Y number of days and x and y
higher, unimaginable when basically
come from a large organization
to a small organization where the
delivery speed is very different.
For me, I think the most important that
thing for a small scale organization
would be optimizing for delivery speed.
And sometimes it's, it's fine to
compromise on some of the reliability
aspects there, but probably investing
that you can deliver those features
pretty quickly to the end users and
automation for deliver investing
into the build process so that those
features are quickly and reliability.
It probably would be the most important
thing for that smaller scale organiz.
But as this company scale, as you go
from like a very stage to something like
a growth stage company, series BCDC,
where you have a number of, I think
aspects start taking more precedence,
you really need to be aware that.
Depending on it on the user experience
and the along with the feature.
So you need to basically wear different
hats to ensure that the reliability aspect
of your product is relatively worth.
And then you are also at the same time
investing in the right set of tools to to.
Those set of users, you are basically
investing into the right SLOs.
Defining the right SLOs, finding the
right reliability metrics, monitoring
them over a period of time, ensuring that
you have the right set of technologies
to support those those metrics.
You are basically.
Displaying those metrics on your
site so that people are aware that
they can trust your application,
they can trust your site, and this is
pretty much available on all of the
important SaaS applications you want.
Today.
They kind of display their reliability
metrics and that is more like a, a
selling point for this companies where
they demonstrate that, hey, we have been
99.99% available for like past 60 months.
Whatever, like past 60 days and that's
the reason you should be buying a product.
Most of the security companies are, are
kind of using this metric as a unique
selling point and that basically, is
something that you should be considering
for that stage of the organization.
I think also accordingly, the security
and the compliance requirements evolve
as the com companies get picture.
Maybe you can just do away
with like some basic PC.
IDS is kind of compliances, but as
those mature, maybe FedRAMP could
be a next priority based on the
set of customers you're addressing.
The different security challenges
might need investment into different
tools for delivering the secure
experiences you should need to invest
into those next level of tools and
technologies At that stage of the.
And yeah, I mean that that's what
essentially happens like, you know, as
you grow from a very small organization
to a very large organization, you need
to really prioritize your reliability
story with the size of the organizations,
with the goal of the organization so
that there is some coherence onto what we
are building, how it is being consumed.
And what's the end goal of your, a
very core aspect of design thinking as
far as the reliability is concerned is
important for a site reliability engineer.
You need to really
evolve with the company.
I can, as you are defining what
assertive mindset looks like and how do
you basically cultivate this mindset?
Some of the core principles that
are clearly required by defining
your reliability story is, are some
of the things that I have here.
First thing that I would really
ask myself is what the customer
experience is gonna look like.
What's my end user?
What is it really expecting from my
application, and how can I really
build my reliability story around it?
So.
Building a customer.
Building a SRE mindset really
starts with customer expertise
first, what is your customer?
What is he expecting
from that application?
To put things in more detailed perspective
or like to highlight an example.
Let's say for an example like presently
the company I work for deliver
some end number of 10 blue links
in whatever, X number of seconds.
For us, the most critical, important
and important aspect is basically
delivering those end number of
results within a certain timeframe.
We need to be accurate as much as
possible, and at the same time, you need
to deliver those experiences to the end
user within one second of timeframe.
And that's where most of the optimization
and most of our energy goes in.
Whereas one of the last organization
I've worked for, I think.
Latency was not much of a concern there.
I think back then we really
optimized for reliability.
We had a status page, which basically
said that we have been up for like last
last 30 days for 99.99% of the time.
And that, that is one of our metrics that,
you know, you can reliably trust us to use
and build your application on top of that.
So I think each, each, a
reliability story essentially
starts with customer experience.
And once you get a grip on the
customer experience, you can invest
in the right set of tools, the right
set of technologies, and basically
define your metrics of success for
reliability based on what a customer
experience is gonna look like.
I always think the most important
thing that UNI should to do, not
just from the Sari perspective, but
even from a Korean perspective, is.
Defining before you actually dive.
Planning is the most important aspect
of any career, any phase, and even
for site reliability engineers.
I think that's the most important
thing that we should be doing before
you actually take on any project.
Defining what are the metrics of success.
Writing it down like, you know, Hey, these
are the five set of things that I would be
addressing with my this X, Y, Z project.
These are my end goals.
These are the metrics.
And the SO definitions for me,
this is how I'm basically gonna
chop out the entire landscape.
I think defining well in advance
doesn't really solve the problem, but
it at least keeps you on the track.
It at least keeps you from getting
detract on something that you
shouldn't really be addressing.
It.
It helps people review your plans.
It helps people basically guide you.
So I think defining before you dive
is one of the most important things
that, sRD should consider from
the mindset building perspective.
The third thing that I think is
important is basically balancing velocity
or, or innovation with reliability.
This to some degree I explained in
my previous slide is like, as the
maturity of the organization, as
the size of the organization grows
from x, y, z stage, I think your
reliability story should really evolve.
But there should be a threshold where
you are really balancing the velocity.
You are really balancing your innovation
with reliability because real people
are dependent on real things for
your applica on your application.
I think balancing velocity with
the right reliability knobs
and bolts is, is very crucial.
And the third thing and the fourth
thing that I think is, is crucial.
As a site reliability engineer is
keeping on top of my mind, like, you
know, things are always gonna fit.
Like, you know, you, you
cannot build for success.
You have to design for failure.
Things are always gonna fail.
There are always gonna be eight scenarios
where, which you never consider,
which always stay off your plate.
And which is something
you should replan it once.
And this is where.
This aspect and this design thinking
comes in place like, you know, you
have to really design for failure.
You are not designing for success,
and that way you really bring
in those critical aspects and
critical thoughts on your mind.
Like, you know, what are the
different ways this application can
fail and how could I avoid that?
One of the things I we largely do over at
Google is even like, you know, running a
lot of the tests it's more like a, more
like simulating failures in an application
before you have actually productionalized
it or, or like, you know, you have
onboarded a new feature is like, you know,
running through different scenarios and
trying to simulate what are the different
failure scenarios you can come across.
And whether it's it's degrading
customer experience one another,
do we have the right alerting and
monitoring set up so that we get.
I alert it well in advance
before customer notices it.
And third, do we have the right mitigation
strategies in place so that if in case
there is a fallout, we have a way to
mitigate that thing before customers
actually feel the heat and you have
a bad reputation going out there.
So I think these are like
different strategies.
Guarding, you know, having the
right guardrails for an application
in the build phase in the.
In the, you know like in the delivery
phase and define what are the
different places where like, you
know, your network can fail, your
disks can fail, your servers can
fail, things can go out of order.
As in data centers my previous
company, we ran a multi easy and multi
data center kind of infrastructure.
Just to ensure that, you know,
if a specific data center of a
specific region is down, we are
always taken care by another region.
You know, there is failover scenarios,
there is replication, there is like, you
know, backups, there is standby backup.
There is a third backup so
that you never lose your data.
So all these things essentially
spin up from the same.
From a very core aspect that you really
need to think about failure while you
are designing this application and
designing it for failure is one of the
very crucial aspects of design thinking
as far as site reliability is concerned.
Another thinking that I think that
has really helped me and I think is
very important as far as the design
thinking of this reliability aspect
is concerned is keeping in mind that
reliability is a continuous process.
It's not something that, you know, you're
gonna define at the start and then you
are gonna achieve at, at a certain point
it's, it's like this infinite curve, which
never really reaches a goal, but each.
Each progression is, it's like it
takes you to closer to your destiny.
And you should think that as a
continuously evolving process where
each incremental improvement is
basically take you closer and closer
to your end goal of defining and, you
know, delivering this super awesome,
reliable experience for their customers.
And I mean, where do you start?
Like, you know, like.
It's, it's very difficult at the start.
It looks like, oh, you're gonna
deliver this pleasant experience
for this millions of users.
But where do you start?
I think each, each great automation
always started with a very hacky script.
Something that was done manually once,
second, and the third time someone
really thought of like, you know,
writing a back script to get things done.
I think that's where the, the.
Automation really starts,
and it's okay to be hacky.
It's okay to write your back script.
It's okay to have like in a very buggy
script to start with, but that's the
first step you need to take before you
actually start investing into way better
tools and way better processes out there.
Keep learning, keep evolving,
but at the same time, you
need to start somewhere, one.
Second, keep your continuous involvement
and continuous improvement going on
because this, this is a continuous cycle.
It is never gonna end.
Each incremental step is gonna basically
take you closer to your end goal.
And you need to basically keep
yourself engaged and involved in
improving the reliability aspect.
And for that, I think you really
need to invest in right, a set of.
As I, as I said in the previous
slide, you know, define the right SLO
metrics, define the right reliability
metrics, maybe start with 99% of
reliability for an application, and
eventually challenge yourself that,
oh, next year we're gonna target 99.9%
reliability, 99.99% of reliability
or availability of our application.
And take it for me, like, you know,
99 and 99.9 is a huge curve, 99.9.
Point nine 2, 99 0.99 is the
second exponential investment
that you really need to make.
There are some crazy numbers out
there at Google, like, you know, that
we consider, like, you know, each
incremental line is like tons of, tons
of efforts basically to get that going.
But I think the point I want to make is
this is a continuously evolving process.
It's a, it's a process that is gonna.
Keep on going, and you really
need to keep yourself focused
and you need to start somewhere.
As for building this
reliability process, oh yes.
And don't expect perfect
results at the start.
It is gonna evolve.
It is gonna basically reach to a
state where you're gonna be happy
for that state of your customer
and for that stage of your company.
But eventually there would be
a next evolution story that
you would go through with.
You might want to scrap a lot of
things and build all over again.
So it's, it's, it's a constant process.
You need to really keep yourself
evolving as the reliability and and
the story of your organization evolves.
As, as we are thinking as we are
basically learning to understand,
how do you start to think?
I think one of the most important
things and the questions to
answer here is, how do you learn?
Because there's this vast
amount of information out there.
You can go all the down to the stack,
like at the kernel level and understanding
how, like, you know, how interrupts
work, how operating systems are basically
designed to how paging and low level
memory mapping really works too.
To things like, you know, how networks
are designed, how, how P-C-P-I-P model
works and how basically with this I
mean, you can, you can look at the entire
spectrum and go all the way to like
how this modern agent AI applications
are designed and what's this ML
algorithm really doing and how this ML
machines and ml models are deployed.
I think.
My point here is this is a worst domain.
Like, you know, you can
always keep learning.
There's also a security aspect of it.
There are vulnerabilities,
there are different attacks.
And as a SIT, as a cyber reliability
engineer, you really need to keep yourself
heads about the ground and understand
like what's going out in the market
to be aware, like, you know, these are
the set of vulnerabilities out there.
You need to basically take those
design considerations while you're
designing those applications.
So compliance requirements is,
is a another aspect that you need
to really keep yourself with.
And while you are like keeping yourself
up with all this traditional aspects
of learning, this lot evolving in
the computer industry, Nvidia keeps
growing out new new hardwares.
Google is coming up with new
technologies, there are new
tools coming up in the market.
Something that you will.
Invested for like last five
years suddenly gets changed.
You were running your monolithic
applications or like maybe design
your VPCs in cloud and design some
E two applications and suddenly
there's a thing called hot Kubernetes
probably helps you do all those
things in the span of a second.
Maybe that's how that is
gonna solve your problem.
So, I mean, the point here is
you are continuously learning.
You're continuously evolving.
Where do you keep yourself grounded
is the most important question.
And that's where I think I, I believe
in this concept of t model of learning,
where you keep yourself breath going,
you keep yourself learning, you keep
attending sessions, you keep attending
conferences, you, you keep understanding
what is going out in the market.
But at the same time,
there is one single domain.
There is one single choice of your
learning that you keep going deep down.
And be, be a expert of that
field that is actually gonna
keep you going on the long run.
And this, there's a number of things
that are happening on the, on the
breadth side of the world, which
will actually help you navigate
your career in the right direction.
Otherwise it gets very crazy.
Like, you know, you cannot really keep
up with what's happening out there.
You cannot really understand each and
every thing and how it really operates.
And it's fine.
Like, you know, understanding
that you don't know everything.
It's way better than saying that I know
everything and I can fix everything.
I, I mean, as a site reliability engineer,
that's one of the important learnings
that I have, that I have had over the
years is you cannot know everything.
There are only be certain aspects of
the system that you can really know
very well, but that also doesn't mean
that you should just stay invested
in that aspect of the problem.
You need to increase your
broader scope of learning.
You need to just.
At least have a right balance of
like, you know, what depth and what
breadth you are basically having for
different set of tools, technologies,
and the new evaluations that is
happening in the, in the market.
And this, this goes a long way, I
think the another thing that is very
core to a site reliability engineer is
basically dealing with incidents like
I always feel Cy Reliability engineer
is more like a soldier standing in the
forefront and ensuring that that is
experiences of his end users are always
protected and mitigated in the right way.
And while you are doing.
This entire incident handling process.
I think one great learning that I
have had over the course of this
n years is blameless culture.
It is a very important part, OFCY
engineers learning to understand what
this blameless culture essentially means.
It is very helpful in basically
when you are defining postmortems,
when you're writing things down.
On a postmodern talk why something
happened, how something happened, it
really addresses the aspect of steam.
It addresses a collective problem solving
approach where you define what really
happened, how it could be avoided, what
you need to ensure what could be done
so that it doesn't really happen and you
are not pointing fingers at other people.
You are basically taking it as a. The
responsibility, your own responsibility
in owning things for yourself.
And I think that this thing
really goes a long way.
The second thing while dealing with
fires in production is basically you
really need to start thinking about
going from this firefighting mode
to basically a fire prevention mode.
If there is fire for
the first time, maybe.
It was not avoided.
It couldn't be avoided.
But the second time, if that happens, then
probably having a mindset that we need
to really address this for a long term is
something that should come to your mind.
And I think that is very important
because that's how you keep yourself
invested into new things rather than
going back to the same old aspects and
keep fixing things again and over again,
over, also from prevention perspective,
I always feel it is more important
to invest in long term projects.
If something has happened for once or
twice, you should really invest your
energy in ensuring that this doesn't
happen and what's the long term solution
to basically address this rather
than showing short term mitigations.
Short term things are medications,
which are good to stop the bleeding,
but long term solutions ensures
that they never occur or reoccur.
So that your energy is not wasted
in figuring out the problem,
or it's not always you are who
is dealing with the problem.
So you are also saving your teammates
basically from from the fire.
So that that's a important thing.
The third and the most important thing
over here is you really need to move away
from tools and move towards principles.
What are the principles on which.
This this observability and this
reliability story is built on because most
of the times the fundamental aspects of
reliability, scalability, observability,
they always have stayed the same.
Irrespective of what tools you have
used and what technologies you are
using to power your applications,
you move from one company to another.
You move from one application to another.
The most important thing is.
The principles always these things
operate, always stay the same.
So I would generally invest my
energies in understanding and
learning more about these principles
rather than the actual tools.
You can pretty much learn a tool
in fuel, a number of days, get
away it and move on a new tool.
But I think investing your right
energy and understanding these
principles is very important and
that's how you pass on the knowledge.
It is very crucial as insight team
Junior if you are defined a certain
principle, if acknowledge something,
you really need to write it down, pass
it on to the next ari, or make this
that, make it more like a defining
principle for your team so that everyone
acknowledges it and follows by it.
So that it's more like a standard.
So setting standards is very important
for for the psychological engineer.
I think last and the most important thing
with the life of an ARI or the mindset
of an sari is you should be involved
and thinking about building a community,
staying with the community, because I
feel community learning is very important.
That keeps you ab upgraded and you abreast
with what's happening in the society.
So going out, connecting with the
people, knowing what's happening
out there, sharing your thoughts,
sharing your insights to the people.
Evangelizing what you have done within
an organization is very important because
it not just helps you grow, but also
helps other people grow along with you.
And it's the collective mindset
that solves a larger problem.
I feel we have been here
because we are standing on this.
Shoulders of this thousand great people
who build underlying technologies.
And we are like, building the next layer
of technology solutions on top of that.
So I think it is very important for
Recit liability engineer to develop a
mindset where he has to learn, but at
the same time he has to like, share
this knowledge and information for
the outer world to basically evolve,
learn, keep sharing, keep growing.
And yeah.
That's, that, that's, I feel is
something of very crucial importance
for a site library to engineer.
Yes, that's all I had for this session.
Hope you enjoyed my thoughts
and and my ideas about site
reliability and the design thinking.
If you have any questions, please
feel free to reach out to me.
If you have any questions, I'll
be happy to guide you along.
And thank you for the organizations
for organizing this awesome event.
Event.
Thank you.