So hello at Cov 42 Site
Reliability Engineering 2025.
Glad that you're here
and listening to my talk.
Yeah.
Let's let's buckle up
and deep dive into it.
The session title is Real
Time Earthquake Color System.
Leveraging serverless
architecture with confluent Kafka.
Basically, it's project which it's
mostly built in AWS cloud with specific
services, mostly serverless and also
in combination with confluent Kafka,
just for the message distribution.
And achieving a fast kind of
delivery of the notifications
where I some bold lines about what I'm
doing, what or what I did in the past.
Cloud development, cyber
security, or kind of projects,
architectures, designs consultancy.
Everything like this project in data
science domain from data extraction,
data modeling until, let's say about
full a TL pipeline or anything like that.
So just trying to provide from real
scenario data, something that's practical.
So just having practical projects
based on specific demands of data.
Multiple security research is
for top pro Romanian banks.
So yeah.
Also this one is is a very
interesting to let's say pen test,
if you want to call it like that.
An a s company builder is serverless.
Niche for one year right now.
If you have any questions after this talk,
ideas, remarks, anything like that, you
could contact me on mail or on LinkedIn.
This, these are my addresses,
so yeah.
Enough about me.
Let's let's try to.
Explain what's in this project.
The story of behind the
research project is like
spread between these questions.
So these these bullet points
are let's say questions.
For example, the first one, why
the need for high performance
earth throwing notification system?
I start right by providing you
an interesting story of what we
currently have in Romania in terms
of Romanian alerting system, which
is provided by the government.
It's the Romanian alert application,
which reaches like very low.
Hardware in our telephones.
So it's basically delivered with the
telephone and they're just emitting these
kind of alerts or a bad weather, critical
accidents, critical infrastructure
failures, anything like that.
But an interesting point
here is that in very.
Large of the cases on
notifications, we receive those
alerts after the event unfolded.
For example, after the
bad weather was just gone.
So if you are seeing the
rainbow, you'll just receive a
message, so that's not very good.
Although the project and what the
government develops is is very very good.
Very nice ideas.
This is why I was thinking back then one
year and a half ago, why not having also
a kind of notification for earthquakes
in that time.
I was thinking to just have the
notifications when the event
happening is happening because I was
thinking that I cannot, I. Predict.
So I cannot have a machine learning model.
We just which is just trained on
previous data and just will predict
something because it's so critical
and it's let's say unpredictable,
let's say it's a natural happening.
So I started to look around
and see what kind of data.
Could I use, because I cannot just
put in the ground some some systems
and just have some some data from
from those, at least not right now,
because in what I'm about to say to
tell you is where I found basically
that the data and in which project.
I found that there is an institute
of seismic movements and earthquake
researches in links to the
Romanian government, which has
some very talented researchers and
very interesting projects there.
And in those projects there was
a kind of very interesting one
called rapid Alerting System.
Or something like that, which was based
on some physical systems placed in
northwest of Romania in the, let's say
the well-known area seismic movements,
at least in the couple of years.
So they placed those systems in those
areas, and they are just emitting data.
When the very little system
movement is detected.
So until now, very interesting thing.
But I was also thinking okay, so
that town is like in distance,
like 500 kilometers from Bucharest,
which is the capital of Romania.
So if we are translating
like the kilometers in some.
Time thing.
There are some couple of minutes
until the full waves, for example,
like a seven fourth wave hits.
There are like a couple of minutes
or at least one two minutes until
the full waves are received in est
in in our towns, like in the north,
central North, three minutes, two,
three minutes, something like that.
So I was thinking what, having this
advantage, so having the advantage
of time, distance, and time use
those systems, basically that data,
which is exposed by them in a browser
application, I think right now and
I can use, just listen to that data.
And use it to spread it to
certain consumers, basically, and
subscribers, which can be people
or critical infrastructure things.
So I just responded almost to also
the second question, where to find
good real time earthquake data.
So like I've said this institute provides.
Very interesting projects.
And that particular one with the
systems placed in the ground, emitting
data at the very little assessment
movements, it was very helpful.
So we integrated with that
with that emitting system.
And we are listening for for
events, basically why choosing
the serverless ecosystem.
So I am ambassador in AWS or serverless
lambdas and anything related to
that, it's from a perspective, due
to my previous projects, I integrated
Lambdas serverless, like anywhere.
But beside the knowledge,
it was also practical.
Why I'm saying practical is because
for this particular project, we
don't need nonstop servers like 24 7.
We just need some some listeners
which need to be prepared when the
earthquake hits, just to spin up those
kind of instances, containers, and use
them to just spread and distribute.
Very fast, the notifications.
This was the first thing.
The second thing is also the costs.
'cause yeah, if we have like servers
up 24 7, it's also a matter of costs
be involved and how to scale them
just on the fly, like in milliseconds.
So these two things were the
base pillars of choosing.
A s Lambda serverless.
Moving on to the architecture of the
serverless identification system.
What you see here is the base
architecture, which is the
first version, let's say.
I'll try to explain you like in
big lines because we will deep
dive in the next next slides.
What in the gray is like the backbone
of the system, which has the Lambda
producers, which I'm calling like
Lambda producers 'cause of the Kafka
integration and also the Lambda consumers.
In the right in the center,
you have the topics partitions,
the backbone of Kafka itself.
The yellow ones are like the.
Error handling mechanisms.
SQS, that letter queues just for
putting all kind of errors like
if there are errors networking or
latency or things like that, we'll
just retry on that code execution.
But if it's like a major failure, we'll
just put it in a particular queue.
And keep it there for a manual studying
of the logs and of the error itself.
The blue ones are for monitoring, just
monitoring the number of instances, how
the system behaves, costs, and are very
important because we are I will show
you afterwards, we are also scaling up.
So we need to see the costs and
how the system behaves, like
little, let's say, central kind of
monitoring or everything for errors.
And yeah, also the end channels, if you
view them you can view them in the right
Twilio, like SMS mail through A-S-S-E-S.
Or through Telegram, which is
like a backup thing from from
our end, from our perspective.
The purple ones are for CICD, like
pipelines for creating the infrastructure,
but also we are thinking you, you can
view it in the next slides to scale up
and down through this kind of CICD idea.
The build some scannings just
automation things on the repository.
And the block with with green,
it's like the application, the web
application where the end subscribers
or the creator infrastructure members
could join into the backbone system.
What I'm trying to say, join is
like just subscribing the system.
Provide maybe a telephone number or some
kind of informations about the subscriber
and based on them, you can see there
that there is a database that's a Dynamo
database connected to the backbone.
Of the system, which
will be just iterated.
So we will just iterate through the
members, through the subscribers
and try to notify everyone.
Also, some lambda functions there
for the different kind of APIs, some
protections through the firewall.
The main application was we're thinking
to put it in like a Kubernetes.
Infrastructure, but we will see maybe use
what kind of serverless also for that one.
Architecture of the base notification
system, like I've said in the previous
slide, this is the backbone the gray area.
If you call it like this, you can see
the Kafka producers, Kafka consumers,
and the Kafka topics in in the middle.
In the Kafa producers, we have
this thing called multithreading.
Just using the, let's say, full
capacity, full resources of instances
of Lambda the CPU, so just using the.
The full capacity and try to separate,
let's say threads and link them to
certain partitions or topics in Kafka.
So this is the beginning of rapid
or fast production and notification.
Basically the first the first step.
We're trying to put like a, also a
topic roulette on top of what Kafka has
like for topics, partitions, and
try to not override messages in
the same partitions, same topics.
Just try to have a thread and
the partition and put the message
on that and try to to connect
it to the Kafka consumers.
This is also like a an interesting
key idea of this project to have the
partitions and basically topics in
Kafka triggering certain instances of
Kafka called the, called consumers.
Achieving a, a parley list, distributing
the message the most fast way possible.
Can be.
The yellow box is monitoring
and mo monitoring, at least
for the kind of major failures.
So for the air errors, which are
put in like the error queue and for
the failed events, health events,
just networking, latency, things
like that, we will try to retry.
Two times, third, three times.
We have the end channels where
the notification is sent.
SMS mailed Telegram is
back up and the dynamo.
So the database, the blue one
is where the subscribers are
just present and registered.
And the Kafa producers listen for
that data, which I've explained
before, which is provided through
through the systems of the institute.
Another interesting thing here will deep
dive bit into the architecture of Kafka
integration in the serverless context.
Like I said, Kafka is is here to somehow
parallel distribute the messages, the
notifications, and to also trigger
parallel pins of plum duck consumers.
So every partition we will have
a certain code execution, like a
certain, trigger, let's say certain
lambda as a consumer, which will
try to notify a certain subscriber.
We have the threads just using the
resources, the topic roulette, build on
top what Kafka or they have or topics,
partitions, and try to fill up every.
Partition to be able to trigger from
it the Lambda consumers, which have the
logic to just iterate the database of
subscribers and notify them in the end.
Yeah.
So here we also have some yellow dots.
Which represent like the scaling
possibilities, so scaling in terms
of resources, threads and scaling
in terms of partitions topics.
And in the, again, in the Kafka
consumers just trying to scale
the triggers based on what Kafka
has and also the Lambda consumers,
the Lambda Kafka producers key elements.
We have the multithreading explained
in the previous slide using those
resources from the Lambda instances
thread lock to not write in the
same topics from separate threads.
Using partition number to not
override data in partitions and
using lambda retrial and sqs
that letter for major failures.
And the retry is just for latency,
networking, minor problems.
Consumer key elements.
Here are some a again, some
nice ideas from our perspective.
Custom timestamp blanc lock for
mechanism for parallel dynamo update.
So we are trying to here
was an interesting dilemma,
let's say, because we.
We saw that
there were multiple notifications
for a certain subscriber.
So let's say one, one one,
one man and one fellow could
receive multiple notifications.
And the second guy could not receive
anything just because the, there
was a, like a. Race between them
and the first one won and just
had all the notifications there.
So we wanted to just lock
somehow certain subscribers.
If those were notified, basically
the code already was applied on them
and they received, or it's like in
progress of receiving a notification
and not, trying to notify it
again, just moving to the next one.
This is like the lock per
subscriber, per item to have for
each individual one one notification.
Optimistic locking in the custom
dyna concurrency control is.
Method, just build on top of the first
one with the custom timestamp log.
We are just putting like a version and
we know if the version changed, if we
need to notify the subscriber or not.
Just let's say another fence of
achieving the concurrency and the
fast thing, but also to notify all the
subscribers and not miss one of them.
Yeah, using lambda retry que
for errors, like for the Lambda
producers and Lambda consumers using
a Coldstar worm start methodology.
We are seeing that using a worm
start helps because it's the
last phase of the notification.
So started from the producer.
Reaching the Kafka cluster.
And after that we need something
that's in a ready state.
Just have it in there, a number of
instances and lambdas, and try to have
them in a ready state, just ready to go
to a list of subscribers, execute the code
for reach, and send the notifications.
But this is again, an interesting
procedure also in auto scaling basically.
So if you have like thousands of
subscribers or reaching a certain
number of subscribers, maybe you
need certain instances in Worm State,
resting cold start, things like that.
The Lambda Kafka consumer
integration with database.
So there is like a custom dynam blocking.
This was the first version, like I've
explained a bit in the previous slide.
So from the earthquake topic, the
partition we're just trying to
trigger a certain lamb execution.
And from that execution, the
code will act on certain items
and using this kind of lock.
Like the timestamp on, on
which we are placing the log.
We know that an item is in progress of
being updated or it was just updated like
one millisecond ago, something like that.
And the next trigger, so the trigger
topic two will go to the next one.
So just going like a domino
thing, but from the front.
So view viewing like a domino row
from the front and just go going
gr gradually with each trigger.
So with which it, with it with which,
which partition just going through each
subscriber and notify each one of them.
This is four, just using the full,
full capacity of triggers and not
wasting like multiple triggers.
So multiple code executions
on a certain item, although
there is there is like a loop.
So going gradually through the
items, we can end up using the
same trigger for the same item.
Yeah, it won't be, notified
like twice or three times.
But we will have we have a
waste, let's say of time.
So trigger the trigger.
We lacked like twice on the same
item, but just updating it once.
Yeah.
So this is like the first version
of what we were trying to achieve.
Concurrency of notifications and
also notifying the subscribers in
a best way and notifying all the
subscribers, the custom dynamo,
segmented subscriber processing.
This was like the second version
of the Lambda consumers logic.
So from the previous version, we are
trying to segment the list of subscribers
and having like logs per certain segments.
So for example, one trigger from a
partition from Kafka will just act on
a certain segment and just lock that
segment with a block ID or something
like that from ID one to ID 400.
Something like that.
So just the trigger will act
on, on that particular segment.
So in this one the the
triggers won't conflict.
There won't be any race conditions.
Let's say each trigger will be
allocated to a certain segment
and will just do the work.
So the trigger can be viewed like
worker, so the worker will do
the job just for that segment.
So from now we can view that domino
ization from the parallel from
the lateral view, we are viewing
with workers, like soldiers, just
particular segments of items which are
basically subscribers, peoples people,
infrastructure members, things like that.
Just on them the triggers
the workers will focus.
This is an improvement in terms of how
we are reaching those subscribers through
Kafka, partitions topics and lambda code.
Different kind of lambda code
executions, which are done in parallel.
Also moving with this
parallel view through the end.
So having the triggers, the workers
act in parallel the subscribers.
But although having one worker for
a segment like one to 400 or 4,000
is like a lot, even though there
will be like, lo, very low level
party threading in that particular
segment, you only have one worker.
It's a hard work there.
This is like the second version,
so this is like a parallel
distribution and segmentation.
In Lambda Kafka consumer, there are like
maxim invocations and locks per segment.
Also like domino style, but
we led multiple executions.
So multiple code triggers to just
act on let's say particular segments.
So we allow multiple workers to
work on the same segment and doing
that low level multithreading.
So letting, I dunno, maybe two.
Like in this example, we let two
triggers just act on on on the
same segment so they can resolve
or notify and execute the code.
Or faster, let's say we can
allocate, like in this example,
maximum workers like five.
Or anything like that, just depending
on the segmentation, which is
done like in an automatic way.
Just just having the nu the maximum
number of subscribers, maybe dividing
somehow that list and having the
numbers of locks Mexican workers.
Things like that.
So what's the important idea is that
we are viewing the domino from the
lateral view and we have multiple
soldiers located for the same segment.
They will not conflict with
each other, there won't be any
risk conditions between them.
They will just act like multiple workers
are dividing the work in the same segment.
This is like the improve the.
Improved version of the distribution
between the Kafka code execution the
Lambda code execution and the Dynamo
where we store the subscribers.
So this is like the level right now.
But we're also trying other things and
just improve the speed and everything,
like I've said with it, that granular
multithreading apply that segment level.
So it is very blow level I could say.
So we will just keep on researching and
see what's the best for for that moment.
Increasing every time with
new, new possible ways.
Again, one interesting thing.
So like I've said Kafka was integrating
here just to resolve this par
distribution, but instead of Kafka, we
could use Kinesis from AWS, which could
work well or a different kind of cues
to just be to just be close to the.
To the cloud, not go to to, to the
internet, the cluster and just come
back, just be in the same network.
May, maybe it could decrease the
latency, but this is for the later
some some things about auto scaling.
Which is very interesting from this
project because we don't want to have
manual interventions when it reaches like
a base kind of stable state, the project.
We won't need those manual
interventions anymore.
This is why we are thinking to put
in place a kind of auto scaling,
scaling up or down the system
based on the number of subscribers.
So if we have like a range between,
I dunno, zero and 201 or 301,
we'll just increase with threads.
So basically resources allocated in Lambda
producer instances topics, partitions,
the Kapha clusters, and also the number of
triggers and number of Lambda consumers.
Yeah, like the warm state consumers, if
we are going down with the subscribers,
we can just lower the resources on
the fly again, if we, yeah, it's hard
to predict something to autoscale
through the roof before having that
major earthquake, but at least.
There is a possibility to scale it
based on this number of subscribers.
For now this is our idea for now, but
we can think about some other features,
let's say which could be linked
auto scaling, not predicting 'cause.
Predicting is hard.
Hard.
We need something that's realistic.
So this was made through custom
scripts like some Python combined
with Azure with A-W-S-C-L-I commands
for for Lambdas, for the Kafka
clusters, just on some custom scripts.
And these were placed in a
lambda, like an external lambda.
We just, which orchestrates the
entire, auto scaling and everything.
This kind of external lamb does
act also like for the previous
segmentation, just allocating
different kind of maximum workers.
Segmentation ID just on the
fly, again, viewing the number
of subscribers, just doing the
calculations and having these numbers.
The custom auto scaling using Terraform.
So infrastructure as a code.
So right now we are trying to reduce
the custom scripts, so custom shells
and things like that and just move
to an infrastructure as a code.
Something that's more
used in every project.
Right now, software project is the
same kind of logic, just, we're
also provisioning the infrastructure
through infrastructure as a code.
It's all the services and
everything, and we also use it.
That's the interesting part, to scale
or up or down with GitHub actions.
Or we could use, something in AWS for
code deployment because we need to check
the number of subscribers and to trigger
the Terraform execution with a new list
of what we need, like parameters, like we
need two threads, we need four threads.
We need four topics.
So these are the kind of, numbers,
which are placed on a certain file,
which is sent to the Terraform
just to execute on on that list.
So it's a very interesting approach of how
infrastructure is a code act or scaling
up or down or serverless, lambda AWS
architecture and, ion system basically.
Yeah.
These were like in the area of development
operations, how to operate entire system
when it's like in a stable position
after we figure out the services,
what we need and so on and so forth.
This like a separate lane of, how
to keep it automatic, let's say also
in for creation of the resources
and the services and everything.
Then to have it a certain time step of
them, if something happens, we could
revert a certain step, certain snapshot
of the resources and the architecture.
And we could also use it for scaling
up or down, depending of the.
Number of subscribers in in this phase.
So this is the project.
This is the researches.
These are the researches done until now.
We yeah, we are in touch with some
we have some discussions how to.
Proceed further how to do other
interesting researches for these kind of
earth failure notifications May maybe to
integrate it in what there is on provided
by the governments, not only Romania, who
knows to have it like an alternative on
just having some kind of integrations.
Between what's already there or
providing new ideas, anything like that.
Yeah, just bringing something
to the table, a kind of
innovation we could we could say.
So if you have any questions
or remarks or opinions.
Please feel free to contact
me on mail, LinkedIn.
Just be aware that the project
itself, it's it's registered.
So yeah, if you want to, if you have some
inspiration from it or you want to do
something similar, please just contact
us or me just in in the first place and
we could align and we could discuss.
Firstly, so like I've said, it's a
protected project under some licenses.
Yeah, we also have some open
discussions now and there.
So yeah.
Thank you.
And thank you for being here.
It was it was pleasure.
And thanks for the, thanks to the
organizers for inviting me to present.
This this research.
Thank you.