Deploying infrastructure is always
a mix of planning and firefighting.
Sometimes everything works perfectly.
Other times you are troubleshooting
at 2:00 AM wondering what went wrong.
Hey guys, my name is Prade Gadi.
I'm a senior DevOps engineer.
My agenda today covers a little bit
about my journey and my experiences
with incidents, tools and SRE world.
Coming from banking and financial
services sector, I started my journey
working with legacy systems such as web
spear, tomcat, and manual deployments.
Custom scripts helped, but they introduced
a margin for error that made me appreciate
the value of standardized tools like
Terraform Helm and CI CD pipelines.
This talk is a collection
of real world SRD failures.
Lessons learned and the
unexpected challenges that come
with managing infrastructure.
So let me go over my
experiences in real world.
Let me start with a data center incident.
Let me tell you this.
Make sure your cloud provider service
terms aligned with your requirements,
especially around RPOs and.
When we signed up for when we signed
up for GCP, we used Google Cloud
storage with dual region buckets.
We assumed this meant our data would
be replicated instantly between
regions, between different buckets.
Then a data center fire hit and
objects in our GCS bucket where
unavailable for up to two hours.
Yes.
We later discovered that gcps default
replication guarantees only 99.9% of newly
written objects replicated within one
hour, a hundred percent within 12 hours.
Meaning if a data center disaster happens,
there is a chance that some of your
objects might be replicated, can take up
to 12 hours to replicate it to region.
They later recommended enabling turbo
replication, which actually guarantees
a hundred percent replication to
both regions in under 15 minutes.
Regardless of object size, which
we would know this before that way
we would enable this feature and we
didn't have to face this situation.
So what's that lesson here?
Always research if a product
meets your S-L-A-S-L-A needs
before you go to production.
Read the conditions,
apply details seriously.
That's gonna save you from incidents
of this kind if such features exist,
so you wouldn't face these issues.
So research the product
before you sign up.
Let me go over my experience and
incidents with respect to certificates.
So SSL certificates, certificate issues
are more common than you would expect.
A few years ago, public certificate
validated dropped from three years
to one year, which means you have to
renew your certificates every one year.
Especially the public wild card
certificates are often reused
across multiple places, which
makes tracking them harder.
So how do you track them?
So let's say if you use commercial
products like Datadog look for
features like synthetic monitoring.
We, which you could use to track the
endpoints and get the certificate expiry
data and renew the certificates on time.
And if you're using open source such
as Grafana, look for Infinity Plugin.
That way you could query the endpoint
and get the certificate information
and keep track of the certificates.
Also, proper doc certificate documentation
and the locations where it installed,
they're installed is very important.
It sounds basic.
But certificate related outages
can be seriously embarrassing.
Lemme tell you an example.
At one of the company, we had an outage
because it was a financial client because
an intermediate certificate was missing.
Let me explain you
certificate terminology.
In simple terms.
The server certificate is signed by
an intermediate certificate, and the
intermediate is signed by a trusted route.
If the chain is, the complete
chain isn't complete, visitors
may see an incomplete chain error.
So how do you overcome this?
The moment you renew any certificate,
go to open source online tools like
SSL Labs to verify the complete
certificate change and make sure
you have your route intermediate
and the server certificate in place.
Also if you have open SSL utility on
your command line, just hit the end point
and use the option called show search.
It's gonna show you all the
certificate complete chain.
Also, you could look for
something called verify written
code to be zero at the bottom.
That tells you like your certificate
is good and the chain is complete.
Let me talk my experience
with logging and monitoring.
Logs as an SRE logs are your lifetime
lifeline during incident, right?
They're your lifeline.
So if an incident happens, you
always look for logs and metrics.
So ensure that all systems have
proper logging enabled before you
even pro before you even promote
them to production and make sure like
those logs are actually forwarded
to a centralized logging platform.
This should be actually part of
your pre-deployment checklist.
So let me describe a recent incident.
So we had this incident where some
of the records were missing from a
database and that database wasn't
configured properly to emit logging.
So there many logs in that database.
Also, the.
Virtual missions, which we are
connecting to, that database had
logs, but they weren't forwarded
to a central logging system.
So we had to look for logs at multiple
places, which delayed our investigation.
So it's always a good idea to, first of
all, have proper logging in place and
second forward those logs to a centralized
system like Datadog or, Elasticsearch.
If you, if.
You don't wanna use commercial products
due to budget consent constraints.
You could always set up open
source like Elasticsearch.
Likewise, monitoring
plays an important role.
Let me give you an in a simple incident,
happened at my previous company.
So I did set up Elasticsearch logging
system, I didn't, I couldn't set up
the monitoring for the disc due to
various reason and time constraints.
It sounds simple, right?
Being an sorry, how could I miss that?
But, sometimes it's all about
the time and priorities.
So I miss set setting up the dis alert.
And moreover, elastic search wouldn't
ingest logs when it reaches 80%
disc due to the watermark setup.
So it's always better to set up.
These alerts the moment you
install these software or the
moment you install infrastructure.
So the best way to best way is to use
some configuration management tools
like Ansible or Puppet to ensure,
like these monitoring or logging
agents are always installed as part
of your infrastructure provisioning.
You all learn from our mistakes, isn't it?
So the takeaway here is, always have
a centralized logging and monitoring
system, and then that way it's easier
to track issues and fix them quickly.
Let me brief my experience with Terraform.
I didn't have any real incidents
with Terraform, but I absorbed things
could be improved at a workspace,
by following few recommendations.
So if possible, use public Terraform
modules provided by cloud vendors
unless your use case is truly unique.
I spent a lot of time writing
custom modules that I later replaced
with standardized, well-maintained
modules from the Terraform, registry.
It saved time and reduced maintenance.
For example, let's say if
you wanna spin up a GCP vm.
There are a couple of options.
You could write all the modules and
then the resources by yourself, or if
it's, or if your is a simple use case,
just try to use the preexisting public
modules from the Terraform Registry.
And then my second recommendation
would be, if possible, try to
integrate your Terraform with CICD.
In my previous workplace, we were
using, we were all using Terraform,
running terraform from our workstation.
You know that sometimes there is a
chance, like you set up some infra
your provision infrastructure, but
that doesn't that doesn't have any
approvals from any of your teammates.
It's always better to have approval
from your teammates when you provision
an infrastructure or, run any code.
So having Terraform plan and apply
steps in your CSCD enables your
teammates to review them before
the infrastructure is provisioned.
Also, you could also use some security
tools like VI to scan your Terraform code.
It catches misconfigurations
exposed secrets and comprehensive
issues before the hit production.
The takeaway here is reuse.
What's reliable?
Shift Terraform into your CICD workflow.
Expect the unexpected.
See, SRE is just SRE
isn't just about tools.
It's about resilience,
adaptability, and curiosity.
Sometimes you are solving infra shoes.
Other times you are
wearing four hats at once.
Yes, but every incident, every mistake,
and every fix is a chance to grow.
In my last company, I did set up whole
monitoring system and I thought, I'm done.
But no, the data which ha, which
was ingested into Prometheus
was coming in different formats.
Some data was coming in proto
of format, so I had to convert.
I had to write a Python code and
deploy it in a cloud function to
convert that proto of data into a
format which Prometheus understands.
So it was an unexpected, crash course
across languages, formats, and platforms.
That's all SRE about.
And one, one other time I ha
we have chosen ela elastic
for monitoring and logging.
Assuming it's a free tire, you know
that the free tire would be enough.
Turns out Slack alerts were
locked behind a paywall.
Basically we ha we, we have
to upgrade to premium version.
If we wanted to send any alerts
to the Slack, then we ended up
writing our own Pi Python scripts
to send those alerts ourselves.
So my point here is, always
pilot tools in dev environments
before moving to productions.
Because if you know what your requirements
better before you even move to production,
then you would avoid a lot of manual work.
You even know, if that product
is really worked for you.
So the key take takeaway
here is, always pilot things.
And then, try to learn new tech switch
hats and fix things under pressure.
You had to be ready for that as an SRE.
Not everything goes according to plan.
Sometimes you are learning, piloting,
implementing, and fixing all in one day.
It's intense, but that's
where the real growth happens.
Thank you very much for listening
to my talk and thank you very much.
This opportunity, please feel.