Speaker 31: Hi everyone,
my name is Sonali.
And today I wanna talk about
something slightly different
from a typical SRE discussion.
When we talk about reliability,
we usually think in terms of.
Things like uptime, latency, error
budgets and system telemetry.
Those are absolutely essential, of course.
But increasingly when we operate
large AI enabled platforms or customer
facing applications, the reliability
is not just a technical problem.
It becomes an organizational
system problem.
And the core idea I want to explore
today is this some of the most
interesting reliability signals do
not come from monitoring dashboards.
They actually come from how
organizations are structured and how
they invest and to explore this idea.
We will look at two very different
organizations though in the same industry.
One is Tesla and the second one is
General Motors, and we'll examine
through a system lens and we will use
some of their financial signals for it.
Before that, a quick
note about my background.
I work at the intersection of technical
program leadership, platform engineering,
and AI enabled customer facing systems.
And I'm also researching in management and
finance and in large organizations today.
Program leaders sit in
a very unique position.
We are not just coordinating roadmaps
or, although we are often navigating
at a very unique intersection of
architecture decisions, operational
reliability, organizational
priorities, and investment strategies.
So as platforms become more complex
especially with AI components,
reliability becomes deeply.
To how organizations make decisions.
So the lens that I bring today is
not going to be purely technical.
It is gonna be a social
technical system perspective.
So I hope you find it interesting.
Let me briefly outline what
we will explore in this talk.
First the premise that financial
signals or organizational signals can
sometimes reflect underlying engineering
strategy of that organization.
Second we'll look at two
organizations, like I mentioned,
Tesla and General Motors.
They are.
System systematically very different
in terms of their architecture.
And third, we look at profitability
patterns and what they might
tell us about the operational
behavior of any organization.
And finally, we'll
translate those insights.
Back into lessons for engineering
leaders and SRE practitioners
who are managing large systems.
So again, this is not a finance talk.
It is really about learning how
to read organizational signals,
the way we read system telemetry.
And given the time that I have, I will
use only a couple of signals as examples.
One.
Moving to reliability and organizational
stability, sustainability one
observation I've seen repeatedly
in large platform organizations
is that reliability is inseparable
from organizational sustainability.
Because if you think about
it, engineering systems do not
operate in isolation, right?
They operate inside organizations that
must sustain themselves economically,
operationally, strategically.
And when you are responsible for,
let's say, a large AI platform or a
global customer facing application.
Reliability is influenced
by multiple things.
For example, how resources are allocated,
how aggressively the organization pursues
innovation, and how much investment is
made in infrastructure and how leadership
balances speed versus stability.
Program leaders often sit right
in the middle of those tensions.
And understanding those signals
will always help us anticipate.
How some of our existing systems
will evolve over time right now.
Coming to the core hypotheses
behind this talk pretty simple.
Like I stated operational and
financial insights can act as
very high level telemetry for
complex platform systems, right?
Think about it.
Distributed system.
We monitor CPU, utilization,
memory pressure Q, depth latency.
I'm sure there's more parameters,
but at the organizational level,
the systems are different.
Financial patterns, investment cycles,
profitability ratios, and all of
these can sometimes reflect what
engineering architecture decisions
have been made by that organization.
What is their operational discipline and.
What is their long-term
system sustainability.
Okay, so for today's analysis we will
focus on three ratios gross margin,
which can reflect production, efficiency
and architectural integration.
The next is operating margin or operating
profit margin, which often reflects
operational discipline and cost control
of the organization and net margin,
which indicates long-term sustainability.
These are all financial metrics, but
they can hint at engineering behavior.
So let's get into it.
Let's start with Tesla.
From a systems perspective,
Tesla always operates with a very
tightly integrated architecture.
What does that mean?
It means that their hardware, there's
software manufacturing, distribution,
they're all very closely connected
in platform engineering terms.
This resembles a very.
Vertically integrated stack that
architecture allows for rapid iterations
across different product layers, right?
Decisions can propagate quickly through
the entire system, and this often
produces very strong efficiency signals,
but it can also create variability.
And because rapid innovation cycles
often require aggressive investment.
And constant iterations.
So for program leaders, this kind of
architecture resembles systems that are
optimized for innovation velocity, right?
Because they are really built
for faster innovation and speed.
Now on the contrary, looking at General
Motors or gm general Motors represents
a very different architecture.
It operates as a mature diversified
system, optimized for scale.
As you may be aware, it has a very
large product portfolio, geographically
distributed operations end.
But very highly standardized processes.
So in platform engineering
terms, this resembles a very
stable, modular ecosystem.
The focus in these kinds of organizations
is less on rapid iterations and
more on operational predictability.
These systems are designed to
be resilient and consistent
over a very long period of time.
So from a systems perspective,
this resembles infrastructure
platforms optimized for stability
and long-term reliability.
Now looking at the gross profitability
comparison when we look at gross
profitability patterns between Tesla
and when you actually conduct certain
research studies, you will find is
a sta set a statistically different
significant difference between the two.
Gross Profitabilities.
Tesla tends to show
stronger margins than gm.
This is likely reflecting its vertically
integrated architecture and tighter
control that we just talked about because
they can control the entire value chain.
From an engineering perspective, this
is somewhat analogous to a architecture
with fewer external dependencies.
Because the title, the integration, the
more efficiency you can sometimes achieve.
And interestingly we see similar
patterns in technology platforms, highly
integrated, let's say, AI platforms where
organizations control infrastructure
models and delivery layers can sometimes
achieve strong efficiency, but.
All this entire integration
also introduces trade offs.
Now coming to the
operating and net margins.
When we look at operating and net margins
slightly different pattern emerges.
Tesla's performance shows
more variability over time.
Shouldn't be a surprise,
something we just talked about.
GM, on the other hand, demonstrates a
more stable operating platform patterns.
This, reflects the two very
different philosophies that
we just talked about, right?
Because Tesla is prioritizing
innovation and velocity.
It naturally introduces variability
that is being reflected here.
GM prioritizes operational stability,
which leads to this kind of a predictable
performance with a more standard graph.
Neither if you think about
neither is inherently better.
They just represent different
system design choices and may apply
different to different, differently
to different organizations.
Coming to.
Organizational signals this is where
the analogy becomes more interesting
for SREs and platform engineers.
You can think of financial signals,
almost like system telemetry, right?
For organizations.
Tesla resembles a. Innovation,
heavy, high efficiency, rapid
but higher vari variability.
GM resembles a mature
distributed system gm.
When you think about it, you think
of a more predictable output.
You think of more diversified
load distribution and resilience.
Through scale.
So for engineers managing complex
systems, these patterns feel familiar.
We see them in platform
architectures I'm sure all the time.
Now looking at innovation, heavy
architectures, specifically innovation
heavy architectures often produce a
higher top line efficiency, right?
But they also.
Like we talked about, introduce
less stability or more variability.
Continuous iterations can
create operational fluctuations.
So when you think from an SRE lens,
this resembles systems optimized for
say, throughputs and experimentation.
And let's say if we take the example
of modern AI platforms, right?
We see similar patterns at least
the current industry trends.
Model training cycles, infrastructure,
scaling and experimentation.
Pipelines can introduce variability into
the production environment and managing
this variability, knowing this as a
fact, becomes a key leadership challenge.
How do you manage all of this?
Similarly now when we look at
mature architecture, right?
Like we said, they, they
prioritize stability.
These systems rely on, they'll have
standardized processes, they'll
have a very diversified workload.
They are optimized operational workflows,
they may not reach the highest peaks of
performance, but they will demonstrate
strong resilience under pressure.
Large enterprises platforms often
evolve towards this model over time,
especially when they support mission
critical applications at a global scale.
Now, what this means for SREs, right?
What does all of this mean?
Even for engineering leaders?
First, reliability, engineering
cannot rely only on technical
numbers and technical dashboards.
Program leaders benefit from
understanding organizational signals.
Stands them apart.
And third is architecture decisions
often reflect broader business
strategies for that organization.
And finally, reliability goals must align
with the organization's risk tolerance.
For example, AI driven platforms
operating in experimentation mode
may accept higher volatility.
In contrast, mature customer facing
platform support that are supporting, say.
Millions of users, they may not
be able to experiment that much.
They prioritize stability.
So I'd like to just
summarize the key takeaways.
Now.
Financial ratios can reveal
strategic decision choices
within large organizations.
Architectures will always
shape operational variance.
That we saw through the
two examples that we had.
And innovation driven systems
will, show volatility, mature
systems will emphasize stability.
And finally, engineering leaders
who understand broad organizations
and their signals, they will always
make better reliability decisions.
In other words, sometimes you know the
most interesting reliability systems will
come from outside of system dashboards.
Great.
And with that I would conclude my talk.
Thank you all for your time and
patience for listening to me.
I hope this perspective encourages
you to think about reliability,
not just from a technical problem,
but a larger system problem.
Because ultimately the platforms we
build are shaped not only by code.
Or by infrastructure, but they're driven
by the organizations that create them.
Thank you very much.