Good morning everyone, and
thank you for joining me today.
As global supply chain becomes more
complex and interconnected, the risks we
face from fraud to equipment failures are
not just increasing, they are compounding.
In fact, recent studies shows that a
single disruption can cascade and impact
nearly half of downstream operations.
But what if your supply
chain could see this?
These risks coming and fix
them before they cause damage.
Today I will walk you through a
cutting edge, a powered framework
for anomaly detection and
self failing in supply chains.
We will explore how advanced
techniques like graph neural networks,
transformers, and blockchain back.
Smart contracts are D driving a
real-time decisions, automating
responses, and saving millions
both in dollars and downtime.
Let's dive into the future of resilient
and intelligent supply chains, the
growing complexity of supply chains.
Let's begin by
understanding the landscape.
Fortune 500 companies now work
with over 10,000 suppliers across
more than 10 TH one 30 countries.
This incredible web of connections
introduces vulnerabilities at every level.
As a result, we have seen a two
17% increase in risk exposure, and
when a critical node fails, 43% of
downstream operations are impacted.
How about the financial consequences?
An average of one $84 million in
annual losses per organization.
This clearly shows a traditional
reactive approaches no longer surface
the real time event processing framework.
To address this, we need real time
responsiveness and with the help of Apache
Flink and Kafka streams, these platforms
allow us to process massive volumes
of events with millisecond latencies.
For example, Flink handles up to 500
events per second with the latency under
8.3 millisecond and Kafka mayonnaise
23.4 milli million events per minute.
All this is orchestrated under
Kubernetes with K native, ensuring
99.995% availability and seamless
scaling for event driven systems,
advanced anomaly detection with ai.
Now, how do we find disruptions
before they escalate?
GNS are key supply chains naturally
form graphs and GNS help detect
anomalies within these complex
networks with 92.7% accuracy and
68.3% reduction in false positives.
They fair outperform traditional methods.
Transformer based models known for
handling time series data identified
76.2% of anomalies at least 14
days before conventional methods.
With fine tuning, we achieve 83.7%
accuracy using just 200 labeled anomalies.
Explainable A with powerful
models, explainability is crucial.
We use sharp values to highlight which
features influence predictions with the
top three features, often contributing
64.7% of the outcome, reducing
investigation time by nearly half.
Counterfactual explanations.
Let operators test what if scenarios
Improving intervention success by
32.6% and attention visualizations.
Highlight suspicious nodes in the
transaction graph, achieving 86.3%, source
identification in under four minutes.
The self-healing capabilities,
detection is only part of the puzzle.
What happens after an anomaly is detected.
Our framework supports full
self feeling, kept full self
feeling using Apache airflow.
We orchestrate workflows that dynamically
adapt to disruption scenarios.
The meantime to resolution has dropped
from 27.3 hours to just 4.8 hours.
82.4% improvement.
We detect, analyze, remediate,
and continuously learn.
It is a full lifecycle
of intelligent response.
The automated inventory rebalancing a
helps prevent problems, not just fix them.
Through dynamic rebalancing, the system
reduces stockouts by 64.7% and cuts
excess inventory by 37.8%, saving $3.4
million annually for a mid-size company.
All while maintaining a service
level above 98.5%, the smart
contract validation via blockchain.
Blockchain technology ensures
trust in a decentralized ecosystem.
Using Hyperledger Fabric, we
validate transactions securely and
eliminate 97.4% of disputes with the
settlement times improving by 89.3%.
Smart contracts enforce compliance
automatically removing 73 manual
checks per transaction and
achieving a hundred percent accuracy
across 2 37 transaction types.
Human AI collaboration, even with
automation, humans are still critical.
We use chart ops bots integrated
with Slack and Microsoft
teams to alert users quickly.
Cutting awareness time from 73
minutes to just 9.3 minutes.
Our knowledge base helps operators
to solve normal issues, 41.7%
faster, and through continuous
learning loops, the system evolves
with each incident, reducing false
positives by nearly 9% every quarter.
Everything is good.
However, the performance and results
metrics, let's wrap up with impact.
87% reduction in undetected fraud.
62% decrease in disruption duration, 43%
improvement in inventory metrics, 91% of
anomalous detected within five minutes.
Most organizations saw Voes under
10 months, and clearly nearly
90% exceeded their expectations.
These are not marginal gains.
They are transformative.
In summary, modern supply chain
demand more than just visibility that
require intelligence and autonomy.
With AI at the core, organizations
can detect anomalous in minutes,
reduce disruptions significantly, and
optimize operations with confidence.
The future of supply chain resilience
is not just automated, is not just
only automated, but explainable,
secure and human centered.
With this, I close, my presentation.
Thank you all for your attention.
I look forward to see your
questions and thoughts.