Good morning everyone.
my name is asis and I bring, 23 years
of experience, in it, specializing
in data engineering, building real
time, near real time, applications,
in business intelligence, data
warehousing, other applications.
currently I'm work employed with,
MasterCard as data architect.
throughout my career, I have
designed and implemented complex data
solutions, for major, organizations
across the industries, including,
British Telecom, Barclays, and then
many other, fortune 500 companies.
my main expertise lies in creating
scalable data architectures, leading
end-to-end data integration efforts,
driving advanced analytics, to empower.
Datadriven decisions.
as data architect, I have had the
privilege of working with, cutting
edge tools and methodologies
like, client cloud technologies,
different type of, architectural
patterns like, microservices,
even different architectures to
solve, real world challenges.
today I'll be discussing, the
design of, distributed applications,
emphasizing the importance of
robust and scalable architectures.
As we explore, the architectural patterns,
we'll identify common challenges and
the best practices that can, that can
guide us in creating effective solutions.
Understanding these elements, is crucial,
for ensuring that our applications can
handle growth and, complexity while
maintaining performance and reliability.
let's go to, have a look.
Our, today's agenda.
Let's go to the next slide.
Here's the agenda for,
today's presentation.
We'll start with, an introduction
to, the distributed applications,
then, the architectural patterns,
the common challenges, the
best practices and solutions.
we'll try to cover a case study and,
then we'll, have the, summary and
question answer session at the end.
A distribution, a distributed system
is a collection of, independent
computers that appear to the users of
the system as a single coherent system.
these computers or nodes walk
together, communicate over a
network, and, coordinate their
activities to achieve a common goal
by sharing resources, datas and task.
the difference between, we, we are
accustomed with, I know, mainly
central, centralized system.
so the main difference between, a
distributed system and a centralized
system is all data and computational
resources are kept and controlled
in a single, in a central place.
So a server in a centralized system.
applications that user connect to this
hub in order to access and handle data.
although this configuration is easy
to maintain and secure, if too many
users access it simultaneously, or
if the central server malfunctions,
it could become a bottleneck.
A distributed system on the other hand
is, it disperses, data and resources
over several, server locations.
maybe like frequently across
various, physical places.
This gives better
scalability and reliability.
since the system can function in
the event like, in the event of a
component failure, however, because
of the numerous point of interactions,
distributed systems can also, Be difficult
to secure and, administer as well.
like we have, heard of like
various distributed systems.
the terminology I think we are
very much familiar of, like
client server architecture, three
to architecture, microservices,
architecture, even given architecture,
service oriented architecture.
So these are the various common, patterns.
We, we.
we hear like an everyday,
in our software world.
so basically, the distributed
applications like, they're designed
for, to improve performance,
scalability, and, reliability.
So examples like, Netflix, Amazon,
Spotify, so these applications, so like
in how they can handle vast amounts
of data and user request showcasing
their importance in modern technology.
So that's how it's, the distributed
systems are so important,
in software, architecture.
this diagram briefly shows like
on a very high level, how, the
nodes are connected to a server.
and similarly there is another cluster
which is connected over the network.
so both of them working as
a, single coherent system.
Let's move on to the next slide,
which is about, the key principles of,
designing distributed applications.
all, the major applications which are on,
let's say like in a banking application or
maybe let's say, Gmail, for instance, the
key principles, which is followed while
designing a, distributed, application,
which is, of very high importance, is, Is
scalability, availability and reliability.
Fault tolerance, maintainability security.
So these are, the main, principles
which to consider, when designing,
distribute applications.
I. like scalability ensures that the
system can handle increased load by adding
resources, reliability, ensures that,
the system can recover from failures.
Fault tolerance, a ensures that the
system can continue to over it, even if
there is some components like that fails.
performance, basically is ensures that
the system can respond to, quickly to user
requests that's connected to scalability.
So these are the major principles like, we
have, we need to keep into consideration
while designing, distribute applications,
which, which is of very high importance.
Here in this, slide, we will basically
listed, the main, architectural patterns.
there are many patterns, but these, the
most, commonly used and important ones.
I have listed here, so we be before,
before you go there, we have heard
a lot about, architectural patterns.
So what are architectural patterns?
Architectural patterns, are, are the.
Are designed to provide solution
to common design problems.
this, there, the, in software
design we may have encountered, many
kinds of similar sort of problems.
so the architectural designs, which
provide solution to those common designs
are called, architectural patterns.
for distributed applications, for
building distributor applications
like, the major, architectural patterns
nowadays, which are being followed, in
modern applications, are, microservices,
event driven architecture, c qras, that
is command and query responsibility
segregation, then service miss.
microservices are, is, we'll go
into these ones in detail later on.
but very briefly, microservices,
involve breaking down an application
to very smaller, components,
which can be independently
developed and deployed and scaled.
I. command, query responsibility.
Segregation is a design pattern
which segregates, read and write
operations in a data store.
this approach allows, each model
to be optimized independently.
There are, drawbacks to this model
as well, but, wherever possible,
and if you follow this, in pattern,
like it definitely gives benefits.
A service mess is a dedicated
infrastructure layer that manages
communication between different,
microservices, in a software applications.
So it provides tools and capabilities to
handle tasks like load balancing, security
monitoring, ensuring, efficient and secure
interactions between those services.
So that's, service mesh.
Now, in the next few slides,
we'll go into detail, a little bit
detail of, these architectures.
we'll cover them, as much as we can.
microservices architecture is a method
of, software development where an
application is broken down into smaller,
independent and loosely coupled services.
each service is, designed to fulfill
a specific business function that
can be, developed, and deployed
and maintained independently.
this approach actually contrast with the
traditional, monolithic, architecture
where all functionalities are tightly
integrated into a single, code base.
the key principles around,
microservices, pattern is, independent
development and, deployment.
so each component can be developed
and deployed independently.
So this helps, in faster, development
cycles, small focused teams.
each team can be like, handled,
given a, specific service so
they can walk independently.
Technology diversity, so each
different microservice can be
based on different, technologies.
which is can leverage different
skills of the teams, fault isolation.
if one microservice fails, then
doesn't affect the entire, application.
I. definitely scalability.
Scalability is a huge advantage in
microservices application that each
component or each microservices can
be allowed to scale independently.
so it doesn't, we don't have
to scale the whole application.
So that's a huge benefit.
how does microservices work?
Basically, microservices communicate
with each other, through well-defined
APIs, often using, rest event
streaming message brokers.
So each service has its own
database, ensuring like a data
autonomy and reducing dependencies.
this promotes, flexibility,
ease of development, and very,
like an easy maintenance.
if you summarize the benefits like,
it's, the modularity and decoupling,
scalability, technology, diversity,
rapid deployment, continuous
delivery, however microservices
comes with, challenges as well.
it's very complex to maintain,
like the managing, multiple micro,
very complex, managing multiple
microservices, may require very careful,
orchestration and monitoring as well.
Testing, as a coherent model may
be very difficult, because of
their inter interdependencies.
data consistency across, microservices
can also be challenging because these are
all independent, independent, services.
let.
Network latency as well, because
there's a lot of communications
involved between those services, so
it can lead to, increase in, latency.
So this is very briefly covering,
covered where, we covered,
the microservice architecture.
Let's move on to, the event given
architecture in the next slide.
In this slide, we'll briefly cover,
the event given architecture.
A-K-A-E-D-A, event driven architecture,
software design pattern where, S
where systems, system components
basically communicate by, generating,
detecting, and responding to events.
events, basically represent
significant occurrences such as, user
actions or, change in systems state.
in EDA, the components are
decoupled, allowing them like
to operate independently.
When an event occurs, a message is sent.
Triggering, the appropriate
response, in other components.
So again, in this, architecture also, the
key principles involved are, decoupling.
this is one of the major, advantage
of, ED architectures, like it's
decoupled relationship between front
end and the backend components is
allow system to share information
without knowing about each other.
So producers can send events without
knowing which consumer will receive
them, and consumers can receive
events without sending requests to
producers, as synchronous communication.
it's basically EDA enables, as
in communication where components
operate independently and as
synchronously, in response to events.
This allows for parallel processing,
real time pro responsiveness as well.
event handling, events are typically
handled like using a publish,
subscribe model, popup model.
So components, interest in
certain types of events, subscribe
to them while component that
generate events, publish them.
So this model, allows for
flexible, scalable, communication
between the components.
if we cover, briefly touch upon
what are the main components of
EDA, it's even source, any component
system that are generat events.
such as sensors, databases,
interface, user interfaces.
Event broker, or basically even bus.
we may have heard it a lot, many times.
So it's an intermediary, middleware
that facilitates the communication
of events between, the components.
So it handles the distribution,
filtering, and routing of events.
a publisher like an A component that
generates, sense event to the event bus.
Subscriber, the component that, like
an expresses interest in those specific
type of events and subscribe to them.
So subscribers like can always
listen for events, on the event
bus and respond, accordingly.
event handler, is a, is a piece of
code or logic like an associated
with a subscriber that specifies
like how to respond when a particular
type of event is, is, is received.
So benefits of, ED architecture, again,
like other, it's flexibility and agility.
it, it allows to adapt easily to
changing requirements, scalability.
it supports scalability by
allowing components to come
to, to operate independently.
systems can handle increased
load or drain data sets by adding
more components to the resources.
Real time responsiveness.
so EDA, one of the major strengths of EDA
is like in real time processing, ensuring
that events are handled as they occur.
So this is, that's why like an EDA is
used in a lot, many financial, like
in applications and IOT applications.
Enhance, modularity as well.
like any other, click the pattern,
BDS has got drawbacks as well.
definitely it's a very complex, system.
then, consistency, like the mentoring, the
order of events and ensuring consistency
across the system can be very complex.
Debugging and tracing as
well, is, is very, Challenging
compared to other architectures.
use cases of EDA is like a financial
services, I said like real time processing
of transactions, fraud detection,
e-commerce, like order placements,
inventory updates, internet of things.
is a very, like a good use
case for, the ED architecture.
telecommunications, like network
monitoring, event driven r communication
with network and components.
Healthcare also, monitoring
patient data, handling medical
alerts and those kind of things.
this is very briefly it's a past topic,
but we've covered it very briefly.
what are, the major components,
their benefits and the challenges.
We'll move to the next, architecture,
which is A-C-Q-R-S pattern.
in the next slide.
in the slide, we'll briefly, cover,
the CQRS pattern, architecture pattern.
So command and query responsibility,
segregation, c qrs, separate read and
write operations like, optimizing,
optimizing like you both, ments for both.
read and write, operations.
So in a traditional architecture,
where we have single data
model is often associated,
both read and write operations.
So this approach, is very straightforward
and suited for basic, crude applications,
operations, but, in modern kind of
applications like, it, poses like a lot
of challenges, mainly around performance.
some of the issues like, with that
approach was like, data mismatch.
the read write, the read and write
representations of data often differ.
Sometimes, the fields that are required
during updates might not be, might be
unnecessary, during read operations.
lock contention, performance problems,
can have a negative, know the traditional
approach can have a negative effect
on the performance because both 'cause
a load on the data store and the data
access layer and the complex request.
You got to re tribe, a lot of information.
which, which is which impacts, the read
and write as well, like at the same time.
security challenges as well.
It can be difficult to manage
security when entities are
subject to read and right.
Operations.
So this overlap can expose data
in like an unintended context.
There are instance where it happened,
so the solution, is, to these problems
is A-C-Q-R-S pattern, where, we use
the CQRS to separate the read and
write operations or basically commands
from the read operations or queries.
So that's what, like it
says, command and queries.
So command commands, update
data queries, retried data.
the is useful in scenarios where
that require a clear separation
between commands and so it's
not applicable in all scenarios.
But wherever there is an
opportunity, we should use it.
so separating the read and read model and
the right model simplifies, the system
design, of course, like an if the system
design allows it to, that use case,
if it is applicable to that use case.
So it, it simplifies system design and
implementation by addressing, specific
concerns for data rights and data reads.
it increases clarity,
scalability, performance,
because those are, now separated.
so if you summarize the benefits of
cqs, it'll be like dependent scaling.
So we can independently scale like, the
command and the query part, separately.
the schemas are now optimized.
They're either right,
optimized or read optimized.
So definitely there's a lot of increase
like in performance security, and also,
by separating data and rights, you
can ensure that only the appropriate
domain entities or preparations have
permission to perform, right application,
right actions on the data or maybe like
on the read, separation of concerns.
then, basically it.
the writing of the queries
can become a lot simpler.
then simpler queries, when you square
much less view on the read database,
the application can avoid, like
in writing complex, very complex.
who has, anybody who has written,
a complicated query can understand,
like the joints can extend and
the query can be quite big.
So if, the, The design
allows us to use this one.
We should definitely use this one.
in, in the next, slide, we
will go over briefly, to the
service, mesh architecture.
So in this slide, we'll briefly touch
upon, the Service MES architecture.
So service, is a. Dedicated infrastructure
layer, that, that manages, manages all
the communication between the market
services, in a software application.
So it provide tools, and capabilities
to handle, the task like load
balancing, security monitoring,
ensuring the efficient and, secure in
interaction between those services.
The, it has two main components.
One is the data plane, the
other is control, plane.
so data plane is basically it's
a, it considers sidecar proxies
that handle the actual transfer
of data between the services.
they also implement like features like
load balancing, service discovery,
traffic routing, and control plane,
acts, as a central management layer.
it, it allows the administrative define
and configure services, within the mess.
specific parameters like, the service
endpoint, routing rules, load balancing
policies, and security settings.
it has got this architecture has got
benefits, namely service discovery, load
balancing, traffic management, security,
and monitoring and observability.
it has got challenges as well.
Like it's very, it one
of the main challenges.
Like it's very complex.
It involves a lot of communication
between the microservices, so there
is a performance over it as well.
There is operational overhead,
like there's a lot of operational
effort that goes into maintaining,
deploying, configuring, these,
this architecture and also that
like the lining curve is very high.
designing a distributed application, comes
with several kind of challenges, which
we have to, which we have to address.
so namely the network
latency data inconsistency.
Service discovery complexity,
then distribute transactions.
and eventual con
consistency, the security.
so all these are, common challenges,
when we have to address, while, while
designing a distributed application.
In this slide, we'll we
listed, the various, ways we
are very much aware of those.
the tools or methodologies like, for,
for designing or increasing scalability,
like horizonal scaling, which is like
an adding more nodes or, computers.
vertical scaling is like an adding more
resources within a particular computer.
So that's called vertical
stateless and stateful.
So we should always go
for, stateless designs.
load balancing, So there, there are
tools like, which are, available, but,
which follow these kind of like round
robin, list connections go geo based.
So these are the, tools.
there are tools available, which
help us to do, achieve all these,
strategies, implement all these
strategies for, scalability.
so we have to like you use them.
In this slide, like when I have
listed out, the best practices,
which are normally followed where,
while designing like distributed
applications, Designing for failure.
Like it's a first and foremost,
fundamental, principle or practice.
we should apply, we should design
the application for failure.
that means we, we assume like that
the application can fail in multiple,
several ways and we just, designed
for, to avoid that, using stateless
comp, stateless component, components.
CICD using.
then, the observability and monitoring
tools, this is, this has become
a very important topic nowadays.
then practicing fault tolerance,
security, load balancing.
Event driven communications,
so domain event design, then,
adopting chaos engineering.
So these other things like,
which we should consider
definitely into consideration.
when we design, distributed
applications, I.
With this, slide we have come to
near the end of the presentation.
so here I've tried to summarize
like, the key takeaways.
so it all depends.
though, when we.
Talk about architectural
patterns, like it all depends on
the right architecture choice.
So we have to choose a pattern
based on, based on the fitment and
suitability, for a particular use case.
and obviously continuous refinement,
this is a very important one, even if
there's an architecture like which is
implemented now, there can be like,
enhancements or, opportunities to, to
use, other patterns as well as you go
along, and as the application matures.
So we have to always be open to that.
so also challenges, like there'll be
challenges and we have to proactively
deal with them and we have to, as an
architect, and we have to anticipate the
challenges, for the next three to four
years timeline, and then plan accordingly.
One thing, which is, lemme just come
up very strongly, with the very,
these microservices event driven.
and the cloud deployment.
investing in strong monitoring
and observability tools,
this is very critical.
I. with this, we have come to the end
of the presentation, so I, I've opened
the floor for questions and answers.
there's an opportunity to clarify
any points we discussed today.
your insights and inquiries are
extremely valuable for me, so please
feel free to share your thoughts.
you can also drop me, email, or reach
me individual like later on as well.
thank you so much for your attention.
please feel free to ask any questions
you may have, but I really appreciate
your time and, and your patience today.
Thank you so much.
Have a great day.