Speaker 5: Hello everyone.
I am Ajay a Ramathan.
I work as a data and AI
engineer at Foursquare.
A portion of my work involves
integrating large language models
with enterprise systems, designing
workflows that allow AI to interact
with real production data and processes.
One thing I have learned quickly
is that while autonomous AI agents
are incredibly powerful, they can
also introduce real operational
risk, if not designed carefully.
That's why a big part of my focus has
been on building guard rails around
agent automation, making sure these
systems can act intelligently while
still remaining safe, reliable, and
controllable in production environments.
Today I'll be talking about
how organizations can operate.
Autonomous agents safely, especially
in high risk systems and engineering
patterns that make this possible.
Before we dive in, here is a quick
map of where we are headed today.
I want to keep it simple, so just
five sections each building on the
last, first, what is happening?
This, the landscape, the rise
of agent tech automation.
We start with the what A agents
are no longer a future concept.
As we all know, they are already
running in production systems,
making decisions, taking actions,
and operating with real autonomy.
We will set the scene, make
sure we are all on the same page
about what's actually changed.
Second, why it's risky
autonomy in high risk systems.
Once you understand what's happening,
the natural nest question is,
okay, but what could go wrong?
We will look at why handing autonomy
to an AI in high stakes environment
isn't just about technical challenge,
it's a safety and compliance one.
Two, why old approaches break?
The limit of traditional automation.
Here is where it gets a
little bit interesting.
A lot of teams try to apply the
same patterns they use for RP or
rule-based system and it doesn't work.
We we will break down exactly why
and what's fundamentally different
about a agents fourth, how we think
about solving it, principles of.
Guard rail autonomy.
This is the mindset shift.
Before we get into tools and code, we
need a framework for thinking about
safety that doesn't kill the very
autonomy we are trying to enable.
Here.
We will walk through the core principles,
and the last one, what we actually build.
Core guardrails for safe agent systems.
And finally, the practical stuff.
Real building block tools, patents
that you can take back and use.
This is where we get hands on a little
bit over the past few years, right?
AI has involved from tools that simply
assist humans to systems that can take
actions autonomously with introduction
of function calling, which is now tool
calls Modern agent frameworks allow these.
AI agents, right?
Frameworks as in like land
graph, Microsoft Agent
Framework, all those things.
They enable these Agent K systems
to plan tasks, call APAs, analyze
data, and it secure workflows
with minimal human intervention.
This shift unlocks enormous productivity
gain and across industries, right?
Finance, operations, it, customer
support, you name it, it's already there.
However, with the greater
autonomy comes greater risk.
When a agents interact directly
with production infra sensitive
data or critical business
processes, even mistakes can quickly
escalate into operational issues.
Traditional automation approaches
were designed for deterministic
workflows, not probabilistic LLMs.
So this creates a fundamental challenge.
How do we safely operate autonomous
agents in high risk environment?
In this section, why it's
risky especially in high risk
production, sy production systems.
We will talk about.
When a systems gain the ability
right, to take actions rather than
generating responses, the level
of risk increases significantly.
A model making a wrong
suggestion is usually harmless.
If.
Taken correctly, but a model executing
an action automatically can affect
systems, data, or users right directly.
This becomes particularly important
in environments like financial
operations, healthcare systems,
infrastructure management, enterprise
automation, customer data platforms.
So these are systems where reliability,
security, and complaints are
critical, so we can't take a chance.
There are several types of risks
that can emerge when autonomous
agents operate in these environments.
For example, agents might hallucinate
actions or incorrect outputs, which
can lead to incorrect distance.
They can also be vulnerable to prompt
injection attacks where malicious input.
Manipulate the agent's behavior.
Another concern is unauthorized
access to sensitive data, especially
if the agent interacts with multiple
systems in complex workflows.
One, incorrect action can also trigger
cascading auto automation failures
affecting downstream processes.
And in regulated industries, mistakes
can lead to compliance violations.
At the core of this issue is a
fundamental engineering mismatch, is
what I feel a models operate using
probabilistic reasoning, meaning their
outputs are based on probabilities
rather than deterministic logic.
But production systems require
deterministic reliability.
It needs to be predictable,
auditable, and consistent in behavior.
So the real challenge is not just
building intelligent agents, but
designing control systems around them.
To safely operate autonomous AI
in production, we need guardrails
and governance layers that
ensure reliability even when the
underlying models are probabilistic.
This is exactly the problem
space we are trying to address.
Now that we have discussed the
risks of autonomy, the next
question is why don't our existing
automation solve this problem?
Traditional automation systems
were built with a very specific.
Assumption about how software behaves.
They assume that system operate
using a deterministic logic where
every input produces a predictable
output or even pre-programmed output.
Most automation frameworks are
designed around predictable
workflows, predefined decision trees.
In other words, every step in the
process is known ahead of time.
This is why.
They work well for tasks like
ETL pipelines bad jobs or
rule-based workflow engines.
These system follow clearly
defined path and they behave
consistently every time they run.
But the agent tick
systems on the other hand.
Behave very differently.
Instead of following fits workflows,
the agent perform dynamic planning.
They decide what to do next
based on contest core available
tools on the current input.
Traditional systems rely
on deterministic logic.
On the other hand, with probabilistic
reasoning we have different actions rather
than, using a predefined script, right?
Another difference is
how actions are selected.
Traditional automation uses
predefined actions while
agents perform tool discovery.
They can choose multiple available
tools to complete a. Particular task.
And finally, traditional systems
rely on static scripts, whereas agent
systems are dynamic and adaptive.
They can adjust their behavior based on
new information or intermediate results.
The key takeaway here is that our.
Existing automation infrastructure
was not designed for software that
reasons about what to do next.
It was built for predictable workflows,
not intelligent decision making systems.
That's why simply plugging AI into
traditional automation architectures
often lead to reliability problems.
To safely operate agent systems, we
need a different design approach.
One that accounts for their
dynamic and probabilistic nature.
So if traditional automation doesn't
work well for agent tech systems,
the next question becomes, how should
we think about solving this problem?
The key idea here is that
solution is not removing autonomy.
Autonomous reasoning is exactly what
makes this systems powerful enough.
Instead, the goal should be.
To bound that autonomy with safety
mechanism, the design philosophy can
be summarized in simple principle,
which is maximum reasoning freedom,
but with strict execution boundaries.
What this means is that agents should be
allowed to think, plan, and reason free.
That's where the intelligence
of the system comes from.
But when it comes to taking
actions, those action must pass
through safety and governance
control before they are executed.
In other words, an AA agent can
generate many possible actions, but
it should never interact directly with
the production system, without the
validation and approval layers in between.
This is where guardrails come into play.
Guardrails act as a control layer that
converts freeform EEA outputs into
a controlled, verifiable operation.
They validate outputs, enforce
policies and check permissions
to ensure that actions are safer
before anything is executed.
The architecture shown here.
Represents a typical
enterprise agent system.
At the top, you have a user or
workflow triggering the process.
That request flows into agent
framework where the model
performs reasoning and planning.
Before any action is executed,
it passes through guardrails and
policy engines, which enforce.
Safety rules and governance.
The agent then interacts with enterprise
systems only through secure tool APIs
rather than accessing infra directly.
And finally, everything is tracked through
monitoring and observ the platforms
which provide transparency and allow.
Teams to detect issues quickly.
So the core idea here is
simple, but powerful agents are
allowed to reason freely, but
actions are tightly controlled.
This architectural mindset is what
allows organization to safely deploy
autonomous AI and production environments.
So we have talked about
what agent systems can do.
Now let's talk about how we
make sure they don't go rogue.
First is programmable safety.
This is about encoding rules
directly into the system's behavior.
One problem is prompt injection
protection means we are defending
against malicious input that try
to hijack the agent's behavior.
Think of it like SQL injection,
but for AI tools like.
Prompt templates by Lang chain TT
Strings, ragas Guardrails Hub Nvidia
Nemo guardrails are built specifically
for this structured output, ensures.
The agent always responds in a
predictable machine readable format.
Like Jason, they force models to
return valid typed output every time.
PTECH is our best friend for validation
on the receiving end, programmable
validations, or custom rules that
checks output against a business.
Logic, like some of line items in
an invoice is equal to the subtotal.
Added with tax and charges gives
you the grand total, right?
You define these rules, it enforces them.
And finally, LLM as a judge is where
we use a second AI model to evaluate
the first one, frameworks like Lang
Smith Foundry service from Microsoft.
They make this structured and
measurable, not just web-based.
The second module is identity
and role-based access control.
Agent need identities just
like employees do, and we start
with least privilege, right?
An agent only gets access
to what it absolutely needs.
Open policy agent is great.
This is defining the fine-grained access
control across services you don't need.
Access to a DB if the agent is required
to only fetch data for example.
And second is managed identities.
Give agent a verifiable, trackable
identity on cloud like Azure managed
identity that can handle this natively.
Session based tokens, meaning it.
It is tied to a specific session JWT or
2.0 flows work well here and time bound.
Access takes this further, elevates
it to a session perion with an expiry.
So key walls or other short-lived
scoped credentials are time-bound.
Third is privacy and safety.
Privacy is where things get.
Things get like underrated.
So what happens is when handling
PIA we can use Microsoft Procedure,
which is a great open source tool.
Detects cla PIA across test with
customizable Recognizes two.
We have AWS Comprehend which
is a managed alternative for
Ion Presidio handles that too.
Automatically removing
sensitive fields before data
is logged or passed downstream.
Masking faker is a great tool
replacing real values with
the realistic looking ones.
Presto also supports it bit with
anonymization pipelines out of the bots
local LLMs for maximum data sovereignty.
Tools like O Armor le let you run
capable models entirely on-prem.
If we have the current hardware
nothing touches the cloud.
Synthetic data tools like mostly
ai for generating statistically
realistic data with zero privacy risk.
And.
Some open source alternatives, like
synthetic data, what can handle this too?
The fourth pillar is human in the loop.
And honestly, this is the
most underrated pillar.
Require approvals, tools like Graph
has native support for interrupt and
resume workflows, passing execution
until a human gives the green light.
Temporal is excellent tool
for longer running approval.
Flows that need durability, allow list.
OP.
A Open policy agent again shines here.
Define exactly what actions are
permitted in a policy files and
enforce them at a middle bear layer.
In terms of irreversible actions,
frameworks like temporal land graft models
have explicit checkpoints that require
human confirmation before even proceeding.
Action level logs.
Lang Smith gives per step trace
for long chain based agents.
S and biases is a great
for custom pipeline.
Traces last observably and evolves if
you can't observe it, you can't trust it.
Log calls using Azure Monitor, Lang
Smith, or Datadog all offers comprehensive
logging of every prompt response
latency, token count, even cost.
In some tools, open
telemetry is the standard.
If you want a vendor neutral
instrumentation, active safety
scoring, LLM Guard run real time.
Content checks on input and
output as they flow through system
catching issues before they land.
Passive evals, DP valve RGAs, or excellent
for running systematic offline eval evals
against historic historical interactions.
So these are great for
catching drift over time.
Unified audit trails.
Datadog Grafana Elastic can pull logs,
metrics and traces into a single timeline.
Aggregated pair it with open
telemetry for standardized
instrumentation across the whole stack.
And that's a wrap.
Thank you for the time and attention.
I know we have covered a lot.
From why agent systems matter all the way
down to the actual tools and libraries
you can pick up and use tomorrow.
The big takeaways are safety
and autonomy aren't opposites.
With the right guardrails, programmable
safety, strong identity, privacy
controls, and human oversight.
With solid observ, you can build
AI agents that are genuinely
powerful and trustworthy.
Thank you.