Hey everyone.
Welcome to Com 42 site Reliability
Engineering conference.
My name is Peter Deten and I'm gonna
walk you through Azure Load Testing.
Now, before diving into the actual
topic, let me share a bit about myself.
So Peter Deten, originally from Belgium,
but moved to the Redmond area about
three years ago, where I'm working as a
Microsoft technical trainer at Microsoft.
I think it's still one of the easiest
job titles within Microsoft, because
what I'm doing is providing technical
training on our Microsoft Azure platform,
primarily to our top customers across
the globe using virtual online workshops.
My career started about 30 years ago
as a physical technical engineer,
literally building physical data
centers, the cabling, the cooling.
And then gradually, as part of my career
moved up the solution stack, you could
say, all the way from that physical data
center, networking, storage servers,
and then gradually moving up to cloud,
where around 2013, picked up Azure for
the full a hundred percent, and then
moved a bit from cloud engineering to
cloud, architecting a lot of DevOps
automation and gradually developing
N AI over the last three years.
You got all my contact details here,
and feel free, I would say to reach
out if you should have any questions
while watching the session, or
obviously if you're watching this
later on as a recording, then more than
happy to provide you with an answer.
Now, the starting point is what is
SRE right now, knowing that the core
topic of the conference today is all
about site reliability, engineering.
Now, where does my Azure load testing fit?
So to me, SRE, if you think about
what you're doing, and again, don't
feel personally attacked about this,
it might be totally different in your
case, but to me, site reliability
engineering means you gonna spend a
huge amount of time on stress testing.
Why stress testing?
Because your goal as an SRE is making
sure that your environment, your workload.
Within Azure, outside of Azure, AWS,
Google Cloud on-prem, not important.
Where the workload is running,
your goal is making it as high
available, redundant as possible.
The way to do that is typically hammering
your environment using low testing.
So to be the perfect example to
talk about low testing in Azure
as part of the SRE conference.
So what is low testing?
First of all?
This is a sort of, I think formal
definition that I found online.
Load testing is a type of performance
testing that determines the
performance of a system, a software,
an application, or a full workload if
you want under, and that's important.
Real life, real workload based
load conditions, which typically
would be the number of users.
Number of sessions, maybe
the amount of traffic.
If you have a lot of streaming data,
like a Netflix maybe, or something
similar streaming media, where all of
a sudden the traffic could become more
important than actual number of users.
From here, we move into
Azure load testing.
So obviously the assumption here is
that you're gonna run your workload.
On top of the Azure platform, where
now we have a service in the platform,
managed service called Azure Load Testing.
Yes, every now and then Azure
service names actually do make sense.
Azure load testing is a managed service
that can be used to, again, simulate load.
Preferably, I would say you're gonna run
this against your production environment
or even more so you're gonna run this in
your test acceptance staging environment.
Because you don't want to impact your
production all the way from there,
you're gonna target application user
interface, like an app service, a
web application or a virtual machine.
And why not API Endpoints?
As long as you can target you,
your backend using A-C-T-P-S,
you're actually good to go.
Now there's one part two testing,
like going in the portal.
No surprise.
I'm gonna walk you through some
live demos there where we have
an application up and running.
You're gonna integrate Azure load testing,
you're gonna use the Azure portal for now.
You're gonna click around and
then you're gonna build your test.
But that's like a one-time shot
or a manual shot out of SRE.
I guess we can all agree that a big part
of your job is also automating your tasks.
So that's where the second bullet
point becomes quite important.
You're gonna build your tests
initially manual and then gradually
automating the whole process.
And the good news is you can
run trigger Azure load testing
as part of your CICD pipelines.
A lot of flexibility where you're gonna
define test criteria, and I'll show
you again in a demo how that works.
And then also crucial to mention here
is that initially, two years ago,
low testing in Azure was based on the
Apache Open Source J Meter framework.
In meantime, it also supports Locust
where you're gonna hear about some
differences between the both scenarios.
But the cool thing is you
manage the Azure environment.
You're gonna bring in one of the two
options to really configure your testing.
Next to that, what do we need as
part of our load testing definitions?
I call this here, the
load testing components.
You need a load testing resource,
literally a top level resource
providing you centralized
place to view your testing.
What it means is go to Azure load testing
as the service, and that's becoming your
dashboard for all testing scenarios.
Next to that, obviously you need
a test, you need a test run.
A test means it's a technical definition.
The run means we actually gonna.
Execute the test.
The test engine is the compute
infrastructure in the backend.
This could be your target instance.
And then last, you need
an application component.
Again, any possible HCTP, htt,
PS reachable backend from within
Azure would be a possible scenario.
Next, we have load testing test itself.
So again, URL based is one option.
The easiest one I'll show you.
As the starting point of my demo,
give me your RL and I'm gonna simulate
testing, obviously not anything that's
running outside of your control.
Second option to maybe make it a little
bit more standardized or maybe even a
bit more advanced if you want, is using
that Apache J meter testing script.
You're gonna build your testing typically
offline, not really using the Azure.
Portal anymore, or why not?
Maybe you have a mixed environment across
different clouds, but also on-prem.
But now you're gonna rely
on that JMeter framework.
Now, the JMeter framework has
some specific characteristics
to it, like the GMX files.
You need like A XML YAML
alike scenario where you.
You gonna provide all the elements
like the controllers, the timing
the assumptions as assertations
and listeners that you wanna
use as part of your testing.
Now the second option, or the third
actually, is using Locust as a, I would
say, popular testing framework as well.
The big difference between J Meter
and Locus is obviously it's not an
Apache framework, but next to that
it also relies on Python and coating.
Instead of the GMX files.
So same concept, slightly
different framework.
That's the summarization of it.
And then what I also mentioned during
the introduction is now we have our
tests and we're gonna automate it.
Where the good news is that at least out
of the Microsoft DevOps solutions, which
means Azure DevOps, or GitHub actions,
you can integrate your Azure load testing.
Scenarios as part of an already
pre-built marketplace component.
You build your pipelines in the exact
same way as you already have CI or cd.
Why not combining?
And in Azure DevOps, you're gonna
bring in a pre-built marketplace
component called Azure Load Test if
you're no longer using Azure DevOps.
But it's all happening on the GitHub side.
That's where you're gonna
bring in GitHub actions.
And again, no surprise, you have.
A GitHub actions marketplace component
called Azure Forward slash Load Testing,
and for now it's still version one.
And then you go okay, Peter
we're not using Azure DevOps,
we're not using GitHub actions.
What are the options?
Good news is since Azure load
testing is just another service.
In the Azure platform, it means you
can target it, you can trigger it
using traditional rest API comps.
I might not have enough time in this
session to show you all three options.
But at least I'm gonna shift to
the next part, and that's really
showing you how all this works.
I'm gonna start with
deploying load testing.
I'm gonna show you one of my sample
backends at just a web app, and
then from there, triggering a manual
test or configuring and triggering a
manual test showing you the J meter
option as well as the locust framework
to give you some touching points.
And then again, if time allows, I'm gonna
show you how you could integrate it.
As part of your DevOps
solutions, see you back in a bit.
So here I'm in my Azure portal where
I'm gonna use the Azure load testing.
Now again, I call this a managed
service, which means you don't
have to install anything.
It's already available within
your Azure environment.
You could obviously create a
new load testing from here.
But to speed up the demo a little bit, I'm
going to use the one that I already have.
If you're a bit into Azure, which
I assume you are, it just like any
other Azure resource, you define
the location, you provide a name,
a resource group, and off you go.
So that's mainly what I did here.
Once we have our load testing service
configured, that's where we're
gonna use some of its capabilities.
You can start with a couple
of different scenarios.
The first one I'll use is over here
where I'm gonna add HCTP requests.
So I'm gonna select, create a
new test, and this is now what
we call the URL based test.
I can provide a name, I'm just
gonna accept the defaults, or
let's call this one the live URL
Test A description live URL Test.
How hard can it be?
Run the test right after creation
and if you want, you can see here
debuting mode, which gonna give you.
Access to debug logging.
If a test is running but it's failing,
it's not doing what it needs to do,
then I would say please enable this.
Enable advanced settings is just gonna
give you access to more options down here.
Let's move on to the next step.
I'm gonna add a new request, and again,
later on, if this is no longer the
first test you're creating or you know
how the Apache framework is working,
then you could also start from it.
Input data input data file.
I'm gonna create a new request.
I'm gonna accept all the defaults because
it's not all that important for now.
And I'm gonna use input in a ui.
What this means is my request name.
So this would be let's say
homepage, HTTP get, and my URL is.
My website, I'm gonna use my production
blog website, oh seven fff learning.com,
and what is the A CTP method.
Now, from here, I'm gonna take a
minute to highlight a few things.
Right here I'm connecting to the homepage.
Now if, let's say your homepage
is your product retail catalog, or
my, in my case, my blog website.
It might all be fine, but what
if I wanna go to a lower level?
Then from here you could
actually add the subset.
Like in my case, I have a section
on my blog that talks about the
books that I wrote in the past.
And I wanna run a test against my
book subsection and not the homepage.
From here, I could move on
like the default would be a get
comment, but as you can see, we're
respecting all rest API codes.
Imagine you have, again, like a
product retail, you wanna test
the performance impact when you're
uploading products, when you're
ordering products, when you trigger a
payment, when you're making changes.
To decide and so on.
That's what you can define here, but
I'm not gonna make it that complex in
my demo scenario, so I'm gonna trigger,
again, you can fine tune query parameters,
like injecting specific variables.
You can tune the headers and maybe
even looking into response variables.
Again, just showing you the options.
What are all the capabilities, and we
can make this super straightforward.
Super easy or rather complex.
Nothing blocks you from
combining multiple tests.
So I could do second URL request, where
now I could go back to the same endpoint
or why not going to a different endpoint.
So this could be my sample, Azure
web app, azure websites.net.
'cause what if my website homepage
has dependencies on websites and
again, using some other URL rest
API call here and then building up
a flow of tests on the request site.
It's gonna run the first
request, the second or third,
how many you want to add into it.
That's up to you.
Clicking next onto the next cycle
where we can define different
parameters, environment variables,
hopefully pretty obvious based on a
variable, this could be dev and test
staging production using secrets.
Imagine that you wanna connect, like
again, the retail example I mentioned.
Maybe you wanna connect to a database,
you wanna interact with Key Vault, you
want to interact with connection strings.
You can define it here, and
obviously the same for certificates.
If you interact with Key
Vault, our Azure Secret Store.
The idea is obviously that your testing
framework, your running test now also
needs permissions to interact with
key vault, and that's what down here.
We're preferably following
Microsoft best practice.
We're expecting you to
define managed identity.
Define role-based access
for this specific test.
Getting the necessary permissions to
hook can to key vault at the same time.
It's not only locking down permissions,
but it's also defining them in a granular,
zero trust approach, you could say.
Moving on to the next, that's where we're
gonna define the actual load simulation.
Number of instances, like how many
simulations, but also how much
compute, and that's where the scaling
details here would be beneficial.
Each and every engine allows you
to run up to 250 user sessions.
So if you have I wanna simulate thousand
users, it means you need four instances.
I'm quite limited, although technically
I could move this up, but my
subscription doesn't allow me to do this.
Physically or technically.
So I'm gonna stay with two.
I'm gonna move up my numbers to 350.
When now it tells my go, wait
a minute, it can only be two
50, so that's a bit confusing.
Two 50 here means two instances.
I'm still gonna simulate 500 users.
So just trying to clarify
the portal a little bit.
I want linear growth.
I want a step by step growth, and you
can see that the parameters are changing.
And you could also simulate Spike
where we start with 250 concurrent
users and then gradually spiking like
a simulating, literally a CPU spike.
Or a user spike, like we got more users
coming in because we offer like some
online food ordering platform, and it's
between six and seven we see a spike For
breakfast, it's between 1130 and one, we
see a spike for lunch ordering coming in.
That's the scenario you
could simulate here.
I'm gonna keep the default of linear
and that should be good enough.
Do you want to integrate monitoring?
What this means here is that we
provide you monitoring dashboard,
but now you could actually hook
into other Azure scenarios.
You could use application insights,
storing data in there, you could
configure some other options
and you can see it from here.
Moving on, where now we can define
even more specific test criteria.
You can define the conditions, like if.
For this specific metric, like
response time, there's an aggregation.
If the condition is
true, do this, do that.
So again, showing you more options,
more granular configuration parameters.
The baseline technically
would be the same thing.
All that summarized in the last
overview, and we're gonna create our
test now, although I started from the
A-C-T-P-U-R-L based, you can see that now.
By design, it's using a JMeter script.
What it's technically doing
here is transforming all my
settings from the portal into
that JMeter framework language.
It's gonna take a couple of seconds
to actually create a test, and
once it's done, we're gonna move
over and we have our testing ready.
So to speed up my demo again a little
bit, I already have one from two days ago.
As you can see here.
I got my test, I got
all my scheduling done.
I'm not scheduling anything, but that
could be another SRE trick here to
build a test, run a test, but then also
scheduling the test, run this every
hour, run this overnight and whatnot.
And then last here, we are
gonna run our test itself.
When we run the test, this is
already done because it's gonna
typically take five minutes, 20
minutes, depending on the timeline
of the testing you wanna go through.
This was a pretty short one, only two
minutes because I don't want to wait
for it to just show you some results.
And what it gives me here is
that linear growth, so this one
was a bit smaller, move up to 50
users, start small, gradually.
Move up and then hammer my platform.
I used HTTP get, and then it's gonna
show me the outcomes of it response time.
In this case, the number of requests,
and then obviously the go-to scenario
would be to add an additional level
of tests, changing the parameters.
Maybe running the test
again with a different app,
service backend and whatnot.
And then it also shows me
some service side metrics, but
this has not been configured.
What I would need to do here
is what I showed you before,
enabling application insights.
Application insights is where you're
gonna hook into Azure Log Analytics,
allowing you to store all the metric
data, not only visible in the portal,
but actually storing the actual telemetry
information and allowing you to again,
do data mining data viewing out of that.
And that's where the server side
metric comes in because it's relying
on some other framework there.
Next to that, I can download my
input file, the logs, the results.
I'm gonna show you the input file.
Why?
Because this is what I need to
show you that JMeter framework.
It's not the best tool, but
I'm gonna use it for now.
Just opening an easy notepad
document and then I could normally.
Not drag and drop.
Obviously not because it's
what am I doing, notepad?
No, Peter, you don't need notepad.
You need Visual Studio Code to do this,
and then I guess I can drop it.
It is in my downloads.
It looks a bit weird, but eventually
it shows up as we expect it.
So this is the J meter config file.
So it has the display name.
What kind of test plan?
And as you can see here, there's
a pointer to the actual JSO file.
It's what you see here looks a little
bit awkward because for some reason
it's not respecting the JSO layout, but
you can see that it has that syntax.
And then the last one
is the actual GMX file.
Oh, there we go.
We could do actually
notepad, but that's fine.
And this is that XML structure
that I talked about before.
So it's gonna show you
like all the details.
Let's see if I can find some of the
settings from my configuration here.
So it's a CTP, that's what we picked.
We had a CTP get.
That's fine.
And this is where I would say go into
the documentation of the Apache J Meter.
The nice thing again is that now since we
exported this, I could technically close
this because I don't need it anymore.
I could now go in and
actually upload a new test.
So if I take one step back, create new
test, upload a script, it's gonna ask me
like, okay, where do you have your files?
It's JMeter.
It's in my local file system.
It's in my repos.
It's anywhere you wanna store it.
And then you don't have to go
through the portal anymore.
So URL Test JMeter, it's
technically almost the same thing.
I would say use that JMeter scenario for
the more advanced configuration options.
The other example we have is Locust.
So again, what is Locust?
It's what down here.
I got another little demo that I built.
Everything that I talked to you
through is exactly the same thing.
I'm selecting a test, I'm running a test.
The main difference here, it's
using a different framework.
The nice thing again, is that
within our Azure load testing,
it's using the same Azure approach
to give you that capability.
Same testing, same ease of use, same
advanced configuration, more granular
options, just using a different framework.
You might have used JMeter in
another cloud, in an on-prem world,
you might standardize on locust.
That's the philosophy behind it.
What is the main difference?
I would say it's the configuration.
This is my Locust Python script that I
used for this test, and as you can see
here, it's using Python scripting language
to define the details of your scripting.
It's connecting.
Two, my workload, it's a get workload.
It's pulling up a to-do item, and
then it's reading out a response to
validate if the response was 200,
retrieve the response, and so on.
Using Python, traditional
ping scripting language.
Running the test, seeing the output of
the test is the exact same experience,
so loading 500, about 500 users.
Four or five minutes and
then reading out the results.
And again, the dashboarding views
are technically the same thing.
Next I talked about using DevOps mindset.
So the example I have here
is connecting to DevOps.
I could show you GitHub
actions as well, but I'm still.
A lot more into Azure DevOps, I guess
out of my background, been playing
with DevOps for I dunno, 10, 15 years.
So Team Foundation
server was my playground.
I got my to-do items, the one
that I published in my pipeline.
And then in here,
what's relevant, apart from the
fact that it didn't run successful,
but it's because I didn't
configure the correct permissions.
This is one single stage.
So this would be part of your
CI build pipeline, right?
Where you're gonna ci ICD pipeline,
sorry, where you're gonna define
the service connection into Azure.
What is the name of the load test?
What is the resource group?
And then from there you're gonna use
this pre-built Azure load test concept.
It needs a load testing config
file, so the YAML file from JMeter
as I showed you the resource group.
And then from there, not
really needing anything else.
Super straightforward.
How can you install this extension?
You go into the Visual Studio marketplace.
I think it's marketplace
dot visual studio.com.
There we go.
And you're gonna search
for Azure load testing.
It's gonna ask you like, where
do you want to install this?
As part of what Azure DevOps organization.
You download it, you install it, and
that's where it becomes available.
If you go okay, that's all
cool, but can you show me how
to do this in GitHub actions?
Although I don't have it up and running
configured, you would go into repo,
you would go into actions, and then
here you would search for load testing.
I think it's one word maybe
to load what happened here.
Load.
Oh, it's not the full action.
Obviously, it's a component
within, it should be here,
Azure load testing,
and then picking the right
version or the latest version.
That's up to you.
And then as you can see from my slides,
Azure load testing and then asking
again for the same configuration data,
the JM Max file, the YAML file, the
config file in JSON format, which
most probably is already part of your
repo anyway, and then running your
pipeline just like any other component.
The last scenario we have.
I have it somewhere on the site is
running it using traditional rest API
calls, and I'm just gonna grab the
little sample code that I have for that.
Just give me a second here.
That's what happens when
you do all this live, right?
It would look a little bit like this.
So first you're gonna authenticate
into Azure Next, it's gonna
create that authentication token.
And from there, traditional rest, API curl
post get anything you wanna do with it.
HT TP, oh, sorry.
This is obviously the post
because you're triggering.
The load testing itself point to your load
testing endpoint using the token and then
defining the header and the actual details
where again, it's pointing to your script.
GMX file.
In this case, it's a JMeter example.
And then running the actual
test is again running curl post.
And then you're gonna run
the actual test cycle here.
Three different scenarios, three
different options, pretty much anything.
I wanted to talk about in
this 30 minute session.
Looking at the clock, I can see that
I'm almost running out of time, so I'm
gonna switch back to the presentation and
closing with the last couple of words.
Awesome.
So that worked pretty fine.
Now we're close to the end of my session,
but allow me to actually fine tune or
close my session with a couple of last
words where one of the last things I
wanna highlight here is that Azure Load
testing is only one of, I would say,
our Azure mission critical components.
The second option, as you can see
here, is Azure Chaos Studio, allowing
you to do chaos engineering against
your Azure running workloads.
If you wanna find more details about
how this technically works, what are
the Microsoft guidelines, the best
practices on building out this sort
of mission critical workload scenario?
I would say go to this GitHub link
where you find all documentation,
including samples, including sample
testing and chaos experiments.
With that, I'm at the end
of my session time for now.
So thank you for watching.
Thank you for being here again.
Enjoy the rest of the SRE
conference here today.
If you've got any questions, don't
hesitate reaching out by email
on Twitter, maybe on LinkedIn
if you wanna stay in touch and
enjoy the rest of the conference.
Thank you for now and see you
again at some other com 42
conference in the near future.
Enjoy the rest of your day.