Good evening everyone.
I'm Sohi Pan Book.
I'm excited to walk you through how
artificial intelligence, when combined
with Microsoft ecosystem is fundamentally
changing how we approach recruitment
from talent sourcing to onboarding.
AI is helping us become faster, smarter,
and more in how we hire top talent.
In this presentation, we'll
explore real use cases.
Performance, improve improvements and
vision of what's next in this space.
Let's see how it works.
Imagine you are having a senior
full stack developer with over 10
years of experience in Microsoft
Technologies, someone proficient in
T net Core, angular, or React, and
databases like SQ Server or MongoDB.
Searching manually through thousands
of profile on job portals can be
overwhelming and time consuming.
So now picture how AI driven equipment
system that transform this process.
First, the profile filtering the AI
scans thousands of resumes extracting not
just keywords, but contextual insights.
It identifies genuine candidates
with proven experience in the
required technologies, not just those
who leased them on their resumes.
It analyzes project histories, patterns of
growth, real world application of skills.
Second powered AI powered wise engagement.
Once a potential match is found,
the AI initiates a natural sounding
wise call to the candidate.
It gathers deeper insights, verifying
their background, exploring recent
project experience, and confirming
their self expectations, ensuring a
strong alignment before moving forward.
Third.
Automated skill assessment.
If the AI determines a strong match,
it automatically sends a personalized
skill assessment to the candidate
via email id, tailored to their
experience and job requirements.
Four realtime scoring and introduc.
Upon completion of the assessment,
they AI affiliates performance
across different sections.
Based on these results, it trigger
another AI voice interaction to schedule
interviews, coordinating seamlessly
with availability of hiring managers.
Fifth, multi round, inter coordination.
Whether the process involves two rounds
of phi, the AI handles all scheduling
logistics, ensuring no time is lost, and
communication is prompt and professional.
Final selection and letter.
This is the final step.
Once all interviews are complete,
the system sends an automated email
informing the candidate of the outcome.
If selected, the candidate receives
the o. Along with the company's
terms and condition, ensuring a
smooth and timely onboarding process,
understanding AI in recruitment,
let's begin by understanding the ai.
Technology is used in recruitment.
Machine learning enables system to analyze
historical hiring data and continuously
learn from outcomes, helping predict
which candidates are likely to succeed.
Natural language processing,
which is nothing but, and LP
allows systems to understand.
Resumes like human would,
interpreting context.
11th and even detecting misleading
claims, deep learning analyzers, video
or audio from interviews to detect
subtle traits like communication, style,
tone, confidence, and culture alignment.
These technologies, when combined
delivered equipment process that's
intelligent, adaptive, and scalable.
Key performance metrics.
AI impact is measurable.
These aren't just concepts.
They drive business outcomes.
Like 45% reduction in time to hire
means roles get filled faster,
reducing productivity gaps.
37% improvement in
quality hire leads better.
Long-term performance, 32%.
Lower hiring cost come from
automation of task and 58% reduction
in unconscious bias through object
to consistent candidate evaluation.
These numbers just demonstrate how
AI turns hiring into high performance
function, not just support process.
NLP, which is nothing but
natural language processing.
Resume screening is one of the most
time consuming steps in recruitment.
Traditional keyword searches
are often rigid and missed
quality hand yet with 10 lp.
The system understands the matics DevOps.
Suppose DevOps engineer or the
cloud automation specialist might
mean the same thing contextually.
It identifies core skills,
certifications, even career progression.
Parsing is format agnostic
with a resumes coming PDF or
document or even scanned formats.
The result is 43% improvement in
resume matching accuracy, helping
recruiters focus on real fix.
AI driven candidate assessment.
Once a candidate passes the
resume stage modern app platform
take out to avoid technical,
cognitive and behavioral traits.
Cognitive testing adapts in real time
to assess logical thinking and learning
potential natural language analysis of
evaluates how well candidates communicate
and fit with the company culture.
Technical simulation validate
practical skills like coding,
debugging, or architectural design.
The AI model then predict on the job
performance con, constantly learning
from actual post higher outcomes.
Predictive ans in hiring predictive
analytics helps sift equipment from
being reactive to proactive by mining
historical data across thousands of.
AI can detect what combination
of skills, experiences, and
personality traits lead to successful
outcome in your specific context.
This results in reduced turnover, higher
job satisfaction, more consistent hiring
Sensor companies using predictive hiring
models have reduced mishires by 30%
enhancing candidate experience.
The candidate experience is just as
important as recruiter efficiency.
AI check bots provide instant answers 24
7, giving candidates timely responses.
Smart adaptive forms eliminate
repetitive inputs and reduce drop off
automated status updates, eliminating
and frustrating black hole feeding.
These innovations have improved a
candidate satisfaction by 41 percentage.
And 89 percentage of applicants report,
more engaging and respectful process
workflow automation bureaus.
Let's talk about internal gains.
Recruitment involves a lot of
repetitive tasks, emailing, scheduling,
coordination, concerning all this.
AI based work for automation helps
head chartings to save up to 25 hours
per recruiter per week, manage more
candidates without additional headcount.
Free up time to focus on
strategy, not administrative work.
This is especially useful during
high volume hiring phases, like
campus drives or seasonal expansions.
Microsoft AI recruitment ecosystem.
Microsoft ecosystem are for seamless
AI powered equipment Experience like
integrating with LinkedIn talent
Solution gives access to passive
candidates and predictive batching.
Integrating with Microsoft Dynamics
365 HR integrate applicant tracking,
onboarding and performance monitoring
into one system, integrating
with Microsoft Azure AI services.
Hello, custom.
Machine learning models for
skills matching, resume passing
and chat bot integrations.
The synergy between these
platform and shows end-to-end
intelligence from the first job.
Implementation roadmap.
So how do you implement all this?
Assess your current recruitment process,
identify gaps and friction points.
Define your AI strategy.
Prioritize use cases like resume
screening, assessment, or entry.
Pilot in one area, test with
specific role in our department.
Scale organization wide, build
integration with existing tools,
continuously optimized track KPIs,
gather feedback and retain model
organization that follow this roadmap.
Report 28% highest satisfaction
and see ROI within the
first quarter of deployment.
The future of AI equipment.
The next frontier in AI powered
equipment includes immersive assessment
using AR or VR for job simulations.
Autonomous AI recruiters that conduct
and analyze fully interviews predictive
workforce planning, that forecast
hiring needs and hyper personalized
career pathing for employee retention.
The future of recruitment is not just
faster, it is more strategic, inclusive,
and aligned with long-term success.
Thank you for joining me today.
AI and recruitment isn't
just about automation.
It's about make data,
everyone, and impactful.
I would love to connect with
further hear your thoughts or
answer any questions you may have.
Thank you once again.