Everyone, thank you for
joining me at Con 2025.
I'm bas, and today we are gonna
dive into one of the most exciting
frontiers in modern systems,
AI driven self infrastructure.
Over the next 20 minutes, I'll walk you
through how AI is evolving s monitoring
and automation into systems that can
truly detect, recover, and improve.
Just someone who tired of waking up at
3:00 AM incidents in the right place.
Let's explore how the future of
infrastructure is becoming not only
smarter, but truly resilient by design.
Let's talk about why this
conversation is so critical.
Why AI driven self-heal infrastructure
is more than just buzzword.
We are operating in a world
where S isn't optional anymore.
It's mission critical.
The complexity of what we
manage today is staggering.
Modern cloud infrastructure spans
thousands of interconnected services.
Manual oversight just
isn't scalable anymore.
Even the best engineers can't
babysit every node, every container,
every function, 24 by seven.
On top of that, our current
systems are still largely reactive.
We wait for alerts, we jump on
incidents, we write postmortems, and
in high availability environments.
Especially in healthcare,
finance or e-commerce, that
model just doesn't cut it.
Downtime isn't just inconvenient.
It's expensive.
We are talking about millions in lost
revenue annually, or even brief outages.
That's why the shift matters.
AI changes the paradigm.
Instead of responding after things go
wrong, we can predict, prevent, and
heal before users are even impact.
This is where we even move from
firefighting to future proofing.
Today, I want to show you
how exactly we got it.
Let's take a quick look at how SRE
has evolved over the years, because
understanding this evolution gives
us context for where we are headed.
We have started with SRE
1.0, a phase with operations.
Were largely man engineers.
Were constantly on call.
Basic monitoring tools helped, but the
response models are still reactive.
This is also when we first saw
the idea of error budgets, helping
balance reliability with innovation.
Then came SRE 2.0 where things
really started to shift.
We embraced automation with infrastructure
as code scripted remediation and alerting.
That got a bit smarter.
Chaos engineering also started to emerge.
Testing resiliency proactively.
We moved from just monitoring to
observability, not just knowing
something broke, but wide broke.
Now we are entering SR 3.0, a new era
where systems are becoming autonomous.
We are talking about predictive
healing, where AI anticipates
problems before they happen.
Engineers don't just respond anymore.
They architect systems
that respond themselves.
It's a strategic role now, designing
guardrails, training AI models,
and ensuring systems evolve safely.
And this shift into AI native
SRE isn't just exciting.
It's necessary because systems are
scaling faster than humans can keep up.
So let's explore what makes AI
powered self-healing possible.
Now, let's.
It's not magic.
It's a structured progression
that builds intelligence into
the systems stage by stage.
It starts with detection.
AI systems, monitor logs, metrics and
signals, identifying anomalies that
a human operator might never notice.
We are talking about subtle changes
in behavior where edge failures or
slowly building patterns that don't.
That feels slow, but never
breaks during the demo.
AI catches those moments.
Next, machine learning kicks in with
production models are trained on
historical data and live telemetry.
The forecast failures are sometimes
even days before they actually happen.
This lets us shift from reactive
firefighting to preventative
action, then comes remediation.
This is where AI really flexes.
It can autonomously trigger
corrective workflows.
Whether it's restarting services, draining
traffic from a failure node, or scaling
a specific region, the goal is rapid
resolution with zero human intervention.
And finally, optimization.
Each incidents become
a learning opportunity.
AI systems use postmodern data to refine
future predictions, reduce noise, and
adapt to all infrastructure behaviors.
This feedback loop creates a smarter,
more resilient system over time.
All four stages, detection,
prediction, remediation, or
optimization build on each other.
In mature systems, we are seeing
up to 85% incident healing
accuracy without human involvement.
That's the real magic, continuous
improvement without burnout.
Let's take a quick look at how one of the
biggest streaming platforms in the world.
Netflix is putting AI powered
self-healing into action.
Netflix uses a tool called Chat
the Chaos Automation platform.
It leverages machine learning to
proactively search for resilience gaps
before real users even notice them.
Think of it like a in very intelligent
troublemaker in the system.
It tries to break things on purpose, but
only to make even everything stronger.
It sharper the false
it injects Aren random.
They're based on calculated risk models,
simulating the most likely points
of failure with surgical precision.
It's not chaos for chaos sake.
It's chaos with intent.
What about the results?
The speak volumes.
Netflix cut their entity by 30
to 50% and proactively prevented
over 200 outages in just one year.
In just 2023.
That's hundreds of moments where you
didn't even get the spinning buffer
icon mid episode, and that's a win for
both reliability and user satisfaction.
And one of the most powerful outcomes.
SRE now focus less on firefighting
and moral architecture.
They are not just reacting, they are
building proactively with strategy.
And
now let's shift to another tech giant.
Where the focus is on precision at
scale, meta runs tens of thousands of
servers and detecting subtle behavior
failure signals across all of them is
like spotting a signal, single flickering
light bulb across an entire city.
That's where machine learning
steps in analyzing telemetry,
where millions of components catch
signatures before they escalate.
Here is where it gets futuristic
when the AI reaches 85% confidence.
A failure is imminent.
The system doesn't wait.
It proactively migrates or migrates
workloads long before any human
would typically react to it.
It's like watching the weather and
evacuating before the storm instead of
rebuilding after it hits the outcome.
76% of potential failures preventive.
A 23% boost in capacity planning,
and over $45 million saved annually.
That's not just resilience,
that's remarkable.
ROI.
And that little chat you see
there, that's the AI predictions,
outpacing actual failures.
It's not perfect, but it gets close.
And at meta scale even, a
few percentage points matter.
Let's shift our focus to Microsoft
Azure, a company operating at massive
global scale managing services
for millions across industries.
Fully AI driven self infrastructure
and the results are both
measurable and inspiring.
First, they have seen a 65% reduction.
That means AI is filtering of
the A charter and surfacing
only actionable incidents.
Think of it as noise canceling
headphones, but for your operations team.
Then comes uptime
improvement, jumping by 35%.
Autonomous remediation means systems are
no longer waiting on a human to jump in.
They're healing themselves,
keeping services running smoothly.
The most impressive number,
90% auto resolution.
That means the vast majority of
common incidents are resolved
entirely without human intervention.
For sre, this translates
to a shift from meaningful.
Of course, cost reduction.
A leaner smart infrastructure leads
to a 44% drop in operational expenses.
That's the kind of number
that speaks to both the tech
teams and as well as the CFO.
This case highlights what's possible
when AI is embedded, not just as
an assistant, but as an autonomous
partner in infrastructure resilience.
Azure, just automating task.
It's reimagining the.
Now we have seen how AI can
transform infrastructure,
reliability, and resilience.
But let's ground ourselves for a moment.
The reality is AI in SRE isn't
all magic and automation.
It comes with a unique set of challenges
that we must be intentional about first.
Explainability AI systems
often behave like black boxes.
They make decisions and the
team is let wondering why.
This creates accountability gaps,
especially during incidents when every
second and every insight matters.
Second, human oversight.
Finding a balance between trust and
control is tough too little automation,
and we miss opportunities for efficiency
too much, and we risk over resilience.
Something that can backfire
during edge cases or.
AI systems, infrastructure level across
access becomes new attack surfaces.
We're not talking about ML
poisoning, where the model
itself becomes the vulnerability.
This isn't science fiction anymore.
It's an emerging reality.
It finally, bias and blind
spots, your model is only as
good as the data it learns from.
And if your data carries historical biases
or lacks representation for each cases.
The system will inherit those flaws.
This can lead to unequal
reliability outcomes.
So while the potential of AI
and SI is massive, it depends.
It demands maturity, caution, and clarity.
If we don't solve these challenges with
intentionally, we are simply trading
one set of problems for another.
Take moment.
Zoom this going.
Assist mostly with anomaly
detection and noise reduction.
It's helpful, but still reactive.
In the next two to three years,
we enter the transformation phase.
This is where AI begin handling
known issues autonomously.
Auto healing becomes a norm
for common failure patterns.
It's not just alerting anymore.
It's fixing.
This shift will begin to reshape
how S teams are structured.
From reactive firefighting to
strategic oversight roles, as we
mature into phase three, AI native
reliability platforms will dominate.
This means SRE won't just
manage infrastructure.
They will take on new roles like training
AI systems, evaluating critical decisions,
and setting governance policies.
The reliability stack will be
AI first by design, and finally,
we'll reach the reinvention phase.
Where AI systems don't just follow rules,
they evolve, they learn, adapt, and
redesign their own operational processes.
Human engineers will take on higher
roles guiding innovation, defining
ethical boundaries, and managing
the complex relationship between
autonomous systems and human oversight.
If we think, if it think
of it as a timeline.
Now AI assists next three to two.
Two to three years.
AI auto heals.
Five to AI infrastructure that learns,
and this isn't Afic science fiction, it's
organizations, and
let's bring
AI.
It transforms, SRE from reactive support
to a forward looking discipline that
proactively ensures reliability at scale,
SREs become architects of resilience.
Second, human element.
AI doesn't replace us.
It needs us.
Engineers remain essential to
tune models, validate decisions,
and ensure outcomes aligned with
business and ethical expectations.
Move from scripted writers.
Signal interpreters from hands on
troubleshooters to strategic AI trainers.
Third, start small.
You don't need a moonshot.
Begin with your biggest pain point.
Observability, remediation, or ity.
Even incremental AI integration here can
yield massive ROI As and as trust goes.
So does the, and this part is important.
AI doesn't.
It's a force multiplier, not a substitute.
What matters most is thoughtful
implementation, not flashy
use cases, but focused impact.
That wraps up our journey into AI
driven self-healing infrastructure.
Thank you so much for your
time, your attention, and your
curiosity throughout this keynote.
I hope this gave you fresh
insight into where site
reliability engineering is headed.
Ideas, challenges,
conversation, going, thank.