Hi, this is Sand ul.
I'm a senior software unit and welcoming
you all, whoever joined in my talk.
And here I'm going to present my
topic on Enhance cybersecurity with
multi authentication and zero trust.
Integrity models, and it's a data driven
approach to modern defense strategies
traditional secure systems to no longer
against sophisticated cyber threats.
So here we are going to discover how
MFA and Zero Trust frameworks works in
revolutionizing defense strategies and
saving millions in breach related costs.
So the rising cost of data breach.
Is gradually increasing by dollar 4.45
million average breach cost global figure.
It's a huge number for 2023 and 83%.
Identify related percentage of breach tied
to the identify compromise and dollar 3.92
million annual savings for organization
integrating MFA and Zero trust.
The financial impact of
breaches continues to rise.
Identify security has become
a critical vulnerability point
requiring immediate attention.
So here though, we can discuss
about the fundamentals of
multifactor authentications.
So in inherent factor like, which is like
biometrics and ion factors like token and
cards and knowledge factors with passport
and pins, where MFA creates multiple
verification layers, each factor provides.
And additional security barrier,
A against unauthorized access.
The productive power of MFA is 99%
reduction in account Compromise the
items when MFA properly implemented.
So let's discuss on
productive power of MFA and.
Here, the financial impact of data
breaches continues to escalates,
so which identify security emerging
as a critical vulnerability point.
As a result, organizations must add up
advanced security framework to product
sense to data and mitigate risk.
So understanding of multifactor
authentications, so each additional.
Verification factor strengthens
security by creating multiple
barriers against unauthorized access.
So MFA is proven to reduce account
compromise the items by 99.9%, and
lower security incidents by 91%.
So compared to the systems relying on
password alone, so the effectiveness of
zero trust architecture in the next slide.
So here in the zero trust architecture,
so one of the assumptions that one is
whether inside or outside the network is
it continuously verifies and authenticate
all the access requests to go less of.
Requests like option.
So this originally ensures the
security is maintained at every
stage of user interactions.
So the zero trust framework have
been significantly reduce the attack
surface, prevents lateral moments, and
within networks and minimize breaches.
So organizations adopting Bureau trust.
See miserable improvements in
security and including reduced
successful attacks and more effect
to containing mental of deaths.
So the zero trust effectiveness matrix
here, the attack surface reduction and
surface and security incidents, and each
breach prevention rate and later moment.
So in the industry, specific benefits
such as improving by implementing
zero trust result in a 93% reduction
in Akon takeovers and dollar 1.87
million in the annual savings
is a huge saving and a around 6%
decrease in fraud investigations.
So healthcare benefits, like by using zero
trust reduction rate is 72% in reduction.
The.
In breaches and in product health
data and increases the hypo.
Compliance like faster than 88%.
So as compared to government sectors,
organizations are a 99%, 7% in classified
data and seven, 6% drop in unauthorized
access events, improving regulatory
compliance and overall security.
These results.
Demonstrate the significant security
improvements that can achieve by adopting
MFA and zero trust across different
factors and integration strategies for
MFA and zero Trust through successfully
integrate MFA and Zero Trust organization
should follow this picture approach.
So assessment like conducting is
comprehensive security audit to identify
vulnerabilities and access risk exposes
and strategy, development and design,
customized implementation plan with clear
goals and with and milestones, resource
allocations and access to buy-ins.
And other strategies in integrations or.
The pilot deployment and the rollout
control trial in a selected departments
and critical systems to test the
effectiveness of the solution.
So faced implementation so
gradually expands the security
framework, provides prioritizing
critical assets first and while.
Adjusting based on real time feedback.
And continuously optimization is in
one of the integration technique.
So establish regular monitoring and
refinement to ensure the solution
evolves with emerging threats.
So here izing, tech authentication
technologies or, so these are
authentications, landscape is
evolving with new technologies.
That offer enhanced security
while minimizing user friction.
So passwordless authentication, so
eliminates the risk of associated
with the password based and securely
while using alternative measures like
biometric or smart devices and biometrics.
So advanced biological makers
such as fingerprints or.
Face shield, recognization, or
user for secure authentication
with anti proofing measures.
So behavior authentication, so
users machine learning to analyze
user behavior pattern and provide
continuous authentications.
So adapt to risk assessments, adjust
the security levels based on the
contextual factors such as users,
location, device, or activities.
So these innovations are crucial
for improving both security and user
experience, allowing more seamless
yet secure authentication process.
So let's continue to balancing security
and user experience and key takeaways for
the by implementing Hero trust and MFA.
Authentication.
So here adopting MFA and Zero Trust
for robust production integrates
MFA and Zero Trust frameworks to
safeguard agonist modern threats.
So pre prioritize user experience,
ENS ensures that secure measures
are implemented in a ways that
minimize friction for users.
Start with critical assessments.
So focus on producting, the most valuable
resources first, gradually expanding
to cover the entire organizations.
So measures and optimize,
continuously track security metrics
and return on investments to refine
strategies and improve outcomes.
So the evolving cybersecurity landscape
requires advanced defense strategies
by amortizing MFA and zero trust.
Organizations can significantly enhance
security, reduce breach related costs,
and stay ahead of emerging threats.
And thank you all who
have joined my section.