Hey.
Hi everyone.
Welcome.
Thank you for joining me today.
In today's session we'll discuss how
SRE approach has transformed financial
operations by addressing system
latency, global access disparities,
and also reliability concerns.
Let's explore the key
strategies and results achieved
through this transformation.
So moving on the next one, what we
are looking at is the challenge.
So what are the challenges which
are, we are currently facing?
As part of the financial
systems which needed SRE.
So the first one, what we see
is unpredictable performance
during the financial close.
The system response time increases
drastically from an average of two
seconds to 30 seconds per transactions.
This latency caused delays in the
consolidation, financial statements
leading to missing deadlines and
the increase in manual intervention.
For instance, a finance team had
to wait for extended periods to
complete each transaction, which
not only slowed down the entire
process, but also led to overtime
work and increased operational costs.
So the second challenge, what we
see is global availability issues.
Teams located in different regions
such as Asia and Europe, faced
inconsistent access to financial systems.
For example, during the peak hours, users
in Asia frequently experienced a timeout,
some slowdown responses while users in
Europe did not face any such issues.
This disparity in system availability,
the availability of the global
teams to collaborate effectively and
maintain the continuous operation.
As a result critical financial processes
were delayed and overall efficiency
of the organization was compromised.
So the next issue, what we
see is reliability concerns.
So the financial system experienced
unexpected outages particularly during the
critical periods such as month end close.
These outages led to incomplete
data entries and disrupted
financial workflows requiring ex
extensive manual reconciliation.
To correct errors.
For instance, a certain system
crash during the final stages of
financial reporting, causes data
loss and also inconsistencies.
Which took several days to resolve.
So the result in increasing in the
operational risk and reduce the
confidence among the stakeholders
and potential financial losses due to
delayed in reporting condition making.
So as an example, like in British Airways
in 2020 the the SAP outage was disrupted.
The payroll and invoicing
cascading into 80 million losses.
Okay.
Moving on.
The next one, what we are looking at is
Ari approach to finance transformation.
So here here we are looking at
three different approaches how the
finance can transform this SRE.
So the first one, what we are looking is
reframe financial systems as services.
So the financial transactions and
reporting processes were treated as
services with the defined reliability on.
Performance targets and similar
to how how we customer facing
applications are managed.
So this swift in perspective ensures
that the financial system receive the
same level of attention and resources
as the other critical business
services leading to improve the
reliability and also the performance.
So the second approach, what we see
is a defined clear reliability target.
Okay, let's say the, a certain example.
Certain example, the set
service level object to.
So of 99.99% of time for the financial
system, meaning it could only be down
for approximately four minutes per month.
This high standard insurance, that
system was almost always reliable,
reducing the risk of downtime.
During the critical periods and
improving the overall user satisfaction.
So Visa sets their at 99.999% to align
it with the business critical operations,
which will reduce overall system downtime.
And reduce the latencies.
So the next one, what next
approach, what we see is implement
a continuous measurement.
Integrate real time monitoring tools,
so to track the system performance
and also user experience and
enable proactive issues protection.
Enable proactive issue detection
through prevent a predictive
analysis and an anomaly detection.
So continuous monitor monitoring
flags will increase in a PA response
time prompting the system to
automatically scale up resources before,
before user experience any delay.
So proactive scaling maintains
performance standards and also
prevent potential slowdowns.
So the next one, what we are looking
at is establishing financials, LO.
So again, we are having four
different approaches here.
The first one, what we see
is availability metrics.
Ensure that critical functions just speak.
The lecturer updates or financial
reporting were almost always
available with the downtime,
less than four minutes per month.
This high availability targets
minimize the disruptions and ensures
that finance teams could rely on the
system to complete their tasks on time.
Our next one, what we see is performances.
So set a performances where 95%
of the financial transactions
should complete within two seconds.
Ensuring quick and efficient
processing this target helps
maintaining a smooth workflow and
reduce the time finance teams.
Spent waiting for the
transactions to complete.
So the Coca-Cola mandated this two, two
second sub-process times for any S-A-P-F-I
transaction during the quarter closures.
So the next one, the third one, what we
are looking at is continuous refinement.
Every quarter the team should
review system performance data and
not just the based on the observed
trends and also the business needs.
So ensuring that.
Continuous alignment with
the operational goals.
This regular review process allows
the teams to adapt and change
in requirements continuously
improve the system reliability.
The fourth one, what we look at
is business aligned Excel goals.
So during month and close, the
Excel was for the availability
was increased to 99.999.
5% allowing for only two minutes
of downtime to ensure smooth and
uninterrupted financial operations.
So this higher target ensures that
system remained highly reliable during
the most critical periods reducing
the risk of delays and errors.
Okay.
So the next one, what we are looking at
is automated monitoring and alerting.
So the first one, what we we have three
different approaches how the system alert.
New alerts will be sent to
the financial processes.
So the first one, what we are
looking at is intelligent alerting.
So alerts for issues affecting month
and close processes, or prioritized over
less critical functions ensuring rapid
response and also high impact problems.
So this prioritization helps the teams
to focus on most critical issues first
that minimizes the business disruption.
So the second one, what we see is.
Proactive detection.
So monitoring the tools monitoring tools
that detect detected increases the latency
in transaction processing and alerts
the system before it affect the user.
So following for primitive actions.
So this proactive approach helps
prevent issues from cascading and
ensures a smooth user experience.
So the next one, what we see is a
comprehensive coverage so monitored,
not just the system uptime and also
the performance, but also completion
rates of the financial processes like
reconciliations and reporting generations.
This comprehensive monitoring
approach provides a holistic view
of system health and performance.
Okay, moving on.
The next one, what we are looking
at is incident response time.
So in order to provide the response time,
so for the incidents to try to take care
we defined the three different topics.
Approaches.
The first one is finance
specific playbooks.
So develop playbooks for common
issues like transaction failures
and data inconsistencies, detailing
step by step resolution procedures,
and escalating escalation parts.
These playbooks provides clear
guidance for teams and ensures quick
and effective incident resolution.
So the second one, what we see is
cross-functional response teams.
So form form teams with both IT and
finance experts who could quickly
diagnose and resolve the issues such as
finance experts identifying the impacts
of system error on financial reporting.
So this cross cross-functional
approach ensure that incidents
were addressed from both the
technical and business perspective.
Then third important one
is blameless postmortems.
So after a system outage conducted a
postmortem to analyze and analyze root
causes and identify the improvements
focusing on process and system outages
rather than blaming individuals.
So this approach fostered a culture
of continuous improvement and also
helps prevent similar issues in future.
So the next one, what we are
looking at is a technical results.
So again, the number speaks.
So the first one the system availability.
So achieved near perfect uptime,
significantly reducing the downtime,
onur, continuous availability
of the financial system.
So this improvement enhance the
user confidence and also reduce
the risk of business disruption.
Ana, an example, as SAP PS Fourna
Cloud achieved 99.99% of time for
Luhan after migrating from ECC ECC 6.0.
So previously it was at 97%.
The second one, what we see as a technical
results is the incident resolution.
Reduce the average time to resolve the
incidents from four hours to one hour.
Minimizing the business disruption.
This faster resolution time
include overall system reliability
and also the user satisfaction.
So third point what we are
looking at as automation.
So within 90% of recovery process
procedures, were automated, human
intervention is minimized, reducing the
error and also speed up the recovery.
So automation ensures consistency
and reliability, which is essential
for maintaining the critical business
operations without any interruption.
The next one, what we
see is business impact.
So again, how it is impacting the
business, how businesses using this SRE.
So the first one, what we see is
a predictable month-end close.
So achieve a predictable month-end close
process with the financial statements
consistently completed on time and
improving the stakeholder conference.
This predictability, reduce the
stress and finance teams and
also ensure timely reporting.
Some of the companies after using this SRE
approach, they reduce it from 10 days to
five days during the financial closing.
The second one, what we
see is reliable reporting.
So eliminated the system errors
in financial reports ensuring the
accurate and reliable financial
data for decision making.
This improvement enhanced the
credibility of the financial reports
and supported better business decisions.
So the third business impact, what
we see is really real time analytics.
System provided real time access
to financial data, enabling timely
and informed business decisions.
So this real time access supported
agile decision making and improved
overall business performance.
As an example, like ma users SA PS 400
plus power BA for realtime container cost
tracking cutting reporting errors by 90%.
That is a big achievement for the ma.
So the next one, what as part of this
is next one is cultural transformation.
So again, we have three different
approaches how it transformed.
So the first one, what we
see is shared ownership.
So both IT and finance teams
participated in the regular,
reliability reviews jointly prioritize
the system improvements fostering
a culture of shared responsibility.
So this collaboration ensures that both
technical and business perspectives
were considered in the decision making.
The next one is data driven decisions.
So use the data from monitoring tools to
identify areas needed needing investment
such as upgrading infrastructure,
opt or optimizing the processes.
Ensuring the resources
were allocated effectively.
So this data driven approach supported,
informed the decision making and
optimized the resources used.
So the third transformation, what
we see is continuous improvement.
So conducting monthly reviews of incidents
and near misses to identify trends and
implement improvements and continuously
enhancing the system reliability.
So this regular review process ensures
that lessons learned were applied and
that system was continuously optimized.
So that is one of the major
major improvement or the
transformation we need to consider.
So we need to keep on keep on adding
the continuous improvement so that
whatever the issues we have faced earlier
should not be receiving in near future.
Moving on the next one, what we have
is a key implementation lessons.
We have we have four different no four
different approaches, what we see,
so the start with business metrics.
So focus on metrics like a transaction,
complete time on financial closer.
Close duration, which directly
impacts the business operations.
So this focus ensures that
reliability improvements were
aligned with business goals.
Okay.
The next one is balance feature
velocity and reliability.
It allows, so for certain
number of errors on the issues.
So LY is balancing the need
of need for new features with
maintaining system reliability.
So this balance ensures that innovation
did not compromise system stability.
We can have a couple of issues which will
come as part of that particular month end.
Okay.
And the next one, what we see is
investing cross trans training.
Conduct training sessions
where SR engineers learned
about the financial process.
And similarly, the finance teams were
educated on relatability principles.
This cross training issues that
both the teams understand each
other, the priorities and could
work together effectively.
The final one, what we see is measured
business outcomes monitored not just
the system uptime on performance,
but also impact on the financial
operations such as time timeliness
and accuracy of financial reporting.
This comprehension measurement approach
ensures that the technical improvements
are translated into business benefits.
So the next one, what we are looking at
is expanding SRE across business systems.
So the first one, what we are
looking is procurement systems.
So implementing reliability targets
and monitoring for the procurement
processes to ensure timely
and accurate order processing.
This expansion would improve the
efficiency and also the reliability
of supply chain operations.
So Boeing applies SRE to SAP Ariba
Slashing, PVO processes latency by 50%.
So the next one is
manufacturing operations.
So applying SRE practices to manufacturing
systems to minimize downtime and also
ensures consistent production output.
So this approach would enhance
production reliability.
And also reduce the
operational disruptions.
The third one, implementing
SRE at HR platforms.
So ensuring high availability and
performance of HR systems such as payroll
and employee self-service platforms.
So this implementation would
improve employee satisfaction
and also operational efficiency.
So the final one, what we are looking at
is where we can apply customer service.
So improving the reliability of customer
service platforms and e-commerce
systems to enhance customer satisfaction
and reduce the service disruptions.
So this focus would support
a better customer experiences
and also business growth.
So this concludes our presentation.
Thank you so much for joining here today.
By addressing the system latency
and global access disparities and
reliability concerns we have significantly
improved our financial operations.
Our SRE approach has enhanced system
availability and reduce the incident
resolution times, and fostered a
culture of continuous improvement.
So we look forward to expanding
these principles in across all
other business systems for greater
efficiency and reliability.
I appreciate your
attention and engagement.
If you have any questions please
reach out to me on my LinkedIn.
Thank you.
Thank you everyone.