Hello everyone.
I'm Mova, and today I'm excited to talk
about how intelligent automation, which
is known as ia, come in combination with
business process management known as BPM.
It's transforming how we operate,
innovate, and deliver the value.
this isn't, just about an automation.
It's about enabling strategic,
intelligent business evolution.
Coming to the next slide, it talks
about, global momentum and market trends.
so what we have seen in the recent,
Deloitte research, it shows that globally
73% of the organizations are already on
their intelligent automation journey.
58% are using AI to scale
automation platform.
and this just isn't a
trend, it's a moment.
In fact, we are seeing an ROI in
under a year for many organizations
with 93% are reporting outcome that
meet or exceed their expectations.
also we have seen that 58% of
organization are scaling AI
enabled automation platform.
And the average, ROI time that
is achieved by most of the
organization is around 11 months.
coming to the next slide, here, I'll
talk about why intelligent automation
and business process management, is used.
so combining IA with BPM unlocks
real, process transformation.
in terms of, process efficiency,
we are talking about reducing
the cycle time up to 90%.
IM improving the compliance, freeing and
it almost free up, 30% of employees, time
spent on normal day-to-day repeated task.
And this isn't just automation,
it's intelligent orchestration.
second about data utilization, real time
analytics with 80% faster data retrieval.
so BBPI, which is also
known as business process.
Integration, it enables advance, data
utilization by ensuring consistency
across previously siloed application.
and in terms of customer experience,
we have seen that there is a 20
to 30%, increase in satisfaction
and 40 to 60% faster service.
Going to the next slide, which,
talks about the key benefits
of, using IEA with BPM.
And, what we have seen is the
impact is multidimensional here.
better decision making,
through machine learning.
Improved customer experience
via natural language processing
and continuous optimization.
And it's not about,
replacing humans, right?
but enhancing what they do best while
machines, handle, the day-to-day grant
work, in terms of efficiency, process
cycle time reduces by almost 90%.
second key benefit is,
regarding, decision making.
machine learning is a
real game changer here.
it allows the BPM system
to adapt and optimization.
On the fly, monitoring, analyzing, and
adjusting without manual intervention,
but still keeping humans in the loop,
for all the strategic oversight.
And that makes the
combination, very deadly.
third important benefit of
is the customer experience.
when we use IE to streamline
customer journeys, satisfaction
increases by up to 30%.
and conversational a ai I AI
understand emotional signal and context
leading to faster, more personalized
support and better brand loyalty.
coming to the next slide, which
shows about, what are the leading
tools used for I-N-B-P-M ecosystem.
some of the top layers include
UiPath, automation, anywhere,
cofaq, and, Pega Systems.
And each of these, tools have their
unique strengths, from document processing
to cognitive automation, to process
orchestration, and tool selection,
completely depends on your business
needs and the strategy, involved.
So UiPath, is a leader in
end-to-end automation with task
process mining capabilities.
coming to Automation Anywhere is a Cloud
Native 360 platform, which is scalable
automation platform, Pega system.
They are very strong in orchestration
and case management, with Pega
Robotics and also they have, coverage
in mobile solutions, as well.
coming to coax, it's specialized
in document intensive process with
RPA, along with very advanced OCR.
coming to the next slide, which,
talks about, how in business process
selection and prioritization work.
so what we have observed is that
organization that focus on business value.
not just the technical ease.
See the most return.
as you can see, that's occupying
the top slab in this pyramid.
It starts with finance,
hr, or tax department.
refer, transfer, transformation, use.
It also uses a formal selection
framework to ensure alignment
with their strategic goals.
The next slide, it talks about governance
framework, for i a and BPM integration.
So this particular, slide talks
about a governance is important,
for how the governance is
important for i a and BPM here.
Governance is the key.
69% of high performing organization
have automation centers of excellence.
Success really lies.
In balancing central standard with local
execution and defining very clear roles
based on the business and technical
teams in order to excel beyond just the
initial pilot projects that they have.
the next slide, it's about the
change management essentials.
how it is essential.
So change management isn't
optional, it's foundational.
it talks about how
involving your teams early.
if you communicate, clearly, share
clear information and be transparent,
communication on role impacts to
invest in reskilling of employees
for strategic skill development.
58%, which is a very high
number of leading organization
are already, doing this.
And leading companies.
around 42% redesign, workflow for
humans and machines to work together
not in isolation, which is covered
in, which is, usually covered in
human machine collaboration framework.
coming to the next slide, it talks about,
the technical architectural, foundation,
a successful, IA and BPM stack.
Is modular, which is required
for adaptability with enterprise
wide standard for consistency.
performance tracking and continuous
refinement through real time data
are vital for a, success offer.
IE and BPM system, with 47%, of
successful organization use process
mining for continuous improvement.
coming to the next slide,
which, talks about the future
of intelligent automation.
so we are heading into a future
where hyper automation, integrating
ai, RPM, RPA, BPM, and analytics.
As process, as a part of process
intelligence, it uses deep analytics to
identify high value automation targets and
self-healing and adaptive workflow forms
part of their auto autonomous process.
with process intelligence in place
and collaboration, we go beyond
automation to transformation.
And, to conclude and final takeaway,
from this presentation, intelligent
automation isn't just a cost cutting tool.
It's a strategic capability for new bro,
business model and resilient operation.
they focus on end-to-end optimization,
not just the isolation tasks.
and usually what being seen
is the winner in this space.
Think beyond tasks.
They reimagine entire process
and build a future where machines
and human co-create the value.
I. So here I conclude.
thank you all for your
attention and listening in.
Hope, that you have gained some insights
about I a. Which is intelligent automation
combined with the Pro BPM and how it is
transforming and delivering the value.
Happy learning everyone.
Thank you.