Hello everyone.
My name is Rinku Mohan.
Today we are going to discuss a topic that
is increasingly significant in our rapidly
changing world, the importance of digital
inclusion for the aging population.
This is closely related to my
research on the digital exclusion
of elderly inclusions, where we
explore the challenges they face and
the solutions needed to ensure no
one is left behind the digital age.
As life expectancy continues to rise
around the world, the issue of aging
has become more and more significant.
This change brings both
opportunities and challenges.
The technology advancements have
the power to transform lives,
offering better living conditions and
opportunities to connect socially.
However, for many elderly
individuals, navigating modern
technologies can be a real challenge.
The digital inclusion is crucial
here by ensuring that everyone,
regardless of their age, has access
to and can use digital tools.
Effectivity.
We can promote social justice
and equal development.
It helps bridge gaps, foster
connections, and improve the
overall quality of the life of the.
This research mainly focuses
on the understanding of the
digital divide among the elderly.
We wanted to find out what causing
all the others to struggle with
technology, how their how this impact
their lives, and why these challenges
differ from one country to another.
So the ultimate goal is to figure
out ways to help them integrate
better into today's digital world.
And we explored three main questions.
What is the current situation
of the digital exclusion?
How well are the older people able
to use devices like smartphones,
computers, and other digital tools?
Secondly, what are the key
reasons behind this difficulties?
How do things like their income,
health or age affect their
ability to use technology?
And how does this impact
their everyday lives?
And finally, how do these issues
vary between different countries?
Are all the peoples in wealthier
countries facing the same struggles
as those in the less wealthy ones?
And by answering these questions, we
hope to provide practical insights
that can guide policies, programs,
and community efforts to make the
digital world more accessible for
elderly, no matter where they live.
Here is something interesting from
the general knowledge about older
age groups and their internet use.
As people get older, their
internet usage drops significantly.
For example, in age groups like 45 to
54, 55 to 64 and 65, plus the number of
internet users is about 10 percentage
less compared to younger groups.
This trend highlights how
technology adoption becomes
more of a challenge with age.
Another point to note is the oldest
dependency ratio the number of older
people compared to the working age
population in most countries except India.
This ratio is above 50.
This means that there are at
least 50 older adults for every
a hundred working a stupid For
India, it's slightly lower at 37.
Looking ahead.
It is projected that by 2075, more
than half the population in these
countries will be senior citizens.
This means that addressing the
digital divide and preparing for
an aging population will become
more important in the future.
For our research, we collected aging
data from five high income countries and
five lower and middle income countries.
The higher income countries include
United Kingdom Germany, Austria,
France, Estonia, and the lower and
middle income countries included India,
Mexico, Brazil, Bulgaria, and Romania.
We selected these countries to
ensure a diverse representation
of economic and cultural context.
By comparing digital exclusion across
these regions, we were able to see
how challenges differ between the
wealthier and less wealthy countries
and gain deeper insights into the
factors driving the digital divide.
And we looked at the data from
these sources over five years,
from 2019 to 2023 to ensure we
capture trends and changes over.
Once we had the data, we analyzed it
using various statistical methods.
For example, principle component
analysis, which help us to understand
the key factors driving the digital
exclusion and the test like five
square and anova, which help us to find
the patterns compared groups and see
how digital exclusion varies between
countries, income levels, and age.
This combination of methods allowed us to
identify the main barriers older adults
face when using technology and how these
challenges differ across the regions.
This table Compass five higher income
countries, Austria, Germany, France,
Estonia, and uk focusing on population
size, age, gender, and digital exclusion.
The United Kingdom stands out with
the largest group of participants
while Austria has the smallest in
terms of age, the median across all
countries is the early seventies,
but UK has a slightly younger
population with a median age of 69.
Gender wise, women are more
represented in every country.
Estonia, for example, has the
highest proportion of women now
when it comes to digital exclusion.
Estonia and France has the
highest rate around 30 percentage.
While UK is doing much better with only
11 percentage of the population excluded.
When we look at the age, the median
across middle income countries
ranges from 64 to 70 years with
bacteria have the oldest group.
The 55 to 64 group is the largest
in most countries, especially in
India and Mexico, where it accounts
for nearly half the population.
On the other hand, the 75 plus age
group is much smaller, particularly
in India and Mexico, where it's
around 16 to 17 percentage.
For gender, there is a fairly balanced
split in most countries, though bras,
Brazil has a slightly higher proportion
of men at 55 percentage, while India
and Mexico have more women at around
53 percentage, the most striking
insight is digital exclusion in media.
Which has the highest rate within
staggering 91 percentage of the
population display excluded highlighting
a major challenge for connectivity.
In contrast Mexico has the lowest
exclusion rate at 33 percentage showing
significant progress in digital access.
Age and marital status are two key factors
when it comes to digital exclusion.
Let's start with age.
Older age groups are significantly
more likely to be digitally excluded,
and this issue is even more pronounced
in lower and middle income countries.
In contrast, higher income countries
tend to do a better job for including
older populations in digital world.
Now let's talk about merit status.
Individuals without partners, whether
single, divorced or widow without
are more likely to be excluded.
This 10 is noticeable in all
countries, but the gap is much
wider in middle income countries.
So what does this mean overall?
The most digitally excluded demographics
are older adults and individuals
without partners, and this is especially
severe in middle income countries.
These findings highlight the
origin need for targeted efforts
to close this digital divide.
The factors affecting digital
exclusion was identified using.
A factor analysis which is a
dimensional reduction technique used
to identify the most important factors.
And it suggests that three different
factors are primarily causing digital
exclusion among elderly, and among which
socioeconomic factors highlight that
the difference in country type education
and math status are key socioeconomic
drivers of digital exclusion.
And the policy interventions
targeting education and mal support
can help bridge the digital gap.
And the component two, which is health
related issues, stress that the physical
and health conditions are significant
barriers to digital inclusion.
And it suggests that the healthcare
support systems that integrate
digital literacy programs are
necessary to bridge this gap.
And the component three, which is age
related limitations, emphasize the role of
age and physical limitations in excluding
individuals from the digital space, and
it recommend age friendly technologies
and accessibility enhancements.
Variations of digital exclusion
between higher income and middle income
countries were identified by square
test, and the result indicate that
there is a strong association between
country type and digital exclusion.
This suggests that digital exclusion
is not evenly distributed across
countries and is strongly influenced
by their economy classification.
Higher income countries have better
digital inclusion due to advanced
infrastructure, affordability and
widespread of digital literacy.
The middle income countries face greater
challenges included, including limited
access to technology, poor infrastructure
and affordability values, which
amplify the digital exclusion rates.
This slide presents the result
of a I square test used to in
investigate the relationship
between age groups of different.
It explores whether the age group
significantly impacts digital inclusion
or exclusion depending on the economy
classification of the country.
The highly significant Kai Square
result confirms that age groups are
associated with digital exclusion,
and this association varies across
higher and middle income countries.
The older age groups in middle income
countries are likely more affected
by digital exclusion compared to
en age groups or their counterparts
in higher income countries.
This could be due to lack of access
to digital technologies, lower digital
literacy among older operations,
or infrastructure and affordability
challenges in middle income countries.
The ANO test was used to find the
variation in the life satisfaction
among digitally secured people
in higher income countries.
And result suggests that there is a
significant difference in the variation
of means across different countries.
And the Austria has reported the higher
rate for the displaced credit people, and
the Estonia has got the lowest rating.
Similarly while comparing the variation
in the life satisfaction among the
digitally excluded people in middle
income countries, the Romania has got
the highest rate, while the India has got
the lowest rate for life satisfaction.
To investigate the impact of digital
exclusion and its interaction with country
in terms of health rating, the two way
an test was performed, and we can see
that the digitally included people in all
other countries, except Mexico is showing
higher rating for health while comparing
to the digitally excluded people.
Final thought.
The digital exclusion has many impacts,
like it reduces access to essential
services, social connections, and banking.
Also, it affects quality of life of.
The key findings include there are
significant disparity in the digital
exclusion rate between higher income
countries and middle income countries
where UK is having only 11 percentage
and is having 91 percentage of people are
digitally excluded, and the socioeconomic
age related and health related
challenges are found to be the primary
con contributors of digital exclusion.
And the successful programs like
Austria's, digital Seniors, and India's
Age digital literacy programs show
promise, but it require expansion and
tailored programs for rural areas and
underserved demographics are also crucial.
The recommendations include expand
digital literacy programs to remote
areas and include affordable devices
and internet access, and focus on most
excluded groups like 75 plus in higher
income countries, and anger and early
groups, inter middle income countries.
Also encourage community based activities
and public private collaborations
to promote technology adoption.
The future research should look into the
cultural and healthcare related aspects
of the digital exclusion and conduct
longitudal studies to track progress and
effectiveness of these interventions.
Collaborative efforts, policy makers and
organizations are essential to bridge the
digital divide and support the elderly.
Thank you all for joining me for the talk.
I truly hope you found it valuable.
It was a pleasure to share my insights
on digital inclusion for elderly users.
If you'd like to continue the conversation
or collaborate in the future, please
feel free to connect with me on LinkedIn.
Also, if you would like to go
further, please check out the
research paper attached for a
deeper dive into the findings.
Looking forward to staying in touch
and exploring new ideas together.