Hi.
Good morning everyone.
I'm Bala pna.
Today I'm going to talk about how Agent
TK is transforming enterprise integration
from being reactive to resilient.
Most modern enterprises confront
significant challenges in maintaining
reliable integrations across increasingly
complex application ecosystems.
As organizations adopt specialized
software solutions, the dependability
of these interconnections.
Directly impacts business continuity
and operational excellence.
This presentation explores how care is
transforming the enterprise application
integration and EDA frameworks through
site reliability engineering principles.
The result is a self-healing, highly
observable integration systems that
substantially improve the key reliability,
metrics, and operational performance.
This is the key for any business success.
Before we dive deep into the agent TKA
framework, I would like to emphasize
the integration challenges that these
enterprises face in today's landscape.
There are three main things that
I would like to highlight on first
scale requirements, the need to manage
growing, number of integration points.
Yes.
every day there is a new language model.
Every day, there are hundreds
of new apps being built.
And these are required for
the business to stay relevant.
And if these are integrated into the
ecosystem, then the integration team
needs to adapt itself and scale itself
to integrate with these new head systems.
Second is the system complexity,
the in intricacy of, integrating
complex heterogeneous and
diverse software ecosystem.
With this growing challenge of
more and more apps being built,
each enterprises has hundreds
and thousands of applications,
interconnected for various reasons.
So these complex ecosystem is a real
challenge for integration teams.
And third is the time sensitivity.
Any failure in integration, and if it
is always connected to any business
critical time, critical interfaces.
It is going to cause a huge
financial loss for the business.
So the business will be always be on
top to fix these integration, failures.
So it is always time critical to
address these integration, challenges.
So these are the three main
challenges the integration team
faces in today's enterprises.
This is where I would like to
propose, the agent TK framework to
resolve these integration challenges.
Let us get into the Agent K framework,
specialist agents, collaborative
intelligence, self-healing systems,
and continuous optimization.
These four components weave together
to make the fabric of the agent K.
In integration specialist agents.
We have task specific problem
specific agents, which takes care of.
Resolving a specific problem and
modeled in such a way that they
don't, overlap with the other agents.
when you put together all these agents in
a workflow, it needs to be overseen by an
orchestrator in aa orchestrator decides.
what agents needs to be involved
in this specific workflow and
they decide and create that
workflow using a workflow agent.
And once that is done, if there are any
issues in this whole business workflow,
we just deduct it and resolve those errors
without any human intervention using the
self-healing system or the remediation,
plan that these orchestrator have.
EA can Hal need.
So we need to put a self-healing
mechanism to ensure and
monitor and detect any issues.
The whole business workflow, can be
optimized by learning new designs, by
learning, the pattern and understanding,
the business workflow that is suitable
for our business and optimized in a.
Best possible way by adhering
to the rules and AI governance.
Let's understand how these agent
aea, correlates with the SRE model.
This slide shows the pillars of
the site, reliability, engineering
model, automation, service level,
objectives, incident management.
Observability capacity planning,
shared responsibility, which all
enhance the service reliability.
This slide resonates with the agent
TK framework where we do automation.
We ensure that the service level
duties are measured and addressed.
the incidents are automatically handled.
We have an observable, highly
observable case where we monitor
and the capacity is planned.
And forecasted and the
responsibilities naturally shatter.
Let us get into the technical architecture
of the agent Dke and understand better
let us get into the technical
architecture and framework of the
A Agents in EEA and EDA piece.
This diagram shows the business
flow and the agent flow.
The business flow has, the external users
communicating to the B2B software, which
internally transforms the data from the
external users, like trading partners,
customer suppliers, or government
agencies and banks, into the, format that
the internal application ERP solutions
CRM solutions require, based on their
own data architecture or the schema.
And that is consumed by those applications
and applies the business logic to.
Or complete the O2 C or P two P or
inventory management or any kind
of, application level business logic
are applied and the corresponding
acknowledgements or the invoices
or the payments or anything is
being rerouted back to the same,
partner in the current framework.
the reports are generated from
these application layer for the
management and stakeholders to
ensure, the forecast is good.
the baseline of the cloud
company is doing good.
All these are happening in today's world.
Over and top of this business
flow, we build an agent workflow.
The customer service agent is the
front end of this whole agent workflow,
which can handle any queries or ments
from both internal and external users.
The customer service agent takes these
requirements, splits it into individual
task, and sends it to the AI orchestrator.
The AI orchestrator consumes
these tasks and, refines it and
send it to the specialist agents.
And each specialization agent
completes the task by connecting to
the corresponding application layer and
ensuring the business logic is implied.
And, completing the whole
any, business processes.
This whole, architecture is
governed by the governance layer.
The governance layer has it,
security, data security, yay.
Governance and policies.
All those are.
based on the corresponding
market that this particular
business is delivering it to,
every data which is being recorded
in this business process is being
stored in the data lake that is
then being refined and again stored
into a training data which trains
these language models and AI agents.
This way, we complete the whole framework
and the continuous, optimization.
continuous, an autonomy and, the, highly
efficient, integration model is being
built using this agent, a framework.
Let's understand its, users
and other functionalities.
In the next slide line,
let us understand the various
specialist agents that are.
Defined in this process.
There could be like several hundreds
of specialist agents that we can build.
one is the validation agent that ensures
the data integrity and SMA schema
compliance in case of, formatted data.
It could be an idoc, it could
be edifact, it could be e an
CX tool or any particular.
Format, that the particular
business use, it could be HEPA
standard or any other standards.
All those are insured in this
validation by this validation agent.
And, translation agents.
Translation agents take care
of transforming the data from
one format to the other format.
The third is the monitoring
and detection agent.
It identifies the anomalies and.
potential failures in different, cases
and ensure the Y agent doesn't hallucinate
or any other process has any bug.
And those bugs are remediated
orchestration agents.
These are agents which takes care
of building this whole workflow
of, collaborative, structure that
multiple agents can work together.
Connector agents are.
To establish a new connection to
your new application, or a new
a system or a new, enterprise to
establish all these connections.
A connector agent can consume whatever
the requirement is, and, generate
the corresponding firewall, changes,
requests, and all those, internal
requirements that are necessary for
completing the connection security agents.
Security agents ensure the security
of all the data security and, user
security by ensuring, that it is
all the data is either encrypted
or decrypted in the right format.
And, similar to, all the cloud native
infrastructure where the IAM module takes
care of the, user, security, even here,
the specialist agents takes care of.
Connecting, user security
and data security.
Similarly, we can build any number of
AI specialized agents, and these AI
agents ensure, to complete a specific
task or resolve a specific problem.
This is a pictor representation
of how agentic workflow in
E-A-A-D-A integration happens.
First, the rating partner
requirements are submitted.
to the customer service agent.
The customer service agents, in its
own natural language processing,
redefines it and marks down as various
steps and send it to the orchestrator.
The, a orchestrator then takes those,
whole checklist and redefines them.
As modular components that will be
assigned to the specialist agent.
From there, if there are any EEA EDA
requirements, the validation agents
ensures that the data or the format
that is required or specified in
the requirements, follow a specific
protocol or specific validation.
From there, there is a technical
processing phase where it evaluates
the best possible optimal.
set up strategy.
The whole, process is being then
implemented, using the corresponding
application and communicated, to the
database for ensuring that the end-to-end
business process flow is completed.
This process flow is being validated
and quality assured by the qualities
assuring agent, and the further data is
being used for training the AA agents.
This is a simple workflow that explains
the EDA integration post implementing
agents in the integration space.
Agent TK implementation in enterprises
do come up with its own challenges,
data privacy, concern being the primary.
One of them organizations are really
worried about the sensitive data
exposure to the AA processing.
Our approach in this architecture uses
federated learning techniques that
allows models to improve without raw
data leaving secure environments, and
we also ensure specialized encryption
techniques are being followed
throughout the business process.
This maintains the compliance
and regulations like global data
privacy regulations and hipaa.
The second is legacy
system integration issues.
Most legacy system doesn't even have
an a PE capability and there are
many limited connectivity, that are
available for these agents to connect.
So ma making these agents work with these
legacy systems is one issue, and these
two are not the primary issues alone.
There could be like a cultural
resistance, there could be also
issues with, other governance issues.
Our approach is not a
big bandwidth method.
Let us go with a phased manner where
you decide and define only a specific
agent where, the organization is
comfortable with, and you expose the only
those data that are not as sensitive,
or not sensitive for this particular
agent, and see how these agents,
explore and provide business value.
I. Based on this approach, we can
definitely, keep scaling these agents
for different, applications and on
a phase manner we should be able to
achieve the highest autonomy levels.
These, agents also enhance the
observability framework, which
is a key pillar of SRE model.
Comprehensive tracing, business
aligned, service level objectives
and predictive alerting.
These are all required for a
successful business to be relevant
and successful in the business.
The end to end visibility in every
transaction is important for ma
various stakeholders, so that has
to be inbuilt in this whole agent
process and business aligned.
service level objectives that
directly reflect business impact
rather than technical metrics,
bridging the gap between IT
performance and business outcomes.
A driven predictive alerting based on
understanding the data and business
flow and completely training the
previous transactions, help and
enhance the observability framework.
Another feature of this whole, agent
TK is self-healing capabilities.
First is the anomaly detection where
whenever there is an, hallucination
in the GT K or if there is an issue
with the business process flow,
this whole infrastructure takes
care of identifying those anomalies
and deduct it, automatically.
And then identifies what caused these
anomalies by root cast analysis.
And that provides a list of checklists
that needs to be done for remediation and
that is handled in an automatic fashion.
And this whole process is logged
in our knowledge base so that
the next, agent or any other.
Business process doesn't face the same
issue again, and the remediation step
can be implemented wherever is required.
This health healing capability
enhances this whole integration
process, to your new level of SRE.
This chart shows post implementation
of Agent TK in different sectors
in our evaluation metrics and.
It shows that healthcare has 87% financial
services has 94%, manufacturing has 79%.
Retail has 82%.
Logistic has 91% improvement.
this helps patient care efficient
processing time, reducing the
waste, improving the sales,
improving and optimizing the
supply chain in various sectors.
This definitely shows that implementing
the agent TK in any sector is a boom.
These are the key metrics that are
recorded post the implementation of
Agent K in application integration,
92% reduction in MTTR 78% fewer
incidents and 320% throughput
increase, and 99.99% system uptime.
These are impressive numbers and this will
definitely drive business to implement
Agent K in enterprise integration.
All these values, definitely impact
the, business baseline and make
the business more competitive.
These metrics definitely prove a
point that agent TK is the future
of integration and a business
will reap benefit out of it.
If you have any further questions
regarding implementation of these
agent TKA in enterprise integration,
you can always reach me at my email.
Id thank you for attending this session.
Bye.