Hello everyone.
Welcome back.
So today we are going to
talk about the Salesforce
integration and the capabilities.
So these days the fortune
hundred companies are also
using the Salesforce integration
capabilities in a enhanced way.
So we are going to discuss what
are the integration patterns and,
what is the Salesforce architecture
that we are going to use for all
these integrations on a brief?
So let's get started.
So Salesforce integration landscapes
this is how the Salesforce integration
landscape on a high level would look like.
So Salesforce and the external system,
if they would like to connect to each
other that's where the integration
landscape comes in the picture, right?
So a p architecture is one of the main
key thing that comes into the picture.
And if there is a middleware
that we would like to use between
these two systems, and good.
We can go ahead and use that
middleware integration system.
The recommended way is to have a
middleware integration always in
place because in case tomorrow the
example Ative system goes away, then we
don't need to do a rework in between.
So that's where the middleware
integration comes in the picture.
And realtime capabilities.
So we can share the data between
two systems using the platform,
events, change, data capture, and the
streaming a p for the minimal latency.
So we have security in place or
authentication is the security
and enforced by TLS encryption
and multi-tenancy architecture
has been implemented in
Salesforce that you all know.
So this ecosystem encompasses
multiple technologies and approaches
designed to address various
integration scenarios, right?
There is a framework that allows
enterprise to connect the Salesforce
with virtually any external system.
Meanwhile, they maintain
the security as well.
And the, all the solutions that
we will be providing is scalable.
So that's how the landscape
would look like on a high level.
So let's move on to the next slide,
how the architecture look like.
So it's com it's a composite of API and
bulk API and soap interest APIs, right?
These are the combinations that we have
when we talk about the architecture.
So Salesforce a p architecture implements
a restful design, so that supports
both simple and complex integration.
So we use restful designs as of today in
every, all of the systems, which is good.
So this will handle a complex integration
patterns as well that you already know.
Bulk API is something that is available
in Salesforce where it helps to have.
A huge data transferred to a different
system or an external system.
So mostly the bulk KPI is a scheduled job
that gets triggered at the night times in
order not to disrupt the business business
functionality in the business time, right?
So this is where a bulk API comes
into the picture, and we can use this.
A method to transfer
a huge amount of data.
When we talk about large volumes,
this is the technique that
comes into the picture, right?
And then rest and soap, APIs as,
and when the data gets created and
it has to be synced with the other
system, that is when the rest and
soap API comes into the picture.
So that is about the high level of
architecture of APIs in Salesforce, right?
So performance measurement framework.
So we have to measure the
performance of each and a every API.
Otherwise the page loads of a user will
be drastically impacting the performance.
So we have to be very careful and these
are the techniques that we have to measure
a performance of an API and the page
loading time so that we know that we are
in time and the performance is good by
looking at these measurements, right?
So the first step is the page request
and then the server processing time, dom
processing time, and then EPT calculation.
So this overall thing comes into
the measurement framework where
everything is measured and we are
gonna take a call whether the a
p performance is accurate or not.
If the a p has to be the performance
of the a p has to be increased, it has
to be increased by certain, changes
to the code and we could remeasure the
changes over here using this technique.
And let's delve in deep one by one.
So the experience page time metric
provides a comprehensive view of page
performance, helping organizations
identify and resolve bottlenecks.
EPT measures the complete user
experience from initial request
to fully interactive page.
Salesforce Lightning
component framework includes.
Built in performance analysis tools that
track component rendering times, server
round trips and JavaScript execution.
These metrics enable developers to
optimize critical path and improve overall
application responsiveness for end users.
So end users are the main things
where we consider the solution
for, so we talked about the
middleware integrations while back.
So here we come.
Salesforce has a inbuilt MuleSoft
integration capability implemented.
So wherever we have a Salesforce
product so we can go ahead and use
the MuleSoft as well as a middleware.
So which will have integrated patterns
already exist between these two systems.
So the integration will be too easy
to establish and all the patterns
are already pre, pre-established
between these two systems, right?
So any point platform.
We also have Anypoint platform serves
as Salesforce strategic middleware
solution, providing a unified environment
for designing, building, managing
integrations across the enterprise Design
Center for a P LED connectivity exchange
for reusable assets and templates.
Runtime manager for
deployment control, right?
Deployment.
Flexibility is also one of the key
points that we are going to discuss.
Enterprises can deploy MuleSoft
integrations in various
environments to meet the specific
requirements and constraints.
Club hub for fully managed deployment
runtime fabric for Kubernetes environments
on premises for data zone view needs.
MuleSoft a p led connectivity
approach promotes a reusability
through three layers of API
systems, processes, and experience.
These structure methodology
enables organizations to build.
A network of interconnected APIs
that can be combined to create
new business capabilities without
redundant integration work.
So prebuilt connector framework
that we have already discussed.
So we have app exchange connectors,
MuleSoft connectors, and external
services, third party applications
with prebuilt integrations
certified by Salesforce, right?
So these are the third party applications
that are certified by Salesforce and.
These are an apps that will be available
from the app exchange where we can
download and use the capabilities,
but mostly these will be paid apps
providing turnkey connectivity to popular
enterprise systems like Zap, Oracle, and
Microsoft Dynamics, mules of connectors.
Over 300 pre-built connectors
for applications, protocols and
services featuring standardized
the connection, handling,
authentication and error management.
So external services, low-code
approach to integrate with REST APIs
directly from flow builder, allowing
business analyst to incorporate
external services without custom codes.
So Salesforce connector ecosystem
dramatically reduces integration
complexity and time to market
for common integration scenarios.
Each connector encapsulates
best practices for interacting
with sales specific systems.
Handling authentication rate limiting
and protocol specific requirements
for custom integration needs.
Developers can leverage extension
points in connector framework to build
specialized adapters while inheriting
core platform capabilities like logging,
monitoring, and security control.
So let's go to the next slide.
Alright, so this is the real
time integration architecture,
how it looks like, right?
So we talked about platform events,
apex triggers, data capture.
And then streaming APIs.
So these are the different realtime
integration architecture patterns
that we have in Salesforce, right?
When we talk about platform events
it can be customized schema defined
events for business processes.
Apex triggers custom logic
execution on data changes.
Okay?
C, d, C change your data, capture, record
level changes, tracking and broadcasting.
So whenever the records gets
updated, create or deleted.
So the changes will be broadcasted to
the external system streaming a PA long
polling for near real time notifications.
So however the streaming works in the
external system, the similar patterns
streaming a PA would also work.
Salesforce, even driven architecture,
enables a realtime integration scenarios
with minimal latency platform events.
Provide a published subscribe
model for custom business events.
While change data capture automatically
publishes records changes to the
subscribed system, so change data captures
will only publish to the systems where
the system subscribe to the changes.
Alright, the streaming a p
supports scenarios requiring
immediate notifications of change
through a long polling mechanism
for high throughput scenarios.
The high volume platform events,
features scale to millions of events.
Per day with guaranteed delivery
and replay capabilities.
Next, go to the next slide.
So we are going to discuss about
the security and governance
framework here, right?
Security.
We know that we have an
authentication in place.
We have different authentications, what
JWT and saml supports and authorization.
We have profile based permissions
and connected app controls.
And encryption is followed as TSL
encryption and Salesforce shield
platform encryption is also available.
But this Salesforce shield is a
additional security measure that we can
purchase from Salesforce and monitoring.
So like we discussed the platform events
so that even monitoring and real time,
even monitoring can also be happening.
So security is a foundational to
Salesforce integration architecture.
That platform implements what 2.0 for
secure delegated access with support for
various flows including web services.
User agent j, WT barrier,
and SAM assertion.
Connected apps will provide a
governance framework for external
integrations with the granular control
over a p access IP restrictions and
session policies for monitoring.
Even monitoring captures detail logs
of API usage while shield platform
encryption protects the sensitive data
with the tenant specific encryption keys.
So for connected apps we have a different
framework in place for authentication.
So we have connected app framework
where we create a connected app
for every external system, and then
authentication will be declared
at the connected app level.
So how scalable and the
performance of Salesforce would be.
The bulk api, like we discussed, if
there is a huge volume of data, we would
like to transfer between two systems.
Yes.
Bulk API is the one, and this
is the limitations that we have.
Rest.
A API is this platform.
Events is having a more capability and
streaming API is having a less capability.
Salesforce's multi-tenant architecture
incorporates sophisticated mechanisms
for scaling integration workloads.
The platforms govern limits in force or
fair usage across tenants while allowing
for high throughput through optimized API.
Patterns, like we discussed for high
volume scenarios, bulk API is the
pattern that we are going to choose.
And within the bulk API, we have an
option to choose the batch stage.
So based on the batch size the number
of records will be process processed
in the batches and all the batches.
Batches will be processed in parallel.
So that is one of the major advantage.
So the best practices that we have
is a PLA design implement system,
process experience, API layer
to maximize the reusability and
minimize point to point dependency.
So batch versus realtime analysis
is something that we have we need
to carefully evaluate the latency
requirements to choose appropriate
integration design pattern.
So if there is a huge data that
has to be transmitted, we should
never go to the realtime analysis.
Rather, we should check with
business to see if a batch is a
best best option for them, right?
So that the latency doesn't
come into the picture.
And then performance testing.
Conduct load testing under various
conditions to identify bottlenecks
and establish a reliable throughput
metrics for production planning,
error handling and recovery.
Implement comprehensive logic, dead letter
cues, and monitoring alerts to ensure
resilience against intermittent failures.
Successful Salesforce integrations
require careful planning and
adherence to establish patterns.
API LED connectivity provides a structured
approach that promotes reuse and reduces
technical deck while proper separation
of synchronization and a synchronous
processes prevents performance bottle mix.
Comprehensive error handling is
essential for production reliability,
including retry mechanisms with
the exponential back of dead letter
queues for manual intervention, and
detailed logging for troubleshooting.
Regular performance testing
helps identify potential issues
before they impact end users.
Alright, so the key takeaways and
the next steps would be architectural
assessment is one of the key
takeaways, technical implementation,
and then performance optimization.
So evaluate your current
integration landscape against
Salesforce best practices.
Identify opportunities to
implement API led connectivity.
And reduce point to point
dependencies that limit scalability.
So technical implementation.
Start with small, well-defined
integration project build capabilities.
Establish standard for error handling,
logging and monitoring before
scaling to more complex scenarios.
Performance optimization.
Implement comprehensive monitoring
for your integration points.
Use EPT metrics to identify and
resolve the bottlenecks that we
have discussed in slide three.
Focusing on high impact the customer
facing processes first, right?
Salesforce integration capabilities
continue to evolve rapidly
with the new features released
in each seasonal updates.
Stay informed through release notes
and trailhead models, and considered
certification parts for technical
team members to deepen expertise.
Remember that successful indication
strategies balance immediate business
needs with long-term AL goals.
By leveraging Salesforce comprehensive
integration platform, organizations
can build the connected experiences
that scale effectively while
maintaining security and performance.
So these are the key take
takeaways that we have.
And thank you so much
guys for hanging around.
I hope you enjoyed this talk.
Please let me know for any questions.
Feel free to ping me on my LinkedIn.
If you have any other questions or
if you are aspirant of Salesforce
integrations or Salesforce or ecosystem,
please do ping me on my LinkedIn.
I am happy to help so that we
grow together as a network.
Alright, thank you.
Thank you all.