Hi everyone.
Hope everyone is doing great.
I'm Ja Krishna having more than 14
years of experience in IT industry
in implementing the high volume, high
performance, large scale investment
products using databases like Oracle
Cyber, snowflake Cloud, stuff like Azure.
A-W-S-D-V-T have a strong expertise
in front back trading applications on.
How they work, how users performs
their reconciliation process for
the regulatory and reporting needs.
As part of my job responsibilities,
I was primarily involved in building
up multiple application using on-prem
and hybrid and cloud technologies
with very strong domain knowledge.
Today we're gonna talk.
Cloud-based reconciliation
system and investment banking.
Let's get into that.
So the investment banking
industry operates on very massive
scale of data processing like
millions of transactions daily.
I. Accurate and timely
consideration of financial data
is essential for compliance, risk
management, and decision making.
This presentation will explore the
transmitted power of cloud-based
reconciliation applications
and the impact in the industry.
First, I wanted to just say few
challenges about the traditional
reconciliation process.
So traditional reconciliation
process is time consuming where
there's so much of manual effort.
While performing data analysis,
preparation of sheets, initiating
the data, and then performing
that matching of the transaction.
And I, in fact, the dispen and
preparation of reports, everything
is time consuming because most of the
things are manual and this can lead to.
In closing the periods,
one is human error.
Any kind of manual intervention
increases the scope of error like
data entry, mistakes missing some
transaction, incorrect data matching.
These error can result in
discrepancies and potential.
To inaccurate financial statements.
Next, this joint systems legacy
systems often work in isolation where
different departments or outside
partners use separate softwares.
This fragmentation makes it difficult
to get unified view of financial data.
And delayed information.
Legacy reconciliation process mostly
operates on batching of the data
updates, which means financial data
is not real time, which results
in not making decisions on time
without, and they have to perform
the reconciliation without data.
Information and difficulty in audits.
With all these problems like daily
data, human errors, design systems
there is more chances of failing
in audits, which again redo all the
process, filling kids a course time.
So this is the current challenges which
currently legacy systems are facing.
So I'm gonna talk key features
of the modern reconciliation.
One is automated data matching.
The cloud-based platforms automate
the process of matching transactions
from multiple sources such as banks,
counterpart, custodians, trend,
tradition, and some trading platforms.
The system.
Internal records with external records
like ledge systems and bank systems,
some statements and it flags any
kind of expenses for further review.
By setting up some rules and
real time data synchronization,
cloud technology allows.
Data to be seen and updated in real time.
This means that as invent transaction
hackers, they're immediately
reconciled with the corresponding
records from other systems or tions.
It significantly speed up the
reconci concession process and
integration with multiple systems.
So cloud-based reconciliation platform
can seamlessly integrate with various
internal and external systems.
Such as, so systems accounting,
softwares, custodian devices,
which provides a unified view of
financial transactions at one place.
And finally, reporting analytics.
Cloud-based systems typically
have powerful reporting tools
and analytical capabilities.
These tools allow forms to generate
comprehensive reports on their
reconciliation process and spot potential
issues early or very near real time.
These are few core components of
cloud-based reconciliation architecture,
which we can talk about now.
So one is data addition layer.
The system employs advanced APIs and
connectors to ingested data from multiple
sources, including trade confirmation,
settling, transaction, and market data.
Ted, the next.
Step is transformation engine.
So this ETL process standardize,
andries the ingested data
through automated workflows.
And once the data has been transformed,
as per the business needs, the
reconciliation engine kicks off with
high performance matching engine
employees, the configurable rules
and algorithms to perform multi
reconciliation across the data sources.
Once the reconciliation
engine finishes his.
Reconciliation process that the final
step is reporting and analytics.
The reporting layer leverages the
business intelligence capabilities to
generate real time dashboards, regulated
reports, and predictive analytics
that drives operational improvements.
So these are some technical
features and performance mat
metrics, which we came across.
So when we implement past three years on
before implementation, what was our thing?
And after implementation of cloud-based
reconciliation what was our metrics.
So it, it includes three
years exception handling time.
Which came down from th around
360 minutes, which is six,
six hours to 18 minutes.
So we can see the improvement and
automatic batch rate, system availability.
We know that cloud system have.
99.99% down to system availability
where we can have region specific
SY systems configured and then
system up time, everything.
It's that technical architecture
leverages microservices with so
many descriptive services, each
maintaining independent scaling
capabilities with guaranteed uptake.
And these are.
How the data quality.
Quality of data is really important in
any of these reconciliation systems.
How we perform the data quality over here.
First you perform data validation.
So new rule network based engines achieve
99.8% accuracy while processing, or
15 million transactions per second.
And then standardization, quantum
resistant encryption enabled
secure standardization across.
300 plus different source
systems monitoring realtime
system detect lys with 99.95.
Nine six accuracy with
50 microseconds Adoption.
Reinforcement learning reduces
implementation time from
weeks to just four plus hours.
The process automation segment in
financial reconciliation has grown.
So much between 21 to 23, reaching
market value of 89.5 billion.
These are some stats, which
we got it from multiple
systems
and regulatory compliance and automation.
Automated reporting processing over 5.2
million regulated reports daily across
1 32 due with almost a hundred percent
accuracy, reducing complaints, relative
operational cost with 78% documentation
management, advanced MI algorithms.
Process 12.3 petabytes of compliance
data daily with travel time, average
35 milliseconds and maintaining a
hundred percent accuracy and emissions.
So even if you see audit trials.
Our blockchain based systems enable
immutable record keeping of 15.7
billion daily events with a guaranteed
detention period of 10 years.
Instant access for regulator inquiries.
So these are some more metrics about
scalability and performance capabilities
in cloud-based reconciliation system.
So at a peak we can get like 12.8
million transaction process per second
during peak up peak covers where
so much data is being streaming.
And even during that time we have 99.9999.
Percent system up and more
than 5.4 million conent.
You just can, be supported across all
over the globe, which is 1 4, 7 countries.
And the system latency is like 12
milliseconds, maintained even at
25 million transactions per minute.
This modern installation platform utilizes
quantum inspired algorithms have achieved.
Super scalability.
Elastic computing resources
automatically provision across 27
global regions within 800 milliseconds
of detecting the demand spikes while
maintaining sub millisecond latency.
So when it comes to implementation,
operation considerations, so
when we use cloud infrastructure.
Almost ev.
Almost every institution now is erupt
into the current cloud and then hybrid
multi-cloud strategy, and then user
training, 96% certification rate
within first quarter of the deployment.
Disaster query.
Active configuration across
five geographic regions.
Support structure.
A augmented systems resolve
92% of incidents automatically.
Yeah.
Financial organizations maintain
an average of 2,840 cloud native
application with reconciliation
platforms requiring integration across
hundred and 67 different systems.
And 89 external services delegate.
18.5% of the Total IT budget for
the transformation initiatives
with change management programs
typically involves 1500 thousand
end users across 45 countries.
So let's think about
our future directions.
Yay, artificial.
In the next generation, AI transforms.
Reconciliation through intelligent
pattern recognition methods
advanced a complex matching while.
Real time anomaly detection prevents
errors before the impact operations,
reducing manual intervention by up to 85%.
And then the blockchain technology
enhances financial reconciliation
by providing a decentralized ledger.
This increases transaction
transparency and fraud production,
and data analytics and visualization.
Real time analytics dashboards unlock.
The actionable insights from
reconciliation, data, interactive
visualization, spotlight trends and
bottlenecks, while predictive model
focus, potential issues enabling proactive
optimization of reconciliation workflows.
Let's conclude.
So of after looking into all these
stats, going through multiple comparison
between legacy and reconciliation legacy
and future based and con cloud based
reconciliation application, it has.
A revolution moment for investment banking
operations by introducing sophisticated
automation, enhanced accuracy,
and robust complaints mechanisms.
These systems have demonstrated
their capital to handle complex
reconciliation process while maintaining.
High levels of security
and operational efficiency.
As the financial sector continues
to embrace digital transformation,
reconciliation platforms will evolve
further in Inc. Incorporating emerging
technologies and addressing new challenges
in the investment banking landscape.
The successful implementation of
these solutions has proven crucial for
maintaining data integrity, operation
efficiency, and competitive advantage.
Thank you so much for
giving me this opportunity.
Hope this gives you some insight
on how current cloud-based
reconciliation, investment banking
evolves, how it'll be in the future.
I hope you have a very wonderful day.
Thank you.