Hi, welcome everyone to the Reliability
Engineering 2025 conference.
I'm Bawan Carta.
I'm a specialist leader at Deloitte's
AI and cloud engineering practice.
Today I will be talking about the
interesting topic of integrating
AI into cloud platforms and
provide a roadmap for enterprises.
Looking to undertake this journey.
So we'll start with a quick
introduction into these topics.
So the fusion of artificial
intelligence and cloud computing is
reshaping the enterprise landscape and
offering unprecedented opportunities
for innovation efficiency.
And, competitive advantage.
So far, businesses this is no longer
just a optional transformation, but
it's more of a strategic initiative.
However, the journey of integrating
these two technologies is is
complex and has its own challenges.
So it requires careful
planning robust architectures.
Also a clear understanding
of operational challenges.
So this talk aims to provide a detailed
roadmap for enterprises that are aiming to
integrate AI into their cloud ecosystems.
Next, we'll move on to the next slide.
So why does AI and cloud
integration matter?
The synergy between AI and cloud computing
is a game changer for enterprises.
Cloud platforms provide the
scalable infrastructure needed
to train and deploy AI models.
While AI enhances the cloud capabilities
with intelligent automation predictive
analytics, and real time decision making.
So together these two technologies
can enable organizations to accelerate
their innovation cycle optimize
operational efficiency as well as gain
actionable insights from vast data sets.
However this process is
not without its challenges.
There are a lot of issues related to data
governance, model management, and talent
shortages that need to be addressed before
we can take advantage of the integration
of these two technologies, please.
So next we will look into why
building the right architecture.
Is key to enabling this integration.
So many organizations operate in hybrid
or multi-cloud environments to avoid
vendor lock-in and to optimize costs.
Integrating AI into these setups requires
a unified architecture that ensures
seamless data flow and model deployment.
Using strategies such as, open standards
Kubernetes for interoperability as
well as implementing a data fabric
to enable consistent data access.
And this combined with emerging
technologies such as edge computing,
serverless computing these are
going to enable organizations to
have the foundational framework
and the architecture required
to support this integration.
Also importantly, AI
integration must align with the
enterprise business objectives.
A use case driven approach ensures
that these AI initiatives are not
just technology playbooks, but that
they deliver tangible value as well.
Next we will move on to look
at what are the key challenges.
In that we see in this journey
and how to overcome them.
So AI models typically
rely on high quality data.
So enterprises must establish robust
data governance to ensure data privacy,
but also to critical things such
as security, compliance, et cetera.
So key strategies here include
implementing data lineage.
And using automated tools for data
cleaning and pre-processing, et cetera.
And on top of that it's also
critical to have lifecycle management
capabilities for all of the machine
learning operational readiness, right?
This includes things such as version
control, CICD pipelines and real
time monitoring of the performance
of these models and keeping track
of them to enhance them further.
Last, but not the least
is the talent strategy.
Enterprises must invest in upskilling
existing employees and attracting
specialized talent to support AI and
cloud integration initiatives to bridge
the skill gap that currently exists.
So now that we spoke about
the foundational components.
Next we'll look at a step-by-step roadmap
for enterprises looking to undertake
the cloud AI integration journey.
So this is divided into a logical
phases four phases that will
help organizations reach their
transformation goals in a phased manner.
Phase one here we start with,
building the foundations.
These include things such as assessing
the AI maturity and identifying like
the high impact use cases, establishing
data governance that we discussed
previously and also, selecting the
cloud platforms and vendors that
align with the enterprise goals and
with those foundational capabilities.
Next you can move on to the pilot
deployment, which would include,
development and deployment of the
pilot AI models for selected use cases.
And then on top of that,
implementing the ML ops pipelines
and practices for model management.
And then also being able to
evaluate the model and fine tune
the model for performance as needed.
Once the pilot deployment is
successful, then organizations can
look into scaling and optimization.
This would involve scaling successful
pilots across different line of
businesses within the enterprise,
optimizing the architecture for cost,
performance, scalability, et cetera.
And also integrating emerging technologies
like edge computing, serverless and so on.
And the last phase would
involve continuous improvement.
This is where the scaled model
has to be monitored and all
the KPIs track diligently.
So that, any process improvements,
any technology related improvements
can be monitored and can be
incorporated facilitating continuous
improvement into the whole framework.
Now that we've looked at how
organizations can take a phase approach
to reach their transformation goals
in terms of AI and cloud integration.
Now we'll quickly look at what
the future holds for this area.
So the integration of AI and cloud
integration is very much a evolving
field with several emerging trends
that are set to shape its future.
Ai cloud cloud management using
AI tools which uses AI to optimize
cloud resource allocation.
Then we have, federated learning which.