Hi all.
This is thank you for joining my talk.
Today I am discuss human AI sym
robotics, which is revolutionizing
the precision in collaborative
systems with datadriven advancements.
The human ai Symbi Robotics is
transforming the collaborative systems
through continuous feedback loops that
enhances both the human creativity and
the artificial intelligence capabilities.
Today, I'm going to present that
explores how these revolutionized.
Systems which is has high impact on
high position fields such as surgery.
And it also helps in integrating
the multimodal perception.
It helps in our medical predictions.
It helps in the bidirectional
interfaces and physical actuation.
In this topic, we'll examine the
measurable improvements in these
surgical outcomes, challenges in
the implementations, and the future
potential of these technologies
which spans across various domains.
Coming to the next slide,
today we are going to discuss
about the architecture of the
human AI symbiotic systems.
It's on the kind of pial structure
where we have shown the, a diagram there
is multimodal perception which is the
advanced sensor fusion technologies.
And then there comes the
AI prediction engines.
Machine learning algorithms.
There is physical actuators, which
has the precision mechanical response
systems, and there comes the bidirectional
interfaces, which consist of the
seamless human AI communication channels.
The foundation of these symbiotic
robotics reached on these
four integrated subsystems.
Advanced sensor fusion helps in
collecting the environmental data
while the machine learning gets the
feedback from the real time data.
It helps in making the computational
decisions into physical actions and
also increases the accuracy up to 94.2.
We have given a use case
for applications here.
We have used the different parameters in
terms of the metrics the decision latency
reduction it helps in the faster surgical
making decisions, thereby increasing
the productivity up to almost 58.4%.
Then there comes the position improvement
where we are dealing with the enhanced
tissue MA manipulation accuracy, and
that comes around almost 29 7% accuracy.
And then there is also the
complication reduction and we are
seeing a significant reduce in
the minor surgical complications.
And that will be around 41.2%.
And also there is average reduction
in the patient stay duration.
So almost eight.
So these surgical platforms based on
the AI has demonstrated significant
improvements in the clinical outcomes.
The it also enhances the surgical
capabilities by providing the real time
guidance and precision instrument control.
Therefore it helps in the just
technological and for the better
experience from the patient perspective.
We have given some diagram, which
consist of different parameters
unnecessary movements total.
Cognitive load and task performance.
We have just try to give this metrics.
So these symbiotic systems practically
improve workflow efficiency
across multiple dimensions.
Almost 25% reduction in unnecessary
instrument movements coupled with
around almost 19.3% decrease in the
total demonstrates how AI optimization
streamlines technical execution.
These systems reduces the
cognitive load by almost 28.4%.
This gives these a lot of help in terms of
the critical decision making rather than
mechanical execution of the routine task.
This use case helps in achieving
the superhuman position.
But there are also human limitations
these surgeons are facing.
Like a lot of issues in the
terms of the micro surgeries.
There can be a natural hand
framer or there is like
induced position degradation.
Visual perception limitations, and
when this system integrate with the
ai the, basically the AI robotic
capabilities enhances this limitations.
There are barriers, tre
filtering and the motion scaling.
There is enhanced visual
feedback with the magnification.
Then submillimeter positions
consistently are maintained in the most
demanding microsurgical applications.
AI assisted robotic systems have
demonstrated capabilities that
exceed expert human performance.
These position enables the surgical
possibilities which are previously
considered too risky and for the patients.
These AI robotic capabilities help since
it's numerous on in this surgery field.
There are also lot of
technical challenges.
We have to deal with latency management
intent prediction and safety.
Though it has really advanced the systems
uht around 5,200 milliseconds in terms of
the critical performance in the critical
applications we, in order to reduce these,
we have, we need further innovations
in terms of the communication protocol
and the com computational architecture.
So in case of the intent prediction, our
current algorithms achieve almost 94.2%
accuracy in predictable scenarios, but
struggle with noble situations and expert
level technique that devi from different
training patterns and safety verification
perspective, formal verification of the.
Systems remains challenging
here, so we have to add up the
AI human collaborative systems.
Bidirectional learning.
I have some here.
There are different forms like human
expertise which provides intuition
creativity and the judgment capabilities.
Then it'll be the human learning.
Hydrogen again, various insights from the
previous decision making AI capabilities.
Then the AI enhancements
also comes into picture.
So the system improves precision
and the Integr collective expertise.
Then the knowledge transfer, so
the techniques are already captured
and encoded into the AI models.
So these systems continuously help in the
bidirectional learning where the humans
and the AI both are mutually improving.
And surgeon also teach the
system their techniques.
While also gathering the necessary
feedback in terms of the AI capabilities.
So this is basically a
bidirectional learning capabilities.
Both the AI and the
are collaborating with.
So there are various multimodal
communication interfaces there.
One is voice control which
consists of the natural language
commands and confirmations.
Then there is gauge tracking.
So the eye movement monitoring
for attention based control.
Helps in the gauge tracking and then
there is the gesture recognition.
Hand and the body movement
interpretation falls under this
and the he haptic feedback.
This will be basically the force
and the tactile sensation delivery.
So these channels has drastically
reduced in terms of the in cognitive
workload almost reduction around 32.6%.
And around improvement of
28% in the tax performance.
These interfaces create more in, I.
By leveraging the natural communication
modes and the providing ens feedback.
The most effective systems here
adapt to the different users
and preferences and needs.
This helps in switching, the multimodal
communication interface, which is.
Then there comes the ethical
framework for the integration
here, the autonomy and the control.
Establishing clear boundaries
for ai, decision making
authority while maintaining
the meaningful human oversight.
And then there is data privacy.
In these developing protocols for
responsible collection and use of
surgical data while ensuring appropriate
patient consent and the revolution
responsibility attribution it'll
help in creating the frameworks for.
Determining the accountability
when the outcomes involve the human
AI collaborative decisions the
access and the equity addressing
disparities in availability of
advanced surgical technologies across
healthcare systems and geographical
regions to prevent the quality gaps.
But we have to consider this in terms
of the ethical guidance to see whether
this integration will be ethically
integrate into this AL practice.
It'll create the trust among the
patients and the practitioners
and the regularity bodies.
We can also use in different
applications apart from surgery.
We can use this in the different
domains like industrial manufacturing
which always need the precision.
And it's a complex environment, so
it's basically needs the flexibility.
We also can explain this use case in
the, space exploration which art space,
latency compensation with the remote
operations and the disaster response.
So in case of any difficult environment
intervention with the human judgment
and then there comes this scientific
research so micro nanoscale
manipulation with the, human creativity.
So these principles and the
technologies developed for the
surgical applications are finding
new homes across diverse domains,
each feel presence, unique challenges
for these human AI collaborations.
But all can be made mutually beneficial.
And these applications can be
span across multiple domains.
It's a multi-billion
dollar industries, but.
In major kit takeaway from
this top the symbiotic future.
So it's miserable impact human AI
symbiotic systems have demonstrated ative,
improvements in this iCal outcomes almost
the precision increased to almost 30% and
the complication reductions to almost 32%.
And it's actually continuous evolving.
We are just doing the ongoing research
in the bidirectional learning and
the multimodal interface in terms of
the latency and intent prediction.
And there is also complement capabilities.
So the most successful implementations
leverage the strengths of the human
intuition and the machine precisions.
And we can be on the surgical settings.
We can expand this to the different
domains like space industry disaster
management had the human judgment and the
mission positions must seamlessly combine.
Here our goal is not to replace human with
ai, but just key takeaway is to combine
the human in the AI symbiotic robotics.
And it is needs to be a
collaborative environment.
So where the, humans or nations could
accomplish anything independently.
Thank you all.