Speaker 35: Hello everyone and welcome.
I'm Yuri Sak.
I'm head of Strategic
Projects at Lion Cell Global.
Today I'll be sharing with you
my knowledge on proactive SRE
for AI driven personalization.
Based on my experience in telco
churn models and grocery pro
engines, I build this over my career.
And now I am using this knowledge
in wealth tech business activity.
So let's move on.
This is just quick about me.
So I am now working at a digital
asset wealth manager serving
high net worth individuals.
Before I was working at Vion,
which is one of the largest telco
globally, and McKinsey is one of the
largest management consultancies.
I led.
Personalization and commercial analytics
project for major telcos and large
retailers across CIS and Southeast Asia.
And today I will be talking about the
problem that I think is going to become
one of the defining SRE challenges.
Over the next few years, how do you
build reliable, proactive SR practices
for AI driven personalization systems?
Especially when your client base is
tiny and the stakes are enormous.
The other congregation is black
swan events that supposed to be very
infrequent but actually happening and
it can destroy your models overnight.
The core problem that I'm addressing this
speech is the traditional system failures.
They are loud.
It's a 500 error, a timeout, a crash.
So your monitoring catches it instantly.
Tell Earth fire, everyone mobilizes
and the MTTR is measured in hours.
Know that it's broken and
you just go and fix it.
However, AI personalization failures,
they're completely different.
They are silent.
Model drift happens gradually.
So feature DK creeps in stale,
embedding star producing sub
clear on recommendations, and
the dashboard still stays.
Green Laing fine, error rate is zero.
Availability is a hundred percent.
But underneath your recommendation,
quality is slowly degrading.
And client lifetime value
can drop one 2% per month.
So nobody notices in a
quarter, even half a year.
But at certain moment, you will
realize that the quality has degraded
and it's either going to be a client
complaint or on just a quarterly review.
You will see the poor performance and
you already lost months in revenue
and possibly you lost a client.
In addition to that there are.
Multiple black swan events that keep
happening and also impacting a lot your
quality of your models in personalization.
For example, October 25, the crypto
market experienced largest auto
de leveraging cascade in history.
$19 billion been liquidated
outta which 3 billion, right?
In, in just 60 seconds.
Imagine that.
So every model is trained on a
normal market conditions and.
The recommendation it can produce
in such situations can be completely
opposite to what normal people
should be recommending, and it might
negatively impact the client behavior.
Similarly, February,
2026, BTC crashed 44%.
It's, negative six sigma move.
So something that should be
happening every 14,000 years
according to a normal distribution.
So again, personalization models, they.
Assume normal liquidity.
So they assume normal market conditions.
They don't assume such a
negative situation that was never
experienced before in the market.
Hence the recommendation that it come
can come into clients can be completely
wrong and, but you can see that in
the both cases, the system completely
working engineering is fine, but the
business logic models, assumptions
about the market, regime, correlations,
liquidity catastrophically wrong.
So no traditional monitoring
would have caught it.
Okay, so what actually transfers
from Telco and retail to WealthTech?
The answer is that it's quite a lot.
So let's start with Telco.
The first is a next best
action engine which is basic.
Which offer to show to which
subscriber that transfers directly
to which fund allocation you
would recommend to which client.
Next is shorten prediction.
It becomes client attrition, risk scoring.
Next is a RPU uplift.
This becomes pure client LTV optimization.
And lastly, real time decisioning becomes
real time portfolio adjustment signals.
What transfers from retail.
Personalized promotion map that moves
to investment opportunity highlighting
then basket analysis which is customer
who bought X typically bought Y.
This becomes clients with BTC,
let's say, exposure that may benefit
from our market neutral strategy.
Now.
Then markdown optimization actually
transfers into fee waivers and
you use it for retention purposes.
And ROI on these models is very real.
NBA deployments next best
in telco achieving two and
a half times A RPU uplift.
For example.
And this frameworks,
they transfers directly.
But, and this is critical.
What doesn't transfer is the assumption
of large sample sizes that you can
use to train these models as well
as fast feedback and easy a testing.
Because in wealth management you have
a small number of clients, let's say
50 clients, and in such conditions
you cannot use their typical machine
model, machine learning models.
So when number of clients equals,
let's say 50 standard personalization
methods doesn't work anymore.
You can't run ab tests,
you can't run build.
Machine learning models and
feedback slopes are very slow.
So what works instead?
There are four approaches
that you can use.
So first is a Ian method.
You start with your prior hypothesis
from telco or retail experience
and then update it sequentially,
which each client direction.
So second is Thompson sampling.
You balance exploration
with exploitation nature.
That performs well even
with the tiny sample sizes.
Third, which is unique for the
small number of clients, wealth
management, is using the relationship
manager as a human sensor.
So rms, they have a qualitative knowledge
that none of the models can capture and.
If you are able to build a structured
feedback pipeline into your loop that
work a lot for the model performance.
Fourth is actually transfer learning.
So if you are able to access any
data samples from the larger but
similar situations, you can pre train
and fine tune your models later on.
And of course, L LMS is a
major breakthrough nowadays.
So with LLMs and a small number
of clients, you can analyze.
Large, lots of different behaviors for
these particular clients and make a
comprehensive picture for each of them.
This is the architecture that makes
small data personalization work.
It's hybrid machine learning,
handles quantitative reasoning.
LMS handle qualitative reasoning.
So layer one data sources which
is a portfolio data RM nodes
market fits risk questionaries.
And for example, in WealthTech RM
nodes are primary input which is
unique to the small number of tech
clients because in telco there is no
RM nos for the 50 million subscribers.
Layer two, the machine learning pipeline
tho sampling for personalization portfolio
risk scoring strategy fit scoring output.
Here is ranked recommendations
with confidence intervals.
It tells you what to recommend.
Layer three.
The L LLMs, it takes machine learning
outputs plus client context generated and
generates personalized communications.
So something like a client profile,
synthesis narratives, market regime,
interpretations, personalized reporting.
But what's the also absolutely
critical for the regulated finance
is that you also have a guardrail
layer rules engine, RMS review gate,
because LLM can produce drought, but in
regulated finance, it's never a final
document when market breaks models.
Breaks with them.
The question is whether you know
this before client can feel it.
So our circuit breaker
architecture has three levels.
Level one, it's a market regime, detector.
It's always on.
If your volatility exceeds twice the 19
day average or correlation mattresses.
Sharply.
It flags the region change.
It widens uncertainty, bounds,
and escalate to human review.
Level two is the model confidence
monitor for each person recommendation.
If inputs looks too far from
training data or confidence
intervals widen beyond normal.
We suppress the automated
recommendation and require RM sign of.
Level three is the conservative
default mode when both levels
triggered simultaneously.
We basically disabled the machine
learning recommendations and revert
to conservative pre-approved defaults.
And in such situations, senior management
sign off required for anything new.
The guide in principle is here
is that, silence is better than
the confident but wrong answer.
So in Black Swan events you
better say, I don't know rather
than you're confidently given.
Wrong answer.
And, just one recent example so
you can see that Bitcoin to s
and p 500 Correlation actually
reached 0 75 in January, 2026.
This is a complete record and
it's actually changing the entire
narrative in the industry and it
moves the recommendations a lot.
So you need to be very.
Quick in adjusting your
recommendations in the models.
If the previous slide was about
what to do when things break, this
one is about catching problems
before they become crisises.
So we have three monitoring tiers.
Tier one is always on daily market
driven indicators, data quality
checks, model confidence score.
Tier two is weekly, so PSI
drift per input feature.
RM overrid rate.
If RM over Verizon, more than 30%
of recommendations, that means
that the AI model is misaligned.
Tier three is the monthly business
metrics RPO uplift versus a
non-personalized baseline strategy
uptake by recommendation source.
And of course we are using a lot
of client satisfaction signals.
And what is key here is the principle that
every alert might be business oriented.
And it's not just PSI exceed
say certain threshold, but
sexually model may be misaligned.
Revenue at risk is X thousand
dollars, and you need to review
recommendations from last X days.
In regulated finance, every
AI recommendation is a
potential regulatory event.
Every regulator demand the same thing.
Explain why specific recommendation
was made to a specific client
at a specific timeframe.
So what we built is a
compliance as a code.
Step one, the AI generates
a recommendation.
All the inputs, model version, confidence,
every important number locked immediately.
Step two, automated compliance validation.
So we check it against the rules
for regulators, concentration
limits, risk tolerances.
Client restrictions if anything fails, so
then delivery is blocked to the client.
Step three, LLM generates a
client's specific explanation.
So it's a narrative that
referencing the actual features.
That drove the particular recommendation.
Step four is RM reviewing and the
proven or modifying the recommendation.
Then step five, everything
goes into audit, log and
retain for a certain period.
The impact here is actually very visible.
So respondent to regulator used to
take weeks in drawing the numbers
and understanding how did it go,
and now it became basically the
download from the system that
can be done in minutes or hours.
And it's not really an.
Only efficiency.
It's a fundamental shift
in regulatory readiness.
Let's move to the numbers now.
What is a real business impact of
personalization is 20 to 25% LTV uplift.
It's a 30% higher client retention, and
40 to 70% MTTR reduction for model issues.
And extremely expedited
compliance audit response.
So all of that makes ROI
greater than 10 to one.
Hence enormous return on investment.
And, what it's important is it protects
against the mis recommendation that can
at Black Swan event actually trigger
massive outflow because even for one
client outflow can be a deal breaker here.
And of course the regulator
compliance breaches.
It's all it's fines and
as well as the publicity.
So the biggest ROI didn't come from
the building, only the better models.
It also come from the kitchen issues
early and operational practices here.
It more deliver model value than
just simple model improvement.
In conclusion, I wanna touch on the
key takeaways from this presentation.
The first is that personalization
is basically the highest return
on investment commercial lever
across multiple industries.
Second is that LLMs, they
come as a great equalizer.
So before you would be able to run
personalization on the industries with
the high number of clients and Uranian
machine learning on top of them.
Now even in the industries with 10 20.
5,000 clients, you can use
LLMs to actually produce very
meaningful personalization with
the small data availability.
Three is AI personalization,
unfortunately fails silently, and
you need to build in models with the
health signals and keep monitoring it.
Four is the Plex one.
Events like the Six Sigma events
actually keep happening and you need
to build the circuit breakers to
be able to tailor such situations.
Five is that compliance is no longer
just annoying headache, but it's
actually a feature that you can build
and automate as much as possible.
And six is industries.
They actually.
Though they're very different.
But for personalization particularly,
there is a lot of cross-industry
experience that you can reuse and
improve in their next place to ensure
that the biggest ROI, thank you so
much again for joining my presentation.
I'm Uri ak.
Feel free to reach out to me
in LinkedIn or in my email.
Happy to discuss any of the
topics that I brought and ask,
answer all your questions.
Thank you.