Hi everyone.
This is ATI ish.
Thank you for joining my session.
Today.
We'll be discussing on zero to 50
engineering sub 50 millisecond.
I am architecture for high
stake gaming platform.
In the competitive world of online
gaming and betting every millisecond of
authentication latency directly impacts
user experience, revenue, and security.
Let's discuss on an innovative identity
and access management architecture
that consistently achieves sub 50
millisecond authentication speed
across global markets at scale.
This presentation reveals
the engineering decisions.
Implementation details and measurable
results for a high performance IAM
system providing actionable insights
for technology leaders seeking
millisecond level responsiveness
in today's gaming landscape.
Let's start with discussing on the
business impact of authentication Speed.
Our data shows the direct
correlation between authentication
speed and business success.
When authentication time exceed
a hundred millisecond transaction
completion rate drop dramatically.
Players expect instantaneous responses,
especially during time sensitive
gaming or betting opportunities.
By optimizing authentication, we
have seen significant improvements
across key performance metrics.
Our data indicates.
18% reduction in transaction abandonment
with 27% increase in user retention
leading to 32% rise in revenue growth.
Let's discuss on the global
authentication architecture.
The proposed architecture leverages
strategically position edge, deployed
identity proxies that dramatically
reduce latency while simultaneously
lowering infrastructure costs by
bringing authentication closer to users.
We have cut network transmission
time by an average of 65
millisecond across global markets.
We used stateless JWT
authentication system.
Our system leveraged Shortlived JWTs with
ES 2 56 cryptographic signing to process
thousands of transaction per second.
With zero database lookups, maintaining
robust security without sacrificing speed.
This stateless approach eliminates
database bottlenecks while allowing
instant revocation through a
distributed block list when necessary.
We also implemented real
time fraud detection.
Our system analyzes behavioral pattern
through streaming technologies to identify
suspicious activities before transactions.
Complete by continuously monitoring,
interaction patterns, device
fingerprints, and transaction velocity.
We can detect anomalies
without adding authentication
latency for legitimate users.
We also utilized intelligent
KYC and compliance metrics by
intelligently offloading KYC
and trust scoring processes.
We have eliminated authentication
bottlenecks while improving regulatory
compliance across diverse markets.
Our system adapts verification
requirements based on jurisdiction,
player behavior, and transaction patterns,
applying appropriate compliance measures
without impacting authentication speed.
Our system integrated web
authentication, and FID O2 integration.
Our integration of these standards reduced
login friction resulting in measurable
increase in microtransaction conversion
rates among high value player segments.
By leveraging device-based biometric
authentication, we have eliminated
password related friction while
substantially improving security posture.
Players can seamlessly authenticate
across devices using fingerprints,
facial recognition, or security
keys, reducing the cognitive load of
remembering credentials while making
account takeovers virtually impossible.
Some of the performance
benchmarks from our study.
We have conducted comprehensive benchmarks
comparing traditional IM approach
against our optimized architecture
across various gaming scenarios.
The results consistently show
our system outperforming industry
standards by three to seven times.
With our edge based JWT authentication,
delivering 32 millisecond
average response time globally,
some of the implementation challenges
and the solutions we followed
our journey to sub 50 millisecond
authentication wasn't without obstacles.
By addressing the core challenges with
innovative solutions, we have created
a system that balances speed, security,
and compliance without compromise.
Some of the challenges were JWTs
can't be immediately revoked.
The solution we found was a short five
minute lifetime with silent background
refresh, combined with distributed
revocation list for compromised tokens.
Another challenge was maintaining
consistent auth policy across regions.
To overcome that, we had to use
centralized policy management with atomic
version updates propagated to edge news
through resilient messaging system.
Our next challenge was.
The varying KYC requirement
across jurisdictions.
To overcome that, we had to deploy region
specific compliance module with local
data residency where required, separated
from core authentication, workflow,
some of the business
outcomes and the impact.
The impact of this authentication
improvement extends far
beyond technical metrics.
Players experience a seamless,
frictionless environment that encourages
engagement and builds trust while the
business benefits from higher conversion
rate and op operational efficiency,
some of the metrics is present.
We did see 92% reduction in authentication
related support tickets, 4.8 out of
five average rating, which was up
from 3.6 for operational efficiency.
43% of infrastructural cost was
reduced, and 72% of peak time
scaling events were reduced.
For security improvements, we saw
67% reduction in account takeover
attempts, and 98% decrease in
successful credential staffing attacks.
Thus, the revenue growth saw 16%
increase in average transaction value
and 24% higher conversion on time
sensitive betting opportunities.
The implementation roadmap and
recommendation begin your journey
to millisecond level authentication
with this faced approach.
We recommend starting with a pilot
in your highest value region to
demonstrate immediate business
impact before expanding globally.
Focus first on core authentication speed
before implementing advanced feature
like biometrics and behavioral analysis.
I look forward to discuss further
on our approach and to answer
any questions that you have.
Hope this gave some idea on.
How to seek millisecond level response
time and how to build an architecture.
Thank you for joining my session.
Hope you enjoy the rest of the conference.