Hi, I'm VA Boyer and I'm a
developer advocate at IWS.
Hello, I'm VA Boyer and I'm a developer
advocate at Amazon Web Services.
So today I'll talk about application
resilience and we'll look to answer
the question, whose job is it?
Anyway, thank you for joining.
During my recent talks on continuous
resilience, I've been asked many
thought provoking questions.
One of the questions that I keep
being asked time and time again
is it possible for application
resilience and innovation to coexist?
So in this session, we'll look at a few
features to look to answer this question.
So we'll look at.
Cultural transformation
for digital transformation.
And then we'll look at the
shared responsibility model
in software development.
And then lastly, we will look
at the technical considerations
for shared responsibility.
We'll look at how all these points work
together to ensure the coexistence of
application resilience and innovation.
So let's begin.
So beyond application resilience,
organizations are looking to
innovate for their customers.
So the questions they ask themselves
is, does the pursuit of application
resilience not hold back innovation?
How do teams organize in order
to ensure that there is both
application resilience and innovation?
And who in the team is responsible
for application resilience and who is
responsible for applic for innovation?
So I talked about continuous
resilience and a quick catch up on what
continuous resilience is all about.
Continuous resilience is when teams move
away from a robustness centric approach
to instead facing up to the fact that.
Applications will fail at some point, and
thus embracing failure with an intention
to build capabilities that ensure that
there's resilience in the applications
when they ultimately experience failure.
I.
Organizations that seek to digitally
transform and become tomorrows disruptors
are not able to do this without
undergoing cultural transformation
silos in software development or care.
When various roles that contribute towards
software development rarely interact
or talk to each other, ultimately this
results in the absence of teamwork.
Silos within a software development
lifecycle get in the way of communication
and collaboration, thus slowing
down innovation and the delivery
of business value to customers.
It's also worth mentioning that silos
can introduce conflicts within roles,
which can manifest through statements
such as that is not my job, and
further compromising a quality product
being delivered to the customer.
So as teams seek to move out of the
silo development approach, communication
between teams becomes very important.
Communication moves teams towards
a shared responsibility model, and
it's very important for innovation.
So there are tools that teams
can explore that support,
collaboration and communication.
So teams can explore tools that
better support collaboration
during software development.
Tools like GitHub are very popular
among developers as they offer
collaborative features that
make life easier for developers.
Features such as code reviews, pool
request notifications, and more.
Software development projects can be
better organized using tools such as
Trello, which lets teams organize projects
into boards so that teams can have a view
of us on the to-do list, what's being
worked on and what's done in order to
eliminate confusion with project status.
So I briefly talked about shared
responsibility model in the
previous section, and I'll expand
on it a little bit more here.
Good quality code is only just
one of the contributing factors in
application resilience, performance
efficiency, security and functional
suitability go hand in hand with good
quality code towards contributing
towards your application resilience.
If you decide to tackle these
contributing factors individually,
it's easy to fall back into siloed
functions where individual roles
within teams are responsible for only
some of these contributing factors.
I. It's however more beneficial for
everyone in the team and ultimately
in the organizations to make
quality a shared responsibility.
This approach reduces development costs
and ultimately the customer or the end
user benefits from a better product.
Now I'm going to paraphrase Eric Madar,
who wrote for devops.com, and he said
that team members are equally ultimately
responsible for application resilience.
Outdated organizational structures,
however, tend to place responsibilities
on a single employee, on a
single team, or on a single role.
Organizing team structures around products
instead of projects will accelerate
innovation and increase the quality
of work due to increased collaboration
that is fostered by this team structure.
So now I'm talking about
shared responsibility.
I'm talking about collaboration,
and it's starting to sound like I
have gone and started a whole other
conversation on a popular term.
DevOps.
So in the book DevOps for Dummies,
author Emily Freeman describes
DevOps as a philosophy that is
meant to build a culture of trust,
a culture of collaboration, and a
culture of continuous improvement.
So Emily Feather goes on to give a guide
on how to design your organization so
that you support this collaboration
and this continuous improvement.
So is the culture of your organization
healthy in that the worst of tech
culture is avoided with diversity
of thought being encouraged?
Are your team members empowered
to make dec decisions without
always consulting management for
every decision that they make?
So staying with this topic of DevOps
a little bit longer, it is worth
reiterating that building a common
DevOps team or having DevOps forecast
members in the team introduces
shared responsibility in the team.
So over time, several essential practices
have emerged when teams are adopting
DevOps, and these practices are continuous
integration, continuous delivery.
Infrastructure is code and monitoring and
logging, but we will look at these in a
little bit more detail a little bit later.
So talking about technical considerations
for a shared responsibility.
So now that the culture has
been addressed, what technical
considerations will support this
shared responsibility in teams?
First we look at distributed
architectures and how they can
support this shared responsibility.
So there is this really
insightful books that I read.
It's the title of the book is Fundamentals
of Software Architecture, where the
authors contrast to architecture
styles monolithic versus distributed.
Monolithic is described as a single
deployment unit of all your code, or as
distributed is described as involving
multiple deployment units that are
connected through remote access protocols.
An example of a distributed architecture
is a microservices architecture.
Which is an architectural style
that structures an application as a
collection of loosely coupled services,
which implement business capabilities.
It's a way of breaking up a monolithic
software into various components that
can function separately, that have
specific tasks and that communicate with
each other through a simple application
programming interface known as an API.
The second technical consideration that
tends to support shared responsibility
is continuous integration and delivery.
So there's a white paper by AWS that
introduces DevOps, and this white paper
highlights AWS capabilities that help
you accelerate your DevOps journey.
And it also talks about services that can
help remove the undifferentiated heavy
lifting that's associated with DevOps.
Adaptation.
It expands on these essential practices
when adopting DevOps, some of which are
already briefly talked about previously.
So this white paper highlights AWS
capabilities that help you accelerate
when you are on your DevOps journey.
And I already talked
about the services that.
Are available that can help
you remove all this work that
goes with you adopting DevOps.
So what are these practices?
The first practice is
continuous integration.
Continuous integration is a software
development practice where developers
regularly merge their code changes
into a central repository, after which
automated bills and tests are then run.
GitHub Actions is a continuous integration
and continuous delivery platform that
allows you to automate your, build your
test, and your deployment pipeline.
It lets you create workflows that
build and test every pool request
to your repository or deploy,
merge pool requests to production.
The next practice we'll look
at is infrastructure is code.
Infrastructure as code is a practice
in which infrastructure is provisioned
and managed using code and software
development techniques such as vision
control and continuous integration.
So when we talk about infrastructure
as code, look at considering tools
like Terraform, which lets you automate
the provision of your infrastructure,
including databases, servers, and
firewall policies among others
across multiple cloud platforms.
If you're looking to get started with
Terraform, you will find a link that
I will share at the end of this talk
that will help you get started with
infrastructure as code and terraform.
Then we look at monitoring and logging.
Monitoring and logging enables
organizations to see how application and
infrastructure performance impacts the
experience of their products and user.
Open Telemetry is a collection of
tools, collection of APIs and SDKs.
Use it to instrument to generate,
to collect and to export telemetry
data such as metrics, logs, and
traces to help you analyze your
software's performance and behavior.
At the end of this talk, I do
link a tutorial that is very
helpful if you're looking to
get started with open telemetry.
Now we will look at communication and
collaboration practices are established
to bring teams closer and by building
workflows and distributing the
responsibilities for communications.
When we talk about security, security
should be a crosscutting consent.
Your continuous integration in
your continuous delivery pipelines
and all related services should
be safeguarded and proper access
control permissions should be set up.
The Open web application security project
known as OSP is a foundation that works
to improve the security of software.
Their programs include community led
open source software projects, and they
have over 250 local chapters worldwide.
The OS Foundation has published a list
of top 10 security risks to avoid in
order to change the software development
culture towards a more secure culture.
So to conclude, it seems that
the old saying remains true.
You cannot keep on doing the same
things and expecting different results.
Teams will have to evolve in order to
ensure innovation for their customers.
Teams will have to evolve into a
shared responsibility model in order
to be better positioned to work
towards application resilience.
So to end, I asked you a few questions
that I want to leave you with.
Do you still have siloed functions as
part of a software development cycle?
Another question I would ask you
is, are you in the process of
transitioning from siloed functions
to a shared responsibility team?
And I'd also ask you, have
you fully transitioned to a
shared responsibility team?
With that, I thank you very much and if
you scan that QR code, you will access
a link where you will find my LinkedIn.
Please do connect and also you'll
find all the links that I've been
talking about throughout this talk.
Thank you.