Hi everyone, my name is, thanks for
joining to my session today on Microsoft
Cloud Agent Insurance And Greetings.
Coming to my session today.
Today we are going to discuss about how
the Microsoft Cloud AI NextGen Insurance,
and we'll be discussing about the core
topics like the core machine learning
morals and discuss assessment under
neural networks in insurance, natural
language processing, in document analysis,
e and LP, performance metrics and
predictive analysis and fraud detections.
And computer vision, performance
metrics and integrated a platforms
and automation, economic impact of
a insurance and future of yay and
insurance underwriting, SharePoint,
AI transformation collaboration.
And these are all the
topics that we are going to.
Talk in this session and how we see
between this traditional methods
and as well as this transformation
between this, what are the benefits,
what is the accuracy and what is how
the under underwritings are going
without the paperless, we'll all see
this features, session this Microsoft
Cloud AI next generation session.
The insurance industry is experiencing
performed digital transformation.
Through a integration fundamentally
reshaping traditional business models
and operational processes with the
global insurance, yay Investments, and
it's reaching 21 billion in 2023, and
the predictions of 45 billion in 2027.
The insurance industry is recognizing
a potential to revolutionizing the
core processes in today's world,
the insurance carriers implementing
AI driven underwriting systems.
Having a reported of 40% risk reduction
in the risk assessment time, and 60% of
decrease in the processing cost and 35%
improvement in the loss ratio production.
Sir, these systems can these systems
can also analyze over 200 unique data
points per application in real time.
Compared to 40 to 50 points in the
traditional underwriting, and this
is all about the key highlight of the
insurance in the industry, then now
we will go by one section how we can
leverage the benefits of using this
gen features in the insurance coming to
this core core machine learning models.
In the risk assessment.
Here we talk about, three models.
One is a random forest, one is a
logistic regression, and one is
the gradient boosting mechanic.
When coming to this random forest the
achieving the accuracy rate is like
above 85% in risk classification.
Significantly outperforming that
traditional actuarial methods can
process up to 75 unique features
per assessment with the optimal
performance through hundred to.
One 20 decision enables and coming
to this logistic logistic regression,
this logistic ion maintains over 78%
of accuracy rate while providing the
complete algorithm transparency for
regulatory compliance, delivering
28% in the improvement of the risk.
Of the risk of segmentation accuracy
com compared to the conventional methods
when it come to the gradient boosting
mechanism, boost things implementation.
This kind of machine learning
model achieve 90% of perception
in the risk classification.
While maintaining the real processing
speeds can efficiently analyze over 300
distinct features per application In.
30 seconds.
Now coming to the next topic of the
neural networks in insurance, the neural
networks particularly is nothing but
an advanced learning architectures have
transformed how the insurance processes
of the unstructured data during the
underwriting, this cutting edging
conventional na natural networks deployed
in properly incidents Now identify.
Potential risk factors from the visual
data with above 91% accuracy, seamlessly
processing 77 50 property images
daily, while dramatically reducing
the need for the human review, the
deep learning experience, the deep
learning excellent unstructured data
processing and structured data analyst.
We'll see how it happens, the
accuracy rate and the processing
and the risk classification.
In each here in the deep learning
excellence, we will see over
91% of accuracy in the risk
assessment, unstructured data
processing seven 50 images daily.
This is what, how the neural networks,
if we implement certain in the insurance
practices, we can achieve these targets.
Like a structured data analysis.
Over 86% of risk class
classification accuracy.
This is how the neural networks
that helps in the insurance industry
for the deep learning, unstructured
data processing, unstructured data
analysis with the accuracy rate.
Now coming to the natural language
processing in document analysis, this
is very important because the reduction
in reduction in manual review time.
Be model accuracy named entity
rec recognition accuracy.
So now coming to this reduction in manual
review term, it's not only about how
the AA features are utilizing it also
should have a manual review review term
reduction, and that how source this in
LP system process, like a tool k plus.
Pages daily, over 300 pages when
we compare with the traditional
manual methods when coming to this
bet model accuracy for extracting
the critical information from the
policy documents and when it comes
to the na named entity recognition.
Accuracy.
It is about 94 percentage in identifying
and categorizing the key entities
with the insurance documentation.
The insurance underwriting's reliance
on document processing has been
revolutionized by the NLP models.
Be based models, trained
on 2.5 million insurance.
Documents can analyze a standard 25
page policy in just a few seconds,
just like 20 seconds comp compared
to 52 minutes of the traditional
methods while maintaining accuracy.
While maintaining the accuracy levels.
About 85%.
Even with the complex riders and
endorsements, and this is one of the
beautiful natural language processing
in the document analysis that helps
in the insurance industries though,
N-L-P-N-L-P performance metrics in.
Insurance.
The here, the main five topics that
we models we are going to talk is
like the beta document analysis,
technical inter interpretations,
the cover gap detection and the NER
systems in coming to this section.
The first topic, like B-R-T-B-E-R-T
document analysis, over 90% of accuracy
rate with 20 seconds around like eight 18.
18 to 20 seconds per document
and the 85% reduction in compared
to the manual processing.
The technical term interpretation.
93 per 93 percentage of accuracy rate
processing over eight 50 documents per
72% of reduction in the processing time.
Cover gap detections, the accuracy
rate will be over 90% and eight
50 documents processed to cost to
savings will be like a three, two.
$4 per document.
Iner systems accuracy date will be
94% rate and 8,000 documents processed
daily using this INER system.
And the cost savings also like
amazing, like a four around
like five $5 per document.
Pre coming to the next section, how
this pre predictive predictive analysis
and the fraud detection this in this
things, in this predictive analysis on
fraud detection, we will talk about like
advanced predictive models time series
analysis and graph neural networks.
And auto auto encoder integrations.
This this advanced
advanced predictive models.
We see this reduction.
It is just like 36% reduction in the
combined loss ratios and 41 point
two percentage improvement in the
risk assessment precisions the time
series analysis, over 84.8 percentage
of accuracy in predicting claim.
Occurrence within the first 24
first 12 months of policy insurance
graph neural networks, over 71% of
implementing fraud detection rates while
reducing the false positives by 62%.
Auto encoder integration.
Over 90% of accuracy in identifying
unknown mollusk claim patents while
processing 65,000 claims daily.
And when we come to this
predictive analysis on fraud
detection, this plays a key role.
This plays a key role when we are using
the a AI features in the insurance ancy
or in any other industry that deals
with the most of the content management
and the document management where the
A underwriters or the officers will
be using on today, day-to-day basis
for collecting the meta content and
metadata from the actual business users.
Coming to the next topic, the computer
Vision in property assessment in, and
this is not only about the insurance.
We have something like property casualty,
specialty casualty, the Iron Show in
a different models of the insurance.
When it comes to the property assessment,
the computer with the AI feature, the
computer vision in property assessment has
like drastically showing the improvements.
One is the image capture.
One is the cost estimation,
one is the future detection and
one is the damage assessment.
It's not only about a small property
like a home or this it also deals with
this like the, a deals with the the
big system like the very San Francisco
Bridge or the New York Bridges.
The, were big malls in the New York, the
big buildings in the New York and San
Francisco and other parts of the country.
When we have a huge like
billions of the properties.
And that also helps this AI also
helps in that assessing with through
the computer vision in the property.
Assessment.
One is image captured here
in this image capture.
We'll discuss it process inserts with
the ultra high resolution property
images enabling the detailed analysis.
They're now coming to the
feature feature detection.
Advanced yolo VFI and Foster CNN
algorithms identify 180 5 distant
property features with 87%, 87.4%
perceptions and damage assessment.
Specialized CNN models achieve
over 90% accuracy in identifying
structural damage, CBRT and extent.
Revolutionary, revolutionary computer
vision systems have slashed the property
assessment time by 70%, over 70%,
while simultaneously initially boosting
the damage detection accuracy by 41%.
This high performance system processes
can impress you like around nearly
2000 of property measures daily.
This deliver delivering comprehensive
assessment results in me 4.2 minutes per.
Property diametrically faster
than 52 minutes required for the
traditional human inspections.
The computer vision performance metrics,
it's not only about computer vision
in the management system, it be how
to check, like how the computer vision
has the performance metrics, how we
can calculate that, how we can, because
the metrics is the one thing that shows
the graphical representation where to
compare with the previous data and the
future data to predict that metrics.
This coming to this section, this
is like a CN instructional damage.
Assessment, security system, fire
assessment fire risk assessment.
Yay.
Virtual traditional inspection over
90 nearly 90% of accuracy rate in
identifying structural damage, severity
and extent, and comprehensive assessment
in just eight point 8.5 minutes.
Per property security system detection
industry leading over 90% of accuracy
rate and 52% of implement in future
detection compared to manual methods.
The fire risk assessment, over
90% of accuracy in identifying
potential fire hazards.
Part of 85% reduction in the assessment.
Yay.
A virtual a versus traditional inspection.
And this computer vision is having a
accuracy rate for around 90% and manually
towards 70 or above 70% accuracy rate.
The average costing can, it can be
around between 200 to 300 range.
The computer, advanced computer
vision algorithms have revolutionized
the property evaluations.
Slashing assessment times by 84%, went
from 50 minutes down to the, just the
8.5 minutes or nine minutes per property,
while maintaining consistently high
accuracy rates across all the assessment
categories, integrated AI platforms and
automation in this integrated platforms.
And automation.
The robotic process of automation one
is policy renewal processing the price
optimization market segment optimizations.
Here in this robotic process of
automation, it achieves industry
leading 97% is accuracy in automated
data entry while processing of
about 7,000 documents daily.
Slashing manual processing
time by 72 point.
5% and maintaining the
error rates below 0.5%.
And when it comes to policy renewal
processing, it's not about only
the policy or the claims or the
underwritings it's also about the renewal.
Process, right?
Any policy is getting renewed within
a 12 months or 18 months based
on the policy inspection date and
the policy inspection end date.
So the policy should get automatically
go for the renewal, so the
dramatically cuts processing times
from 22.8 hours to just 18 minutes
per policy while sustain sustaining
98% accuracy, efficiently handling.
Close to 9,500 complex renewals monthly
market segment optimization provides
exceptionally over 88 percentage of
predict to accuracy for customer responses
to price adjustments across diverse market
segments, directly contributing to 2.3
percentage point market share growth.
We'll also see about we, we have
seen about the computer vision,
how the platforms and how the,
a integrated platforms and how
how the neural networks helps.
Now, we'll come like
it's not about always.
Leveraging the AA features
or any other technology.
It is also important to see how
economically IT impact of AA
insurance when it comes to this
operational cost reduction, processing
efficiency, and customer experience.
This is the most important
when it's not only about.
Implementing a features or gene
features a new AA feature, but it's
also important to see how how economic
impact of a insurance, the operational
cost reductions, integrated AA platforms
resulted in average operational
cost reduction of three point.
8 billion annually with
the return of investment.
Typically assured within 1818 months of
the deployment processing efficiency,
if you see the processing efficiency,
the reduction of around reduction
of 58% in end to end processing
time for the standard insurance
operations while improving the overall
accuracy by 41% and processing of 12
k plus insurance transactions daily.
When it comes to the customer experience,
at the end at the end customer experience.
Is the most important thing, and
here we'll see how by utilizing this
economic impact of AI in, in insurance.
So the carriers utilizing this, the
carriers utilizing this AI systems
has reduced policy processing cost
by 62% while improving the customer
satisfaction metrics by 35% through faster
response time and reduced error rates.
The future of EAA, the future of
EA. Insurance underwriting, current
implementation near term elu evolution.
The future transformation.
The current implementation is like the
operational efficiency, and the cost
reductions near term evolution, dynamic
risk assessment and personalizing.
Pricing the future transformation.
Fully automated underwriting.
Fully automated underwriting with
a continuous risk monitoring.
The integrated the integration of the
integration of artificial intelligence
in insurance underwriting represents a
paradigm shift in the risk assessment.
Under the policy management methodologies.
This transformation extends beyond
me automation fundamentally.
Altering for altering how business
insurance companies evaluate risk
process, document the fraud detection,
and interact with the customers.
All these technologies
continues to evolve.
The insurance industry is positioned for
further innovation, particularly in areas
such as personal personalized pricing.
Dy, I'm sorry.
Dynamic risk assessment
and automated underwriting.
The future will be, the future will
likely see even greater integration of AI
technologies leading to more sophisticated
and efficient way of operations.
That better both carriers
and policy holders.
And coming to the topic
like the SharePoint yay.
Transforming collaboration.
If you talk with insurance, we
should talk about SharePoint.
That's how it is tightly integrated.
The technology integrated with
insurance, because insurance is
all about the content Metadata.
And the file repository, the SharePoint
here, that the day, the SharePoint
bond, it has has the come up with the
features with each version, and it's
trying to help the insurance, the
life sensors and the construction in
industries the most of the tough way in.
Industries when it comes to this tofa
industry, the always the insurance
industries will place the first with
the SharePoint, where it has the
best, the Microsoft SharePoint provide
the best repositories, the cloud
repository, the collaboration, and the
collaborate and team collaboration.
Platform for leveraging this share pan
features like the automation Yay, power.
Now, the now coming to that the latest
feature of this share pant, yay.
How they transforming the collaborations.
And in today's world, like the Microsoft
yay, a integration is revolutionizing
again, the share pant capabilities.
It's not only about the SharePoint, the
Microsoft itself is coming up with this,
all the products by the AI integration.
Okay.
The delivering measurable, productive
gains and transforming the collaborative
workflows through intelligent features
that adopt to our organization needs.
Co-pilot in co-pilot in SharePoint co.
The introduction of this the co-pilot
or integration of this co-pilot in
SharePoint provides contextual assistance.
For the content cre, for the content
creation knowledge discovery, the
real time data summarization within
SharePoint, reducing this information
ritual by 40% while enhancing the
decision quality through personalized
insights and recommendation.
Now come when we talk about the
AI power authoring, the enhance,
it enhances the document it
enhances the document creation.
With the intelligent suggestions, right?
That's how the authoring
will happen, right?
EA powered authoring, it enhances the
document creation with the intelligent
suggestions like a contextual formatting
and tailor the content recommendations
that align with your organization,
communication patterns and the institution
knowledge, increasing the content
quality and the consistency up to 35%.
Coming to the intelligent
content management.
So the, it automates the content
classification, which improves
the searchability and delivers the
personalized content experiences
based on the user behavior and the
organizational context, resulting
in 28% efficient information.
Discovery under knowledge sharing.
Now we'll talk about AI powered
intelligence agents and automation.
So these a powered intelligence, the
agents and automation, how it plays
a key role in the insurance domain.
So the coming to the SharePoint
agents like the intelligence agent.
Autonomously.
Handle autonomously.
Handle autonomously, like it's
independently, handle the routine task.
Okay.
While continuously learning from
organizational patterns, these AI entities
proactively monitor content anticipate the
needs and deliver the actionable insight.
Based on the collective knowledge reducing
administrative overhead by up to 45%.
The SA workflow automation, this AI
driven process orchestration identifies
the bottlenecks and the and implements
optimized workflows in the real time.
This one, automation eliminates up
to 60% of the manual interventions,
ensuring the consistent quality and
adopts for changing business requirements
without restricting this operations.
And thank you for joining my session,
and thank you for joining my sessions
and I'm having like around 10 plus
years of experience working with this.
It industry, particularly
with the insurance domain.
If you have any questions, if you have
any, if you need any PS or related like
how you want to move the content from
the source to the cloud and how you
want to leverage this AI features, how
you want to plan your strategy with
the SharePoint to moving the content,
the versioning, the collaborations
between this insurance remains.
And the technology, you
can always reach out to me.
You can.
I'm very happy to help you and thanks
again for joining my session and see you.
Thank you.