Hi everyone.
I am
it professional with 20 years of
experience as a retail architect.
Today we are looking at our
site reliability engineering.
Our SRE helps scale a driven
retail logistics platforms with
rising customer expectations.
Retail needs, smart, reliable systems.
SRE brings the tools and mindset
to keep these platforms resilient,
scalable, and fast, making a powered
omnichannel experiences possible.
Let's explore how reliability
powers the future of retail.
Thank you.
Let's look at the evolution
of retail logistics.
We started with the traditional model.
Others took days processed
through centralized warehouses.
Then came the omnichannel era,
blending online offline channels,
cutting ment time down to 24 hours.
Next, AI powered micro
fulfillment centers arrived.
Using predictive algorithms to
pull bill orders within hours.
And now we are stepping into the
next generation where predictive
systems start processing even before
the customer finishes their order.
Retail logistics is getting faster,
smarter, and more proactive than ever.
Now let's talk about the core SRE
principles in retail logistics.
First, we have error budgets.
They help quantify how much risk
we can accept without impacting the
operations next service level objectives.
Our SLOs, these align technical
performance with what really
matters to the customer experience.
Then there is automation key to
reducing manual work, especially
with continuous deployment pipelines
like CICD pipelines.
And finally observability, giving
us deep visibility into complex
distributed logistics systems so
we can detect and fix issues fast.
Together these SRE principles.
Keep retail logistics reliable,
efficient, and customer focused.
Let's talk about building resell and micro
fulfillment center, MFC infrastructure,
A key piece of modern retail logistics.
First, the business volume.
We are aiming for 98.7% order accuracy
with one hour delivery windows.
That's the kind of precision and
speed today's customer expects.
At the core is the A intelligence layer.
It powers predictive inventory placement.
And accurate demand forecasting
enduring products are where they need
to be before the customer even clicks.
By
supporting that distributed
systems architecture built with far
tolerant microservices and regional.
Failover.
So even if one part of the
system goes down, the operations
keeps running smoothly.
All of this runs a strong infrastructure
foundation, Kubernetes orchestrated
container that can be at scale to
meet changing demand in real time.
The lead approach keeps MFCs
fast, reliable, and ready
for peak retail perform.
Let's explore our advanced observability
solutions, the backbone of reliable high
performing retail logistics, starting
with tropic monitoring our enterprise
grade distributor pricing system, and 10
x tropic spikes during sp peak shopping
times without any performance drop paid
with the smartly detection algorithm.
Our systems alert engineers to potential
issues before customer even notice.
And the performance analysis side,
we use custom metrics to precisely
track fulfillment velocity across
all our regional MFC networks.
Real time dashboards offer instant.
Comparison of actual versus expected
performance for every geographic zone.
And when it comes to business insights,
we connect the dots between technical
metrics and business outcomes.
Our SL word tracking doesn't just say.
In the engineering VLM, it feeds
into initiative executive dashboards
clearly showing how infrastructure
health impacts customer satisfaction.
In short, our observability is then
just about keeping system running.
It's about keeping customers
happy and the business growing.
Let's talk about a powered
route optimization at scale.
A game changer for last mile delivery.
It start with position analysis.
We use realtime GPS data from our
delivery fleet to know exactly where
every vehicle is at any moment.
Then we layer on traffic prediction.
Our machine learning models
forecast congestion patterns
before they happen, allowing the
system to stay ahead of delay.
Finally, the root competition dynamically
the fast, most efficient farts
through complex urban environments.
Adapting in real time as conditions
change the result faster deliveries,
lower cost, and happier customers.
Let's walk through our service
level objectives framework,
which align technology, customer
experience, and business outcomes.
Starting with technical vos, we target
99 point 99% system availability.
A PA responses under a hundred
milliseconds and other processing
latency under 50 seconds.
These ensure our backend stays
lightening fast and dependable.
Next, our customer experience SVOs.
We aim for delivery time accuracy
within plus or minus five minutes.
Other accuracy about 99.5% and app
transaction completion rates over 98%,
all focused on smooth,
reliable customer journey.
Finally, our business customer outcomes
SVOs connect performance to impact.
We keep.
Cart a abandonment under 15%.
Push for a repeat purchase rate above
65% and optimized delivery efficiency
to x, exceed 12 orders for hour.
This framework keep everyone
from engineers to execute.
Two focused on what truly let's drive
into our incident management framework.
Designed to respond quickly and
efficiently when things go wrong.
Detection.
Start with automated alerts through
pager duty, customer feedback,
monitoring and synthetic transaction.
Canaries proactively catching issues
before they affect the users for response.
We have a structured incident command.
With cross-functional teams,
communication channels are pre
dependent, ensuring everyone knows
their role and process to Palo.
When it comes to remediation, we
use playbook driven procedures,
including automated rollbacks
to restore service quickly.
We also focus on customer
impact mitigation.
Minimizing disruption for the end user.
Finally, in the learning phase, we conduct
blameless postmortems to understand what
went wrong without pointing fingers.
We track systematic improvements
and update our knowledge base
to prevent future incidents.
This framework ensures.
We respond fast, learn continuously,
and keep our services reliable.
Let's talk about chavos engineering in
practice, how you proactively test and
improve the resilience of our systems.
It starts with.
Hypothesis formation.
We begin by formulating precise
hypothesis about the systems, study
steps and predicting how the system
will behave when disruptions happen.
Next, we conduct controlled experiments.
Our engineers intentionally
introduce calibrated failures
in production environments.
To test system boundaries and assess
recovery mechanisms, essentially
pushing our systems to their limits.
Then we measure impact.
We correlate technical metrics
with customer experience indicators
to understand the real world
impact of system degradations.
This helps us quantify how
failures affect the customer.
Finally, the insights we gain
help us improve resilience we use.
That's what we have learned to develop
automated recovery system, self ailing
infrastructure, and a detailed incident.
S. All aimed at making our system more
robust and responsive in the future.
Chavos engineering isn't about
causing harm, it's about making our
system stronger and more resell.
Let's talk about our lift shift security
approach, which integrates security at
every stage of the development lifecycle.
Starting with development, we focus on
real time vulnerability detection directly
in the rd, sorry, ID using automated
security linking and code quantity
quality gates to catch issues as early
as possible in the development process.
In continuous integration, we apply.
Comprehensive static application
security testing automatically
scan for CV vulnerabilities and
validate third party dependencies to
ensure they don't introduce risks.
When we move to deployment, we
implement container image scanning,
runtime application, self production,
and ensure automated regularity.
Compliance verification to keep everything
secure during the deployment page.
Finally, in production,
we imply advanced treat
intelligence monitoring, leveraging
a powered ity detection and well
defined incident response protocols.
To stay high head up, potential traits.
This approach ensures security is
embedded through preventing risk
before they make it into production.
To wrap up, here are the key takeaways
for building reliable retail logistics.
Define clear lvo.
It's critical to balance technical metrics
with customer experience indicators.
This ensures we meet business goals
while keeping customers happy.
Invest in observability.
Build comprehensive visibility across
all distributed systems so you can
detect and address issues in real time.
Embrace automation, reduce manual effort
by implementing infrastructure as code.
Enabling faster, more
efficient operations, faster.
A real a resilience culture.
Promote blameless problem solving
and continuous learning to
improve systems and processes.
No matter the challenges.
These principles will guide you.
Towards a more reliable,
efficient, and customer centric
retail logistics operations.
Thank you.