Speaker 15: Hello everyone.
Thank you for attending this
session at com 42 SRE 2026.
Today I'll be sharing with you a real
incident that I have experienced in
Bernet environment while explaining
why kus default load balancing
doesn't work for HT TP to traffic.
But before that, let's
have a quick note about me.
Hello, I am Maryam.
I work as a society engineer.
I spend a lot of time running and scaling
Kubernetes platforms in production.
This is why today this
session is about Kubernetes.
So starting with the agenda for today
first we'll talk a little bit about
the incident that we have encountered.
And after that we will explain why
Kubernetes default why kuber load
balancing behavior behavior unexpectedly.
And then we'll explain why HTTP two
traffic changed the traffic distribution.
And then we'll dig a little better a
little bit about how could proxy handles
the load balancing in environment and
why it was a bottleneck in this case.
And finally, we'll go through
the temporary adjustment that
we did, and we'll talk about the
long-term solution and the lessons
learned through this incident.
So let's talk a little bit
about the incident itself.
So it was the first time that
we have introduced HTTP to
traffic for some of our critical
Kubernetes services in production.
As a result, there was latency experienced
by some of our, external users, it was not
that significant latency, but there was
about more than 300% milliseconds latency.
So we did notice kind of unusual load
patterns in in our HTP two traffic
distribution across the backend pods.
Specifically there was one single
pod which was serving the whole
incoming traffic while the other
pos that were simply staying idle.
So that was the observation
in that incident.
So this is a visualization diagram before.
So what you have expected
and what was the reality.
So we expected an even traffic
distribution across all the backend pods,
but the React, it was not that case.
There was embassy in traffic.
One single PO was having like a high
load serving all this incoming traffic.
What, what made this incident
confusing for us at the beginning.
So basically there was no
kind of resource concern.
We had plenty of idle capacity,
whether it's like for the pods
or the nodes in the cluster.
Also the HPA, the horizontal PO auto
autoscaled was working normally and it
was not affected by this traffic pattern.
And even after killing the single server
serving po that was, serving the whole
traffic that actually didn't help.
So the traffic is still persisting
on one single pod and there was
no kind of redistribution of the
traffic to the rest of the pods.
So our mistake, it was that we
did expect HTP TRA to traffic to
behave the same way as HTTP won
traffic in Kubernetes environment.
So that was one except from our side.
And, caused by lack of knowledge, like
how things works behind the scenes, like
at a deeper level in bernet clusters.
As I said earlier, what we were expecting,
we were expecting even distribution of
the requests across the backend pods.
The scaling should be working fi fine.
But the reality, it was not that case.
Okay.
Now let's dig a little bit deeper
into how Kubernetes service by default
do the road balancing in Kubernetes
traffic in Kubernetes clusters.
So by default Bernet service performs
layer four TCP load balancing.
So it works at TCP layer.
When doing the load balancing.
Here could proxy select one
single pod when one when A-U-T-C-P
connection is created the selection
is based on round robin algorithm
and it chosen pod should handle all
the requests on that connection.
So here yeah, so here everything is
working at the connection level and
nothing is inspected at the request level.
I. So why this works fine
for HTTP one traffic.
So the typical behavior of HTP one
client is that it opens multiple
short lead TCP connections.
Each new connection should be route to a
single, also to a different backend pod.
And as a result the request should
be distributed even across the pods.
In the case of HTP two, this, it doesn't
work simply because by introducing the
concept of request plexing over a single
connection, this changes a lot of things.
So the key differences
here is that the client.
Can send multiple, many requests
over one single TCP connection.
And in most of the cases,
those connection are existing.
They stay long leave.
So as a result, Kubernetes
here is gonna routing all of
the requests on that specific
connection on the open connection.
So here, all of the requests
will be brought to the same po.
So let's now explain what actually
happened in that incident.
So basically after introducing
this h, the HTT P to traffic that
one single pod get overloaded.
So the CPU's h spiked because that was
CPU throttling due to the high load.
Which was, which caused like
increasing increasing at the latency
level and as a result so yeah, and
as a result, this caused the latency
experience at the user interface.
Okay, now let's, we'll talk a
little bit about the short term
adjustment that we did to improve the
performance degradation that we have
observed during the, this incident.
So basically all of the work
that we did temporarily, it
was at the application level.
So we tool the application
keep life sitting.
Also we reduced the connection reuse for
the HTP two clients, and we did increased
the number of active connections.
So that was our temporary
solution for the incident.
So that helped doing the traffic
distribution, but basically everything
was temporary, so nothing was permanent.
So this is, just a screenshot
about the configuration that we did
quickly to save solve the problem.
Yeah.
And now the key question how
to permanently fix the issue.
So we will talk about
the long term solution.
Yeah, so the long-term solution
it was introducing layer for layer
seven routing kind of service mesh.
It could be service mesh or it could
be any H-T-T-P-O-R-O r in proxy.
Or for example, an API gateway or
ingress with request level routing.
Here you have the choice.
We did choose, in our case,
introducing service, meh,
specifically eo and the whole project.
It took about six months just to roll out.
Okay.
Yeah, so basically by adding an H-G-T-P-O
routing LA layer so the requests now
are balancing at the request level.
So the connection level
is no longer involved.
And as a result, like basically we'll
have now traffic distribution, even
traffic distribution across all the
backend pods without any, major problem.
So e even it's not that equal, but we
still have acceptant results regarding to
using the default proxy road balancing.
Yeah.
So here just a simple diagram explanation
about how the traffic flow should be.
Working in the case of TCP connection,
like the default TCP the default
Kubernetes service load balancing, and the
one when we did introduce surface mesh.
So basically we use it the layer
seven and we no longer involving the
TP connection layer in this case.
Yeah.
So basically here what the proxy is doing
is just inspecting the HTTP traffic and
making requests and making decision at
the request level based on, for example,
request path the headers if you have
any kind of routing rules configured in
your proxy this also gonna get involved.
And also then any kind of latency,
for example, or health endpoint
issues experienced at the backend pos.
This also will get into consideration by
doing the writing decisions by the proxy.
So this is a visualization diagram
about how the traffic should be
working when introducing layer
seven load balancing in Kubernetes.
Yeah.
So finally, key learning
about this incident.
Yeah, so the first one,
never rely on the default.
Could proxy load balancing when you
are introducing HTP two base traffic.
It could be persistent connections.
It could be GRPC protocol.
So any kind of traffic that is
based on HT HTP two traffic,
it's not that optimal to use.
Good proxy load balancing.
So instead you need to introduce
layer seven load balancing
for this specific use case.
Yeah.
And also try to have as many backend pos
as possible just to have enough capacity
to distribute incoming traffic easily.
Yeah, that was pretty much it.
Thank you for your attention.
Okay.