Speaker 36: Hello everyone.
My name is Vishal Sha.
I am a lead AI engineer and my work
sits at the intersection of large
language models, agent systems, and the
kind of production infrastructure that
keeps API running reliably at scale.
I have spent the last several years
designing AI power systems and one
of the most persistent underestimated
problems I keep running into isn't
model accuracy or inference speed.
It is this, when developers
hit a wall with any PI.
How do we give them a response
they can actually trust?
Today I want to share an idea.
I have been building and refining a
framework called Human in the Loop for
reliable EPI support by land of this talk.
You will have a clear technical picture
of how it works, why it is different
from what most teams are doing today,
and how you can start applying it.
Let's focus on the challenge,
balancing speed and reliability in a model
modern develop developer support systems.
Let's start with the problem because
I think we need to be honest,
but how broken the status quo is
a developer hits the 4 0 1 invalid
PITH two A. They search the docs.
The top result is a stake overflow
answer from, let's say, 2021.
That references a deprecated
authentication flow.
It's right there.
Error are changes, but it is still broken
by the time a human expert see ticket.
Ours have passed and the developer has
already introduced a misconfiguration.
Into their production environment.
This isn't a failure of
a documentation effort.
It is a structural failure.
Support systems today are either too
slow, dependent and entirely on a human
bandwidth, or too fast and wrong, LLMs
generating plausible sounding answers.
With no grounding in the
current a PA behavior, and
neither of that is acceptable.
And as AI engineers, we are in a
unique position to fix it because we
understand both the capabilities and
the failure modes of the systems.
So what do we need today is we
implement a robust support framework
that balances agility and accuracy.
We need to establish a clear
protocols for regularly updating
documentation and knowledge base.
We need to ensure that
documentation reflects.
The latest API changes and best
practices leverage automation tools to
streamline the support process, provide
developers with immediate feedback
on common queries through automation.
Reserve human resources for handling
a complex or high impact issues.
Foster a culture of continuous
learning within the team.
Now let's go to the next slide and
see how we can start achieving this.
Let me introduce a reliable API support.
So here is an, here is the media.
Reliable a PA support built on human
in the loop agent rag architecture.
Let me unpack quickly for the
technical folks in the room.
Rag retrieval, augmented generation
grounds responses in real.
Retried knowledge rather than relying on
parametric memory, baked in at training.
This is critical for API support where
documentation changes frequently and
the model training data is almost 13.
Still, the agent layer
adds active reasoning.
The system doesn't just
retrieve and paste it.
Plants queries multiple knowledge
sources, evaluate relevance,
and synthesizes a response.
Think of it as react, style, loop,
reason, act, observe, repeat until
it has enough context to generate
a high confidence provisional.
And the human in the loop component
is where this diverges from.
Standard rack chatbot, no responses
published towards developer
until it has been reviewed and
validated by a domain expert.
This is the trust layer and it is
what makes the whole system reliable.
Let's see the core
architecture components.
We have three core architecture components
com component one, and multi-source rack.
The knowledge base isn't
a single vector store.
It's a federated retrieval layer
that pulls from API documentation
version, change logs, and internal
incident reports, or curated effect
use, and even verified community exam.
Now you can see that we are relying
on so much of information and each
source is indexed with metadata version
confidence tier on last verified date,
so the retrieval pipeline can read
licensing and authority appropriate.
We use dance retrieval with
embedding models combined with spars
keyword search for exact error core
matching a hybrid approach that I
outperforms our either method alone.
Now let me take it a little further.
Let's say we have a pull off.
APIs and each pool belongs to
a specific product category.
And then we want to provide so
much of documentation to that.
We also need to come up is
the multiple vector sources.
So far what we see about curated
FAQs, internal source version
change log, that is a one.
Collection of document or a knowledge
base for just one product, API.
Now similar product, a similar collection
of documents will be there for each of
the product we are supporting from an API
perspective, see how huge the data is and
how much important this multi-source rack.
We'll become when we try to
provide a solution for such a new
system to the entire community.
Now let's jump to the second component.
Here we are focusing on
provisional response generation.
The agent doesn't just return
the top retrieved chunk.
It synthesizes across sources reasons
about conflicting information and produces
a structured response that includes a
proposed solution, supporting evidence,
and a calibrated confidence score.
Low, medium, or high.
High confidence responses still
go through review, but maybe fast
rank, low confidence responses are
flagged as priority escalations.
That is where our confidence
score and AI will also help us to
fast track the query responses.
Now let's go to third component three,
because now we have some of the responses,
which has a very low confidence score.
How we are planning to tackle that.
This is where the expert
verification comes into a picture.
This is where this human in the
loop gate comes into a picture.
Senior engineers, your s.
Review the provisional responses
against the live API spec.
They can approve, edit, or reject.
Now every edit feeds back into the
system as a label training signal.
That information will help
the turning human correction.
Into future model improvements.
That is a very important things.
Now we can go into little more details
about a query workflow where developer to
export validation, how the things work.
We will see that into the next slide.
Now, here.
Let me trace a full query
through the system so you can
see exactly how the data flows.
Now, as a step one
developer submits a query.
Let's take an example.
API request failed.
Because of Inval chain, the agent receives
this and kicks off the retrieval cycle,
and it queries the knowledge base using a
hybrid retrieval strategy, pulling chunk,
ranked by semantic similarity and score.
Then as a step two, as agent
enters a reasoning loop.
It evaluates the retrieved
context, identifies whether the
error matches a known patterns.
For example, incorrect key format
versus an expiring versus a rate
limit acceler rate, and generates a AL
response with its confidence rating.
Now step three happens, the
response goes to the expert.
Now here is a very important thing.
How do we also want to
notify an expert too?
There are so many differences.
Few of my personal likings are integrate
this with Microsoft teams, so all your
Slack or a discord where they can see
this information directly on their mobile
or they can immediately check it out,
approve it, and it can move forward.
There are so many ways we
can integrate this mechanism.
Now going back to what happens in expert
three, the reviewer sees the proposed
answer, the retrieved sources it was
grounded in, and the confidence score the
verify against the current API spec, make
any corrections, and then approve that.
The corrected response is published
to the developer and simultaneously
locked as a label example for the next
fine tuning or rag re ranking cycle.
The whole loop from query submission
to expert verified response is designed
to complete within a defined asai.
Developers get, they also get
accuracy, and your experts are
focused on judgment, not of volume.
This entire process promotes continuous
learning and ongoing improvement.
One of the key push, key part to keep
the knowledge base the data up to date.
Now let's see how the continuous
improvement timeline helps you.
Oh, before we jump to the continuous
improvement in more detail,
let's go back and check feedback
loops for enhanced reliability.
Here also, we are focusing
on continuous improvement.
Let's start first with how
the things are settled here.
Now that part of this architecture I
am most excited to talk about is the
feedback loop because this is what
separates Protic support tool from a
system that genuinely gets better over.
Every expert correction
is a labeled signal.
They if then, if the
agent proposed a solution.
A. And expert correct.
Ready to solution B. The data is captured
and over the time this direction are
used to read the retrieval system,
fine.
Tune response generation, and update the
knowledge base with verified content.
The system learns what good looks like
from the people who actually know.
User feedback adds another signal layer.
Developers can rate responses.
Did this actually solve the problem?
A thumbs up or thumbs down on
a validated response is a data
point that triggers a review.
A thumbs up reinforces the
retrieval pathway, and, excuse
me, the result is of flywheel.
More queries generate more corrections,
which improve the retrieval quality,
which increases the confidence scores.
Which reduces the expert review burden.
Over time, the system becomes more
autonomous as it earns the autonomy
through a demonstrated accuracy.
Now let me call it out.
One more thing here.
If your product is in early development,
where you are introducing so many new
API features and other things, definitely
it'll not have a high confidence score,
but your product is in a good state.
The changes are not that huge, or it is
hap or it is a situation where changes
are not happening in an existing API.
But changes are happening in a new API.
Then all the queries on existing APIs
will definitely have a high score, and
your feedback is already taken care of
generating the high confidence score.
Now let's go to the next slide
where we will discuss more about
a continuous improvement timeline.
I have actually
made it into a three phases.
What we will achieve in a phase one,
what we will achieve in a phase two,
what one can achieve in a phase three.
Obviously, whenever we make
this kind of projects, we cannot
roll out everything in one goal.
We usually try to measure our success
over the time with different metrics.
Now, I'm not discussing the
metrics here, but how we can
roll it out in different phases.
That's what I'm trying to focus here.
I want to give you a realistic roadmap
because building this correctly takes
time, and I would rather be honest
with you about the phases than over.
Sell a quick win.
Now we know phase one, the
work will be foundational.
Setting up a right pipeline,
indexing the initial knowledge base.
Building an HITL review interface and
running the first end to end test.
This phase is about
getting the plumbing route.
Every shortcut here compounds downstream.
We established a baseline retrieval
metrics precision at K. Mean
reciprocal rank to objectively
measure knowledge base quality.
Before we over touch the LLM
layer, now comes the phase two.
The system went into active use, real
developer queries started flowing through.
We it treated on the retrieval strategy.
Tune the confidence threshold and
build the feedback pipeline that routes
expert corrections back into the system.
This was also when we measure
the first meaningful reduction
in repeat ticket volume.
That should validate our approach.
Now what we can achieve in a phase three.
The focus of phase three is on
scale and monitoring, satisfaction,
core scores, response accuracy
rates, and expert review time.
All this needs to be
tracked in a dashboard.
That's just where the metrics comes.
If we want to represent, the success.
The system is now at a point where high
confident responses can be fast tracked
with a minimum touch or light touch,
and that should free freer an expert
bandwidth for a genuinely hard problems.
Now let's take a step back
and compare our traditional
support through this new support
in.
What will be the benefit
to the tail community?
So let me be direct about the risk
of the alternating, because this
isn't just an optimization, it is
a risk management decision as well.
Traditional API support
has two failure modes.
First is the static documentation models.
Docs go still.
Developers follow updated guidance and
you get production misconfiguration
that trace back to a support resource
that was last updated eight months ago.
And it's a realistic problem.
Whoever has seen this kind of scenarios.
As a developer, we go and make the
applications or API, updating very fast
that goes deployed to the production.
But there is a lot, many time happens
that the API documentation, which is
publicly available, not immediately
updated, or it takes some time to operate.
Now, that's where the
misinformation gets in.
The second failure mode is.
The Nave lab, LLM, check
Bot, which is fast, which is
fluent and frequently wrong.
L lms, hallucinate, they confidently
describe API behaviors that don't
exist in the current version
because when was trained, those
information, was not even available.
Okay.
Without grounding layer and
the verification gate, you are
handling a developer's system.
That sounds authoritative, but it's not
Human in the loop agent
approach addresses both.
The rag layer ensures responses
are grounded in concurrent.
We verify documentation and
not into the model memory.
The HITL gate ensures that before any
response reaches a developer, a domain
expert has confirmed its accuracy
and the feedback loop ensures the
system corrects itself rather than
repeating errors for Sari e teams.
This maps directly to reducing
while improving MTTR and building
the kind of trust in your support
system that actually scales
key takeaways for reliable API support.
Let me crystallize this into
four engineering principle I
would put on the wall of any team
building this kind of system.
Number one, ground every response.
Parametric model knowledge is a liability
in fast moving API environments.
Rag with version metadata.
Tag the sources is non-negotiable.
Number two, calibrate confidence
explicitly don't like the system.
Treat all responses equally.
Build a confidence score into the
architecture from day one and use
it to route responses appropriately.
Fast track the high confidence 'cause
you don't need your expert review,
but at the same time, escalate the
low confidence so that expert can
pitch in and provide the right answer.
Now, number three is make H-I-T-L-A first
class component, not an afterthought.
The expert review interface matters.
If reviewing a response takes
more effort than writing one from
scratch, your experts will route
around it, designed for low friction.
Number four, close the loop.
Every correction is a training signal.
If you're not capturing and using that
signal, you are leaving the most valuable
data in your system on the table.
Now let's go to the next slide and talk
about next steps for enhanced API support.
So if you want to start building something
like this, or you wanna evaluate whether
your current set of has this property,
here is how I would approach it.
Start with an audit.
Pull your last three
months of support tickets.
What are the top 10 error types?
Which ones keep recurring that tells
you where the ever, where the knowledge
gaps are and gives you a prioritized
backlog for your initial knowledge base?
Bill?
Then build the retrieval layer first
before you touch any LLM integration.
Invest in getting your documentation
indexed version and queryable measure
retrieval quality with objective metrics.
A great rag pipeline on mediocre
retrieval will always under performance.
Simple pipeline on great review
layer in the LLM response generation.
Once your retrieval is solid,
add confidence scoring.
Build A ITL review queue or human in the
loop review queue instrument, everything.
Retrieval latency response,
approval rate on expert edit
rate, developer satisfaction.
This matrix style, where the system is
working and where it needs attention.
Architecture is sound.
The tooling exists.
The only thing standing between you,
your team, and the support system
developers can genuinely trust.
Is the decision to build intentionally.
That being said, that's what the idea is,
and I thank you.