Speaker 8: Hello everyone.
Thank you for joining my session today.
I will be speaking on.
Sorry for national scale regulatory
reporting, high availability,
disaster recovery audit design.
In this session, I'll explain why
regulatory reporting systems need a
different reliability model than a
traditional enterprise applications,
and how high availability,
disaster recovery and audit designs
together create a resilient and
a complaints focused platform.
A regulated reporting infrastructure
is very different from normal
business systems because it operates.
Stakes are much higher.
Data volumes continue
to increase submission.
Windows are shrinking and regulatory
aspects, outputs that are both
accurate and fully auditable.
In these enrollments, a delay is just
not a service issue, and an incorrect
output is not just a data issue.
Both can become complicated failures.
This result in penalties.
Further financial institutes.
That's why reliability has been built,
architecture from the beginning.
The core challenge is that
many legacy architectures.
Were not built for national
scale regulatory workloads.
They often struggle in five critical
areas, high availability, peak load
performance, data accuracy, auditable
outcomes, and disaster resilience.
During a reporting windows, even a
small outage or a slowdown can impact
submissions timelines at the same time,
every transformation must remain accurate.
Even results must be traceable,
and the platform must recover
quickly from the failures without
losing your data consistently.
This session follows a simple flow.
First, I explain why legacy reporting
platforms fail under modernization,
regulatory reporting pressure.
Next, I'll be moving towards the design
principles for high availability,
disaster recovery and audit readiness.
Topics then will give a brief walkthrough
to end-to-end reference architecture
and the major operational controls.
Finally I'll close with practical
implementation guidelines and
the key takeaways for building in
repeatable regulatory SRE model.
One of the most important ideas
in this presentation is that SRE,
just not an operational function
here in regulatory environments.
SRA directly affects compliance outcomes.
If a reporting badge misses a
deadline because of a poor failure
or a weakness in the process, or
insufficient capacity or a planning,
this won't be an operational issue.
It becomes a compliance issue.
This means service level.
Object to incident response,
error, budgets and all need to be
aligned with regulatory reporting,
deadlines and commitments.
Before selecting tools for the platforms,
the architecture must be driven by
three non-negotiable requirements,
high availability, disaster recovery.
Audit readiness I availability means
eliminating a single point of a
failure and maintaining a predictable
performance during critical windows.
Disaster recovery means recovery.
Targets must be aligned with
filing deadlines, not high.
Generic IT recovery goals.
Audit readiness means the system
must preserve enough evidence to
explain trace and reproduce if it
is submissions whenever is needed.
This slide shows end-to-end
reporting pipeline, including the
ingestion, validation, transformation
submissions, monitoring and audit play.
Each stage has a different
technical responsibilities
and a different failure modes.
The key design principles here is a
fault, isolation, a problem in one
stage, should not silent, corrupt.
Down system processing.
A mature regulatory pipeline is not just
moving a data from source to destination.
It also preserving the control,
traceability, and evidence
at each step of its process.
High availability in regulatory
reporting is about more than
just keeping the systems online.
The platforms must also maintain stable.
Throughput during a peak filing window
that require active redundancy, stateless
scaling when possible, durable storage
for critical state resilient load
balancing and automated health checks.
The important point is that
availability must be tested under
bus traffic and peak concurrency,
not only under normal daily load.
Disaster recovery for regulatory
deporting must be deadline aware.
Recovery objectives cannot
be chosen in isolation.
They must be tied directly to how much
time remains before a submission cutoff.
For example, if an outage happens
close to a filing deadline.
The platform still needs enough time
to recover, validate the data, complete
the processing, and submit the results,
and it should have enough time to
validate the results before submitting.
This is why failover must be tested
under realistic load conditions and not
treated as a theoretical design exercise.
This slide focus on audit readiness,
which is one of the most important thing.
Regulatory reporting system, the platform
must not only produce the correct
submissions, but also prove exactly how
the submissions was corrected, created
that require immutable logs, full data
lineage, and deterministic replay.
In other words, we need to know the data.
Coming in, what roles we are applying in
and what ions were performed, and must be
able to rerun the process and reproduce
the same results whenever it was asked.
Traditional infrastructure
monitoring alone is not enough
for regulatory workloads.
We also need observability in
the business process level.
That means tracking record count,
validations, pass, and fail rates.
Q, depth, stage, level
latency, submission, timings,
and acknowledgement status.
A server metrics may show that
mission is under stress, but business
telemetry tells us whether the
reporting deadlines itself is at risk.
One of the highest risk in regulatory
reporting is silent failure.
A platform may appear healthy
while records are being dropped.
Validations are skipped
or acknowledgements are
never fully confirmed.
These failures are especially
dangerous because they may not be
discovered until much later during
the audit or regulatory review.
This prevents the architecture needs
to end validation gates and controls
experts, confirmations that need
each record as a correct outcome.
In many organizations, regulatory
reporting platforms cannot be fully
cloud new because of security presidency
or legacy integration constraints.
That is why DS must work across
both cloud and hybrid and
environments that target is not.
Simple to move everything to a cloud.
The target is to create a platform that
can controllable, observable, resilient,
and audit readiness in any premise.
The practical message here is
that organizations do not need
to rebuild everything at once.
A good starting point is to identify
current failure modes, define compliance.
Aligned service level objectives
improves telemetry and test
and disaster recovery events.
In your real scenarios, audit controls
can be strengthened incremental,
especially around submission gates.
In other words, the path for road
is to measure first modernize
intelligently and harden the most
critical control step by step.
When reliability engineering is
treated as a co-design principles,
the cells are measurable.
Organizations typically see a
better throughput, lower end-to-end
processing times, and data accuracy.
These are not just
operational improvements.
They are also strengthened compliance,
confident because the reporting
platform becomes more predictable,
more transparent, and easy to defend
during the audit and regulatory reviews.
The key takeaway takeaways from
this session are straightforward.
First, in regulatory reporting and
enrollments, reliability, engineering
directly shapes the compliance outcomes.
Second, high availability.
Disaster recovery and audit
readiness must be defined as
designed, constrained from the start.
Third, the silent failures are often
more dangerous than visible outage.
And finally, disaster recovery is only.
Credible whenever it's tested
under realistic conditions.
The final architecture view
brings everything together into
repeatable reference model.
It organized the platform into a layer,
capabilities and ingestion, process
submissions and observability services.
The value of this model is that support
incremental adoption teams can modernize
and harden one layer at a time.
Thank you for everyone for
giving this opportunity.