Hello everyone.
Good morning, good afternoon, and
good evening to wherever you are.
I am really excited and thrilled to
be speaking in front of you today.
Today I'm going to be talking
about unlocking observability
with react and no J Applications.
My name is Moi Ani.
I am currently a staff software
engineer for Twilio and I've been
with them for almost four years.
I'm part of the phone numbers
product and what my team is basically
responsible for is procuring numbers
and all of its management so we
can enable our cross channels like
email messaging and also drive other
communication products as well.
But for today we'll be diving
into a critical piece of.
Full stack observability specifically
for applications built with React
on the front end and no js on the
backend in today's digital landscape.
Understanding how these two key parts
of our application work together
has become more important than ever.
So without further ado, let's dive in.
So quickly going through the agenda
today first I'll be talking a little
bit about why do I think there is
a need for a unified view, and then
I will talk about what does this
unified full stack observability mean.
Then next we will look at how
can we correlate the data that
we receive on front end with
the backend for observability.
Some case studies tools, best
practices, and then we'll conclude
with some some of our findings.
Our applications are no longer monolith.
We have sophisticated user interfaces
built with React, interacting with
backend APIs, powered by node js.
This complexity makes it challenging
to understand the root case, root
cause of issues when we treat the front
end and backend as isolated systems.
Traditional monitoring approaches
which look at these in silos,
often fail to capture the crucial
interactions between them.
This is where full track
observability comes in, offering
a way to see the entire picture.
One example that I really like to use it,
think of it like, trying to understand
a play only by watching the actors on
stage or just by reading the script.
You need both to grasp the full narrative.
Similarly, we need to see both the
user experience and the server's
operations to truly understand
the state of our applications.
So what exactly is unified
full stack observability for
react and no J applications?
It's about having a single comprehensive
view of everything that's happening, right
from the user's interaction on the React
interface to the server side logic, and
then data handling at the data layer.
This approach recognizes that the front
end and backend are deeply connected.
And their performance
would impact each other.
To achieve this, we basically need
tools that can automatically link data
from both sides, giving us a complete
understanding without any manual effort.
This is a significant step up
from traditional monitoring
with the front end and backend.
Teams would look at these
things in isolation.
They will have their own dashboards, and
then they will try to connect the dots.
Okay.
Imagine a slow loading page.
Is it the React code
rendering, the network request?
The No J server processing
or a database query?
Unified observability should help
us answer this exact situation.
It moves us beyond from just
knowing what is happening, to
understanding where in the system it
is happening and why it is happening.
So let's talk about why should
we strive for this unified,
integrated observability?
The benefits are substantial.
First, when issues would arise, we can
pinpoint by looking at the dashboard
the cause much faster because we are
looking at a complete picture, right?
So it'll cause a significant
or reduced MTTR or MTTD.
Secondly, it fosters better collaboration
between the front end and backend
teams as they would have a shared,
collected view of the system's health.
Thirdly, we can gain deeper insights
into the performance and then use it to
prepare for ongoing releases as well.
This will also help us in
identifying the bottlenecks.
That might span across a front end
backend, or it could also be something
between front end and backend.
This data then allows us to make informed
decisions about how we can optimize
our applications and also allocate
these resources more effectively.
Finally we can use anomaly detection.
Across our entire stack which
can, which will often help us to
catch potential problems before
they can even affect our users.
Ultimately as we've discussed this would
lead to a much better user engagement.
To the point I would like to say
happiness for our users and customers.
More efficient development cycles.
At a more stable, more efficient,
and a more reliable application.
Think about also the cost savings
from reduced downtime and the
increased user satisfaction from
consistently performing application.
So next, the interesting part is how
do we correlate the data coming from
the front end and the backend, right?
Because as we just discussed, we want
our whatever action is happening from
front end, we want to be able to click
it down from backend to the data.
There are several
techniques to achieve this.
One is trace propagation.
Where a unique ID is generated and
whatever user action happens it's
basically assigned a unique id.
And that unique ID is carried
through the backend requests.
We do have some standards for that, like
trace context and adders and like Ry
Trace or Trace Parent facilitate this.
Another thing we can do is we can use
correlation IDs or session IDs to link
these user activities and embed these
IDs and our logs allows, will allow
us to trace a re request journey.
And importantly, many observability
platforms integrate real user
monitoring on the front end.
With a PM on the backend application
prog performance monitoring
automating this correlation.
Open Telemetry provides a vendor
neutral way to implement this
context propagation as well.
As you can see I've added a
request with get host transparent
and Trace Parent and trace State.
This ensures that when a user clicks
on the button on the front end, we
can follow that specific action as
it travels through the entire system.
If we do not have it.
You are basically looking at fragmented
pieces of information, and as
discussed earlier, this definitely
makes debugging very difficult.
Now to effectively monitor our
react and node JS applications,
we need to target track specific
KPIs or key performance indicators.
So I've added some key performance
indicators in this table.
Let's go through them one, one by one.
And I think they are some
of the most important ones.
For example, users perceive
latency tells us how quickly
or how fast the application is.
Error rates across both front end
and back end are basically telling
us how stable the application is.
What kind of errors can also be monitored,
are being experienced by the users.
Then we have end-to-end request
latency, which basically shows us the
total time a given request is taking.
Then we have throughput,
which is basically how much
our application can handle.
Then our resource utilization helps
us identify our potential bottlenecks.
You can figure out which part of our
resource chain is getting slow or acting
up, and we can address this accordingly.
Then user engagement metrics is
connecting performance to user
behavior and core pep vitals
are crucial for understanding the
front end user experience, which
is often influenced by the backend.
Tracking these KPIs together like
in a dashboard, a setup will give
us a comprehensive understanding
of our application's health, both
on the front end and backend.
And these KPIs in a way could, the way
I see it as that they would basically be
starting conversation starters for front
end backend teams to discuss performance.
By monitoring these, my
metrics holistically.
We can understand how changes in
one part of the stack can affect
the other, and ultimately the user
experience and the user engagement.
So as we discussed, distributed tracing
is a powerful technique for understanding
how requests flow through the application.
It involves breaking down each
request into a series of operations.
That's called a span.
And a series of a series
of spans form a trace.
Now the key here, as I mentioned, was
the key here is context propagation,
ensuring that each span, whether it's on
the front end or the backend, is linked
together using the unique trace id.
This allows us to visualize
the entire journey of a request
and pinpoint exactly where any
slowdowns or errors are happening.
Telemetry provides a standard
approach for this to implement this.
And tools like Yeager and Zipkin
allow us to visualize these traces.
Now let's imagine a slow, API call
distributed tracing would allow us to see.
If the delay is in the front end, making
the request, the backend receiving
it, or a specific function within
the backend, a database query, or it
could be like a external service call,
which is taking a really long time.
This level of detail is invaluable
for very efficient debugging.
Now let's look at some
real world scenarios.
Imagine if there was a sudden increase
in your errors on the React front
end with unified observability.
You would be able to see that this might,
let's say, be coinciding with an increased
latency in your specific backend.
API call immediately pointing to the
backend as a source of problem, or
perhaps you notice that users are taking
a particular path on the front end.
That leads to high CPU usage
on the backend service.
This could be a specific
endpoint or a specific route.
By seeing both these sites you can
optimize that the specific user flow.
For instance, if a user has a payment
failure, a trace might show you the
front end request, the call to your
back backend, and then a timeout when
your backend is trying to communicate
with a third party payment gateway.
Okay.
Similarly, slow loading of product images
on the front end might be traced back
to a slow API response from your node
JS server fetching that image data.
Now, for those using the MON Stack
observability solutions often
provide specific integrations to
monitor all of these components.
Together, these examples highlight
how unified observability
transforms, debugging from
guesswork to a very precise science.
By connecting this user behavior with
backend performance, we can quickly
understand the impact of technical
issues on the user experience without
losing that critical time during
an incident, and obviously saving
a lot on the revenue side as well.
Okay.
Let's look at some of the tooling
and products available to us for
implementing this unified observability.
Again, it's a very
crowded space right now.
You have platforms like Datadog and
New Relic, which offer comprehensive
solutions for both React and node js.
Allowing for a seamless
correlation of data.
We have Honeycomb, which focuses
on providing a unified way to
analyze all of our telemetry.
Then we have our Dynatrace ai.
They they basically help us and detect and
analyze issues across the stack as well.
Then you have Elastic Observability and
Grafana Cloud providing robust platforms
for unifying and visualizing data.
Observe specifically focuses on
connecting the front end user
experience with backend troubleshooting.
We have open observe, which is
an open source alternative which
has an open source alternative.
And then underpinning most of these
solutions is open telemetry, which
provides a standardized way to
instrument our all our applications.
Myself for Twilio, we are considering
Open Elementary right now.
Again, I think it's there's
no one size fits all.
Choosing the right tool
depends on your specific needs.
What is the scale and where the,
what your exact requirements
are based on your stack.
Most of these companies offer free
trials, so I would recommend also
exploring doing a few POCs and
taking feedback with the team.
To figure out which we which one fits
your team's work for the best and
provides the insights that you guys need.
Awesome.
So let's talk about
some best practices now.
To truly leverage Unified Observability,
we need to adopt some best practices,
creating dashboards that show key metrics.
And traces from both our front end
and not just backend in one place.
I think it's very essential
for a holistic high level view.
We should set up alerts that
trigger based on correlated data.
For example alerting us only when we
see both us spike in front end errors
and an increase in backend latency.
Then comes
then comes anomaly detection.
Which can help us catch issues
we didn't even know to look for.
Consistent tagging of our telemetry
data also makes it easy to filter and
correlate information.
Defining clear observability goals
and service level objectives helps us
understand what good looks like and
also improves our monitoring setup.
Finally, it is crucial for, to involve
both our front end and backend teams in
defining what we monitor and how we are
alerted, ensuring everyone has a shared
understanding of what good looks like and
making us a very strong, cohesive unit.
One more thing to remember is we
are not just collecting data, but
we need to collect the right data.
And then how do we turn that
data into actionable insights?
Only then we can improve our
application and the user experience.
Regularly review your dashboards
and alerts to ensure they're
still relevant and provide value.
To conclude this talk, embracing
Unified Full Stack Observability
for our React and node applications
offer significant advantages.
It allows us to resolve issues
more quickly, gain deeper insight
into our application performance.
And also allow allow us to resolve
and proactively address
potential problems.
By moving away from siloed monitoring,
we can achieve a much more comprehensive
understanding of our systems.
With the help of modern tools and
open standards like Open Telemetry,
this approach is becoming increasingly
accessible and essential for
building and maintaining reliable.
High performing applications that
deliver excellent user experiences.
To finish, I would like to say
that it, we have the right tools.
It's just that how we use them
to understand and manage these
complex systems efficiently.
Unified, full stack observative
is not just a trend.
But I think it's a fundamental shift
towards building more resilient
and user-centric applications.
I want to thank all of you
for listening to this talk.
I had a really great time sharing
all these insights with you.
If you have more questions, please
don't hesitate to reach out to me and
I look forward to connecting with you.
Bye-bye.