Okay, thanks for.
Joining my session this is
Tackling Alert Fatigue with SLOs.
My name is Mandy Walls.
I am a developer advocate for PagerDuty.
And if you'd like to get in touch
with me, I'm happy to chat anytime.
You can email me.
I'm mWalls@pagerduty.com.
You can reach out on Blue Sky, you can
hit me up on LinkedIn if you'd like.
You can reach out to our whole team.
We're community team@pager.com.
Or you can scan that QR code and join our
community forums if you are a PagerDuty
customer or maybe in the future, you
can join us there and hang out, ask
questions, answer questions share fun.
It's all good stuff.
So that's all I'm really gonna talk
about as far as PagerDuty goes.
So if you have other questions
about our product, please
join us in those other forms.
So I'm gonna be talking about
alert fatigue and using SLOs
to help you deal with that.
So let's let's set a baseline for
what alert fatigue actually is.
A lot of you out there may have actually
experienced alert fatigue, maybe even
if you didn't really know that term.
But basically alert fatigue
can happen when your team is.
Constantly inundated with alerts, events,
alarms, notifications, sirens, claxons,
blinking lights whatever the case might
be from your various monitoring systems.
And we know folks have a lot of different
monitoring systems depending on the
solutions that they need for all of
the services in their environment.
So there's lots of stuff out
there that can be sending you.
Noise notifications, and it doesn't really
matter if the alert is a positive event,
a negative event, high priority, low
priority, false positive, whatever it is.
We're really just dealing with the,
just the sheer volume of alerts,
distractions, things that pull you
out of your work, that contribute
then to what we call alert fatigue.
Unfortunately.
Our entire working life is full
of things that alert at us, right?
Your chat application,
your email, your phone.
Like I turn a lot of notifications
off, but I know lots of folks don't
like, they fear they're gonna miss an
important notification or whatever it is.
But like I'm in 15 different slacks.
None of them get to play any sounds.
So like when I hear someone
else's slack noises.
On a call.
I'm like, do you really
need to know the noise?
Oh my gosh, that would drive me crazy.
So you're already in a place
where we're set up to be
distracted all the time anyway.
And then if your team has production
responsibilities, you have all this
other stuff that then piles on top of
that and it really can just drive people
crazy, when we talk to, folks who are,
who maybe called pre on-call folks who
aren't going to, aren't on call yet,
but are going to be on call, right?
They don't currently have on-call
responsibilities, but it's coming.
That's one of the things they
worry about is you know, how many
alerts are there going to be?
How often am I going to be pulled
out of the other things that I'm
doing, the other work that I'm
doing, or even, my personal time, my
sleep, and all that kind of stuff.
It's the biggest part of,
dealing with being on call.
It's just the volume of
things to come through.
What we want then is to make
sure that the stuff that.
Comes through to notifying human beings
about the production environment is
gonna be the right stuff, going to
the right people at the right time,
and it's going to be important.
And we find that too many teams.
Alert on stuff that doesn't
really meet that criteria.
So there are lots of concerns about
the volume of alerts that teams
get and how they deal with them.
For the rest of this talk, I'm gonna be
referring to alerts as specifically the
real time events that send notifications
to some human responder, right?
So there's lots of
different terms for that.
Different products, call
them different things.
And we're just gonna be referring
to those just generically as alerts,
but specifically the things that
need to be actioned in real time.
They represent some kind of, or
hopefully represent some kind of
issue in your production environments.
We're gonna focus on
that sort of definition.
So there's plenty of signs of alert
fatigue, some of the main ones.
Maybe you've experienced these, maybe
you see them on your team right now.
The big one is going to
be delayed response time.
That's going to impact your
customer experience, right?
Your potentially your bottom line as well.
If there's a lot of alerts, it
takes longer to deal with the volume
and find the real problems, right?
Because you're constantly
shifting through all this stuff
that's maybe junk, not helpful.
Not informational enough
to do anything about.
We also find that folks
just simply miss alerts.
It looks like all of these 10 things
are the same, but it turns out that
the ninth one was just a little bit
different and actually a problem.
But again, if you're drowning under a
huge volume of alerts, it's a lot more
likely you're gonna miss something.
Folks also ignore false
positives for the same reason.
Everything looks the same,
and you just assume that.
It's the same as those other
ones and maybe it wasn't, right.
New alerts may look like they're
not a problem when they are.
All of this then leads to
increased stress and burnout.
We see this across the board for very
busy teams with very rate high rates of
incidents and notifications during their
on-call shifts anyway, and the volume of
alerts is definitely contributor to that.
Based on market conditions.
Sometimes folks will leave,
sometimes they feel like they can't.
There's a bit of that, but at the
same time, like job satisfaction,
stress, burnout, if you are especially
a team manager, team lead, those are
things that should concern you, right?
Like folks are going to their job
quality will decrease if they are
under a lot of stress and maybe not
sleeping, or they're feeling burned out.
So that's something to keep an eye
on overall, then it all contributes
to decreased productivity.
That's probably the
most obvious one, right?
There's lots of alerts coming in,
there's more distractions, there's
less useful work being done.
And while one of our primary
recommendations for folks who are going
to be on call is that they don't carry
a regular workload during their on-call
shift for that week or whatever it is.
They still should be able
to do something, right?
We don't want them constantly inundated,
just buried under a flood of alerts 24
by seven while they're on call, because
there's always work that can be done as
far as like documentation or updating
monitors and those kinds of things.
But overall, what we end up seeing on
teams that have too many alerts is a great
decrease in their productivity overall.
Then that gives you.
The less ability to learn from all
the stuff that is coming in, right?
You have lower quality, instant
reviews and documentation.
'cause there simply isn't
enough time to deal with all
of the stuff that's coming in.
Sift through it, find the things are
important, find the things that you
haven't seen before, document those update
monitors, whatever the case might be.
They folks just never catch up
to do that kind of work that.
Is the stuff that we really
want to get out of having
incidents in the first place.
We bring these alerts into our systems
because there is something wrong and
we want to get to a place where we
can shore up the systems so that we
don't see those problems the same way
in another time when we run outta time
to do that if folks are too buried.
So some basic things we can
be doing to improve your alert
volume and overall alert health.
Are going to help us before
we can get to using SLOs.
Even if you don't have access to SLOs,
these things are gonna help you, right?
So if you haven't gotten to a place
yet where you're going to deploy those,
or think about SLOs, this stuff is
still gonna help you if you feel like
you have too many alerts coming in.
So we'll set a good baseline for
things all teams can really be
doing or thinking about to improve
their overall alert volume.
The first one's a big one.
Like just get rid of something that's
alerting you when something succeeds.
There are very few cases where
this additional noise is helpful.
Like I, we're all dopa fanatics.
But get your dopamine hit on Instagram
or social media or somewhere else
don't have your systems like constantly
pinging you with success, right?
Unless you absolutely need to know in
real time that something succeeded.
Maybe you've got like a long running
pipeline, or you've got some ETLs
that are important or whatever.
Some reports or something that runs
none of that stuff really should
come to your real time notifications.
And by that comes to your phone pages.
You in the middle of the night,
sends a text message, like
that kind of immediate stuff.
Things that go to chat channels that can
be responded to asynchronously that are
deferred for not necessarily real time.
That's great.
That's a great place to put
those kinds of notifications.
Where they don't need to be
coming to is basically what you
think of as your pager, right?
For your emergencies.
Number two, get rid of
anything that isn't actionable.
I know there's stuff out there that
I was assisted men for a long time.
There's chronic issues.
Let's sneak into the production
systems, and if it's stuff that happens
all the time and can't be fixed and
the people that you're notifying
about it can't do anything about it
anyway, don't notify them about it.
Track it as a metric to say,
oh yeah, last week this thing
happened 17 times this week.
It's looking like it's
gonna happen 25 times.
Use that as leverage to get things
fixed with your product managers.
Have that discussion, especially if you're
the manager or team lead advocate for
time to fix these chronic issues, but
don't notify people who can't fix them.
Part of that too is making sure
alerts go to the right people.
So if you have a bunch of stuff that
comes into your team that's like.
This isn't really our responsibility.
We don't have access to fix this stuff.
Maybe it should go to
somebody else, have a talk.
With that other team that should
be getting those notifications.
I know that's challenging in lots of
environments because you've got like lots
of different platform teams and someone's
responsible for the cloud account.
Maybe somebody else is running
your Kubernetes and then you
have your application teams
and they know about the code.
There's a lot of division of labor
and you wanna make sure all those
alerts go to the right places.
But if stuff is coming into your
team can't do anything about,
you don't want it, turn it off.
Anything else that's low urgency
that's coming in is just an
informational notification.
Shouldn't be going to real
time notifications to humans
again, somewhere else.
Put it to Slack or Teams or whatever.
Something that's asynchronous that's
just there for information, right?
Have a channel for your bots
on your chat and pipe it there.
Not to a place that is going to notify
someone at three o'clock in the morning.
Right?
Low urgency.
Maybe it comes into your regular
system, but it doesn't notify people.
You can set in PagerDuty in particular,
you can set the notifications to not.
Notify people via SMS or app
push for low urgency alerts and
they just will hang out there.
You could have a goalie or
triage time in the morning to
say, okay, nine 30 we're here.
We're gonna go through everything
that came in overnight that was low
urgency and deal with it that way.
You can also push things maybe
to a ticketing system instead
of your real time notifications.
If it's stuff that can really be
deferred and be decided on later, you
can be super aggressive with these.
I know everyone thinks their
baby is beautiful, but if you put
stuff out into production and your
users aren't engaging with it.
Maybe you can think about lowering
the urgency of your response to those
parts of the service and reevaluating
those on a regular basis to say, has
this reached a threshold where we need
to up it to 24 by seven urgency, high
urgency alerts, or things like that.
Be aggressive with all of those, right?
And then finally delete
or suspend broken alerts.
Like it happens code changes somewhere
and there's, a mess and like the monitors
don't quite work, but you haven't
had time to go back and really dis
distinguish like why they don't work.
Good practice means all the alerts get
updated when the code changes, but if
you've got janky stuff sitting around.
You might have some of these old alerts
that aren't being super helpful, don't
necessarily reflect the state of the
current code and, just dump them.
If you wanna save them for a while just to
make sure that maybe you can go back and
fix them, that's fine, but disable them.
You don't have to turn them on to
keep them ping people in the middle
of the night if they don't need to.
What you're doing with
this whole practice is.
Helping with alert fatigue by
creating mental space, right?
You're increasing the cognitive capacity
of your team to deal with the things
that are real and urgent and impactful
by getting rid of all the stuff that
doesn't meet that barrier, right?
Everything that is extraneous.
So if the alert isn't real, dump it.
If it's not urgent, create a record.
Make a ticket.
When you're left with just
the stuff you care about, then
you can be more productive.
So how can you go about doing
this if you feel like your team
is really drowning under a lot of
alerts that aren't useful to you?
Try and declare an alert, cleanup,
sprint, whatever it takes.
You are the impacts of alert
fatigue are real, right?
We talked about them in the beginning.
They are going to be impactful for the
reliability of your services and systems.
So if you are in danger of experiencing
alert fatigue, it is worth investing the
time, and it is an investment, right?
It does take resources to fix the things
that are going to impact your reliability.
That means you cannot be
missing important alerts.
You cannot be ignoring the
things that are coming in.
But if you have too many alerts.
You are gonna have to deal with that.
So give your team some time to take
stock of the alerts you are getting if
you feel like you have too many, right?
If you start with, say, the 10
most noisy alerts, you walk through
the list by frequency, you deal
with the noisiest first and a
kind of snowball effect, right?
So we deal with teams that have tens
of thousands of alerts in a week, and
like they use AIOps and some of the
other tools to group things together
into a limited number of incidents.
But like taking stock of all those.
Alerts and making sure that
they are meeting your criteria
is going to be super helpful.
And just going through them
list by list for every alert.
Marie Kondo, that thing, right?
Is it actionable?
If not, we're not gonna alert like
we will maybe track it as a metric,
leave it in the dashboard, but it
doesn't have to go to somebody's
pager in the middle of the night.
Is it urgent?
If yes, fine.
Get it in front of a responder.
If not, log it to future work.
Send it to the Slack channel.
Create a low urgency queue, whatever
it takes, but get it out of the
flow that's gonna wake someone
up in the middle of the night.
Is it telling you something important
about the performance of the service?
That is a big one, and we're
gonna talk about that more.
If it doesn't turn it off, set it
aside for discussion, maybe revisit
it if it might be helpful, right?
You want to take a good look
at what you're alerting on and
how you're alerting about it.
If you have a bunch of baseline
alerts that come in all the time.
It's maybe time to have another
sprint about best practices
for your services, right?
Stuff like running out of capacity have
a discussion about how to set up the
system so they rightsize automatically
how to see the trends that would lead to.
Services being outta capacity.
If you're running in Kubernetes
environments, all that
stuff is available, right?
You just need to be able to make
sure you're deploying it correctly.
Things like memory leaks,
other chronic issues.
You might have to have a discussion
with your product managers.
Put that stuff in the backlog
for engineering investigation
to get it fixed, right?
I used to work in Java applications
and like memory leaks are par for
the course at that time, deal with
those in a more productive way.
Just don't it's easy to get to
feel like you're not gonna make any
progress with these if they have
been alerting for a very long time.
But you can push back on your product
managers and have that discussion.
'cause again, if it's gonna
impact your reliability, sometimes
these things get hidden, right?
If you've got a service that has.
A thousand instances across however
many availability zones, like it
is easy to hide that one of them is
restarting for a memory leak every so
often, but can still be a chronic issue.
You may have a lot of legacy alerts
that no longer make sense, right?
Depending on the mix
of newer versus legacy.
Services in your environment.
You may still have stuff that's
like alerting on disc full and
things like that really take a
hard look at whether the or not.
Those things are super helpful to you.
They feel comfortable, right?
We, they're well understood if nothing
else but they may not be anything
that actually gives you a hint
of the performance of the system.
There may be some that are there that
might be helpful, but there's gonna
be a whole lot more that maybe aren't.
So once you've called these alerts,
take a hard look at the ones that
you've determined are important.
Part of the problem we see folks deal with
is a lot of their alerts look the same.
You look through a list of incidents
that have been created, you cannot
tell from one incident to the next
what exactly why they're different.
Because the first couple of
lines are all exactly the same.
Are your alerts giving
you enough information?
Can responders tell that something
important is going on from the
first initial line of the report?
This is easier to do in some
monitoring systems than others.
Some of them are very verbose.
They give you a lot of stuff, but.
The stuff that's important and indicates
what's going on, if something's
hidden or hard to find right, or hard
to surface in a way that makes it
immediately apparent to your responders.
And we get a lot of questions about
this because folks are relying on
SMS in particular, and the questions
always are can we add more to the SMS?
Can we add links to the SMS?
Can we do this?
Can we do that?
The long answer is a whole other talk,
but the short answer unfortunately is no.
Because SMS is governed basically by
each country in the world, like everybody
has their own different regulations.
Some places you're not
allowed to send a link at all.
And the US we get a lot of spam.
Suddenly there's other things that
are allowed and disallowed and
there's all these rules about it.
So we've dialed back our SMS.
On our delivery systems to
be lowest common denominator.
So you're very limited in
what things can go through.
'cause we're a global company.
We have customers all over the world.
To avoid those kinds of undeliver ability
errors, we've cut things way back.
So thinking about how your
notifications will get to your humans.
Is also part of making sure that
your alerts are working correctly.
The other part, like I mentioned
earlier, is making sure they're
getting to the right team.
If you have division of
responsibility across the
different layers of your platforms.
Also making sure that all those
actionable things are going to the
team that can actually do the action.
Also super important, right?
If your application development
team knows nothing about the
Kubernetes other than it packages up.
Their CICD tool packages
things up into a container.
You can't ask them to respond to
errors in the Kubernetes layer.
Same with the virtualization
layer, whatever it is, right?
However many different teams you
might have responsible for things,
making sure that when that alert comes
in, the responders that receive it,
have the access and knowledge to fix
it, is part of all of this as well.
And if you need to ship
things off to another team.
That's also helpful if you are in a
more sort of advisory SRE kind of role,
putting together good guidelines about
that sort of separation of duties and
separation of alerts and what alerts
should look like, should be part of
the things you provide for folks.
It's part of your.
Golden path, right?
It's part of your best practices, your
recommendations for getting things into
production, what these alerts should look
like, where they should go, what kind of
information they should convey, right?
It's all part of that advisory role,
if that is how your SRE team is set up.
So there's a lot of.
Things to think about there
and things to work on.
If you are coming into this from a place
where you have a lot of noise in your
alerts, maybe a lot of legacy systems
to deal with that maybe are being
modernized or reworked or whatever.
So there's a lot of, it feels
like it should be super simple and
unfortunately it never is, right?
Because this systems themselves are
complex, making sure they're running
correctly is also going to be complex,
and that's where SLOs come into the play.
Once we've cleaned up our junk alerts,
it's time to talk about improving
the alerts that aren't junk, right?
So if you're not currently working with
SLOs and SLIs, or maybe you're planning on
looking at those to improve your position,
your reliability, there's lots of.
Resources.
I'll mention a couple at the end
that you can take a look at, but SLOs
essentially are the team goals that
you set for your production metrics.
They are usually inside any
contractually obligated SLA, so like SLA.
Often has lawyers involved.
There's contracts involved, like
that's the legal part, right?
Like service level agreements between
your company and your customers.
Your SLIs, your SLOs sit inside of that.
And what I mean by that is if you
are a promising 99.9% reliability
on some system, you are setting your
personal goals to like 99.99, right?
Whatever that is.
And they may be focused on certain
parts of your customer workflow.
You may have other components
that are fall outside of SLA
because maybe they are not GA yet.
Maybe they aren't used as much.
Maybe they're premium features and
there's other things going on there
that's a whole other discussion.
But SLOs, like I said, your are your
team's goals for your production metrics.
They are the level of
reliability your team commits
to delivering for that service.
They can encompass anything
that you think is important.
Anything that your customers
determine is important, right?
Service, speed, payload size, any
metrics that matter to your users,
and they may be different for
every component in the ecosystem.
There's no O universal best set of
indicators to set your objectives to.
It's going to vary depending on
what your users do, what things
they interact with, what they expect
performance wise of your services.
So they can be very individualized
and in that way take some work and
may require some tooling, right?
Others, you can back into
a system data, right?
If you have an application
that slows down.
When some system resource threshold
is met, you can monitor that
system resource as a proxy for the
behavior of that service, right?
Some of your SLOs are going to be
around metrics that are easy to count,
but also transient, noisy, right?
Especially if you have a system that has a
very large number of hits or interactions.
One or two little errors pop
up occasionally anyway, because
that's just the nature of
packet switch systems, right?
So if you've ever been called by an
executive because they couldn't access
a service that's working for someone
else, and you're like all our monitors
say it's fine, and I have no idea why
it's not working for your, from you, for
you from your pineapple farm in Hawaii
when everything's hosted in Dulles.
The Internet's in the way,
there's ocean in the way.
There's lots of things in the middle that
are, preventing that, that performance.
You, the magic of SLOs though is that
the, it allows you to account for
some percentage of those errors before
blowing up everybody's phone, right?
You have everybody gets 500 errors.
You wanna alert on them at some point.
Do you have.
Do you have to alert on
every single 500 error?
That's the question, right?
If you have a site with a very large
capacity, very large traffic numbers,
one 500 error out of 10,000 hits,
probably not something to worry about
unless it keeps recurring right?
In a small timeframe.
So when you're combating.
Alert fatigue.
SLOs are gonna help you with two things.
They're gonna help you determine urgency,
and they're gonna help you reduce the
overall volume of notifications and alerts
that are getting to your human responders.
Having these SLOs attached to your key
metrics means that you know how many
failures you have before they're, you can
really say, oh yes, this is a problem.
There's no need in a lot of cases
to alert on every single failure.
You don't wanna burn through your
entire air budget on a single instance
of alert, but you be able to better
manage the importance of a single alert
versus a group of them in a given time
period, one every couple of hours versus.
10 in the next five minutes, right?
Like those are extreme cases, but example
for, how varied the situation can be.
So if your SLO is like a 95% success
on some key metric, you can alert your
humans starting maybe at 97% instead
of 100% success minus one error, right?
That's going to lower the volume
of overall alerts your team is
receiving on these key indicators.
So what an error budget looks like.
It's really your wiggle room, right?
There are the places where you can
be a little bit unreliable, right?
And your customers are
okay with it, right?
Some of these are gonna be a
discussion you need to have
with your product managers.
'cause they're gonna know, hopefully,
what the data looks like for how
customers engage with your systems,
where customers abandon stuff, right?
But the error budget is where the
magic of SLOs meets the annoyance
of realtime alerting, right?
Once you decide on your SLOs for a
particular service, you can determine how
much of your error budget you wanna spend
on any given series of errors, right?
A single isolated error on a very
busy service shouldn't wake anybody
up in the middle of the night.
You want a cluster of them
before you wake someone up,
you might wanna note it, right?
And it comes in maybe as low urgency until
there's a whole bunch of 'em, and then
it jumps to escalated to a high urgency.
So you have some record that it
happened, but you don't necessarily need
to wake some up at 3:00 AM about it.
So your users really are
the point on this, right?
The entire reason we have all these alerts
and notifications and all this stuff
that comes in is because we have users.
They wanna serve them a good
experience, so they keep coming
back and engaging with their stuff
and maybe paying us for it, right?
So we're not going through this
exercise simply because it's fun.
We're saving our human team
members some sanity, right?
By cleaning up all the alerts and
giving our customers, our users
the best experience by focusing
on what they care about, right?
You might have to talk to users.
You definitely wanna talk
to your product managers.
You might wanna do some experiments.
The good thing about using SLOs in
particular is that they're movable, right?
And like I said, they're, as
long as they're inside your,
the boundaries of your SLA.
Like you can move them around and
do what you need to do with them in
order to, flex around how the system
is performing, the goals that you can
actually meet and how it's impacting
your cus your actual human team.
Knowing what your users are expecting
is gonna help you determine,
is future work necessary here?
Are we slipping out of our tolerances?
For these particular metrics.
'cause maybe there's no amount of
notifications of people overnight
that's gonna fix the thing that
is giving you a chronic issue.
And it's time to go back to
the product manager and have a
discussion about reliability and
how it's impacting the system.
So there's a lot of flexibility here.
These tools can be fairly
sophisticated, so you might wanna
talk to a vendor about them.
So overall, our goals are number one.
We want to reduce our overall
alert load that is going to
help our alert fatigue greatly.
Even if we aren't in a place to
deploy to SLOs, right off the bat,
we'll have an lower volume of high
urgency alerts and they will be
legitimately be important, right?
They're going to things that we need to
see in real time in order to preserve the
reliability of the system for the users.
Every alert that comes to a human
responder should be actionable and
it should require human intervention.
There are lots of other things
that we can de to deploy in this
workflow like auto remediation, other
points of automation, maybe some
machine learning to help us out.
You can also make use of.
But everything that comes to our humans
needs to be actionable over time.
As you clean this up and keep things
rolling in a good with good hygiene,
mostly alerts that come to your
responders are going to be novel.
They're gonna be stuff
you haven't seen before.
In the same way they're
going to be things that are.
New to you or are completely dependent on
the sort of climate in your environment
at that time and not chronic issues
that you can't fix or can't deal with.
So in summary number one, clean
up your alerts even if you have
no intention of deploying SLOs,
making use of those as a tool.
Helping your team out by making sure
your alerts are good and coming into
people that can actually work on them
and actually make sense and are helpful
is going to help everyone out anyway.
Like we, like I mentioned
at the beginning, we all
have enough notifications.
Without production responsibilities.
So if you do have production
responsibilities, you're already shoving
all this information into people who
are already maybe overwhelmed by how
many notifications that they get.
So we're gonna focus on the users with
SLOs and we're gonna prioritize the
things that are important to the users.
And it doesn't matter if your
users are internal or external
or somewhere in between, right?
Everyone has things that they care
about and the systems that we run.
So we're work towards that.
You can then think about getting
the junk out of your workflow with
automation and machine learning.
If those things are in your tool
set and you can deploy them,
you're gonna get more out of them.
After you've cleaned up your alerts,
then you would, if you just throw
the fire hose of all your alerts at
them, it'd be more helpful that way.
If you get to a place where your manager
is not bought in on this, remind them of.
The six points I mentioned at the
beginning about missing alerts and that
impacting your reliability and burnout
and all those kinds of things, right?
Negative impacts, especially if
you're already seeing them on your
team, and you might be right, you
might have folks who are burned out.
You might have folks that
feel like they're drowning
during their on-call shift.
If you're getting more than a
handful of major alerts during a,
like a week long shift, like you're
basically drowning people, right?
There should be a limit.
So make sure you're focusing
on the language around your
reliability your customer
experience, your bottom line, right?
You are running these things
to make money in some way.
And if they aren't running
well, then that's impacting
your potential bottom line.
So some resources for you.
We have plenty of stuff on
our blog about alert fatigue.
You can check all those out.
If you are new to SLOs and haven't
encountered those before, the Google SRE
workbook has an entire chapter about them.
You can also reach out to
our friends Noble nine.
We use their stuff to manage our own SLOs.
They have lots of
documentation on their site.
They wrote a O'Reilly book about
SLOs and can get you going there.
So if you're totally new to this
and you're like, I don't understand
what you're talking about, plenty
of information for you out there.
Lots of resources to, to take a look at.
So I hope that was helpful and I hope you
enjoy the rest of the sessions at com.
42 SRE.