Hello everyone.
Welcome to Con 42.
My name is, and I'm a DevOps
consultant with over 15 years of
experience in the IT industry.
Twilio of those are deeply
focused in the DevOps.
My areas of expectations include CICD,
automation, infrastructure, asset
code, and cloud native solutions, and
more recently, governance and security
within DevOps workflows, what I'm
especially passionate about is helping
the teams build pipelines that are
not just fast and automated, but also
secure and compliance from the start.
In today's fast-paced DevOps environment,
speed and automations are essential.
They often come at the cost
of security and compliances.
Traditional manual six can keep up with
the velocity of modern software delivery.
As a result is configurations,
compliance gaps and the security
risk often go unnoticed until
it's too late The solution.
Policy as code allows organization to
define and enforce governance rule as a
code, ensuring security and compliances
are automated, scalable, and consistent
throughout the development lifecycle.
When integrated with the CICE tools
like Jenkins, PAC empowers teams in
the shift left security, catching
the issues early in the pipeline
before they reach the pipeline.
So let's dive in.
What are the challenges in the pack?
What are the manual
securities that it's failing?
The most alarming statistics in
modern DevOps engineering is 60%
of security breaches are cast by
the mis config infrastructure.
That means more than half of the
security incident organizations face
three are not due to advanced trust or
zero to exploits, but because someone
forgot to close a port, left default
settings on the production container.
Or misconfigured cloud permissions.
This especially critical in DevOps, where
we move fast, automate everything, and
rely heavily on infrastructure as a code.
Small misconfigurations can be replicated
across dozens of environments instantly.
That's why integrating security
early in the DevOps pipeline
through DevSecOps is essential.
Things like policy as code, automatic
configuration, validation, and
continuous monitoring can dramatically
reduce this 60 page, 60% each or less.
In short, our goal is not just the
faster deployment, but the safer ones.
So what are the challenges?
And the other one is going
to be the human error.
Staggering 87 percentage of security
issues across modern IT environments
are caused by human errors and DevOps,
where teams are constantly deploying,
configuring, and scaling system.
Even a small O site, like
a misconfigured S3 bucket,
forgotten an environment variable.
Or incorrect firewall rule
can lead to a major breach.
The takeaway manual steps are risky.
Wherever we can eliminate the human
error through automation, validation,
and the policy enforcement will
significantly reduce the risk.
That's why practices like infrastructure
code CI ICD pipeline, security gates
and an automated misconfiguration
scanning are no longer an optional.
They are very essential.
The financial impact of security
incidents is very massive.
On average organization
spends around 3.9 to million
recovering from a single breach.
And this isn't just about fixing
the technical issue, it includes.
Downtime that stalls
operation on the delivery.
The data loss are corruption in impacting
the business integrity, the legal fees,
the fines, and the compliance violations.
Reputational damage that is hard to
rebuild, plus the cost of rebuilding
the trust within the customers.
For DevOps team, this
underlines the business critical
role of secure practices.
Investing in a secure pipeline's,
automated compliances and continuous
monitoring does not just reduce the
risk, it protects the bottom line.
So what's policy of code Policy as
a code is a practice of writing and
enforcing the security compliances
and the operational policies using the
code, which can be version tested and
automatically executed just like an
application or an infrastructure code.
Policy as a code is about
shifting the compliance as left.
So instead of waiting for the security
teams to cast the issues after deployment,
we define the rules as a code and bake
them directly into our DevOps workflows.
It's how we scale security.
Reduce the risk and ensure the governance
without slowing down the deliveries.
So policy as code policies are issued
written in mission readable formats
such as Jason or YAML or Rego or
open policy agents, each format
has its strengths and drop access.
For example, Jason and Yam L are popular
for configuration files while Rego is a
policy language tailored to validate the
complex policies and what's the benefit.
Consistency, automation and
traceability automates governance,
ensuring the uniform policies are
applied across the entire pipeline.
It reduces the human intervention and
the chances of error leading to faster,
more secure deployments, and it allows
to frame the track, the policy changes,
ensuring the accountability and the
visibility into the government actions.
So let's discuss about the policy as a
code throughout the DevOps lifecycle.
As a developmental stage, our goal
is to catch security issues as
early as possible before code even
reaches the staging or production.
This is where policy as code comes in.
By defining our security and
the compliance rule in the
code, we can integrate them
directly in our DevOps workflows.
So the moment the developer writes or
commence the code, it's automatically
checked for violations like the
open ports, unencrypted data or
the noncompliant address confis.
If something violate its
policy, the pipeline fail fast.
If it passes, we move forward.
This approach ensure we are building
a secure software from the day
on and not retrofitting it later.
Once the build is done, sorry.
Once the code is written uncommitted,
we move to the build station where
things can start to get packaged.
This is a critical point to validate
where we are actually building first.
We are on the software compostion
analysis tools to identify any vulnerable
libraries or outdated packages.
These are common sources to exploits.
Next, we scan the container
image for misconfigurations, like
running as a rule, unnecessary
port open or insecure base images.
We then use the policy as code to
enforce our bill standards if an image
does not meet of a security criteria.
We break the build.
This ensures that only secure
complaint artifacts move forward.
In the test stage, our focus is
on validating the security posture
of an application itself, not
just the code or a container.
We must run a mix of tools like SAST for
scanning the source code for a security
box, DASD for checking the vulnerabilities
in the running apps, IASD for running the
insights during the test executions, but.
Testing isn't enough.
We need to enforce policies.
That's where policy as
code plays a critical role.
It allows us to define the thresholds
like no critical vulnerabilities
or 90% security test coverage,
and an automatically blocked
bills that don't meet them.
This ensures that we are not just
testing, but enforcing a minimum bar for
a security quality before ever deployed.
In the deploy stage, it's essential to
ensure that the infrastructure itself
is secure and compliant before anything.
We use the infrastructure code tools like
Terraform or a cloud formation, or define
our environments, or before we provision
policy as a code is integral here.
It allows us to define security rules
in the code and automatically enforce
them, making them an only complaint.
Infrastructure gets deployed.
If something offs like an insecurity S3
bucket of an improper IA permissions,
the deployment fails by shifting
left security to the deploy phase and
automate compliances be drastically
reduce the risk of misconfiguration and
unauthorized access in the monitor stage.
Detect and alert our runtime policy
violations does not end with just
deploying the code or infrastructure.
We need to keep the constant watch
on runtime operations to detect and
respond to the security violations
in the real time by monitoring
both application infrastructure.
We can catch issues that occur like
the deployment, like an unexpected
configuration change, or an unauthorized
access to the sensitive data policy
as a code continues its role here.
Providing runtime checks that
enforce security rules even
after the resources are live.
If the policy violation occurs,
say if a server start using a
weak encryption or an unauthorized
user tries to access the resource,
the system alerts us immediately.
These realtime alerts combined with the
tools like SIEM systems for a centralized
logging enable a rapid response to
any violations allowing us to respond
to incidents before they escalate.
So here comes the real question.
Why Jenkins for policy as a code?
It's because of the factors like
ecosystem integration, pipeline
flexibility, community support,
and established infrastructure.
Jenkins is well known for its ability
to integrate with various different
tools, making it a very easy to integrate
policy enforcement without needing an
overall of existing infrastructure.
Jenkins provide flexibility.
By allowing policy checks to be inserted
at any stage in the DevOps pipeline,
whether it's during a code checking
or build, or testing or deployment.
Jenkins offer with larger user
base and extensive documentation,
which ensure that there is an ample
community support and the resources
available when implementing the bank.
Jenkins has already widely deployed
many organizations, so implementing
PAC and Jenkins leverages the existing
infrastructure and tools that many
DevOps teams are already using.
And so how it's done,
how to implement the pac.
Storing our policies in a source control
like GI gives us a powerful way to
track the changes, manage the versions,
and keep a clear audit trail for the
compliance on the security purposes.
By version controlling our
policies, just like application
code, we can see who changed.
What and when, which are essential
for the compliance audits.
We can even roll back to the
previous versions of the policies
if needed, and if ensures the
transparency and the accountability
in how policies evolve over time.
Collaborations become much easier because
a team can propose review and approve
the changes to the policies directly
in the version control repository.
And of course, by trying the policies
back act as a policy, as code
frameworks like open policy agents.
We can automatically enforce these
policies in our CICD pipelines.
To integrate the policy as a code in
our CICD pipelines, we installed the
policy engines like A-O-P-A-O Ps,
or open policy agents or con contest
directly into the Jenkins plugin.
This allows us to enforce the
policies automatically whenever code
or infrastructure changes are made.
The open policy agent provides the
flexible engine for writing the policies
in the Rigo, which can cover a wide range
of compliances and the security checks.
The contest on the other hand,
is perfect for enforcing the
policies on a configuration
files such as the A ML or json.
Once the policy engines are
installed, we configure the
Jenkins to run these policies at
a specific points in the pipeline.
Usually during the build or
deployment, if any policy violation
are detected, the bill fails, and
then team gets an alert preventing
noncompliant code from going live.
This seamless integration of a
policy as a code ensure we have a
transparent, automated and a reliable
enforcement process within the dev
workflows to integrate the policy
as a code in our CI ICD pipeline.
We start by defining the pipeline
stages in our Jenkins file.
These stages control the
flow of the pipeline.
Include building, test, and the deploy
At the early critical checkpoint in the
pipeline, we insert the policy validation
slips to make sure the code infrastructure
and the deployment configuration meet
our security and compliance standards.
Before the build, we an open policy agent
policies to validate the code itself.
After the testing, we run the
contest to check for the compliance
issues in the configuration files
and before the deployment, we
validated the infrastructure and
the deployment configurations
to ensure no misconfigurations
are going into productions.
If any policy fails, the pipeline
automatically stops preventing
non-compliant code from moving forward.
This issues, we enforce security
and compliances consistently
throughout the entire pipeline.
One of the most important decisions
in integrating the policy as code
is how we handle the violations.
Should the pipeline stop immediately
or should it keep continuing if the
violation is critical, such as a security
vulnerability or a compliance breach.
We should stop the pipeline to prevent
non-compliant code from being deployed.
This is the default behavior for
the critical security policies.
For non-critical issues like a code
style violations or minor configuration
issues, we must report them the violations
stopping instead of stopping the pipeline.
This keeps the process moving while
flagging the issues for the future review.
The beauty of policy as code
is that we can customize
failure actions per policies.
For example, a security policies might hal
the pipeline, but a performance policies
might only log and report the violations.
This flexibility ensures we can
balance the security enforcement
and develop an agility, allowing us
to maintain a high quality without
unnecessary slowing down the deliveries.
So what's the popular.
Policy enforcement tools.
It's examples like a op
contest, HashiCorp Sentinel.
So what's an open policy agent?
One of the most popular
tools for a policy as a code
enforcement is open policy agent.
It's general purpose policy engine
that can validate and enforce
policies across multiple system,
and it uses a declarative languages
called rego for writing the policies.
The key advantages of
OPA is its flexibility.
It allows you to centralize the policy
enforcement across multiple platforms,
reducing the complexity of managing the
policies across the diverse technologies.
Additionally.
The open policy agent integrates
seamlessly into the existing CICD
workflows to enforce policies during the
build, test and the deployment stages.
By using the open policy agents in
the policy as a code approach, you are
ensuring that policies are consistently
enforced, which helps reduce the risk
and ensure compliances across your
organization's entire infrastructure.
Contest is a specialized tool for
the testing configuration file
against the defined policies.
It's particularly useful for validating
the YAML and the JSON files, which
are commonly used into the tools like
Kubernetes, Terraform, and Health.
With contest, you can write the
policies in rego and apply them
to your configuration files.
This ensures that your configurations
are in line with your organizational
standards before they are deployed.
Contrast integrates easily
with the CICD pipelines.
During the build or deploy stages, it
can automatically test your configuration
files, block the non-compliant
configuration, and provide detailed
feedback for the developers to quickly
address the issues using comp as a
part of your policy as a code strategy.
Issues that configuration across
your enter environment or secure.
Compliant and consistent.
The HashiCorp Sentinel is a powerful
policy as a code tool embedded directly
within the several HashiCorp product.
Unlike other standalone policy engines,
Sentinel is natively integrated into
the tools like Terraform Vault and
Console making it ideal choice for
the in infrastructure governance.
The integration of the Sentinel
within the HashiCorp products ensure
that the policies are automatically
applied and enforced as a part
of normal deployment process.
Without the need for the external tools.
It also provides a scalable solution
to the policy enforcement across
the cloud native infrastructure.
Decentralized policy enforcement
ensures that the governance is
consistent and automated across the
environment, saving time and reducing.
The manual oversight.
So here comes the real world
policy examples, like preventing
public S3 buckets, enforce resource
tagging and container security,
and identity and access management.
Policy as a code can be used to
enforce the security policies that
prevent exposing the sensitive
data, such as rejecting AWS
infrastructure, changes that might have.
An SD public pocket described a policy
that requires a special tax to be applied
on all cloud resources, making it easier
to track and the managed cloud costs.
The policy as a code can block the
deployment of a container that's
either have known vulnerabilities
or configured or run as a route,
reduce the attack surfaces.
Fact ensures that the IDD and
access management policies follow
at least the privilege principle,
ensuring the users or a service only
have the permission they need it.
Let's quickly walk through of a sample.
Jenkins Pipeline with
the policy as a code.
So as you see, we have
multiple different stages.
First stage code is checked from the
version control, then use contest to test
the Terraform files for policy violations
before resources are provisioned.
We had another stage to
generate the Terraform plan.
Which outlines the infrastructure changes
and the Terraform plan is tested again
against the policies to ensure the
compliances and the deploy stage only if
the policy is passed, the infrastructure
changes are deployed using the Terraform.
How to integrate the pack into the
deployment development workflows.
One of the best ways to integrate the
policy as a code into the development
workflows is by providing instant policy
validation, directing within the I IDs.
This means that as a developer write
code, whether it's an infrastructure
as a code, like a Terraform, or an
application configuration like a
Kubernetes yaml, they get real time
feedback about whether there are changes
are compliant with security or compliances
and other organizational policies.
Tools like VS.
Code Intelli and other popular
IDs allow developers to install.
Plugins that validated configuration or
code against the predefined policies.
This provide immediate feedback on
the issues like insect configuration
or non-compliant resource definition.
Allow developers to resolve the issues
instantly before moving forward.
The benefits are very huge.
Increased productivity because
developers don't have to wait until
the pipeline runs to find out if there
is an issue improved, code quality
as a violation, or cut early leading
to a better and more compliant code.
The faster delivery asset
development process does not get.
Delayed by the last minute policy
violations or a manual check.
By bringing the policy enforcement
right into the development environment,
we make sure that policies are
continuously enforced in the real time,
reducing the friction and ensuring
the consistent compliant deployments.
The pull request enforcement is a powerful
way to integrate the policy as a code into
the development workflows by automatically
running the policy checks during the code
reviews, you ensure that only compliant
code and the secure configurations
are merged into your main branch.
Before a pool request is approved,
automated tools such as run policy
checks that validate the code
or infrastructure against your
predefined security compliance,
and the best practices policies.
For example, the policies can ensure
that the Kubernetes CML file contain
the necessary resource limits or
data, terraform code compliance
with the access control policies.
Benefits are clear.
Prevention of non-compliant changes
by catching violations Early in
the poll request process, you
can prevent non-compliant code
from making it to the production.
The streamlined code reviews.
This reduces with the burden on the
reviews since the policy checks that are
automatically handled, letting them focus
on the logic and the design of the code.
As every change is checked against
the policies, you maintain a high
level of consistency in the code
quality and the security practices.
Integrating PAC into a pool request
process helps ensure that the development
process is not only fast, but also
secure and compliant, which the key
delivering high quality software.
The critical component of the integrating
policy as a code into the development
workflow is the use of pipeline gates.
These gates are automated policies.
Enforcement points into the CICD
pipeline, that block non-compliant
changes from progressing to the
next stage, whether it's a build.
Test or deploy the gates ensure
that only compliant code and
the infrastructure gets through.
For example, in the build stage,
we can configure the pipeline to
check the security vulnerabilities
like insecure, hot coded credentials
or compliance violations, such as
missing required resource limits
in the Kubernetes YAML files.
If the violation is
detected, the pipeline stops.
Preventing the deployment from
the non-compliant changes.
The main benefit of the pipeline gates is
that they automatically enforce policies
as a key stages of the pipeline, reducing
the need of a manual interventions and
ensuring compliances at every step.
This provides faster feedback to the
developers so they can fix issues.
Earliest consistency in enforcing the
policies across all the environments.
Most secure under compliant code
base by ensuring the only policy
compliant code can be deployed.
By incorporating pipeline gates into the
CICD pipelines, you are ensuring that
the every piece of code that reaches
the production is properly vetted
for security compliances and the best
practices providing stronger governance
and the reducing risk The compliances.
Reporting is a key factor.
The key aspect of a policy as
a code that ENS ensures you are
prepared for regulatory audits.
These automated reports track and
they document policy violations
in the real time and they include
the essential information such as
timestamp, who made the change, and
what specific policy was violated.
This level of documentation is
invaluable when it comes to providing
a regulatory compliances in the audits.
The benefits of complying.
Reporting includes the ability to
generate the auditable reports without
manual efforts, a proven track record
of a compliance with the industry
regulations such as GDPR or hipaa.
The ability to continuously track
and improve the compliance approach
over time by reviewing audit data
and taking proactive measures to
correct the policy violations.
By automating compliances reporting,
you ensure that your organization can
always prove compliances and quickly
respond to regulatory requirements
with up to date accurate reports.
What should be done to
we get started today?
So start by identifying the most
important security and the compliances
policies, those that address the most
common or critical security risk.
The recommendation is choosing the
tools that work with the existing stack.
Example, the open policy
agent for the most cases.
And should these tools integrate
seamlessly into your pipeline, always
start small with the non-production
environment or with the policies set to
one only mode before fully enforcing the
heart failures as a measure of success.
Expand the policies.
Always reassure the audience that
policy as a code is an IT process.
Security improves as more policies
are gradually implemented as we go on.
That we all hope we had a good
touch base with the policy
as a code and it's useless.
Please feel free to reach me or
email my profile for any assistance
or help needed in the future.
Let's get the environment safer.
Policy.
Thank you for your bye.