Speaker 11: Hello everyone and
thank you for joining this session.
My name is Joran, and today I'll be
presenting work on AI govern Lakehouse
ingestion, pipelines and reliable data
ops using Apache Flink and Kubernetes.
So modern organization, it relies NY
or large scale data pipelines that
ingest information from various data
sources like databases, APIs, event
streams, logs, so on and so forth.
However, these pipelines frequently
break due to schema evolution,
semantic inconsistencies,
and operational complexity.
In this talk, I'll introduce an
architecture that combines train
processing semantic intelligence and
cloud native infrastructure to build
ingestion systems that are self adapting,
resilient, and production ready.
Before we begin, let me
briefly introduce myself.
I currently work in distributed
data engineering and reliability
focused data platforms, and I'm also
an independent researcher focusing
on large scale data infrastructure
and autonomous data ops system.
My work focuses on building self-healing
ingestion pipelines that can adapt
to evolving upstream data sources.
I'll talk more about these
in the coming slides.
So some of my main areas of interest,
it includes distributed string
processing, lakehouse architectures,
data platform readability engineering,
and AI driven data governance.
So in this slide, I highlight the
core ingestion challenges, which
modern Lakehouse platform faces.
So first, let's focus on sche on
drift In large distributed system,
upstream services evolve independently.
So teams may rename fields, change
column types, or remove attributes
during deployments, right?
So for example, a column like customer
id, it might change to user id.
So from upstream STEAM perspective,
this is a small change, but downstream
ingestion, pipelines expecting the
old sche might, may fail immediately.
So schema drift is therefore one
of the most common operational
causes of pipeline failure.
The second issue is semantic gaps.
Even when the structure of
the data remains valid, the
meaning of data may change.
For instance, a column named transaction
ammo, it might switch from storing values
in dollars to storing values in cents.
So the schema validation will pass, but
the meaning of the data is now incorrect.
So this leads to silent corruption
of analytics and other dashboards.
So finally we have manual time
When these issues occur, SRE and
data engineering team must manually
diagnose chema changes, update
transformations, and redeploy pipelines.
So instead of focusing on innovation,
team spends large amount of time
firefighting ingestion failures.
In this slide, I explained why
static schema registries are not
sufficient for modern evolving system.
So the first limitation
is binary validation.
Schema registries validate structure,
but not made As long as the
incoming data matches the expected
structure, it is expec accepted.
However, the data may still
be semantically incorrect.
For example, as I said earlier, right?
The numeric field might change units,
or a renamed field may represent the
same concept, but a PS completely
new attribute to the registry.
So the second limitation
is nor drift intelligence.
Schema registries do not understand
the context of schema evaluation.
When an upstream team renames or
restructure fills the ingestion
pipeline breaks until engineer manually
reconcile the schema difference, right?
So this creates delays and increase
mean time to recovery for data pipelines
because of these limitations, static
schema validation captures only subset
of real world data quality issues.
So at the bottom of the architecture.
So this slide essentially
introduces the AI governed
multimodal ingestion architecture.
And you can see at the bottom of the
architecture, we have core ingestion.
So this layer collects data from multiple
modalities, including databases, even
streams, APIs, and unstructured sources.
So you name it like logs or
any other unstructured sources.
So traditionally pipelines would
perform basic validation here and
immediately push data into storage.
The next layer is AI extraction.
So this layer uses large language
models and intelligent parcels to
interpret incoming data structures.
It can recursively, pass nested
information, align timestamps across
systems, and interpret schema changes.
So at the tops, it's the semantic engine.
This layer learns patterns from
historical data, it models, attribute
relationships, detect anomalies in
value distributions, and evaluate
temporal behavior such as seasonality.
Together these layer replaces brittle
point to point validation with a
governance plane that continuously learns
and adapt to evolving data sources.
So here I focus on semantic contracts,
which extends validation far
beyond traditional schema checks.
The first concept is value
distribution modeling.
This system.
In this case, the system learns
statistical baselines for each
attribute using historical data.
So if a value suddenly deviates
significantly from expected distributions,
the pipeline flags the anomaly.
For example, if all totals typically
fall between certain ranges, but
suddenly spike dramatically, the
system detects it immediately.
The second concept is attribute
relationship and code.
So many fields in dataset
are logically related.
For example, tax amount,
it should correlate with
total purchase value, right?
It could be seven percentage or 10%,
and now some patterns will be there.
So by learning these relationships,
the system can detect inconsistencies
that structural validation would miss.
The third concept is
temporal pattern awareness.
So data pipelines often rely
on time-based presence, such as
hourly traffic, daily transaction
volumes, or seasonal behaviors.
So time series modeling allows the
system to detect unexpected changes such
as S spikes, drops, or delayed events.
So these semantic contracts, it
ensures that pipeline validates not
just the structure of data, but also
its behavior and meaning over time.
So here I try to describe the
self evolving schema intelligence
layer, which enables pipeline to
automatically adapt to schema changes.
The first stage is detect evolution event.
The system monitors ingestion
streams and detect signals that
indicates structural changes.
For example, a new field may appear,
an existing field may disappear,
or an ED object structure may
change, so it'll detect evolution.
The second stage is infer semantic equal.
Using embedding similarity
techniques, the system determines
whether the new schema element, it
corresponds to an existing concept.
For example, if customer I becomes client
identifi, the system can recognize that
both likely represent the same entity.
The third stage is generate
transformation logic.
A large language model, it generates
transformation rules that map new schema
into the existing Lakehouse model.
So these rules may include renaming
fields, restructuring nested objects,
all applying type conversions.
So by automating these types or these
steps, this pipeline becomes self
adapting dramatically, reducing manually
interventions when schema evolves.
So modern data platforms must process
many different types of input data.
We have seen different
data sources, right?
So the first category
is structured sources.
So these usually arrive through C,
D, C, which is change data capture.
So the CD, C streams, databases,
changes such as inserts, updates,
or data from systems like, MySQL
or post does, or any database.
And it actually ingest into
our pipeline in real time.
So the second category, semi-structured
data such as JS or parque.
So these formats often contain
nested fields that evolve frequently.
So recur passing and AI assisted
schema inference allows the pipeline to
interpret these structures automatically.
The third categories, unstructured
data, example, include application
law, emails, or documents.
So here we rely on LLM or lab ed
models to extract entities and convert
pre-form text infrastructure attributes.
So all of these modalities are unified
using the data flow processing model
implemented by Apache Print, even
time L alignment and watermarking
ensure de deterministic processing
regardless of the source format.
So at the core of the architecture
is Apache Flink, a distributed stream
processing framework designed for high
throughput and low latency data pipelines.
So the first key capability is
exactly one sematic processing
exactly one processing semantics
through checkpointing and two fees.
Commit, change Flinks Gallery.
That records are written exactly once to
the lakehouse, even if failure knockers.
The second capability
is staple processing.
So Flink operator made
a long running state.
It's backed by ROCK db.
So ROCK DB is essentially a high
performance embedded key value
store used to persist large
streaming state efficiently.
So in this architecture, the state
store contains semantic contract,
baselines and temporal model.
So ROCK DB essentially stores
all these semantic contracts
and all the temporary models.
The third capability is
a Synchron snapshots.
Based on the distributor snapshot
algorithm it's Shandy Lampo it's a
well-known distributed snapshot algorithm.
So based on that algorithm, Flink
can capture consistent pipeline state
without pausing data processing.
So this is critical for pipelines
operating under low latency service level
agreements, or we call it as SS. One Flink
provides streaming computation engine.
Kubernetes provides the operational
infrastructure layer, so running
Flink on Kubernetes enables dynamic
scaling and safe deployments.
One important capability here is cada or.
Kubernetes event driven autoscaling.
Instead of scaling purely on CPU
metrics, ADA allows workload to scale
based on external signals such as capa,
consumer lag, so Kappa consumer lag.
It represents how far the system is
falling behind the incoming events,
so using lag as a scaling signal,
it allows infrastructure capacity
to match actual data pressure.
Another important feature is
operator based rolling upgrades.
So Flink jobs can be upgraded
using safe points, which preserve
the entire pipeline state.
So this allows new version of the
pipeline to be deployed without losing
state or inter interrupting processing.
So introducing AI components
into data pipelines also
introduces new failure scenarios.
So resilient patterns become,
extremely critical here.
So the first pattern is a circuit breaker.
If the AI in different service
becomes unavailable, the pipeline
automatically falls back to the
last non good semantic contracts.
So this prevents localized failures
from cascading through the system.
The second pattern is dead letter queue.
Also, DLQ.
So at dead letter queue, it stores
records that pay semantic palliation.
So instead of breaking the pipeline,
the problematic records are routed
to DLQ with lineage metadata, so
engineers can investigate them later.
So this is very quiet, a
normal scenario in the pipeline
mechanism, ingestion mechanisms.
The third pattern is back
pressure propagation.
Patchlink uses a creating based
flow control mechanism that
slows upstream producers when
downstream operators become slower.
So this prevents memory of flow when AI
scoring introduces additional latency.
So deciding autonomous ingestion
systems, which requests balancing
several important reliability trade off.
The first trade off is
latency versus accuracy.
So deeper semantic analysis improves
anomaly detections accuracy, but
it increases inference latency.
So to maintain throughput,
semantic scoring is often executed
asynchronously with bounded ses.
The second tradeoff is autonomy
versus audit auditability.
While the system can auto automatically
generate schema maps using nms.
Every generative information must
be locked version and reviewable.
So this ensures that automated
decisions remain explainable.
So auditing is, very cri, quite
critical in the enterprise system.
The third tradeoff is model
drift versus stability.
So semantic contract models
evolve as data evolves, right?
But they must be version independently
from the streaming pipeline, so that
model can be rolled back safely without
affecting the running fling job.
Operating these systems in production
reveal several real world challenges.
The first challenge is a model.
So when a completely new data source
appears, there is no historical
baseline for the semantic models, right?
So the system therefore requests a
short supervised warmup period before
autonomous governance becomes relevant.
The second challenge is
a stage store explosion.
So tracking semantic baselines for
thousands of admins across many pipelines
can cause or ogb states to grow rapidly.
So techniques such as we should
look at TTL time to leave eviction
policies and tiered state storage.
It helps to control the state through.
Third challenge is LLM rate limited.
So LLM during burst of schema,
ation, right inference request
can spike, can exits API quota.
So using local em, embed models and
caching it, it significantly helps reduce
the dependence on extra external LLM APIs.
So to conclude, there
are four key takeaways.
First, ingestion systems must move
beyond traditional chea registries.
Semantic contracts that learn value
distributions and relationships can
detect data quality issues, that
structural validation a lot cannot.
Second, LLM based automation can
dramatically reduce operational
time, embedding similarity, storing,
and automated transformation
generation allows pipeline to
adapt to schema changes quickly.
Third Apache Link combined
with Kubernetes, it provides a
production ready foundation for
reliable streaming data systems.
So exactly once processing,
autoscaling and stateful upgrades
enable resilient operation at scale.
Finally, reliability Team
AI govern data systems.
It requires auditability.
Every automated decision must
be low version and reversible.
Thank your time.
I hope this session provides
insight into how AI governance,
stream processing, and cloud native
infrastructure can work together
to build resilient data platforms.
I'd be happy to take any questions.
Thank you.