Hello everyone.
My name is Ravi Kala, and first
of all thank you for giving an
opportunity to introduce myself
and then conference opportunity.
So if you have any questions regarding
this topic, you can reach out to me
over the email or and link it in.
So today I'm going to discuss in
this conferences the evaluation of.
A enhanced automotive infotainment
system and that and as well as the,
I'm going to discuss the technical
innovations and then future prospects.
So let's start with
the, some basic things.
So you are, automotive entertainment?
Automotive entertainment is information
plus entertainment is entertainment.
When you are, when you sit in
a car, you see the display in
front of your old driving suite
or in front of, in the console.
That is the infotainment system.
You can listen the songs and then,
you can entertain the, things
like you could do the video games
or in a parking, in a park mode.
And then as well as the, you can do
vehicle a operations, like change
settings or that is the info system.
So hope you are, you know that.
But yeah just wanted to give you
brief overview, but in this topic
I'm going to discuss how the AI.
Is influential, the info interacting
with the infotainment system,
automotive infotainment system.
So in this conference, I'm going to
discuss the technical framework and
challenges and as well as the breakthrough
solutions driving the development of AA
power automotive infotainment systems.
So let's start with some basic
thing like the market growth
and technological evaluations.
So if you see this there are the 2023.
Around 21 part six, 3 billion revenue
from infotainment a infotainment so
that, that use that will be projected
like 37 part 6 billion by 2023.
A enhance system, which is
currently accounted for like
around 42.3 of the market.
That is expected to dominate
like, more dominate the future,
grow future automotive industry.
For the a. But the basic thing is
bias recognition because of, you need
to talk with you need to talk to the
infotainment system or that is the
easiest and more, more fastest way to
communicate with your infotainment system.
So in 2020 2020, the the wise accuracy,
it used to be like an 82.4 percentage
around around 20 wise commands.
Almost three or two operations.
Operations, like in a wise commands got
failed able to process that command.
But in 2023 that increase to 96.2,
right now it's almost 99.99 percentage
accuracy of the, of your wise commands.
And then the, and the other
thing is the fast response, the
responses also very reduced a
right now it's 2.7 seconds to get.
Get your answers whatever you
are asking to the entertainment
system it'll respond like that.
And then and then the there are
so many things involved we will
get into that things first of all
computational architecture evolution.
So in 2020 in 2080, let's
start with the 20 28, 20 18.
So we used to like in automotive
industries, used 1, 2, 2 processing means
we call the vehicle interface process.
The vehicle is.
Consisting of ecs, electronic
control units, each con, each
ECU consisting of specific set of
operations BC body control module.
It's specifically designed for
braking system or lighting or some
of the most critical operation.
And then there are lightning module,
especially for lights, lightning system.
And then there are like, vehicle vehicle
control units and then as well as the like
you audio amplifier amplifier modules.
Amplifier modules are like, audio systems.
Those kind of things are like, it's
consisting of the auto, the vehicle
is consisting of number of, so
in 20 20 18, it used to be one to
two crossing limits, but 2020 we.
It increase it to two to four
processing units more demand, more
more capabilities are introduced.
And then 2023 and 2022 at used it was
like, five to eight processing units.
So imagine 5, 2, 8 is 1
trillion operations per second.
The whatever the, the five
to eight crossing units.
It'll it'll operate 1 trillion operations.
And right now we are almost triple
that 3 trillion operations per second.
That's how we increased the
capabilities of the operations
and then low power consumption.
That is also another another thing
we need to we need to consider.
All, automotive is first
priority is safety.
Safety is when you are driving your
car safety is the first priority
for the automotive industry.
That's why.
Every automotive industry when
they are implementing any.
Any any capabilities or anything,
the safety is the first reality
for their for their operations.
So that's the that's how they operating.
So let's get into that.
Drive driver monitoring
and personalization things.
Let's the AI is also uses not only for
your voice recognization, but also camera.
So how the, how you are whether you are
sad, whether you are sick, whether you
are, based on your eye movements, based
on your facial expressions it'll recognize
and then say, based on your command if
you are a dull if you are, if you got into
a trouble or anything, it automatically
detect and directly connected to your
when you are in got an accident any.
Need anything any, any sudden movements,
it automatically directly connected to
the back office systems, and directly
connected to your 9 1 1 to get get help
as possible and then car your incidents.
That's how this AI is added those
capabilities and as well as the.
I just I just your information like, your
personal information whether it's saved
saved, locally, saved in the back office,
but it's but it's needs to be private.
You.
No, no need to be shared with someone.
So that is our sort priority for the ai.
And then there is an name.
Neural networks.
That is like analyzing multiple input.
You are driving same location
multiple times, and then a, recognize
that one and then determine okay.
You are going to this one you are
going to this road, and then is
there any traffic in that location?
And then it'll give an in
input, like no suggestions.
Oh, hey you are going into this direction.
We have some trouble.
We are closing some roads
or something like that.
So then he, then you know you
have any better better things
and better schedule in your day.
So that's how the, your
your time is saved.
And then you can, you can you can
like in safety of your when you were
driving safety is also considered.
And then as, as well as the
driver attention when you are
driving telling me, traffic.
We had you as like something.
Then it'll recognize that.
Then think, okay, hey, there is a traffic.
You need to be alert.
Then you can do that.
That's how, yeah.
These things are working.
So let's predicting a and
context context awareness.
There are four things we need to be
considered temporal analysis and then
geo pattern intelligence and then
behavioral pattern, the communication
and feedback loop integration.
These are designed for a different
different, things like, day after
week pattern recognization when you
are when you are particular day, you,
you are doing something like, you are
able to do something, then a, predict
that one then give the suggestions.
And then there is another thing
like, you were able to you are a AV.
Electrical vehicle, your charging
station, recommended charging stations.
It'll give the recommended
charging station.
And then audio setting based on your
mood, you can the a give, Hey, I'm
going to set up this songs for you.
Whether you agree or
disagree, it's up to you.
But yeah it'll give an suggestion and
then behavior pattern based on your
mood, based on your your preference
based on your media preference.
It'll it'll give an a, like an, okay,
I'm playing this song and looking, okay
I want to play this song, yes or no?
Yes.
Yeah, you could it will play then
without your without, much thinking of
your it automatically recognize your
mood and then it'll, and then feedback.
Look, that is another thing.
When you are when you are like,
when the a given in suggestion, but
you don't like it, it's okay, but.
It'll why it is rejected.
It'll analyze the ai and then
next time, don't repeat that.
Mistakes.
So that's how it yeah.
This AI is working so.
And then resource
constraints and optimization.
In the automotive industry so there
are hardware limitations and then
power efficiency requirements and body
management and safety critical ation.
So these are the main constraints for
aa advancements right now there are,
hardware limitations that like, one of the
core hardware in the automotive industry
it is to it used to be $1,200, but now
it's almost three to $5,000 per need.
So that's how and then the budget
is also very important for the,
and the space restrictions.
Also, you need to be small.
The electronic control unit, a CU
is must be small, and as well as
the doing more operation, trillions
and trillions of power operation.
And then second thing
is battery efficiency.
That in automotive industry EV ranges
question for hey my, my company's
doing six 50 miles per full charge.
A my, my ev is like 300 miles
per full charge within 15
minutes, something like that.
No, power efficiency is after
thing we need to consider.
And then memory management then.
So how many operations we are performing
to the users, and then we need to show.
We need to store and then deploy and
then use that, those information, and
then give it to the right feedback.
Write write information to the try user.
And then there is safety
critical operation.
That is the that is one of the performance
determin performance guarantees.
Oh, hey, my automotive industry is
doing good with this operations.
Something like that.
So that's how it's it's working.
And then there are privacy
and data management.
This is another thing.
So privacy is the main important
for for our automotive industry.
Whether when you are introducing the a
into the automotive industry, because
of you share your personal data, because
of, you shared your personal data, you
shared your things to the, your car and.
That needs to be stored
somewhere personal.
That's how and then there are
different things we need to consider
as an automotive automotive engineer.
F first thing is.
And device process only since two
data are stored in locally, like in
your vehicle, and then the remaining
things are like, stored in cloud
services and then reduce the privacy
exposure to the remaining vendors.
And then and the differential privacy.
And then noise.
Transmission and math mathematically
guaranteed individual privacy
while maintaining the static
statistical usefulness document.
These are the things, and then the
federated learning that dis distributes
model training across the vehicle.
Keep the raw data in local, allowing
the fleet wide AI operations without
centralizing the personal data.
So time limited storage hey I'm going
to store this data like one month,
three months, something like that.
When you change the, it'll let
automatically delete delete
your data, delete your personal
data, and then keep the vehicle
three without any personal data.
That's how privacy.
We are going to introduce to
the automatically systems.
And then safety.
As I mentioned before, automotive
automotive's automotive is first
thing is the safety and distraction.
Distraction mitigation.
So safety is the first priority.
We never, we are implementing anything.
Safety is the first degree reality.
So what are the medications
we are going to?
First thing is workload.
Adaptive interfaces.
When the when the UI elements based,
standard driving complexity, reducing
the car, congregating calculating load
by 43% during hiding, driving situations.
And then multimodal interaction design.
Whether you are using voice, a touch or
architecture anything it need to be no,
no need to be distract you and driving.
That is another thing.
There are there are couple of
things we need to consider.
Driver must be consultation
on the road without without
doing any further aggressions.
Hey, touching something on
the entertainment system.
No.
We are not doing that one 'cause of,
safety is the first the first ity, and
then attention and avail interruption.
You, if you are talking to Thea, that's
okay if you are like, if you are not
concentrating and concentrating not
concentrating on your driving things then
that's the interruption comes into the
picture and then we can notify the driver.
Hey.
We need to be ice on your
road, ice on the road.
So that's how different things mitigation
we are going to implement into that safety
structure, destruction, mitigation things.
And then the further thing
is testing and validation as,
how the testing is conducted.
So first thing is we are doing some
basic basic testing the National Highway
Traffic Safety at the administration
whatever the guidelines they.
They're provided.
We do that some basic things and as
well as the, some of the more generic
principles principle verifications, and
then brand specific interaction standards.
And then I. Then there is a
controlled environment test testing.
We are like, we are tested like, only
certain things and then certain behavioral
analysis and then certain task we need
to give to the entertainment system and
then perform do observe the behavior.
And then further we are we are
going to develop that driving
simulator validation that is just
in in just in, in, in house driving.
But you are giving all the feedback to
the AA and then how the reaction time,
and then how the it how it is working.
And then the third, the fourth phase
is realtime real world validation.
We have in a certain drivers, we
will give the vehicles to the owners.
We call them test fleet
owners, test fleet vehicles.
And then the owners will give an a
complex instruction to the AA and then
how they interacted with that things.
And then we can modify, and then we can
rectify those things, and then we can
improve our aa into the info system.
And then future directions
and technical group.
So in the future, there are things
need to be considered in our ai.
So first thing is multi
modern, deep deep learning.
Integration of vision, audio and
sensor data and unified AI model
AI models, and then autonomous
integration so when you are driving
with hands free, hands, self driving.
So you are, you don't need to
be looking into the road or
some like fully autonomous.
You don't need to be, but semi-autonomous,
yes, you need to be sometimes you
don't need to be hands on the wheel
like autonomous, but in that state,
we need to be interacted with that aa
to that autonomous inter interaction.
So we have a better autonomous system.
And then AI documentary
reality integration.
So that is that is another thing
like, wind in the windshield.
We can show hey.
This is the information, this is the this
is the weather, this is the speed you
are, this is the, this is the traffic
you are going to, in the, in 15 minutes
or 10 minutes, something like that.
And then emotionally based on your mood,
based on your emotional state driver.
The AA will give an advice and
responded according to your modes.
And then V two X vehicle to everything,
communication, V two vehicle to
network, vehicle to other vehicle to,
a charging area, vehicle to interface.
So this kind of communication
is vehicle to another vehicle.
Vehicle to vehicle is also
another communication.
So how that things are we
need to looking into that one.
So this is how a we we will use into
that automotive industry and then we
will focus more on the deep learning
models and as well as the, how the.
A is interacted with infotainment
system and then as well as the
autonomous integration into data
infotainment system will achieve a
better and bright automotive systems.
Thank you so much and thank you.