Hi everybody, thank you for joining me today. Today we're going to talk about CSP.
How is it broken? What can we do to fix it?
Or at least just demystify some of it? My name is
Amir Shaked. I work at perimeterx. I did
the R D there, software engineer for many years,
R D leader for a few as well and building
things with good people. And this talk we're going to talk a bit about breaking
and building things and how they come together when we're talking, but CSP.
So let's begin with these story. And I love to
begin with stories. The story here is I wanted to enable
CSP on my website. I read and
understood the full meaning of all the directives that the implementations,
the CSP two, CSP three, all the variances
in the standard. I added the header to the website with
a report only option and started
getting traffic into some lambda
functions that consumed all the reports.
About a day later I went over the reports. It was very
clear which report is what. I marked all the resources that are
related to our website and updated these policy.
I switched the policy to block policy which basically means no reporter
what's blocking policy and I
had zero issues. The website worked flawlessly
and without any problem or anything
crashing, no support call to say some part of the website stopped
working somehow and I think nobody ever
said that story when it comes to CSP. I've talked to many people
in the industry who tried to use this really
positive standard with good intentions, but everybody had
some kind of issue along the way trying to improvements it in
their website. More common case
that we have seen is on several
websites is a case where they're getting some call from
their credit card company or another vendor. They're working on mostly the credit
cards company telling them that there was a breach.
Credit cards were stolen from their websites and when they're
doing the deep dive, usually with some consultant
when doing the deep dive trying to identify where and what and
how the breach was made, they end up finding that actually there
was no direct breach to the site, but a breach
to a third party vendor. And that vendor was responsible and
it was basically injecting additional code on
the front end and sending data to some new destination.
Now in practice, this is something that CSP
by design should have stopped. And yet time and
time again we see these cases happening on websites
where even though that should have been in place and
CSP in some cases was in place,
still the attack vector succeeded and data was
exfilterated from the site and
we touched on a few points on why even though you have CSP you
don't usually have it all the way and where are gaps
and problems with that. So just
in these word what is CSP? And I'm going to do a short technical session
here on what is CSP and how it's actually being used and
works. So CSP is a policy. First of
all that's important to remember. It's a policy which
adds another layer of security to the site,
mostly to protect from XSS and data
injection and data existration to different
domains. First introduced by the way all the way back in 2004.
But since 2013 went these
multiple iterations of the common standard
that we have today that we see today on many websites, with the
final version of version three
pretty close to being finished. So it's a very late draft
and version two is the one most commonly used today in websites
with CSP. So how does it work?
Basically you have an HTTP header that you add on the
back end and you have two of those. And we're going to touch on
the difference. The header says that you have in
this example what we have here. So we have default source saying self,
default source, self mean by default sources
of different elements can come from the domain itself, the parent
domain that serve the website scripts can come
from two destinations, self and these cDNJs net
another network. And if these is any kind
of validation, the report URL where data should
go is the top level domain CSP logging.
So that's these destination that will receive all the reports of
all violations happening on the front end on different users
to the CSP policy that we defined here. And then we
have in the HTML page two elements, the image and the script.
And both will work. The image will load because it's coming from on
the default source and these script will load because
it's allowed as a script source on that specific directive.
Now if somehow in some way the
last element here would have been added,
the directives that we had would make that forbidden and
we would have been receiving a report saying cdnjs.com
try to be accessed and to load a script.
So where is the problem with that?
Once you go into specifications, the problem is
they're not fully defined. And even though going
back here to this example, most of the directives are
very well defined in what they should do and shouldn't do. It's still an
RFC, it's still something that every browser need to improvements on their
own. And nothing here says what should be the report. And I'm going to
show example of where everything has all
the variations. So what a report holds. For example,
every browser can decide what they want to push into reports.
We do see an improvement there with more considerations,
but again there are variances that we've seen with
different browsers reporting the same violation when to
report. Another interesting point, should I report only once?
Should I report every time per session, per page?
And that leads to a lot of inconsistency and affects
how the system that you're using can learn from that.
Implementation itself may be lacking in different browsers.
We're going to touch on one example for a specific
CVE, but there are a lot of other cases where the browsers don't implement
that complicated RFC as it should and
it's usage dependent and that can be abused. And we're going to do a deep
dive to an example of why by design
there is a flaw in the concept of policy and
a whitelist. So let's start with numbers.
I think numbers talk better than anything else.
It's a standard that was been existing since 2012,
how much is it used, how often it is
and how everybody are using it. So this data is based on
information that I extracted from
HTTP archives going over their scans on the past
two years. Excellent data source if you want to research how
the web changes and behaves over time, by the way. So an excellent data source
to use. And what we have here is scan domains
over time and show it with the mouse.
So we have can domains over time. So that gives us the reference
point of how many domains are being tested. And what we can see is
that content security policy is actually
being uses more and more over time, which signifies
a positive trend until you're starting to dive into the details
and you see what's the difference. So we
see a great adoption of other security headers.
You can see the list here on the left,
on the right, sorry, which different security headers
were found on those scans.
And we
see that CSP is behind adopted on the rise
as more or lets about 10% of the websites.
So it looks like a positive trend. But when you would deep
dive to see what's actually being used along these different directives
for CSP, these are the numbers that pop up when you're
inspecting. So we had 690,000 domains that
actually used CSP at all,
out of 4 million websites,
sorry, 6 million websites that were scammed.
And the first, these are actually
just a replacement of obsolete security headers
that were common before. So the frame ancestors simply
says, do you allow the browser to load your website
in a frame or not. That's one upgrade insecure.
Again, replacement says that for previous
security header, mentioning that the
traffic should only be HTTPs. So don't allow HTTP traffic to the parent
domain only HTTPs traffic and block mixed content.
So again an additional layer on that only the follow
up if you're going to default source where it's actually getting
interesting, actually use more complicated
directives and trying to actually use the policy of where data
should be loaded from or sent to. And that's only 17%
out of the 620.
That means a much lower number actually
implementing CSP and trying to get all the value
out of these directives. And that's a very
sad data point. And I think a really big part
of it is some of the reasons that we're going to talk on later on
on the difference between the concept,
which is great, and the difficulties in implementing it
which makes it very hard to be uses out there.
So and
I'll give one example, diving into the directives themselves that we
see being used in the wild here is one example. You see the default
source and there is a very big difference between the
two options here. What you see on the top one is on
this one is on their website, allowing on
these default source any unsafe eval,
meaning any script can use eval and basically
run any code you want and any inline code in the
page. That basically means that between these two options anything can run on
the page. You didn't really enable any additional security
layer, you're allowing everything to run on the page.
That's the worst kind. On the far left
of the security spectrum you have actually nonsense
of the hash of the script itself that should be allowed to
run and that's great if you're using
that feature. That means that only specific scripts can run
and inline scripts can run and not everything. So being a
very strict great option, but very few websites actually
use that one. Besides that
we've seen again deep diving into the data from actual websites,
really poor usage and I was looking for common
directives being used and there should be around 30
and I found over 700 with some really
mind blowing examples here. I don't understand this, go for it. But then all
kinds of just bad implementations. I don't know if it's in
policy or the web servers, but it's really sad if somebody
actually tried to use the policy and then broke
it with invalid information in the policy itself.
If you're trying to use it, please I beg you, uses something like
this link here, the CSP evaluator by Google, which is
really good, and save yourself the trouble of having
worked so hard to create a policy and then having it be
unavailable to websites because it has bugs in these configuration.
Okay, so we talked a bit about the policy. Let's talk about the
reports. I have a policy in place. I want to dissect the reports and understand
them and the data isn't normalized at all.
These two links here are actually fascinating when you
inviting you to go and browse into them and you will see different types of
examples of reports coming in from
websites. And these reason is you will get violations from
a lot of stuff which are unrelated to the website. And that can be very
causing when you're trying to understand you see some two
or three reports of some domain and you can't find
how it's related to the website itself. And that could very well
be coming from somewhere else, say extensions, ads,
web proxies, both injecting code into the page,
completely irrelevant to the policy and the website you actually
build. So you need to find a way to reduce
all that noise and focus only on the interesting reports.
One way of doing that is by numbers.
If the number of reports per incident
per domain, for examples, is low or too low,
it might be a good indication that it's noise and you can ignore that and
focus only on the high number of reports.
That's one example that you can use.
But again, very interesting examples and I invite you to
go through them. I didn't want to do that, waste our session for
that. And these last is browser misalignment.
That's actually a very big issue and you should be aware of that.
Different browsers do different things. This is
the latest information that I have might have changed a
long time because the browsers are always updating the way they
report. But from our last
these, we saw that these kind of differences, I'll highlight
only key ones for chrome. If you have a repetitive call
to a blocked resource, you only get one report.
For Firefox you will get repeating reports. So that's different.
With Safari, you might get only the truncated
top level domain and not the full blocked uri, which you might
have wanted the full uri to see more information. So these
kinds of differences make it very different to analyze the reports that
you're getting between browsers. And like we saw here, between other
things that might create noise leading
to a problem of essentially log spamming.
There is no validation, there is no validation on who is sending the
data. And anybody can push information
into your system on supposed violations.
It could be even fake reports hitting directly
your API and reporting fake CSP
violations only to try and game your
system. If you have say an automatic system that automatically
whitelists domains per number of occurrences, somebody can
try and use that and create some adversarial
machine learning concept of tricking the system to whitelist
a domain. Haven't seen that yet, but definitely a
concept that is out there being discussed.
Okay, another thing is
it has an implementations gaps like everything. In this case
you can see the cves over time with different browsers,
specifically mentioning CSP and the various implementations
that it has in browsers. And I want to touch
on one specific CVE that we discovered and reported
on about a year ago, and that is
this one. So using the above policy,
which seems very strict, objects can be loaded from nowhere
and child from nowhere, and scripts only from the parent domain.
And the trick here is we define
a URL obviously coming from an unauthorized location,
and we're creating can element and doing child
append with that element. And the script runs and
it doesn't run, sorry. And these script doesn't run.
But if you're running the same thing this
way this call will succeed and will be evaluated
and these code will be loaded into the page. Why is
that? Because of the complexities of how
the engine, browsers engine works,
and it's quite complicated to create a very bulletproof system.
So this is an example where even though you had a very strict
policy, we found a way where the code
were still running and loaded, even though it should have been running.
That CB has been reported, has been closed. But it's just an example where
even though you think you have a very strict policy, there might
be a bug in the browsers itself, causing it to be irrelevant.
An interesting point to make. Websites that loaded,
that used these nonsense for the timeline scripts
were not vulnerable to this bug because they were
restricting inline scripts to come only from those
known hashes, which is why this
works on some websites and not on other websites that were more
strict in their policy.
The point to make here is that a very strict policy,
a very good policy, might also protect you from potential bugs
in the browser's implementation.
So what can possibly go wrong with these policy?
We've talked a lot about different aspects of
CSP, the implementation, the configuration,
but there is a core issue with the concept of a policy that
makes it vulnerable, and I want to touch on that because it's a very interesting
one. In this research we
took a different approach. We said, and this is over time, let's look
at the most common allowed targets. Whatever it's
coming from, the script, the default, the object, whatever it
is, these are the common allowed targets. And we
can see here a specific domain coming repeatedly
Google Analytics on the different variations on
March 2000 and went it was more common. It was common on June
2021 it was way more common.
And we said okay, let's pick these top one the most commonly whitelisted
domain on website and let's think
what can we do with it and how can we game the concept and
abuse the CSP policy simply because that domain is
whitelisted? And it's a fascinating one
once you have a safe list, if the safe list is
a generic destination where everybody can create an account
in, nothing really protects you from sending
different kinds of information. And point to make here for Google Analytics
is we added this code into the website
that had CSP with a very strict policy
but had Google Analytics allowed.
And essentially what this means is that we
can send information to any id that we want
to show you here where it is. So the
tid, we basically can define any id that we want to send
the information to, which will allow us to see
the information sent on our dashboard of Google Analytics and not
another dashboard. And example here is you saw the code
collecting the information and sending it and you can see it here,
very simple. In the Google Analytics dashboard we have
the hash, we can dehash it, we have the username and the password
being sent from a website that had a
policy but allowed Google Analytics.
The next these was let's try to protect it,
maybe by query programs or something else. How can we at
least improve the system? So wouldn't this be nice if we could have said
ok, you can connect to Google Analytics, but only to a specific
target id, not any target id. And then you can protect the
system but you can't. And the quote from
the RFC basically says the exact point
query strings have no impacts they're not being matched
on, meaning you can't add that layer of protection.
And we are focusing here on Google Analytics.
But it's important to remember, if we go back
to this list, there are other domains here which simply pick
the top one and said can anybody create an
account, in this case a completely free account, and use that
to exfiltrate information simply because it was whitelisted.
But other domains here are easily,
easily applicable for them as well, simply because the way the concept
works of the safe
list, and it's not just
a theory. We published a post about
the method in June 17 and just
a few days later, other security vendors found
that specific usage being used in the
wild by attackers to exfiltrate information and
basically abuse that layer of protection coming from CSP.
So think about it. We added all the layers of protection,
we configured a very strict policy, we made sure it is working
properly. But the basic flaw
is that one domain that we uses is a generic domain that
anybody can open an account on, top level domain,
and that allows anybody to bypass all the protection
that we're trying to add with CSP.
Basically, it's crazy if you think about it now,
one would claim that it
might be valid, but where did the code come from?
So they might be able to abuse the destination, but can
they abuse the source of the data?
And that's an interesting point to be
made. A very common Tac vector would
be to target an open destination that
you're using and replace their code. It could be a third party vendor
that you're using that you already whitelisted.
It could be obsolete domains. And these are
examples that we've seen, domains that were whitelisted.
And because it's a whitelist policy, you don't get reports of the part
of the policy not being used. So you had a vendor,
maybe a startup that you tested and you worked with, you added
them, you tried to see how it works,
maybe even uses them for a while. They closed the domain, might even be
up for sale, but you did not
remove it from your policy. Because of the way these process works between
say DevOps and front end development
or whoever actually added it, it could be even somebody from the marketing
team and these domain
has been open for purchase and somebody could take over
it. So we saw examples of domains being whitelisted
that are no longer valid. But even
taking can example from earlier this year,
2021 where Cloudflare had
a bug was discovered in the CDNJs network
that allowed an arbitrary person to
come in and replace code with any library that
sits on the CDN.
That means that these risk there
was that anybody could create a hijack and replace the code. And if
you're loading libraries from that specific destination, you could
have been exposed potentially to such a risk. Now that vulnerability
was discovered and closed. So it's not actively a
risk, but there are other such cdns and
vendors that everybody are using that are always at risk.
So the point to make here is
both destinations are at risk because of the way the policy is
defined with the whitelist. So somebody can come in
through an allowed service and send exerted information
to another allowed service. In the policy.
So where it went wrong, it went wrong because
first of all, managing a policy, it's hard. It doesn't
always hold in today's modern web apps with these rate
of changes and things being added and basic things
of abusing the safe list to inject
code and extract information simply breaks the entire
concept that sits behind CSP, kind of rendering
it invalid, which is a very bad using.
So how can we make the best of it?
Well, in coming to look at this problem,
one would say it's a terrible idea, don't use
CSP, there is no value in it. So I wouldn't go that far,
but I gave examples. But once you understand the gaps,
the potential gaps, you understand that CSP is a good layer
of protection that you should add what you should use it for,
but it's not these holy grail. It doesn't stop everything.
So you shouldn't count on it as the only thing that will protect you
against access or data injection
or data exfiltration from the front
end of the page.
So a few would say tips
on how to make the best of it. So filtering the report is definitely something
that you should do and not spend your was your
time going over all the violations?
A b testing the policy a wonderful concept.
One way to reduce the risk of having
obsolete domains in the policy is doing a b
test on the report only policy.
So you could have a very strict report
only policy, constantly adding and removing
domains from the list. And if you see that
you have a domain that you don't get any reports on, that means that
it's not being used anymore. That means you can remove it from the
strict blocking policy, because if you're not getting reports and this allows you
to test if a specific domain is being used or
not without damaging the experience of the users. So that
allows you to keep a very clean and lean domain list
in. The policy has
different levels of strict policy for different pages.
A sensitive page page with purchase login,
things like that is definitely a place to have a very strict policy
and also reduce the number of libraries
that you have there. The Google Analytics was an example. Let's not have
it in a specific page that has
a risk of
that specific link that we discussed. And if you don't have it, then you reduce
the risk altogether. And you can limit the problem
for specific pages with that PiI that
you're trying to protect, not necessarily the entire website clean
up every once in a while. That connects very well to the third point of
how you can actually do it. Always consider
adding additional layers of security, such as the nons and the hashes
for the inline scripts and the external scripts. Again,
it could sound very difficult and a lot of work, but if you limit that
to sensitive pages then
the work is much smaller and it's very specific,
so it's more manageable. I would say for a modern web app with multiple
components going back
to being the same thing, context aware. And the last thing I really wish
anyone here in this forum, especially with
this conference, the conference two focusing on JavaScript and I don't
know how much you want you like security, but it's a big part of what
you can do with it on the front end. So contribute to
the CSP three with comments and I think any improvement can make
this better. And that's
it. A few takeaways just to consider in
mind. So we talked but skimmers in a brief those
using the javascript to inject content and steal
data from the website. It's an increasing
risk and you should take it in mind when you're adding and removing libraries
into your website, specifically JavaScript libraries,
that CSP is not a silver bullet and we've covered very extensively
why and that you should have the checklist
for your own site, what you should do and which resources are critical.
Yes or no. These are the three things I want you to take from this
session, and I will have be able to answer
questions on the discord or you can reach out to
me if you want later on.
Thank you,