My name is Mitri Vaishinka. I am a software engineer at my games.
In this talk, we will look at the latest features of Python 312.
Today we are diving into four key areas, typing,
syntax performance, and debugging. Let's dive into these
enhancements one by one. So Python 312
brings exciting typing improvements. First, we have generics
with a new, cleaner syst syntax. It makes
writing generic classes and functions simpler.
Next, typed dixed allows for precise type annotations
of dictionary keys and values. The override
creator ensures methods overrides those in superclass accurately.
Advanced type parameters cater to more complex
typing scenarios. Type lss are now easier to declare
and use. They make code more readable and maintainable.
And lastly, we will talk about lazy evaluation and scope
rules. New syntax changes how we
declare generics it's now more straightforward.
Before, we used typefar for type parameters and
classes needed generic t. To use generics,
write the type in square brackets, look at the
max function, and list class examples. The new
way is clearer and simpler. No more extra steps or wrapping needed.
This makes our code cleaner and easier to understand.
Web 692 has transformed how we use quarks.
It brings typed dict into function signatures.
This means we can be precise with keyword arguments.
Before, we had to use broad types,
this didn't tell us much about the expected keywords.
Now, with type dict, everything changes. We define
exact keys and their types. This makes our function
clear and safer. No more guessing what quarks
should contain. It's a big leap for Python's type system,
and it's great for functions that depend on
keywords arguments. This clearly reduces aurora and proves
readability. Pep 698
introduces typing override.
It's new decorator for static typing.
It marks methods that should override superclass
methods. This helps catch discrepancies
earlier, before method mismatches could slip through typers
and method names went unnoticed. Typing override acts as a
safeguard. It features our overrides are intentional and
correct. This boots quadrability and main attainability.
Web 695 marks a big step towards the
Python's type system. It now supports type
for a tuple and param specs directly in type LSS.
This means we can define more complex types with this.
For example, we can create a type for functions returning integers,
or a tuple type that starts with a string followed
by any number of elements. We can also restrict
sequence elements to be hashable, and even
define sequences that only contains integers
or strings. This update simplifies the creation of generic
types. It makes our code more expressive and easier to
understand. With these tools, we can write more robust and
type save Python code. Pep 695
brings a latest features type aliases now we
can declare type aliases more easily, even with generic using
the type statement. It makes our code hints cleaner
and enhances their expressiveness. Before this update,
defining LSS was more complex.
We used typevar or dialect assigning types.
This new syntax simplifies the process, making our code
more readable. Python 312 introduces lazy
evaluation for types. Types are evaluated only
when needed. It's a big change, especially for complex
types. Let's look at an example. We define a
type alias that should cause an error, but the
error only comes when we access a specific attribute.
This allows for more complex type definitions,
including immutably recursive type aliases.
Before, such constructs were cumbersome. Now they
are straightforward and elegant. Let's dive into
syntax improvements. Python 212
has made app strings even better. Now we
can reuse quotes inside appstrings without hassle.
Nesting f strings is straightforward with no limits.
You can spread app strings with multiple lines,
even add comments. Backslashes and Unicode work
smoothly in fstrings. Error messages got an upgrade.
They are cleaner now, and there is inner tools batched.
It's a handsy new addition. These changes make
coding in Python simpler and more powerful.
So let's look at these syntax improvements. Python 312
simplifies f strings. Now you can reuse quotes
inside them. This change makes string formatting
more intuitive. Here is an example with a reading
list. Notice how the quotes are consistent throughout.
Before, we would have caused a syntax error.
Now the same quotes flow inside and out seamlessly.
This update streamlines string composition in Python.
Now you can nest f strings with each other
as deep as needed. This makes complex
string constructions easier. Here is an example
to illustrate. We nest several f strings together.
This was not as straightforward before Python
212 introduced multiline f strings. You can now include
comments right inside them. This makes complex
strings clearer and easier to maintain. Here is how
you can format a movie list with comments.
Each movie is annotated with its unique attribute
with this feature enhances code reliability significantly,
especially when dealing with intricate string constructions.
The new update expands f strings to include backslashes
and Unicode. Now special characters and Unicode
symbols fit right into f strings.
Here is how you can separate items with new lines in an f
string, or join them using Unicode character
like a black heart. With Python 312,
f strings get better at showing where errors are.
Debugging f strings is now quicker, thanks to clearer error messages.
Here's an example of an error in an app string.
The message points exactly to where the mistake is.
It even suggests you might have forgotten a comma.
This precise feedback makes fixing errors faster.
The new release introduces a handy tool iter
tool batched. This function breaks down
data into fixed size pieces.
It's perfect for working with big data or streaming in parts.
Here's how it works in a new version. Just a
few lines of code and you are patching data easily.
Before this, you had to write your own function for batching.
Python 312 brings exciting performance boosts.
First up, async I O is faster.
That's great for async programming.
Inspect and typing models are quicker. Now we
have immortal objects too. They streamline memory
management. There is a new guild strategy. It's unique pair
interpreter comprehension in lining speeds up your list and
dict creations, and more and more enhancements under the hood,
Python 312 boosts async speed significantly.
Benchmarks show up to 75 increase
in speed. Socket writing is now more efficient.
Creating async tasks is faster than before.
Current task is now implemented in C. This change along
speeds things up by four to six times.
These improvements make asyncular slicker and
faster. And for I o bound tasks,
this means better responsiveness. The inspect
and typing modules are now faster. Inspect get ultra static
sees speed increase by up to six times,
as instance checks against protocols are much
quicker. Some checks are now 20 times faster
than before. However, protocols with over 14
members might be slower. This tradeoff
targets efficiency for most common use cases.
These enhancements aid in better code analysis and typing.
Overall, Python's introspection and typing are more efficient.
Pep 684 brings a game changing update
to Python. Each Python interpreter now gets its
own global interpreter lock. This allows
true parallelism across multiple cpu cores.
Currently, it's accessible through the C
API. A Python API is expected in version 3.13.
This feature opens a new door for high performance Python
applications. It's a significant step towards optimizing
Python concurrency. Model 709
marks a pivotal shift in Python comprehensions.
It introduces inlining for lists,
dictionaries, and sets. This eliminates the
need for creating temporary function. Objects comprehensions
are now up to twice as fast.
They also keep variables isolated,
enhancing code safety tracebacks
and profiling. See some changes due to this.
The SIM table module adapts along with locals behavior
in comprehensions. Notable quark involves iterating
over locals during tracing. There is a straightforward
workaround for that. Pep 683 talks about
a new idea called immortal objects. These are
special because they don't need tracking how many
times they are used. This is good for big apps
like Django codes with lot of users to run smoother in
Python, using an object normally means
it gets counted, which can slow
things down. But with immortal objects, this counting
doesn't happen, keeping things fast.
Still, this cool feature is only useful for a
few Python projects. Pep 688
makes a buffer protocol accessible from Python. Now classes
with a buffer method works as buffers.
It introduces two new magic methods,
buffer and release buffer. There's a new standard way
to talk about buffer objects in Python, a new
set of options for making buffers just right.
Two new special methods make buffers easier to use in
Python. This is great for sharing data, especially with
C extensions, but most Python users
might not found this very useful. Python 312 brings
a mix of performance boosts. The vault optimizer
is now in experimental phase. It promises a noticeable
increase in speed. Regex substitutions are quicker
by two or three times, comprehensions for
common collections are more efficient and calls
to the super method are now faster.
Debugging in Python 312 got a big upgrade.
Name error suggestions are sharper now.
They got you better. Syntax and import errors
messages are clearer. They are more helpful now.
New API for monitoring Python execution
events these changes make debugging less
of headache and more of breeze. Python 312
makes error messages more helpful.
Name errors now offer suggestions for fixes.
It can hint at missing standard library inputs.
It also suggests correct instances
attributes. For example, it might recommend
using self attribute. These changes
make debugging much easier and new release
improved syntax error messages errors like import
x from Y now have clearer guidance.
Import error now suggests correct names from
the module. These changes simplify debugging.
They help quickly identify and fix import errors,
especially useful with unfamiliar libraries.
Pep 669 transforms how we monitor
Python execution. It introduces a new low
impact monitoring API. This is perfect
for profilers, debuggers and monitoring tools.
The API covers a broad range of events with little overhead.
Debugging and coverage can now be nearly overhead
free. Here is how to use the new capabilities in
Python 312. Previously,
tracing calls had a higher performance cost.
With Pep 669, monitoring is
more efficient and less intrusive. So we've covered
the updates in Python 312. Improvements touch
on typing, syntax, debugging, and performance. These changes
significantly simplify development. They make code more reliable
and understandable. So thank you for your attention
and see you next time.