Hi, my name is Phil Wilkins. Thank you for joining me today
on this session about Fluentd and how we can use it to
make our logs so much more productive. Let me
start by giving you a brief introduction to myself.
So in five a family man, a blogger,
an author of several books, I am both a technology evangelist
for our team and a technical architect, which means
not only do I have to talk about these technology, I have to actually go
and make it work. So a lot of this is hard
won, proven stories. So I happen
to work for Capgemini in the UK and our
team has won quite a few awards over the last 510 years,
which we're as a team very proud of and continue to work
to innovate and deliver excellence.
As a team. We work with Oracle Technologies. So that's
Oracle Cloud, that's Oracle middleware, as well as
a lot of open source. And a lot of people perhaps don't realize
Oracle have really embraced open source in the last few years.
Again, there's a lot out there that's based on open source technologies
as well as licensed product. And of course if you want to know lots
more, that my website's got logs and lots of information,
including material around this session. If I'm not writing,
I'm also helping host a meetup based in London,
which at the moment is being done virtually. But hopefully
someday in the not so far away future we will
be back to getting together physically and of course talking about
fluentd that I have to obviously drop a little plugin. I'm in
the process of finalizing these book called logging in action. You can get
early access to it now and a lot of examples
and content that I'm going to talk about today comes from the book.
So hopefully you will find this useful and perhaps
go and buy a copy. I mentioned Capgemini, it's a
substantial organizations and thriving despite
the difficult times that we're in today. But I would encourage you
to go have a look and if you're thinking about jumping a ship,
then we are looking for good people. So I always try and start my
sessions with a little bit of context and logging and monitoring
our interest in animals because we all come from it from slightly different perspectives
as applications development, as package integration
perspective, from an infrastructure perspective.
And what we look at logging and think about does actually
vary quite a bit. So I think the key messages here
is about it's information over time. So time is an important asset.
It's about what is changing and what is happening and helping us
understand what's evolving now that sounds a little bit obvious, but in the
different perspectives, that information and what it
is differs quite significantly. So let me
illustrate this in a little bit more practical. From an infrastructure perspective,
you're more likely to be worrying about things like the CPU
and your memory resources, disk storage allocations
and details like that. These as an apps
person or DevOps person, you're probably going to
be looking more at the textual logs which characterize
what's going on, rather than numerical statistical figures.
You have 80% CPU usage. You're going to be seeing SNMP
teams where file write errors occur and things like
that. You're going to have your applications logging. If you're a Java person,
you've probably been using something like sl for j or log
for j or one of that kind of family of logging
frameworks. But of course if you're then dealing
with end to end stories, you've got to think about the tracing dimension
of it, of what happens at each point in the solution, not just in my
little bit of code. So you can track what's going on, where is
something getting held up or falling over. And we can look at
the different aspects and these trace information
vis the log information, vis the metrics based
information against the different layers. So a hosting
layer is heavily influenced by metrics low on the
log characteristics, on the textual content. As you move
into virtualization and containerization you're into a
bit more of the logs because you're going to have your VMware
or Kubernetes environments writing a bit about what it's
doing and so on. But you've still got a strong percentage statistical
analysis going on of resource utilization and things like
that. When you get into applications. We are now really starting to
look at a lot more of these. What's the application doing,
where is it executing some numerical data still? Because we're
still collecting metrics, numbers of users signed on, things like that.
And then of course if you're a business person, you're going to be more interested
in business application, it's still monitoring, you're still interested in
what's going on, but it more becomes who's doing
what, when have they done it and how many transactions are
allowing in the environment at this time and things like that.
But theyre all logs, they're all numerical data. Theyre will need
to be monitoring and either sucked into a graphical
representation of percentages used and things like that,
or into textual search engine to start analyzing.
And of course then around these side you've got security considerations
and your capacity even in today's world of
cloud, you need to be looking after your capacity. You got elastic
scaling, that's fantastic. But is somebody doing something that
means that your scaling is just running away and you're going to be bring on
a lot more money than perhaps you expected. So capacity
monitoring is still something to be considered. So let's look
at these applications of the logs. I've touched upon some of this, but obviously
one of our key issues is looking for unexpected errors
or warnings of an error scenario occurring. If we're getting
our file system getting used up to very high percentages,
then we are likely to get faults start occurring because files
can't be written. So it's worth thinking about that, because one of the things that
we'll see is we tend to look at logs in retrospective,
rather than looking at them as opportunities
to be precursors and therefore become preemptive.
Rather than waiting till a problem occurs, we can use the logs to
warn us or give us indications that a problem is going to occur.
If we don't intervene, we can look at performance issues. I've talked about
cpu and dis storage, but what about slow queries in
databases? There are plenty of databases
technologies out there, but most of them give you access or insight
into what's underperforming or performing badly.
Some dedicated tools exist to do that, but perhaps you
want to look at that in the context of how your application is
performing as well. What is cause and what is effect?
Obviously we've got, in this day and age, the world of security to
worry about as well through SiEm tooling.
And that's quite interesting, because quite often you'll see a completely
different set of tools for analyzing that information compared to what DevOps
teams or app developers might be using. And of course, as we
get into bigger and bigger systems, we need to bring the picture together
from lots of different components distributed across our network to
be able to understand what's going on end to end. Otherwise it's
very easy for one team to blame another and say, well, our system
looks like it's performing and reporting okay, problems somewhere
else. Not me, Gov. The bottom line is, whatever we
do with logging, we actually are monitoring.
It's all got to support the business and it's all got to
come back to what is going on and how does it impact our business.
If you're monitoring something that's not related to the business at
all, ultimately what value is it going to bring? Could be interesting.
It might be a potential problem, but ultimately in
most organizations everything comes back to increasing
or improving the business value, and we need to overcome
that. There's very few organizations that are going to
let you do some blue sky thinking in the monitoring space.
These diagram is trying to help us understand
or visualize the way monitoring has evolved and just how
complicated the problem has become. Years ago we used to be
on single applications, single threads,
single machine applications. Great,
fantastic, easy to monitor because it was just one location that
was producing it. And the chances are you would be able to spot
the cause of problems quite quickly. As we've evolved over
time, we've started to see concurrency and these asynchronous
behaviors. So we start parking activities temporarily
whilst we wait for something to happen and then pick it up, which is what
we see. We node, we see multithreading in a more
traditional concurrency and we get thread blocks and things
like that. And these of course in the last five years
or so we've seen the likes of containerization really
take that to a whole new level and that's increased distribution of
solutions as well. The latest generations of that sort of
thinking in serverless functions means that the
whole problem gains another scale of complexity, because now
each part of your application is completely transient.
It fires up, does its job and then disappears.
So how are you going to go and see what was bring on?
Because the container that was running or the platform that was running,
your solution will have gone by the time you probably get to
the logs. A real challenge there to deal with.
Okay, so I've set out the landscape somewhat, and I want to
talk a little bit about getting to fluentd now and talk about what it is
actually capable of and set the scene for that. Most people have
heard of fluentd because of its involvement in CNCF. If you're
working with containerization, you've probably heard about
fluentd as an option for log driving in
Docker and its relationship with kubernetes
particularly. But not so many people understand quite
what it's capable of. So let me drill in and just show you
what it is. So it is a highly pluggable framework.
In fact, everything is pretty much seen as a plugin,
or described as a plugin within the fluentd ecosystem.
Now, within fluentd, it starts with a collection of standard plugins
being present, but everything operates in the same model,
which makes it very extensible. And one of Fluentd's
benefits is the amount of work that's been done not just by the
core open source team and the committees that work hard on
fluentd, but also organizations beyond
that. As a result, we can take in log events in
many means different ways. It's not just a case of just polling
file systems looking for logs or maybe talking to
an SMP framework. It can talk to many,
many different sources. It's very flexible. It is largely
platform agnostic. It will run on Windows equally as comfortable as
it will run on a Linux environment or a Mac on outputs.
It is equally as powerful, perhaps even more powerful
in terms of plugins, because one of the beauties of it is if you
can get all these different types of information sourced in,
everybody's going to come to you to get that information into
their product. You've got custom plugins for Splunk,
for Prometheus, for Grafana, kafka,
jabber tools, slack emails,
and the list goes on and on and on. So it's very,
very flexible. And this is part of the core story around
fluentd. It talks about described itself as a log unification
layer, which means that we can bring all the logs together,
unify it and then feed it to where it needs to be.
That can be more than one system, as we'll
see in a minute. Of course formatters are necessary. Different sources
will describe their logs in different ways and structures,
whether that's a CSV or JSON or XML
or some custom bespoke format.
But theyre are many, many formatters that can cope with that and therefore we
can translate the log events into a consistent form
to be consumed into the different systems.
We can filter things, some log events are just
not relevant beyond perhaps keeping a local copy.
Just show that everything is running smoothly and you
might want to just be told about things that are abnormal.
So we can filter out the log events and say, well that's interesting that
we can just bim because that's just the application confirming that everything
is okay, we compose it. This is important not
only just to help do major transformation of data
structures, but importantly to translate logs
as data to logs to something meaningful. We need to take what could
be a huge great string of key value pairs and translate
it to something meaningful that can be acted upon or queried
a lot more easily. And that requires parsing buffers and caching.
So in the day of distributed solutions we need
to pass these things around. And you do get transient errors in networks
from time to time. Therefore we need to buffer and cache things up
to stop losing the information.
Whilst those connections restore themselves, you can use
your buffer and cache bring obviously to optimize processes
of distributing the logs as well. So we get
efficient use of the events and of course,
storage. So if you're not sending it to an active storage
solution, we might just want to write it to a file for legal
archival issues. If we're creating a record of what's
happened in these system, just to show all is well and that
there have been no security breaches, and you might need
to retain that for a long time. We just want to write that to a
storage system that is very efficient and only
pull that out of storage and consume it into an analysis tool
if or when there is a real problem. And then, as you may have guessed,
there is a clear and strong framework for building
your own custom elements so you can build your own plugins.
It's all based around Ruby, which means it's pretty portable
and very flexible, and most people can get their heads around
it. It's not like it's a very weird bespoke language.
If you're an average developer, you'll soon get to grips with it, because the framework
makes it very easy to understand what to look at and what you
need to produce to get a plugin up and running and get it deployed.
So fluentd looks at logs in the form
of three parts, a tag, which is just effectively a label,
so we can associate it with something that's just a shortcut,
largely timestamp, which is critical, because as we said,
all events are in context of time, and then the record,
which can be just about anything you like. But the more meaning
that's in there, the better it is, because it means that we can
process the record in more detail.
As I say, to make the most of fluent D,
we need, or logs in generally. Actually, we need to go
from capturing, just capturing bits of strings or data
to actually translating it, to being very meaningful. And you've got
a kind of lifecycle of events here where we start at
the source, these capture, just get the information in to process.
We then need to structure that information to work out
how to handle it and process it with a bit more meaning.
Then we're into the world of potentially aggregating
and analyzing it. So looking for repeating events,
things like that, and we're starting to move in to
the world where other tools are better suited, and we
use fluent D to get that data there so that we can maximize
the other tools. So yeah, when you get into these analytical
processes, unification tools is not the best thing.
You want a data analytics engine that's looking at data that
you've made structured and meaningful, and fluentd
is passing it all to the right places to then do the analysis
of course, once you've done login analysis, we need to do
some sort of visualization to make it easier to consume these
information, pull out what's important, not present every little detail.
And of course, ideally when things are indicated as
not healthy, we're generating alerts that could be a
Jira ticket to give details of an error that's been thrown in the
application. That could be a service desk support thing.
That could be a slack message to someone looking after the system at
that moment in time to say the file system on server XYZ
is about to hit 100% use. Go fix it now
mate. If you've heard of fluentd, you've probably
encountered the two common stacks which are described
as the elk stack or elasticsearch, log stash
and kibana, which is this. And as you can see,
I've taken that lifecycle and drawn it into
these core, these the log aggregation, the unification,
the basic transformation to make it meaningful,
which is log stash primarily with a
baby brother of beats, which is ideal for
very, very small footprint deployments. You've got elasticsearch,
which is your analytics and search engine, and then Kibana gives you
the visualization. But there is an alternate stack that's coming
up getting more and more mention and that's the EFK,
which is essentially the same thing, except we now replace log stash
with fluentd. Now the reason for doing or considering
doing that replacement and moving from milk to fc is the fact
that logs stash, whilst it's a good tool, has a bigger footprint.
It also has the disadvantage, the fact it is a
product aligned to a vendor in these form of elastic. Nothing wrong with
that in itself, except elastic perhaps don't make
it or encourage the development of plugins,
which means that the number of systems that logstash can reach
is smaller than fluentd by quite a margin.
So that's one of the key benefits of considering moving over
to the fluentd approach. There is also the fact that
if you're working with Docker, there are pre built
drivers to take docker logs and just pump them to fluentd.
And again, there's a lot of work being made available to package
up and make fluentd available to kubernetes
based environments out of the box or
very close to being out of the box, because you do need to obviously apply
a few configuration items like where your servers
are. So theyre the differences there. There's nothing
wrong with elk, but there are more opportunities,
let's put it that way, with the fluentd based stack
and they work equally well. They just need slightly different configs
at the bottom. So I'm going to do a little demo in a moment.
I'm going to run it for you, but let's talk about what the
demo does just to give you some real world events of the art of the
possible. I'm bring to start with a setup where I've got,
let's say a couple of applications running in a Kubernetes
environment. They could be running in a vm or running on
bare metal. It really doesn't matter particularly fluentd
does not care. It works in legacy environments
as equally well as the most modern containerization setups.
It just happens that those people on the containerisation
end of that scale perhaps are a bit more aware of fluentd.
And what we got in our demo is we've got what's
called a pipeline, which is going to take one log file been
generated or simulated. I don't actually have real applications.
I'm going to run what I've built as a log simulator,
which is a utility that can generate log events or play
back old log files and restamp them so it looks
like it's can active live log. And we'll see the log
files being filled out in real
time, rather than it being one great big lump that can
be passed instantly. And in that file I'm going to do
a little bit manipulation, because in one file, as you will
see in a minute, it describes as payload using one attribute,
and in the other application file it describes
it slightly differently. And what I want to do downstream is
to process the log events in the same way.
And it also just pumps out the log events to a file.
So we got an audit trail of how log events have been tweaked.
And that could be one node or it could be many. Okay,
so that's the aggregation and we can scale that out
and we just get more and more fluentd nodes doing that preprocessing.
So I'm going to do with it, I'm going to do the fun, funky thing,
because what I often encounter is a lot of people think about
logs as things to search after an event,
but we should be and can be preemptive. If you've
got a log event that indicates something is going to become a
problem. And this is a great way of dealing with legacy applications.
Over time you'll understand what the log messages mean. And sometimes
you get these little log events that look quite
innocent but actually indicate a serious issue. And one
of the things we can do with fluent D is actually process it and go
actually, whilst that logs innocent, it's a precursor to
a very very significant issue and therefore you can act upon it
before your system collapses because something is broken.
In the demo, we're going to have just one node running that and one node
running on the source, both on the same machine.
One of the things that I mentioned fluent and fluent bit its baby
brother, are tiny footprints. So you can run all of this in
these most simplistic of machines if you
want. And what we're going to be doing on this second node is again
filtering it out, going to write all the logs to a standard
out, which could be a more practical use case of warboard.
And I'm going to send to slack anything that has a
particular context in the log event. So you can see
it pushing a message to me very, very quickly. And of course therefore we
need to run this across a network of some sort. I have talked about
and mentioned these existence of elasticsearch and Prometheus
and Sim. We could equally also route these events to
an analytics engine for looking for anomalous
behaviors and for doing other mining of log events
as well. And we could separate that out that we can do both.
It's not of one or the other. We're not tying our notifications and
alerts to the analysis these which if
you used splunk or tools like that, they will alert
off the analysis these once they've ingested the
log event and theyre run their queries.
But for today I'm not going to do that. I'm just going to concentrate on
this little piece just because it's quite funky and it gives you something
fairly visual to see. So let me show you the setup.
This is the configuration file for these first
server node one which is generating the source. As you
can see it's a combination of XML style teams
and name value pairs. It's a bit strange
to start with, but the moment you get your head round it,
it's incredibly easy to work with. Here are the two
sources. You can see two different files coming from two different solutions,
and I've set it up so that we can track them. So if
my fluentd node was to be stopped temporarily,
or it gets reconfigured or moved around the network,
it will know where to pick up and carry on.
It can deal with all sorts of things like log rotation and stuff like that.
And it's going to convert the payload. Let's move on. And the
next bit is filter, which is going to actually
apply a record change. Now all this is doing is because they're
coming in with slightly different structures. This is going to
adjust the log event so it has the same structure.
In one message. I'm bringing the payload, the core payload
in with a tag called event and the other one is message and
I want to make it consistent and I'm going to actually just flag that
it's transformed and then I'm going to do the routing and
sending of the events. As you can see, I've got these file store
there and I've got a little bit of buffering going on, just so the I
O is a bit more efficient. And then on the right
hand side you can see I'm sending to another node on my
machine every 5 seconds the log events
for the second node to process, which gives
us this configuration. And you can see now I'm
saying, okay, I'm going to accept from anywhere this is a pretty promiscuous
ingestion of log events that have been transmitted.
I'm then going to filter it out and I'm looking for anything that has got
a reference to computer, so it can be
a lowercase or an uppercase c for computer or anything like that
out of my log events. And then if it's got that value,
it will go to my slack channel. And just
to show you, here's this open source utility I've built for helping
to simulate application logging.
It means that we can configure and test our fluent
d pipelines without needing to run these real life
systems. And if we want to see what happens when an
error occurs, we can ply log file with errors in
into the environment as if it was live and
see or confirm that the right alerts are being generated
and whether our analytics engines is going
to be able to pick up these details.
And as you can see, importantly here is how I
am structuring the payload. And you can
see I'm saying it's going to be an event. And that's the payload
log payload. And over here I've called it message
and I've put it in a slightly different sequence in the file,
but it will find the message piece and do the analysis
to determine whether it talks about computer. And this is what
we're going to see in a moment. So let me drop out of the presentation
deck and we'll see this happening for real.
I am bring to just run a little startup script
which is going to fire up a number of shell
windows which are going to give me the two log
generators which you can see here. One is going to be fairly
quiet. One is going to be very chatty because I've got the different settings.
Then I've got two fluent D nodes. There's server one,
here's server two.
And you can see it's just reported the console,
the configuration file it's picked up and what it's up
to. And you can see over here on fluentd node
two it's actually receiving the log events and
theyre all coming through with message in the title.
All right. And up here you can see that's very quiet.
This one is being verbose and it's showing me the log
event source file it's processing and
how many times it's looping through that data set to create
log events. Just to understand,
rather than playing real log files or application logs and generating
them, I've set my tool up to run from
a mock data set which is just basically
full of jokes. And what we've got over here,
this is my slack desktop client
and you can see here that
periodically it will scroll as new messages
come in. And it's just the messages
that have got a reference to computer. So you can see, there you go.
Node two says oldest computer can be traced back to Adam and Eve.
And you can see every one of these.
Whilst these are just junk jokes
being pushed through, you could imagine that this is a genuine log event.
And whilst I'm just showing what the text is, you could very easily say okay,
when I identify this event, I'm going to
put a more meaningful message in. You could
potentially put hyperlink into your
ops processes to how do I resolve this?
And things like that. So that's
what it's doing. And if I come into here,
what we're going to see, if I just stop that,
if I go into the demo folder,
we can see there is log
file being generated and there's
a folder for it, for it. So one of the logs
we've got is log rotating. So if
I go to label,
label pipeline and we look in here,
I haven't left it running long enough,
but you'll see given
enough time it will do log rotation.
And you can see the two position files that I mentioned. So it's tracking
what's going on. So if I restart stopped and restarted, they would
carry on consuming from where they left off.
Okay, I can see it's just on a log rotate there for label
pipeline file output. And there's one and there's two.
So there we go. Let me take you back
to the deck and we'll wrap up. So one of the things
that's, yep, that's fine, that's a little bit Mickey Mouse, but you'll get a
sense of the art of the possible there. And certainly in terms of making
things proactive, why filtering out log events is certainly
a possibility, but in the real world we've got to deal with things like
scaling. I mentioned the complexities of highly distributed
solutions and the fact that we want to bring logs together from
logs of different sources to be able to analyze it properly end
to end. Are we seeing messages, know API
calls coming in that hit our API gateway, but never seem to move
beyond that? Things like that. So as I say, lots of
challenges. There is a pretty modern piece of thinking around
what's known as open tracing, which is the idea that we can start
to create a means to trace events through the different
applications. We got to deal with the possibility that in
a lot of organizations, different teams with different jobs
will want to use different tools. And in that kind
of situation, you either have one tool pulling all the logs together
and sending them across to splunk or whatever the dbas
are using, or the infra guys if they're using nadias,
or you end up with your database server having three different
agents, which is a bit overkill. And of course the network
setup is that much more complicated as well. Whereas if you've got a
log unification engine like fluentd or log stash for that
matter, picking all this information up, sending it over
to these right places, or sending it to a central distribution
point, then your network is a lot more controlled
and your security guys are going to be a lot happier. I mentioned
briefly these idea that doing this sort of thing, we can these address
some of our operational monitoring challenges around legacy applications
where people don't want you anywhere near it. So you can just
start interpreting the logs and saying, well, actually this innocent logs
log message is significant, or when it reports this, it's actually
the root cause is that those more delicate systems,
you can do more preventative action rather than saying it's in
kubernetes, it will recover and sort it out for us.
So here's a scaled deployment where you can see,
I've got five servers across the top. Now we're collecting different types
of logs, different information from these servers, and they're
sending it to a concentration point or two concentration
points, which are then processing those logs
and doing what's necessary. The ops alerting,
potentially the very minimum, bringing it all together in a common platform
for doing the analytics, you can see the dash lines
where we could put failover and resilience into the setup as well.
So if concentrator node in the form of one of these
mid tier servers is enabling,
then the sources of the logs will look for
the next node that you've identified and use that.
And that can then start passing the logs through so you're not losing
stuff. The important thing is that's classic deployment. There's no virtualization
here theyre is no containerization going on.
But I could make this containerized or virtualized.
And if you looked at this from the perspective of
a containerization model, on the left I've
got the apps now just spitting out to system out or
a file that's set up appropriately in
the container environment. And then we have a
demon set, as kubernetes refers to it,
running fluentd, picking up the logs from the different
bits of kubernetes, plus these log capture,
that is going to standard out and system out and assuage
standard error that's happening in the applications in their pods and
sorting that out and getting those routed to the right places. Or you
can go to the next level and start colocating
either fluentd or fluent bit into a pod, which is
what you've got on the right. And we could adapt the
other pods to be more like that. Or we could even go
to using containerization patterns like
sidecars to deploy our fluent
bit or fluentd nodes. That gives us enormous amounts
of scaling. The other thing to keep in mind is that a
lot of people like Prometheus and Grafana for visualizing and
reporting on their activities and what's going on.
Nothing to stop you from doing that. Fluentd becomes a
contributor to the whole process. This is the architecture
for a Prometheus setup. And you can see on the left hand
side we've got fluentd feeding details into
the core server and taking, we've consolidated
data and Prometheus monitoring data out on
an export on the left hand side. And of course if Prometheus is
filtering out or doing correlation analysis,
it could generate new log alerts and you could then use fluentd
to route those to all the different systems. So in addition
to the raw data, you could be taking the Prometheus alerts
and combining that with your log analytics
platform, for example. So not only do you end
up with a history of what happened, you can put into your
core analytics log analytics when it was recognized
that there was a problem and alerted. So you can then show when something
was addressed or should have been addressed in the process.
Yeah, that could even be. Whilst Prometheus is done in,
fluentd is actually kicking off an active process to remediate.
Now this is a platform set up that has been shown logically
that we've established in the past. It's a real use
case. And across the bottom I've put the lifecycle that
I introduced earlier on into the diagram.
And on the left hand side you can see the different types of sources
that we're handling. So we have got kubernetes clusters
involved and we are running a demon set. So we're using fluent D rather
than fluent bit because it's a little bit more usable for
that kind of use case. But we've also got dedicated virtual
machines. We are running this particular use case
in a multi cloud setup. So we are doing cloud watch,
which is giving us specific information from that cloud
vendor. When we're pulling that and combining
that with other sources of information such
as logs for J. So we've taken a legacy app that's been migrated to
the cloud and rather than trying to configure it all so that that
goes into cloud watch, we've just said, okay, we'll leave it
as is untouched and we'll put a fluent bit node in play
and there's a bit of open tracing going on.
So we've got the Jaeger collectors and Jaeger analytics to help with
the tracing, showing these performance of open tracing
information. And it's complementary. It's not instead
of, and we could easily put that into fluentd as well to
do further processing on those trace
steps. And of course we want to analyze it. So we've
got the elasticsearch and Kibana for visualization and we've
started to put a few small alerts into
a slack channel and a secondary email that
could easily be pager duty dealing
with the fact that you might be running around these clock and who's on
call overnight rather than just slacking. Everybody.
And that's me done. Thank you very much. Thank you for listening.
I hope that was really helpful. If you want to know more
then please visit my website. There's plenty more
information there. The slides will be available and
I can be contacted through the site if you're interested
in allowing more. Otherwise, thank you very much.