My name is Moshe Zadka. My website is cobraism.com,
where you can find every way of getting in touch with me known to humankind.
And today I want to talk to you about Python sidecars.
I do want to start with an acknowledgement of country. I live in
Belmont in the San Francisco Bay Area peninsula, the ancestral homeland of
the two Sholoni people.
I want to start with a quick Kubernetes refresher, make sure that we're
on the same page. Kubernetes is pretty big, so this
is definitely not a comprehensive Kubernetes review.
So let's start with nodes and containers.
A pod is a basic execution unit. In Kubernetes
that's what we execute. It's usually not what we configure and that's going to be
really important both of these things later. A pod is made
of n containers. A pod can have more than one container. They're all going
to be in the same pod.
They do share a network space, which means for example
one twenty seven zero zero one is the same ip for
all of them. They might share the
process namespace. You can configure it on and off and we'll
talk a little bit, but this later they
can share volume mounts, so you can mount the same volume
into both of them and they will share that part
of the file system, but they never share the overall file
system. So this is like the
little bit of things that are going to be important later as we are talking
about how to operate your sidecars.
The other thing that's important in a pod is that
readiness. Readiness is kind of a weird thing that
is basically the criterion. Is the pod good?
Why do you need to know if the pod is good? We'll talk about this
later. This will become very important later. The usual
way to determine if the pod is good is do TCP or
HTTP check, which means you are sending in a TCP checks.
If it connects and does a TCP hand check, it's successful.
The more sophisticated checks that Kubernetes can configure is the HTTP check,
which will fail on any status that is not two xx.
You can also configure command checks.
Basically there's a whole raft of issues around them.
Usually I would not recommend them. And we'll talk about some of
the ways that writing sidecars
can alleviate the need to write command checks in Kubernetes.
The next thing that I want to make sure that we're all on the same
page in is deployed and services. There's many
other things that you would need a sidecars for that are not deployments and services.
But since these are the most common, let's focus
on them for this talk. So a deployment is
kind of a weird Kubernetes object because it's really just something
that will automatically configure a replica set and a service. So if
you understand those two, you also understand what deployment
is. A replica set is a collection of identityless pods.
And what I mean by identityless, there's no sense in this insurance
things. Pod is the fifth pod in the set.
If it's six pods, there's six pods.
But if two die, it will bring up two other nodes,
but it doesn't which one is like the true continuation
of the next pod. There is no sense that this would make a sensible
question. A service is something that can route to good
pods. There's many ways to route and
I will not go into them because for the most part they're not going to
affect our talk. But it's very important because if
you remember earlier, I said that radiance check is deciding what's
a good pod. The reason you need to know if a pod is good or
not is these service can know whether to route to it or not.
And again, all of these things are a
very important context because they will be important later.
Side cars, not an atomic thing in Kubernetes there
is no point where you will write in your Kubernetes YaMl configuration
sidecar. You can if you call
something a sidecar, but that's not a concept, that's not a type in Kubernetes,
but it is a pattern. And specifically in
Kubernetes, often when we say a pattern, what we mean is it's
a shape that a YAml file takes. And when the YaMl file takes
that shape, we'll call the resulting thing a side
cars. What does a sidecar pattern look like?
It looks like a container, a pod that has an extra container.
And usually it just needs a second container because usually you have
a main container that does the things that you
are doing with the pod, right?
If you think in terms of like a web application or a web API,
this is a thing that actually runs a web server, right? If you think
in terms of a queue consumer, this is a thing that consumes a
queue and does something with it, nodes processing and
takes it away. The idea of the sidecar is
that it takes care of the rest.
And obviously this is a pattern. So all
these definitions of sound fuzzy and
to be very honest, it's kind of not really a meaningful
debate to say whether a specific thing is a sidecar
or not. What's important is to know that this pattern
is a pattern that will be really useful when you're designing
a kubernetes installation. So you say, oh, well, what could be a
useful sidecar here, right? There's no reason
to get hung up on the definition of whether it's a true sidecar
or not. So here's like
an example of a sidecar. The main container writes a
web application, and then these application wants to cache to files.
Now, usually it's kind of awkward to also have the garbage
collector sitting in the same process, right? Because web
servers run in a specific framework that's got to manage
all of these things starting to shove like an extra thread
or spawning a process and then having to manage
what happens if process dies. That's why
we have kubernetes for, right? Like the whole point of kubernetes manages
that kind of stuff, right? If you wanted to manage that, you wouldn't be
using kubernetes in the first place. So what
you can do is you can have a sidekick container and that looks at files
that are like, say too old and removes them. So it
basically functions like the garbage collection thread
or process. But now Kubernetes is managing it. It's managing
a different container. And one
of the things that is a different container, it is
built separately, right? You build those containers into separate like CI
pipelines or whatever it is that you use to build containers.
And so you don't have to use the same base image, you don't have to
use the same platform, you don't have to use the same language.
So why I thought has useful. So first of
all, you can separate the resource limits,
meaning you can make sure that your web application can take only so much memory
and your sidecars does. A garbage collection can take so much memory
and you know how much memory you allocate to each. They can't kind of go
and steal from the other one's memory. And that's very useful
when you want to do very careful capacity
planning. At some point you will need to do.
They're also legible to Kubernetes dashboards, right? If you put
both of these things in the same container and they die and
they get restarted, you'll have to also
make sure that you keep track of that somehow to make it legible.
If you put them in separate containers,
Kubernetes knows if a container died, Kubernetes knows
to separate the container's logs and so on. So that's very
useful that you can, obviously there's like the native Kubernetes
dashboard and quite potentially like whatever cloud provider
has more stuff around kubernetes. So that's why I don't say the Kubernetes
dashboard, it's general Kubernetes dashboards, right? It might
be Prometheus grabbing data from Kubernetes.
Whatever way you have observability for kubernetes,
the sidecars will be legible to it.
But most importantly, it simplifies these container, right? Like if
we want to go with the model of a container, it's supposed to be
very simple. This is a way to offload the
complexity to Kubernetes. These you want it
and to have each of these containers, both the main container and the side container,
each be much simpler than if they would somehow have to be carefully
finagled to been the same container.
So obviously the reason I talked so much
about readiness earlier is that that's
going to be one example for why you would need a sidecar. So for
example, with a readiness sidecar, you can check that the file exists or
that the file is pretty new. You can check the contents
of an HTTP response. This is not something that's very easy to do with the
Kubernetes management, but you can easily send an HTTP
code, and now you write your own code. So you can write
it in a nicer language like Python. You can have an arbitrary
logic and you don't have to start shoving
in shell commands into Yaml and have them execute in these
kubernetes container and make sure that they properly
offer and stuff. And there's a whole thing. This is
easier, right? You can just write code in Python. Python is a nice language.
You can easily check the containers, do all kinds of
complicated logic. It's easy.
The other nice thing that you can do with side cars, collect metrics.
What if the original container wrote some code and that wasn't formatted
in the way that your metrics management, say Prometheus,
which most of them kind of are compatible with, can read well.
You can grab those metrics via whatever reformat them
into promotes. You can also do synthetic checks. You can
send a query to an API endpoint, measure how much
time that took, and that can be like a nice gauge or a histogram,
depending on exactly how you do that. You can even
scan a log file, check, say how many black lines are there.
And that can be your metric, right? Like how many lines were written in the
last minute. That's a useful metric
that you can expose. And so there's a bunch of stuff that you can do
that's like that, that you can just do in a sidecar.
You can also do scheduled tasks, right? Like I already gave these example of garbage
collection, or you can do some sort of a re indexing operation.
Again, like the sidecars shares all
the knowledge that the main container has. So it can directly go with
the API and kind of grab the data,
do whatever indexing you need on it, and then shove it back through the
API. Why write side
closing Python? So there's a lot of things that
make Python an ideal choice for sidecar.
So if you think about it out
of your examples, if you really knew that you needed that functionality
early in the development process, you would already kind of but it in
the design and made sure it fit right. The problem is retrofitting it.
That is hard, but that also means it's late in the development process.
You don't have a lot of time left in your schedule.
Luckily, Python is a great prototyping language. You can whip out something
that kind of works very fast.
So that rewards the ability of python to quickly
prototype. Now,
the main thing that the sidecars will do is to look
good in some sense on the dashboard, right? That means that
you want a very fast feedback loop.
Again, that gives you a lot of
reward for fast iteration speed, right? It's not just easy to write
the first version of Python programs, it's also really fast to iterate.
And Python has a lot of facilities that makes iteration a
lot faster and also
kind of the way politics in engineering works.
Often the sidecar will be built by slightly different people
than the people who build the main car, right? Like they might be know
kind of the deployment team or the infrastructure team or the SRE
team, people who kind of adapt to that, maybe an embedded SRE,
which means that the container will keep moving and the sidecar
needs to keep moving along with it. It's really nice if you have something
where you can adapt as changes in the container cause
whatever logic you had in the sidecar to go out of date to be
faster. So this means that if you can chase the container
code faster than the container code moves,
you're in an advantage. If you take longer for
your cycles to modify. When the container code moves,
you're perpetually going to be more and more behind.
So I think this is
kind of the fun part of the talk where I will give you an examples.
The challenge I gave to myself is to feed a sidecar on a slide.
That does mean that the code is optimized for the slides,
not best practices. This is not how I would actually
write this nodes. In practice it's mostly to show what
bits and pieces would make a sidecars work. And hopefully
they're going to be fun because you can kind of get all the details
in one slide. This also does mean the slides are going to be a bit
packed, so get ready for a fun journey.
So here's like a really quick
readiness sidecar. As you can see,
in order to raise an exception, I just divide one by
zero because that's literally the fastest code that will
these shortest code that will raise an exception in Python, just three
characters. So things means that I can grab
the data, compare it to, let's say five,
and then return the response okay, if it's not five, I raise an error.
Most web framework will automatically give
you 500. That complies with kubernetes. I have
just enough code to hook this function
into pyramid. I have routing, that's it.
Other than imports things is fully functional code that will give you
a readiness check. Assuming that you have a JSon that
has a key called value, that has to be five. So this
is fully functional readiness sidecar.
Here's a metric sidecar. It takes a little bit more code because I have
to integrate with the Prometheus
client library. So that means I have to build these collector registry
and I have to build a gauge for latency.
And then I basically send a synthetic request,
check how long it took, set the latency and
I generate the Prometheus
thing. And again, if you set everything up
in kubernetes correctly, set Prometheus up with the right
configuration. This will give you a gauge that shows
the latency of the application, which means if the application
is heavily loaded or it's like garbage collecting or something,
this will take longer and you will be able to see it on a dashboard
and you don't even have to count on the application actually measuring
itself at any point here.
Here's a simple example of a scheduler side cars.
All it takes care of just periodic making sure that the
application flashing bits queue. You might think, well, why not just put a Kubernetes
quant job? Well, a quant job is a job, which means it is a pod.
But let's say that you want this. Every single
container of the main application has its own kind of internal queue that you want
to flush once in a while to make sure that it flushes this
is fully functional code and it will actually do the job and
you actually don't have a much easier way to do that. So three
lines of python. This was very easy to fit on a slide.
So those are like some fun sidecars.
Now I'm going to fail in my challenge because the next sidecar
I have is going to be slightly longer than a slide, but we will break
it down to a few slides. So it's going to be my log analyzer
sidecar. To challenge myself, I gave myself
kind of like some fun parameters,
right? Like I said, you can actually mount a volume
and so share files natively. But let's say
for any kind of reason you don't want to do that, right. It just doesn't
fit your model. So there
can be all kind of permission issues and look, weird corner cases where it wouldn't
make sense. So the main container logs to valog something.
That valog something is inside the container's file
system, so it wouldn't be accessible naively to other
containers. And you wind these sidecar that processes has
a log in this example, I think it's going to count the lines, but obviously
in real life you'd do something slightly more interesting. But this
almost seems like an impossible challenge. So I think the fact that
I can't fit it in one slide is maybe, okay, I will fit it
in like a handful of slides.
So the first trick is that to configure the pod correctly.
So we need to share the process namespace. Process namespace.
That doesn't sound very useful. So the
first step is to find out why
do you have to know yourself? Because you can't know others unless you know yourself.
This sounds like a weird, like mystical philosophy,
but I promise you this is actually concrete technical advice,
because now we can look for another process which
has a different root than ours.
Now we managed to get to the other process roots,
right? Which means we already have access to the
peer Containers operating system. So that's
pretty cool. So now we have access to the file system that's
in the other container. Now we
can just read the log, sum the lines,
and then post it to some kind of push metrics collector,
let's say. And that's it, we're done. So it was a
bit more than a slide, but in three slides we did something that
most people would tell you is impossible. So I
think that is a pretty cool thing
about showing both the strengths of the kind of stuff you can do
with sidecars and the kind of power that you have with python.
That you can do the impossible in three slides,
not even full slides worth of code. So I think
that's kind of cool. So I want to leave
you with a few final thoughts about containers.
They're black nodes, right? You don't want to mush around
with a container. Like once the container has been tested, you want to keep it
as is throughout the deployment cycle. Then you
want to keep your container simple. The simpler the container is,
the easier it is going to be to manage.
But you will have to always add something.
Pods and equivalent things. On other frameworks
that run containers, what they do is they allow adding stuff
from the outside. At least it's a clear ish
separation of responsibilities. So that's pretty useful.
You can build the container to be more sidecar friendly. That's actually
more important than building a container, to not need a sidecar. And one
trick is to just have good APIs inside these container. You can,
for example, listen on a separate port that's not exposed
outside, so it's only going to be exposed to your peers, which means
you can do a lot less permission checking,
but still define a really well defined API. Which means
you don't care about security, but you do care about portability,
so that it's easier for the sidecar container to know
which API to expect.
So packaging stuff with containers is pretty good.
This is not a controversial statement. In 2022, everybody agrees
packaging stuff in separate containers is even better. You don't want to
shove a container that is like the everything container or you're back
to like, why even have a container?
So the more sidecars you have, the better
your packaging architecture is. And with that,
thank you so much for listening to my talk. I hope
you had fun, and I hope you're going to go and write a lot more
sidecars.