Hi, this is Gordon Rudd coming to you from Python 2021,
brought to you by conference 42.
Today I'm going to be speaking to you on a subject that's really near and
dear to my heart, creating scalable and sustainable cybersecurity
for any size organization. I'm very excited
to be these today, simply because many years ago, I started my technology
career as a programmer, you using a programming language that
most of you have probably only read about in history books called Fortran.
Today we're going to be speaking at a conference with one
of the premier languages on the planet, especially a premier
language in the cybersecurity field. I'm sure you're aware
that every computer on the planet has the ability to
create log files and literally record everything that's going on on the machine.
Sounds, areas, but it creates a
river of data, and these river of data flows into a data
lake that creates a data ocean. And cybersecurity
professionals such as myself, we're only interested in really one thing. We're trying to find
where the bad things might happen. Well, you can imagine
when we look at a river or we look at an ocean, we're really
only seeking one drop of water. And it's very difficult
to find that drop of water without a tool that's going to help you isolate
these exact drop and then figure
out exactly what that means. Python is
one of these tools that helps us to create safer
systems, systems that we can secure and to find the bad actors,
and we find it everywhere. If you're a penetration tester,
or pin tester, as we call it, Python's your tool.
You're going to be using many different tools, but when
you're going to create something, it's probably going to be in Python. For today,
we've got a really short agenda, but it's really packed
with content. We're going to try and define these relationship between scalability,
sustainability, and the flexibility that's required in any
cybersecurity programmer department. And we're going to try and show you
how that scalability and flexibility relates to your Python programming
every single day for your organization. And we want
to walk you through how an organization should
assess their cybersecurity program and assess
its operational readiness. Successfully communicating with your
governance risk committee teams, your C suite and your board also
a critical function of cybersecurity. Identifying and
focusing on the top five areas where cisos need to be successful,
is one of the last things we want to do. And I want to make
sure that as we're going through this that you all
get a sense of what it takes to be a success at that sea level.
So you may want to be in the sea level one day, or you may
just work for people that are in the sea level and you want to understand
them a little better from a security perspective.
We've been doing this for 1000 years.
We've been building castles to protect ourselves and protect our
tribes for a thousand years. And we haven't changed the way we do it today.
Cybersecurity today works very much like this. We've got inner
walls, the watchtower guard checks, limited entry.
We've got a demilitarized zone, or a DMZ, as we refer to
it. We all use this castle doctrine, which is what we refer
to this model as to create scalable cybersecurity
for every organization. That's the model that every organization uses.
But scalability is directly equatable
to economic flexibility. I had several of
my friends call when Covid hit a year or so ago and say,
oh, my God, the C suite has gone crazy. They're sending
out laptops from XYZ company that
haven't been vetted, we haven't been able to touch them. We're doing all
these crazy things. What should we do? How should we handle this?
And my counsel back to them was very simple.
The C suite and the board are doing everything they can to keep the organization
afloat. They're doing everything they can to make sure that those checks
that come to your bank account automatically every other week keep coming.
So perhaps you should help them do what they're doing right now to
keep the company alive and we can recover on the back end
and see if we can't plug any holes that we've created for ourselves.
That's the kind of attitude I think we all in technology need
to have, is how can we keep the organization going, yet accomplish our objective
in cybersecurity? We have all these layers that we work with constantly,
and at the same time, we've got to maintain that CIA
triad. The confidentiality, integrity, and availability of the data.
Those things areas never going to change. They're constants in our organization.
So when I go in to consult with an organization,
one of the first things that I ask is, what is your cybersecurity readiness?
And they'll say, well, what do you mean? And my next question is always,
would you have a sock or no sock? Well, if you don't
have a security operations center, you probably
don't have the kind of cybersecurity readiness that it's going to take in today's
world, we're having pipelines shut down. We have the ability
to shut down nuclear reactors, any power
generation station. We can shut down radio and tv stations.
Hackers can just about do any darn
thing they want to do today. Well, it's up to us not only to build
the castle, but to watch what they're doing. If we don't have a SoC structure,
if we don't have a formal place to center all
the information and all the analysis, we're really running
behind the power curve. So as we're building our
castle, as we're building our castle doctrine
security system that we all use,
the first milestone that I always ask everybody for is your security
education, training and awareness program. Do you have one?
Cybersecurity today, simply put, is a team sport.
And everybody in your organization, every single person in
your organization, is part of that team.
So from a programmer's perspective, you're part of that cybersecurity
team. Also, you should be thinking about security
education, training and awareness. And your cybersecurity team
should be helping you out with that. They should also be looking to you for
help in how to create secure code, how to do code walkthroughs,
how to do structured code walkthroughs, things that are going to help the
code that comes out of your programming department to be more secure
and to make sure that we're trapping the right errors. And that that security
that's baked into our applications as we develop them
is also part of the overall security fabric of
the organization. Because the other thing that you have
to do as a CISo, when you come in, you're going to identify your
stakeholders, and you're going to have to understand your numbers. Your stakeholders
don't just include the board of directors and everybody that's in the C suite.
They also include every line of business owner, every line of business manager,
director, whatever you want to call them. Any department head
is one of your stakeholders. You've got to understand these
needs. Now, as a programmer or business analyst that's creating
programs, you're going to have a very unique perspective
on at least one department, maybe two or three. You're going to
understand the handoffs between departments and between programs.
You're going to have to help your cybersecurity team make sure that
they know where those touch points are and that they're doing
everything these can to make sure that those touch points are secure.
You also have to understand your numbers. A small to medium sized organization today,
let's say it's a three to $5 billion bank in
the finance industry. They're going to see at least 500 million
bad actors pass their firewall every year. That's a ton
of bad actors. Now, as Covid ramped up,
that number jumped up to about 750,000 attempts
to ping, map, see into those
networks. Not a good place to be. And then you have
to understand your governance, risk compliance, and those five ps
GRC's, five p's are programs. You've got a program for vendor
management, cybersecurity, and on and on, and that sort of thing.
Every program has projects, processes, procedures, and people.
And those are really the five P's you're looking at. Program processes,
procedures, projects, and people. That is the key element to
milestone four. Who are those folks? Are they part
of the security team? How do you fit into that as a Python programmer,
as a security expert? And then you're going to look at your overall security
architecture to make sure that that security architecture is exactly where
you want it to be and is operating efficiently and in a manner that
makes sense for your organization. And there's no one size fits all.
Every organization is different. The other things we've got to do, and Python
is kind of mission critical in this area. We've got to identify every
asset that's on our network. That means when
you look at these network, if you just think of it as a wired infrastructure,
everything that's attached to that network, we must identify printers,
fax machines, laptops,
desktops, the heating and air systems. Anything that's attached to
that network, we need to know about it. It's part of a triangle
we're going to talk about later, of looking for threats and
finding those threats, identifying your vulnerabilities and then patching
these accordingly. Your business continuity and disaster recovery plans
are mission critical. And again, as you're developing those,
you can see exactly what the roles are going to be for
the different departments. So you want to make sure that as you're developing
your business continuity and disaster recovery, that you're including programming,
because I promise you, when a disaster
occurs, they're going to be places where we're going to want to
make some temporary patches and do some temporary things.
Python is an excellent way of doing that. And, of course, risk management.
Everything we do is based on risk. We're looking to identify the risk.
We want to make sure that we've got the inherent risk, the risk that comes
in with whatever the asset is or whatever the company is identified.
And we want to make sure that we know what mitigation we're going to be
able to put in place to reduce that risk.
And then we want to know for sure, for dead
certain, what our residual risk is and also
training and cross training. A lot of organizations see these as
kind of a waste of time, but I'm going to take a little different opinion
of that. Even if you're a programmer, you need to have an understanding
of upstream and downstream. So you may want to know what DNS is.
You may want to know exactly what the stack that you're working
within is. You may not be a full stack developer, but you should understand the
stack. And that means you've got to know a lot about networking and a lot
about how everything's put together within your organization
and its unique footprint so that you can create programs
that are safe and securing. We're all looking for the same
type of place to start, and we always start with these data. That's always
the right place to start. We're always going to have an app that's going to
be around the data, that's going to help us read and write the data.
That app is going to be on a host system of some kind. That host
is going to be attached to a network. That network is going to have perimeter
security of some type. It's going to have physical security of some
type, and it's going to have policies,
procedures, and a security education and training program
wrapped around it so that everybody can make sure that
these model we use, which is really these overlapping layers of
security, is in place and working correctly.
Now, as a programmer, you may not be directly involved
with a lot of these, but web application, security,
traffic optimization,
those kinds of things are going to be areas where
you can contribute. They're going to be areas where the cybersecurity
folk may actually want to put a little python program in place to
look at some things. But we've got overlapping layers for
a reason. That means we're going to have, if we take email as an example,
we may have three or four different pieces of software or hardware
devices that actually touch an incoming piece
of mail, and they'll do different things along the way,
so that if one of these layers of security
misses a bad actor or misses something, one of the other layers
will catch it. And that's really what overlapping layers are all about.
Now, today, it's kind of like the sign says we want the AI inside.
Artificial intelligence is going to give us the
insight into how the data moves and how
the humans on the network actually interact.
And once it learns our normal standard behavior. These, it's going
to be able to alert us to anything that's abnormal, and that's really what we're
after. If you look at the first layer in any security model, you're going
to have that security incident management that we saw earlier, your web app,
security content filtering, traffic optimization,
firewall, VPN, intrusion prevention detection,
load balancing, those kinds of things, all indicators of
a really sound first layer. And then the second layer complements
the first layer. We're going to look at our threat intelligence, and here's
where we really come into that triad on the left side of the screen here.
As you're going down that column, you're going to see threat intelligence. Every cybersecurity
program needs to know what threats areas in the wild. A vulnerability assessment
requires you to know all the assets on your network talked about that.
So if you know the threats that are coming in and you know the assets
on your network, you can make an intellectual decision on what your vulnerabilities
really are. If we take a step back to
something like a patchwork quilt of effects
that came into being over intel processors that we
euphemistically gave a couple of labels to,
you're going to find that even though there was a threat there,
there was a vulnerability in those old IBM
processors, and Microsoft did have a patch for it.
You'd find that as we went through the process of identifying
those threats, I hate to call them threats
because there wasn't really anything we could do about it. But as we're
looking at those old threats that came in and looking at patching
them, the patch would break the computer. And what
I'm talking about is Spectre and meltdown. When Spectre and Meltdown came about,
there was a lot of organizations that threw up the red flags and said,
oh, my, these are threats. Great.
Did we have that vulnerability? Well, yeah, everybody had them. We all had intel
processors running somewhere. Microsoft came up with a
patch for the Windows servers. And, oh,
yes, in testing, the patch worked, but it
broke the apps that were on the server. Break is probably too
strong a word. It slowed them down to the point that it appeared broken.
Not really a functional fix. We had at that time to
defend the perimeter against anything that would come in so that
we could not see or allow any spectre or meltdown
weaponization within our networks. And of course, we've got
these tried and true access control authentication,
endpoint security, email security recovery and backup.
You want to put a halt to ransomware,
make sure you know your backup and recovery cycle. And make sure
you know that you're doing it in isolated network segments.
Make sure you understand your backup, whether it's
towers of Hanoi or mix and match, or last
in, first out, whatever backup and recovery methodology you're choosing,
make sure that that methodology will
get you a recovery point. If you end up
with ransomware. It's really incredibly important that
you do that. The third layer in any model is encryption. As you
can see. The second word on every one of these bricks, these are the bricks
in the wall for your castle. Every single one of them has encryption at
the bottom. You want data encryption, you want email encryption, and you want
device encryption when it's practical. That's your third layer and your
center layer, and that's going to really create this layered security
model for you. So you're seeing everything put together
in one model, one wall of that entire castle
of the castle doctrine as we're going through this,
that will give you what you need for cybersecurity
today. The other component that I'm going to suggest
is one we cannot live without any longer,
is the AI insight. Artificial intelligence allows us
to watch, monitor and alert on
all the activity on the network. So we can watch all the data that's
going by in the river, we can watch all the data that's in a lake,
we can watch all the data that's in a data ocean. And we can actually
parse it with AI and find the points that we need to
find to determine if there's been data exfiltration,
or if there's been some access control violation,
or if one of our end users has decided
they want to zip up everything they've been working on and take it
home with them. I don't know why, but for some reason,
human beings in the last two weeks of their employment with any organization feel
it's a moral imperative to zip up all their files and take them with
them. Well, the AI inside can help you spot that and can
help you eliminate that once and for all.
And again, I want to caution you and remind you
that one size doesn't fit all. There's no way you're
going to take a corporation that's a billion dollar corporation
or a trillion dollar corporation and use the
same tools, the same cybersecurity tools and setup
as you would a mom and pop shop. Completely different size
organizations require a completely different
methodology for making sure that they're secure.
Now, to avoid any mistakes in
cybersecurity, we always have a choice to communicate
or speculate within the cybersecurity community.
We communicate threats just as quickly as we can to as many people
as we can. Within your organization, if you think something's wrong,
it's up to you to communicate it to the proper channels. And again,
every organization is going to be different. I would rather have a
lot of false positives, a lot of people within the organization communicating
things that turned out to be false positives,
as opposed to them sitting around and wondering because
everybody in the organization is part of the cybersecurity team. Remember,
cybersecurity is a team sport. Having said that, not everybody has the
same cybersecurity awareness, not everybody has the same cybersecurity training.
So within your organization, make sure that you've allowed
for that communication, and make sure that you understand a typical
CMMI model or capability maturity model index.
If you look at the small organizations, you're going to see that they're characterized
by the level one that you would see down
here on this level. That's going to be
competent people and heroic efforts keeping everything running.
Now, unfortunately, as operations grow, they don't always compensate
for that. They still will have a lot of very heroic
efforts. Competent people working long hours to make things work. But as you
go up the model, you see we've got basic project management and we're starting
to use different tactics to make sure that the organization has
processes and procedures in place. And the level these
of any model, you're going to see that process standardization comes on.
We're going to have the five P's. This is our process, these are our procedures.
This is how the projects work. These areas, the people that are on it,
and it's all standardized. You get up to a level four,
you're going to look at the common approaches to
quantitative analytics taking their place
beside everything else that's going on. So you're going to measure and count,
you're going to quantify what's going on. It's a simple thing,
but you have to be a fairly large organization to be able to afford quantitative
analytics. And five, that would be something that would happen
with the federal government or with one of the big defense industrial
contractors, something that would allow them to move their folks
around in a manner that would give the organization the
opportunity to take full advantage of continuous process improvement,
because that's something that a large manufacturer has
to constantly do, those process improvement cycles.
And you want to look at this model as it fits into the cybersecurity
department, and you want to look at how it fits into your information assurance
and your cybersecurity as well as your governance,
risk and compliance. Those are all areas you need to make sure areas
taken care of in any size organization,
bigger the organization, the more formal the process. A small
business is not going to have the same type of
cybersecurity that everybody else does. They're going to be using a different class
of routers, switches, hubs, firewalls and that sort
of thing. They'll be using the smaller products by Sonicwall and
Fortinet and some of the other vendors.
CISO has some small products for small businesses.
I say small products. They have some scaled down products for small business
that are very effective. So all those types of things are going to be coming
into play as we draw near
to keeping our confidentiality and integrity
and availability model intact. You're going to be pulling
in everything you can still creating that castle doctrine
model, but you're going to be doing it with a different tool set. You're not
going to have as much flexibility. You won't see as much data passing
through your filters and through any
particular program you're using inside to determine what's going on.
And that's really a level one organization. If you look at this particular slide,
you're going to have a lot of mom and pop shops that are going to
be having a router and wifi and a firewall,
and they'll have printers, laptops and desktops attached to these.
It's a simple model. It's every mom and pop shop
that I've ever been in. And again, they're going to be using not necessarily
the industrial strength router switches and hubs that we had used in a larger
organization, but they're still going to have them. They're still going to be using them
no matter how big or how small. We get these
four points of alignment areas going to be mission critical
for you. The economics, the talent, the existing equipment,
and the function. I can't tell you how many times I've
seen an organization want to replace a piece of software when
it had the functionality they needed. They just hadn't gone
to class, didn't understand, hadn't taken the time to
find out, or hadn't upgraded that particular piece of software
to its latest model that would give them that functionality.
The other thing, and that's part of looking at your existing equipment,
because what we have on the ground have the right functionality.
The existing equipment is identifying that asset.
Do we have assets in place that will do that right now, or do we
need new assets and then talent? We have to
have people that know how to corporate in the environment we're in,
you're always going to have folks that are turning over.
You're going to have new employees, you're going to have current employees terminating
and moving out. But you're going to have to make sure that you've got the
talent to run your equipment, no matter what size you are. And it's got
to be economically effective. Again, your C suite is going to
be doing everything they can to make sure that the organization
stays afloat and make sure that the organization does not go
broke. So you've got to take a look at the economics of it.
And part of that is saying, okay, if I've got an asset that's a dollar,
I don't want to spend a dollar to secure it. You're going
to have a risk appetite statement within your organization. You're going to have
to use that risk appetite statement and the risk assessment process
to make sure that these economics are aligning with the
risk, so that if you've got an asset that's worth a dollar,
you might spend $0.10 securing it. That's simple,
but exactly what you want to do.
And we need to have an understanding of routers and how routers
work and switches and hubs and that sort of thing,
especially within these cybersecurity team. But it
also doesn't hurt for anybody that's in programming
to understand these things. Single band, dual band,
that kind of deal. Are you doing anything that's
going to securing your wide area network or your routers?
We've got wired connectivity everywhere, especially when we moved everybody home.
Everybody's working on a wireless network at their house.
Could be trouble if you don't have the right security in place. It would behoove
as programmers to understand these difference in
wired and wireless and to understand a single wan versus
a dual wan, how that works, these types of things are
mission critical for us. And remember our four points of alignment.
You got to always go back as you're looking through here at
the economics, the talent, your equipment on the ground, and the functionality
that equipment's giving you. It's not going to change.
If you look at the Internet today. Thank you,
Kopersky, for this picture. If you look at the Internet traffic today,
and this is just one rendering of it, this is what's going on all the
time now. The opportunity for something to break or something to
have a hold that's not plugged in it in a network that's
literally worldwide is incredible. So as we've
got nation states, and really sophisticated bad actors
trying to take advantage of it. It behooves us to look at how
we're going to handle the next level up. When we come out of the mom
and pop shop and we get into a growing organization, we're going to have
multiple routers, we're going to have multiple wireless networks, we're going to
have multiple points of entry, multiple points of egress.
It's going to be a battle to make sure that as
the equipment grows, so does our capability,
so that we are absolutely able to take advantage of
every nuance and every single thing that's available
to us in the products and services that we bring to bear
to secure that organization. Now, the third level,
believe this is a CISO diagram. So thank you,
Cisco. If you look at this, you can see how
we start out with a lot of equipment on,
usually the ground floor, and then we move up. But each one
of these racks supports multiple users. As we
go across, it's imperative
that we look at standardizing our requirements
development, our technical solutions, our product integration,
the verification and validation, the process focus and definition,
the organizational training. All of those things need
to be dialed into a comprehensive approach to managing cybersecurity.
And at this point, we're going to have log files turned on.
We're going to have a sim running so that we're collecting data, not all
the data, but we're going to be looking at specific data elements coming
out of every computer. We're going to be looking at specific data
elements that we're going to be parsing out with tools like Python
to make sure that those organizations are safe.
And as we move on to the fourth level, and this is definitely a
Cisco design, you are going to have multiple buildings. You're looking
at a campus structure here. This is where you need that quantitative approach.
We need to be looking at tools that are going to help active directory.
And remember, active directory has two flavors. There's one
ad for hosted, which this is a pretty good diagram of,
and there's a different ad for these cloud,
for the azure cloud, that is. And we want to make sure that we
understand those different directory structures. We want to make sure that we understand
everything that's different between hosting it ourselves and
what's in the cloud. And we're going to have quantitative project management
at this point, projects are going to be brought together into a project
portfolio, and there's going to be project portfolio management going
on, and it's all going to be based on numbers and resources, that sort
of thing. The organization is going to be bigger and much more spread
out at this point than it has been in the past. And it's going to
be imperative for the cybersecurity professional to make sure they can secure
it. And when you get to a level five, all of a sudden you're looking
at a department that's outsourced, you're looking at a new company
you're bringing in, you're merging. You're going to segregate a department
for regulatory requirements. We need a chinese firewall over there,
so wall those people off so they can't see all the other data,
those kinds of things. And you're still going to have that campus communication fabric
from the prior slide that you're going to be working on that particular diagram
in the lower half of this. Now, we also start doing something
early on that should be part of our process of
drilling down on any fault,
flaw, error, intrusion, whatever is causal analysis.
What caused it? If we're looking at the pipeline ransomware incident
that we're just experiencing, what caused it? Where did it come from?
What happened? And we're going to be making sure that
we've got all of our intellectual property secured because that's our
competitive edge. That's exactly how that organization
that we're in differentiates itself from other organizations
within the industry or within its particular area of expertise.
We're also going to have artifacts that we need to be collecting along the
way. And this is another area where programming really helps.
We're going to have threat hunting that. We're going to have to bring
in artifacts from log aggregation. Again, we don't take all the data
elements out of a log, we aggregate them, but we're collecting specific data
elements out of different types of computers. And we're looking at things like firewall clustering
and AI. We're using behavior analytics
to determine what Mary and John and Joe are doing on our network
and what's right and wrong with it. What kind of success are
Mary and Joe having in exfiltrating data? Are they actually
taking data out of the network for nefarious reasons, or are
they just copying it onto their laptop and taking it home so they can work
a couple of hours on it? We're going to look at things like incident response
and forensics. And when we think about forensics, there is a
chain of custody that must be maintained with any
forensic analysis. And you've got to make sure that you've got the necessary
artifacts in place, the necessary projects, processes and
procedures in place, so that when these things occur that
need forensic analysis, these things being incidents or events.
You're going to want to make sure that that forensic analysis is
done according to a very specific set of processes you've
predefined, that maintain these chain of custody.
And of course that old training and cross training, I really
think we can't live without it. But that's just one man's opinion.
Your network endpoint defenses, we're always going to have
endpoint defenses, we're always going to have some firewalls
set up on the endpoints. We're always going
to have some kind of virus protection malware identification
on our endpoints, always going to be there.
We want to make sure that we're doing HTTPs inspection,
that we've got all the bot protection that we can afford,
and that we've got application controls in place. And that's
another point that Python programmers can help, or any
programmer for that matter, in that application control,
because we've got to be able to predict exactly how those applications
are going to react in certain circumstances.
And of course you're going to have that ur filtering. It's just going to be
part of that process. And by now you're going
to be saying, well, that's a lot.
Is that actually enough? Can we get by with that?
Well, probably not. Nothing's foolproof. It really isn't a
magic bullet. And if you give me enough time and money, I can pretty
much get into anything. That's true of
any bad actor. And nation states have a
lot of money, so they can buy a lot of time, these can buy a
lot of hardware, a lot of software. The old thing true is
users do make mistakes. I have myself gotten
in a time bind and been crunching things out for two or
three days at a time. Had our person that was doing
the phishing testing sent out an email
that looked exactly like you
have a phone message on our VoIP phone system. We had
little emails that come in that say this person called,
click these to hear the voicemail they left you.
Well, she sent that out. Looked exactly like it
to me. I'm in a rush, did not notice it, didn't come from
the right email address, clicked on it and instantly
got sent to additional training, which was
the correct thing to do. But users do make mistakes. We all get in
time crunches, we all have bad days, we all have sleepless
nights. Those types of things cause us to make mistakes at work.
It's up to the cybersecurity professionals within your organization to
anticipate those. And of course, vendors make most.
I guess, in my mind, in my humble opinion, the two most vivid
examples of vendor mistakes would be target and the bad actors
coming in through the HVAC vendor. And then the
other vendor mistake that I would want to use
as a cautionary tale would be the Facebook example, where Facebook hired
Cambridge Analytica to do particular data science
elements and data science work on their information.
Tons of data analytics going on, but that
not necessarily a secured place to be, and that data
was repurposed several times before anything
happened there. Then the other
thing that we have to be constantly aware of is what we don't see will
kill us. It's absolutely a mortal certainty that if
you don't see it, it's going to get your brute force attacks on all your
assets or your local accounts, detect the invasion,
the local events, the privilege escalation, lateral movement
within your network. If you've got a network set up and you can't see lateral
movement in it, which is always indicators of those level one networks,
that could be a problem. So you have to make sure that the other companies
of your cybersecurity matrix, your overlapping cybersecurity
layers, are going to catch that lateral movement in different ways.
You also need to make sure that your new local user accounts
are being created appropriately, that you're not creating one for a bad
actor. And you've got to look for things like protocol poisoning, especially within
web applications. There's just tons of ways to
bust a web up. If you're not familiar with the OWASP
model, as a python programmer, I would suggest that you
get familiar with the OWASP model and that you make sure that everything
you do is going to be geared to
one of those standards and that you're looking at that model as kind of
guidelines. Like, okay, did we think of this areas? We covered for that. What happens
if this happens? What happens if that happens? Protocol poisoning being just one
of those areas. The way we get to see what's
going on is the AI inside machine learning. We can use things like cluster
algorithms or add staff, and that's an expensive option.
I personally would rather add machines all day long than
to have to add staff. If you can automate it and not
have to add staff, you're going to have
the ability to remove the human factor out of the area,
out of that equation. And if you look at the RSA
compromise that happened several years back, they had all the staff, they had all
the processes and procedures, but they were bringing so much information in and it
was generating so many false positives that the humans that were looking
at it were ignoring the errors that were indicating that there
was a bad actor on the network. That's where the specialized applications come
in, the ones that actually start looking at what's going on laterally in networks
that understand exactly how to find that bad actor.
Take a look at that behavior, because really what we're talking about is behavioral analytics.
If we remember that a bad actor is going to be on
a network for like 280 days, give or
take, depending on who you listen to, before they actually start exfiltrating
data, that means they're going to be on the network and taking a hard look
at what's going on. That gives us an opportunity. If we've got AI
and behavior analytics operational, it gives us a significant
opportunity to make sure that every single thing
on that network is being watched and that the anomalous
behaviors are being popped up and brought to a human's attention
to decide on whether or not an action needs to be taken.
But again, we've got to minimize the number of events these humans
have to make a decision on. So that means we've got to put a little
more time into developing our AI algorithms and our behavioral
analytics algorithms. It's imperative that we maintain those at a
high level. We must make sure that we're
able to connect the dots and expose intruders.
That's another area where large data sets
are very useful. But if we don't have a tool like Python,
if we can't write some quick and dirty, don't mean it in a bad way.
Quick and dirty programs to reach in and look at
the data, to do some data analytics on it, then we're never going to know
what's going on in the river or what those molecules are all about.
Don't forget that AI is going to give us the ability
to scan our networks and all the devices on it and do these
vulnerability assessments and create remediation workflows and tracking,
but it's only going to be giving us advice on those vulnerabilities.
So we've got to make sure that we're using it correctly and
that there's not a flaw in the process
or a hitch in the get along, as some people might say.
For our cybersecurity professionals, they've got to have complete
picture of everything that's going on. And if you look at the benefits
well, we're going to keep our vulnerable systems on our radar and
watch them closely. We're going to look at the notifications we're getting from
those systems. We're going to be planning our remediation processes
and projects. We're going to be tracking remediation, and we're going
to be making vulnerability management workable.
Whole goal is to decrease our attack surface. Now having said
that, I want to remind you that
we are going to be looking at
threats, vulnerabilities, again, knowing all the
assets on that network and then looking at patch management and how we're going to
handle that to decrease those attack surfaces. And when you start identifying,
even in an organizational of let's say 800 people,
you may run some piece of software to go out and identify
all the assets on the network. And the first time I did it, it came
back with something like 8 million assets. And my
first reaction was we only have 800 people.
You don't think everybody has that many computers. But when I started
going through the file and parsing through it, I found that every
Adobe reader since dirt was
on most of the machines that we had because we
had an image that we were using when we renewed our pcs
through their normal lifecycle that had every one of
those on it, it had all the updates, it had all the patches net
frameworks do the same thing. You're going to have net remnants
from dirt that are going to walk through your network. You've got to be
able to look at those data sets, parse those out and say, okay,
those 1st 27 Adobe's we can get rid of, then you've got to have
a process and a project to get rid of them, eliminate any potential
vulnerabilities that they may have had. And again, we're always looking
at decreasing that attack surface. That's where we're trying to get to.
And then you've got to tell people what you're doing. In cybersecurity.
It's very important that we report our activities
and we report what's going on so that everybody in the organization
can have a vivid understanding of
exactly what's happening. We're going to report to the board
quarterly, at least if not monthly, to a committee of
the board, which would be the audit committee, the compliance committee, the technology committee,
and those sorts of things. Those committees, again quarterly if not monthly.
And if we're reporting into a committee of the board, that board committee is
going to turn around in the very next board meeting and report up to the
board so we can cover that in that manner. We want to make
sure that the CEO gets a monthly update or as needed.
PRN is a term from healthcare that means as needed,
the point of keeping the CEO in these loop is because he or
she's going to be the person that everybody's going to turn around and look
at and say, what do we do now? And that
CEO is going to be the face of the organization. If we should have
an incident or if we should have a breach, you want to make sure the
senior management team isn't surprised again, monthly or as needed. And your
key stakeholders, the people that are heads of lines of business or department heads,
you want to make sure they're in the loop. They've got to be critically
informed on everything that's going on within cybersecurity.
Now, what do you put in those reports? Well, the board needs to know
something very simple. Are we safe? I've sat through governance
committee meetings, and you would try to explain something to
the committee that would have the senior management team on it or the board on
it, and they would start asking questions,
really, because they didn't really know what the words
meant. They might be asking the questions incorrectly. And when you
drill down in every instance, the bottom line is the men and women
that make up your board of directors and your senior management team want
to know one thing, are we safe? These it's up to us to give meaningful
metrics, budget performance and a snapshot of
our overall program status to those people, either monthly,
quarterly and certainly annually. We certainly want to do an annual
recap for our board, committees of the board, same as the board,
they want to know, are we safe? Your C suite. Well,
you're going to do everything you're doing for the board. Plus you're going to add
in your threats and vulnerabilities and how they're affecting your
patch management. You want your C suite to understand what a threat
is, whether or not you've got that vulnerability on your network
and what you're going to do to patch it, what process you're going to go
through. And of course, you want to make sure your events, incidents and breach management
processes are in place and your key stakeholders, you want to
do everything you're doing for the C suite, all of the above and
that line of business information, it's all critical to what they're
doing every single day in every single way. Now, we talked a
little bit about risks and identifying risks.
Well, every organization should have a risk appetite statement.
Actually, in reality, maybe 30
40% of organizations have a formal risk appetite statement.
The rest of the organizations may or may not even know what
that means to say, hey, we need a risk appetite statement.
Well, that just means how much of a loss are we willing
to endure before we're going to take corrective action
or mitigating action to reduce those risks? I always
encourage folks that I work with to just ask their chief financial officer,
Mr. Or Miss CFO, what do you consider a material loss?
The bank I worked at, the first time I asked it the first week I
was there, these CFO said 25,000. The last
week I was there, I asked him what a material loss was and he said
300,000. If it's less than 300,000, I'm not going to worry about it.
Anything over 300,000, I'm going to scrutinize heavily. So we
knew that the risk appetite for the organization was at the $300,000
mark. So any threat that was going to cost
us 300,000 or more, we needed to mitigate. Use a
framework, and there are many to choose from. In the US,
you're looking at NIST and Europe. In the european theater,
you're looking at ISO. The Koso framework is always really good for
cybersecurity. Of course, the NIST 800 and ISO 27
and whatever will also have cybersecurity
framework components in them. Those are places that you can go
to find out exactly what you ought to be doing. And of course you're
going to have to do an assessment on whether or not it's working.
And I always like to just use the old stoplight method. Is it good,
green, yellow or red? What process are we in?
What is our assessment going to look like? Well, the things that
we're going to assess are going to be our people,
our processes and our technology. Do the people have the
right training? Do they have the right set of program in place or our processes
there? Do we understand that tailgating is a bad thing in a secure area?
Do we understand that not emptying our waste bins every evening
into the shred bins is a problem? Do we understand our
technology and we're keeping the CIA, the confidentiality, integrity and availability
triad intact? Do we understand our threat
matrix, our vulnerability matrix,
and our patch management matrix? And are they actually working together? Are they
tied together? And we're going to look at our talent level, how can we
improve it? Where do we need to shore it up? How can the talent that
we've got in house laterally train others to bring them up
to that level? And we're going to look at our overall project management capability.
And these are all assessments. And we're going to assess our standardization.
Do we have standard ways of standing up a server do we have
standard ways of setting up a desktop? That standardization is critical
to security of the organization? You don't really want to set up a
lot of desktops and not restrict the
admin account on those desktops and laptops, because people will
go out to the Internet and they will find things they like and they will
download them or they will click on things that will automatically download something.
You don't want to do that. You want to standardize it, lock them down,
see if you can't harden them as much as possible. You need a server hardening
policy. You need a desktop hardening policy,
and you want to start counting. You want to make sure that your quantitative
management capability is intact. You can quantify
everything you're doing, that you've got a baseline you're measuring against.
And these, you're always looking at that golden circle. And the golden circle
is just your area that you want to keep everything in.
And that's if you look at these old Venn diagrams and put three of them
together for confidentiality, integrity, and availability, where they
all meet in the middle, that's your golden circle. You want to make sure that
you've got the numbers to support that, that you're looking at these
things that are mission critical to your organization.
The other things you want to do is to make sure that you understand the
skill level of people in your department, especially within cybersecurity.
We do this all the time. We take the person, what role they're in,
what skill level they're at, what their current scalability is,
what the ideal capability for that individual and that role would be.
And then we've got some development action. Are we going to send them to training?
In former lives, I made sure that my security teams and
my teams train for one week every
quarter. So every 90 days, they were taking five days to train
on something. And while that may sound excessive, I would submit
that Moore's law has been cut in half, that we're
now down to an 18 month life cycle on new equipment
coming out that is so much better than the equipment we've got
in place that it's going to be hard not to upgrade.
And we see that with Apple upgrading to Big Sur,
all of a sudden we've got to have a hardware platform come up to meet
that level of excellence. Because the new operations system is
little more than the old hardware platforms can
adjust to in some instances. And that happens with Windows,
as they develop new windows, that happens with Apple as they develop new
oss. It happens on our smart devices, on our
phones and tablets all the time. All of a sudden you'll have an
iPhone or some other Android device
that will not be able to utilize the new software
that's coming out or the software updates that you're updating automatically.
So compensate for that. I strongly suggest that five
days out of every 90, your team is training everybody
on your team, and they'll be training in different areas, but that training is critical
and you're going to look at your projects in a project portfolio
manner as you grow. You want to make sure that you have a project
status in place so that you can look at how a new project comes
in, how those milestones are monitored, how you add
and manage resources to the project, people, money, time, and how
you track progress and these, the workloads. And you
also want to make sure you close projects out. A lot of organizations,
especially with cybersecurity projects, the project just kind of goes on and
on and on. A project that doesn't have a definite end is a process,
and that process may be broken if it doesn't have a stop and
a start in it. You want to make sure that you understand how to close
a project. If you've got a project going that you can't close
for any reason, call it a process, close the project and say,
we now have this process in place, and away you go. Only real way
to make that happen for you. The rest of your project
portfolio dials into your project portfolio
management. You've got to make sure that you're strategically aligned with
the strategy and tactics your organization is going to use.
And you want to make sure that you can execute and deliver on
everything that you're doing in a project. You're going to have tools and methods.
One of those tools for projects in a project portfolio environment,
it's always going to be a programming language. Python is a great one.
I see a lot of java, I see a lot of python. I'm starting to
see a little go. But predominantly python. For the cyber
people in the tool set, always good governance. Got to
have that securing committee on these projects and make sure that you're
dialing in your existing governance. Your existing governance
risk and compliance is going to inform you, or you're going to inform
them both on your project status and they're going to give you advice on how
to handle these projects. Absolutely a normal part of it. And if you
look at it governance, these two off on the right, the strategic
planning, you need an IT and a cyberstrategic plan.
You also need a way to request projects and tasks.
Now, I'm not saying the rest of that's irrelevant, but those two off on
the right, as far as governance is concerned, are your cornerstones.
What's these strategic plan for the organization? How does the it strategic
plan and the cybersecurity strategic plan dovetail into
that organization's plan? And how do we handle projects? How does
a project get started, how does it run and
how does it close down? Those are two critical areas that you want to
make sure you understand. And when we start talking about frameworks,
these is, in my humble opinion, what those frameworks should be used
for. NIST, CFS, of course, is cybersecurity. These CMM
is going to be software development, Koso Enterprise
risk management, Cobit going to give you some really
good controls. Itil itsm always
a good one to have. Itil one of the first ever
attempts to say, this is how the whole thing that is, it should
operate. Your ISO IEC 2700s
cybersecurity, Togaf, Sackman, lots of frameworks out
there. Find one that works for you. If you're in the US,
you're going to look at NIST, probably if you're in Europe or Asia,
you're going to look at an CISO standard. Doesn't matter which
one you use. They all look about alike when you get down to the absolute
nuts and bolts of them. But make sure you've got a standard. Now,
I always have a clock in my head, and I found out a few years
ago that not everybody does. So I've started including this in
everything that I do. The clock in your head is
important. You've got to understand that. I have my teams justify their
technology every 18 months, because again, as we discussed,
Moore's law has been halved. So that what we're seeing is
new products and services, new software updates, new patches
coming in that materially affect our operational capability.
About every 18 months, training every three months,
each member of your team has to go to training. And calendar up is a
little tool that I kind of stumbled onto 40 years ago.
It's having a Monday morning meeting at 08:00 a.m. On Monday morning.
And just asking everybody around the table, set your team in
a room or in a Zoom meeting, and just say what's on your calendar this
week, just this week. And somebody might say, well,
I'm going to be out Friday, or I'm going to install a new router,
or I'm going to do this, I'm going to do that. Somebody else around the
table, if somebody says, I'm going to install a new router on Wednesday.
Somebody else around these table might go, oh no, you're not.
I have to do this before you can do that. And I can't get that
done until these other things happen. So that Monday morning
meeting and allowing the team, not you, but the
teams itself, to decide the work and the work pattern that's
going to happen for the week is kind of critical. Now we may have
projects going, people may say, I'm working on Project A.
I got to be doing a this week. I'm all project a all
week. Well, that's great. You know what they're doing and they're pretty much
going to be busy all week. GRC, you want
to have at least a monthly governance risk compliance meeting,
your framework adjustments every twelve to 18 months,
no matter what in mws, no matter what.
Take those frameworks out, take a look at them and make any adjustments
you have to have or as needed. You may have a
framework if you're in NIST, if you're in the finance industry, that NIST framework
may get updated every year and you may have to go back and say,
okay, well, we're now doing business continuity management
and it's not working exactly according to the framework. So we need to kind
of modify what we're doing to fit these framework. Your GA
releases again, twelve to 18 months,
no more than that. And as
needed, vulnerability assessments, we do those daily. What new
equipment is coming on the wire? What are we taking off of the wire?
What vulnerabilities do we have? What's our exposure? What's our risk?
And that clock keeps on ticking. Your risk assessments need
to be done annually. Anytime you're adding a new product or service,
the cyber people need to be doing that. So as needed as
every new service, every new product comes about, we need to be doing a risk
assessment on that product or service. Our code reviews development
is a team sport as well. You don't develop in a vacuum.
The days of being able to have an isolated programmer that
creates all this magic and just throws it over the wall and we turn it
on and just say it works or doesn't. That's in the past.
We've got to do things like adhere to the Owasp model.
It's absolutely critical for our web application development.
Everything's getting a web interface patches.
You want to make sure that you're patching something every week or as needed.
Patch Tuesdays is areas thing. So as Microsoft releases patches,
you want to make sure that you're testing those patches before you implement them and
making sure that they don't kill. Production system configuration.
You want to do that pre production. You don't want to configure a system
that's in production. I know some of you have done that,
but it's not that good an idea. The other thing
I want to make sure you understand is your cybersecurity roadmap.
These are those milestones, your set of program, security,
education, training, awareness. Number one thing to have in place, because cybersecurity
is a team sport. Know who your stakeholders are. Watch your budget. Watch your number
of employees. What's your burn rate? Your burn rate is, how much money
do you spend every month to keep the wheels on cybersecurity
from a programming perspective? How much money goes into our programming
effort every month? And know your four P's, your policies, procedures,
processes, and projects. Make sure you know your security
architecture and you're able to identify your
assets. Don't forget the cross training. Whatever you do,
let's not forget the cross training. So, at this
point, you've built your castle. Everything should be fine.
You should be rock solid on what you're doing,
and we're ready to talk about those elements that make a CiSO successful.
Your EIQ, your emotional intelligence quotient,
mission critical. You may be the smartest technologist on the
planet, but if you can't deal with people and you can't control your emotions,
you're worthless in a corporate environment. So you got to make sure your
EIQ is there. Your iq, you only get
sharper if you keep learning. So you're going to be a continual
learner. Is your technical
ability kung fu or Krav maga? And if you know anything
about martial arts, you'll understand that kung fu is a very elegant sport.
Krav Maga is awfully brutal, so there's a
difference. Technologists tend to take one of those two tacks. They're either
brutal or they're elegant. A lot of times you don't have time for
elegant, and you go with brutal. I would suggest that we all
start polishing our kung fu. We want to be a little more elegant,
and you want to make sure that you understand high performance team building. And you
got to understand third party risk management. Those pesky vendors will get you every
time. So if you have any questions, this is obviously recorded.
You can give me a call, you can send me an
email. You can look me up LinkedIn. I'll be happy to interact with you at
any time, answer any questions. You might have comments,
criticisms, emotional outbursts, whatever it is, thank you
so much for spending this time with me, and please
have a great rest of your conference.