You. Hello everyone,
welcome in the presentation about how to go multicloud with your application.
Today I will show you the framework, open source framework
that enables full deployment of your app using different cloud providers,
which is important. It is not only deployed,
I will show you also how the platform self can enhance your
application. So when this already deployed, how we can
optimize it, how we can improve the current configuration
of it. The platform itself is called melodic,
yet I will today also use the word morphemic which is a natural extension
of melodic as both projects are open source.
Morphemic gives some additional features
to melodic that I will describe later.
I don't want to go too much into the details of how
to use the platform, but to show you the main key features
and how we can benefit in
our application when using melodic. Here you
can see the main dashboard so we
can just get into the
starting deployment. Yet before I want to show you
the credentials that we need to set. As I mentioned before,
the important part of multicloud is that we
can use different cloud providers. You can have
here a list of different credentials.
Here I have one of the most popular
AWS and also the OpenStack which is University
of Oslo cloud provider.
I need to specify all the details here to be able simply to
communicate with this cloud. So for AWS,
which we will use today, we need to have the credentials of our account
that we need to put here. And the same would go for the OpenStack.
And this is pretty much all
for the initial startup. We'll then go to the deployment part
when we can select and start our application.
Here I will check, I will
choose the XMI file
that I will describe in a few seconds.
Let me give me a few seconds. I need to find
it and upload it. And here's the important part. As you can see,
I am importing uploading a file which is
informaticsmi. It is a converted file that has been described
in camel model. Camel model is based on terraform.
It's a total independent language that is
fully cloud agnostic, which is really important that
we can configure our application in this language.
And at this point we are not
thinking about specific cloud provider.
In this file there are many settings that can be set,
many important parts that are later used for improvement
of the application. This is for example, or the prerequisites or
the requirements of the hardware of the machines that will be
set up, but also of the metric system that will
be used.
It can sound a little difficult yet we have a GUI
modeler called camel designer
that enables to use drag
and drop and also other easy
and much much easier and visible images
to do it. Here you can see I
need to put additional credentials.
This is totally requested by the application itself
as it will have an access to the s
free database. So this is not needed by the
melodic. It is just an additional usage for
the application itself. Another variables.
Okay, I don't want to go too much into the details
of this file, how it was created with Camel,
yet it enables to
define many different aspects of the
application, which are important and how it
can improve it later. The next step is
just choosing the credentials that I have earlier
defined can move forward and
then the last part is just pushing the big green button.
As you can see it is quite simple. The starting the deployment
is extremely easy. The main part
is the definitions, all the definitions inside
camel. Yet as I mentioned, it is much easier to
done with camel designer. Here are
the main steps of the deployment that are run
by the melodic. I will go into the details of each
of this box in seconds as I believe this is important to understand
what actually melodic is doing to find
the best solution to also to optimize the application.
But before I want to show you a small diagram about
what application we are actually using. And as
you have seen before, it is called genome. Here will be a small
diagram, maybe a small diagram of the app.
And I want to point out here that genome is not just a
testing application, it is a real case scenario that was developed
with collaboration of University of Belistock.
And the idea there is that there are multiple
large data sets of both genomic and genetic type.
And there is a need to
like. The algorithm is based on feature selection,
based on the binary variable. The algorithm
uses the extensive search of the entire space of tuples. So this
is extremely time consuming. It's extremely resource consuming.
Yet as there are multiple simulations to be performed,
multiple computations, it is quite easy to
be paralleled, to be optimized. So it makes it
a perfect example for this platform.
Here you can see a diagram that I mentioned
before of how it will be of the setup of the initial
setup. So we'll have two components,
component master and multiple workers. The master
is based on Spark master, which is
a tool used for distribution of
many computations of big, large data sets for
big data computations. So we would
have Sparkmaster that schedule jobs
for workers and melodic
is handling this setup. So it will be up to melodic to determine how
many workers are needed and it will be also communicating
with both master and workers,
let us show you. Maybe I will minimize it.
That will be visible during the explanation of
each of the steps that modic is performing.
Okay, as you
can see, we have five steps. It will still take a few
minutes until the deployment is finished. So we
have a few minutes now to discuss it. And the
first one is fetching offers. This is the first moment when the melodic
is communicating with cloud providers. So at this point it
gets the information of what hardware, what machines,
what software, like for example operational system,
what such cloud provider offers. So this is the first step.
We communicate with the cloud. Later. There is an important step
which is called generating constraint problem. Inside camel
you can put many constraints. You don't need to put hard
coded specific values. You for example,
put limits to them, like for example
minimum ram value or maximum ram value
for a component, but also
many other. You can put some other
variables, your custom ones.
And here is like this creating
context problem that later would be solved. So this is some
sort of, let's say preparation step. The main
part is done in reasoning,
where a solver is finding a solution to the
earlier created constraint problem.
So based on your requirements, your constraints,
you put on your application.
Melodic would find best solution here.
So it would find the specific values of those variables. It will find
the specific values of ram, hardware or other
variables defined by you that would meet your needs.
And I mentioned that it's find the best solution.
And I think this is important to say what does it
mean the best? And we of course want to optimize
cost and performance, but this is up
to the user, up to you, how you define
what is called utility function and the utility function simply
give us information of how good the solution is,
or pretty much what we want to optimize.
And this function can be really sophisticated. It is not just
performance to performance to price ratio,
but it can be really complicated. There is also in melodic,
there is also attached an additional tool that enables graphically
create such custom functions. It totally
depends on the applications what really you want to optimize.
Here at the step we are using a
function that is based on both price and
both price and performance. We want to have the
best solution to pay the last possible, but still
to get all the computations done
by the workers.
At this moment we don't have that much data that we wish to.
It's hard for us to say what is the
performance of the current solution, as it is not yet deployed.
So at this moment, any quite simple
one is chosen. We would start with one master component,
with one master node and one worker,
that would be the initial setup most likely,
yeah. And as we can see, the cardinality of worker equals one
and the cardinality of master equals
one as well. Okay, the next
step is deploying. This is the
part where we communicate with
cloud provider to set
up all the nodes to start all the virtual
machines. It is also important
that it is not just saying for example
AWS to start the machines as melodic is also communicating
with those machines. There is a need to for example,
install some software.
So for example, if your application, Java, Java will be installed
there. And also, which is important,
the connection established to gather those metrics inside camel,
as I mentioned before, you can define metric
system. So pretty much you put names
of the metrics that you want and how they are gathered.
And in this case you can use some
default metrics. So it would be simply just expressing
that you want, for example price metric or
ram usage metric or cpu metric,
cpu usage metric. But they can be totally custom ones
like simply sending some data about
those workers.
Okay. And here in genome we have six metrics
that I will later discuss in the different views in Grafana.
And as you can see, the deployed
is finished. So I think this is the moment that I
can navigate to the Grafana tool.
And Grafana is
a monitoring application that enables
us to see the details of the app
that we have deployed, in this case genome.
Let me log in once
more.
Okay. I will navigate to dashboard of genome.
Okay. Here are the details of our app, the genome application.
And as I mentioned before, just a reminder that we
will have multiple computations to be performed by workers.
This will be scheduled by the master
node. The number of simulations at the beginning is as
far as, remember almost 600. So we
start with 576 computations and
which is important, we also put the constraints inside camel,
we put the constraints of the constraints
of time. So we want all those computations to be performed
in 60 minutes. As you can see here is the
time left indication. So we
want all of them to be performed on time. Yet, as I mentioned
before, we also want to optimize the cost.
So we are not just setting up multiple
machines to finish pretty much
every simulation instantly, but we want to have
it done in this time limit with regard of
the cost of the entire setup.
Okay, so here you can see the number of instances.
We start with two, which is one master and
one worker, and 600 simulation that
already started to be performed by one
worker.
Okay, inside camel,
which is now that we can smoothly go to the part of
reconfiguration which is extremely important as
so far you have seen how to deploy an application
in multicloud, which is I think already quite
much yet. What now is being
done is really important because based on those metrics,
we have multiple metrics here indicating
simulations, performance or current
setup. Based on those metrics, melodic can make decision if there
is a need to. Maybe I'll close it
can make a decision if there is a need to reconfigure.
And in this case, as I mentioned before, it would be increasing
or decreasing number of workers. And this decision is made totally
automatically. So as you can remember, from the
moment that I have pushed the bitcoin button,
there is no need to interfere at all. The melodic
makes sure that performance is fine, that the
cost is fine, that everything is at this specific
moment in the best possible reconfiguration. And as
you can see, this is actually what will be done here, as this
red colorful light will indicate if
current constraints are met. So in this case, we have estimated
time and as you can see, the estimated time is
higher than the time left. So at this moment, the current solution
would not make all the computations of time.
So melodic would reconfigure. So melodic,
based on those metrics,
would increase the number of workers to make sure that
the computations are done on time.
And I think I can navigate again
to the view of demolodic.
Oh, it is already done. So the
first reconfiguration has been done and I
will just explain what happened here. Now it's
the second one as this is possible to have multiple reconfiguration.
In this view we can see what is currently happening. And as you
can see, we have reconfiguration process which is free boxes.
Then in
the end we would have a better solution
that better meets our needs and which is important.
I think what is important to say here is that those box are pretty much
the same that you have seen during initial deployment. So reasoning
is what I told you before, that it is finding
values of the variables, finding the best solution based on
the utility function. And the difference here
is that we have much more data than we used to.
So during initial deployment, we didn't know much
about those metrics, values that are also needed to find
the best solution. Here we have all those data. So based on
those metrics, based all those data that we
have, the melodic is improving, melodic is
setting up a better configuration and
deploying is again communication with the cloud provider.
So for example, setting up a new machines or deleting the old ones or
that can be all the front part of
communication with the cloud provider.
I will go back to Grafana.
So I assume we will see an
increase of the worker in a few minutes.
We will see. It takes a little time.
We can see here with the solution that has been found.
We can see the cardinality of the master is one, as it is
also the limit put inside camel. And also
worker cardinality has increased to
two. So the melodic made the decision to start up
a second machine, a second worker.
Okay. And here you can see this is the diagram indicating the
cardinality of the numbers, the cardinality of the
workers. And as you can see, also the
estimated time decreased. So I will
assume that in a few seconds
we will see that the current solution is just on spot,
but I guess also needs a few seconds to
process everything. Ah,
so the estimated time decreased and the
estimated time increased. And now it is lower
than the time left. So at this moment it will be a totally sufficient
solution. Yet have in mind that we don't
have that much time to wait until all the perfect, you can
see green light, as this is currently the best solution and
all the constraints are met. We won't
wait until all the computations are performed. We still have like
500 of them. Yet have in mind that it
is totally possible, and very possible that we'll
have many reconfiguration. For example, if the estimated
time goes, the difference between estimated times and
time left would be too much. It indicates that it's
possible to optimized cost.
So it is very possible that one of the workers
would be stopped, or maybe if some
of the computations would take longer to perform, which is totally
possible, maybe it would be an increase of
the workers. And as I mentioned before, it is
done totally automatically. So you can see I haven't interfered
with the application at all from the moment I started it.
Okay, so this is the main part of melodic. I also
want to go a little bit in the extension of melodic,
which is morphemic. And one
of the additions, there are quite many of them,
but one of the addition is called forecasting
model. And as you can see,
we can see here, as you can see, there are few diagrams
indicating the values of the metrics, yet you can imagine that
we have such, I don't know, we have time left, for example,
or we have simulations to be performed in weeks,
or, I don't know, months, and the platform would handle
it. But yet with forecasting model, we can predict the values
of those metrics. So at
this moment, when I just started, there is still not sufficient
data for forecasting model. To forecast
anything yet, I will go to one
of the deployed, which is also a genome, but with much more data
and a little bit, a little bit bigger
time constraints. So I will show you, for you
to this one that you could have a look
at how at forecasting model,
which is pretty much all those colorful lines.
And as you can see, it has been quite a
bigger example. We started with almost 800,
800 simulations at the beginning and I had to
start it at the beginning of the day as it takes around seven to 8
hours to finish all of them. Yet those few
hours is needed to gather enough data to
get predictions. And the forecasting model is gathering
based on those data is learning to perform
predictions model
what is used here for forecasting is quite many different
machine learning models. We have here some of them that
won few competitions in data series forecasting.
So for example, we have Arima, TFT,
NBITs and a few others like
CNN or profit. Yet, which is important, you can
see a few of them are not very, not very accurate.
It's still, there is the forecasting model is quite complex.
There is some ability to.
There is a model that is also taking into account many
different models. So this is not just one model taken
in account. There is also a model that is
merging them and assembling them to make sure that we always have
the best predictions. But why actually we want to predict
those metric values. And the point is that as
you can see, that based on the predictions, we can
look into the future and we can optimize, we can start a reconfiguration
before. So in this case,
maybe in this case, it's not that visible what
improvement we can get. But for example, imagine a totally different application
where for example,
we have multiple nodes that are
handling requests from the users and
based on those metrics, we can for example, predict when
there will be an increase of the users. So like an easy example
would be that for example, we have more requests after 05:00
p.m. And after a few days, the melodic
or even sooner morphemic would learn that
such an increase happens and would start
reconfiguration even before this increase is
seen. So we would not be adapting the platform for the current
situation, but we would adapt the application
just before it is needed. So based on the predictions of,
for example, increase of the users, your application would be ready.
You would have enough nodes, enough nodes to handle
all the requests,
all the requests that appear after 05:00 p.m.,
okay, so this is the example of
also forecasting model that is an
addition from morphemic. There are
many more. Also a few of them are under development.
For example, also an ability for the platform to
improve also the
architecture of the current solution. So for example,
change node to work to change
node from cpu to gpu usage to
make sure also that we have always the best configuration and
best architecture. To learn more
you can go to the website of morphemic and melodic which
is already under use and
today this will be all for my presentation.
Thank you all and I hope you enjoyed and I could see that
even with such simple be not simple, it's not simple,
but accessible tool as it is open source
and everyone can contribute to it or use it.
With such a tool, how you can improve it improve
your application. Thank you very much.