Our name
you. Hi, my name is
Joylynn Kirui. I'm senior cloud security advocate advocate
in Microsoft. And today I'll be taking you
through the art of defensive programming. So a
little bit of stats here. We are
seeing that around 68% of companies say that their ceos
demand DevOps and security teams not to do anything that's
slows down the business. So this leads to around 52% of companies
sacrificing cybersecurity for speed.
57% of Ops team pushing back on security best practices
44% of developers are actually not trained on
coding securely. And this also comes from
a result of having adopting
a lot of open source code as well, because you're seeing
80% to 90% of the code in your application comes from
open source. And if you don't take into consideration
the amount of security vulnerabilities that is in
the open source software that we are using,
then we are introducing security vulnerabilities into our
coding environment. So a
little bit of test as well there. We are saying that we have around
570 times more developers than security researchers.
In that case, it's almost impossible to have
one to one equivalent in terms of pushing
and evaluating security, all the code that's actually
being built by developers. That's why it's quite important for
us to go in and do a lot of automation
as well. So other sources of security vulnerabilities
that we are seeing are unchecked
dependencies. And then we have also employee errors.
This includes exposed access tokens and
safe code patterns. One thing that I have learned from this
journey as well is that in most cases, developers actually push
code and they know that they're actually pushing vulnerabilities
code. In most cases, they already know that there's a
vulnerabilities in their code. As we had earlier,
we have 570 times more developers than security researchers.
And damage is usually exponentially greater when it
is found in production than in
development during the development lifecycle.
So why do we have to shift security left? So the
importance of shifting security left is
because to get the developer cloud against new
threat types, the answer is always to shift security left and
to leverage cloud native security as well. So shifting
left helps enterprises find and remediate vulnerabilities
earlier and across the development lifecycle.
In this case, enterprises that extend security to development
reduce security instance by 80%.
And this is not just a reduction event.
There's also a financial component. It costs 60 times more to
fix a security defect in production than in development.
So blending security and development together within the
development workflow remains a challenge for many enterprises.
So while more enterprises are starting their transformations,
there are still 62% of enterprises that have yet to
integrate security into the development phase. So let's
dive into how security fits
into the development lifecycle. So each stage of the development
lifecycle has unique security components that when
used together help prevent threats at all critical
junction. So for the commit stage,
it's important to start with a focus on threat modeling
and understanding the threat landscape to grasp the overall risk
of what you are looking to bring to execution in
code. So in the thought of having defensive
programming, the first component is usually that's
very important, especially during the commit
is doing threat modeling. It's trying to evaluate and
see, okay, what threat vectors can be used by a hacker to compromise your system
during the design stage. So at least you can scope out and say okay,
so these are the areas, these are the endpoints that would be public facing
and these are the threats that would be faced in this API
that's actually publicly exposed.
And then you can be able to now think of ways of defending
against those threat vectors from being
exploited. So you need to employ a range of IDE security
plugins as well and pre commit hooks to
make sure that the code you're generating adheres to security standards.
So during the pre commit stage, you also have to make sure that you have
secure coding standards in place for your organization that
your developers are adhering to.
So I'll give a brief about some of the
secure coding standards that should be adhered to
in a defensive programming environment.
On basis this ten would be equated
for an environment for any developer where we are
always talking about input validation.
Make sure that you never trust what a user is inputting. That's why we're
looking at checking the data length,
validating the character sets, using restrictions as
well. Another security coding standard that we
have to make sure that we are checking is managing authentication
and passwords. We are making sure that least you're
using TLS client authentication,
you're using the correct authentication and authorizations as
well, and you're not transmitting passwords in the
clear, you're making sure that you're transmitting passwords securely.
So this is a key concept that should be followed by all developers
in terms of managing authentication and passwords. And for passwords,
make sure that you're using a secure vault like Azure
key vault to store your credentials
as well. So a third security best practice that you
can follow is to make sure that you're always sanitizing your
data fast, and then you send that input to other systems
as well. So you can use a whitelist to
allow a particular data is
actually allowed, or a blacklist, or you can use escape inputs
to keep things safe as well. Another concept that you should
follow for secure coding is adopting the principle of
least privilege. If someone should not
have access to something, they should not only have access to what they are required
to have. So this is where we need to validate permissions
as much as possible. Another concept for secure coding that
we have to follow in the art of defensive programming is
to make sure that you have an architecture in place where
you have to make sure that you're using secure
architecture. We have several like the OWaSp
secure architecture practice that are available for you to view.
So you need to make sure that for every organization you have secure
architecture and design that all developers follow.
The 6th that I would say is to deny access
by default for all systems.
These are talking about zero trust in
almost all levels of your infrastructure as well.
And we also have to make sure that we are keeping that
you have very many layers of defense. So this is where we're
talking about adding several layers of
protecting your application, protecting your data, protecting your APIs,
protecting your containers, making it very hard for hackers
to actually compromise your system in terms of also
natural segregation, in terms of the kind of environment
that you are building, that the developers are building
is also secure. Another concept
for secure coding that we have to follow is make sure that
you secure the kind of environment and working
communication that you have. So you have to make sure that you're
using strong encryption.
You protect your databases as well. We make sure that you sign your code before
releasing it. And another one that we have to
follow is to check the quality of your code and follow coding standards.
We have to make sure that you have a good peer review
of your code before pushing
that code, before you commit the code as well.
So this is quite an important concept in
terms of defensive programming, whereby you take into account threat
modeling, IDE security plugin,
precommit hooks, security coding standards,
peer review as well. So for today,
we are actually going to go through a way of you
as a developer integrating Codeql as an
IDE security plugin and identifying security vulnerabilities on
the go. Another key concept that we
follow is running
static and dynamic analysis. So another aspect of securing
the developer workflow is through assessing our
own created code. So one of the ways to check our
code is with static and dynamic analysis. So it is best to
use a combination of these techniques to make sure that the findings are
prioritized in the right way. So static analysis
examines the code base and finds potential vulnerabilities
that may be present in the code being created. And dynamic
analysis reviews running code and runs simulated attacks
on the code base itself. So that's why we talk about SAS
as well as DAS. And I'm sure we have several
other sessions that are covering on SAS and DAs.
But for today our main area of focus
will be on code scanning using CodeqL.
CodeqL allows your team to treat code as data and it
enables them to create their own queries in addition to the standard community
powered queries. For today we
are going to see how we can be able to use the community powered
security queries on your code to find security
vulnerabilities when you are using your IDE.
We'll dive right into the demo.
So I will practically show you how to use CodeQL
on your ide to identify security vulnerabilities
using the community built queries for security,
which I will just show you here.
So you can see we have all
these security cwas and
they're named coding to the particular ids.
So you can go in and query any of these available queries
against your code base to
see if it's actually vulnerable. So CodeqL
is an open source static application security
tool. It allows users to also write
queries to find bugs not only for security vulnerabilities,
but also any kind of bug from their source code.
So how do you get started with
CodeQL? So when you are in your ide you
can go to your extensions, go to your marketplace
extensions and search for CodeQL and
make sure that you install the plugin.
In my case it's already installed,
but it's as simple as that. Going into the
extensions marketplace and making sure that you
have the extension installed.
And then the thing with
CodeQL, it analyzes your code in terms of
a database. So you need to
generate a database for your code. So the
way I usually do it is through
since I'm using Windows operating system here you
can go to GitHub and then there
is a folder that is zipped
for CodeQl which you can extract
for your windows, for your Linux,
for your macOS as well. And once you
extract them, you can be able to add them to
path and make sure that you are able to run CodeQL
CLI from your machine.
So once you're able to run CodeQL CLI,
you just clone the code
that you want to review or to research
on. It might be from GitHub as well.
And then what you do, you build a
database for that particular project.
So you run a code like CodeQL database
create, and then you give it a database name and you specify
the language of that particular project that you're
using. So in this example, if we are using Java,
so it will be CodeQL database create.
Then you give it like Webgood language Java.
So it will take a bit of time just for it to build a database.
And then once
it creates a compressed file like
it's database, what you do, you come back to your visual
studio. There will be this extension
for CodeQL. You come there and
then you add a database.
You add the database here. So I had already added
this particular database. We've already
mentioned before that CodeQL will analyze your code
in terms of database. So if you're running like
marketing application that's based
on Java, so what CodeQL will do,
it will wrap that up and present
it in terms of a database. So you add it here under databases.
And then what you do, because you want to use
the community built queries, you go to GitHub
repo and then you use that
code already. You clone that
into your visual studio and then you can be able to run
all those queries that are already built from
the community against your code. Remember,
in this case, your code is in
quotes database. So in this particular instance,
what I wanted to run against my code
was to check for cross site scripting
vulnerabilities.
What happens is I
had this open already. So you will find that
you have this particular file, this particular
query for SQL injection
that's already available, but also have all these other
queries that check for particular common weakness
enumerations. So for today
we will cover CWE
79. So we want to see if our code is actually vulnerable
to cross site scripting. So it's as easy as
going into that folder
and checking for the query language for XSS.
So what you do, you go to XSS query language
and then you right click and run
the queries in the selected files. So it will
take some bit of time just to scroll through all
your lines of code to check for this particular
cross site scripting vulnerabilities.
And then what it does, once it's finished,
this is what it will give. It will give you all
the lines that are actually vulnerable.
So let's run that once again. So right click
and say codeql run
queries. So you'll give it a few minutes just for
it to scroll through and see which
particular lines of code is actually vulnerable. So remember,
you don't have to only use this security queries,
you can build your own as well. So you might be coding
and then you notice that I actually did something wrong
and then you want to see okay, what other
code have I pushed that actually has this running
or has this particular vulnerability? So as you
can see here, there will be a pop up on the bottom
right, just checking for running the queries.
So after a few minutes the XSS
query will have run through your whole code
and given you the lines of code that are actually vulnerable.
So as you can see here, it tells you that
cross site scripting vulnerability due to a user provided value.
So when you go to that particular line, it will tell you
that you need to change this. So as you
can see, it's very important to make sure that you're using
IDE security plugins whenever you're coding
to make sure you identify the security vulnerabilities as early
on as possible, even before you commit your code.
And as well as having secure coding
standards set in place. I've seen events
whereby you only have a checklist only for the developers
to follow four
lists to do or to adhere to whenever they're coding.
But it's also important to have regular security training for
the developers, as well as having security champions
among the developers who will advocate for the
others to take security seriously,
and as well as being quite intentional about training them.
Every so often in the past, what I've done
is at least once a month you have all hands
for developers to make sure that they are
up to date with security best practices.
And every so often for security champions, at least
you have them on a more regular basis as well.
So maybe some call to action as well.
You can go to aka Ms devsecopsolutions
and get to know some of
the solutions that are available on Azure as well as GitHub
for your complete end to end Devsecops journey.
We have very many tools there available, including Microsoft
Defender for DevOps, also some tools
available for container security as well in terms of
infrastructure as code, and a
lot is available there as well. So if you want to learn around
Codeql you can go to codeql GitHub.com.
There are very many docs that are available. You can
see ways of integrating or installing
the codeQL extension by yourself, and how
you can go about and querying the
community security queries against your code to make sure
that to find out if you're actually vulnerable.
So on top of using CodeQL on your IDE,
you can also use it as part of GitHub advanced security in
GitHub. So this is available as well for
both public and private repos.
So if you have your public repo, you can go to the security tab and
make sure that you have security scanning enabled
and as well as dependable enabled dependency scanning enabled.
So GitHub advanced security will cover your code scanning
and as well as your credential scanning and as well as your dependency
scanning, and it will still
use CodeQL to scan for your code
security vulnerabilities. That's it
for the day. You can catch me on Twitter at
Jolene Underscore kirui. In case you have any questions,
you can link with me on LinkedIn as well using Joylynn
Kirui, and I'm very happy to answer all your
questions. Thank you very much.