Hi everyone, everyone, my name is Dmitry Bardysh and I'm happy to see you all.
The conference today I'm going to share my thoughts on the emergency
of e commerce and the future of traditional shopping.
So let's get to the point. I think everybody knows that
while e commerce is growing quickly, the physical stores themselves
continue playing a major role. The question remains whether
in store shopping can survive and compete with the convenience and
personalization of ecommerce over the long term, or if
online shopping will eventually dominate the retail landscape.
But first of all, let me give you a quick introduction about me.
So here you can see my career highlights and I've got more than
six or six years of work experience at ride changing,
food, tech and delivery and here are some links if you want to connect
with me. I'm happy to have chat with you guys on the various of topics.
So let's talk about the problem itself, how it all started and how
it is going now, right? Ecommerce has undeniably
surged in recent years, with sales skyrocketing
to over $6 trillion globally in 2022 and
still poised to climb even further.
Its share of retail market has also seen remarkable
growth, reaching 18% in 2022 and
projected to hit almost 22% by 2024.
With estimated almost 3 billion online
shoppers in 2024, the digital
shopping landscape is expanding rapidly,
fueled in part by the COVID-19 pandemic which accelerated
online adoption during lockdowns. On the
other hand, instore shopping remains robust, bouncing back
in 20, 29 21 sorry. With an
almost 8% growth to almost 21 trillion of dollars,
surpassing pre pandemic levels,
a recent survey shows that almost 43% of
the consumers still prefer the tangible experience of
in store shopping. So with
that all being said, we may come up with the hypothesis like that the
future of commerce is a dynamic interplay between the digital
and traditional retail realms. But let's
try to answer the simple question why people can't resist online shopping.
In order to find the answer to this question, we have to go deep into
the main reasons of ecommerce. Boom. And it all
started from the obvious, the rise of the mobile devices when
it comes to number of factors, right?
And let's get a bit more in depth about
them. The first one is a global reach. Ecommerce provides
businesses with the ability to reach a global audience,
breaking down the geographical barriers. They have 24
per seven days. Accessibility.
Online stores are open almost every
hour, every minute, and it basically allows customers to
shop there at their convenience, regardless of the time zones or
business hours. Also, about the convenience, right? Consumers can
shop from the comfort of their homes, avoiding the need to travel to
physical stores. Also, it's all about the
wide product selection. Ecommerce platforms themselves offer
a different number of products, often more
extensive than it is available in brick and mortar stores.
Don't forget about the cost savings. Both businesses and consumers
can save on costs related to physical storefronts such as rent,
utilities, travel expenses and salaries.
Don't forget about time efficiency as well. Online shopping
eliminates the need to wait in line, searching for the crowds
or deal with the limited store hours. Also, don't forget
about the personalization. Ecommerce websites can offer
personalized recommendations based on the user
preferences and purchase history. Also,
it's all about the ease of comparison.
Consumers can easily compare prices, features and reviews
of products across different brands and vendors. We already
talked about the personalization, right? But don't forget about the user
reviews themselves. Customers can make informed
decisions based on the experiences of others and
reviews shared by other buyers before even trying to buy the
real product. Also,
ecommerce boom gives accessibility for small businesses.
What does it mean? Basically, it's all about the fact that ecommerce levels
the playing field, allowing small businesses to compete
with larger enterprises on the global scale.
Also, it's all about reduced marketing
costs. Digital marketing is often more cost effective than
traditional advertising methods make it more accessible
to businesses of all sizes. In addition,
it's about data collection. Ecommerce platforms can
collect valuable data on customer behavior,
helping businesses refine their strategies and offerings.
Also, due to the ecommerce boom, we can see
the faster transactions between people and between the company and people.
Online payments and digital transactions streamline the purchasing process,
reducing checkout times. Also, in terms of the
inventory management, basically, ecommerce systems
enable efficient tracking and management of inventory
levels, reducing the likelihood of overstock on stockholms.
Also, we already spoke about targeted marketing, but let's say about
that as well. Businesses can tailor marketing efforts
based on customer data, ensuring that promotions are super relevant
and appealing. Also, don't forget about the
flexible shopping experience. Consumers can shop
using various devices such as smartphones, tablets,
computers, even TV, changing flexibility.
Also, it is important to say about the environmental impact
digital transactions and online shopping contribute to reducing the environmental impact
associated with traditional retail practices.
Also, there is one thing which is quite important for the companies,
it's the dynamic pricing. Ecommerce allows for them
dynamic pricing strategies. Adjusting prices based on demand,
seasonality or other factors. Also altogether
gives them ability to focus on the customer service and chatbots
automated systems which can handle routine customer
inquiries, basically improving efficiency and responsiveness.
And finally, don't forget about the scalability.
Ecommerce businesses can easily scale their operations
abroad, accommodating increased demand without the need
of significant infrastructure changes.
When we talk about the ecommerce,
we have to talk about some main trends which take place
at the moment. And let's start
from the first one. I think the most notable
trend in ecommerce is the surge in mobile commerce.
For example, in 2019, mobile ecommerce constituted
only 67% of total ecommerce
sales, but by 2021 figure
projected to rise by almost
73%, according to Statista.
This shift is fueled by the widespread of use of smartphones
and tablets, providing the convenient shopping experiences for
businesses to remain competitive. Having a mobile friendly website
or app is quite crucial at the moment. Another trend in
ecommerce is the increasing importance of social commerce.
Platforms like Instagram and Facebook and TikTok
and others are now becoming significant sales channels for
businesses. According to Shopify,
almost 80% of american consumers say that
they have discovered products on the Facebook and 55 of
them have purchased products online after discovering them on social
media. That's why I can say that user experience is
quite crucial to the success of the ecommerce
websites. And the last
one. According to a study by Kiss Metrics,
47% of consumers expect a page to load
in 2 seconds or less, and 40% will abandon
a website that takes more than 3 seconds to load.
Additionally to that, 88% of online consumers
are less likely to return to a site after a bad experience.
This basically means that businesses need to invest in fast,
responsive websites, intuitive navigation and user friendly
interfaces.
But the question is still in the air. Why do
people still love shopping in real life?
In my point of view, there are four main reasons for it. The first
one is tangible experience. Despite the
conveniences of ecommerce, many still favor
in store shopping for its tangible and experiential
nature. The second one is the avoiding risks,
which may happen in online instore shopping has
some online risks like shipping fees, delays and
potential issues with damaged items.
A retail dive survey reveals that 62% prefer
physical examination of the products, with 49% aiming
to dodge shipping costs.
Also, don't forget about the face to face experience and according to PwC
survey, 74% of global consumers desire more
human interaction while shopping. And the last one is
overall appeal. And I would say that music, mood,
sense and visuals contribute to overall appeal,
as indicated by a survey where 90% of people are more
likely to purchase than they enjoy the stores environment.
But let's think about some examples of really big
companies, how they adapted to new reality.
In my opinion, they use a kind of mixed approach and it
can be stated that we witness some kind of
omnichannel revolution. That basically means
that successful retailers, or e retailers
as they say, will use online and in store experiences
to define the unique and successful brand differentiation.
Basically, there are three good examples which I would like to point
out. And here are the success stories of Walmart,
Starbucks and Sephora. All of them integrated physical and online
channels for a seamless shopping experience. And all of them benefited
from it by getting an enhanced convenience
selection and better personalization for customers.
But let's talk about some numbers here. For example,
Starbucks recently reached 31 million monthly app users
and 41% of US sales from rewards
program. In terms of Walmart, Walmart has
more than 268,000,000 customers and
more than 63% of growth in ecommerce
sales year over year by the 2021.
In terms of C four, they got 31 million
loyalty members, exceptional customer retention and
according to recent research.
But let's talk about some future trends
in retail. I personally would like to point out three
of them. The first one is a personalized mobile
shopping. And I think that consumers seek tailored
recommendations and experiences by using their mobile
devices, laptops or whatever. And the good example
here will be Shopify's success,
who's got 1.75
billion merchants and 86% revenue increase
in 2020. The second one is sustainability
practices. It's all about the growing demand for eco friendly practices
in retail. And I can say that there is a leader in Patagonia
which company donates 1% of sales to environmental
causes. And the third one is the emergent technologies.
And I would like to stay here a bit for more.
I personally believe that all the things related
to new technologies, such as virtual reality,
using chat, GPT, using all
other things which are kind of popular right now,
enhance immersive shopping experiences. And the good example
here can be Ikea's AR app,
which basically boosts online sales through visualizing
products in customer homes.
But if you think about the future and about the upcoming years,
the question will be quite simple. Can retailers
crack the code to seamlessly blend the tactile allure of physical stores
with the boundless possibilities of digital shopping,
ultimately sculpting a retail landscape that caters perfectly
to diverse consumer needs and preferences?
And in my opinion, the short answer is yes.
The first point here is diverse consumer
preferences. And I would say that physical stores appeal to
tangible interactions and immersive experiences, and online
shopping caters to innovation, convenience and personalized recommendations.
Also, the second thing here is omnichannel integrations.
It's all about the blending physical and digital models which enhance
convenience, loyalty and data insights.
Also, it's all about the ongoing innovations. And as
I said earlier, it comes to the personalization, mobile tech and
sustainability which contributes to reshaping the retail landscape
itself. The third thing here is adaptable brand for the future.
And I think that traditional retail's future
relies on adaptable, creative brands. And it's all about
the thoughtful transformation of physical spaces which can maintain
relevance. And the fourth thing here is a consumer driven
equilibrium. I think that future success
depends on defining the ideal balance between in person and digital
experiences. And retailers must listen to consumer preferences and strategically
chart and omnichannel courses for added value for
the final customer.
Now we come up to some kind of conclusion and
I would like to say that going forward,
traditional retail's future depends on adaptable and
creative brands that keep pace with the consumer's changing
needs. Purely physical stores may fade
over time, I hope. No, but thoughtfully transformed
spaces can retain relevance. Ultimately,
consumers will determine the ideal equilibrium between
in person and digital, weighing each channel's
upsides and downsides.
Retail will remain vibrant if retailers
listen carefully and chart an omnichannel course
that adds some value to the final customer.
So guys, here is thanks for
your time, thanks for listening. I'm happy to answer
your questions, I'm happy to share my thoughts
and I'm happy to have any kind of discussions on related
topic. Thanks for your time.