You. Hello everyone,
my name is Susiesu. Welcome to my today's talk on the
transformation of diverse and information security
in AIoT. Before we just
start our today's session, I would like to express my gratitude
to the 42 for inviting me
to be here and meet all of you. Let's just begin.
Here is quick introduction about myself I'm currently
working as a DevOps manager and a software operations architect
at signify formerly Philips lighting three years
ago I have actively dubbed into
AI and machine learning et cetera,
which is the reason why I'm here. Look at the
lecture side. In our tech industry we
strive to contribute to open source a lot.
So if you would like you can scan this QR
code provided and you can gain my articles,
tech events and speeches and also
my upcoming books. The first we will
talk about what does Iot mean AIoT?
So actually it's just a new term. It means artificial intelligence
in IoT. For example like automated vehicles like
Tesla, gilmore, et cetera. And for example like
smart cities. Our company's lighting is a
leader industry and also the radio surveillance,
monitoring traffic and smart buildings for
the manufacturing. Like we take advantage like deep learning and
deep neural networks for production line to
do this kind of quality checks.
As I said, my strength is
in Iot lighting industry. So I take the
relevant for example so let's
imagine I visited the Black Forest recently
and I captured a photo at the right side illustrative.
Now I'd like to recreate the same ambience
in my bedroom. Can AI achieve it?
The answer is yes. So first I got
this photo, black Forest photo and we
need to have some conversion from image
to the test all to some parameters that
hardware can recognize. So far, definitely we can achieve
it. For example, a couple of weeks ago OpenAI launched
one of the six features.
One of this is dell e three and it
can support this function very well. And then
we will just upload this letter
e three to convert
to process this photo image to the
text related to these lighting parameters
that hardware can recognize. Then send the command to hardware
like hardware processing. Finally we applied it
become this. It's quite astonishing,
right? Go ahead. So second
part we will discuss how AI and
AIot affect our DevOps roles.
I believe most of you, you are maybe either
DevOps engineers. Let's go ahead. So what's
the current AI capabilities? I have to tell you
so far I provided the data here is quite
a little bit old because I got it a couple
of months ago and two weeks ago operations
on the OpenAI's dive days, they launched the six
features and the new data, new knowledge and
a new function and a new modalities.
IoT dramatically challenges the current AI capabilities.
We definitely need to jump into what I say, the AGI
era. What does that mean? Is artificial general intelligence
era. As open
AI CEO simside,
he just defined AGI as a kind of median
human can lets your work
effectively as a coworker. So return
to this topic. Yeah, definitely. In the future or in
the very coming future, the AI capability will
increase twice or three times than current data.
I shared. So what's the current data? So AI is
equal to a Google level three software
engineer. If you're not familiar with Google's salary hierarchy,
here it is. So for the level three
Google's software engineer, they can earn like
around two hundred k dollars per
year. And it can be replaced right now.
And AI is also equal to a
qualified Stanford students. You think maybe just a yin
major? No, it's a yin. 16 units seem like
16 majors. It's really super intelligent
Stanford students, right?
Actually over the decade we have a lot of
discussion about AI. AI actually is
not a new term, but did you realize this
year AI become very popular and
what I say is kind of prominent any
time in the past years? As I said,
the answer is we are definitely into the
AGI era. So what does it mean actually?
OpenAI's GBT four turbo, the recent
model, the recent API actually can
just bridge the gap between human common sense
and AI capabilities. So over ten
years ago, we had a prediction about AI.
Yes, it's all about like telemarketers,
they can be replaced easily. And also bookkeeping
clubs and the competition and the benefits managers,
et cetera, or receptionist. But actually
this year, after we jump into the AGI era,
things changed. Here is some statistics,
data from very official website.
Here are the ten roles that AI is most likely
to replace. Unfortunately, I have to tell you, in tech jobs,
for example, like coders, software engineers, data analysts,
their job can be replaced by AI easily.
And also media jobs. Do you remember this protest?
Like Hariwun, they have contender
creations. Protest for protecting their
ip, right? And also the legal industry
jobs. For example like paralegals, legal assistants,
our market research analysis, also teachers,
and also finance jobs like financial analysis
and financial advisors. And also like stock
traders, graphic designers,
accountants, customer service agents. But for
our DevOps, we will focus on software engineers.
Now you may feel oh very worried about our
role, our job. But what AI cannot do
here it is. So AI cannot do a lot of things.
But I will focus on these four parts. So first,
AI is incapable of handling intricate
problems. We are in the reality.
So the real world case is not like one
plus one equals two. It's very complex. For example,
especially like big firms,
developers consistently encounter real world open ended
questions and challenges. Big firms, they are a
Iot of departments. For each department they have
a different perspective. And when they
work together to achieve the same goal. And also
there is an old business and focus on like a migration.
We always encounter this kind of situation like a operations,
because we know if it's completely new, we can do
it easily. But for migration, we need to
keep the zero down time for the
running business, for these kind of intricate problems.
So far AI cannot do it because it means
the kind of multi departments,
cooperations and also very little
things, not just only related to technology, it's also
related to the models, the business models
for our customers business.
What should I say is a kind of interpersonal skills, something like
that. The second part is AI lacks the depth
of thought. For example, like I mentioned,
AI current capability can replace the
level three Google engineers. But how about the level four level,
the top one? I think everyone just
know actually as DevOps.
So we are not just only focused on the development, we focus
on the operations as well. I forgot who said it.
DevOps is similar like a philosopher. It's not just
one piece of technology. They must know the
whole picture over the
entire lifecycle of a business, from the
human communications and also the
technologies like development operations,
Linux and networking, et cetera, et cetera
and so on, a lot of things. And when it comes together,
it's really difficult to be replaced by
AI because AI cannot do this depths of
thought. For example, like the top Google engineer,
they are kind of the master in our tech industry.
They are the person, what I say is kind of
a game maker. And they are the person to make
this role. Yeah right. And also the third
one, AI is deficient in critical thinking capabilities.
As I mentioned, there is six features
has been launched on the dev day of OpenAI.
One of it is modalities and IoT means
in the future, and OpenAI also maybe
other AI companies, they will launch
more and more sophisticated models.
So it means it will affect our daily life,
it affect enormous range
of fields. But about
this thinking model, we will be the person to choose is
what I like. It's not what I like. If I need to
focus on we questions. It's not my thinking model, it's not my
belongs to my personality. I'm the person I question
this, it cannot nurture
myself thinking model. Because we as
a human, we have our personal thinking model.
So what should I say is
one of the most important capabilities we needed
to focus on? I mean, critical thinking, it means
we cannot replace by AI.
And I could say critical thinking is kind of
for one difference between human and AI.
And also the fourth one, AI strategies to
engage in real world collaborations and communication,
cross various departments and teams, right? For example,
like a software skills, communication should be fine.
But how about interpersonal skills?
They didn't know how we feel. Even we use these
words, right? But related to the kind
of humans words or even their innation,
it's really complicated. It's not like if it's
just a machine, just because of your test, can understand
what you really mean. So it's kind of interpersonal skills.
AI cannot do. It also like leadership
and being the influencer to affect
others and problem solving. Yeah, this AI
may be helpful, you know, for the
entire intricate problems, they cannot
do it. And also like teamwork.
And for example, like maintaining the work ethic this
AI cannot do. We mentioned the
AIoT and also how affect our dev
throws. But then the third one is AI security.
Actually, you know, definitely in
principle, not for
in IoT industry. For example, like a software attack
by AI, it will just let your
website go down, right? Or maybe you
got some financial losses. But if AI hacked
IoT industry is so horrible, it means
it will kill someone. It will affect
individuals directly. Let's focus on the
IoT industry first. As I
said, AI is not new term so far. It becomes
very prevalent just because the GPT
four has been released in
March 2023. But actually this term has
been coined in 1956. So it's
almost 70 years ago. What I mean is
AI security, it will grow up gradually,
not just so far. I give you the AI security scopes, but it
definitely is coming very soon. It will be
expanded, but we can learn from
the traditional classification related to security, right?
For example, the right side is the diagram
I drawed. And here you will see
information security include cybersecurity
and cybersecurity and
it security. They have overlap. It belongs
to network security. Let's go ahead.
Cybersecurity and is IoT just here.
So network security, cloud security,
endpoint security, application security, then Iot
security. So we will extend
this part a lot because as I mentioned,
Iot security we must focus on very
much. It will affect our lives.
IoT will affect the safety of the
city, the entire country or the entire world.
So Iot security related to for example like 5g networks
related to IoT, like Internet of vehicles
Iot industrial, industrial Iot.
So IoT looks like the right side is ICI is a separate
incident timeline. It's a real case,
some real case happened over the past thousand
years, 100 years. Sorry.
So first for example since the 1903
let's take one for example. So 212
there is campaign it's about the guys pipeline
cyber attack. So for example like synclates pipeline.
And also think about a nuclear industry.
If IoT has been attacked by AI, IoT means
not just one person or a few operations,
they will die but it will dramatically
erupt and destroy this entire city
or the entire country. So horrible, right?
So is the reason why we must focus on the
AI security, especially the Iot industry.
So here is AI security based on my
personal ten years cyber security expert
I defined this with my three years
working experience in AI. So let's
just have a look go through the whole one,
two, three. The AI security because
it's dramatically, not dramatically, it's kind of very
different from the traditional security scopes.
So first let's go to the data security. So protects
AI data confidentially and integrity and availability
and uses encryption and access controls
to secure data storage and also anonymize
the data to prevent lets. For example here
is quite a new feature because take
one for example like JBT. We have interaction with
JBT, we send a question but this kind of question doesn't
view related to our real life or
is something related to our privacy.
And when we nominate it even you have intact it's
nothing. Yeah, Iot won't be a big deal for us.
And the second privacy preservation.
So what it can do to
protect this privacy preservation. So for example like
differentiate privacy in
compresses like methods we introduce manage
the disturbance or other noises
into this data to safeguard individual privacy without
compromising the general usableness of data.
So even it has been all hacked or et cetera,
we do not know. We got some noises we
cannot get the general useful of the data.
And Saturday the learning allows for the
spreading the training procedure over various devices
to prevent the disclosure of raw data,
right? And the
third one is traditional one information security like
application cloud infrastructure,
incident response,
cryptography and disaster
recovery, vulnerability management.
All types of information security we need to focus on in AI,
right? And explainability and transparency
is also very important one for AI security because
it can identify vulnerabilities and understanding
how decisions are made and the transparent
models are easy to audit to debug. For us,
we are the human but IoT is just a machine. We give
the data no matter what kind of
things. We need some,
it can be explainability and also
transparent. Otherwise we do not know the machine will go which kind of a direction.
Maybe it's a disaster, but we even didn't know it because
it dramatically not transparent for us,
right. And then the IoT security,
like we have failed networks, like the
self driving and the IoT, we definitely
do not want the AI attacked us,
right? What I
say is so terrible.
And human AI interaction security, like protecting
user data, preventing the impersonation attacks,
ensuring that AI generated outputs are not exploited
by malicious purpose.
Yeah. For example, we have the interaction and with Chinatip,
with some model learning model
and we are focusing, we are just younger,
very real teenager or these
kind of things, if they have been attacked,
okay. And IoT has been exploited by
malicious purpose. Wow, it's really horrible.
It can train our children, our next
generation, or even for us to kind of nurture
your religion or something affect
your culture and to influence you
to do something very bad. Oh, it is so horrible.
And then it's also special when in AI,
because as I mentioned, there are a
lot of modalities, like models, so many models
so far in reality. And also in the future there are more and
more models will be launched. So what
we can do to protect this model security. It's the
close things for AI security,
because AI is kind of a set of various
models. And so first, as adversarial
perturbations, like malicious impose craft
to deceive AI models into making incorrect
predictions. Also the transfer attacks like
reversal text that work across
different AI models. For example, like red box, the black
box attacks, which depend on attackers knowledge of the target,
like model's architecture. For example,
if your model, for example,
like a business prediction model has been attacked by your
competitors, and you just generated,
and AI just generated a laser prediction that you go this
way, but dramatically wrong, maybe just after
two years you just realize, wow,
it's completely wrong prediction. But you already to
plays everything there. You contribute to your business,
you cost the money for everything. But it's so horrible,
right? Bias and fairness security.
We are human around the world and
with different cultures, different civilizations, different religions.
It's so difficult in our
daily life to do our best to mitigate a bias for
this machine. Of course, they didn't know what
is bias. So we definitely need to this
technology techniques to identify and to reduce the
bias in training data is what we view.
Streamlining this machine and also fairness
aware learning, so created to design models
that make fair predictions across different demographic groups,
different cultures, and then lifecycle
security. AI is not like,
oh, we just invent some software.
We developed our software, one day we just
terminate, we do not use it anymore, leave it.
But AI model or AI
stuff, you cannot just like we
started coding practices and
regular updates. But how about when you will determine
this project, you must make sure everything
proper disposal of these systems,
you end this project and determinate
this project. It should be fine. But if something ongoing,
we must make everything sure we have the lifecycle,
we make sure everything know
what's the matter. Stipend the regular updates,
that's quite most important part.
And then regulation
or regulatory compliance.
If we just rely on the AI firms itself
to be warm heart, to be a good heart to
help the technology go the right
direction is ridiculous.
We cannot rely on them. We need involved
in what I say, the regulations and
also the legislations, for example like data protection
laws, GDPR or industry specific regulations
and icicle guidelines. Right.
And it's the last one. But last, but not the
last one. But I don't think Iot will be the last one.
Definitely in the near future it will be extended human
in the loop, because if there is no human view
like white box, black box,
we don't know what is the machine will go, will the machine will go
which direction or the machine has been attacked.
The machine got some threat detection, but we must
have some human expertise with the AI analysis
for this threat detection. And also be
curious and be cautious.
No matter how we call us.
It's not wrong, honestly. We need to have this overall
human oversight. So we have
discussed the alt definition and I also give
you the lighting application example in reality.
And also I have shared how AI and alt
affect our DevOps roles and what we can do,
what I can do and what AI cannot do. We will focus
on this one. And then the last
but not the least, we have a discussion about
the information security, the traditional classifications,
and also we focus on the IoT security. Definitely.
I give you the new definitions
and also the scopes, different scopes of AI security
we need to focus on. Yeah. So here
IoT is. So I hope all of you
can get a little bit inspiration from my today's talk
and anything practical you gained.
I will feel really grateful and
you enjoy today's talk. Thank you.