Hi everyone. Hello. Welcome to Chaos Engineering 2024.
My name is Indika Wimalasuriya and part
of my presentation I will walk you through smart Chaos,
which is about leveraging generative AI to build
autonomous chaos engineering workflows. During my presentation
I will talk about distributed systems and mainly
its importance when it comes to resilience. So why we have to make
our distributed systems resilient? And then we will
discuss high level what is chaos engineering and generative AI as well.
Important part of my presentation is discuss about methodology
of chaos engineering and then how we can apply
generative AI solutions into the different aspects of
or the life stages of the chaos
engineering workflows. We will discuss about quite a lot of
use cases, and I have used AWS Partyrock to implement some
of these use cases as well. And then we will check
how we can build an autonomous chaos engineering workflow
which can learn and which can act, and we can generate
the chaos solutions using generative AI
without human intervention. Finally, I'll wrap it up with
some of the best practices and pitfalls based on my experience.
So, moving on, I hope you all understand,
the distributed systems are very complex. One of the main reason
why they are very complex is we have layers of architectures,
right? We have the hardware layers. It can be your serverless,
or the computing layer or the front end layers as well.
What these layers has done is in case if there's an issue in any
of these layers, it will have a ripple effect on other
layers as well. And one other challenge is in case
of a bug in one of the layer, again, it can cause
different behaviors to the impact or ripple effect
to the other layers. And what we also know
is bugs can appear anytime, right? It can be that
you did a deployment last week, but maybe bug might appear today.
So managing these complexity distributed
systems is a challenge because there are a lot of unknowns.
And even though we think that we are knowing everything and we are
on top of the development rigor, the test
rigor and the CI CD pipelines and all the
automations we are bringing in, we still tend to encounter
issues. And that is one of the challenge. And that is something
probably you will ask why? Like why are we not able
to make management of distributed systems easy? Or is
it something down to the skill level? Or is it something down
to the people aspect? Or what is it? That's something
probably you want to find
out, and probably you want to answer. And if you are
thinking that these issues are only bound to
a certain level of size of the company or size of the
engagement. But I think you are wrong. Why?
Because I am giving you a couple of examples here. If you
look at it, during 2021,
Facebook had a massive outage which impacted Instagram
and WhatsApp and it outage lasted around 5 hours. This has impacted
Facebook badly and it had an impact on their
stocks as well. And same here, one of the leading
content delivery network, the fastly had the outage
which lasted around 1 hour again and it had
the impact on series of other applications or systems.
Mainly this is down to fastly being one of the leading
CDN. It has been used widely across the industry.
So this impacted Amazon, eBay,
Reddit and Twitch, Guardian and
even the New York Times and even some of the uk government websites.
This was identified that there was a bug in the software and
which has got move into production
and which has resulted this outage. So this is again one
classic example, one issue impacting multiple systems.
And this is kind of a classic example of the complexities
distributed systems are bringing. And last year
we have seen Datadoc, one of the leading observability tools
and it's kind of like probably number two
in the gardener observability magic quadrant. So Datadog experienced
a substantial outage which resulted in impacting
almost like most of their customers. Because Datadog,
as a SaaS solution, people are dependent on the
systems being up and running to enable their
systems, getting the alerts and other observability
related work. So this is again identified
that there was a route and there's a restart
required. So this is again a classic example. Like even
with companies which has money, which has
able to invest money on the proper tools, processes and
even people is not immune
to outages. So again, now you will
question this, right? Why? Because if you are spending
money, if you are bringing in the right tool, right people, and we are building
the right processes, then why are we every
day like ending up with these kind of situations?
And one of the key thing, what you have to understand is
we are doing lot of testing. And you might even ask that these
systems are going through a rigorous testing cycle.
It can be the developer testing, it can
be the regression testing, it can be performance testing,
it can be loud testing, it can be security testing. And once even
you deploy your code to production, you will do a post deployment testing.
So there are a lot of testing happening in these systems
and even with this testing, and we have using
lot of tools and automations to
improve our testing capability, why are we still
encountering major issues? And one of the answer is
we are only testing what we know. So example,
if I take example, if a customer gives a requirement,
developer go through the requirement, probably, and the developer
and the business analyst is converted to these stories. And then
these stories, developers will start building parallel.
The QA team, the quality assurance team will go through these requirements as well.
And they will come up with their test cases. And this is a very
important point to remember. So when the QA team is coming up with
the test cases, what they are doing is they are referring to the
requirements and they are putting their thought and they are coming up with those
test cases. So what we have to understand is the QA
team is coming up with what they know,
right? So we are good at testing what we know. So that
is one of the main thing. And most of the time when we are coming
up with issues, what we have seen is it's the unknowns
distributed system, because they are very complex
and because it's like vast and it's difficult to manage,
there are a lot of unknowns. And these unknowns are getting missed
out when we are doing testing,
because we test what is known to us.
So this resulted in these issues getting creeped into our
production systems regularly. And this is one of the challenge,
and this is a challenge where we are planning to address using chaos
engineering. So if you look at chaos engineering,
chaos engineering is pretty much trying to understand what are
the unknowns, right. As I said,
when our quality assurance teams going and doing testing,
they are only doing testing on knowns, what is known to them.
But assuming a distributed system deployed in a data
center, are we thinking of like someone in the data center pulling
a cable or someone is switching off the machine accidentally or
some router is enabling and which has resulted in traffic is
getting failed. So those are the scenarios usually
are not being conscious or covered. Part of our typical,
the quality assurance testing. And one of the main reason is there's
a lot of unknown here. So why chaos engineering is
we want to develop a
mechanism where we can test unknown. So this is nothing new.
Chaos engineering is here in industry for some time now.
So this was pioneered by Netflix. Especially when they are moving
out, they are on premise to the
cloud. They developed this chaos monkey, which is used to
go and do some chaos in their production environment.
So this allowed them to understand what are the issues
and what are the reliability issues and the resilience issues in their system,
so that they were able to develop a world class streaming media
platform. So one of the reason chaos engineering
is very important is it is able to test your resilience
and it is able to do sometimes some things which
we are not even thinking. So that is the advantage.
So chaos engineering is allowing us to improve our reliability and
build our systems with resilience in mind,
and it's allowing us to achieve our service level objectives,
and even it's allowing us to achieve our meantime to result
and other targets. So this is very important for
any of the distributed system to look at chaos engineering seriously.
So with this, I'll park the topic of chaos engineering for
a moment, and let's move into generative AI. So I'm probably sure
you all are aware of generative AI. With the hype of chat GBT.
Now, everyone is aware of generative AI, and everyone is using generative
AI. So generative AI is nothing but the ability
of AI models to create new content or create original
content. By looking at the large amount of
data, these large language models are able to come up
with innovative solutions. When comes
to creating new content, it can be either images or
the videos, or it can be in any media form.
So some of these models are really helping
us to make a difference in our operations,
or how we work, or how we approach our day of
life work. So if you look at applications of
generative AI, as I said, one of the top use cases is
the text generation. So it's not just a chatbot or just a
standard bot which you can communicate. So the same text
generation concept, you can apply into your coding,
and you can apply into the writing, you can apply
into the production support, you can apply into manage knowledge
bases. So the opportunities are endless, has good as your imagination,
it has the capability of image generation as well, and video
generation, and so many other things. So this is helping
us to come up with the new innovative solutions for
some of the problems or the challenges we have.
And again, coming back to chaos engineering. So even
though we say chaos, we want to do chaos engineering in
a methodical way. So there's nothing like doing a chaos engineering
a chaos way, and that will not give you any value.
So what we want to do is come up with the proper methodology,
which will allow you to develop your workflows,
and then come up with the proper chaos engineering mechanism. And even
though Netflix has been pioneered and they are able to do this in production
environment, we currently suggest you started in your non production
environments and then expand it later. So what are the
key steps of chaos engineering?
So the first task is discover,
discover your services, what are the components of your application,
where your application is deployed, and what are the dependencies
upstreams and downstreams, those are very important because
those are the places where things can go wrong.
So discovering your service is very important.
Then you have to understand your steady state studies is nothing
but what is good mean for you. It can
be like example,
if it is web application, it's about application has
to be up and running, application has to serve customer request within a
certain time. So that is what goods mean for you.
So every system we have to understand what is the steady state
and that will allow us to understand
and ensure that we have one identification.
When we say good, so good can't be based
on different people's opinion. It has to be something which
is written and something which is acceptable
to everyone. And then we will build our hypothesis,
what are the failure scenarios for this application? And the hypothesis
will help us to come up with experiments and then
to run them. And when we are running we will verify and we
will do an improve and continuous improvement of this cycle.
And we are obviously able to integrate this with CI CD pipelines.
But this is at the moment happening manually. And one
important thing you have to be remember is when you are following this process,
you have to have ability to measure everything.
There's no point you do chaos engineering or chaos testing,
but you are not looking at how your systems are behaving. I'm sure
you have heard of this term called wisdom of production. It's about getting
the knowledge of how your systems are running in production
or production environments, or even some environments
which are identical production. Remember I said you are not supposed
to or encouraged to do chaos engineering testing in production. But what you
can do is you can build an identical environment and you can do where you
can get the experience and the knowledge.
So key things is parallel to your chaos testing. You have
to have your observability in place. So observability is
looking at the external outputs, trying to define the internal
state of your system. So that is very important. When the chaos is happening,
you want to know how your systems are behaving and then you have to have
your SL laws defined and they are in place so that
you will able to understand when these chaos testings are run,
what is the impact on your service level objectives. And that is directly
correlated with what is impact on your customer experience.
So at this moment we are not probably have the ability to understand
what is customers feeling, but we have some service
level objectives which are very aligned to customer experience.
So this is allowing us to understand how this is impacting
to our customer. And finally you can look at
the latency traffic error and saturation. So combination of
all of this will allow you to measure everything. So this is very important.
When you are going through the chaos engineering process, you have to measure
everything, otherwise that is a waste of time.
So now let's look at part of each
different stage of chaos engineering, how we can bring generative AI.
So that is the key. So here I'm looking at ten
stages, ten step into the chaos engineering workflow,
and we'll try to go and see how we can actually
leverage generative AI to
provide solutions to this area. So one is
discovery. So we are able, like the traditional way
is people will use manual
approach or something very close to manual to
discover things. But we have the option, like we have sometimes the
observability tools and our apms application performance supporting tools
where it can create service maps, but that again will
help us to do discovery. But sometimes, most of the time this is happening
in manually and dependency identification. So this is
again something which is currently happening manually and we
are able to bringing in generative AI solutions which we will look at
in future. And steady state defined.
So steady state defined is you are looking at your architecture,
the services and everything, and you are defining what is good
mean to you. So this is at the moment pretty much happening manually.
And this is something, again you can leverage generative AI solutions,
hypothesis is nothing but your failure scenarios.
And this is again at the moment what's happening is your
entire team will start looking at the services, the architecture
diagrams, system dependencies, bottlenecks and probable
causes, and then come up with the failure
scenarios or the hypothesis. But then again there's a human intervention
required. And you all understand, if there's a human intervention means
there's always humans will do what is known. So we are missing out the
unknowns. So that is the area where again we can leverage generative AI,
an experiment design, again something which is happening
manually, or we can do it in a partial automation, but with this
generative AI, we are able to full fledged automate this,
like we can full fledged use generative AI and its
content creation capabilities. And to come up with these
experiments, and once you have the experiments, you will have
to understand the blast radius. I mean once you
come up with the chaos engineering test, you will not go and just execute it.
You want to understand what is the impact it's going to cause upfront,
right? So that we call blast radius. So once you are
doing that experiment, you can understand your blast radius is correct,
or whether it was less or whether it had a wider impact. That is
again a learning. So understanding
blast radiance, which is usually happening in a manual way
where you can leverage generative AI solutions to
do it in an automated fashion. And there's
something called Rumsfield metrics, which is about known knowns,
known unknowns and unknown knowns, so which we will cover in
a subsequent slide. Here's again about
coming up with a hypothesis for known knowns,
what you know in your area, likewise.
So this is again a place where we can use Geni, and then
about monitoring and analysis. We can plug our geni solutions with
observability tools, and then we can bring in
the capabilities large language model is bringing to the table,
and we can leverage that documentation and reporting is something
a bread and butter for generative AI, because it's kind of like
what is supposed to do or the basics. And then obviously we
can go through this in an iterative way. We can share all the learnings,
the observability data, service level objective data and other
the latency, traffic saturation and error rates,
and all those four golden signal data and feed them into
generative AI, where it can come up with the holistic approach
and to improve your systems or the workflows of chaos
engineering. So, moving on
now, I will go to the stages which
we have discussed and discuss about how we can leverage generative
AI for this. I am at the moment using one of the architecture diagram.
So these architecture diagrams, I have pulled it up from Amazon.com website,
one of their case studies. So probably one glass,
you might have an understanding of what this architecture diagram, or probably
it will take a little bit of time for you. And the idea is that
that is why we need generative AI. So we don't need
really SMEs to be involved all the time.
So this is the architecture diagram of an electronic vehicle charging system.
So it's hosted in AWS, it has components
like Route 53, you have your network load balancer,
it's using Fargate, and it's using some of the IoT
components, and it has lambda SQS,
step functions, and it has the Aetna,
DynamoDB, S three, and other visualization
tools as well. So this is again a very comprehensive,
probably a highly complex distributed system.
And what we are going to do is we are going to use this as
our base and see how we can automate some of the stage
just which I discussed earlier.
So, moving on, one of our first task is,
can we identify the dependencies here?
What I'm doing is. So all those examples I have tested
using AWS, party Rock AWS party rock is one of
innovative the AI play pen
which AWS has released. So if you are aware, AWS has
the search maker which is about hard way of deploying and
managing your AI models. And then you have bedrock where
it's API based so that it's more of a serverless kind of experience.
And party rock is where you kind of like plug and
play and start using models. So if you want go to AWS party
rock where you can experiment and create all those things which I'm
discussing here. So here what I have done, I used
that architecture diagram I showed you earlier. I created a
small app where I have given the architecture diagram
and I asked generative AI to come up with system dependencies.
As you can see it says based on the architecture
diagram, here are some of the key dependencies. So it's identifying
EV charging station, OCPP protocol handler
charging station management system, payment provider notification
component, telemetry induction, billing system authentication
has the key system dependencies. So this is good without
us looking at this, without someone
from the team or the SME looking at this generative AI,
just by looking at architecture diagram, it's able to derive this.
So what you have to understand is this is not just image
reading. So this is about just image reading.
Then understand those components using the
massive amount of learning or the data it's have make a
story which makes sense. So that is the beauty of
large language models. So here it's able to easily
come up with the dependency list. So here's the example.
Like when you are coming up with the dependency list, like you can change
the model types. Now here if I'm not mistaken, I am
using the model call command. So here my
output is more accurate,
or I would say it's kind of like very clear
compared to the previous one. So it's a pro tip. So if you
are using large language model, like ensure that you are using the
right model and that will give you more accurate data.
So moving on, next aspect is understanding
the steady state of this application or the system.
Here again, I'm using party rock. I have given the architecture diagram
link and then I have asked to come up with the steady state definition.
So what the party rock or the large language model is producing
is it's providing the steady state definitions.
So it's saying API gateway. The API gateway is available
and return the correct response code, 200 code
when OICP requests are sent to API.
And likewise it's able to list all the steady state
definitions. Example payment gateway, it says the payment gateway
is available and successfully processing payment for
charging sessions. So this is the steady state.
So our generative AI is able to look at the architecture diagram
and then define what is good mean without
even human involved.
So moving on, this is about hypothesis creation.
So creation of what are the failure scenarios? Again, what I'm
doing, I have given the architecture diagram link and I
have asked generative AI model to generate the hypothesis
so it's able to come up with a meaningful and relevant
accurate hypothesis. So first one,
it says if the OCPP handle goes down,
electric vehicle charging station will not be able to start stop
charging sessions, leading to inability to charge the vehicles.
So likewise, if the billing system goes down,
new charging sessions cannot be started, has authorization,
and payments cannot be processed. So it's coming up with the failure
scenarios and also potential impact. So as you
see here, again, I am simply giving generative AI
the architecture diagram and asking it to come up with this hypothesis.
But probably you might already understood
it. Now, I can improve this massively, not only architecture
diagram, I can give the observability data,
I can give the other services, I can give a live service map taken
from an observability tool, and I can give a
lot of data so that generative AI can improve its answers
and then experiment design. So again,
as I discussed, I'm giving the architecture diagram. I'm just
asking generative AI to come up with the experiments.
So if you can see, it's able to come up with hypothesis
and steady state and even list the test case.
So here it states test case, simulate a failure of CPP
handle by powering off the server or disrupting the network
connection to the OCPP handler. Observe the behavior of
system and impact on EV charging process. So again,
another test case, simulate a database
disruption by stopping the database service or corrupting the database files.
Observe if the charging stations can continue charging and if the
charging stations data is accurately recorded and updated.
Likewise, I mentioned to you, so generative AI is able
to smartly come up with these experiments. So this is again helping
us massively to cut down human involvement and
moving on. Once you have the experiments, it's about understanding blast
radius. I mentioned to you, when you are executing your chaos testing
or experiments, you have to understand or have some understanding of
the impact. So here again what I'm doing, I'm giving the architecture
diagram so that generative AI can have a big
picture. And then I'm giving a test case. Then I'm asking it
to come up with the blast radius. So here it says this is a blast
radius for the test case. So here we know it's going to impact
OCPP handler, EV charging state,
back end services and users. So this is
massively advantage. So generative AI without
even us involving able to come up with this kind of data.
And as I said, now if you remember I used
architecture diagram to get all this data.
And probably you might think architecture diagrams are sometimes outdated
and can we improve this? Of course, this is
an example of a very simple application where
service map was generated by Cloudwatch x ray
where once the application is being used, so I know the client is there,
API gates, microservices, my databases.
So I can just feed in this diagram with
the architecture diagram so that generative AI solution can
compare what is in the architecture diagram and what are the services
it in live or operations or in whatever the environments
you have deployed this. So this will allow it to. So the
more data, more accurate data, more information we
are feeding into the chaos engineering or the generative AI tool which
is going to do this. This will allow it to come up with more
accurate answers. So next,
so we quickly touch about this Ramsfield metrics.
So this is about known known. So when you say non known, it's about
evaluating components of your system that are familiar and thoroughly
understood, such as system architecture, infrastructure,
identified failure points, CI CD test, and then we have
the known unknowns. And this is about investigating potential issues
and vulnerabilities in your system that are known but
haven't undergone rigorous testing or validation,
such as theoretical vulnerabilities or unverified
failure scenarios. So that is again a known unknown. And then
we have the unknown knowns reviewing issues that are
considered but may have been forgotten or overlooked
with passing of time, such as adherent to best practices,
documented procedures, or insights from historical incidents.
So this is known as known unknowns, known unknown
knowns. And finally, it's about unknown unknowns conducting
comprehensive chaos testing to discover, foresee and anticipated vulnerabilities
that may emerge unexpectedly, leading to
surpassed or often unpleasant nature. So Ramsville field
just gives kind of an approach where you can plan your chaos
testing or when you are coming up. So what we can do is we
can feed this data or approach or the framework of
Ramsville metrics into our generative AI here. What I'm
doing is I have given the architecture diagram, then I'm just saying,
come up with the known known. Or I could have improved this thing by looking
at this, come up with test cases or hypothesis to map to
known known and moving on. I was able to do
the same thing for known unknown as well. So I'm
sure now you have that understood. We are able
to use generative AI, every aspects
of our chaos engineering workflow. We are able to
use generative AI to discover our services, we can able
to use it to understand the dependencies, we are able to use it to define
steady state, we are able to use it to come
up with our hypothesis, we are able to use it to come up with
our test cases or the experiments. And then
we are able to use it to come up with, what do
you call after test cases? The blast radius.
So those are the ingredients or the pieces of our chaos
engineering workflow. So if you are looking at a typical CI CD
pipeline, you have the developers coding and committing code, you will build it
and you will deploy it for testing and probably you will do the deploy as
well. And then you have the observability tools which if you are using
AWS, you can leverage cloud matrix,
cloud logs or x rays. And here we
can plug our chaos engineering pipeline to here as well.
So what this does is part of this pipeline, our chaos engineering
pipeline can get invoked and then it will start triggering
a workflow. So what this workflow is, this is
what I call the smart chaos. This is about autonomous
chaos Engineering. So what we are doing is first
our generator AI will have access to the training data set.
This about your architecture diagrams, this about your service
maps, this about observability data, this about all the
inputs which we can give it to generative AI to come up with the proper
solution. Then it's able to
come up with, I mean it will obviously come up with
the defined steady state. It's able to come up understand
the dependencies and it will come up with a hypothesis.
And then based on that it will try to come up with some experiments.
So what we want is when we are creating experiments, we want to
create templates, small experiment templates, so that
we can make it as a collection and reuse. So that is
probably we can give already some of the templates like
API failures or instance termination or system
resource filling up and those things as
the templates so that this workflow can use.
Then this workflow can create these experiments and
then start executing it. And then once
the experiments have been executed, we are able to monitor
using our observability tools, like we are able to monitor the observability
data or the telemetry data. And we will start monitoring our service level
objectives and the traffic saturation error and other
things. So that is again will give more data
points to this workflow. So what we have to do is
we'll come up with a small blast radius and we'll ask the generative
AI to use a small blast radius and then increase
it in subsequent runs. So this is more of a very automated workflow
where we are leveraging what I mentioned to you, right? Each stage
I have shown you how we can use generative AI
and now we are bringing it all together to come up with a proper workflow.
And if you look at it how this can be actually look at
in an actual production environment or a typical other environment.
So you will have your DevOps and sres which are doing your
changes. They will ship these changes using CI CD
pipeline which will go and deploying into your different environments
and parallel that we can trigger your smart chaos. And smart
chaos is also integrated with observability, service level objectives, error budgets.
And what smart chaos will do is it will try to pull up
the observability tool and get the actual service
maps, and then it can refer the knowledge it's having about the architecture
diagrams and all the other diagrams, the logs and the metrics
and traces and everything based on that, it will try to come
up with what are the steady states, what are the dependencies?
It will come up with hypothesis and it will design experiments.
And based on after it design experiments, it will look
at a library of templates, which we call experiment
templates, and then combine those templates scripts.
It can create the actual chaos workflows and then
it will start pushing this into the relevant environments to run.
While doing that it can start monitoring it and look at
the telemetry data and improve, right? Obviously it will look at
controlling the blast radius and then increasing in subsequent runs.
So this is happening fully autonomous where we don't have to spend time,
we don't have to get our peoples involved. We can let the
generative AI learn about our application setup and
everything and then build smart chaos or
the chaos engineering automations for us. This I like
to call autonomous chaos workflows. So with
this, before I wrap up, so if you are seriously trying to get into this,
I have a couple of best practices you have to consider. One thing is
as like any other generative solutions,
this smart chaos is depend on providing good
quality data to our generative AI models. If you provide
unclean data or data which might not be relevant,
then your model will struggle. And then one
of the best practices have a big template
library ready with some of the small subunit
of experiments. So this will allow our workflows to quickly
use these templates, bundle it up and create one template.
And other thing is that let the
smart chaos expand gradually. Don't go into in a big
bang way. I mean, that is always not the best or advisable thing.
Let's do it in more of the control
and way that we can expand.
And one other thing is have the feedback loop, right? You can introduce some
of these feedback loops so that generative AI can provide
notifications and all those insights and runtime, you can look
at how things are happening and then also based on that,
you can fine tune some of these workflows as well.
And what are the pitfalls to look at it? So one of the big pitfall
is when you are looking at generative AI, sometimes we
have seen there's a data bias. So you have to ensure that
when you are providing this data, so the model will not
go into a data bias situation. So here, when I say data bias,
so example, it's about balancing the flaws, right? So it can
identify some of the critical workflows and non critical workflows.
So what we don't want the model to be is biased to the critical
workflow where it will go and only look at the critical workflows.
But then we want to have some kind of good
cover of non critical workflows as well. And then
we want this approach to expand
in a controlled fashion, not avoid rapid chaos expansion,
because that is
not a recommended thing. And we want it to feed all the
observable telemetry data and everything, so that experiments,
monitoring, measuring, everything can be comprehensive, and then it can learn
and iterative in a nice fashion. And finally,
what I want to tell you is, even though this is a very good approach,
and I'm pretty sure we are going to see this in happening real time,
there's a need of human expertise. Don't eliminate your human
completely, still roping him in.
Start looking at the areas, try to look at the bigger picture,
look at things from holistically, and then try to see how we can improve
this in a holistic way with this.
I'd like to finish my session. It was wonderful being part of Chaos
Engineering 2024. I hope you enjoy my presentation
and there are a lot of other presentations. Please go and check them as well.
And I'm very much happy if you are still in and
if you are listening, I'm privileged to be part of this.
And I'm wishing and hoping that you have
learned something which you can go back and used in your
day to day work with that. This is nice, us doing this
presentation. Thank you very much. Have a nice day.