Hi there, and welcome to the typing biometrics journey. Together,
we'll go through some theory and practice of that, and by the end of
it, you're going to find out how you can win some limited edition swag from
typing dna. So, without further ado, let's get it started.
First of all, what exactly is typing biometrics?
So, this is something also known as keystroke dynamics,
and it is embedded in people's behavior when they type on a keyboard.
So, yes, you heard that right. The way that you type is unique,
and it can be used for various purposes that we're going to explore
further in this presentation. Now, this might sound futuristic,
but it dates back to World War II,
when the military used to communicate through the Morse code.
So, using a methodology called the fist of the sender,
military intelligence were able to detect
the rhythm of the operator's
point, recording the dots and the dashes,
and they could identify ally from enemy
in this context. Now, since then, the preference for written
communication grew, and with it,
the field of typing biometrics evolved.
So one area which is the most
explored and developed at the moment is authentication.
So, using the way that you type in order
to authenticate you. Now, at this point,
I think we can all agree that passwords alone are not enough to secure
your account. So I want to make a short detour to the authentication space
before going into more details on typing biometrics.
So, when we talk authentication, we can basically split
the different factors into three categories,
knowledge, possession, and biometrics. Knowledge is
something that you know, such as a pin or a password,
or the security question, such as what is your mother's maiden
name? The possession factors are something that you own,
like a phone number, an email address,
a token, something that you could further leverage,
that could receive kind of a one time password or
code on it. And the third category is
biometrics. And here we can further split the
factors into physiological, something that you are.
And here you can have the fingertips, the face recognition
or behavioral, something that
is related to the way that you behave, such as the way that you walk,
the way that you talk, or the way that you type. Now,
if we were to compare the security aspects
of them, the security and ux point of view,
the knowledge factors are the most user friendly because
people are already used to them. However, they tend to be
not so secure, because once somebody hacks your information
or finds out what it is, then it's very
easy to break. And let's not forget that people usually reuse,
share the passwords or the information to make it
easier. Now, possession is a bit more secure,
but it tends to be not so user friendly because
the devices could be lost or stolen.
So then imagine you are stranded somewhere,
your phone got stolen, you're trying to contact,
let's say, your bank, or you're trying to send an email, and then
it sends you the SMS and you cannot basically log
in, authenticate because your device was initially lost or
stolen. So it can generate some user experience
problems here. Now the third category, the biometrics,
are supposed to be the most secure ones. However, this could
also pose some user experience issues because they might
require kind of a heavy interaction
from the user side. It can also have some problems in
detecting it because nothing is black or white here.
This is not a one or zero response to authentication as it is in the
case of the knowledge or the possessions ones. And you're basically basing your
authentication assumption on a certain
certainty threshold. But among all of this,
we believe typing biometrics to be the winner in terms of
adding two factor authentication.
And this is because, first of all,
it's very secure because it's hard to break, it's hard
to mimic. Even though somebody is next to you and sees
what your password is, they cannot replicate how
you type it. It's also compliant with the latest
regulations. So according to PSD,
two rules, typing by matrix is accepted
as a second factor. And it's very user friendly because you
don't need to do anything additional than what you're already
doing, basically typing. And you can use your own device, you don't need
another keyboard or other hardware.
And it also evolves as the user's typing
behavior changes over time. So it's constantly adapted to
the behavior and it's kept as
updated as possible. The more that you type then the better your
typing profile gets. Now, this is currently
being heavily used into elearning,
especially since COVID hit and more and
more universities and courses moved online. Also, the need
to secure the courses and certifications
grew and we have various clients that reached out and
they implemented typing dna authentication in
various steps of the journey being it while taking the
exam. Also at the end, to ensure that the person who
started the exam was also the same one that was
continually doing the exam and finished it, and is the
same person as the one that took the course initially,
we also have clients from the banking area financial services
because I was mentioning the PSD. Two regulations now require
online transactions to have a second factor in place and
many of them turned to typing biometrics in order
to secure the transaction and the identity access
management providers could also not stay away from this opportunity.
So you can now have typing biometrics at the
click of a button, literally drag and drop in your favorite IAM
widgets such as forestrock or Azure,
ADB to c. All right, now that it's been a lot of talk,
so let's see how this would actually work in practice.
So the first step, as with any other biometric, is recording
the behavior. And we do this through an open source recorder
through which we capture the times needed to press and
release keys. Also the way that you move between
the keys, the way that you hold your phone if
you're on a mobile device, and how you basically
interact with your device, including the mouse movements. So all
sorts of data points are collected through the
open source recorder and then the output of this
is taken through data engineering so as to extract
only the signals which are the most relevant and used
for creating your typing profile. We do this initially two
or three times to create the user's typing profile.
This is very similar to what you do when you have a new phone and
you need to configure your fingerprint scanner. So you do it in the beginning a
couple of more times until the system literally creates
your profile. And after that, every time you come back, we compare
the typing profile to what we have stored as your typing
profile. And if
the matching is above a certain threshold,
then we say okay, yes, we allow the authentication so it's a success.
If it's not, then we say okay, probably this is not
the person who he or she claims to be.
Right, so enough theory, let's see how this
would work in practice. I'll just switch now
to the typing DNA website and show you a bit of
an already done widget that you can super easily implement.
And this is for demo purposes so you also see how it would work.
And then I'll show you how you could alternatively
use the authentication API so you make your own custom implementation.
So, right, we are on the typingdna.com website. What you need
to do firstly is create an account so you sign
up. All of our accounts are for free so you don't need to
pay for any of the solutions. And after you sign up you're going to be
redirected to the dashboard where you can find your information
also from the verify product which is
the already made widget. I'm going to show you in a moment, but as well
for the authentication API. But let's start with the demo.
Let's see how this could actually work from here. You can do
the verified demo here. I already opened it.
So to begin with we need to create, as I was mentioning, the user's typing
profile and we also need a route of trust to
see if basically to have a data
point that would associate a typing profile with the
person. And we need to make sure that this person is indeed the
one that provided the phone number or the email address if they have it.
So I'll just go for email and
I'll write here a dummy email address. I'm going to
do this for the first time so you can see the flow end to end.
So I input my email to have a data
point that this is basically
the only contact Pii information that we have over you.
And it can also be used as a fallback method in
case something goes terribly wrong. And let's say you temporarily
break your arm or something happens, then you can opt for the fallback
method and you're still able to access
your two fa, right? So I'll just start a demo now and
I need to write these words. As you can see,
the number of words or characters is not so
high. So the user experience is good. And here on the right
side, this thing shows that the typing pattern has been recording while it typed.
Now, because this is the first time I do it, I need to create my
typing profile. So this time only I need to type two more
times and one more
it. All right, now I will receive again one time
only, a security code,
just copy paste it,
right? So my typing profile has been created
and it was the same as the one that I inputted the first
time. So how can I say that the second
and third type profile like behavior
typing behaviors were similar
to the first one that I did first. But let's start this
over. So now I have my typing profile created and
I'll try to authenticate. I'll start again. I'll use
the same email address so it knows which Devin profile to
access and I'll start it right?
And that's it. The verification has been successful and I was
allowed into my account. So see, as easy as typing
four small words and you already have your two fa
in place. So if this made you curious enough to
want to give it a more of a deep dive, try. I'll show
you now how you can implement it with how you
can test out basically with the authentication API that
we have available. So I'm going to use postman for that.
The first step here is basically
is to go to the typing DNA page. Go here and access
like download the Postman library collection.
It's very easy to get it from here and import it into
your postman account. I already have it imported here.
Now after it's imported, you need to add your credentials.
So you go back to the dashboard, you switch to the authentication API
tab and you take your key and your secret. From here
you go into the configurations basic auth and put your
username and password. This is for us to know that it was you accessing
the API. Now. Next we're going to use the auto
endpoint. This is basically a magical endpoint that
does everything for you. So it will firstly,
the first three times enroll the typing pattern. So an
enrollment means adding to the typing profile
of the person to create the profile itself.
Also every time we have a qualitative typing
pattern, we add it to the typing profile so it's
kept up to date. This is also part of the enrollment. And the
auto endpoint also does all the verifications. So here you
can see multiple endpoints. But basically auto is the one
that you can use for almost all the use cases that you have,
unless you want to make it a very custom implementation
case which you can use these other two. Right, so we have,
let's say the back end configured now with postmo. Now you might be
wondering, all right, but where can I get a typing profile so I
can start testing? And we have that figured out as well.
So if you go on the typingdna.com website under
authentication API, we have created this typing pattern
viewer which is basically a tool that outputs the
typing patterns after you write in the text box here.
So I'm going to use this type to output tool to generate the typing patterns
and then verify them through postman through the typing dna
collection. Ready? So we already have a phrase for this.
I'll type it now.
Make yourself necessary to somebody. We ran multiple tests and
apparently this phrase is very effective into
the, how can I say, improving the accuracy of the verification with
lowering the number of characters needed. So this is a perfect combination
of short text but good accuracy in detection and it generated
the typing patterns. Here you can see three types, same text,
any text and extended the difference between them. So with
the same text, this means that every time you're trying to perform
authentication, so create the typing profile of the user
and verify it like authenticate based
on it. You must use the same text,
identical same text every time.
Now with any text we allow you
to write or the users to write anything that they might think of.
However, we require higher number of characters here.
So same text works better with short but
identical text every time, whereas any text is more flexible, but it requires
the user to write more. Then it's up to you how you decide to do
the implementation. But for the sake of the exercise, we'll go for the same text.
So we're going to use this phrase to create the typing
profile and then authenticate based on it, right? So now I'm
just going to copy this copy, go into my auto,
I'm going to create a new user here. So this is
sending basically the user Id. Please make sure this is an
id that you're sending if you're going to implement it, not some type of
Pii. We don't want that. And we just
copy paste here the typing pattern that we were generated
before. I'll hit send and the message came back,
right? It seems I used this user before and
if I were to check for it, let's see, how many typing patterns did
I have on it? So the thing is, I used the same user id
before. We already have a typing pattern
profile basically for it, and now we just did the authentication not from the
beginning. So for just the sake of this, I'll just use
let's do it like this for sure. This one I didn't do. I'll go back
and do it again.
It, as you can see, many mistakes but nowhere is there.
I copy this, I go back and the reason why
I didn't hit send with can user Id is because
no typing pattern, no two typing patterns are identical, not even for
the same user. So if I could have tried
to send the same typing pattern as before, then I
would have gotten an error back saying this might be a fraud
attempt or like an attack. So that's why I prefer to generate
a new one that I'm going to send now under this new user did
and it says the pattern was enrolled, but they're not enough
for verification. So I just enrolled it. The action done was
enrolled. I need to do this two more times in order to create the
profile, right? So going back here, reset, writing the
exact same text,
get this copy paste
and send again, not enough for verification. I just
enrolled it now I should have two and one last time
I get this, I copy back here,
I send it over right the third time I
enroll it. Now if I go into the check user, I'll just copy the
user id from here. Check user is going to show me how many
typing patterns I have for this user. And it says
I have account of three, which is good, means my profile is complete and
I can proceed with authentication and verification. But all
of them are on desktop. So desktop and mobile are different
because the physical keyboards behave differently than the mobile ones.
So this is why if you want to verify from
the mobile device, make sure the mobile profile was created previously
or you ask the user to create it then. Right? So with discount of three,
I'm going back to auto and now my profile is created.
I'll try to do the verification. Going back.
I reset it, try to examine same text.
I get it.
And the message came back, it's done. And what it said is,
first of all we did the verification and
it was successful because the result was one. And then because
we believe this typing pattern to have
a high quality, then we also added to the typing
profile of the person. So enroll. So we did those verification
with the result of one, which meant authentication successful and
enrollment with the result of one. Meaning we also added to the
profile. Now, I asked a colleague of mine to generate
a typing profile before this talk on
the exact same text that we used, just to show you what would happen
if somebody would try
to break in into your account by the typing behavior.
So I already have a typing profile previously generated.
I will just copy paste it from here and see what happens.
All right. So the action done of it was verification and
the result was zero, meaning the authentication was not
successful. We don't believe this person to be who they claim to be.
And because of this, we also didn't do any enrollment because
obviously the typing pattern does not belong to the person, so we don't want to
add it to the typing profile. Pretty interesting,
right? I really encourage you after the talk to go and play a bit around
with it and try to test out with different friends or families and see
how it works with your own eyes.
Now, going back to the presentation, I know this
talk was on security and on the security
stage, but there's also one field which is worth
mentioning in the typing biometrics space, which is the e health.
So there are currently various startups and companies around
the globe which are investigating and researching into
how you can apply type in biometrics for e health purposes
to detect various diseases associated mostly with
your brain and how you can detect it
and also help you throughout,
let's say, improving your state. So constantly monitoring
and taking action on the findings there is also quite
promising and I'm looking forward to see where this will go in the future.
Imagine you would have an e health app that
based on the way that you constantly type on your phone, on your
computer could say you might be at risk of having
this disease, maybe you should get yourself checked, or if you have the disease,
all right, your threshold now or your behavior indicated a
progress, or maybe that your state just
went worse over the past one month or so on. So a lot of
potential here. I'm looking forward to see these companies evolve
over the time. But we at typing genetic could also not stay
away from the e health area because it has so much potential and
room for growth and for helping people. So we very recently
launched Focus, which is an app for improving your productivity.
So basically we
track how you type and then we can predict your mood
based on that and give you some recommendation on when you should take a
break or when you're the most focused.
And all of this with the purpose of improving your personal
productivity. So this app is also available for free. Now just go on
typingdna.com slash focus, check it out and let us know what you think
and if it helped you. Well, at TypingDna,
we are on a constant mission of improving people's lives through typing biometrics.
We believe this field to have great potential and we keep on exploring
over it. And I hope to have made you curious enough to
want to explore it further and test it out. And if this presentation
was not enough, we also created this special landing page
for the event. Typingdna.com conf 42.
Here we're going to find demos, contests,
challenges, more information about what we discussed today.
And with every contest that you're participating in,
you are closer to winning some limited edition cool flag.
So get on this landing page, have fun, and get a
chance of winning some cool stuff. We are always available
for questions, so don't hesitate to write to us and
end. I want to thank you for your attention and leave you with a final
thought. So, as Picard rightfully said,
things are only impossible until they're not. And typing
biometrics is the perfect example for that.