Hi, welcome to this comparison of data Space and shuttlers.
They are both platforms for
development and deployment of cloud
applications, and they both support rust.
You can also see the content of these slides
on GitHub pages, or you can clone it
from GitHub or you can download the pdfs. If you
clone it and you follow a few steps in the source of
ReaDMe, you can also view them offline
and at your pace. Standard disclaimers apply.
The main ones are that this is not those complete
introduction to either platform. You do not
need any deep knowledge of rust for
this, and surprise,
these platforms are new and they are work
in progress, so there are good things coming,
and if this gets outdated, please let me know.
Some of the features and limits are not draft specific, but they
do affect how the applications are deployed
and for what purpose. Hence I'm including them here.
You can also look at the source code of my four applications,
two for each platform I used three rust
framework web frameworks for them.
They're trivial applications and useful.
One for each platform show the system
information like directory listing quotas
or the available space on the
mounted drives,
and one on shuttlers shows those
headers as data used to
document that. Neither of the platforms shows IP
addresses coming from the client. On data
space you can see transient web
dev server. It's a tiny one that
it uses its data space's file limit
of up to 500 or so megabytes
and I will be sharing my bookmarks and
highlights for Firefox on data
Space shuttlers and rust,
so feel free to use them. Even though it's
a transient file share,
it will be synchronized from my Firefox, so if data restarts
it for any reason, it will get synchronized
there soon. And I've documented
steps on how you can read and synchronize those
bookmarks into your Firefox. Spoiler alert. I love them both.
Before we get into the qualities
and limits of each platform, let's have a
quick look at the source code and some configuration.
Data space uses Space file,
which is YaML file with
simple entries. It's very well documented,
and if all you need is default, or if
you don't need any private routing or special features,
it's very easy. However, rust support
is quite new at data space,
and occasionally rust applications
don't work if you build them with standard target
that uses Glipc. Because of that,
I suggest that in the interim you use the
mucil target, which is a lightweight, Linux statically
compelled target that doesn't use glipsy at all
it has its own implementation of STD library
and that works very well on data
space. You use whatever crates you
want or you need in your application and there
are no specific crates from data
needed other than the unofficial data
space SDK. The configuration
gets done in your application
where you need to read the port environment
variable and use that as the web port
of your application. Or actually it's not the
application, it's the micro, which you can have up to five of them
in the same application. We'll get to that soon. In shuttlers
there is no mandatory configuration file other than
that there is a file called Shuttle Toml,
but all it does for now is that you can
specify the application name in it, but it's optional and you can specify
that in the CLI as
you deploy the application. Anyway,
configuration is done or those
integration with Shuttle is done through custom crates
provided by Shuttle and you can see them here. For example,
this is a cargo tunnel for a web app that uses
XM and shuttlers provides two XM crates, shuttlers exum
and shuttle runtime. Then let's look
how it is used and here you see an attribute
procedural macro shuttle runtime main,
which you apply to the function that serves your
application and in this instance the result type
is custom to shuttlers XM
that is very well documented with examples
or tutorials and it works well
out of the box. However, since we are looking
at the source code, you may want to remember
that if you are using advanced features of
those frameworks supported by Shuttle,
it does get complicated because you
may use features like retrieving
or handling and setting non default headers,
or your own MIME types, or anything
that is non default is not trivial with
shuttlers. You may find tutorials
on the web on how
to implement it with exum or the
other frameworks for sure. But if you then want
to connect it with Shuttle, you may need to do more
exploration and you may want to be combining
and experimenting, but that's
part of our passion. Here's an example
of cargo tumble for Actix web deployed on shuttle
and again you have two special crates,
shuttlers web and shuttle runtime,
and here's how it is used. In the source code you
apply a procedural attribute, macro shuttle runtime main and
the async function actics web returns
custom type shuttlers web both platforms share
these features. They are deployed on the Linux machines,
but you can locally develop on Linux, Mac OS
and Windows. We don't have SU
or sudo access and we cannot customize at docker
level. Neither of them provides
access to the client ip address. So you cannot
do IP dependent logic rate
limiting or geo IP handling.
With data space you can, and actually
most likely with shuttlers. Two,
you can use special headers, for example,
from Cloudflare DNS, and both platforms
are active on discord. The community is helpful.
Here are data space features. The applications
can be private, accessible to you, the developer
only, or public. That's one of the main differences
between data and shuttlers,
as shuttlers doesn't have private applications on
data. You can access those private applications if you authenticate
in the browser and most likely with C URL
or other tools too. On data, you can also
publish test versions,
deploy test versions that are not published, and they stay
private until you publish them. Data doesn't have
access to your password for authentication that goes through AWS.
The other big feature is mesh design. Your application
can be a mesh of up to five computes,
each with its own limits and file
system. They can communicate between themselves,
even though some of them or
most of them can be private and not directly accessible
from outside. You can also have routing public routing that
specify which compute which micro to
use for which URL patterns.
That way you can integrate with third
party applications. And those
don't have to be in rust because data space also
supports several other languages. That's the other feature. It's a
mesh of languages or frameworks. The disadvantage
is that rust support is quite new and
it's still work in progress. Rust applications don't get special handling,
which gives you some freedom. For example,
you can choose your rust version or
any framework, or you can use nightly rust if you like.
Rust bindings for data API are
only unofficial at the moment, but the HTTP
rESt API itself is well documented.
You don't need any special rest crates or macros for your code from Detaspace.
It doesn't favor SQL
rdbms like postgres, SQL,
or MySQL, unless you have a pool manager,
and data space doesn't provide any of such
databases. Yes, you probably want
mutual target at the moment, and big
limitation may be that it doesn't
support background or long tasks. Discord boards implementation
of discord boards and websockets data space
provides storage, both NoSQL,
called database and object
or file storage, called data store.
They are their proprietary APIs,
well documented but not
available outside of their platform. You can use them locally,
though of course, and they may not be so fully proprietary
because data is pretty open source.
Data isolation is very good, and you can clone
someone's application have it with your
data isolated and your instance is completely independent.
Even if the original instance owner
publishes new versions, your application
is not affected unless you choose to receive the new
versions. Data supports cron like schedule actions
with granularity down to 1 minute, and it promotes
personal or private instances.
For example, the subdomains are anonymized with a random
postfix, and forking instances is very
easy. You don't need developer skills for that. There is
the marketplace where you can share your
applications and when you can see what others are sharing
and then you can experiment with them. And there's a plan
to offer paid applications that would
generate revenue for the developer. Let's look at shuttlers.
Shuttlers specializes in rust and
it's top class edit. The tutorials
are well written. It also documents how to
connect the middleware, some security and
cryptography features too.
The applications deployed on shuttlers are suitable for background on
or long tasks. It provides much richer storage
as there are four SQL options,
postgres, MySQL and MariaDB as dedicated
instances. And postgres also has a shared server
from Shuttle or Turzar which is a distributed
Sqlite fork that is not hosted by
Shuttle. Hopefully it will be so one day
or there would be an option for that, but for now you would
need to get free or commercial hosting
from Turuso and it also has a dedicated
crate from Shuttle. It offers now SQL
MongoDB shared by Shuttle or
proprietary key value database called shuttlers persist.
The data is well isolated.
A small disadvantage or limitation of shuttlers is
that because they provide their specialized crates,
those are pinned at some versions and they require specific
versions or potentially a
limited range of versions of dependent
crates. Those MySQL and other SQL
crates or MongoDB crate and the same with
Turzo. It's pinned to fixed version and the rest
itself is pinned to fixed,
but a fairly recent version too.
Shuttle does have much longer build times because they
provide attribute macros and those
use Serdi for syntax
passing and handling, which is complex.
It can take long to build and it
can involve from around 300
or even up to 600 dependencies in your
project. But if you're building it locally then any
successive builds are incremental by default,
so then it is much faster.
It doesn't have TMP folder only
dev SHM for memory sharing
or temporary file system. So if
you have an application that uses temporary file
system you may want to choose one or
you may want to customize it to you. If it
depends on TMP, it doesn't promote
targeting or sharing clones of applications if you'd
like to share your application so that others
get their own instance of it on shuttlers you
need to do so on GitHub or some other source sharing
service and they will need to go through the steps to deploy
it, which is not rocket science, but they
need some more skill developer skills than with forking
an application. On data space. There is
a limitation of, I believe, up to five applications per
user for free, but these limits are not enforced yet.
And if you contribute to shuttlers,
or if you create useful
applications that help people, shuttlers may
reward you as a hero and their
hosting and services will be free for you for life.
For commercial purposes you can or
they are planning that you can use your own AWS
account. Here are some quantitative and other differences so
these don't come out of design and
hence they are more likely to be more
flexible than the qualitative differences earlier.
The biggest ones are memory limits,
which are not very clear, but on data space you can have
250 megabytes per each micro
per execution, and on shuttlers you can have
usually up to 6gb per container.
There is no timer to limitation on shuttlers or it's
not specified, and on data space it's 20 seconds.
And there are differences between the temporary file system
size, but those will hardly
make a difference for mainstream applications.
If your application is parallelized
more than a usual async web
application, you may want to look more at the limits
on processes or threads. On shuttlers it's only four threads
per project, on data space it's 1024
per micro and if you need to
handle more than five to five megabytes
HTTP payload, then at the moment you
need shuttlers. Those storage limit
on shuttlers is 10gb on free
tire, but it's not enforced yet and it's not specified
on data space, and they both use AWS
with at least data space. Also planning for
using GCP or other clouds choosing between
them there are some minor criteria
or trivial ones if you need a temporary
file system on TMP,
or the quantitative differences
if those matter to you, and if they
are not likely to be changed by the platform,
then you may choose one or the other, but you may still ask
around because they are work in progress. If you
need your applications to be private with
single user only, then at the moment you probably want a
data space, but then you still need to want to
consider the storage. You may want this option if
you are open to using their database or data
store. If you need more than two authenticated users,
then you can use either one because none of them
supports it out of the box. If you need to mesh
various components into an application, or if any part
of the application is not in rust, then you want data
space. You could potentially
implement a mesh of rust components in
shuttlers with some routing or
proxy, and that could be feasible
if those components use the same web framework
for Rust, but especially with shuttlers
special crates. It could get complicated very soon,
very early. If you want first class support
for rust then shuttlers are
leading and also
they offer background or long tasks and discord
bots. And at the moment if you'd like cron
like schedule actions, then you go with the taskbase. Stability and
ergonomics is better
with shuttlers because of their attribute macros
and their support for Rust as their only
programming language. But if you don't want any special crates
or macros, then you may want to go with data space as
well as if you need to use a custom version,
a special version or a special channel of rust
with those storage. If you do not want to
use a third party SQL
or NonSQl,
and if you do not want to adapt or
to use database or data store,
then you want shuttlers. Otherwise you
get perfect storage with data.
Those commercial plan for large
deployments going over the storage quotas
is not mentioned by data space yet, and it's only
planned by shuttle. The free sharing of applications
on the platform's website itself exists
only in data as well as the
commercial models well, which don't exist yet,
but they are planning paid marketplace
thank you for listening. I hope you will
look at both data space and shuttle rs and
enjoy them. Develop good applications, share them either on the
platform itself or on those git. Love rust.
Take care.