Saudi
2022. My name is Handoyo Sutanto. I am the CEO of
Lyrid. I'm so excited to be here today as this is
my first time speaking at Cloud native and let me tell you
a little bit about my self I'm a software engineer solution platform
engineer by true father of two and prior to starting
Lyrid I was a director of platform engineering.
I have spent more than 15 years building cloud solution from the ground
up. I build everything from a data center infrastructure to
a globally available applications and web services and
two years ago I started lit as an idea on how
to seamlessly integrate and deploy cloud infrastructure
using cloud agnostic technology while breaking
any reliance on any one cloud vendor. So in this talk
we will walk you through on what it takes to build a scalable
solution, applications or web services that
utilizes cloud agnostic design principle,
the four keys engineering decisions that we took to make it happen and
what is the outcome for us. And by the end of this talk
you will learn about the pros and cons of going cloud agnostic
and have more actionable tips on how to implement
cloud agnostic in your organization. If you learn anything
interesting, please tag me at hondus Twitter and
use the Con 42 hashtag. Let's start with
what does it mean to be cloud agnostic?
By its most basic definition, a cloud computing is
the delivery of services such as compute, databases and
networking over the Internet, offering faster
delivery and innovation to vendors like Google Cloud,
Microsoft Azure and Amazon Web Services.
But what does it mean to be cloud agnostic?
By definition, cloud agnostic is a strategic
process of using two or more public cloud for
your workload. Generally, before going cloud agnostic,
companies are restricted to one cloud vendor during their app
development and challenge with keeping the operational costs
low while maintaining scalability and availability.
While there are many reasons cloud agnostic can be great for
your business, youll first want to determine your specific
business needs. Let's walk through its benefit. The first one we
want to mention is that cloud agnostic creates freedom.
With Cloudagnostic, you're in control of all your tools,
making, tailoring and feature pairing seamless for
all your business needs. At Lyrid, our tooling
enables the deployment of user solutions in any cloud environment.
Depending on the business needs of our partners,
we give our users the freedom to access the tools
and the features they need whenever they please. Now, the second
benefit that we want to mention, cloudagnostic provides you with choices
as region, offering prices and all important factors
when it comes to choosing cloud providers. Implementing cloud
agnostic mindset. Youll will be able to make informed executions
on these factors and many, many more. It grants
flexibility to meet all your needs, whether it's financial,
functional or performance based. Having multiple
providers to depend on is critical in such a
changing it environment. This flexibility
is also apparent in solutions portability and streamlining
migration process. The third one we want to mention is that it
lets you scale when it's needed. Contrary to common
belief, this type of platform making scaling
so much easier, especially for complex enterprise applications.
Youll infrastructure scales with your solution without
the need to configure or write a new code.
We've been doing this and we've been helping our partners leverage
Kubernetes auto scaling solutions with some benefits of
this including automatic application management,
a decrease in engineering maintenance and significant
executions in overall costs. Fourth one,
it provides long term savings.
Cloudagnostic strategy lets you lower long
term costs without forfeiting data efficiency.
The flexibility of savings multiple cloud platform under your
belt allows you to switch providers or even
see service with a provider if a better deal comes along.
Now let's take a deeper dive into what
are key decisions when it comes to going cloud agnostic development.
And before you start coding a single line of code,
the first point is that youll technology stack matters.
Pick the right technologies and as an
engineer, your goal is to deliver a timely solution
to the stakeholder within budgets.
Consider your executions, compute, storage, database and
network as the lifeblood of your application infrastructure.
Make sure you know what you're putting into your lifeblood and
choose the one that are not restricted to your
application. One of the biggest value
proposition that cloud company have is the ability to create
any infrastructure with extremely low
costs that bypass the barrier of entry.
However, some of these services implement technology stack that does
not exist on any other cloud platform.
A good example of this is database that only run on certain
cloud vendors. These services provide the most seamless integration to
their services. However, they also have the least migrable
database services to other cloud providers.
So I like to start small with bring your own distributed
database and then extend.
Choosing this technology doesn't mean that you'll compromise in
scale in the future. So we pick technologies that can expand seamlessly
with no downtime and some of these open source technology with
high availability and redundancy options are the way to go
here. And there are many technologies that is built
on top of that and that can ensure that your data can
also be distributed across many cloud platforms. Once you
start putting your solutions together, you'll want to
make sure you start with abstraction on libraries that you
think youll need to be migrated or run on multiple platform.
So my next point will be use abstraction library
as much as possible. An abstraction pattern
library is a code that is common in solution development that allows
developers to interact with a system using a more
generic interface and one example of
this is using object relational mapping or ORM.
ORM itself is a programming technique for converting data between
type system using object oriented programming language.
Some of the example if you use Prisma for node JS,
SQL alchemy for Python or entity framework
for. Net you have used these types of abstraction
and at layerit we use ORM and other abstraction
databases layer for our messaging use system as well.
For our job distribution for Google, pubsub, AWSQ,
SWS, SQS and Redis we have been able to
convert between cloud services for some of our service that
requires a more global distribution and on
premise deployment in an instant. So once
you have built a concept and have a running application,
what do you have to do next and for the next
key decisions that we actually have to build is we would like you
to embrace the distributed architectures and
design for replaceable and migratable microservices.
For cloud solution deployment, we recommend utilizing
distributed computing because it embraces redundancy
as well as high availability. Modern development
has always advocated for smaller component that can be
easily run on any system with a distributed storage system
continuously making data copies, allowing a great deal
of flexibility around costs, time to recovery,
durability and more. They are extremely tolerant
to compared failures. Outright distributed architectures
have become more standardized in the developer world with the help
of a massive cloud adoption, along with the wide adoption of technologies
like docker containers during development?
Ask yourself these questions. Can this same code
or API run on another cloud platform? If not,
why is that? What do you have to do to mitigate before
you're going to production? And for the last keys
engineering decision that we made to be a cloud agnostic company
is to build and keep up with your migration plan.
At this point you have all your solutions in place
and are probably only using one deployment
region and cloud services for your application. So the next
thing is to come up with your plan b, a high level
option to adopt a cloud migration strategy with one or more
cloud vendors in order to quicken workload and data
migration to another cloud. However,
this option can be costly at first and may not be critical to running
your business executions initially. But if you build
your solution using the first predecisions above, we can
always start small and design a manageable plan and identify
important pieces that can be easily migrated. As you're running your solution,
pick a target cloud vendor or technology to migrate to and
test and run youll migration once a month or so.
We like to put ourselves as a case study on a
company that implements all those four key decisions.
We would like to show our current technology stack infrastructures
and with this we were able to automate, design,
control and distribute our platform to multiple cloud
vendor. As we mentioned earlier in the talk,
we chose Kubernetes as the base of our platform.
Kubernetes is an open source container orchestration
system for automating, software deployment, scaling and
management and for storage and data.
MongoDB and Minio are our go to internal database and
storage. They both are excellent open
source technology that can provide the flexibility to be distributed anywhere
along with redundancy and availability and
backups that are required for us to run our operations.
For database redundancy we rely on building MongoDB
container instance inside all the Kubernetes cluster that we maintain.
This is to build a globally distributed read only cache.
This proved to be very benefits for our end users
experience and something that is crucial for
us is the ability to distribute our jobs and build
and deployment globally. This scenario we use Google
Pubsub as one of our job distribution infrastructure,
but internally we can easily switch between Google Pubsub to
a self hosted redis pub sub for
our development. These are the base of our
infrastructure that runs our platform and with this we have created
a distributed deployment engine along with an API layer
that connects with outside services to create a public
cloud compute abstraction. So we
made our platform with a goal so that it's easier for anyone
to build using these same four principle.
So let us show you how you can accomplish this in a quick demo of
our platform. In this demo I will show how alert uses
these four keys and where they show up in our platform.
Our platform is free for everyone to try what I'm doing here, so just sign
up and log into it and let's deploy alert pre made
cloud agnostic application. The technology on
what you pick here matters and these are some of the example of
application that we have published the template on GitHub to
help accelerate your development. Feel free to check back in
the future for more pre built templates, but for today
I will deploy a next JS application into our platform
and what this does is that it will create a clone of
our pure next JS code that does not contain any
cloud library or signature. So let's click deploy
here and what happened in the background here is that the template
is copied into our minio backend object storage and
we start to distribute the build jobs across our cluster.
I think youll pretty familiar with some of these logs that these
are built container build jobs on our distributed
docker container engines that lives inside our cluster.
The distribution of the jobs is handled by Google Pubsub,
but it's also working on Redis pubsub for our clients that
requires more security in their environment.
Now once the build is complete, our platform will
start the distribution of the code to the public cloud vendor that we support.
This is where our platform does the heavy lifting of creating and
configuring the appropriate public cloud services. Without the
need for you to know a lot about AWS, Google Cloud
or even Kubernetes. We create our cloud specific deployments
and abstract approximates to you so that
you only need to focus on what's important to you, which is your
application. And when this is
done we provide you with alert API endpoint and this is
a publicly available HTTP endpoint that is running an API
gateway into the execution of all
the deployed application services. Let's open it and check our
splash page if it's working. And by default this only runs
in our layered cloud platform. I will show how to set
a policy to this endpoint so that it utilizes other clouds.
But let's download the code to take a deeper dive into the next JS code.
And I extracted and opened the folder in visual studio code
and you can already see the structure of the code right here.
Other than our definition file, we are not requiring you to download
any packages that are cloud specific. The package JSON
file shows that this is a pure next JS application and
the only file that's required for us is our alert definition
file that tells the platform on how to build and pack the services.
Now if you know a little bit about next JS, the code structure is
pretty standard with styles public and pages folder.
And in this code we added an API endpoint that can
show the current next JS node JS version as
well as the unique environment of Lyrid that
can return which cloud environment that is currently running on.
Now let's get back into our UI to set the policy and for
deployment and execution. But before that we
need you to set the credential that will be used under youll cloud
account. This is an IAM role to be configured in your cloud
account and our documentation provides a list of permission
that you will need to set in order to interact with alert platform.
Now we can set the executions platform to all in which
it will run the service on any cloud and this policy to
create a distributed application on all public cloud vendors.
In this page you can also set different regions for Google
and AWS. This will be the region used
to deploy the first service in that cloud and
the closer it is to the bulk of youll user, the better your user experience
will be. Let's jump back into the web browser and check the endpoint
and let's execute the version. Get endpoint and zoom a bit
here. As I refresh really fast you can
see that it is load balancing between AWS, Google and our own Kubernetes
cluster. Congratulations, you have successfully created a
migrable and distributed application. Now let's do a
quick check what we deploy on AWS by going to your AWS
lambda page. And now let's
check on the monitors and let's
do the same thing over in Google Cloud.
Now keep that in mind that everything you see running in our platform is also
running inside our Kubernetes platform that we maintain and we are working on
the ability to connect also to your own
clusters. There are additional things that you have to put into consideration
when you're implementing a cloud agnostic solutions and
the first being security and compliance.
I often get asked how do youll make all these
solutions secure? And one of the
issues that often come up in multiple cloud environment is that you
can no longer rely on one cloud security
mechanism anymore. So in this scenario,
zero trust security becomes a very important concept
for us. This is a security model
where you never trust and always verify.
Devices should never be trust by default even
if they are connected to a permission network such as corporate lan or
previously verified certificate and HTTPs on
everything is always a good first step to secure your communication
between machines. We build and use multiple Kubernetes
native servers that integrate with Cert manager. Let's encrypt
to authenticate and verify communications between
all our production machines and some implement other
security measures such as active container scanning,
hardening, role based authentication
for the Kubernetes cluster that we maintain and many many more.
The second consideration is the integration costs.
Adding more deployment environment into the platform will
cost us some more development time.
Just remember, even if they are providing the same technologies,
there are always little differences on how one cloud vendor delivers
its solution. One example that we encountered here is our Kubernetes
AWS deployment development. We noticed that the load balancer
uses Kubernetes ingress services, uses public DNS
instead of public ips. Monitoring is also
a very cloud specific function that can be a bit challenging to create,
specifically one that spans on any cloud infrastructures.
And in order to overcome this we utilize Prometheus Grafana for our
infrastructure metrics. Considering that runs within our internal
environment ecosystem. During our platform development,
we made sure every part of our infrastructure ecosystem
is ready to be fed into our Prometheus infrastructure.
Considering this is where we made our decision on where
and how to automate our infrastructure expansion. All the
data that is coming into our Prometheus platform and
just like databases and storage executions, there are other infrastructure monitoring tools
that spans multiple cloud vendors and able to run on
any cloud infrastructure. Just like everything else in the world,
nothing is perfect, not even cloud agnostic. Now cloud
agnostic is seen by many as the future for cloud computing
and while there are benefits, you should also consider these drawbacks.
The first is being that it does increase complexity to your
system and one disadvantage is that by
gaining flexibility and features, your solution can
become more complex and require more management.
Portable solution and technology support come at
the price of increasing complexity. Now keep that
in mind. The second is that you have to consider is that there is
a slightly higher upfront cost that youll may incur in your development.
Now, while cloud agnostic does have the potential to save you money exponentially,
in the future, you will face a slightly higher upfront cost.
These come from various things like when you're not utilizing some of
the feature of a certain platform, but you need the properties
of the others. These can potentially add to the price,
and data transfer costs can also become more
expensive. With the cloud agnostic approach, sometimes you'll
face unexpected data transfer which can be also confusing
to predict. However, all these additional costs are manageable.
If you set your budgeting accordingly and you
have to quickening your development, you'll want to take the time
to examine your organization's need to determine if a
cloud agnostic approach is beneficial to your need. And in
conclusion, there are many benefits to going cloud agnostic
for youll company. But just like everything else, you have to tailor and
evaluate the pros and cons specific to your company's need.
And just let's recap the four key decision design
principle that we ran to make our platform cloud agnostic.
And they are number one, as picking technologies that you
can control. Number two, we use abstraction libraries as
much as possible. Number three, we embrace the distribution architectures
and design for migrable microservices. Number four,
we build and keep up our migration plans
and we have followed these four key design principles to build our platform
and we here at Lyrid use this platform to help companies
to build their solution using the same cloud agnostic principles.
So let us know if you have any question, concern or comments.
We're hanging out at the discord channel. Feel free
to say hi to us or email us. Email me at htanto
at lyrid IO or drop me a message on my Twitter and LinkedIn.
Thank you so much for watching my presentation and we hope you learn a
thing or two about building cloud agnostic solutions.