Hello and welcome to my talk. My name is Michael Birch. I'm a senior Rust
engineer working at Aurora Labs. I've been working with Rust since 2018,
but before that I was doing functional programming in Scala. I love
how Rust is an imperative programming language, but takes inspiration from some
of the best features of functional programming, some of which we'll talk about today.
My goal with this talk is to show how patterns in functional programming can be
used in rust to write code that is easier to test,
maintain, and reused in multiple applications. In your tech stack.
In particular, I'm focusing on how we applied these ideas at Aurora to
do what it says in the title, turn our main smart contract into
an indexer. I hope this talk will be both accessible
and interesting to blockchain developers, rust experts, and functional programming
enthusiasts. Though each group may find different parts of the talk more
or less informative in terms of an outline, I'll begin
by getting everyone up to speed on the basics of blockchain
technology. Only what you need to understand what I mean when I'm talking
about smart contracts, indexers, and how they relate to one another.
Next, I'll talk about the key features of the rest programming language
that enable us to do this smart contracts into indexers trick.
And finally, we'll do a deep dive into some real code that showcases
how these ideas were applied at Aurora.
So, to get started, let's talk about blockchain basics. What is
a blockchain? A blockchain is an appendonly data structure
with immutable history. What I mean by this is
the data structure can only have additional data added to
it, and once something has been added to the blockchain, it cannot
be changed. Up on the slide, we have sort of the classic
depiction of a blockchain. The squares in the diagram
are the so called blocks which represent the individual chunks
of data in the data structure, and the arrows show how the
blocks are connected to one another. Hence blockchain.
This data structure you can imagine extending infinitely to the
right by adding a new block with can arrow pointing to the previous block.
As I mentioned, the history is immutable because the connections
actually depend on what data came before it.
So you cannot change that earlier data and still maintain that
connection. This is cryptographically secured, but the details
are not important for what we're talking about today. So you
might ask, what goes into these blocks? And the answer is
transactions. For typical blockchain applications,
you have transactions that are interpreted in some kind
of virtual machine, which causes some kind of global state to change.
For example, in the case of Ethereum, which is a relatively large
blockchain platform you may have heard of before, the state consists of all
of the accounts and contracts that exist on the platform,
and the virtual machine is the ethereum virtual machine. The EVM
transactions can be things like send three ETh to some address
or call some method on a contract
that was previously deployed. And speaking of smart
contracts, let's talk about those. A smart contract
is a program that can run in the virtual
machine of whatever blockchain you're talking about. Up on
the slide. I've got sort of a simple example where
in the first transaction you deploy some contract,
it gets included into the state, and then in a later
block you have a new transaction that is calling a method,
in this case, the method foo on that contract.
Smart contracts can do all kinds of things. They're limited only by the
power of the virtual machine that they operate in. For example,
smart contracts can represent tokens, maybe even tokens
that are tied to some real world currency, so called stablecoins.
Smart contracts can be marketplaces where you can trade
between those different tokens, or they can be escrow lockers
to facilitate some kind of exchange. Maybe even in the real world,
smart contracts can be validated storages
where you can prove that off can events happened,
say for example in the leaderboard for blockchain enabled games.
Or even a smart contract could be the
entire virtual machine of some other blockchain platform.
And this might sound crazy, but it's an important part of this story
that we'll come back to later. For now, let's keep being with our blockchain
basics. All of this is just about a single copy
of the blockchain and how it evolves. But in a real blockchain
platform, the blockchain is distributed and
continuously built by multiple participants that are
decentralized, the so called nodes of the network,
and the transactions are submitted by users.
The nodes eventually agree on the blockchain that they're all collectively
building up to some point using a consensus algorithm.
Again, the details are not very important for what we're talking about here,
but suffice it to say the blockchain is
only eventually consistent, and getting data about
the blockchain off of the network is slow because of the decentralized nature.
So how do users actually get the data off of the
blockchain? They interact with some kind of RPC.
Usually that RPC is run by a third party service, but users
can choose to run their own code that are a part of the network and
still expose an RPC interface to themselves. The key point
here is that getting data off of the blockchain is slow because
it requires multiple network calls, and even still
because of the decentralized nature, it's only eventually consistent.
So something that happens in one node may take a long time to propagate and
be visible by any given RPC for a particular user.
So to help address that problem, we have this idea of an indexer.
Given the wide range of functionality of smart contracts,
it's not always efficient to query a blockchain platform directly
against its RPC. There's just no way for a single RPC
to capture all of the different possible variations on
the states that different smart contracts could hold. And indexers
help address this by having a specialized view of the blockchain state which
is optimized for particular queries.
For example, a block Explorer like Etherscan, which is
the biggest block explorer for the Ethereum blockchain.
It'll show you all of the tokens that are held by
each user. Up on the slide, I've taken a screenshot of ether scan where
I've selected some random account and you can see it holds 23
different kinds of tokens. This kind
of query would be very difficult or maybe even impossible
to do with just the RPC because the mapping
is actually reversed on chain. Each token knows
the list of balance holders, but there is no
index for all of the tokens held by each of the
addresses. So to solve that problem, Etherscan has
an indexer which maintains that reverse lookup and makes
the queries efficient when a user visits their website.
So the way to think about how indexers fit into the
story here is you have some user talking to some
application UI which is talking to an indexer,
and the indexer is fed data from an RPC and the indexer
is maintaining its own internal specialized view of the state.
Indexers, like I've been saying, help create low latency experience for
users or web, two experiences in the sort of blockchain
jargon. Since the indexer needs to populate the
database from blockchain data, it needs to understand what state
of the smart contract is important. Therefore,
smart contracts and their indexers are always related to
one another. So can idea we might have is
to have a single source code, single code base
that contributes both to our smart contract and our
indexers. Again, because they're so closely related to one another,
this would be great since it would mean less maintenance.
There's just less code overall to maintain. And even better
still, it would make our indexer more powerful than your average indexer,
because it would have access to all of the smart contract's logic,
and it would be able to do things like simulate an entire transaction
off chain, and that gives you free low latency
feedback to users about potential errors. So this is
what we're aiming for. This is our idea. How are we going to accomplish
that using rust? So there's a few key concepts that
we want to take a look at. First of all is different compilation
targets. So up on the slide I've got links
to the official rust documentation if you want to sort of take
a deep dive and read more about this yourself. But at a high level
you have the rest compiler giving you some kind of
output from your code, some kind of executable output from your code.
In the typical case, it's an executable for whatever
operating system you're running on Linux, Windows, Mac,
and maybe even specialized to the specific hardware of your machine,
say it's an arm or x 86. But there are
more executable targets than just these. In particular,
webassembly is an important one for this story, because the
blockchain platform that Aurora uses has webassembly
as its virtual machine. So on the slide
I include the commands that you would use in rust to
install the webassembly target compilation
target, and then how you would select that targets to build
your project.
Now, given that you can have these different
targets, it's useful to be able to write code that selects
or is specialized to a particular compilation target.
Conditional compilation allows us to do this.
Again, I've got a link up on the slide which you
can do some further reading on if you're interested. But long
story short, the syntax looks like the example I've got
up there. So we have some function Foo, and the implementation
of Foo depends on if we're compiling to wasm or not.
Again, this is useful because it lets us make specific choices
that only work on that architecture. So in the case of webassembly,
you have this notion of host functions, which we'll talk a lot about later.
But host functions are functions that the host, that is the computer
running your webassembly virtual machine exposes for
the WASM module to use, whereas in a normal application
those don't exist. But in a normal application you do have
access to disk, for example, so you could use that to access storage.
Now, the drawback of conditional compilation is that it's
a little verbose, and it makes the implementation a little hard to
read, right. You can see, the function foo maybe looks
a little awkward because there are these two totally separate branches.
Additionally, because you have these separate branches, it's a little tedious to
use inside of an IDE. Your iDe will usually
only show you one branch of the conditional compilation at a time,
so you have to sort of switch back and forth between them when you're trying
to write code for it. But fortunately,
we can minimize the amount of conditional compilation that we're doing by
abstracting most of our code over the
platform specific effects.
And to do that, we have this idea in rust called type generics.
So the whole point of a type generic is you
write a function, in this case get balance,
which takes in some type, but we don't care what it is,
we only care that it has a particular interface,
and that interface is defined using a trait,
and indicated in the syntax they are using a so called trait bound.
So we have in the brackets
between there the angle brackets I O
says that whatever this type I is, it must implement
the IO interface defined by the IO trait.
In this example, I'm keeping it pretty simple with just the read and write methods,
and the type signatures are maybe a little suspect. You can imagine maybe that there
should be some kind of option or result involved in the read, but for
the sake of example, let's suppose this is what it looks like. The point
is that when you have this type generic, you don't care what the specifics of
the implementation are, you can still make use of those methods in the
implementation of your function. So in the case of get balance, we're imagining reading
some bytes out of the state and interpreting them as a
U 128 value. So this get balance
function is now totally generic over anything
that implements I o. And in particular we can imagine implementing
this for webassembly as well as native
code. And these would look a little bit different because of the different
implementations that are possible in those targets.
So for example, on the indexer side maybe our implementation would be reading
to a database on the disk, while on the webassembly side it
would be calling to a host function like I mentioned before. But either way,
after we've done those implementations, the getbalance function
is now available and identical in
both situations. So this code is generic and
reusable in both cases. Now,
of course, this particular example is a little bit silly, because get
balance is just a one liner function, so you
probably would imagine it wouldn't be that big of a deal to duplicate that logic
in the two places instead of jumping through all of these type
generic hoops. But this idea
scales, right? It doesn't matter how complicated the get balance function is,
and at some point it's complicated enough that you don't want to have to duplicate
it into both places.
So this is the whole point of the
functional programming patterns. Let's take a step back and just
talk about the big ideas here, because this really isn't about just rust
or just blockchain. This is programming style in general.
The code concept is when you're writing code
for environment specific effects like reading and writing from state,
you can abstract over them in your core
business logic to make it pure. That is to
say, it doesn't depend on the particular environment, it doesn't depend on
any compilation target specific effects,
and by factoring those things out, pushing them into
a trait, and only having those trait implementations has the boundaries of your applications.
The result is most of your code is easier to
test and easier to maintain because it can
be tested using in memory
structures, right? Just different implementations of those traits
that don't even actually do the effects.
So in the case of storage, right, you could have
just a simple hash map in memory that you're reading
and writing for your
tests, but still be able to test all of your business logic code,
because again, it is agnostic to the details of that implementation,
while in the production implementation you're actually using
a real database. And again, all of the code
that is being used with that database has still already
been tested in this in memory environment.
The other nice thing about all of this is
this code is easier to reason about. You don't have to worry
about are there going to be random side effects
in particular parts of the code because they're all
explicitly given in the type signatures. You can't
do I O without having the I O trait
present. If you're writing code that is generic,
overall possible compilation target. So whenever
you see a piece of code that doesn't have the I O
trait on it, you know it's not doing any I O.
And conversely, when you do see a function that has the I
O trait, you know that some state is being used by that function.
This is something that you might have heard before, has the principle of
least authority, where the idea is that code should only have access
to the minimum amount of capabilities that it actually
needs to function. So code that doesn't need I O doesn't have
I O, and similarly for other effects. Finally,
this code is easier to reuse, and that is kind of
the whole point of this talk. Once your code is
written in this abstract way, you can use the same code
for any different application that
you need. So in the case that we're talking about, it's a smart contract and
an indexer, but you can imagine that the same kind of thing would work.
Say, if you had a web application and a mobile
application, you could have the same rust code base at its
core and compile it to webassembly. That gets used
as part of a web app or down into
a mobile code and used in your mobile app as well.
And again, it would be the same idea where if you're abstracting over
the FX, you don't need to worry about whether you're talking
to a javascript wrapper in the browser or an
Android operating system, for example. But all
of that aside, let's get back to our
main topic here. So at Aurora, we made
use of these ideas, like I've been saying, to make an
indexer out of a smart contract. So what is Aurora?
Aurora is an ethereum scaling solution built on top of the near blockchain
platform. I've got a couple links up on the slide if you want to
read more about that and dig deeper.
That's available. But for today's story,
the part that is most important is Aurora's
core product is this EVM, the Ethereum virtual machine we talked about before.
But it's deployed as a smart contract on top of near uses
webassembly as its blockchain VM,
which means it's super powerful. Rust compiles to it,
no problem, like we saw earlier. And you can write an implementation
of the EVM in Rust, compile it to Webassembly. Now you have
it as a smart contract on Nier, and that enables
this whole scaling solution where now you're using Nier to run
the EVM transactions instead of Ethereum itself.
So you're benefiting from near's better
scaling, the sharding and consensus and all this stuff.
But again, out of scope for today,
the most important detail to continue our story is Aurora
claims to be compatible with Ethereum tooling,
including the metamask wallet, the hard
hat developer tool. And if these
are not familiar to you, don't worry about it. Suffice it to say, these are
tools that are very common in the Ethereum ecosystem,
and they rely on a particular RPC, right? They rely on the
RPC that Ethereum nodes would expose. So for Aurora to
be compatible with them, it must also expose that same RPC interface.
So there's sort of an obvious implementation on how to do this.
We know that this thing is deployed on Nier, and Nier has its own RPC.
So you can imagine a proxy which translates Ethereum
RPC requests into the
corresponding near RPC request that's talking to the Aurora contract,
and then translates the response back. But as we've mentioned,
this is quite slow. It involves multiple network hops,
and so you may end up with lower latency with a higher latency
than you want. The other issue is some of the RPC
requests on Ethereum are fairly beefy.
You can ask an Ethereum RPC node to simulate entire
transactions, and if you're trying to do that on
a network node inside of webassembly,
it can be additional latency on top of the
just simple network latency.
So getting to the main point here,
the way we can solve this is by writing an indexer
that is actually able to function has this ethereum
RPC. So again, because it needs to do
this whole transaction simulation, needs to have
all of the functionality of the aurora contract baked into
it, and we're going to use the
exact methods that we've just been talking about to make this possible.
So all of this code is available on GitHub, it's all
open source. I've got a link up on the slide if you ever want to
go and take a look at it yourself. But we'll take a look at a
few snippets and get a sense of what's going on here. So the
code that's up on the screen right now is the
real code out of the actual Aurora engine. So here's the
actual implementation of get balance that I sort of gave a toy
example of earlier. It's pretty similar to the toy example,
with a few extra error handling things going on.
And similarly for the setbalance,
again, notice the IO type generic,
right. We are using a read and a write on type
that we don't actually know its concrete value, we only know its interface,
and we can compose these together into more complicated functionality.
So the add balance function uses both get and set together
to add an amount to a balance. But again, you can see the
I o trait is present so that it can be passed along to
the other smaller functions.
So let's look at what the implementation of this I o trait actually looks
like. So this is for the webassembly side. Notice that
the main struct we're interested in is just a singleton struct. It's just called
runtime, as in the near runtime, as in it is running inside
of wasm, and it's a singleton because it doesn't
actually have any fields or state that are important. The implementation
comes from the host functions that the near runtime
exposes to us. So you can see in this implementation we're calling this storage read
function. It's all fairly low level and the details
aren't super important. The point is that we know that this host function
exists and we can call it, and that gives us access to
the storage. And the same thing, on the
right side, there's a host function we can call it. We're passing in some pointers
because it has to do with the host, reading out values from
the WASM memory and writing the value
into the actual underlying storage that the near node has.
But again, details aside, it is implemented
using these host functions and it satisfies the interface that we've
defined. Now on the other side,
the indexer side, this is native code, and it's a little more
complicated. We have the last field, there is a database
handle to a RocksDB database, because that's where the storage
is actually going to be located in the case of the indexers. And I see
a few other fields as well, because we want there to be conditional features
that the RPC implementation has as
compared to just smart contract. So for example,
we needed to have access to the whole history of the state,
not just the state, at any given moment in time. The reason is because
when a user is accessing the Ethereum RPC, they can
actually specify previous blocks to simulate their transaction against.
And similarly, because we are interested in the
potential of simulating transactions without actually committing them to the state,
we need all of the changes to happen in memory instead
of being eagerly written to the database. So that's what the
transaction diff and output parts of the structure for.
So this is what the read storage implementation looks
like. Again, the details are not super important.
What matters is that this is satisfying. Exactly the same interface,
but the implementation details are different. So in this case we are taking
a look at the in memory changes first.
Again, because they weren't committed to the database, and if it's not
present in there, that is, the key hasn't been written before in
this transaction. Then we have to go back and look at the database. And the
database has an iterator in it, because we are going backwards
through the history to find the key value pair that's
relevant. Similarly, on the right storage side,
same kind of same point,
right. It implements the interface that we've defined, but in
this case it's writing to this in memory diff instead of writing to the
database, or in the case of the webassembly calling
a host function. But what's very
cool about this, and you might be
know Michael, there are webassembly
standards that tell you what interfaces should look like for interacting
with storage. You don't necessarily have to jump through all these hoops. But the point
is that this isn't just about storage,
it's about any kind of environment
specific effect. Storage is one that we commonly think
about. But in the blockchain world there are other effects
that we care about as well, and they have analogies in other
contexts too. So for example, the environment variables
are things like what block height are we executing in, who signed
this transaction, what time is it? All this kind of stuff is all set in
the environment of the transaction's execution and is
available in the webassembly contracts from host functions.
But we still need to be able to access that stuff when we're simulating
the transaction locally. So we have a trait that exposes all
of the things that a user could potentially ask for,
and we have a separate implementation for the indexer.
In that implementation, the information comes out of
the actual block that we're consuming. Or in the case of
a user submitted simulated transaction, we just fill in default
values for these. But you could also imagine an
implementation where these were literally environment variables, as in system
environment variables, right. Say we were writing some kind of CLI
application to interact with this instead of making it as an RPC.
Then you could read environment variables as part of that
command line call to fill in this as well. Right.
And that would be another implementation, which again our sort
of core business logic is agnostic to, but opens up the opportunity
for making these other applications. Similarly,
there's this idea of promises, which is actually a near
specific concept on
most blockchains. Well, specifically on Ethereum,
calls to other contracts are synchronous. They happen all in
the same transaction and all at the same time in the same block.
But on Nier, calls to other contracts are asynchronous.
This has to do with the sharding model. Again, the details aren't super important,
but suffice to say, this is another kind of effect that
exists in the webassembly smart contract context,
but doesn't exist in the case that we're running an indexer,
right? Because the indexer only looks at the
Aurora smart contract itself, it doesn't index the whole
near environment. So it's actually not able to simulate these
cross contract calls, but we can still factor them
out as a trait and put in no op implementations
for the case of the indexer. And this also works fine because
most transactions on Aurora are contained within the EVM.
Like I mentioned, the EVM tends to be this synchronous
all in one block type transaction. So most of the time we
don't actually need these, but sometimes we do,
and therefore we need the code to handle it and we're still
able to factor it out and do it sort of for real in quotation marks
and webassembly and just no ops in the indexer,
and have it also work totally fine.
And all of this sort of builds up to huge
complicated functions, right? So this is just the interface
of the submit function. This is sort of the main entry point
for users when they send an EVM transaction
to Aurora. And so you can see we've composed together all these
different kinds of effects. We've got the I O for storage access,
the environment variables that are present, and the possibility
of calling other near contracts.
Now if I left the implementation off, because again
the details aren't really what's important here, but the
point is that this is a relatively large,
relatively complicated function with multiple lines of code, and having
to duplicate it between both the indexer
and the smart contract would have been too big of
a maintenance burden and wouldn't have made sense. But because
we can write this abstract code that is reusable for both,
it enables us to have this indexer as
RPC. So as a final
point here, this is what the actual RPC
code looks like, or part of it anyways.
So there's a particular RPC method for Ethereum RPCs called
ETh underscore estimate gas. This is one of those transaction
simulation RPC methods that I've been referring to.
And this is sort of, it's only
a snippet, it's not the full implementation, but this is sort of the main points
of what's going on. We have to set up the
structs that implement the traits that we've set out,
right. So this is the environment
variables. You can see we're setting default values because it's
just fixed. In this case it's just a simulation. And then
we also have the engine access struct
that we saw on an earlier slide, and we're accessing it at a particular
block height and transaction position because again the user can specify
those things in their request. And the actual implementation
of this, which I've left off the slide because again the details
aren't important is a closure
that accepts this I O object. So now it's got access to the MV object
and the I O object, and it can call methods like submit. And again,
the point is that it's not duplicating any
of that complicated logic that exists in
sort of our functional programming generic core.
It just calls the method submit and then does something with the result.
So in conclusion,
at the highest level, the thing that
I want you to take away from this talk is that you can write your
business logic in a way that uses pure
reusable code by abstracting away platform specific
effects. And as a nice side effect, this code is
actually easier to test and to maintain.
In this particular talk, we were using Rust as our programming
language of choice, and Rust can accomplish this using traits
and type generics along with a little bit of conditional compilation.
And for the specific example of this that we talked about today,
it was in the blockchain context where Aurora has
the EVM smart contracts that is able to also be
an indexer and share a code base, and this enables
their low latency RPC
for Ethereum compatibility. But as I mentioned before,
there are other possible applications for this. For example, using the same
code in web and mobile applications, I'm sure you can come up with
other examples based on your own fields of interest.
Maybe you're working in embedded devices and you want to share a code base between
the embedded version and say, the simulated
version of your hardware, et cetera.
Again, the main point is functional programming patterns
enable you to reuse code in a way you may not be able
to otherwise. Thank you all
for your attention. Got some links up on the slide here. If you
want to read more about near or Aurora. If you want to learn more about
me, you can get in touch with me directly on Telegram at BirchMD.
Or if you want to take a look at other code that I've worked on,
you can check out my GitHub under that same username. And I also have
a blog that I occasionally write to on my website,
Typedriven CA, and I write about mostly rust and
mirror, but some other stuff occasionally as well.
Thank you for your time. See you later.