Hi, I'm Taslan Graham and welcome to my talk on automated
web accessibility testing using playwrightjs
and Ox core.
First, a little bit about myself. I am a full stack software
engineer from Jamaica. I primarily develop web
applications and I am mostly interested and focused
on node and JavaScript technologies.
What's on the agenda for this presentation? First, we will
look at what is accessibility? Why is accessibility
important? We will also look at the web content accessibility
guidelines WCAG. We will
also look at the WCAG principles of accessibility.
We will look at common accessibility issues. We will
take a look at what is accessibility testing? And then we
will finally look at automating accessibility testing.
So what is accessibility?
Software? Accessibility refers to the design and development practices
that make digital applications, website and software
interfaces usable and navigable by individuals
with diverse abilities and disabilities. It involves
ensuring that all users, including those with visual,
auditory, motor or cognitive impairments,
can interact with software comfortably and effectively,
thus providing equal access to information and
functionality. Accessibility also deals
with how websites are structured. Are they using proper semantic
HTML? Are they easily navigable with assistive
technologies? Now, why is
accessibility important?
First, inclusivity and equal opportunity.
So when you
design with accessibility in mind, you are able to create
a software or an application that is more inclusive to a
wider range of users, regardless of any challenges that they may
have.
Accessibility is also good because it makes it
easier for assistive technologies to be used to navigate your
website or your application. When you design with accessibility
in mind, you also expand your user base because now
your software or your website, your application,
it is now accessible to a wider audience
of users. Also, it improves
user experience. So many of the features of
accessibility is beneficial to all users and not only
users with some form of disabilities such as for
example, if you were to add alternative text to images
that is both beneficial to normal users and users who may
have visual impairment.
Accessibility also helps with search engine optimization.
When you develop with accessibility in mind and you follow certain accessibility
practices such as ensuring that all HTML
pages have a title and
other practices such as ensuring that images have can alternative
text, you usually get better
search engine optimization and then search engines
will actually rank your websites higher.
Finally, accessibility is a legal requirement.
Accessibility is a legal requirement in some countries.
The web content accessibility guidelines so
the Web content accessibility guidelines WCAG are
technical standards on web accessibility. Developed by the
Worldwide Web Consortium, the guidelines aim
to make websites, apps, electronic documents, and other digital
assets accessible to people with a broad range of
disabilities, including sensory, intellectual,
learning, and physical disabilities.
The WCAG has a set
of principles, a set of accessibility principles which
we should follow when we are implementing accessibility
into our applications and the principles of accessibilities
are one perceivable. This means that you
should make it simple for users to see and hear the content
in your application. You should present text alternative
for nontext content. You should provide
captions and alternatives
for multimedia content. You should create content
that can be presented without losing meaning when using assistive technologies
such as screen readers. Another principle
is operable. This means that you should make all functionality
accessible straight from the keyboard. You should give
users sufficient time to read and use the content that
is being displayed. You should avoid using content
that might trigger seizures.
You should also facilitate users to navigate and
find content easily on their web application.
Understandable. This means that you should build text
that is understandable and readable for users.
You should create content that appear and operates in a predictable
manner. You should also develop your application in a way that
helps users to avoid and correct errors.
Your application should also be robust. This means you
should maximize the compatibility of your application with
present and future tools.
Also, elements in your web application should have a start
and end tags and they should be nested according
to their specifications. You should also aim to provide
a name, role and value for nonstandard
user interface components.
Now, what are some common accessibility issues?
A common accessibility issue is missing alternative
text on images. Missing alternative text for images
is one of the most common accessibility issues in web design.
According to web Aim, 31.3% of
homepage banners actually miss actually does not have an
alternative text on their images.
Another accessibility issue is poor color contrast.
This is one of the most common accessibility issues noticed
on many websites. Poor contrast makes
it difficult to read content on your website.
Poor HTML heading structure improper use of
HTML headings, that's h one to h six,
can make reading your website content unorganized and very
confusing to navigate. Additionally,
assistive technologies such as screen readers uses headers
to navigate websites. Therefore, if you have improper
header header structure on your website or improper header
hierarchy, this will make navigating website using assistive
technology much more difficult for persons who rely on such technology.
Missing area attributes area
attributes are a set of attributes that can be added to HTML elements
to enhance the accessibility of web content. These attributes
provide additional information to assistive technologies such
as screen readers in understanding and interacting with web content.
Area attributes help to make dynamic and interactive web applications much
more accessible.
Missing form labels is another common accessibility
issue and when form
fields form input fields don't have a label,
it makes it difficult for users to understand what exactly
they are supposed to enter what information this form field is trying to capture,
and for users who rely on assistive technologies
such as screen readers, it becomes even more difficult as the
screen reader is unable to determine and inform the user of
the type of information that they are supposed to enter into a
particular form field.
Keyboard inaccessibility is also another common accessibility
issue and this is where websites or applications
are not navigable via keyboard input.
Also, not having a mobile responsive design is a form
of accessibility issue and this will make it an
unpleasant experience for persons who are using mobile devices
as they will not be able to properly access and use your
website. So now
we move on to understanding a bit about
accessibility testing and the first question we have to answer is
what is accessibility testing?
Accessibility testing deals with testing the features of a
web application in a ay that ensures that all users,
irrespective of most disabilities, will be able
to interact with the software to its full potential.
This includes allowing disabled users to perform all
key actions without external assistance
and making the application inclusive for all users.
So, with the general understanding of what is accessibility
testing, the next question to answer is what is automated
accessibility testing? Automated accessibility testing
can a website's underlying code and existing
content and flag errors based on the web content accessibility
guideline? It is important,
though, to note that automated accessibility testing
is not a replacement for manual test,
but it should be used in conjunction with
manual testing for a more holistic testing experience. And this
will allow you to capture unique accessibility
issues that an automated test cannot capture.
And also the automated test will allow you to easily capture
some common accessibility issues that
might be a bit more tedious to capture in a manual process.
Some of the common issues that accessibility test
that automated accessibility testing can capture
is missing area attributes, missing alternative
text and images, poor color contrast,
missing landmark labels, missing page titles, and these are to
name a few of the things that can be captured.
So now we move into some of the tools that we will
be using to perform automated accessibility
testing on a web application and the first tool to look at
is ax alley engine.
So Axe or Axecore is an accessibility
testing engine for web applications. It enforces
a number of rules and best practices to help you easily catch
and fix accessibility issues.
It's fast, secure, lightweight and was built
to seamlessly integrate with any existing test environment
so you can automate accessibility testing
alongside your regular functional testing and with this ability to
easily integrate it within an existing test
environment, makes it easy for you to introduce
accessibility to testing to an existing project.
The second tool we will be using is playwright. And playwright
is a framework for web test and automation,
and we can integrate playwright with Axecore to perform
automated accessibility testing.
All right, so now we will take a
look at how we can set up automated accessibility
testing in a project, and then
we will demonstrate how we can use that automated accessibility
testing to capture some accessibility issues.
And then we will look at how we can introduce that
accessibility testing as a part of our CI CD pipeline
in GitHub.
Okay, so we have this very simple website here,
and it actually has a number of accessibility issues.
And what we are going to do is we are going to implement the automated
accessibility testing as a part of our test suite in
the application so that we can identify
some of these issues. Now, as mentioned in
the presentation, the tools we will be using is Axecore
and playwright JS. So let's just take a quick look
at those. So I'm on the
GitHub page for oxcore,
and as it says here, axecore is an accessibility testing engine
for websites and other HTML based interfaces.
Also makes mention of the rules that axecore
checks, and it has different types of rules.
WCAG 2.02.12.
.2 it
also has a link to the
individual rules.
Each rule has an id, a description. It gives the impact
of that particular accessibility issue.
So it has three impact levels,
moderate, serious, and critical.
It also provides a
link to
a page where you can learn more about the particular issue.
You can see examples of cases where
it would pass, and also example of
cases where that particular issue would pop up.
So let's head back there. The other tool we will be using
is playwright,
and specifically we will be using playwright
test alongside Axecore playwright.
And Axecore playwright is a package that actually makes the axecore
engine available or accessible within
the playwright testing framework.
So let's head over to our code editor to get that
set up.
So the first thing I'm going to install is Axecore
playwright,
and then I'll install the playwright
package. So to do that, we actually say NPM init playwright.
At latest,
it will ask a series of questions. Which language am
I using? I say Javascript. Where do you
want to put my end to end test? I go with the default.
I won't add a GitHub action.
Do I want to install the browsers? No, I won't install the
browsers. I'll include that step as a part of the
actual execution of the test.
I'll choose no.
After we set up playwright, we'll notice a couple of
things being added to our code base.
So first we have a folder test for end to end
test as some simple test case.
There's also a test examples folder which has more functional test
in there. And it
has a playwright config JS file. And this is where we
actually configure the behavior of playwright.
So we tell it the test directory should
it execute in parallel. The reporter here this
is telling playwright how do we want to
have it actually report any accessibility
issues to us? And there's a number of options
we have list line junit Json HTML
I'll actually stick with the HTML.
I'll remove this section.
And the projects section is actually where playwright configures the
different browsers that the tests will actually get executed on.
So we have a configuration for Chrome, one for Firefox,
and one for Safari.
All right, so first thing I'll do is I'll make
an update to this file. I'm actually using ESM.
So I need to update this import statement and
update the export.
I'm also going to delete the functional test.
I'll rename the existing test.
So I'll call this home page since we will be testing the home page of
the website.
And I'll just replace
this with the actual test code.
So let me walk
through this. So what
we have here, we import the test and expect
from playwright. And we
went ahead and configured our test.
We then navigate to
the particular page of the website. It's actually the home page.
So we navigate to that page and then we actually set
up an instance of the axe builder.
And the axe builder is actually a class that you use to
configure the behavior of the accessibility testing.
And the most simplest form is actually what
we have here, which is just new Aux builder. We pass the page information.
So that's the page that playwright is currently on.
And then we call the analyze method. And the analyze
method will actually check this page against the different accessibility
rules. We store the results in a variable
accessibility scan results.
And then we have a simple expect statement
where we're expecting that the accessibility scan results
should be an empty array.
Now let's execute this test
by running NPX playwright test.
All right, so when we run the test, it actually prints
out, it prints out the issues
that it found. It prints it out to the terminal. However,
because we had indicated that we wanted the reporter to
be can HTML, it also opens
a web page where we can see more information
about the particular issues.
Let me zoom in a bit. So for each issue that
our accessibility test discovers,
to typically follow this pattern where it has a description
so looking at this first issue, the description is ensures
the contrast within foreground and background colors meets WCag
two wa minimum contrast ratio.
If we scroll down, we see that it has an id.
And this id actually makes it very easy for us to go
back to the axecore documentation and
find more information about that particular
accessibility issue. So if we head over here and
go to the list of rules,
we can actually find it by the id and
there's a link to further documentation explaining more
about this particular issue.
Also, there's a help URL
property in the results, the test results, and it provides
a link. And that link actually takes you to a web page
where you can learn more about that particular issue.
It gives more information. So it gives information
on the background color that's being used. Also gives
information on the foreground color that's been used. And it
mentions the contrast ratio. So the
expected contrast ratio for accessibility
is 4.5 to one. We can see here that the
actual contrast ratio of the website falls short.
And if we scroll down some more,
it also provides the HTML line of code
that was checked when this particular accessibility
issue was discovered. So this line of code here, where I have
a link with teams as
the label for that anchor,
that's the line of code where we actually discovered that contrast
issue. Now, if we scroll down, there's a
lot of contrast issues.
It's another issue. So this one is opensource.
Each HTML documents document contains
a non empty title element. And this is indicating that our
website page of our web page actually does not have
a title element. Once again,
it provides a URL to our
web page where we can learn more about this particular accessibility issue.
Provides an id that we can use to easily find this accessibility
issue. If we are looking at the axecore list of rules,
it shows the impact. So the impact.
There are three levels of impact,
serious, moderate and critical. So for a missing
HTML tag, a missing title tag,
it's actually an impact level of serious.
So that's pretty much a breakdown of how
playwright and axecore reports accessibility
issues that's discovered in your application. So I'm
going to head back over to my code editor
and I'm
going to open a pr with what we have here,
which is we have simply added the automated accessibility
testing. I'm going to open a pr, and then after opening
a pr, I'll also go ahead and add this test as
a part of a CD pipeline.
All right, so if we head over to a browser and
go to the git repository to
create the pr.
All right, so at this point, as you can see, there's nothing happening here
in terms of accessibility testing. So what we're going to do
next is actually add a GitHub workflow that
will make the accessibility testing a
part of our CI CD pipeline process.
So first add a GitHub folder.
We have a workflow file here called CI and
we're configuring it to run on
pull request. So whenever you open a pull request and whenever
you make subsequent commits to that pull request, this particular
GitHub action will get executed. We're running it
on an Ubuntu platform. We set up
node 18, go ahead and install our
dependencies. We will then start the
server, and then afterwards we will run the test. So that's
the general flow of how this particular GitHub
workflow will operate. We'll set up node
18, install our dependencies, and then start the server,
then execute our accessibility test.
So one more thing is we
need to have a test script npm
run test, just double checking that's actually there.
With this workflow now added
to our code, I'm going to commit this.
And what will happen is that this will result in
the accessibility test being executed on our pr
as a part of our CI CD process.
So know if
I head back over to my browser and go to
repository,
we now notice that on the pull request
we're actually seeing the test being executed.
So let me click on that's
and at this point it's installed in the different browsers.
So we can see here that the workflow got executed and the
accessibility test got executed as well.
And it discovered the different
accessibility issues that we have.
And once again it gives sufficient
explanation about each issue that's discovered.
It provides the impact level.
It also provides the HTML
code that's causing this violation.
It also provides the URL,
the help URL, which gives you more information about that
particular accessibility issue.
So we can see here that our accessibility test got executed
as a GitHub action, and what we could actually do
is upon resolving all the accessibility issues,
we could eventually configure our repository
to require that these tests to
require that this accessibility test successfully passes before we're
able to actually merge in a pull request.
However, I am not going to demonstrate that
as a part of this demo. So this actually concludes my
demo. So thanks for joining me as I
discuss automated web accessibility testing using playwright,
JS and Axcore. If you'd like to get in touch with me,
these are my social media handles on Instagram. It's at
taslang on Twitter. It's at taslanagraham on
LinkedIn. It's Taslan Graham, and my email is taslan@taslanagraham.com.
Thank you for joining and I hope you enjoyed this presentation.