Hello everyone, my name is Adhikar. I'm a senior product manager at
Worldpay. Today I'll be talking about aification
of financial services. It's a very interesting
topic and there's lots of information to absorb.
I'll try to keep it short, simple and hopefully sweet.
So let's begin. So before we understand the
AI repercussions in financial services, here's a quick
recap of what does AI mean? What is an AI 101?
So the various types of AI which exists, the first is predictive ML.
So this is basically the AI which exists today and
potentially what all financial services are using of
today. So this is all machine learning
based, rules based, doing simple text
analysis, data extraction, predictions on the basis
of you feeding the AI, the artificial
intelligence, some rules. Now, the new hype, or the
current hype is about Gen AI or generative AI.
Now this is where OpenAI and the GPT era has,
has come into picture. Now this is more capable than predictive
ML because it is multimodal, which is AI
speak for saying that it can process information of various types,
be it text, videos or images. It can do data summarization,
it can be used for code generation. And most importantly,
or what we are seeing right now is it can do contextual conversations.
Building on this, the future is going to be general
intelligence or auto generative AI. So this
is basically gen AI, but with deeper context, a persistent
memory, so it remembers what the previous conversations were,
and a system, two kind of reasoning. So it can not just to
summarize information or give you insight, but it can actually
try to be more human like in nature,
more proactive. Now, this is where the future is going
to go towards why is AI coming into
so much popularity right now? So it's a case of,
it's a case of multiple reasons. So firstly,
competent elements. So you're seeing players like hugging phase Openeye
or Google's Gemini come into the market with really strong
processing and really capable large language
models. There's also traction. Now, chat JPT has
been one of the fastest companies to reach
10 million users. There's a lot of enthusiasm
about chat GPT and also other AI models like mid journey,
which is used for creating art.
Along with all of these positive, there's also a lot of hype. So for
example, I'm just trying to give some examples of what
I consider hype. Oral B coming up with an AI kind of a brush,
Microsoft adding AI into its PC. So there's
a lot of hype about, about AI right now in the tech world.
And for that reason, even financial services are curious
to understand what could be the repercussions or benefits for
them. The potential is huge. It has
use cases panning over over industries.
So that's why AI is becoming so crucial right now.
In terms of who benefits, there would be three key archetypes
for companies who can truly unlock the power of AI.
Companies which are data rich, so they have the network effects going
on. They have a large amounts of data which they can use to
come up with recommendations or insights.
They are very compliance driven, they are focusing on
monitoring and governance. And third, the company
or the organization is product led. Now, all of this is
not possible if you're not really able to quickly test out
your ideas and see if it works or not. So in terms
of the gen AI or the generative AI in finance today,
in my opinion, I'm largely seeing these use
cases emerge in personal finance. So companies like Monarch
and Clio are trying to use this for spend management,
budgeting and just acting as your AI buddy
when it comes to spend management, we are seeing
a lot of uptake in customer support. Almost every big
bank or fintech has an AI enabled bot.
Interestingly, Klarna recently claimed that their AI
is able to do a work of 700 agents. So we
are seeing already that the conversational side of the AI
is being heavily leveraged by the financial services.
Now going in the future, I see that these
use cases will go deeper into three key areas, which is
risk and compliance, developer tools and internal process.
So now let's try to unpack this a bit. So risk and compliance
in terms of making real time decisions, in terms of understanding
the risk, the credit of the unbanked or
the underbanked population, be it to b two c or b two b.
I see AI playing a huge part in this. We are already seeing this
happening on the b two z side with bnpls leveraging AI
for real time credit decisioning. But I see this
making a huge impact on the b two B side or the trade financing side,
which has been largely unexplored in terms of
internal processes. We are seeing companies such as Stripe or highradius
use this to make sure that the internal data is optimized.
So for example, you want to run a query or
understand data for your company, you can just ask AI
that. Hey AI, I want to find me the transactions
for the past 30 days. I want to figure out what has went wrong
and these conversational kind of things could be converted into
actual insights. This is going to really be a game changer for
larger financial organizations where finding data and
creating insights is often a challenge in
terms of dev tools. Again, I think stripe is one of those early AI
leaders who are trying to integrate AI into
developer experience. Potentially you will
see in the future this becoming omnipresent. You will be seeing developers
just conversationally asking that I want to create a payment service
using stripe as a payment service method,
using Worldpay as an acquirer or any other XYZ
service. And the AI is going to ensure that
every connection comes into place. With all of
this AI bruhaha, there's a word of caution which I feel
we should be taking in context.
So with AI, there are certain challenges. The AI
hallucinations are real, are a problem. So this is
basically making some
nonsensical assumptions or creating data
out of thin air. We have already seen examples of how
AI can just sometimes go off topic.
So second is the data integrity or the data quality.
So it's basically garbage in and garbage out. As my stats
professor used to say. If the data is not cleaned
enough, has not been removed of any particular biases,
the AI is going to be trained accordingly. So companies need to be
careful of what data sets the AI is getting, is getting
trained on. Third is governance controls in terms of monitoring
what AI can and cannot do, how, which of these are mission
critical, which of these are regulatory driven and ensuring that
AI has proper compliance and governance controls?
And fourth is overengineering. Simply putting
AI into your product is not going to solve a problem. As I
gave these some examples earlier, AI is
a means to a problem and not the opposite way.
So it should be carefully helping you solve your problem
rather than a solution looking for a problem.
So given all of this context, how should fis or the financial
services respond? So as I pointed out on the
last slide, first and foremost, find the right problems to
be solved using AI. Look for critical,
manually intensive tasks that AI can truly help
you solve and can make it more optimum
for you. Second is assess options. Look what's out there from
an AI perspective, do you need to build by or
partner to current options, meet your needs,
understand their abilities and limitations before trying to integrate
them into your day to day reorganize.
I think it's very important for organizations right now to
understand that AI is a critical element of
your organization and build a culture and the right
talent pool which can help your organization adopt to
AI. And fourth and foremost, the most important bit is experiment,
build, test and iterate. Look at what works for you, what doesn't
understand the proof of concepts for various
use cases to really understand whether AI is fit for
purpose for you. I thank you for taking this time
to hear my talk. You can find me on X or Twitter
or you can just do message me on
LinkedIn. I have a very searchable name. Adhikar Babu.
Thanks for your time.