Hello everyone. Hope you all are doing well. So let's begin
the session of stack by first introducing myself. My name is
Raid Asan and I am Pakistan's youngest rsecurity expert,
and I've also spoken at many conferences and events like Black Hat,
JISEC, and rsecurity summits held by government congresses
as well. I'm also a threat researcher and a security researcher,
along with being a certified purple teamer, which means that I can perform
red team as well as blue team operations together towards protecting
an enterprise rsecurity infrastructure. And I'm
also available on LinkedIn for connections. So feel free to ask me
any questions or any doubts that you have in a session
or want to learn more about it. So yeah, feel free to connect and let's
jump right into the session of stegnography. So in
today's session we are going to have a look at a live demonstration
of how adversaries are able to intercept your request of
steganography. Like basically, steganography is the art of embedding
data behind media files and people like
why do people use it? Basically, IoT is to keep your
confidential data safe from any unauthorized third party
access. Now suppose you are sending a confidential
data that is containing some bank details or username or
passwords of any server that is pretty much confidential,
and you don't want any unauthorized third party to gain access
to it. So what you do is this is just one of
the methods of encryption, or not encryption.
Basically, it's just one of the ways of keeping your confidential
data safe during transit or when it's in dynamic
motion. So what you do is that you download
any source, or you have any image, or any media file,
or any audio file, and behind that image or any
media file, you store your confidential data.
And if you talk in terms of accurate terms, it means
that you are embedding your data behind that media file.
And what embedding does is that even if
it's leaked to an unauthorized third party, they will open it and
the data won't be seen, only the image will be seen.
But if the adversary has both of the images or both of
the media files that was original and as well as
that was embedded with the data, there will be a difference between
file sizes. The one with the embedded data will
have a larger file size, and the one with not, which was originally
downloaded or was from an original source won't
contain any varying between sizes.
So let's see it in action of how adversaries do
this. Here I have the Kali Linux machine and on this
side we have our target, which we are going to hack.
Now what we are going to do is that we are going to access,
first of all we are going to scan it if it's working
or not, and if it has a web server
application running behind it. And as we can see it has a port
80 open, that is the HTTP port. And by this
we know that there is a web server running behind it.
So we are going to access it on our browser.
And this is for demonstration purposes. So I'm going to show you.
This was a directory that a hacker is busting
on the web server. For directory busting you can use go Buster OwAsp
directory buster or the normal, the ordinary
directory buster tool that is pre installed on your Kali Linux machine.
And here you can see I have the image TxT and I have the secret
TCM this file as well. So for now we are interested
in the image and here you can see it's a normal image of
a Lamborghini car. So we are going to
save it in our directory of steganography hacking
and we are going to verify it if it's of correct formatting.
Yes, it shows that it's JpeG format image data
and it's not malfunctioned or mal,
the headers are not misplaced and everything is accurate
over here. So we are going to also have a look at the secret
TXT over here and it says please
don't share the credentials for my file. It's a secret data TxT
and password 1234. Now we know that
there wasn't any data TXT over here, the file
wasn't listed and nor the password over here. Like any,
every credential was stored in the secret TXT. So this gives
us a hint that it can be in either of the two
files, it can be in the Jpeg file or it can be in the web
file. So most people prefer keeping their data
or embedding their data behind image files. So we are
going to see if there is any embedded
data behind this image. And what tool I'm going to use is staghide
steg hide is something, is a tool that
you can install on your Kali Linux machine or any hacking platform that
you are using. And what it does is that it
gives you some functions that you can perform. For example, you can extract data
as well as you can embed data into images or any media file.
You are focusing into embedding your data and
sending Iot to your receiver or your colleague, et cetera.
So we are going to use this tool called stackhide. We have the image
jpg with us and we are going to extract
it from the source file of image gpg.
And as we know data txt from
the secret txt file which was posted on a web server,
we know that there is a data txt or
there can be this file with this password that
we need to track.
Now I'm going to exfiltrate this data
txt from this source file and it requires a passphrase.
And here we have a passphrase over
here, password 1234. We can test it
out if it's working over here.
And yes it did. Here it's showing
that wrote extracted data to data txt.
Now here you can see we have data txt with us and we are
going to see what content IoT has for us. It shows that the username
is trunks and the password is user hint s
is in dollar symbol. Now what IoT does is
that it has exfiltrated the data from that image file
and given me the access to the credentials
that was stored in that particular file. By cracking
that file's password, which was just hosted
on the web server in clear text. So there was no complex cracking
methods of password cracking like John the ripper or any password cracking
tool that you might use. So it was just a simple task.
Now this username and password can
be connected over ssh with the victim as well. But for
clarity, I'm going to access it directly on the victim's machine over here
so that you get a better understanding of how hackers do this.
Username is trunks and the password we are going to use is
user with the dollar symbol.
And as you can see, I have successfully gained access over the user account.
Now for verifying, I can show you the id mih
trunks. Now, a hacker doesn't want to stop
here. What he aims is that he needs to escalate
his privileges. And from my perspective, my best
practice is to see the bash history or the commanding
history that the victim might have typed on his or her system
or the server they are working on, because history might contain
some juicy information. For example, you might have written your username or
password, you might have logged in into some of the websites or
any other system you might have connected to using RDP,
Ssh, FTP, any other protocol you're connecting. And that
can show the hacker, the adversary, what usernames and
password you might have used. So we are going to access the
bash history over here. Can bash history
here we can see a Perl programming
language command over here that shows
the user has created a user called Tom
which has been assigned the root privileges and it
is stored in the etc password directory. And the password
is password at the red 973 which is again encrypted.
So we are going to see if that user really exists which has been assigned
the root privileges. Now it's asking for the password
of the user tom. So we are going to use the password at
the rate 973 in order to
see if Iot really works. So I think I have written
the password wrong. Password at the rate 973.
Yes, so we are successfully inside
the root privileging machine. Like I have escalated my
privileges from user to root, and I am able to perform any
administrator task on this Linux system.
For example, I can verify who am I and the id is
zero, which means I'm the administrator and we can
txt for where you got root. So we have
successfully escalated our privileges and I have shown you
a way, or the method of how hackers use
stack height like tools in order to extract data
that you might have embedded behind your media files for
confidentiality purposes. And in this way the confidentiality
and the integrity and the availability of the data has been broken,
like the complete CIA tried has been broken by the adversary
by just using the steganography cracking
technique. And you also know the tool that's called the staghide.
You can also learn more about it for educational purposes of how
hackers and adversaries use these tools in order to extract data
and also store data in multiple formats of files. For example,
in our case we had a JPEG file, but people
can also store it in audio files, in video
files, or any document, so that they like
the format of embedding data behind images
is a traditional method. Every hacker, whoever sees
these images will surely go in depth
of it, will scan it, will analyze it in depth.
We'll use these kinds of tools like Steghyde, to see if any embedded
data is there behind the file, behind the image file. But if
you're using documents or audio files or any video files,
that might iot be like the hacker might not go into
in depth analyzation most of the times.
So this was it for today's session of mine, and I hope you have a
great day ahead. And you got to learn some new techniques and insights
on how hackers use stenography techniques in order to exfiltrate
your confidential data and gain access to your system. So once again,
thank you very much for joining my session, and I hope you have a great
day ahead.