Hello everyone, and thank you for joining me for today's talk. My name is Travis
Rodgers. I'm a developer relations engineer over at Teleport,
where we provide identity native infrastructure access
for engineers and machines. Now, the title of my talk today is replacing
privileged users with automated, just in time access requests.
Now, we could start this off with some history or with a bunch of definitions,
but instead I'm going to start off with an end state in mind,
an ideal end state for replacing privileged
users with automated just in time access requests. There's going to
be four parts to these ideal state. We'll talk in detail
about those four parts, and then I'll move to a practical example
of what this would look like using the open source solutions teleport.
If all that sounds good, let's go ahead and get started.
So what is this ideal scenario? So there's four
parts to it. Number one, everyone has a least privileged
policy. Number two, the ability to elevate
privilege upon request and approval. Number three,
this elevated privilege needs to be just in time or
temporary, not perpetual. And then finally,
there needs to be automation in place to ease this workflow.
These are the four parts of this ideal scenario. So for
now, let's take a deeper look at these four.
All right. Number one, everyone with a least privilege policy.
So the principle of least privilege means giving a user account
or process only the privileges which are essential to perform
its intended function. So there are two groups.
These, there's privileged users and there's privileged users.
This principle can be applied to both groups. Just because
you're a privileged user doesn't mean you should have blanket access
to everything. So, privileged users, now we do need
some privileged users. Someone has to create your account as a new employee,
right? Someone has to grant you a role or set you up can active directory.
And that person often has privileged access to do
so, allowing them to do so. These are it managers,
these are system admins, database admins, security teams,
et cetera. But again, this doesn't necessarily mean that
they need blanket access to everything available. Access that they don't
use regularly could be requested on an as needed basis
and approved by other admins granting that approval.
For example, there could be a super admin role, not a super admin
account or super admin user, but a role that could be assumed
temporarily for duties above the access of these privileged
users. Maybe these could be a role for production Kubernetes clusters
that no one has but would need to requests in order to
access. This would dramatically shrink the attack surface for
production clusters I mean, no one has that access unless
requests temporarily, but we'll talk more about that later.
As far as nonprivileged users, we can define this as users without
administrative privileges. They have very specific roles assigned
according to the principle of least privilege in relation to their titles
or duties. So overall, in both of these examples,
we're eliminating blanket super users with everyone
abiding by the principle of least privilege. All right,
number two in this ideal scenario is the ability
to elevate privilege upon request and approval.
So this could be assuming a role temporarily, like a
super user role or a particular role set up
for production clusters or whatever. This can also be accessing
some very particular piece of infrastructure temporarily, like a server,
a kubernetes cluster, or a database. And there are
two parts to this. So number one, a request is made.
An engineers requests access to a role or resource. And number
two, the request is approved. Another engineer with the
rights to approve these requests will approve. Maybe only
a certain group can do the approving. There's flexibility in that. So there's two
parts to it. There's the requester, and then there's the approver
with RBAC that can decide who has the ability to do either
one of those. And number three, in our ideal scenario,
is that this elevated privilege needs to be just in time or
temporary, not perpetual. So there should be no standing privilege
or broad user access privileges that are always on.
Access for a resource or role is often granted permanently
and painted with a broad brush. I mean, it takes time
to figure out the exact pieces that a user needs to elevate. So why
not just grant the whole group out of convenience, right? You've done it.
I've done jit. I mean, as engineers, often we don't know exactly what that
person needs, so we just give them more access than they really need.
In addition, this access can come in the form of keys or passwords
to an account or resource or some other form of
shared secret that's passed around between engineers.
Think about a Pim key or a kubeconfig. Oh,
you need admin access. Just use mine for now. But instead,
an elevated access should be a just in time access.
Just in time access is these way to enforce the principle
of lease privilege, ensuring that users and service accounts
are one, given the minimum amount of access needed
or required, and number two, only granted that access
temporarily. And then finally, the fourth
piece of this ideal scenario would be to have automation in
place to ease these workflow. Now, without automation of some sort,
we have a big annoyance. Instead of someone putting in a request for some
privileged escalation and having to wait for it to get process and
probably trying to have to reach out or tag someone to look at it sooner
than later and then multiplying that by 20 engineers a day. We need
instead to make JIT easier to approve these requests.
If we have to continually monitor tickets coming in for requests,
we can't get our own work done. We need to automate this at
least partially to ease this workflow. And I say partially
because the whole security of it all required that it be approved by others
on the team. Years ago I was an SRE and I got put
temporarily on a developer project as a developer,
and when I initially tried to build my dev environment, I ran into issues
with not being able to access files in Azure storage and
we had to create ticketed with the SRE team to get access to
that azure storage. And don't ask me why sres are supposed to do
this, but they're the ones to contact in these setting. On this particular
contract that I was on, we were supposed to reach out to the sres and
they would grant us access, but it would often take them days to
get to the ticket. And if you tried to reach out directly, there would be
pushback. Rightly so. Sres, I understand, and often
they would settle with just giving you blanket access to the resource that you needed
instead of trying to figure out the particulars of your place on
that project. And again, that's out of convenience.
Like I don't really know what you're supposed to have or what your teammates have,
but I'll just give you admin access for now, and for now turns into
perpetually. And this happened over and over as I got further into
the project and it was a real pain, but automation
could have eased that pain. So that's number four,
have automation in place to ease this workflow. So we have
these four requirements. Let me go over them again. Everyone with the least privileged
policy, the ability to elevate privilege upon request and
approval. This elevated privilege needs to be just in time or temporary,
not perpetual. And there needs to be automation in place to
ease this workflow. Now, before we move forward, I can
hear your objection. Okay, it goes something like this. Bad actors
can still get access to privileged user accounts and break havoc
just because there isn't blanket super user access, and regardless
of just in time access, it doesn't mean that a privileged account can't get hacked.
And you're absolutely right. However,
this is why the concept of identity is so important when it
comes to access in general. So let me take a minute to
talk about identity. Now, with true identity,
like biometrics, you can get rid of passwords and secrets and
API keys in anything that can be shared or impersonated.
Think about a password and how it's supposed to link identity, but it's not
true identity though, as it can be shared or stolen or users
by someone else. Just because it's my username and password
doesn't necessitate that it's actually me. And if someone gets
my password or secret and they authenticate with it,
then they're authorized to access what I have access to,
and the audit trails falsely show me performing
those tasks in any shared secret,
granting access to standing privilege is dangerous, and this often
happens where an engineer shares his admin access with another engineer,
whether a kubeconfig or a PIM key or some other form of
secret, so that they can perform administrative duties.
And this is normally for convenience reasons. If there is no
secret at all, and we are forced to prove identity,
then we can successfully use RBAC and just
in time access for privileged access. And this isn't
just for users, but also for machines. Machines need
an identity as well. And with all this being said, let's bring
it all together with an open source identity native infrastructure access
platform called teleport. And before we get to the just in
time access part of teleport and that demonstration, let me just explain to you
a little bit about what teleport is. So,
teleport allows you to access all of your infrastructure in one central
location, and it does so by deploying this identity aware proxy.
So this is the teleport proxy. From here,
users and service accounts will provide identity
to gain access to this proxy. And that's done via
web authent. So, biometrics service keys, it also
integrates with your SSO solution. And the teleport proxy
comes required with an RBAC system. So you're able
to provide roles to decide who has access to
what infrastructure. So you can access databases,
servers, windows, desktops, kubernetes, clusters,
and web applications. Intelliport has a built in certificate
authority that issues short lived certificates to
access this infrastructure. So in this entire setup, there are
no passwords, keys, or secrets that can be shared.
There's short lived certificates, there's an RBAC system deciding
who has access to what. And to access this identity aware proxy,
you have to prove your identity and let me actually log in and
show you what this looks like. So here I'm at the login screen.
And I have different ways to log in, but I'm
just going to log in via a GitHub SSO setup.
So I'm going to click GitHub and this is going to issue me a certificate
to access this proxy for 12 hours. Once inside,
I have a role that allows me everything, pretty much. So here are
all of my servers. I can connect to a server from
within teleport. I have applications,
I can do the same thing here. I can launch the application. I have
kubernetes clusters, I have databases and
I have desktops. So as an engineer, you log
in and you can access all of your infrastructure from one central location.
If I go to management, you'll see we do that via roles.
So if I go to this cube access role, you'll see that I have access
to all Kubernetes clusters, because you can assign labels to clusters
and then roles based on the labels. So these two stars mean
I have access to everything, all labels. So there's a complete
RBAc system, there's an auditing system. So here's the audit log of who's
logging in, what certificates are being issued,
et cetera. But we're here to talk about just in time access, right? So I'm
going to log into my own cluster that has that set up already.
So here's the login to another cluster that I have set up for this demonstration.
And I would normally just go passwordless and touch my fingerprint reader,
but since my computer's closed up, I'm going to go back and put in a
password. So, Travis admin and
then I'm going to touch my security key as a second factor and
I'm logged in now, just in time access, of course,
is not exclusive by any means to teleport. However,
teleport provides a complete, secure, and frictionless solution
to your engineers to access their infrastructure and
has this just in time access fully integrated with it.
So, taking a look again at our ideal state, let's compare this with
what teleport offers. So number one, teleport has a built
in RBAC system to configure least privileged policy
for users. Number two, teleport provides the ability
to elevate privilege upon request and approval.
Number three, these elevated privilege requests are just
in time and they're not perpetual. And then four, teleport integrates
with tools like Slack, Pagerduty, et cetera,
to provide automation conf 42 ease the workflow of
requests and approvals, and we're going to look at all of that now, so we're
going to look at three examples here. Number one, we're going
to look at a simple role based access example with open source teleport.
So let's say we have a user named Bob who's on the security team.
He often needs access to the Kubernetes dev cluster a couple of times
a week to run scans. In fact the project manager also
needs periodic access as well. But due to internal
hypothetical reasons, we don't want to grant either team permanent access
to our cluster. So what we can do is assign them a role
that allows them to request access to the Kubernetes dev cluster for
a short time. So let's imagine Bob on the security team needs an hour
or two to work on the Kubernetes dev cluster.
So if you look at Kubernetes you'll see that there's a cluster called minicube Dev.
This is the cluster that Bob is looking to access for a couple of hours.
So if we go to management and find Bob here,
we see that Bob has a role called Jit Kubernetes dev
admin. If we look at what that role does,
that role allows whoever has it to request
access to this Kubernetes dev admin role. Whoever has this
role is allowed to request access to this particular
role. So Bob has that, he should be good to go and
able to request access to that role. And we're going to use
the terminal for this teleport has a CLI
called the TSH CLI to do this. It also has a tcuddle
CLI for administrative duties which we'll see in a minute. So first
we have to log in as Bob. So Bob opens his computer and he
opens up his terminal and he's going to log in and then request access
to this Kubernetes cluster. So Tsh login,
we'll put the proxy address, auth is local and the user
is Bob hit return.
Bob will punch in his password and touch his security key
as a second and
you'll see here you're logged into the proxy as these
Bob has these roles, Kubernetes is enabled but he doesn't
have access to any clusters. And you can see
that by doing TSH cubels. What Kubernetes
clusters does Bob have access to? Right now Bob has access to
no users. So what Bob wants to do is to request access,
a just in time access request for this cluster. So in
order for Bob to request access to this role or this
cluster, he just needs to type in TSh request
create and then for the roles flag the role that
he wants to request Kubernetes dev admin in giving
the reason, the reason he gave is fixing a pod error. So this is all
he needs to do to request just in time access to that
role. So he'll hit enter creating
request and the request is created. It's currently
pending and it's waiting for request approval. By default
this command will block until the request is approved. To submit this request without
waiting for approval though, just add the no wait
flag. But what we'll do now is the administrator
can now go to the terminal where teleport's hosted
and can do a let me see which tcuddle we're going to use these tcuddle
ClI now so pseudo and I'm going to do the full path here
user local I'm
going to do the full path here user local been
tcuttle and just do a request ls
to see what requests are in the queue. And there's currently the request that Bob
put in and it's currently pending and
as an administrator you can approve it. And I'm going to make this smaller
so that we can see this get approved.
So what you'll do to approve it is just tcuddle requests
approve and then the id of the request.
So I'm just going to copy this id of the request and paste it
here and hit return to approve
JIT. And over here you'll see approval received, getting updated certificates.
Now you'll see that Bob has a
role of Kubernetes dev admin and it's only good for 51
more minutes. He put the requests in, it was good
for an hour, now it's only good for 51 more minutes. So now he
can do tsh cube ls to
view his available clusters and that cluster should now be available mini Cube
dev and he can do tsh Cube login mini
Cube dev to log into the cluster and run Kubectl
commands. Kubectl get pods all should give us
these pods and after
50 more minutes this elevated request or privileged
access will be gone. The administrator can also deny this request
with a reason. They can put a reason like hey, we're currently in the process
of doing a cluster upgrade deny and Bob will see
where he's denied that access. So that's the first example. The second
example is an automated, more advanced role based access
example with enterprise teleport in Slack.
So this gets much better in the enterprise version of teleport
where this can also be managed in the UI and integrated with Slack.
So in this scenario let's imagine that one of our project managers,
Alice, often needs access to the Kubernetes dev cluster.
So let's log in as Alice. I'm going to go over here Alice
PM project manager. I'm going to put in a password and touch
my security key and
you'll see that Alice has access to like nothing. There's no servers, no applications,
no databases, no Kubernetes clusters. But she
often needs access to this Kubernetes cluster. So instead of having
to use the CLI she can use the UI here so she can go to
access requests. And it's this simple, just click on new request
and she has a role that allows her to requests access to
this Kubernetes dev admin role just like we saw with Bob.
So all she needs to do is click add to request,
proceed to request, and then she can put in a reason,
need to update a pod or something like that.
And when she submits the requests, instead of someone having
to check the review requests here, which is also available
in the UI, we're going to get an automated message on Slack.
So your team is using Slack. There's a group of administrators
or whoever that can approve these requests that's going to see that come
through in slack just like this. So she's going to
submit the request and here
in slack we're going to see something pop up.
You have a new request, here's the iD, here's the cluster.
The user is Alice PM. The role she's requesting is this Kubernetes
Dev admin role. And the reason is that she needs to update a pod.
Now me as an administrator, all I need to do is click on this
link and I see
the review here and I can say yeah, that's fine,
approved, have at it and
submit review. And I've approved the
request. You'll see that updated. Also here in Slack status
is now approved and Alice falls. She has to do
now is go back to listings, check her review requests.
And now that it's approved she can just click assume roles.
To assume the role, that privileged role.
So click assumed roles and you'll see here kubernetes
dev admin role assumed and expires in 56 minutes.
So this just in time. Access is much better in
the enterprise version of teleport. It's still available in open source,
it's fully functional, but we get to use
the UI for these and the integration with Slack.
And again this role runs out in 56 minutes. It's just
in time. Now the third and final scenario here is an example of resource
based access. So in the first two examples that was role based.
So you request access to a role and you get whatever that role allows you.
Well, in these scenario we have resource based access requests.
So let's imagine that we have a contractor that just needs periodic access
to one of our servers. Okay. Just needs periodic access
to one of the servers. So I'm going to log out as Alice. We're done
with her. And let's log in as Tim
contractor. He's a contractor
that just needs access to one of the servers.
So you'll see this contractor signs in. He has access to nothing,
nothing here, but he needs access to one of the servers. Now in this example
we're still requests a role, but the user doesn't need to know anything about
roles or RBAC controls used under the hood. They just see the
resources they're allowed to access. But just to let you know how this works,
if I go to management and users, you'll see that Tim contractor
has a resource requester role. So if we take a look at that,
this role actually allows all of the resources
that an access role can access.
So you're not requests a role, you're requesting access to
resources that a role can access.
So we have a role in here called access and it actually allows
you access to everything. But we'll see in the case of Tim
here, when he goes to access requests, we'll see
that he can access particular resources.
So applications, databases, whatever we
want access to a server. So let's go to servers. There's two that
this access role allows you to access. So Tim
is able to request access to individual resources this way.
So let's say this is the server he needs add to request,
proceed to request, just need
to update the server. And when I
submit this again, it's going to come through Slack and it's going to notify that
team that's allowed to approve it. So submit
request and open slack. And we see we have a new requests.
Here's the iD, the cluster users, Tim contractor.
These role is the access. And the reason is just
need to update the server. So again you click on the link and
me as an approver, I can say sure, let's approve it,
go for it and submit review.
And if we go back to Tim, go back to listings
and Tim can then assume the role.
And for this one he has 12 hours. That one wasn't set. So by default
you get 12 hours and he can then go to his servers. There's his
server and he can log right
into it. And let's run a few commands. Ls PWD
exit and what's neat about teleport, just to add
to this, is that it has a full audit logging capability
here. So you can go to audit log and you can
see who logged in. Tim Contractor has
an issued certificate, started a session, and that
server that we just logged into, you can actually playback
that session. So if I click on this, I can see exactly what Tim did,
which is great for auditing and compliance reasons.
So everything that comes through this proxy is also audited with
all sessions having the ability to be played
back. So for more information about access requests, you'll see
here we have documentation on role requests,
resource requests, and then the open source role requesting that I
did in the first example. There's also more access request
plugins. We have Slack, mattermost teams, Jira,
Pagerduty, email, and Discord. In addition,
the teleport API allows developers to define custom access
workflows using a program language of their choice.
So with just in time access, you can move away from
super privileged accounts. You can see that everyone abides by
the principle of least privilege and can request any privileged
access easily with automation in solutions
like teleport. If you had any questions during this presentation,
feel free to email me your questions at travis rogers@teleport.com
also, check out our community slack. We're very active there. We can
answer your questions@teleport.com.
Slash Slack and slash Labs will take you to
our interactive labs where you can try our product hands on.
Hope you enjoyed the presentation and have a great day.