Hello everyone, welcome to the Conf fourty two and the ballerina programming language
session. In this session I'm going to discuss in detail about
ballerina programming language, which is an open source programming language.
It makes it very easy to write network based application
for the cloud. Before going to the details, let me introduce
myself. I'm Anupama Pathirage, currently working as director of engineering
at WSO two. WSO two is a leading technology provider
in the domains like integration, identity and access management,
API management and so on. Ballerina language is
designed and implemented at WSO two, but currently it's driven
by the open source community as well.
WSo first, let's look at what are the problems that we are facing
today and where we are in terms of application development
methodologies. If you look back the history a little bit, in many
decades ago we had systems like mainframe systems
with legacy and centralized applications.
And then gradually client server based distributed
applications came into the picture. And after that,
with the improvements in the Internet and cloud based
technologies, things has evolved a lot. And the way that
we are writing programs and the way that we are designing things
has evolved a lot. And then as developers,
everyone has to adapt to these changes. And if
we look at how we approach the given problem or
when we are developing solution for a given programming problem,
in the old days, we considered libraries
as a unit of logical components,
as that is the component that we are dealing with on the
systems, which are very much centralized. But in nowadays,
it's unavoidable to have communication links between different
systems. That means we have to talk to different endpoints and
get some data and process them and send them over wire to
some other place. So that's a normal thing. And that means
APIs are becoming the natural unit of execution,
natural unit of applications these
days. So if you look at any
kind of application, it usually has a front end
as well as a back end. So back end means
in nowadays applications, it doesn't work on its own.
It has to talk to many different systems and it has to extract data,
process data, and then move it out from
that system to some other place. That means it involves
with many different network protocols, many different data formats,
so it's unavoidable to deal with that complexity.
And also, in today's world, there are so many languages,
programming languages, which can handle great front end
stuff as well as backend things. But although
there are a lot of such languages to develop backend applications,
it is not that easy when we talk about
this problem, because API integrations and this integration
problem is complex due to the
network interactions as well as different data types and
also different communication paradigms.
So that is the problem that we are trying to solve because we
observed this problem or this hurdle for the developers
for a long period of time. And if we look at the different
technologies, integration products and technologies in
one side, for example ESPs, e, AI,
BPM, those things are not that much cloud native
and those are giving proper or
great functionalities, but maybe
not the ideal solution for the cloud. And on the other
hand, we have general purpose programming languages and frameworks
which are very much flexible, but at the same time they don't give
the right set of abstractions to deal with the problem in this
domain. So that is why we have introduced another language
called ballerina to deal with those two different
ends. It is providing the capabilities like
any other integration product and technologies, as well as it
gives the flexibility of the programming language to deal with the
complexities of the application developers while providing the
right set of abstractions. So if I talk
a little bit about the history of the language, we started it
in around 2016, but real idea came into
the picture even before that, maybe around 2010,
because in WSO two we developed application for
these domains and we observed the problems and we identified the
blockers that developers are facing. So then we
thought a programming language would be the ideal thing to solve
this problem. It's a general purpose programming language, and if you
look at the syntax, you may feel like it's
familiar because we have CC plus plus family syntax
in the language, but at the same time it is specializing
in the domain of integration and cloud based
problems. It provides the right set of abstractions
and various tools to make it easy for
the developer and it's open source project
which is given by the open source community. We started in
2016 and it went through multiple iterations because
we have our own compiler and platform
around that to make it a complete thing. And we
released our first version in 2019 and the
current major version is Son Lake. We released it in 2022 and
right now we are developing many features improvements
over the sown lake as well as we are doing separate
tracks to deal with other things like different language
aspects or major additions to the spec,
as well as native compilation to
support native compilation for the ballerina language. So that's
the status of the language. And let's look at what
are the unique features of ballerina, which makes it easy for
the application developers. One main thing
about programming is there are many different programming
language. It can be different kinds,
data oriented, object oriented, function oriented and
so on. In Ballerina we consider it as a data oriented
programming language, because if we look at any programming
piece of program which works with many different entities
or endpoints, usually what we share is data.
In earlier days we share code over the network,
like in the RPC style of applications, but we no longer
do that because of the security concerns and other things. Instead we
move data around. That means we need to have better ways
of representing data in the network as well as the data
in the memory. So in Ballerina we designed
in a way that we emphasize the plain data concepts
that is independent of any code and protocol and
the ways of processing, especially how we can access data,
how we can transform data. So those
things should be very easy and intuitive for the application developer.
And at the same time in ballerina we have
different support for different protocols
and especially different data types. For example JSON XML.
Those are primitive types in the language like string,
int, flot like in other languages. And also
ballerina language provide query like syntax.
If you check this code, you can see SQL like syntax
here. This is to process the data which
are coming from the wire. You can see the data received via the wire
is assigned to memory in memory type that
we defined in the application level and
then we process it using query like syntax.
It is very easy because we don't have to write complex
logic to get lot of filtering as well as processing
of the data. And then we provide network
oriented capabilities because network is the primary thing
when we talk about integration and cloud native applications
and type system type system is playing a
key role here because we have to deal with the data on
the wire as well as data in the application or memory level
as well. So here you
can see we are talking to endpoint and talking to endpoint is
very easy in the language. The concepts of the client service are very
much intuitive and then the return type represent
the output from the network. Endpoint usually JSON XML
type of responses. And we can map it directly
to a data structure defined in the application without
doing explicit casting or any other processing. So that eliminates
very much boilerplate code if you want to convert things.
And it support well known data formats and converting
and accessing is very easy.
And other concept is service.
Service means similar to retrieve data from other
endpoints and services. We have to serve data as
well. So ballerina service concept gives you a
very much easy way to write services.
A service concept is a first class thing in the language
and depending on the listener that we are binding to, that it
act as a different service type. If you can see here we are attaching
HTTP listener to this service. That means this will
act as a HTTP service. So based on the
attached listener service will behave differently because
here you can see we are developing HTTP listener
and you don't need to worry about internal network details. All the
things are handled by the listener and the service itself.
What you have to do is implement the resource functions to match
with the requirement of the service. So in HTTP world it's usually
get post delete those kind of operations and we can
write resource functions for these things. You can see get here
post here. Those goes very close with the HTTP
world and what you have to mainly focus on the business
logic, not anything else about the network or the underlying
complexities. And it returns the data types in the
language itself or the data types that you have defined,
and then the listener will handle it internally when it's returning to
convert it to the proper format, the default formats and so on.
So here also we support two different interface styles.
You know, in RPC style we usually have remote
methods. In that case within the service you have to define remote methods
and restful style like HTTP graphql.
We have to write resource functions. So what the developer
has to do it is focus on the business logic because
the right level of abstraction is provided by the language
to deal with the community of developing the services
and the boundaries and how we handle things.
And also concurrence is playing a key role here.
In network applications, concurrence is kind of unavoidable
thing and we provide different concepts
and support even during compile time to guarantee the compiled
time safety as well as runtime, concurrency,
safetiness and similar to the services,
clients are also very much important. Clients means we
need to invoke other endpoints of different types of protocols.
So language provides support for different clients
and depending on the client, client is a language concept
and depending on from which protocol that you are,
depending on which protocol that you are using to access the client,
we can define different type of clients. It can be GRPC,
Websocket, graphQL and many more different protocols.
So creating a client is easy. You can provide additional
parameters if needed and also invoking the
functionalities or get the details
or get the response out of it. Also very easy.
The syntax for calling or invoking an endpoint
is like this, and also you can bind data very
easily the response data. So then
that means with all these things developers can focus on
real business logic and they can then take
more time to focus on that and another concept
is when we think about enterprise application,
concurrency and reliability is very much important because
we have to always make sure our applications
are behaving in a reliable way. And also in the integration
world, concurrency is mandatory thing.
So like any other language, we provide concurrency
handling constructs. We have asynchronous function calls,
workers and strand concepts,
which provides a logical thread of control.
And all these things are there. At the same time,
ballerina guarantees or provides many mechanisms
to ensure the concurrency safetyness during the compile time itself
by means of different mutability
concepts. So those things are a little bit complex
and difficult to handle in a small session like this. But Belna
tries to be proactive when giving
the warnings and other errors related to concurrency
problem without waiting till the runtime. And also reliability.
That means usually, for example, transactions plays
a huge role in enterprise applications. We need to guarantee
the atomic operations. And in ballerina,
transaction is a first class thing, and it's a syntax by
the syntax itself, it defines the transaction boundaries.
And you can write your business logic within this
syntax block, and then it guarantees the
atomic operation of the execution of the internal
code. So likewise it tries to address
the problem of the problems that integration developers
are facing. And there are many more such
concepts like HTTP resiliency
protocols and how we handle things like that.
And another important thing is usually when we design an application,
we write or withdraw diagrams to explain things and
to understand things and to visualize
things properly. But in ballerina we don't have to
do it explicitly because it provides different level of diagrams
to make it easy for the developers. So every
piece of program that you write, there's an equivalent diagram
which is automatically generated. So this is a program in the
left side, and in the right side you can see the diagram
which is automatically generated. And also the important thing is
we maintain the parity between the code and the diagram.
That means if you change something in the code, it appears automatically
in the diagram. And if you change something in the diagram, diagram is
editable. You can see these plus points where you can
add anything that you can do in the code side
using the diagram, and it will generate the code
if you add things on the diagram side. And when you look at the code,
sometimes you can't identify high
level view, what are the interactions, which is very important
in integration kind of application. So here you can see
we are interacting with two different endpoints. One is
GitHub and other one is Google sheets. And then we
are getting responses and do some processing. And this is the diagram
generated in the VS code plugin. You can install the VS code plugin
from the VS code marketplace and this gives the diagram
view automatically. So that's very much
helpful when you are talking to some other stakeholders
or if you are discussing among the developers about the application,
or if you are trying to understand the application overall. Big picture.
So this is like a sequence diagram where we have vertical
lines which represent each thread of execution as well as
different endpoints. And these horizontal lines represent
the interactions between those different endpoints and the
actors. And those are the not only
diagramming features that we have in the Belarna.
We provide different level of diagram capabilities. One thing
is the sequence diagram, and there are so many other
things including architecture diagram as well.
If you are developing a complex application which involves multiple
components or services or multiple modules,
then it gives that view as well,
like high level view on how different components are interacting
with each other as well. What are the dependencies and how
they are in working different application.
And another thing is the data mapping feature. So usually
when we deal with data coming over the wire,
we have to process them and especially we have to convert them into different formats
or different data types. So as you can see here, language provides
the capabilities to map in
a very convenient way, because if you have to write all the
logic of mapping in hand, it's very difficult task if
you have large payloads, but in this
view you can easily drag and drop or connect the different
fields from opensource type to the target type.
And also in between you can type whatever the custom logic
in mapping. Sometimes you may have to do some intermediate
step or calculation before mapping, then ballerina
support that as well. So along with all these diagram capabilities,
it's very easy to write programs even if you doesn't
know much about the language. And then another
feature is built in observability. Every ballerina program is automatically
observable by any open telemetry tool.
And it has three main areas like matrix tracing
and login. And you can connect to external
systems like Prometheus, Grafana, Yeager or
any other login platforms to visualize or
to observe the behaviors in the runtime. So that
capability is built into the language. It's just a matter of
enabling or disabling it, and it gives the
support to connect with these tools.
And another important thing when it comes to the cloud is
how easy it is to develop or using your code
or deploy your code in the cloud. Usually the
practices developers are developing it and it hand over the
relevant artifacts to the deployment engineers and then do
all the artifact generations to the cloud
environment and the deployment environments, and then do the deployment.
But in ballerina, since it's focused
on the cloud deployment most of the time, we provide easy
ways to generate the deployment artifacts as
well. Here you can see Bellbuild command. This is a simple hello
world program or service written in ballerina. In the Bellbuild
command, we can provide additional argument called cloud
and with the parameters of the environment
that you want to deploy. For example here,
this example, it's kubernetes. It can be Docker things like
that. And when you provide that, it builds or
it generates the artifacts that you need
to have to deployment as well. For example Docker
files as well as Kubernetes artifacts including service
deployment and other YAML files. So then
when you do that, what it does is it extracts
some of the parameters and other things from the code itself. And also
you can config things. Sometimes you
might need to improve the behaviors by providing more
memory and other things. You can provide those in config
ToML to change the generated artifact values. And then
based on all these things, it will generate the cloud artifacts
where you can customize and deploy if you need.
So that is about making it easy for the cloud.
And that is not only about that, because since it's a full platform,
it has support for many cloud connectors
and cloud deployment capabilities and
different ways to connect different cloud providers, things like
that. So one other
important thing is right now, ballerina is written in Java.
That means compiler is written in Java and it generates JVM
bytecode. And also it provides Java interoperability
because of that. So that means if you have a piece of code
written in Java, and if you want to invoke it using a ballerina
code, you can easily use the Java interoperability
capabilities so that you can link that Java code
into the ballerina code. And also, although it's
written in Java and generate JVM bytecode, the semantics of
the langauge were carefully designed to be independent of the Java and JVM.
Because our target is to create another implementation
which generates a native bytecode, that work is currently in progress.
That's what we called N Valorina, and also recently
we introduced a native flag which generates gralvm
native executables when building the ballerina project.
So ballerina is designed carefully not to have
tight coupling with the Java or JVM. In future
we will provide more native kind
of artifacts as well.
And also, ballerina is not just a language,
it offers a full platform,
especially the Vs code plugin which provides all the capabilities
that I have mentioned including source and graphical editing,
debugging and diagram generation
for like architectural view and other things. And it
provides the capabilities that any other
vs code plugin provides for any other language, but at the same time
with the diagram aspects and deployment aspects
it provides some additional features as well
and also generating or working
with the schemas like Open API, GraphQL,
GrPC. Those are very much easy and to generate
the API documentation we have commands and also
test framework is similar to most of the language just
but with service mocking and other stuff too.
And Belna contains
standard library and extended library which provides
support for many different protocols like HTTP,
GrPC, Websocket as first class
things. And also we have extended library with
a lot of connectors for different APIs
as well as SaaS applications. So Balna Central
is a centralized place where you can host things if
you want to share your code with other developers, so that
if others can benefit from your code, you can
package it and share it using ballerina central,
our module sharing platform which is free to use for anyone
and then for other features, runtime features especially like observability
and DevOps capabilities. Balana language provide
better features.
Also WSO two is providing another offering
which we call Choreo SaaS application development platform which
makes it really easy to develop,
deploy, manage and observe the applications
in the cloud. So it's not directly related to Ballerina,
but at the same time it will give you more
features and more capabilities if you combine ballerina and Corio
together because it addresses the problems of the entire
application development lifecycle. So in today's
session I covered in
detail about features of
the language, but it is somewhat high
level list because in language there are so many capabilities
that you can try out. And so my request is
try the language and try to use it in your applications and
share your feedback with us. We have a community
around us, opensource development community in various
platforms including Discord, Stackcore,
flow, Twitter, GitHub and so on.
So feel free to join with us if you're willing to contribute to
the language as a developer as well as if you want to use it in
your applications. So that's about some high level
overview about the Ballerina programming language. Thank you very
much for joining today's session and hope
you will enjoy the rest of the sessions as well.