Hello everybody. Thank you for attending my talk. My name is Audrey Long
and today we're going to talk about keeping your enemies close and your
secrets closer. So a little
bit about me. I'm senior security software engineer engineer at
Microsoft. I have my master's degree in cybersecurity
from the Johns Hopkins University. I have my bachelor's degree in computer
science from the University of Cincinnati. I'm a diversity
and inclusion ambassador here at my job at Microsoft,
and I like to play pc games. Some fun facts about me I'm
a moderator for korean food forum and I think a hot dog
should absolutely be classified as a sandwich.
So let's get into the crux of this talk. Today we're going to be talking
about security tooling, and this slide demonstrates some of the
repercussions of not practicing good security hygiene. Data breaches,
unfortunately, are not uncommon. There are around 30,000
attacks on websites per day, which a data breach can
have a significant effect on both a company's public image
and their customers welfare. Many of these are easily
preventable by introducing secure code hygiene into pipelines,
and it's a serious issue with a total cost of
$6 trillion worldwide, which was sourced from 2001
study of cybersecurity ventures. However,
credential scanning could be a potential solution that we can easily introduce into
any kind of pipelines environments, both development prod
testing and any kind of pipeline really to
ensure that we have secure code hygiene before
reach of production,
let's talk a little bit about some common security missteps.
Stored test passwords can allow an adversary to glean significant information
on password structure and requirements. Not practicing
secure development can also generate more openings for adversaries,
which could include finding out significant information about your
system and finding those passwords that we accidentally add into
public repositories. Storing sensitive information in open
source repository, though, can lead to insights from malicious
activities because they allow for adversaries to see how the code
base functions and which vulnerabilities can be exploited.
Reuse of passwords is also very common, especially in
IoT devices, so we need to make sure that we scrub any
of those configuration files before we accidentally publish those to
any kind of open source repository. Trying to tack on security
at the end of a project is unfortunately very common.
However, we need to be more vigilant about shifting security to the left during
the requirements phase. If we shift in early enough,
we could hopefully mitigate against a lot of these bad hygiene
practices that we see so much in open source and in projects worldwide.
Let's talk a little bit about resiliency. How do we improve the
security of our applications? By adopting an adversarial mindset.
This can help tease out prime attack vectors and entry points into our applications
and systems, build countermeasures, and develop mitigation strategies
to address and identify risks. We could use threat
modeling exercises as an example to help tease out
these risk factors and develop mitigation strategies.
Sometimes this is left off of the developers table.
Unfortunately, however, I think that we can be more vigilant in including these
practices in any kind of DevOps environment.
We also need to build countermeasures and develop mitigation strategies
to address some of the identified risk from threat modeling activities,
and we could do that also in a Devsecops continuous integration
and implementation strategy. We also need
to implement security tooling available as to remove accessible secrets
and make security easy and accessible. A lot of the
times we see security as very difficult and stringent,
which makes it so developers don't like to introduce some of these hygiene and best
practices into their pipelines or into their development strategies. So we
as security engineers, or just engineers in general, need to make security easy
to use and easy to understand. So it's not just something
that's burdensome for anyone to take on any kind of security tasks.
We also need to integrate security practices at the beginning
of the project lifecycle. In the long run, baking in security is
going to be way more cost effective than tacking it in at
the end. So why is this important to my team? So my
organization close here at Microsoft is comprised of
many software engineers compared to security engineers,
and I know here in the devsecops world that's very common for others
amongst security engineers. Both software and security engineers need
to have some understanding on how some of the industry best
practices are leveraged within each organization so that we can
both be on the same page. There is a need for tooling which should be
easy to understand and easy to use for developers.
The tooling also needs to be modular so they can be swapped in as they
are created and updated. And modularity is also very important
not only for security, but for devsecops and for software
engineering best practices as well. Lots of the times we see libraries and
modules go out of date, we need to make sure that we're using the
highest and the most stringent modules that we
can find. Security is also dynamic, so we
need to have scalable and dynamic solutions as well.
But sometimes solutions are hard to research, hard to create, and definitely hard
to maintain. There's two areas of software insecurity, and they
tend to be very siloed without much explicit understanding between the two.
To remedy this, we as a security field need to
shift left both in the requirements phase as security engineers
to inhabit the software engineering space to better understand and
work directly with software engineers and the projects that they work on.
These learnings could tend to lead to discovery and prevention of attack vectors
within software projects. Now let's talk
a bit about developers. So what exactly is
developers? Essentially, it's the addition of security
layer over the normal DevOps pipelines, so tools that
take the place of the SEC portion of developers
can be created to address many security concerns. With the development process,
we can ensure that developers don't allow secrets gaps in
their pipelines by implementing such tools early on in their development phases.
We also can allow for the ability for continuous monitoring and fixing those pipelines
whenever we find any kind of mitigations against
any type of alerting that happens throughout these observability features.
Due to its automated nature, it can help address
risks without significantly impeding development.
And that's the beauty of Devsecops. We are continuously improving and
continuously developing new practices. This allows for
continuous enforcement of good security practices throughout development.
Devsecops is a step in the right direction to bridge the gap between security
and software. However, more needs to happen. Is there
a single tool that can handle all security scenarios in any kind of DevOps pipelines?
No, there isn't. There is no single tool
to cover all the bases. Many tools are needed to
cover all the scenarios. Static code analysis dynamic code
analysis infrastructure as code credential scanning container
scanning, open source scanning. The list just keeps going on and on and on,
especially when we keep continuously maturing in the
way of development and of security.
However, my team and I have created and we'll go more into
this and a demo later on into this. Talk about a tool,
the detect secrets tool. Now, first and foremost, I don't want to
sell a tool. That's not what the point of this conversation is
about. The point of this conversation is to showcase that we need
to scale and make dynamic tools depending on our scenarios and with our
customers, what they need. And making easy harnesses
to better adapt and grow tool sets throughout when we need them
and plug and play them when we need them as well, is really important.
So what my team and I did is we wrapped Yelp detect
secrets. So Yelp was an open source tool
which could find any kind of secrets within the code
base, and we took that tool and wrapped it with an Azure DevOps
open source visual studio marketplace extension.
And we did those for a few reasons.
First and foremost, we did it to make it easier to integrate
a credential scanner into a Azure DevOps pipelines.
And we did it to ensure that the
coding and integrity within our development crew was always
going to have credential scanning to snuff out any accidental
secrets that were going to be included into the code base. Open source reliability,
which allows quicker detection of shortcomings in the code
base as well. So not only do we need to
find proper tools for the job, but we need to understand the tooling vulnerabilities
to configure them properly into the code base. Too many times a security engineer
will unbox a tool and just let the default configuration do the job.
Is this good enough for security and for our developers?
I don't think so. Before we get into
the demo, let's talk a little bit about the reusable architecture of the
code that was created. So my team and I have created a reusable foundation
to plug and play command line scanning tools that are needed throughout many projects
that we work on. So the need to
be scalable and dynamic is crucial for success. So we
work with many different customers throughout many different engagements
or projects throughout the year. So we always need to
be vigilant about what tools are out there and what we can create
quickly and easily for our customers and developers to use. The need to
be scalable is very important, especially dynamic.
The overall tooling architecture here reads as follows.
The first and foremost thing we need to do is we need to do some
research over some tooling, figure out which is the right
tool for the job. A lot of the times there's lots of tools out there.
There's new tools that get released like every week it feels like.
So we need to figure out which tool is going to be best for us
and our customer, then we need to grab the inputs from the configuration
file. Having a good understanding on the optimal configuration
to run a tool is really important. I don't want to
preach to the choir, but there are a million and one ways to run a
tool, especially if there's so many different command line arguments that you can give it.
So understanding which one's the optimal one for you and your crew
would be really important to figure out. And then we need
to execute the desired scanning Cli so that we
do get that optimal solution. After that,
what our tooling and foundation does is ingests
the scanning report and it converts it so that it's easily ingestible
by the Azure DevOps pipelines dashboard.
And then we generate a report based on those results so
that we could also look through it easier instead of seeing it spit
out on the command line, for example. And then another thing that we
did that's really novel and interesting in this talk is craft the pipelines
code to easily introduce those findings into the Azure DevOps backlog.
So this one's really important because a lot of the times you
will see pipelines perhaps break or
fail, and we sometimes don't get around
to fixing it. Well, we kind of gave you an option here to
include it into a backlog so you could see what jobs
also failed, why it failed, and always have a record
for you and yourself to review later on.
All right, let's go a little bit into the demo now. All right,
so here is the detect secrets credential scanner that
my team and I made. It's a visual studio marketplace extension
so that we could easily ingest it into Azure developers pipelines.
And that was kind of the, a lot of the customers that we work with
like to use Azure developers pipelines. We also work with GitHub
a lot, but in this scenario, we couldn't find a really good free,
in this case credential scanner to be used for a customer
that really needed it in a jiffy. So that's kind of the use
case and the purpose of this project. And like I said
before, I'm not trying to sell you a tool here. Instead I'm trying to sell
you an idea, which is we need to make scalable tools
that can be easily ingested into pipelines so that we
can progress and move development crews further along instead
of pushing them back. So for this credential scanner,
as I said, we wrapped Yelp detect secrets.
And the overview isn't really much to
see here, other than the fact that this is just like a nice little landing
page for anyone to come and actually download this tool. Right now.
It's actually not available for anyone to download publicly.
However, that will be changing here soon.
Now, before I get into the tool, I really wanted to showcase to you
what I'm going to be scanning for this tool demonstration.
So it's called OASP webgoat. And I would highly recommend
this website or this application for really anyone who wants to do
some kind of tool discovery. So what this is is Oauth
foundation. They have created this bad,
vulnerable application, and it's
a really great playground for us as security engineers also to
kind of do some tooling testing to see what kind of vulnerabilities do
some of these tools actually pick up.
And owasp Webgoat is definitely one that I'd like
to use as a nice little playground to
test tools. And if anyone is looking for
something else, I would definitely recommend using this to do
any kind of security tooling testing.
All right, now, before we get into it, I just wanted to showcase to you
what the user inputs actually look like for this tool.
So my team and I did a lot of research in all
of the inputs for the tool, and from those
research and that inputs we can determine what we actually want our users to
be configured with. So that was kind of interesting in this regard
to figure out what would be something that's really simple, a really
simple UI, just for our users to really have a good understanding on
how to use this tool without getting completely buried
with a bunch of perhaps cumbersome information.
So I'm not going to really go that deep into any of
these configuration details other than the fact that we try
to make it simple where I say, hey, where would you like the code to
be scanned? Otherwise it'll default to scanning the whole repository,
unless you wanted to just scan a certain section of the repository.
We allowed a word list, which in this case is
called, in older terms we
called them blacklists and whitelists. However, we'd like to
step away from that language and like to use more inclusive language
such as allow list, disallow list, or in Yelp's case they like to use
the word list to use as one of
those allow lists. So we can skip over
some of those false positives that any kind of tool will find.
And that's really important to also include in any of your tooling
if you decide to make them in the pipeline, because there will be false positives.
Unfortunately, I've not been personally a tool
which hasn't picked up on a false positive. If you definitely have
found one, let me know. I'm really interested to hear what you guys have recommended,
but if anything, also calling it
a word list, allow list, disallow list. If there's anything from this talk
you take, I hope it would be to help change that language because it starts
with you. And we also gave an
option to treat warnings or treat findings as warnings instead
of failures. I think this is really interesting,
as a security engineer to really allow our users to
kind of skip over this. However, I think it's really important that
we make our tooling available for any kind of person who wants to use
it excuse
me. All right,
now here is what the output will actually look like once you run it into
your pipeline.
So for OWASP, we have about 150
secrets that are contained into this repository, which is another
reason why I really like this repository, because it showcases also
just how good some of these tooling can actually be.
Sorry. Okay,
now another thing about this tool, as you can see, is we ingested the reporting
from the command line into this Azure DevOps dashboard. So we
can see line by line, what actually was
picked up from the scanner. And this is really interesting
and cool to kind of see it like this, because we could go ahead and
make bugs as well. So if you go up here, you could create
any kind of a bug. So we could say this was
for the demo,
save and close it, and then it's going to just show up right in your
backlog.
Excuse me, so sorry.
This is for the demo. Oops, I clicked on the wrong one. But whatever,
here you go. And then it'll actually showcase you that.
It'll link out to that
issue that we found, too. So making
sure that making a tool to give you that backlog report
is really interesting and something that we found in our organization
to be the most beneficial in regards to actually solving anything.
Now, let's talk a little bit about some forward thinking. So smarter secrets
detection through the use of more advanced scanning methods and algorithms,
as well as security research, will advance and progress throughout the years.
Advanced entropy engines to better generate streams which
closely resemble secrets and more integrated security tooling are needed to
make security easier. Machine learning models are also
very significant to reduce the number of false positives detected.
Simple models do exist currently. However, more robust models
in the future will need to be made with more advanced learning so that
we can bypass more of those false positives. Also, secure code
pipelines would be integrated by default.
Adding more tools to our security toolbox is also going to be very
forward looking, and a lot of the times I do get on some of these
engagements with really smart engineers, and I still don't see security
being integrated into all the pipelines, which is bothersome.
All right, let's talk a little bit about evolution. So,
software and security need to continue to become a union, both on the development
side of the house and the security side. There needs to be better integration
between security and software at all levels of development.
Security landscape is always changing, and as such, we need to be dynamic in our
security practices. We need to develop and scale
security practices, solutions and tooling to generate more
secure standards across every single industry. Security research and
findings are also very siloed from each other. We as a community need to do
a better job at letting others know about some of the tooling practices
and vulnerabilities that we've been finding within our projects.
And that's it. Thank you guys so much for listening to my talk.
Please connect with me on LinkedIn. You can see use the QR code
or you can go to that URL. But thank you so much
and I appreciate everyone listening. Thank you.