Hi, my name is Mariah Peterson. I'm really excited to be talking to you
today at Comp 42 and I thank you all for tuning in to
my talk. We're going to be talking today about how to go
from zero to hero when learning
how to code using go. Just a little bit of background
about me I currently work as a data engineer
at a software company based out of Lehigh, Utah. It's called Weave. I am
also a board member of the Forge foundation, nonprofit where we
sponsor local events, conferences, meetup, et cetera,
for people in the tech community. I am the mother
of two beautiful dogs and you can find me on
Twitter, GitHub, LinkedIn, but most easily
on Twitch where I do streams multiple times a
week on anything and everything that I have learned.
New technologies I do learn and I love to just
meet new people and chat and answer questions on there.
So best place to reach out to me,
definitely Twitch. Let's talk a little bit about go.
So go is a great, wonderful, amazing programming
language. People choose it because it's fast, because it's
reliable, because it's compiled, it's super stable, super scalable,
has multiple threads. It's amazing. Everybody under
the sun uses it. It has a great community. It's the best language in the
world. Everyone should use go. But for me, go was my very
first programming language. Well, my very first professional
programming language. I learned it at my first job,
my very first tech job. And if anybody
ever asks me, I say my first programming language was
Go, which is very, very uncommon.
Go and all of its learning materials are really
kind of centered on people who've programmed before
things is just a little bit, a snapshot of what you can find on
the resource section of the
Go website. And it's really based for
people who have used a command line before, who understand functions
and type and all of the basic structures
aligned with programming. And so it's very easy to get into go
and to read use go if you've programmed before, but because
a lot of the tools are based out of the command line, because it's a
compiled language and it doesn't really have a lot
of learning tools that are built into the web, it's not super
accessible to people who have never programmed before.
Or in other words, there's a really high barrier of entry for
getting into go, which in my opinion is the
best programming language, super readable and just ideal
first time programmers. So essentially what people
end up doing when these want to learn go is they either have
learned before and they'll go find some online quick tutorial,
go through syntax and these, they can just dive intro the code and
that's really easy, super open sourced, good for everybody
else. But if you have never programmed before,
you usually end up coding to udemy or udacity
a boot camps and you're spending tons and tons of money to get
the skill of programming before you can learn.
Go. And for some people this presents an
conditionals barrier to entry, where they have to put in
money, research and effort to find quality courses to
gain skills when they don't always have that. They might be coming from low
income backgrounds, they might be working full time jobs, they might be
single parents of children, and they just don't have time to go to school,
or they might not have the extra resources to pay for a course. And so
I'm a really huge proponent of something I like to call open source
learning, or that idea that people who have the
skill, people who have spent time
learning, can share their knowledge in a way that's
more similar to how we interact day to day. We always
look for articles that are free, we look for examples that are
for free, or tutorials that are free. And once you're in the industry, that's super
easy to do and glean skills from, but if you're just coming in, that's really
hard to do. And to be frank, it's quite frightening.
So coming from that experience, these go ins, my first language,
and really being a proponent for this open source learning,
I put together a nice little tutorial that's currently available
on my GitHub with the idea of capturing that audience
who havent never programmed before and teaching them
how to program using go. Like I said, there's a lot of
challenges to this and it's not easy,
but since it is open source, since it's
free for everyone to access, we want to have multiple
contributions and everybody who's ever wanted to share
that knowledge can come in and participate, write some lines of codes, write some
example, and really help people overcome the barrier of entry
to not just go, but programming in general,
and have free resources to learn and to grow and to
gain access to good jobs and available
income. So just really quickly, I plan
on kind of running through a little bit of my strategy, the way I approached
it, the way I approached it in relation to go, as well as into
learning programming for the first time. And then we'll talk a little bit about some
pitfalls, some hurdles, some stuff that's specific to go, and then how anybody
listening can get involved in not only creating the course, but also
taking it if they want to help out in that nature. So the
first section is just can essential intro to programming.
Normally, the first project you do in any programming is considered
a hello world project, right? Where you just get the program up and
running and it just prints out a little hello world. But with go,
you have to install a binary, you have to make sure it's set up.
You have to get your go environment set up, you have to have a gopath
set up on your command line. You have to know how to run all the
go tools. And so that barrier for entry for someone who's never programmed before
gets higher and higher. So what we tried to do with
that is using some online tools like go playground or go play
space, in addition to being able to embed those in
a site, we're kind of removing, abstracting out the tools
and going through things that are much easier. Things like what
is a function, what is a package, what are main functions,
types, certain organization elements and things. You need
to know just the basics, removing all of the necessities of go and just
going into it. So we start with your essential hello world program,
right, where we just go on to a site and just
press run and see the code come up. And we'll just start
dissecting what each piece of that code means, so that they can get used to
reading code and understanding what's there. The next
thing is types. Now,
types are very essential to go it ins,
how we navigate and manipulate data by creating new types,
by using existing types, and by parsing
the data through it, right? So we're going to introduce what's an int, what's a
string. These are all things that people are familiar with, right? They know what numbers
are, they know what words are, these know what letters are, they know chat.
Chinese characters are characters, but we havent to introduce that in a way that they
now know what the syntax is for programming, right? Know what a byte is?
It's just a little fragment of information, right? And a string usually is
the text that we see. Ints or numbers. We have floats and
doubles, floats mostly,
and go and ways to use these numbers and store these numbers
to preserve certain types of information. Things that the words,
they might not be familiar with, but these concepts everybody gets
just from general life. The next thing we want to kind of dive into
for somebody who's never programmed before now chat, we know how
it's structured. Now that we know how to save data and
use data, is kind of the methodologies that
we use when telling a program what to do. We use functions
for this, right? But now we're teaching people that they can tell,
programs tell a computer essentially how to do certain things,
and that's new. They've never told
these computer what to do thing. They just typed buttons.
So there's two aspects we need to work on here, not just defining
functions, but how to use them, right? Like talk about the arguments and parameters
we take and talk about what we return. Talk about putting logic inside the function
and then calling that function inside a main function so that it can
be used efficiently and that these can really gain
confidence in things. Idea of programming and manipulating
code and giving commands and expecting
certain kinds of outcomes. The next things that I
think is really important and super beneficial is to understand the
idea of conditions. Really. This is
control flow in these more like computer sciency
term. But I didn't want to use control flow because
that's a computer sciency term, right. We're trying to keep it in a way that's
a little bit less of a barrier to entry. So this idea of programing a
condition that has to either be met or not met.
So we're doing things like if else statement switch,
introducing the idea of boolean conditions that can be met or not
met, right? That idea of true or false, yes or
no, and that different kinds of functions or different
kinds of logic can be run based on meeting these conditions.
Right. Now, this is where we start to really make
our programs dynamic or smart, or when
we start to really gain confidence as a programmer
and do things. So by going in ins order
and then hitting the conditionals right after the functions, they really start
getting a little bit of momentum, a little bit of comfort in the idea chat.
They can then tell a program what to do
and how to do it. And these, the last thing is, I think,
kind of like the meat and potatoes of everything is this idea of running loops,
or being able to repeat your code a certain amount of
times or an unknown amount of times in order to get a certain result,
you do honestly have to have a basics of
what types are and functions, how we run functions and loops,
how we put loops in functions, and as well as conditionals and how they're met.
Before we can really leverage this idea of
repeating code effectively, right? Like we may need to count
over a slice, which is a type we have defined, or we may need
to iterate through an array, or iterate through a map,
or run your while style loop
until a certain condition is met and until we've had all the background
to get loops, we really can't start to write
just basic programs that do simple tasks.
But now after hitting all of these bullet points in just
kind of this basic digest, what is programming and how we
do it, regardless of code, we can really start
getting into the things that make it, that are required
to be an efficient go. Programmers. Yes, we've been doing all of this
stuff in go, but we've been using online playgrounds and things that kind of abstract
a lot of the go tooling. And now that they're familiar with
programming and have a little bit of consider, it's time to dive into a little
bit more of like the developer side of tooling and things that make go
really have an advantage. When I started to code,
the thing I was most scared of was honestly writing in the terminal.
I thought I was going to click a wrong button. I thought I was going
to nuke my computer and really not be able to go anywhere
from there. And to be fair, once you have
a basic of programming, like 90% of the code I write every day at
work can be done just with a lot of basics.
But I have to do a lot of things in the command line to be
able to run the code, to be able to test the code and do all
those other ins of things to really be an effective developer. So even though they
know the basics, they're not even ready to start developing
and go. And so that's why this section comes into play, right? Like using your
terminal, using your command line, and becoming comfortable with
the developer environment. Something that we often take for granted,
but is really a massive barrier to entry. I know lots of people coming
out of boot camps who have never touched a terminal
and chat really is not going to let them get
a job. They're really kind of at a disadvantage as far
as being able to work efficiently and effectively.
So in this idea of touching the
command line or learning from the command line, there's so
much to learn here, but just high level basics, enough to
be able to just get started in your environment and go forward.
Most important, of course, like running bash commands,
simple things like PWD, CD,
CP, MVRM, RM,
RF. Right? You're removing, you're moving, you're copying, you have to be able to navigate
and copy paste and do all those kinds of things. It's like really critical for
that. But when you have a low barrier at entry, you end up with
two things. You end up with people on Mac or Linux environments
and then people on Windows environments. And those are two totally separate things.
I havent never programmed in a Windows environment. But some
people only have Windows computers, right? Like we're trying to lower the barrier of
entry and that means using whatever tools they have at their disposal. And that might
be $100 Chromebook. That might be. I bet we would need
the section for Chromebooks. See, things is open source learning.
So if you need to go add the stuff for Chromebooks, feel free to go
add that to the bash session, right? But they might have an old Windows machine,
they might be on a Mac laptop that they
used. INS design school. We really want to be able to have
resources for everything and go super basic, super high level, let them be able to
navigate, right? Create directories, organize their code,
and do things that are just considered smart practices. Next thing,
git source control is important. And if they're going to
get a job, they have to be able to put code on GitLab,
BitBucket or GitHub to use as a resume to
say, hey look, I've done projects. Hey look, I've contributed to open source projects.
Hey, I know how to keep track of my code in an organized
manner so that I don't ruin everybody else's commits,
right? It's like essentially anymore, to work on a team you have to be able
to manage source control, and that's just super basic, super fundamental.
And consider how dependencies are managed in go.
You really can't do a whole lot without Git and understanding
the idea of versions and how to manage that after they've gotten
kind of familiar with git bash and that stuff. Time to now
install go. This is pretty easy and straightforward, but there are things you
have to do, like setting up a path so that the binaries can be
accessed, right? You don't have to have a go path. You do have to have
a go path so that they know where all of the source folders live and
creating those things and having them persist in a way that they
can be easily accessed as part of your environment. And last but not
least, choosing that ide that's
best for them, right? Like I will always recommend vs code for somebody who's never
done it before. I use Vim. Some people go way out of their way to
use Golan to have a curated environment that was,
and these developers need to know what's out there, what's best
for them, and how they can work most efficiently. So they might be in a
full ide like Golan, or they might be writing really
simple scripts in Atom or emacs or whatever works best
for them. And so now that we've got, with those basic fundamentals
out of the way, you're learning go get rid of that barrier to entry.
It's really time to start writing go code,
right? You might not be a go developer, you might
be new to go, I'm a go developer. And any developers really
just want to write code, right? Just want to write something so
really basic. In the standard library, you don't have to go external
at all. You can just write your simple go server,
right? Write up an API, throw messages on it,
see the messages print out, come back, and you can do all of those
things so quickly and you can save it ins git, and it can become like
one of your first example projects, really easy and just kind
of like reestablish the things you learn ins typing.
Honestly, APIs are how we communicate through almost
everything, right? We do so much API connection, it's a really fundamental skill
and it just boosts up that confidence, right? And so now
you've gone through three sections, right? You've learned how to code, you've learned the
basics of a terminal, and you've really produced the first Go program.
Now they can say that barrier to entry has been erased, they're now
go developers and they can start building projects.
And so the next section really of the tutorial or what
I had in mind, right? We're going from zero to hero, not zero to I
can write code. And so that means you have to start developing skills
that make you employable, right? You have to start doing things that make you comfortable,
not only in the go ecosystem, but in the ecosystem
where you are maintaining projects, where you're deploying code, where you're working
with other people, and where you're contributing to larger projects,
right? So those are other kinds of things we have to start tackling,
or at least introducing, right, in this idea of the tutorial. And nothing like
super complicated, really easy. But my thought was,
first thing first, we'll start with what has historically been
a rough spot and go dependencies, right? Like how do
we use libraries outside of the standard library,
how do we bring them in? Kind of introduce this idea of what the Gopath
ins, how they're managed, doing versions. Go modules are really easy
to navigate, really easy to add, to start up to use. You have an
entire libraries at package go dev of
modules. You can use the docs forum and start pulling
things in, right? Using libraries that aren't part of the standard
library. That could be the testify library. They could use a muck
server. Me, I really like machine learning
libraries. None of that's part of the standard library. So I pull in lots of
machine learning libraries and use those in. So just build a tiny
little project that doesn't use something from the standard library that
requires go modules and that can really get them used
to things. Idea of looking
for tools that somebody's already made, right? Like these next obviously is
going to be contributing to open source, right? If there's not a library that does
chat you need, then create that library and maybe somebody will use it later.
The next important thing is this idea of checking your code. People who are in
the go ecosystem tend to be very,
very particular about this. People I interact with or have always been very particular
about it. First one is linters go. The standard library
has like govet built into it, has the format
tool, but thumped built into it. It has the import tool built into it,
and the community has really piled on that and they've established really
strict linting guidelines, just as de facto standard in
the community for maintaining certain kinds of code that can be read by
any go developer that can last forever, that anyone
can get up and use. And it's oftentimes and companies
will implement linters, right. For certain coding and standard practices.
So it's a good idea for them to get familiar with linting, get familiar with
the idea of coding standards, and to be able to use that and leverage that
to the best of their need, right? Whether it be in the CLI or in
their text editor. A lot of people do it in CI
CD. We're not quite there yet, but next, testing, right?
This idea that you can write unit tests, that you can
test your code, that you can validate that certain pieces
of logic of your code, right? Things is where we like one of
my favorite concepts when it comes to unit testing, ins writing testable
functions, right? You have business logic that you want to be able to
test, right? So that really helps you simplify your functions, make them
compact and make them handle one piece of logic that can be easily
tests and chat. You can have multiple test cases for, and then you
can test using the Go test tool that's part of the standard library. Then you
could start running the test coverage tool suite that also exists
in the standard library and really do things that
are just cool. You'll look at Go libraries and
they'll tell you how much of it has test coverage. And this is all built
into the standard library. These are just essential things that come part of Go
that they need to be familiar with to really be effective. Go developers
and then tacking intro that writing a project
will allow them to implement tests to use test
coverage, and writing a project that will let them branch kind of off of this
idea of APIs and grow bigger. I actually did this
project myself recently on my Twitch stream, and it was
really good. It was a really good way for me to practice testing. It was
a really good way for me to explore do I want to use
an external library? Do I want to write it to myself?
It's really simple web crawlers, super basic,
almost as basic as an API, but it's a really good way to illustrate
these concepts and use these tools and just get familiar
with the things around you. And probably the last thing that I put in here,
maybe not necessary, but just this idea of
deploying a service, right, like deploying is not hard,
but it's also not trivial. And with the Waco works,
right, you're using binaries or executables or little
compiled functions, and it's not hard to be able to just put
that in a little Docker container. Get that docker container running on your machine,
put your dependencies in Docker and start using Docker and Docker files.
It's really basic. I didn't really go much farther than that because then
you get into, well, do you want it on a server? Do you want it
on a website? Are you doing different kinds of deployments
you want on the cloud? And it was like at a certain point
they just need to experiment and do it themselves. But Docker seems pretty
fundamental and everywhere I've looked it's almost
standard anymore. And I feel by this point, once you get familiar
with Docker and how it works, you can put a service,
run it through a docker container, you're pretty employable.
I've seen people with fewer skills trying to get go jobs,
so it's a good step out there and
it's definitely a way to get forward. And like I said, there's probably a lot
more we can get into with deploying a service. And that's why this
is an open resources tutorial, right? Anybody can contribute.
They can contribute things that are required, things that are optional, things that are good
to learn, and little tutorials that can help a person really gain,
develop and augment these skills. So if you've liked what
you've seen so far, I encourage you to get involved.
Feel free to reach
out to me, look at the code on GitHub,
really do anything. You can sponsor the
project on GitHub, right? That way anybody who works
on that project will get funded, get a little bit more motivation. They can
work on it with more of their time, right? Go ahead and just take the
course, run through it, no issues that have come up. Feel free to
reach out to me on Twitch. I do a couple of times a week.
I've been trying to get on there and work on this course, really get it
out there. The next big thing will be implementing the
go playground into a site
so that the person can start doing those intro
to code things right there with the text. They don't have
to go to a different site, they don't have to export to the GoPro ground,
they don't have to watch a video. They can just read and interact and
go from there. And that's my talk. Thank you so much for listening to my
ideas of using go as a first time
programming language. I really hope that I might have inspired some of
you to get involved and contribute to open source learning through
courses through meetups. Feel free to
contribute to this course on GitHub. I can use all the help I can
get and to really enable people to start developing
and getting more tools. And I hope to see you guys again soon
at another conference on Twitter, on Twitch or wherever,
and enjoy the rest of the conference.