Hello everyone. My name is Vipin Jain and I am
speaking from a beautiful city of India called as Jaipur.
It is also called as the pink city of India.
As already told in my introduction, I work
for a company called as Metacube Software. As a senior
delivery manager and head of the QA department.
IoT is my second love after my job
as a delivery manager. And this has been always a
challenge in front of me. How to develop a strategy
to test IoT end to end. Now, end to
end testing, we all know where we do the system testing, the integration and
unit testing. But since IoT is not just a
single software or a single hardware, it is a mesh of hardware,
software, lots of protocols, there are
APIs, there is a
huge bandwidth connection between them. So I always
ponder about how to test or how to develop a
strategy for embedded systems, particularly Iot.
About end to end testing. So in my talk
end to end testing strategy for embedded systems, I will
give you certain suggestions from my experiences.
So let's move forward now. First and
foremost question that comes to our mind is why do we even
need to end to end test IoT setups when
we can test each aspect of the application? So we
can test software separately, we can test hardware,
protocols, firmware, everything can be tested in a
separate way. So why we need to
perform or develop a strategy to
test the IoT application end to end?
Because we do not want to be in such a situation.
This is a brilliant example of evolving an
end to end solutions without developing
a strategy. And you can end up in such a
situation. So let's begin by a
very brief history. So in the very early phase, IoT was
developed as a two layer architecture where you
have lots of devices and then you have lots of sensors
or the things. IoT is Internet of things,
so lot of things which produced data,
and there is a two way combination between them
and the cloud and the devices. As the application
started getting complex, the IoT infrastructure or
the architecture also started becoming complex. And then
we introduced the third layer. And hence IoT
became a three layer architecture. Where there is an application layer,
a transportation layer and an interception layer,
the things become more complex, the infrastructure becomes more
complex, and similarly the software has become more complex.
And ultimately, after lots of,
I would say development and lots of thinking,
a new seven layered architecture was introduced.
And this is the one which is currently being used.
If I quickly take you to what this seven layers architecture means,
these are the seven layers where the lowest level
or the things which produce the data, they are
the physical device layers. Then there is a connectivity layers, edge computing
layer, data accumulation, data abstraction,
application layer and finally the collaboration and process
layer. Now all these layers were introduced because the modern day
applications are very complex and lot of communication
happened between layers. So then in order
to develop it or in order to test it, we need to apply our
logics at every layer. And this is the base
of my strategy. Now, what are the challenges
in IoT testing? As I've just explained,
IoT is a multilayered system. Then there are
lots of dissimilar technologies being
used in developing these systems, changing from very low level
microcontrollers and very high level server programming.
The functionalities span across multiple layers.
Hence the communication between two layers become very important.
Then the devices follow protocols, but then different
protocols can be applicable to different devices,
which means the protocols can become incompatible.
The functionalities were developed by different teams or the teams
which are sitting geographically very apart. So hence,
because those teams are not working together, sitting together,
there are scenarios where the use cases, they do
not match with each other. The solution looks simpler
because there is a very limited UI, but below that interface
there is a very, very complex architecture and code
is very less to justify your testing because I can
write 100 test cases and can say that look, everything is working
fine, but those 100 test cases are actually just
testing the code which is written, which can be only
10% of the entire architecture and not enough test cases
are written to test that architecture.
So these are some challenges which are different from the
challenges we have faced in testing noniot applications.
So what is the general practice when we start talking about e
two e testing? Organizations use e two e testing
at system level. They follow the most logical option available,
like assemble the system fully and then test it,
which gives a realistic simulation of the end user
experience. But the issues that they face, as I
explained earlier, also systems cannot simulate
all the situations. Building such a system is very time consuming
and costly. You need to gather every component, make sure all
the components are connected with each other, the protocols are
compatible and so on. Testing become very changing
as it involves many applications working in tandem.
APIs become very, very important here.
The error detection happens in late cycle because everything is
made, then it has been simulated and now if
you can find an error then the entire setup or entire development
process Iot needs to be reworked upon. This ultimately
results in a lot of delay in the time to market and
the responses to that application are very verified and they become
very difficult to handle. I take a very simple example
which is called as a blood glucose tracking system. Now what
happens here is,
as you can see in this diagram, there are
two variables. One is the glucose sensor and the other is
the insulin injector. And then there is a smartphone
which acts as the middleware. So very
simply put, there is a glucose sensor,
like a small, I would say a patch which has a chip
and that is inserted on. There's a small pin inserted
inside your stomach and the patch is stuck on your
stomach. And then it is constantly checking the blood sugar level.
If the sugar level goes above or below a certain
threshold value, it sends a message to the mobile.
And from the mobile which acts as a middleware, it goes to cloud
where lot of healthcare management system takes place. And as a
result it sends an instruction back to the insulin pump
if required, so that the pump gets activated and
some insulin is secreted inside the body of the patient.
So he gets immediate attention despite of where
he is standing or sitting in
the world. So this is the blood dugout tracking
system that I want to explain. So this sensor monitor the
blood for certain parameter, and the insulin injector follows a programmed
schedule. But the problem is, if it is disconnected from
the other components of the system, then there can be
issues, right? And we'll see each issue one by one.
Let's see this diagram in detail. So now you can
see all the movements of the data and the instructions
between various places. And let me explain each one of them.
So, as I mentioned, the smartphone app serves as a middleware.
And in addition to providing simple analysis to the user,
the app forwards glucose level information to cloudbased
healthcare system for additional processing.
This cloud application compares the current measurement to the historical
data of the patient and perform advanced analysis.
And IoT constantly keeps looking for some unwanted patterns.
If any unwanted pattern is found and IoT can
lead to a potential danger, the system sends a warning directly
to the user or reports to a human medical staff.
Specialized medical consultant can immediately analyze the data and
decides whether or not a special alert needs to be generated for the
patient. The patient receives an alarm and guidance
for the next steps, which can include change in the medication dosing.
After the patient's approval, the change are delivered to
the injector. But there can be a scenario where
the patient is IoT able to respond. In that case, the medical consultants
can send the GPS information packaged with
the smartphone data to send an ambulance. Your mobile's automation
can be tracked and immediate medical help can
be sent. Right?
So this is the entire blood tracking system
diagram which I just explained. So this healthcare system covers everything
here the phone acts as the middleware and
immediate helps from the doctor to the patient. Can happen
if the healthcare system alerts this and all this
data gets recorded in the cloud, so that the next time something happens,
it is again matched to the historical data which is already
present. Let's see some wider scenarios. So what
is the basic use case here? The blood sensor is simulated,
the data package is selected, the data moves
to the cloud, the cloud generate alerts. After comparing the current
data with the existing data, the medical staff responds
to the alert either by injecting the insulin or by
changing the dose of the insulin, or by alerting some medical staff
and ambulance nearby. The patient also receives those
alert and notifications and ultimately the injection schedule
and the injecting of insulin is completely
automated. And all of these things still have to
follow, still have to cater to these market requirements.
Test early and test often speed versus quality time to
market automation. We need to still perform all
of these. But this is a typical IoT application.
And if you see there is a cloud storage, there are
data moving, there are bandwidth involved, there are
devices, there is mobile, there is Internet speeds,
all of these need to be tested. And then
only we can say that I have what is called
as an end to end testing strategy for
testing blood glucose patient monitoring systems.
So what is the solution, how to perform these kind
of testing? Deconstruct the system into layers
for more effective testing. So rather than taking the entire application
as a whole, break it down into perception layer, network layer,
middlewares, business layer and application layer.
Your perception layer consists of the physical objects,
sensors. The network layer consists of the transmissions,
three g, four g. The middleware layers consist of information,
process, action, the storage,
whereas the business layer, it takes a look at the analytics and flowcharts
to see the data. And finally, the application layer where
the smart applications and their management resides.
And then in each layer, isolate the components
and test early. So if every layer just
separate out the components. So your wireless, IoT devices,
IoT smartphone, laptops, security gateways,
security devices, just separate them and
then test each one of them. Few are already
required as tested by their vendors and few we have to test as
testers. Right?
So this is the two things that I want to
explain. And now let's
move forward. Deconstruct the system into layers,
which is the first one. What are the primary challenges?
Designing the system in such a way that it can be
conducive to deconstruct in smaller blocks with well defined interfaces.
Just like we say that in manual and automation testing automation
needs to be built into the code so that when we automation
engineers want to perform it, then they can do it.
Similarly, the system should be designed here in
such a way that it can be broken down or deconstructed
into smaller blocks, and each block should have a well defined
interface. And then you have to build automation around
these blocks. And there is always a discussion that
goes on between unit testing versus functional
testing. So in general, a test plan should include
a combination of unit testing, integration testing,
and endtoend testing. The proportion of unit test
to integration test may vary depending on the complexity
of the solution. The more complex the solutions is,
the more important unit tests become, because as
the complexity grows, it become more and more difficult to
simulate high level interfaces that ensure that various paths are
executed. Unit testing, though, is expensive.
We all know that, and it is expensive in terms of time and resources.
Therefore, someone with a programmatic experience,
for example, an engineer, must write the test,
and because they are closely tied to the code, unit tests are
also brittle, which means changing in a code could
easily impact them. So an engineer is required consistently
to maintain the tests as you move further up
the stack. Function level tests are less prone to breakage,
but it becomes hard to identify systematic issues when
a unit test fails. On the other hand, identifying the root cause is
very simpler, so you have to actually do a trade off to
find a balance or create a blended approach to
see a balance between unit test and functional
testing. So use a blended approach for testing IoT,
deconstruct the system into layers, right. So what
we want to discuss here. So for IoT
solutions, the first natural layer contains
the wireless communication components. This is where
the subsystem interacts with the APIs. Now,
underneath the APIs are messaging protocols such as
MQTT or HTTP, which send payloads
like JSON and Rest, as well as the proprietary protocol
and binary payloads. In the IoT world,
the communication usually follows a publish
subscribe model or a request response model.
This model involves broadcasting data while other
components listen for and then consume the published data
and perform an action in request response model. We just
send a message to the server directly and asynchronously
waiting for a response. Automation is the key.
What does that mean? To do this,
you have to have a framework for simulating the sut
system under test and verify its response,
as shown here. For simple scenarios,
Python or simpler steps can serve as service testing
solutions. There are a number of stepping utilities
that easily allow you to send payloads for testing purposes,
but this tactic doesn't scale as the number
of test scenarios grows from few hundred to few thousand,
adding and changing the scripts become difficult and inefficient.
So implementing more complex parameters is very difficult to
do. With simple scripting tools.
For smaller small sized things, it becomes very useful.
You also can automate the server components.
For example, you see this cloud healthcare system.
There is this API layer. The message or the payload is sent
to the services. The response comes back
and then from the cloud two messages can go, one to
the medical point location system and other to the medical
staff consultation center. So this is a
back end, right? The database contains all the historical
data. The process is similar to testing the sensor.
Simulate the system by sending a simulated package of data from
the patient. Now the blood scan report, which comes back
if it has some deviation, which means a warning needs to
be produced. High priority warning involves
human medical staff, low consultation. The warning message is
sent back to the patient may contain information about the nearest
hospital, urgent care or other medical facility.
The testing framework will execute a number of test cases
containing different values for different patients and expect
specific warnings to be generated in the response.
We can isolate the components and stress early,
so let's also use a case here. Scan blood to
determine glucose level we could potentially place the sensor
probe in a liquid with a known level of glucose and other parameters corresponding
to real blood, but this approach is neither practical
nor it is scalable. A better approach would
be to intercept the function call that reads from the probe
and redirect it to the testware stub or mock for generating
and simulating a response. It will eliminate
the probe itself from the testing process while enabling the
opportunity to perform automated testing of all the
other parts of the system. A mock of the
interaction needs to be installed to emulate a hardware function call.
The stuff should be able to respond with reasonable values during the test
process, using hard coded values or reading test data
from an external data source. You also have
to isolate the server side components, which again looks
like the client side components, but there is some difference.
For simple test cases, you can use a stuff that contains a node JS
script to produce the standard responses. But for
more advanced scenarios, a service virtualization tool
can allow you to define a response depending on
the input pattern. You can also use service
virtualization to record actual traffic and replay it
to simulate the real operations of a connected system.
In some cases, you may want to switch even between
a real system or a virtual asset. So a
group of medical experts here are connected to this prioritized queue
for consultation requests. The first person that becomes
available, processes the next highest priority
request to enable the automated testing,
we need to replace this part of the system with a virtual
equivalent. So this is how we can separate
the components and then test them separately, whether they
are the server side components or whether they are the
client side components. So you have to remember a few things.
IoT systems require thinking about the software quality
in a larger scope. IoT solutions,
such as our medical device examples,
they are different from the normal systems because an
individual feature may span multiple layers of the solution.
Which means if we start testing these individual
functionality, you actually have to traverse between
various layers. That means the communication
between any two layers becomes very important.
The response request models or the published consume models
are again very important because data gets published from
one layer, may get consumed at some other layer.
Similarly, the response sent or the request sent from
one layer may receive a response from another layer.
So at every layer we need to ensure that we should be
able to send data or we should be able to receive data.
Then delivering a high quality system, it requires testing
capabilities at every layer. But the problem here is
the low level layer has a lot of c
code, the API testing layers, and then there is a backend
part which is the very hard to access layer. So you have to
develop strategy to cover all of these.
You also have to consider a lot of cost which is associated with
the system, because the reason is quite simple,
a design failure that can outweigh the cost of deploying
or testing solution. If you encounter such,
ensure that you have a
testing solution which enables you to isolate the test
components or the API testing or the backend testing.
So with this I come to the end of this
talk. I hope you got some valuable information out
of it. IoT testing is challenging, but it
is not difficult. You have to upgrade
yourself from your normal testings to IoT testing, and you
also have to upskill yourself from testing softwares
to testing hardwares. Firmwares have
a mix of all kind of testing, and then you should
be able to test Iot quite easily.
Thank you. Thank you for hearing me patiently.
I'm open to any kind of questions. Thank you.