You. Hi everyone,
good morning, good afternoon, good evening. My name is Romansh
Yadav. I welcome you all at Con 42.
Thank you for joining. So today we will talk about
attacking defending mobile apps in this session and
below. This is our content for today's session.
We will talk about Android introduction and basic. We will
try to set up Android pen testing environment and we will do reverse
engineering and runtime manipulation. We will also touch Android
components, application components and security issue in Android.
And in the last we will touch defensive tool and techniques
for Android. So let's start with the Android Introduction Basic.
As we know Android is an operating system and here
is the architecture of Android. We have application layer,
then we have application framework, then we have libraries and
Android runtime, and then we have Linux kernel. So we will start from the
Linux kernel. So Linux kernel provides some basic system functionality like
process management, memory management, device management, right.
Kernel also provide the user basic permission model, process isolation,
right? And now we have libraries like we have webkit
libraries, escalate libraries like we use. So these libraries support
our application. Like Webkit libraries support web browsers,
escalate library support, escalate database. So these
are the supportive library that support our application. Now we have
Android runtime, like Android runtime and we have
core libraries and Dalwig virtual machine, right? So like Dalwig
virtual machine which is specifically designed by Android open
source project to execute applications written for Android.
Each apps training in the Android device has its own Dalwick
virtual machine and Android runtime is an alternative to Dalvig virtual
machine which has been released with Android four as
an experiment release. Like in Android Lollipop, it will be complete,
replaced by Dalvik Virtual Machine. I mean art will replace Dalvig
virtual machine in Android Lollipop. So the
changes in art is like ahead of time. We call
it arts ahead of time compilation. So basically there are
two terms like one is Jet git,
sorry, just in time compilation in which bytecode are compiled.
Bytecode are compiled when users run the apps. But in
AoT ahead of time compilation, Android apps will
be compiled when user installed them on their device.
Right. When we are installing the app that time whitecode
compiled in AoT ahead of time compilation. Now application
framework, right? Like application framework layer provide many high
level services to the application in the form of Java classes
like activity manager, window manager, content provider, content provider
is used to share data with one app to other app,
right? Notification Manager, broadcast, we will see here some
broadcast receiver also here, right? And at
the layer of application we have application all whatever we install
the application that come on the application layer.
So this is the Android architecture
and we can see here different, different layer, right. And we
will see in upcoming slides which layer
used to do what kind of stuff. Right now
this is some fundamental Android application.
Fundamental Android apps are written in the Java programming language
as we know. But nowadays like we can develop, we have
some many multiplatform frameworks like Kotline,
like Flutter. So we can develop multiplatform application within
one framework, right? But at the back end at the basic,
the part of Android is written in Java programming language. So this
is the Android file system structure. We can see it's
based on Linux so the file system strip iOS similar to
Linux. We have root ATC and we can see sd card
and external sd card. If we put any external sd card, sd card.
So we will see the external sd card folder here. This is the Android
permission model and sandboxing as we know that it is managed by
the kernel Linux kernel. So Android assign a unique user
id to each Android application. Suppose we install a app,
one, app two. So every app will get a unique user id that is used
because Android use the UID to set up a kernel level application
sandbox. So if suppose here we can see data,
this is a kind of sandbox that this
app cannot access the data of app two or app two cannot
access the data of app two. So app one. So this is related
to the all sandboxing, right? This is the process of building
apk. Like suppose we want to build an apk.
Now we have a Java code. Then we convert the Java code into
bytecode with the help of the Java compiler. Then we convert
bytecode into the DeX code with the help of Dex compiler.
Then we build the apk, right? So that apk we can
install into our system, into our emulator
or into a mobile operating system. This is the Android components we have activity
activity is a screen. So we see login screen, vc,
register screen, vc, whatever the screen is that we call activity
services. Like suppose we are listening music in the background,
we are doing some chatting, so the
background service is called a service, music is called service. Then we
have broadcast receiver. Like suppose we want to give a
broadcast notification to each and every of that. The battery
is down, we receive battery down, broadcast receiver. And so many
broadcast receiver like notifications also comes into broadcast receiver,
right? A content provider. We use content provider like we share
data one data to other one data from
one app to other apps. So we use content provider and
we have intent also so intent bind individually component
to each other at runtime. Suppose we are running two,
three, four app and suppose we want to open a link and
we see a link in the mobile app and we click on that will go
to web browser. So that will happen
with the help of intent. Okay, now let's see, let's set
up the pen testing environment lab. So I would suggest
if you are new so you can download directly mobile
access. This is the operating system and this is a complete vm.
It will come up with all the tools that require for Android
and as well as iOS pen testing. And if
you are like suppose you
want to create lab for your own, you want to install each
and every tool step by step, one by one. Then you can download Jenny
motion, you can download apps, apps, iOS, a toolkit
that has eight to ten, eight to ten tool for Android
pen testing. And then you
can install any custom image of Android iOS. And then
you can install the ADB Android debug bridge.
And then you can start with the Android pen testing. So I will show
you. This is my Jenny motion here. You can see
this is my Jenny motion here. And suppose I am running this
emulator or I will close it and I will start again. As you
can see it is starting. So Jenny motion
need virtualbox. So you need to have virtualbox in your
iOS and okay it is starting, it's almost started
and you can do some configuration as well. So you want
to take it on net or you want to right now
we cannot edit it, but you can change the network as well. Bridge or
Nat, whatever you want. Because the system
what you are using should be on same network, right? Suppose now
I have already installed the ADB. ADB is
a Android debug bridge. So you can see we have so many
options in ADB, we can do push, suppose we want to do some
push some file to the Android emulator, we can do that.
If we want to pull any file from Android emulator
we can do that too. And then, okay, now there is a
command to check if device is listed or not. Here you can see yes,
device is listed and we can give a command and ADB shell.
So now we are into the Android emulator. You can see who I
am root, right? We can see all these files here.
Now we will exit it from here. So this is all about
setting up the Android pen testing lab because we have only
40 minutes to complete this session. So that's why I
am little bit going fast, right, so this is here.
Now this is the mobile access, you can download it
from Google, you will find it. So this is
complete if I.
Okay,
yeah. So you can see the tools
that already install in the mobile
access Zdex leader GDGI Lockhead
padcad whitecode viewer. It is a complete
vm for mobile Pen testing. Like you can do Android and
iOS as well. You can see here so many tools here,
iOS John, Android, John, and all you can see here,
right, bub suit and you can see Iogen
passive suit is there for Android, iOS,
MOFs is there for.
So we are all set with our lab.
If you face any problem then please message me.
I will drop my email. So you can message
me or you can email me right now.
We will move forward, we will try to now deep
into mobile pen testing approach. So there are two types of mobile
pen testing approach. First, static pen testing and then
dynamic pen testing. So static pen testing, we do static
pen testing when app is not running. App is like
in a rest mode. Suppose we get ApK and we
are not going to install the apk. We have to just do some
decompilation, decompilation signing, try to,
try to dig into the application without running it on the emulator,
right? So it's called like static pen testing.
When we install the application, we try to intercept the traffic.
We see the traffic in burp suit and then we try to
do some access controlled issue, some token related issue,
and we try to manipulate some data that, and sometimes we try to
hook the app by using serial tool.
We try to do some runtime manipulation that call dynamic
that's come into the dynamic pen testing approach.
Okay, now let's do some reverse engineering.
So we will start with static
pen testing. We have already an app, it's called Piva.
So you guys can download it again.
You will find it. It is a very good app.
I also type the link,
this one. This is a very good app for the
beginners as well, right? Basically beginners can easily
run it and it contains so many vulnerability as
well. So like reverse engineering.
Now, reverse engineering is a process where we try to
extract the code from APK.
So we will use the tool, APK tool for
reverse engineering. So we can see here,
it is already there. So I will remove it.
Okay.
So it will override it. No problem. So now APK tool
is like you can see here, loading table resources,
decoding Android fest file, then loading resource,
then regular, then decoding file resource. So it
will decompile this. Right now, if we go into this
directory, we can see so many files, smallly original.
We can see Android manifest file. Now after
doing the decompile of the ApK. Our first job
should be like understanding the Android manifest
file. Now what is Android manifest file? Android manifest file
iOS the central file of the complete
Android application. So whatever Android application is using,
how many activities are there, what kind of permission they are using.
They're asking for the user how many broadcast receiver, how many
content provider, all are mentioned inside the Android
manifest file. If any activity is
exported, is there any broadcast receiver or broadcast
whatever they have exported? Everything is mentioned
inside the Android Menson file. You can see
here sorry get account,
read profile, read contain and now you can see here
write external storage permission. Read external storage permission,
right. Cell phone so everything mentioned
inside the Android mansource file and we will
see here some backup. Yes, backup. Backup is true.
So anyone can take user can take the backup,
right? So after that we
can go in assets, we can see
assets. It is not any sensitive information.
Json.com now the thing that
we have to see is string. Also it
will come in resource, I guess classes
build ss excellent Java. So we can go step
one by one by one and we can see and
explore each and every file.
We can see this string here value,
value, right? Sometimes what happened,
they mention some authorization inside the
script. So iOS, the admin is yes or no. So that
kind of stuff sometimes nowadays it's not happened, but sometimes they
have mentioned in the side this string file and
then you can see original again
the file metanfo you can see certificate here.
You can see the certificate, right?
It's a signed certificate.
Okay, so the point is like we can
decompile the application, we can read the Android manifest
file, we can read all the files. If we know the smally,
if we understand the smally, we can also see the smally so
that it will give us the idea that what kind of vulnerability we can find
easily. What is the hanging fruits right now
there iOS a different thing. Like suppose we want to tamper application.
So suppose tampering is a process. When we change some data,
like suppose we want to do backup is false,
we want to backup is true, or we want to do some code
change in smally files, then we have to
write some small code inside the application, right? So whatever,
we will change it and we will temper it. Then we have
to again recompile it, resign it. Then again we can
install it inside the emulator. So we
have done the decompilation, right? Smallly code. Now there
is a different tool, d two jdex
two jar. So what this tool do?
It will create a jar file and we can directly open that
jar file into the, it is also a Java decompiler so
it will create a jar file and then we can open
jar file into jdgui. It's a very nice, we will also try this,
okay, we will try here. So this
is Java decompiler Jdgui and
this is here we can see our
application. Now we
will try to dex
to jar. Right now we will give the file
name,
okay,
it's successful. Now we will try to open this jar file into
Java decompiler. So we can
go directly into this path here.
We can open it so
we can see here Android this is here all
activity we can see about classes,
botcard classes, build config. We can see here debug mode.
So suppose we want to search anything. We can search
it also we can see, okay, database created classes
here. Suppose we want to search anything. We want to suppose search
username, right? So we will enable it filled string,
right? Yes, username. So we
will see here authentication class.
This is like username and
this is username
test. You can see hard coded, right? We can
see password, hard coded here also very complicated
password. You can see test users, right? So these are,
you can see access. This is inside the
application. So this is
all about the decompilation.
We have to move forward. So you can search anything,
but you want to search password. You can
search password. You will see here, okay, let me
again. Password here
and then you can see here password,
you can see here, right? So suppose you want to search any API
key, any inbuilt API key API.
You can search API. So if
there is any API key that you will find here, right?
If you can search about keys token,
these are some keyboards that you can search inside the
application. Okay,
now let's move to the next part as we
see, okay, we have already see the Android Menson file service.
Continue provide activity broadcast need to be mentioned in the Android menus
file permission and exported services. Right now
we will try to recompile the app. We already recompiled
the app right now. We will try to rebuild
it and resign it. And then we will try to again
install this app, right? So, okay, it's very
simple. We can do this with the help of APK tool.
So now I'm going to change something.
I will change very small,
like suppose I want to make this,
it's already true, but okay, let's make it false.
Okay, make it debuggable false. Also right
now we have made some changes.
We have to give the folder name Piva.
Now we will try to build it.
So we will get APK inside this
Piva folder. Build APK successful.
Here we can see we will go to Piva
folder, we will go to test destination and
here you can see we got this apk
bit. But this is not signed APK, right?
So again we have to sign it with any Java signer,
right? We have a signer. So what I will do it.
I will copy this.
First I want to change this name, right new
one APK.
Then I will copy it one,
two, yeah.
Okay now I want
to copy this.
Here we will find this one.
So this is the new one, right? This iOS the new one.
Now we already build
our APK. Now we have to sign it. So we need a
signer. We have already signed up so this is our signer. In this directory
we will again go to this Java,
Java, right and we need the file name so
we can easily give the file name here.
Okay jar
sign jar sorry.
Right now we will get the new
signed apk at this path, same path.
This one. This is the new signed one, right? So we will change
iOS name hello
new we'll make it hello new
okay now we have a hello new, right?
So now we are going to install this.
First let me uninstall this one.
Uninstall finish. Okay, right now
this is uninstalled. Now what I will do, I will install new one
Adb install hello
new and okay we
got the success. We can see here if the application has been
installed. Let's check it. Okay this
is there and we can even see their test and
we can see the password is there, right we
can see the password is here,
very complicated.
We can copy it and
we can paste it here,
right we have login and we can see there are
so many okay this is stb ssl
web uas vulnerability. So now after login inside
the application let's go to about the project and
try to understand the project. So here we can see list
of vulnerability cover in this project. So there are
so many vulnerabilities lists that this application will
cover. Suppose like this, I mean these are
not so risky vulnerabilities but it
all depend on the application nature and behavior.
Like uses of weak initialization vector possible man in the middle attack
remote URL load in web view object desolation found
right enable debug mode weak encryption hard coded encryption
key as we've seen hard coded username and password dynamic load of code
creation of world readable item file as sometimes what
happened app create a world readable and item file inside the external
storage, right? Or maybe internal storage use of uncreative
app is communicating in ACET protocol weak hashing
algorithm app is using MD four, Shaw one or MD five
kind of algorithm that is weak app iOS creating predictable
numbers generator function app is using suppose
they are using just s random. So basically
there are so many number of vulnerabilities
you can find in this application and you can do your practice.
It will be very helpful and it will be a very learning experience.
You can see part traversal is there self signed ca enabled in webview clear
test HTTP js
temporary file creation is there displayed set pluginistic
in webview untrusted ca accepted uses
of ban API function. So you will get to learn so
many things. Why just write some test
cases in this application. Okay now
we will move to our next Android
runtime manipulation. So basically we will use the frida
for doing the runtime manipulation. And frida is a world class dynamic distribution
toolkit. It's very good. And if you want to set up
the freeda so you can go to this blog and
you can set up the freedom even he also
shares some trick for bypassing the ssl pinning using
frida or you can also bypass the root reduction. You can
do so many things with frida even if your device
is not rooted then you can use the frida gadgets. So without
even rooted your device you can use the Freeda gadgets library
and then you can do runtime manipulation. So I
already installed the freedom and do one thing sorry.
Make sure you have to match the server and
client version same. So when you install the freedom
server it should be
same right inside your emulator and inside
your operating system, your base operating system. So I
already installed it. So whenever you are set then
you can give this command frida psyphon u it
will show you all these I already
installed the feeder. Now it
is saying that cedar is okay. So now we have to start the feeder
server. This is the command in what
happened? Let me watch it.
So this is the command to start the freeda
server inside my gen inside my emulator.
So I will give this command
and now the feeder has been started, right?
If I try to give this command it
will show all. Now feeder has started and
we can see all the apps
here with their package name. Suppose we are
not able to see the st bridge, right? So because the app is
we should be here.
We can see here. This is the app that we are going to pen
test.
Suppose we want to hook this app. So simply we can
run this command simply,
we can run this command Freeda
and then package name.
And then the filter script is
necessary, right.
Package name,
package name I have to, sorry,
copy package name.
Let's copy the package name where it is.
Ht bridge this one.
Okay, now this is the package name,
right? So it's a command, this command,
we have to run it with this script,
no CdA package
name. Hyphen F is also there for hosting.
Then hyphen L for script pinning
script now and then no
pause. So it will, no pause, it will hook
one time and then resuming
main set. Process terminated. Okay,
piva has a stop. So basically it creates some problem with
the emulator, but when you will run it on your real device, it will not
create problem, it will hook successfully and
it will bypass whatever the script you will use for
like pinning or do deduction or whatever the
script you will use. So it will work. So this is the way, like we
do with Frida, we work with frida, like this one, we give the commands
with package name, we hook the application,
right?
And now we have application component security
issue. So many like
we have seen hard coded credential inside the,
inside the device when we did
the Java decompilation,
this is also a vulnerability. Sometimes what happened?
Developers store the data inside the mobile device. So we
can also check if they are storing
some sensitive information inside the mobile device.
So we can go adb shell, we can see, okay,
data, then again data
and then we can package name here
and now here we go shared information.
We see, okay, we can get this file
stand on nothing in this file, no problem.
We can files
block file,
you can see here test and very complicated password.
So this is the credential they are storing inside the device,
right? So in that way we check if they are storing
any hard, any credential or any sensitive information inside the mobile
device.
Other bugs like there are so many bugs like idol.
We can test idol API vulnerability,
we can test API vulnerabilities, access control issue, ox related vulnerability,
jw token related vulnerability. So what we will do,
we will try to do
interception, no problem,
we have fine,
I'm going to add a proxy.
Okay, 8090 I
will proxy
has started, right? Nice, right.
So I have set
up a proxy here. So for that you can also install
the burp certificate for intercepting the HTTP request.
So in that case you just type here burp httpp
and you download certificate like here because
it's already installed. But I will show you how to do that.
Okay, maybe so
here, if we click on this ca it will download started
downloading. I don't know what iOS
stopping but when you download it you can go to
gallery.
Gallery? Yeah this is downloads.
No item here it is not downloaded actually.
Okay, no problem. So I will try to
do a restart of this sometime. It's create
problem while doing it starting. So there is another way to
push. Suppose we want to push a certificate or
whatever we want to push so we can directly push
from here. Adb push
user I
might having a certificate.
You can see here I have a certificate. It is a del extension.
No problem.
We will try to push this certificate just
for the demo sd card.
Here we can see one file push. If we see this file.
This is the file and that is already a certificate.
Here I push before. And one
thing, you can face some a problem when you try to install
app. This is Jennymotion arm transaction.
So sometime what happened? Like the
app is not compatible with arm processor.
So then you have to install this Jenny motion arm
translation. So after installing it you have
to just flush it and then you will be able
to install any app, right.
So I
will show you how to intercept the traffic. I mean traffic
is already coming, okay,
this is my work. Suppose I want to intercept browser
traffic. So here you can see I
already installed the certificate. Now traffic is coming here.
So I can see all the traffic. And I can found access controlled vulnerability,
idol token related vulnerability,
even I can open it. This app itself,
this one, right.
So this is SSL API.
You want to try the API bypassing. So you can use that
API and here test. Okay, now I will
see,
okay, it is not going to server, the traffic is not going to
serve, it is checking internally I guess.
But this is the only traffic going to server.
Suppose we want to go here st bridge. Okay if
you want to see this link three, it will go to there
because we can also perform the cross site descripting inside
a mobile device. That is the option. That is the vulnerability
that inside the web view. If the GS
is enabled inside the web view, then we can perform the cross site
scripting,
right? So you can see here access
because the script is hosted at this URL.
And if we are enabling that,
we can load a remote URL inside the web view without
any validation. So we can do access. Also we
can go to, okay, no problem. So for
that go to Piva,
right. So now here you can see so many
vulnerability. You can test it. So many vulnerability,
so many vulnerabilities. So guys,
okay, try each and every vulnerability,
try to understand and try to replicate these,
all the practical and whatever you find
or whatever, you face any problem, then you
guys can reach out to me anytime. And this is
my email id. You romansh
yadav@gmail.com so you guys can reach out to
me and I can give you the suggestion or whatever where
you are stuck in. So I can give you the advice
or I will try to solve your problem. All right, guys,
so that's all from my side. I'm glad you have joined
me for today's session. Thank you very much.