Hi. Hello and welcome to the case study of building operations team
at Makolab. For last three years I effectively and
efficiently built area of DevOps operations, maintenancesupport and support
that delivers outcomes by going beyond the standard DevOps framework
with diverse competencies. Every day I'm going out
of the box. Extending classic DevOps approach in multidimensional
operations that boost up projects and deliver highest
quality. I'm from Wooch. Woodch is a very colorful city,
the center of Poland and in case that you will visit it,
let me know. I can guide you through the main areas
that you should visit. Okay. My name is Grzegorz Sztandera
and for the last 20 years I'm working for the
banking and it industry. Twelve years for the project management
and also last few years, as I said,
building the DevOps area at Macula,
providing services for multiple industries.
Personally I like traveling to extraordinary
destinations like on the picture you can see me in front of the fourth
reactor of nuclear plant of Chernobyl in Ukraine and
also I'm working on the free shifts because I'm working at Makolab
and also I have two sons being creative
means. Also that I'm a painter for the board game Minifix
and recently I wrote a book stories for kids which is
in printing process right now. What is the pipeline
for our today presentation?
First I would like to highlight our
areas of expertise with our plugin approach of the operations team.
So you will see what we reached after two three years of building
that area. Then I will explain more about operations
team and I will cover multiple stages and aspects
of building this team for the last few years.
Before the end and before the summary, I will present
few projects that we were taking part of on
a general layer and after that I will share a few takeaways
with you. The most important from my point of view, which was crucial
for this success story. Okay,
let's start DevOps up. Plugin approach what does it
mean? We are in the middle of the ecosystem,
so generally I will explain the plugin approach later. But we are
between the project developers, QAS and
project management and we are taking care of everything. What is needed for
the project does mean we are taking care of
test int e to e environments and also
supporting testing for the project. From the second
side we are supporting customer, third party
companies and end users taking care of everything
around us. 360 we are taking care
of environments including production, monitoring of the
environments. We are providing the whole scope of it
services and maintenancesupport building
and delivering the CICD processes also
hypercur with extended productivity and predictive
maintenancesupport everything in the 24/7 manner of on call
and if possible and if we will have time, we are providing also
a lot of automation inside our
work. I can divide my team services
into three areas, as I said, Dev, Ops and sub.
So Dev, it's strictly connected with coding and
creating something. Ops in my
understanding means that we are operating what we did
create or what we receive to operate from the
customer with extended productivity, predictive maintenance
and so on. SAP refers mostly to itil
processes and standard support extended with deep
analysis of case within our team from
my perspective as an operations manager,
we are capable of creating any architecture and providing
the ideas for service architecture for the customer to
suit the customer needs. After that we are managing
it in example on production and after
delivering or having the application or
the product that is needed to be on production,
we can optimize and provide service optimization based
on our know how and our operations. For example from
the monitoring systems plugin approach,
the sample activity for plugin approach is just
in case of need. We are capable not only
to provide the full scope of DevOps operations, maintenance and support services,
but in case of need we can plug in into the project or into the
customer environment, perform the tasks and then switch
off the sample of that is for example
building the automation with terraform for AWS
environments. We had a project where
customer asked us to look into
the manually created AWS environment for the product
to optimize it and after that to create it using
terraform. So we were plugged into the project,
we provided the terraform scripts, run it,
deployed a new infrastructure and after that we
switched off from that specific project. This is the plugin approach
so we are not only providing the complex services but in case
of need. Like a wanting army, we can act and
provide the specific tasks that are needed
by the project or the customer. On the screen you
can see just the sample list of the activities that we can provide.
Also, we are multi cloud team, so we are capable
of providing the solutions on for example AWS.
On azure environment we are the can in black,
so we are available and we are providing the services during
the day and the night. In case of needs. During the
day we are providing knowledge sharing with the project or we are participating
in the standard activities that project is having
in the scrum or agile methodology. So to
sum up, we are able to deliver the whole DevOps
classic approach, including development and QA based on other
Makolab teams. But we are involved in any of
those eight activities, as you can see on the screen, in a different
way of working in a different approach.
Now we will move to the building of my team.
When I came to Makolab three years ago, I had a team
of three persons and after a month two
of those free persons gives the resignation letter.
So at the very first month
of my potential of leading the team, I left with one
person having one project on production and
supporting in the full 24/7 manner.
So it was not the best
start. But as you can see on the chart,
based on the FT number of employees in the team,
it was rapidly growing. Between 2021 and 2022
I will focus on those two first years of building the team because right
now it is quite stable and the competition are
growing and the projects are changing
so very fast. I was forced to deliver
additional engineers into the team. It was done by
adding a person by the both leasing,
not by direct hiring, but generally
starting from 2021, we are permanently,
almost permanently looking for the new engineers
to join the team. What brings it also
so having 24/7 on production gives
the necessary on being on the permanent on call
for the first year of my existence in the team,
supporting the team for providing the highest quality of our
services based on the ITIL methodology.
So in the first year I did over 100
overtime hours per quarter. And also
the team as it was growing and the number of competencies both
combine with the number of work that
has to be done was rapidly growing. We had in
the first year around 1000 overtime
hours. In 2021, at the
end of 2022, we had ten people on board.
So from one to ten within two years, it was also
combined with growing the competencies, growing the
number of projects which I will show you later,
I was recruiting mostly junior and regular DevOps
engineers, each in different specialty.
While to be able to do all of the possible tasks,
as you can see on the screen, there are some
amount of daily tasks common for the whole team.
But case on the individual specialized
into different areas. Like one person was more
an expert in the databases, the second person was more the expert in
IT processes. I was able to very
fastly deliver the high quality for the
first project and other projects that was started
within the operations team at Makolab. What is
the advantages of having the junior regular team
on board with some areas of expertise they learned
from each other. So based on the person that is
specialized in databases, he didn't have the well
and deep knowledge about IT methodology.
So the person that is not knowing much about
databases is an expert for him because he
is an expert for the IT processes and opposite,
the person that was taking care of the IT processes
was saying that the database
person is the expert for him. So the team was
and is constantly learning from each other and
they are experts for each other and they are not in
the point that they do not see any possibility to grow
within the team and within the company.
Okay. I also have line manager who
is taking care of the HR processes. And this
at the very beginning stage of my journey of building the
operations team at Makolab was very important to have such support.
And also today having line manager
in the scope of the team is giving a
boost for both technical and business
area. So generally the team evolved into having
competencies in sub areas and having the commitment
for the common tasks and providing the
proper quality. Also, what I want to highlight
that at the very beginning of creating this team,
and also even today I'm looking on the personality
even more than the technical skills,
because I believe that we can learn everything, but we are not
able to change our attitude as fast as
we can learn the new technologies.
So that was the time of building the team. It was
quite interesting and I really love the time with
the retrospection from today, a lot of work, a lot of challenges,
which gave at the end a lot of positive
effects. Going further to the overview,
you can just see the number of deployment
releases, because deployment was releasing
one of the projects due to some security reasons,
we were not aligned with the standard DevOps approach.
But what is important in this chart that you
can see how fast we were growing with the number of tasks.
And it is also showing
how we were expanding our competencies,
team and projects within the first year
of building this team in Makolab.
So I was looking for multiple data
that I will be able to show you. This is presenting the best the
whole scope of growing,
expanding and building the team based
on the sample data from the deployment releases from
one of the projects. Also, as you
are able to see on the previous slides, there was a lot of work
for the certifications. Just to confirm that
we have the competencies and
how the team was built. First I was providing an
onboarding. It took three months for every single person.
And after some time we discovered that the best person
that will be providing the onboarding for the new joiner will
be the person that was recently joining our team.
Because that person has the best overview
for the onboarding process. It was very effectively and also was
able to integrate the new person to the whole team based on
daily connections, not only with the team,
but deep connection with the last onboarded person. So it
was very smooth to join the team and also to join the
tasks and competencies. After some time
at Macolab there was a decision to run a bootcamp program.
First it was for the Java, but after some time the
decision was also to start it for the DevOps area,
for the operations team. So we started that.
It is also the three months program that we can hire
juniors or even persons that were not familiar
with DevOps activities before. And ensuring those three months
we are teaching those persons in area of
AWS, terraform Jenkins and it
processes. And after that that person can join
very smoothly the team and start working on the real production
environment. As I already said,
personality was more important than technical skills.
And also for the team, a lot of trainings and certifications were
provided. So how to integrate the remote team? This is
when it's creating. I joined during the pandemic for
building this team. The first was
that all of the calls are with cameras on and there is no excuse
for that. We work on a daily basis with each other.
So we are not looking how someone is looking on the very
specific day. We want just to see each other and see the emotions
and be able to integrate more. Also after
a few months I decided to have one on one outside the
company area and discuss how the team is growing and
what is the perception of the engineers about
the team. And it also gives me a
very big boost in the possibility to understand
exactly what was going during that
time. After that we are joining during
the weekends, we are going to one of the cities in
Poland and we are spending time together
just to integrate more than only on the remote.
If possible, I'm also available at the office. And from
time to time someone is just joining the
office to have at least few minutes of talk,
even if I'm overwhelmed with the
meetings, which I will also present later. So I
building the team that feels the responsibility of
the tasks of the common tasks, that those are not the
tasks of the company, but tasks of the
team. And everyone is responding
for delivering the high quality. And also we have
a trust for each other inside the
team. What is not obvious,
but also very important risk management.
So from the very beginning also this is the culture of
Makolab, of having the strong risk management processes.
I was identifying and managing the risks,
which I can say that 20% of the risks are
connected with people, 50% were connected with quality
and 30% with the customer or the competencies that at
that time we didn't have in the team.
So this process is quite critical for delivering
the high quality and being able to scale up
very quickly. From my management point of view,
what I did to also have
the team working together in the close knit
manner. I provided some logo type for our team
and also t shirts and some other gifts for the team.
So for understanding that we are a
team, we have something in common. And also I was promoting
on the webinars internal webinars competencies and
the team inside the company to let everyone know
that there is something going on in this area and we are growing
with the competencies multitasking. I will present on the
next screen the sample week of my calendar. But all
of the work for building the team brings me to
the time that I have six or even sometimes seven meetings
in parallel. So I was able to take two, one of
laptop and one of mobile.
There was an issue, I was able to listen to them both in
parallel, but if someone asked me to
speak something, it was quite difficult for having those
two meetings. I work under it and right now
I delegate some of the tasks to my team and
also optimize the
calendar on my side. From the internal development.
Before I joined the team, I completed MBA
studies and also it project management studies. And during
the first both months I did personally
quite a number of cloud and related certifications. And also after
that the whole team was certified with the ITIL
version four. From the external development I am
talking for example to you about how the team was built up.
And also in 2023 I
was presenting a lot of talks on multiple conferences in Poland
and across Europe.
I built the process knowledge base and
competencies inside the team. So we have the training
program, the bootcamp program and also
multiple documentations like the tasks list,
emergency procedures, first aid kits,
FTE reports and so on and so on. So generally
based on the growing of the team, there was a need for
having more and more data combined to
having the information about how the team is growing,
how the team is delivering and
what we can offer for our existing and new
customers. So also some acquisition,
negotiations or transition of the processes,
providing the information that hello, we are the operations
team and we can deliver some added value for your projects.
And it really gives us the boost in the number of projects for
the recently 2021 and 2022.
What is also important, based on the IT report
from ITMT in Poland,
they are dividing the leaders into four groups, people leader,
business leader, technical leader and additional leaders,
corporate architect. So I believe that
what helps me most was that and I
am more the people leader then I'm looking also on the business area
and also due to the fact that there is no much time
for that, I just delegate the
leading, the technical part for the team. And I believe
that they are specialists, there are engineers and they know what they
do. I need to provide them the right environment
for delivering the outcomes. Okay, I said
that I will show you my sample calendar. So one
or one and a half year ago it was looking like
this. So there was no much time for me
to work. I changed it, I moved some competencies to the team and also
then I was able to take some responsibilities.
So it was really demanding time at the very beginning
to make it working, to build it, to make it efficient
and to integrate the whole team together.
How I can see the future. So right now we
have one manager with assistance of line manager and we
have a team of engineers. In the future,
when the number of project and variety of competencies
will grow, it will lead us to
extract two competencies areas within one team and
deliver separately the IT processes within
one team and the DevOps processes within the
second team. If there will be growth
above, for example, 20 to 30 people, there will be
also the third team. The operations which now in this plan
is combine between the ITIL and DevOps
teams on a different technical layer.
What about the project? So we started with one customer and one project.
We received the feedback that we are the first company that was
taking care and was correcting 100% of the issues
founded on production. Also under
cooperation with developers, they start asking us for the help
that they usually should receive from the corporate IT
area. But they were so used to receive support from us.
So even with those tasks that were coming to us and
being honest with the customer is also very important.
So if we find the bug, we inform the customer.
If we find vulnerability on production that is not in our scope,
we also inform the customer. And based on our
competencies, we can advise other teams and say
them what to improve. So this approach and this high quality leads
us from one customer and one project starting 2021,
to seven customers and twelve projects overall,
eight running at the end on 2022.
Also within the five tier, we provide
the team and competencies give
us the possibility to double the revenue from
the first project. And within two years, the overall
income for the operations team was
tripled. I am not revealing the numbers from 2023,
because it is not ended, but we can discuss it and hopefully
next year I will be able also to show this area
some statistics from one of the products that
we are running. Those statistics are from the
two years period. So weekly inside the applications
we are taking care of 200,000 processes
and during those two years we provide over 500
deployments. So it means that every single working
day in average growth and deployment based
on our productivity. Because we are also looking
into the logs, the operations team,
without any incident from production,
was able to identify over front hundreds defects that
the end customers end users were not
able to see. And we were able to fix it before
being hit by the critical incident of production or something like
that. During that time we received over 1000 incidents and
our SLA for delivering the solution was over 99.5%.
And also as we were working in a quite complex
environment with multiple other companies and applications connected
to us, we did create over 600
incidents to other teams. And unfortunately the SLA
was not as good as ours because it was around 95%.
So usually we were struggling with the issues, sometimes that
were not our fault and we were hited by other
teams failures. On production.
We also provided the independent monitoring of application on production,
which brings us the possibility of having
faster notification of possible errors, because from
the customer side we're alarmed after ten or 15 minutes of
having some issues. For example on production, based on our
own monitoring of this application, we are able to identify the
issue after 1 minute and start working to provide the
resolution. Okay, that's all. Regarding the building
of operations team, right now I will quickly switch
to the sample projects
that we are or were running for the customers. So one
of these is service event assistant. I will not go deeply into what
the applications was doing because from the DevOps,
operations, maintenance and support, it is important to make the application
operational and understand what the application is
doing. But generally the business case is not always the most important part
for having it maintenance on production.
So for this project we provided the whole CI CD
processes, including deployment of those processes,
everything in 24/7 maintenancesupport and support on
call model. It was based on AWS.
We provided a lot of monitoring. For example Kibana Grafana Dynatrace
and we are analyzing locks, including for example 1
million locks per week. Based on
that, as I said, if we see any possibility to automate
our work, we are providing automation with terraform and symbol
cloud formation, but also scripting in bash or python
if the tasks is possible to be done
automatically. The next one from the aviation regarding
the applications, which were the flight components
with the whole ecosystem of for example communication between the
ground and aircraft, Macaulay provided the whole development
into scrum agile methodology, including quality
assurance, UX and project management.
We as can operation team. We are
providing 24/7 maintenance and support in a call model
and also expanding the monitoring, for example using data docker or
using new relic with log analysis and also
incident management based on the IT processes.
The last sample that I have for you today is from the health industry.
And here based on AWS and based on cloudformation,
we did provide the full DevOps engagement,
which brings us to the situation that we are building
the environment from the very beginning. First,
because it was important to deliver it quickly,
so it was manually. Then we provided the cloud formation for
building the whole ecosystem and expand for the new customers. And after
that when there was some time for looking
deeper into what was needed
exactly for specific customers, we started cloud cost optimization
process which can bring to lower
the invoices with a really
huge number, even over 50%
after that time of optimization.
Okay, going to the summary, I want to share with you
some takeaways. The most important things
that I believe drives us to the point that
we are and being able to rapidly
expand the operations team within the company and within new
projects, new competencies and new team members.
So the personality at the very beginning, in the
long term is more important for the team success than technical
level. If you need something to be done right now,
today, and you don't have time for building the competencies,
you should hire a senior person that is an expert in this
area. But if you are building something and want to make it stable,
it is in my perception better to give
people the space for learning
and take to the team the persons that will bring the
same, maybe not personality, but the same
level of understanding why we are here, what we want to do
and where we want to be in the future.
Small teams of course are more flexible and are being
more able to be integrated and working closely together.
And as I said, the role of line manager and the team leader can
be like an intersection. And generally
I really love working with the line manager right now and in the
very beginning because it boosts up the possibility of
expanding the team as now at the end,
for the customer we can be one man army, but inside
we are not one man but one team army.
And we are working together to deliver the results
for the customer, for the company and for the team. And we should understand that,
that we are not an individuals that are making individual tasks,
but those individual tasks are combining
into some common added value that we can share with the customer
and bring it and build and
expand the cooperation with the customers.
I always trying to give my team the broad context on the business,
operational and other layers if possible, because the better
we understand what is behind the task that we have
to do, the better we are able to deliver it.
So it improves quality and it is really working. So at
the end, if you are building such a team, I will say
that be more people leader than technical or business leader at
the very beginning to build the common goal,
to build the common sense of being together
and working and delivering the tasks. And I think
it will work not only in the DevOps operations area but also in
multiple other teams, not necessarily
in the IT industry.
Okay, if you have any questions or you are in any stage of
presented projects, you can contact me anytime.
When everything around is on fire, it is sometimes
good not only not to extinguish a fire, but to
grab a coffee and have a short discussion because it can bring us to
the good conclusion and we will be able to move
the things and deliver
something better than just the fire around us. So you
can join me on LinkedIn and if needed
I will give you assistance with your
issues. Thank you very much.
Jacobs Andra Makolab enjoy the other talks from
42 dev sec ops 2023 and
see you in Ouch.