You. Hello everyone. Thank you
so much for joining this session. My name is Karan and
today I'll be talking about the topic why clean
code is no longer a myth. So before I begin
with the presentation, I would like to thank the entire team of
Con 42 for giving me this opportunity to present
my talk. So thank you so much.
Here's a brief introduction. About me so I have been
working primarily as an Android mobile developer for the past
five plus years now. I have been working mainly on technologies
like AI, AR and VR. More recently
I've been involved in developing web applications using react and
angular, and my current work assignment includes developing mobile applications
using React native. And apart from being passionate
about technology, I also love writing poems,
traveling to different places across the globe, and meeting new
people. So that's about me in a nutshell.
Now, needless to say, most of us are working
in software projects which are agile in nature,
and they are characterized by the fact that they are result oriented,
involves continuous improvement, and no
longer are we working in silos. We are all working
in either small or medium sized cross functional teams.
The second block actually talks about software design principles.
So I've listed four of these software design principles,
and these software design principles also have been there for
quite some time now. However, it is the lack of the
early adoption of these principles in software projects that
has actually caused a lot of concerns. Now, more often than
not, software projects tend to incorporate
these principles either towards the frag end of the project,
when it's going to be launched, or sometimes even after it
has launched. So here it is important to know that these kind of
software design principles have to be incorporated as early as possible
in the software development lifecycle. So here I would like to specifically mention
about one of the principles, which is separation of concerns.
Now, separation of concerns basically means that you divide
a program into say exists sections and then
each section basically handles a separate concern. So these
kind of software design principles are especially important nowadays
in software projects. Coming to the third block, which talks about
the age in which we all live in, which is the age of automation.
Now, the age of automation, basically one of the benefits of
the age of automation is that you get to use more tools and accelerators,
and one of the main advantages is that it helps to reduce the overall
cost and the effort. So the age of automation certainly
is something that we are all a part of,
and we are all using it in our day to day lives as well.
So before coming to the main
topic of the presentation, here is a short disclaimer.
So this session is not about why to write clean code,
or neither does it talk about what is clean code or what is clean
architecture, nor does it try to answer the question about
why don't so software engineers write clean code. So the objective
of this session mainly is to describe how one can actually
go about developing or writing
a clean code. And it's talking about one of the tasks
that software developers even today feel that it is something
far fetched. And if you happen to be one of those developers,
then perhaps you might have guessed it by now. It is
writing clean code. So that is basically
the objective of the session. So years are
trimmed down, a version of a day in the life of a software
developer. So software developer is someone who
checks in his code at say regular intervals and
submits finally a pull request, which is then internally
reviewed by a team of developers, so colleagues or
senior members in the team. And basically
the developers would then provide some feedback based
on which the person who developed the code would refactor
it, and then finally this would go on until
the PR has been approved. Now once the PR has been approved,
this would basically trigger some scripts, so it can be some build scripts
which would in turn execute a pipeline.
And here is where the DevOps team would come into picture,
where they would be involved mainly in the monitoring of
the pipeline, determining whether the operations of the pipeline are going on
smoothly. And the output of this process would be say a binary
or an artifact that would be produced, which would then be deployed to a QA
environment. And here is where the testing team would come into play,
where they would actually be involved more in the testing of
the app or the solution, and against a set of test
cases, of course. And then they would also be providing their feedback
on a continuous basis to the development team. So now,
assuming basically all this has happened and the
issues have been resolved and there are no potential bottlenecks,
then the testing team would ideally give a green signal and the
application would go into production or
something that we call as going live. So this is
a feeling that I think most of us have experienced
by now. And when this kind of a situation or moment
comes in, we feel something like this.
It's this kind of a moment where you feel that your code actually
has worked and you have actually produced a working
version, which is fine and it has gone into production. But if you're
one of those who loves writing clean code, then perhaps
this is really not the icing on the cake. So there are
some drawbacks which are basically associated with this kind of an approach.
So in this case, the developers, they are mainly focused on
making the solution, I would say work. So I
would say there's less amount of time which is actually spent on the refactoring
of the code. So there are no, or I would say limited precommit checks
which are in place. And there is always an ongoing debate
of whether the developer should actually invest his time
in writing a working code, or whether he should invest his time in writing
a maintainable code. So there is always a debate
that goes on about this.
So these kind of problems do exist, but then there are some ways
by which you could tackle them. So for now,
let's try to deviate from the world of technology
and move to the world of human psychology.
Now, in case of human psychology, there is something that we all
have known about which is nothing but a habit.
So habit is something that is not developed overnight.
So writing clean code also needs to be, or become
a habit. So what are the four stages, you may ask,
of building a habit? So I have listed them down, so they are nothing
but queue craving, response and reward. So q
is nothing but something that triggers your brain to initiate
a particular behavior and action, and also basically helps you
to predict or provide some more information of the actual reward.
Craving, on the other hand, is the motivational force behind
developing the habit. The response basically in this
case represents the actual habit itself. And the reward,
as the name suggests, basically is the results or
the outcomes of developing this kind of a habit.
So these are the four stages, I would say, of building a habit. But if
we had to map this in terms of our
main objective of writing clean code, so this is what we
would eventually come up with. So in the case of writing
clean code, our queue basically would involve removing of debt code,
finding of unused variables, automating the formatting of the code, and applying
certain custom rules. On the other hand, our craving basically, or the
motivation behind developing this habit would be to write maintainable
code to maximize the refactoring of the code, and eventually to minimize
the amount of bugs. The response in this case would
involve using githubs and linting, which I'll be talking about in
the subsequent slides as well. And although the rewards
of developing this kind of habit would be many, but I have listed down
three of the important ones, which is basically consistency in terms
of the code, effort and cost savings in terms of
the development time, and also achieving a higher code
quality. So these are the three important rewards of developing
this kind of a habit. So the question now is that how does
actually one go about developers this habit. So one
of the steps that I found useful in this is something that
I usually recommend, which is basically using something called as
husky. So husky, for those of you who are not aware,
is nothing but a popular Javascript or NPM
package which is already out there, a framework which allows developers
to run certain scripts while doing certain specific actions.
Now these actions can be either in the form of githubs, which are
internally also scripts which run every time a particular
event occurs in your git repository. And these events also can
be of different, different types. So it can be a
pre commit, a pre push. So these are the various events, and the gith
basically would be executed each time, every time a particular event occurs.
So in that case, how does actually one go about installing
husky or setting Husky up? The answer is pretty straightforward.
You could just use a simple command. So in this case, the command is
NPX husky in it. So, which basically would inject a kind of a
prepare script in your package or JSON file, and the installation would
move on. Pretty straightforward. So this is basically a simple way
by which you could install husky. So here I would like to also
mention that it is recommended to use, of course,
the latest version of Husky, because if you're one of those who have used Husky
before, and if you're now migrating from say a low version,
say version four, to the latest version around this time,
which is six. So you have to note that there have been a lot of
significant changes in the way husky now actually interacts with the whole JS
ecosystem. So it has been actually kept away. So I would say decoupled
in a way and making it more
easier to use. So that is basically one of the advantages with the newest version.
So I would recommend people trying husky for the first time to use
the new version and set it up.
So this is about the setup, which is basically pretty straightforward.
So let's now understand, how does one write his
first pre commit hook. So a precommit
hook can be also written in the form of a script. So in
this case, basically I have included a pre commit hook as a
part of my script. And in this case, this is a pretty simple example
where I have actually used a precommit hook,
which does an Eslint kind of task. So it does an
Eslint minus minus fix, which is basically going to
find out or solve the most common errors or commonly
occurring errors for me. So it can be in terms of white
spacing, or it can be in terms of variable declaration. So this would
basically help me to ensure that developers,
before developers check in their code, most of the commonly occurring
problems have been fixed and the developers can then
check in their code. So this kind of a pre commit hook would,
although it's a pretty simple one, but it would help you to ensure that
whatever code has been checked in, it's of good quality. So this
is basically a very simple example of a precommit hook.
So coming to the next slide, so I mentioned about Eslint,
one of the slides prior to this, and I
mentioned that Eslint is also one of the popular frameworks which
are there, and Eslint actually helps developers to
find problems in their code without actually running or executing
it. And prettier on the other hand, is like an optional code formatter.
So there are many code formatters out there, but prettier is something
that one uses quite often,
especially in terms of JavaScript and react based applications,
I would say. And if you are one of those who uses
react JS or is developing react JS based applications, then the
good part is that the create react app already comes bundled
in with the Eslint config. So as you might be aware,
the eslint has a lot of plugins that it
has, and you can actually include them as a part of your
configuration. Or in that case, if you are using react
JS, there would be already a, by default a set of plugins
which would be there, but you can always go ahead and install any
other plugin if required. So that is one of the things
that you could do in case of Eslint. And prettier on the
other hand, would be something that also you could use if
you are well acquainted with it, and if you'd like to make
code formatting a lot easier. So that is basically done using a
simple command which I have listed down, which is basically doing
a yarn add and to include prettier in your application.
So this is basically a pretty simple way of installing
Eslint and prettier and coming to the next slide.
Now, Eslint, as I mentioned, would help you to find
out problems in a code without executing it, and that is
because of certain rules. So there are certain rules
that you could add for basic syntax validation or
variable declaration or say brace styles to fit your requirements
of the project. And there are two ways actually of
configuring Eslint. So one way is basically you create an eslint
RC Js file at the root level of your project.
Or you could ideally go with the second approach, which is to
add Eslint config feed in the package JSon. So this
is another approach where you can specify your rules and
your configuration. So I have actually gone with the first approach. In this
case, I have created an Eslint RC Js file in which I
have included all the rules which are going
to be applicable for my project. So the good part is that here you
could actually do
a lot of customization in terms of your rules and try to make it
more stricter or depending upon
your project requirements. So Eslint offers you
that flexibility and one can actually take into
account all the commonly occurring problems or commonly occurring
issues that developers face and also try to set up some rules so that
it could be avoided before committing the code. So these
kind of rules also can be added as a part of the Eslint
RC js file. So this is a simple example of how
one can configure rules using Eslint and
coming to the next slide. So in addition to linting
of code, I feel that one of the most important tasks
which is often neglected is providing meaningful commit
messages. So in addition to linting of code, I would say commit linting
is also especially important when it comes to writing or
writing clean code, and even in that case tracking down of
commit messages, especially in software projects which have been going on for
like say several years. So it's very
important also to make sure that every developer basically
follows a particular standard in terms of commit messages.
And for this, basically one can actually leverage the commit
lint. So the commit lint also can be, it's also nothing
but similar to the ES lint. But in this case you could
have different set of rules. So of course this will be more related to
related in terms of the way you name or provide your commit
messages. So in this case also you could use
a simple yarn command which I have listed down to include those packages
as a part of your project and you could get started using it. So this
is also pretty straightforward where using this kind of
a linting type, actually you could ensure that every
developer follows a particular standard in terms of his commit
messages, which eventually, later on maybe in the project,
can be tracked by someone in case of an issue.
So that is also something that I would recommend using
as well. So coming to the next slide, which talks about
environmental configurations, now this is again a very important
aspect of writing clean code, because as developers
we often work on different operating systems,
be it windows, Linux or macOS. So based
on the different versions or different dependency versions,
there's always some kind of a conflict that may arise. Now, usually in
a dev environment, one does not typically run the NPM install command
unless he or she is running the project for the first time or there are
some version changes that needs to be done.
So in this case, the good part is that we have something called as
a node version manager. So this basically it is used to
install a specific version, or you can say multiple versions of a particular
framework or library, and one can do that using say
the command like NVM install where you specify
the version you want to use, and then using the NVM use
command, you start using that in your particular project. So then irrespective of
the version that runs on your operating system, this version
would then be specific to that project, and it will help you
to ensure that you have a consistency in terms of the versioning
with other developers who might be using maybe a different operating
system or a different version on their system. So this
would help you ensure that there's a consistency among
the versions and could help you to basically even avoid any dependency
conflicts, aversion conflicts in the future. So this is one of
the, I would say one of the main advantages of using
this kind of an environmental configuration as well.
So moving on. I would say writing clean
code definitely would help you to improve the efficiency and the overall
output of your code and the code quality itself.
And I feel that project team should basically focus more on the
environmental setup and configuring
the frameworks for clean code before even the actual development starts.
And in my opinion, refactoring should definitely be made a
continuous process where developers should focus more on refactoring the
code rather than actually producing, say, just a working version of the
code. So that's it from my side. And before I
conclude, I would like to share a very interesting quote that I
came across on the Internet, which says that every
developers loves to write clean code, yet not
every developer writes code in the same way. So that's
about it from my side. So here are a few references based
on which I compiled my presentation today,
and thank you once again to the entire team
of Con 42 and hope all of you enjoyed the session.
Please feel free to get in touch in case of any questions or
any queries. So thank you so much once again.