Hi, today we will talk about a two hot topic
in the software industry today, especially on the web GUI,
the microfrontend and the design system.
Before we dive through on the main focus of today's
talks design system for the microfrontend ends,
it is important for us to have the common understand think
about what micro front end and design system are the
micro front end are independently deployable front end application that
is modeled around business domain. It is
an effective way to use the domain for
the software boundaries and some other technique is by
using the features to divide front end applications.
Microfrontend ends is a technique for decomposing
the front end application into smaller and simpler chunks that can
be developed, tested and deployed independently.
In other words, we'll be able to change portion of the application
front end applications without having to change anything
else that's been micro front end give
an ability for the incremental change
and upgrades independent deployments and
opportunities forming an autonomous team the
SAF organizings and independent team the
design system is collection of the reusable components guided
by the clear standards that can be assembled together to build any
number of applications. Imagine that we
have new teams that consists of the designers and developer.
When we do have a design system already the developer
be able to develop the page, the new page or the
new model. In fact the prototype faster
than having to build from the scratch
and the designer have the base for them to
do. The designs design system enable
teams to build a better product faster by encourage
teams to develop a component in abstract
way because that makes the component
become more reusable and the reasonability
makes the skill possible. A design system unites
the consumer of the design system,
applications and the product around the common visual
language. It bridging the
gap between the design and the developments.
A design system provide documentations component
that been published into the living styguide and
usually we use the tools like the storyboard js that
have an options to
review how the component been implemented and also
the living styguide like the storybook provide a playground
for the developer to play around with the components.
For example, if we have the buttons in the living styguide,
then developer will be able to click the button, hover the button and
to see what is the outcome. By interaction with the components
and the living styguide provide a framework for development.
It is isolated from application implementations,
then the codes will be much simpler and the
storybook gives an option for the buffer to copy
the implementation code from the
styguide and use in the application.
By having the living styguide documented.
It makes the living styguide
the single source of truth for the design and the components.
Let's go through on the first design system called
centralized design system. We will analyze,
we will discuss is it that this centralized design system is
suitable for the microfrontends.
A centralized design system having a
central design system where it consists of a core component
developer which is the maintainer,
the developer of the component that be reused by the
application across organizations. The way
that they use the component design system component is
by using them by
toggling the version in the package JSON because
the design system will be published, design system component will be published into
the package manager control like the NPM
or internal package manager like the Vedasio or Nexus.
The change that we made by the teams require
for the consumer of the design system to
recompile the code base and redeploy their
applications or their portion of the front
end applications and
for the teams to make a change
into the design system component require for them to make a
pr or the pull request as a contributor.
Their quotes will be reviewed by the core component
developer,
the core component developer will make a feedback and
if everything is on the green
light then the change will be merged into the design
system components,
right? So that is that this centralized
system is suitable for the microfrontend. And I
would say no because we not be
able to do independent deployment because change
in the design system component required for recompile and redeploy
of their consumer, the applications and the
team is decoupled because they need communication to make a change
between the contributor and the reviewer and somehow
they also needs to communicate about the
change across the team so they be able to have
an options to either stick with the old version or
upgrade to the new versions. But the benefits of this
centralized design system is of course it's
easy to make incremental change because consumer
of the design system be able to toggle the versions of
the design system components.
The second one approach of pattern is called
independent design system. Independent design
system usually use the modifierations that
been provided by the webpack Phi and by using the
modal federation we'll be able to make the design system as same as the
application because they can be independently deployed into
the productions. Once it's been deployed, the consumer
of the design system which is setting
up or been configured to fetching or
gets the design system component through the networks.
The chains will be reflected into the
consumer of the design system without the needs or recompile
or redeployment of them however
that they always have a possibility or risk
for the teams to accidentally
push or commit the change that
have a breaking change and if they
did that then it will affecting all of the
consumer of this design system because they only have a
single version of the design system component.
In order for the teams to avoid the breaking
change that reflected into the consumer of the design system
then the owner of the consumer of the design system required
to make a coordinated release. They need to communicate
with all the rest of the team to give
the awareness about the preparations
that they need to do in order to avoid the breaking change.
And on my opinions, the independent
design system also not suitable for the micro front end because
it has decoupled between the teams to do the
coordinated communication between them in order to
avoid the breaking change.
It's not convenient to make incremental change
because of because
of it is a possibility for the team
to make breaking change and it
require for a lot of effort for the testing team
to test to make a test of all of the
applications and it require a lot of the efforts.
Then my recommendation is to use a design
system called provider consumer design system.
The provider consumer design system is separated
or divided into first the provider design system
and the second one is the consumer design system. The provider design
system have things like the color system
that have all the colors, standards, colors using uses by
the rest of the consumer design system.
The spacing system, there needs to be standards, the icons,
typography and the fonts and they
also have the atomic component which is the small UI build
blocks that will be used and be customized by
the consumer design system. And they also have
the complex component in the form of the composite
components. By using the two patterns called
the headless UI and the compound component. The headless UI is the patterns
to provide you the functionality which is the
UI logics and the UI
interaction handling handler and
it gives the maximum flexibility for the consumer design
system to decide on the UI user
interface look and feel while the compound component,
the way that they provide the component in division
of the component. For example if
they provide the academic component, they will provide set
of ecudent header, academ body, academ title,
et cetera, et cetera. The consumer of the
design system we use the sorry. The consumer
of the design system we consist of the customized atomic component
and implemented composite components.
The headless UI make a separation
between the extraction and implementation where the provider is the one
who provide the extraction in the form
of UI logics and UI logics and the interaction
handling to the consumer of the design system and
they will implement the extractions and they will
work on the look and feel.
This is an example the headless UI in the
react JS as you can see in the red circle, those is
the UI logics and UI interaction
handling methods and properties and
we will use those things to develop the
combo bots. And this is an example in the angular
way, the headless UI in the angular way where
the same things on the top, they have the UI logics and UI
interaction handling in form of the properties
and methods. The last one is
the VJs example of the
headless UI.
So by using the provider consumer design system,
it will give an faster
and convenient way for the teams to make change
upgrades and of course do
faster deployment. Because the deployment
will be independent based on the team,
the other team will not blocking the other teams. They will be
free from breaking chains across breaking
chains that will ripple or cascade into the other
teams. And each of the team
we provide their own implementation of the provider design system
which is the consumer design system. And the provider design system
will be used by all of the consumer
design system, which is the applications. By maintaining use of
the package manager control like the
NPM, Pedacio or Nexus. Because it's
not frequent for the provider design system to
be changed, then it's all right
to retain the use of the
version control. And if they have the change
in provider design system, they need to recompile and
redeploy. So in the summary,
by using the provider design provider consumer design system,
we'd be able to have an independent deployment,
forming an autonomous teams that is couple
and scalable organizations, and to
make an incremental change, it will be component and
easier for the team. That's all for my talk.
Stay tuned and stay safe.