Welcome to my talk about buildings. Well,
let's start explaining what is Golings.
Golings is a tool to help beginners to learn
the programming language by fixing small
problems. This is malpractice. They have
some errors in the problem so
you can compile them before you fix them.
And there are some
other exercise that they are
actually tests. So you need to make
the tests pass so you can go to the next
exercises. The tests are already written
in go. So your task is to
fix the test so you
can remove the comment that I will explain
later. I'm not done and you can go to the next
exercise.
So why I created golings?
Well I created golings because I
believe in fast feedback while learning new
programming language. So go links
like rust links for rust and zig links for zig.
They behave the same way, they work the same
way. You have a tool, a binary that you can
install in your computer, a program and this
programming. You can also
download the list of exercise and
a file that is indexed for all this exercise
and you can run go links to verify
if you check if your exercise
are correct after trying to fix them trying
to fix them. So this
is what Golings is.
Now I will show you the
repository and here you can find Golings
GitHub. So you
have pretty good documentation here
it can guide you installing
the program. You can
install it either by using
the go install comment or finding a
binary for your operating system
and architecture here in
the releases page.
Okay, after downloading
go installing go and
cloning the repository and installing
the golings binary, you can start to
fix all the exercises. Right.
All the exercise can be found in the director
Golings exercises and the top q
one sugar the
file the
file infotomo. It has a list of
all the exercise. They are ordered by the difficult.
So if you start right now,
the range of difficulty of the exercise will
be from the most east to the most hard exercise
to the harder exercises.
Okay, let's try
go links.
Okay, before I
go into the attempt
of fixing some exercise,
I want to give you my thoughts about fast feedback and
a little more detail on why I created the goal links
for the goal language.
I believe in fast feedback because when you
are reading a book, the book has
a lot of theory that is very important
and necessary. But some
books they don't have the fast fit backup
beginner needs.
Sometimes, even if you are experienced programmer,
you know most of the theory behind the programming language.
So you are used
to learning new programming language. So it gets easier with time
and you want fast feedback because you
want to learn faster and you don't
want to get stuck by reading a huge book
before typing some code.
So this is where Ato,
like Golang, shines by
giving you fast feedback. And fast
feedback is something very important to me,
and I believe that it's very important for beginners as
well. Now, how does Goldink work?
When you want to try
gold links, you can run
gold links.
Let's install so I
can copy it here.
Okay, it's installed, it's already cloned,
right? And you can type
go links. Run next. Go link is run. Next is a
comment to run the next exercise that you haven't fixed
it yet.
Now after running the comment,
we can see that it tried to compile
the exercise.
It has an output of the
error of the compiler,
right? It says that there is a syntax error in
your program. It was expected to have
the variable was expected to have
a name. Variables in go have names.
You can declare it either with VAR or
with column before they cosign.
And also you can see that in the end of the
output of the comment,
it tells you if you are stuck trying to fix
in the program, you can ask
a hint to the program and all the hints are declared in the promo
file. So let's ask a heat for the
program. Okay, variables that have
names. Yeah, let's open
the exercise and fix
it so you can go to the next. There's another comment called
Golings.
Golings verify it
runs all the exercise from the first
to the last to
check if you succeed by
fixing all the exercises.
Okay, it stopped it in
the first because you haven't fixed it yet.
Variables. Let's open the
program here and we need a variable.
The printf call here,
it says that it has a message.
The first argument of print chef is
a format string, right? It's a message.
And the next parameters are the variables that must be
interpolated here.
So it says that x has a value,
the value and the format.
It's integer. It's how you represent
an integer when formatting a string.
So we need to add the
axe name here and it will
compile. Let's check go
links. Run next. Okay, it says
we are done and it now
passes the compiler rules and
the programming outputs what we were expecting.
Nice. We can
remove the comment. The comment is what
makes you that?
When we remove the comment, go links
know that we want to go to the next exercise,
right? If you don't remove it here after fixing
the problem, it won't run the
next exercises. So let's remove okay,
now it goes to the second exercise. It tries to compile and
it failed to complete. You now
can ask another hint to
the problem. It says
that we miss a symbol
used to declare initialize variable variables.
Now you can open it here,
right? And you can declare the
variable the right way using
the column and
I can remove it here and run the verify.
It runs the first for the second. It runs all the exercise.
This is how golings work.
Let's add a new exercises to
the Golings repository so it
will go to the main upstream.
Actually go links is a tool that works
with any folder,
with any exercises. We can
have your own exercises. You just need to have
your own thumb file to describe the exercises.
Your own exercises actually. But if you feel like your
exercises will be useful to other beginners,
other students of the language,
I will be very happy to review your pull
request so we can merge it to the upstream
branch. Okay,
let's create a new exercises here.
Struct okay,
we can copy copy this
can copy create a new folder.
Struct three. Now we can
copy the second exercise.
Let's do something similar.
Great.
Okay, let's move it here
it is just a comment.
Let's create an exercise that it
must print the person full name,
right? So we
can change the message here. Person full
name is and use the s
person s. It means that you are
format I string and full name is a string.
Change name replace name
by first name and
surname.
It's also string.
Let's do the structure with the right attributes.
It's not. Let's put my input
my name here.
Well, one of the problems
of any kind of this cool is that the
problem just it just passed
the compiler. It must obey the compiler and
if the compiler is happy,
you will succeed. So we can
add comments to make the person that
is using all links to help
the person to know what
they need to achieve. Like here
it must be.
It must output person
full name is Maurice.
Okay,
let's add this exercise will
be about adding a function to a struct.
So we need to
create the exercises. Added exercises
here. Strep three
actually two. So I can edit
right after the second exercises.
Guys, about structs. Struct three struct
tree since
it is.
Let's add a hint. You can
add a function to a struct by
adding code similar to
the one below.
Funk the something structure
here the something.
I think it's
a good hint to the person so they
can explore in the Internet books
to find the answer.
The something return.
Let's submit it here. We already covered
the function, so they will know that
functions can have return types return
values actually with a type.
Okay,
now let's change this comment,
golings.
There's a way to run a specific exercises,
so let's run it stripped three.
Okay, now it outputs the error and
you can ask a heat for go links.
And now we have a new exercises.
Well, this is golings. I hope you have enjoyed this
talk and if you want to know more about the
project, if you want to know how it works in
details and help with new features or
issues, you can send me DM
on Twitter or find me on GitHub.
And that's all. Thank you.