What do you do with your metrics? You either
save them and mostly visualize them.
The talk is about a tool called Openmetrics
exporter. I'm Pivot Sharma,
I'm CTO and co founder at lastcent IO.
And is this talk about yet
another exporter? Because openmetrics in
favor of hotel and lot of other formats have probably fallen out of
favor. Let me walk you through the journey of how
and why instrumentation and metrics are important.
All modern cloud components are built on complex layers
before you even get to instrumenting
your application code. The application
code that you deploy is deployed across layers
of infrastructure, layers like it probably is
deployed on a kubernetes. That kubernetes is running on a set
of virtual machines which are supplied by the cloud and
maybe which is connected to a disk as well underneath.
And all of these components that are complex layers within
themselves are speaking with each other. Before a request reaches
your application, it probably passes through a load balancer which
reaches an ingress controller. Then it reaches your pod
over there, there may be another Nginx running and then
it hits the application and each one of these
complex layers and handshakes are breaking
almost all the time. To stay on top of it,
you need instrumentation. One of the industrial ways of
instrumenting and observing is metrics.
And one of the formats that have been the pioneer here is the open metrics
format. But how do you observe such dynamic
components and infrastructures these days? A typical landscape
of observability in the modern world looks like this.
You probably would have a can somewhere. And this is a typical example
of any web application. There would be a CDN.
There are instances, instances which are running some stateful
workload, there are pods. Almost everybody runs kubernetes
these days. There is some reverse proxy in form of ambassador or a
traffic, maybe there's an NgInx as well as an ingress controller.
And each one of these layers in the name of instrumentation are
either emitting data in form of metrics or in form of logs.
If you have metrics, well and good. If you have logs, you got to transform
them into openmetrics. The way to export these metric,
if the provider is already servicing these
components like cdNs, like load balancers, you might
get the data natively into the metric storage
layer which is provided by the cloud. But if it is not, and it's a
managed infrastructure that you are managing by yourself,
you would probably be running some kind of exporter somewhere,
a metric exporter, which all of it is unifying
into a metric sync now, these metric syncs are also diverse.
The cloud provider's metric sync is different from your metric sync.
And consistently you're trying to build a correlation
because they are effectively talking about the same component
or the layer underneath. All of this consolidation
and aggregation is mostly done at runtime using a visual
tool, which very famously is grafana, almost as
a de facto standard. And there's a human trying to interpret
a dashboard, a dashboard which is speaking to the diverse
layers, which are effectively talking about the same thing here.
Now, what do we observe here? And these are certain
challenges that I want to raise, among many other challenges of
these metric syncs and data lakes.
The first metric here is just an example. It's a namesake Go GC
duration seconds. How often would you have seen this metric?
Almost all the time. Every metric page that is emitted
by Prometheus. You see this metric somewhere. But have you ever
really alerted on this metric? If not,
what is it doing there? If your scrape interval is 15 seconds,
which is the default of Prometheus, you're emitting this
metric four times. And every such emitter is
all other Golang codes are bringing in such
metrics everywhere. You would be surprised to know is
something that we observed across our customers is that 40% of your
metrics might not even be accessed ever. But they
are all sitting there in that metric storage layers
and you would have heard it@your.org as well. I have heard it@many.org
where the very common component is about, hey, our dashboards
are getting slower. Our dashboards are getting slower because there's too much
data in it or there are too many requests in there. Now what
is that data in there? Is data that you don't even know? Is that
data that you don't even use because it's coming free from
the exporters that we actually use? If we take a step back and
say, how did we even get here? How do you observe,
for example, an eks cluster? There are some
metrics about this eks cluster that Cloudwatch is providing you.
But there are some metrics which you are emitting by yourself in form
of kubestate, openmetrics or a c advisor. Very likely
that there is a Prometheus sitting in their free, which is also being observed
via somebody's grafana. She's emitting metrics
in two formats about the exact same thing.
Isn't that a problem? At the same time,
do you even know if the exporter is lagging somewhere or
has it crashed? Or because it is creating data from
Cloudwatch in a pursuit to unify the metric.
It's just raking up the Cloudwatch bill every single run of its
own, every single time where it pulls data,
the bill just keeps increasing. And it is probably dumping
a plethora of metrics that we don't even have any control over.
If I was to ask a very standard question here,
if, for example, I want to emit and observe an SQL database,
what metrics are even being emitted by the Prometheus
exporter, you're going to have a tough time even figuring out
what metrics are in there. So if I was to summarize these key
challenges, sources are consistently changing.
We're in an infrastructure world where everything is ephemeral.
Servers go in pods, die in by the hour. Infrastructure is
changed. The functions, the lambdas, which we literally don't even have any control
over. Fundamentally, there is no correlation between
the entities that we speak. At the same time, there's a metric
explosion happening because there's a lot of unused information.
And there's literally no way of prioritizing urgent versus
important versus unused metrics. And every single new source
of a type of a component that you have to observe, it's a new
binary, a new exporter that needs to run.
If only we could actually make this declarative infrastructure.
The cloud component creation world went through a transformation
like this in form of tools like terraform. They made
infrastructure as code. We actually,
openmetrics exporter proposes to make.
Observability was a code. It's a three step process.
Step one, you declare your observability.
There are certain metrics that matter, and there are other metrics that do not
at all points of time. And this is very subjective. This is domain specific as
well. The same Nginx could mean different in different domains. You declare
these, you declare what type of components
do you want to observe. You run a plan locally on your computer.
You validate if the data is coming in. If everything looks
well, you dispatch it. Once you dispatch
it, openmetrics exporter will export all
the metrics on a slash openmetrics page along with the timestamp of it.
Once it is there any standard Prometheus agent,
be it form of Prometheus agent, a Grafana agent, or a
VM agent, can carry these highly precise selected
metrics into the metric lake, where what is sitting
in your metric lake is now something that you duly alert on,
is important to you, and more importantly is what you have
selected. An anatomy of an openmetrics
exporter looks like this. You declare a scraper,
a scraper is a first class entity which can connect to a cloud
source and has certain attributes to it. These attributes
are what form the metrics. There are different kinds of
gauges, vectors and histograms, which are
pretty much vector is kind of a summary as well. There's a dynamic label
to it. Every definition of this metric type
carries a query inside it which is specific to a source.
Once it speaks to a source, it can pull that data,
and more importantly, it can use this as an engine.
If you pay attention, there's a resources each load balancer line.
What it effectively does is that once that I have written this file,
it is enough for it to run across any selection
of load balancers that I may want to run. So I write this code
once, but I run it multiple times for each load balancer.
We've spoken multiple times about correlations,
but what exactly do we mean by correlation? Let's take
the same example here. There's load balancer data that
I get from Cloudwatch, which I observed
to say namesake is at throughput right now, but at the same time
the latency is being tracked elsewhere.
Assume that this latency was being emitted into Prometheus.
And once it is in Prometheus, I effectively want to emit
them with the same label sets, but a different metric name. How do I do
that? As a part of the same metric file is what openmetrics literally
unlocks. I just add a new stanza called gauge
latency. But this time around, the source will be PromQL.
It's a standard promql query with certain functions written here,
which are manipulations of data being done. And this
entire scraper runs together. So when it runs, it pulls data
from Cloudwatch and from PromQL and emits
it together. What it means is that if it fails,
it fails both of them equally. There is unification,
there's a correlation of data happening here. And when it does,
it emits it with the same label set. So if there's any
change happening, the change is uniformly being applied in both places.
Many a times there are sources. And this is one of the fundamental
powerful features of open networks, is that the data at
source can constantly change. And this
is applicable in, let's say a stateful system where you're
saving your openmetrics like SQL, where the
data might alter because there is
look back and lag, which are the fundamental first class properties
of any scraper. What it means is that you can actually stay
on top of this data changing. Very rarely you would see uses them
together, but they can powerfully
be used in conjunction with each other. What look back means is how
much time should I look back into the
time frame, so that if there's anything that is changing
in the past, can be emitted with the same timestamp. Now,
most native exporters, what they assume is that
the time of scrape is assumed as the time of insertion.
But at openmetrics, we retain that timestamp across all sources.
So what it effectively means is that if any point in the
future a historical timestamp has changed, it can actually get
converted into your metric, sync with the corrected value.
In certain situation, you may not want to process any pipelines
until the value is converted, and in such cases, lag is
your friend. You can apply a lag and the whole
pipeline will not emit fresh data until that point
of time. One of the lessons that we learned
from cloud systems,
and trying to automate a lot of cloud operations
that we do via terraform, the fundamental patience
test that happens is the feedback loop is extremely painful
and small. We want to change that with openmetrics exporter.
So what we did was we added native Grafana support here.
So every open exporter file, every run
of it, is resulting in a new dashboard
which you can debug later. It's the same example here where we're
observing an RDS. If we run here with two parameters,
the first parameter being the endpoint of the grafana, where I'm
running my local grafana, it could be a hosted grafana as well, and along with
it, an API token, it actually emits a dashboard.
Once I visit that dashboard, I can visually see if everything
that I had emitted looks correct or not. If all
the statistics are correct, I may have not accidentally uses an
average in case of max or a sum or a query is not misbehaving.
And once I'm confirmed, I'm happy to dispatch
this into production.
Software engineering's fundamental principle is about reusability.
We want to write code once and reuse it as many times as possible.
We brought the concept of reusability and modules
as first class citizens into openmetrics exporter.
If we look at the same module, the same scraper files
that we have been writing for a while, all we need
to change is one single keyword. Instead of
identifying the scraper uniquely,
we replace the word as module. This very simple
and a small fix here, what it does is it makes the
entire selection of metrics that I've carefully
crafted be available as a blueprint to be run
every time. What it means is that once
I've identified the key metrics that are extremely
important for me. I can save them, I can create a blueprint,
and elsewhere where the next time I have to run
this, I can refer to this as a remote URL.
Every single scraper that I have to write once can
actually be Prometheus to be used across the community
or my subsequent deployments. And before that, binding blueprint
or a guardrail, which ensures that everything is observed
homogeneously. On the left is an example where instead
of scraper I call it extends. And that's it. Boom. Job done.
What I'd also do is we create a catalog of all
the important openmetrics that we seem to be relevant
across. All of these components that are available across clouds.
This is a registry that you can actually visit.
We have a default catalog that is consistently being updated, but you
can always contribute as well. It's open source.
All of this is only meaningful
if they could speak with multiple sources of data
and sources, just like terraform has.
Providers is a first class entity here. Openmetrics exporter
can help you pull data from Prometheus, from Google, Stackdriver, from Amazon,
Cloudwatch, Redshift, or any other SQL power database. It can also
speak with other Openmetrics backend along
the lines we actually saw these syntaxes, they may have looked familiar,
the syntax is written in etc. A lot of
people ask me, why is it not Yaml? Well, here's a joke.
Yaml provides you job security, etc. Lets you concentrate.
But again, why not Yaml? If we look
at a smallish example here, what I'm trying
to do is I'm trying to run over a resource all cluster I'm joining,
splitting, and then doing a format. Any such
manipulation of data is almost impossible
to be done as a first class language construct.
And you know, every DSL as it evolves wants
to add some programming logic to it, some iterators,
some conditionals, some ternary operators, some boolean expressions.
Now, because all of these are available as first class in HCL,
what it means is you can add some logic,
not obnoxiously complex logic, but some logic,
into the configuration templates itself,
which means that that is less code, which is actually to be
written. Now imagine if you had an existing
exporter that you were using, which was off the shelf, and all
you had to do was add a certain formatter of a string, or a
certain split, or a certain join, or a certain regular expression.
You would have to go edit the code and maintain a fork.
But if the language spec becomes powerful where you can freely run these expressions,
it only provides for more reusability, and that
is the fundamental principle behind etc. It's human readable.
Humans can interact with it better. It effectively means
that it is less learning curve. It will fit all existing editors
as you have seen with terraform console or nomad,
all the editors will continue to work. Your existing Gitops pipeline
will continue to work. Now, if we take a recap here
and we try to understand how is this different from the existing Prometheus
exporters that we would have actually used in case we
were trying to build this as well. I want to go scenario by
scenario. If there was a new source of data
in an existing exporter approach, we would have to dispatch
a new binary. Every single new binary that gets dispatched
onto production is another point of failure, which needs to be tracked further.
Now, who keeps a track of the binary? Probably another binary,
and that's kind of a recursion that keeps going on. With openmetrics exporter,
you just have to write a scraper file. Now,
open matrix exporter has been written for massive concurrency. It's backed by
Golang. We are on a single machine which is probably
six cores and some 6gb of ram.
We've been able to scale it to 500 scrapers and up to three to 4
million data points being emitted.
We also touch the part of what metrics do you have control over
in existing exporters, let alone controlling at times finding
it becomes really hard with openmetrics exporter because it's observability
as code. We get to pick and choose the metrics that are important
to us and what should reside in our metrics.
Lake building correlation is
a job for post processing. Post processing is that
you would carry this data into another data lake,
and thereafter we will write complex pieces of code using
some sort of another language which can help us extract
some knowledge out of it, so that we can see the data together from two
things. Or it would just be a visual post processing in
form of a grafana dashboard. With openmetrics exporter,
it becomes a native support because you can club these metrics together and
emit them as unified, homogeneous under the same
label set, logic manipulation is almost impossible.
We are at the mercy of editing
the code which is a part of the exporter itself, but because it is
a first class function via etc, the native
expressions allow very easy manipulation inside openmetrics exporter.
Now, how does this all fit together? Let's take an example. The step
one is the sub and ship cycle. You would download the
binary from an artifactory as a practitioner
you would write certain etc files or you would reuse existing modules
that are available. You run them, you plan them, you run a grafana
on them. Once everything is sorted looks good you commit it to a repository.
From the repository you would probably create an artifactory of the etc
files on the deploy side which is the step two the same
open metrics binary which is a flavor specific to the deployment server
tries to download these etc files and then emits
the metrics. These metrics are exposed on a slash metric page which any
Prometheus running in agent mode or a VM agent or a grafana
agent can then ship it to the Openmetrics receiver.
Openmetrics exporter was actually born at last nine.
That's a company where I work at and we allow people to ship
reliable software and the very first step of
building this reliability stack is building a consolidated
metric layer. You can visit OpenMetrics exporter
at our last nine page and well happy for feedback.