Hi, I'm Michael Davidson. I'm going to be speaking
about security domains, what they are,
why they're so important. I'm going to start with a bit of background
about myself because I think that will help explain my
passion for this topic. Nowadays I work as
a software architect at Dell, where I lead the
public cloud cybersecurity for youre
Powerflex product, which is a software defined storage
product. In the past, I've worked both as software architect and
a security architect at a number of different companies. Before that,
I was a software developer. I sometimes lecture academic
courses in cybersecurity and in
agile and software development methods. And the
reason I started thinking about why we need security domains
is because I was thinking,
why isn't there enough diversity in the field of cybersecurity? I think if you
look at security, for instance, if you look at women
in security, those are less women in the security field than are in
tech in general. And it's definitely not at 51%,
which is why I'd like to see. So I
started to think that this is happening because we're looking at
security as those single blob, those single thing of like either you
know security or you don't. Either you're a security expert or you don't.
And usually using a security expert was kind of
thought of as being a hacker. I mean, a white
hat hacker, someone who's doing it for a valid organization
and a legal purpose, but still someone who has that capabilities of
reverse engineering, of hacking. And I think when some of us
were seeing those films
and tv shows where youre see a teenager in the basement,
like tapping away a keyboard for two or 3 minutes and then breaking
into these really impressive security systems like a bank
or the Mafia or the CIA or whatever.
So it could have us feeling like, okay,
I can't do this. So I guess this isn't the field
for me. And that's something that I want to change
because there's a love room for many diverse
perspectives in security with many diverse backgrounds.
I want to encourage all of you who are interested in security to
listen during this talk, see what fields you're interested in, what domains
within security are interested in, and then maybe that will help you pursue
your passion to become an expert in those specific security domains
without necessarily having the capabilities of
being a hacker. And we're also going to see later on how this whole hacking
thing of tap tap and you're in a system is a myth. So that was
my first motivation for this talk. I'm very passionate about increasing
diversity in the field of cybersecurity. I write
a blog on medium about developing your cybersecurity
career, your software architecture career,
the broken rung, which is something I find very interested
in and being able to help women promote their careers.
I also write there about software security and about software
architecture, zero trust cloud security.
So youre welcome to follow me there. Michael Davidson
at Miss Architect on medium. Another reason
I thought this talk was so important was because we
talk about security as a single thing. You're going to then not
necessarily know how to develop your career in security because
you're not going to necessarily know what paths to take within security.
And also in terms of creating community. Let's create communities around
these subdomains of software security instead of having like a general security.
General security conferences are great, but sometimes youre need to find
those niches and help those bloom. And they're not actually niches,
they're like pretty large industries with thousands of people working in
them. Just, we've never actually made that division that happens in other aspects of
computers, like you have hardware and software
in computers, networking, storage,
AI. And we need to, within security, stop kind of breaking
this up into different domains in order to create these communities
and networks, develop our careers. And also if you're looking
for talent instead of, I often see these titles,
security expert, security engineer, security architect,
and the title is going to be the same and then the listing underneath is
going to be like a whole different set of capabilities because you need to think
what is the expertise you're looking for? And zoom in on that
instead of finding a security expert who's really good at one thing and
doesn't really have background in something else. So that would help you
when you're searching for career expertise as well, or it
could help you say, hey, this is a field that's really interesting to me.
I may not think of myself as a security expert, but maybe this is a
field I'd like to learn or I want to give the opportunity to someone else
in my team to develop their expertise in that category.
And I think that's something that could really be impactful.
But from those technical point of view, I would say actually the most important
part of this talk is developing holistic security, which means
when you don't just think of one aspect of security,
you're not going to be in those situation where you really zone in. In one
aspect, maybe one aspect of security, you know, well, personally, one aspect,
your customers are asking for federal compliance. That actually often
happens and you're going to say, you're just going to really put all your attention
there. You're going to have this door that's locked and bolted with like 20 padlocks,
security point of view, and then you're going to have a wide open
window next to it, which an attacker can easily get through. That's not what you
want to have happening. Instead, youre want to be going around your system,
which is kind of like going around your house from the outside and bolting every
single window and every single door and your garage door. Right.
And I think that's kind of thinking about security holistically. That's looking at every
single security domain and thinking, did I think about that?
Did I address that to have your holistically secure system?
So I did is I was thinking, okay, security is just like too
much of a single blob. I want to break it into domains.
Now, when I was thinking about it, I broke it into these six domains.
Now, you may come along and say, I don't agree, I want to categorize
it differently. I think there should be five domains or four domains or ten domains,
and I'm going to give them different names. That's fine, right? That's actually great.
What I'm trying to encourage here is this, thinking like, okay, security,
let's break it down. Let's address all those different aspects. Let's understand
those are different domains with different knowledge, different background you
need to know and different things you need to think of. And that's the main
message that I want to get across here. So I'm going to go through these
domains. If you afters want to, I'm actually really interested to hear how you
would split up the domains. If you want to drop me a note, I'd be
really interested in discussing that further. I wrote a few blog posts on
this. I'm always happy to update them with different ideas. The main
thing is we start thinking about how we break security into these domains.
I'm going to start with compliance because compliance
often gets the most attention and focus, often because
of money, right. We're trying to sell our products, and youre customers are
often asking, are you compliant? Are you compliant with SoC?
Are you compliant with ISO 27001? If your
customers provide federal
suppliers, then they often may need to be compliant with the federal program. Fed wrap.
There's also the executive order that came out relatively recently.
Youre also going to see compliance around specific
industries like the HIPAA for healthcare,
PCI, DSS for credit cards. Youre using to see compliance
around specific features and domains like GDPR
for privacy and the El for logging. But what's
unified about all these compliance is, first of all, they're third party standards
that we need to comply with. And that kind of leads us to the second
point, which is they have to be generic, right? They have to be a template
that any system can try and comply with.
Any system can work through that checklist. The result of
that is, first of all, is a lot of focus on the process, on creating
the process in your company. And the
second one is that because of that,
it's really impossible with this single generic compliance
requirement list to capture all the complexities of
your system. So it's going to capture a lot. Going through compliance is definitely
going to make your system, typically, unless you're already extremely
security conscious, but in most cases, going through compliance is
going to make your system more secure. But I don't
want you to think if your system is compliant, that means
your system is secure because there's always going to be that gap,
right? There's going to be that place. So the compliance didn't necessarily think of
or address because it is this cookie cutter thing. And that's why
it really is important to think of compliance as just one aspect
of your security profile. In other words, it's not like, okay, I'm compliant with
either 27001, therefore I am secure. It's just our
way of being able to publicly state to the world and to our customers
what process we went through. And I see that
kind of as the initial stepping stone. It's always good to also have that internal
understanding of your system to see where else you can improve it.
Now I'm going to speak about network security, which I
would say from the technical point of view is really what's been getting the most
attention in a long time. Because network
security classically was about protecting
data centers on prem networks, on prem preventing
really physical network access, and then always checking
who is trying to gain access to my system.
That's the authentication, who are youre, who are, who is your device?
And then the authorization, which is the, what do you want? Do I want
to let you do this or not? Based on
that giving network access or giving
system access, right. That has evolved
in the last few years, I would say because of cloud security
and because of zero trust, which kind of came together. There's this concept,
okay, we can't just be asking who and what, but youre suddenly asking why?
Why are you doing this? And youre need to be constantly asking that. That's kind
of a big part of the zero trust principle.
You're not just saying who you are and what youre want, but like why?
And you constantly do this, why? And that way you're
hopefully, if there's a malicious attacker who maybe has stole someone's valid identity
or is doing something malicious, or maybe you have a malicious user who
is authenticated and is authorized for certain actions, but why are they doing this
kind of anomalous behavior? Maybe there's a risk here. Maybe there's a threat
here. By this constant automation, youre improving
the security of your system. So network
security has evolved, right? It's more than just the original
network protocols we learned about. We have the SSO piece, right? The single sign
on multifactor authentication, identity and access
management. Im is something that you often see critical in
cloud security.
Let's say the closed data center networks have kind of evolved into
a virtual private cloud in the cloud. It's those concept of this
network, even virtually, that you don't want others to gain access to.
Even things like firewalls, which youre going to see on permian, is he translated into
security groups on AWS. So there
is a huge amount of importance in network security.
You definitely have to be tackling your network security thinking
about this piece, which is really a lot more than the network security. It's also
the identity and access management security.
But it's still not going to be 100% enough because I sometimes see
systems where let's say there's mutual tls, right,
and there's mutual authentication and using the latest protocol,
but then when you actually start analyzing the system, you're saying, okay, but this TLS,
right, is using a certificate with a key pair. How are you protecting
your private key? Can a malicious user actually come and steal your private key and
kind of spoof those tls or all these kind of points where
network security alone isn't enough. And like we're going to see, we're going to need
other aspects like cryptography too. So when you're putting
together the security of your product, maybe you're starting with a
compliance, you're speaking about the network security, but we're going to go on and see
other domains that matter. Too often people who are
experts in network security, they may be coming here with a security background
or a development background. They may be coming here with an IT background, which is
incredibly useful here. So there are really a lot of different ways
to kind of develop in the network security field.
Now I'm going to speak about monitoring. The idea of monitoring
is this automation of looking at
the system and seeing when someone is perhaps an intruder,
right? Maybe they're doing, you want to detect the intruders. Ideally you'd like to
prevent the intruders, and it's not going to be those static analyst analysis
of, okay, are you valid or are you not? You're going to need a learning
piece because you want to first see what is as typical
behavior, and then you're going to be able to identify anomalies,
what's unusual behavior? Maybe this is a threat, right?
Maybe this is a risk. It doesn't mean it is, but let's start looking at
it better. Let's start analyzing it. And what I find interesting about
the monitoring domain is it's an anomaly within itself.
Or in other words, most people who are experts
in developing and designing monitoring tools
are not going to be necessarily with a security background, rather with an AI background.
Really useful nowadays, data science, machine learning,
because those are really the key skills you need in order to develop these systems.
Now, yeah, they're going to be developing security monitoring systems
and definitely a lot of collaboration with security experts,
but often the expertise here is actually more from the machine
learning field. And monitoring is seeing a ton of
growth in the last few years, I would say, because of cloud security.
Just in general, like the scale of our deployments on
the cloud and the fast pace means that really those static
security review is not enough. You want to
have tools that are constantly monitoring as well. You don't want to rely on a
single human being or even a few human beings. And because
of that, you need that automation, you need those capabilities and you need that monitoring.
So that's really developing. And if you look at cloud security, by the
way, a lot of what youre using to be seeing, that's kind of called cloud
security is using to be these monitoring tools developed for the
cloud, right, like CNAP and CSPM and CWPP,
the cloud workload protection. It's all
about developing your systems the same way,
not the same, but similar to how you would on Prem with kind of
slightly different cloud constructs. But then on top of adding in
those security, these cloud monitoring tools to
give you that extra level of protection.
So this is like a whole cool new developing domain with a lot of potential
where if you're interested in security and perhaps you're coming with a different
background like data science or AI or ML, this could be a great way for
you to kind of enter the security world. Now I'm
going to speak about cryptography. Cryptography is what initially kind
of drew me into security. I did a regular computer
science degree. I didn't even do a cryptography course. I didn't do
security course. I'm kind of embarrassed to say that, but I
really knew nothing about security when I started off my career as a software developer.
And then I started developing smart cards.
And through that I needed to understand what these smart cards
were doing. And I started to study cryptography.
And I discovered that from my point of view,
I thought it was like a fascinating field because youre taking
maths and it's not particularly complex paths.
As quantum cryptography evolves and elliptic curves
and stuff is getting more complex in general, you're taking these
mass concepts that really anyone can, with some kind of mass background can
understand, and you're using those to protect
the security of the whole world wide web. Right.
I thought that was amazing. And I just started learning more
and more about cryptography and liking it. So if you have
a math background, it doesn't need to be a very advanced math background, but just
if you maybe like paths, it's a great way to kind of work
in the field of security is cryptography. Youre often using
to see advanced mathematicians with pretty advanced
paths, backgrounds working in the field of cryptography.
And something I want to say to all of you is if you're interested in
security or you're already working security and you don't have this crypto
background, I think it's a really great thing to have. Like there are a lot
of courses available online for free. I'm going to link to some at the end
and just understanding about private keys
and public keys and asymmetric cryptography, what asymmetric cryptography
is, what symmetric cryptography is, what's those difference between
encryption and decryption versus signing and verification?
Just kind of those basics are going to help you so much because
then when you look at protocols, security protocols like TLS and network
security, youre going to understand them much better, much more in depth. You're going to
be able to have a much more in depth conversation,
and I think that's really invaluable. So my recommendation
to everyone who's interested in security is to look at cryptography just
a little bit to get the introductory concepts.
Within cryptography, there are niche fields. And I called
out here embedded security, because embedded
security is its own field.
It really looks at the security of chips. Nowadays,
we have trusted execution environments. For instance, if you have
bring your own device, so you're going to have your smartphone, right,
with all your photos and everything. And you want to be able to install whatever
app you want there, and then you're going to have maybe youre employer's email account
there, and your employer wants to make sure their email is safe.
So then in those cases, maybe youre employer is going to be
utilizing, for instance, a trusted execution environment in your device
to make sure that that specific area is running in a youre secure mode.
So there's a lot of work about those security of chips, the security of
runtime environments on chips secure boot,
which means validating every single stage of your software to
make sure it's trusted, because security is a lot about trust here. Can you
trust this application that's running? Can you make sure it's not created
by someone malicious and
embedded security, often people go there with a background in electrical
engineering, and then within electrical engineering, you can start getting into embedded
security, or you could come to it from a different security background,
but it's a really cool domain.
And crypto analysis is actually, I find the fun part of cryptography
because it's kind of trying to attack the cryptography and trying to figure out where
the floors are, where you're going to break it. And there's that kind of cat
and mouse game there that there is in general in security, which is another reason
I love security. Right. It's never going to be static. There's always going to be,
okay, this is the system we're designing in now. Let's try and
attack it and let's try and improve it. And security and
cryptography kind of go together because like I said before, if you're
using a security protocol, youre do need to be thinking about things like how
do you protect your keys? How do you protect the cryptography that's
using those keys and putting the effort to think
about those are going to help you develop this more holistically secure
system. Now, security architecture is
those field that I love because it kind of pulls a lot of what we
discussed before together, right. You want to be thinking about a lot
of different aspects and thinking, okay, how do I create a
secure system? Many people, when they hear security architect,
they think of the security review process, because many products
have the security process where you look at the analyze the
whole system, perhaps you do threat modeling and you try and
think where are the flaws, where are the vulnerabilities? How can I
improve the security of those system? And what I want to say there is,
if you're doing, and I really hope you are, this security review process, please do
it as early as possible in the process so it can have the maximum impact
because what often happens is a company is going to come and do those security
review at the end, and at that point, maybe someone's going to come along with
this whole list of flaws, but the company is going to be like, okay,
we need to reduce it, right? We need to get this product to market.
We're going to postpone this list. Like, thanks for finding this all out, maybe in
the next release, but it's not something we're able to tackle now.
And often the whole thing's been developed, so it's a lot more effort to change
it versus if you did security review right at the beginning of the process.
It's also going to be less effort to make changes before development is
complete, and it's also going to give you more time to be able to make
these changes. So the same review with the same amount of
effort invested in the review is just going to improve the security of your product
and have more impact if you move that to earlier in the development
cycle. But the other thing I wanted to add here was
security architecture could also be not necessarily just reviewing
a product, but developing a security product.
What's a security product? It could be a monitoring tool youre spoke about. It could
be a new protocol for a new industry.
Sometimes security architects, security engineers are actually
looking at new products.
How do you, from the bottom up, design them
securely? And that's really interesting field.
And what you're going to usually do that is use these building blocks. Like we
mentioned before, you're going to use the network security available when
possible. You're going to use the cryptography available when possible.
There's always this idea of don't spin your own crypto, which is
like, don't rely. It's always better to rely on cryptography that's been
tried and tested and validated rather than trying to invent the wheel.
But taking those building blocks together and then building something secure and making sure
that it's not vulnerable to attack is something that is
a really interesting aspect. And domain.
Now, I those, I've shown you that there are so many different domains in
security and we haven't even touched on hacking and reverse engineering yet.
So if any of those domains interested you, maybe you have a background I mentioned,
maybe you're just interested in want to learn. I just want to start by
wishing you good luck because you see, it is possible to become a
security expert without necessarily knowing hacking.
Now, when I say hacking here, I'm obviously speaking about white hat
hacking, which is legal hacking, when the
company is actually hiring those hackers to develop the
vulnerabilities in their system because they'd rather they find out
and not malicious attackers. There's also pen testing, which kind
of ties in with the security review I mentioned before, where you're looking at
the system and trying to analyze it kind of theoretically
to find the vulnerabilities. But I also want to speak about reverse
engineering, because, like I said,
when you see these films of, like, okay, tap, tap, and you're in a system
and you're not able to do that, it can cause imposter syndrome.
So I personally was already kind
of in the security field for a few years, and I felt, okay, I want
to know how to do reverse engineering. And I
did actually study a bit. And what you discovered then was quite interesting if
you want to study it. First of all, there's, like, great resources, for instance,
in cybery on how to do reverse engineering, there are tools
like IDa and Letty bug that can really help you look at
binaries, find passwords there,
find places where there are vulnerabilities.
But why discovered is there's a huge amount of time and patience discovered.
It's really not that tapped up on the keyboard that you may be seeing.
And I'd like to compare it to Sherlock.
If anyone has read or seen where Sherlock needs
to take together this shredded stack of papers and
piece it together very painstakingly to find out the message.
So it shows him with this huge stack of shredded papers. It shows him sitting
for like, 2 minutes. It actually shows him sitting with the papers. In practice,
he does it for like a week, and then at the end, he has this
message put together, and it's too boring to watch that whole thing.
So just kind of pulling
that into here. There's a huge amount of effort, time, and patience involved
in hacking. So if you do see someone just run something in one,
2 minutes and crack into a system, they're usually using it
off work that someone else did in order to put that
script together and actually find the vulnerabilities. So you shouldn't think that
if you're not able to do that, youre not able to be a security
expert. So, to summarize, we spoke
about these different domains. Youre could divide them differently.
I hope I was able to convince you that security is more than
one field. There are many subdomains there. They're all
interesting. Within your career, if you're interested in security,
you could continuously build your expertise in different domains,
and that means you're going to be able to, at the end, provide a much
more holistic security for your system. But it's really
okay just to start with one or two of the domains and develop
your expertise in those. I'm going to provide now
some resources. Like I mentioned, cryptography.
There's a great introduction to cryptography course on Coursera available
for free. There's a software security course which is more focused on applied cryptography.
We have here. Cyber is a great resource if you
are interested in ethical white hat hacking and penetration testing.
These are things that youre can learn. And there are some really interesting blogs
on medium. I personally really like cloud security guy on Medium's
blog because he really writes about what's developing in the cloud security field.
And Professor Bill Bulhanan speaks in cryptography in
a very interesting and relatable way. I just
love if you follow my blog on Medium is Architect, where I speak about cloud
security and zero trust security and software architecture and
developing your career as a software architect. So I hope
we can stay in touch and thank you. And thank
you to consolidate for this lecture.