Hello everyone. My name is Humaira Ahmed. I'm the founder and
CEO of locale which is a mentorship platform
created for women in the workplace. We focus on one
to one matching with industry leaders for mentorship as
well as guidance on the go. I'm so honored to be here in
the company of incredible people like like yourself.
And today I want to talk about a topic that is near and dear to
all of us, that impacts us every single day.
It's the topic of fear. While fear has many different
forms, it's a broad topic and I want to focus on two
types of fear today. One is a fear of
failure. It's the fear of losing, the fear of rejection and
fear of not being good enough. And we all feel that.
And there is the other type of fear that I believe is worth fearing.
It is the fear of regret. Because it's the fear of regret that
drives us forward, unlike the fear of failure
that holds us back. So let me put this into perspective for you.
I'll share three of my life stories to give you more
insight and to help you really understand the difference.
Story number one, I was born and raised in Pakistan and my family moved
to Canada 15 years ago. So I moved at the age of
20. In case you're wondering. I don't know how
much you know about Pakistan, but it's a very male dominated,
mostly suppressive society towards women. Growing up,
I was always told what I could do, who I could be,
what I couldn't do, who I couldn't be, and most importantly,
and unfortunately, who I would marry. And at
the age of 15, I was engaged to a man twelve years older
than me, almost twice my age. And guess what?
I hadn't even seen him. I also want to highlight something here
that in Pakistan, engagements are as serious as marriages.
It's the status quo. And although I hadn't seen the
guy and he was twice my age, what mattered the most
was that he was educated, he had a great job and he had
money. All the key ingredients that parents look for.
There was no consent on my end and I was told there was nothing I
could do to get away from all of this because parents
know best. On the one hand, I had fear of disappointing
my parents. I was always on a vegan girl, wanted to
make my parents happy. But on the other hand, I could also see my life
being thrown away. It wasn't what I wanted. I had dreams,
I had goals like all of you. And I had
ambitions. And I knew that this marriage would take it all away.
There was only one thing that I could do. And I'm going to tell you
that it's going to sound lame, but that's the only thing I could do.
And I did. And it was to cry. I would cry every single
night. Go to my mom, tell her how
much I didn't want to be married and I wanted to do big things in
my life. And she would tell me to go study. This was going to
happen. We are your parents and we have decided for you
we know best. But two months before the wedding, something happened.
I became really, really sick. I was so sick that I couldn't eat,
I couldn't walk. And the doctors couldn't really find out what was going on.
Until one day, one of the doctors diagnosed me with acute depression.
At 15, I was depressed. The medicine I got
was for depression. And it started to work. After weeks,
I became better. And then, guess what? The marriage
was happening again. Back on track. But one month before the wedding,
my fiance called up my dad and he told him that after four
years of trying, he finally received his h one visa
to go to the USA to work. He was so excited. And he gave my
parents two options. He said, well, he really
wanted to take on this opportunity. He had worked really hard for
it. And he said one option is that we get married in
the next ten days and he goes to us while I stay with
his family for three years in his aim and wait for him to
come back and he'll take me with him to us. The other option,
equally charming, was that I wait for the next three years
until he returned and know we could get married. So all
this time, either way, I was supposed to be tied
to him. And then, remember I told you that engagements
were has serious as marriages. His parents thought the same thing. They didn't
think anything would happen. I mean, negative. My dad, on the other
hand, was furious. He knew that I
didn't want this marriage. He saw me cry every night.
He told a guy in that moment that
it was over. Nobody could believe it, but he said it was over because
my daughter is not a burden on me. And by the way, she's not even
happy with this marriage. And the options you've proposed are unacceptable.
So this engagement is over. That's how I escaped my first engagement.
And the lesson that I learned from this is that you never know.
On the one hand, I did have this fear of disappointing
my parents. A failure. But the bigger fear
was the fear of regret. I did the only thing I could
do. And little by little, my tears had an impact on my
body, on my family, and in the end, it all worked out.
So listen to your body, listen to your gut. When something doesn't
feel right, it probably isn't. Story number two.
Roughly a year later, guess what happened? I was engaged again.
This time I had seen the guy and I can tell you did
not like what I saw. But you know what, he was also, by the
way, twelve years older. That's the theme here. But he had all the key ingredients
that parents look for. He was educated, had a job,
had money. This time. I mean, I'm seasoned here. I've done this before.
I did my crying again, but I knew it wasn't going to
be enough this time. So I applied to the best schools and I knew that
if I got into the best school for engineering,
I could negotiate with my parents. I was really determined to make my
dreams into a reality. And I did get into one
of the best schools for software engineering in Pakistan. And my parents
were so proud. In that moment of pride, my mom
called up my fiance's mom and she told her that I got into
the best school for software engineering and that she'll go to school soon. My fiance's
mom hung up and called back after half an hour and I was
sitting right there with her, with my mom, and this is what she said.
So I've spoken to my son and he's basically said that Shemera
is not going to go to school. She's not going to go to school because
three reasons, very good reasons. She'll lose her complexion.
I mean, I'm going to get tanned. They like me because I was light
skinned. For Pakistan people, that is the thing. Two,
I'll have affairs because that's what happens. He doesn't want his fiance to go
to school to have affairs. And three, that I
wasn't going to work anyway after school. So why
waste your money? So three good reasons. Loose complexion,
she'll have affairs and she's not going to be working after marriage
anyway. Why are you wasting your money? Very good reasons. But here's
the interesting part. Not only that, they actually recommended
three things that I should be doing or my parents should be doing to
help. The first one is to learn to cook different types of
breakfasts because my fiance didn't eat
the same breakfast every day. So I mean,
of course that's a useful skill because that's how I'm going to make my husband
happy. So one was to learn to cook different types of breakfast
every day. Number two was to lose weight.
I was fat. I mean, I wasn't fat. I was athletic. But there's no
such thing as athletic in Pakistan. I should lose fat and
stop eating rice and potatoes and focus on my looks.
And the third thing is, I should learn to be a good housewife
and learn all the skills that I need to. If I really need to go
to school, I could go to home economics and just focus on how to be
a good housewife. These are the lessons that they believed that were going
to be useful to me, helpful to my parents, versus going to school
for software engineering. And how could I? I mean, he was also, by the way,
an engineer. How could I compete with my fiance?
So my mom was dedicated. And I remember she looked at me in the
eye and said, I am so sorry. We made another mistake. We rushed into
it and I think we're going to end this for you. I just couldn't believe
it. I mean, once, sure, you can get away. Second time,
yes. My dad got home from work and my mom told him everything.
And my dad asked me for the rink back. I mean, I knew this
was legit, this was going to happen. And so
my dad called up my fiance's mom and said, we would
like to have you over tonight and talk about something important. And guess what?
They were waiting to come to our house. They came over
that night in full core with ten people. They have their family,
like the brothers, the sisters, the kids. Everybody came to tell
us how it was going to be done. And my dad, he just looked
at them and he's like, whoa, before you say anything else,
here is your ring back. This engagement is over.
My daughter, again, is not a burden on me. And you have shown us
your true colors even before marriage. And it was over.
They were crying. And anyway, long story short, that engagement ended,
too. So the lesson I learned from that was to commit to
yourself. I knew that crying
was going to help a little bit, but because I had done it before,
this was not going to fly. This time, I needed a legit reason. But I
did that by really working hard to get into
the best school, because that was so important. I mean, in Pakistan
and a lot of cultures like Pakistan, education is everything.
Like, you need to be a doctor, scientist, lawyer,
engineer, all of those things, and you're respected. And I
had gotten into the best schools. So that
was the one thing. If I had just sobbed and not worked
hard to get into this school, I mean, none of this stuff
would have happened, right? So commit to yourself.
Show up for yourself. That is an important lesson
that I've learned that we all need to do to
further our lives in the way that we want. Last story.
Story number three. Fast forward ten years from then.
I'm in Canada. Barriers to the guy of my dreams. I have two little
girls. I'm a mother of them, and they're just so wonderful.
And I have all the support in the world. It sounds fantastic,
but less than three years ago, I had an idea about my company,
Locelle. I wanted to be an entrepreneur. Many people told
me that only 5% of ceos in tech are women.
And over 90% of the tech startups fail in the first year.
So if you put the two and two together, the chances of me failing were
really, really high. Why bother? Not as many
female role models. And even today, there are so few women
leading tech companies. And I could have taken the easy route or
get worried. Fear of failure, fear of losing. Fear of rejection.
But I have two little girls, and I want them to lead life fearlessly.
And I wanted to set a really good example, not just for them, but for
other women and girls. So instead of fear of failure, I focused
on the fear of regret. Hey, sure,
a lot of companies fail, but what if I was one
of a few success stories? What if I didn't even try? I would never know.
So when you have that feeling that you want to do something, go for it,
listen to it. It's rarely ever wrong. Lots of failures,
lots of challenges. But I have no regrets.
I've pursued every opportunity, including this.
And we're working with amazing tech companies, very reputable
tech companies, as clients, and we're making the world a better place.
We are on a mission to create equitable workplaces
for women. And that's exactly what we're doing through our mentorship,
through our guidance, through our democratization of access
to knowledge for women. Because, again, we don't
have a playbook. We are creating that playbook. So, I challenge
status quo. I am one of the 5% of the CEO
in Canada today, but 90% of the companies
fail. Sure, I knew I would try it and see
what if I became one of the 10% of the companies that
actually succeeded? And I'm so excited to share with you that
we actually just celebrated a third anniversary last week,
and less than 30%
of the companies actually make it beyond the three years.
So in some ways, we have already challenged status quo.
And we have actually done a lot core than people
expected of me. I challenge status quo every single day.
By being a woman in tech, by being a woman leader,
CEO in tech, woman of color. And it's all worth it.
So with all these three stories, I want to share. Recap the
common three lessons. One, challenge. The status quo.
Especially if it's the right thing to do. There will be people who will
tell you what to do, do what feels right to you. Two,
persevere. Persevere with all your might for
the right things in your life. Never give up. And the
last lesson that I can share with you today is to commit to
yourself. Show up for yourself. And I know a lot of
themes, especially has girls, just people in general. We're raised
to put others before us, care for others, especially women
and girls. And we give more than we take. But you know what? Sometimes it's
really good to be selfish and show up for yourself and put yourself first.
And so I'm now happily married with two girls. I'm an entrepreneur.
I'm doing great things with my company, and I can tell you, even my family
is very happy. My parents are so proud. They share about me with everybody.
My girls have someone to look up to, and I'm helping other women
because I did challenge the status quo. I did persevere,
and I showed up for myself. So today, I encourage
all of you to connect with people at this conference.
Reach out. They're amazing leaders here.
And show up for yourself. And today, I also
want you to think of something you really, really want for yourself. Write it down
and focus on it. Something you'll regret in life if you
don't go for your dreams. So I'm going to end this talk by
sharing that. Do not let the fear of failure stop
you from shaping your life. Use the fear of regret
to drive you to do the great things you are meant to do.
Thank you so much.