Good evening everyone and thanks for joining my talk on leveraging blockchain
for secure and immutable updates in which we're going to see how you can
use blockchain into your OTF firmware
distribution infrastructure to make it more secure.
So a bit about myself, I'm swapil
Shinde. I was previously Google Summer of code mentee at OWAsp,
Mlitch fellow at near protocol and LFX
mentee at Linux kernel mentorship program.
So before moving towards the problem, let's see some stats.
Currently there are 15 billion IoT devices connected IoT
devices as per 2023 report, and it will
going to rise up to 30 billion IoT devices by
2030. So you can see with
this much huge jump in the count considering
the given time frame, there will be a lot
more rise in security attacks cybersecurity attacks
into these devices. So now moving towards
some security attacks that are performed as
per 2022 reports, you can see 77%
increase in firmware blues attacks, which means the attacker
compromises your update infrastructure and injects
malicious code into your firmware and then the firmware is distributed
into your IoT network. The second one is DDoS attack which
means like the attacker performs
distributed denial of service into your centralized
server and then your server won't be able to
serve the firmware updates to your IoT devices. And the third
one is man in the middle attacks which are also increased day
by day like your
wireless connection between your IoT device and your server
can be compromised because it's wireless and the attacker
can spoof in between them and then can
upload malicious code. I've linked the sources, you can
go check out these reports in more detail
for better understanding. So you can see also see a graph in which
you can see IoT device is
more serving in the consumer sector and you
won't be pushing malicious update
to your users. So you have
to make sure that your update infrastructure
is more secure and cannot be compromised easily.
Now you can see there are two types of update
techniques. The first one is like your
IoT device will be connected to using a wire and
then you upload your firmware using that wired
connection which is much more secure. But it is not
that practical because you won't be
calling off all your devices and then updating them
into your service center or giving the
authority to your users to update,
depending on your users to update your IoT devices.
So this is not that practical. So the other way is doing it
wirelessly which is the over the air updates.
And the thing is that it is not that secure because obviously
you are exposing ports, you are exposing wireless connection.
So anyone can attack using
their methods that they will be using.
So you can see there's a potential risk
that chances that your centralized server might
get compromised, which is the worst you can do
because it will be on your company if that happens.
So we will be seeing how this can be solved using
adding a third entity into your firmware update
infrastructure. So let's
see how your firmware update works. Your OTA
works. First thing is you have your firmware
instruction code written in any language,
but mostly it is c or embedded c. So it
is then compiled and linked to a single binary and
then that binary file is uploaded to your OEM cloud server
and then your IoT pulls your firmware update
from that server and then installs
it into itself. So let's
see this in more detail. So the first
thing is your vendor service, which is your company pushes
the binary file to the server and then the server
replies with the location of
that firmware, a binary file. And then you push
MQTT request call to your IoT
devices that okay, there is a newer update, you can pull this update
and you also send the URL for that
update. Then now your IoT device knows where the binary
files of your firmware update lies. Then it will pull
the binary files and your firmware hash
and then it will check if the like you can see in the next slide,
it can check if the hash is valid and based on
that it will make its decision
to either install the new update
or roll back to the previous updates.
So let's see some of the security vulnerabilities that is used to exploit your
OTA infrastructure. So the first one is man in the manual attack in
which you have your IoT device
and you have your OEM server. Then the attacker might try to
spoof in between them because it's a wireless connection. And then
your IoT device will think that okay, this is the original server and
I should pull update from this server and then it
unintentionally downloads the malicious
update and thus compromising the IoT device.
And the second one is distributed denial of service attack
in which the attacker distributedly floods your
server with multiple requests, thus ensuring
your server to fulfill the request of the update from
IoT devices. Trust delaying your IoT updates
obviously that DDoS can be secured
easily by whitelisting the IP addresses, but still
the third one is which is the worst? It is centralized
server got compromised, so now the attacker
has compromised your centralized server and now it has access to
all the functions that you can do to update
your network or your IoT device. And from there
the attacker can easily create a new update and push it
to or even modify the current update and push it to the
network of your Iot devices.
So here you can see we have our vendor organization
which pushes the update to the server and then IoT device will pull the
updates from that server with the update hash.
But this is centralized, why not replace it with blockchain?
So we have the features, or, sorry, the advantages of the
decentralized storage or computing at the same time.
So for those who don't know about what
blockchain is, let me give you a little touch up so that you are
in the same pace for the next slides.
Blockchain is basically a chain of blocks
in which each block contains
a data and plus the hash of that data.
Then the next block will contain the
data of itself and obviously the hash of the previous block.
And if somebody tries to change the data in first block,
then the hash will also be changed in the second block, thus invalidating
your whole chain, like the chain reaction kind of thing.
And basically this is not blockchain, this is just a ledger.
And to make it blockchain, to add a network layer, to add
a consensus mechanism, all this is handled by a piece
of software called node. And this node is
responsible for adding or mining new blocks
to the ledger, or even deleting the
blocks or even modifying the blocks.
But obviously these last two
features are not generally implemented into the blockchain. But you can easily
do that by creating your own blockchain. Since this is just
one node and it is centralized, you can connect it
with multiple nodes. You can use multiple instances of
same nodes. And all these nodes are connected with
each other via a boot node and they are generally
in sync. And this sync is ensuring and secured
by a consensus mechanism, which can be a
proof of work. It can be proof of stake or any other
mechanism that is available out there.
So let's see, if somebody attacks
this first node and changes the data in
this node, then your chain will be invalid and
the node will try to sync the data from other nodes
and other nodes will give the data back
to this chain, and then
this chain will recover automatically from that
invalid insertion. So this is how it generally
works.
Now let's see, like, you know, what is blockchain, let's see why we are
using it. What are the features it is providing us.
So first one is obviously immutable ledger.
So you have the ledger which is immutable and it is being
insured via the blockchain node. And the second
one is smart contract enforcement. So this
smart contract thing is a feature introduced by
Ethereum. It is basically, you can imagine it as a piece
of code, which is responsible for changing
the state of the ledger. And it
acts as a plugin to your blockchain node or
extension to your blockchain node. So how it is done is like
you write a smart contract like
trust or solidity. In Ethereum, you usually do it by solidity,
and then you compile it to bytecode and
then push that bytecode to your blockchain. So now you
have all your functions.
Your instruction that is written there, it is compiled to a bytecode and then
you push it to the blockchain via transaction.
And then the code is stored inside these blocks.
And you can run that code by simply
calling the transaction id of that block with the
function that you want to run, plus the arguments you want to pass.
And then any one of the minor
nodes will take the transaction and
run the code for you and change the state of the blockchain using
the code that is written in that smart contract. So when
the smart contract is run inside a minor node and it changes the state
of the chain, the minor node will obviously circulate
the newer state to all these other nodes. And this is how
the smart contract is generally run into in
the blockchain. So the feature of this smart
contract is that you don't need external entity to
external entity to run your code or to
decide what should be added to the blockchain.
Now the third thing is decentralized security. Obviously you
have decentralized infrastructure in the blockchain
and thus you get decentralized security which is
like you are protected towards DDoS attack, because if
you have thousands and thousands of nodes then it will require
a lot of infrastructure power to the attacker
to attack your
infrastructure. Blockchain infrastructure. And obviously blockchain is
quite slow in nature when you query it.
So obviously it will going to take time to them to complete
one request.
Now let's see how you can implement this into
your infrastructure. In this we will see how you can create your own
blockchain and customize it according to your needs
and then how you can integrate it with your old
OTA infrastructure. So the first part is choosing
a blockchain. In this you have two options.
Like you can either go with public blockchains or private blockchains,
a public blockchain, like if you upload any transaction
to it, any data to it. Then your data will be stored
in the public ledger so that anyone can see your data,
which is not that much secure and you won't be wanting
that thing to happen. So obviously you can create your own private network.
So this can be done by these three options. You can use Ethereum's
geth, which is go Ethereum implementation of Ethereum
node in Golang. You can use that to create your own private
blockchain by changing the Genesis block and the
network ports and running your own internal infrastructure.
Then you can use Hyperledger or polka dot substrate.
So these two are more like frameworks. You can use them to
create your own blockchain. You can write your own consensus mechanism.
You can use the proof of work, consensus mechanism or proof of stake.
So if you go with proof of work, you have to
give much more compute power
and thus you have to pay for your resource
intensive use, which is not what you will be wanting.
It is much more secure. But obviously based on your use
case and your needs, you have to choose your consensus mechanism.
So you can either develop your own or you can use any lightweight
consensus mechanism that compromises over security.
The hyperledger is developed and maintained by the
Linux foundation using the Hyperledger foundation,
and the substrate framework is
developed by Polkadot. So you can go with either of them.
It is totally fine Hyperledger fabric in
that the most common language is Java, and in
Polkadot substrate you have rust. So based on your preference,
you can go with any of them. Okay, so here
I've prepared a block diagram in which we are using Hyperledger fabric
as our main blockchain. And then we have our vendor service and
our IoT device. And all these three things are
running in localhost. That's why you can see the ports,
your IP being mentioned as localhost. So here
the first thing we do is the push call to
the blockchain. And before that we'll be
assuming that we have deployed our smart contract or chain code
in case of Hyperledger fabric. And your smart
contract is deployed to the blockchain with three functions, which is
your push function,
then your verify function, and then your query function.
So the push function can take data like your update
name, your version name, version name for that update,
and your firmware binary hash for
that update. So using push call, you call
that smart contract, the particular function which is push, and then you supply
all these three arguments. Now your hash is stored
into the blockchain. So simultaneously what you do is
you push your binary file
from the centralized server to your IoT device,
and your IoT device will take that binary
file and then calculates it hash. And also assuming
that for this you have to modify the
OTA library for this IoT device
such that it supports calling the blockchain network
or calling RPC or HTTPs endpoints.
So from here, when the it device calculates the
hash of that firmware, it queries the blockchain
using a verify call, and that verify call takes
the parameter which is the hash
of that binary file with the version name that you are uploading.
So now the smart contract will see if
the hash is correct for that particular version and
return if the hash is valid or not. So if it is
invalid, then obviously rest of the things are same. The execution
inside the IoT is same, it will reject the
update and it will revert back to its original, sorry,
the old firmware update. So this is how it works.
You also have a blockchain explorer in which you can see all the blocks
in real time. You can see all the transaction being happening in real time.
So this is the overall infrastructure here
is like the calls that we have
written into the smart contract, so you can see in
more detail and what these calls will be taking
as parameters. So you can see your firmware hash
in verifying the transaction id, then your transaction
attributes and all these things.
So now let's see how strong
it is when somebody tries to attack into
the infrastructure. So I guess the image is not
loading correctly.
Okay, so this image is taken from this
research paper, and it is a very great research paper.
You can read this and it mentions how you can transfer
your infrastructure and add this blockchain to your
OTA. So in the end they have mentioned what
they have performed to check the security
of this infrastructure. So they performed
denial of service and man in the middle attack in the infrastructure.
And they
were unable to perform these two attacks into the system
because if you perform man in the middle attack, then you
upload your invalid,
sorry, the malicious code into that IoT device.
But that IoT device had already written instruction
into the library that you have to query that blockchain
to verify if this hash is
correct for this current update or not,
and obviously deny log service. If somebody
do a DDoS attack, then you
have a time constraint between your updates. Then the update will
obviously fail and will revert back to the old updates.
So they have also
mentioned the performance and scalability vectors and how
this infrastructure performed. So you can read
this. Also you can see this is the Go ethereum implementation.
This is the GitHub URL for it. This is for Hyperledger fabric and
this is for the polka dot substrate.
Now this is the overall explanation
that I have to give.
So yeah, you can also see the sources. You can check out this
PPT and go to these individual sources and
read it in more detail. Okay, so now I'll demonstrate the
project my team is working on for a hackathon for the similar use case of
securing OTA updates using blockchain.
And in this project structure we have code for both vendor
service as well as our chain. And you can see in this build
this update CLI which is the CMD update
CLI. This is our vendor service and this one is
our chain. And our chain is already running because it
takes time to initialize the chain and run it.
And the CMD
update CLI, it is a CLI but it also consists HTTP endpoints
which you can query and do your transactions.
And here you can see this
chain is built using hypersdk which is developed by avalabs.
And you can use Hyperledger as well or other
frameworks also like polka dot substrate. But for this
use case for the hackathon we are building it on hyper
SDK. And here we
can run our build update
CLI chain. Watch just to see
the transaction happening inside the chain.
So okay, it is running and we will also start our server
CLR.
Okay, so now I'll go to my endpoints,
HTTP endpoints and from here we
can query our vendor service.
And also since if you want to do
transaction in the blockchain you should
have a wallet but you cannot implement wallet inside
your IoT device, but you can do it by
creating a separate service which will handle the wallet thing and you can expose
HTTP or RPC endpoints that your IoT device can
call and do the transaction. For ethereum cases
you can do similar with infura which is also the
similar kind of service. And we have built this service inside the
update CLI only. So if
I go here you can see this hyper OTA. This library
we built using elegant OTA which is this
hyper OTA is basically fork of elegant OTA and we
have changed some code to call our chain and
then get the validation of that hash,
binary hash and we will upload this into
our ESP 32 which is here.
Currently it is connected wired connection,
but this wifi is connected to my
home router because we connected this wiredly
because we wanted to see the serial
outputs of whether the update is happening or not.
Okay, now I'll upload the initial code
to my ESP 32.
Okay, so it will take a little bit time.
So till then I'll explain you some
of the parts like how my system works. So here
we'll call the chain with the binary file and then
binary file will be uploaded to your ipfs, to our
IPFS server. So IPFS basically is
the decentralized storage and
you can even in the presentation I explained you that your binary file will
be uploaded to your centralized server. But to add more
extra security layer you can move it to the decentralized storage
so it becomes hard to gain access to that file.
Once you upload that file you cannot change it and then your ipfs
URL of that file will be uploaded to the chain with
the hash of that file. Okay, so our
code is uploaded, I'll just monitor it,
it's reconnected.
Okay, so our ESP 32 is successfully connected to my wifi router
and since it is connected now we can begin
our firmware update. So the first thing is creating a
project inside the chain. So we'll just
call it hyper updates and we'll upload it.
Wait a second. Okay, the response is our transaction
id of this data. So we can just call
the chain using this transaction id and we'll get this data back.
Now we'll create an updates to this transaction id
so that this transaction id is basically
pointing towards our project and our
single project will have multiple updates for that. So that's why
we are pointing it using transaction id,
our device name and our version name with the binary
file. So what we'll do is we'll just change
something here,
okay, we'll change this dot to plus,
which means these consecutive dots will be now
displayed as plus. We will compile it again
and then what I'll do is I'll delete this firmware
file and I'll copy it
from the build. So the build is successful. We'll copy
it and then we'll paste it here,
move it here,
name it to firmware bin. We did this because the
PIO is like hidden directory so we
can't actually see that from our postman.
So now we'll go to documents platform I protection.
Here you can see our binary file. So now we'll just
create an update. And now this will be uploaded to the blockchain.
First the binary file will be uploaded to decentralized storage
which is ipfs. And then the
URL of that binary file will be mapped into our
chain data. And now to
see what is stored inside the chain. We can even see
it from here. You can see this transaction
being happening in our chain and also
we can see it from here by just calling
this endpoint. So you can see this is the ipfs
hash of our binary file. So we can
just go to this hash and download, but we'll not do that here.
And also this is the URL for this repository.
We have our library for ESP 32. We have
our chain code here.
Okay, so now we'll call this endpoint
which is the most important. Here we will add the transaction id of the
update and then IP address of our device.
Currently it is connected to our local host, which is this one.
So we'll just make it like this only
and then we'll just send it. Now if we see here,
you can see the update is happening.
And this was the URL called by our ESP
32 to the vendor service,
sorry, the chain to
get the valid transaction, sorry, the valid hash of
this firmware update. So we pass that hash that we calculated
inside our, inside our ESP 32 and then we
send it to the chain and the response was valid
and it successfully updated. And remember that I
changed this dot to plus and now you can see it is serial
outputting the plus symbol, which means the update is successful and
to demonstrate some attacks. I cannot do that because this is
still in development. But yeah, I cannot attack like
the ipfs easily because my binary file is stored in ipfs.
So I cannot change that. I cannot change any data inside
the blockchain. So it is mostly secured.
And you can obviously read this research paper to
see the attacks that they performed and how
they secured it. So thank you everyone for joining my talk.
And if you still have any questions left, then you can just directly reach out
to me by scanning this QR code you will get all my social handles.
Or you can just directly type your question into the Conf 42 discord server
and hope you enjoy rest of the conference. Thank you.