Let's start a session and talk about container and Kubernetes security
policy design and ten critical best practices.
This presentation is divided into seven sections.
I'll start by a brief overview of Project Calico
and what it is that we are doing at Tigera to help you
in your cloud native journey. Then I will switch
top application modernization and its relevance
in the context of container. Then I will
delve into the topic of container security to
highlight some key best practices to secure
your containerized applications. Next I
will discuss network segmentation, which is
a critical part of securing your Kubernetes cluster.
To better understand the best practices part of the
demo, I'm going to talk about the policy enforcement
and policy resources in kubernetes.
Finally, I will conclude with a section on monitoring
why it is necessary to have it and how it can help you top,
detect and respond top security threats in real time.
To bring all those topics to life, I will wrap up with
a demo where I do my best to demonstrate these
concepts in action. If you're new to kubernetes or
container networking, don't worry, I got you covered.
At the end of this presentation, you will find a link
and a QR code to all the resources that you will
need to recreate the demo in your own lab environment
and brush up on any concepts that
you might be unfamiliar with. This way, you can
redo the demo part as many times as you like
and gain a deeper understanding to the topics that
it covers. So let's get started with Calico.
Project Calico offers a pure layer three approach to
virtual networking and security for highly scalable data
centers. We offer Calico a free and open
source networking and network security solution for containers,
virtual machines and native host based workloads.
Calico supports multiple architectures and platforms
such as X 86 and ARM 64,
so you can basically install it on any environment.
Today, Calico offers four pluggable data planes that
can be switched on depending on your needs and environment.
A standard data plane is based on iptables that
provides fast networking, security and compatibility
for all environments. Calico EVPF Data
plane is another data plane created by Tigera,
which uses the power of EVPF to provide blazing
fast networking and security for your environment.
EVPf data plane offers capabilities such
as complete Kubeproxy replacement
source ip preservation and DSR.
If you're running a hybrid environment, you can use Calico for Windows,
which is based on Microsoft HNS and can deliver
networking and security to your Windows nodes.
VPP is the newest data plane for Calico. Currently in
its beta phase, which accelerates the networking experience
by utilizing the power of user based programming.
In fact, EVPF and HNs are some
of the foundational technologies that provides networking security,
observability, image assurance, and runtime
threat defense in our enterprise solutions
at Tigera. Project Calico is an inclusive,
active community about cloud networking
and security. Feel free to join our community using these
social networking handles and drive the conversation
where you see a need for a change or seek
help for your Calico adventure from developers who
are actively working on the project. We're also excited
to announce that project Calico will be attending Kubecon EU
2023, which is happening from
April 18 to 21 in Amsterdam.
So come meet us at our booth, Booth 28.
We'll be there from 10:30 a.m. Onwards to answer
your questions or help you with your cloud journey.
All right, so application modernization is
the process of updating or transforming existing
legacy applications to make them more efficient,
scalable and cloud native. This approach helps
businesses to meet the demands of modern customers
and remain competitive. Modernization typically
involves the replacement of older systems
with new ones, the integration of new applications,
and the development of new processes and workflows.
Some common approaches to application modernization includes refactoring,
code replatforming, rebuilding the
infrastructure. Now you might be thinking, what is
a motivation behind it? Well, legacy applications
are often complex, outdated and difficult to maintain.
They may have been built on older technology platforms
that are no longer supported or require manual processes
that consume significant resources and manpower.
As a result, they may have limited scalability,
poor performance, and present security
risk. To remain competitive, businesses need
to embrace modernization,
accelerate innovation or agile
workflows. Optimizing costs
and improve security are some of the reasons
the ideal design for the cloud is break up
everything into microservices that can communicate
with each other and your storage of
choice. This distribution allows you to go beyond what
was possible with the old technologies in terms
of serviceability, scalability and
reliability. While application modernization offers
many benefits, embarking on this journey is
not an easy task. It requires a significant
investment in people, process and
technology to achieve the desired business outcomes.
The right foundation must be established
from the beginning. Top avoid this high cost
of rearchitecture, which can be
a major roadblock in achieving success.
One of the key benefits of modernization is
ability to package applications and their
dependencies into port, table and lightweight
container images that can be easily shared and
distributed. By packaging your application and
its dependencies in a container image,
you can ensure that your application is isolated
from the host system and other applications.
This can help to reduce the risk of security breaches.
When creating a container image, it is important
to include only unnecessary components. This means remove
unnecessary files, libraries, and dependencies
that are not required for your application to run.
And finally, when you package your application,
scan them for vulnerabilities.
There are several tools available that can help you
to scan your container images for vulnerabilities
and identify any potential security issues.
And in the demo part of this presentation,
I will show you how to use Tigera scanner
to scan your images for vulnerabilities.
The choice between using a public or private
image registry depends on an organization's
specific needs and requirements. Public image registries
can be a convenient and cost effective option
for smaller projects or open source software,
while private image registries may be necessary
for larger enterprises or those with specific
security or regulatory requirements.
For example, government agencies and
banks prefer private images repositories for
several reasons related to security compliance
and data protection, and also since government
agencies and banks deal with sensitive information that
must be kept confidential.
Private image repositories allow these organizations to
keep their software, assets and intellectual
properties within their own secure infrastructure,
reducing the risk of leaks or unauthorized
use. After your container is created and stored
in a registry of choice, you need to provide isolation
on a networking level for it. Kubernetes network
segmentation is the process of dividing Kubernetes
clusters network into smaller, isolated segments.
This can be achieved by using network policies to
restrict communication between different pods,
services, or namespaces within the cluster.
Network segmentation is important for security
purposes as it helps to limit the potential impact
of security breach by segmenting the network,
an attacker who gains access to one part of the network
will find it more difficult to move laterally
and access other parts of the cluster.
If you're using capable CNI such as Calico,
you can also add RBAC roles to your segmentation
process. All right, so let's dig deeper
to the realm of security and networking.
Kubernetes has built in resource, which is
called Kubernetes network policy that can shape
the security posture of your cloud native environment.
However, like networking, Kubernetes doesn't
enforce these policies on its own, and it delegates
the responsibility to the CNI plugins.
So it is vital to use a CNI that offers such
capability to secure your environment.
These policy resources can be attached to namespaces
and pods to block or permit a
traffic flow. While these policy resources
are a great tool to secure your cluster,
they have some limitations that might be a problem down
the road. These policy resources don't have
explicit action attributes, which can cause a
bit of problem in massive clusters. You cannot
also write node specific policies,
and you don't have policies that can affect the
cluster as a whole. Similar to Kubernetes,
your CNI of choice might offer security resources.
For example, Calico offers two set
of security resources that can be used alone
or with Kubernetes policy resources to further
lock down your cluster and bring security to your environment.
These two resources are Calico network
policy, which is a security resource that can be applied
in namespaces, and global network policy,
which can be applied to the cluster as a hope.
On top of that, Calico provides a host endpoint policy
resource that can be used to secure non namespace
resources such as host processes
and host network cards.
Monitoring is a critical component of container
security because it allows administrators
to detect and respond to security threats in
real time. Container applications
are highly dynamic and distributed with
many different components running across multiple
nodes, making them more difficult to monitor
and secure. By monitoring containerized applications,
administrators can gain visibility into behavior
of these applications, identify potential security
issues, and take action to mitigate them.
All right, so let's start by infrastructure monitoring.
Container rely on the underlying
infrastructure such as the host OS,
network, and storage to function
properly. Infrastructure monitoring tools
can help detect any issue or vulnerabilities in
the infrastructure, such as resource utilization,
network latency, and storage capabilities
that could impact container performance and security.
Next, application monitoring containers are
used to deploy and run applications,
and application monitoring tools can help detect any
issues or vulnerabilities in the application code or
dependencies, such as memory leaks, errors,
and crashes that could impact container
performance and security. By monitoring both
the infrastructure and application,
it teams can gain a comprehensive understanding
of container environment and detect any potential
issues before they become critical.
All right, it's time for the demo.
All right, so let's start the demo. By using multipass
to create the infrastructure environment, I'm going
to instruct multipass to create three vms,
one as a control plane and the other two
as worker nodes. After completion,
I'm going to use multipass transfer command to move
the kubeconfig file from multipass VM
to my computer and use it to access my
cluster. In order to use the Kubeconfig file, I'm going
to create an environment variable called Kubeconfig
with the path to the transferred file and replace the
localhost IP address with the multipass instance IP.
Now I can use Kubectl to access my cluster
and change configurations.
Next I'm going to compile a simple hello world application
into two container images with different base image
layers and scan the end result with the Tigera
image scanner to spot any vulnerabilities
that might be inside the container image.
Now that the compilation is done, let's take a closer look
at the docker file.
As you can see, there is nothing special in here and the
only notable thing is the use of Ubuntu latest as
the base image.
Now let's create a container with the same application and
a different base image.
As you can see, this time I'm using the scratch layer
to package my application. All right, before scanning,
let's check if the image size is different.
Seems like the scratch image is significantly
smaller, but the image size is not the only
difference here. Let's go ahead and scan the Ubuntu based container
with the Tigera images scanner. As you can see,
there are two vulnerabilities in a hello word application
that I just packaged. Let's scan the other
one, and as you can see, there are no vulnerabilities
because the scratch image doesn't include any libraries
other than the ones that we specifically say.
All right, let's get back to our Kubernetes
cluster. At the moment my cluster is not ready
since there is no CNI installed on it.
We can change this by installing Tigera operator and
Calico on our cluster.
If you recall, during the presentation I talked about public
and private registries. Most manifests on
the Internet are shipped with a public registry
path to offer easier accessibility for
everyone. For example, if we examine the tiger
operator manifest, it shows the quie IO public
repository as the image storage location.
So for the next part, I'm going to configure
another multi pass vm as a private repository
and push all other components of calico into
it so we can install everything from our private
registry. And to make my life a little bit
easier, I'm going to extract the private registry IP
address and the desired version of Calico
and save them in two environment variables. To prepare
for the next part of this demo.
Now let's pull Calico Typho, one of the components of
Calico, into our local docker
and tag it for the private
registry and push it into our private registry.
Since my private registry is configured with
a self signed certificate, I need to explicitly
allow it inside my docker settings.
To do so, I'm going to head to the settings
in my docker desktop and select docker engine
and add the IP address of my private registry
as an insecure registry here and apply
and restart the docker daemon after
I'm done.
This will take some seconds, but after it's done,
we can easily push every image
that we want into our private registry.
All right, let's go ahead and check again.
Perfect. The image is pushing to the private
registry without any problem.
All right, now let's every other component of Calico
into our private registry as well.
Changing the image location that is used for
each pod can be happened in different ways.
For example, Calico installation resource,
which is used to instruct the operator on how to install
Calico, offers an attribute called registry
which can change the default image registry that
is used for the installation process.
Let's use this value and install the remaining components
of calico from our private registry.
Other than the installation resource, Tigera operator
offers a Tigera status command which could be
used to observe the Calico installation process.
For example, here I've chained the Tigera status
command with a cube kettle weight to form an
interactive weight that will end when the
calico installation is done.
Before going any further, let's verify that calico
components were actually pulled from the private registry
by issuing a describe on one of the calico components.
Excellent. It seems like private repository was
the registry that provided the image.
Next stop is network segmentation.
First, let's create a namespace for our monitoring solution,
which we will deploy later on this cluster.
After that we need to create a cluster role resource
with the expected privileges that our monitoring
user should hold, which will be used
by the monitoring program. Next,
we need a user resource in our cluster
to be associated with the cluster role, and after that
we need a cluster role binding to glue together the
cluster role and the service account.
Now let's apply the resources for these cluster
roles and service accounts to actually
create the resources in the cluster.
Let's carry on by creating a couple of security policy
resources to segment and secure communication
between Calico and Kubernetes components.
This first policy will permit host network
containers to communicate with the local host
IP address,
as it is suggested by this picture.
Calico node and Calico typhoid pods which are
located in the Calico system namespace,
are now permitted by the previous policies
that we applied to communicate with the host
OS local host IP.
Next policy is the famous deny app policy,
which you have undoubtedly seen as part of our
documentation and free certification programs.
As it's illustrated by this diagram,
DenyApp policy will block all communications that
are happening by namespace resources,
except the ones that are distant for
the core DNS pods to query DNS information.
To make a long story short, I'm going to stop narrating
what these policies will do and just apply them to
my cluster. But if you'd like to know more about
these policies, how to write them, and what they actually
affect, check out the best practices
for securing a Kubernetes environment folder in the
GitHub repository of this demo. The link will come
at the end of this presentation.
All right, let's go ahead and add infrastructure
and application monitoring to this cluster as the final
step. First, let's enable application
monitoring for Calico. Calico components
are capable of exposing Prometheus metrics,
however, this is disabled by the default configuration.
Enabling monitoring is pretty easy.
All that is required is changing two values
from calico configurations. After each
enablement. We have to create service so
it can act as a load balancer for metric collector.
For infrastructure monitoring, I'm going to use the
node exporter helm chart that can gather vital
information from my vms and expose them in the
Prometheus format. Next, I'm going to
pull the node exporter image from the public registry
and push it to the lab private registry.
Now that the image is set, I can modify the helm
installation to use the private registry for building the node
exporter image.
Now that the both monitoring solutions are in place,
I can use Prometheus web UI to validate the
procedure.
That's it. There is a lot more to
discuss about container security and security in general.
However, that would require you to sit through more of my boring
explanations. So, as promised, you can use
the top link in this page to create the demo and
check each step by yourself on your own time.
If something goes wrong or you got any suggestions,
don't be shy to contact me. I'm reachable at
dsocial places and calico users like
so that's it for my presentation. I hope you
have enjoyed it and I'd like to thank you for viewing.