Hi. Today I'm going to talk about why the future is cloud native
and why your organization should be too.
Today we're going to be covering what a cloud native system looks
like, why enterprises are making the move to cloud
native and why not. I'm then going to look into
a case study in the banking sector and their cloud transformation.
Then I'm going to talk about the benefits of adding cloud native package repository
like cloudsmith to your tech stack. Then I'm going to look into
what you should consider when selecting cloud native tools.
Hey so I'm Kira Carey. I work in developer
relations in Cloudsmith. I'm nearly there a year and before
this I was a software engineer for over ten years. I worked
on web services and web apps, in printing,
in security products and in computer vision applications.
The biggest change I've seen in software development over the last ten years has been
the availability of cloud infrastructure and that move away from data
centers. It's changed how we develop software and
what we develop. I worked on cloud transformations and
had to really skill up on all that cloud stuff on Docker,
microservices, event messaging and changing those config
code. It was
a huge learning curve for me and has given me a lot of empathy
for developers going through the same cloud transformation.
So before we go on, I want to talk about Cloudsmith. Cloudsmith is
a cloud native fully managed package management as a service.
We host and support over 28 different types of package formats
and we securely store your packages in a private artifact repository
and we make it easy for you to automate and integrate your artifact registry
with your existing CI CD tooling.
So what does it mean to be cloud native?
Cloud native systems are architectured and developed to take
advantage of the latest cloud technologies infrastructure
provision and configuration is automated.
Resources are dynamically allocated and reallocated
at deploy time based on the needs of the application.
Cloud native software development usually needs microservice
architecture. You expose functionality via restful
APIs. You probably use containers
with Docker, you have some sort of container orchestration
software like Kubernetes, youre use messaging systems
like Kafka and RabbitMQ,
and you probably automate your CI CD process to
build your software into the cloud and to deploy to cloud
infrastructure. You're probably building and releasing code multiple
times a day and you probably also have a cloud made of tech
stack to help you with your build process for your CIC details
for your package management tools, your observation tools,
and your security tools.
In Cloudsmith we've seen a huge increase in the
number of packages stored on Cloudsmith associated
with cloud native technologies like helm and Docker. From 2020
to 2021, new helm packages are up 271%.
New docker packages are up 236%.
And from today
to the started of the year, new ham packages are at
last year's 70% level, even though we're just a quarter way into the year.
So if cloud is so amazing, why isn't everybody just hopping
on that bandwagon? Well, this is not just an engineering
decision, it's an executive level decision. The big boss
man upstairs. There's huge upfront
costs. Rearchitecting your systems is a huge
undertaking, especially if you have a lot of legacy code.
It's likely to take up many engineering hours,
changing from a monolithic application to microservices.
You need to update your tech stack, getting rid of your on prem systems
and moving to their cloud offerings, or maybe changing supplier.
You need to renegotiate these contracts, review new products.
Your build processes are likely to change with new tooling and
increased automation, there's probably going
to be personnel changes. You need to train up your developers and
your it team job does may change.
You may need to hire in new developers and maybe even a consultancy
team. And you possibly
need to train up your customers as well.
So there's risks and security issues also associated
with moving to the cloud. At cloud service providers,
issues become your issues in December
last year AWS had an outage in
us eastern region and it affected loads of sites
and applications like Tinder, IMDb being Netflix
and Disney. So it's no joke moving to the cloud.
So this seems pretty tough. Why would anybody do it?
Well, there's loads of really good reasons. Reduced overall
cost. I mean for businesses it's the bottom line.
Improved performance, enhanced security, it's brilliant for
distributed teams and customers. And bit also facilitates
innovation in your product. Let's go
into these reasons in more detail.
Let's start with cost. Oh, it didn't
change over cost,
so running data centers is costly. They require a lot
of electricity for all that air conditioning and people
need to run it. Infrastructure and cloud
native services are fully managed. You don't have to worry
about maintaining your on prem software or infrastructure.
No updates, no security patches, no replacing obsolete
hardware. There's economies of scale to consider.
Third party providers like AWS, Google Cloud and Microsoft
can offer economies of case that a single organization could
not realize on their own. It's a price thing.
And we should also consider opportunity costs. Every dollar youre invest
in an engineer not working on your core competency youre
core products has an opportunity cost associated with it
and also there's clearer pricing. It's generally
you pay for what you use in some sort of subscription model.
There's performance benefits. Cloud native
software can quickly scale and readjust its resources to meet demand.
A company experiencing rapid growth can use the cloud to expand
its infrastructure and computing power. In contrast, the same
company using on prem infrastructure would have to quickly invest
in more hardware, software and engineers to keep up with
this rapid growth.
Cloud native applications arent bit to run the cloud
and they're designed with redundancy and high availability in
mind. High availability is made possible by redundant
and failover systems. Data and services are spread
across regions to avoid that single point of failure.
So let's talk about security with cloud native systems,
people are afraid of the loss of control and security risks
in using cloud infrastructure. A secure system
needs a secure building, training, constant security updates,
high availability monitoring and disaster recovery infrastructure.
Although many companies that host their software on prem take security
very seriously, it's expensive and requires
many working hours. You can actually raise your
security posture using cloud infrastructure and cloud native services.
There's 24/7 monitoring.
Security expertise is beyond the reach. Expertise is
available that is beyond the reach of most in house teams.
Cloud infrastructure can provide you with internationally recognized
accreditations. Your HIPAA, your isos, your fips,
your sock two. And they can also help you achieve those
third party accreditations for youre products.
I know being cloud native helps cloudsmith achieve our ISO
27 and one last year. It made the process much
faster and more streamlined.
Cloud infrastructure providers have security and
compliance services to help you manage,
access, analyze data for irregular activity, and they can also
tap into machine learning capabilities.
Developers can then use these services to automate security.
They also provide services to prove your compliant relations.
This is really important to those highly regulated industries like
insurance, banking, pharmaceutical, that kind
of thing. Security is definitely a risk when moving to
the cloud, but designing a system with security in
mind and by incorporating security into youre build and deploy
process, your system can actually be more secure than a traditional on prem
system. Let's talk about how cloud
native systems can really benefit distributed teams and customers.
Well, first off, Covid has really supercharged the rise
of the distributed teams. Many teams are remote bursts
and have members that reside around the world. I'm a remote
employee myself. Our head office is in Belfast
and I'm in Dublin on Prem.
Software solutions tend to be faster the closer you are
to the infrastructure. So if you have a team in the US and a team
in Europe and you only have one data center,
one of them is bound to experience lag.
Cloud native services are multi region and provide
consistent response times no matter where you are in the world.
This helps with collaboration and productivity on distributed teams.
Cloud software can use techniques like content delivery
networks and edge caching to further improve performance
on their cloud native systems.
Cloud native systems can also accelerate innovation
in products. Modern DevOps process make it
easy to release and build code multiple times a day.
Deploying new product can take weeks instead of months.
Also, you can tap into that data analytics that's really
associated with cloud native systems.
Data aggregation is made more efficient in cloud native systems.
You can actually build products and gain insights powered by this
data. Another thing to consider
is you can plug into the world's innovation.
You can buy cloud native tooling that can bring you instant and
continual benefits with features getting added without needing any upgrades.
The next section I'm going to talk about this case study into the banking sector
and their cloud transformation the
banking industry has been pretty slow to adopt to the cloud and update their
systems to be cloud native. Banks have long understood
that using cloud infrastructure has cost benefits, but they didn't feel
like it was worth the risk. There's loads of understandable
reasons for this, including they're in a highly regulated industry
and they're reluctant to move from their on prem systems due to
privacy and regulatory reasons.
Banks arent reluctant to move away from their legacy technology,
especially their Carey tech systems that do all those millions of
transactions every day. Because it works. It's familiar.
If it ain't broke, don't fix it kind of thing.
Banking executives have conflicting priorities,
making it difficult for them to prioritize a major huge it
project, especially one associated with such so
we've noticed in cloudsmith over the last few months that
financial institutions have been interested in cloudsmith because
we are a cloud native SaaS product, they're not asking
for our on prem version anymore, which is great because we don't have one.
I've being looking into reasons for why there's been an
increased interest in our product, and I found that several
banks have undergone a cloud transformation during the pandemic.
Capital one announced in November 2020 that it was going
all in on the cloud by closing all its data centers and
migrating everything over to AWS.
JP Morgan, HSBC helps Fargo,
and also there's been comments about it in the New York Times and Forbes
talks about bank's great core to the cloud migration.
Why did this happen now? Well, it's not all banking
cloud infrastructure offerings have matured. They have
services that helps provide to help meet security and
compliance standards in banking.
Regulatory agencies in the US, the UK,
the EU and others are now more open to cloud
only banks.
Several larger banks have undergone a cloud transformation
during the pandemic. This is not a coincidence.
Customers aren't going into banks and they're demanding services and real
time results that require bank systems to
undergo a cloud transformation.
There's also market pressures that banks have to consider.
They're worried about these young pups, the fintechs of the world,
revolut and big techs even like
releasing financial products, and that in order to keep up with
the competition, they need to evolve.
There's also staffing reasons. The pool of technical
talent that understands these legacy systems is
shrinking and aging as the
technology ages. Alan McIntyre
from banking, a senior director for
banking at Accenture, talked about the
causes for the core to the cloud and how it's reached a tipping
point. Now the journey has been worth
the effort.
Well, what do the banking sector get out of
this cloud transformation and these cloud
native systems? Well, all the stuff I talked about before,
reduced cost, performance improvements,
security improvements and security province,
that these cloud
services can now prove that they're compliant
to the regulations that banking have to, that's important
to banking. It's really helped
distributed teams and distributed customers, and it's
also facilitated innovation. So maybe
youre see new features in your banking application. Maybe you're
able to access all your banking products from a
single application now, your mortgage, your credit card,
your savings accounts, they're no longer stored separately.
There's fraud detection features. And also
we're now seeing real time results where before youre
might have to wait a few days, a few days to see your real balance
while it's doing all this batch processing in the background.
And now you're instantly seeing real time results.
Ok, the next section I'm going to talk about how
adding Cloudsmith's cloud native package repository to your
tech stack can really help
your build pipeline. Hey, so Cloudsmith
is a cloud native, fully managed package management as
a service. We host all your packages in any format,
just in case you were wondering about what a package was,
because not everybody is like 24/7
talking about package management.
A package, an artifact, an image or a binary groups together
files containing your software along with metadata about
the software dependencies, those third party dependencies,
maybe open source dependencies or in house dependencies,
all in a well defined format in that package.
So maybe it's a maven package or a Nuget package or
NPM or a docker,
a package repository, a registry or feed. It's a place to
store all your packages. If you have adopted DevOps
practices, you'll be building your packages
a few times a day and pushing them to youre package repository.
So your package repository is at the heart of your software
pipeline and has the potential to be a real bottleneck.
You can see here an example of a build pipeline where you're
building a few times a day you're pushing your package to
Cloudsmith. We're hosting it for you to be available to
deploy to cloud infrastructure.
So one of the key benefits to our customers is that
our cloud native service means that you can push your packages up and
deploy them anywhere in the world. Scaling is handled
by us, distribution is handled by us.
Maintenance and upgrades, that's us as well.
24/7 report support and we
can provide a service level agreement guaranteeing of times.
I think it's like 99.5 but it's generally
99.9, something like that. It's good.
And how are we able to achieve this? Well, Cloudsmith is designed
from the ground up as a cloud native application. We don't
offer an on Prem variant. It means that we
arent multiregion, globally available and scalable.
We're a fully managed package management. As a service,
we're built on top of a content delivery network with over
225 points of presence, allowing us to efficiently
distribute and deploy software artifacts globally.
Another huge benefit that our customers get from using a
cloud native packages manager is that we provide simple pricing.
You pay for your usage and your storage,
your bandwidth and your storage.
Efficient and simple access and analysis of data is part
and parcel with being cloud native. We're also able to provide
our customers with detailed analytics about their repositories
about who has downloaded what and where.
We also provide information
for you to monitor your storage, your bandwidth and your token usage
so you won't be surprised by an unexpected overage
and it'll give you a bit of time to change youre settings before you reach
your limits.
Support is really important to Cloudsmith,
but I have to say it's actually easier for Cloudsmith and
cloud native tools to provide quality support.
We support one tool running on our infrastructure,
other tools, other on prem tools have loads of different
versions out there running in the wild on customers'hardware.
The permutations involved in supporting that make it very difficult to
provide quality support. We value support at Cloudsmith,
but we also benefit from being cloud native.
There's actually a lot of innovation happening in the space of securing
your supply chain and package management.
It's really hard for people to keep up with all the advances in package
management. But because Cloudsmith is cloud native, youre are
always on the latest version with the latest features.
And it's great because our cloud native architecture and DevOps processes
allow us to build and release code several times a day.
We can also release versions of features behind
feature flags, which allows us to kick the tires and reduce
our risk in launching features. We actually have a lot of stuff coming
up in quarter two. We have new formats like Conda for
those data scientists out there. We have support for software bill and
materials. We have support for new ways to sign packages,
more logging and service accounts, and more.
And once they're done, youre customers get those features straight away.
So cloud native engineering teams need a cloud native
tech stack to help them build their software. It facilitates
increased automation and stability. I'm going
to talk about what a cloud native tech stack can look like for building,
testing, packaging, securing and monitoring your software pipeline.
And then let's talk about what to look out for when adding a
cloud native tool to your tech stack.
So what would a cloud native software pipeline
look like for building and deploying your software? You'll need
some source code management.
You'll need CI CD for automatically
building and testing your code anytime a new commit is
made. You need a package management tool
in the center there for hosting
your packages and making them available to deploy
wherever you are or to cloud infrastructure.
You have monitoring tools or observability tools
like your datadogs, your splunks. You have security
tools for scanning your packages or
scanning your code. You have tools for
deploying to infrastructure like Ansible, terraform,
all that kind of jazz.
And cloud native engineering teams need
tools that are stable, that are highly available,
that encourage you to automate your software pipeline,
and tools that are easy to integrate together. Because you can see here
from this image, there's so many permutations when
you're building your software pipeline. All these tools need to
play well together so that you can have the setup that you want.
So what should you look out for when youre adding a cloud native tool
to your software to your tech
stack? It should be easy to sign
up and you should get immediate access to the tool. No waiting for
accounts to be provisioned or permissions to be
granted.
It's frustrating to use and maintain a tool with no does or poor
docs. Features should be well documented, and also
your APIs should be well documented as well.
There are so many permutations for building your software.
Your tooling should provide robust APIs, nice integrations,
and webhooks to allow you to automate your software pipeline to suit
your organization. When something
goes wrong, you want to be able to speak to someone quickly about
what's going on and know that they will help resolve the issue.
So I think there's things that you should consider and
thanks for listening to me. So the cloud has been around for over
ten years, is matured enough so that even highly
regulated industries like banking are moving their core systems
to the cloud. Cloudsmith is a package management
as a service, and can be part of your cloud native
tech stack. I think the journey is
now worth the effort. Thanks so much for listening and
I hope to see you again.