Thank you for joining us today. We're here to explore the role
of GitHub as a platform engineer platform. We'll take you
from the traditional code DevOps world, through the collaborative DevOps
environments to the forward looking platform engineering world.
Today, we will show you how GitHub is not
just a repository, but a key factor in building robust,
scalable and efficient platform engineering solutions through
the use of GitHub actions let me begin with a small
story. Not too long ago, the CEO of the
company approached both my boss and me, asking us
to set up a VM for him. This task took some time,
and during the process he asked about the possibility of automating
this process. He expressed the desire not to rely
on us every time he needed to update the code or deploy a
new vm, as most of the times we were busy with other
projects. In response to his inquiry,
we developed a solution and today I will be
presenting it to you. Depending on the size of the
company, your infrastructure needs can
be met by the project's own developers, a team of sysadmins
or a team of DevOps engineers. I will illustrate the
evolution of each approach, guiding you from a code DevOps
world to a platform engineer environment swiftly.
All of this will be achieved while ensuring that everything is checked
into GitHub. Not too long ago,
companies heavily relied on sysadmins, who are responsible for
deploying and maintaining everything. Typically,
this is admins employed scripts, repositories with key files,
config files, and documentation to set up requested resources.
This manual process consume a significant amount of time
involving handson configuration, going through documentation,
and so on. We are all aware that everything we
do in a manual way often led to problems or omitted
details. With incorporation of cloud providers,
certain tasks became easier,
but spinning up a VM and configuring it often involved
clicking options and going through a web console.
This consumed a lot of time and was prone to errors.
The evolution of sysadmins bought us to DevOps engineers
and DevOps to the adoption of infrastructure as
code tools such as terraform and ansible.
This transition improved the establishment of standards and
the automation of repetitive tasks through code implementation.
However, managing the code, configuring variables,
and adjusting settings for specific scenarios proved to
be time consuming. While these tools accelerated
repetitive deployments, they weren't easy to adjust for each
environment. Most of the times, customization was required
after finished initial deployments required time to set
up, but subsequent repetition streamlined the process,
making newer deployments quicker and maintenance more
straightforward. Nevertheless, even with the
addition of automated pipelines and configuration management tools.
Some manual intervention remain necessary.
After performing these repetitive tasks across
numerous repositories, we developed a tool to automate
this process, minimizing manual intervention and saving time.
This open source tool we created aimed to
eliminate as much manual effort as possible while offering
flexibility to adapt to individual user requirements.
To achieve this, we integrated popular infrastructure as code
tools, incorporated automation scripts, included pre
and post hooks to execute scripts, and encapsulated
everything within a docker container to eliminate the need
to install anything, reducing compatibility issues.
The result is speedops, a tool designed to automate deployments
adjustable to specific needs, maintaining simplicity
throughout the process. However,
there were still some requirements, such as defining config files
and structuring the repository in a certain way.
After that was done, it required pulling the code and executing
it with a docker engine. This is where GitHub actions played
a crucial role for us. We incorporated scripts
into our actions to generate the necessary elements for Bitovi to
work out of the box, allowing customization through the
workflow inputs. This approach effectively separated
the end user from the code while maintaining transparency
for those curious enough to inspect it.
Furthermore, you will find that within our actions, we provide a variable
for obtaining an artifact containing the ansible and the
terraform code. The beauty of it all is that everything
you perform happens within your repository,
ensuring traceability while keeping your repository free
of unwanted artifacts like scripts and
terraform code. And this is how GitHub transformed
into a platform engineering platform for us.
And we are here to share this journey and of course the
CEO satisfaction with you. However,
if you're like me, you might be wondering if Bitovi
is essential for this setup. The answer is no.
It plays a pivotal role in our story and for many of
our actions, but it's not mandatory. In fact,
some of our top GitHub actions don't use it at all.
What we want to share the most in this talk is
the experience we had transitioning to everything GitHub
action and the tools we created during this growth
so that you can leverage on a knowledge to get you to a
platform engineering world in little to no time.
But in the end, it's all about the end user experience.
From the DevOps engineer perspective, the action
yaml defines the inputs and outputs the
action will take and generate. The action specifies
the steps to run and the logic behind it.
Just like a regular script, each step could
involve executing a command, running a script, or even calling another
action. This provides a wrapper for the infrastructure as code
tools and an isolation layer for the developer,
it only exposes the inputs and outputs you define.
If you're familiar with terraform, this might ring
a bell. It looks a lot like handling inputs and outputs
in a terraform module.
Shifting to a developer perspective, in your repo,
you could have one or multiple workflows already
created based on your needs. You might be running
some syntax checks or some code matrix checks.
Adding one workflow to deploy your code to an
easy to instance is as easy as adding
another workflow and setting the correct inputs.
You know that you could trigger all of them at the same time. You could
create subsequent steps based on results.
The possibilities with GitHub actions are endless.
Now, taking the broader view, the platform engineer
can outline the entire necessary infrastructure
using various actions. In the illustrated diagram,
we present an example of an environment based
strategy. In this particular case, there are three
repositories, each corresponding to a distinct environment.
Say you have a dev environment. In your dev environment,
you can designate a workflow for every resource
that you need, providing a clear and an organized
approach to managing infrastructure for all of
your environment. You can then copy that complete environment,
adjust the required variables, and set up another environment
in just minutes. That way, you could have the same things
in development, QA, and production really easily.
These workflows can be configured with manual triggers,
scheduled runs, et cetera. You could, of course,
take another approach. This is just an example of how we achieved it.
In the upcoming slides, I'll show you some example of our actions and
demonstrate how simple it is to deploy various components by setting up
a workflow. As you can see from the screenshots,
deploying your project to GitHub pages takes only a few
lines of code. We try to make the dev experience as
simple as possible with our actions. If some adjustments
should be made, you might find what you're looking for in one
of the many exposed inputs.
Digging deeper into the storybook to GitHub pages actions, you will
see that the main goal we had was to simplify and reduce
the steps into a single line, wrapping up some tasks that
we did repeatedly and assuming some default values
in some cases. For some developers, knowing all of these steps
was really tough and really complicated.
One of our goals as platform engineers was to automate
these tasks with simple solutions. By the
way, if you're interested in more details about how to deploy
storybook to GitHub pages, please check their official documentation.
Now let's shift to a more interesting and complex deployment.
One of the things we didn't like about reusing terraform code was
the fact that we had to manually set a lot of variables each
time, so we needed something more dynamic.
We solved the dynamic part by using the repository
specifics, say the repo name or branch,
as inputs for the variables.
We kept the rest with some same defaults.
That way you can get your resource up and running
with little to no intervention in just a few minutes.
But let's say you want a different instance size. If you want to
add a proxy to a database, expose a port, et cetera,
you can easily change that by adjusting just an input variable.
We went through the process of creating one action for each particular needed
we had during our work assignments,
but in order to produce what we needed in less time, we created
a common code for all of our actions. That way we
reused a lot of code and reduced the time
to add new ensures.
This is a summary of what we produce in just a few
months of work. This allows any user
from a dev to a DevOps to
assist admin to freely deploy and automate the resources
with little to no interventions in just minutes instead
of days. This is what we wanted to show as
platform engineers how we simplified and accelerated
deployments of on enhancing the end user experience.
That's it. Thanks for watching.