You. Hello.
Welcome to Conf 42. Today I
will be talking about modular approaches
of structuring react and redux apps
and a little bit about me. My name is Sergi,
I'm from Ukraine. I have been working as a web
developer for about 1010 years
more and I work with different technologies
and platforms, but last time I worked mostly
with front end and with react.
I'm really a fan of JavaScript so I
participate in different events and
I write articles about it and also I conduct JavaScript
courses sometimes and also I like table
tennis, fishing and traveling.
First of all, let me introduce a little bit
what we will be talking about today.
And I will start from talking
a little bit why good structure of redux
application is important and about state management
problem at all. What is wrong with common approaches
in redux applications? We will check what is dax
and reducks, what is redux toolkit,
and a little bit about testing of Daxis.
What is problem with state management?
State management in modern front
end applications is quite a common problem for
different frameworks and libraries, but especially
it's a problem in react ecosystem.
I think that one of the reasons why we
have the state management problem in react,
it's because we have different types of state.
First of all, we have components. Local state is the simplest
state. And today, using hooks,
we can have local state in functional components.
And also of course we can have local state in
components, class based components.
Next type is components shared state.
And sometimes we need to have a data,
some data that we need to display in different components.
And one of the easiest approaches that people
usually use is to
lift up the data into a common parent and then
pass this data via props.
By the way, today I think you heard about
recoil library, and some
people think today that for such types
of state, recoil can be a good one.
Maybe. By the way,
I had some articles and
presentations about recoil, just check it.
But in Internet. Yeah, thank you. And applications
global state, it's a
main type, I think of the state in our react
applications and usually it can be
an object and quite a big one that contains all
the data from all our applications application.
And we use this data in different components.
And I think that this global state usually
can be splitted.
It contains as well two main parts.
It's a UI state and cache UI state.
It's a data that we use to configure
our application and it's something that we use a
configuration for the look and feel like theme,
and also it's a data that we display.
And what about the cache. Almost all our
modern applications, they do API calls. And when
we retrieve the data, usually we also
store it and
we need to call it cache because it's actually
a cache. And I think that most
of the developers that work with Redux,
we all do such things like API calls
and store the data into our global
state with all the rest of the data.
And right now a lot of developers started
to think that maybe we need to separate this
type of state, I mean cache into separate,
maybe a separate object or separate state
array, and maybe even different
libraries can be used for different types of state.
But today we will be talking about redux.
And some people can say redux
in 2021.
Why? We have a lot of new stuff. Do we really
need redux today? And I should say that we had
several times we had situations when something appeared and
some people said, okay, so now we don't
need Redux anymore. The same thing was with context
API. And I remember a lot of people said,
okay, we don't need redux anymore. We have context API,
but they will run, as we can see here, that context
API, it was set last year that
it cannot replace Redux.
And we
can see today, like here in the
open base, you can check this Openbase website
and they have this ten best react state management libraries
article. And there you
can see the list of most popular
state management libraries in react. And just
check the numbers for redux. So GitHub
stars and weekly downloads, those numbers
are amazing, but in the same time you can see that user
rating is not the highest.
And we all know that a lot of
developers coplained a lot about Redux as
well. But it's still very popular,
why it's popular and why developers
complain about it. I think that most
problem about Redux,
that people usually say it's about its
boil plate. But let's talk
about this a little bit later. At first, a small
disclaimer, Redux,
it's part of our application, it's a
part of the architecture. Actually it's
implementation of the flux architecture. But today
we are talking about the structuring of the application
because we decided that we use flux. If we
use Redux, then we use flux architecture. But we mostly
talk today about structuring the application.
So what is the common problem of
just standard react applications? Here we can see
example of very popular, very common react
redux application. And here we can see
that all redux artifacts, they are
spread it all over application into different folders.
When we start our application, when application is small
and we add redux it looks quite good.
And when we add Redux and such folders,
sometimes we can even think, now my
application looks professional, but later when we
need to maintain and support such
project, it can become a nightmare to support
it. Because just imagine when you need
to add a new entity, you need to create the
same files over and over again in different folders.
If you need to modify files, you need to go to
those files in different folders. If you need to
remove entity, you need to go to different
folders and remove different files.
So this approach scales very bad.
And yeah, it has a lot of
problems. What we can do about
this? First of all, I would like to recall
that we have several approaches for structuring it's function
first and feature first approaches. I think we all
know about them here.
I would like to add that sometimes we can
mix those approaches and
also one very important
moment that we need to think about our application on
the long run. So we need to imagine
what happens if we switch from
react to another library for example,
or if maybe
we will switch from react to react native. Yeah,
then maybe we would be able to
reuse some parts of our application and especially
the state management.
And that's why people started to think that maybe we need
to separate state management from UI and
ideally it can be added
into a shared library.
That's why Eric Rasmussen, he started to think
about problems of Redux. He also
didn't like that we need to add a lot of files in
different folders and only
because we need to import some
actions or reducer.
Ideally he thought that it would be better
to isolate the model,
the state management, our bundle,
and ideally we even can move
this bundle into a shared library.
And here he created
Daxis ducks.
It's a one file that contains
all redux artifacts.
I mean it contains actions, reducers,
action creators, selectors, saga and all of that.
So everything that you have around one
reducer that you need for one reducer you have
in one files. Even tests can be added
directly in this file sometimes.
At first for some people it looked very scary,
but for small applications, when we don't have
a lot of code for those artifacts,
that idea was awesome. When I first
look at this, I liked this and I tried in some
applications and I also proposed this approach to
my colleagues, but they afraid to try this
at first.
Daxis has some rules and when
you follow those rules, then you will
be able to import actions
and reducks. By the way, why docs?
Eric explained it that he thought that
Java has jars and beans. Ruby has gems.
So he just suggested to call those
reducks bundles as Daxis or DAX
as last syllable of
redux.
How we can use docsis. So when we have everything in
one file and we export only
reducers and only actions.
So when we need reducers we
still can just import them directly from
one dux. The same
for actions. When we need actions we also can
import them from the same
duck.
And if you need anything else it's
quite flexible. So you also can
export another artifacts
that you need actions from
the ducks and then you can import them.
Here. I added a few links to different implementation of
Daxis today. Maybe they can look
a little bit outdated, but today
I'm talking about Daxis and I will be talking about
reducks now just to
go through the history of the redux
evolution. And Dax was
the first attempt, as for me, to change
the rules of the game and
after that redux appeared.
The difference between DaX and Redux is that
Dax's modular approach is nice, but it
doesn't work. When we have a lot of code in the same file
then it can be a problem to support such
file. So some people, they proposed
to split the code
from the docs into several files. So here
we can see example of the redux doc.
By the way, the name also just created
to sound like Redux. And here we
can see that in one ducks folder.
Ducks is one of the entities of our application like
user. We can have different files
in this folder like actions, operations,
reducks, selectors, test types, utils and we
export anything that we need from this folder
via index file. Redux also
has some rules that you need to follow.
So like DAC
contains concepts or I call them artifacts that are
related only to one entity like product card
and all of that. It's one doc years. So we should have
index files that exports everything and
we split reducers, selectors, actions and all
of that. We keep them in
separate files. And also this folder can
contain tests. Of course,
here we can see example of types.
They can be the same or similar on
Daxis in reducks, but of
course in Daxis they are edited in the same file
and redux in the separate file. So we can
have actions, operations,
reducers, reducers. By the way, it's the main
part of the redux.
That's why all this approach,
Dax and Redux, they were built around reducers,
as I said, reducers bundles.
So daxes are actually reducer bundles.
Yeah. Also we can have selectors. By the
way, I like to use reselect. I hope you do.
With Redux.
And we of course have index file where we import
and export all the stuff that we need
in other parts of our application.
And about DAX tests for Redux
and DAX, we can easily add tests
directly in the DAX folder and
then all tests that are related to our Redux
artifacts,
they are bundled together with the code that we test,
and it's very scalable. So when we need to add a new
entity, again, we add all the code and we add
the tests in the same folder. And when we need to remove
one entity, we just remove ducks and at
all, we remove ducks with all artifacts and
with tests as well.
And finally, we have a Redux toolkit. Redux toolkit.
I think it's an amazing thing. And as for
me, Redux Toolkit is a logical continuation
of this saga, I mean story with
Daxis. I think that Redux toolkit
slices that we have, they implement exactly
the idea to bundle all the stuff that
we need for one reducer in one place.
Redux toolkit, it has very good documentation,
a lot of different articles and all of that. So you can investigate.
And I think you already use it, most of you already use
this. So I just want to remind a few things that
Redux toolkit has. Redux toolkit
has configure store. It's a helper or
wrapper for create store. It help us
to create store very easily with
one or two, just a few lines of code. And by
default it supports Redux thunk. But usually
I use sagas, so you can easily configure a sagas as
well. And also it supports redux
details extension. It has createred
function, it has create action,
create slice and some additional utilities.
Yeah, just a small summary. Redux,
Redux and Redux toolkit.
As for me, they use the same pattern or approaches
for improving the structure
of the redux application.
React Redux feature
basic separation of the redux code is more flexible
and allows more opportunities for scaling when Cadaway
is growing. But if we are talking
about feature basic separation of the
redux code, not when we are talking about
all react application. So very important thing is
to move all state management
aside. For example, sometimes I
just create redux folder
and then I place all ducks here. There.
Yeah. So redux toolkit provides useful tools and
best practices. And really it is.
So I think many
of you heard that for angular,
when people say about angular,
even about Vue js, that when
newcomers start to work with those frameworks,
they can easily do the correct structure
because they don't have a lot of options. But with
react and Redux we had very
flexible approaches so we could implement
anything so newcomers could
create not very optimal solutions and
structures. But Redux toolkit is exactly
quite opinionated tool for structuring
redux applications. And by
the way how do you structure your Redux app? Please share
by the way here I added a bunch of links
to their articles or comments that
I shared in my talk and also I added
a link to my repository and to
the repository that I created especially for Con
42 and there I added
quite simple basic redux application
and also I created different branches
where I refactorate the basic
application with different approaches.
At first it's improved redux
approaches, then with Daxis, with reducks and
with Redux toolkit.
So if you would like you can check that
repository. I have just quite basic
stuff there but I plan to improve this repository
for better user experience so you can investigate and compare
and thank you.