Hey everyone, my name is Argo, and I'm a computer vision engineer at
Diagnacad. So today I would like to talk about a cool little technique
in computer vision, and we will discuss different cases
where you can use it. Let's start with some basics.
Computer vision is, generally speaking, when we use an algorithm
to analyze an image. In our case, we're talking about
deep learning and neural networks. For image processing,
classification is the simplest problem,
and it is used when we want to know if there is a
can or a dog on the image, for example.
So, classification is the most basic one. We give an image
to enroll net and get only class prediction.
But in the real world, classification is not that useful just by itself.
In a lot of cases, we need an object detection or segmentation
algorithm. In an object detection task, we just
have two subtasks. The first one is to localize
our object, and the second one is to classify that object.
And when we find an object, we localize it with a bounding box or
a b box. Computationally speaking, object detection
is a lot pricier than just classification. So we are
going to keep that in mind. Let's get closer to real
case, where we can make use of an object detection
algorithm for solving business problems.
Imagine that we have a lot of security cameras,
and we want to make sure that our building is safe.
Maybe it's a school or a shopping center. And we
want to detect any situation where someone gets in with a
gun. It would be really expensive to have a lot of
security guards who were watching every security camera. So it
would be nice to have a neural net, which can process video
streams from all cameras and send an alert
if something suspicious is happening. That's an
object detecting task. But because the system will work 24/7
we will get false alarms. Pretty much
a lot. And by false alarm, I mean when
the model thinks that, for example, a cell phone is a
handgun and gives a false alert.
So we would like to have an operator to validate
that. Alarms difficulties.
Yeah, there are some in this task, and we're going to talk about a couple
of them. The first one is that our solution needs
to be fast. It means that it should be
able to process a lot of frames per second and more
cameras we have in our building, more frames we
need to process. We can't use infinite amount of hardware,
of course, because if the solution is expensive,
it doesn't make any sense. Faster neural net, we have more frames
per second. We can process on one server. The second
problem, a lot of false alerts. We have already
talked about it a little bit, but generally speaking,
our video stream should be
processed twenty four seven. And that's more than
2 million frames per day per camera.
That means even if we have a really low rate of
false positives, we're still going to get them.
So we have to deal with it. And the third problem is
that our first two problems don't play well with each
other. Unfortunately, as it's always a tradeoff between
accuracy and speed. Faster neural net we have, less accuracy
we get and more false alerts we create. Usually, if we
want more accurate models, we need more hardware for
running bigger models at needed speeds.
But is there anything that can help a little bit with this tradeoff?
Yeah, fortunately there are several techniques,
and I'm going to talk about one of them, which has shown
its efficacy in different cases. So how
can we increase our accuracy without
losing processing speed and using the same amount of computing
hardware? We can get pretty close to that with this
idea. And the technique is to use two
neural nets in cascade. So one after another.
But both nets are tuned in a specific was to
complement each other. The first neural net is a
fast detector, so it runs on the whole frame,
but downscaled to 640 by 640 and localizes
interested object and classifies it. This model
should be tuned to have higher recall, sacrifice and
precision, which means that model will try to
always detect a gun, but will often give a false positive
on a cell phone or something else.
Detectors should be trained on relevant to inference images
with guns. The second neural net is a classifier.
It runs on the crop made by a detector,
so it runs only if detector finds anything at
the frame. Classifier's task is to
validate if chosen by detector object is a gun or
not. Classifier should be trained on crops from the detector.
So again, real images but
crops from the detector and classifiers should
have several classes. Not only a gun, but some
other objects which are often detected as a gun, for example,
cell phone, umbrella, bag, or something else.
The goal of the detector is to detect an object which might
be a gun. Classifier should be able to correctly validate that
object. So training both nets is done based on
that. I should mention that classifier is easier to retrain based
on real cases after deployment. So that's a great thing too.
So why does it work? Let's discuss a couple of things.
First of all, why is it fast?
Basically, the speed of our solution is tied to
the speed of the first neural network, the detector.
It's because our second net runs just in
cases when firstnet finds anything.
So 99% of the time second
net is idle. The second thing is that because we have
our classifier and it can
really validate our solution,
our prediction, we can pick a
fast detector. And now let's discuss why we gain accuracy.
First of all, we use an ensemble of two models.
Then second model gets full resolution, part of the image,
not downscaled like the first net. Third one,
we use different data set data sets for our models and
our classifier is tuned to distinguish guns
and other similar object. And one
more thing, from detector we need good detection. From classifier we
need good classification so we can choose models based
exactly on that. We do not need to sacrifice
classification power of the detector just because it
is fast. Here are some metrics. As you
can see on the right side we have slightly decreased
recall but noticeably increased precision.
And that's good because we don't want to spam
operators with our task. Now let's
touch a little bit on specifics of collecting the data set for
this technique. Of course you should remember about general things
like collecting balanced data set, data set,
diverse representative, have a good and consistent
labeling and so on. But here are a couple of things that
I want to mention for the detector. You need to collect data
as close to inference as possible. If your inference
is going to be on security cameras, you would want to collect your data set
on cameras close to that ones for
sure. You need to place it correctly and have correct angles.
Just how inference cameras are going to have your
object in the frame should be close to inference too.
So in an example with a gun, you don't
need to bring gun like to 10 cm in front
of the camera because it is not realistic. So collect
realistic images for the classifier. You would
want to create a lot of crops with your detector.
It's a good idea to run a detector with a low threshold
to get a lot of false positives. Then try to analyze images
and select groups like cell phones.
If it shows up often and create a separate class,
then you can create a class named other and put there all
images which do not belong to any created
class. Yeah, I will
also mention deployment slightly. As we have said,
it is important for us to have fast solution so we
can just train a model on Pytorch or tensorflow and call it
a date. I highly recommend converting your models to tensor
RT and it's basically an optimization for
Nvidia's gpus as
it will make your model like two to five times
faster and you will need less vram
on your inference so both things are
really good when you want to process as many video streams as
possible. With Pytorch, you can also have
a look to Tors script, but basically tensor
RT is always better, I mean faster.
So have a look to Tensorrt.
The second thing I recommend having a serving solution,
serving software such as Treetonserve or torch
serve or maybe tensorflowserve.
Basically it's like a backend where you store your model
and then send requests with images to process
that will help you for
scaling your deployed solution. And let's have a look to a
couple of examples so you just know where
to start. As a first neural network
detector, I often use yellow models. You can have a
look to yellow v eight and
there are several different models from nano
version to extra large, so you can really find
what you're looking for and what is important.
Yellow models converge to tensor RT really easily,
so keep an eye on that.
As our second model classifier,
I often start with efficient net maybe efficient
net version two. It also has
different sizes, around eight, so you can choose.
All right, let's sum up. When you need to deploy
an object detection solution which is going to be
need to increase precision without sacrificing speed.
Try using a classifier as your second model which
runs on the crop of the detector when it finds anything.
Thanks for your attention.