Hello and thank you for joining me today. Today my talk is
on end to end testing formerge and why it's the latest
and greatest best practice in continuous integration and continuous deployment.
And I'm going to show you how you can do it by leveraging ephemeral environments
with your CI. All right, let's get started.
So today at Comp 42 DevOps, I wanted to give
a quick outline of what I'm going to talk about. I'm going to start off
with the three main types of automated testing. Then I'm going to go into how
you can get more out of your CI by using it more frequently and testing
more often. And then I'm going to introduce the concept of ephemeral
environments as a vessel for more frequent testing.
So here are the three primary types of automated testing that you'll
run into in your CI, and these are all things that you can do in
your CI, but the question is how often? So unit tests generally
can be run against every commit in PR, just because they're
very simple. They usually just give an input and assert that
it equals to what's returned. Integration tests are
a little bit more complex. They're testing your function against existing
functions and ensuring that the results match. But end to
end tests, which is what our focus is on today,
test entire application workflows, which can be really difficult
because they do require a production like copy of the latest changes to your
code base, which is why end to end tests often
don't get run until your staging environment. That's just often very difficult
to do, to spin up an environment on every single branch,
and most companies do not have the infrastructure for that.
I like to think of CI as more than just a pipeline,
also a principle, as opposed to bundled releases.
You're having frequent smart commits and maybe deployments
every single day. If you're so lucky, you're able to automate
your tests and run them on smaller code changes. You can
also automate things like builds and limits,
and that way you're continuously writing code that's getting merged
to your main branch as soon as possible.
So I wanted to give a quick overview of what the default end to end
testing workflow tends to look like at most organizations.
So oftentimes you're working on a branch and you're developing
to the point at which you're ready to open a PR at
which you'll loop in one of your friends, one of your peers for code review.
They'll check that out, they'll give you any feedback, and then you'll keep
iterating until it's merged to main and deployed to your
staging environment, at which point your end to end tests will
be run against your staging environment. Although they might be run against
instead of just your own PR and your code
changes themselves, they might be run against multiple merged branches from
that day, because who knows,
you might be only testing maybe twice a week. So once
you get back, the QA engineers are going to sift through all
the bugs that were uncovered on the staging environment and send you right back
to the drawing board, at which point you're going to try to fix
those bugs, open a new PR loop in your peer again
for code review, and the process will continue until all the
bugs are eliminated. And so this makes it really
difficult for QA to estimate releases because
you don't know what bugs are going to be uncovered and when they'll be fixed.
And you oftentimes have several days of waiting in between a merge
pull request and a test run.
So there is a solution to
this and it's testing before merge, and there are many benefits
to running your end to end test closer to the PR.
You're identifying issues faster, you're keeping bugs closer to
the developer, and you're limiting context switching. And it
really just enables flow for a developer to be able to run their tests
every time they make a commit and have those bugs be identified right then
and there, and they can just go back and fix them, make that commit
and be absolutely certain before their PR gets merged
that it's entirely bug free. And this is what
the workflow tends to look like. It's a lot faster,
it's much less of a loop
and more of the inner loop is entirely
for debugging. And the outer loop is pretty straightforward
because the only bugs that you tend to run into are your features interacting
with other features on the staging environment. But basically you'll be
developing. You'll open a pull request which will trigger your CI to
run your end to end tests against a fully built ephemeral
environment based on your branch that you're working on. And at
which point it's important to loop in your peer after the tests
have run, because it really shouldn't be their job to uncover any bugs
in your code. They're just really checking for best practices. And then at which point
if there are any bugs, you've solved them, you've passed the code review.
You can merge that to main, deploy it to staging, which again will run
your end to end tests one more time against the multiple merge
features and then you can deploy to production. And this is a much faster,
much faster workflow because it cuts out oftentimes several days
of waiting. And once
you have your feature, it's pretty much in. You're not constantly
iterating and patching it, you feel confident in it.
And you've tested before merge. And so
in order to do this, I touched on this a little bit earlier,
but what you need to do is you need to work with PR environments.
And what you'll do is you'll attach a full stack ephemeral environment
to every pr, and this is going to be based, built based on
the branch that you're working on. And it will be infrastructure identical
to your branch, including the database. It's basically going to
be a copy of production with
a few things simplified, like you'll have less data,
but it will be very realistic. And then against this environment,
you can run all of your tests. You can run any test that you would
against your staging or your production, because you'll be able to run your
unit integration and end to end tests against this environment.
You'll be able to perform code review.
You won't just be looking at the code itself, but you'll be looking at the
code side by side with interacting with the environment
and seeing how your features perform through human testing.
And then what's really nice about these environments is because
they're Gitops enabled, their lifecycle is automated,
so they will automatically shut down upon a merge.
So I just wanted to give a quick demo on using
Cypress end to end tests on an ephemeral environment with
shipyard in GitHub Action's CI workflow.
All right, so here I wanted to show you what it looks like realistically
getting your app set up to run end to end tests before merge
using an ephemeral environment. So here's my application.
You can see that it's built and run using Docker build kit.
Can see the front end and backend services here.
And I define these services in my docker compose file,
which we can look at here under the configure tab. And it parsed out the
services right here. We're going to direct our tests towards
the front end service, and our back end service has a
database attached to it.
And right now we have some nvars that are injected during build
and runtime. And one of the nvars that we're going to pay attention to is
the front end domain for the front end service. And this
is where we're going to point our end to end test. So that will come
in later. We're going to configure our application that way. I'm just going to
show you what it looks like creating an account and
using this application. This was developed by the Cypress
team. It's basically a Venmo clone, and it's a great
way to showcase end to end tests with Cypress. And this
one here we're running in an ephemeral environment. So as we can
see, this is a Venmo clone. It has a few basic features. It has user
settings, you can add multiple bank accounts, it even notifies
you when you've been requested to pay. And since this
is all fake money, we were just going to make a request for $1,000
for lunch just to show the functionality.
So we can see that there are a few main things we can test here,
but I've written a few short Cypress
end to end tests that will just do some basic functionalities just
for this purposes of this demonstration.
So I'm just going to go to my terminal and I'm going to run the
Cypress tests that I've written and we're going to see them
run now. So I configured the app to point the end to end
tests at the ephemeral environment URL, which you
can see right at the top. So it's going to be the environment
that I just showed you. And these tests are super simple.
All they do is they just create a username, create an account, sign in
with that account, and go to user settings.
So years we can see everything's working as it
should.
And I'm just going to populate these fields with an email and a phone number.
And this last part here is just checking to make sure that the save button
is of type submit, which will matter later. All right, so as
expected, all the tests passed, but I want to take this to the next level
and I want to do this entirely in my CI.
So I'm running this. So I forked this copy from Cypress and
I do have a GitHub actions workflow set up.
And what I'm going to do here is I'm going to set this up to
automate my end end tests.
So right here we're using the shipyard GitHub
action, which you can get on GitHub marketplace. And basically
what it does is you go to your GitHub actions,
environment variables, and you set your shipyard API token and
your bypass token. And what it will do is it will take those and it
will auth into your ephemeral environment and it will be able to run
the end to end tests against the environment. So that's a real sample workflow
that we're looking at right now. And it's quite simple.
We're just going to use a custom run command because we only do want to
run that particular end to end test in this case
and that's our custom command there. So that's the exact thing that I ran
in my own terminal and it's going to perform
exactly the same, except this time it will be automated on every commit and
pull request. So here
we're going to see this run, but this is going to take a while.
So in the meantime I want to create a new feature. So right
here I'm just going to change the submit button to a button of type reset
just for testing purposes. And we're going to pretend that it's a cool
feature.
So I'm just going to commit
that in a new branch and
publish that.
And then based on the new branch we're just going to create a new pull
request to the base branch of my forked
repository. We don't want to accidentally send that to Cyprus's repo
and we're just going to pretend that this is a PR for a really cool
new feature that we've added that we do want to run end to end tests
against because we want to make sure that everything is functioning as it
should before we merge it. So very nice thing
about this is we have set up our GitHub actions workflow which is going
to be triggered upon that PR opening and
that will run just like the one that we were previously viewing.
It's going to take a while to run, so let's go back and let's see
how our initial run of the CI workflow is going.
It's been about a minute and a half and we're getting
through the workflow. All right, so I just have this
sped up a little bit, but what it did was it authenticated
into shipyard, it has the necessary
environment variables and now it's running end to end tests against
the environment. And again, this should function identically to how it did in
the terminal because it is just connecting to that environment based on
the URL and bypass token. And the first test passed
and as expected, all the tests have passed. So that's awesome.
And the nice thing about this is now this will happen on every single commit,
so that way you can make sure that your new feature
branches are working. But let's go back and let's see how our
pull request branch is doing so that pull request has built
in a new environment. So we're testing against that new environment environment
separately from the base environment. So I
have this at like eight times speed, just because we don't
want to wait through this, but everything is going as it
should. We're just about to integrate shipyard. All right, that worked.
And we're going to run end to end test against the ephemeral environment.
So again, this is my new feature in a PR environment. And I did change
something that I specifically changed so it would break the end to end tests,
because there is one test that specifically checks that that button
right there is of type submit. So it's struggling here.
And thank goodness we found this out now before merging that
to the staging environment, because we wouldn't want to break staging with failed
tests. So I think it's pretty clear here. I think,
thankfully, in this case, we know exactly what to fix. But before we
do that, we want to go to the PR environment and we want
to do a reset here. So it's
connected to our base environment and they share the same database,
and we want to load a snapshot from the base environment into
the PR environment and we want to make sure
that we reset it to a previous state because we did
create a new user account and we did a few things with the database that
we want to kind of clear from our view, just so we
can start fresh and be running the end to end tests against
the environment with an identical database every single time. So we're
just copying that back there and we are going to
fix this little bug that was uncovered that broke the end to end test,
which is just as simple as changing a button,
and we're going to just push that, commit, and just like that,
it's going to trigger our CI workflow once again, which I
also have at eight times speed.
And right there, we're authenticating into
shipyard into our environment.
All right. And then we have our environment here.
All right. And as expected, the first test passed, but now the moment
of truth, if the next test passed with our fixed
feature.
Again, thank you very much for joining me today. I hope you enjoyed
this presentation and I hope that you learned something new. And if
you have any questions, feel free to email me. Natalie at
shipyard build and I'm more than happy to talk about end to
end testing, ephemeral environments or anything DevOps related.
Always happy to hear questions. I hope you enjoy the rest of comp 42
and have a wonderful day.