Hello, my name is Pina Resnick. I'm CEO and co founder of Resing.
We are a startup and building carbon reduction platform.
And today I'm going to talk about carbon reduction,
carbon reduction in context of it and SRI specifically.
First question, how bad are bananas? Now that very interesting
book, I really recommend reading it about all the different emissions coming from
carbon footprint, coming from different things. Since this is not an interactive
presentation, so I'll just keep it in mind and I'll answer
this question. Is this all climate change?
It's the real thing, right? It's a stark question,
although at this point it's answered thousand
times. There is a consensus among scientists
that the climate is changing. There is tons and tons
of research and generally there is an agreement that if
the temperature is changing, it will be really bad.
And farther it goes, worse it will become.
Right now the temperature increases about 1% or so,
but if it will get to, let's say 8%, not percent,
degrees celsius, if it gets to 4% it
will be really bad. And if it gets to 8%, it would be
properly terrible. And as we can expect,
the richer countries or bigger, or countries with more industries and
more cars and stuff, they emit more. So you can
see that Europe, US and others, they actually emit more.
But now China and India and others are coming
as expected and join in the trend. A somewhat
optimistic parameter is that actually the
rich countries like US and European Union and others,
they are actually significantly reducing their emissions
for already quite a few years, for a couple of decades, the emissions
in US and Europe and other countries are going down
optimistic. But it's not good enough because
other countries like India and China are growing.
And that's why overall the world is still emitting
more and more carbon equivalents, which is
in total about 56 billion tons a year.
An interesting thing is that you can see COVID in
2020 when we stopped traveling
effectively entirely, and that had effective about 5% reduction
in carbon emissions. But a year later we picked it up
like it never happened. So we are still emitting more than before. COVID what
the governments are doing, actually some of the governments
doing a lot, specifically more than anyone, is EU
and UK and some of the. And some of us.
And the biggest agreement that we had
was in 2015 in Paris, climate agreement.
That's the commitment of the entire world.
Most of the countries is to keep the climate change below 1.5%.
And there's a bunch of other things that the governments are investing in, like sustainability,
development goals and ESG. Those are different things. Each one has
an element of climate change control, but they
go beyond that. It also about poverty and clean water
and food and all kind of things. And also ESG is also
about social and governance. So those are different things,
not just the environmental change. And also the environmental change also goes
into things like plastics and other things that are bad for
us but not for the climate. So there's quite a lot of things
and there's quite a lot of confusion, but generally there's a lot of regulation
coming from the governments. A very specific piece of
regulation that is probably the most relevant for us here in Europe is EU green
deal and specifically fit for 55, which is a commitment
of EU all you countries to reduce carbon emissions by 55%
by 2030, which will lead to massive
demand on everyone in new emissions.
That's the reporting part, which is called CSRD,
which is now a requirement for major enterprises and
gradually will become requirements for everyone. And of
course, you can imagine that carbon emissions reporting is only
for step towards actual reduction. Who needs the reporting?
Who needs the numbers? Unless this is just the first step,
it's just a baseline so we can set the reduction targets
and then we will find on those who didn't
actually reduce fast enough or carbon taxes to actually increase
the cost of services and products that
are carbon breach or emitting more emissions.
We can expect significant increase in cost of
not reducing carbon emissions. Let's try to understand a bit more.
What are carbon emissions in it, where they come from?
Generally IT industry is not really something
people talk about, but actually IT industry needs more carbon
equivalent gases than airwand industry,
which is surprising because airwand industry is everywhere in
all the news. But actually currently the IT industry emits about
three to 5% of total gases, carbon equivalent gases,
and it's expected to grow all the way to 14% in
2040. If we do nothing about that,
because of AI and cloud, and effectively
it becomes and central part of
any other industry. There is almost no industry today that is not using
significant amount of ag. So we will need to reduce,
like I said earlier, we need to reduce by 50%, 50 55%
within six years and by 90% within 25
years, while double going and
delivering ten or hundred times more it services.
This kind of challenge of do more with less is quite
a big problem. And the emissions are generally divided into three
scopes. The scope one is actually burning things that pre carbon emissions,
like fuel in the car or when the cement is produced,
or steel. There is also direct carbon emissions and then there is indirect
scope to through the electricity, and then somebody else is producing electricity
emitting those gases. And scope three is through indirect consumption.
Consumption of services are good. For example, I buy cloud services
from Amazon or Google or AWS
or Microsoft. They give me compute
services and they do all this scope one and two, and that becomes
my scope three. And when we measure, so when we report
on scope, on carbon emissions, we need to report on all three scopes.
And when we reduce the emissions, we need to reduce on all three scopes,
obviously, because what's the point? Yeah, what's the point of reducing
one but not the others? Actually, there is a point, but it's not
all of it. And we need to remember that my
scope one and two is somebody else's scope three.
So if I produce emissions, I'm not
doing it for myself. I'm doing it to generate certain goods and services
I sell to somebody else and not become scope three emissions for
them. And the regulation is going into direction that everyone should
report everything. It means that we will need to report very
detailed, very accurate, both real time emissions to
our customers, and we will need to collect from our supply chain. And it
will be more like the nutrition value on the food, but it needs to be
very accurate. It also needs to be detailed in real
time so we can actually act on it. If it's not real
time and it comes once a month or something like that, it's,
it's not something you can use if there is no feedback loop, it's not something
we can use to actually take actions and see the result.
So what we really need from our software service or
it service providers, we need them to report everything.
And when I say everything, it needs to be not just the electricity they are
consuming, but also embodied carbon in their hardware,
but also the buildings, and also the cooling and heating and also
everything else, all the emissions that they produce while they're
generating the services for us that needs to be attributed to
us. And then we can then calculate that and then send
it over to our consumers and to collect
all this together. The Green Software foundation created
software carbon intensity specification. Greensoftware foundation is a
nonprofit organization actually promoting
green software. Right. Green culture, practices of sustainability. And it.
The general idea of SCI is that there are four things.
Here is e, which is energy consumed by piece of software.
So when you run, you use cpu, ram,
networking, storage and other things. So it needs
energy, right? So that's the e. And we need to calculate
the energy very precisely for that specific application.
Then there is carbon emitted perfume. So basically,
carbon intensity in the grid, we are consuming energy,
which depends on the grid intensity. So in Poland, for example,
80% is coal, in Germany is 50%, and in
Norway and Sweden, almost entirely green energy.
M is the carbon emitted during production
of the hardware. So the embodied carving, and that's
per r, per unit of calculation. For example,
a call to API or a tweet or some sort of
calculation. So when I do that, I need to know for each of those
calculations how much carbon emitted specifically for that
calculation. And then that parameter is
called wrong ways to do, to reduce emissions or
not reduce emissions. The first one is greenwashing,
which is basically talking about reducing emissions but not doing.
A lot of companies are doing it, but generally governments
really don't like it because it actually doesn't do anything. It's all
about talking, not doing.
It's about pretending and hiding from responsibility.
You can find many different ways to do that. You can read more
online if you are interested. But there is so many ways
to hide emissions and pretend like it's okay.
And generally, governments are introducing more and more directives
and rules about eliminating that. So recently, a few
weeks ago, EU released new directive against greenwashing.
So you can just say that you agree you actually need to prove it.
And they're finding the law for different bad things companies did
to do it wrong is carbon offsets, and they're not always wrong.
Carbon offset is when you buy, when you continue
generating carbon emissions. But you buy offset, so you offset,
you buy something that actually reduces carbon emissions. For example,
somebody who plants trees or does others or
captures the carbon and you pay them to do that.
So you can put it in your accounting and pretend that you didn't emit those,
those gases. Most of them are not
real. Right. Really recommend to watch this very
funny dialogue by John Oliver. It's about 25
or something minutes and it's actually explains the carbon
offsets very well and it's very fun. So the other thing
is follow the sun. This is like in support. When we
have people around the globe they can support during the
day, right? So around the sun, yeah. Similar principle
is when there is sun, obviously there is more sun energy.
So more greener energy mix becomes greener.
So theoretically we can relocate our loads around different countries
and then enjoy the benefits of green or
basically carbon awareness. So greener energy mix,
but it's not always value, but it's always really
helping us because first it's very, it's not that easy to actually relocate
services. It's quite a lot of work and we need to consider how much
emissions we're going to generate while we actually
doing this work. Then potentially we need capacity in
different regions, and then there's embodied carbon and idle
energy consumption. So potentially it may not even reduce the emissions.
And then when we relocate to green areas, if everyone is
relocating to Norway, maybe it
will be okay for everyone, but then potentially the
cost of the services in Norway will go up because everyone
wants to be there to be greener. But then either it will be more expensive
or Norway will not be
able to generate green energy, sufficient amount of green energy, and they will start
doing non green energy. So they're all different difficult
questions to ask. But this strategy is
not bad per se, but it's not.
If you're not optimizing and just going after greener
energy, you're ignoring embodied carbon and all
kind of other things. That strategy, but it's not
automatically a good strategy. So what should we do then?
First, there's three major elements in this.
All we can divide work into three major areas.
One is energy efficiency, so basically, how we use less energy
do our work, applications are running.
Second is hardware efficiency. So how we reduce the amount
of hardware to reduce the embodied carbon in that hardware. And the
third is carbon awareness. That's the migrating to after
greener energy, migrating our loads after
greener energy. And not all of
it should come, must come in the same time.
So we cannot expect to just jump into being
awesome and cream overnight. So it's a
process. And although we need to act dramatically
faster than we are doing now, there's still,
it's impossible to do it overnight. But this is a great
project also by grant software foundation maturity Matrix,
which basically shows that it's a process of maturing.
So there's quite a lot of things we can start with and then gradually
improve over time. And the things that I would recommend
doing now immediately, is organizational, is about
acquiring knowledge and convincing the management to invest in this
and these kind of things, and make it critical,
strategic. And the second is collecting information,
because in our experience, most companies don't really
collect data about carbon emissions, or don't even know how
to collect the data. How it all connects to and
why SRE could be very valuable and helpful to actually achieve those goals
is if we look into SRE, what's the actual purpose of it is
the slight balance between the speed and reliability.
And nowhere mentioned anything about sustainability.
But yes, there is continuous improvement of
reliability of the software and also of
productivity of the developers, but the sustainability is not
part of it. And we know that when we look into
Sre, there's these four golden signals that are typically used to
measure the SLE, the SLos
and SLA's and Slis. They are almost based on latency,
traffic errors and saturation. Those are
the key elements, key golden signals, and they don't actually
reflecting the sustainability. Right. So what we would
recommend is to start using the fifth golden signal,
which is SCi, the software carbon intensity,
which I explained earlier. It is not so easy to
calculate right now, but it's generally not.
It's a very precise metric that can be calculated for each piece of
software. It's the energy consumed by the applications
multiplied by the energy mix in the grid, plus the
embodied carbon per unit of calculation.
And if we can attach to every single piece of application,
we can attach the SCI. We can also start measuring
and improving on it, in addition to those four other metrics,
then it's very important to change our objectives,
not just from speed of development and resilience
of the application. So reliability of the applications, but also
to keep our planet healthy, right. We have to keep
reducing our emissions and we have to measure an SRE is positioned
in precise place where they can have
immediate impact. So if we can define the carbon
emissions as the objective,
then we can define SLA's and SLis
in the terms of carbon intensity. And we
can continuously measure emissions and
then identify the anti patterns and reduce them. And the same
as we would do with reliability metrics, we would systematically
identify the waste and emissions and then would
systematically reduce them. I already said that aspect measurements
are very difficult, but there are some measurement tools that can
help, and that's the beginning. And we expect those tools to expand
the new tools to appear. An example is Kubernetes
Kepler. So Kepler, which is a tool that is managing,
it's connecting information about energy consumption within Kubernetes
and export it through Prometheus.
So it's not exactly showing the carbon emissions, but it
shows the energy consumed based on different physics,
which is much more accurate and much more definitely real
time. And it can be integrated with graphamin and normal monitoring
systems. You can actually see the energy consumed
by applications within your clusters.
Another one is scaffolder, which is also
which is focusing on mostly on the bare
metal and hardware through the kernel codes. There are all kind
of details you can find scafander. Both of them are open source projects, and both
of them are somewhat advanced, but not yet
covering everything. In Vasync, we are working on a
project called ether, which is carbon observability platform.
Sorry. It's carbon observability tool that also
integrates with Kepler, but also directly looks into virtual
machines and other things in the cloud and on Prem. And it
can generate detailed view on energy
consumed and embodied carbon emissions
and all converted into carbon emissions based on
the actual energy grid. So we're also going and checking with tools
like energy mach to understand the current
energy mix in the grid. So in any given moment. So this
way we can collect information in real time,
accurate detail and real time information about carbon emissions,
different it systems on Prem and the cloud, and then show it to
the users. This one is also open source. You can go to GitHub and
encourage you to give it a star and continue
to ask questions. The next level of
tooling is profiling. So there are quite few different
profiling tools that also can. So there is a
way to convert effectively every line of
code into energy consumption, and then again converts it to carbon
emissions. And you can find those two really good talks,
one by Ng and one by Firefox.
So you can see this presentation and the
links will be available in the presentation. But those talks
are going into detail of really debugging or profiling the application
line by line, and seeing each line, how much emissions it produce,
and then figuring out which algorithms or way of coding or
different data structures, how they affect sustainability.
Of course there is different programming languages.
Each one of them is different. Some, obviously the interpreted ones,
are heavier than compiled ones. This is
not very up to date, but it's
not just about languages, but it's also about different tools like
databases and everything else. So each one of them would have different
carbon footprint. And if we have a general understanding
how much each of the tools in our system contributes
to the emissions, then we can start taking actions.
So there are many ways to reduce the emissions. There is the
most obvious ones, it's just reduce waste. So kill the zombies,
descale your clusters, they just shut down
things that you're not using. Some of the clouds are greener than on prem,
or maybe the other way around. It depends. It needs to be measured. But there
are many ways to improve the energy consumption. On energy mix.
Auto scaling is always very important because otherwise
we tend to over provision and then just run unneeded resources.
There is a big difference between x 86 and our own
energy concern. And those are just examples of
different patterns that can be quite easily improved.
For example, we say if you have in the same cluster,
very stable load, with some spiky
cron jobs or some white cron jobs,
then those things could be separated and run
in different ways, or there are different strategies to
deal with it. But basically if you separate the loads, or if
you pre provision or dynamically provision the hardware for those
spikes, you can often reduce the size of a
cluster, sometimes by 50%, with no
impact on the actual applications. We need to
make sure that we only request the needed amount of resources.
CPU and RAM are the most energy consuming components.
We need to make sure we don't request more than we need. There are all
kinds of different things to optimize, like container images,
jvm settings, not to grab too much memory, not to build massive
images. All of that translates into more energy
consumption, which translates to more carbon emissions.
What we see often that people deploy too many test environments.
I understand this is very. This is what continuous delivery and
continuous integration require. But actually it's not,
right? So if you provision an environment on each pr, on each commit,
and you don't really use or on tests on it, then what's the point?
And maybe it doesn't cost you much because you already pre committed
to those servers, but it still consumes
energy. And if you provision those things, yeah, you're just emitting
more current. Or another example is if your
business doesn't require higher availability, don't do
it. Because that will mean not just additional cost but also additional emissions.
Right? It means more is more redundancy,
more different zones, all kind of different things.
And there is different tools, different databases, some of
them are heavier than others. Do you really need something like
Cassandra? If you can manage with a small postgres and
stuff? It very much depends on the use cases
and there's a lot more. And also there is strengths in paging
software foundation, also quite useful. And we always seem
to remember it's not just about energy consumption, it's also about embodied
carbon. This is an example of a Dell server which is over 7000
tons of emissions over the course of their life.
It's emitted before it actually was sold, right? So it's
the embodied carbon which when you buy the server, it's already emitted.
Now the question for how long you will keep it? You keep
it for four years, then it's one and a
half tons a year. If you keep it for ten years,
it's 700 kilogram per year. It's a big
difference. And generally it also costs you money to
buy new servers. Of course there's also a bit of balance.
Like newer servers are a bit more energy efficient.
So it's still not black and white. We need to understand in
detail the energy consumption and budget carbon, and then make
the decisions based on combination. So in this case,
about 17% of lifestyle emissions
will be from embodied carbon in case of this specific server
on average. And another example,
Amazon recently decided to extend the lifespan of their service to
six years. And that saved them not just a lot of emissions,
but also $900 million. In our experience,
we can expect quite reasonably easily reduce
the emissions by at least 50% just
by fixing infrastructure waste, removing infrastructure
waste, and then potentially another 20 30% by
optimizing the software, which is. And then more,
by using more efficient tooling and replacing them with
less resource intense tools. That's about
it. Just answering the questions about the question
about the bananas. The bananas are actually not very bad.
Bananas are at single banana average. It depends
if it was flying or not. There are all kind of different considerations, but generates
about 110 grams of CO2 each a
spoon bowl. Bananas are not that bad. Couple other
examples. So an email, it goes from 0.3
grams on a spam email that no one opens. It is
still a bit of emissions, because there is brick sending and stuff
all the way up to 26 grants. If you send it to,
it takes you ten minutes to write some screen time, and you send
it to 100 people and they open it and they
look at it for 3 seconds. So again, all the servers around
and screen time and everything, it means that when
you send things to more people, then you produce, generate more missions.
So you need to consider, every time you do things, there is impact, especially if
you do it on scale. A typical laptop and
actually laptop or a phone.
So both of them generate about. Actually both of them both.
83 84% of emissions on average would
be embodied emissions and not energy consumed.
So the energy is actually only 15% and then
only 2%. And the services around the Gmail and
networking and whatever is about 15% is
an interesting thing. So people think there is
no emission, but actually there is embodied emissions in the bike
itself. And also we, when we bike,
we expand, we use our own energy. So if we bananas,
it's 40 grams/mile
how much? 4.7 kilogram air
freighted asparaguses. Right? So that's how
much energy we expand to go a mile on the bike.
If we compensate it with elephant sporagosis, that's that
much. 4.6 hundred times more.
It basically shows that asparaguses are
the worst. Generally speaking, beef is the worst
meat. And then in terms of emissions, and then
one, and then chicken, and generally
the grown food is less impactful cryptocurrencies
is a big deal. They are 0.12%
of total world carbon emissions and it doesn't sound a
lot, but actually considering that this is not really essential,
like all this cryptocurrency mining is
quite stupid way to create. I'm not expressing
my opinion about cryptocurrency or blockchain technologies,
but in general we are wasting a lot of money,
resources and generating a lot of emissions.
Cloud altogether is about quarter
of a percent. It's 1% of global electricity and quarter percent of total
carbon footprint and in
total is 1.4
billion tons. Right. So it's three to 5%.
Depends how we can grow. And I actually
recommend you to read these books. There's how bad are bananas?
Really good book. To get a feeling how the carbon
footprint is calculated. The best and probably the only
technical book around green software is by Ann
Sara and Sara building green software. It's a great book.
It was released just a few weeks ago and then the other books are pilgrim
still probably the best book on high level and not
the end of the world. I really recommend you if you want to have optimistic
and realistic feel. And the last one is just an interesting one.
It's not very easy about. You'll see.
Look into it. It's an interesting one, but not like the others.
Thank you for listening. And the last thing I would say is
that if you think what's next? What can I do next? I would recommend you
to read the building green software. I think that's an excellent book
that will give you a good overview of on the technical level and
start measuring. Try to at least roughly understand what
are the emissions generated by your systems.
Thank you and please get in touch if you have more questions.
Okay.