Okay, let's begin. First we are
going to talk about the Darwin kernel.
Darwin kernel is the kernel of all Apple
operating systems. Was created in 2000
by Apple based on BSD
and match with parts from OpenStep.
You know that OpenStep was an open API created
by Next and San microsystems based
on the work that SteveJots made in next
computer. Because next computer is
not solvent in financial way,
Steve Jobs thinks about to make an
open API with open step with
the possibility to work in Windows or
even in Apple machines. And in
this project, the result from this was
open step. And this is the core of the iOS
ten operating system. It supports all
Apple OS, macOS, iOS,
watchos and tvos. And maybe the next reality,
iOS. It's an open source project and it
iOS a kernel that supports the Appkit or
Uikit development APIs. You know that
Appkit is from macOS and Uikit
is from iOS and the other mobile
development, mobile systems like TBOS or
watchOS, including the macOS interface.
Aqua that. It's the interface, the API for
the interface. IOS built in C and
C. Okay? It's the kernel,
it's the core of the operating system,
and it's the same core for all the
operating systems from Apple.
We are going more deeper and for
understand all the things about the security of the iPhone,
we are going to talk in a brief,
secure history of the first iPhone.
Because I think it's very important to
know the past, to understand the
present and the future. And we are going to make this
brief security, this brief, secure history of
the iPhone. Okay? Today, there is no
doubt that January 9,
2007, the wall changed with
the introduction of the first iPhone.
Okay. But the first iPhone model,
however, was far from the current ones.
In fact, it was way less secure than
the actual iPhones. For example, the iPhone
edge was a full feature smartphone,
but it had no apps. It's a closer device.
When asked for apps, Apple's answer
was web app, not third
party apps that runs naturally in the
device. Apple defended to the hilt.
It was not necessary to have third party software
on the iPhone. And these closed functions were
enough. The first idea
about the iPhone is to make a device similar
to an iPod with closed functions.
Not the possibility to expand it,
but with more functions, but all
the functions that the
mayor of the users needs to work needs
for his device. But Apple and Steve
Jobs was not sure about apps
could bring something interesting to the users.
And well, for now they
speak about to use web apps.
The iPhone was totally closed in system
and kernel. It's like I said, a closed
device. Otherwise, the initial
scroll, the pinch, or the capacitive touch screen
were some of its milestones.
And let someone talk about this with
software. Now, software on mobile phones is
like baby software. It's not
so powerful. And today we're going to show
you a software breakthrough. Software that's at least five years
ahead of what's on any other phone. Now,
how do we do this? Well, we start with a strong foundation.
IPhone runs OS ten.
That's the key. Now,
why would we want
to run such a sophisticated operating system
on a mobile device? Well, because it's got everything we need.
Good question. It's got multitasking, it's got the best networking.
It already knows how to power manage. We've been doing this on mobile computers
for years. It's got awesome security and to write
apps. It's got everything from Cocoa and
the graphics, and it's got code animation built in, and it's
got the audio and video that OS X is famous for.
It's got all the stuff we want and it's built right into iPhone.
And that has let us create desktop class applications
and networking. That's the
most important key about the iPhone because
it runs os ten.
And like Steve Job said, it's got awesome security.
But the iPhone was software locked
to what it has preinstalled, like I said before.
And it used the Darwin kernel
and the new Coco touch library on top of
it. It's an extensive framework with
Uikit and other framework, other APIs
like your session or cocore animation,
core audio and the other APIs that Stigob
said in the keynote presentation.
The kernel being based on BSD is
the same kernel that we said before.
The Darwin kernel that fits without any
problem in its 128
megabytes of rAM that the iPhone
has. Okay, but you know
that native apps were programmed in object
C. And Apple, this is the most important thing about
security. Implemented digital signatures for
code execution. And this
is the way that we guarantee
the security of the device.
And for make this to ensure
this security, app used this on
certificate authority to disallow the execution
of code that was not signed of
them on the system. Because of this,
as you know, if you try to execute
any software on the iPhone, even if
you could compile a program for
this, it's not execute because it's not
signing by app. But do
you know that Apple think about third party
software from the beginning? Yes.
Let's read this. We define
everything that is on the phone. You don't want your
phone to be like a pc. The last thing you want is
to have loaded three app on your phone and then you
go to make a call and it doesn't work anymore.
These are more like ipods than they
are like computers. This is the first
way that Apple see its
device. But jobs add
this. That doesn't mean there's not
coding to be software to buy that you can load on them coming
from us, it doesn't mean we have to write it all,
but it means it has to be more of
a controlled environment.
Steve Job said this on January Twelveth,
three days later from the
iPhone keynote presentation on the New York Times.
As you see, Apple was thinking
about the possibility of the App Store. But first they
want to know if the iPhone will be
a success or not. Obviously.
Okay, well, but we
are going to talk about the security of this first iPhone,
that it's way far from
the actual security because of this.
Okay. The first iPhone has a cryptographic coprocessor.
Well it's so. Well, because it
needs to validate the digital
signature of the software. It has two
AES keys engraved in the ship which
cannot be extracted a Giid,
a global key which is the same for all the
devices and other that iOS unique for
each device. The combination of these
two keys makes the way for the
cipher for the cryptography needs to
encrypt or decrypt data or validate
the detailed signature of the programs
in the boot process. The did and the UID keys
are used to create the keys to
be used by the device and those limits its exposure.
Okay, the passcode was
recorded in the keychain with no hash.
It's open even more.
If you clean the record in the keychain
for the passcode, you are open the iPhone
and that was passcoded to anyone.
Okay, well this is the security.
It's so easy. It was so easy to
clean a passcode in the first iPhone and
obviously was
increment version by version. The security of the
device, the device keychain was and still iOS,
an sqlite three database.
But most important, only the password elements
were encrypted, were encrypted. The other was
open in plain text. The encrypted elements were
encrypted with the device key and a random initialization
vector. But it was only one key for the
whole keychain because if you make
a brute force attack, you could
extract the key and access to
all the keychain and all the items, not only
the items in the keychain, also the
future keys in the keychain could be extracted
if you make this brute
force attack to this only key,
I repeat only for the password
elements. The other are recorded
in the keychain in plain text format.
The iPhone Os one file system was not
encrypted. Use a file system similar
to the iPod and you
can see all the folders with a special
software. But any executable maybe
the most important using about the security of this iPhone
had to be signed by Apple to run on the iPhone.
But maybe you are thinking about
what is a digital signature. Okay, we are going
to talk about it. The digital signature, it's a method
to ensure that a certain file or
data is not modified in the
time since it was digital
signature detail signed, okay. It is a
method to ensure the integrity
of a data and the
fact that this was not modified, okay,
works in this way. First we have
a document and then we are coding
to calculate a cryptographic hash of this
document. A cryptographic hash that validates
its content. Okay, we have this cryptographic
hash. Then we used a
private signing key from a certificate.
The private key is used to encrypt and
the public key is used to
decrypt it. IOS like you have the rare
or unrar or thief or antip,
something like this, okay, you have two ways
to make or extract,
okay? With the private key you can encrypt
something. You can encrypt this
cryptographic hash, but with
the public key that you can put
in something or give to anyone. With this
public key you can only do
a decryption. You can't encrypt
with this public. You only come to decrypt with
this private signing key, you encrypt
the hash. Then when you are encrypting
the hash, then you are going to
attach this hash to the document.
And now we said that you have assigned
document, okay, well,
and then time goes by and
later on we can check the signature
and the integrity of a file, a file
with its digital signature attached
on it. Well, the next step
is to calculate the cryptographic
hash without the encrypted signature part.
We are going to recalculate the cryptographic hash
because we need to know what is this hash
for the file. And then we used the public
key to decrypt the signed
cryptographic hash.
When we have the cryptographic
hash under the decrypted cryptographic hash for the digital
signature, we are going to compare.
If these two hashes are the same,
it means that has not been altered
and is validated and has been signed by the
authority that encrypted the hash in the first steps.
That's it. This is a digital signature.
Well, let's talk about next step
with the a seven code. The secure enclave
chip. Apple evolves
the encryption engine that has from the
first iPhone to a
multipurpose chips intended for all security and
encryption functions on the systems, including the
biometric features with a new
security chip called Secure Enclave,
a chip that iOS iOS property
is a property of the kernel of the systems.
As you can see, the keys never
leave the chip to another context.
The keys that the system uses
or the biometric data for
Touch ID or Face ID never
leave the chip to another context.
Secure Enclave is a black box.
It's a black box responsible
for encrypting and decrypting any data. But you put
a data on secure enclave and secure enclave returns
the data with the encryption or
the data decrypted.
But you never know how
this chip works internally.
Okay? This is the most important thing and
we don't know how iOS or what is
this mathematical way to storage.
All the things about the geometry, the Touch ID and the Face ID
and other thing that Apple makes is
to encrypt each file with an independent
and unique key for each file, not one
key for all the file systems, okay?
And again, all inside this
secure enclave, only the chip finger
is able to access the contents of the chip memory.
Even if we read the memory, we will not be able to
extract anything of it.
Sand hackers and security investigators
try to read this memory, but this
memory is not able to track anything.
The chip has an as 256
bitelectic curve, cryptographic key
enzyme and four megabytes of ram
in its first version. With this,
we have this black box and ensure
all the checks about encrypting data,
signing data or biometric data,
and all the things related to the security of
the device. And obviously the system behaves in a very
fluid way because there is no weight for these tax
on the system. Okay,
we are going to talk about additional layers of security
that have been incorporated over time.
For example, access to user information,
extensions, services, or even iCloud is
controlled by digital signed entitlements.
But what is an entitlement? An entitlement allows the
app to use certain functions or obtain specific
permission to run some services or features
on the system. If you want to use
something that is not allowed for certain functionality,
you can activate this entitlement. In fact,
Apple could authorize
you for certain entitlements after
you ask the permission for certain features.
Okay? And these entitlements allows you
to use certain kind of APIs that
in the first way it's forbidden for you. For example the
diecloud or something else. Okay.
Another thing that was implemented in the
iPhone was ASLR or
address space layer randomization that
iOS incorporated in the system.
This was a kind of security that iOS in
each operating systems like Windows,
Linux, et cetera.
This function creates a table that ships
important areas of the system such as the kernel,
so that they are not always in the same place. And your
process must have permission to ask
about these tables to know what
is the memory address of the kernel
or other operating system important
parts to access to them.
Obviously you are not allowed to ask about this
in your app, but the system have
this security to guarantee the
security and the integrity of all the system.
About this iOS use Armxn
or execute never. This is a way which
marks memory pages as nonexecutable.
If you put some code in the memory,
you cannot execute this
code. You are not allowed to execute
code in any memory position in
the device. Why? Because you
need a valid entitlement of the associated
app, but will be able to execute
this code in memory.
Each app has its own entitlement
and if a code is not
from this certain app is
not allowed to execute this code
in this place in the memory.
Okay. This is the way that
the system guarantees that you are not
allowed to execute or to inject
any code on the system to execute
it. If this code is
not from an autorespond app that
it was a valid digital signature. Okay.
Another thing iOS about network communications,
we're going to talk about app transport security.
ATS ETS is a set of requirements for
securing network communications. It force
the exclusive use of your session and URL
connection even for third party network
APIs. Because of this,
all the third party network APIs
are wrappers of Apple's native
APIs. If you use Af
networking or Alamo fire,
you are using a wrapper of URL session.
Okay? From iOS
nine. This set of requirements are
mandates for things like the users
of TLS one two or even
TLS one two three on all server
certificates, 2048 arse
encryption or 256
bits elliptic curve key signed with
SHA 2056
using AC DHe with
firewall secret this is a
protocol to key agreement between two
servers. You make a
public key and send to another server and this
server makes another public key and sent to you.
And with this you can create a key agreement and
create a private key that iOS shared between
two sites from our server
and the other server or from our device to a server
and we have a private key that iOS
different from each side but you
can use it to decrypt the same data with
this public key associated this is a key agreement
protocol communication encryption.
Okay, allow exceptions
for this. If you don't want to use a secure
connection through HTTPs or
another protects, you can allow
Apple allow the exception for for example
multimedia content streams with AV foundation
that can do it in HTTP or
webview request or maybe local host
usage when are working in debug
code. Okay.
All these things are mandatory standards
since the end of 2016 which evolved
year after year to comply with best practices in
communications security. We must know all
these rules to ensure the security of
our app. Okay, well we
are going to talk about data encryption. The use
of data encryption is free to use but with recommendations
for Apple. For example, Apple does not recommend the use of R
C, four or three DES algorithms.
Both are compromised and will be removed to avoid
their use in future versions. For encryption you must
use AesGCM or
Chacha 20. That is two
encryption algorithms that both support from
Apple's cryptokit API that it's available
for the system from iOS 13.
Cryptokit is a swift native
APIs API for encryption.
Also if you work with SwiftuI
in open source, you can use Swift crypto
that is the same as cryptokid but
using the coding SSL Google engine
to make the same things with the
same specification with the same interface.
Because of this you can work in encryption
in for example server side in vapor or in
your app using Cocotach or Cocoa.
With cryptokit these algorithms have the
advantage of allowing not only encryption but also
checking whether the data has been modified.
We can validate the integrity of any
data that it's encrypt of the crypt with these algorithms.
Also all the files on the device are encrypted
and we have several encryption modes to set for
each file that we can use when
users the metal safe from a
data type. For example,
we are going to talk about these four
system code for encrypting data in storage.
The first one iOS NS file protection known there
is no encryption on the data. It remains open even when
the device iOS locked. However, it requires
the file system to be mounted because when
your device is turned off the
file system is not mounted. It needs that
the file system is mounted and then anyone
can access to these files.
The next level is the NS file protection, complete until
first user authentication. As you can see
this name is from objective c. Obviously this
option is the default for the system,
it means that the file is encrypt and inaccessible
inaccessible until the device is unlocked
for the first time. When you put the first time your passcode
or your password okay.
It also locked after 20 or maybe
44 hours which requires real locking
with passcode instead of touch id or face id.
Do you know that between 24 hours
or maybe later the device will ask
you again for the passcode?
And because the system rancrypt all
the file system and needs you to
put your passcode again.
Like I said, this is the default code for all
the files and it's a code that
allows to access the files even when
the device is locked. Okay,
but you must put the first passcode
at the beginning for processes that need continuous
access to data, music, podcast,
Bluetooth devices, your location, et cetera.
Even if you have your device locked,
your files are visible to
the file system and the apps can access them
while the device iOS not in mode.
For asking you to put again the passcode,
the next step is NS file protection
complete unless open. In this
kind of security, all the files are encrypted
and can only be opened when the device is unlocked.
When you locked the device, the file iOS encrypted and
iOS not allowed to access to any app
or any process in background.
But there is one exception.
Files are not locked or encrypted
when the device is locked. If they're being used, they wait
to encrypt when no threat is using it.
Imagine you have a background process and
you locked the device.
Well if you lock the device and the file
is using, the file is not encrypted
unless it's closed.
Unless complete. Unless open okay when
the process is finished, then encrypt
the file and the process or any other app
cannot access to them. Okay recommended for the process
when you have uploading or downloading data over
network, which must be encrypted when
the background process will finish. Okay, and the
perfect method the method I use for most
of my data is NS file protection complete.
NS file protection complete is the higher security code.
IOS files are encrypted and inaccessible
until the device is unlocked. Okay, if you have
your device unlocked, okay your device your
files are ready to access, but if you locked the
device, then all the files will
be encrypted and it was impossible
to access for any app or process.
Okay, files are locked and
any threats to them are cut off when the device
is locked. Okay recommended
for most update how can
you use it? How can you use this?
Well, using this code as you can see
you have a try data
write to URL and then you users options.
And in these options you can put enumerations
in an array. The first
is atomic.
Atomic. It's a mode that opens
a temporary file to write
all the data buffer, all the process to
write the data buffer to this temporary file.
And when all the data buffer is
write to this temporary file, the temporary file is
closed and then moved to the final location
in the disk on the disk on the
location of the app. Okay? This is a
secure way to ensure that
any other process cannot access to a
writing process. In my application also
you have complete file protection. Complete file protection
iOS, the last mode that we
are talk the code that encrypt the
file in the moment that you locked
your device. Okay? This is the way you
can use this. With all
these things in our hands,
we have to ask you ourselves,
are our iPhone secure?
No. No system iOS secure.
Even with all present of feature security features,
no device iOS ever 100%
secure. They never will
be. Never. It's impossible.
Okay, if someone says you
something, someone says you that your iPhone or
any other device is 100% secure,
it lies to you. Okay?
Every operating system and even hardware
can have bugs in its design or iOS code
that allow vulnerabilities to exploit
it and do things that a system is
supposed to be protected against. It's easy
to understand what is a zero day because
it's a software that tries
you not to do something has
a bag and this back
that allows you to do it.
That's it. And there's
no system without this kind
of errors. How can I protect against
this? Okay, the only way to be protected is
update our system as soon as patches
are released for the bugs that are discovered.
But part of our responsibility as
developers is to take into account best development
practice that improve security and make it more
difficult for civil criminals to compromise
our systems. Okay? If we
do the right using to
make our app more secure will
be hard for these civil criminals
to compromise our app and our users'data.
Okay, that's it.
We are going to talk about Swift Swift security
because Swift has security as its
core. Why? Okay, Swiftui, like many other languages,
is made in c, in c language, okay,
but Swift is strictly typed,
value oriented language. But what
does that mean? Okay. Means that
data is self initialized to
data types and isolates them by
default. When you put a number
one in your code, one is not a value,
it's a type. It's a data type.
That's because we are talking about value
typed because the values are typed
and converted automatically into
data types because it's self initialized
and there's no values in Swiftui,
there's data types. Because of
this. You can infer when you put let
a equals one, a iOS
integral type because one is not a
value, one is an integral type.
Self initialize it. Okay? This is
value typed language, okay? And is
strictly typed. Because of this,
the different data types are not allowed to
work between them. Also, swift runtime
is static. It's not dynamic, so it
does not allow runtime injection of
any elements. Because of this, when you work
with TDD, with test driven development,
you have to create code,
the injections or the mock
objects, et cetera. You cannot use
an API that injects dynamically
like objectise or even other languages like
Java because Swiftui has this
static runtime and you cannot modify anything
in the execution of your app collection
types even is fully
dynamic, so it avoids buffer
overflows as its foundation. A string
data, an array or dictionary has
no initialization for
the initial storage if all
this kind of data are 100%
dynamic. A string has
a dynamic storage and creates more storage
when it needs in real time.
Okay? Because of this, it's impossible to
do a buffer overflow when you code in impure
swiftui. Okay, the use
of uninitialized variables is prevented.
As you know, we all know the optional values
and iOS a compiler error for Swiftui forcing a
defined initialization or the use of
optional values. As you know, all the
data in Swiftui must be initialized
before we are going to users it.
Okay? And if some data
we don't know the data, we are going to storage them,
we must users the optional values. Optional values
are an uninitialized variables. No,
because an optional value when you're defined it
has an inferred initialization equals
nil when you put bar something column
int question mark and
the compiler inferred equals
nil. Because of this, all the data
are initialized before we
used. Okay.
Also, code compiled in Swift is obfuscated
by default. Any code
compiled in Swift is not readable,
is not accessible. You cannot
read a compiled code in Swiftui because it's
obfuscate. And obfuscation is when you
change the name of the mail dots and the variables
to something is not readable like
randomized characters. Okay?
You have a table for
the corresponding names between the readable
names and the non readable name that it's obfuscated.
Okay, this table is the symbols.
When you strip the symbols in Swiftui compilation.
You're making this table and this table
later you have to upload, for example
to chrysalytics in Firebase to make the
match between the obfuscated names and the
names that the program used. Okay, this is
the script symbols functionality, the feature
let's go. And we are talking about insecure that
data recording. We are going to talk about best
practices with data. We have to know
that any data recorded in flat persistent is
visible by anyone such as using JSon,
paylist or even core data or sqlite databases.
It is wise to audit the sensitivity of the data
before developing and decide how it will be
persisted and where and if any data
needs encryption or maybe any data have
to be storage in certain locations,
for example the keychain to
avoid the access or read from
anyone in the flat persistent,
okay. Sometimes they are very sensitive data
that either should not go on the device. For example,
some data must be only in server
side and if you work with this data
only in your memory, this data iOS secure.
But if you storage in your device with
a JSoN, with a paylist, with a database,
et cetera will be visible
in, like I said before, persistent,
flat persistent, okay. Because of this,
the best way to work with certain
data is not to a storage on the device works
only with server size and with
memory or have their own container
in the system to be stored. The keychain
health data or maybe honky data
has its own container in the system and
you have to use it. Okay, even more,
the users of local databases should be
properly encrypted. It's a best practice
to make a transparent ledger between
your database, for example with
core data or even when you store directly
in your application a JSON file.
Maybe it's a good idea to make a transparent
layer for encryption in these databases.
Okay. If you users realm, for example
realm has this feature,
you can set an encryption
key on realm and then all the data
in this database will be encrypted and is not
visible to anyone that try to read
the database. Okay. But with code data you
must create this transparent layer
for encryption and decryption. It's not so
hard because you can users extensions
for the data types, okay, but well you
must do it. This is your responsibility.
If we persist, for example, an enumeration that is part
of a sensitive data set, we should not
duty its value as a string or sequential
numbering, okay, if you users an
enumeration and you are
typing with string,
it's more secure to put strings that
is not equivalent to its
value. Okay, because of this, when someone
read your code, when someone read your data,
they don't know the equivalent,
the equivalent of these values.
Okay,
more now we are going to talk about
data encryption and has calculation. Okay,
maybe you are thinking, but to use encryption,
okay, we are going to see it. The first things we want to know.
IOS cryptographically secure random numbers
okay, what is this? Okay, first of all,
before playing with cryptography, it iOS necessary to
be able to generate random numbers,
but secure random numbers.
Cryptographically secure random numbers,
cryptographically strong random numbers
which are built in arrays of bytes in
a data type and not with numbers.
Why we use them? Because these do not use
any type of value from the device itself like other
randomized algorithms.
With this way we use algorithm,
algorithmic formulas that guarantee that no
pattern can be found that will discover them.
It's a totally, absolutely randomized
number with created without pattern,
okay, it's a cryptographically strong
random number, okay, how can
we create it? Okay, it's so easy. We can
use the sec random copy
bytes method from the security
of the keychain and all the things
about the security framework in Swift.
And then we can use
something that is so good from
swift five. The array
of u int eight and
signed integral of eight bits.
An array of this swift native type
is convertible, is directly convertible
to data type with the constructor.
Okay,
as you know, you can convert a double
number in int or int in double,
okay, you can put an in number double
parentheses in number parentheses, and then you have a
direct creation, a direct transformation
between types using the constructors, okay,
an array of u int eight has
direct transformation with
data type. If you have an array of
using eight, you can put this data in
data constructor and you are
making a new data type, a new row bytes
data type. We are creating an array
with empty values with zeros. Then we
send to sec random copy bytes with
the property ksec random default.
Then the count bytes bytes
we desire and then the reference with
the ampersand of random bytes.
Then sec random copy bytes returns in
random bytes. The strong, the cryptoker,
the cryptographically strong random number.
Okay, it's so easy to make with
this we can use data encryption.
For example, when you have to store
a password, you must store not in
plain text, please, you must store
in hash.
With a password hashing, even the
best way to do it is with hmac
256 algorithm,
okay, hmac, what is hmac?
It's an algorithm that uses a key to ensure
that hashes are not repeated in their
calculation. For the same data. One of the
most important problems when you calculate a hash is
the collision, okay? When you have a collision
in a hash calculation, it means you have two
different data that has the same hash,
okay. And that it's a great problem to
try to resolve this.
HMac put a key when
you calculate the hash. Because of this, if you
don't have the key, you cannot
check the data. You cannot create the
same hash for the same data.
Because for validate a hash,
you must have the data and
the equivalent and the key we use to create this
hash. Okay, how can
you do it? Okay, using cryptokit,
this iOS the easiest way
you received a key, a key
that can be a
cryptographically strong random number. We create
in the path before, okay, we use
this number and then we send us a key,
okay, with this cryptokit
creates with the data a symmetric key.
And then with hMAC 256
dot authentication code, we obtain
the hash for a string
using the key, okay. And then because
a code authentication code returns an
array of using eight,
then we are returning in the constructor
of data, okay. Then this data
can convert to, for example, a base
64 string. For example,
how can you use this function,
okay, in this way? It's so simple.
Random key generator of 2048.
Then H Mac 256 ck
string and the key and then obtain
the base 64 encoded string.
Then this base 64 encoded string is
the value you must to store.
Okay, then how can you validate
a password? Okay, the validation of
a hash is to convert
the plain text password,
making the hash again with the sync key.
And then you compared the
encrypted hash with the new one.
And if it's the same, it's the same password.
Okay, why we
use hash? Because hash is an algorithm
that avoid to make
the transformation, the decryption of the data.
When you have the hash, it's impossible to
know the data we are
hashing. Okay, this is the security
way to ensure this
feature. Okay, when you want to validate an
authentication code for hash, the only thing you need
is to make HMAC SH 256
iOS validated authentication code. And then when
you put in authenticating the plain text
password that the user introduces with
this, you are comparing the HK
that is the hash with the value in plain text in
Cadena, okay. And then using the
key, the key for validate
the hash. Okay, it's so easy.
Next step, we are trying to make encryption,
okay. AES 2056
GCM encryption.
The AA. The AES GCM
is a galua code code.
It's a cipher mode that is one of the
most widely used for its performance and
efficiency and it's recommended by Apple. It requires
two keys, a cryptographic key
as well as an encryption authentication data.
You need two values to make this encryption.
If we do not have both values, we cannot decrypt the
content. Okay. The operation is an
authenticated encryption algorithm designed to provide both
data authenticity, the integrity of the data
and the confidentiality. Okay.
Makes these things altogether.
GCM can take full advantage of parallel processing
if we have many threads. The algorithm use these
many threads and implementing GCM can make efficient
use of an instruction pipeline, of a hardware
pipeline. For example, when you have many threads and have
an encryption engine like an M one
for example, okay,
how can I do it? It's so easy. With cryptokit
you have to create a sealed box.
Okay, with try you are using AES
GCM seal and in
this seal you have to provide the
data you want to encrypt, the key
you are using and the authenticating
data. Okay. With this
you obtain a sealed box and
when you access to combined property,
you can extract an
encrypted string.
You can storage on
base 64 for example. Okay,
how can I decrypt this?
Making the same. But in this time you are creating
a celebrate box. Okay. With AasgCM
you use the
initialization initialize
function sealed box with the combined data
you are storage before. With this combined data
you are creating a new sealed box and
then you can open providing it
the sealed box, the key and the authentication,
and then it returns the data decrypted.
This data you can convert with
string, for example, string data with
the data that returns this function.
And in UTF
eight, okay. And with this you can see
the new data decrypted. Okay. It's so easy,
it's not hard.
Next step, swiftui code security
best practices one
of the things we are so
important is to try
not to show any sensitive data when your app goes
to background. Because of this,
the app makes a screenshot of the last screen it
showed and then your
application the screens when you buy
from one application to another. In this screenshot you
can see maybe any sensitive data.
Well, this could result in an unintentional capture
of sensitive data and we have to do some process
to control it. What process?
For example, if you use SwiftuI, you have a new
modifier, privacy sensitive you
can put in any view. If you put
this modifier, when you put the app
in background, this data will be
blurred and the user
cannot see. It's so simple. But when
you use another framework or maybe if
you use SwiftuI or even UI kit
we can capture system notifications. Okay, you can capture
the system notification UI application will resign active notification
and did become active notification will resign iOS
when the app goes to background and did become active
is when the app is going foreground.
Well with this you can use this code you
make an observer to UI application will resign
active notification in the main queue
and then creates a black view controller and then
put it on your present
it in the root view controller. Okay?
With this you can create
a UIB control that puts in
front of your screen at the moment you
are entered to background. Your app will your
app screenshot will see blank. Okay,
how can you dismiss this blank
interface? Okay, capturing another
notification it become active notification.
In this you make UI application shared Windows first root
view controller dismiss and then the
black view controller dismiss it. And then you
can see the app when you enter infogram
again. Okay, that's so easy.
Another thing is to avoid backup copies of key files.
An iTunes backup, for example, can allow access to files in a very
simple way. Okay, since iOS eight
three, Apple does not allow access to the sandboxing.
But if you make or someone
makes an unencrypted backup in itunes of your
devices,
they code to extract data, compromise your
security or your privacy. We have to configure
the resource of the URL file itself.
In this way you prevent that
a file will be included in iTunes
backup. Okay. Or maybe iCloud.
It's important to remember that except jailbreak, the only
way to explore the file system on an iOS device is
through an iTunes and encrypted backup.
We should never trust any device that
is not ours when it show us
the alert to trust in this device.
How can I do it? Okay, it's so
easy. You have to modify the values of the URL type by
adding a URL resource value object like
this. If I want to write
a data one TxT, you have to
config URL resource value is
excluded from backup. True. And then set
resource value with this your
data one TXT are not included
in your iTunes backup or in your iCloud
backup. Final conclusions as
developers, okay, we are always
behind the system. We have the responsibility with
great power code, great responsibility.
As you know, if it is vulnerable,
so is our app. But doing our
job well is a guarantee for our users.
Okay? Everything we have said
should be a lawyer. That is part of your day
to day part of your development routine.
Make your APIs, make your helper
functions, make all the things you need to secure
your application. Make a swift package,
for example, and use it in all your apps
to ensure you make the
best secure coding in iOS or
other Apple systems.
Being responsible for security, data and good
development practice will make our developments
better and more efficient.
And don't
forget to update any third party libraries
you use. But maybe
it's better not to use it. Maybe a better option
if you can iOS try to go completely native
because many times and don't forget this,
we don't know who is behind a
third party library and we are relying
on their good faith and
good security practice blindly.
That's not a good option.
Remember, don't trust anyone,
okay? And that's
it. Thank you so much. I hope
you like this talk and I hope
you are now you
know kung fu in security
and then your code will
be more secure. Thanks to conf
42 for the opportunity to make this
talk and as I said,
always in my podcast and
live streams.
Best regards and good apple coding.