Hi everyone, my name is Tal. Thank you for joining serverless security,
top ten here at 42 Cloud native.
Let's start. So before we start,
who am I and why am I here? So my name is Tal, as I
said. Now I'm the head of security
research of cloud Native technologies at
contrast security. I got there through an acquisition of
Cloud Essence, a company I co founded that
created a serverless testing, security testing solution.
Prior to that, I was head of security research at Protigo,
another service protection solution who got acquired by Checkpoint at
2019. So I've been doing serverless for the last couple
of years and I'm here to talk about it.
So I know we've all talked about cloud native in
this conference, so I'm not going to add too much of it.
But you can see that Forrester predicted that 25 of
developers are using serverless regularly already.
So I'm assuming one of four
of you now, if you join the talk, probably more
are using serverless and this is why we are here.
Okay, so this is how a typical, actually not
so big serverless architecture look like.
This is one of the accounts that we monitor at contrast, and you
can see a lot of resources and cloud services
connected to each other in a very complex
way, we can say, but this is not so complex.
However, there are many security challenges
when dealing with such environment which you don't have a big flow,
a server or monolith with one big logic
flow, but instead you have a lot of resources and
services that are disconnected to
each other by nature and then configured
to create some kind of a logic with each other.
What is a serverless environment is can
event driven architecture. Actually, when you have in AWS,
for example, you have lambda functions which basically host
your code and run your code, execute your code
based on cloud or events in your cloud.
Events can be API gateway, so rest
APIs, HTTP request could be table changes,
Iot rules, logs at three buckets
of files or anything that you
can think about. And those functions really run your code to
interact with other services, typically in the
cloud. But because this is your code, this is also
where you have create your mistakes,
especially security mistakes that can cause
some cloud damage. And we'll talk about it.
So we said lambda
lambdas are really the compute, the service that runs your code.
Those are read only environments that
have a slash tamp folder if you want to run
or to write some files. They are
not wired to the Internet in the sense that you cannot ssh to them.
They of course have connection. You can create HTTP requests
or any type of request, inside or outside, but you cannot
connect to the runtime. The data is
temporary. Once the runtime or the code finished
to execute, it evades,
so the data doesn't remain
there. It's ephemeral. The code itself resides in the environment.
So when the code needs to run, basically AWS in
this case, spins up the environment with the code inside and
execute it. Also, the permissions for the function,
which are the keys translated to the keys in the
runtime, are located in the environment as
environment variables, so the function can interact with other services
based on its permissions. All right,
so we said we're going to talk about this security top ten, so whatnot.
If the main project OS serverless top ten
project that right now interprets the
original top ten security top ten, running an open call
for a few years, there is little data,
so we're waiting for more data to come up. To create a serverless
tailor top ten, you're more
than welcome to contribute to it,
right? So let's start with number one event injection.
Like any other injection attacks that you're familiar
with from web technologies, pretty much the same.
The difference here mostly is the entry point.
So it can come not just from an HTTP request,
but by many uncontrolled entry points. And we'll talk about that.
We mentioned a few of them, like s three so files, emails,
IoT, and we'll talk about it in a second. Traditional attacks
still exist like injection command injection, SQL injection or NoSQL
injection code injection, depending on the
runtime of the function. And there are new types of injection like
email injection, which we'll see later on MqtT
pub sub. So things that you weren't really familiar with,
and even voice command injection,
the impact depends on the function's permissions.
So if I have an injection attack, the impact that the attacker
can cause it depends on what the function
can do in the cloud. So few entry points,
so rest APIs, of course, maybe the most common ones. But we
can also have three party applications connected to our application to
our functions, cloud storage, authentication services,
logs and events, IoT, voice command via alexa,
search for it on Google, you'll find something,
email, SNS, code pipelines and many other things.
Anything basically is a lambda or the function can be connected to.
So what are the best practices here? Well, like traditional
application, never trust, pass or make any assumption
regarding input. The problem here is that we
don't have security controls in the perimeter
because actually with serverless we kind of lost the perimeter. We don't
have the network access to the entry point to the function. We don't
control it. Basically when we run function we just can the
code. So the code has to secure itself. So we
need to use positive like whitelist input
validations inside the code. API gateway can also allow
configuring some JSON models to limit the
type of request. But you have to make sure your code
can secure itself. You have to consider all event types
and entry points. If before voice command
injection owasp not something you should think of now
you should. And of course just to limit the impact,
you should run functions with list privilege managing
just the required permission for the function.
So of course there are some commercial tools
that helps you protect your functions in runtime or
detect security.
Best practices shift left basically
second part is broken authentication we've seen before the
image with all the resources connected to each other. So the
functions are really stateless, they don't really have a session to them.
So there are more tricky ways to
control the authentication. But basically think about
zero trust functions cannot really trust anything, they just execute
the code. You can store a session out of bound like a database,
but I wouldn't say that's a common way nor
that's a best practice. You could have multiple
entry points, services, events and triggers that come into
your code with no continuous flow to control the authentication.
For example, here you can see a lambda function which is
maybe secured by itself so you cannot reach it
directly. But there is can open sns here,
an open ses here that triggers the function.
And if we can get directly to the ses, we can actually run the
code we as an attacks.
So you have to make sure the function can secure itself
without even knowing who is
going to send the email. In this case best
practices. So if you're using AWS, use cognito
whenever possible you can use of course other authentication
services like Okta. Depending on the service on
this cloud that you're using, use access tokens that
can include custom data and can be
signed jot tokens. For example, if you need
external user perform input validation. Run with list
privilege is always a best practice and
just in case if you need out of bound security state.
But I'd say the best practice here is
to be able to run
with zero trust. So when the cloud runs, it already
knows in a way that the user
was authenticated. So you must make sure of that.
Number three, sensitive data exposure.
Well that's really same as any other cloud
based data. Our data is stored in the
cloud, so we need to protect it in a different way than on
our say. It doesn't mean it's less secure.
In many cases, I'd rather my data to be
stored on databases and be managed
by cloud providers like Google Azure or AWS
rather than a small company. In terms of
customer data, when we execute code, the data is stored under
temp. We also have other sensitive data like
the environment variables that can contain tokens,
access keys and other secrets.
Other types of sensitive data, which is very common is
data in buckets. We've seen many times exposed f
three buckets which breach that
expose data that was unsecured
or put into a cloud storage. But the configuration
of the cloud storage left it open for hackers
to access. Source code, as we mentioned,
is also in the environment. So if someone can run access or to
gain access to your lambda function, they can also have access to
the source code. The best practice.
So if you're using a lambda and you store data into slash
temp, delete it after the use so another execution won't have
access to it. Use kms the key again, if we're
using AWS, kms and equivalent to encrypt environment variables
to encrypt data, and you can use also secret storage
if you need to transfer data secrets between
lambdas and services.
If you're using other services, make sure you're securing
them. For example, buckets don't make them public.
That could be a huge risk for your company.
Again, if the lambda handles
sensitive data, make sure you run with less privilege. We'll hear it
again and again because it limits any type of
risk, and we'll talk about it independently later.
And you can use other services. Again, if we're running
AWS, you can use Macy, for example, to identify sensitive
data in your buckets.
All right, so we talked about list privileged a lot. So overprivileged
function is number four. In this case, I'd say
that more than 90% is an understatement.
I'd say more than 95% or 99%
are misconfigured. The difference between small mistakes and
big mistakes. That's the difference. Functions tend
to use many permissions that
are not required. The reason for that is that because it's hard to configure
a very tight security for each function for
many reasons. Maybe we don't know exactly what is their right
permission, or maybe lack of time, or could be other
stuff. In many cases, security teams inside organization
even give the developers predefined
roles, which has many functionalities
and many permissions that they don't need, but they tell them to use them.
So the developers are really limited
to use those. The impact of
other vulnerabilities and other security risks that we discussed again
depends on the permissions of the function. Because if the function only
has permission to execute the code, and I don't know,
write to the log, to the STD, out to the log system
service, then the impact here, even for a
code injection, is quite limited. On the
other hand, if the function has permissions in many cases like wildcards,
to services, to add three buckets, and we will see that in a demo later,
you can see how big of a mess it can do. Okay,
in many cases it's going to be limited,
maybe stealing some data from database or from your cloud
storage. But in extreme cases it can
really lead to a disaster into leading to your
complete cloud account takeover.
Here is an example. So the last
part on the left is an
s three permission that has really
a wild card both on the action and the resource. In the middle
we've added some security, which is adding
the specific bucket, but on the right side is the list privilege. We can
see the getobject and the bucket name. So this really
limits just what we need into the function.
And again, best practice, review each
resource is function and apply list privilege. There is almost
impossible to do manually unless you have a handful of functions.
So you have some way to automate that service,
that thing, and make sure each function that goes into your
production has its list
privilege, right? Number five,
vulnerable dependencies. Of course, this is very
common. Using dependencies can be insecure
if you're importing dependencies with security vulnerabilities,
because functions tend to be very small in types of the custom
code that you write, they tend to bring a lot of
dependencies, right? So a lot of imports.
In that case, it may lead to security breaches
in your code. Again, depends if you're actually using
the vulnerable part of the imported dependencies.
I probably don't need to explain that to you,
but when you import a specific library
like request, in this case it brings with it
the whole family and everything, all the dependencies of the
dependencies and the dependencies of the dependencies and so on.
So best practices, scan your dependencies before deploying
into production. Use open source or third party solutions
that can make sure if you can
use secure versions whenever possible. Replace library
or apply your custom patch if there is no
security patch outside.
Number six, insufficient logging and monitoring.
So why is it different here?
Well, because we're using serverless and cloud technologies.
There is a logging and monitoring service by
default in AWS, but you need to know how to use it. So it's
a little bit more complex because you need to know how to extract
data from it, how to access it, how to automate the process,
because of course you cannot manually go and check.
So basically if you have
a production environment with millions of invocation, it's really hard
to understand or learn anything from that.
All right, because of time
limitations, we're going to see a demo now and then we'll cover
really quickly the other security issues.
So as you can see here, we have
a user that sends an email.
The email then triggers a lambda function number four.
And the function does two things. Store the file
that was uploaded to an athlete bucket and then reply directly
to the user. So the user doesn't have direct access
to the function. Right, but the
email service does. In this case we'll see a
demo, how the hacker, in this case the user send the malicious
file into the lambda function, which has of course
a vulnerability. The vulnerability would then impact
or cause the lambda to run malicious code
and change the security configuration of the bucket,
as well as submit emails to
other destinations. Okay,
let's see.
So in this case this is a call for papers system
and the user is going to send an email to
the CFP system,
sending an innocent PDF of course,
just to check the system and see how it works. And as
you can see,
after a few seconds we get a reply. Thank you
for your submission, Defcon. Of course.
So in this case what I want to do is send a malicious
file just to see what happens. Now,
just a regular malicious file.
The PDF that we've now submitted has some malware in it
and we've got two emails. The second email which
says we've identified malicious
content in your file and there was a link to Verus total.
Okay, so now what we're going to do is well,
let's try to exploit the function that does the security
verification. Okay, so I pre wrote
a security code
that will be downloaded by the function
and will send emails to different
destinations that I want. In this case I'll
reply to myself, but I can send to whoever I
want. But the best part is I'm going to change
the security configuration of the cloud storage, the s three bucket that
holds all the submissions, all the CPF to
a public bucket, and then I'll be able to access all the
submissions of all the users.
Let's see how that plays.
Okay, I'm uploading the file
to my own bucket, just so I'll be able to access it through the web.
The lambda will be able to access it through the web. Then I'm going to
send this file with a malicious file name that
we're going to exploit. A command injection in the lambda tells
it to download my file from that bucket and
execute it,
uncompress and execute it. And just for fun,
I've added some requests. This is the s three bucket that holds
all the submissions. As you can see, I don't have access
when I'm trying to.
Okay, let's send the malicious file then.
Here on the right side you can see that I've
got some notifications. I just wrote some to myself,
some notifications, so I'll see that things are happening in the background. And as
you can see now, I got two emails back. One is the regular one,
but the second one is part of the exploit saying, hey you,
congratulations, you were accepted to
Defcon. And here is your honorarum
of $300. So click here to
gain access to that money. But this is of course a phishing link
which I can send to other participants. And this is
the first part. But the nice part, the second part is here where the
bucket was not accessible before,
is now fully accessible. And I can see all the submissions.
I can also download them to my own computer.
Okay, so we're done with the demo,
let's continue. So we've
covered six of the top ten. We have four more.
One is open resources. So we've talked about broken
authentication, but we can actually have just open
resources like queues, like SNS
services, like s, three buckets, like API gateways.
Those can be just misconfigured to be open and can lead
to, in this case, security issues.
The next part is denial of service versus denial of
wallet. So lambdas have limitation of 1000
concurrent lambdas at the same time for
all the lambdas in the account. If I'm limiting that,
I can have denial of service even if not because someone can actually
send more than 1000 requests in
parallel. But in any case, I'm going to have this debate
between denial of service and denial of wallet because execution
of lambda functions cost money per execution.
So if I'm not limiting the user, and the function
can be accessed from unauthenticated user or for a registered
user, then they can cost money.
If they leave multiple requests overnight or over one
week, I'm going to pay for it. So yeah,
the payment is by the millions, but if
it's a targeted attack, it can cost me a couple
of $100 insecure shared space.
So we've talked about the slash temp.
So between executions, if I'm running
in parallel, then they of course don't share the same
runtime. So they don't share the same data. But if I'm running a
request after a request for performance reasons,
performance reasons, the runtime is recycled by the
cloud provider, leaving the data inside. So if I
have access to slash temp from the outside,
if the developer didn't delete the previous execution,
I can access it and I can steal data of other
requests coming from maybe other users.
And the last one of course, is insecure
secret management. Again, this is some kind of a
complex because lambdas are independent,
stateless and ephemeral. And it's kind of hard
to gain access to store data. Developers tend
to store data hard coded. This is very unrecommended.
You can store data in your environment variables if
you encrypt them. If not, again, it's a risk.
There are other services that allow to set place like
a vault that you can extract sensitive data from like
secret managers or really vaults if you're
using terraform or something like this.
Hashicorp okay, so we've covered
the top ten. We have, at contrast,
our own method to do that. We're doing it
not by protecting the function, but by testing the
function for security vulnerabilities to remove the risk,
including list privilege. So we connect to an account, we scan
everything, we monitor everything and everything that we find on your
lambda functions and the connected resources like APIs,
API gateways, and f three. We can detect misconfiguration
and security vulnerabilities in your code.
In your custom code we can detect functions with over
permissions, and in that case we can secure your
serverless environment.
This is an example of a list privilege permission, so we
can detect that the function needs only one specific permission.
In this case was DynamoDB scan.
Okay, if you want to learn more about security in serverless
environment, you can use DVSH, an open source project
owned by OASP that lets you both secure and
play the offensive part. In a service
environment with just one click you can deploy it, but make sure
you don't do that in production because unless the account
is native to that environment, you can
have some problems.
Okay, thank you very much.
Tal, shoot me an email if you want to discuss more about serverless and
serverless security.