Hi, I'm Brian Contos. I'm the chief security officer with phosphorus
cybersecurity. And this presentation is cameras, caCs, and clocks.
XioT security sucks, a story of 2
million interrogated devices. So let's go ahead and just jump
right in. So, first off, what is XioT?
So fundamentally, IoT is a combination of
three disk but overlapping areas. The first
is what we might consider enterprise IoT, or Internet
of things. Those are things such as printers, voiceover,
IP phones, KVM switches, ups,
any kind of sort of enterprise dumb, if you will,
device that's operating on the network. In addition, two that those
are network devices such as network attached storage, wireless access points,
load balancers, switches, so on and so forth.
And then finally, it's the OT or industrial control
system side SCADA devices. These are things like plcs
or programmable logic controllers that typically operate in batch and
discrete manufacturing oil and has production power
and energy and many other sort of utility or critical infrastructure
type organizations. Collectively, we call those IoT
or attendee Internet of Things.
Now, these are purpose built devices, typically with specific hardware and software.
They're usually running operating systems we're all familiar with, like Linux,
Android, BSD. Sometimes on the OT side, it's a
real time operating system like Vxworks. They're network connected.
Not all OT devices are network connected, most are these days,
but certainly on the enterprise IoT and on the network device side,
hence the name network, they're network connected and
they can't run endpoint security, which is a big one, right? I mean, we talk
about our servers, our rotations, our laptops, a critical database,
whatever the case might be, even in a virtual machine, we're going to have some
of endpoint security, anti malware, intrusion prevention,
localized firewalls, so on and so forth. These devices, you cannot do
that. So at Fosfer cybersecurity, we've been
researching this space for over five years. We've looked at millions and
millions of devices across public companies, private companies,
healthcare, financial services, military, government, you name
it. And in doing so, we found some really interesting
sort of trends and statistics and use cases,
as well as a group of devices that we like to call the devices
that suck, not because they sucks in terms of how they operate, but their security
certainly is lacking. So hence the title
for this presentation. But we'll get into that in just a little bit.
So I want to share just a couple kind of interesting things here.
I recently went on showdown, and I think most of you are familiar with that.
It's like a Google search, if you will, for devices that are connected. Two,
the Internet. I just typed in words like camera, voiceover,
IP, phone, printer ups, things like that. It's not a very scientific
study, but I just wanted to see roughly how many of these devices weve exposed.
And there's probably some percentage of honeypots and some percentage of mistakes there.
But even if it's 5% or so, still we have about 5 million
cameras. We have over a quarter million voiceover IP
phones, printers, about 83,000. And I have no idea why,
but over 13,000 ups systems connected.
Now, IoT devices don't need to be Internet
accessible to be attacked and manipulated and used for a number of
nefarious things, but it's certainly one way in.
In fact, most attacks we're seeing today, interestingly enough, like a phishing
attack, they're going after someone's laptop, and then once they get in through
it, they're looking for XIoT devices to IoT to.
And then from there, they're attacking both XIot and it
assets, and even cloud assets from those XIoT devices because they
can maintain persistence and avoid detection. But we'll talk a little bit more about that
in a compiled of use cases in just a moment. But a funny thing
about this, maybe it's not too funny, but take upss, for example, so uninterrupted
power supplies, generally speaking, if you have something plugged into that, it's because it's really
important because you don't want the power to be interrupted. And one
of the most popular brands is APC. It's a very common ups that we see
out there. Now, if you go onto Google and you just type in default password
for APC ups, you'll find very
quickly it displaying, saying, hey, the password is APC
and the username is APC, and they're both lowercase.
I've never seen an APC UpS system where the password is changed.
In fact, we have a running joke at phosphorus. That is, if we ever actually
find an APC ups system where the password and username
aren't APC, APC and lowercase, we'll buy everybody in the company a steak
dinner. We've been eating a lot of chicken. So all
this to say that one of the easiest ways to get into a lot of
these devices are, number one, is it Internet accessible? And number two, does it run
the default creds? That's all the hacking is involved, if you can
call it hacking.
Now, nation states get this, cybercriminals get
this, too nefarious operators have taken notice of
XioT over the last few years. And a great example of
this is Russia. So Russia, the russian
FSB actually hired some contractors to build an XioT
tool that would actually go out and discover XioT devices,
compromise those devices, and allow them to be controlled for
multiple nefarious things, for spying, for distribution
of malware, for ransomware attacks,
to add to botnets, and again, to my point earlier,
to actually use to attack it assets. In a lot of these cases,
it's used to attack IoT assets to then exfiltrate sensitive
data. So these Russian FSB had this XIoT hacking
tool built. It's called frontin. Now, frontin is
a military grade, nation state built XioT
hacking tool. Unfortunately for Russia,
the digital revolution hacking group got wind of this. They actually stole
a copy of the tool and they released it online. So if you go to
some of your favorite torrents and places where you get such tools and you can
read Russian, you can have access to a nation state
grade, military designed XIoT hacking tool
available to the world. So again, nation states are taking interest in
these types of tools. Another example, nation states,
is China. So China actually kind of skips the middle ground.
So instead of having a device to go out and find
IoT devices or malware to compromise those devices,
they actually manufacture the devices with the malware pre built.
So it's already inside you. Just skip that middleman. And I'm
not calling out China or all chinese companies. There's just a few companies that
certainly have been identified here. In fact, in the United
States, weve actually passed a law that prohibits the use of many of
these devices in government organizations and with government contractors.
Those are things like Hickvision, Huawei ZTE,
and a few others. And some of the problems with a few of these,
and I'm not going to call it the specific brands, but some of them have
a little light on them that's green or red. So green means I'm recording
video and I'm recording audio. Red supposed to mean I'm
not recording video, I'm not recording audio. Pretty simple,
right? But what we found in some of our testing is when you actually say,
stop recording video and stop recording audio, it does turn the green
light to red, but it still continues to record audio and video.
Furthermore, it's piping that information out to
some location remotely, which theoretically is making
its way back to whoever designed this malware in the beginning,
this organizations in China. So these are
architectural capabilities
that have been built into these devices specifically to spy
on organizations. And a lot of the compromised that you see in
Iot or a large number of them, are about spying.
I can see you, I can hear you, I can use this to capture data.
You see other attacks that are more physically based, like, I'm going to shut your
power off, stop your elevator, modify your HVAC system,
open all the doors to your building. Those are kind of physical arena
attacks. And then there's the other attacks. The ransomware
compromised 10,000 devices so you can do cryptojacking. So mining
cryptocurrency. Actually, a Iot of organizations
sadly detect that these 10,000 security cameras
have been compromised and been uploaded with a crypto minor,
not because of some great cybersecurity tool or some xiot
security tool or some great incident responders. It's their power bill.
Their power bill is a lot higher because, as most of you know here,
if you're mining crypto, it takes a lot of power and energy.
So certainly attackers like that. But again, the biggest ones
are using these devices to attack it assets and
hide, maintain persistence and evading detection.
These allowing me to attack other tools. So this is just
one example. China is not the only country that has devices like this that are
doing nefarious things, but it was interesting that Russia
built a tool specifically to attack these tools, and China ships the tools
already with nefarious capabilities built in.
Now, going back, one of the cameras here that's been banned is
hickvision. So we already know hickvision kind of makes a malicious
camera. Well, in addition to that just announced,
and this was on August 23 of 2022,
over 80,000 hickvision cameras were found
to be exposed online. So just like we saw in that search
that we did for cameras a little bit earlier, using showdown 80,000
cameras that were hickvision specifically that
were vulnerable to a critical command injection flaw. CSO, not only do they
ship with kind of malicious design,
but they also have vulnerabilities on them, too, that can be exploited by
other attackers. In this case, it was discovered that over 2000 organizations
across about 100 countries had not applied the security firmware patch that
had been available all the way as far back as September 2021.
This doesn't surprise me at all, and I'm going to share some statistics with you
in a little while. But a lot of the firmware that we
come across is like six, seven years old, and a
lot of it has actually been end of life beyond six or
seven years. So the fact that this patch was around for over a year,
we think of that for maybe a mobile phone or laptop. Oh, why would you
wait a year for a lot of these devices, they're simply not being
managed. So I'd be remiss
if I didn't talk about the Marai botnet. If I'm talking about Xiot security,
this was kind of the Godfather, or the grandfather, if you will,
of Xiot attacks. IoT started back in 2016.
So that's why I call it these grandfather of these attacks.
So what was it essentially? So people were using Shodan
or other tools to find Internet connected cameras. At least
that's where it started. So once they found the cameras, they said,
furthermore, I want to see if they're running the Cleartext protocol Telnet.
Okay, so I found the cameras. Now they're Internet connected, they're running Telnet.
Furthermore, I want to see are they running default passwords or maybe one of
know, eight or so pretty common passwords that we
run across. And sure enough, they were able to find these cameras.
Well, just with those basic searching. And remember, we're not hacking anything. We're looking
for a camera that's connected to the Internet, that's running Telnet with a default or
a relatively common password. That's it. No hacking involved,
nothing was exploited.
Just creating a botnet predicated on that
set of cameras. They're able to, nefarious users
were able to use the Marai botnet to control these cameras, to conduct DDoS
attackers that were very impactful on big companies with big networks,
right, Reddit, Netflix, Sony, PayPal, Twitter,
GitHub and a few others, especially some big telecoms as well.
Internationally, these, it took them down just a few little
cameras, right? But the cameras collectively had massac
process and network capability. But this is what's even more interesting about Mariah
Botnet, because there's a lot of
white labeling and shared libraries in the Xiot world.
That means the build that went into things camera might
be very similar to what was used in this printer or this voiceover IP phone
or this audio video equipment. So they're being explored running
Telnet with the same default passwords, maybe the same vulnerabilities
and things like that. So even though I'm sharing your library, that's allowing me to
do ABC, that library also has vulnerabilities,
XYZ. And I'm sharing that and sharing that and sharing that.
So what we found is even though they started with cameras, this expanded was past
cameras and started including printers and phones and other devices as
well. What's also interesting about this is it was way back in
2016. We still see devices today when
we're out at customer sites and we're all over the world. So this isn't just
specific two, one country or another that are still vulnerable to these.
Marai botnet back from 2016, they're still vulnerable.
And we're even finding devices that have Mariah Botnet
still on them because they've never been fixed. Hey, as long as
the printer is printing or the camera is recording, we don't really
know how to manage it or who's managing it or what to do, so just
let it do its thing. They're not being monitored, they're not
being managed. So again, maintaining persistence, evading detection
is a big deal. This is back in 2016, and things really haven't gotten any
better. So this is a little bit more werent.
So this is can attack. That was announced by Mandian called
quiet exit, and this was May 2 of 2022,
so pretty recent. And this is all about achieving that persistence
from this apt. So what these attackers did is
we feel they got in through phishing attacks, again through a laptop,
social media, whatever the email or whatever
it was, they got in through some type of attack that got into someone's laptop.
We all know there's a gazillion ways to do that. So once they're on the
laptop, they started looking to pivot to XioT
devices. Why? Because no one's looking at them. Also,
they generally have default passwords. If they don't have a default password, they're probably
running in an old firmware with lots of vulnerabilities that could be easily exploited.
A lot of these guys, we see levels, eight, nine, and ten level cves
on a score of one to 1010 being the worst. So in this
particular case, once they got into the environment, they started looking for these
IoT devices, and they found some, and they were looking for some network devices,
wireless access points, load balancers, NAS switches.
A lot of these systems run BSD, and they're also looking for traditional IoT
devices. Voiceover, IP, phone, security cameras, printers. Most of those run
Linux, some of those run Android, but very popular
operating systems. So they recompiled, reconfigured their solution.
And their solution, the attacker solution, was dropbear. Ssh. Nothing too crazy
about dropbear, but they installed it on these particular devices, which allowed them to
have a reverse SSH tunnel, CSO client, server, communicate and
control these devices remotely. So typical command and control,
c two tunnel back and forth over SSh. But they were communicating with
these XIoT devices, which made it a little bit more novel, right?
Once they got onto these devices, they used those devices
not to hack really, but to make API calls to the local
exchange server and the Microsoft 365
in the cloud. So both on Prem and in cloud, API calls
were made to extract sensitive information. And what was the sensitive
information? Email between corporate executives,
corporate development folks think m a think BD people,
and even security staff. So they Iot in through it,
pivoted to XIoT, used that to attack both cloud and
on Prem. It exfiltrate the data. And the worst part of this,
in most cases, these guys maintain persistence and
evaded detection for over a year and a half. Again,
because no one's looking at these devices, no one's paying attention. The bad
guys know it, the nation states know it, the cybercriminals know it. So they're really
taking advantage of these. And I can almost guarantee, as we
all know, there's probably plenty of organizations out there that have been compromised
with this, where data is still being exfiltrated as we
watch this video. So another one I wanted to share with
you was a russian xiot botnet. And this was a takedown.
So this was a success case. The US, the UK, Germany,
Netherlands, and actually a couple other companies or countries working together
took down a botnet. And as we all know, botnets are kind of like
DNS, right? Or a Christmas tree. It's very scalable. So you take out a piece
here, a piece here, maybe it pops up someplace else, but if you get to
the top of it, you take that down, maybe you've taken it down now
for a few weeks or a few months, you're not going to take it down
forever. People can rebuild someplace else, but it does cost time,
money and resources for the bad guys. So it is a success case.
But the reason I wanted to call this specific one out, it's called Rsox,
was pretty interesting. Primarily it targeted in the IoT realm,
the OT devices, those PLC skated devices that we talked about.
There was some network gear, and there was some IoT gear, just to
be fair, truth in advertising. But the majority of it were industrial
control systems, programmable logic controllers, these types of things that are digital
equipment that operates physics, flow, pressure,
voltage mixtures, robotics, arms, things of this nature.
And again, these are usually real time operating systems, Vxworks and things
of that nature. And there's some other more esoteric ones that are out
there. And what they were doing was, it was so successful, they were saying,
hey, we're going to rent this out. We're going to rent this out to people
for about $30 a day. I actually think if you pay, I think,
$100 a day, they give you access to the broader network, and they
also provided technical support, which was, they operate these things
like a real business. Right. Obviously, they're money makers. But I thought, again, what was
interesting about this, the reason why I wanted to share it, was primarily based
on those OT devices. So they're not safe from this either.
And again, it wasn't attacking the OT device to break
manufacturing of a vehicle or screw up batch manufacturing
of some chemical or some pharmaceutical or blow something up on an oil pipeline.
It was simply adding this device to a network of botnets to use it
to attack other organizations. Now, could they have been used for what
I would consider much more nefarious things like blowing up a pipeline or screwing up
a medical batch that's being produced? Absolutely.
They had control of these devices, but in the cases we saw,
they were Iot being used for that. Another example on
the ot side, and again, ot makes up one of the these pillars.
Of course, for XioT, this was an attack on Siemens.
And how we think of attackers on the it cyber side today
is a little bit different than these because they're really, really based. So basically,
if you sent packets to this specific device, and this was called the s
seven plus crash, that was the name of the attack.
You send packets over TCP port 102 to a remote
device. It's unauthenticated. Not most, but a
lot of these devices operate with no authentication. CSo, you use any kind of
tool you want, Netcat, whatever it might be, to send packets port
102 to that device, it causes a DOS attack. Now, some of these
devices have what are called set points. Like my temperature can go up to 75
degrees and down to 65 degrees, and it has to stay between those two.
If it drops too low or goes too high, it means it passes that
set point, an alarm goes off, tells my ScadA system, hey,
something's happened. Take a look. Well, if you increase the temperature of something
and you're dosing it IoT doesn't have any time to respond, it can't send out
the packets because it's basically sucks. So maybe now the temperature is at 100
degrees instead of 75, but it can't do anything about it because it's
stuck. It can't communicate that an issue has happened. The reason I want to bring
this attack up, yes. It's extremely simple. Right. And it can
have a big impact as well on the organization. But Siemens came out
and said, hey, here are some suggestions to fix this. I like to show
this because in the XioT world, XioT security today
is kind of like iT security was like back in 1995,
we didn't really know where all our devices are. We had kind of poor discovery,
we had poor patch management and software update.
Management just wasn't as broad as we would have liked
or as well adopted when it came to credentials and password, rotation,
complexity, things like that. It was all pretty early stage,
but this is what Siemens came out and said, look, for this attack. This is
what you should do. Number one, update your firmware. You should be running more recent
firmware. Number two, enable access controlled. Consider using
a username and password. Number three, set a password.
So don't just enable it, but actually set one. And I would say set
a good one and make sure it's rotated. And all the things we
all know also disable unneeded protocols.
A lot of these devices speak, a lot of extra protocols they don't need.
Certainly on some of these devices, they probably speak TCP, IP, maybe serial
over Ethernet, some more proprietary stuff like Modbus or DNP.
Three, they've got wired, they've got wireless Bluetooth,
Bluetooth, low energy. So some of them are actually very much what I would call
hyper connected. But I just thought it was very interesting.
Hey, patch your firmware, set a username and password,
and get rid of services that you don't need. Again, it security
kind of 1995 CSO. In our research,
again, we've been doing this for a little over five years. What we found on
average is there's about three, two, five XioT
devices per employee in the organization. So a 10,000
person organization probably has somewhere between 30 to 50,000
XioT devices. Now, when we go into an organization, at the beginning of a proof
of value, a POV, and we say, hey, take a guess, what do you think
you have? Almost consistently, they're off by 40% to
60%. These say, hey, Brian, we think we have 20,000. In the back of
my head, I'm thinking, okay, so they got about 40,000 devices,
and that's about what it turns out to be. Now, there's a bit of a
curve on this. So, for example, a law firm,
they're going to have a little bit fewer. A retailer or somebody
that's working with industrial control systems, they're probably going to have a lot
more. So there are some differences, but on average, what we
see healthcare, financial services on and on
about three, two, five, devices per employee, and it's always a lot more
than people think they have. So what percentage of
Xiot devices operate with default passwords? So think
about that. What do you think it might be? It's actually about half.
About half the devices operate with default passwords.
As I just said. Go Google. Default passwords, APC,
UPs, it's no super secret. And it's like that for
a ton of these devices. So you don't need to hack anything, you just
need to log in. So whether it's Internet accessible or you're already
within the internal network, it's default password. Now.
Forget rotation frequency every 30, 60, 90 days, forget complexity,
even when the passwords are changed, and sometimes they're changed at the point of
deployment. For some newer devices, it's usually changed to something pretty weak and
usually not very long. When we say uppercase, lowercase numbers,
special characters, at least 20 characters, passwords, not password.
All these things that we talk about in good practices, they're not happening here,
right? And there's a bit of a curve to this one has, well, we say
50% on average, but upS systems, as I mentioned before,
that's closer to like 100%. When we talk about audio, video equipment,
we find that's actually in the high are some devices,
again, where the password is changed. Two implementation. We don't see that
as much actually on the enterprise side as the consumer side. We focus mostly on
the enterprise side. But in those cases, when they're changed, sometimes they're just
changed to what the product is, security camera or the name of the company.
They're pretty basic things. It's certainly things that could be added to a brute
force attack pretty easily. But default passwords half the
time. So think about this one. What percentage of xiot
devices operate with end of life firmware? Again, these are
devices where the firmware has been dead.
It's like running windows nt three, five one, or Windows Nt 4.0,
which actually, I bring those up because we do see those on the critical infrastructure
side, because they depreciate the servers that operate the turbine at these
same rate. They depreciate the turbine, which is over decades, Iot over
like five years. So the answer to this is 26,
werent. 26% of the firmware is actually
end of life. And the remaining 74%,
the average age is about six years. Could you imagine your smartphone?
I'm sure all of you watching this have some kind of smart device. If you
didn't upgrade the underlying operating system for six years,
or even the apps that are running on top of it.
Honestly, it probably wouldn't even work. You probably couldn't even connect to the environment you
wanted to connect to. Everything would just be broken. But these devices on
average is six years old, which means it comes with a lot of vulnerabilities.
So think about this. What percentage of IoT operates with Endeli firmware?
We said that was 26%. Look what comes along with this.
We're seeing that about 50% of the devices
have CVSS scores. Again, one to 1010 being the greatest.
CVS scores of 850 percent of these have level
eight. That means they're very hackable. Can additional 18%
have nine and ten? That means very hackable with almost zero
skill remotely done. And to give me full administrative
access to that device, that's 68%. That's almost
70% of all the devices have level eight, nine and ten.
That's crazy. If I just told you your it assets had that, you jump off
this video right now and go fix them. And again, I've got in a
company of 10,000 people, I've got 32 50,000 of these things,
half of them with default passwords, old end of life firmware,
and 78% or 68% of them have level eight, nine and
ten CVSS scores. What? That's insane.
It's not even fair, right? This is really making things easy
for the bad guys. So let's talk about
the biggest offenders. Now, I dont have them all listed here. I'm not calling out
a specific brand or model number or anything like that, that wouldn't be fair at
all. But I did want to share some of the devices that we find time
and time again that are just, they're super vulnerable and
they're being exploited at a very, very high rate.
So the first one, KVM switches, suck. Now I love KVM
switches, stands for keyboard, video and mouse, as most of you know. And the idea
is I've got one of these switches with one keyboard, one monitor and one mouse
connected to 510, 50 different devices,
whatever the number might be, and you find them a lot of racks and data
centers and things like that, and they allow us to be extensible.
The problem is, and these run Linux like most of these devices do.
Linux is by far the most popular operating system we see out there for these
XioT devices. These run Ubuntu. They run Ubuntu version ten quite often.
We're on version 21 now, right?
So it's a little
dated. It's about a decade old and they're shipping and they're shipping
with tons of vulnerabilities because it's a decade old version
of Ubuntu, right? And you can go find out all the vulnerabilities that are
on bunto version ten that come by default on these devices.
Now the problem is this is a device that manages devices.
So if you can get access to the KVM switch, you can cause a lot
of problems on the devices. Managing network changes, power down the device,
make other configuration adjustments, et cetera. Next one,
lights out management. Controlled suck things is kind of like KVM
on steroids, but for a point device. Now that little arrow
there is pointing to what looks like an Ethernet port, but it's actually a lights
out management port. What this allows you to do is access that device. By the
way, that's a Linux. It's running Linux, right? It's nothing crazy.
You might have heard terms like iDrac, ipmi,
Ilo. It depends if it's HP, Dell or supermicro. Those are the
big ones that you see in this. But it allows me to get access to
the device. What's interesting about this is I can actually open up a shell.
I can spawn a virtual terminal. I can actually even upload software or
malware. These are very simple
areas to attack. These get plugged in, nobody updates them. A lot
of times there's no password, they're vulnerable. It's just giving me full access to actually
do malicious things. And people don't think about it. When I say, how many
devices do you think you have? Nobody's thinking about KVM switches or
lights out management. And this is why.
Server cabinets and racks. Here's another thing. A lot of these are smart
cabinets and racks. They've got tamper detection and temperature controls
and cable management power, a whole bunch of other capabilities.
Again, these devices have all the same problems
with the other devices we talked about. Old firmware, default passwords,
extraneous protocols. These problems with this particular group of devices is,
generally speaking, if you want to update the firmware on a rack,
you have to do a power cycle, which means everything that's connected, two, the power
supply there has two, then be cycled. So when people are scheduling downtime to
update servers and databases, web servers, critical assets like that,
not really taking into consideration the racks
that kind of manage these devices and that they operate in, so they never get
updated, which means they're highly vulnerable. You get access to a rack now,
and you can do nefarious things to all the devices within that rack.
Physical access controllers suck. This is a big one.
We actually did a pov with a very large financial services company where
weve able to, with no hacking, we were able to access and say we
can open and close 6400 doors
at our discretion, including things like the front door.
Right, and the back door doors that are probably pretty important for them.
But 6400, forget all the cybersecurity you have in
place. If I can just access this system and make some changes.
There's a very popular version of physical access controlled called nortech security
control. I don't want to pick on them, but it's pretty well known that they
were shipping with CVSS scores of 9.8 out of ten and ten out of
ten on their devices. So has you unpackaged it? You took
out of the box? You took it out of the wrapping paper. Oh, it looks
so great. You're all excited. You plug it in, it's got level
ten vulnerabilities on there, just right out of the box.
So craziness. And this is allowing people to do really
malicious things, because we talked before about shutting down power,
stealing intellectual property, doing cryptojacking.
Well, this is actually physically unlocking, or maybe during
our emergency, locking doors that shouldn't be locked. So there's a lot of crazy things
that could happen there with physical access controls.
Another one are printers. Everyone's got them. They're super promiscuous.
So printers really suck. And why do they suck so bad? When I
say promiscuous, what I mean is they want to be connected. Two, so they're
running wired and wireless and Bluetooth and other communication protocols.
And you can connect to me via HTTP or HTTPs or SSH, or Telnet or
FTP or whatever it is. They've got all these ways because these want to make
it easy. And that makes sense because at the end of the day, I want
to use my printer to print. The issue that we found of these
guys is a lot of them are running like, they're mostly running
Linux operating systems, but they've got like 60 to 80 gig hard drives,
not huge, not small at today's measure, but it's a pretty big hard drive.
When they're being compromised, they're being compromised because of all the problems we talked
about before, default passwords, vulnerabilities, old firmware,
but they're a great place to hide. And because of that big fat hard drive
on there, they're extracting sensitive data. We actually saw one customer
where they were pivoting from hundreds and hundreds of printers that have been compromised,
attacking it assets, downloading the data compressing
it, exfiltrating IoT over ICMP because no one's watching that. Some of
these cases longer than a year, right? We work with hotel chains that have
20, 30, 40,000 printers,
so it's not uncommon to just have an astronomical number
of printers out there. And if they're all or possibly a
great majority of them can be compromised and used to attack you.
That's a huge attack surface, right? That no one's looking at, no one's
managing, no one's monitoring. Black has, back in 2019, they announced
the discovery of critical level vulnerabilities on over 10,000 different types of
printer brands. Again, it's not surprising at all,
but it's actually one of the most targeted. Not the most, but one of the
most targeted XioT assets out there.
Voiceover IP phones, video conferencing systems, I kind of put those in the same group.
Those are usually Android OSS. But what's interesting about
these guys is we saw some commonality between some video conferencing
systems and some voiceover IP phones because of that whole white
labeling and shared libraries we talked about before. So one
of these phones, it's a very major vendor. If I said the brand, you'd go,
oh my God, they shipped with their phone running SSH
undocumented. It was never written that they even had it with
default username and password. The problem with that was
they didn't even have a security development lifecycle mature enough to say, hey, let's figure
out what ports are running on this thing before we ship it out. And oh,
lo and behold, it's running Ssh. What kind of password set on that thing?
So that's pretty grievous. And I don't want to call these out and say they're
doing a bad job, but when it comes to security, it's not their primary goal.
They want to get to market, they want blinky lights, they want it to do
cool things for the end user. And I get that. But if it's in
an enterprise and opens up these vulnerabilities in the back end, of course,
that's a huge risk, right? That's something that we need to concern ourselves with.
I bring up the video conferencing cameras as well. Again, because of the white labeling,
these shared libraries, that exact same build was existing on these
video conferencing systems, which again, we talked about spying before
with the cameras. These devices can be used for that as well. We've actually seen
instances in production customers where those devices, in fact,
were being used for that purpose. So again, these devices aren't
really being built with security development lifecycle in
mind. So I've covered a lot
of devices here, but I haven't covered the number one. So think
about what do you think is the number one biggest offender?
It's security cameras. Security cameras suck.
The know, security cameras are great doing their
security camera thing, but we talked about some of the ones out of China that
have actually been based. Certainly they're bad.
They often run operating systems like busybox and other forms of Linux out
there. Sometimes, again, they ship with the malware. There's exploits
to take advantage of them, like we saw with the Hikvision camera and all those
Internet accessible devices where you could run remote commands
on these devices. But the biggest problem with security cameras is
actually this. You have to understand that. Are they
a dumb device? Yeah, they're a dumb device, but they have the same storage
and processing capability and memory and input output capabilities as
a laptop. Some of them actually even more. Some of these are really quite
heavy duty. Consider them like workstation level security
cameras. They're very powerful, so don't think of them like as a weak device.
They're actually a very powerful device. These just happen to be an insecure,
very powerful device running an operating system that allows you to do all the
same things you could do on a laptop. So just think of it. That was
these other thing with security cameras is most people don't have in the enterprise a
handful. They have thousands. In some cases.
We've seen tens and tens of thousands. We're working with a major
casino that actually has over 50,000. 50,000 security
cameras. Right? So the worst part of
it is this, when we're talking to these organizations, two say, hey, here's the
problem, we can come in here and help you. Who manages
these? Oh, it's corporate security thinking. They're like, oh,
no, it's network operations. Not us, it's the
Iot sec. No, no, it's a third party vendor. So it's kind of
like the end of Spider man. Everyone's point, who is it? Is this guy?
Is this that guy? So nobody wants to take responsibility.
And I get it because historically there was no way to really fix these devices
at scale safely. These, you're going to have somebody,
a football team of people with a paperclip to go do a physical reset to
update these firmware. That would be nuts, right? You'd never do it. So if
you can, what happens? It's just not done. And that's what the bad guys are
counting on, that you're just not going to do anything.
Now, weve mostly been talking about Enterprise Xiot
a little bit on the industrial side with OT, but I want to call it
just a few other areas before I go deeper. There's also Internet
of battlefield things. These are tied to all the military devices out there. There are
certainly things that are specific to the industrial side. We kind of got
these tip of the iceberg there, but there's a lot of very specific purpose built
devices for batch and discrete manufacturing.
Oil and gas, power and energy, water, traffic,
sanitation, agriculture, you name it. That's a really big realm
of the OT devices, right? Healthcare also has a
lot of specific things. Another big one is things like smart buildings,
smart cities, smart ships. Difference between smart ships and
smart buildings is one floats. They're all the same devices,
to be quite frank. But if you look at this all collectively,
it kind of gives you. Okay, wow. Beyond the enterprise, things actually has a
global impact, right, on cities and counties and states and
countries and regions. Everything is ultra connected.
And if you think about these first official, the first unofficial
IoT device was back in the 1980s. It was a coke machine. That was
an arpanet. Okay. But then we fast forward to the.
We had a TCP IP toaster that was connected. That was the first official
IoT device. Well, Dublin,
Ireland, is the first official
smart city. So within 25
years, plus or minus, we went from a toaster to an entire city.
So everything I've talked about here and everything I'm showing on this slide,
this is only going to expand exponentially.
Everything everywhere always is going to be connected with these devices,
and hopefully we can get them beyond 1995 security.
So I've talked a little bit about, or a lot of it, about sort
of the bad side of this, right. The use cases, the things that suck the
most. But let's talk about getting rid of that suck.
Let's talk about making it so it's not easy for the nation state
hackers, the cybercriminals, malicious insiders, so on and so forth.
So what can we do? Well, the first thing is discovering, as we talked about
before, three to five XIoT devices per employee is a lot.
And the fact that if you don't know where even half of those devices are,
that's a big problem. Now, old school discovery solutions,
and I say old school because they're really based on it and it centric adaptations.
You look at like a vulnerability scanner for discovery. They're going to
send malform packets and kind of see what the device is going to come back
as. That could be a tenable, a qualis rapid seven, great for
it, not really fantastic for IoT. They can actually crash
systems. You don't want to scan in an OT environment, for example,
sending malformed packets to a PLC device from the 1990s,
you got about a 99% chance you're going to crash that thing. In a world
where availability is everything, right? So the traditional
scanners don't really kind of work.
Then you say, okay, well, what about packet sniffing? Well, sniffing is okay.
You Iot, a lot of span ports, a lot of taps, there's a big network
out there, but also a lot of the communication is encrypted, so you're not really
able to glean a lot of metadata. You might be able to say, I think
it's a printer, maybe even it's a HP printer,
but I can't really get deep into it from sniffing to really
give granular detail. So that's kind of lacking. And then there's
traditional asset management solutions, again geared for it environments.
A lot of them look at Mac addresses. So the OUI, the organizationally
unique identifier. Oh, you're a jet direct. You must be a printer. Well, could be.
Could also be a phone. Right? So those are great
again for it. Not so great in this world. They have a lot of lacking.
So there's a new kind of based of solution. I'm going to share some of
the vendors at the end of the presentation, but it's called enterprise Xiot
security platforms. And the way these usually work is they actually communicate
with these devices. They interrogate these. Think of like c
three po from Star wars. He could speak like a million languages and
even water evaporators and things like that. Very cool.
So being able to not can the device, not sniff the device,
but communicate with that device in the way it was designed to be communicated with,
being able to scale that for obtain million types of devices,
that's really key because now that you can communicate with it,
you can extract much more data, firmware model number,
serial number, ports and protocols that are operating
credentials. All the little isms within that product can be pulled out
through that interrogation. So that gives you a very robust sort of starting
point. Now I know what I've got, and it's not based on
some packet scanner that was developed or
based on technology in the 1990s with malformed packets
or sniffing. It's actually communicating, interrogated these
devices. Right. So that's step one. The other part of
this is upgrading firmware and hardening.
So now we found the devices, now I want to remediate it.
I actually want to fix it. So back in the day, a lot of people
said, well, there was really no way to fix it, so we're going to hide
it behind a Vlan. Nothing against
VLans. I think Vlans do add an added level of security. But, man,
if you're a 10,000 person company again, 32, 50,000 xiot devices,
you're going to vlan all that stuff off. And Vlans aren't the
end all, be all of security. Plus, what are you evaluating? Off. You're vlanning
off devices that have bad passwords, old firmware full of vulnerabilities,
kind of covering your ears and your eyes and just hoping nothing's going to happen.
I mean, think of it this way. Like I'm typing and, oh, I cut my
hand, my left hand's bleeding and I really need to go to the doctor and
get this looked at, but instead I'm going to put a sandwich bag on it
and wrap it up with duct tape. Okay, well, now I'm not getting blood in
my right hand or my keyboard, so that's good,
I guess, but I still got a bloody hand in a bag, which is
really not the best thing to do in a VlaN situation.
Your seal is saying, I got all these vulnerable, broken, defaulted password devices,
but they're behind a vLan, so it's okay. Not a great approach.
It's great to use in addition to fixing your devices, but who wants to do
that? You would never do that with your it assets. Why would you do it
with Xiot? Now with enterprise XioT security platforms,
part of what they do is say, okay, I know what my device is,
I can communicate with it, I can also upgrade the firmware.
And because of these interrogated process, there's a lot of minutiae
that can be extracted. Like, hey, I'm on version seven. The latest version
is version ten. Can I go right from seven to ten or do I have
to go seven 8910 or let's say
I'm on version five and there's a log for j vulnerability. On version
five we tell the vendor, the vendor goes, look, we're not going to have a
fix for this version six for like another seven months. I can't wait that
long. Everybody and their brother is hacking everything with log for j right now.
But version four didn't have that. So maybe I want to downgrade
my devices until that new version is actually available.
So when you do that interrogation, as part of the discovery phase, you actually have
that type of knowledge, which is really, really cool now.
So now I can actually upgrade the firmware and downgrade the firmware
if I need to as well, and do pre flight checks. Two, make sure that,
hey, I'm not basing this on a Mac address. I actually know
this is an MRI machine, or I know this is a printer, because the last
thing I want to do is I don't want to turn my MRI machine that's
$2 million into a printer. That's $500 with the wrong
firmware. People tend Iot to like that, right? So you have to have very
high levels of accuracy. In fact, you have to be 100% accurate. There's no room
for 99%, certainly 5100 percent accuracy
during discovery, so you can do the upgrading of the firmware. And while
you're doing that, we talked about the Siemens stuff earlier with the OT hack
by sending TCP packets to port 102.
Siemens said, hey, turn off some of the protocols you don't need.
Well, in hardening, you might say, you know what, I only want to run
wired. I don't want to run wireless on all my printers, for example. And no
more bluetooth, low energy, and no more clear text protocols. In fact,
I just want to run SSH and HTTPs, period. Port 22 and four,
four, three. That's it. Anything else for this particular set of devices,
I want to change it. I want to do that for just devices in North
America or just HP printers, or just HP printers.
Model ABC. One, two, three. CSO. You can be very fine grained
in how you push it out, and you can push those out manually, one at
a time, or say, I'm going to batch those up into a large group.
Right? So again, that's another value add that you get from these enterprise XIoT
security platforms. And again, this is a relatively new thing. These haven't
been around. It's not like a firewall or IPS or a scanner. It's been around
forever. So I found my device, I've fixed
the firmware, I've hardened the device.
Now I get into credentials and certs. So Pam
solutions, things like Cyberark, Thicotic, Hashicorp,
some of these others that you see are great. They're fantastic tools
and been used forever, and they add a lot of value. They store your passwords,
they have rotation policies, frequency, complexity, all that.
But they don't speak to Xiot. They can't, and they don't want to have to
build that. So these enterprise XioT security platforms that are again,
like C three Po. They can talk to all these devices and say, hey,
there's 50,000 devices on this network. I'm going to automatically enroll them in Cyberark,
for example. And in doing so, I'm actually going to also tell Cyberark,
just like I knew the firmware upgrade paths. I'm going to tell you for my
credentials. Hey, this guy can only take a four digit pin. This guy can take
ten characters, but he can't use a backslash escape sequence.
Stuff for like, SQL injection, whatever. Or this guy can go up
to 20 characters, but IoT can't use the number nine. We see
all sorts of crazy things. I don't know who designed some of these, but there
are some crazy isms that are related to that. Well, all that intelligence is put
in when you create that policy, automatically enroll that device. So I've just enrolled 30,000
devices. This group falls into this category. This group that, this group
that. Then you can apply your whole 30, 60, 90 day rotation,
complexity, length, all those variables that you would in the IT environment.
But now you're doing it with your Pam solution, which talks to an
enterprise XioT security platform, which then talks to all these
devices. Very clean, very simple, very scalable,
and takes advantage of some of your existing controls. The same thing
applies to the certs. You might find out that, especially on the
network side, about a wireless access point. That's like TLS version
1.1 or 1.2, go, oh, it's too old, or it's a
self signed cert, or it's an explored cert. We see this all the time,
not just on network devices, but other XioT devices,
too. But wireless access points are a big offender in
things world. So by talking to those devices that
manage the certs, just like Pam, for managing the credentials, you can go
ahead and make those changes and make those updates. So I found my device,
I'm managing the firmware. I'm harding, the device, I'm managing credentials,
I'm managing the certs. Now you're getting your xiot devices to
the level of your IT security, which is pretty incredible, because your
solution before was do nothing, cover your eyes, cover your
ears, and hope that nothing happens. Maybe Vlan, a couple of
your devices, if you can get at it, but probably not.
So we found our devices, we fixed our devices,
and you'd be remiss if you said, okay, that's it. What you want to do
is you want to have those devices automatically reinterrogated, probably on
a daily basis. That's kind of the gold standard, right?
And by reinterrogation, what I mean is let's reconfirm that years
you were on version seven and you're still on version seven of the firmware,
and that's the latest version. You did have a great password through Cyberark,
and that password is still being managed. But what if someone walks up with a
paperclip and does a hard reset? I was on seven, but now I'm on version
five. I did have a great password, but now I'm back to the default password,
ABC, one, two, three. Well, now you can say
across my 50,000 devices, these are the five devices I have to take a look
at right now because they've drifted, either because somebody did a paperclip
attack, paperclip hack where they've reset the device with
the little black button on the back of these XIoT devices,
or maybe there was some kind of fault in the system that made it revert
back to default. We all know there's reasons why these things can happen, some nefarious,
some benign, but in any case, you know that something's
changed. And these are the devices that now you can look at and you can
manage them by exception. And this is important because it means now
the enterprise IoT security platform provides scale because
you can manage by exception. You can have a team manage tens of thousands
or hundreds of thousands of more of devices, because now you're going to be notified
when one of those devices has a material change in
addition to being able to productivity push, credential changes,
new hardening gold standards, if you will, firmware updates,
patches, so on and so forth. So I really like the value
they add in terms of monitoring for that environmental drift. To me,
that's how automation equals scalability right there, plain and
simple. The last thing is reporting these enterprise X
Iot security platforms can actually report on what you've got. How great would
it be to know that, yes, I've got 50,000 devices, and by the way,
I've got 300 that have end of life firmware. I've Iot 3000
that have default passwords still. I've got 4000 that I've enrolled through
my Pam, I've got these vulnerabilities, I've got 1200
that have level ten cves. These are the types of things
I know, and now I can trends things over time. We were this bad last
month, now we're only this bad, and hopefully next month we're going to be
that bad, right? And it's this continuous process of reporting on
this and having APIs that tie into your existing reporting structures,
being able to talk to splunk, being able to talk to ServiceNow Demisto
other tools like that is really important. And these enterprise X Iot security
platforms provide that. So last slide here.
I just want to touch on a few things. In general, organizations don't know what
they have, so discovery is so important,
so they don't know what to fix. So if you don't know what you have,
forget remediation. But remediation is so key. What's the point of finding
your devices if you're not going to fix them? Okay, I didn't know what I
have, and now I do know what I have, and everything's broken. What do I
do? Okay, what's the next step? But if you don't know what you have,
you don't know what to fix, then you're not able to fix these,
even if you did know what you had to fix. Are you going to be
able to fix 20,000 cameras or 40,000 printers manually
without some type of automated solution? And then once they stay fixed,
you want to be able to monitor those devices, and people aren't able to monitor
them because they don't have tools to inspect them. You can't monitor by sniffing traffic
or doing a scan. You have to be able to interact with that device at
scale across, again, hundreds of thousands of devices.
And this isn't just putting your XioT devices at risk, your printers, your cameras,
your ot devices, your network gear, but the IT and the
cloud based assets as well. Like we talked about in quiet exit. Right? It's putting
that infrastructure and all the sensitive data that lives in that infrastructure
at risk. And this results in everything from data theft and ransomware,
so on and so forth, spying, physical attacks,
et cetera. Right. So the results of attacks on xit
are very wide and can be extremely painful for organizations.
IoT doesn't have to be that way. This new generation of solutions,
these XioT security platforms, again,
phosphorus, we offer one as well. But there's other vendors out there that do
things. We all do things a little bit differently. Some of these companies, Armist,
Nizomi, they're really focused on just discovery. Other companies like phosphorus,
we look at discovery and we integrate with them as partners as well. And we
also primarily focus on remediation. And some of these others do something in
between. But there are solutions now. So I implore you,
take a look at your IoT environment. Try to determine what
it is you've got and what the problems might be. And if you think
you might be in a situation where hey, what Brian just
covered in this presentation makes some sense, I think I'd like to kick the tires,
reach out to phosphorus or some of these companies and say hey, I'd like to
do a proof of value. I'd like to find out what I've got and what
problems I've got in my environment and what I can do to fix it.
Because I'm telling you right now, the XioT problem is growing exponentially.
It's a much larger footprint than traditional endpoint
devices or cloud combined by
several orders of magnitude. And again,
they're all traditional servers, Linux, Android based. They're just
unmanaged and insecure and access points to attack
your rest of your environment. And the bad guys are hoping you're not paying attention
because things is a window of opportunity for these. They know it's there,
but do you know it's there? And are you going to take steps to remediate
IoT? So with that, thanks everybody for listening to my presentation.
Again, I'm Brian Contos, I'm the chief security officer with phosphorus.
If you'd like to reach out to me, here's my email and you can
hit me up on LinkedIn and Twitter. I'd love to chat more about about
XioT security platforms and certainly what phosphorus and some of
these other players can provide. You have a great rest of the event.