Hi everyone. My name is Arunddeep and I'm a solutions architect
manager at AWS. I lead the developer experience
team for AWS amplify. In today's
session, we will talk about how to turn on easy mode
for full stack app development with the most popular design tool,
Figma and AWS amplify. So let's
dive right in. I'm going to
dive into the design to app workflow now.
Our expectation is that we have an idea or a project that
we start off with and we are going to work with the designer,
and the designer is going to work with frontend developers to get their
changes implemented, and then they work with back
end devs to get the cloud logic in there and the infrastructure up there.
And we expect customers are happy and everybody's having
a great experience, right? But unfortunately,
that does not happen. In reality, it does not go smooth.
There's likely additional changes that is coming in from the designer to
the front end developer and the frontend developers and designers
go back and forth with changes to the UI, and some changes
are not possible and it creates additional communication overhead.
Then there's more changes that is required to the back end that the front
end engineers are dependent on. This starts to slowly
lead to disjoint processes and it spirals out of control
and eventually it leads to a lot of chaos. And unfortunately,
this is the reality that we live in. And we have
deeply analyzed why there is a little bit of friction here,
especially on the front end developer side. They spend months pixel
pushing. For those not familiar, pixel pushing is like
literally making tiny minute UI changes just
so that it looks pixel perfect in the end. And we have
deeply analyzed on the other side that designers
are not happy and about 50% of the designers are
not satisfied with the implementation.
So designers are not happy and developers are frustrated.
So there must be a way where designers can provide Figma designs
and a magic solution converts it into functional
react code. And this solution is amplify
studio. So let's take a look at Amplify studio.
Amplify Studio helps you to convert designs
built in Figma to reusable react components,
saving you from writing thousands of lines of code, and it
eliminates the design development gap. Now, it comes
with a pre built UI component library where you can select from
a dozen of popular react components such as feeds, contact forms,
e commerce cards, primitives, such AWS, buttons,
text fields, you name it. You can then easily bind
that to data so you can visually connect your UI components to your backend
data model using a point to click interface.
And finally, you can improve team collaboration. You can
bridge the gap between designers, front end developers and
product teams with centralized workflows that mitigate costly
rework. You can easily build your app
front end with AWS, amplify and the Figma to code plugin.
Now these are coming in from the Amplify UI
components which are built with plain react and CSS
to provide a solid foundation for building uis and design systems.
Now these components are themable, responsive,
composable and accessible. They play very nicely
with other UI components or styling frameworks.
These components have accessibility built in
with the popular standards of WChe.
Now amplify consists of connected components that accelerates
the development of common workflows like authentication,
which can have like sign up, sign in and location
saving developers hours of development time.
Amplify UI also includes UI components like newsfeeds,
contact forms and e commerce cards. And you could also use
the primitives such as buttons, text fields,
cards, layouts, etc. Now before
we jump into a cool demo on the ability
of how you can actually build an app which is fully
responsive using Amplify studio, let's take
a quick look into the overview of amplify and what
it offers. If you take a look at Amplify,
it is a suite and tools that are built for front
end developers to build rich and performant web and mobile
applications. It has five main categories.
The Amplify libraries are use case centric libraries to
provide the ability to build cloud powered mobile and web applications.
Amplify Studio, which we just spoke about, is a visual interface.
Think about it as any visual development environment for setting
up your app backend, and you can easily connect figma
designs into your app backend. Now amplify CLI
essentially does the same thing, but it's a CLI tool chain rather than a visual
development environment. And then you've got the Amplify UI
library, which is an open source design system that is
composed of like connected components, primitives and
other pre built components that are actually themable.
And last but not the least, we've got amplify hosting,
which is a fully managed CI CD hosting provider
for easily being able to ship your app into production.
Now, features that you can build with AWS Amplify. You can interact with
multiple data sources amongst AWS databases. With the data modeling
that amplify provides, you can have low latency content delivery.
With amplify hosting you can have multi factor Auth sign up,
sign in and forgot password workflows easily built within
minutes rather than hours of development time. You can also build
real time interactive experiences using websockets that is based off
of the backend data modeling. You can have stored user
content such AWS photos and videos, which we will take a look at it in
the cat application. You can also have aipowered chatbots
in your web or mobile applications, and text translation that is easily provided
through amplify use case centric libraries.
Now, what are the benefits of AWS amplify? With all of these features, you can
get to market faster. You can build feature rich applications, and the
best part about it is you can scale. It's global, it's reliable,
and it's secure. Now, in order
to showcase the endless possibilities, we'll go ahead and build an
end to end cat reviews application. Imagine if you had
to work on a cool app that could take images of
cat and review it, and you could customize it to a greater
extent. But we'll see how you can get started with AWS amplify.
Now here's what we'll build. So let's quickly build an app to review
cats. Imagine you had a farm where you can review pet cat images.
You can extend this app to also take real time can
photos, and upload it with reviews for fun things such AWS like
parability, friendliness, et cetera. For the purposes of this demo,
we'll input the URL of cat images. You can see that the feed
has been populated with the images of the cat and with the description I've
just taken a space cat, for example, you can
wrap the app with amplify UI authenticator to easily add
authentication capabilities as well. What I'm doing is
just building a feed of wants and adding
in ratings for all of them.
The left portion of the screen actually
showcases the form build component of amplify studio,
and on the right hand, we have added some UI code to go
ahead and build the feed that goes ahead and renders the component
that's been generated for you through figma design.
Let's go ahead and add the third cat in there, and then you should be
able to see that we also have a confidence cat that is
finally looking really cute.
All right, so the first main step is to get started
with building a new app in amplify studio. So you go into the AWS
console, go to AWS amplify and give the name for your app.
And in the backend it is going to start setting up the resources
for AWS Amplify Studio, which will just be done
in a couple of minutes. But in the meantime, you can also go
ahead and install a create next apps,
which is the starter template to create a next application.
You can go ahead and input the parameters
to build out your next app. In this particular case, I'm not going to use
typescript and I'm still going to use the sources
and pages directory for building my app so
that it's easier for us. And then the
backend environment is now being initialized with Amplify
Studio, and once that's complete,
you should be able to launch Amplify studio.
Now in the interim, what we'll
do is we will enter into the directory of the new app that we just
built, and we
will go ahead and set that up. So the second
step is to install the amplify packages and build your
data model. So I'm installing a bunch of dependencies for
AWS amplify. The most common one is the Amplify
UI react dependency.
And once Amplify
Studio has been launched, you can actually go into the data
section to build your data model. Now in this particular cat review
application, my data model consists of a reviews model and it needs
to have the name of the can, a description for the cat,
and a rating for the cat, which is set to float
because you could have a cat with a rating of 4.7 and optionally
the image of the cat AWS, well, you would typically include an image of
cat. And once you've defined your data model,
you just go ahead and click save and deploy. Now it's going to deploy this
data model into the backend. Now this abstracts the
complexity of the underlying GraphQL API that
is powered by AWS app sync and amplify
studio makes it real easy for front end developers to define this.
Now let's go back to studio and let's go ahead and
use the UI library to
go ahead and sync in with Figma. So you can actually use the
pre built Figma template. And that opens up the Figma
to code plugin and choose your Figma account.
And once you enter into the Figma account, you can actually see that it
contains themes, primitives and components.
So I'm actually going into the component section here
straight away and there's a pre built component called
review card that I can go ahead and reuse.
Now this is the one that amplify has built for you, but I'm
going to make some changes. I'm going to remove the
description to just be a single description of the
product.
I'm also going to go ahead and remove the pricing because
you don't necessarily attach a price to a cat. I'm also
going to ensure that you can have a
button to favorite the can based on the reviews.
And because it's not properly aligned, I'm just
going to make sure that the name of the cat and the icon
to favorite the cat is in a single row.
And while I'm doing this,
I'm also going to ensure that the whole
card component is actually a little bit nicer
and it looks curvy on the end. So I'm just going to
add a value there. I'm going to clip content to ensure that
we have rounded corners. Going to leave the
rating component as it is just cleaning up the
divider there. And I'm going to copy
the Figma file URL and paste it into amplify
studio. And then I'm going to say sync with Figma.
Now what this does is it's going to fetch all the components and
the primitives from Figma.
Now you can click on accept all to accept all of the themes,
primitives and components. And then let's take
a look at the review card and you can actually see it looks exactly like
how we made the changes in Figma. And in the
meantime, our data model that has already been
deployed has created certain forms. But we'll
talk about it in just a second. For the image,
we'll set it to reviews image.
And for the title,
we're going to set that to reviews name.
And for the description, we will map it to the reviews description.
And finally, for the rating, we're going to set the
value of the rating to be
reviews rating. Now this showcases
the power as to how easy it is to make all
of these changes and bind your UI components to data through
the visual development environment.
Okay. All right,
so next we're going to create the form and
associate the form with data. So this is
the form builder component. So here we have
the name description that has automatically been generated by you based
on the data model that we defined. But the description has been modified
to a text area. The rating, I just changed that to a stepper
field so that it's easier for users to come in and use the
stepper field to input the data. The image is
again optionally containing a placeholder. I'm just adding
a descriptive placeholder text that says enter
the image of your cat here, and that
should be it. Now these changes are automatically saved in
studio as and when you are making them.
All right, now once you go into the data section, you have
the code to pull the code locally. So once
you do amplify pull with the optional application id
as well as the environment name of staging,
it is going to pull all of the code that is there in
studio to your local development environment so that we can continue
to function locally. Now once that's done, it will ask
you to log into amplify CLI and you can log
into amplify CLI and then you can pass into the workflow
about choosing the basics of a JavaScript application with the source directory
build directory, and then you will let it complete
after the app is pulled down locally.
You should be able to open that in an editor of your choice.
In this particular example I'm choosing vs
code and you can say that you plan
on modifying the backend AWS. Well, although for the purposes of this demo we are
not going to be modifying the backend. And you can see now
it's generating the UI components. So all of the UI components that we had
defined earlier, it is going to convert them into functional,
reusable react code and components that can be extended,
right? And then now we're going to set up the application
code and we're going to create a collection in order to render the components.
You can go and say yarn dev or any
package manager of your choice run the local server and you should
see the default create next apps. This is a next 14 app because now that
next JS has released next 14, that's the default that comes through.
And right after that I'm going into app js file
and I'm defining the amplify imports
along with the configuration that is required. I'm also adding the
interfont that is required by this particular application. You can optionally
choose not to if you're okay with the default fonts that are being
used. And then now I go ahead and build
my actual application. I'm going to import the reviews create
form from amplify UI components and I'm going to export the default
function. I'm just going to name that as home. And then I'm
going to call the reviews create form component.
Let's wait for that to be complete.
And once that's done, I'm just going to rerun
the server and you can now see the same form that we designed on
amplify studio is running on your local environment.
Now let's go back into the reviews card component and we
can create a collection. Now collection is a group of components
and studio automatically gives you this ability. Now you can actually
see that there's dummy data in there already. Now, these are not production data
just yet, but you can also have a look and feel as
to how your data is going to look like. Now, any changes that you're going
to make on studio, you need to pull them locally. So I run an amplify
pull just to ensure that all the
components are pulled in locally. And now I'm going
to go ahead and finalize my app code with
the theme provider and I'm going to have a
couple of imports in here. I'm going to be importing the reviews
card collection. I'm also going to be importing
the API category from AWS amplify. I'm also going to
go ahead and import subscriptions because you would
want to go ahead and look at the changes that
happen in real time. And the data modeling capability
of AWS amplify creates the model in the
backend, which is powered by GraphQL APIs that
come through from AWS appsync. And this
provides the ability to go ahead and utilize
the subscriptions feature where you can listen to real
time events through websockets. And once
you subscribe to the event of any changes in this particular model
that I have, I'm actually going ahead and subscribing to on
create reviews. So you can actually see that
I'll be subscribing to the on create reviews
here. And as soon as a new item is created,
I'm going to be displaying that item through collections
here. And in order to
make the styles, the look and feel better,
I'm actually importing certain predefined components from
the UI react library and primitives.
So there are like view text and flexbox that
is provided by amplify UI library. And I'm going to
build my application code here and
that's it. Before you can know, you have already build
the app that we looked at, which is the cat reviews application.
So in a typical workflow for an app
that would have taken multiple hours
or days or months of effort is now reduced to potentially
less than an hour or minutes with AWS amplify studio.
So with that, thank you so much for listening in and hope you all
enjoy the rest of your conference and have a wonderful day.
Thanks,