Hi, my name is Ishuah Kariuki and welcome to
my talk in this session. Today we're Golang to cover terminal
emulator basics in Golang. A bit
about myself I am the principal backend
engineer at hover. The mission at hover is to create
an inclusive Internet. This entails
creating technology and services that enable developers
in emerging markets to actually build for the community
around them. I am also a triathlete in
active training. Makes most of my mornings miserable,
but also goal oriented.
And finally, I am an untenable troublemaker.
First thing we're going to deal with is the Linux Tty subsystem.
The Linux tty has a very rich history and
I'm glad for this opportunity to talk about it.
TTY stands for teletype, and the
definition of the word teletype is a printing device
resembling a typewriter that is used to send and receive
telephonic signals. This is the image you get to see when you
google the word teletype. It was mostly used in
the early to mid 20th century and was developed
as an improvement on telegraphs. So how
did this typewriter looking device end up being an essential
part of the Linux operating system? So earlier computers could
only run one program at a time. But in
the 1960s computers were powerful enough to interact with users
in real time. So pragmatic engineers
at the time thought about the situation and instead
of creating new input output machines,
they reused teletypes as input
output machines for computers to enhance the
real time interaction of users with computers. The main
reasons were teletypes already in the market.
People knew how to use them and technically
they fit the bill. You could input by a keyboard and
output by a printing paper. The image you
see on the right is an output
from the game. The Oregon trail. The very first version
I'm pretty sure you've heard of, or you
played the game at least, the Oregon trail.
But the first version of the Oregon Trail
was created in 1971 and it ran on
a mainframe computer and user interaction was via teletype.
This is actual output from the game on a teletype.
So as technology improved, video terminals
replaced hard copy terminals as paper terminals.
And the teletype that you see here, the terminals that
you see here is the VT 100. It's one of the most popular ones
and it's also one of the first terminals to support unseen escape
codes. Focuser control now we get
to see how physical terminals is connected
to computer. From the image.
From diagram you can see that the terminal has a
direct connection to the computer via a
UART module UART stands for
universal asynchronous receiver and
transmitter, and the main purpose is to receive and transmit
serial data. Now, from the diagram above,
you can see now the TTY device consists of
the UART driver, line discipline, and the
TTY driver. Let's dig a bit into this component.
The UART driver manages the transmission of
bytes between the teletype via UART
and line discipline. What it does is transfer
keystrokes from UART to the line discipline.
It also sends back anything that's sent from the line
discipline back to the teletype. So that's
it. That's basically command execution, sends characters
in and characters out. The second part is a
line discipline, and the line discipline maintains
a character buffer. This is anything that's typed
on the teletype is buffered on the line discipline until
the user prints enter and the characters
are sent forward to the TTY driver.
Line discipline also handles special editing events.
Backspace, enter, clear line,
and then final thing, it echoes back,
keystrokes back to the URT driver so that
the user can see what they're typing. Then the final component
is the TTY driver, which sends characters to the foreground process.
Any program that's waiting on the foreground will receive user
inputs. Most of the time you'll find that that program is
either shell or a subprocess of the shell.
This model, the TTY device,
the whole of the TGI device resides in the kernel.
So again, technology improved and
processing power really improved on computers. Also, computers shrank
in size, so there was really no longer a need to have physical terminals
connected to the computer. Instead of having
physical terminals replaced with software terminals,
software emulated terminals. That's where the term terminal emulators
comes from. A point of note is that terminal
emulator basics not be confused with a shell,
and we're coming to that in a bit. Terminal emulators
just work in the same way as their physical counterparts,
with the biggest difference being that there's no uart
connection, there's no physical Linux between terminal emulator
and the line discipline. So again, in this model
as well, the terminal emulators exists in the kernel.
One of the biggest constraints with having the terminal emulators
in the kernel is that it was a rigid design.
Programmers could not build on top terminal emulators basics
since it resides in the kernel.
An idea came about where the terminal emulator should
be moved from the kernel and maintain
the rest of the TtY subsystem still in the kernel.
So line discipline, session management still remains
in the kernel and then move terminal emulator basics user
land and that's where we have pseudo
terminals. That's how we have pseudo terminals.
It's an improvement on the existing design.
So terminal emulation moves into understand and the Tty
subsystem remains in the kernel. This diagram explains how
the pseudo terminal works. Pseudo terminal consists of
two files, the Pty master and the Pty
slave. The Pty master is attached to the terminal emulators
and the Pty slave is attached to the foreground program
or the program that you want to control.
A note about shells. A shell is a program that resides in
user land and manages user computer interactions.
A good example is z shell. Fish bash,
you're all familiar with this. So yeah,
this is the basic history of terminal emulator
basics. Why we have pseudo terminals. The next
part we're going to dig deep into how
to create a terminal with Golan.
Cool. So this is a very simple
program that draws a UI with
awards. Hello, conf Golan 2021.
When you run this program, this is what you get,
just a simple print. This is a user interface,
a very simple user interface that is by the end of
this code lab will be somewhat interactive.
Terminal a basic terminal that's interactive. So the
first thing we're going to do is connect
to the pseudo terminal.
The pseudo terminal we're going to use a package
called Pty. It's an amazing package.
It's very intuitive to use and
we're just going to dig in. There's really no introduction
to a codelab. You get into it
and start with my imports.
So this is what I'm going to use.
Going to create a command execution and
I'm going to use the time package.
And then let's import the Pty
package creek Pty
GitHub.
It's very intuitive. The documentation is amazing.
If you want to work with pseudo terminals you can check it out
if you haven't used it before.
Cool. So first things first, let's create a command
execution with the bash.
The shell create a command execution
of the shell so that we can actually connect
the pseudo terminal slave to the shell and get a reference
to the pseudo terminal master.
Let's start with this.
If I sound a bit out of breath just
from my evening run,
so do not hold it against me.
Bear with me. That's what best time to use.
Ben Bash.
This is a path to the actual
executable bash. And this
line creates a command execution command
struct that
specifies we want to execute the bash,
we want to execute bash. Cool.
And then the next thing we're going to do is
now we're going to assign a Pty slave
to this command execution.
Like so.
This function will assign
the Pty slave to the command execution of the bash.
In simple terms, we're going to attach the bash to the
pty slip and this function returns
reference to the Pty master. That's what
we're going to call P. P is now the Pty master.
And if you can remember, pseudo terminal does contain
two files, the Pty slave and the Pty master.
Pty slave is connected to a
process you want to control, which is now bash. And then Ptymaster
is attached to the Terminal emulator and that's what we're going
to use every single time we want to run a command execution.
Let's just check if this fails.
If that fails, what do we do? We red quit,
we say log the error could
not open Pty and
then we're going to exit infrastructure.
And finally we want to make
sure that when we quit,
when we finish, when we terminate our terminal
emulator, we also terminate,
we as well terminate the bash execution struct
that we created earlier. Cool.
That's that. So we have this, we have P,
which is now P
is tty
master. So we have P.
What do we do with Ptymaster? You send commands
to it. So let's just write a simple
command,
a very simple command,
right,
sorry,
bytes.
So this sends a command lf and
the return courage, return courage is a presenter.
This tells the
line execution that, okay, we are ready to send this command
to the foreground process and
let's do this,
let's wait for a second and
then read from the
Pty master. So we do that,
make,
create a slice of bytes, we read from the
Pty master into this slice of bytes and check
if there's an error.
New,
we do have an mention
that we can't read and yeah,
last thing we want to do is this
is what sets the text that you see on the Ui.
Let's remove this and say
what do we want to print? We want to print a string
of the slice of bytes, convert the slice of bytes
to a string and then print it to the Ui.
That's it.
So what happens when we execute
this program? This is what we
get. You can see the command
ls and the return carries,
which has unfortunately been also printed.
And then that's the only file in that directory.
Boom, that's it. So we
have a connection to the pseudo terminals we can send
commands to pseudo terminals. At this point we haven't
attached the keyboard yet, so that should be our next step
to make it interactive in real time.
So next step,
connecting, reading from the keyboard, the better way
of putting it.
When reading from the keyboard,
we need two callbacks.
One that reads, that listens
on events on special keys,
specifically the enter button. When the
enter button is pressed, we know we're ready to execute the command.
Send the command to the foreground process and see what happens.
The second callback function is going to read runes.
This is any other character, any other key that's pressed on the keyboard
that's not a special key, any other key that's not either, enter shift,
backspace, deletes, arrow keys, all that.
So that's going to also, we're going to listen
for all those key events. Anything that's pressed, we are
going to write it directly to the pseudo terminal master.
Boom. Let's start. Start with special
key. Press callback.
It's going to be called untyped rune.
Sorry, untyped key.
Fine key. The event.
This also relies on the fine.
That's what I'm using to draw the user interface.
Sorry if I did not mention this before. Fine ui toolkit.
It's amazing. If you haven't used it before, you can check it out,
tinker with it. If you're building any front end user interface and you
haven't bumped into this yet, please tty it out.
Sorry,
it's meant to be that. Okay,
here,
what do we do? We write,
we write to the pseudo terminal master and
we say we are ready to executed.
Cool. That's the return carriage tells
the line discipline that we are ready to send this to the
foreground process, toi driver and to the
foreground process. Second, callback function is
character callback.
Going to call this untyped rune and
it's going to do this.
Take that rune and just send it directly to the
pseudo terminals muscle.
We're converting it to a string and send it to the pseudo terminals master
as a string. So we
need to bind these two callback functions
so that anytime a key is pressed,
this callback functions are called so on.
Type key on type key.
Okay,
now we've set callback functions. Anytime you type on the keyboard,
it's going to type anything.
Press enter. That command or
whatever string you've typed is going to be sent to
the pseudo terminals master, to the line discipline and
tty driver into the program process.
Now we also need to see what we've printed.
So let's write a very simple go routine that's
going to refresh the Ui. So Ui.
So this is function and
then sorry,
we're going to sleep for 1
second it,
sleep for 1 second it.
And then make a slice of bytes.
Let's make a slice of two wondered and 56 bytes,
then read from the Ptymaster error
equal and
then we
log that error you
it's
log it's.
And then just update
the Ui.
Convert the slice of bytes to a
string and update the UI. And of
course make sure this is called and
then write it Linux
64 I
have something. Sorry, this is
meant to be.
Anyway, we're not doing this anymore, but ideally
this should be.
And remove this to use this.
We're Golang to use this.
Think we're good now,
are we? Yes, should be good.
So cool.
So when you execute, when you run this program,
you're going to get this.
And this should
be slightly more interactive than what
we had before.
Yes, you can see the output, but it's mangled.
It doesn't make sense because
you are basically waiting. The go routine is sleeping
for a second. Let's go back to this,
probably sleeping for 1 second,
reading everything and then setting the updating the UI
so it's chaotic,
but it sort of works. Now let's try running a program
that will stick to the foreground, let's say ping h.
Yeah, UI is updating, but it's
not making sense. There's no command history.
We can't see a buffer of commands, of outputs.
We're only seeing the last line that was written to
the PTy, to the sudo Terminal master.
And yeah, it's just chaotic. So let's
try and make a more legible user
interface. Let's print better to the screen.
That's the next step.
So in order to get this working
correctly, we're going to do two
things. We're going to have two go routines.
We're going to update this go routine that refreshes
the UI, and we are also going to create a new go
routine that reads from the properly
reads and puts everything in a buffer.
First of all, you're going to have a buffer and the buffer
size. Let's say we're going to have a buffer size of ten
and that
buffer is going to be updated every single time. So when
we get to a buffer size of
ten, if it's at the max size, the first item
at the top, the item at the top is going to be popped and then
we're going to append the new line at the bottom.
So this buffer is going to be updated.
So it's going to look much better, much nicer,
and we're going to have,
it's going to be more orderly semblance of orderliness,
if that makes sense. Awesome.
So let's start with this first
go routine. Let's ignore that and
have this read Rome
Ptymaster function.
Sorry then.
Now.
Cool. What do we do?
Before we create that, let's declare two
variables. The buffer,
which is going to be a
slice of a slice of room,
of slices of runes. Let me just
explain this. So it's
a slice of a slice of runes. Each slice of runes represents
a line in
the terminal output. So every time there's a new
line character, we're going to move to a new line and then happens
all the new rooms that we read to that new line.
Then let's have a better reader.
Let's have a more orderly reader.
We're going to use buffyo
new reader.
And this is, we are reading from the Pty master.
Let me also take the time to update my
imports and
just make sure I have all this
looks good. Cool.
Let's go back to it. So once again,
this is the buffer. This is what we're going to
use to maintain a history of lines of
output on our user interface, on our terminal.
This is going to hold the history of command outputs
and the reader is a much better
reader. We're going to read runes now from the Pty
master. Okay.
So first thing let's happens a
line to our
buffer.
Buffer is initialized. It's empty.
This just adds one line,
an pty line as well. It's just empty.
So this
is a loop that does a lot of the
heavy lifting. All of the heavy lifting actually read
rune. This just
reads a rune from the
Pty. Reads a rune.
If,
because you have an error and if
that error is
ten file,
then we stop,
we just return.
Otherwise we exit.
Now, if it's an end of file error,
we return and then regardless,
whichever error we receive, we're going to exit.
Cool. Then the next
step is to append the
line, the rune that we just read to
the current active line and then
updates the buffer with this
new line updates the buffer
index. We know this is the active buffer index because it's
the length of the buffer.
It's the last available element
in the buffer. So, for instance,
if this is a brand new buffer and this is the first line,
we're going to update that first line to this
line that we've just appended the room thread and
then. Okay, I'm using spacefam.
Spacefam is amazing. It might make you lazy, but it's awesome.
We just checking if the
rune that we just read. Check if the rune that
you just read is a new line character. If it is,
then we move to a new line on the buffer.
So first we check if
the length of the buffer is
greater than, let's say our maximum size is
ten. If it's greater than ten, then we pop
the last item in the buffer.
The first line that we appended to the buffer is popped.
That is if you've got into the maximum size of the buffer. Then you
pop that first item. And then to that we
append a new line that
we just created a new line. And then we append
that new line to the buffer.
Cool. That's it
then. The next part is
now updating this go
routine that renders to the screen. Let's reduce this
time to 100 milliseconds
and then let's
clear everything, blow everything up,
and then we're not going to use this line.
Sorry, I am breaking so many
vim rules right now. If you're a vim user, bear with
me. Just bear with me.
So instead of reading from.
Instead of reading from pseudo terminal
master, we created a go routine to do
that above. So what we are going to do now is read from the
buffer, our existing buffer.
So let's say string
explaining this in 1 second.
Sorry, line range,
we're workings through all the elements in the buffer.
All the lines in the buffer, the slice of
runes in the buffer, all the slices of workings in the buffer and
then lines is
going to be. We are just creating one long string
from all the elements in the buffer and
then setting this.
Sorry. And then set
that as we
look to the buffer, append all the lines into one long string
and then write that to the user interface. And that's it.
Those are two go routines that we need.
First is create a buffer.
Read drones from the pseudo terminal master while
we happens it to the append all these drones
to the buffer, to a line and then all these lines to the buffer.
And then second go routine reads everything from this buffer
and then prints everything to the screen.
It makes the
interface a lot nicer than what we had before the chaos that
we had before. So when you run this, this is what
you get. And let's say
type a command. There we
have it. The user interface
is a bit glitty because the refresh rate might
be a little slower than the way we are reading from the pseudo terminal
mass, the way we are reading from the buffer,
and it's a bit
glitchy. So let's say. Let's type something else.
A new command. New command.
Let's say cow. Say moon.
There we have it. Let's do what you did
before. Run a program that will stay
in the foreground.
Boom, boom, boom. And that's
it. The user interface is refreshing. We can
type commands from the keyboard. They're being executed as we
expect. Foreground programs are remaining in the foreground.
And this is a basic terminal. This is a
very rudimental terminal. Of course,
elements that are missing. We're not interpreting
ansi escape codes. We're not interpreting
a lot of special key presses like tab backspace,
delete the arrow keys.
We're not interpreting signal interrupts. Control C, control Q, control Z.
There's a lot more to build on top of this,
but this is the basics. This is how you can
start off with a terminal emulator in go.
Yes, and that
has been my time. Thank you so much
for having me. It was a joy having this talk.
My handle is at issuer.
Understand on Twitter. Reach out if you can. If you have any
questions or any comments about this talk, best way
to reach out to me is via Twitter. Thank you so much.