Today I would like to discuss with you current status and problems
which I see in the industrial equipment simulation software
area. First of all, I will
briefly describe the problem as I see it. To highlight
the details, I will tell you how engineers deal
with the equipment simulations, what they call process,
how different related to difficulty technological processes
can be. We will take a look what
currently happens with typical simulation software
and its main restrictions. Also, I will describe a
real example of gas compressed simulation software,
which was implemented by me and show
out of boundary way how it integrated
into existing modeling structure.
Last but not least, I will tell you why all
of this is important and what possibilities I see
in area of equipment simulation.
So let's start with problem itself. There are
a lot of industrial companies in various sectors of industry.
Some sectors are more advanced, some of them
are conservative and dogmatic, but all of them
want to be effective and successful. To do
so, they want to plan better.
Better company plan better. It spends its resources,
saves where it can save and spends only
where it is necessary to spend. Any company want
to understand its technology. Often industrial
companies are big and complex with a
lot of different people involved in operation,
such as engineers and managers.
Bigger companies have very complex and often
interconnected technologies in operation, and clear
understanding of the underlying technology is a
key to companies successful operation.
During last years, there was a clear trend in industrial
companies to be more digital.
Even companies from conservative areas such as oil
and gas, for example, cannot ignore benefits which
modern software can give to them.
And often when such companies faces their challenges,
sometimes which nobody encountered before,
they find that they don't have proper instrument
which can help them to solve their problems.
And software tools, which they have,
doesn't have enough features or such features
cannot be directly used in their cases.
In other words, industrial companies missing software
tools. But let's go a little bit deeper to understand
a problem. To get better understanding,
first I have to explain based terms which
used in engineering across industries.
And I would like to speak about a thing we call
process or sometimes technological process.
In engineering. Process is a series of
interrelated tasks, which takes something
on its input, do some transformations and
provides a desired output.
Processes can be very different, but all of them
follow this paradigm. For example,
converter on car plant takes parts
and assemble them into the car,
breweries convert hop into the beer,
chemical plants mix chemicals into medicines,
and oil plants distillate oil into petrol.
And all of these processes can be described and represented
as mathematical models, which later can be implemented
in related modeling software. But let's look
what we can do right now. So in
general, we are very good in mathematical modeling.
We have a strong knowledge of mathematics,
physics, chemistry and other sciences.
It is not a problem for us to do any calculations
with base physical parameters such as temperature,
pressure, flow rates, energy, et cetera.
We can do such calculation fast and without anything
special required, for example, using software tools
like Excel, especially if correlations
between parameters are simple and linear.
But also we are quite good in more complex mathematical
models, especially in well described areas such
as thermodynamics, hydrodynamics, or chemical
reactions. We start to
see some difficulties here, mainly with calculation
complexity, when our process includes many
interconnected parameters, or we have
several interconnected processes which need to
be simulated simultaneously,
which actually leads us to things we model not
so well. One of
such example is industry rotary equipment.
In my case, I would like to focus on a modeling
process of such equipment as a compressor.
If we speak about gases or pump in case of liquids,
compressors and pumps are quite similar machines with
common principles, but everything I say also
applies to any other complex industrial
rotary equipment.
For better understanding why compressors are so difficult
to simulate, I shortly will tell you about its structure
and application. So the main
purpose of pumps and compressors is
to increase pressure of medium. Process of
increasing the pressure is used in various applications,
starting from quite simple air conditioning,
where relatively small machines are used,
and goes up to natural gas transportation processes,
where series of huge machines which has physical
size of typical country house do
a lot of compression work. Such machines differ
in structure and in size, which is measured
in maximum consuming power, in watts.
And since this is an active equipment
which consume power to do work, it is
always accompanied with some kind of engine,
electric motor or gas turbine, for example.
But if the main process of such machine is just an increasing
of pressure, which is one simple physical parameter,
why is it so difficult to simulate it in software?
The answer here is variation.
So due to nature of such equipment,
the process cannot be stable every moment of
time. There are a lot of parameters change
every moment of time, and pressure is only
one of them. Each model of such machine has
its own unique fingerprint, a chart
called performance curves. This is a chart
which includes ranges of various parameters such
as pressure ratio, flow rates and power
calculated for specific impeller and for
specific rotation speed. Change of
rotation speed parameter leads to change of the wall
map and all interconnection of
parameters will also change,
all of this multiplied by all possible variations
in hardware designs. And do not
forget that machines can run in parallel or in
series influencing each other.
So literally it is almost impossible to do
universal software solution. But is
it really that nobody tried to do so?
Actually, not really.
There are process simulation software exists and
some of tools are actually very powerful,
but usually not with rotary. They help engineers
to do quite complex calculations. But I see one big
issue here, flexibility.
First of all, almost all such software
are proprietary with closed sources.
If you want change something in the way how it simulates
your equipment, no, you cannot.
Often such software do a lot of simplifications and
also do not pay any attention to rotary equipment
complexity. What companies can do,
they can write messages to support with request to implement
required changes and wait for next visionis version,
sometimes for years. Or there is another option.
Try to implement its own model and software
and sometimes find very unintuitive ways
how to embed it into existing modeling infrastructure.
Here I want to show one example. I worked
in company which had a complex simulation model of
all assets in the one of its projects.
There was no problem with simulation of any equipment
except rotary. To do precise calculation
we had to implement our own Python software
which made a precise modeling of particular installed
compressor type. I had to investigate
what can be simulated in each part of
the machine. Since it was a series of
huge 16 mw machines driven by gas turbines
with various impellers installed. I had to find proper
mathematical models for each part as well
as find their correlations. All this work
was implemented in separate Python models which
later was combined. At the end,
my software were able to calculate precise fuel
gas consumption per machine in all
apparition range by approximation of performance curves,
converting apparition parameters to required calorific
value through mechanical and heat power and fuel gas consumption.
The funny thing was that it was also possible to interconnect
it with petroleum expert software through interface
called Openserver from their site, which originally
was used only to extract some reports.
Our software led us to do precise prediction
of compressor power consumption, which is actually a
company loss on fuel gas. And actually
this leads us to the question,
why is it important? Actually the
demand of such precision is questionable until
you don't try to look for long term planning.
There can be situations, especially on very big
and long processes, when cumulative
effect of nonoptimal operation can
lead to significant losses of money later.
For example, here is a chaos of
typical oil and gas production profile.
It shows how much product will company get during
its operation time. On this chart,
company plans to operate for 20 years,
which is quite normal for typical oil and gas project.
Blue line here shows overall production figures
without any losses in real operation.
Some of product is used for own consumption,
for example for energy generation or as a fuel
for compressors.
Currently companies just take some fixed percent value
and deduct it from overall production to get final
figures. It is shown by orange line.
The issue here is that condition of
operation will definitely change a lot. And without precise
modeling there definitely will be an error.
The green line here represents simulated results
and all the difference between green and orange lines
on chart is actually potential money losses
due to incorrect planning, which actually can
be avoided. For the first view,
the gap between lines is not so dramatic.
But don't forget about cumulative effect and the
scale. Often we are speaking about
up to hundreds of millions dollars per year.
What is important here? This effect can be seen
already on the middle of the project life. And you can
see this time point as blue vertical line on
chart. Also there are another important
time point exists in any such project.
The moment when you have to stop your production so
called abandonment phase. Any production
in this phase cannot be profitable in any
way. So you are interested to start
the construction works as soon as you get to this point.
Otherwise you just will lose money.
Without precise simulation, you can miss this time point easily.
It is clearly seen on the chart as it's shown by two red
vertical lines. For almost a year,
company's cost will be higher than profits
in total. It's not only lost money,
but also additional and avoidable spends.
So in a nutshell, there are options.
Companies can do simple use,
conservative approach and mostly likely
lose some millions in future. Or if
they want to be safe, they can do investment in modeling
software development now and save a lot money
later. As a conclusion, I can say that
I see a great potential in modeling software development.
There are a lot of blank spots on this market
and definitely more discussions are required.
I personally would like to see more movement from industrial companies
to open source world and vice versa.
I hope this presentation as well as described experience
can be as such step. So thank
you very much.