Um, hello everybody,
welcome to my talk in Conf fourty
two this year on the DevOps tracks, we will talk about
how in my favorite banks, we made these reality
to implement the it controls, especially the security controls
over the complete release supply
chain, whatever the technology,
whatever the teams, whatever the departments,
because some of them may have some different released processes,
especially because of the technology, but also because of
what they know and what they've done so
far. But at the bank level,
some controls, some security checks are defined,
and we make sure that these controls
are a reality.
So I will start with a
small presentation. I'm Manuel. I've been working in these
DevOps world since long time,
even before the term DevOps did exist.
I worked in several companies. You see the logos, the last ones are
electric cloud or cloudbees or Wipro. And I'm also a
DevOps Institute ambassador where we talk and
think about the human aspect of DevOps,
which is very important in the project, as we will see today
in that lessons learned oriented
talk, a little bit of history.
Just to start, we will not
go through everything, obviously, but over the last
25 or even 30 years, which is roughly
the time I've been working, there has
been a lot of changes in the infrastructure in
these application architectures.
That leads to a certain number of challenges.
Okay, roughly, if we want to sum up
at the maximum, we've switched from the
monolithic application to modular application,
whatever it means. Today, modular means microservices oriented
architecture, and it brings,
I would say, a little bit more of complexity
in the release process itself.
So roughly,
if we look back in the past
years, we've had several waves,
languages, method, process or
product. And then now DevOps. Each of these waves
has been characterized by some
capabilities oriented on
languages, oriented on the first case,
tools for constructing software systems
and monitoring. Then came the CMM,
it and agile. And now we are talking about DevOps,
about pipelines, about automation,
obviously applied to the application.
One of the main characteristics that comes from the state of
DevOps report is that the
deployment frequency recently grew
a lot, really a lot, because mainly
of the microservices application microservices
architecture that intrinsically brings
a lot of capabilities in releasing fast,
releasing fast, mean release frequently.
So when we talk about DevOps
tooling that has matured, we roughly
at the very beginning switch from a
job based release
orchestration, release management to a pipeline
based for a second generation. So we had some scripts,
and basically what we have done is that we have wrapped
these scripts into some stages and environments.
Obviously, even if it was
a quite poor automation.
We had the ability to define some access rights, for example, which is a
very first important step,
second to third from pipeline based
to adding a lot
of additional things, testing for example in
the automation process. So stages
and environment to QA
CI, a little bit of
release automation, starting with some
best practice, the fidelity across the environment,
the inventory, know where we are and what we do,
the change management. Why should I
start from a point a to go to a point b and
requirement management. What are the link between what
I'm doing and some requirements? So this is
where Jira grew up also to
make the link between all these aspects
of software delivery. And obviously because
this is one of the purpose today, add more security.
Security in terms of security of
the software and security of the process. So approvals,
know who did what. Audit trail.
All these security aspects that grew up
between my second and third phase,
between third and fourth phase, where we are today,
a fully configurable system where we can
have scalability and ease
of onboarding for new applications.
Very often we have some model
based tools, model based, that allow
us to switch from the simple
pipeline to a proper DevOps platform
where we decouple the deployment
activities from these release activities.
So what does it bring? It brings a complete audit trail with the
approvals, with the ability to automate
the approvals and all the reporting
and dashboarding that I can imagine on all the data I'm gathering.
Self service. It's ease of use for the consumers,
for the new projects
that are onboarding on these platforms.
Roughly one, two, three and four.
When I think about the evolution
of DevOps, I'm also thinking in terms of
enterprise scalability.
And I've gone through some challenges that I still have
to face today. Okay. Challenges in the financial services
world, where I work mainly, and we
will focus today on the third one because
it's devsec abstracts. Security and compliance.
Security and compliance. I go through some organization potential
problem.
Sometimes there is one centralized tools
group that makes decisions which are
not necessarily linked with
the field, people that actually do
the development or the operations.
But I also have to deal with the platforms.
Several clouds, several technologies. Am I fully
kubernetes? Do I use Openshift
or Tanzu or rancher?
And each business unit that may have
its own way of working with a release team,
with a specific technological
stack, with some licenses and with some different
processes. So it's not always easy to deal with all
that and to define something that would make everybody happy.
Okay, you recognize here the
wall of confusion between development and operation in the background.
So the challenges, I will not go through this slide
because it's unreadable,
because I have too many challenges. Challenges in terms
of spending, in terms of visibility
and in terms of morale,
the business loss or the people lost also.
So in order to try to address all that
and all that can be quantified,
okay. It's quite
easy to have the ability to put numbers
for spending, for lack of visibility,
for lack of morale or business losses.
And at the end of the day, we can calculate, and this is what we
will do in a couple of slides, a return on investment.
When we think about another solution,
a new approach that
will allow us to have a better visibility,
have a better morale of
the employees, have a better flexibility,
and to really scale, okay?
Which also has some impacts. Impacts in teams of spending,
in terms of overtime, I will spend more time, I will
spend less money in hardware
or in spending in my different
clouds and in efforts,
because I do not have to maintain a homegrown or some
homegrown solutions. When I define based
on some market tools that can
be open source or not, it's not the question,
but if I choose something that I can rely on,
I can, but the effort to
maintain these on ground tools. So my return on investment,
what is it? For the very example
that I'm talking about today, the return on investment, it's been quite
easy to calculate. You have the cumulative spending
investments in red and the benefits in
blue. So we are with a
fair case. It's not the best case. It's not the
worst case. It's a fair case. And you see that we have
the return on investment after five months of
fully using a new approach,
a new production that will allow us
to have that transversal matter
in terms of security and implementing
of devsecops. So what does it mean in
terms of processes? Okay, so I
focus on the security pipeline. This is not the only pipeline
which is transversal, but this is our topic today.
That security pipeline is roughly
the answer to several questions. I want to do CI CD,
I want to be compliant. I want to build a bill of material.
The bill of material. We will go back on that in
several slides. Joe Biden has
published an executive order on the bill of
materials. So it become very important to be compliant.
But it's not my focus.
If I am working on a project, it's not my focus.
I'm okay to be compliant to these security standards,
but it's not my job. My job is to develop
applications and to make sure that these applications while
verifying these security standards will work
in production. So I'm doing DevOps, but security is
something that I want to complies to, but it's
not my job to define how I have
to be compliant. So basically what
we have defined as a DevOps
team, we have defined a security
pipeline made of several stages that
we have agreed with the security people,
where we have to comply to
several stages, several tasks
in the stages for development, for integration, for delivery,
for pre production and production. We have to do some scans,
we have to verify some security aspects.
So let me introduce these generic
checks and controls. The important thing
is that they cannot be changed by me. I am working on the project,
so I don't have the choice to go or not go through that security pipeline.
I have to be compliant. I cannot bypass these checks.
They can change anytime, even between two deliveries.
We will go through an example of that,
which was a workshop I did some time ago,
which is these very explanation of this
change that can happen anytime. They are flexible enough
to cover all the cases for the technologies, for the
process itself. So a huge number of parameters and
they are open and scalable so they can embrace new tools and
new technologies. Let's focus on
that security pipeline. So it's made of examples,
the examples we have made for this implementation,
the checks could be other ones, it could be other tools rather
than Sonacube or checkmarks or the IQ server.
But roughly this is what we go through and
we will see how we feed back that information in the
main application delivery pipeline.
Just a small focus. The stage of development,
we have to go through some SaaS analysis with
three different tools. But before doing that
we ensure that the user has gone through the training,
so he knows what he's doing and he knows how
to analyze the feedback he will have. And at the end
I have an exit gate, so I will block
the delivery if the thresholds for
these three SAS analysis are not met
or are not satisfactory.
Same thing. Another example for the preprod deployment.
I verify that I have gone through these
checks, so a dust and some of
the different checks. And at the end of these day I will verify
that my preprod rules are okay in
order to allow to move forward.
So my security pipeline will be
used by an application pipeline. Remember I am the
application. So once more I still want to do CI CD, I want
to be compliant. I want to build my bill of material using
the security checks that has been defined over there
and building my bomb and applying these
internal controls for compliance and with built in security.
So what does it mean? It teams that you remember my
pipeline for the security five stages. My application
pipeline may have some very different stages, okay?
It has been defined like this in my department since
years. So I like to have these environments.
So what I will do, and this is what we've done,
we just synchronize things. We synchronize saying,
for an example, okay, to start the QA stage
here on my application, I have to wait for
the results of the integration checks in security.
And if these integration checks in security are
okay, you remember my conditions for passing
the gate. If I can pass the gate out
of integration in security, then I can
move to QA and deploy to QA and do my QA
test, and then after that my sight system integration
test and so on. So I synchronize the two pipelines,
the application that can change and the security
that never changes. An example
of application release pipeline where
this step start, my security
pipeline cannot be removed, cannot be bypassed.
You remember, I have to go through that, and it will
make sure that I synchronize everything
afterwards. So, well, my pipeline is quite
big. I have several checks
that are related to my application. I use
my own ticketing system. For example, in stage seven,
I check the bomb entry,
the CMDB entry, the mutability.
These are things that are related to my application.
But in the meantime, in parallel, I will have all my
security checks. The example,
if I do a small focus, what happens in development and
the conditions. User has gone through the training to
enter once more and the
gate rules to get out. I have to have
the same threshold,
okay, for the different analysis, same thing for
the production here. So it becomes serious. I'm switching
to production. I'm handing off. I have to make
sure that I have a bill of material. I have
an entry in my CMDB because this is the
way my favorite bank works. I have to check the immutability
of that information. And I have to have an SKU,
because any application that goes into production
has to have an SKU in my case. But you can
define all
the rules that you want in order to condition
what will happen afterwards,
the processes. So focus on the bill of material.
I promised you that five minutes ago.
Since may twelveth, the president,
Joe Biden, has issued an executive order.
If you want to read a little bit more about that, there is an excellent
paper on TechCrunch of Ben Higgins that explains very
well how that executive order works.
Basically, any vendor has to publish
a bill of material, of what is selling.
It's very simple. So the typical use cases
of the bill of material, it's used
for automation, know what you have. It's used for compliance,
for security. This is what we're doing and for
understanding the complexity. So the bill of material
has become an artifact,
but it's an artifact that describes all the artifacts
that are used or that has been generated to deploy
the application. So just like in 75
Unix introduced Yak, which is yet another compiler.
Compiler. For those who know that feature of
Unix, I would say that
the bill of material could be yet
another artifact. Artifact, because it's a meta artifact
describing other artifacts. If you are interested
about that. By the way, in other conferences
I have delivered a presentation which
focus was the bill of material. With all these standards
and the explanations of how to build a bill
of material and how to use it in the software supply
chain, we consider it as
the single source of the software delivery proof.
So the bit of material time ago described
how we were building the software. Now it describes how
we are releasing the software. It's just some kind of extension
because time ago we had some sources,
we had a build methodology and we produced some executables.
Roughly it was done okay,
now we have to deliver. So to go through a
pipeline to do a certain number of tasks and
to deliver the application in production and to see how it works.
So it's just an extension. But since it's an
extension, the content of the bill of material may
change over time because I will analyze,
I will scan, and the results of my scans of
my analysis because of the audit trail are also
part of my bill of material. So it's very important to understand that notion.
It can change over time. So it's very important
to make it immutable so that I keep trace of
all the scans of all the different
steps that were used to build my
bill of material.
So this is roughly the
explanation and the presentation of
what we did. So if I sum
up in three sentences a
security pipeline, which is the same for
all the applications and all the technologies,
an application pipeline that can change,
obviously, but that will always call that
control pipeline, that security pipeline. I say control because
the security pipeline is not the only one. There are some
other pipelines that are called still executing
in parallel, still synchronizing with my main pipeline.
But I am sure whatever my
department, whatever my technology,
whatever the application I'm releasing that if I got the
okay to switch to handoff to
production, it means that I am clear for the
security aspects and for all the other control aspects
that has been defined at the bank level.
A couple of lessons learned. I made this slide,
just one, to be very focused and
to really understand what we've done,
I would say, rather than some technical aspects
that were very interesting. But one
of the first lessons is implement. Do implement.
Okay. DevOps processes, DevOps controls, automated bill
of material. Just do it and do it now.
Even if it's with a minimal set of tools,
even if they are internal or
external, even if it can look
difficult to gather all that information,
the return on investment is tremendous.
It's fast and tremendous. So do
it now. Do follow the state of
the art company wide, because the competitors do.
If you didn't do CI five years
ago, the competitors were doing it. If you didn't do CD
two years ago, the competitors were doing it.
If you don't orchestrate your releases today, if you
don't do devsecops today,
if you don't look at value stream management today, the competitors
do. And they will get an advantage if you do
not do it before them. So do follow the state of the art
in your company. And the third lesson,
with the automation that we've implemented and the
self embedded controls like the security ones
I have described, it's very easy that
the culture and the best practices will get disseminated
within the organization. So at these, end of the day,
what we have noticed in that project
is that at the very beginning, users were
some kind of trying,
okay, they were not very keen to be chosen
to try that new system because they didn't know
what they were wanted.
They were not sure of what to expect from that.
They were afraid to have a constraint of
going through security and so on. Now we have a
queue, okay, very clearly we have a queue of people
asking to be embedded into the system. And the
only slowness that
we have is from the ability of
embedding new people, onboarding new
people, and growing the infrastructure.
But roughly, this is something that we managed
to do. So I thank you very much for
your attention. Please keep
in touch. You have my contact details here on the
screen. Do not hesitate to contact like me, and very
happy to have been part of Confo v two these
year. Goodbye and see you soon.