Hello. Happy to have you with me today. My name is
Mihaelaroxana Ghidersa. I'm a software engineer and
besides being passionate about software and technology,
I also like to combine it with this public
speaking area and more like in the area
of sharing my experiences,
gather, bring from other people's experiences
and things like this just to shape content
that I can share in presentations
as I'm doing today. So I really want to take to the organizers
for having me. I feel honored to be part of such an amazing
lineup of speakers. First of all, I got to say that
this time is not going to be so much about technical stuff.
I'm not going to give you the perspective on the best architects.
Actually, I think this is a toxic tree that we have sometimes because
we think that it's always about the technical knowledge.
We need to just stop for a minute,
put aside our rules, positioning levels,
never ending processes, and just look at a team and
use the expertise that we have at hand and the knowledge
to see the shape of the current context.
Developers are real people. I know it's hard to
understand it, but they are real people. So we need so much
to take care of teams, dynamics and how we actually
build the product in the end, how we collaborate in building that product.
My feeling is that when it comes to technical
matters, we find a lot of resources on the Internet, so it's
easier to actually work with that part,
easier than working with the way
we interact at team level, the way we
shape team dynamics.
But before that, I want to let something very clear from the
beginning, beyond delivering a presentation, I'm here to
contribute to creating better teams and better project. And I'm
also extremely interested in learning from you and your
experience. So just join me in
this discussion. So what is architecture
when it comes to clearly defining what architecture is?
Along the way I found many interpretations and definitions,
many of them confusing abstractions.
The more I gain,
more knowledge I encounter also some that
were more, let's say, more simple and on point.
But the general feeling was that they were pretty abstract
for a developer that is in the beginning of
his or her career.
So beside all those definitions, abstract or
whatsoever, I think that architects
is a base structure upon which we build. Step by step,
one component after another, we create relationship between
them. Of course high level, we are talking about the high level.
Consider that all this structure
and decisions regarding this structure are being
made while taking in consideration the whole picture of the product.
So when I'm talking whole picture, I'm not talking only technical matters,
I'm also talking about feedback
and perspective for more stakeholders.
Another important aspect to discuss now that we've
opened the discussion about architecture, is that in many cases
it is confused with design. And this makes me think that it's
another consequence of the fact that we have this tendency of
defining everything in a very abstractions way from one
level of
experience. So, as already discussed,
architects is a structure. It's a blueprint that defines
our high level units, the way they interact,
the way they evolve, and so on. On the other hand,
system design shapes things more at code level,
the way each
class evolves, the propose of each
element, and so on. Having a strong system design
helps the development team be more efficient and organized in terms of
understanding what are the responsibilities of some functions,
some modules, some classes, what they can
and can't do, and so on. All of this is possible
by identifying a systems design so we can later
decide maybe what kind of design patterns we should use
in certain contexts. Extending the
discussion a bit about design.
Well, actually, design and architecture, I really liked how
Grady Bach nicely talks about how architecture represents
the significant design decisions that shape a system
where significance is measured by the cost of change,
how nicely put and how nicely
having into consideration this cost.
And we will also discuss about cost and impact.
But basically, if it's just to simplify everything,
significant decisions are architects, everything else is designed.
His words. Later on, we will go a bit deeper also
in the decision making subject. But before I
just want to conclude that simply says software architecture
is focused on the entire system. Software design focuses on
more specific levels.
Since I'm coding people, I also
like this presentation from Simon Brown that
he's saying that architectural decisions are the ones that you cannot
reverse without a high degree of effort.
You can't change an architectural decision in an afternoon.
So just think about this when you make your own change
in the future in the architecture, or maybe
also in the code,
but precisely because we can change a decision
related to architecture in an afternoon, the first step in architects
software is about understanding what is significant
and why.
Because when we
focus very much on code, on how to follow some well tested approaches
and just check our tasks and
feel happy about the fact that we've just finished
a day, well, sometimes we ignore architecture
and think that it's not important. What we miss is the actual
understanding that there are actually some very important benefits
of getting the big picture. You get to understand how components
in the system should interact.
You get to understand the responsibility of
the components, the impact that each
component has, and very important,
the cost in time of the changes that I'm going
to do. Having an overview on the architectural dynamics helps
answering questions like this.
Above all, I really dare to say
that the scalability
to predict change, it's extremely important.
And you know how Darwin's theory
says that the species that survives the
longest is not the strongest one, but the one that adapts better to change?
Well, if Darwin would have worked in software development,
I think that he would have stated that the system that survives longer
is not the system that has
the strongest banners of things like this, but the
system that has an architects that is able to predict and adapt
better to change. So the best solution is to build an architecture
that anticipates change and evolution in a cost efficient way.
And this is something that as developers we can't
ignore. So just take your heads out of the ide
and let's continue the discussion.
So we are discussing before about how
we lose perspective and just
give importance to only some pieces.
Other times we get stuck into the mindset that we have to just
mind our own business, do our
job, focus on the things that we have in the
job description and not concern about
things like architects. This is a very
wrong way of looking at things because guess what, we are
building upon that architects.
And there are so many benefits to having a look from above at what you're
working. I will give you my perspective in a moment
that I just stepped a bit away from the id and
this was because some things were not clear
and I became frustrated at
some point because I wasn't understand
some of the things that I had to do. So I just looked up
and tried to see exactly what is happening. I started asking questions
and suddenly instead of just complaining about problems
that we were having in the system, I started looking for
solutions and trying things in order to make things work.
So I was able to see where some technical guidance might be
needed, where I wasn't having
the knowledge to actually give an opinion or maybe to understanding
what is happening in the system. But I was always also
able to visualize component interactions at a high level
and it changed the way
I looked at things. We changed my perspective
and I actually started liking my job more.
If you ever had the situations like this, I'm sure you understand that
you just have this drive of doing things because
now everything just makes sense. I felt that.
And besides this
pleasure, by having this mindset switch,
I was able to quit some of the teams that
I've grown to believe in time, such as, okay, software architecture
is inflexible and forever like someone said it
in the beginning and that's it. Or the architect is not
my problem, is an architect's problem. So I'm just going to go
deal with my task or architecture is not about coding.
Like architects just discuss business stuff and that's it.
They don't look at the code, they don't care what we are doing in the
code. And I'm pretty sure that at least one
of this, it was part of your career,
you had it at some point.
But more important is to discuss them and break the
toxic cycle. And as
the discussion will evolve, you will see that
we'll just destroy them one by
one. And by being able to destroy
them one by one, we have to think about this person
that seems to be sometimes maybe in the traditional way of doing
things, seemed to be like the God of architecture.
So what is it? An architect,
independently of what we are about to discuss or how often
the role of an architect is pretty
easy to confuse you. I really
think that you don't become architect only by receiving a promotion.
There is a strong need for evolution.
Gradually working with some situations,
growing the expertise,
gaining the attitude in time, that will help you faces the role as
it comes. Because this role ones both with challenges and a
lot of decision making at the same time, I feel that
there has been an evolution within this role,
as I was saying, from a traditional way of doing things
to a more like hipster style,
more open and relaxed
approach. So we are going to put in balance why we
should implement certain approaches over others.
For the longest time, as I was saying, it seemed that the architects
is, besides the fact that we can define the role,
we weren't able to define the role that good.
It seemed also like you can't touch the architect.
He's just standing in there doing very important decisions
and you are just staying in front of the ide and coding.
And I'm not exaggerating because I've been
part of a team where I think it was my
first project ever and I've been in that team for
like over a year.
And I don't know
who the architect was. I never met him, I never interacted,
I never. Nothing about the architect and also
about the architecture. It was like we were so
just doing things in our tasks and that's it. So you can understand that
in the moment when I changed to another team and
the architects was standing like the
desk next to me and he was so open to discussion
and always being involved without
actually being part
of the development team directly, and he was just open
for discussion. He was there for the people that needed
him, but he was building his
things also, and he was just
available when we needed to discuss some things that were important.
So, yeah,
although we have all sorts
of situations like this, for me, this kind
of switch helped me to actually
understand the difference between a title and a role. And this is
the first thing that I want to discuss, the fact
that the architecture is not being built
by one person only. We need to just quit this mindset
that the architect architects the architecture. As I was saying,
one of the myths that we are discussing before, I'm not saying that
teams shouldn't have someone clearly ones a role,
but somewhere in time, any team member can come with
ideas and insights that can impact the current state of architects.
This is what I mean by a flexible collaboration,
a flexible role that stands in collaboration actually.
Then of course, again,
for the longest time, the feeling was that the architect
has to know it all and has to own
the whole stack. And I was thinking like, oh my God,
every technology and every detail. That is preposterous.
Why would anyone ever want to have such
pressure and would ever consider taking
this role? Who would ever
be good enough for this role if the
requirements are so unrealistic?
Well, how about we usually use
the technical expertise of the team while raising
the teams, taking part in the development process,
either by pair programming, doing some
code reviews, just looking from time to time to
what is happening in the code base, gives you the smallest effort,
gives you an idea about whether or not your architects perspectives
are grounded in reality. The sooner you have this kind
of feedback,
the sooner you can ensure that you work on the evolution
of an architects that is actually implementable,
that works with real life scenarios, and it can be implemented
by real people. Then we have the third point that
the architect used to in the traditional way
of doing things, the architect was defining and actually
taking care that the architecture stays like that. And I was thinking
like, I can't believe that we need architects.
Police. Is architecture
something so fixed and hard to implement that it needs someone to
guard it? But how about understanding
the system, combining this understanding with
collaboration and feedback, as we were previously discussing,
and create a more grounded
in reality system, a system that is understood
by the team, and a
system that the team is actually able to build
and understand why it is important to build in a certain way,
why it is important to enforce some approaches, some best practices,
some patterns and things like this. So definitely architect,
as we are saying, it's a flexible role. An architects
uses the technical expertise of the team while also growing
the team and with the team. And of course
the architect understands the system,
keeps high
level mindset, but also looks at a developer's perspective
and tries to see if his objectives and
his vision is actually understood
and implementable in the end.
So now we can consider that some of the myths were invalidated
and we will discuss later
even more details to bring some light.
But right now I want to go a bit and
discuss about two approaches when it comes to the architect
role. One is leadership
over management and how we are actually
placing this role. And the other one is expertise
over knowing it, everything. And somehow on this part
we already touched some details.
If there is something that you remember from
this talk about your architect and maybe something that
you can just look at your architect and see if he's doing that,
please make these two things. That's something.
So let's discuss the first ones, which is leadership goes
over management. There's a difference between management and leadership.
Management is a lot about tasks, very specific
steps, achieving the end goal, which is not a bad thing.
On the other part though, leadership is about people,
who you are, how you get to those people, how you inspire them,
how open are you to those people.
I really think that an architect should be a leader.
A leader that has a very good overview, that has
experience in a lot of areas and that
can give insights both functional and nonfunctional.
He actually has the responsibility to grow the
team in the end.
And maybe something that,
again, I've seen in teams, and it seems
that it's not clear, is that each member of the
team has a
certain level of knowledge. So as an architects,
you have in the moment that you approach a team,
you have to find a way, a common language in
order to make sure that everyone understand what
you are trying to enforce in the team.
So everyone in the development teams needs to see the
essence of software architecture, the consequences
of not thinking about it. Before we start talking about things
like, you know,
the way we evaluate people and the
way we evaluate performance and other things and language
and things like this, we have to understand the consequences of
our work. And to be honest,
some recent events that I witnessed showed me that
people really need to be in touch with the architects.
People really need to be
able to ask the architect about some of the decisions to understand
what is happening. And I've seen this in one of the teams that I
worked with where we barely,
this is another team, it's not the first team that I was telling you about.
We barely interacted with the architect. So until the
moment that I just, I'm very persistent.
So I just went to him and asked
for explanations and things like this. Well,
in the moment that I did this and the moment that we actually received
some answers and things like this, the team expressed,
the rest of the team also expressed the need of understanding the context
and how important is and how they
don't see what exactly they are building.
At the end of the day, what is the result as
a whole. So we don't usually talk
about the soft side of being a software architect, even though
it's so important. I felt it and I'm sure that
a lot of you also felt it. If there are
any in there that were just fine. Well, with the
situation when I had for you, it means that
you had a real leader in that. But in
the real world, an architect's role is both worrying about the important
technical decisions, but also he has to lead,
give the team a direction.
Collaborate coach we are basically
talking about a full time leadership role.
So yeah, soft skills are extremely important and
I'm just going to insist on this only once
more. A team with the same view and that finds
it easy to collaborate, is more engaged and delivers both
quality and quantity. So team dynamics
are so important and the architect
has a very important part in all this process.
Then we discuss about the expertise of our knowing it all.
We were discussing already, owning the whole stack is not
possible, more like users, also the expertise of
the team. And I
think that the real skill
of an architect is not mastering the whole stack and knowing
it everything and being the best of the best and things like this. I think
it needs to have some
background in software development. Yes, but the most important I think is
the ability to switch between code and implementation details
and the architects big picture. Because yes,
as an architect you should own best practices, approaches,
overview and design and patterns that bring more value to some
of the technologies in order to choose the right technology or
in order to just go with the project
in the right direction. But when it comes to keeping an
eye on details, low level code, I think it's true
value exists in using the technical expertise of the team.
The software architectural can sometimes even for one
idea, be of another team member. We just need to create trustful
and a trustful
environment. An environment where we can collaborate,
where people can express their ideas and show
their expertise, be confident enough to show
what they know and learn on the process.
So being an architects is challenging and takes a
lot of knowledge and experience. At the same time, you dont need to be
an expert in any particular area of software development to become
one. It is better to have a wide
understand of software development and be able to communicate your knowledge effectively
while being backed up by best practices.
I find it important to know that you don't have to be the God of
the technology stack in order to become an architect.
I find it useful to have a big
picture, to have emotional
intelligence and also coaching. So it's
a very good combination of technical and soft skills.
More specific, I really
find that there are some general set of skills that embody the architect
role, like being pragmatic
when it comes to requirements and constraints.
Being able, and this is something that is being built in time and
with experience of being able to know where you can take a risk
and where you can't take a risk, and be
able to make some decisions regarding
design. Be very careful in the moment
that you have to make some decisions. If you gain some technical depth,
well, how you are going to manage that technical depth, like keep track of
that, because at some point it might get so hard to manage
and the architectural vision might be
so damaged that you can't do much about it.
And also the combination with the other soft skills
that we've discussed, such as keeping
close with the team, be a leader,
inspire people, grow, raise people, and try to
be the best influence
in the team and keep everyone aligned.
We were talking before about taking risks,
making some decisions. Well, each project that I ever worked on has
evolves in time. Requirements changed because maybe
of the competition. So they had to change the main features
or you have to be creative
because some new technologies and trends appeared. And yeah,
you need to stay up to date sometimes when it brings value to
your product. Maybe some stakeholders change
the way they look at features and they
change the perspective, they change what they wanted, they try
to want to try something different,
where sooner or later, depending on the context and domain,
something is going to change. What we need is to
actually think in terms of building tolerance to
change in the system. Observe where and what
kind of changes appear, iterations, and this way
you can expect these kind of changes and be prepared to meet them.
That's why we are doing so much analyzing, because I
really liked this idea from Jane's
clear, with saying no and yes
and how no is a choice and yes is
a responsibility. Because every time we assume a final decision,
we are also saying no to some more
details that we might receive in time
in the future. Details that
might be significant and might help us make
a more informed decision that
once you committed to something, you already decided how that future block
of time will be spent and how the product and the architecture of structure
will evolve. So be very careful
in what exactly you invest.
Just think about it.
So making decisions concerning architectural aspects is
a very sensitive aspect because those decisions
have a huge impact. And one of the best practices in
software development is to avoid making decisions until the very last moment.
Because, yeah, especially in architecture, there is a high level of uncertainty.
So a good strategy in order to be prepared
to make commitment is gathering a lot of feedback.
If we talk about an existing system. But yeah,
dont get lost in details and accept
there are some parts of the
project that you are just discovering time and that
is okay, but also especially for the existing products,
accept when you made a bad decision in the past and
just change the perspective. Accept that maybe some
parts of the systems can be,
you can rethink of them and give them another shape.
A better strategy for delaying commitments
and making decisions when developing complex is not actually delaying
the commitment, but more like always
build your system in terms of evolvable
structures. Like always keep in mind that you need
some degree of some
capacity for change into the
system. So keep your system open to
change in the future.
Now I would like to point that
becoming a software architect is not something that you
become automatically, as we discussed, it's a role,
even though it's not easy to strictly define it,
just as architecture.
What a coincidence. Well,
we actually can
agree on the fact that the road to coding an architect is full of challenges
and experiences and expertise and confidence, and we just build
upon that in order to be ready for the,
as I was mentioning before, the challenges and
the decisions that you are about to
take. So you have to be ready for the role. You can just be named
an architect just like that.
But from what we've discussed, maybe with some exceptions,
architecture is a part of the development process, part that
later is taken over and implemented.
Actually in the team architects is not about forgetting about
implementation details and getting drawn in abstractions,
but about keeping them balanced.
Sometimes maybe you put more accent in one side, sometimes maybe
the accent goes on another side. I think that you become
a good architect when you are able to slightly move from one
to the other. And I
was able to witness this and I was very
inspired of an architect that did something
like this. So in the end, software architecture
is all about understanding how the system works as a whole.
And since we are discussing
in here about duties and professional
duties, I think that on one side the developers
should cross the line and break the rules
and be curious and always check on how
you ended up with doing what you're doing in the code and how your
code complements the structure of the system. Then also
the architect should break the rules and
make more informed and reality oriented
decisions. Then we
are talking about, okay, but can
actually every developer be an architects or what's the deal? How we are going to
grow to that role? Because I've received this question before.
Well,
it's not an easy road and sometimes you might be thinking,
okay, but if it's not something clearly defined
and the collaboration with a
team is so strong,
couldn't we just use self organizing teams and just get
it over with? This architects troll and whatever we are
discussing. Well, I don't agree with
that part. I think that an architects in a system that
evolves and a system that in times adds
up complexity, it's important to insist
and have this role defined and have
a person with the responsibility of the role because the
team components, it changes.
Every team member has a different level of engagement.
You need someone that keeps things on track.
You need someone that stays engaged with the product that we
are building. Because if you
are doing things right and you are keeping the
relationship with the team and also with the other stakeholders
and try to manage
all this context well,
the results are visible
and an architects is important in the team. If we
are discussing maybe a product that just needed some
structure in the beginning, a product that is not that complex, that is
not evolving that much, the architects
can be like someone that maybe just from time to time
goes into the teams, or maybe in the beginning gives a
structure and that's it. If it's a very simple
product that does not evolve in time, it's just fine.
From my perspective whatsoever, the process of becoming an
architect is not a very well defined, as I was saying,
we don't have like the ten steps of becoming an architect.
No, you can just look at the
ones that you have near you,
undertake some parts of the software architects
role, architect role without actually
losing the perspective that you have as a developer.
Just try to contribute. Look at
what maybe the closest architect is coding or
the closest, most senior person that you have
and try to do it step by step, even though maybe
your goal is not to become
an architect, it's just to become a professional with more
like go to the next level. It's also okay to look at someone's
journey and just go and ask,
okay, what have you done to actually work
in this role and what should I do?
And things like this. So your evolution
is your responsibility.
So go ask well
about this. I think we've discussed how important it is to actually
change perspective, change roles from time to time.
I really think that as an architect, you need
to understand the concept of the application from a developer's
perspective and take more informed and realistic decisions.
And this way, by having clear what
they are building, also the team will understand the impact and the importance of
their work. And yeah, we'll trust you more, but also they will be more
motivated and engaged with the product in the end because they are able to
see the whole picture.
So yeah, I don't
think that coders should just code and the architect
should be concerned only with the architecture.
Sometimes it's good to just change the
revolves and wear someone else's shoes
just to see how we can impact their
work. Although we discussed a
lot about the best ways to do things, there always appears
a gap between the development team and the architect. Unless the
effort is mutual and
both parts the
effort, you can't make things work other way.
Software development is a team activity and in the end even
unintentional. We help each other grow.
For the developers that are thinking
maybe about taking the role of an architect or just wanting
to step up to the next level, don't be
afraid to look outside your daily task. Try to understand the
context of the product.
When you don't understand something, speak up.
When you have maybe something
to some solution idea,
share it, try to get feedback on that and
always ask to be
involved in the decision making. If again you
have a perspective and some arguments for the
ideas that you are promoting.
Architecture is not an esoteric concept, but it's not an easy
road either. And one step at a time, you can grow
in the direction that you find interesting. Always surround yourself with people that
are better than you. See how they approach certain areas,
read their code, look at the decision and see
or think about how would you have decided
in your case it
then for the architect?
Well, don't be so you
so obsessed
with your solution, except that you are also doing some
bad decisions.
Stay close to the team and collaborate with the team from
time to time. Get your hands dirty, because when it comes to building the
right architecture and for the right context,
I came to learn that.
Actually I came to learn this the hard way, that it's important
to have the architects state engaged
with a team. The value this approach brings in terms of
feedback and collaboration and instant click
when it comes to some solutions is incredible.
On the other side is the best way to keep the team aware about the
technical vision and the architects
direction and you don't
have to be 100% involved in the code.
Do some pad programming, look a
bit from time to time in the code base. Whatever works for you.
Just don't get lost in abstraction.
Being a developer is not easy. Right. And being an architect is
definitely not easy either. What I really believe in
is the amazing benefit.
Benefit? Yeah, of every development
teams considering architecture.
Failing to do this just brings inconsistencies,
integration issues, code base that is
hard to understand and to extend.
And yeah, just not mentioning a lot of the quality attributes
that we should enforce. Just becoming harder
and harder to maintaining as the system evolves.
I'll finish by leaving you with two ideas for developers,
think globally, understand the whole
picture and try to implement in the details
towards that big picture.
And for the architects, we'll work on
the abstractions. But please, from time to
time, just give an eye to the details, to the code base,
collaborate with the team and just
try it. And maybe later give
me a sign on LinkedIn or Twitter and tell
me how it went that for you. Thank you very much.
And let's see if there are any questions.