Welcome everybody to the talk about implementing of GnEi in
banking context. I will be speaking from practical and
business perspective because currently I am chief product officer of the company
which created geneae solution for the bank.
We actually had a lot of communication with the banks around
leveraging AI in banking environment.
Firstly, we'll discuss about context and use case overall.
Then we'll go into short description
of the product. Then we'll have a deeper dive of
technical aspects of product,
how was it created? And then we'll
discuss the frequent concerns of the banks of launch
product within the banking environment. And in the end,
we'll speak about the team which is required to
create such kind of solution. So let's start.
If we are talking about potential market of
software for the banks, it is really huge. It is
more than $4 billion.
It is just a service addressable market,
but actually it is much larger. We believe
that this market is growing.
At this market, we focus on actually
two solutions. Our company focuses on two problems.
The first problem is that when you try to open account in
a bank for your business, this takes a
lot of time. Like according to our survey, it is seven
days and more than 400 pounds per
one customer. Also, we know that there is
a huge problem with transaction monitoring and why
so. And according to our research,
if we look at the onboarding process of
business customers for the bank, you can see that some
parts of this process is very much automated. It is
like verification in registers, identity verifications,
et cetera, et cetera. But there is a part which I
colored green, which is very difficult
to automate. And this part is related to two things. The first thing is
back and forth clarification. For example, you ask customer to
provide a contract. Customer provided to you.
Your manager read the contract and realized that the
contract is expired and you need the fresh
one. And you write a message, could you please provide the new
contract? And this usually takes two days. It is
a significant amount of time. And secondly,
actually reading of the loan documents take a lot of time.
Sometimes contracts provided to the banks could
be 50 pages, 100 pages. And you
can imagine how much time managers
spend on reading such documents. And our product actually
resolves this issue and it
is not covered by the current players yet.
And what we are doing, we launched
a system which
is talking to customer in chat. It is AI
powered chatbot. It collects documents,
it extracts data from documents,
does all the checks which are required and prepare compliance
report. And this compliance report looks like
this. You can see that in this report we
provide all the discrepancies found in the documents,
all the issues, all communications from customer
around it. And in the end compliance officer, the person who is
making decision about open account just read
our report and take decision to open
account or do not open account. And it takes for them just
like ten minutes but not seven days as it
was previously. So this is our use case, this is the product we
are offering for the banks and
this product, the benefits for the banks is of course cost
reduction on burden speeds. Customers are happy and
actually many others. And this
product is like I will speak a bit
more about how was it built from
maybe technical perspective if we try to
create such product just based on LLM. As you know,
LLM will not have a structured discussion
on some topic. Even if we make very good prompts,
very good structure, the stability
and ability to control what is going on will be
very low. That's why we decided that
we should have a hard coded dialogue
scenario. So we should ensure that system
will ask customer for example for
registration documents for the company contracts,
invoices and if customer has some
questions or would like to discuss anything around these
documents, we'll support it. But it will be very well
guided dialogue. And you can see that we
have splitted this flow into the
small steps. Like for example
we tell the task to LLM customers
asking us to provide some information about requirements
for the invoice and LLM just
answer to this particular small question and this is
small task we are given to LLM. We are not trying to ask you
to collect all the data and secondly
we use separate OCR service like
the quality is higher and we do not use even llms
for this. And we see that stability is
very good with it. Thirdly, we do extraction
and also it is a separate task to the model using
OCR we converted images to
text and now we use LLM to
extract from this text structured data. We need to
make documents analysis and
finally we decided that it should be not
only LLM and OCR
but also we would like to use APIs to enrich
additional data for this particular case.
So we have integration with registers. For example, we are
taking data from there, comparing this within
data we extracted from the documents and as
the result received very well structured
reports. If we're talking about integration
perspective here,
it is actually a very important concern of the customer. Like when
it is a bank, they have very very
complicated architecture and
with a long history and it is very difficult
and takes a lot of time to to integrate
seamlessly in this kind of architecture. That's why for the
proof of concept. To make this much faster,
we created kind of fast integration approach. It looks like this.
For example, bank would like to open a business account for
the customer and customer usually
fulfill forms on the website of
this bank and they authorized and we have this
and we do not integrate into.
We do not integrate API using API here.
We just do an iframe integration. So we find some screen and
put it there and it is very fast.
Second approach is that our service which is actually
creating all of this, which is in the cloud.
After user talks
to potential customer of the
bank in iframe
chat, which is actually our chat, we created
report and we send this report through email.
Very straightforward. We can do it of course through API. But as
I mentioned that for the banks it can take a lot of time.
Rolling out such kind of fast API
takes one week and it is
much more interesting for the banks to try
our product. Moving on, I mentioned
that we used to face different
concerns to llms and
overall usage of GPT in the bank
environment. And the first concern is for example that
most of people believe that OpenAI use
client's data to develop new models.
And we prepared special
documents which confirmed that corporate
API that
OpenAI declares that they
do not use any client's data in
corporate API and is protected by agreements and is
protected by all necessary
policies. And we show this to the
customer and usually this helps.
Secondly, many people still
believe that chat boxes are not reliable. For example,
I have heard such concern. Yes, I like your solution
is great, but we like this
part when you are checking the documents, making compliance
checks. But this chat is like. I personally don't like
chats. Chatbots, can you please implement
this kind of dynamic form where a customer can fulfill
some information and get the response, but not in chat.
Also very very interesting
concern because people still see that chatbots
are not reliable. And this is true actually. And what
we can do here, as I mentioned that firstly
we made our chart very structured.
Also we limited answers
to internal database. So if our chatbot
answering to customer, it is not using any information from the Internet,
it uses information from
the data source which is checked and we are sure that there will
be no hallucinations around it. Also we are
adding where it is possible, we are adding some
hard coded logic and quick buttons which can skip
chat communication where it is not necessary. So I
would not say that we have kind of clear chat.
It is mix of chat and hard coded logic.
And this helps with banks when
we are trying to convince them that this product is good enough.
Number three is the quality. Of course,
from the beginning people remember that if
we are talking about machine learning,
when you need to read, when you need to
read any new document with a high quality,
you need to train model on thousands and thousands
samples of such documents. And they do not understand that
situation has been changed. And actually you do not
need so huge train data to
to have a good quality. And we actually support
our sales materials with the results
of the testing and we suggest
them to try their own documents. And after they are trying
this, usually this helps.
And number four, I also already
mentioned it, but maybe elaborate a bit more. That of
course banks afraid of hard integration
and for proof of concept they would like something small what
they can try. And we created
this kind of quick integration scheme. And also secondly,
we started integrations with the large
CRM and compliance case management systems
like for example Salesforce and
banks which are using Salesforce.
When they think about
integration and when they understand that this one will be that our
product will be part of the Salesforce flow,
it is much easier for them to take this decision
to get our solution. And now let's move to
the team. Of course it could be different
team working on such projects, but I would like to mention a few mission critical
roles. I think they are
necessary for the success of such product. Of course data scientists
and when we're talking about generative AI,
the role of data scientists have changed.
It is already more prompt engineering,
already more about data extraction from the text
and it shifted. But what
is important data scientists from the knowledge perspective,
they can structure working on the quality and
I think this is critical. They can create a
great data set, they can ensure the quality of the
data set, they can ensure that the labeling
process is set up properly and you can test
it properly.
This role shifted, but it's still the core in this process.
Second role, this is actually the new
role and I have not heard about this role
before this project, but I think it is kind of role
just appeared the previous year.
QA engineer with prompt engineering experience.
It's a really interesting mix.
The people who can test quality
of responses of llms
on the high volumes, so they can use,
they are very experienced in prompt engineering. They have
all the tools which are required and they can write actually these
tools for automation of such QA.
This is new role really helping a lot to our
product to ensure quality of chat. Duck and
number three, of course, back end developer who
actually currently can do prompt engineering as well,
integration with different models,
but important that this role should be combined with
DevOps or it should be a separate person develops on the team.
Because if you need high quality environment for the banks,
your infrastructure should be really great and I
would personally recommend to have this role in your team.
So to wrap up about my
talk, it is a huge use
case for ginia in the banks and it is a
great potential of implementation.
The main pain for the banks actually working with a
large volume of different documents and different processes. It's not
only compliance process, could be lending process,
credit process and due diligence legal process.
So there are a lot of them. Our company
created chatbot which collects and verifies documents for
the banks and we have experience in implementing it.
Most of the banks do not fully understand the opportunities
and we see that banks
actually risk averse organizations and we
hear a lot of concerns and you should be prepared to argue
and to provide support that the
risks are not so high. And as a hint
to overcome the concerns that prepare maybe
responses to frequently asked questions.
And second one to have instant
proof of concept so you can prove that your solution works.
Well, that's it from my side. Thank you very much
and have a nice day.