Hello everyone. In this session we will be talking about Gopher opinionated
Go framework for accelerated microservice development.
Our todays agenda will be to start with an intro to Gopher.
Later we will move forward to its features. After that, I will show you
how you can build a sample API using Gopher with MySQL
as a database. Later we will conclude on what
we have discussed. Gopher is an opinionated web
framework written in Go. It was built with the aim to
extract the process of building robust and scalable applications
and is designed to offer a user friendly experience for all the developers.
It helps in building robust and scalable applications. The framework
is designed such that it powers you to focus
on the main features rather than worrying about a
lot of minor things which we will discuss now with
Google. Developers can bid fable to tedious setup tasks and focus
on what truly matters building exceptional services GoPro streamlines
this journey by offering a feature rich framework that empowers you to exploit
development and build production ready solutions. Here is a brief
list of features Gopher offers to its developers. Out of the box
observability gopher shifts with built in observability as
soon as you build your application. It provides detailed traces and matrices.
Say goodbye to guesswork. Your system is production ready from the get.
It also allows you to create your custom traces and custom
metrics as per your need. Authentication GoPro
has inbuilt support for OAuth, basic auth and API key
based authentication and systems. You need not to worry about
that, you can just use the feature which is already present in proof,
fine tune logging and on the fly. Log level management
our framework offers granular log level at different
levels which are worn in four notice debug pattern.
You can tailor your log to different environments, ensuring clarity and efficiency.
It also provides you to change the log level on
the go without restarting your applications or changing the deployment
support for both rest and GRPC based APIs.
It provides you with inbuilt configuration management where you can
set the configurations and use them in the application. Go for
supports MySQL, redis and popular pubsub systems like Kafka,
Google Cloud and MQtt. And guess what? We are actively adding more
database support. Your data layer your choices when
making an endless service call. Woofer provides you with an option to add a
circuit breaker to your application which makes sure that you don't hit the
same service again and again if it is not responding back.
This is an open source project which is built by developers for developers
making production ready applications. Let's dive
into code to see how you can use code.
Let's start creating our sample project. We are in the new directory
sample API. Let's initialize our project. We have
done our basic setup. Let's get go for using
Go get. This is the basic setup we need to write
a gopher application. These two lines, go for new and
app dot run are the most basic lines which will be
present in every gopher application. Go for new is called.
It initializes the framework and handles various steps including
initial id using logos, metrics, data sources,
etcetera. Based on the context provided when app run
is called, it configures, initializes, and runs the
HTTP server and serves middlewares.
It manages essential features such as routes for health
check, endpoints, metrics, server etcetera.
By default, it starts the server on the port 8000,
which we can override using the configs. Let's try to
register a route for our project. When we register
our route, it takes two things, the route itself and a handler
function. Handler function takes the context and
returns interface and l. Let's return hello
world from here. Let's take the dependencies
and run our project.
Our server runs on port 8000 and we see proper logs
coming in forever stuff which go for let's
hit the green endpoint and we see the well
formatted output of hello world on our screen with a proper status
code 200 which go for is setting it for us based
on the rest API guidelines. Gopher formats every output
in the data struct to keep it consistent among different multiple
microservices. Gopher also formats the
logs for every request. It generates a
new request coordination id and
with a proper status code in the log at the time taken by the let's
connect our application to a database. Gopher supports
connecting to SQL databases as well as redis based
on configuration variables. Let's get the
configuration from over documentation to connect to MySQL,
let's run the MySQL instance in a docker container.
Let's get the configurations to connect to the database.
These configurations are in sync with the docker command if you run it.
Configurations are present in the config directory in env file.
Let's run our application.
Our application is connected to the MySQL database
test DB just a few configs and Google let
us automatically connect to a database and users can conveniently access DB
methods from the context itself. Let's try to run a database
command now read handle club c
dot equal dot value.
Let's run show databases scan.
We can see that the application ran successfully and we were
able to get a response information schema from the database.
Go first. Suppose MySQL postgres was SQL
databases. It also supports Redis and Mongo which can
be used directly without much code. For changing from MySQL to
postgres, user needs to update the configuration and just need
to change the DB data from MySQL to postgres. Gopher also
pushes let's change the log level from configs
to debug.
We see that the debug logs are now coming in. Let's run
the again so we
see that the query row is coming again with the very which we
actually ran. This helps in performance training
the application and we get all the logs by default using
by changing the document exposure to
tracing. Woofer provides this user with this set of features to
track down their applications performance. Monitor any bugs making
it production ready let's start with metrics. When we
run our application, Gopher by default starts the metrics on
port 2121 which is evident from the logs.
Let's see what all metrics are being used. Gopher by default pushes
some metrics related to the application function which are the number of both teams
SQL in use connections, SQL pen connections.
When we send a request, offer by
default adds those metrics like
apps equals bucket like how much time the request to the SB
response bucket, how much time they want. Apart from the path
which was at the status return, users can
also add their custom metrics from the context with
the method metrics. It allows you to
create a new metric as well as increment the older metrics which were already created.
Go for sports four types of metrics counter upgrade,
counter histogram and watch.
Users can also change the default metric port 2121
from the configs by adding the config matrix.
Now the metric server is running on port 1900.
Offer also utilizes the open elementary standard for tracing,
providing detailed information about each user request.
This helps you understand how requests flow through your application and identify
potential issues. Let's set up tracing for our application.
Let's save on our documentation to see the traces
we need to install zipkin in our system. I already have it
running, so it is.
Let's add the context here.
Tracer post which is 2005
in my case and praise exporter
which is zip code.
So now we got the one that sporting precise.
You see the let's get the quotation id of the request.
When we search the request, we got the flow of the request application
we had the green endpoint, it went to the router and later it
came to the handle. Let's see go observability in action I have
known the Gopher repo and using the examples present there.
I've used the public dashboards available for Gopher on grafana.com and set
it up in my local system. Grafana is an open source data visualization and
monitoring solution. With Grafana you can easily correct,
correlate and visualize the data using informative dashboard.
I am running HTTP server from Gopher. Examples have generated
a load to replicate the production load. Here you can see
how our application is performing as well as we can
see the number of requests received, time it took
and the status quo returned, along with the number of outbound
SQL queries which ran and the Redis commands which were executed
in the dashboard. Innovation let's see how distributed tracing
works in Gopher. I have set up two different applications,
one of which is using redis as well, and we can see the places here
where we can see how the request is flowing from our first application
sample API to using HTTP service and
it is coming back to the sample API where it is
being processed further. Gopher allows developers to not
worry about the other has such as managing a database connection or
implementing tracing and allow them to focus more more on what really matters,
the core functionality which leads to less time production,
easy to debug code and it increases the developer productivity.
Thank you everyone. This was it from my side.
Hope it was informative. Do visit our repo on GitHub
and give it a star if you like it.