Are living in can era of technological marvels
wherein new industrial revolution is triggered by
new advances in science and technology.
We talk about different technologies like artificial intelligence,
machine learning, nanotechnology, cloud and virtualization,
et cetera. But while developing any
new product we tend to forget the amount of
energy it is producing as well as the amount
of energy it is consuming. This is
harming our environment gradually.
Have you ever thought how new
products that are being developed impact the environment?
Hello, I'm Dr. Anubha Jain.
I come from Pink City of India, Jaipur.
I am working as a director of School of Computer Science and it
at is deemed to be university Jaipur.
In my talk I'll be talking about the role of technology
in developing sustainable environment for us
and our coming generations to lead a safe
as well as a smart life.
I start with this funny video of Charlie Chaplin
wherein there is a mechanical device feeding charlie.
This was a technological marvel of its time, but science
and technology has come a long way since then.
We are heading towards a world of communication
and connectivity as well predicted
by a futurist. Everything will be connected to everything.
We are witnessing a world wherein devices
are talking to other devices.
Individuals are connected and communicating
to devices at higher scales
which were unknown previously. And central
to this concept of communication is connectivity.
Things around us are connected together in
a mesh of smart devices which
communicate with each other over the Internet seamlessly,
thus forming Internet of things.
This is transforming the way we live and we
work. And as we can see from this graph
generated by Statista,
the number of IoT connected devices worldwide
has been increasing. In fact,
from 2020 to
2030 it is expected that these devices
will triple down from 9.7 billion to
29.4 billion devices.
And most of this share of
devices are from consumer segment
like smartphones and your autonomous
vehicles, it infrastructures, asset tracking,
monitoring and asset growth. In fact,
National Intelligence Council of us has
identified six civil disruptive technologies
that are going to rule the world and Internet of Things
is assumed to be one of them. By 2025,
IoT will be residing in each and
every device that you use, maybe food, package, furniture,
paper, document or anything else.
Now, what is fueling this IoT revolution?
As we all know, the electronics are getting more
compact yet more powerful and widely available.
At the same time, the backbone of your Internet
is getting stronger. The Internet infrastructure
has advanced from three g to five g.
Thus the protocol has also improved
and the adoption of IPV six has increased the number
of available unique identifiers that
we have. So each device may get a
unique address and still addresses may remain vacant.
So there will be a time where more connective devices than people
will be available to us.
Now. The enabling technologists for IoTs,
RFID sensors in actuators, smart technologies technologists
for tracking the data as well as processing
and drawing decisions from this data.
Along with societal and technological challenges,
there are environmental challenges being faced by IoT. So the
growth of IoT does not come for free. It has a
major impact on environment. Let's look at IoT how
as the number of connected devices are increasing,
the energy being consumed by these devices is again increasing
and the usage of batteries is increasing.
Also, electronic appliances production has
raised as we need more devices to safer to
people. All this have resulted in
increased e waste and landfills
plus greenhouse gas emission.
This all has led to something called global warming.
Thus the concern of environment
and sustainability is at break in case of
IoT. Thus,
the solution for all this is should we do away with
technology? No, we should use technology
for a better tomorrow. In order to build a
safe smart world, which is sustainability,
it is of utmost importance that we go
green. Thus we have to become
green in using these connected IoT devices
also. So the green IoT is a
scenario where we optimize Internet usage to save energy
by judiciously using available resources,
by using renewable sources of energy and
building energy efficient procedures.
Now this greening in IoT can
be done by greening can
IoT or greening by IoT.
While greening of IoT focuses on manufacturing
energy efficient IoT hardware as well as
building greener software. While greening
by IoT involves IoT as an enabler
to create a sustainable environment. So let's
look at it into detail that how
greening of IoT and greening by IoT can
build sustainability solutions. Now,
first we look at IoT as a game changer.
IoT has just transforming the entire world by
making all the devices smart, maybe in the sphere
of industrial automation, homes,
transport, healthcare, agriculture or
any other industry. So let's look at some
important use cases where IoT has been
used to build sustainable solutions.
So the first and foremost use case that we see
is the safer management that we can do at different
levels. Maybe household offices at sea
level or wastewater management.
Smart utility meters can be applied
for real time power usage monitoring that collect,
store and send data to smartphones
to manage energy and water consumption at
households and at office and industry level.
At sea level, aquaculture can be done wherein IoT
systems track animal health and environmental factors
that impact them to adjust the conditions
for happier and healthier fish. It will help in decreasing
time to market as well as reduce
the waste by doing predictive analysis that
will help farmers for faster harvest and
looking upon what and how much fish will eat based
on different temperature levels, health timing, et cetera.
Also, it will comply with environmental and food
safety regulations. The next important use
case is smart homes or
smarter offices wherein smart
lighting, demand driven heating and cooling for improved
comfort in homes as well as offices can help
in saving energy consumption as well as
energy start certified thermostats can be used
which can learn what temperature users prefer to
build a schedule around that setting to make buildings
more sustainable. During pandemic,
the overall energy consumption of New York City reduced
approximately by 15% by using
this smart lighting technique.
Then IoT plays a pivotal role in smart healthcare
by building smart telemedicine services
and predictive health care
monitoring for betterment of society.
It was seen during pandemic that senior citizens started
using more of telemedicine services and
IoT devices helped along with big data
and analytics for quicker diagnosis of health issues
and also decrease the expenses of hospitals
in terms of system cost and for patients in
terms of actual visit to hospital.
Smart city is another example of IoT
making the life sustainable by smart parking,
structural health, noise, urban maps, smart detection,
traffic congestion management, safer management,
etc. IoT can also help in maintaining
biodiversity of wildlife as well as marine organisms
by making use of technologies like
drone technology, acoustic monitoring.
In fact, the connected collars which have been used
by smart breeding management systems allow
farmers to increase production while minimizing
cost and the use of resources.
It allows the breeder to get information about animals conditions
and behavior of their body temperature,
ovulation, gestation period, et cetera,
which can be helped to maintain better
health of animals and they can locate their livestocks
using connected sensors. Another use
case is in smarter waste management which can help
in optimized routing of the
garbage and cleaning of garbage can
and properly dumping of them at the manufacturing plant
using IoT devices. Then we have something
known as Internet of energy.
IoT can be employed for improving energy efficiency,
increasing the share of renewable energy and
reducing environmental impacts of energy.
Using IoT devices the energy industry is creating
something known as Internet of energy to
manage energy generation and different energy
resources. Big data analytics
provide grid operators energy producers with real time
energy consumption trends, allowing them to forecast
where and when energy demand of energy consumption will
peak. Direct adjustments in the energy supply
can be done as needed.
These are the allied technologies which
can be used with IoT for making the world greener.
These technologies, along with mathematical algorithms are
making IoT more intuitive and user friendly.
Energy and facility management software based on AI
are being devised as part of green IoT movement
and it is adopting nanotechnology to design smaller nanoscale
devices for improved functionality,
energy efficiency and accuracy while reducing
the size. This is the green IoT lifecycle.
So for any IoT product to become green,
it must go through a closed process,
including green design to green production to
green deployment as well as disposal of
the product should be in a greener way such that it can be
recycled. Green design involves designing cooling
equipment, servers, computers and energy efficient components.
So the sustainability design is the first
initiating point where in greenness should
enter in the lifecycle.
It will be carried forward in different phases of the lifecycle
in producing computers, electronic components and
other associated subsystems and it will
be monitored to keep these electronic items
power usage to a minimum and developing
recyclable electronic equipments so that
whenever they are no longer in use, they can be recycled
accordingly. Then we look at green
in IoT. So how IoT procedures
can be made green. They can be made green by developing
hardware efficient devices.
Efficient software coding can be done. They can
be habitual based, awareness based, policy based as well
as recycling based. So building hardware
which is efficient the design of integrated circuits is
crucial for energy conservation. Green IoT
enhances IoT network architecture by integrating
sensors and processing powers on a single chip
to minimize total infrastructure energy consumption.
Also, the processors based with energy efficiency
can be split into two cores, low computing task
and high computing task and then scheduling framework
can be used to assign tasks to reduce energy consumption.
In case of software,
the software should be built in such a way they
are energy efficient, carbon efficient as well
as they
are energy efficient carbon
efficient and they should be able
to work to optimize the hardware.
We should build our habits in
such a way that we all start thinking
of saving energy in our day to day lives.
Building such habits will build a very
small effect in saving upon energy, but when looked
upon IoT worldwide, it is definitely
going to make an impact and we should
also work on creating awareness about how
we can go green, how we can save energy by building
campaigns or maybe by giving notification
and alerts through phones, through software applications
so that people get a checkpoint on
how they are saving upon energy. And industry
is still building green policies in order
to build standards which are sustainable for companies
to practice. Now, the enabling technologies that
we saw earlier in case of Internet of things like
RFID, wireless, sensor networks, et cetera, they also
need to go green by making use of
recyclable material and smart
algorithms in order to become more sustainable.
So the RFID,
WSN or M two M,
they all need to become more sustainable by making
use of more and more smarter algorithms,
energy harvesting mechanisms and different
scheduling practices. Even the data centers and
the cloud computing should become greener by
making use of virtualization techniques and
nanodata centers that are more energy efficient than
conventional data centers. Now we were
talking about greenness and software. So we should build applications that
are hardware efficient, carbon efficient, energy efficient,
which should at the same time spread carbon awareness and
optimize each step of software development
lifecycle. This can be done using
green coding, low code development and
automated software quality monitoring.
All these depend upon the factors
like choice of language design,
encoding options, AIO models and different software
development techniques. As they all contribute to
developing greener software. The choice of
language again plays a very crucial
role. Whenever we use software, we think that
software do not contribute to carbon emission,
but they do. They do not do it directly,
but as they control the operations of the hard way.
Thus, they are indirectly contributing
in carbon emission. And in fact,
a research was done on different 27
different programming languages and it was
study how much electricity they consumed for ten
different problems. So a software
was built for solving ten different problems using 27
languages and it was studied how many much electricity
was consumed and the speed and memory usage
of each language. And it was
found out that still c comes out as
one of the best language in terms of energy efficiency.
AI models also contribute
in carbon emission as they
are creating and sharing reproducible code.
And it is also helping in developing
generative AI models which can be converted
together, integrated together to build greener coding solutions.
Now, in order to get a reliable software,
it is mass that that software is well tested,
but in the lens of carbon
emission, the test cases that we execute,
they also emit carbon in the environment for
each of the test case being executed,
as it requires cpus to be working
at extra times in order to run the test cases
and generate reports.
So we need to build a clean testing
environment in order to save our environment.
Maybe we can use cloud virtualization techniques
for greener testing process. We can build smart
test selection processes.
Also, we should shift early the
testing process so that in order we get
the bugs early, it will
reduce the cost of running the test cases.
Companies are now building their own green business
model where there is a transformative shift
upon circular economy as compared to the linear
economy which was followed earlier and asset
upcycling. They are also making use
of AI and ML driven energy
analysis to build faster applications
which are more sustainable and which
can draw decisions in keeping energy efficiency
in mind. Now let's look at the principles
that should be followed in order to build greener
solutions and become more and ecologically friendly.
Turn off facilities that are IoT needed so sleep
scheduling can be employed in order to
make the sensors go off to sleep when
not needed. There are two types of sensors, active sensors
and passive sensors. So these sensors can
be activated or they can be put on to sleep accordingly.
Send data that is needed predictive
data delivery definitely helps in
predicting which data is required, and faster
data delivery can be achieved without consuming
more energy. And IoT also helps in minimizing
the length of data path by employing different
smarter routing schemes. There should be
a trade off between processing for communication.
We should start using more greener communication technologies
and machine to machine communications.
We should bank upon more renewable green power sources
like solar energy, wind, thermal, et cetera,
as well as we should raise awareness on lowering
our energy usage by putting checkpoints,
notifications, smart metering on the devices that
we are using. So now let's look
at what is the future of IoT.
As we can see, in future,
IoT will be integrating with
artificial intelligence to build more
intuitive and more smarter solutions. In fact,
IoT devices can be thought of as digital nervous
system, while AI IoT applications
function as the brain of a system.
AI has ingrained into our daily lives nowadays
and even very small devices
like glasses are now having artificial intelligence
to build smarter vision into this. Other future
applications are green social network as
a service unmanned aerial vehicles,
which can be used for machine to machine communications
in drones, which can help in
energy efficient solutions
by having lower flight time, gathering data by
lesser delay. Other applications are green connectivity
data and context aware applications as
well as nanodevices. Green social
network as a service can enhance the system's
energy efficiency, service provisioning
sensor networks, and cloud based wireless
sensor network management.
Now, these are the few points which
we can delve for future research for making IoT
more greener, more sustainability by
building energy harvesting techniques and
low power chipsets.
More radio optimization techniques such as modulation,
optimization or cooperative communication can be
applied to reduce the power consumption of the nodes. Energy efficiency
routing techniques like cluster architectures
or multipath routing can provide efficient solutions.
Leading opinion makers think that the
future pattern of development will be
largely influenced by renewable sources of energy.
Some attach topmost priority to knowledge as
a source and innovation as a force.
With this, we come to an end of my
presentation, which I usually end by saying
this quotation that we should go green. As there is
no planet b, we all should put
in our own bit, which will definitely
be small, but when looked at a larger
scale, cumulatively,
we all can definitely make an impact by
cautiously checking our everyday practices,
our everyday digital transactions,
which all are emitting some
amount of carbon and depleting our
layer of Earth. So let's all join
hands in order to make this planet greener
and safer for our future generations to come.
Thank you. I'm available for any questions.
Thank you for the patient listening.