You. Hi everyone, my name is Swapnil
Deshmukh and I'm the CTO and co founder of Certus
Cybersecurity. Certus Cybersecurity is a security
consulting company and we provide security services to
various Fortune 500 companies. And a common theme
that we have seen across the board is that we have new
terminal logies from a non production network standpoint itself,
such as shift left, where all the security continous are being passed over
to either developers or are being tool based.
And they have a certain set of policies that needs to be adhered to during
the entire code of software defined lifecycle.
And on the other hand, we have traditional
technologies like red teaming exercises that happens in addition to
that. Now there is chaos engineering and there is mitre attacks.
There are apt relevant exercise as well.
So something very narrowly focused than what Mitre would.
And the reason for that exercise itself is to not
be very intrusive from the testing protective itself, but just to
do a pressure test to identify how
vulnerable an infrastructure would be.
And both technologies in itself, in its
own right, are something that we certainly need.
But what we see is that there is a gap when it
comes to communicating from what learnings we have from
shift left perspective, and also the learnings that we have
from our red teaming, or from mitral attacks,
or from chaos engineering itself.
And since there is a gap, the non production tends to
have similar set of issues that gets trickled into production
itself. And all of these attacks
are mostly point in time. And what
that means is that if I do my testing
today, but if you push the code tomorrow
itself, I would not be able to test it because the time has passed from
a testing perspective itself. So all of these engagements are not continuous testings per
se, they are point in time testing. As a result of that,
if after the test has been done, someone pushes a new code
to the production for the things that were already validated in non production
itself, it tends to have these insecurities again passed
over to the production network. As a result of that.
We strongly recommend that people
must be thinking, should be thinking about how can they integrate
continuous feedback between these two silos
that we have non production network and production network, and the testing that happens between
the two from a security standpoint. And that's what we are proposing
from a shift up perspective. So shift up perspective,
we are talking about continuous feedback loop. And that feedback loop
essentially means that the production network, whenever it's
discovering new things from a policy standpoint, that they are updating within
their ecosystem itself should automatically get trickled down into non production
as the policies that they need to enforce as well. And it
could happen in two ways. Either it can have similar infrastructural
and the infrastructure talks to each other from an API
perspective itself, where these policies get pushed and then these
get validated during the non production testing that is performed
through pen testing for example, or could be dynamic testing like
dast for example. So it gets validated there.
If it's application level testing itself,
then the non production learnings that they have would
get trickled down as a policies into the production. So this talking
back and forth itself is what we are proposing.
And we have seen that that has been very, very effective for a few
of the companies that we have worked with in the past.
However, there is a course, there is a journey that company needs
to embark whenever they are thinking about integrating DevOps
or devsecops, or integrating security and compliance
within DevOps pipeline itself. And the journey needs to be first it
needs to be done manually so that you can have a lot of historical
data about all of these policies,
all of the different security controls that one should be considering, and then
looking at those policies and translating that into
either of the networks to
give you an anecdote around it. We had a WAP solution
that these company was using and the VAP was obviously automatically updated
thing the attack trees. So whenever it will identify
that there is a certain set of attacks that is happening, it will look at
what are the new regexes, what are the new
attack patterns that an adversary is trying to attack them with. And it will,
behind the scenes start updating those regex in production
and in the non production itself. They did not have the WAF at any
given point in time. As a result of that, those policies were never getting updated.
However, the application was very resistant against
SQLI injections itself or SQL injections because it
had its own set of rule sets. One fine day they
discovered that Wap was completely misconfigured from
a SQL injection standpoint. As a result of that, an adversary
had passed through into the application layer directly.
Without these, new WAF can directly talk to the application itself
and could have tried to perform SQL.
Now, fortunately, the company had already thought
about it and started integrating that into the application because non
production never had the WAF or the luxury of WAF and testing
always would have found it. But if
you have to set up the shift up properly, then you should
mimic the production network as it's so the WAF should have been
there, then you can perform two set of testings where you have
a test with the WAF and one test without the
WAP. And you can see how resilient your application is
against SQLI by doing that exercise itself. But then by having both
talking same terminology from layer defenses perspective itself,
it becomes very easy for us to perform
more set of testings when it comes to penetration testing itself
and non production. Because even if we take down the run production because
these sqlites up, it doesn't have any impact on production. As a result
of that, all the learnings that we have during that exercise itself and all the
new regexes that it has created, they both should be syncing
together on those regexes. As a result of that, the policies
would be updated on both ends are supposed to be updated in one
there was a company that wasn't doing SQLite properly,
very very big name in telco,
and in this particular company itself they fortunately
had a bug bounty program where we were able to identify a lot of SQLis
by just using this as an attack pattern itself.
So we were able to penetrate into their WAP regex and
directly communicate with it because they never had either shift
up or the continuous feedback from their development team itself
back to these production. So I hope this
concept of integrating chaos engineering and integrating
with the learnings that we have from the production itself into non production and
vice versa in a continuous fashion would help create
a very resilient security system for your
company. Me. And if you have any questions or if you want to
reach out to us, please do not hesitate in reaching out to our
either company which is Certus cybersecurity.com or our
email address is info info@certuscyber.com.