Hello everyone, and welcome to another conformity two talk.
I'm very excited to be presenting to you today and thanks so
much for joining me as I try to tell you how how go taught me
to love building applications again. But first,
a little bit of background about myself. My name is Andrew Williams.
I'm a software engineer author. I've been leader of
various technical teams, and I've been working in open source for the last 20 years.
It's possible that I bumped into you at earlier projects. I've been a
core developer in the maven and enlightenment projects,
including the foundation libraries, which taught me a lot
about widget toolkits and how you can build applications that are efficient.
I founded the fine project when I started being a
Go developer early in 2018,
and I'm now also the CEO at Finelabs, where we build products and
services that help businesses and individuals to get more out of
their applications built with the fine toolkit.
When I'm not developing or hanging out in
open source support channels, I do quite enjoy a bit of
Sci-Fi going to some music concerts
like the Zelda one you see there pictured, or riding
around my garden on a train. Three very different
interests. I wanted to be able to express this in one. So I thought about
asking chatgpt or an OpenAI client if they could come
together in some way. And then I realized it's not really necessary because
Disney World is actually all of those things together,
the happiest place on earth. Now that might be
quite a peculiar segue for something that is about a go
programming talk, but there is a connection. I promise if you've
been to one of those attractions, you'll know that one of the key things about
it is all of the crew in the park come
together as a really great community to give you a fantastic experience.
And I think that has been a huge part of my experience
with the Go programming language is the people around it and the
support that's available for anything that you're trying to do. It's helped shape this
project and hopefully we can give a little bit back through the fine
toolkit and talks like this. But before we dive
into the details, let me do a small background on graphical
application development. The picture that you can see there is
something very early days back in the 1970s. It's a system called
Star, built on the alto from Xerox
ParC. Things have obviously come a long way from there,
and yet at the same times, kind of they haven't.
So this was a little bit before the C programming language, but only
slightly. In fact, most graphical systems that you see
now have a fairly substantial C heritage in
them, which means you're going to have to deal with memory
management and thread handling. And also
these platforms were built before Webb was really popular,
and so it wasn't really baked in. In fact,
when you look at it, if you were to be coding in C like some
of the toolkits are based, they didn't even have a good understanding
of strings, never mind what Unicode and multibyte runes
were going to be. So we've got a lot of things that are kind of
missing because of where they came from. There are modern
alternatives that we can work with. In fact, there's lots of
options available in Go and Rust and JavaScript, but a
lot of these are bindings over old technologies,
which means that you don't have the same learning experience you
don't have, I suppose the idiomatic way that
this all comes together to feel completely obvious to code with.
I think that's one of the main reasons that it seems to be
quite complex to learn application development. Even some
of the best in class platforms, like those from Apple and Google,
are based on a lot of heritage. That means that
you have to know things, or it makes assumptions about your experience,
which is really not ideal at all. And because
they bring a lot of legacy with them, they could be really,
really large to get started with. I saw a hello world example with
a toolkit that I won't name that required you download 10gb
of data, and it took up 40gb on your disk before
you could even write your first line of code.
So really, there's a lot that could be done better here.
And like I said, there are modern alternatives available,
but they are typically platform specific. Companies putting
effort into this space want you to build applications for their platform,
not for everybody's platform at the same time.
And so this sets the scene for an opportunity that
any language or project could come along and fulfill. And I
have found that go does a really good job at filling the gap
there. Why? Well, to start with,
as you all know, you get to write your program once and then it
can compile to run on any device.
Applications are going to just work. The single binary distributions
that we create have no runtime dependencies and, and aren't going to
require any setup for your end users. We're getting
native performance on all platforms at no extra cost. The compiler
is just doing that for us. So the applications are going to run as though
they were hand coded for every single system we
get. The joy of working with a modern programming language with
all the benefits that come with that. The techniques have improved
over the years, and having certain modern standards means we can spend
less time worrying about how we write the code, how we pull it together,
and more time spent actually building the things that we
are looking to create. And all of this, I think,
means that go is providing a great way to lower the barrier of
entry to building graphical applications, just like it does command line applications.
And so we have a new hope for app developers.
And this is where the fine project stepped in. We saw
that opportunity and we thought, there's got to be a way
to make a toolkit that's just as simple to, to build graph collapse as that
which we have for command line apps.
Now, I've got a few photos in here. I think they're all of gophers.
This one certainly is. As you'll know, some of the others might
not be. I'm not so great on understanding the different types of
nature, but hopefully they can provide a pleasant interlude through the
various sections of this talk. So I've told why
it might be good to have this opportunity to build
again. But why would we start a new
open source native app toolkit when there are so many others out there?
Well, for all the reasons before, it's great to have a fresh start and
build on the technologies that are now available.
We wanted to have something that was easy to understand and simple
to contribute to. And that's only possible if you have a completely open
ecosystem, all of the libraries and the supports as well,
to create platform independent native apps like Go and
a couple of other languages are uniquely connected, capable of doing,
and at the same time to deliver natively onto all of these platforms
that are taking lightweight applications and running with really
good performance and looping right back to
the beginning of my introduction there to be community driven, to make
the most of this fantastic group that we have around us to give
back, but also to develop our platform along
with the people that are using it and feeding back their experiences
along the way. And that is the find toolkit.
We aim to deliver the simplest way for
developing beautiful and user friendly native graphical applications for desktop,
mobile and beyond, such as the web and embedded devices
and other things that you might see a fine app running on.
The project, like I said, has been going for around six years now,
which does seem like a very long time, but there's a huge amount of work
here. And with this little graph of GitHub stars
you can see that this is a project that has grown faster than any other
like it, and continues to grow month on month.
Hopefully some folk here haven't heard of it and are excited about the
opportunities, so maybe you'll all go away. Give us a little star and
try out your first project after finishing the video today.
And a fine application is going to work on
all desktop and laptop computers as you'd expect. All of
the targets on of go executable I
suppose. But of course we've got mobile device support
baked in there as well, so your applications can compile to native
iOS and Android devices, and we're delivering over
the web as well. The support there is not quite
100% complete, but it's very close. The next release will take it there,
which will enable your applications to run through the browser if
the user doesn't have a device available to install the software onto.
And like I said, embedded devices are a possibility there as
well. It takes a little bit more code because it doesn't have the traditional
user interactions, but it is possible. And we've seen devices
running with tiny little screens in industrial settings or
kiosks and things like that built off Raspberry PI devices as well.
And so our first hopefully gopher in the wild there says
let's build our first app, we'll get it done in
just a couple of minutes. If you haven't built
a go app before of any kind,
you're first going to need to install a go compiler.
We're working with at least version 1.17, but of course
everybody should be using one more recent than that to get your security updates.
Because we're working with low level graphics and building native
applications, it's going to be necessary to install a c compiler
as well, I'm afraid. Now, if you're a Linux user, there's a good chance
it's there already. If you're on Mac and you have been doing any
application development, you'll already have Xcode installed as well.
Windows users will probably need to go through a little setup for msys two
and Mingwoo. There's more information on our
website if you're having a little bit of trouble getting set up, and if
you're going to be developing with Android, you'll need the libraries downloaded. But onto any
type of computer, it should be possible to run off just
about anything. IOS because of Apple's licensing requires
that you're running on an Apple Mac computer. But of course
when it comes to coding your app, that's not necessary. That's really
just when it comes to the build time so you can get the application binary
prepared for iOS devices. Hopefully that all makes sense.
Like I said, there's more information on the find IO website if you need
to check that out in more detail. But let's go
and start setting up our new project.
Because we're using modules like all good go programs
do, we'll create a new project directory and
then initialize the module in that space,
and then to install the fine code off the web, we'll just
go get fine IO fine V two at
latest. That's going to download the latest released
version of fine, and that's of the V two major version.
As you'll have noticed with some projects go quite rightly
changes the import path if you have a major breaking API change,
which we did a number of years ago, we're trying to keep everything
now within the V two namespace, but that import path is
pretty straightforward to understand. And next we're
going to write some code. I'm going to possibly use
Vim here. Actually, I'm just going to show you the code on screen and avoid
the live code. Other text editors are available, of course, and you might
well choose to use a more substantial development environment
to edit your go. But here is our first fine
application. It's pretty straightforward. We have our
main package because it's an executable. We're going to import
two sub packages of the Find project app
and the widget packages, and do make sure it has v two
in the import path there. It's possible that some systems can auto import
the wrong version. We'll open our main function
and call app new. This is what initializes the
application in memory. It configures everything for the computer that
it's going to be running on and gets all of the internal state
prepared to run a full application. We'll create
a window for that app using new window and
the string that we pass it there. Hello is going to be used in the
title bar if our system has title bars,
typical, I suppose, on a desktop computer, but less so on mobile.
The content of our application is just basically there
inside the setcontent call, as you might
not get any prizes for guessing. That's going to set the content of our
window and we're passing in a new label widget.
All widgets in fine are created with a simple constructor from
the widget package. And so here we'll be creating a label and we're
passing the string hello fine to display in the content area.
Lastly, we call, show and run on the window,
which is a shortcut for showing the window and running the application.
You can have multiple windows, you could show them and hide them separately.
We just need to make sure that our application has a call to run
at some point, usually at the end of the main method, because that's going
to keep running until your application quits. Okay,
so we have written our code. What do we do
next? Well, we want to run it, but we have just
made some new imports. So for good practice
we'll call go mod Tidy in case there's any downloads necessary.
And then we're just going to go run and that is going
to load the window that you see on screen. If it was bigger,
you would see hello written in the title bar, but you can certainly make out
hello fine in the content area. So there you
go. That's the first application written, but we should
probably do something a little bit more substantial because hello fine
isn't really going to excite
you enough, I suppose, to feel that this talk was worth looking at.
Instead, let's look at a markdown editor,
something that we could actually use in our day to day activities.
So I'm going to arrange this as you see on screen, with an adaptive grid
that has an entry for the input and a rich text widget
for the rendering. Now, adaptive grid might be a new term
to you. We use the word adaptive to mean that it will orient according to
the output display. So in this case a
normal window will position left and right the items inside
it. And if you were running in a landscape screen
on a device, it would do the same. But a user rotating,
perhaps their phone or tablet, would arrange the content
appropriately. And to make the application work I'm
going to put together a connection from the entries unchanged
event to the pars markdown function
called in the rich text, so that each time there's a textual change
we then update the output to render it.
Hopefully that makes sense. Let's just look at a little bit of code again.
It's not a massive application. We start out the same
with an extra import here for the container package, which is where
these containers that I mentioned are all stored.
We will start our main function in the same way by opening
an app and then creating a window. And this
time it's the content of the application that is a little more complex.
We'll create a new widget called Edit, and that is a
multi line entry. It has nothing stored in it right now and
it is set to be multi line so that we can write lots of lines
of content. Our second widget there,
which is called preview, is our new rich text widget.
Here I'm using a demonstration that markdown can be passed
into the constructor. So new rich text from Markdown.
You could have any markdown document passed in there,
but we have an empty one to match the content of our entry widget.
And then the next line is the thing that makes the connection every
time the entry is changed. We want
the preview to parse the new markdown. And this works because
unchanged is a function that takes a single string parameter
passing the new content, and parsmarkdown
receives a single string parameter which is expected to be
the markdown content which you're to parse.
Then we set the content of our window to be that new container
that I mentioned. It's an adaptive grid, and we say
that it should have two rows or columns depending
on the way around that it is, and they are the edit and the preview
widgets. So then just again we show and run
that content. Hopefully this time it will
look a little bit more impressive. There we go.
So as you can see, we have our entry where
we're entering markdown on the left, and on the right hand side
we have our rendered markdown. It includes various types
of typeface, some a divider
link, and an image as well, which are all just part of the rich text
widget and the markdown parser built into. Fine, I could leave that
there. It's a pretty cool application and something that you might choose
to use or build on yourself. But before we move
on, let me show you that the same code, exactly the
same code, can be used to build a mobile application
instead. And this is in fact that same application
running in the iPhone simulator, it's gone into light
mode because that's the default for iOS. Whereas before I was on my desktop
where I prefer a dark mode setup, and here we have very
similar content on the left, and it's been rendered on
the right hand side, as you would expect. But as I
promised before, we can rotate the device
and have that adaptive grid change the orientation.
So if we were actually utilizing a portrait
mode, we would still be able to interact with the application rather
than having it squeezed up with a central divider.
Excellent. So that is our application running,
but there's a lot more of course to building an application than simply
writing some code and running it. So let's move
on there to testing and distribution.
The first thing I wanted to touch on is unit testing, which has
typically been quite difficult with a graphical application.
But this is going to be really a lot easier. I mean
go has unit test support baked right in. You can see here the steps we're
going to run. We'll edit some code and then we'll just run the
test runner and see the output. So let's have a
quick look at the unit test here. The imports are slightly different
and we're happy to be running in a test package. Seems like best
practice there as well. I'm using the assert package which I find
to be very helpful with my test assertions. And I'm
also importing a test package from fine. So let's see why this
is useful. We open a new test function
and for this I'm going to test the selected text of an entry.
So I'm creating a new entry widget and then I'm going
to simulate the user typing some content
into this entry using our test package. So we call type
and say that the hello string should be typed into the entry.
And then we check that the text content is in
fact hello. This test is going to pass.
Then we could use another function of the test package called double tap.
And that as you might guess is going to simulate the user
having tap twice in the content quickly, which should select
the word underneath where the tap
event happened. And here it is,
the general area. We don't specify
the coordinates specifically because that is the full
content that the selected text is equal
to. Hello. And also we can check that
the cursor column has moved to the end so
we can run that like a regular unit test. And it's not going to pop
up windows on screen, it's not going to grab our keyboard focus.
The test runner is able to completely execute
a fine application in memory without requiring those
input and output devices. So they run really fast as well.
But let's move on to packaging your application.
There's a really helpful command line tool also called fine.
You can get it by calling Go install, you pass
it this URL fine IO fine v two CMD
fine at latest. It's always a good idea
to have this tool at the same version of the library that you're installing and
that is going to help us with our local packaging
of a graphical app. I mentioned that we build single binaries like
Anygo, but graphical apps on some platforms expect
more metadata or bundling to be present.
So instead of just go build we can now call
find package and that is going to create just the right type
of artifact for our platform. So if
I was running that on my Mac, it would create
a app bundle which I could then drag into the applications folder.
If it was windows it would be a exe as you'd expect, but with the
icon and other metadata embedded. Now as a developer,
often what I want to do is compile the app that I've been building on
and just use it locally. So we have a tool for that as well.
It's just fine install. If you do that and then
go to your application launcher like I've done here, you can search for your application
and it will be registered and installed. But like
normal on the Mac, it's simply in the applications directory.
For your Windows computer. It would be in the start menu and
somewhere in the program files. That's great. I've got
it on my local computer, but I want to do more. I want to get
this out to other people. So we also
have as go would have you expect, the ability
to cross compile to other systems. So here I could build my
Windows executable from whatever platform I'm currently
running on. Or as I showed earlier,
we could have a mobile app built in the same way with
the OS specified as Android or iOS.
There's a little bit more data needing to be passed in here because
the sandboxes on mobile platforms require to have some
unique identifiers called the app id. So we pass one of those in
and you can see a screenshot here how your iOS
group could look like if you installed a few fine applications using those tools.
Now I mentioned earlier, you do need some c compiler
installation for this to work. And the cross compiling is no different.
It can be a little bit complicated to manage. And if you would
prefer not to, or if you're having any trouble, then you should check out the
find cross tool that's going to manage all of this
for you. In containers that are going to bundle
the developer tools, it will launch the container,
do the compile, close the instance down and provide you
with output files. And so here
you can see the different files that you might have available.
For our project, we created main go already.
We had the go mod file and I dropped an icon Png in there to
be used for the application metadata. And on the second row
of icons there you can see I have my Android app, the APK,
the macOS app, and the Windows
app, which is a Exe, and I could share those with anybody I wanted
to across the network, uploading to the Internet, or just downloading it onto
their phones when they come around for dinner. So we've packaged our
applications, but how do we get them further afield?
Well, the find app is also going to be able to help you
with that. We have a release sub command which is
aiming to help you get your applications up to the
stores and marketplaces. So here a quick example.
I'm releasing my app with a specific app id. I think
this command would typically be used on Linux where there's not a standard
store. So it's going to bundle up the artifacts ready to be
distributed in whichever manner for iOS
there is of course a standard store. In fact, most geographies, it's the
only store. And you would upload that by
having an Apple account and getting a profile and a certificate
distributed to you signed by them.
You'll download that locally and then using this release command, you can
build the app bundle with the appropriate signing and
it will actually create a slightly different type of, of file output.
And you will then install that to the, upload that to the store by dragging
it into Apple's transporter app. It's similar.
Again, we want to release for the Android OS. We're going to
tell it the key store that's available, which is a Java key store which you
can either set up yourself or download from Google's
Play Store, I think. And once you've signed that, then you'll be
able to just upload your new aPk by dragging it
into the browser window when you're configuring the app to be distributed
through their website. Now, there's a lot of parameters here
that I have discussed. It can get confusing.
So we added a new file called Findapp Toml,
which is a simple text markup. And as you can see here,
we have got various standard parameters that allow you
to write them once save it into your source control
so you don't have to remember what all of those parameters are.
And we'll also auto increment some of those numbers when the release
process is executing. Whoa. Okay. So hopefully
that has helped to show how you can get the
tools installed, write some code, and create an application all the way out to the
store. But of course we didn't see too much of the app
toolkit itself. So let's explore that a little bit
further. So there is a find demo application
that you can run and that shows the various things available.
And we'll start here with graphical capabilities.
You can draw, as you would expect, lines,
rectangles and rounded rectangles, circles.
We also have text, of course, different types of gradients
and also images. We have both vector images
and raster images. And all of those graphical
elements are what are pulled together to make everything that you see
on screen, and also they are optimized
to make the most of your graphics card. So we use OpenGL
and various hardware acceleration capabilities to make sure it's always super
fast. Also, if you tap down to the
theme icons, you'll see that we have them bundled
into the applications so you can have standard icon capabilities
in your app that people will recognize, so you don't have to worry about that.
And also we have the light and dark theme that you've seen both of already,
the toolkit. So your application is going to blend in with the desktop
or the mobile that it is running on.
So also of course, as you might expect from a widget toolkit,
there's lots of widgets available. I've grouped this into basic
widgets like the label which you have seen. We have buttons that can
have an icon as well as text progress bars. There's a
card for grouping items together, and also the rich text
that you have seen which supports markdown as well.
And there are a few other things like a toolbar,
text grid and accordion item separators.
All sorts of things there that help to display information to
your user or arrange or group items on your screen.
Then we have input the types of things that you might want
for building forms or getting data from your users.
A password entry where you can hide and show the content,
sliders for inputting a range of values, a checkbox,
radio item. They both come in group forms as well,
and a select like a dropdown. There's also an editable
select. We can have an entire form as
well. And that means it's possible
to get all sorts of different kinds of data input into your application,
again using just standard widgets. And these could pack into a
form as well in whatever combination you're looking for.
Those are all quite straightforward. You know, one line shows you one item
on screen pretty much, but then you add a
little desire to show lots of data,
something where you need to scroll very fast through
lots of things like your tweets or your email inbox.
So we added the type of widget called collection. Now,
there's actually a few of them, but here I'm illustrating with
list. We're using a few callbacks that mean that
we as the toolkit can take
minimal data and display only what is necessary on screen at
any point in time. So it's very quick and you can scroll through
hundreds of thousands of items with no slowdown in your application.
For the list with these three items, the first function is asking
how many items are there so we know how long to make the scroll bar.
The second callback which is here creating a new label
is creating the template object and this is what's going to be reused
each time a new item needs to be displayed on screen.
The last callback is called the update callback and
that says for a certain item id and
a reusable object, make sure that the right data is displayed
and so we will call the last one quite a lot. As you scroll
through creation, the template object creation
doesn't get called much because that's a lot slower. So with this way we
can support really fast user interface with lots of data.
And like I said, there's a few of them. So you could see we also
have table and tree and also the grid wrap.
Thinking of things like file
browser where you've got lots and lots of files but not necessarily lists but
displaying them as icons in sort of square areas instead.
Lastly, if you want to put more complex
applications together, you're probably going to look for various types of
containers that help to move items or position them in screen
with potentially some interaction. Here we have the
horizontal split in code, but there's a vertical split as well and that allows
your user to move the space allocation
around the user interface. We have app tabs
which allows you to have different areas of the application separated behind tabs,
and also a version of that called doc tabs, more suitable for managing
documentation, different documents and you can add
them and close tabs away when you're done with those documents.
Also you could have a scroll around just about any content if you want to
have your window be smaller than the content that is currently
visible. What I've showed you so far, the content was basically
keeping the user interface open. The default window
size is so that all of the items can be visible at the same time.
And so scroll can help us to shrink that down a little bit.
But a container can have any layout that you want.
You can just say container new and pass it a layout and then the
objects that it should be responsible for. And that
layout could be anything. You can implement the layer interface
which simply says how big should something be at its minimum
and what do you do to lay things out internally?
But the last two illustrations there, the darker colored
one there is the border, but the second is lots of different layouts
in different containers brought together. So you can see how it's possible
to build up a complex application with the basic
functionality that I've already showed you. There are various
other common activities in a graphical application that you
might be familiar with the dialogues, things that we might want
to be displaying to our users on a fairly like
a confirmation dialogue. Are you confirming this
next step? We could have our input,
we could display information,
or we could have the need for a color to be chosen.
All pretty standard ways that we might ask users for information.
And these are all provided through the dialogues package in find.
Lastly, there is also the file dialog. You can
open files and save files. This is where things get a little
bit more complex because a file is actually not
such a concrete thing as you might imagine. Like a color. We can
pick a color, but when we're looking for file input,
it may not be a specific file on the system that we're looking for.
So working with files in a platform agnostic
way is a little more complex. So I wanted to show you this
illustration about how we can open a file
with the dialogue package we'll call show file open and
in a similar way to the collection widgets,
we use callbacks here instead of a standard constructor.
Our callback is going to be executed when the user has made
their choice, and so we have some checks to make in our code here.
Firstly, we ask if there was an error. Did something go wrong when
they were picking their file? If so, we'll show an error.
Also, it's possible they pick nothing, in which case the reader to
the file would be nil. So we will return then as well.
The rest of this is handling what we should do with the file that we
were passed. Now you'll notice the parameter is a
URI read closer. It's not a file at all.
It's like a reader, in fact. So we will use ioutil or the
replacement in the IO package to read all of the content into our
variable data. If there was no error,
then we will make sure that the file is closed when we're done, or rather
the stream of data. We will set the text of our
entry widget for this illustration to the content of the data. So we've essentially
opened a text file and dumped it to screen as this is
a URI read closer. We have an additional function on top
of the standard readcloser functionality, the ability to get its
URI, that is the universal resource identifier,
I think. So by doing that we can find out
where this data came from. It might be a file path like you have
seen in, I suppose, file based
access in a web browser. If you've built your web server, you'll be familiar with
it. It could be a remote source on an HTTP
server. So you might look at that and find it's a URL
inside it, or it could be something completely different
based on the data provider that's available on the current
system. Of course if something went wrong, we'll show an error again,
and that is all passed into the show file open. And we
also tell it which window to display the dialog in,
because in fine, minimizing the number of windows open
is desirable. And so we display dialogues inside a window
rather than separate to them. So I showed you before
that it can create a file open dialogue
like that, relatively familiar, and we're looking at files,
but we won't always be looking at files. And this is why it's important to
not assume that there is a file there. Here I've just
opened the same code on an iOS app, a fine based iOS
app, and it has allowed me to pick files based on what's
available on the current system. You might notice that this is
a standard picker from iOS and it's allowing me to access
data from the web through iCloud.
Equally, I could use that for importing data from other applications
like Dropbox or my gallery app, and in those situations
it's actually going to be streaming data directly from one app to another.
And so there was no file there at all, which is why this is so
much more flexible. And you should consider taking this pattern if you're working
with files in your application. Goodness,
this has been a bit of a fly through. Apologies for there's just so much
to cover, but there are so many things I didn't manage to show you.
You can have a main menu in your window, you could have a system
tray if you're running on a desktop based runtime
and that code is still the same code
running in your application, you just do a runtime check to see that it is.
In fact, you can use data binding as well. This is a
slightly more advanced topic, but it means that you can have your data source
separate from your user interface code, and you will be able to wire
those together with our data binding package that
uses events and a two way data binding model so they can
stay in sync without having to depend on one another.
And as you saw earlier, there is the find demo app that covers a huge
amount of the things that you can see, and probably
all of the functionality is demonstrated in there at some place,
but that's the standard toolkit. We also have
a great community out there that are contributing their own work as
well. The ability, because of Go's packaging system
to just import an external source and call
the constructor it makes available and we'll have a widget in our UI.
It's going to work just like any other widget. So here
I've just used the Find X package,
which is the community contributions to the find project,
to create a new map widget. And then I display that in my window and
I have a map. Similarly, there's a terminal.
You can drop a full blown terminal into any find based application
by using the terminal package, which is one of the fine repositories.
And it's just there another widget in your application.
So many possibilities here, it's just impossible to cover
them all. Hopefully. This looks like a
joyous thing that I was demonstrating. It's just so easy to get started.
In fact, hundreds, in fact hundreds of thousands of people
have given this a go and built applications of their own.
There's a number of open source projects that you can absolutely check out.
If you go to apps find IO, you can find some of these fantastic
applications out there. Terminals, games,
music players, chat apps, notes, all sorts of things.
If you're wondering where to get started or how you might build
something, it's a great place to look because all of these applications are
open source and well coded to describe how the application is
put together. At Finelabs we are working on
an app builder, so you don't even have to do the coding. You can
drop into a project and visually put your application together.
You can find out more and sign up to be a tester at fission app
if that is interesting to you. But of course it doesn't
have to stop at a single application. You could,
if you wanted, go bigger. And in fact the community has done
just that. There is a desktop environment called Find Desk
that is part of the Phishos distribution, which is a Linux
based operating system where all of the applications are fine applications.
You can see a whole load of them on screen there, like the chess game,
text edit calculator. And in fact an application for
managing your applications, all written using the technology that you've
seen in this presentation. And of course we have a
lovely login manager as well to complete the look.
Indeed, you can see we're running on that system now with virtual
desktops and a little terminal at the top.
There's all sorts of things that you could do with this,
including an integration with that application
editor that I mentioned earlier. There we can
see the calculator app for example.
Hopefully that has inspired you to check it out,
have a go and build something that you can imagine but haven't
figured out how to code. If you'd like to learn more,
then just feel free to jump right in. We've got a load of documentation
at docs find IO or if you prefer video. We've got
a find IO YouTube channel with plenty of tutorials and
demonstrations. If you prefer to read
books, then you can check out building cross platform GUI applications
with fine. That's published by Pact and available on Amazon and
in Barnes and Noble and good booksellers everywhere.
I'd really appreciate it if you would leave a review of the
book if you enjoy it. Of course, this project
would not be possible without the contributions of everybody who's been involved
over the years. We have a fantastic team, but of course we're always grateful
to welcome new people in. Whether you're interested in coding,
testing, writing, documentation, or helping us with the design,
the sites, anything that you see, it's all open source. You can get started wherever
you'd like and it's hosted at our GitHub organization,
starting with of course, the main library, which is
in the fine repository. It would be lovely if you
wanted to support our work through sponsorship. Do check out the URL.
We've got so many amazing sponsors that have contributed over the years,
but it's not just monetary. If you can help
us in any way, do reach out and just
help to be part of the future of this project. Thank you
so much everyone. I hope that you've enjoyed this talk, and I also
hope that you enjoy the rest of Comp 42. Have a fantastic day
and hopefully I'll see you at another event sometime.