Hello there. Welcome to the Conf 42
Rust Lang two conference. My name is Atmaram
and I am going to talk on the topic of journey of journey
programming language written in rust by tester.
None other than me. There are so many programming
languages out there, yet I felt need of writing another one
just for testing and I am going to talk about all my experiences
in writing this language in rust.
About me I am an occasional speaker. I talk
at multiple conferences. I am blogger. I write lot
of blogs about testing and systems engineering. I am passionate
programmer. I like writing code, writing good code.
I'm tester by profession. I do testing for
earning money. I am open source contributor.
I occasionally write on Twitter with the Twitter handle atmnk
nine. Don't forget to subscribe and I work at Sedin Technologies
as test manager. So I am going to walk you
through the agenda of this topic. I am going to
talk about the idea of journey programming language first. Then I'm
going to quickly show you the demo of how journey programming language
works with its quick application to sample application.
Then I'm going to talk about how it came into existence
into various phases, how it started as a
pet project in Java, then in between how I felt
need of writing the same tool in different programming language.
Then I will talk about how I chose the rust for
writing this tool. Then I will talk about
how I created a project plan and how that project plan
worked. Then throughout this journey of writing tool,
how different features came into existence, got added and
some of the feature got removed. Then I will talk about my experiences
with Rust while writing this tool and I will show you
an extended demo of the same tool and I will
show you some rust code as well where this tool is written
and I will conclude my talk. So let's
talk about the idea of journey programming language.
While I was doing testing, I felt a need of
some tool. Why? Because I was doing
so many mundane activities and routine activities repetitively,
I failed need for automating those repetitive
activities. I felt there should be some tool where I can automate
these activities as command. To elaborate
more on this idea, what I failed was
I should be able to quickly create commands for multiple or
repetitive use. The command should be parameterized
means I should be able to invoke same command with multiple different
values while running the command. If the tool doesn't
know specific value, the tool should ask invoker of the
command. The specific values and these commands could be created
for multiple tasks or automating multiple activities like test data
creation or creation of mock server. So that was
all idea and I will show you how this idea came into existence
with a demo. I'm going to show you a quick demo
of core compiler which has programming abilities.
Program which core compiler requires can be written in journey
programming language which is an open source tool.
So what I am going to do is I am going to
switch to the postman. So I have created one server called
as a to do server, our goto application for
doing pet projects. Right. This to do server has
rest APIs. So if you see the post
method in this postman has
localhost 9001 as an address.
Now if I send a post request with
a title bring milk, what happens?
It creates a to do with a title bring milk.
It gives it an id one and it sets its
status as done as false. I can
create one more to do bring eggs
and it created one more to do. I can get all
to dos using get method. So it gave
me both the to dos bring milk and bring eggs.
I can get a single to do like I need to provide
the id of the to do. So I provided id as one
and it gave me to do with id one which has title bring
milk. So this is a sample application. Now I
am going to show you while testing this application you will need to create so
many data and all right what you can do with the tool
which I have created. So I am going to
go into the terminal now. Let's try to
create a to do. So what I'm going to do is I'm going to run
a command car, run create to
do. Now if you see this command ran and
this command is stuck at something, it's asking me please enter
value for title of type catering so I can say
bring vegetables. And it said
it has done executing journey.
Now let me see on postman whether
this to do was created or not. So I'll say get all to dos
and it has created a to do bring vegetables.
That was the same to do that we created right over here on
terminal, bring vegetables.
Now to get all to dos I needed
to go to postman, right? But same can be done with the command
which I have created. What I am going to do is get
all to dos. Now if I run this
command, it is giving me all the to dos.
If you see the response is a string which
has to do with title, bring milk, bring eggs
and bring vegetables. Now this is not what
just the tool can do. I'm going to show you one more
command, create multiple to dos.
Now I want to create multiple to dos. Now how many to dos
I want to create this is what tool is asking. Please enter value of to
dos to create length. Now I'm
going to give let's say I want to create twelve to dos.
Now the tool is asking do you want random to do names?
And the value which is asked is of type boolean.
Do I want random to do names? Let's say yes and it
said it's done executing the journey. Now let's
get all to dos. Now you
will see all to dos are over here.
Whatever to dos these random to dos with random title were
created. This is what tool can do.
Now you must be wondering that is this tool
just coded for to dos? No. In fact get all to dos
create to do. These are all scripted. You can
create multiple commands like this in the tool,
how to script this and all. I'm going to show you in an extended
demo. So let's switch back to the presentation.
Now I am going to talk about how this idea started. It started
with a lazy tester who wanted
to automate mundane activities. Now this tester
initially started this project with plain Java.
Initial pilot was started with the java the tool which you
see right now. The same tool was written in Java
at the right hand side over here if you see there is a screenshot
attached for how you going to create the commands.
The entire tool was config driven right hand side. Whatever you see
is just a config for creating commands.
You needed to create folders and files in specific structure.
All control structures were config driven. If you see all the
control structures like block post all this info were
config driven. It was highly designed on a specific
convention that needed to be followed. Like you need to understand the convention
with which these configurations to be created.
To run a tool you needed to have specific version of Java and tool was
bundled as a jar. It was used for real project
as a productivity tool. So my past organization, in my past project
I have used this Java based tool for creating
multiple commands, productivity commands. Now what was
the overall feedback? So I spread this tool across my
colleagues and they started using this.
And what was their feedback? They said the idea is really good
tool like this simplifies lot of mundane activities but
for creating actual command it is bit difficult and creator
need to understand lot of convention followed.
Also the tool has a dependency on specific version of
Java and user needs to install Java. The tool is
restrictive in terms of possibilities that can be done with it.
So overall the feedback was this guy over at
the right hand side saying then I felt I need to write
this tool in a different programming language. Why? Because we
need a language which can produce native tools. So I discarded Java.
Not to bash Java. Java is useful in many places,
but for this tool Java was not useful. Then I charted
down what are the different needs from the programming language that
I am being to write this tool in. So I said language
should be able to produce cross platform executables
because I needed a native binaries and I was intending
to distribute this tool across Mac, Windows and Debian OS.
So I needed a language which can produce cross
platform executables. Language should be memory safe
since tool is going to be highly programmable because
we are going to write so I discarded the approach of config driven commands,
rather I took the approach of code driven commands.
So we are going to write a programming language or a domain specific language
and as it is going to be highly programmable,
the language in which we are going to code. This should be memory
safe. Language should cater to high concurrency needs
since tool can be further adapted for writing mock servers
and load test because we are going to write mock servers which could be invoked
with high concurrency and load tests with high concurrency.
So language should cater to the high concurrency demand
ecosystem around. Language should have ready made libraries for creating
CLI tools. As you saw in the demo, we were invoking entire tool
with the command line arguments, so we needed to create a CLI
parsers and all language should be systems programming
language since tool may be further extended for lower level programmability.
Language should have low or no GC footprint since tool will
be further extended for load testing because in
load testing every user's interaction matters,
right? So it should have low or no GC footprint
and language should be typesafe. So based on
this, I evaluated three systems programming
language, C plus plus, Rust and Go. At that time,
both all C plus plus, rust and Go are systems programming
language. They can produce native binaries and they can support
very high concurrencies and they have libraries for building
CLI tools. Everything was same for all, chose three languages
up till here. But when it comes to memory safety,
memory safety is not a language feature and is programmer's job in
case of C. In case of Rust,
Rust is a memory safe language and memory safety is
forced on a programmer. In case of Go is
also memory safe, but it's not forced on a programmer and programmer
can choose to escape memory safety. When it comes
to C. C has no GC footprint and memory management is
pure programmer's job when it comes to rust. It has
no GC footprint and rust forces memory management via borrow
checker when it comes to go. Go has a
little bit of garbage collector which periodically scans heap
for unused objects. So when I
compared the need with the languages and the three languages,
I thought like Rust will be matching most of the needs.
I never knew how to write code in rust.
I was new to the rust, but I still took that challenge
and I started writing this tool in Rust. The lovely
rust. Rust is called as the most loud programming language.
I have heard this statement about Rust that
Rust takes its type safety on steroids. Like you can't
escape rust type safety. The code won't even compile
if it is not type safe. And there was one exaggerated
statement I had about trust that if your code compiles
it will less likely have any issues. Like even to get your
code into the compile state you need to fight lot with the compiler.
That's what I have heard about trust. Although it is an exaggerated
statement. Your code may still have functional issues and other issues,
but you will have some sort of assurance if your code compiles then
I created a project plan for this entire project. I designed
the architecture which you can see on the right hand side. All the green
boxes over here are the code blocks.
All the blue boxes over here are the compilers and tools which
I use for creating this project, and the black boxes
which you see are the binaries which are produced. The pink box
over here is a small plugin that I created, and the red box over
here is an intellij idea for which this plugin was created.
This entire tool was written in rust programming
language, although there was some one more project
where I created a plugin for this tool
in a Kotlin programming language. But wool tool
is written in rust programming language.
The plugin which I was talking about is an intellij
plugin which can be used with Intellij idea.
So that Intellij idea understand this journey programming language
and it provides intelligence around its syntaxes
and other stuff. So in the project plan I designed
and created architecture of this entire project.
Writing unit integration and end to end test were necessary
for this project because this was going to be an open source
project and I may sometime have time or sometime
may not have time and if there is a need for any feature
then I should be quickly able to tweak the code with
getting lot of backlog that I have lost my
touch with the code. So I should be quickly run the test to
verify whether I am not breaking anything. Creating Intellij
idea plugin for adoption of language was
also necessary. Adding more features as
and when required was also necessary. Evaluating existing
open source libraries for not reinventing the wheel like
in the entire progress of this writing,
this tool, I used so many libraries which I am going to talk about
so that I don't need to write so many code, custom code by myself.
This was a project plan that I had. I'm talking
about the designing and architecture of this project. This project
was built into four different components.
There were three rust crates that were created
which was one of those was server, other was compiler and
other one was library and there was separate project for Intellij plugin
which was Kotlin Brace project. The server which I called
Cors was a websocket based server which can be interacted
with. It can be integrated with any messaging application.
So the tool which you were seeing, the commands which were invoking on
item or command line can be invoked from any messaging
application. The compiler or the core compiler
that compiles project and creates distributable package which can be
used with servers and other was also one of
the crate and most meaty part of this code was
a library that has most meaty parsing and execution logic which can
be reused in server and compiler. And the plugin was an intellij
plugin to provide intelligence around syntax of the language
and I needed to write unit integration and end to end test as a safety
net throughout this project progressed.
This project started as a tool for test data
creation by invoking rest APIs, but it saw
lot of demand for the features. Like one of my employer
asked me to add a feature of service virtualization because the
product which we were testing had integrations with lot of third party
systems and those third party systems were not providing good sandboxes.
So we almost automated like ten plus third
party systems. We service virtualized those ten plus third party
systems with this tool with the added feature of service virtualization.
I also added feature of test data creation directly into DB. So you
saw I was creating test data using rEst APIs, but I
can create test data directly into the DB using the tool as
well. Then one of my employer was
testing websocket based servers. While I was
researching for any ready made tools for load testing websocket
based server, there were some tools but they were not handling
event loops properly because I used Tokyo in this project
which was already having event loop. So I just needed to spawn
the scripts in a load test manner. So load
test feature also got added into this tool. Then later
on I removed cores which is a server component
which can be reintroduced later because it had low
adoption, many people were not using it.
I added CI CD pipeline to automatically create platform specific
installables like Homebu, formula, windows installers
and debian installers. And all these installers are being used because some
of the folks from the teams were using Windows machines, some of the
folks from the team were using Linux machine and some of the folks from
the team were using Mac machines. Now throughout this
all writing journey of this tool I had
really good experiences with Rust. I had initial typical
struggles of fighting with Rust compiler for code to compile
entire async ecosystem in rust is highly customizable.
Crates like Tokyo, Asyncrate, Norm, Clap Sud were highly
used needed to use nightly since many
language features and libraries used require nightly features.
Some libraries were either nonexistent or were not
in mature state. So I needed to create quick and dirty reusable
libraries like async, rdbc, etc.
Every time a code that was compiled was rewarding since
it used to ensure something working has been reproduced.
Writing unit integration and end to end test provided necessary
safety net to modify features regularly without being anything
so I can carelessly tweak the features
and unit integration and e two e test used to give me enough
safety net that I am not breaking anything because there were already
users using this tool. I got all answers in community forums
and on community discord server when was stuck.
I used different libraries while coding for this tool.
Like a norm for creating parsers and ast I used
Tokyo as an asynchronous runtime.
I used hypher for low level servers, I used
cert and cert JSon for serialization and deserialization.
The clap library came handy for cli parser futures
and futures utils for some readymade futures features.
With async code there is this very good trade called async
trade for lot of async code with trades. I use
async recursion as well because at some places I needed to write recursive
code in async blocks. I use fake library
for writing some fake data generators. I use Mokito as well
for creating test doubles for test and I use many more other libraries.
Now we will see the extended demo of this
tool. So you must be wondering like
how this code is written,
right? So let me show you the code which
is creating a to do. This is very small
chose which is just eight lines of code. You can see
I have a create to do which is parameterized
which has title. I am calling post request.
So if you see this looks like a programming language, you can see the syntax
highlighting as well. Post request I can pass URL text this text
is like a text template. I can pass. I can provide variables as well over
here with body object title title.
Now if you see over here, title is nowhere,
nowhere asked for or nowhere coded. So this tool
uses a principle of correlation. Whatever is not known it will
ask the user. So I'll show you quickly what
I mean by that. So when I say chose run
create to do what is actually happening is
it is looking for title within a code
within its existing runtime. While this script is running,
it didn't find title so it asked user please enter
a value for title of type string. I can say
bring tomatoes and it ran
the journey. Similarly,
when I am calling get all to Dos, you will see I'm calling a
get request with URL text like this. Now here
you will see there is one more correlation happening matching body
object result. So this tool has ability to capture response
from the rest APIs as well. So if you see get request
is done over here. But this additional clause
matching body object result will capture the
response in the variable result. And here we are printing text
template result. So if you see I have used text template
with a variable result. So if I say get
all to Dos, let's see what happens. Get all
to Dos, you will
see this code ran get request. It stored the
response in result and it printed the result as
a single line. You can see this code is
just six lines of code and it can produce tremendous results.
Now let's talk about get single
to do. Okay? Before going showing you
the script, I will just run get single to
do. Now it is asking please
enter value for Id of type positive integer. Like what is
the id of the to do? If I say id is three,
it gave me the to do with id three. Now let's see, what is the
script written for this? So you'll see it is calling a
get request. And as we said like this is a
text template where we are passing id as a parameter
and we are declaring that the id should be positive integer.
So while you saw it asked me please enter value of Id
of type positive integer. So let's call
the same script and let's see if I provide text
instead of integer. It says that invalid
value. Please enter value of type positive integer, right? So if
I say, let's say ten, it gave me to
do with id ten. Now you are seeing
all this is happening on a server, right? Like to do server.
In fact this entire to do server is also written in the journey
programming language. You can see how we can do service virtualization.
So you can see here what we are doing is we are listening on
9001 with these scriptlets
like we are saying on post with URL. This is again text template matching
request body object title. So we are capturing variable
title from body object and we are
creating a to do object. We are pushing it into the
temporary variable to Dos and we are responding with status
20 one and body object to do. So. This is like a dynamic
service virtualization that we did for entire to do server. In fact we
wrote entire to do server in this programming
language. Similarly, when I say get all so
I am just returning all the to DoS like respond
with status 200 and body object to DoS.
When I am asking for single to do. I have this
text URL as a parameterized id as
a positive integer. So it will automatically grab
from the URL the number and it will
assign id variable that value. The resultant
status is 404 and resultant body is to do
not found. If this loop doesn't succeed then
this value will be remaining as it is. So you will see on the for
loop what we are doing is we are searching for that to
DoS for. So this variable is iterated and item
Id is compared with this id. Now once this
id is found then we are setting response
body as item and response status as 200 and we are
responding with a status r status and a body object
r body. So this is how we did entire service virtualization.
In case you are interested to have a look at the code of
the server. So this is purely written in rust.
As I said, there are three major crates which are written
over here. One was deleted, course is deleted. So we
have only two now. Chose and Corlin, I have examples over
here and playground over here like playground.
I created just for testing the scripts actually.
But if I say chose,
if I say cargo test,
it will run all my test. The entire project is test
driven and you will see all the code written
over here has followed the rest structure.
We are writing library in journey
states, steps and all. So you have
seen like this has passed so many test cases.
263 test cases are passed.
So this was all about a presentation.
Now I'm being to conclude my talk with this demo. Overall,
writing a programming language in rust was a very rewarding experience.
The tool created and a programming language created has
been used by my past employers and present for service virtualization
test data creation load testing, hence it had a very well adoption
as well. The whole rust ecosystem is a great place for experiments,
tools and projects like this. The feared learning curve with
Rust had a minimal impact as the
programming settles. With Rust, it feels more rewarding to
create great code than initial struggle of fighting with language.
No wonder why Rust is called most loud programming language
and I consider journey programming language is as one of
my best work and I feel really proud about creating something
that is useful using Rust.
I convey my sincere thanks for free peak and canva
for all graphics for this illustration. I am thankful to confortito
for opportunity to present and entire rust community for
awesome support and ecosystem. Thank you.