Good evening. My name is Giulio Vienne and today I will
talk about the continuous stream of patches to update our
systems, how it impacts the technological value streams,
and its relation to what is known as technical debt.
Today we leave a change in information technology that
impacts more than security packs,
development, deployment and operations. In other
words, the entire devsecops pipeline.
Critical vulnerabilities are no more a rare
event. Every day a new vulnerability is
discovered in some component part of our systems,
so much that people are waiting for the next major event
to happen this month, December 2022.
Vulnerabilities are limited to the operating systems,
to code written in CE or in assembly. They are
found in all languages and platforms,
and the traditional monthly patching is not enough anymore.
What happens is not developers fault.
Security is a hard problem and tooling is constantly
catching up with new problems.
If it is not developers fault,
clearly this cannot be classified as technical debt,
can it? I hope to convince you
that we enter a new era where we must take into account
the entire application environment.
In the past, with a slow pace of change,
we were able to reckon this work of continuous
update as technical depth.
But today we must bring into the light
and put a different label on it has
jungle savages barbarian may elicit some
smile, but won't help a conversation with engineering,
management and businesses I
organize the content in three moments. In the first section,
I'll focus on the frequency of updates for our system and
applications. In the second part, I propose
some definition for continuous updating that may
help in discussing with management and planning.
Finally, in the third and final section, I will
hint at the engineering behind continuous
updating, what current tools offers and their limits
let's start our journey exploring the current landscape
of updates and patches, a simple
but not simplistic description of any execution environment.
Consider three layers, the operating systems, the application stack,
and the libraries. The operating system is your Linux distribution,
the docker base image and the Windows
installation. Whatever the application stack or runtime
is your node JS interpreter, the Java runtime engine,
the net runtime, the DLL or
shared objects linked to your c executable, and so
on, so forth. Clearly this could be part also of
a docker image, and finally the libraries that may
be statically or linked to your executable.
Some languages like go, they embed the runtime,
the final executable. The runtime version
is so tied to the compiler and linker version.
Each layer has its own independent sources of
updated and patches. Depending on your
architecture and deployment mechanism, each layer
can be updated independently from the others or
they are bundled together in a single deployment unit.
I spent some time researching these sources
of patches, how frequently each layer receives and
updates,
analyzing public repositories and sources.
I found this data for operating systems.
In average, we got patches for the operating systems
every three or four weeks.
Moving to the next layer application runtimes we
can observe more spread between different sources of
data and patches. We must not be deceived
by major or minor releases. The frequency of patches
is substantially higher. It ranges from a
bi weekly patches for the most commonly
used client runtime, which is the Google Chrome
browser, down to the Java SDK,
which usually have three months between
patches. Someone may wonder
why I included MongoDB in this list.
From a practical perspective, any modern application relies
on many different components, databases,
caches, queues, messaging system, et cetera,
et cetera. Their update reflects
the entire application security and behavior, so I
included Mongo as a representative of these other components
just to see how often it gets updated.
The next and third layer are all the
libraries included and linked to the application.
A modern trend is the increased dependency
on third party libraries. I can remember when people
worked in c plus plus they used a couple of libraries,
maybe four, maybe five. Nowadays it's
a lot more common to use
open source libraries instead of buying libraries from a
vendor and has we can see from this chart from
son of type. The trend is hugely increasing
year after year. Every major open
source repositories is registering a
huge amount of increase year over year,
in this case from 2020 to 2021 in
the absolute number of downloads, 50%,
70%, 90% even. This is related
to the language platform, and above
that we have some interesting considerations.
Different runtimes they have a different
number of average libraries. So for example,
JavaScript uses a lot more separate libraries
compared to a Java or a.
Net application. They use a lot less in the
order of tenths compared to a JavaScript application that uses
hundreds of libraries.
The net result is a constant shift of the stack,
all three layers, the need to
protect the entire software stack and the chain that produces it.
So we need to update the software a lot more frequently.
Let's move to the second section and consider what is
technical debt and if the phenomenon that we described
can be defined as
technical debt. We all know that technical
debt is a metaphor. We use the word depth
to better communicate with known technical audience.
The listener may be an expert with a master
in economics, or have a simpler common sense idea.
I put in this slide three definition for
depth. There are
common elements across the definition and these
elements are three and key to
understand what technical debt is compared to the
normal debt. They are the will, the principal
or capital, and the interest.
A person does not enter debt without agreeing
or accepting it, or searching for it.
It is always an act of will to borrow
some money from someone else.
He borrows an exact amount of money, the principal,
for a certain duration of time, more or less rigid,
and part of the contract is the interest to pay as time
passes could be zero interest, or usually it's
more than zero. And debt
can be renegotiated, for example
by delaying some payments.
Moving to the technical debt it was introduced
by Ward Cunningham as an explanation
for a technical problem. So the technical debt
metaphor matches the three core elements
that I described before. The engineering team
knows that a design solution is
suboptimal and which other
solution would be preferable. This is
matching perfectly the wheel element. You don't get technical depth
by chance. The team have
an estimate for a future solution and
for the temporary solution. If not,
they will never choose the worst and
shortcut solution if it's not able to
implement in a lesser time compared
to the other one. So it must be cheaper to
implement. Finally, the capital
element. Oh shite.
Finally, the interest. Shite.
Sorry, shite. Ward Cunningham
introduced debt as an explanation for a technical problem.
The technical depth metaphor matches the three
core elements I described before. The engineering
team knows that a design is suboptimal
and which other solution would be preferable.
This is the will element.
The team has an estimate for the future solution and
for the temporary solution, and they know that
the temporary solution is substantially cheaper
to implement. Otherwise, choosing to take the shortcut
would be an irrational way of thinking.
This estimate to implement the
solution is the capital element. Finally,
what matches the interest?
It is the delays in paying back
the debt. The longer it takes you
to go back and implement
the desired solution instead of the temporary solution,
the harder it becomes, the harder is
to fix the software and maintain and
evolve the software. So this is
like the interest that the amount to payback grows
and grows over time.
Continuous updating is something different from
refactoring. It is a simple adaptation
to the environment. No new domain knowledge
or user feedback require architecting or refactoring.
So which analogy should we use
to explain it? I do not see the three
elements that characterize debt.
Thus I'm suggesting other terms borrowed,
pun intended, from economics. My first
proposal is the term depreciation. It captures the
fact that investment in software is not a constant
value, but decreases over time.
This analogy has a limit and is that
depreciation is an accounting, a fiscal
technique completely disconnected from external
events. So we don't capture the external
push with vulnerabilities that we have
to update software. Another terms
might be inflation. This metaphor has an
advantage over depreciation because it catches
the external elements. Inflation is something that happens
outside your control.
The ratio of the software value changes is
not a constant. There can be periods of high inflation
and this could be resemble
a technology leap or new attack techniques.
So high inflation, the value of my
solution due to these factors and there are period
calm with very low inflation, there are
no big external events and forces us to update
our software very frequently.
Another final way to describe the need
to update constantly is an increase of operational costs
to keep the lights on, the cost to rebuild,
track, store and deploy. In my
opinion, all these ideas operational
costs, technical inflation,
technical devaluation are all
three more effective to explain the continuous update
phenomenon compared to the concept of technical depth,
we reach the third part where we analyze
what continuous update means. In practice,
continuous update is not continuous delivery nor
continuous deployment. The necessity of frequently
updating a system independently
of source code changes necessity.
We must update to prevent attacks frequently
because we probably have to update every day.
If you average what you have seen changes
in operating system level in the runtime in
the libraries we have frequent updates
independently. Means that when there are
no functional changes, we still have to rebuild and redeploy
to production all the patches in the many
other layers which are not our application.
The source code changes excludes the
portion of build and deploy scripts which identifies the
version of dependencies. So these changes
are not considered source code in this definition.
In practice, we can be lucky and have
a monolith application running on a virtual machine.
In this case, it operation is responsible for updating
the operating system and maybe even
the runtime because it's preinstalled on the machine.
So developer and the pipeline
are used only when there is a change in the
libraries, so less frequency of update and
redeploy because we have independence between
layers. But if we consider a microservice architecture,
each service is packaged in a docker image and the docker
image contains all the layers,
application libraries, runtime and operating system. So we
have to redeploy the whole image no matter
which layer we need to patch. This is an
interesting downside of containers. It applies anywhere
immutable infrastructure is implemented, not just
containers. The simplest way to
implement continuous update is to rebuild and redeploy
all your application every single day,
no matter what? This is easy if
your portfolio is just a few application and pipelines,
it clearly does not scale very well for
an enterprise portfolio. The sheer cost of rebuilding
can be huge and impressive.
To do an optimization,
we need to pick up our
software bill of materials and our configuration
items and bring this information together so we
can easily locate which component requires
a rebuild and redeploy. As soon as we
have the information of
what needs to be patched. Could be
a piece of operating system or a library or whatever.
The next logical step to automate the process
is an automatic update of all the references
to the patched component. This could be
build scripts like a Palm XML CS Pro J
packages. JSon for JavaScript could be
the docker files, so the reference to the base images
could be ansible puppet or chef scripts that
are patching operating systems or infrastructure
as code in the form of terraform, cloud formation,
arm templates, scripts.
Finally, we need to kick off
the pipeline. After we patch these
scripts, the pipeline will rebuild
the component, the image, and redeploy it.
Note that in this scenario the normal approval process may
face short you can have a lot
of software to be rebuilt and redeploy thinks of log four j
and you cannot approve 100 different pipelines
in one go. You need something different, some expedite
approval process that will encompass all the impacted components.
Consider what is required to automate the process in full.
This is the flip side of the coin. We need a strong
test harness around the application to guarantee that a
patch will not break any core functionality.
If you have a big portfolio of components
based on the same technology, for example Java,
a single library upgrader can start a buildstorm
with hundreds of build queuing at the same time
and running for hours or more.
This will kill not just
your build infrastructure, but also your production
infrastructure, because you are deploying everything
simultaneously. At the same time,
huge spike in disk, network and cpu usage,
not counting the downtime that user
might suffer. Another side effect might be
the increase of the usage of storage for all the intermediary
artifacts, especially if you're using
the immutable infrastructure pattern. So you are producing a
lot of images, everyday new images for a
lot of applications. The current image
technology is not optimized for frequent and small changes
to images, but this will probably improve
over time. Finally, the increased adoption
of safe languages like rust may
translate that in a few years. Adopting these languages,
we won't see so many security patches,
hopefully. Back to the original
question that gives the title to this speech.
Is technical depth the right metaphor for continuous
update? I think the
answer is a clear no, at least in my
opinion. Technical depth is a great
metaphor for some kind of problems we face while
delivering software. We borrow time when
we judge. Better taking a shortcut than going
through the long way. Nowadays we
face a new phenomenon.
Perfectly working software weakens
over time and need continuous maintenance.
The speed of decay is noticeable much
more similar to inflation. Our money value less and less
as time goes by.
My name is Giulio Vian. I'm italian. I work in
Ireland as a principal engineer for Unum,
a Fortune 500 insurance company.
I post my thoughts on DevOps and some random
topics in my blog. I repost on LinkedIn and
some other media. To prepare this talk.
I researched a number of sources which are listed in the
next three slides.
I won't apologize for the font because it's not meant to be read.
Now you can easily download the deck and follow
the links or any articles or paper that
is linked here from the conference site or
from my own site.
I want to thanks again the sponsor that made
this event possible. I want to thanks the organizer
and I hope you have lot of questions and
we can interrupt and discuss the idea that
I throw to you today. Thanks once
more for staying to the end and hope you enjoy
the content. See you soon.