Hello everyone. Today I'm going to talk about the biggest challenge that
many designers and engineers and startups are facing
is building a design system within limited time frames.
So time constraints can make it tough to start,
maintain, keep consistent and scale.
So we'll explore strategies to overcome these obstacles
over your approaches to protest components
and dive into different plugins and AI tools to
build design system faster. So first thing first,
let me introduce myself. Currently I'm working
at Poly AI and I'm designing better user experience for
conversational AI systems. I have more
than nine years of experience as a product UIx designer
and also work with multiple design systems for large
companies and tiny startups. Also in the past and
right now, I have multiple degrees as an accountant
and digital designer and I really love mentoring designers
and help them at early stages of their career. But why
design system? Probably you heard a lot,
that design system is really helpful. It makes
companies deliver feature faster, it helps engineers to
reuse code and also it increases revenue and
just reduce time spending on design
components and tickets. It's really beneficial for
companies, especially startups, to spend time on designing
and creating building design system because using
design system is all about saving time and money.
But it's also challenging when you start working on
design system, which means you, you should think about consistency.
Also you usually have resource limitation
and also communicational gaps and you need to align your stakeholders
and other departments. And also usually you have technical constraints
and issues with adoption. But when we're talking about
startups, we have even more challenges.
Like usually startups don't have time to anything,
speed is really high and also roadmap is very
dense. Usually there is no sign team to
create design system and also there usually scalability issue with
a platform and especially with the design system itself.
And usually there is privatization conflicts due to roadmap.
What you should do technically when you just create your company, when you
start working on product, you can use happy
path. And just by re already
existing design system there is few platforms where you can
make it happen. So you definitely should look at
these platforms. There is a lot of design system
for different type of products, for different size
of company and different size of product. There could
be a really complex design system for like hundreds of components
and a really simple one for tiny startups who just
start date path. So you can use
this design system that already exists in.
Usually they have Figma file and files
for engineers and links to repository to use it and
just use for your platform. But when we're talking about
existing products, an existing team
that already have design system or Uikit.
It means that maybe they don't
have this opportunity to use happy bug. Probably they can
improve their existing design system or move forward creating
design system. So first of all, what you should
have to create very successful design
system is to have roadmap and also long
term vision. And your design system should
be valuable for its users. So you definitely should have
users. By users I
mean engineers and designers and other teammates
who can use the design system on daily
basis. For example, usually it's designers,
engineers, qi engineers or marketing team.
And also it's all about value. So this
design system should be really valuable to its users.
And at the same time you should have metrics
for a design system to check if this design system is okay.
For example, this metrics could be satisfaction of your users and
you also should create some specific adoption plan how to
make these users used and love your design system.
So when you realize that you have users
and you need to create design system and it will be valuable,
you should start from something. So you probably
know that usually design system have really specific
components, for example buttons, inputs, color palette,
grids and icons. So you should think
about prioritization, where to start, what components should go first,
what element you should build first.
In this case, there should be, there are existing
few types of prioritization. First of all, you can use
any prioritization tool you already use on your product,
for example. So technically you have four
columns, must have, should have, could have, and won't have where
you can place any of your components. For example from
experience, usually you should place color palette, grid system
icons and fonts to must have.
And for example, if you are early stage startup,
so you probably don't need to think about creating
some specific components like combo books or data
pickers. So in this case it could be in a column
of one half or one half right now.
And there's another approach of prioritization.
This is technically system methodology for designing called atomic
design where you have subatomic components such
as color palettes, typography and spacing,
and also you have other components that is more complex
like atoms. You see this could be icons,
buttons, labels or inputs,
molecules, organisms, and more complex elements
such as pages. And usually work starts from
subatomic and atoms. And then you go to
the more complex one, one more prioritization thing.
Prioritization methods is roadmap based.
So technically you can see, just imagine this is your
roadmap. You have features on this roadmap and it means
that you can start working on design
systems, you work on your feature. So technical case close
to atomic design,
atomic methodology,
because at the beginning you should work on the
most basic components such as colors, buttons,
inputs, and then you go further with second
feature, there could be different components, so it could be input.
So usually with this approach, with this roadmap
based approach, there will be lots of work. At the beginning
with your design system and then closely
closer to the middle of your roadmap,
you will see that your design system is already ready.
So most components are already used. I might say from
my experience, I usually use atomic approach
and roadmap based approach and sometimes I
use something like collaboration
mix of these approaches. But usually I start from subatomic
components such as colors and color palette, and then
I go with features and components that is
connected to each feature. And I might say I really
recommend these two approaches like roadmap
based and atomic design approach.
So since we agreed, and you agreed on moving
forward with some specific approach of prioritization,
it means you should think about process of
creating your design system. So first thing first you
should think about why
do we need this component? So this is discovery stage,
the same as working on every feature. You would have discovery,
design development and release. And also you can go
back and forward in some steps.
And also you can see there's few additional steps
in each of this phase. So there should be
audit, discussion, scoping,
kickoff. Then there should be exploration,
user testing of course, and documentation at each
step. And also when you release, you also should
think about announcement because you have users and
you should definitely share what's different,
what's new in your design system. And also you should have metrics to
check. Sometimes you may not have metrics.
For example, there are five people who are using design system and
the metrics you can have with just satisfaction.
And technically yes, you have metric, but at
the same time it's not that metric as you probably could have
on your product because your
metric is your user feedback, definitely.
So what's next? We understand what
approach to use, you understand what process can
be. So next step is design phase.
So color palette is the most basic
element of your design system, but also time consuming.
Work on color palette can take from few hours
to few weeks, depends. So instead of
spending time on this basic element, basic element
of your design system, you should use these plugins on
figma to generate your color palette.
I will show on my presentation only plugins for figma
because last five years I use figma only and I
know that number for designers who are using figma is
growing every year. So if you use sketch,
I'm really sorry but currently I'm sharing everything about
figma. So as you can see you can use this
plugin on figma to generate your color
palette. Then also you can use this plugin to
create your color palette as the styles
and variables. Or you can use this plugin that
also have an AI to generate
your color palette. Creates everything styles
based on pictures or image or your printing
guidelines. So I absolutely recommend to use any of
this plugin to create your color scheme.
Typography is also time consuming. You also
can spend from hours today to create your typography
styles and sometimes it's really
challenging when you have already existing product and you
need to gather everything together. So this plugin
can really help you to save hours of your
life by just some of
them gathering all color styles that you already have on your mockups and figma.
Some of them help you to create type
scale specifically for your needs.
So I definitely recommend to use any of this.
Next is icons. Why icons?
It's really interesting because designers already
designed like thousands of different versions of
home icon. You can find it everywhere.
So instead of again spending hours on this basic
element such as icon, you can buy already existing
icon set on this website for example.
Or you can use any of plugins that you can find
on figma, for example material symbols or
the same plugin from iOS. So it will help you save
hours of your life on creation these icons.
But again, there is a lot of other
icons that you can find on different other websites.
So I think you definitely could find something that's
really suitable for your branding for your website to make a
shiny and save time. What else?
I would like also share my thoughts about these three
plugins because these three plugins are just
recently showed up and they're in beta version.
But what they can do previously on previous
slides I shared that you can create icons,
colors and typography by using different plugins.
And these plugins on this slide there can do
everything, but you need to prompt,
you just need to prompt what you would like to create.
Unfortunately, these plugins again embedded version, it means they are not that
functional as they can be. But in the future I
see that by prompting them, by adding few lines
of text, you can create your own design system.
Currently they can create styles, color fonts and few really simple
design components. Design system components, but that's it.
But anyway, they're really powerful and
instead of having like five or ten plugins
for different reasons, you can use any of this and
it's really could help you save time. And when
we're talking about designing, it's not the end
after design. Usually we should go to the development phase.
So we should move up design for Figma two code.
Unfortunately, and fortunately there is not that many plugins
or tools that can help you move your Figma
file or design on Figma to code because Figma already did
it. Figma introduced depth mode that
help you just copy this code
that Figma generate and paste it to your repository,
to your files and it's really helpful. Unfortunately, there is
no other tools that can do something
better and there is not that many tools that you can
try really. But using dev mode is really
beneficial for our team. So it definitely
should help you to build your design system faster.
And also when we're talking about building design system,
usually I see that people and other companies and
other teams use storybooks as a visualization
of what you can find on Figma, what you can see on code.
So it's really helpful. It helps engineers to understand what's going on,
what other state, what other patterns or styles you should
use, or it also help with version control.
So storybook or its alternative is
definitely really helpful to save time and help with
communication between different departments.
Also, when we're talking about design system, it's all about
documentation and guidelines. I might say that
when we're talking about documentation, first thing first, what we're thinking about
is chat DPT. There is no longer need to
have open tab of chat VPT because
you can find this plugin and figma
that also have chat DPT. So it means that
you just open this plugin and prompt few
lines of text about what you're gonna choose,
what you going to generate and this plugin
will do everything. I use it a lot in the past,
I will use it already for my design system. I'm working on
design system and it's really helpful. Also when we're talking
about design system and components, it's usually all
about anatomy of components, means you
should use and you could use and I recommend to
use this eight shaped specs plugin because it
really helped to highlight these different measurements
between components, space between components and
everything and leave comments and
some specific details for your
engineer. Definitely should use it. And when
we talking about documentation,
these applications are hey is really helpful
because this is perfect place where you can place
everything, all documentation that you have for both engineers
and designers and for third parties or other departments
in one place. You just create one page
where you explain everything about some specific component,
or you can explain patterns or use cases for
specific elements. So it's really helpful to use this
app as a source of truth for everyone.
And since we already discussed components
and where to place it and how to move it from
design to engineering, we also should think about
scalability. Because yes, we have users,
our design system is valuable and how to scale,
because when you cannot scale, it means that your
design system would be really hard, really difficult
to maintain. You could spend a lot of hours
on just creating new components and there will be no scalability
at all. And eventually you can just
lost your users and metrics gone wrong
and there is no option at all. So you
can try to make your design system scalable just
to add a lot of collaboration between different departments and
collaboration between users and people who are building this
design system, because this collaboration
can help to understand point of improvements
or weak points or this strength of design
system. So collaboration is essential for building
scalable design system. And when we're talking about scalability
is all about documentation. So everything should be documented
and your design system should be flexible and modular.
Because when you cannot create your design system,
when your design system is not that scalable,
not that flexible, sort, it means that
every time when you need new component, when you need specific
component, you cannot use existing one, you should create new
one. And it means that you would end up
with a lot of the same, very similar to each other components.
You will end up with a lot of documentation for all of them.
It's definitely should, you should definitely try to avoid
creating a lot of components. And you should definitely think about
adding flexibility to this component.
And your design system is all about version control. Because if
your design system is evolving, if you create a new
component, if you add in documentation, you should definitely think
about how to show versioning,
how to help user to understand that this button
is the most relevant one and previous one
issue duplicated. So version control is everything too.
And once you done with everything, you create
scalable design system, next step is adoption.
If your design system have value and also have users,
it means that you should educate and train all users that
can possibly work with your design system. Because training
and education is the most essential one for adoption.
Because people should know what to use and how to
use this component. And also it's all about feedback.
And if you would like to scale your design
system and make it living and breathing,
you should think about improvements and how to improve is
just gathering feedback because user will say, will tell
you what should be improved. And also to
make your design system perfect for adoption
is your design system should be
impactful for users, for company,
because if there is no impact, there is
no chance that company will use it and users will use it.
And we're talking about people who are
creating Zen systems. So it's all about recognition because people
who build Zen systems should be motivated and they
should be recognized. So it's just tiny thing,
but recognition is something that
should be done for better adoption.
So thank you so much for listening. My presentation about
design system.