Hello everyone, this is Jin Wei. I'm very happy to
introduce the Apache API six Ingress project.
This is a simpler and easier kubernetes ingress
have something about myself. I'm Apache API six PMC,
Apache Skywalking committee, and the founder of Apache API Six
Ingress controller. So what is Apache
API six Ingress controller? It is another ingress controller
implementation based on Apache API six,
and it supports declarative configuration which
can be configured through native ingress results or
through custom results definition. We call it CRD.
This picture tells us that the Apache API
six Ingress controller is usually deployed at the
age of the cluster, serving as a cluster
entry and forwarding business request to the services.
Well, we also need to introduce Apache API six.
It is a high performance four dynamic real
time API gateway and it is also a top level
project of Apache foundation. This is the
architecture diagram of Apache API six,
and the left part show us Apache API six how
to process business traffic with rich plugin functions.
On the right is the controller plan of Apache API
six. Here we mainly focus on admin
APIs, through which ingress controller
synchronize results to Apache API six.
Okay, let's talk about the working mechanism
of Apache API six Ingress controller.
The Apache API six Ingress controller watches events from
the Kubernetes API server, something like secret
endpoints and Ingress in kubernetes,
as well as custom results definition such
as API six root API six,
upstream API six tls and so on.
And then the channel resource objects are covered,
compared, and finally the results are synchronized
to a patch API six cluster by invoking
admin APIs. So this diagram
fully shows the relationship between Ingress controller
and Apache API six. Apache API six Ingress controller
is used as a controller plan to calculate and
synchronize restores configuration between
Kubernetes and Apisix cluster.
Well, what can we do with Apache Apisix in grace?
I list many important features here such as
dynamic configuration service discovery,
flexible load balancing strategies, out of the box,
health checks, traffic split and more than 70 official
plugins, as well as the configuration of custom
plugins, ability and so on.
Welcome to watch the project and get more future
information. Let me show the path
of Apache API six Ingress controller in
2019. I wrote the first line of project
and donated to the Apache foundation
in December 2020 after half
a year of community polishing. The first
GA version was released in June 2021.
Until the last version 1.4
release, Apache API Six Ingress
has been used by more and more enterprises and
working in production environments.
Much has been learned along the way and soon
we will be raising version 1.5
in midmain. This is contribute
growth curve of the Apache API Six Ingress controller
and its steady growth shows that the project
has maintained a good level of activity.
Well, there is a question I think you will ask. We know
that there are many ingress implementations in
kubernetes, but why we still create another
ingress based on API six?
Of course, as a gateway with excellent performance,
Apache API six is necessary to implement
ingress in order to help users to
use it on Kubernetes platform.
Apart from that, we certainly have other reasons
that are why I recommend API six
ingress to you. First.
All configurations of API six take effect
dynamically and there is no need to
reload when the configuration is changed.
Compared with some other ingress implementations,
using API six ingredients has nature advantages.
Apache API six ingredients is easier to use,
the declarative configuration is more readable
and complex scenarios can be defined in
a single result. This example shows
that an API is assigned to different upstream
according to weights. Of course that
certain condition must be made.
Here we can see that the complete traffic split
configuration are delivered into two parts,
match and back end. The match part defines
the root matching rules and the backend
part defines the weight between upstreams.
The whole configuration is very easy to read.
Third, API six have strong scalability
following the above configuration. If you want
to add some features to this API,
such as the ability to support cross domain and
URIW, we can use plugins
to empower the API. If you want to
add more features, just add plugins.
I'd like to say that the design of the plugin
is very compatible with the declarative configuration
and because of the in cap solution
of plugin, you do not need to write
code slaved in declarative configuration
and no longer need to pay attention to these code
logics. The only thing need to be case
about is some simple variables which is
more general and more readable.
Okay, let's come back and talk
about the flexibility of the architecture of
Apache API six. Ingress controller Apache
API six ingress does not combine controller and
proxy like other ingresses.
The advantage of this is that you can
deploy them together or separately.
When Ingress controller and API six are deployed
together, they are used to handle ingress requests
to a single Kubernetes cluster,
no different from traditional Kubernetes ingress.
You can also deploy them separately. This is awesome.
As shown on the right, API six
cluster is deployed outside the Kubernetes clusters
and can manage the traffic on multiple Kubernetes
clusters. In this way all resources
be managed in unified API cluster
and also reduce one traffic forwarding.
The only thing you need to care about is
the networking between the Kubernetes clusters.
Here are some complaints using Apache API six
more and more enterprise customers are using Apache
API six for production environments. More and more
user are adopting Apache API six Ingress solutions.
That's what keeps our open source
project going. Okay,
I'd like to share with you the future plans
of Apache API six Ingress controller.
We are supporting the Kubernetes Gateway API and
we are also preparing to support a new scenarios
which is to support cluster deployment without
etCD. I think users who mind
etcd being stateful will be happy to hear
about that.
Why we made such changes because this needs
from the community are very reasonable and
this is the driving force for the project to continue.
Okay, the above is the whole content of this sharing.
Looking forward to build a patch API six community together
with you. See you next time.