All right, let's take a look at what Gitops is with Argocd,
and then we'll spend some time understanding vault and the injector
in kubernetes. Then we're going to follow that up with a demo.
So, intro to Gitops with Argocd if
you're not familiar with Gitops, it's the process of having your
application code and your infrastructure code all
stored in git. And basically git becomes
your source of truth and you deploy straight from git.
In this case, Argocd is a tool that implements Gitops
principles and it's implemented as a Kubernetes controller
which continuously monitors running applications
in your environment. It compares the current
live state against the desired target state
as specified inside of your Git repo.
A deployed application whose live state starts
to deviate from the target state is considered out of sync.
You have the option to have auto sync enabled, so revert
back to what you want your desired state
to be, which is in your Git repository. And again, that's a source of truth
that is available, or you can leave it at the default of manual
and then you can alert on a deviation if you wish.
So ArgoCD reports and visualizes the differences
while providing facilities to automatically or
manually sync the live state back to desired target state, as I mentioned.
And then any modifications made to the desired
target state in the Git repo will automatically get applied
and reflected in your target environment. So it's
an amazing technology, and many organizations are moving
to Gitops. Now let's take a look at the app,
the demo app that we're going to use today. I call it the school app.
And as you might know, I offer
an academy, a teaching academy for DevOps and platform
engineering. And as such I use this school app
as a demo application in my
tech and aid academy. So here what we're going to do, we're going to have
this application that allows users
to enroll in courses. And you can
see the back end here, the course
that was created and what users or what students
have been enrolled into that course. And the components
of this application is basically it's written
in view JS. That's the front end JavaScript
framework that is used for the user to interact with
the front end. The backend API is written
in fast API, which is a great python API
framework. So as the user interacts with
the front end, the front end talks to the
backend app, and then our data layer is using MongoDB,
that's our database, and then our API
talks to the database and of course the database
responds back and then the data is
rendered back to the user in their browser.
Now, in the very beginning of our demo, we're going to hard code the
connection to MongoDB inside of our app.
So the credentials, the username and password, they're going to be hard coded
in here, which is definitely not the way to go in production.
You need to have some sort of a method to
automatically rotate secrets and store those secrets outside
the application. In a secrets management store such as
Hashicorp Vault, the application
output in Kubernetes will look something like this. When you run Kubectl
getall, you're going to see that we have three pods. We've got
an API pod, a front end pod and the MongoDB
pod. They're all deployed as deployments. And of
course we have services for each one of those
pods and they're using cluster IP for
their service type. All right, let's now add
vault to the mix and see how things will work for our school
app application.
So once again, we have the same workflow. We got our user
talking to the front end and we've got our fast app API
and we got the front end talking to the API.
And then MongoDB needs to be accessed. But this time
we're going to rely on vault to supply us with the
necessary credentials. So the API will reach out to vault,
it needs to authenticate into vault and then reach
out to get the database credentials so that the API can
now talk to the database. And of course the database talks
back to the API and the front end,
the application is rendered in the front end. So to get
to that step, we need to understand first, the first step of accessing
vault and in our unique case here is going to be using
Kubernetes authentication method. So the
Kubernetes authentication method is one of many authentication methods that
vault allows. And in this case it
is a method to solve the secret zero problem.
Basically what the secret zero problem is, how do you access the
first secret, how do you get secrets out of vault?
But first you need to authenticate into vault. So how do we authenticate into
vault securely? So that's where we have
a vault agent sidecar that can sit beside your
application container in the same pod.
This pod is going to have a service account or
youll application is going to have a namespace and a service account.
And what will happen is the application pod will
get, or the vault agent will get a jot token from the
kubelet inside the node where the application is running
and that jot token is going to get passed over as the vault
agent authenticates into vault. And there is
a connection between the vault server
and the Kubernetes API that we'll set up. And that way
the vault server can pass that
jot token over to the API and basically ask the question does
the pod or did the pod that I just used the jot token for,
was that initiated under your management, Mr. Kubernetes?
Kubernetes will come back and say yes, I know about it, it's under my management
and that is the authentication piece. Then what will happen is
vault will come back, deliver a token and a token has a
policy attached to it to authorize the application or the vault
agent to retrieve secrets at specific paths.
So that's kind of the Kubernetes authentication method
in a nutshell. And from here we want to talk a little bit about the
vault agent sidecar injector.
So the vault agent workflow in Kubernetes looks
like this. You have an application Kubernetes pod
with a mounted volume inside of this pod.
We've got our application. So our app lives here.
We also have the vault agent sidecar that I just mentioned and
we have our vault server. So what happens
is the vault agent will go ahead and authenticate with the vault server.
The vault server will respond back with an application token.
The vault agent will store this app token inside of a
sync file in the mounted volume so the application can
actually access this token. And if the application is
vault aware we can stop here and the application can grab this
token, talk directly to the vault server and retrieve the secrets
directly. But that of course means that youll application code
needs to have a way to talk to the vault API and retrieve secrets.
So you're going to have to make changes to the code.
But we can take this a step further and we can actually say, you know
what, let's have the vault agent retrieve secrets on behalf
of the application and that way it makes the application
vault unaware and you don't have to make any changes to the application.
Of course vault needs to check against the policy that's associated
with that token to make sure that the vault agent can retrieve secrets from
the server at the particular path that it requested it at.
And from there there's
something called the vault agent template where we can actually templatize
how we want to render those secrets for our application.
So what happens is now the vault agent is going to
use this template to grab the secrets and render them in a particular
format to allow the application to retrieve
my username and password for my MongoDB. And once
the application can read this out of the file that's again in the
mounted volume here, it can now connect to the MongoDB
database and the application continues to
run as before. So let's talk a little
bit about the Vault agent sidecar injector.
What it is it really alters the pod specifications
to include the vault agent containers that render vault secrets
to a shared memory volume. Using vault agent templates.
The app containers within this pod can consume vault
secrets from the shared volume without being vault aware. As we saw
in the workflow, the injector uses or
is a Kubernetes mutation webhook controller
and it works by intercepting pod create
and update events in Kubernetes and then the controller parses
the event and looks for the metadata annotation.
Hashicorp.com agent inject is true
and if found, the controller will alter the pod specification
based on other annotations that are present so
mutation effects. Every container in the pod will be configured
to mount a shared memory volume. This volume
is mounted to the path vault secrets by default.
Of course that's configurable and will be used by the vault agent
containers for sharing secrets with the other containers
in the pod. There are two types of vault agent
containers we can inject. There's the init
and the sidecar, and the init container will pre populate
the shared memory volume with the requested secrets prior to
the containers starting. And these are very good
for cron jobs. So if ever I'm running a backup job,
for example using cron, I will use the init container
for that. And then the second one is the sidecar container
which will continue to authenticate and render secrets to the
same location as the pod runs. And this one's really good for long
lived containers. And if you use
dynamic secrets later, which I highly recommend you do,
as those secrets change over time, the sidecar
container can render those secrets for the application dynamically
and then using annotations. Init and sidecar containers can also
be disabled so vault
agent configs to render the secret there are two methods of
configuring the vault agent containers to render secrets.
The first one is using annotation agent inject
secret annotation the second method is to use a configuration map
so config map that allows that contains the vault agent config
files and only one of these two methods
may be used at any time. The config
map can provide more details for configuration beyond the
annotations. So what's
an example look like? This is what we're going to do in our demo.
Here's our annotations and you can see here that agent
inject is true. Agent inject token is true configures
vault agent to share the vault token with other containers in the pod.
This is helpful for Vault aware apps that need to communicate directly
with vault but require auto authentication provided by vault
agent. So if you're just going to use the token
for a vault aware app, you need to have this.
The update blocks further mutations by adding the value
injected to the pod after successful mutation.
And here's where we render the vault token in this particular
path. App secrets and under the file called Token
and we'll see it in the demo. And the role we're using here is called
school app.
If you want a full list of annotations, you can go to this particular URL
to see all the available options for you.
Let's take a look at the vault agent template.
Quick review here. Vault agent uses
the console template project to render secrets.
So the console template is a project that was actually used with Hashicorp
console that got extended over to the vault agent
to be able to render these secrets as a template. And then this is
useful for vault unaware apps. As we mentioned before, the app's file system
has the secrets dropped in by vault. The app doesn't talk
to vault directly and all it needs to know is
what files to find those secrets from and how to read them.
And just again, a quick overview or quick review
I should say, of this workflow. Once again we have the mounted
volume where application lives. The vault agent lives here in the same
pod. It talks to the vault server by first authenticating
using the Kubernetes authentication method. The vault server
responds with a token. That token gets stored in the sync file and we
can stop here. As I mentioned before, if the application is vault aware,
can retrieve the token from here and talk to vault directly.
Or we can take this a step further and get the vault
agent to retrieve secrets on behalf of the application
and store these secrets in a particular
file that is based on
a template so we can get the particular format that we want for
our application to talk to whatever it needs
to talk to, in this case the MongoDB database.
And now we're good to connect. What does this
look like in terms of more annotations? So now
we stopped here last time at this line here, but now we want to
take it to the next level and add the templating for
our application. So as youll can see here, we are
adding this annotation agent inject secret school
app MongoDB username and this is the path
inside of vault at this MongoDB path inside of
internal data school app. And then we also have the password file.
So these two will effectively tie into two
files that you'll see down here. Down here you
see another annotation for our template and
this is what the template looks like. So all we're going to do is just
render the school app DB
username right here in between here.
And this is using Golang's templating language. So we're grabbing
the MongoDB username from this
path inside of vault and also doing the same thing for the
password in a separate file. So we'll see this inside the
demo, inside our container. You'll see that we have two files
that will get rendered app secrets school app MongoDB
username and school app is going to be
the username and then app secrets school app MongoDB
password. The password is going to be Mongo root pass that's going to
get rendered in here and that's pretty much it.
From a slides perspective what we're going to do,
let's now dive into a demo together.
All right, let's now have some fun with our demo.
So I've got this all set up for you in GitHub
and you can use code spaces to get this all set up without
having to do anything on your local machine. So if
you go to our repository here,
the GitHub repository, first thing you want to do is fork it into your own
environment. So make sure you go ahead and fork it. And then
once you fork it, you can run a code space on main like
this. And I already set up the
necessary dev containers that will set up a
mini cube Kubernetes cluster. It will set up really
everything that's needed in our environment. So the one thing
I will note though is for this to work, you're going to
need to have this run in your own
visual studio code on your desktop.
And I'll tell you why in just a minute. So go down to the bottom
here where it says code space at the bottom here and select
open in vs code desktop. What this will do is
it will open this particular code
space remotely inside of your visual studio code
installation on youll machine. So I'm running this in Windows here.
It doesn't matter what operating system you're running it in,
it's going to get started. And you can see at the bottom it says opening
remote. So it really is talking to code space,
which is GitHub's own cloud, where you can have
development environments in there. And I use it quite extensively in my
courses, makes things much easier for my
students, so they don't have to worry about binaries and
dependencies and things breaking. If it
works in my code space, it will work in your code space, that kind
of thing. All right, now the reason why I'm asking you to run
this in your own visual studio
desktop is because when it comes to
the communication between the front end, the back end,
the database, we're running all on
local host. If you were to try to run this in
codespace, Codespace gives a
port. If you go to ports here, it'll give a port for each
one of the exposed ports. It will have a particular host theme,
and my front end won't know how to reach the API,
and the API won't know how to reach the database and so on. So because
this is a demo, I want everything to run on local host. So you'll need
to do this in your visual studio code desktop.
So while I was chatting here, our minicube cluster should
be running right now. I have a bunch of aliases,
if you notice, in here. In my startup script for this code space,
I use a bunch of aliases for kubernetes commands to make my life easier.
The most famous one is KGA, which Kubectl get, all kdell
for kubectl delete and a bunch of others kg for
Kubectl get. So I kind of render this here to make my life easier.
I also have k nine s installed here as
well, if you like that. And I also
have KubectX and Kubernetes installed,
which is really good for me when I
want to work with namespaces.
So let's render this on the left here so we can see a bit
better. And I'll go ahead and
pull up my readme file, which I have all my notes here,
and we start to look at the demo
steps one by one over here.
So let's look at KubectX. We'll see that we have only one
context minicube. If youll run Kubernetes,
that will show us we've got four namespaces, just the default mini
cube cluster. So first things first, let's install the
school app, and I'm going to run a bunch of commands here to
get this going? I'll explain this of
course we're creating a new namespace called School app.
We're creating a helm repo well adding a helm repo
for Bitnami, we're creating the MongoDB Helm
chart and then I'm going to create my
application here I've got my helm chart.
I've exposed my application or packaged
my application as a helm chart,
called it school app. And from here we can
quickly take a look at the new namespace
called School app Run KGA. And I see that MongoDB
is installed here. Now I'm
going to install my front end
and use helm install front end to install my front end.
I'm going to use helm install my API to install
my API. And now if I run kubectl
get all I see that I am running
my containers here. They're not quite up yet, so we can
do a watch kubectl
get pods and just wait until my
containers are up and running. And they are. I can see API
front end and school app mongo.
So as I showed you in the slides, here is my school
app ready to go up and running. Just out of
curiosity, if you want to see what this looks like,
let's expose our
front end and our back end. So that's the
front end on port 8001, the back end on port
5000. I can open these in a browser window.
And here's our fast API running. If I
go to the docs URL I can see all my endpoints
and if I'm interested now of course to see my front end,
I go to 8001. That will bring
me to my front end of the application. I can
go to the admin side of things. I can create a course or
add a course. Here's my vault 201 course
which a plugin here. All what I'm showing you
today is from this course vault for applications in Kubernetes.
If you're interested in that, of course you can check that out on
my technate academy site. Now we
can also see the
front here, front end for the application for the users,
they can enroll into a course, enroll here. And now
this user is enrolled. If I go back to my admin I can see this
user is enrolled here and I can delete
as well. So just showing you how I'm interacting with my database
and storing things in the database, deleting things from the database,
everything is running very well. And however though
everything is running with credentials that are hard coded
into the application. Meaning that if I go in
and let's see here. If I create
a new tab and I open my,
let's see my API logs.
If I run this command, it will show me the API logs
that we are looking for here that we were running. And if I get
this correct, here we go. You can see that MongoDB credentials
using hard coded values that appear in GitLab, which is not a good
thing. Basically these are hard coded into the
application, they're pushed into git,
and they're visible for anybody who has access to the git repository.
This is a big no no. We don't want to do that. So we're using
to introduce vault next.
Okay, so let's get out of here and
let's see where we're at. We are going to now install
Argocd. Okay, so what we'll do
is we're going to install the ArgoCd server. So let's create
a new namespace, call it Argocd.
All right, and we're going to use this Kubectl
apply command to install Argocd for us in that particular
namespace. Let's change our
namespace to Argocd.
And let's watch our pods to make sure that argocd is
up and running. So we can see here a bunch of pods that are
still in the process of coming
up.
Almost there. We just have a couple more that
need to be ready before we go and we're done. Perfect.
That was quick. All right, now let's expose the ArgoCD
API server so we can actually see
the UI so that
we are exposing now port 8002. Let's open
that in our browser. And from here
we should be able to access Argocd. We just need
our username and password. So let's go ahead and grab that.
By default, ArgocD puts the password
in here in this secret. So let's grab it. And there
it is. Let's copy that and log in with admin
and sign in this way.
All right, we have a freshly installed Argo CD
server. No applications ready or no applications deployed just
yet. All right, so let's go ahead and deploy our
application. But first let's
go into our school app and delete
this namespace altogether because remember we now want to use Gitops
as our approach to deploying this
application. So let's run Kubectl
or kubectl delete or kdelete namespace
cool app to delete this namespace.
And we'll just double check, make sure everything is gone before
we proceed because obviously again we
want to use ArgocD as the tool, our Gitops tool,
to spin up our application so it can monitor
this application and make sure there's no drift.
All right, let's run Kubectl, get namespace.
Our school app namespace is gone. And now what we're going to do is
we're going to run Kubectl apply and
use this ArgocD school app manifest to
render our application. If you want to see what this manifest looks like,
it's pretty straightforward. It's an application for
Argocd. It's going to be in the namespace
Argocd. The name is school app. The destination namespace is
school app. The server is our Kubernetes server.
The path is school app subchart,
which is right here. This is what we're rendering and
we are grabbing the repo, which is our repo
that we're in right now, the ArgoCD vault repo.
And we are creating a namespace as well. So if I were to
run Kubectl gate namespace,
I don't see anything yet. It should show up. So let's take
a look and see what happened in the UI. There it is. So all
I need to do is just click sync.
And now our application is progressing,
it's syncing. As you can see here we have all
the different pieces are running and
there is an issue here with our API pod.
And the reason for that is before recording I forgot to
change my values for my
application here to I
need to disable these two fields
and then we'll come back and fix it later. So let's go
ahead and disable this.
All right, so true to Gitops, I'm making a change in
here. Okay. And now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to push this back to my git
repo and argocd is going to notice the change and
go apply the change.
Okay, so we've got status disabled, kind is disabled.
Let's go ahead and commit this. Let's just
call it start fresh commit and
let's sync our changes. And now
that is synced, let's go ahead and go back into our
ArgoCD dashboard. I'm going to click refresh
just to get this to move faster. Otherwise we'd have to
wait I think two minutes or five minutes by default.
So we click refresh. You see out of sync already.
And why is this out of sync? You can
click apptif and it will show you what the difference is.
You can see the annotations are going to get removed, for example,
and our vault status here,
this is going to be disabled, meaning that we're removing vault from the equation.
And this is what we should have started with. But it's actually a good exercise
to show you Gitops in action. So now we can go ahead and click sync
and we're going to synchronize everything.
And this should fix our API
deployment and it should be healthy after
this works. So let's see here. So the replica set
deleted our pod and see if it will create a
new API pod for us. Just give it a few seconds
here,
maybe even a quick refresh, because I'm impatient.
And there we go. Yeah. So here we go. We've got our API pod
running. If I go back in visual
studio code and run get namespace,
I see my school app here. So cuben school
app and run qCtl, get everything.
My API front end, school app, everything is running.
If I go back and just stop the connection and secrets
the connection to my front end and my back
end, I should be good to see my application
once again. So if I refresh that,
I see my application once again, I can add courses,
I can remove courses, I can interact
with my database, no problem.
Okay, now remember, we're still in the
phase where we haven't introduced vault
yet. All we've done is we've introduced
Gitops through Argocd. So with Argocd,
we can monitor the desired state in our git repo
versus the active state, which is what we see here. All is
good, everything is healthy. Next step is to introduce vault,
which is our final step for our demo today.
All right, so let's go ahead and go back
to my guide to see where we left off.
All right, so we've deployed the app with Argocd now,
and we saw that it's using hard code secrets from before.
Okay, now we're
using to install the vault server in our environment
using our helm chart. So let's
create a new namespace, call it vault.
Let's introduce or add our repo, our helm
release here, or our helm repository. And then
we're going to install our vault server
inside of the
namespace vault. And let's see
what we have here. We've got containers that are starting.
I can see the vault container.
I can see the vault agent injector, which is what is the
mutation webhook that looks for annotations and goes ahead and
creates an agent sidecar for us.
So let's watch this until everything is
ready. Okay, we're running. Notice that the
vault node or the vault server
is not using to go into the ready state. It's running, but it's not going
to go into the ready state because we need to initialize an unseal
vault. So to do that, first of all, we need
to exec into our container. So let's do that.
So now we're inside the vault container and we need to run a few commands
here. First off, we need to initialize
vault using the vault operator command. And just
notice that this is a demo environment.
Please don't do this in a production environment. Production environment. You'll need
to do a whole lot of things when you initializing vault.
And by the way, vault doesn't need to live inside
of a Kubernetes cluster. Your vault server can live somewhere else.
But you will need the injector inside of the
cluster so it can listen to annotations or see annotations
and then inject the agent.
All right, so this is important. The unseal key and the root token.
We need those. So we will save these in a notepad file.
So I save them here in this notepad file. I'll make it bigger.
All right, we're going to come back and use these very shortly.
Actually right now. Vault operator unseal
and we need that unseal key. So this
is what allows us to unseal our vault cluster.
And now our sealed status is
false means that we are unsealed, which is great.
Now let's go ahead and exit this container.
Okay. Actually one thing we
want to do is I
want to make sure that I add my authentication,
kubernetes authentication into vault.
So we actually need to stay inside the vault container
to do that. So let's go ahead and go back.
All right, so we're back in the vault container and we're going to do a
couple of things. You need to export the address, the vault address to
port 8200. And we need to log in. So vault login.
And you need that root token that we just saved.
And if you have
spent more than 5 seconds with me on any of the vault tutorials
I present, you'll quickly hear me say
that the root token is only for creating authentication methods and
it is to be revoked in production environments. Of course,
this is a demo, so we're going to play with the root token. We won't
bother doing anything else. Now here we have
our first secret that we want to create.
First of all, we got to create a secrets engine.
This is the KV version two secrets engine. We first enable it
and then we're going to put our secrets in here. Remember our MongoDB username
and password? So here's our username and here's our password.
And if you want to retrieve that you can run this command
and it will come back retrieve your username and password right
here. Now we need to create a school
application policy. If you recall when I talked about the token and the
policy, you need to have a policy in place that allows
the holder of the token to access particular locations.
So you see here the path internal data school app MongoDB
is the same path that we wrote the secret into.
So we need to have this policy in place so that the vault
agent will have this policy as part of its
token when it goes out to authenticate against vault.
So now let's set up the Kubernetes authentication method in vault.
This allows our vault agent to talk
to vault. So this is just a
bunch of config that you'll have to create
really quickly off Kubernetes config the issuer,
the token reviewer the Kubernetes host the Kubernetes Ca
Cert we're writing or binding to
this service account and this namespace called School app.
Very important policies is app which we wrote up here.
So this policy is attached to this role
that we're creating, the role called school app and we're giving it
time to live 5 seconds and maximum ttl of 20 seconds.
But basically this is our way of getting
kubernetes or vault set up with kubernetes so vault
can authenticate against Kubernetes and figure out if any
of the resources or pods that Kubernetes spins up belong
to the Kubernetes API and that
allows vault to authenticate applications into Kubernetes.
All right, let's now exit the container. I think
we're done with all the configuration for vault.
And now let's test the school app with the vault injector. And how
are we going to do that? I have this all set up with templates,
helm templates and so on. So all we need to do is go into the
values Yaml file here as
part of the subchart. And I need to just make changes here to
do this. Instead of vault being disabled here I want
vault to have status of KV, static injector,
template file and kind injector. And that
basically will allow us to use vault to render secrets.
Now I'm going to say use vault for secrets. I'm going to
commit this and I'm going to push that.
And again, in a production environment, you won't just have the ability
to commit and push straight to the main branch,
of course. You create a pull request or merge request,
you have a peer review and then that gets merged into
your main branch if that's the strategy you're taking.
All right, so that gets pushed through again, I'm going to hit a
quick refresh inside of argo CD and
we can see now that we're out of sync, right, so we
need to sync this. But before we sync, let's again look at the diff.
And as you notice here now we have a bunch of annotations. And if
you recall I told you that you need these annotations for the mutation
webhook, which is the agent injector, the vault agent injector.
Once it sees these annotations it's going to mutate
the pod specification and that's how we're going to see
an agent, a vault agent injector or,
sorry, a vault agent show up inside of our pod.
So here's the annotation. If I make this a bit bigger, maybe to see better,
you can see the agent inject is true
what we saw in the slides, basically the different
agent injector annotations that we expect.
And here's the template where we're going to render the password, render the username
and it's going to be at this particular pass app secrets that
we'll see inside the container. All right, what else?
Vault status from disabled to kv static injector template file
and that should be good to go. We can go ahead and sync that
synchronize and from here we'll
wait till the API gets recreated and if we
go into the logs of the API, which we'll do in
just a minute and this is complete, we'll see that.
Now we're using the agent injector. So let's go ahead back in
here and let's
make sure we are in the
school app namespace.
And if I run Kubectl, get all I can see. Now there are two containers
running inside of my API pod. One is for
the agent, the vault agent, and the other one
is for my actual API application.
All right, and now what we'll do is
take a look at the
logs for my API and you can see here credentials using
Vault KV with injector and templates for vault unaware apps.
You can see my username and password. This is grabbed or taken directly
from vault and it's not hard coded anymore anywhere in my
application code, which is amazing. So with
that I can go back of course to show you that the application still
runs. I'm going to re expose my ports for my
application and
then go back, refresh this.
I can now once again add the course,
I can delete a course and my application
is running smoothly talking to my mongo database,
no problem. So next I just want to
show you what happens inside of
my API pod. So if I go back here and
I go into my pod, so let's clear and run
kubectl exec and
I'm going to exec into my pod to show you inside my pod.
So inside my pod I have my main py
file, of course my python file, but if I go up
one directory and ls you see secrets,
if I go into secrets now the path is
app secrets and if you recall app secrets is through the
annotations is where I'm storing my vault
token and I'm storing my username and password files.
So if I run cat token, this is the vault token
that a vault aware app can just grab and talk
to vault directly. Authenticating to vault directly.
The school Mongo username
is my username that gets dropped in here school app as you
can see as part of the agent template.
And then finally my school
app Mongo password allows
me to see my Mongo root
pass is the password to access MongodB.
And if I'm using in this case I'm using static secrets
because I'm talking to the static KV secrets engine in
vault. But you can always go to a dynamic secret
engine and I highly recommend doing that. MongodB Vault
has one for MongoDB and what will happen is every
time the application needs to access Mongo,
it can create on demand just in time
credentials from vault to use to connect to
Mongo. And there's a time to live for those credentials.
Once the TTL expires, then the application needs to go
and recreate a new set of credentials and in
that case we no longer have any long lived static credentials
in the environment. All of
this I talk about in a lot of my courses in the tech
and aid academy. So feel free to check out some of
those courses. I have extensive coverage on Hashicorp vault.
Once again, you can check out the vault 201 Kubernetes
applications with vault. If that is something that that interests
you, please take a look at that and that is the end
of this talk. I hope you enjoyed it and I hope you enjoy the
rest of the talks at Conf 42, dev stock ops,
and I will see you in other videos.