Hi everybody. My name is Jesus and I'm currently working at Globant.
We're a digitally native company thats helps organizations
revenge themselves and unleash their potential. We are
the place where innovation, design and engineering means
scale. Right now I work in the data and AE studio
to develop incredible stuff with data and mature
learning. But I'm talking too much about myself.
Let's talk. But a much more interesting topic.
Artificial intelligence. Artificial intelligence is all
the rage. That's a fact. And sure, this concept may
sometimes be hijacked by marketing teams to give a modern look to
a product. However, the reality is that we are living a
revolution in terms of this technology. And it
is not by chance that I use the word revolution, because in
general, we are talking about a new industrial revolution.
But what does it mean? An industrial revolution
is defined as a process of profound economic,
social, cultural and technological transformations.
To better understand this concept, we can go back to the first industrial revolution.
This revolution was caused by several reasons.
The growth of population due to a long period of peace and improved farming
techniques. New technologies such as the steam engine that allowed
mechanization, dispensation of the international market
with the appearance of the steamship, and finally the emergence of workshop
and factories where people began to work much more productively.
But perhaps this all seems too far away, right? After all,
the stimages engine was invented in the late seventy?
S sixty s. But let's slow down.
Don't all these points unfamiliar to you? For example,
thanks to industrialization, the world's population grew
from 1 billion to 2 billion people between the
centuries. Today we are almost 8 billion people
in the world. If that's not growing, just let me know.
Also, I guess that you have heard that the smartphone in your pocket
is much more powerful than all the technology in the NASA when the
man landed on the moon. Right? Now imagine applying machine
learning to all this technology. Incredible.
And who has never ordered something through Amazon or
even an express? It just works. No need to explain it.
Finally, the way we work is also changing. I don't
even have to see my colleges anymore and we can keep building amazing
things together. However, I miss coffee breaks and after
works, don't you? After all this,
it is clear that we're immersed in a new industrial revolution
driven by artificial intelligence. The development of
new and powerful machine learning algorithms, especially these learning ones,
has helped this technology to become part of society.
And we didn't realize chatbots or recommendation
systems are just a few examples of how machine learning is becoming an
everyday thing. But why is this happening
if you stop a moment and think about it. Worker productivity
has increased incredible thanks to technological advances
and specialization. But even today,
we still perform repetitive, mechanical and tedious tasks.
In that sense, machine learning offers a new level of depth.
Thanks to machine learning, machines can perform those repetitive jobs
for us quickly, efficiently, and tastily,
far increasing productivity. But what is
our role in all of this? Because it's clear that people get stopped
to insert inside those tasks, leaving this space to computers.
But this does not mean that jobs will be destroyed.
Instead, they will be displaced. We won't be replaced by
a machine. We will just leave that position to start performing
new tasks that best match our skills.
Sound interesting, right? So let's see what those skills
are. And when algorithm will we never be able to replace us
first? Curiosity. We are naturally curious.
Children learn to ask questions without anyone teaching them.
A machine learning algorithm, on the other hand, only knows how to do one
thing, maybe a handful of them, and it does it very
well, better than anyone else. But it is not capable of
performing any other task efficiently.
And that is why we are so important.
Machines are great at giving answers,
but it is us, the people, who will ask them the right
questions. Creativity is also a very
human skill, because human needs to communicate
and express what we think and feel. Also,
we're able to ask questions and use the tools that we have
to solve those problems. Machine learning is just
one more tool, and it can be the solution to a very specific problem.
But not all of them. We choose how and when to
use it. Finally, humans are curious and creative
because inside us there are feelings that move us to investigate and
express ourselves. And those feelings can only be understood by
another human. Perhaps a computer vision
application may be able to distinguish what emotion you
are feeling through your facial expression, right? But no matter how sophisticated
the system is, every time you call to your bank to make a transaction
or to the hospital to make an appointment, you expect to hear
that person's voice on the other end. And if not,
you will say, whoa, that's a robot again.
And you're not alone. It happens to everyone.
Only people understand other people and are able to communicate
trust. Lisa Messenger, CEO of Collective
Hub, once said that everything in business comes
down to humanizing things. And she's right.
The world is for people, and only we can adapt it to
our desires. Maybe a machine learning algorithm will
be able to detect a need, but only a person will know
how to satisfy it. For these reasons,
it's a good idea to let the machines do 13 tasks.
Because while the tickets or the boring part,
which they do so well. We can use our time and effort
for those skills that make us unique and.
Okay, thats sounds good, right?
But it's still a long way off, isn't it?
Sorry, but let me tell you that. Not so much. Today we
have very sophisticated machine learning tools capable of doing incredible
things. Let me present you a couple of them. Let's start
with code generators. If you're watching this talk, you've probably
heard of GitHub copilot. If not, stay tuned because you're going to
love it. GitHub Copilot is a tool capable
of generating code for an input. Still not clear.
Imagine implementing a method or a data
structure through a simple comment in your code. Just write
how you want it to work and that's it. It's a bit
dicing, right? It almost seems that it could
replace a programmer. But don't start looking for another
job yet. A code generator is just a tool and
needs a programming to work. It's like a hammer needs an arm
to hit. Can you remember that only one
person understand another? Imagine that customer who
doesn't even know what he wants trying to explain it to a computer.
Impossible. Programmers. Our job is safe
from this point of view. The birth of these kind of tools
is amazing for us. As long as we master them, we will
save an incredible amount of time. We will be able to implement
complex applications in a much more agile way.
And not only that, people with little experience will be able
to approach more easily and study more complex concepts
without having to spend so much time implementing them simultaneously.
This is benefiting programmers with deep knowledge and facilitating the interest
of new students in this field.
Machine learning, but of job, not just for programmers.
Have you ever used Photoshop or after effects?
If you have, I'm sure you agree with me that editing an image
or a video is not can easy task, not to mention audio.
However, I know a couple of artificial intelligence who don't think so.
For example, deleting elements in a video, including the watermark,
or stabilizing the image, or even adding more frames,
are just one sum of the things that algorithms trying
to understand the optical flow of a video can do.
On the other hand, images work in a very similar
way. They can even be put into motions into machine learning.
Once again, artificial intelligence make it possible for an
audience, without solving editing skills, to be able to generate content
of increasing high quality. And in turn,
it makes it possible for professionals to perform this
task faster and easier. And not only that,
it also offers new possibilities such as restoring all
photographs and making them look like they were taken by a modern camera or
a mobile phone. Or even isolating an instrument in a
zone that you can study. The notes thats display this open
up the possibilities for the birth of new businesses thats we
will soon see as a commonplace. However, there is something
even more impressive. Thanks to machine learning, in addition to
modifying multimedia files, it is also possible
to generate them. And that's incredible.
Let me show you. One of my favorite
examples is Dali. An artificial intelligence capable
of generating images just through description.
For example, an astronaut playing basketball with cats in a
space in a minimal style. And here it is.
Or if you prefer, teddy bears, working on
aa research on the moon in the 80s.
Granted, it's incredible. That's simply awesome.
But wait a minute. These images
does not exist. They are part of the imagination
of an artificial intelligence. Does thats mean that they are
creative? On this topic,
there is much debate. Especially because if so, that will mean that machines
come to possess one of the qualities thats we have said
that are part of us, of the humans.
But in any case, the key here is that the algorithm
needs an input to work. It needs a creative person behind it,
a person who thinks those crazy images.
And the only thing thats it does is to generate a series
of images based on others that it already knows.
This kind of technology will revolutionate the world of design,
but designers will not disappear. After all,
anyone is capable of asking for a bowl of soup.
That is a portal to another dimension, right? But only someone
who knows basket style can make the algorithm generate
this picture. So, as we have
seen, the future is for us to start working side by side
with artificial intelligence, eventually making it one
of our everyday tools. And that's
simply exciting. That's incredible, isn't it?
So all this brings us to a
new concept, the augmented intelligence. Augmented intelligence
is nothing more than the use of artificial intelligence to augment
your own capabilities. Okay, wait,
let's stop a moment. They may sound a bit like science fiction,
right? But let me give you an example. Remember when you
used to add with your fingers, for example, one plus
two, three. Oh, that's perfect. That was a safe method
with a very little margin of error, but it was also
tremendously slow and efficient.
Remember now, the first time that you use a
calculator, it took you longer to
type in all the numbers than to find the result of preparation.
The use of artificial intelligence will be exactly the same.
Right. Now, when we think about machine learning, we imagine an expert mathematician
typing like those codes right. And there is such a profile,
and it's very, very necessary. However, those algorithms will eventually
be packed, polished, and make available to anyone
who wants to use them. And you won't even need
to know all thats complicated mathematics behind it
for you. It will be as simple as learning how to use a
new tool, just like when you learn how to use a calculator.
And that's the key. Artificial intelligence will become so commonplace
that almost anyone will use it in their job.
The challenge will be to understand how these machine
learning algorithms think and how we must
communicate with them to get the results that we are
looking for. And thats skill, along with the other
three d web that we have discussed, will distinguish us as
the professional of the futures. But this
is a topic for another talk. Thank you for
joining. Thank you for being here. And I hope that it
was great for.