Welcome to my talk principium diving into the quantum
hardware ecosystem and today we are going to
look into the quantum hardware picture that is there
and what quantum hardware means, what are the different global
scenarios that we are looking into and what the current
and the future of indian quantum ecosystem looks like and what
are the different use cases that we will be going through. So moving forward
with the topic and the talk today.
So before we dive deep, I'll just give
a brief intro. About me so my
name is architect Shavastava and I have been fortunate enough
to found ATM along with my colleague,
which is a quantum hardware community focused on improving
and spreading knowledge about what the quantum hardware is.
And I have also in my college
days founded Circuit Quantum Research.
In my college which was RV College of Engineering and in quantum
Computing India, I, along with few of my colleagues,
we were fortunate enough to found the
quantum hardware learning circles that were there over there. I also worked
on various use cases and various topics
and it is a very good platform where we can learn a lot
of things. In my final year of college,
I was the quantum computing intern at Bose one QSI Private Limited.
Currently the company is one of the leading firms in quantum simulations
in CFT field. I am also
a quantum evangelist at Inaugurus where I
am working on the GKQCTP project and
how it can help India in the coming
years. And currently I am working as a senior technical consultant
at zero nine Solutions, Bangalore, Karnataka.
And personally I'm more interested in solving
use cases of quantum computing where we can
look into how to integrate quantum computing in the
areas of astronomy astrophysics if we look at the
motivation of the topic. So there is a lack
of knowledge about quantum hardware ecosystem and the need for growth in the domain.
And we need to increase and
spread awareness about various topics related to quantum computing
hardware. And there is an immediate need for people to indulge in the
development of quantum hardware to realize effective quantum computing solutions in future.
Because without effective quantum hardware solutions,
we cannot essentially look at having optimized quantum
software solutions also. So looking at today's
contents, what we have is first we'll
look into the introduction of quantum hardware,
then we'll have a global picture, then how the indian landscape looks,
and we'll also look at the different use cases that are there.
So a brief, not so brief introduction
about what the quantum hardware is. So when we talk
about quantum hardware, people think that this is a quantum computer and this is
the only hardware, but this actually is
not the only picture that we have. So this
is a relatively bigger picture if we see here, this is
what the scale looks like. So we have the qubit signal amplifier here,
the input microwave lines, the superconducting coil
lines, also the cryogenic insulators, quantum amplifiers.
This is the mixing chamber that we have here and various
other components like cryogenic shields and everything.
And we have various temperature gradation
happening also. So as we move down the dilution
refrigerator, the temperature decreases. And at
the bottom of the contraption we
have the qubit sitting where the temperature is nearly ten millikelvin.
So I don't think it will be fair enough if I call this
as the complete picture that we have right now.
If you look at the bigger picture more. So this is what a
quantum computer mostly looks like. So this
was the thing that we think is a quantum computer.
But actually this whole picture is what
the quantum computer comprises of. So we have the
qubit at the lowest end. We have amplifiers,
we have microwave electronics, we have the software
solutions also. And various,
various things that we can have,
we have here. So there
are different readouts, there is computation going on.
And a lot of things happen when we send signal and we receive
signal and how the circuits are connected.
It is not just the dilution refrigerator or
the picture that we generally see of a quantum computer,
which can be called as a quantum computer. But according
to me, this is what the whole picture of a quantum computer
looks like. What is under the hood of a quantum computer,
you have. First we have the user interfaces. As we
saw in the previous diagram. There are quantum algorithms and applications,
logic level compilation, circuit optimizations happening, quantum error
corrections, hardware optimizations, and various
stuffs happening. Along with quantum firmware, which is
called as the hardware error mitigation, we have various
things on that level and the physical qubit hardware that we have.
Finally, a generic quantum
classical interface. How it looks like is the quantum
classical interface involves several key elements required for
quantum computing, control and readout subsystems.
So these systems are distributed between
the room temperatures at 100 milli kelvin.
And so as we saw that
the temperature decreases as we go down. And we
also have a readout transceiver equipped with an integrated field programmable
array or FPGA. And there are various D
two cs ADC's, which allows a simultaneous readout
of multiple qubits. We also have a cryogenic CMos
brown chip that addresses the input output bottleneck
that is there. And we also have various
qubit test platforms that are there and qubit planes,
readout multiplexings. We have various applications,
quantum algorithms error corrections happening here, along with qubit control and
the classical computer. And we have controlled
readouts along with the routing and I O management
and readout multiplexing is also happening.
And at the bottom, we have the quantum chip
that is there. So if we look at the circuit diagram
also. So it looks something like this that we have read out resonators,
read out transceivers, read out control. We have a DAC.
And as we move down, the temperature starts
dropping. And this is a picture
what is happening on a very granular level that is
there. So if we move forward with the
talk, what we have here is how
the quantum computer looks. So if we look
specifically at the dilution refrigerator. So, we have various
parts like quantum amplifiers, cryogenic shields, quantum signal amplifiers,
input microwave lines, and in
a general or a very bird's eye view picture,
what we have here is the. The things that are happening
in various quantum computing fields are the quantum computing theory
that happens on the quantum complexity theory and the quantum algorithms.
In the quantum programming, we have this layer.
And in the quantum computing architecture, we have the system organizations
and Quantum Microsoft architectures. We have
the QVC and FT implementations, classical control interconnections,
topologies and floor plannings, technology building
blocks, which are the qubit interconnect technologies,
qubit storage and gate technologies.
So there are various qubit
architectures that we can look. And this,
personally, are my three favorite illustrations,
beautifully drawn by my colleague Abhir Vaishnav.
So, superconducting qubit, trapdance and photonic, these are
very common architectures. And there are various architectures that we
may look into. So if we look into
the superconducting qubit, that's that we have
here. So this is what a superconducting
qubit looks like. And we have resonators. We have.
So, in this picture, we currently have five
qubits and qubit one, qubit two. So these are various qubits.
And there are resonators in between for.
And there are. There are lines for input
and output that we can have. And this is a picture of
the condor chip that IBM announced,
and it has 1021
qubits that are there. And on a very bird's
eye view scale, this is what the qubit architecture looks like.
If you talk about the iron trap qubit
architecture, we use laser beams to control ions. To address the two arbitrary ions
in the string of trapped ions. It can be done with
beams, the red ones that we have here. And this method
can entangle two arbitrary qubits on the string of ions that are
there. The basic principle that goes
are the entanglement and superposition of the qubit.
So, this is how we realize an ion trap qubit.
So if we look into another simplified
model of a compact ion trap quantum computer demonstrator.
So, this actually is a simplified scale
model of the quantum computing demonstrator, housed into an
18 inch racks, which are there.
And the modules in the red correspond to the optical systems
that we have. And in the green, what we have is for the communications
and the readout. The blue is the electronics and amplifier is yellow is
the fiber routing and switching. And the purple is for miscellaneous of
the core module. So what we see here is
basically a concept of a compact antwrap
computer demonstrator. And this is from
the. From a paper named as the compact ion trap quantum computing
demonstrator. And it is a very good paper to get an
idea about the concept moving
forward. We also have the photonic qubit
that we have. So, in photon. Photonic quantum computing architecture,
photons are basically used as the basic blocks,
building blocks of a quantum computer. And, uh, photons are basically,
uh, entangled and, uh, sent into superposition. And the,
uh, readout results, um, are then, um, checked and,
um, maintained. And various quantum computing
solutions are also realized using a photonic qubit.
So. And the photonic qubits are
also relatively easier to realize than
the class, than the classical, uh,
superconducting architecture, which is very popular around.
So, if we move towards the global picture, how the
global picture is looking for the. For the quantum hardware.
So, the current global quantum computing market
is approximately valued as at $500 million,
which was in 2021. It is
expected to reach nearly $1.7 billion by 2026.
And the major investments are happening from the tech giants like IBM,
Google, and Microsoft, and significant
government fundings and private sectors. Investments are happening worldwide,
along with rapidly growing interest from sectors like finance, healthcare and logistics.
And these are not the only sectors that are attracting quantum computing
investments that can happen. So, if you
look at the picture of what the quantum computing
companies look like, uh, these are, uh,
only the 102 companies that are shaping the quantum computing landscape.
And it actually is, um, like just 102.
And it is a very, uh, dynamic and, uh,
continuing, constantly developing area there.
We are having a lot more companies popping up
on a daily basis. Uh, so we can have a very, um,
uh, like, bird's eye view of what different companies
are working on different technologies. So we have superconducting photonics
across industry and various companies, and we can see very
big, big names also over here, and very new
players also that currently are
working rigorously in the domain.
So if we look at how the
current global market for the quantum computing is look
like, so quantum hardware specifically is marketed,
is valued at 300 million
and it is projected to grow at 1.3 billion by 2027.
And there is an increasing competition
from startups and event trends. And if
we see the quantum computing global market to increase on a daily
basis, and there are a
lot of investments happening and a lot of innovations happening
regularly, and if we look,
what will be the long term benefits, we ask is
the enhanced computational power which
we get from these quantum computers are
driven to innovation and economic growth of any country that
follows it. It accelerates advancements in AI,
cryptography and material science. It attracts high tech investments,
talents in boosting GDP, thus increasing the employability
in any country, and strengthens national security through
advanced encryption and defense capabilities. Because quantum
computing in a very generic sense is very vast.
And quantum cryptography, as mentioned above, is one of the key
areas where a lot of development is happening globally,
and it will increase the security landscape
drastically that we can have, and it promotes leadership
in the global tech landscape also, and along with various international collaboration.
So it is not only if a country is developing the
quantum computer or the quantum hardware ecosystem,
but it happens based on how things
are looking and how intercontinental or intercountry
relationships work. And it increases
the level of technology
that we have. And any country that is
investing in also increases the
chances of better inflow of technologies
amongst them. And if now
we look at how the future looks like. So the expected
market size of quantum computing is 2.5 billion by
2030. There is a continued exponential
growth in the R and D investments, increased partnership between academia,
industry and government, and rapid improvements in qubit scalability and
stability, broadening application areas
like healthcare, finance and climate modeling. And the
quantum computing, like very various
fields that we have in major mega
science projects along the globe, is a
intersection between academia, industry and government. And quantum computing
for any nation cannot be realized without
the interaction and involvement of all these three together.
So it is a very holistic
space where all the three come together and develop
the whole country together.
And looking more
at India. So how the indian landscape
looks currently is the India
is coming out as a key player in the strategic investments
for quantum computing, and national quantum missions
and technologies and initiative that
government is promoting is actually helping the ecosystem
to grow a lot. And a lot of startups are coming on a
very regular basis, and resource institutions and academia collaborations
is increasing along with industry and the startup ecosystem that is existing in India.
And there is a focus more on quantum cryptography,
simulations and AI applications of India because it
serves as the need for the r for the development of various
other technologies in India at various scales
and for other future technologies for the quantum computing field.
Government is supporting various R and D projects,
R and D initiatives, assigning budgets
and fundings and development of skills in quantum technologies.
We also have so, uh, these are
very like one of the places
where and institutions,
communities, college groups which are promoting quantum computing
at various levels and both professionally in academia,
in industry, and I'm really sorry
if I miss out on a lot of
new upcoming initiatives or
companies, and these are
very few of them which I could have a grasp of and
I'm really fortunate enough to have been part of a
few of them from this. So quantum Computing India boson
QSI Akum circuit in a gris kino Labs UPI
AI is C IIT Madras TIFR
and these are various quantum computing
communities, companies, college societies,
initiatives and colleges universities
which are day in and day out working together to bring
up the quantum computing and hardware ecosystem in India.
If we look at the National Quantum Mission which the Government
of India has initiated, so it is intended to invest approximately
8000 crores of indian rupees over five years, which is focused
on fostering research and development and deployment of quantum technologies focus
on quantum computing, communications and sensing applications, which will help
in development of skilled manpower and established quantum labs and test beds,
which will help position India as a global hub for quantum technologies and
innovation. And if
you look for future of India, so because of the heavy
investment of government of India and by
the help of national quantum Mission,
we are going to have an increased
ecosystem of quantum computing in future. And we
currently also see a lot of quantum computing initiatives
and companies coming up on a daily basis and
they are fostering creating jobs in various areas.
Strategic partnerships with academic institutions and international quantum research
centers are also in place and are happening on a
daily basis and they are increasing the academia
industry interactions that happen.
And there are a lot of emerging startups which are focusing on quantum hardware
development and it is expected to that
the quantum computing market share of India will increase in
the future in the Asia Pacific region and also globally.
And India is anticipated to be
one of the biggest contributors in the quantum technology globally
by 2030 and focus on sectors
like cybersecurity, health, finance is underway and
various projects are happening in India which are focusing on this
like cuno Labs and various other
communities and companies working on it and
it aim, India aims to establish it as
a significant player in the quantum computing landscape that is there.
So if we move look at the various use cases that quantum
computing can address. So what we have with us is
a varied variety and an infinite amount of possibilities
that can happen. So we have protein folding, quantum chemistry,
design optimizations, supply chain inventory optimization,
disease risk predictions, finance modeling and portfolio optimization,
and various other. So these all areas
where quantum computing will be implemented based
on the quantum hardware that we, that we will be, we will be
having, will help in addressing various
scenarios and use cases in our daily
lives in the longer term, say 50 years or 100 years,
and achieve innumerable possibilities
that we cannot even think of as of now.
And giving a brief about
a very interesting topic. So this was my talk
that I gave at CoN 42 last year, and its name was inignoitis.
And I tried to touch very
slightly on how quantum computing can be used in
the area of astrophysics. And this
I presented as my
personal interest about how
it can be related to a very,
very different field and how it
can help in the development of that. So please
check this talk out and if interested,
just reach, reach out to me on LinkedIn. And I
hope that this talk gave you some information about how
the quantum hardware ecosystem looks like and how what
quantum hardware actually is. And I
wish you a great day. Thank you.