What if you could work with some of the world's most innovative companies,
all from the comfort of a remote workplace?
Andela has matched thousands of technologists across the globe to
their next career adventure. We're empowering new
talent worldwide, from Sao Paulo to Egypt and
Lagos to Warsaw. Now the future of work
is yours to create. Anytime, anywhere. The world is
at your fingertips. This is Andela.
Hi there, my name is Kazgir. I've been calling
go for nearly four years now.
Today I'd like to talk about how go works to bind
a port and listen for the port when starting an
HTTP. HTTP HTTP HTTP HTTP HTTP.
HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP HTTP server on
random available port inside of standard libraries. Net and
syscall. I hope you'll find it helps
you understand HTTP and TCP programming
in go. First,
let me introduce myself. I am a backend engineer
at autify. Autify is a no code AI
powered software testing automation platform.
You can find me on Twitter. I've been publishing
blogs and presentation materials on this
Twitter account. Please follow me and check it out.
Let me explain autify just a little more.
First, autify allows anyone to automate testing
with a no code solution. Otifi records
the user's action on the service they want to test and
converts it into a test scenario.
Second, AI updates test scenario
accordingly. As the application changes,
it dramatically reduce maintenance cost for the users.
We have two services, autify for web and OT,
five for mobile. We are taking democrats
from you.
Okay, let's get down to the main topic. Let's say
you need to implement an HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP.
HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP.
HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP. HTTP server
on random available port an HTTP server or
HTTP server. In this case,
the code does not specify a port where the servers land.
An HTTP server binds an available port dynamically
and listens to it. How would you implement this?
The answer is straightforward. Here is
a sample code with a minimum number of lines.
Look at the second argument of the.
Net list function. In the second line,
I passed dell to the second argument.
This way, the port assigned changes each
time the server runs. As you see in this slide,
the go document of the. Net package describes the behavior.
If the port in the address parameter is empty
or dell, a port number is automatically
chosen. Some standard libraries
invoke the listen function in this way. For example,
we can use the HTTP test library to start our
server for testing, but internally the
new server function called net listen
function, specifically the new local listener.
An unexported function in the HTTP test
library invokes netlistentcp function with
the port zero.
It's an excellent and easy interface
for us so that you can use this capability easily.
However, what I want to describe in this talk
is the specification and the internal implementation
of the. Net package by leading go code.
Knowing the internal specification will help you
make more profound design decisions.
For example, what kind of infrastructure is
suitable to deploy this HTTP server?
What is the range of network ports that
the server will bind?
This talk will give you the basic knowledge to answer these
questions. Let's have a
look at the signature of netless function.
The first argument network specifying the
network type the network must
be Tcp tcp four, tcp six,
Unix or Unix packet.
Regarding TCP, what you should specify depends
on whether the server instance supports IP version
four or IP version six. TCP four
means IP version four only, and TcP
six means IP version six only.
TcP indicates either IP version four or version
six. Then let's move on.
The inside of. Net listen function here
is a diagram visualizing the relevant
parts. The two main libraries involves.
Net and syscall.
Subsequent slides will provide more detail.
First, the listen function uses a.
Net listen or listen config extract a
helpful tip for your daily go life is that if
you want to pass the context on the application call side,
use listen config instead of listen.
Then next there are listen function of listen
config stack called default resolver
which resolves the network IP address.
Specifically invokes a method resolve
address list. It invokes many
functions, but the following method is relevant for setting the port.
It is lookup port lookup
port looks up the port for
the given network. For example,
if you provide a port zillow to this method,
it returns zillow. It is
an exported function of the. Net library so
that you can check the behavior directly.
The main point is that it does not
specify food port a server will run on,
but leave it at zero.
Next listen invokes a sys listener
that contains listened parameters and
configuration. When the network protocol is
TCP, it invokes the listen TCP function.
Then next listen TcP invokes
net internal socket, which returns a
network file descriptor ready for asynchronous
I O communication using
the network puller. This function
mainly handles low layer handling such
as OS socket types and system calls,
and so on. This code gives sock slim
as a socket type.
OS layer technology, such as a Linux main page defines
several socket types. When you start
an HTTP server, the network type is tcp
and go program uses a socket type SoC stolim,
a stolen oriented socket type.
Otherwise, when you start a UDP server,
it uses a socket type sock d glam.
It is a datagram oriented socket type
like this Google codes that perform network communications
internally select the corresponding
socket type. Then the
internal socket function invokes the function that
bundles necessary system calls according to the
socket type. For example, when the socket
type is SoC stolen, it invokes the listen stolen
function which handles listening to storing
oriented connections such as TCP.
It has been a long journey, but here we'll
get to the heart to answer our original question.
How does go implement to bind one available port?
Dynamically, the function executes
three system calls in order bind,
listen and get sock name bind
assigns a socket address specified by the given address
to the socket referred to by the file
descriptor. Listen marks the
socket referred to by the file descriptor as
a passive socket. That is, the socket is
ready to accept incoming requests using another system
calls. Accept Getsocnab
returns the current socket address.
We got to the answer the rule over random
port is the specification of the binds of
each operating operating system. For example,
if you start a server process on a Linux server,
the system called binds will bind to an
aheminal port. An ahemular port
is also calls a dynamic port, as is a port
that is used for only a short period of the duration of
a communication session.
You can see the port range from the bank specification.
For example, if you use Windows Server 2003,
support range is from 1025
to 5000.
We will learn that when you want to launch HTTP HTTP HTTP
HTTP HTTP HTTP HTTP HTTP server on random available
port. The three things first, you'd better
confirm the bind specification.
Second, you'd better check if your infrastructure
lecturer can use an ehminal port. For example,
suppose you use AWS Fargate, a fully managed container
orchestration service as an infrastructure.
In that case you can't binds a Hemine report because
automatic assign reserves them.
Third, you'd better check the range of a Hemine
report considering a network firewall
setting may be necessary if you use this capability
or remote server. You can see more
detail in this article. Please check it out.
That is for me. Thank you for your watching.