Hello everyone. Thank you for joining me at Conf 42. Today we are
going to learn about dynamic user interfaces, harnessing AI, and machine learning
for personalized, emotion aware experience. Picture this.
You are about to watch a movie and your tv already knows what you
are in the mood for. Or you are playing a game in an adjust the
difficulty because it can tell you are getting frustrated. Sounds like magic,
right? It's all thanks to AI and machine learning. Today we are diving
into how these technologies are transforming our interactions with devices,
making them more personalized and even more emotionally aware. Ready to see
the future? Let's go.
So what's on our magical mystery to today?
We'll start with a quick history lesson on user interfaces, then see
how AI is making them super smart. We'll check out some emotional aware tech
that's straight out of Sci-Fi dive into cool real world examples,
peak into the future, and wrap up with some important ethical stuff.
The evolution of user interfaces first,
stop the past. Remember the days of command line
interfaces? It was like speaking another language just to use
a computer. Then came graphical user interfaces with
windows and icons. Much better. Mobile and touch
interfaces made everything super intuitive. Just tap
and swipe. And now we have voice assistants
like Siri and Alexa and mind blowing AR and VR
experiences. You all must have heard about the Apple illusion Pro and
Meta's quest, so you know what I'm talking about.
The evolution of user interfaces has been a wild ride.
The role of AI in user interfaces let's talk
about how AI is shaking things up. Personalization is
the name of the game. AI learns what you like and
gives you more of it. Ever wonder how Netflix knows you so well?
Like you are streaming a couple of Marvel
movies or maybe some science fiction drama?
And then a week later, when you open up
Netflix on a Saturday night, all you're looking at is a
lot of content that is tailored fit for you. That's AI
at work. Emotion aware systems take it up a notch by
reading your emotions. Yep, your device can now sense if
you're happy, sad, or even frustrated. And adaptive
interfaces change in real time based on what you're doing.
It's like having a digital buddy who just gets you.
Let's talk about Apple's dynamic interface.
This isn't completely new and has existed in limited
forms for a long time. Technically, the battery meter
on your smartphone is a type of dynamic UI. It will
change color as you process through it.
These types of use cases are obvious, but what
we are seeing now are more interesting and nuanced ways to leverage dynamic
UI the best example is Apple's latest iPhone.
You all must have heard of Dynamic island, which is the
notch that has moved down on the interface and now has interactive elements
playing around it. And it also has cool features,
a lot of cool features.
So Apple is great at doing this. MacOS has adaptive
dark and light modes based on time. IOS 16
started to do this with lock screens. They leverage modes of
focus to then show you custom lock screens, wallpaper,
widgets and more. Now these lock screens are mainly manual
and can be engineered through automation. For example, iOS can
turn a mode on based on a location that you have, but that
needs to be set up by you in the first instance. You can use Apple's
shortcuts and a couple of other features to do this.
Customizability has always been a push for a digital product,
and one hypothesis here is that even Apple,
who's steered towards strict design with their
products, are now bowing down to Gen Z's driven demand.
Ways to leverage dynamic UI the cool thing about this is the
number of use cases one could have for mobile and wearable devices. These things
track all sorts of measurements, the Apple Watch being a great example. These things
are just the health trackers example.
They have features like temperature sensing, sleep tracking,
ECG, health notifications for
your heart and blood oxygen. Outside of wearables,
there's plenty that digital products can do to leverage dynamic uis.
Adapt core functionality as this will be used the most, and tailoring
to specific circumstances can be very helpful.
Tracking different data points to bring more specific information
to light at key moments, create intuitive changes like
location and time. Manual customizations when you have a large
amount of super users so they can control their usage too.
Imagine logging into your favorite app and seeing everything tailored just for
you. That's the magic of personalization. AI analyzes
your habits and preferences, giving you the perfect content. It's like
having a personal assistant who knows exactly what you want.
Netflix's movie recommendations are Amazon's product suggestions.
They are spot on because AI is behind the scenes, making sure you are
happy. Now let's get emotional. We'll talk about
emotional aware systems.
Literally, emotional aware systems use AI to understand your
feelings. Facial recognization can tell if you are happy
or sad. Voice analysis picks up on your mood from your
tone, and text analysis figures out your feelings from what you
type. These systems make interactions so
much more engaging and human like. Imagine a game that
eases up when you are frustrated, or a customer service bot that's
genuinely empathetic when you're upset. So let's talk about
the benefits of these emotional aware systems. Why do
we want our tech to understand our emotions? Has anybody ever asked this question?
That's because it makes everything better, more engaging interactions,
higher satisfaction, and greater loyalty. When your
tech knows how you feel, it can respond in ways that makes you
feel valued and understood. It's like having a super attentive friend who's always
there for you. So what are the
AI models that can help understand
and personalize your interfaces and also
show emotional awareness? Let's talk about AI
models for personalization and emotional awareness. Here is the
geek part. The AI models behind all is magic.
Supervised learning uses labeled data to make predictions.
Unsupervised learning finds hidden patterns in data without labels.
And the reinforcement? Learning is all about learning from experience.
It's like training a dog with treats. These models help AI understand
and respond to our preferences and emotions, making our interactions
seamless and intuitive. Integration of AI
and ML in UIs let's break down how
all of this works. First, we collect tons of data from user interactions,
clicks, browsing history, you name it. Then we train AI models to
predict your preferences and emotions. Real time
adoption is where the magic happens. The interfaces change based on what you're doing
right now. And of course, we need powerful computers to handle all of
this processing. And we have to keep your data safe and private.
It's a complex but fascinating process.
Let's go through a few case studies to understand how personalization
and emotional awareness works. So, case study one. Personalized learning
platforms lets see this in
action with personalized learning platforms, these AI driven
systems customize educational content for each student.
They analyze learning history and suggest the best materials.
For example, at the Southern Nevada Urban Micro Academy,
AI recommends lessons tailored to each students needs.
And during the pandemic, platforms like Prender helped students
learn at their own pace, leading to better engagement and
performance. AI makes learning fun and effective.
So what happened to the results? Studies in real world applications have shown
that these platforms significantly improve learning outcomes.
For instance, schools using AI driven platforms reported higher
engagement levels and better completion rates among students.
Let's go to case study two. Let's go to case study two.
Emotion aware gaming emotional
aware gaming involves integrating AI to detect and respond to the emotional
status of players, creating a more immersive
and engaging gaming experience. By understanding a player's emotions,
games can adapt in real time to enhance enjoyment and maintain
engagement. Are there any gamers
here? This one's for you. Emotional aware gaming uses
AI to detect your feelings and adjust the games accordingly. Facial recognition
and voice analysis gauge your emotions
and the game adapts, lowering difficulty if you're frustrated or ramping
up the challenge if you're bored. This dynamic adaption keeps
you engaged and makes gaming even more immersive and enjoyable. It's like having a
game that's always in sync with your mood.
Looking ahead, the future is bright and super exciting.
AR and VR are already giving us immersive experiences, but we are just scratching the
surface. Brain computer interfaces are next, allowing us
to control devices with our thoughts. How cool is that?
Future interfaces will be more natural and intuitive with voice and gesture
recognition. Making tech feel like a natural expansion
of ourselves. And multimodal emphasis will blend voice,
touch and gestures for seamless interactions.
Looking ahead, the future is bright and super exciting. AR and VR
are already giving us immersive experiences, but we are just scratching the surface.
Brain computer interfaces are next, allowing us to control
devices with our thoughts. How cool is that?
Future interfaces will be more natural and intuitive with
vision and gesture recognition, making tech feel like a natural expansion of
ourselves. And multi model interfaces will blend voice, touch and gestures for
seamless interactions. You can already see there's
a new company that has just come out called Human AI,
which tried a similar experience
for users. They launched AI product
that has no screens, no digital touch interface,
and all is done through your audio, your voice.
The device just captures what's in front of you and recognizes
what you're doing or what you're looking at. It'll just understand
and explain you what it means. Let's talk about a
couple of ethical considerations. With great power
comes great responsibility. As we innovate, we must address
ethical issues. Data privacy and security are top priorities.
We need transparency in how AI makes decisions and accountability for
those decisions. And we must prevent biases to ensure
fairness in AI applications, clear communication and informed consent are
essential to maintaining trust and integrity.
As we continue to innovate, let's ensure our advancements are inclusive,
fair and sustainable. Together, we can create a digital world that not only meets our
needs, but also makes us feel understood and valued.
Alright, let's wrap this up with a fun challenge. Imagine the possibilities.
What new dynamic UI would you create with AI and ML?
Maybe a virtual shopping assistant that knows your style, or a learning
platform that evolves with your interests? The sky's the limit. As we
move forward, let's make sure our innovations are inclusive, fair and sustainable.
Together, we can create a digital world that not only meets our
needs, but also makes us feel truly understood
and valued. This is Yashran Kotha
and thanks for watching.