You.
Hello, everyone. So in this talk, we will be talking about
protocols which are used to enable IoT systems.
And these protocols are wired as well as wireless.
So we will be discussing about various protocols
in this particular session. So, like,
the first question which we want to ask is why protocols
are important. See, to make any system work,
we need to have a set of instructions which are also known
as protocols. So to enable
IoT systems, we require certain set of protocols
which needs to be followed. And let's
see. So the Internet of Thing is something which is
realized by the interconnectedness of the devices.
So to enable this interconnectedness, we need
various protocols. And in things session we will see
which all protocols are needed. So basically there
are two types of protocol. One is wired and another one are
wireless. So first we will see wired protocols,
and after that we'll see wireless protocol.
And let me assure you that wireless protocols are much more interesting than
wired ones because wired ones is something
very basic which we can see like everywhere around us,
but wireless. Many new protocols
are coming up every other week for the
wireless Internet of things. So that part would be more interesting.
So let's start with wired Iot protocols.
So these, like, as the name says, wired protocols
or wired Internet of things protocols are enabled
through physical cables. Like we have
real physical cable which goes from point a to point b
to make sure that our system works.
So these wired protocols,
there are certain advantages of these things, like they
are more reliable and offers stable connection.
And these protocols are generally used to
make connection between sensors and the microcontrollers,
or microcontrollers and the gateways. And sometimes
if we are using like Ethernet Internet, then from gateways to the
server as well. So let's see, what are the advantages,
what are the disadvantages and various types of wired
Iot protocols. So, like as you can see in this image,
there are many small electronic
components connected with each other. So how these components
are talking to each other, that is
defined by these wired IoT protocols. So one
advantage of wired IoT protocols is they are much
more reliable because we know
a clear path from where the signal has to transfer from
point a to point b, and that path is through the wires.
So there are very less chance that some kind of interference
will occur or some kind of intrusion will occur.
And it offers better security because everything is
enclosed in a physical space and no
one from outside can read those things.
See, definitely it will offer better speed
because we know at our home also, WiFi is
always slower than the physical lan cable.
So same things applies here, because if we have wires,
we know like 100% the signal will go from point a
to point b. And the range, like it offers good
range because through wires, we can transfer the
signals from kilometers to kilometers.
But IoT also depends on the protocol,
like how the signals are being transferred. So the range is
something which may fluctuate for different protocols.
So let's begin and start with the most basic,
most basic IoT protocol, or let's say most basic
electronics protocol. This protocol is
used in almost like all of the electronic appliances,
be it your smart tv, be it your speaker, be it your
mobile phone, or be it your vehicle, or like
anything. UArt is the most basic protocol which
is being used. It is a serial protocol, like the
data goes after one after another.
And this is basically used to
enable the communication between two devices
over a shorter range of distances.
And it is very simple to implement. There are various
libraries and packages available for all the microcontrollers.
And this is the most basic protocols, which if you
are getting into IoT, you need to study about this thing and use it as
well. And there are some disadvantages,
like it can only be used for shorter distances
and interface interference is also
there. Second one is like I two c.
So advantage of I two c over any other
wired protocol is that we just require two wires
to enable this particular protocol. And we can
connect multiple hardware on those two lines.
So it works as a multimaster, multislaves.
Like, we just need to have two wires. And on
these two wires we can connect hundreds or thousands
of different devices or sensors
or actuators. And like each sensor or actuator
will have a particular address. So these two
guidelines, which we have, one is for the address and another is
to transfer the data. And this protocol is
also used in various sensors, if you startups exploring
any industry grade sensors. So most
of the sensors work on like I two C bus.
And it is efficient for shorter distances.
But for longer distances, there could be some synchronization
issues because see, like on two wires we are using so
many hardware. So some issues will be there.
But yeah, another thing to note down here is
if we decrease the number of devices
on I two C bus, we can increase the range or we
can increase the speed. So that is one thing
to note. Another important protocol for
like enabling wired Internet of things systems is
SPI. SPI is, let's say more advanced
version of the protocols which we saw
like earlier. So this also works on a master
slave architecture, but there is always one master in
this particular case, which is usually the microcontroller.
And these slaves will be all the sensors and actuators.
The advantage of using SPI is it works on
very high speed communication, and IoT
requires more wires. It requires four wires
to work for each slave. So, like,
if there are multiple slaves and
one master microcontroller, then the number of wires will
increase for SPI. And SPI is also used,
like in many of the gateways. If you see anything with
antennas, be it your Wi Fi router or be Iot
the cellular signals, antennas,
like these circuits, will be having something
or other which is working on these, like, SPI protocol,
because it is very high speed. Now,
these three were the most basic electronics,
or like IoT protocols. Now we will move to something which is specific to
industrial IoT, or let's say specifically
for IoT things. So one of the protocol is
modbus. This is very much used in industry.
Manufacturing. Like anything in your home which is manufactured
in some or other kind of factory must
have been gone through this modbus protocols, because these
machinery which is controlling that manufacturing plant
or the machines which are present in that manufacturing
plant is certainly working on things. Modbus protocol.
And it is very simple to use, and it is
widely used in manufacturing and other
industrial grade IoT systems.
This protocol, I think, like every one
of you have used, like, if you are a bit from
the older generation, because like earlier, we don't used to
have WiFi everywhere. So we used to have that lan
cable which we have to drag and put
it in the Ethernet or RJ 45
port in our laptop or computers.
So this is also like very old protocol,
which is still being used in many IoT
systems. This is used in industrial as well
as like home or office networks. Advantages like
high speed, it can support up to one gbps
of speed. Like, I have one gbps connection in my home,
and through WiFi, I am only able to get 400 to
600 mbps. But from Ethernet wire, I get exact
one gbps speed of Internet. And limitation
is like, you cannot drag it anywhere in
the house. It can only be enabled
at a particular place. If you have a cpu in your room, then you can
only use in that cpu. If you have laptop, then you have
to physically put this wire in your laptop.
You cannot use it, like anywhere in the house, like Wi Fi.
This is very interesting protocols, which is like
OPC, UA. This is like a unified
architecture which was formed by the consortium
of many companies
who work on Iot. So this is a standard.
Like, they made a particular standard for like, m to
m communication or machine to machine communication.
This protocol is also used in manufacturing and process controls,
like in your electricity grids or your water
system. Advantages like,
there are many companies who make their own products.
So all these companies thought like, let's make some unified
architecture for our IoT products. So in this thing,
you can have a gateway from Samsung and a
sensor from Siemens or a sensor from
Honeywell, and they all will be working with
each other. So this protocol provides interoperability.
But at the same time, this thing is a bit
complex to implement. But for
us, we always have sdks to just use these
things easily. So this is the thing,
another protocol, which is like almost used
in all of the vehicles, be it your two wheeler,
four wheeler, trucks, or anything else.
So this is a standard protocols for
your vehicles. You can also access a
part of this protocol if you have access to the OBD port
in your vehicle. So what usually happens is
if you are driving a four wheeler, there will be many things
happening, like engine rpm, coolant temperature,
the speed of the vehicle, the amount of the fuel present.
So all these things can be accessed through the can protocols.
We just have to plug in obd reader
and all these information can be read. So this particular
protocol is used in vehicles or
like vehicles, be it two vehicle, four wheeler,
or like trucks or buses or
anything. But IoT is not used in railways or like airplanes
for those things. There are very specific protocols which
we will not be discussing in this talk.
So the
scenario of wired protocol is very
small. Like, you only have certain set of protocols
and they work like that. There is not much innovation
happening in things particular field as compared to
the wireless IoT protocols. So let's move
on to wireless IoT protocols and see how that scenario is coming
up. So, in wireless protocols,
like we know, there is no physical connection. We can have
two devices present anywhere,
there is no physical connection between them, and they are communicating
with radio waves. So this is used in
variables like your smartwatch is sending the data to the phone
through bluetooth. Or smart cities where your traffic is
controlled by some IoT protocols,
like the street lights, it is controlling the street lights, or it
is controlling the traffic signals. There are remote sensors which are
reading the temperature, humidity, or like air quality values.
Transportation, where you can track your vehicle. Where is my
vehicle present right now? Or if you have booked an Uber,
you can track where is your Uber? Like, all this is happening through
wireless protocols. So, first of all,
we'll see what is the advantage. I think everyone knows. Like, it offers flexibility,
IoT offers mobility. Like you can move your things from
one place or one room to another and it will still work.
Scalability. So suppose there is a wifi in your house and you are
using four laptops with that. And suppose your friend,
up friend comes to your home, he or she also wants to use your
wifi connection. They can easily connect to your
network without any trouble. But same thing, if there was
a lan connection and you have to put an ethernet cable, then there
will be various issues. Like first of all you have to put a cable in
your router. After that your friend will use that cable and
like again, range. Like if we speak about 4g
or 5g connections, so they work like all over your city.
So it offers good range as well. Now first
of all, we'll go through some protocols which we all
have heard about. The first one is bluetooth.
So it is something which is for shorter range because bluetooth
signals cannot move beyond say 2020,
5 meters. After that they will start to decrease.
And in bluetooth we also have various
flavors of bluetooth, like we have ble, which is bluetooth
low on energy. So ple is used
for systems like your smartwatch because we need
to conserve the battery life in the watch.
We can trade off it with the range, but in smartwatch,
either way we don't need higher range, like maybe two or
3 meters. That's it. IoT is
present everywhere. Like any electronic
device you buy, be it any smartphone or
laptop, bluetooth will always be presented that. And now
Bluetooth is mostly used with Bluetooth speakers, Bluetooth headsets and
all these things. So Bluetooth is
like the most basic wireless protocol.
Second widely adopted wireless protocols is Wi Fi.
It is also used in many IoT systems.
See, most of your smart home things will be using
Wi Fi like smart lamp or smart speaker,
or if you take the case of Amazon Alexa.
So like alexa connects with the Wi Fi to stream the
songs or give any of the information to you. So it is used in local
area networks, smart homes, offices and these public
spaces as well. High transfer data rate.
I think with Wifi five or six, like we can
get one gbps of speed. But one thing
to note is it uses higher
amount of electricity, so you won't find Wifi
protocol like in the appliances or IoT devices
which run on battery. It is like
always present in something which runs on the mains power supply.
One important protocol for
IoT is Zigbee. Zigbee is mostly used in home automation
and the advantages it offers a decent
amount of range with very less electricity. So if you
have any of the IoT devices in your home,
which requires a special gateway,
that IoT device is most probably using a
Zigbee protocol. So, Zigbee is also
very similar to Wi Fi, where you need to have a router or a gateway,
and all the Zigbee clients will connect to
that particular gateway. And like, another advantage
is it gives us the
option to exploit the features of mesh networking.
So, mesh networking is something like, if there are four devices
present, four IoT devices present in your home,
they will relay their information from bones to two to three, and the
third one will relay it to the gateway and something
like that. So all the IoT devices will be able to connect
to each other and send, and finally send that information
to the gateway. Speaking about
the range, so, Zigbee gives a decent range of, say, 100 meters.
So that is decent for any of the smart home
scenarios. Another protocol, like in
wireless protocols, the scenario is there is always
a fight between two protocols. So there is a fight
between Zigbee and Zwave. So these two protocols
offer almost same advantages,
and they have same disadvantages,
but let's go through them.
According to me, I think in the war between Zigbee
and Zwave, Zigbee has already won
that war, and like Zwave is slowly
and slowly going out of the market. So, IoT also
offers same flexibility, that is
of Zigbee, low powered wireless communication. And it is also used
in smart home scenarios, mesh networking and all these things.
Now we will move to some interesting wireless protocols.
Like the first one is my favorite, which is Loravan.
So when we see
these particular protocols, they are called as
long range, wide area network,
or like wide area network protocols.
So these are also wireless protocols, but the
range is like 5 km or 8
km, something of that scale.
So, in Loravan protocols, you can place a gateway inside
your home. It's not very expensive, like you can
plays it in your home and in your city,
you will have your private network connection for
say like 5 km. So, like, any of the sensor
you place in that five kilometer range will have the access
to your private network. And these
sensors, the most important advantage of Loravan
is that IoT requires very low
amount of electricity. So the sensors, which are,
let's say, battery operated, can run for like
five, six or eight years without any interference.
So this particular protocol
offers long range with low
power consumption. But at these same time, there is the trade off
with the speed. So you won't be getting
any gbps or mbps of speed, like rarely
you will get five or six kbps
of speed, but it is still decent if you have basic
sensors for which you want to send the data.
It is mostly used in smart cities and like also in
smart agriculture. It is
very much low powered. Like a battery operated device
can also run for five years at least.
And transfer speeds
are pretty low. At the same
time, like in this particular space, which is like Lpvan, low powered,
wide area network. There are many other protocols. Another one
is nbiot. So, Loravan is
something which operates on ISM
frequency band, which is industrial,
scientific or medicinal. But like
NBIoT, for this, you need to purchase the spectrum to
run this protocol. And this protocol is
usually offered by the ISPs
or SIM providers in your
area. So if there is Vodafone,
like Vodafone will be providing 4G or 5G services as
well as they will be providing NBiot.
Similarly for AT and T or any other protocol.
So like one advantage of NBIot is
for these service provider or for these
network provider. These don't have to install additional antennas
to give access to this protocols. So if suppose at
and T already has thousands
of antenna in a country using those same
antennas, using those same four g, five g antennas, we can also give
access to this IoT protocol. And it is also being
used in smart cities asset tracking. And for
these also the sensors can be run on battery.
And they will be providing battery
life of say five, six years. I personally have used Loravan
as well as NBIot. And these two protocols are very
similar. The only advantage to go for Loravan is
like you can have your own private infrastructure, but with IoT,
you have to go with the network providers.
Another important protocols in this particular space is like
lp van space is Sigfox. So like,
speaking of the advantages, same advantages things gives low
power, long range connectivity. And it is
having same disadvantages,
which are like slow data rate and all these things.
So it is almost similar to IoT
and Loravan. But this protocol
is also slowly and slowly getting outdated.
So Sigfox is moving also out.
One important startup about which I want to talk about is
lacuna. It is project Lacuna.
And what these guys are doing is they are placing
Loravan sensor in these satellites
around the Earth orbit. And what they are
claiming is like if on planet Earth,
from anywhere, if you have access to the sky, you can see
the sky from your line of sight.
You can use Loravan protocol because those
guys already have the satellites in the space.
So if you have any of the application where things are
moving on a ship and you want to send
some data to your server, then you can use
Loravan protocol to send that information from
that ship to the satellite using Loravan protocols,
and that satellite will relay the information to your servers.
So, like in wireless protocol, many new things are happening.
Now, let's see, what is a comparison
between wired and wireless? We cannot say like
wireless is the winner or wired is the winner.
Like almost in every case,
these two things will work in conjunction
of each another. So if you have
IoT system, a complex IoT system, it is surely
using wired as well as wireless protocols.
The choice is up to you, like which wired or which
wireless protocol you have to use. But these two
protocols will always be used together.
Most of the sensors, actuators or microcontrollers
connection will be happening through wired protocols. And from
microcontroller when we are relaying the information to the
gateway or from the gateway to the server. Most of the
time we prefer to use wireless protocols.
So advantages of wired protocols is like
they offer very good reliability and stable connection.
And they are more secure because in wireless,
like someone can eavesdrop on your signal and try
to decrypt it. But in wired protocols, there is no chance like
anyone will be able to read your signal.
And wireless protocol advantages like you
can place your sensor anywhere. You don't have to care about laying the
wires or something like that.
And like in wireless, there are many protocol you
have to first understand your use case. After that,
choose between if your sensor or IoT
device will be having access to mains electricity
source, or you have to use a
battery to operate your devices. Maybe it could be solar
powered. And you also have to think
about the speed at which you have to transfer the data. If you
have some basic sensors, which just has to
send like a temperature or humidity values, then we
can use like LPvan protocols. But if you have some
IoT device which is sending like say a
video stream, then we require something high speed like
Wifi, or we can also use wired protocol like
Ethernet for that. So when
we talk about real world applications, like smart home
is one of the scenarios where IoT devices are
growing at a very fast pace. So in
smart home, if you see any of the device, IoT is using wired and
wireless protocols. Let's say you
have a smart led present in
your house. So that led is actually an actuator
which is controlled by a microcontroller. So that microcontroller
to led IC signal will be something over wired
protocol, but that MCU will
be connected to the server or to the Internet
via Wi Fi or Zigbee or any other protocols.
So both wired and wireless
protocol are being used similarly with these case of industrial
automation. Like suppose we have a factory where machines
are working together to manufacture your
products, something of the use. So those machines will
be controlled by a protocol, let's say modbus.
And in that smart factory, there are various sensors
which are present, let's say temperature and humidity
sensor, just to track the working conditions of that factory.
For those sensors, we can have protocol like Loravan
to send the data to the server and all these things. So in
short, like any IoT system will
be using wired as well as wireless protocol. And if
you are making a system, then first of all, you have to
understand your use case. And after that you have to see
which wired protocol I will be using or which wireless protocol
I have to use. So this is the trade off which you guys
have to choose. And I think all
for this talk. Thank you guys for
listening to my talk. And I am very much passionate
about IoT. And if you guys are also passionate,
then we can also connect on LinkedIn. Or if you have any question or queries
you can anytime ask me, I would be more than happy to answer it.
So thank you guys, have a nice day.