Hi everybody, this is Andrea from Forkbomb and I'm
here to tell you about the Xandrum virtual machine and its ecosystem.
I am on the Xandrum homepage, xandrum.org,
and I'm going to jump to the specs. So I'm scrolling down
here to the specs section and I'm going
to start from the bottom right. So Xandrum is written entirely in
c, meaning that we have binaries command
line for all servers on
all the architectures. We have libraries for Android,
iOS, and we also have a transcompiled version of
Xandrum running as a
Wasp module inside an NPM package,
meaning that Xandrom can also run in the browser or in
an old application. Xandrom can also run
in very small IoT chips
like Cortexm, and we have bindings for most
languages that you can ever need.
Zenroom has a very tiny payload, so the binary
is usually around a megabyte and it usually
needs around 500 k's of ram to do
its computation. It's fully deterministic,
meaning that given the same inputs, you will get the same output
on any platform you run it on, which is crucial for a
blockchain virtual machine.
What can Zendrum do? So, first of all, a lot of cryptography,
meaning a lot of different kind of signatures,
ECDSA used by bitcoin, Ethereum,
EdDSA, schnorr. We can also
do quantum proof signatures using the deletium algorithm,
which is one of the algorithms selected by the NIST
competition this year. And very important, Xandrum can do
a lot of blockchain interoperability for Ethereum,
bitcoin and more.
Zenroom can also do advanced cryptography such as xeonology
proof or offline xeonology proof like ZK
snarks. It can do multi signature w
to receive verifiable credentials and more.
Possibly the most interesting feature of Zen room is that
it can be programmed in can English like
domain specific language inspired by BDD
or Gerkin, which is designed to be
read and written by people with no
programming background. I'm going to scroll
down a
little bit further. So here you have all the latest
downloads for all the platforms, and here you have
instructions to use Xandrum in JavaScript,
Python, along with
bindings for a bunch of different languages.
I will jump to a demonstration
of the Zen code using our online
ide and playground API room.
I'm going to reload the page here, so when you
land on Apirom net you will see something like
this. So you want to start from the examples
here we have an extensive library of examples
to be used as a cookbook to write smart contracts.
So in the beginning you have generic
scripts to do all sort of computation.
Here we have a section for cryptography. So hashes, as you
can see, we can do different kind of hashes as SHA
256 and twelve kdf,
PBKDF, HMac, and we have
currently added a couple more, which we haven't documented yet.
Here you have features
that you can use to create microservices
using the Xenrome ecosystem. I'm going to go back to this.
You have a quantum proof section, so deletium
signature and key exchange mechanisms such as
kyber and interop.
Our Xeonoj proof Zkatesnarx
flows multi signature and
verifiable credentials. So I'm going to jump to
an example that can be easy
to use by most people.
So I'm going to produce ECDSA signatures
of a string and
an array of strings. So this
is what a Zen code script looks like.
The script is divided in three steps. The given step where I
load the data. This step is strictly read only.
In the second step, which is the when step,
all the computation happens. And in the third step, which is the
then step, the data produce in the previous step
is formatted and printed out.
So here I am stating my identity and loading
my key ring, which you can see here. This is
a bunch of private keys that can be used to do cryptography
and bitcoin as
a blockchain. Interoperability. Then I'm loading
a string which is nested inside
the JSON object, and I'm loading an array of
strings which is this. In the one section
I am first creating an ECDSA signature
of the array, which I'm later
renaming, and then I am creating a
signature of the string embedded
in the JSON object. In the last
four lines I am printing out the string,
sorry, the array of strings, the signature of
the array of strings, the string, and then the signature of
the string. When I press run,
the output of Zen proof comes out and this
is the string loaded. This is its ECDSA signature with the
usual RNS formatting.
And the same thing happens for the array. In the bottom
we have a bunch of information about the execution.
So the xenrome version, the git commit,
the curves loaded at the moment,
as well as the memory
usage and the execution time. So very
important to understand is that this smart contract that
I just executed runs here in the browser.
So this application in this situation
it's using zenroom transcompiled
in WASM and embedded into a node package, an NPM
package. So I run it again. You see that the
memory usage is always the same and the execution time is always between 30 and
40 milliseconds.
I want to tell you more about the blockchain
interoperability. To do this, I'm going to jump to the zenroom documentation
page so that zenroom.org
when you start here, you want to scroll down.
We have an extensive documentation of the
Zen code language as well as
how to integrate Xen proof in different
kind of applications. I'm first going to jump
to the Ethereum scenario.
So a scenario is in xen room, an internal
library that can be loaded at runtime
and contains several contains functionalities.
So here I am producing an Ethereum private key.
When I create the Ethereum key,
then I will create the Ethereum public key.
And based on that,
so based on the private key, I'm going to create the Ethereum address.
This is what the script looks like here.
If you scroll down, you will see how to create the transaction
and how to sign the transaction.
And the same thing we can do for Ethereum,
bitcoin, as well as hyperledger fabric, Hyperledger,
Sotooth, Yota and Planet Mint, which is a
new blockchain, a rewriting of big
can DB. You will now wonder what
you can use Xandrum for in this situation.
So using Xandrum, you can
effortlessly build a
browser based multi blockchain wallet.
So imagine metamask supporting bitcoin,
all its derivatives, ethereum and all its derivatives
plus fabric. And so,
and the same wallet can
run in the browser, or you can embed it in a PWA
and have it run in a mobile. And with very
little code modifications, you can also run it on react native
or as a backend application.
So here you have examples on
how to embed Xenro. For example in a node
application, the backend,
how to run it in the browser.
Yeah, so there is an NPM package
called Xen proof, and we have examples
to call Xen proof from Javascript, Python and
other languages as well.
Okay, this was the basics of xandrum. Now I'm going
to jump to the xandrum ecosystem.
So I'm going to jump to the forkbomb on page forkbomb
eU. Here we have
the summary of what I've just told you about the Zenroom stack. This is
again a page about Zenroom. So I'm going to jump
over, I'm going to jump over to Zentswarm.
What is Zentsworm within
the EPSI project?
EPSI stands for european blockchain service infrastructure.
We have developed a swarm of
blockchain oracles technology. So we have
packaged a Zandro microservice
into a node
based application to do
mostly blockchain interoperability.
So the oracle listens to
a blockchain, waits for an event, and when
a certain event is produced, then the oracle
is triggered. A smart contract is executed on the
Oracle, and the oracle can
reply by computing
something, for example for blockchain interoperability or
feeding the blockchain with data from the Internet.
For this, we have also developed a dashboard.
So here you have a screenshot of the list
of oracles active at the moment, and the screenshot was taken.
We have built in monitoring for each oracle.
Something you cannot really see here because the
screenshot is too small, is that when each oracle
goes online, it announces itself to
the network using a w three c did
document, which is something I'm going to go back
on in a second. Okay,
back to the forkbomb u homepage
after xanthworm, I'm going to show you Zantworm storage.
Zantmo storage is a distributed key value
storage for caching and sharding. Something I
didn't mention is that all the code you've seen is open source.
So here you have
the source code of Zanswarm. This is the
source code of densmore storage. And under GitHub.com slash
dine slash zendrum, you find the source code of Xandrum.
So what is densmore storage is a
tarantool based distributed caching
and sharding application that allows you to do
key value storage where both the storage and
the retrieval are based on policies that are coded
in the application. The last thing I
want to show you is our w three CD method.
So we have implemented
our w three CD method initially for the
appsy project. The very first implementation we did
was in order to allow the oracles to identify
themselves, and we're now growing it to be more
generic in order to accommodate human users,
to accommodate web services, or to accommodate objects
of different kinds. Our debut receded method
has a focus on cryptography. So in the w
three did document we have embedded
public keys for all the signatures that
we are capable of working with, including the
quantum proof delithium signature scheme.
And the w three ceded method provides
you blockchain anchoring, meaning that when
a did document is produced,
the did service stores
the did document also on blockchain and it
stores the blockchain
transaction in the did document, meaning that
the validity of the did document
can be checked on blockchain at any time.
Okay, I think that this is all I
will conclude showing you the
GitHub repo of Xandrum. So if
you go here, you do GitHub.com,
dime Sandrum and
here you can follow the development.
Thank you very much.