Hello. My name
is Andrey Slastenov, and I am the head of security at Gcore.
One of my primary goal involves protecting our customers
from DDoS attacks, and we have extensive experience in
this area. Additionally, with a highly distributed
infrastructure capable of repealing attacks of more than 100
terabytes per second, we have such number of customers
protected within our data centers and worldwide.
We are always up to date with the latest cyber threats
trends and gather comprehensive statistics on both existing
and zero day threats. As we examine the
landscape of cyber threats, it's crucial to recognize that
the escalating scale of the DoS attacks. In the span of
just two years, we have witnessed a significant surge
in the average attack size. In the beginning of 2021,
we saw average attack peaking at 300 gigabit
per second. Fast forward to 2022.
That number has more than doubled to 650
gigabit per second. And by the beginning of 2023,
we're facing average attacks of 800 gigabit per
second. This trend is not just a set of
numbers, it's a clear signal that attackers are becoming
more powerful. And as we go into the evolving landscape
of cyber threats, IoT becomes evident that the increase
in these DOS attack size is closely linked to their increasing
of IoT devices. What is
interesting that the generation of attacks exceeding
one terabit per second has surpassed the capabilities
of cluster of servers, or virtual machines
to execute such strong attacks, thousands of widespread
devices with high data transfer capabilities are necessary.
IoT and 5G technologies are particular suitable
for this purpose, as they offer exactly their
characteristics. Why are IoT and
5G devices frequently used in cyberattacks?
Let's go into that topic. Many of devices,
while technologically advanced, have lag
in one critical area, security.
They may run on the software that is not regularly
updated or might still use the default passwords
that were shipped with. There is vulnerabilities like
open doors for cybercriminals.
Just take a moment and think, when was
the last time you updated your home thermostat
connected to the Internet or changed its factory
set password? Well, this is not just a personal
oversight, it's just a collective secured gap.
These is devices are usually made to be easy to use,
but not always secure enough, making them easy target for
the hackers. With five g now in the
picture, there is security problems can get just much worse.
5g fast speed and the better connection can turn a
small security issue into big cybersecurity
problem very quickly. So securing these
is devices extends beyond just a regular updated and
strong passwords. We need a complex security strategies
that recognize and effectively counters the risk of
IoT and 5G technologies. Want to
know how the big problem is? Look at the
picture on my slide. So I get this information from
very popular showdown site which showing by
some filtering rules which I put
there like you
can see that I just searched for the microtech with open
port 80 and you can see how many devices
is there open for the access
through the Internet. So this is a huge
problem of such kind of devices.
Let's explore the structure of their attacks.
Typically they involve key
elements. These attackers a command and control center
and network of bots known as the botnet.
Looking at the mechanics of DDoS attack in the
context of IoT drive and botnets, we can identify these several
steps. The first step involves the
attacker selecting their target. This target could be
a specific device, a website or an online service.
These choice of target is often strategic,
aiming to cause maximum disruption or damage.
For instance, targeting a financial service website could
have a far reach implications affecting the numbers,
users and transactions. The next
step is orchestrated by the command
and control center. This center act as the
orchestrator for the entire botnet. It sends out the
attacker instructions to all of the compromised IoT devices.
These instructions are to start sending requests,
typically in overhauling manner to chosen
target. The command and control center does
not just initiate the attacks, it also coordinates the behavior of
entire botnet, ensuring that the attack is sustained
and effective. The final step is
the actual execution of the DDoS attack. All the bots in the network
now acting under the instructions from the comment and control
center, start sending large volume
of the request to the target. This volume
of traffic is intended to overhand the target resources.
For website, this could mean making it inaccessible to
legitimate users, essentially taking it offline
for device or server. This could lead to system
crashes or several disruption in
traffic functionality or the surface.
As we go deeper into the complex structure of IoT drive
and botnets, it's crucial to understand that their
threats extend beyond the just launching DDoS attacks.
Botnets represents a complex and layer of danger, not only because
they can disturb the services through DDoS, but also
due to their ability to continuously
and recruit other IoT devices. This self propagating
nature of botnets makes them especially threat.
As such, compromised devices becomes a tool for further
expanding the network. Let's talk how
botnet infect another devices. Botnet periodically
scan the Internet for vulnerability. IoT devices
these could be anything from home security cameras
to smart thermostats. Many of their devices have
default or weak passwords, making them easy target
the betnot net use automated tools to scan the
vast ranges of IP addresses,
looking for the devices that respond and show signs
of the vulnerability. Once a vulnerability device is
identified, the attacker exploits these vulnerabilities to gain the
control. This often involves injecting malware into the
devices. The malware is typically sent from
load these servers, which stores the malicious gcore.
The code is designed to give
the attacker remote control over the device, and can
often evade basic security measures.
After device is compromised, it becomes part of
the attacker's botnet. It now responds to the commands from
the command and control center. Just like other infected devices.
The newly recruited bot is ready to participate in the
DOS attack or any other malicious activity dictated by
their botnet apparatus. And also
the infected device may report back to the command and control
center. It may relay information about its
capabilities, location, or even find
a report about these vulnerable
devices in the same network. This information
is used to further expand the botnets or to optimize
the attack strategy. The process of infecting IoT
devices and incorporating them into the botnets is pretty
straightforward for the attackers. This underscores the critical importance
of securing the IoT devices.
Well, in the first half of 2023 alone,
we have witnessed a huge over 300%
increase in IoT driving these DDoS attacks. This unprecedented
rise is not just a number, it represents a significant and growing
threat to our digital infrastructure.
It's important to note that 90% of their sophisticated
attacks are based on the botnet. There is multivector attacks
combine different types of attacks patterns
and this make them harder to defense against.
These DDoS attacks has far reaching and often devastating consequences
for businesses and organizations.
It can be like direct financial losses.
So the financial implication of the DoS
attacks is easy to measure.
For instance, online store in 50,000
euro per hour will get the same amount of losses
for every hour of downtime caused by the DoS
attack. Another potential threat is the
loss of the customers. In industries where
the competition is huge,
downtime can drive customers to competitors compensation
expenses. Particularly for service based businesses
like SaaS, there is often expectation
to compensate these clients for the downtime.
So it's also oding to the financial strain
caused by the DDoS attack itself.
And the final one, the loss of customer loyalty.
So the Internet provides a powerful platform for customers to
voice their dissatisfaction. So negative
reviews can deter their potential customers, leading to a
loss of business and customer loyalty.
So in the light of the increasing threats posed by
IoT driving the DOS attacks, it's imperative that we
discuss the best practice for safeguarding our devices
and the networks. Effective protection
measures are not just an option, they are necessity in
this rapidly evolving digital landscape.
From IoT devices side the first and fundamental
step is to change their default password on
all IoT devices. Default passwords are often easily
guessable and are common entry for
point for attackers. By setting strong unique
passwords, you significantly reduce the risk of your devices
being compromised.
Also, you should regularly updating the firmware of
your IoT devices to fix the
critical vulnerabilities.
Manufacturers often release firmware updates
to patch the vulnerabilities. By keeping your
devices up to date, you always ensure that
any known security flows are addressed promptly.
Another point is implementing strong notification mechanism.
This scope may include two factor notification
or digital certificates. Strong notification
ensure that only authorized users can access and
control your IoT devices and the final
one is exploring and considering IoT
security frameworks. So these is frameworks provides
the guidelines and best practices for securing IoT
ecosystems.
Adhering to their frameworks can help
in systematically securing devices and
the data they handle from the network
site. It's crucial to protect against IoT driving
botnet attacks with specialized DDoS protection
solution usually this solution is not on premise,
it's cloud based. So there is solution
designed to detect and mitigate the DOS attacks, providing an additional
layer of defenses. They are especially
important for organizations which
is heavily rely on line services and so
they are at higher risk of being targeted.
And usually the cloud based
DDoS protection systems can provide a huge
amount of capacity so
they can sustain the attacks which is going over one
terabit or even thousand of terabit per
second. And let's now
look at the real world example to better the
dynamic of IoT botnets attacks and how it was successfully
mitigated this case studies from
Gcore provides developable insight into the nature of these
attacks and importance of the robust response strategy.
The client faced a DDoS attack that was highly distributed
involving numerous of devices. The attack method used
was known as the carpet bombing which utilized UDP
traffic to overhelm the target. This type
of attack is particularly challenging because it
spreads across multiply client addresses, making it
harder to isolate and defense against
such kind of attack. This not only made it difficult
to detect the attack, but also led to the overloading
of uplinks, that is their cumulative traffic.
The big volume and distributed nature of the attack posed
a significant threat to the client network.
Well, the key to our success
was identifying the common pattern in the attack.
So usually the botnet used
the pretty similar devices and pretty
common the attack patterns which can be
easily identified. Like for example, you have 1000 of
devices which is doing the same
thing and using the same approach for the attacks.
So the
good analytics system can help you to
identify that pattern and block such kind of attacks.
The post investigated investigation that we did
revealed that the attacker used the botnet exploit
in the health check kiosk. These kiosks were
used to construct the botnets network, demonstrating how
everyday devices can be weapons.
So as you see on that pictures, our analytics
system easily detect inside the packet that red
highlighted pattern which was used to block the
whole attack. The size of attack
was almost one terabit per second.
So in the previous slide, we examined a real
world case study of IoT botnet attack.
Now let's discuss the key elements that enable us to
sustain and mitigate such attacks effectively.
Understanding their tools and strategy is crucial for any organization
looking to improve the cybersecurity defense, or who just
want to use these
third party vendors to provide them
the DDoS protection services. So the first line of
defense against widespread IoT botnet attacks is their distributed
architecture and distributed infrastructure,
seamlessly integrated, in our case, in our CDN
content delivery network. This setup allow
us for the distribution of the network load,
preventing any single point of failure in the face of the
huge DDoS attack.
This distributed nature helps to absorb and dispense
their massive
amount of the traffic, thereby safeguarding the core
services and assets. The role of sophisticated
analytics cannot be overstated. In today's digital age,
there is attack patterns are complex and constantly evolving.
Traditional static defense mechanisms are no longer sufficient.
These is systems provide agility and
intelligence necessary to identify, analyze,
respond to threat in real time. These is
system learn from each attack and provide the necessary data
for the next element. And the next element is
deep packet inspection plays a pivotal role
in our auditos protection system.
Deep packet inspection goes beyond IP address filtering.
It examines their data within the network packets.
Attack can be blocked not only by IP and protocol
headers, but by the content of the packet itself.
So as the conclusion, first let's acknowledge
the paradox of progress. While five G and IoT technologies
bring unmatched connectivity and convenience,
they simultaneously escalate the threat of landscape,
particularly in terms of sophisticated these DOS attacks.
These dual nature demands our attention
and action. The enhanced speed and connectivity
offered by 5G are not just a bonus for our digital
lives. They also amplify the potential severity of the cyberattack.
They vary features that make
5G revolutionary also make it potential
for malicious activities. When it
comes to IoT we face a vulnerability crisis.
Many of their devices are not fortified with robust
security measures, making them attractive and easy
target for cybercriminals. So these
vulnerabilities is not just a risk, it's just a gaping hole
in our digital defense.
Well, addressing these risk is not just a
task for tech experts. It secured a collective.
So we need the widespread awareness about their threats and
the implementation of standard security protocols across all
IoT and 5G devices. It's a shared
responsibility to fortify our
digital system, not only from,
let's say, the organizational side,
but from the user side as well. And lastly,
I want to recognize these value of the specialized high
capacity DDoS protection systems, because usually
you cannot avoid or
fully mitigate IoT based DDoS attack
because the high volume of the traffic. So there is services
equipped to handle the scale and
complexity of the attack in the IoT environments.
So they provide an essential layer of the defense and
can sustain more than several terabytes
of attack. I think that's all for today.
Thank you for your attention, and I'm ready to answer
any of your questions. Thank you.