Everybody. My name is Mardente, I'm a
principal engineer at Cisco Systems and my
talk today is about scaling secrets in Kubernetes,
a secure multi cluster approach, essentially how to manage
secrets when you are dealing with a fleet of Kubernetes
clusters, data security is
critical as we and that includes keeping secrets
confidential. So first of all, what is a secret? A secrets can be anything
like APIs, keys, password, certificates,
SSH keys, and if those falls into the
wrong ends, it can have serious consequences.
Secrets management system address this problem by storing
your secrets in a secure encrypted format,
which makes it more difficult for attackers
to steal them. And also the secrets management system also
provides a simple and secure way for authorized
user to use this information. So there are a lot of benefits of using
a secrets management system. As I
mentioned before, security secrets is never
stored like in plain text. Secret is always stored like using
strong encryption. And only authorized user
can access this information. Convenience,
because you have a single place where you can go and
create, update or delete your secrets.
Doesn't matter wherever you are, as long as you have access to the secrets
management system, you can do that. And the secrets management system
provides you with detailed audit logs so you
know who has access what and when. And this is
important because it helps you comply with security regulations.
And also if an incident happens
now you know where to start from, you know what information has been accessed by
whom, and so you can start from us tracking from there.
What if your applications are running in a Kubernetes cluster? How do
you manage your secret? In that case, we listed
the benefits of using a secret management system, which means
clearly we want to use a secrets managing system. But the secrets management
system does not run in your Kubernetes cluster.
So you need an application running
within your Kubernetes cluster that can access
the information present in the secrets
management system and makes it available to the application running
in your Kubernetes cluster. External secrets operator is
one of those tools. It's an open source tool. It integrates
with AWS, SQL manager, Azure Control,
Azure, Google SQL Manager, IBM Cloud and
many more. And what it does, it synchronize the content
that is present in the secrets in the secrets
management system into your Kubernetes cluster.
So let's see how that is done. In this example,
we have a cluster and the external secret operator
is running within this cluster and we do have a Google Cloud
secret manager and the external
secrets operator has been provided with the confidential and
information to access the Google secrets manager.
The external secret operator detects that there is a secret in
the Google Cloud secret manager and syncs it into
the Kubernetes cluster. And it does it by creating a Kubernetes
secrets into the Kubernetes cluster. Now the content of this Kubernetes secret
matches the content of the secret
present in the Google Cloud secret manager,
which means another ten point like any application running in the Kubernetes cluster
can access this
information. But the external secret operator doesn't stop
here. Let's say that we update the secret
in the Google cloud secret manager because that's the only place where we want
to create, update or delete our secret.
Now the external secret operator detects that
a change has been made. It knows that at this
point the cooperative secrets is out of sync compared
with the content that is present in the Google Cloud
secret manager. And so it updates. And now your Kubernetes
secrets thanks to the external secret operator is back in
sync with whatever you have in the Google Cloud secret manager.
Now this works perfectly if you have one cluster,
but what if you have a fleet of Kubernetes clusters to manage?
Well you may think that you want to install external
secret operator, deploy external secret operator in each one of the clusters that
you manage, but that is the wrong approach. It's not
scalable and error prone. Think about the case where
first of all you have to configure the external secret operator like in times.
But think about the case where you want to change
the credentials used by the external secret
operator to use to access your secrets
management system. Now there are place where you have to go and
update this information. So if we have a fleet
of cluster, this is where Sveltos can come and
help. Sveltos is a Kubernetes add on controller.
So if you have a fleet of Kubernetes clusters using Sveltos,
you can programmatically deploy add
ons and application in this fleet of clusters.
How does Sveltos work it run in
management cluster. So you have a Kubernetes cluster which you use a management cluster.
Sveltos is running there cluster profile is the
custom resource definition which is used to tell Sveltos
which add ons and application to deploy where on
which clusters and then you have a fleet of Kubernetes
clusters. Those can be cluster API power clusters.
Veltos has built in support for clusters API power cluster which means
that if you create a cluster using cluster API,
there is nothing else that you have to do as Sveltos automatically
detects those clusters and can manage application and advance in those clusters.
But then you can have any other type of cluster,
GKE cluster, Sivo cluster, rancher,
any type of clusters you can easily register to
be managing by Sveltos. The only things that Sveltos
require is that there is a network connectivity from the management
cluster to the cluster that you want to be managed by Sveltos.
Cluster profile as I mentioned, it's the
CRD that is used to tell Sveltos what to do
and it contains like few sections in the spec.
The clusters selector field
is a Kubernetes label selector which selects all a set
of clusters. In this case it's selecting all the clusters which have label
environment set to a theme which stands for
functional application. Then it has an helm chart section.
In these helm charts you can put one or more helm charts and
what Sveltos will do, it will take each one of those and will
deploy those in every cluster matching the cluster selector. In this case
we only have Caverno. So Sveltos will deploy Caverno version
2.6.0 in every cluster matching the cluster selector environment.
Functional application. Then you have a customization
ref section and you
have a list of customization configuration. Here each one
of those entry points to a directory
which contains customized files. What Sveltos will
do will run the customized SDK on top of those.
We'll take the output which is set
of Kubernetes resources and we'll deploy those Kubernetes resources in every
cluster that matches the cluster selector. And finally you
can put the Kubernetes
resources you want to be deployed in a secret. So in a config map,
both secrets and config map have a data section
and so in that data section you can put one or more Kubernetes resources.
You can use both Yaml or Json.
What Sveltos will do we'll take the content of any secrets and config
map that is referencing and will deploy in every cluster which is
matching the cluster selector. Now another
strong point for using Sveltos is that anything
that you want to be deployed can be expressed as a template. And Sveltos
has the ability of instantiating these templates using
resources which are present in the management cluster
at the time of deployment. So in this example we're telling Sveltos
take the content which is present in the config map into the full name
space called info. Know that this is a template
and instantiate it using the
content which is present in this secrets in
the management cluster in the default namespace called autoscaler.
So let's see how we can integrate together external
secret operator on Sveltos to efficiently manage
secrets in a fleet of Kubernetes clusters.
Well, it's very easy to do. So we'll start creating one
management cluster and in this management cluster we deploy both Sveltos
and the external secret operator. Then in this
example we have two managed clusters, one GK cluster and one
cluster API power cluster. We have a
Google Cloud secrets manager and we configure external
secret operator to synchronize
whatever information, whatever secrets is present in the Google cloud
secret manager. So what external secret operator will
do? In this case, it detects that there is a secret
called Sveltos secrets in the Google Cloud secrets manager.
It takes this information and creates a secrets in the Kubernetes cluster.
In the management cluster, Sveltos has been
instructed to watch for this information,
take this information and pass it to every managed cluster.
So at this point you are secret.
You added your secret in a single place, the Google
Cloud secrets manager and you're using the external secret
operator to sync that information into your
management cluster. And then you're using Sveltos to propagate this information
to every cluster that you manage.
What happens if the secrets gets updated?
We go and update the secret in the Google cloud secret manager
well, external secrets operator, as we saw,
detects that there was a change
and updates by updating the Kubernetes
secrets management cluster. And now Sveltos detects that
the external secret operator has updated the secrets that they manage and
it takes the content and updates the content like in every managed cluster.
So it's very easy and programmatical way of
efficiently managing secrets in a fleet of
Kubernetes clusters. If you want more info,
you can check this Sveltos repo, this GitHub.com project,
expanders and or the external secrets
operator Repo, which is again on GitHub external
secrets external secrets thank
you so much. That's all for me. Thanks a lot.