Hello everyone. How are you doing? My name is Jeronimo Medina Madruga,
and today we are going to talk about how to use Python
to create better math lessons. Jose da Silvera
Alvis is my advisor in my master's course and
has contributed to the creation of this content.
My masters these is in the field of
mathematical educators at the Pepe match program
in the Federal University of Pelotus, and it still is
a work in progress, but it already gave me so much information
that I use part of it to create these talk.
My research is on how to use programming
to teach math to teams,
and at this moment, I have already read articles,
papers, books and thesis from all over the world,
trying to comprehend all the possibilities that technology
may add to the classroom. This talk will be very
light hearted, it won't be very technical, because there is
so much to talk in such a short time
that I think that if I went too deep in one or two tools,
we would miss the whole universe that is around
it. So if you want to
go deeper in some of the topics, you may
contact me. In the end of these
talk, there is my information, my contacting
information, and if anyone may not have
noticed my accent, I would like to say that we
are from Brazil,
specifically from the south of Brazil, Hugh grand du Su.
And when we talk about Brazil,
it's the land of the best football there is. Especially when
we say that the real football is the one that we play with our
foots and the most amazing combination of samba,
Captain America and Mickey, something that you never see on
Disney plus. So if you notice some little failures
in my english, please just know that that is
my second language. And now, jokes aside,
I love to work with quotes and from my favorite authors,
I think that in this talk, I would be
obligated to come with Kitty Yates,
the author of the book the Math of Life and Death.
His quote is very interesting because I think that connect
with the emotion that I get
when I start reading. All the experiences and many
scientists and authors that have before me
already went very deep
in this field of knowledge.
So the beauty of mathematics lies
first and foremost in its ability to act as
a practical tool to make sense of our complex world.
That's a great invitation to rethinking our
way that we view math, learning and
tech, because a lot of time we just think about numbers,
but we don't really connect them to our reality
somehow. So I would say that this is
the main topic of this talk, to rethink our relationship
with math and tech.
And the first question I would
say that my research led me to was
a traditional question, like, how do
students see math? And most of
us may have that impression that everybody hates
math because everyone criticize it, has problems.
But we are going to see that that's not really the
reality. Most teachers, like this
one that I'm quoting here,
actually show that students like math, or most
of the time they don't hate it. But it also points
out that the students have problems understanding
where they are going to apply the concepts. And sometimes that may be
one of the motives that leads them to not understanding
or even trying to go deeper in the
field of math. So it's really
important that educators understand that and start
to see how the students see
math, not only what they are trying to teach.
And although we may see that
students don't really hate math,
at least here in Brazil, we are seeing, and most countries
in development, we are seeing that the
performance and evaluations of
the students is not going so
well. Most of these countries are suffering. Some even
are not evolving. And that may
be indicated by tests such as Pisa.
And we have to really understand that,
okay, we have students that like math, but we aren't able
to improve the quality of our education.
And although we
are unfortunately not improving the quality of our education,
we are seeing a world that needs most of
our math. We are seeing that
almost the new careers,
new jobs that are arising within this information
technology, the digital age, they are connected
to the traditional Stein fields, which is science,
technology, engineering and mathematics. And we
might even say that some of the manual labor
shall be automated in the next decade more
than it has happened before. And that
makes us think what we are going to do, how we are going to
make this transition. We are going to have to
really rethink what we are teaching, how we are teaching,
because we need more than ever to have
students that are really good with the technical side,
with math, with technology. And that's
really important. And another quote
that I think that's essential to this little
revolution that I'm trying to spark here is from Seth Godin
in his free e book, stop stealing dreams,
when he's talking about how fast the modern
world has changed because of technology and
the industry and everything. He says the economy
has changed, possibly forever, but the school hasn't
changed. So it's really important that we understand
that our education, how it's functioning
today, and how can we change it for the better. I'm not
saying, like some may say that, oh, our education sucks,
let's burn the books. Let's throw everything away.
But I think that we can really do better than we
are doing as of this moment.
And in order to do that, we must first
ask ourselves, how are we really learning
math traditionally?
Well, I think that everybody that has done
calculus, algebra, geometry, shall remember
these infinite amount of exercise that our teachers recommended
to us, hundreds exercise of calculus,
of integrals and euler theory.
And these repetition might be
essential to understand how to solve the equations
and problems. But does it
help us to understand what really is going
on beside the numbers, beside the solution itself,
what it represents in reality? How does
it connect? And does that motivate the
students? Or it might make them a little miserable
and frustrated when they have issues. Because a
lot of times some students may have trouble
understanding how to calculate something,
and because they don't even understand how it
connects to the world around them, they just give up.
And on top of that, when we are talking about
math, we are mostly talking about X-Y-Z
delta angles, using square root,
euler and quadratic equations.
But can we translate those
variables to reality? Well, we can. But are we,
can we connect our studies with what we
see around us? Do we really understand what it's
being represented in the problems that we are solving?
I think this repetition and abstraction might
be the first problems that we might see with
the traditional education. And then
we have to think, do the students really learn from this?
From my personal opinion and from most that
I have found from my research, I think
it's safe to say that we have real issues to
deal with when we talk about learning, especially when
we talk about math. If we look at the numbers from
universities, from schools, we may see that
most subjects that are connected to math have
a really high number of students who fail or drop out
of classes, or even the traditional educators or
course. And most of the time it's due to having
a really poor foundation of these concepts that are
required to understand.
So we really have to change when
you are talking about teens and kids, how they are learning,
so they really think that they understand
more math, not just, oh, I know how to use this formula,
but I don't know anyway how this connects to
my reality. And okay,
we get that students like math, but studying math
in the most traditional methods suck a little.
But still, there is another piece to
this puzzle, which is making the school, these teachers and
the students understand how important
math is in our modern world.
And this
meme makes me think, because sometimes we see
people just reading at these screen and trying to do everything
that they learn from it, or they see,
I don't think that's learning most of the time. We even call it
sometimes in programming, the famous tutorial
hell where people just learn to repeat, repeat, repeat what
they see on YouTube and other
channels, other media, but they don't really think,
and that's really important. In order to
have a better education, we must first
have to stop thinking only in solving the equations and
drawing graphs for the most of our time,
learning math, and really make the student a protagonist in their
quest for knowledge. The student have to
know what they are learning and have a genuine
interest in that.
And the great part about all of this is
that, at least in theory, we already may
have a lot of answers. We have seen the rise
of many pedagogical strategies that are
very easy to deal with this issue and many more,
I would say, like project based learning,
the famous PBL, the use of gamification,
flipped classroom, and many other modern
education strategies have already
dealt with this problem. Most of them have
in common the fact that these make the students actively
seek answers and research, and sometimes even seek questions
itself, and that helps to motivate
them to learn more and be more engaged
in the classroom. And we
could talk about papers, piaget, Paul Frery,
bell hooks, vigotsky,
ZDP, many other classical thinkers
and concepts related to education. But I
will try to make a simple example out of tv series,
and I really hope that I'm not giving any
foiler doing so. Cobra Kai is
in its fourth season now,
and in order to teach the best karate, the Miyagi
do and ego Feng dojos have to teach their
students together, mixing their style and lessons.
And that way we can relate to the
concept of praxis, which is a classical concept that
connects education in a way
that we have to mix practical
teachers and theory teaching together in order to achieve
better results. We shouldn't just
focus on creating something. We have to create
something and at the same
time try to teach the theory behind it.
So we have the student engaged and learning
the concepts. And that is really important.
I think that most of the classical thinkers
that I have said would connect a
little to this Cobra Kai connection here.
Okay, I think that most of us will agree with that,
but how can we do that?
We will have to change our approach to traditional
math. Like in this example, everyone learns
how to solve quadratic equation during their high
school years. But do you know what
you are going to do with it? Well, some of
us might even still remember that we
can draw a parabola from the quadratic equation.
We may have the roots of the equation, the delta,
and. Okay, but how
is that connected to your reality, to the reality of the
student? Simple example, a parabola
or a quadratic equation may represent the jump
of a character. Or when you throw
a ball in a basketball, or anything
that has movement, it can
be connected to that formula. So one of
the ways that we can teach quadratic equation in
a way that it's not only about variables and numbers
is trying to create an animation that
works inside a game that
may be one of the most effective was to teach.
And while we are in that subject,
we can see that a lot of math concepts are connected
and scattered around the gaming world.
For example, I am a really big fan of fighting games,
especially street fighter. And in order to understand the game
at its highest level, you need to understand these animations for the
moves and the frame data there is so that you
can work in a mathematical way
of how a move should behave.
How should you react, what should you
bet that would be the right answer to your
opponent? And so it's not only about
how you can, and sure you can, it's about numbers,
calculations going on all the time.
And we can also use music creation as
a topic to learn math, from formulas to create sounds,
to compass, to rhythm, to tempo. There are many
mathematical concepts involved in the creation of music.
You can't have tango, pop, r and b without
numbers on the background. So as
we can see now, it's really easy to see mathematical
concepts being used all over the world of technology.
And that might be essential to develop
the education for the generations that are growing
up nowadays. Okay, although technology
might seem the silver bullet,
I have found many hiccups that might occur
when we see who already tried this
change in education. First of
all, we have the expression these in Brazil, that when
something is really expensive, like oh, can iPhone,
that it costs a kidney.
And well, as we can see from this slide,
some math solutions really cost a kidney,
especially in countries that are in development,
because the exchange rate to
dollar and euro and other most
popular currencies is really high.
So how high would it be?
Well, in our case here in Brazil,
$1 would be almost six
hais. And if you want
to think about that, you have to also think about
import technology and hardware and paying license
fees. And you also might even think,
one of the problems is that nowadays, most software,
you aren't really buying it perpetual
license. You are going to buy it for one
year or two years or sometime.
So if you think about the
cost of disclosed proprietary
technology, I think that most public institutions
and even most private ones would not
really have a way to deal with that. And also,
if we had the money that we don't have most of
the time, I would have to say that a lot of these
solutions based on proprietary software
may be quite limited. They remind me a little bit
of the calculation machine, also known as the
Skinner machine, and it
was one of the first machines focused on mathematical education.
It was basically a machine that fed the student with a
problem, allowed him to write his solution,
and also gave him the correct answer after.
So it indeed was useful because it allowed
these student to understand if he was right or
wrong. And it was
created many decades ago. So in that
time it was revolutionary. Today it's not
so much, but still it doesn't leave a
lot of room to create or explore or to understand
the nature of the errors that might occur while
the students trying to solve the problem. And that is really
essential to a good education.
Also, when we talk about disclosure solutions,
most of them aren't internationalized, which means
that students that aren't american or
don't have English as their primary language, and even
the teachers that might have to use these
tools will have to deal with another setback in
order to use the software learning commands and interface
in another language. I have to highlight that,
because here in Brazil we have really low
percentage of students and teachers who are fluent
in English, and that might be a really
big bump on the path to a better teaching methodology.
And we also have to say that in South America,
the hardware costs are rising almost every
day in the last few years due to the
weak currents that we already have talked about due
to taxes, to the pandemic, to the scarcity of
components, and even competing with cryptocurrency
mining, which I will never forgive
bitcoin for that. But even in educators
facilities that were already more structured in the
past, we still have some old equipment almost
everywhere. So it's vital that software solutions
may be as simple was they can be, and that they
can run in an open source environment,
just not only on Windows or Mac.
And a lot of educational
facilities here still use Linux.
Amen to that. Okay,
that leaves the question. Buying a software package
may really solve the problem related to technology.
Or should we focus on another type of solution,
given that these is a python conference? I really think that
these is a very easy question to answer, of course.
But the really big question is related not
only to technology, but the whole scenario around it that
we have just described it. How can we make the learning
experience more effective for the students.
First of all, I think that a part of this solution is
really outside of the question. We need that governments,
schools, universities, educators, communities and many
others to understand that we need this
change based on that. We need new curriculums
like we can see already for quite some time and already
working in England,
Australia, Israel, China. I think that
Sweden, I have seen Latonia
and many other countries that already are
trying to fit in programming and technology
inside the reality of each student. It is
also important that the teachers may participate
in programs that may refine and
update their skills and their views regarding
to the usage of technology in the classroom,
as we can't really make these change
without the contribution of teachers. And some of
them have not
been around so much technology as
we might have seen with the newest generations.
So it's really important that we stop at
this moment and say, okay, we have to first of all
teach the teachers to have
a different view on technology and how they are going to use it
in their classroom. And in order to do that,
we have to create this link between math
and technology. The good news is there is a lot of
people around the world already thinkinkering with new educational
concepts that may build this bridge between
these traditional fields. In our case, we are talking about math,
but we can do this with physics,
with language, with communication, with chemistry.
Everything that you can think now can connect to programming and
technology. And I may suggest one example
from my fellow friend and colleague Rafael Spetch,
who shows how to play around creating
images and sound by using math and the
web audio API. The link is in the source
of these slide and it's essential that
we risk this type of experimentation, new types
of education that goes well beyond the
traditional hello world when we talk about programming,
because we really need students to
be creative and to learn to deal with problem
solving that are
required traits to many of the new fields of work that
are coming from this digital age.
Now we can talk a little bit of already
there are a lot of open tools out there and at
this specific moment, I'm not going to talk about Python.
There is a motive about that. And I'm going
to start with logo. Logo is one of the most
traditional and maybe the oldest solution that
connects math and digital technology
as a teachers tool.
And it has already more than 50 years since
its creation. So what its basics
allows us to do is to work with geometry related
skills by creating shapes, drawings and much more through the
usage of its interpreted language,
which is really easy to use and quite direct. It just
feels like drawing on a board, but with your keyboard.
Another tool that has been quite popular in classrooms in the last
couple of years is scratch. That's created by the
MIT Media lab, and it uses really simple
visual blocks to create a programming language that's
so simple that you just have to click and drag to create
your program. And scratch has managed
to be used from small
kids all the way up to the university, and even
to teach teachers, as we have said before,
to really deal with technology in the classroom,
to really use it in their reality. And it
has a really simple learning curve.
And it's also multi language by design,
so it's really easy to everyone to use it. You can
manipulate visual objects, you can interact with the
user, you can calculate variables with this really
simple interface. And I'm
a big fan of Samaro. He's one of
the creators of Sonkipi.
That's an ed and also a programming language that
uses the language rails under the hood.
And the ide. And programming language
allows us to create music, to create sample and sounds by
using programming. And it's really interesting
to see how many loops and variables it takes to
recreate some popular songs out there. If you research a
little bit about it, you can see people creating Star
wars music, Mario music, everything that you
may think about, there is already
a little code that turns into a beautiful music.
And, okay, of course, we are in a python conference.
We have to talk about Python,
and it would be very disappointing.
Like if you go to see Spider man,
no way home and finding out there were no three different Spider
man in that movie, that was a lot of expectation,
and I think that's also the expectation that
most of us have here in this talk. And when we
talk about Python and math, first thing
that most people will say is that Python can
be used as a calculator. And that's not wrong. That's great.
But I really think that there is so much more
than that we can do with it. First of all,
I think that people have trouble understanding
how programming languages really work.
So I would like to point out a tool that's
not directly connected to the math context of this
talk. But it's a great tool to teach
people that are starting to learn how to program.
And it's called Python tutor, and it's an
online tool that allows us to see how
a program would work in a visual representation
of variables, lists, and many
other data structure that may work within a program.
Next up, we have the turtle model. That gives us the ability
to use logo commands and have the same resources of
the original language, but this time using it
within a Python environment.
Well, as I have said, that Python
should not be seen only as a calculator.
But the truth is there is a lot of
modules that are really handy in that department and
we could not talk about them.
One of this is the math module that
allows us to use most of the traditional math
functions that are defined by the C standard,
like the factory of function. So a lot of things
that sometimes you have to program in another language
in Python, you have, oh, okay, it's already packed,
you can use it. And we also have the
iTEr tools module that makes it easier to calculate
iterations, permutations and combinations.
And we could also talk, I think,
most of these time of this talk about other modules
like these statistics and so on.
But I decided to show the ones that I have
used so far more in my research
and that are more related to what I'm
researching at this moment. And now
going outside of the traditional Python modules, we can
see a vast array of tools that our community have built
for many different objectives. For example,
Jyton music might be an alternative to Sonicpy,
and also there are other tools to create
music with Python. I'm still learning Jytum,
but the jytom music environment, how to use it. But I
think that it has a good potential.
And another two tools that I think that
is essential to talk about is the blockpy
and the Ado blocks that work in a
similar way. That makes scratch
programming so amazing. That works with block programming.
And the most interesting thing about both of these
tools is that they allow to create traditional
Python code so that we can use the
visual programming, the block programming
as an introduction to programming with Python,
and make that transition from block programming to
traditional programming a little easier.
And now one of the most amazing tools out
there is Pygame. Okay.
Pygame is focused on a set
of modules that make it easier to work with SDL
functions, and that allows us to create
games very easy and very fast.
And now we are not talking about creating
games as, oh, we are going to sell games.
No, that's not these focus here, but allowing
these students to create. And also
when they are creating, these are using to be manipulating the environment
and mathematical concepts around it. So that's
very important. And also they can create
digital assets that they might play a little after
all the work is done. And if we
really want to go deeper, for those thinking about
data science, we have anaconda that not
only is one of the best tools to install Python
environment, but it's already one of the
most used tools around these world in this field of
knowledge, allowing an easy setup with a few
commands and clicks and having the best tools
out there. Most of the data science
tutorials point out anaconda as
their default tool. And one of the tools that
are included in this anaconda package that it's worth talking
about is the Jupiter notebook.
If someone doesn't know it, it allows these
creation of digital notebooks that might include text,
image, snippets of code and much, much more,
making it these ideal tool to create your digital classroom.
You create really an interactive book with
programming inside of it. You can really create
an environment so the student can learn
what are these concepts? And after it he can program
and go building his portfolio
of programming with these tool.
And we could go on and on and on about all the tools
that Python provides that are related to math,
but we have not a lot of time.
And also the most important thing that I would like to
point here and to show is that Python is
not only about the language. We have many open
source languages that are great, but the
great difference in my point of view is the ecosystem
around of it that has so many solutions
that might help you, your class, your teachers,
your community, to create better lessons,
to create a better classroom. Most of the time you don't
really have to create something new. You have to only understand
what is the right kind of package to this situation.
And also, I really have to say that,
don't forget the number one recommendation.
Read the documentation. Most of the problems that
already have been dealt with when we talk about
Python modules and everything, but it's just a matter
of understanding how the functions work and how
the tools that you are using may help
you. Okay, how can we
use everything that we have just talked about? I love
a simple example here to just wrap up this presentation
that is creating a snake game. It's really simple and
we think, oh, it's a game. What we are really talking
here, we can say that it's
only about 100 lines of codes that
you are not going to really learn so
much about it.
But in the big but here, the snake
game isn't only about the snake game, it's about
math. And when we talk about vectors,
about speed, about the direction,
it's really what we are doing. When you are reading
the keys and the movement, everything around
that. And that is really important because most
of the time when I use this example and show people how to
like in an hour and a half,
you can create this Python code to work
as a snake game. People are really
impressed, first of all,
that it's really so simple to create this code.
And after that they
really love the fact that it's math and
they don't realize it sometimes when they are building it.
And that's so great. And I think that
we have to have more this kind of experience
in the classroom. We have to create digital assets
and make these content around of it.
When you are building, you are learning at these same time.
And okay, I have convinced you, you are interested,
you want to know more. If that's the case, I will
refer you to some of my favorite
material. First of all, I'm really a
big can of Al swagers. He has this book. You can find
most of it online and free,
but if you can also buy it, that would be great.
That's inventing your own computer games with Python.
And it's not a book that talks directly
with math, but when you see these examples,
you are going to have the same kind of view
that I have talked about the Snake game, that every game has
a lot of math concepts behind it.
And math adventures with Python from Peter
Fahel. It's already one of my
favorite books because it teaches so much from
math that you think that you are learning Python and
you are learning math with it.
And that's the same experience that I
get from Amit Saha. And both of
them also have YouTube and also
eager also was YouTube channel and YouTube videos of
them talking about it. And so it's really amazing.
I'm really passionate about it. I think that this
is the kind of book that can really make the difference.
And also I really like. It's a little old now,
but I think that this video from
the Pycon Australia from Liam Calloway talking
about his experience of using math in
the university to teach Python.
It's great and it's really
one of the shortest talks that I have recommended
and might be even better than these talk that you are seeing
here today, now. And just
so we can end it all, the last
quote from John Dewey, can educator that
I think that summarize everything that we have talked so
far in a more theoretical way.
If we teach today as we learned yesterday,
we are robbing students of these tomorrow.
So, guys and girls, that's it.
Find me or these slides. There is my
contact email, Twitter, my slideshare. I will upload
the slides shortly. And I have
to just thank everyone for watching
and hope all of you or some of you
might get this passion about
math and python and starting fingering and experimenting
and bye.