You. Hi and welcome
to my presentation about the digital factory,
how we can industrialize our product development.
First to myself, my name is Romano Roth and
I am chief chief of DevOps and partner partner
at Zirke. I work now since 21 years
at Tilke. I joined Tilke directly after
university, became a junior
net engineer, then an advanced software engineer, then an expert
software engineer, then a lead software architect, and then a consultant.
And one thing that was always at my heart
is how can we continuously deliver value? How can
we ensure the quality of what we are
building, and how can we automate things?
And when the whole DevOps movement started, I jumped
right on top of that, became one of the organizers of
the DevOps Meetup Zurich, which is a monthly meetup
we are doing in person in Zurich. And you can always
join us, it's completely free. And I'm
also one of the organizers of the DevOps days
Zurich. The DevOps days is a global movement.
In all of the big cities all around the world,
there are DevOps days. And I'm the president
of the DevOps Days Zurich. And you can see
DevOps is really a topic that lies at my heart.
And that's also why I have my own YouTube
channel with over 100 videos all around
DevOps platform, engineering, architecture and leadership.
And I'm also posting quite
a lot and tweeting quite a lot. You can always follow
me on all of the social media channels
that you see there. When you want to learn more about
DevOps in the products that
I'm doing, I work for different clients in
different industries and I do DevOps transformation.
Now when I'm at such DevOps transformation,
or when I go to the clients, then I
see the following picture, which you can see here.
The business together with the clients, they have great
plans. They are putting these great plans
into ideas and they put that into
word documents and into gyra tickets.
And then they throw these word documents and chira
tickets over the wall of confusion to the development team.
The development team looks at these documents
and they say, yeah, if you want to have that, we can
implement that. And they implement it and then
they throw it over the wall of confusion to the testing team.
The testing team looks at that, what got delivered
and looks at the specification, and it
is not the same, but they test something, it's green,
and they throw it over the wall of confusion to the operation team.
The operation team said, how should we
operate that? That will never ever work in production.
But of course, somehow they get it to
work and it goes back to the customer and to the business.
And they say, hey, what is that? That's not
what we wanted. This is not usable.
And what you can see here is actually this
infinity symbol. This is a value stream.
And in that value stream you see all of these walls
of confusion. And these walls of confusion,
they are coming from the silo organization, which we find
in many companies. So the value stream, the value
flow is broken by these walls of
confusion. You also can see that there is no alignment.
These different organizations, they don't work at the same goals.
And overall there is a very bad developer experience
and a complete lack of excellence, also of
software engineering excellence.
Now there is this big movement of DevOps,
where you put the client into center, you stop
using projects, you go into product development.
So you have products instead of projects,
and you continuously deliver value across the
value stream. So DevOps is a mindset and a culture and
a set of technical practices which allows you to continuously
deliver value or the products to
your customer. So when we talk about DevOps,
then we also need to talk about that term, DevOps, because that
term DevOps is not so well chosen. It says
development and operation. And of
course there are some people,
smart people out there, they say, yeah, we need to fix that term, because nowadays
security is very important. So let's call it devsecops,
which is development, security and operation.
And others say, no, we need to call it
Bisdev ops because the business is a very, very important,
they are giving us the money. So BisdevOps business development
and operation is the right term. And you can see this
discussion does not go everywhere, because as I mentioned
before, it is about organizing across the
value stream, bringing all the people together which work on
a product. So we should need a term
like Dev, Sec bits, Arc,
user experience, quality assurance,
Ops. Or we just call it DevOps,
because DevOps is about bringing
all the people, process and technology together to
continuously deliver value. This is what DevOps
is at its heart.
So what does that DevOps bring us?
So science has looked at that, there is this
state of DevOps report and the amazing book accelerate which
had a look from a scientific perspective to
DevOps. And they are comparing companies which are not
doing DevOps versus companies which are doing DevOps.
And you can see the benefits are huge. For example,
you have a 973 lives,
increased deployment frequency. So how many deployments you can
do also faster lead times into production,
faster time to discovery, and you have
a much lower change failure rate. When you summarize all
of that, then you can clearly say when you are
doing DevOps the benefits are you get more
value for the money, a faster time to market,
a better quality, a higher customer satisfaction
and top qualified employees.
This is the benefits of DevOps.
So now we have understood what DevOps is,
but doing DevOps is already quite
difficult. Scaling DevOps
is even more difficult. Let's have a look how
we scale that. So usually what we
see in companies is this picture. You have different development
teams and then you have the wall of computation and then
different Ops teams. And many companies
try to fix that by establishing a DevOps
team in the middle. While this is sort
of an okay start point,
it is not a real solution to the
problem, because with that you are just introducing another
silo and you are not organizing
yourself across the value stream and bringing all the people together
to work on a product. So it's just another silo.
But of course it can be a starting point.
Now, how does DevOps look like when you are doing DevOps?
Then you will have such a picture where you bring all the people together,
not only dev and Ops as you see it here. So there will
be all of the people which are working together in
product teams. But this
is also not the silver bullet, because with that you are
introducing quite some inconsistencies and some
redundancies. And you also can see
that many of these teams, they are lacking product or
operation experience. And of course there is also that
complexity, for example of the toolings
of the cloud and everything. So there is quite
a lot of cognitive load on these teams. Let's have a
quick look on the tooling. You may have heard
of the term CI CD, which is continuous integration and
continuous deployment or delivery. And usually
what I also say is this is not enough because
what you have in front is you have the continuous exploration
where you are doing the requirements, engineering, the ideation and
all of that, the backlog management. And in the end you also have
the release on demand where you are continuously deploying
and switching on and off features.
So the whole thing is called continuous
delivery pipeline. And here you see just an
example of such a continuous delivery pipeline.
It's really an example of what kind of tools you have in
there. But what you can see is you need to
integrate all of these tools together and you also
need to maintain all of these tools. And when you have
DevOps teams, they need to maintain
that there. They need to maintain their continuous delivery
pipeline. Of course, there are big vendors out
there which say, hey, we got you
GitLab, GitHub or Azure
DevOps and other vendors are out there
which say, yeah, we have that DevOps platform
for you where we can
cover everything. When you take a closer look you will see,
yeah, they have a platform,
but still you need to integrate quite a lot
of tools in there. And also they
are promising that they have everything, but in the end they are also integrating
some other third party tools into that and you still
need to maintain, of course the integration
is quite good and everything is okay.
Nevertheless, you need to understand these platforms.
Now you have recognized that DevOps
is a mindset, a culture and a set of technical practices.
It's not only about tools, it's also about
these technical practices. And here I
show you in this DevOps cycle what that
means, these technical practices. So if you want to
build great products, if you want to do modern software
development, then you need to
implement these technical practices in
order to continuously deliver value and
build in quality. Of course you don't need to implement all of
that, but some of them need to be
implemented when you want to build great
products. And what you also can see
is, and especially when for example I
join different clients, what I see is
when a new team member or when I join a team,
the onboarding takes quite a lot of time until I have
really access to all of the environments,
to the source code, to the repository, to the
CI CD pipeline, to the Kubernetes cluster,
it takes weeks and even months.
And then when I want to have for example a new Kubernetes cluster,
new VM or a new database, it again
takes quite a lot of time until it gets provisioned
for me. And also when I got it,
usually I need to configure it according to
words document or a gyro ticket. And when
it comes to devsecops, doing devsecops, identifying all
of these vulnerabilities, this is also quite a huge
topic. When you enable vulnerability scanner
license compliance, scanner software composition analysis or
SAS, you get a lot of
vulnerabilities and you need to make sense out
of that. In the end, what you can see in
most of the product development or the projects,
you have a bad time to productivity, a slow
time to market and low quality and no standards.
So this is quite bad.
Can you at all scale DevOps? Is that really something
that is possible? For that we
need to make a step back and think about
what do we want or what
does our company want. And I'm bringing now
you a picture which I will build up so that you
understand what we really want.
On the top level you have the board, the board of directors,
the management and what they
have, they have a clear vision where they want to go with
the company. So, for example, in this example here,
you have a drone, you have a small market share and
you want to have more market share. In the end, you want to earn more
money and get bigger. So potentially you want
to have more drones. When you only have software products, it's the same.
You have a small application and you want to have more application or
a bigger market share. So what does these
people do? They are the portfolio level. There you
have the portfolio of all the big initiatives.
They have a portfolio backlog, and in the portfolio backlog,
there are all of these bright ideas,
and now they will choose the most promising
bright idea and give that down to the
product level where the product managers are.
So in this example here, you see the
board of directors, they have chosen that
they want to build a drone which can lift heavy
weights. So that's the idea. It's not yet a product
around that. And they give it down to the product managers
to sketch it out. What do we need to
make? Sort of a drone which lifts
heavy weights. So they give that down and the product
managers, they will have a look at that and they will
extract the features out of it,
which you need to build. For example, a drone
which can do the heavy lifting in software, it would
be the same. Perhaps you want to have an additional software,
additional feature and you would give that,
again, down. So on the product level,
you have the product backlog, where all of these features
are in, and these features are then broken down
into user stories, which you give down to
the team level. And of course, they are all discussing
these things. They are working very closely together.
You always have feedback cycles from
the top to the bottom. But in the end,
you have teams, perhaps already working teams, and you
give these user stories down there. They are going on
the team backlog, and the teams are continuously
working on these user stories. And of
course, because you are now creating perhaps something special,
like here, you perhaps also need a new team
in order to create that. And this is where
the platform engineering comes into play, which builds the
platform for these teams. The teams are
owning their own platform, but the platform engineers,
they are providing these platforms
to the teams so that they can work efficiently
on these platforms. Here in this example, we will
create a new team with their new CI
CD pipeline. In the end, all of the parts are
coming together, are getting assembled and it
will be shipped to the customer
and the customer will be, of course, happy about that.
But the most important thing is now we
have implemented the first step, we deliver
value very fast to the customer.
Now what we need to do is we need to get
feedback from the customer and we
need to make sense out of that. And it's not only customer
feedback, it's also the whole telemetry about how
our application is working so that we can again give feedback
also to the teams. And you see that in there, feedback goes
everywhere. It not only goes to the teams,
to the product level, it also goes to
the portfolio level, to the board,
because they had an idea, an idea
has hypothesis, and now they
can evaluate if this hypothesis
is true or false, if they want to invest more money
into this idea, or if they want to
stop investing money in this idea and build
something else. And what you see here is
exactly a digital factory. And this is
what most companies want to have.
Talking about this platform engineering,
I think here we need to dive a little bit deeper so that
you get a better understanding, because the
platform engineering is the foundation of the
digital factory. So in the end, what you want to have
is you want to have product teams which take
care about a product. They build it and they
run it. So the whole operation is within them.
In the middle you have the platform team. But bear with me,
this is not a silo organization
which you have, and you again have walls of confusion.
No, they are building a product which
the product development team can
use. And the point lies
on can. They don't need to use it,
they can use it. They need to
love that product. Let me give you another
picture about that. You see, the platform team
builds the platform and the platform can be different
things. It can include API gateways,
CI CD pipelines, repositories, synthetic test data,
kubernetes cluster, and so on and so on. So really the
platform where the products of the product
teams can be built upon that.
So the platform teams, they develop,
build and maintain the whole platform. So they
are generating value for the product teams.
The product teams, they generate value for
the customer. So the platform team,
they are enabling the teams to do
DevOps, because the platform teams will build
and run and maintain their products using
that platform. And here again, it's very important,
they need to love the platform. So the platform
itself is a product and you should never force
the teams to use this platform.
They need to want to use your
platform. That's the approach you want to follow.
But platform engineering is not the only thing
you need to do. You really need to look at
the digital factory from a holistic point
of view. Because when you want to deliver complex
products. This always requires a holistic
approach. And it's not only about that platform engineering which
you have in the DevOps part, where you have the
platform, the CI CD pipelines, the platform engineering,
also all of the practices. You also need to
have the right architecture to ensure
the scalability of what you are building. You need
to have the quality standards and also the
APIs. But not only that, you also need to
have the data because you want to make
something out of the data. You want to have effective
data pipelines, you want to use the data.
So in order that you can make the right decisions.
And this leads us to customer experience only
with the right data you can have a great customer experience.
Because customer experience is all about gathering
feedback from the market, from your clients, and ensuring
that you have a great end to end customer experience
and to continuously deliver. You need
to have an agile program delivery where you
have the different teams and how they are working with each
other, backlog management and all of that. And on
top of that, you need to have the product management
where you connect the strategy with the
execution. So all of that is
needed to build a digital factory.
As you can see, the platform engineering which
this conference is all about, is about building
that foundation of a digital factory
which enables their teams
to do DevOps. And as you can see,
this is how we are entering the age of industrialization
in software development. Thank you very much.