Hello and welcome to the future of work.
I bet you didn't realize that we were going to get here literally overnight.
But here we are in a completely new landscape.
And as we prepare to emerge, merge into a new set
of normal, many are taking this time to evaluate what
habits and routines bird that of COVID necessity
should be added to our new normal, what should be omitted
and what could be changed. And one thing
that has taken the world by storm is the
emergence of remote teams and remote work.
And while there have been some organizations,
this has been the norm for many, many organizations.
Remote teams were unheard of a few months ago.
And as we reemerge into a collective
society once again, many organizations are
re evaluating the benefit and challenges
of remote teams. Which leads me to this.
How do we build and lead remote teams?
Well, my name is Amber Vanderburg, and I'm the founder of the Pathways group,
where we work with teams from all over the world,
training in effective leadership, team building and strategic
human resources. Now, I've traveled physically with my
mask and virtually around the
globe, speaking and consulting with organizations
that are transforming the way that we do
work. First, let's acknowledge that not
all remote teams are equal. There are remote teams
that are globally remote, meaning that there are
teams that consists of remote workers from all over the
world. These teams,
they can be more diverse. They have a greater breadth
of network experience and knowledge, but it also
has additional challenges in cultural communication and
collaboration, and of course, time zones.
And today I lead teams that are globally remote.
But in the same regard, there are domestically remote
teams in addition to locally remote
teams. And these are teams that do work
from home, but they are in the same general
geographic space. And then there are
hybrid remote teams in which employees
and team members work sometime at home,
and then they also spend time at the office.
So it's important to keep in mind what type
of remote team player and what type of remote
team that you are leading as you're seeking to build
and lead your team. And so identifying
what type of remote team that you have can really act as a
guide for creating your policy, your leadership style
and your organizational culture.
Now, I've lived and I've worked all over the world in international
business, and I believe that leading great
teams boils down to four pillars of
team management or human resource management.
Now, this is not using humans as resources.
It's provide resources to humans so
that they can be as successful as they can be. And it's providing
resources so that your team and the people within
your team can reach their goals.
And if you are successful in all four of
these pillars, then you're doing all right. And while
the application and the tools towards success are
slightly different in physically
close teams rather than remote teams, these pillars
and these main ideas really do remain
the same. And the first pillar is to build
your team. That's right.
It's really that simple. Build your
team. See, if you're a hiring manager,
you are a decision maker in the future of
your company because recruitment is literally
how organizations build the future. So what
factors should you consider whenever building your team?
What specifically should you be looking for?
Is it personality? Experience? Education?
I was working with one hybrid remote team as the HR
director, and we had a serious discussion
about what our ideal team player looked like.
And one of my favorite leadership gurus
and authors, Patrick Lynn Sioni, writes that the ideal
team player has three major factors that
you can look for in your remote teams.
The first is to look for a team member that is humble.
Now, a humble team member is trainable and open
to healthy conversation. They don't have huge egos
and they truly are a team player. A humble
person is adaptable, which is really important
in remote teams. They listen to others and they
admit mistakes as learning opportunities.
And in a remote team, the likelihood of mistakes
due to miscommunication and cultural misunderstandings
is massive. And so a humble team member must
be able to acknowledge misunderstandings and be proactive
in learning about other culturals,
communication styles and ways of work.
They must be adaptable. It's so important
that your team member can adapt and change to
new situations. And whenever you're recruiting for a humble
team member, ask specifically about their
experience when working with different cultures and
communication styles. Ask about adapting
to new landscapes and dynamics,
and ask them about any misunderstandings or
miscommunications and how they have or would
have handled that situation.
Remember, it's really important to recruit
a team member that is humble. The next
major factor of an ideal team member is someone who is
hungry. Now, a hungry team member is always
longing to improve and be better. They love
to take on new opportunities, they have really good
work ethic and they have a drive to grow.
Hungry people have an energy and a passion that is unmatched
by some companies that have warm bodies
of building the seats, right? So we want to have people that
are hungry. And whenever you are recruiting a hungry
team member, ask about something for which they
have worked hard. Ask them how they spend
their free time. Ask about their work ethic as a
youngster, and these questions will help you to
get an idea of the type of hunger
that your applicant or potential team member may
bring to your organization. Remember, much of
remote work is self driven, and in
any team, trusting your team members to be good stewards
of time and energy and resources is really important,
but it is an absolute dire necessity in
remote teams. You want to have confidence
that your remote workers are hungry and self driven
and self motivated. Emerging technology
plays a critical role in remote work,
and equipping your team members with continuing education
and tools to thrive in remote workplaces
is really critical. So ask your candidate or
potential team member about their experience with continuing
education and their openness to new technologies.
In particular, assess current technological literacy
and also forecast future technological learnings.
The world is quickly changing and it
is vital that your remote team members
be eager to learn and to change to stay
relevant in our evolving workforce.
You want to seek a team member that is hungry.
The final factor that Patrick Lincione tells us to look for in our
team members, especially in remote teams, is to find
a team member that is smart. Now,
a smart team member is both technically smart and
also is people smart. So they have a high EQ
and a high iq. A smart person is capable
of doing the job. And when recruiting for a
smart team member, ask about their personality,
ask about handling difficult colleagues,
ask about their ability and skills to do the specific
job, and these questions will help you get an idea of the
spartness that your candidate will possess for
the job as a player in your organization.
Empathy is key in a remote employee
and it really requires a specific ability and intentionality
to do well. And oftentimes empathy is overlooked
as a critical skill, especially in remote
teams. A major pain point in many remote teams
is a lack of personal connection, and a
smart teams member builds connections with others and seeks
relationships. A smart team member is well
equipped to do the job in ability and skill in IQ,
but also has a tremendous high level of
EQ and people skills as well.
Also, remote players,
they have to be adaptable to different cultures and schedules
and of course, if you're in a globally remote team,
time zones. So ask about flexibility to
schedule and if they can be smart in those different relationships.
Remember, there are different skill sets that you
use in a remote team, such as having
to be very good at email and video conferencing
and technology, whereas in
a physical brick and mortar team, it might be a little
bit different skills that you're looking for as well.
So there is a difference and so be very specific in
knowing what the job is so that you can be very catered
in the questions that you are asking to assess the smartness of
your potential candidate. So seek a team player
that has a high EQ and a
high IQ EQ being emotional intelligence.
So an ideal team member
doesn't possess just one or two,
but actually possesses all three of these factors.
And if any one of these factors are missing, then the idealness
of the candidate begins to wane a little. See,
a hungry and a smart player that isn't humble will
be very arrogant to the team and not want
to train to improve. And a humble and a smart person
will do the job, but not have the drive to do
anymore. And a hungry and a humble player
that isn't smart will work really hard, but not
be of maximum use and productivity to the team.
So depending on the job, the fact that somebody
has a great personality and is personable and dresses
for success might not have any influence
on getting the job done. The fact that he is
a poor communicator through email might actually play
a very significant role. And so the questions and the factors
that we seek in our remote workers are not exactly the same
as our brick and mortar employees. So here's
what I want you to do. I want you to look at
your interview questions, review the questions that you are asking in
that interview process, and intentionally recruit your
ideal team member whenever building your
team. And that's your first pillar, is to build your team.
The next pillar is to value your team.
So we're going to value our team.
And whether it's in person or remotely,
it's actually really critical that we express value to
our team members, because people want
to feel valued. And one simple way that
we can show our value is to provide the right
tools and systems for our team.
Communication, project management, and HR tools are
all really important for equipping our teams to be
successful. And if you say that you care about team success and
then deny the right tools and investment and resources,
it can be really, really frustrations for your employees.
So take a moment to look at your toolbox.
The tools for remote workers are slightly altered
from brick and mortar. Also, logistics are a
little bit different. Time zones,
mediums of communication, time off communication are
all a little bit different, especially in terms of
being mindful of emails and phones.
Personally, it is my belief that it is worthwhile to
try and separate personal and professional
phones and emails and mediums of communication in
that onboarding process for a couple of different reasons.
First, it's a very clear distinction between professional
life and personal life, which is a good mind difference
for your employees. But second, it makes
for a very clear offboarding process if and
when your employees and your team members are
no longer a part of the organization. And so it makes for
a very clean onboarding process on the back end.
Another way that we can show value is through communication
and through benefits. And for a remote team,
it is a little bit different from brick and mortar. I mean,
does anyone actually care about teams Friday?
Not really, especially not in a remote
team. See, compensation takes into
account industry and organization and position,
no matter the status of work. Now,
some have begun a conversation about the physical
cost of living and people that live in
different places and those different costs of living and how that has an effect
on remote workers. This is a conversation that is
still ongoing. There is a variety of different opinions
that various organizations are looking into.
So that might be a factor that you want to include within your conversation
whenever you are deciding your communication. And your benefits is
the physical cost of living of your remote workers.
And then you also can look at your benefits.
Now, benefits is a really fun part about leading teams
and here's what I want you to do. Very simple,
ask your team members what benefits your
employees want. So take the time to listen to
your employees and ask those questions.
Also, there are ways that you can engage your
team members and valuing your team
by actually valuing your team.
Lack of social interaction has proven to be very tough
on some remote team members. So send
care packages, check in. Be intentional about
building a relationship. Find ways to
connect with your team members through your Zoom meetings.
Beyond just professional gap, some teams
are doing this through themed dress up days for their Zoom
meetings. They're having happy hours with
their team members. They're having game nights. I've hosted a
number of different game shows to really engage our
team members and to move beyond that personal,
professional gab and still have that personal connection.
Any way that you do it, be personal to your teams, but find
a way to show that value by building a
personal connection and a personal relationship
with your team members. So we
have built our team. We valued
our team. Now it's time to train
our team. So I always think about Rocky
in the first rocky whenever he is training for a
championship and he goes up on top of the stairs
and he raises his hands as he is training. And so I always
think of training as raising my hands.
See, I oftentimes think about a famous
professional sporting teams. I think of a professional
NFL teams. And imagine if you built
a solid team. You recruited the best players in
the industry, you paid them the highest salary and
then you never went to practice,
you never trained. The likelihood of you actually
winning a championship is very, very small.
Recruiting the best players and paying them the most salary will
not guarantee success. You have to train in between
Sundays so that you can compete on game day.
See, the world of work is ever evolving and
we must be able to train our employees
to stay relevant and to stay competitive and
to truly stay engaged. Virtual meetups
and continuing education can be really powerful.
Also, don't discredit the power of in person
meetings, say annually or biannually.
Some, if they are domestically remote or locally remote,
will do monthly meetings depending on how
vast your geographic separation is within your
remote teams, find ways to offer
confronting education and continuous training within
your team. This is where we truly
offer the opportunities for our hungry team
members, for our driven team members to continuously
improve and progress. So continue to stay up
with your team and to stay up with the learning opportunities
and the growth opportunities within your team
and continue the best practices to empower your team members
to move forward, both professionally and personally.
So first we're going to build our teams.
We're going to recruit humble, hungry and
smart team members to our remote teams.
Next, we're going to show value to our team,
which is shown a little bit differently in remote teams
than brick and mortar teams. Next, we're going to
train our team. And training your team is
critical again, both in physical teams,
physically close teams or remote teams. And we're going to
do that by offering different technologies and offering
continuing education opportunities and offering different ways
that we can flex our muscles to continue to
grow and to continue to improve so that we can stay competitive and
we can stay relevant. The last pillar
that you can use to lead your remote teams
is to retain your team or to keep your team.
Hold them close and you might be thinking.
Amber Vanderburg my team members get to stay
at home in their pajamas. They have a flexible work schedule.
Why would they ever leave? I hate
to break it to you, but you're not the only team that
offers remote work. See,
it's so important in this time that we keep
retention at the forefront of our conversation,
even in, especially in remote teams.
See, retention in remote teams probably won't
come from an over annoyance from the
person down the hall or the person in the cube next to me that
is talking loud on the phone and eating chips very loudly
every day. It probably won't stem from that, but it
might stem from a few other ways.
And like in your recruiting process, relationships require
a lot of communication see, as we are
building our team and valuing our team and training our team,
there's one constant that is a
thread within all of these pillars and that is building relationships,
building quality, intentional relationships and
being intentional. And I mean quality communication.
See, this is a place for digital communication.
One of my favorite authors and leaders, Dr. Mark Rutland,
writes that quality communication comes down to the right
message, to the right audience in the right way
at the right time. So it's important as you are leading your teams,
you're asking this quality question, right? Is this the
right message? Is this the message I should be delivering?
Is this the right audience? Are the right people
at the table? Are the wrong people at the table? Right. So we're going
to assess are the rightfit people at the table?
Next, is, is this the best way to
deliver my communication? And this is really
important. See, oftentimes there's a lot of attention
given to the actual message, but not
enough given to the actual method.
And the method of your communication is so critical.
Generally, whenever I work with teams, we discuss
how many emails or how many texts it'll take to
solve the challenge, to come up with an answer before
it's important for us to pick up the phone or get on a Zoom meeting.
Generally with most teams it's about five to seven. So an
average of six. So an average of six emails
going back and forth. If it's going to take ten emails,
if it's going to take 15 emails for us going back and forth
to come up with a solution, then email probably isn't
the best method of communication for us to use.
We should probably go to a different form of
communication. And this does a couple of different things.
First, it allows you to get answers quicker,
which is something that we all would love to do rightfit. So being able to
get those answers more efficiently and so that is super
important in itself. But even more so on the relationship
side. Whenever you are delivering a
message and there is a span of time in between each
message in the correspondence, there is a span of time
for emotions to build and there's a span of
time for the words to sink in. Now,
this is really, really desired. Whenever you are sending,
say, love letters, see, there is a span of
time between each letter for the words to sink
in, for the emotion to build, but it
is not as desired of a products.
If we are talking about something that is more technical,
maybe something that has an emotion that is not affection,
but could be a little bit more tense or more challenging, and having a span
of time in between each email can result in
some avoidable tension within teams. So it's important
to be intentional about the method of communication that you
are using. In the same regard, there are some phone
calls, stand ups, in person meetings, or zoom meetings.
That could be an email, it could be
a text, it could be a memo. So generally,
whenever I work with teams on deciding the best method of communication,
I actually look at the responses and does
this require a response? Is it going to be just a
couple of responses or is this going to be a long thread
of communication and correspondence? And then you can decide your
method of communication there the best method of communication
from that. And then the last factor is,
is this the right time to deliver this
message? See, it's important that we be personal
and that we be professional.
Now, in our professional lives, we have
a lot of messages that tell us to be very brief,
but let us not conflate our brief communication
with clear communication. And the time that
you save in fewer words typed
could actually result, it could
result in more time being spent by the team trying to
figure out what you actually meant and then misinterpreting
it. So it's really critical in those
memos and in those texts and in those emails that we
are very clear in our communication.
So don't bombard your team with a lot
of messages that are conflating that brief
communication with clear communication. So we want to be very
clear in the communication that we are building
also. So that's one way that we can really keep our
team is to provide clarity.
And that seems very simple. But by providing
clarity in our communication, in our leadership,
in our job on what I'm actually going to do,
that can eliminate so much frustration and tension within
our team, people will more than likely
want to stay there. Right. We want to stay in a place that has
that clarity within our teams.
Also create opportunities for
growth within your remote teams. Now see,
whenever I am joining a remote team, whenever we have people
that are joining remote teams, there still is that
drive, especially if you are recruiting hungry people, a drive to
move up in the ladder. So make sure to offer those
continuous opportunities for growth. Yes, in the training,
we're growing in our skill and in our talent, but in the
retention efforts offer opportunities for growth
within the organization and within the company. Now,
whenever I work with teams, we actually look for
flexibility on a ladder scale. So moving
vertically, but also moving horizontally as well. So if
someone is not happy in their position, they have a lot of different options
that they can go to throughout the organization to
really be successful,
offer those opportunities for growth and offer some sort
of a timeline expectation within
your employees, for your employees that are wanting to
move within the communication, that are changing to grow within the organization
and that are truly wanting to bring success
within your team. So going
to go through the four pillars one more time and
see these pillars are so important.
It reminds me of one time I was actually working
with a team in India. I was actually a football coach or
a soccer coach for Paris Saint Germain or PSG
academies in Bengalur, India. And I
recall one time I was coaching a very young
team and a young lad ran out onto the field.
He was about six years old and it was his first day of football.
And so he came running out onto the field and
he began yelling,
pass. And I noticed
that he was yelling, pass even whenever the other team
had the ball. And he was yelling, pass when
he was miles away from the action. And he was yelling,
pass even whenever he had the ball.
And so he was running with the ball yelling,
pass. Pass.
And so I asked him, I said, why are
you yelling pass? And he said, miss Ember,
I do not know what it means. I only know it as a football word.
And sometimes I hear organizations, I can hear leaders
sound a little bit like my young soccer
player friend yelling, build your team.
Recruitment, collaborate, compensation,
retention, innovation, yelling all of
these words because we know that they are really good words
that can lead to big goals. But if we're in the wrong
position, if we're miles away from the action,
or if we even have the ball and we don't know in which direction we're
going, then saying these words are not only ineffective,
but they're actually detrimental to the overall communication
within your team. But if
we take the time to build our team
very intentionally, by finding team members that
are humble and are hungry and are smart,
if we take the time to value our teams
being very catered to the value and intentional
value that we can bring to our remote team members in
a creative and personal way, if we take the time
to train our team in new best practices
and new growth opportunities in talent and in skills,
so we can stay competitive and we can stay relevant, and if we
are intentional to retain our team and to keep our
teams by provide a more
efficient and a more effective and a more enjoyable
workplace, then we'll be in a position
to yell pass to receive the ball,
to move forward and to score really
big goals. Welcome to the
future of work. Let's go score some goals
today.