Hello and welcome to conf 42. Today we will discuss
about quant quantum sensors, how it will
revolutionizing the traditional GPS technology.
And I am pursuing my bachelor's degree in computer science
at Asan Institute of Science and Technology. You can
connect me in LinkedIn. I am just one message away.
What is quantum sensors? Quantum sensors are
an advanced sensor technology that detects
the change in motion, force, electric and
magnetic field by collecting data at atomic
level. So why we need quantum sensors?
The quantum sensors are more
precise and accurate than the traditional sensors
and there are many disadvantages of traditional sensors
utilize the properties of quantum mechanics
such as quantum entanglement, quantum interference
and many more. Type of quantum sensors
there are many type of quantum sensors, but mainly it
is used to precisely
measure the acceleration force,
magnetic and gravitational fields.
Quantum accelerometer the quantum accelerometer
uses ultracooled atom to make a highly
accurate measurement. When it cooled to
extremely low temperature, the atom starts to display
quantum nature, resulting in wavelike
properties. As the atom moves the
sensors, an optical rule.
We can measure the acceleration by
using the optical rule. It will
be more accurate than the traditional sensors.
The quantum compass most navigation today
relies on global navigation satellite system,
also known as GNSS such
as GPS which sends and receive the signal
from satellite orbiting the earth.
But the quantum accelerometer is self
contained system that does not rely on
any external signals. It is independent
navigation using quantum accelerometer.
The navigation using a quantum accelerometer
we need precise starting position
and by using the quantum accelerometer we
can measure the acceleration very precisely.
So we can use this port data to determine
our position in 3d space.
Traditional navigation system versus
navigation using quantum sensors to navigate using
global positioning system which is also known as
GPS, we need external source like satellites
and for precise measurement we need four
to five satellites. Because of all
this, it is quite
expensive and it depends on
external source. That's why it's easy to jam
and hack. This will not rely on
any external source. Because of that, it will
give more accurate navigation and
it's quite difficult to hack it.
What is the progress? The UK's first quantum
accelerometer for navigation has been demonstrated
by the team of Imperial College London. A prototype
of quantum sensors built at Imperial will be
applicable in GPS free navigation
has been tested in collaboration with Royal Navy.
So we are getting progress in
the GPS free navigation
system. But the quantum sensors are
quite big. So this is the disadvantage
of quantum sensors. But the advantage is it
is more accurate than our GPS systems.
Thank you everyone.