All right, so we are here to talk about Pachamama,
the planet, modern nature and how as a develop or
as human bring. You should care about it. I consider
myself as a political activist with a h because I'm a developer as well
as I will tell you in a second, my name is Manuel Carrasco Molina.
On the Internet I go under blip.org
is so blip means stays in German. It's my journalist
activity following the environmental movements. I like to
play around with final cut pro and logic pro and try
to do some hopefully good video. I'm a
french speaking spanish guy, born in Belgium, which has been living in
Germany for the last 18 years. We see. Yeah, I basically love Europe,
except for the way they treat refugees at the border. I'm not 24 years
old, I wish, but I am a dinosaur in this environment
of developers because I've been developer for 24 years, developing for the iPhone
since 2008. But I like way more than nature. So this is why
I'm pretty critical at Apple when it comes to environmental aspects.
Ten years active with the Green party, four years in the city council near
a city that I will show you where there is a big coal pit called
captain. We moved three years ago, we bought a new house, and so
now I am since last year again involved in the city
council, but this time also in the regional council. And I hope that my political
career will go further on just for the sake of protecting the environment.
Considering myself a climate activist and also refugees activist,
I do this mix of politics, activism,
journalism, free journalism, reporting on the field,
being with the real activists, I would say.
But I see myself as part of the global solution,
being just hopefully a tiny part of it.
Eight years without any meat. I wrote a book on APIs called
Karma based API on Apple platforms. It's about building privacy into iOS
and OS apps. If you take a picture of this
QR code and you will make a tweet that you like the book,
even though you haven't read it yet. And I will pick the three first ones
that are retweeting this thing and all the others. I hope you can help me
spread the good message about our privacy is an important thing.
I gave talks about privacy also at different conferences. You can find
it online. Let's look at the mass, as I call
it. This is what we always refer as like the base point.
Obviously since were industrialized, we've fixed a
couple of problems. We have less poverty than we used to have. It also
means that growth comes with a few problems. As you can see by this
curve, it goes all the way to the top. And we are right now about
1.2 degrees. This is why every time you hear 1.5 degrees,
which is the goal, we have to reach it, actually, because if we dont,
we will be in a big mess, especially people in the global south. In this
talk, I will play a couple of videos. The next one is from ITV News.
Let's go into it and let's face the truth, truth,
truth. Scientists say that since 1970, temperatures have risen
faster than in any other 50 year period over the past 2000
years. They fear that a target of keeping warming
below one dont five degrees will now be breached within 20
years unless there is immediate,
rapid and large scale reductions in greenhouse gas emissions.
So this is what we have to do together.
Immediate, rapid and large scale reductions.
So as an
industry, as developers, as ceos or whatever, we can be responsible
for large scale reddictions. The socalled obviously depends
if you are whatever, the CEO of Facebook or
if you have just an app which three people have downloaded.
But every one of us can do something at this scale, and also every one
of us can do something personally. So this is why this talk is also
about, not only about you as a developer, but also you as a human
being. One of the things that I do since many, many years is I go
with my camera, with microphone and whatnot,
call the years that are necessary to do, to produce those kind of
videos. Some people that I know are going with drones,
for example, and we follow the people that are
doing basically civil disobedience.
Thank.
It's happy.
That's.
Thank you.
All right, so the video goes for another, like, in total for 14
minutes. So check it out if you, if you'd like. And basically,
they were fighting against the next problem, so to
say, which is gas, and generally lng,
which is the liquid gas imported from the global source,
from parts like Argentina, from Vacamuerta,
for example, where basically indigenous people are
endangered. Another thing that is more like
the current problem, but which is hopefully starting to be fixed and
being phased out, is lignite. So it's bronchial, as we
call it in German.
A big chunk of Germany is filled with those holes,
which I explain you a little bit on the right. And this
is the biggest polluter in Germany, which is just a couple of kilometers
away from where I live. And it produced every year as much co2
as New Zealand. So as you can tell. So I'll
show you in this map over there. If you go somewhere over there,
it's very tiny. But if you look it up on Apple Mac, for example,
this thing is actually where the image
on the left is. And this other thing
over there, this huge thing, is actually the could
pit. It's actually as big as cologne itself. And you might recognize
that over there it says Hamburg forest.
So it's the forest which has been decimated
for the last 40 years. And hopefully, luckily, all the
activism together and a little bit of political work and whatnot
could stop this madness.
So this part you see is still there, but because
there are lots of problem with water not being there,
where it should be, nobody knows if the trees will
actually survive. All right, let's move on a little bit and speak about another
way of activism. It's about moving to a plant based food.
And I show you another small video,
which is called in 20 to 30 years. So it's a video from five years
old. So that's why I call it in 25 years, the world would be mostly
vegan. So you could technically start today by at least reducing meat.
I'm not asking anybody to start today to be young vegan myself.
It took me two years after my father was
ill from cancer, to start reading about it and understanding the problematics
around cancer and what food had to do with it and whatnot.
And then after two years of reducing meat, I became a pescatarian,
which is basically only eating fish. And then
after three months, I became a vegetarian. And for little
under three months than three years. Sorry. And then I became a vegan five years
ago. Animal agriculture contributes 51%
of total global greenhouse gas emissions. It's responsible for
91% of Amazon deforestation, and one
to two new acres are cleared every second.
One third of all freshwater globally is used by the
meat and dairy industry. A vegan can be fed on just one 16th
of an acre of land for a year. A meat eater needs 18
times that much land. Waste and pollution from animal farms are
an environmental catastrophe. This is why you can call us crazy
and you can think like, oh no, I'm not going to stop on meat because
this is so tasteful. And whatever. The fact is that at one point
or another, it won't be possible anymore to eat as much meat as we do,
for obvious ecological reasons. And if you think politics will solve
the problem, it can. In some ways, at my level,
I'm trying to fix some stuff, but not only
in terms of food. I'm also bring to have lets space for cars and more
space for bikes, for example. At the more local
level, right now in Germany, the greens with the socialists and
the liberals are trying to bring Germany on the target of 1.5 degrees.
We are trying to phase out coal by 2030
without making nuclear longer because
nuclear station power will be phased out next year
in Germany. I'm happy to speak about terrium and all those kind of stuff,
but I just think this is not the solution. And so in
some ways it can. But if you think about the cups, we had
26 of this and I just don't trust it. I don't trust
it because as Greta was mentioning, this is a lot
of blah blah blah, build back
better blah blah blah, green economy,
blah blah blah, net zero by 2050, blah blah blah
net zero, blah blah blah, climate neutral blah blah
blah. Our hopes and dreams drown in their
empty words and promises. They've now had 30 years of blah
blah blah. And where has that led us? Over 50% of all
our co2 emissions have occurred since 1990 and a third
since 2005. If this is what they consider to be climate
action, then we don't want it. They invite cherry picked young people
to meetings like this to pretend that they are listening to us,
but they are clearly not listening to us, and they
never have. Just look at the numbers, look at the numbers, look at the
facts. And most of those world leaders aren't listening to
us. So one way to solve the problem is we will solve
the problem. It takes some of us to go into politics, which is
not always easy, believe me, in the way,
I am pretty radical. So I have to do some compromises, which I don't
really like a lot, but it takes of us to do some civil disobedience to.
Look, if it wasn't for the activists in the Hamba forest since
2012, we wouldn't be speaking about phasing out coal
by 2030 in Germany. Actually, up until three years ago,
the discussion was still 2045,
so we were going to phase out coal in 2045.
Let's try to fix this together. And speaking of problems,
there is this tiny it problem. It's like kind of the
elephant in the room. You can imagine we are generating a lot of co2.
There are a lot of things to fix, and can we fix it together?
So let's try to fix it together. I give you a few tips. One of
it is a search engine. We search all day long,
right? We go like, oh, how do I convert a swift ui
font to can ui font? Yeah, go for it on Stackervoplo
and you'll find out it's a terrible enum thingy and
then oh my Ruby version is not found. So my fast lane isn't working
anymore. Or am I going to fix it? And how many engineers does it take
to save the world? Well I dont know, probably not
too many but at the same time a lot. So you get
it right. We are constantly looking it up.
And when I'm saying searching, looking it up you're probably thinking of a word
in your mind. And this is my question to you. Are you still googling?
You want to sell sugar water for the rest of your life or do you
want to come with me and change the world? Come with me and change the
world and stop searching and start planting, right. Stop using Google,
use Ecosia. Some of you might know them.
Ecosia.org, it's a german company which
is being founded by this guy Christian Krell. As this
german newspaper was saying, he prefers to plant trees instead
of making millions. So what they do is you search the web with Ecosia
and by the way they are based on bing, so the algorithm is not too
bad. And if by any means you dont find what you find
over there, you just click on another link and then you go to google just
in case. Google is better, they generate money with ads just like
Google does or bring does or whatever everybody does. But the
difference is they do it with good ads. So by good I means
they will never put you an ad for fossil
fuels or for flying from Hamburg
to Berlin for example. And they do some money
out of it. And once they get the revenues,
like the pure revenues, 80% of it, they use it to plant trees with partners.
So it means they pay their people, they pay
their computers, they pay their servers or whatever. And the money they still have,
they use 20% of it to make the company a little bit
richer, so to say, so that the company can grow a little bit, but 80%
of it, they just plant trees. Tune your code. And if
you think, or if you thought that this
talk was going to be only about this, then you were obviously wrong.
I give a talk about this at least at iOS devs UK,
but I think at other conferences as well, which is about optimizing
your code. This is very specific in this case to
basically Xcode and iOS, which is the tool in which you
guys watching this video are commonly
using. One thing you can do over there is you can use the gadgets and
see basically what's the load like.
You see you're using 30% of location, so it means
what are you doing all the time with location and
Whatnot? Yeah that's one thing. The other thing is
related to that. If you go in your iPhone, in settings battery, for example,
this is basically were users go if the battery is draining.
Right. So you really dont want your app to be in this list because
it's kind of like the losers list at the same time. It also means that
if you are over there, it means that your app is well used by the
user. Right. So to give you an example on those two
screens, the top app over there, which is Tiger show, is from
the first channel in Germany from IRD.
So I use it a lot. But what's interesting is that it's kind of
weird that it has been draining 27% of my
battery. What's even more weird is if I go to the next screen is you
will see that it has
actually been only used 18 minutes in total. So it's really
not a lot. So I wonder what was
wrong over there. Right? And so you have to
have a look at this. And actually I hope that not only you as
a developer, but you as a user, look at over there or in
macOS you have the same thing. Look over there on the top bar, what kind
of app is using your better and just report to developer,
say to the developer what's wrong? And so
yeah, that's one of the things you can do. The other thing you can do
is run 100% renewable energy, whether it's your app
infrastructure or your company or whatever. The best case
is to have your own pvs photovoltaic like solar
panels. That's what Ecosia do by the way, they run all
their business renewable and
they generate actually more than 100%. They generate I think 200% or something like that,
or 250 whatever. And if it's not possible to have your
own pvs, then run from 100% renewable energy provider,
right? If you have to go from the grid. But please don't pick a mixed
company. And by mixed company I mean like for example RWE
in Germany, this big bad company which has been digging holes. Sure they
have green products, right?
But yeah, that's not the idea behind
it, right? Sure you can probably order your vegan food from Amazon,
but that's also not the idea behind it. Right?
And so speaking about apple, apple goes were carbon
neutral. They go on their website, if you have a company you
should do something. But my point here is carbon neutral is great,
apple, but it's not enough. It's just not enough. You should be 200%
renewable and they should say, hey, we're carbon negative. And actually apple
just for you. I made you a badge that you can put in your website.
Let's try to fix this together altogether. Right? Right.
Another thing, go vegan again. But I'm
not specifically saying that to yourself. But I'm also more
your company. You don't have to become yourself vegan from a day to
the other. But what if as a company you would say during lunch like Ecosia,
you wouldn't have any of those products. If you offer lunch,
it's actually pretty easy and it's actually better for the environment
because fruits belong to startup anyways, right?
So if you just have fruits and
add lots of fruits, people eat fruits so they will eat less of
the other stuff during the day. So that would
be one thing in your company. You could also go plastic and packaging free.
Why not? In case you order pizza for example. That's just one
of the example. There is this website called order Green, I think it's only in
German but you get the idea. And they basically made
this reusable packaging. If you want to have a vegan pizza,
a lot of pizzeria they dont have it. Just take the vegetarian
pizza and ask them to not put any cheese. Offer breakfast at
your company would be also a way to go kind
of packaging free. Because if you have like cereals in ten kilo
packages we buy at home, for example, a lot of our stuff, whether it's
pasta or cereals in big ten kilo packages.
We're a big family of six people. So we try to generate
less plastic and use, please use ceramic
cups, not plastic cups. And stop grabbing a coffee
with something you have to throw away. If you
want to grab your coffee in the morning, then have your own cup,
even if it's a plastic cup. Obviously it can be. But the
one you reuse all the time, right? And finally go out
to eat with the company because when you go out at lunch
there is a big chance that you are actually producing less crash,
right? Because call of those companies, like all of those
restaurants for example, they just wash their dishes, right?
Also we need more home office, it's less cost,
right? But it's also less traffic, it's less co2.
So less people taking their cars or whatever. The downside is that each one
is taking their own decision, for example in electricity wise.
So even if your
company has a green provider, you cannot be sure that
the people that are working for you at home have their
own green electricity. Write them an email and say
hey, we are happy to be 100% renewable
at the company. But would you want to
help us do the same thing at home. Maybe you can even strike a deal
with some electricity company. I don't know. If you're a big company enough,
you can have a rebate. The upside is that it's also way better
work life and family balance. I've been working myself remotely
since many, many years. And really, I don't know why I would want to go
back to regularly, at least to the office. My current
company, to give you an example in terms of the cost,
has an office, or we are about to change the office and
the new office will have room for 35
people. The thing is, until we move over there, we will be 70 people,
right? So you're getting it so it years that we will have a system
where you have to kind of say, register when you want to
go to the office. If you absolutely have to go to the office. Are you
walking or are you biking? Right. Call.
Right? You're not neither. But you're taking the train, right?
You are taking the train. But worst
case, you have an EV, right? Like an electrical vehicle,
like battery powered. And my car
is 100% based on renewable energies at home. I'm really happy
to speak about evs. I've been driving an EV since three years.
Way better is to use the train and way better is to use the bike.
Or if you can walk, it's even better. Try to reduce or quit flying.
It's been three years. I'm fine with it. I haven't been flying
anymore. I'm sure at one point in the future I will have to
fly again for whatever reason, but I'm trying not to. Even when
I was, for example, going to iOS devs UK, which is in Wales,
which was a long trip with the train, basically the whole day I took the
train. And it was interesting. You see a lot of years
and you can work also longer.
Online conferences are great. And otherwise,
like I was telling you, just use the train and please stop
going for a company weekend in Mallorca if you are a german company
or whatever. And generally please stop going
because it's cheap. Don't go into this thing like,
oh, it's cheap. So I'm going for two days trip in Majorca and over there
I'm going to do some nature mountain biking.
It's ridiculous. Make an app that does good for the world,
not just the next useless app.
Be that CEO, the one that cares about the world. If you can start a
company like sonomotors, for example,
they are working on a solar powered
car which will hopefully see the light of the day in 2023. Right now prototypes
are there and they started their company with
the idea of not selling a car
to every single person, but sharing the car with other people. For example,
it's weird to start a company, a car company to have
lets car, but that's one of the goals they will most probably achieve.
And it's a mess out there so there are many problems to fix. Keep it
small and so you generate less
co2. Use the inspectors like the network's inspector seeing to see
which part is that you will probably discover that there is like a four megabyte
pictures over there which could be actually six hundred k.
Do you really need that 100 megabyte video on the front page?
Probably not. And also please don't do autoplay. It's not
only bad for the environment, it's also bad in terms of user experience
because I don't want to go on a website having a video played on my
face. The iPhone, since the iPhone X has been using an OLED screen,
we still don't have older on the iPads and still no OLEDs on the Macs.
That's too bad. So really you might notice,
but a dark pixel on an older screen is actually not turned on.
So it's sparing energy. Turn off your tv, use a power switch.
Automatic updates is the thing that I will show you now, which is that if
you look over there, what you
can see over there on the top, I turned off
the automatic app updates and apps for whatever
reason. I have music over there and books as well.
So it means that every time that I will download a music on one device,
it would download on the other one. I'm not sure how old the screenshot
is, but definitely when I install an app on
a device, it won't install on another device because this is not what I
want. And also the updates. I know it's kind of weird,
but one of the thing that I like about doing the updates myself,
besides the fact that I don't want to have to update some
of the apps every two weeks, there are a lot of
apps out there like Facebook for example,
which are basically working in this sprint update
thing. Like every two weeks they will release a new app and so I don't
necessarily need it. But the other
thing is, I realize a lot of time, oh, this app, I haven't
been using it forever, so I'm just going to delete it.
Stop. Now I really, really have to stop.
And this is why I'm really happy I'm
saying Shukran here, which is thank you in Arabic.
You can find me over there at Seth MC on Twitter.
I'm on Instagram as well with Seth MCM, and this is my email
if you want to get in touch with me. And now I am really,
really more than happy to speak with some of you in the Q and A's.