Hello everyone, I am Myron Giannakis and I
hope you are as excited as I am to join my
talk on implementing quantum algorithms using Qiskit.
First of all, let me introduce myself.
I come from Greece where I am studying computer
engineering and for the last two years I
am the coordinator of the Quantum Computing Students group
pertain of the IEEE brands of the University of Padres.
There we try to introduce and get involved
into quantum computing more of our university students,
and what I'm going to talk about today is
a game I developed in order to make this task
more interesting and easier for the new members.
I will be more than happy to get in touch with any
of you via either LinkedIn or email so
you can find both of them on this first slide.
And please do not hesitate to send
a message.
My talk comprises two main parts.
The first one is more theoretical,
providing an abstract of quantum git distribution
and the protocol BB 84
that I'm going to talk about. And the second
part will be code oriented where I
will present more practical concepts
of the project, the main idea,
the code and the game.
First, I would like to briefly introduce some
of the prerequisite theoretical aspects just
to make sure that we're all starting on the same page.
The subject I will focus on is, as I
said, quantum gear distribution, or QKD for sort,
and specifically the protocol BB 84,
a scheme developed by Charles Bennett and Zilbrasard
in their paper published in 1984.
Being the first quantum cryptograph protocol,
QKD aims at the creating of a
secret key shared between authorized partners connected
via both a quantum channel and a
classical authenticated channel.
The security of the key relies on two conditions.
First, the existence of an authenticated public
classical channel and second, and most more
important, the no cloning theorem that
states that unlike classical computing
in quantum, it is impossible to copy a quantum
state. It is a quantum property that
information gain is only possible at the expense
of disturbing the signal.
Talking about security the uncertainty principle of
quantum physics gives rise to new cryptographic phenomena
unachievable with traditional transmission media.
For example, the communication channel described in
BB 84 protocol is impossible
in principle to be eavesdropped without a
high probability and really high probability
of disturbing the transmission in such
a way as to be detected, making it
secure against any traditional kind of creating without
putting any restriction on an eavedropper's power.
So it is basically unbreakable, we would
say.
Now let's see what exactly is adjusted by the
protocol. Here you can see the
circuit as well as a demonstrative example,
we consider two users called Alice and bob,
a and b, and let Alice choose a
random bit string and a random sequence of quantum games
had the mart's or identity.
She then creates a train of qubits. It's initialized
to one bit of the string and passed
through the respective gate. Bob on the
other end of the channel, receives these qubits and
decides at random whether to apply on
each of them a hadamard gate or not,
before measuring it and collapsing its state
into a classical zero or one
a classical bit. It is not hard to understand
that in the case where Bob uses the same
quantum gate as Alice, he will certainly get
the bits he initially sent, while when
they use different games he will get a random bit
that doesn't contain any information thats
Bob obtains meaningful data only from
half the qubits on average that he receives
those for which he guessed the correct gate
exactly. These bits are the
ones thats are going to form the key at the end of the protocol,
but the users do not know yet which ones
they are. Each one knows only the gates they
used and the bits they sent or received,
whether they're Alice or Bob.
So they have to communicate through a classical channel
to pass the needed information.
Though since this channel will
be susceptible to eavesdropping,
they should not reveal the bits values, but communicate
only the games they applied.
In that way, any eavesdropper would
know which bits have been transmitted correctly, but not their
actual values. The security
of the process during both
the quantum and the classical communication is guaranteed in
the quantum since an IFS dropper would disturb
the quantum state and thus be detected. According to
the no cloning theorem, he cannot
replicate the state. So Bob would extract
wrong data and understand that there would
be a problem in the classical case.
In the classical channel,
the security is guaranteed because there's
not using transmitted any information about the key,
the data thats is transmitted the games. It is useless
to someone that does not have access to either Alice's
or Bob's bits.
At the bottom here of the slide,
I provide an example of
application of the protocol where I demonstrated
all the before mentioned steps.
On the first row, there are the initial bits
that Alice sent, then Alice's and Bob's gates,
and the received bits, and at
the bottom part is the communication through the classical channel.
We're finally keeping only the correctly transmitted
bits to form the secret
key.
Now that we have seen the theory of the protocol, let's try
to think of a way to motivate students to
get involved into learning it. My idea
was to use Qiskit to implement the
protocol and organize a competition,
a competitive game where I
would send a secret message to all the students and
they would have to write their own code to decrypt it as
fast as possible. Qiskit,
for anyone that doesn't know, is an open source
quantum software development kit provided by
IBM. It is available as
a Python library, which makes it really easy to
implement, and it simulates the operations
of a quantum computer while also
allowing operations that would not even be possible on
a real quantum machine, for example,
peaking in a superposed state without
disturbing it.
I exploited this fact to make
my game easier to implement and more interesting,
and add more learning
value to it.
Let me now describe the structure, the main idea of
the program. While it is based on the BB
84 protocol, it differs from it on
two main points.
First, Alice does not
send a bit string, but a character string. Its character
is represented by a quantum circuit
of seven qubits instead of one qubit, and they
correspond to the seven bits of its
ascii code. And in order
to not complicate things, all games
that are applied to any circuit
or qubit are applied to all
seven qubits of it.
The second difference is that the data transmitted
through the whole process is not a key like in
the BB 84 protocol,
but it is the whole message.
This requires retransmitting many
times.
Probably it has a complexity of log of x,
since each time half of the
characters are expected to be received correctly.
So it should be a complexity of
Big O of log x, where x is the
length of the message, and each
time the new message is games as the
previous one, excluding the correctly received characters.
We will see it in more detail in a
few minutes. The initial program is
composed of three main parts of code that
are those that you can see in
the image in the slide. The first is the
crypto circuit class, which inherits
Kiskid's quantum circuit.
The characters that I talked about are encoded in
instances of this class.
Second is the class protocol BB
84.
It contains the static methods
that implement the sender, the receiver,
and the classical channel of the protocol.
And finally, there's also the main function which
controls the whole program and processes
the data that are sent and received
transmitted in general.
Let's get into the details of the program's code.
Starting with the main function here,
you can see the whole code of it,
and the main part of the function is this
while loop, which repeats the transmission
until the whole message has been received correctly.
Then the methods of the protocol
BB 84 class get called,
each one provided with the information that
it should have access to, and only this information.
So the receiver gets
us input only the circuit because we're talking about
the quantum channel. And then the classical
channel method gets us inputs the games
of Alice and Bob's that
Alice and Bob have applied. Finally,
at the end of the function, we get the part
of the message that Bob received and calculate the
message that Alice will have to resend in order to
continue this process in the while
loop loop.
Now let's dive a bit deeper,
looking at how the previous static methods
are actually implemented. On the left you
can see the sender method, whose input is only the
message for its character of the message it
creates. The quantum circuit initializes it
to the correspondent ASCII code,
applies at random the Hadamart or
identity games, and returns an array
of the circuits and one of the gates that
were used. On the right.
The receiver method gets as input
the list of the circuits received by Bob,
and for each one of them applies his random gate
and measures the result, getting an ascii character.
This method returns the received characters
as well as the array of Bob supplied games.
Finally, the method of
classical channel receives as inputs
the two lists of Alice's and Bob's games,
and returns the indices of the correctly
transmitted characters, the indices and not the actual characters.
Of course, for the reasons that I mentioned
before, these methods
are not complicated and don't do anything more than
implementing what was described in the theory.
Finally, the class for
the circuit, the class where r encoded
all the characters that are to be sent is the
cryptocurcuit class, I'm sorry. Which extends
the kiskit's quantum circuit and adds the
necessary methods for the program. For the game.
The methods initialize, add, gate,
and get measurements are asked to respectively
set the circuit to an initial state,
add or not Hadamard gate,
and get measurements for the circuit's qubits.
The interesting method here though is
the visualize, which displays the
multivector of the circuit.
Here I have added a simple example of a
circuit to make it easier to imagine how the
circuits would look like this one comprises of
only three qubits representing
the bits zero, one and zero as
it can be seen from them if
we read the visualization. And on
the right I have added
a hadamard gate on the circuit so you
can see the 90 degrees rotation
of the three block vectors.
This is the case that was mentioned before where
Bob doesn't get any information about the characters,
about the character since he thats the same probability
to get any character. Each one has
50% probability to give measurement of zero or
one. You can see under the block spheres
that the result of the measurement is a
random triplet of bits and not the
initial 3010. Getting to
the last part of my talk, how did I get from the
program to the game? For that? Instead of
calling the main function, I called directly the
sender method and saved the results.
The lists of circuits and games in two
files representing the two channels respectively,
quantum and classical for the circuits and gates
in each one you
can again see the code here. It is
nothing too complicated.
And then I shared these files with
the students along with Jupiter notebook
containing the basic codes, but leaving a
big part of the protocol to be implemented by them.
More specifically, the crypto circuit class
was provided so they
can properly use the circuits and the protocol
BB 84 class is as
it can be seen here in the image.
It missed entirely the sender method
since it wouldn't be of any need for them,
and the receiver and classical channel methods
were empty to be implemented
by the participants. The participants also
had to write some kind of a main function
that would call the methods process.
The outputs take the needed actions in order
to get to a result.
This whole thing was done in the form of a
competitive game where winner would be the
first person to manage to decrypt my initial
message. So this
was how I implemented a variant of the
BB 84 protocol in a game,
hopefully fun, that engaged many of my
fellow undergraduate students in quantum computing.
Thank you very much for listening. If you are interested to know
more about this and other projects,
please check out my team's GitHub repository
and I am looking forward to connecting with
you for further and deeper discussions.
See you.