Hello, my name is Chris Ayers and today I'm going to talk about CI
CD with GitHub Actions. I'm a senior customer engineer at Microsoft
and I work on the fast track for Azure team. We're part of Azure
engineering and we help customers build and deploy
software to Azure securely,
reliably. I have a big focus in DevOps and what I do,
I'm on Mastodon, Twitter, LinkedIn. I have
a blog and all of my code samples are out on GitHub,
so feel free to go out to my repo and take a look and I'll
be sharing that. So I first want to talk about YaML
and then we'll dive into CI CD, go into some
of the discussion around actions, and then I want to show some demos and have
a fun time playing with those. So GitHub
actions are part of workflows and those are all written
in Yaml, yet another markup language. And you have
lists that can start with a dash. We have key value pairs
that are separated by a colon in a space. Then we have objects
which are very similar to key value pairs,
but all of the properties are below the object
and indented. And I'll show some examples of that shortly. I just want
to make sure that those three kind of basic things are covered.
And something that's very important is if you get your indentation wrong or your spacing
wrong, it can cause problems with your workflow. So having good
tooling like Vs code with the YAMl plugins
and extensions can be really helpful in this.
And another thing is I like to talk about,
we have CI CD. Well, there's two types of CD
that come into play, and you can do all of
these things with GitHub actions through the workflows. Like you
can run your builds, you can run your unit tests, you can deploy
things out, and there are ways to stop for
approvals and see if you want to proceed.
Maybe you deploy to dev and you want someone to sign off before it goes
to QA, or you deploying to QA and you want some approvals
or time windows before things go to prod. You can do some of that.
But usually I think some of the differences between continuous delivery and
continuous deployment are youll do have push button deployment,
but things slow down and you have a human in the loop that can approve
or not approve. Now, actions are event
driven, so there's a large number
of events that can trigger if a workflow
runs. All GitHub actions workflows live
in the GitHub workflows folder and they're all defined in Yaml.
Now what's different about GitHub actions from maybe something
like an Azure pipelines is in Azure pipelines you
have to specifically say I want a new pipeline using this file.
But with GitHub, if youll drop a Yaml inside
that GitHub workflows file, and it's a valid workflows YAml,
it will start running whenever it's supposed to be triggered.
Now if that's a manual trigger, if it's on a push, if it's on a
schedule, as soon as you put the file in the repo and
it's a valid yaml that matches the schema, it'll be
run whenever it's supposed to be triggered. Now,
events trigger workflows, and I'm going to show you a big list of
events. I'll probably bring it up in a moment. But a
workflow contains one or more jobs. So we have a job.
When the workflow gets triggered, a job is
going to be kicked off and that job can
have one or more steps. Those can be like command line
steps, like a bash script, they can be actions,
they can be shell commands,
it can be a number of different things. Now, each of those jobs
runs on a runner, and like I said, you youll have one or more jobs,
and those jobs by default run in
parallel. There's no dependencies between them,
they're just jobs. If you have like five or ten jobs, they could all try
to kick off right at the same time, unless you have
some explicit dependencies between them or you have some needs
between them. Now, each job is using to run on its own runner
and what a runner is, and I'll talk about those in
a little bit more depth. It's like a vm or a docker
container, something that is spun up for the purposes
of running your job. Now, if it's using a
GitHub hosted runner, which I'll show you some documentation about,
it comes with a ton of tools. If it's a self hosted runner that you
built and are running yourself, it is going to have whatever
tools you put on it. So let's get into some demos and
just see what we're talking about. This is
where all of my demos live out on GitHub. But I
wanted to talk a little bit first about those events, those actions.
So in GitHub we talked about events
that trigger workflows. So like I said, there's a workflow,
there's a ton of different events that can trigger stuff like
someone tried to push something against main or
they created, we can go right here,
they created a branch or a tag. You can
see what happens if someone forks your code. That can be a trigger.
So triggers are not just limited or the events are not just
limited to things like pushing or pulling code.
It can go far, far beyond that. Like someone created
a project or moved a card or made
a comment, or you want to do it on a schedule. So you want like
a nightly build. This one is one of my favorites.
It's super important. Workflow dispatch out of the box. There's no
manual way to trigger a workflow. You have
to add workflow dispatch if you want to manually trigger
a workflow. So let's take
a look at one. So I've got up here in my GitHub actions demos,
you can come here to actions and you can see I have a whole bunch
of different workflows listed here. So if we just start
on this first one, I can
take a look at it and I can open up what a yaml file
looks like. In this particular case, this workflow. So we've got a name
and you can see I've got on. So these are
those events that are going to trigger the workflow to
execute. So on a push, on a pull request,
and on workflow dispatch, so I can manually trigger it.
And then I'm going to list out my jobs. So I'm going to have one
or more jobs. And in this case I'm going to name my
job build. So I have a build job that's indented under jobs
and I have to tell you what it runs on. It needs an image
for this job to run on. So this one is going to run on Ubuntu
latest, and I've given it some steps, like it's going to check out the code
base and it's going to run an echo command.
Well, maybe I want to build net
or maybe I want to build Java or go or something.
Do I need to go and set up all those tools and configure them?
Well, I don't, because like I said, they already exist
on a lot of the runners. So if I just do another quick search for
hosted runners, again, great documentation
comes right to it. And I can see kind of an
overview of what I'm getting. I've got my workflow, it's running
my jobs. This is giving you
an example of different ways to specify if you want to run
on Windows or Linux, but out
of the box you pretty much get like a two core cpu, seven gigs of
ram, some space, and there's lots of
different tags for different versions, even Mac if you need to do like a mobile
app or a Mac application. But trying to understand what's installed on
it, I can look at my runner history and I can
see what's on that machine, or I can also come here and see what's available.
So on my run, if I look at
my build, I can see the log for it and
I can expand out setting up the job. I can see the operating
system, it was an Ubuntu 20 machine, and I have a runner
image and there is a link right here for my build on
the included software. Now this has
so much stuff, it's kind of funny how many languages
and tools and packages are available out of
the box like Docker and Kubectl
NPM. We have CLI tools for pretty much every cloud out
there. So right out of the box, using one of these hosted agents,
I can run and do lots of things very quickly across
a wide range of languages, and I don't have to do a lot of configuration
to do it and I can get status. So let's go back
to our actions. We had a basic trigger.
I showed that we might need the workflow dispatch event,
so if I want to run this, I can say run. And that
enables the button here so I can manually run my workflow whenever
I want to. So I'm triggering this run and
what we'll see momentarily. There we go. It's manually run. It's queued
up right now. I can go in and see kind
of in real time as it executes,
so I can get real time logs, I can get the output
of individual commands.
Cool. Well what about doing something a little bit more complex?
Well I do have a more complex job,
but let's say I don't want to build it on every push.
I can have filters, I can do limitations, so I
only want it to build on the main
branch when I push on the main branch, or if I use
a pattern of release something so the
starstar will do things under that path.
Maybe I want to only build it on v two tags or using
star. I only want to build it when I touch Javascript
files. So I have a lot of different options for controlling when things
run. I youll do a schedule like a cron job,
so I can specify cron syntax, so I have a lot of different
capabilities. And just like with all the others, I can come
out here and look at GitHub action workflow
syntax and this is going to give me a detailed breakdown
of all of the structures of the workflow.
Yaml so I can see on pull request on branches,
including branches, excluding branches using
the not symbol. It's all very well documented out on
the GitHub documentation page, so we have a lot of different options to
build and record.
Let's see what else we got. So what about multiple jobs?
And I will go ahead and kick this one off and we'll take a look
at it when it triggers. So I mentioned a workflow is made up
of one or more jobs. I also said they all kind of run in parallel.
So here I've got not one but
two, three jobs, and job three finished first, so we
had no real idea what was going to go when
they all ran in parallel. And what that looks like
if we're looking at a job, is I've got job
one and it runs on Ubuntu and I've got job two
and it runs on Ubuntu. So I have this list of jobs
that I've built out, but what if I want
some sort of dependency between them? What if I don't want job
three to finish before job one?
Maybe I want job one to always run first and
then I don't care if job two or three finish first. That could
be I want to do a build and then I want to run some acceptance
tests or some unit tests.
We can structure our jobs in any way we want.
GitHub actions and the workflows are an amazing toolkit that
lets us kind of automate and trigger our
workflows as need be to match our working style
or our requirements. And the way we can set
up these dependencies in our workflows is using
the needs keyword. So job two
needs job one. So we can establish that dependency
very easily. Let's keep going, let's see what
else we got. So steps, there are lots of different steps.
And I'll go ahead and run this guy and we'll go into what steps look
like. So with
steps they can be, like I
said, commands tasks. Once this job loads
we should see all the different steps. So we got all sorts of stuff.
So I'm running, if we look at the setup job, I'm running on an
Ubuntu machine, so it's Linux and
I can just say echo my path. So I'm doing a bash variable
environment, variable reference and it's spitting out my path.
And try doing CMD. But CMD won't work because CMD
is a Windows specific thing, but out of
the box. The Linux machines come with Powershell
because Powershell is cross platform, but not
Powershell like the Windows 5.1 version.
I can also specify random shells,
like I want to use Python, or I want to do something with Perl.
Or I can specify a checkout action.
Like I want to use the checkout action. I want it to be locked to
a specific hash, a specific shaw like commit.
For this checkout action. I can also do
different versions, like I want to do version two or three based on
tag or based on a branch. I can check out things.
So how do I know about this
hash, this version? Well,
actions besides my simple commands that I want to
run. If we scroll all the way to the top of the GitHub site,
we'll see the marketplace. So the GitHub marketplace is
where we have all of those great actions
that are built by the community, by people,
by companies to help do things.
In this case we had the checkout command. So if
I look it up, we've got a blue check mark to show
it's creator verified by GitHub. We've got stars.
We can see version information about the individual
actions. And the latest version we have tags on
if it's built and test. Any action in the marketplace
needs to be in a public open source repo or a public repo.
Anyone pretty much can go and see issues or do
pull requests. For now, almost every well written
action you'll find has really good documentation around the
usage of it. The options that you can pass into it,
scenarios like they might give you scenarios on how to leverage
it, to do certain things that you're trying to do. So looking
for an action in the marketplace is a
great thing to look for. And we can go right to the code
base so I can click on the action and
it's going to take me to the repo that has that action,
so I can look at how somebody implemented something
or how something was done. I can also go right to the open issues.
So if I'm having a problem, I can go look at the
issues that are affecting that particular version or
that action. And so we have
a lot of ways to look for and find
capability that people have already implemented and consumed that
now, something that you might have noticed and
I kind of skipped over, I was passing information into the
action. Well, we also can do environment variables,
and these all kind of flow together into what are called contexts, and we'll talk
about those momentarily. But let's say I want to
pass information, I want to have some variables I
want to pass something down into an action into my job should
trigger it
already ran. I can run
a script and say I have environment variables
that I'm going to call, and you can see I passed in my environment
greeting hello name world.
So I can pretty quickly, pretty easily pass
information from my top section
in my workflow. I can pass the name of a service
or do some sort of dynamicism like string manipulation,
and pass it down into lower level jobs and have
those picked up. Now, something else that I think
is really important to cover when we're dealing with variables is there is
a hierarchy that exists. So when we have
workflow level variables, or we have things
like job level variables, or even step level variables,
they can override each other. Like if you invoke the same
environment key like environment name,
this is saying hello from location step,
and I've passed in information. But if I go and I look at
my workflow, you'll see what's happening. I've defined at
my workflow level a location workflow.
But as I start executing on the specific job,
the job overrides the workflow value. As I get
down to an individual step, the step overrides
the job level value. And so when I'm running
my command hello world from step, I'm getting information from
my workflow, from my local step
in my environment. So understanding how
youll can leverage values defined
higher up in the hierarchy and how you can override them lower down in
the hierarchy is important.
Now we're dealing with variables. We're starting to pass stuff.
Let's get into conditionals. So conditionals are a fun thing where we can
add a job, we can conditionally execute jobs
or steps based on values, and those values can
be everything from the branch we're
on or the environment we're in. So here youll notice run
goodbye did not execute, but run hello did,
and we can see why that is when we look inside
the file. So we can do stuff like if,
so if this expression is true,
we can run this step, we can do things around jobs
like maybe we don't want to do our deployment job if we're not on the
branch main, if we're not in an environment like production.
So we can have some conditional control
of our different workflows, of our different steps.
And conditionals are really a form of expression.
So let me just show you what some expressions look like where we can
do string formatting and we can do string interpolation.
We can put values together and we can build up things.
So if we want patterns and naming, we can leverage that. We can check
if stuff ends with or contains strings.
We can do array manipulation, so we can give it
like a JSON String and make an object out
of a JSON string. And then if it's an array, we can check to see
if something contains an entry in the array, not just a
string, but the whole array. And then we can do stuff like joining and
concatenating, and we can print those out. So those all
work very much like you would expect. We get some
basic dynamicism and we can play
around with string manipulation in some of our workflows, and some of
our actions and expressions
are essentially a type of context. So I've got a
couple of contexts here, and I will show
like the GitHub Context gives you a lot of information about the
repo and the
check ins and the commits and the users. So there's a ton of information there
about the repository and the, you have stuff
about individual jobs, like if they've run steps.
So if we look at our GitHub workflow
context, contexts are something that comes up quite
a bit when we're building
out things. We've got our environment. So if we look at our
environment, we can see all of the different values that have been defined.
If we're doing a job, we can find out information about the container and
the services, if we list it out, so we can define
different things. So contexts are going to be an
object that we reference as we're doing some more complex interactions with
the different workflows.
And then secrets are a type of context. So secrets
exist in GitHub under settings. So if we come over here to
settings in my repository, you'll see down here under security, we've got
secrets and we have actions.
And you'll notice I have environment secrets which are listed
here in this top section. And then down below I have repository secrets,
which are for the repository. And just like
we had a variable hierarchy, there is a secret hierarchy.
Like you can have level secrets and repository level secrets
and environment level secrets. So you can have different secrets that
can override each other. I can edit
this, which will change the value, or I can remove it. And the way you
access, and you can see I've got some environment secrets
here, I'll show those in a moment. But the way you
access your secrets is
relatively simple when you're looking at the workflow. So if we're in
our workflow and we want to get to a secret,
we do the dollar kind of handlebars secrets
name. And if this did not
exist as a secret, it will just come back as an empty string. It doesn't
want to give you an error that that secret doesn't exist. That could kind
of give people a way to hunt around to see if you can find the
secret. Now,
notice I'm passing it two different ways. I a lot of times will pass
it by environment variable over passing it
in the command line, just in case something is
like listing processes on the system. Though I
know there's arguments about passing secrets via environment variables.
It's a little bit of a debate. Whichever way
you want to do it, GitHub actually tries
to protect you a little bit and tries to not
print out things. It knows our secrets. So if
I go into the logging and I look at these two
things where I've passed it by context, it knows that was a secret
and doesn't print it out.
Same with environment, but with the environment,
it knows I'm pulling the environment name, it just
doesn't print out the value. So this
can give you a little bit better information. If you're troubleshooting
things, this might give you a little bit less, but there's
multiple ways to do that. Now, I mentioned
that the secrets come from
the environment or from the individual
actions. So environments are listed here on the left. So we have
under code and automation, environments and environments give you a
couple of different things. You can just hit new environment
and make a new environment. So I can do something
like this, and I've created an environment. Now I can ask
for approvals. I mentioned that earlier with the CD part, and I
can say I want someone
to be a reviewer before you deploy into that environment.
I don't have to have secrets or resources, it's just a tag.
But if my job says it's using
this environment comp 42 environment, it'll ask for approvals.
I can also have protection on this environment, so I can say
I can only deploy to this environment if it comes
from my
main branch. My main branch is the only one that's
allowed to deploy into comp and maybe have secrets
that are specific to this environment.
Now, a lot of times what I'll do is I will have multiple
environments with the exact same secrets. It makes it much easier
for me to reuse my jobs or to copy and paste them.
I'm still leveraging all of the same secret values. I'm just referencing
them from a different environment. So that's
how I can interact with my environments. If I
have multiple environments like this, maybe they have multiple secrets.
And that's okay, I've got secrets and
I access them the exact same way. So when I'm accessing my
secrets, it doesn't matter if I'm accessing a secret from
my repo, from my, or from my environment.
And I know Linux environment,
shell environment versus environment,
a little bit of reuse and I'll show some end to end examples
in just a few moments. I want to talk about matrixes,
matrices for a second. So matrices are a really cool feature that
is available in workflows where maybe
you're a library builder or you're building an application and youll
want to be able to test it on multiple versions of
software or multiple OSS. Well I
can define a matrix of I'm building a python library or a
node library and I want to test it on node 1214 and 16.
And I need to make sure it works on Windows and Linux. So I can
define and you can see I've kicked off a
bunch of node builds and a bunch of windows builds, but I can go in
and say I'm building
node and I have a strategy, it's my matrix. So here
are my node versions and here are my windows oss,
and I'm leveraging these just like I do secrets and
other contexts, Matrix OS
and matrix node version.
So I can access the same values because it's part of my matrix
strategy. This is going to be my matrix context and I can access
the thing. I'm only building out
the job template essentially one time, but this gets
copied three times, two, six times
for the full matrix. So I think that's a
really cool feature that some people need to leverage. Not everybody does,
but it's a good to have. So let's
look at some end to end stuff. I've got three
workflows left and I just want to walk through a couple of
examples. So like net, for instance,
I do similar patterns to what I've done in
other pipeline
CI CD platforms, which is I'm a big fan of separating
out my build and my deploy jobs stages.
I like to have a build that
compiles tests and then gives me an artifact.
And I like that because I can get really fast feedback on it and
it gives me an artifact that I can redeploy later.
I can youll back and forward pretty easily and just redeploy
that one task without having to rebuild everything. Because I know I had
a good binary. I usually also do infrastructure
as code. So you'll notice I upload two artifacts here one
is my web app and one is my
infrastructure as code. So it's IAC. So I'm
uploading both infrastructure's code and my compiled application
so I can deploy it out. Now I said environments
can have approvals. Well I set up an approval here on
this environment. And before I approve it, if we go
take a look at the Yaml file,
I'm doing some interesting things where I'm only going to run this workflow if
I like no paths. So remove
all the paths and only add in the. Net sample. So only do it when
I touch that folder. And I'm doing
some builds, I'm setting up net and giving it the specific version
I want. And these are cool actions
that you can look at. Anytime you look around on GitHub and
you find someone using an interesting action, you can come out here
and you can look up the action, you can see use cases and
how that interacts. So I
poke around a lot of open source projects to see
how they're doing things. Cache defines one. It provides
you with this type of syntax for compiling nuget
packages and. Net packages a little bit more quickly that cache
things. But I'm just doing individual commands to restore,
build, test, publish and upload artifacts.
Now this is where it kind of gets cool on my
deploy, it needs build. So my deploy has to wait till the
build finishes and I'm using an environment. So this
is where I have an environment called net and this
is where it's asking me do I have an approval
to deploy into my net environment. I'm going to download infrastructure
as code and I'm going to log into Azure because I want
to deploy an arm template or a bicep file and I
deploy out my infrastructure as code.
There is an id here which I'll touch on momentarily. And then
we get the web app and it deploys to the
output of my deploy step.
So because I gave this task an id
of deploy, I can go steps deploy and
I have an arm template here that has outputs so I can do outputs.
Web app name I don't know what the name of this web app will be
at the time I write it. Like my dev environment
might give a different name than my prod environment because it's
driven by a secret. So I don't know what to deploy to. So I
need to get the dynamic output of this step right
here in order to pass it to this step right here to
deploying out my code. So let me go ahead and
approve this so I can give an approval. I can
leave a comment. This will now start kicking off the job and
it'll spin up infrastructure, get the dynamic name,
pass that into my deploy and deploy software
onto that web service that got created. You can see it's
pulling down the actions it needs and it's going to do that
task. Now this
is using the older style of Azure login, using the credentials
with a service principle. They've got a newer style that's really nice called
Openid Connect. They actually link to it right there
in the conversation or in the log.
And what's awesome about OpenID connect is you
don't have to pass a secret,
so you don't need a password like Azure and GitHub
trust each other. And I might show this
if I have a few minutes, but really look
into OpenID connect. It's pretty neat, but yeah,
I'm running this deploy. I don't know the web app name,
but it's creating my deployment and
then when that's done it's going to download the
web app and deploy that out there and we
can see kind of what that looks like in an older run
that I did a little while ago. So if we look at our
deploy here,
it's getting the deploying and because I had
a secret as part of it, it's obscuring it, but it
gives you the URL to access the deployment and
passed it in and it worked. Well, what about containers? What if I
want to deploy a container? Well,
containers are very easy to work with. In GitHub actions.
We can log into Docker Hub. So if we want to log into Docker
hub or ACR for Azure, the Azure container registry,
you can use the Docker login action for both of those. If you want to
do a build and push or you want to use build to compile
a container, I'm giving it a folder of container example and
I'm saying I want youll to push this code with these tags
so you can have multiple tags on a container.
Now I do have another sample
out on GitHub that you can look at if you're interested
in.
That one is kind of more slated directly to containers.
Anyways, I will find that in a minute.
Could have sworn I had it right on my main page. But that
one's another fun one where you can see a couple of
steps like I want to do trivia scanning, I want to scan my container,
maybe I don't push it when I first build my container and then I scan
it and then I push it up.
GitHub also provides a superlinter, and a superlinter will pretty
much look at all of your code base in pretty
much every language you can think of. It's really
neat for just trying
to standardize types along your code,
just some weird stuff. Best practices. It has
so many linters, it supports so many languages, and there's
some config files you can check in that will help
standardize how you want to do it. So if you want to turn
on certain ones or turn off other linters, you have full control
over how those different linters work.
Now you might say, these actions are awesome. How do I get started?
Well, you can just go to actions and say new workflow.
And what this will do is it'll look in your code base and try
to give you an idea.
It'll scan your code and try to give you a starting point, like it's a
docker image or net app or a grunt app.
And you can search for these workflows. If I was doing like,
oh, maybe I want to do NPM, well, there's a whole bunch here about oh,
I want to do a node JS package and I can hit configure.
And what this will do is it'll already set up your repo
GitHub workflows. It'll give you this and
it'll start you out with a reasonable place
to start from. You can also search the marketplace right there.
So I said I'm doing Azure. I can
click an Azure button and add in an action
potentially, so I can find
a version and I can copy it and I can paste it
over here and then I can delete the stuff I don't need.
So it gives me a starting point.
Another thing that I think is really interesting is the
paths up here. Not everybody.
It's interesting that it
might have a whole bunch of stuff there. You can name it whatever you
want, it'll automatically pick up those actions.
Another really cool thing, GitHub has
build essentially a training platform based
on GitHub actions. So skills. GitHub is
a full training thing built on this.
Remember I said there were events around what happens if you fork
it, or what happens if you comment or push?
Well, when you use this template and you make a
fork, it starts doing stuff and then
it starts prompting you via
pull requests, issues, comments. And if
you come in here and you're curious how it works, look, they have some scripts
and they have workflows. So this is going to
unpush to main, it's going to check
on a conditional is this GitHub a template,
so you can see some cool tricks based
on how things are working in the
actions. And you can look across
GitHub. So if you're looking at like GitHub workflows,
you can go see what other projects are doing,
doing codeql analysis,
checking for spelling. So you can go take a
look and see what people are doing. Oh, they're using a c spell action.
That's cool. I didn't know I could do that.
That's all I had. Please feel
free to, like I said, follow some
of my repositories and take a look. Feel free
to clone some of these
repos and play around.
That's the best thing you can do,
play around with actions, try them
out. It works really cool, really well.
And there's even a way,
if you're really interested, to test some of these locally. You can
see here, I'm doing a build, I'm doing a scan. So there's
a tool out there called act that I
like to recommend to people. If you're playing around,
it is super cool. It runs in a container, but essentially this
will let you run your GitHub
actions locally, like you pretty much say act,
and it'll pull in your
workflows and it'll run them inside these containers. So you can kind of
test things locally while you're trying to get stuff working.
I've used this many times and it's a really cool repo,
it's a really cool project. And it's something
that I think if you do all these a lot, if you
make a lot of workflows, that this is something that is a helpful tool.
And I did not get into some of the reusable workflows
or the templates, but again, search for the
documentation and it'll work out.
You'll find it. The documentation is incredible, so you'll be
able to find that pretty quickly. And so with that,
I'd like to thank everybody for joining me today, and happy
deploying and playing around with GitHub actions. Thank you.